<act><tid>679372</tid>
<title>THE DELHI RENT ACT, <year>1995</year></title>

ACT NO. 33 OF <year>1995</year>
[ 23rd August, <year>1995</year>.]

An Act to provide for the regulation of rents repairs and mainte- 
nance and evictions relating to premises and of rates of hotels and 
lodging houses in the National Capital Territory of Delhi.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- sixth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>5733</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1818058</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Delhi Rent Act, <year>1995</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>712488</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the areas included within the limits of the 
New Delhi Municipal Council and the Delhi Cantonment Board and to 
urban areas within the limits of the Municipal Corporation of Delhi 
for the time being:
Provided that the Central Government may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, exclude any area from the operation of this Act or 
any provision thereof:

Provided further that the Central Government may, by notification 
in the Official Gazette, exclude any premises or class of buildings 
from the operation of this Act or any provision thereof.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>251182</tid>
<number>3</number>It shaft come into force on such date as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1601535</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>1480714</tid>
<number>a</number>" Bench" means a Bench of the Tribunal;

</section>

<section><tid>1023715</tid>
<number>b</number>" Chairman" means the Chairman of the Tribunal;

</section>

<section><tid>1958470</tid>
<number>c</number>" fair rate" means' the fair rate fixed under section 39 
and includes the rate as revised under section 40;

</section>

<section><tid>734308</tid>
<number>d</number>" hotel or lodging house" means a building or a part of 
a building where lodging, with or without board or other 
services, is provided for a monetary consideration;

</section>

<section><tid>118553</tid>
<number>e</number>" landlord" means a person who, for the time being is 
receiving, or is entitled to receive, the rent of any 
premises, whether on his own account or on account of or on 
behalf of, or for the benefit of, any other person or as a 
trustee, guardian or receiver for any other person or who 
would so receive the rent or be entitled to receive the rent 
if the premises were let to a tenant;

</section>

<section><tid>475829</tid>
<number>f</number>" lawful Increase" means an increase in rent permitted 
under the provisions of this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>15961</tid>
<number>g</number>" manager of a hotel" includes any person in charge of 
the management of' the hotel;

</section>

<section><tid>608123</tid>
<number>h</number>" Member" means a Member of the Tribunal and includes 
the Chairman;

</section>

<section><tid>1675227</tid>
<number>i</number>" owner of a lodging house" means a person who receives 
or is entitled to receive whether on his own account or on 
behalf of himself and others or as an agent or a trustee for 
any other person, any monetary Consideration from any person 
on account of board, lodging or other Services provided in 
the lodging house;

</section>

<section><tid>1604875</tid>
<number>j</number>" premises" means any building or part of a building 
which is or is intended to be, let separately for use as a 
residence or for non- residential use or for any other 
purpose, and includes-- 
 (i) the garden, grounds and outhouses if any, 
appertaining to such building or part of the building; 
 (ii) any fittings to such building or part of the 
building for the more beneficial enjoyment thereof; 
but does not include a room in a hotel or a lodging 
house.

</section>

<section><tid>626378</tid>
<number>k</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>135128</tid>
<number>l</number>" Rent Authority" means an authority appointed under 
subsection (1) of section 43 and includes an additional Rent 
Authority appointed under sub- section. (2) of that section;

</section>

<section><tid>1712299</tid>
<number>m</number>" standard' rent", in relation to any premises, means 
the rent calculated under section 7;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>268251</tid>
<number>n</number>" tenant" means any person by whom or on whose account 
or behalf the rent of any premises is or, but for a special 
contract, would be payable, and includes--

<subsection><tid>410332</tid>
<number>i</number>a sub- tenant;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>720557</tid>
<number>ii</number>any person continuing in possession after the 
termination of his tenancy,
but does not include-


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>410332</tid>
<number>i</number>any person against whom an order or decree for 
eviction has been made, except where such decree or 
order for eviction is liable to be re- opened under the 
proviso to section 3 of the Delhi Rent Control 
 (Amendment) Act, <year>1976</year>; (18 of <year>1976</year>.)

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>720557</tid>
<number>ii</number>any person to whom a licence as defined in section 
 52 of the Indian Easements Act, <year>1882</year> (5 of <year>1882</year>.) has 
been granted;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>288710</tid>
<number>o</number>" Tribunal" means the Delhi Rent Tribunal established 
Under section 46;

</section>

<section><tid>749735</tid>
<number>p</number>" urban area" has the same meaning as in the Delhi 
municipal Corporation Act, <year>1957</year>. (66 of <year>1957</year>.)



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1283886</tid>
<number> 3</number> Certain provisions not to apply to premises.
<section><tid>1175797</tid>
<number>1</number>Nothing in  
this Act shall apply--

<subsection><tid>71458</tid>
<number>a</number>to any premises belonging to the Government or a local 
authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>996859</tid>
<number>b</number>to any tenancy or other like relationship created by a 
grant from the Government in respect of the premises taken on 
lease or requisitioned, by the Government:
Provided that where any premises belonging to Government 
have been or are lawfully let out by any person by virtue of 
an agreement with the Government or otherwise, then, 
notwithstanding any judgment, decree or order of any court or 
other authority, the provisions of' this Act shall apply to 
such tenancy;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1024553</tid>
<number>c</number>to any premises, whether residential or not and whether 
let out before or after the commencement of this Act, whose 
monthly deemed rent on the date of commencement of this Act 
exceeds three thousand and five hundred rupees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>696730</tid>
<number>d</number>to any premises constructed on or after the 1st day of 
December, <year>1988</year> but before the commencement of this Act for a 
period of ten years from the date of completion of such 
construction;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>244150</tid>
<number>e</number>to any premises constructed on or after the 
commencement of this Act, for a period of fifteen years from 
the date of completion of such construction;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1078785</tid>
<number>f</number>to any premises, being a premises not let out within 
seven years before letting out the same, for a period of 
fifteen years from the date it is let out;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>139275</tid>
<number>g</number>to any premises let out to a citizen of a foreign 
Country or an embassy, high commission, legation or 
commission of a foreign State or such international 
organisation as may be Specified by the Central Government by 
notification in the Official Gazette;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>651332</tid>
<number>h</number>to any premises belonging to such religious, charitable 
or educational trust or class of trusts as may be specified 
by the Central Government by notification in the Official 
Gazette;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1618338</tid>
<number>i</number>to any tenancy, whether entered before or after the 
commencement of this Act, for a period of twenty years or 
more and registered under the Registration Act, <year>1908</year> (16 of  
  <year>1908</year>.) and not terminable before its expiration at the 
option of the landlord.
Explanation I.- For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared 
that the provisions of this Act shall apply to any premises, not being 
a premises mentioned in sub- section (1),- 
 (a) let out to the Government or a local authority; 
 (b) let out by a hire- purchaser, lessee or sub- lessee, 
by whatever name called, who has been allotted such 
premises by, the Delhi Development Authority or any 
other local authority by way of an agreement of hire- 
purchase, lease or sub- lease, even before the full 
ownership rights accrue to such hire- purchaser, lessee 
or sublessee, as the case may be.

Explanation II.-" Premises belonging to the Government or a local 
authority" shall, notwithstanding anything contained in any judgement, 
decree or order of a court, not include a building' erected on any 
land held by any person from the Government or a local authority by 
virtue of an agreement, a lease, licence or grant although such land 
under the conditions of such agreement, lease, licence or grant may 
continue to belong to the Government or a local authority.

Explanation III.-" Deemed rent on the date of commencement of this 
Act" shall be the rent calculated in the manner provided in section 7, 
together with revision, if any, as provided in section on 9 and 
decreased in the case of premises constructed after the commencement 
of this Act at the same rate as the rate of enhancement stipulated in 
Schedule I to reflect the position on the date of the commencement of 
this Act.

Explanation IV.-" Date of completion of construction" shall be the 
date of completion as intimated to the concerned authority or of 
assessment to property tax, whichever is earlier, and, where the 
premises have been constructed in stages, the date on which the 
initial building was completed and an intimation thereof was sent to 
the concerned authority or was assessed to property tax, whichever is 
earlier.

Explanation V.-" Premises constructed" shall include- 
 (i) re- building of more than seventy- five per cent, of 
an existing building; 
 (ii) additional construction to an existing building.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1498159</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), in 
the Transfer of Property Act, <year>1882</year>, (4 of <year>1882</year>.) the Code of Civil 
Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>.) and any other law for the time being in 
force, the Rent Authority shall have the jurisdiction to decide all 
disputes relating to tenancies in respect of the premises referred to 
in clauses (c) to (i) of sub- section (1).

<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1121227</tid>
<number> 4</number> Registration of tenancy agreements.
<section><tid>817515</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding  
anything contained in section 107 of the Transfer of Property Act, 
<year>1882</year>, (4 of <year>1882</year>.) no person shall, after the commencement of this 
Act, let or take on rent any premises except by an agreement in 
writing.

</section>

<section><tid>336126</tid>
<number>2</number>Every agreement referred to in sub- section (1) or required 
to be registered under sub- section (3) shall be registered under the 
Registration Act, <year>1908</year>, (16 of <year>1908</year>.) within such period as may be 
prescribed and for this purpose the agreement shall be deemed to be a 
document for which registration is compulsory under section 17 of the 
said Act.

</section>

<section><tid>607563</tid>
<number>3</number>Where, in relation to a tenancy created before the 
commencement of this Act,-

<subsection><tid>1761557</tid>
<number>a</number>an agreement in writing was entered into and was not 
registered under the Registration Act, <year>1908</year>, (16 of <year>1908</year>.) 
the landlord and the tenant shall jointly present a copy 
thereof for registration before the registering officer under 
the said Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1945609</tid>
<number>b</number>no agreement in writing was entered into, the landlord 
and the tenant shall enter into an agreement in writing with 
regard to that tenancy and present the same for registration 
before the registering officer under the said Act:
Provided that where the landlord and the tenant fail to present 
jointly a copy of tenancy agreement under clause (a) or fail to reach 
an agreement under clause (b) such landlord and the tenant shall 
separately file the particulars about such tenancy with the prescribed 
authority in such form and in, such manner and within such period as 
may be prescribed.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>921263</tid>
<number> 5</number> Inheritability of tenancy.
<section><tid>509389</tid>
<number>1</number>In the event of death of a  
tenant, the right of tenancy shall devolve for a period of ten years 
from the date of his death to his successors in the following 
order, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1637501</tid>
<number>a</number>spouse;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1495069</tid>
<number>b</number>son or daughter or where there are both son and daughter 
both of them;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1169232</tid>
<number>c</number>parents;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>929260</tid>
<number>d</number>daughter- in- law, being the widow of his pre- deceased 
son:
Provided that the successor has ordinarily been living in the 
premises with the deceased tenant as a member of his family up to the 
date of his death and was dependent on the deceased tenant:

Provided further that a right to tenancy shall not devolve upon a 
successor in case such successor or his spouse or any of his dependent 
son or daughter is owning or occupying a residential premises in the 
National capital Territory of Delhi.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1685945</tid>
<number>2</number>If a person, being a successor mentioned in sub- section (1), 
was ordinarily living in the premises with the deceased tenant but was 
not dependent on him on the date of his death, or lie or his spouse or 
any of his dependent son or daughter is owning or occupying a 
residential premises in the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>6</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

National Capital Territory of Delhi, such successor shall acquire a 
right to continue in possession as a tenant for a limited period of 
one year from the date of death of the tenant; and, on the expiry of 
that period, or on his death, whichever is earlier, the right of such 
successor to continue in possession of the premises shall become 
extinguished.

Explanation.-- For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared 
that-


<subsection><tid>1206927</tid>
<number>a</number>where, by reason of sub- section (2), the, right of any 
successor to continue in possession of the premises becomes 
extinguished, such extinguishment shall not affect the right 
of any other successor of the same category to continue in 
possession of the premises but if there is no other successor 
of the same category, the right to continue in possession of 
the premises shall not, on such extinguishment, pass on to 
any other successor specified in any lower category or 
categories, as the case may be;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>123538</tid>
<number>b</number>the right of every successor, referred to in sub- 
section (1) to continue in possession of the premises shall 
be personal to him and shall not, on the death of such 
successor, devolve on any of his heirs.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>319979</tid>
<number>3</number>Nothing in sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) shall apply to 
a nonresidential premises and the vacant possession of such premises 
shall be delivered to the landlord within one year-

<subsection><tid>880891</tid>
<number>i</number>of the death of tenant, in case the tenant is an 
individual;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>306415</tid>
<number>ii</number>of the dissolution of the firm, in case the tenant 
is a firm;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>233463</tid>
<number>iii</number>of the winding up of the company, in case the 
tenant is a company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1743886</tid>
<number>iv</number>of the dissolution of the corporate body, other 
than a company, in case the tenant is such a corporate 
body.
CHAP

RENT

CHAPTER II

RENT




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1980167</tid>
<number> 6</number> Rent payable.
<section><tid>12006</tid>
<number>1</number>The rent payable in relation to a premises  
shall be-

<subsection><tid>819523</tid>
<number>a</number>the rent agreed to between the landlord and the tenant 
as enhanced in the manner provided in Schedule I; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1263999</tid>
<number>b</number>the standard rent specified under section 7,
as revised under section 9.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1686732</tid>
<number>2</number>In the case of a tenancy entered into before the 
commencement of this Act, the landlord may, by notice in writing to 
the tenant within three months from the date of such commencement, 
enhance the rent as specified under section 7 and the rent so 
enhanced, shall be payable from the date of such commencement.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>7</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1578355</tid>
<number> 7</number> Standard rent.
<section><tid>244349</tid>
<number>1</number>" Standard rent", in relation to any  
premises, means the rent calculated On the basis of ten per cent. per 
annum of the aggregate amount of the cost, of construction and the 
market price of the land comprised in the premises on the date of 
commencement of the construction:
Provided that the standard rent calculated as aforesaid shall, be 
enhanced in the manner provided in Schedule I.


</section>

<section><tid>639267</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes of this section,-

<subsection><tid>299572</tid>
<number>a</number>cost of construction shall include cost of electrical 
fittings, water pumps, overhead water tanks, storage tanks 
and other water, sewerage and other fixtures and fittings in 
the premises;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>483449</tid>
<number>b</number>in case any fixtures and fittings referred to in clause 
 (a) are in common use by more than one occupant in a 
building, such proportion of cost of the fixtures and 
fittings shall be included in the cost of construction of the 
premises as bears the proportion to the plinth area of such 
premises to the plinth area of that building;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>2567</tid>
<number>c</number>the cost of construction shall be the actual amount 
spent on construction, and in a case, where such amount 
cannot be ascertained, such cost shall be determined, as per 
the scheduled rates of the Central Public Works Department 
for cost of construction for similar construction for the 
year in which the premises was constructed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1999049</tid>
<number>d</number>the market price of the land shall be the price for 
which the land was bought as determined from the deed of sale 
registered under the Registration Act, <year>1908</year>, (16 of <year>1908</year>.) 
if construction commenced in the year of registration or the 
land rates notified by a local authority for the year in 
which construction was commenced, whichever Is higher;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1127229</tid>
<number>e</number>the land comprised in the premises shall be the plinth 
area of the building and such of the vacant land up to fifty 
per cent. of the plinth area as is appurtenant thereto;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1488083</tid>
<number>f</number>in a case where a premises' forms part of a building 
having more than one premises. such proportion of price of 
land forming part of such building shall be taken to be the 
market price of the land comprised in the premises as is 
equal to the proportion of the plinth area of such premises 
to the plinth area of that building;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1972954</tid>
<number>g</number>notwithstanding anything contained in clauses (c) and 
 (a), the cost of construction and the market price of the 
land comprised in the premises purchased from or allotted by 
the Government or a local authority shall be the aggregate 
amount payable to such Government or the local authority for 
the premises:
Provided that the Rent Authority may, for the purpose of arriving 
at, the cost of" construction and the market price of the land 
comprised in the premises. allow addition, subject to a maximum of 
thirty per cent. of amount payable to the Government or the local 
authority, to the amount so payable for any expenditure incurred by 
the landlord or by the first or any subsequent purchaser or allottee 
for any improvement, addition or structural alternation in the 
premises.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>8</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>242040</tid>
<number> 8</number> Other charges payable.
<section><tid>1475781</tid>
<number>1</number>A tenant shall be liable to pay  
to the landlord, besides the rent, the following charges, namely:-

<subsection><tid>945727</tid>
<number>a</number>charges, not exceeding fifteen per cent. of the rent 
for the, amenities as specified in Schedule II as agreed to 
between the landlord and the tenant;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>525435</tid>
<number>b</number>maintenance charges at the rate of ten per cent. of the 
rent;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>510859</tid>
<number>c</number>without prejudice to the liability of landlord to pay 
the property tax to the local authority, the pro rata 
property tax in relation to the premises.
Explanation.- For the purpose of calculating the monthly charges 
payable by the tenant to the landlord towards the property tax, the 
amount paid of payable as property tax for the immediately proceeding 
year or the estimated tax payable shall form the basis.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>547328</tid>
<number>2</number>Th landlord shall be entitled to recover from the tenant the 
amount paid by him towards charges for electricity or water consumed 
or other charges levied by a local or other authority which is 
ordinarily payable by the tenant.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1521476</tid>
<number> 9</number> Revision of rent in certain cases. Where a landlord has at 
any time, before the commencement of this Act with or without the 
approval of the tenant or after the commencement of this Act with the 
written approval of the tenant incurred expenditure for any 
improvement, addition or structural alteration in the premises, not 
being expenditure on decoration or tenantable repairs necessary or 
usual for such premises, and the cost of that improvement, addition or 
alteration has not been taken into account in determining the rent of 
the premises, the landlord may lawfully increase the rent per year by 
an amount not exceeding ten per cent. of such cost.
<section><tid>1558173</tid>
<number>2</number>Where, after the rent of a premises has been fixed under 
this Act, or agreed upon, as the case may be, there has been a 
decrease, diminution or deterioration of accommodation in such 
premises, the tenant may claim a reduction in the rent.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1475575</tid>
<number> 10</number> Notice of revision of rent.
<section><tid>1278300</tid>
<number>1</number>Where a landlord wishes to  
revise the rent of any premises under sub- section (1) of section 9, he 
shall give the tenant a notice of his intention to make the revision 
and, in so far as such revision is lawful under this Act, it shall be 
due and recoverable from the date of improvement, addition or 
structural alteration.

</section>

<section><tid>948700</tid>
<number>2</number>Every notice under sub- section (1) shall be in writing signed 
by or on behalf of the landlord and given in the manner provided in 
section 106 of the Transfer of' Property Act, <year>1882</year>. (4 of <year>1882</year>.)



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1719244</tid>
<number> 11</number> Rent authority to fix standard rent, etc.
<section><tid>1902185</tid>
<number>1</number>The Rent  
Authority shall, on an application made to him in this behalf, in the 
prescribed manner, fix in respect of any premises-

<subsection><tid>730315</tid>
<number>i</number>the deemed rent for the purpose of clause (c) of sub- 
section (1) of section 3;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>587950</tid>
<number>ii</number>the enhancement in rent in the manner provided in 
Schedule I:

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1480520</tid>
<number>iii</number>the standard rent as per the provisions of section 7;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1832765</tid>
<number>iv</number>the other charges payable as per the provisions of 
section 8; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>674895</tid>
<number>v</number>the revision in rent as per the provisions of section 
9:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>9</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Provided that it shall not be permissible for the landlord to 
apply for the fixation of standard rent as per the provisions of 
section 7 in the case of a tenancy entered into after the commencement 
of this Act.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>729532</tid>
<number>2</number>In working out the cost of construction of any premises or 
the., market price of land comprised in such premises for the purposes 
of section 7 or the expenditure incurred for any improvement, addition 
or structural alteration or the decrease, diminution or deterioration 
of accommodation in a premises for the purpose of section 9, the Rent 
Authority may take the assistance of a prescribed valuer who shall 
carry out the assessment in the manner prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1637927</tid>
<number>3</number>In fixing the standard rent of any premises or the lawful 
increase or decrease of the rent or determining the other charges 
payable, the Rent Authority shall fix or determine an amount which 
appears to him to be reasonable having regard to the provisions of 
section 7 or section 9 or section 8 and the other circumstances of the 
case.

</section>

<section><tid>1271965</tid>
<number>4</number>In fixing the standard rent of any premises part of which 
has been lawfully sub- let, the Rent Authority may also fix the 
standard rent of such part sub- let.

</section>

<section><tid>793283</tid>
<number>5</number>Where for any reason it is not possible to determine the 
standard rent of any premises on the principles set forth in 
section 7, the Rent Authority may fix such rent as would be reasonable 
having regard to the situation, locality and condition of the premises 
and the amenities provided therein, and where there are similar or 
nearly similar premises in the locality, having regard also to the 
rent payable in respect of such premises.

</section>

<section><tid>1934079</tid>
<number>6</number>The standard rent shall in all cases be fixed for a tenancy, 
of twelve months:
Provided that where any premises are let or re- let for a Period 
of less than twelve months, the standard rent for such tenancy shall 
bear the same proportion to the annual rent as the period of tenancy 
bears to twelve months.


</section>

<section><tid>407745</tid>
<number>7</number>In fixing the standard rent of any premises under this 
section, the Rent Authority shall fix the standard rent thereof in an 
unfurnished state and may also determine an additional charge to be 
payable on account of any fittings or furniture supplied by the 
landlord and it shall be lawful for the landlord to recover such 
additional charge from the tenant.

</section>

<section><tid>501836</tid>
<number>8</number>in fixing the standard rent or lawful increase or decrease 
of rent or determining the other charges payable in respect of any 
premises under this section, the Rent Authority shall specify a date 
from which the amount so fixed shall be deemed to have effect:
Provided that, in the matter of standard rent, in no case the 
date so specified shall be earlier than the date of the filing of the 
application for the increase or decrease of the standard rent:

Provided further that if the increase is because of improvement, 
addition or structural alteration, it shall come into effect from the 
 (late of completion of such improvement, addition or alteration. 


</section>

<section><tid>1433915</tid>
<number>9</number>The Rent Authority may, while fixing standard rent or lawful 
increase or decrease in rent or other charges payable, order for 
payment of the arrears of amount due by the tenant to the landlord in 
such number of instalments as it deems proper.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>10</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1150627</tid>
<number>12</number>Fixation of interim rent. If an application for fixing the 
standard rent or for determining the lawful increase or decrease of 
rent or other charges payable is made under section 11, the Rent 
Authority shall, as expeditiously as possible, make an order 
specifying the amount to be paid pending final decision on the appli- 
cation and shall appoint the date from which the amount so specified 
shall be deemed to have effect.


</article>



<article><tid>214067</tid>
<number> 13</number> Limitation for application for fixation of standard rent, 
etc. A tenant may file an application to the Rent Authority for fixing 
the standard rent of the premises and a landlord or a tenant may file 
application for determining the lawful increase or decrease of rent or 
other charges payable,-
<section><tid>1806255</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of any premises which was let and in which 
the cause of action for lawful increase or decrease of rent 
or payment of other charges arose, before the commencement of 
this Act, within two years from such commencement;

</section>

<section><tid>1779177</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of any premises which was let after the 
commencement of this Act,-

<subsection><tid>127537</tid>
<number>i</number>for fixing the standard rent thereof. within two 
years from the date on which the premises was let;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>620329</tid>
<number>ii</number>in any other case, within two years from the date 
on which cause of action arose:
Provided that the Rent Authority may entertain the application 
after the expiry of the said period of two years, if he is satisfied 
that the applicant was prevented by sufficient cause from filing the 
application in time.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>367290</tid>
<number>14</number>Limitation of liability of middlemen. No collector of rent 
or middleman shall be liable to pay to Ms' principal, in respect of 
any premises, any sum by way of rental and other charges which exceeds 
the amount which he is entitled under this Act to realise from the 
tenant or tenants of the premises.


</article>



<article><tid>1987465</tid>
<number> 15</number> Receipt to be given for rent paid.
<section><tid>559308</tid>
<number>1</number>Every tenant shall  
pay rent and other charges payable within the time fixed by contract 
or in the absence of such stipulation, by the fifteenth day of the 
month next following the month for which it is payable and where any 
default occurs in the payment of rent or other charges, the tenant 
shall be liable to pay simple interest at the rate of fifteen per 
cent. per annum, from the date on which such payment of rent and other 
charges payable is due to the date on which it is paid.

</section>

<section><tid>1769454</tid>
<number>2</number>Every tenant who makes payment of rent or other charges 
payable or advance towards such rent or other charges to his landlord 
shall be entitled, against acknowledgment, to obtain forthwith from 
the landlord or his authorised agent a writen receipt for the amount 
paid to him. signed by the landlord or his authorised agent:
Provided that it shall be open to the tenant to remit the rent to 
his landlord by postal money order.


</section>

<section><tid>234547</tid>
<number>3</number>If the landlord or his authorised agent refuses or neglects: 
to deliver to the tenant the receipt referred to in sub- section (2), 
the Rent Authority may, on an application made to him in this behalf 
by the- tenant within two months from the date' of payment and after 
hearing the landlord or his authorised agent, by order direct the 
landlord or his authorised agent to pay to the tenant,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>11</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

by way of damages, such sum not exceeding double the amount of rent or 
other charges paid by the tenant and the costs of the application and 
shall also grant a certificate to the tenant in respect of the rent or 
other charges paid.


</section>

<section><tid>1877488</tid>
<number>4</number>If the landlord or his authorised agent refuses to accept or 
evades acceptance of receipt of rent and other charges payable to him, 
the tenant may, by notice in writing, ask the landlord to supply him 
the particulars of his bank account in a bank located in the National 
Capital Territory of Delhi into which the tenant may deposit the rent 
and other charges payable to the credit of the landlord.

</section>

<section><tid>146084</tid>
<number>5</number>If the landlord supplies the particulars of his bank 
account, the tenant shall deposit the rent and other charges payable 
in such bank account from time to time.

</section>

<section><tid>1240242</tid>
<number>6</number>If the landlord does not supply the particulars of bank 
account under sub- section (4), the tenant shall remit the rent and the 
other charges payable to the landlord from time to time through postal 
money order after deducting the postal charges.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1970360</tid>
<number> 16</number> Deposit of rent by tenant.
<section><tid>848801</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the landlord does no  
accept any rent and other charges payable tendered by the tenant 
within the time and the manner referred to in section 15 or refuses or 
neglects to deliver a receipt referred to therein or where there is a 
bona fide doubt as to the person or persons to whom the rent and other 
charges are payable, the tenant may deposit such rent and other 
, charges payable with the Rent Authority in the prescribed manner:
Provided that in cases where there is a bona fide doubt as to the 
person or persons to whom the rent and other charges are payable, the 
tenant may remit such rent and other charges payable to the Rent. 
Authority by postal money order.


</section>

<section><tid>389544</tid>
<number>2</number>The deposit shall be accompanied by an application by the 
tenant containing the following particulars, namely:-

<subsection><tid>542202</tid>
<number>a</number>the premises for which the rent and other charges 
payable are deposited with a description sufficient for 
identifying the premises;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>746244</tid>
<number>b</number>the period for which the rent and other charges payable 
are deposited;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>498691</tid>
<number>c</number>the name and address of the landlord or the person or 
persons claiming to be entitled to such rent and other 
charges payable:

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>703402</tid>
<number>d</number>the reasons and circumstances for which the application 
for depositing the rent and other charges payable is made;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>418985</tid>
<number>e</number>such other particulars as may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1577989</tid>
<number>3</number>On deposit of the rent and other charges payable being made, 
the Rent Authority shall send in the prescribed manner a copy of the 
application to the landlord or the persons claiming to be entitled to 
the rent and other charges payable with an endorsement of the date of 
the deposit.

</section>

<section><tid>424854</tid>
<number>4</number>if an application is made for the withdrawal of any deposit 
of rent and other charges payable the Rent Authority shall, if 
satisfied that the applicant is the person entitled to receive the 
rent and other charges deposited, order the amount of the rent and 
other charges to be paid to him in the manner prescribed:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>12</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Provided that no order for payment of any deposit of rent and 
other charges payable shall be made by the Rent Authority under this 
sub- section without giving all the persons named by the tenant in his 
application under subsection (2) as claiming to be entitled to payment 
of such rent and other charges payable an opportunity of being heard 
and such order shall be without prejudice to the rights of such I 
persons to receive such rent and other charges payable being decided 
by a court of competent jurisdiction.


</section>

<section><tid>977803</tid>
<number>5</number>If at the time of filing the application under sub- section 
 (4) but not after the expiry of thirty days from receiving the notice 
of deposit, the landlord or the person or persons claiming to be 
entitled to the rent and other charges payable complains or complain 
to the Rent Authority that the statements in the tenant' s application 
of the reasons and circumstances, which led him to deposit the rent 
and other charges payable are untrue, the Rent Authority, after giving 
the tenant an opportunity of being heard, may levy on the tenant a 
fine which may extend to an amount equal to two months, rent, if the 
Rent Authority is satisfiend that the said statements were materially 
untrue and may order that a sum out of the line realised be paid to 
the landlord as compensation.

</section>

<section><tid>1927951</tid>
<number>6</number>The Rent Authority may, on the complaint of the tenant and 
after giving an opportunity to the landlord of being heard, levy on 
the landlord a fine which may extend to an amount equal to two months' 
rent, if the Rent Authority is satisfied that the landlord, without 
any reasonable cause, refused to accept rent and other charges payable 
though tendered to him within the time referred to in section 15 and 
may further order that sum of fine realised be paid to the tenant as 
compensation



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1638049</tid>
<number> 17</number> Time limit for making deposit and consequences of incorrect 
particulars in application for deposit.
<section><tid>31923</tid>
<number>1</number>No rent and other charges  
deposited under section 16 shall be considered to have been validly 
deposited' tinder that section, unless the deposit is made within 
twenty- one days of the time referred to in section 15 for payment of 
the rent and other charges payable.

</section>

<section><tid>1009832</tid>
<number>2</number>No such deposit shall be considered to have been validly 
made, if the tenant wilfully makes any false statement in his 
application for depositing the rent and other charges payable, unless 
the landlord has withdrawn the amount deposited before the date of 
filing an application for the recovery of possession of the premises 
from the tenant.

</section>

<section><tid>1610537</tid>
<number>3</number>If the rent and other charges payable are deposited 
within the time mentioned in sub- section (1) and do not cease to be a 
valid deposit for the reasons mentioned in sub- section (2), the 
deposit shall constitute payment of rent and other charges payable to 
the landlord, as if the amount deposited had been validly tendered.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>994231</tid>
<number> 18</number> Saving as to acceptance of rent and other charges payable 
and forfeiture thereof in deposit.
<section><tid>636620</tid>
<number>1</number>The withdrawal of rent and  
other charges payable deposited under section 1- 6 in the manner 
provided therein shall not operate as an admission against the person 
withdrawing it of the correctness of the, rate, of rent and other 
charges payable the period of default, the amount due, or of any other 
facts stated in the tenant' s application for depositing the rent and 
other charges payable under the said section.

</section>

<section><tid>814968</tid>
<number>2</number>Any rent and other charges payable in deposit which are not 
withdrawn by the landlord or by the person or persons entitled to 
receive such rent and other charges payable shall be forfeited to 
Government by an order made by the Rent Authority, if they are not 
withdrawn before the expiration of five years from the date of posting 
of the notice or deposit.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>13</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>371251</tid>
<number>3</number>Before passing an. order of forfeiture, the Rent Authority 
shall give notice to the landlord or the person or persons entitled to 
receive the rent and other charges in deposit by registered post at 
the last known address of such landlord or person or persons and shall 
also publish the notice in his office and in any local newspaper.
CHAP

REPAIRS OF' PREMISES

CHAPTER III

REPAIRS OF' PREMISES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1149290</tid>
<number> 19</number> Duties of landlord.
<section><tid>1914960</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to any contract in writing  
to the contrary, every landlord shall be bound to keep the premises in 
good and tenantable repairs in relation to matters falling under Part. 
A of Schedule III.
Explanation.-" Good and tenantable repairs" under this section and 
section 20 shall mean such repairs as shall keep the premises in the 
same coudition in which it was let out except for the normal wear and 
tear.


</section>

<section><tid>16262</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any repairs, in relation to a. matter falling under 
Part A of Schedule III, without which the premises are not habitable 
or useable except with undue inconvenience are to be made and the 
landlord neglects or fails to make them within a period of three 
months after notice in writing, the tenant may apply to the Rent 
Authority for permission to make, such repairs himself and may submit 
to the Rent Authority an estimate of the cost of such repairs, and, 
thereupon, the Rent Authority may, after giving the landlord an 
opportunity of being heard and after considering such estimate of the 
cost and making such inquiries as it may consider necessary, by an 
order in writing, permit the tenant to make such repairs at such cost 
as may be specified in the order and it shall thereafter be lawful for 
the tenant to make such repairs himself and to deduct the cost 
thereof, which shall in no case exceed the amount so specified, from 
the rent or otherwise recover it from the landlord:
Provided that the amount so deducted or recoverable from rent in 
any year shall not exceed one- half of the rent payable by the tenant 
for that, year and any amount remaining not recovered in that year 
shall be deducted or recovered from rent in the subsequent years at 
the rate of not more than twenty- five per cent. of the rent for a 
month:

Provided further that where there are more than one premises 
owned by a, landlord in a building,: he tenants thereof may jointly 
carry out the repairs and share the expenses proportionately.


</section>

<section><tid>1626246</tid>
<number>3</number>Nothing in sub- section (2) shall apply to a premises which-

<subsection><tid>78872</tid>
<number>a</number>at the time of letting out was not habitable or useable 
except with undue inconvenience and the tenant had agreed to 
take the same in that condition;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>161587</tid>
<number>b</number>after being let out was caused to be not habitable or 
useable except with undue inconvenience by the tenant.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>276964</tid>
<number> 20</number> Duties of tenant.
<section><tid>1569211</tid>
<number>1</number>Every tenant shall be bound to keep  
the premises in good and tenantable repairs in relation to matters 
falling under Part B of Schedule III.

</section>

<section><tid>1605913</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any repairs, in relation to a matter falling under 
Part B of Schedule 111, without which the premises are not habitable 
or useable except with undue inconvenience, are to be made and the 
tenant neglects or fails to

<pagefootnote><pagenum>14</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Make them within a period of two months after notice in writing, the 
landlord may apply to the Rent Authority for permission to make such 
repairs himself and may submit to the Rent Authority an estimate of 
the cost of such repairs, and, thereupon the Rent Authority may, after 
giving the tenant an opportunity of being heard and after considering 
such estimate of the cost and making, such enquiries as he, may 
consider necessary, by an order in writing, permit the landlord to 
make, such repairs at such, cost as may be specified in the order, and 
it shall thereafter be lawful for the landlord to make such repairs 
himself and to recover the cost, of such repairs, which shall in no 
case exceed the amount so specified, from the tenant.


</section>

<section><tid>266371</tid>
<number>3</number>The landlord or a person authorised by him shall have the 
right to enter and inspect the premises after notice to the tenant in 
the manner prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1465825</tid>
<number>4</number>The tenant shall make good all damages caused to the 
premises by Ms negligence within three months of being informed in 
writing to do so by the landlord failing which the landlord may apply 
to the Rent Authority for permission to make good the said damages and 
the Rent Authority shall decide the matter in the manner provided in 
sub- section (2).

</section>

<section><tid>1581971</tid>
<number>5</number>The tenant shall hand over the possession of the premises on 
determination of tenancy in the same condition, except for the normal 
wear and tear, as it was in when it was handed over to him at the 
beginning of such tenancy and in a case where certain damages have 
been caused, not being damages caused by force majeur, the tenant 
shall make good the damages caused to the premises failing which the 
landlord may apply to the Rent Authority for permission to make good 
the said damages and the Rent Authority shall decide the matter in the 
manner provided in sub- section (2).

</section>

<section><tid>847922</tid>
<number>6</number>The tenant shall not, whether during the subsistence of 
tenancy, or thereafter, demolish any improvement or alteration carried 
out by him' in the premises or remove any material used in such 
improvement or alteration, other than any fixture of a removable 
nature, without the permission of the landlord failing which such 
demolition or alteration shall be deemed to be a damage caused by such 
tenant under sub- section (4) and shall be dealt with accordingly.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1863471</tid>
<number> 21</number> Cutting off or withholding essential supply or service.
<section><tid>1719518</tid>
<number>1</number> 
No landlord or tenant, either by himself or through any person 
purporting to act; on his behalf, shall, without just and sufficient 
cause cut off or withhold any essential supply or service enjoyed by 
the tenant or the landlord, as the case may be, in respect of the 
premises' let to him, or as the case may be, under Ms own occupation.

</section>

<section><tid>1603053</tid>
<number>2</number>If a landlord or a tenant contravenes the provisions of sub- 
section (1) the tenant or the landlord, as the case may be, may make 
an application to the' Rent Authority complaining of such 
contravention.

</section>

<section><tid>72417</tid>
<number>3</number>If the Rent Authority is satisfied that the essential supply 
or service was wilfully cut off or withheld, it may pass an order 
directing the restoration of the amenities immediately pending the 
inquiry referred to in sub- section (4).
Explanation.- An interim order may be passed under this sub- 
section without giving notice to the landlord or the tenant, as the 
case may be,


<pagefootnote><pagenum>15</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>917306</tid>
<number>4</number>If the Rent Authority on inquiry finds that the essential 
supply or service enjoyed by the tenant or the landlord was cut off or 
withheld by the landlord or the tenant, as the case may be, wilfully 
and without just and sufficient cause, he shall make an order 
directing the restoration of such supply or service.

</section>

<section><tid>1173822</tid>
<number>5</number>The Rent Authority shall complete an enquiry under sub- sec- 
tion (4) within a period of one month of filing of an application for 
enquiry unless the Rent Authority, for reasons to be recorded in 
writing, decides that it is not possible to complete the enquiry 
within such period.

</section>

<section><tid>655183</tid>
<number>6</number>The Rent Authority may, in his discretion, direct that 
compensation not exceeding one thousand rupees be paid to-

<subsection><tid>338509</tid>
<number>a</number>the landlord or the tenant, as the case may be, by the 
complainant if the application under sub- section (2) was made 
frivolously or vexatiously;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>35252</tid>
<number>b</number>the complainant, if the landlord or the tenant, as the 
case, may be, had cut off or withheld the supply or service 
without just and sufficient cause.
Explanation I.- In this section," essential supply or service" 
includes supply of water, electricity, lights in passages and on 
staircases, conservancy and sanitary services.

Explanation II,- For the purposes of this section, withholding any 
essential supply or service shall include acts or omissions 
attributable to the landlord or the tenant.. as the case may be, on 
account of which the essential supply or service is cut off by a local 
authority or any other agency.

CHAP

PROTECTION OF TENANTS AGAINST EVICTION

CHAPTER IV

PROTECTION OF TENANTS AGAINST EVICTION




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>842228</tid>
<number> 22</number> Protection of tenant against eviction.
<section><tid>33319</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding  
anything to the contrary contained in any other law or contract, no 
order or decree for the recovery of possession of any premises shall 
be made by any court, Tribunal or Rent Authority in favour of the 
landlord against a tenant save as provided in subsection (2).

</section>

<section><tid>356099</tid>
<number>2</number>The Rent Authority may, on an application made to it in the 
prescribed manner, make an order for the recovery of possession of the 
premises on one or more of the following grounds only, namely:--

<subsection><tid>179360</tid>
<number>a</number>that the tenant has neither paid nor tendered the whole 
of the arrears of' the rent and other charges payable for two 
or more consecutive months legally recoverable from him 
within two months of the date on which a notice of demand for 
the arrears of such rent and other charges payable and 
interest at the rate of fifteen per cent. for the period of 
default has been served on, him by the landlord in the 
manner provided in section 106 of the Transfer of Property 
Act, <year>1882</year>: (4 of <year>1882</year>.)
Provided that a tenant shall not be entitled to the benefit 
of service of notice by the landlord under this clause where, 
having obtained


<pagefootnote><pagenum>16</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Such benefit once respect of any premises, he again makes a 
default in the payment of rent and other charges payable in 
respect of those premises;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1462366</tid>
<number>b</number>that the tenant has, on or after the 9th day of June, 
<year>1952</year>, sub- let, assigned or otherwise parted with the 
possession of the whole or any part of the premises without 
obtaining the consent in writing of the landlord.
Explanation.- For the purpose of this clause, any premises 
which have been let for being used for the purposes of 
business or profession shall be deemed to have been sub- let 
by the tenant, if the Rent Authority is satisfied that the 
tenant, without obtaining the consent in writing of the 
landlord, has, after the 16th day of August, <year>1958</year>, allowed 
any person to occupy the whole or any part of the premises 
ostensibly on the ground, that such person is a partner of 
the tenant in the business or profession but really for the 
purpose of sub- letting such premises to that person;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>374133</tid>
<number>c</number>that the tenant has used the premises for a purpose 
other than that for which they were let-

<subsubsection><tid>1033279</tid>
<number>i</number>if the premises have been let oft or after the 9th 
day of June, <year>1952</year>, without obtaining the consent in 
writing of the landlord;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1933862</tid>
<number>ii</number>the tenant has not been residing therein, without 
obtaining his consent:
Provided that no application for the recovery of possession 
of any premises shall he under this clause unless the 
landlord has given to the tenant a notice in the prescribed 
manner requiring him to stop the misuse of the premises and 
the tenant has refused or failed to comply with such 
requirement within one month of the date of service of the 
notice and no order' for eviction against the tenant shall be 
made in such a case, unless the Rent Authority is satisfied 
that the misuse of the premises is of such nature that it is 
a public nuisance or that it causes damage to, the premises 
or is otherwise detrimental to the interests of the landlord;


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1228650</tid>
<number>d</number>that the premises were let for use as; a residence 
and-

<subsubsection><tid>1739548</tid>
<number>i</number>neither the tenant nor any member of his family 
has been residing therein for a period of six months;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1136117</tid>
<number>ii</number>the tenant has not been residing therein, without 
a reasonable cause for a period of two years. 
immediately before the (late of the filing of the  
application for the recovery of possession thereof:
Provided that the landlord may, on request in writing of the 
tenant, permit occupancy of the premises by a person other 
than the tenant or his family not exceeding the period of 
tenancy.

Explanation.- For the purposes of this clause and clause (r), 
" family" means parents, spouse, dependent sons and daughters 
or such other relatives as are ordinarily living with the 
tenant and are dependent upon him:


<pagefootnote><pagenum>17</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1512572</tid>
<number>e</number>that the premises or any part thereof have become 
unsafe or unfit for human habitation and are required by the 
landlord for carrying out repairs or re- construction which 
cannot be carried out without the premises being vacated:
Provided that no order for the recovery of possession under 
this clause, clause (g), clause (h) or clause (i) shall be 
made unless the Rent Authority is satisfied that the plans 
and estimates of such repairs or re- construction, as the case 
may be, have been properly prepared and that the landlord has 
the necessary means to carry out the said repairs or re- 
construction:

Provided further that if the landlord proposes to change the 
use of the premises after re- construction, then, he shall so 
specify in his application for recovery of possession and, 
after such reconstruction, the landlord shall, if it is 
otherwise permissible under law, utilize the built up area 
equal to the previous area for the original use to the extent 
required for the purpose of sub- section (1) of section, 32 
and the rest for any other use;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>54818</tid>
<number>f</number>that the premises or any part thereof are required by 
the landlord for the purpose of immediate demolition ordered 
by the Government or any local authority or the premises are 
required by the landlord to carry out any building work at 
the instance of the Government or a local authority in 
pursuance of any Improvement scheme or development scheme and 
that such building work cannot be carried out without the 
premises being vacated;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1688447</tid>
<number>g</number>that the premises or any part thereof are required by 
the landlord for carrying out any repairs which cannot be 
carried out without the premises being vacated;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>651171</tid>
<number>h</number>that the premises are required by the landlord for the 
purpose of building or re- building or make thereto any 
substantial addition or alteration including construction on 
the terrace or on the appurtenant land and that such building 
or re- building or addition or alteration cannot be carried 
out without the premises being vacated;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>726090</tid>
<number>i</number>that the premises consist of not more than two floors 
and the same are required by the landlord for the purpose 
of immediate demolition with a view to re- build the same.
Provided that where the building of which such premises or 
premises possession in respect of which has been recovered 
under clause (e). clause (f), clause (g) or clause (h) forms 
apart has been re- built to an extent of less than seventy- 
five per cent., a tenant so disposses sed shall have a right 
to re- entry at the new terms of tenancy in a premises in 
the re- built building equivalent in area to the original 
premises for which he was a tenant;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1260224</tid>
<number>j</number>that the tenant, his spouse or a dependent son or 
daughter ordinarily living with him has. whether before or 
after the commencement of this Act, built or acquired vacant 
possession of, or been allotted a residence:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>18</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Provided that the Rent Authority may in appropriate cases 
allow the tenant to vacate the premises within such period as 
he may permit but not exceeding one year from the date of 
passing of orders of eviction;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>87075</tid>
<number>k</number>that the premises were let to the tenant for use as a 
residence by reason of his being in the service or employment 
of the landlord, and. that the tenant has ceased, whether 
before or after the commencement of this Act, to be in such 
service or employment:
Provided that no order for the recovery of possession of any 
premises shall be made on this ground if the Rent Authority 
is of the opinion that there is any bonafide dispute as to 
whether the tenant has ceased to be in the service or 
employment of the landlord;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>364478</tid>
<number>l</number>that the tenant has, whether before or after the 
commencement of this Act, caused or permitted to be caused 
substantial damage to or such alteration of the premises as 
has the effect of changing its identity or diminishing its 
value.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this clause," substantial 
damage shall mean such damage as shall involve an expenditure 
equivalent to six months' rent or more of the premises or 
such less expenditure as the Rent Authority is satisfied, 
keeping in view, the special nature of damage, justifies the 
same to be treated as substantial damage for carrying out the 
repairs for such damage:

Provided that no order for the recovery of possession of ally 
premises, shall be made on the ground specified in this 
clause, if the tenant, within such time as may be specified 
in this behalf by the Rent Authority, carries out repairs to 
the. damage caused to the satisfaction of the Rent Authority 
or pays to the landlord such amount by way of compensation as 
the Rent Authority may direct;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>312135</tid>
<number>m</number>that the' tenant or any person residing with the tenant 
has been convicted of causing nuisance or annoyance to a 
person living in the neighbourhood of the premises or has 
been convicted of using or allowing the use of the premises 
for an immoral or illegal purpose;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1459334</tid>
<number>n</number>that the tenant has, notwithstanding previous notice, 
used or dealt with the premises in a manner contrary to any 
condition imposed on the landlord by the Government or the 
Delhi, Development Authority or the Municipal Corporation of 
Delhi while giving him a lease of the land on which the 
premises are situate:
Provided that no order for the recovery of possession of any 
premises shall be made on this ground if the tenant, within 
such time as may be specified in this behalf by the Rent 
Authority, complies with the condition imposed on the 
landlord by any of the authorities referred to in this clause 
or pays to the authority imposing such conditions the, amount 
by Way of compensation as the Rent Authority may direct;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1259567</tid>
<number>o</number>that the tenant in his reply having denied the 
ownership of landlord, has failed to prove it or that such 
denial was not made in a bona fide manner,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>19</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>54973</tid>
<number>p</number>that the person in occupation of the premises has 
failed to prove that he is a bona fide tenant;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>384383</tid>
<number>q</number>that the tenant after having agreed with or having 
informed the landlord in writing the date to vacate the 
premises does not do so on or after the date so agreed or 
informed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>679266</tid>
<number>r</number>that the premises let for residential or nonresidential 
purposes are required, whether in the same form or after re- 
construction, or re- building, by the landlord for Occupation 
for residential or nonresidential purpose for himself or for 
any member of his family if he is the owner thereof, or for 
any person for whose benefit the Premises are held and that 
the landlord or such person has no other reasonably suitable 
accommodation:
Provided that where the landlord has acquired the premises by 
transfer, no application for the recovery of possession of 
such premises shall lie under this clause unless a period of 
three years has elapsed from the date of the acquisition:

Provided further that where an order for the recovery of 
possession of any premises is made on the ground specified in 
this clause, the landlord shall be entitled to obtain 
possession thereof on the expiration of a period of six 
months in the case of residential premises and one year in 
the case of non- residential premises from the date of passing 
of eviction order.

Explanation I.- For the purposes of this clause and sections 
 23 to 26,-


<subsubsection><tid>1731317</tid>
<number>i</number>where the landlord in his application supported by 
an affidavit submits that the premises are required by 
him' for occupation for himself or for any member of 
his family dependent on him, the Rent Authority shall 
presume that the premises are so required;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1241301</tid>
<number>ii</number>premises let for a particular use may be required 
by the landlord for a different use if such use is 
permissible under law.
Explanation II.- For the purposes of this clause or section 
23, section 24, section 25 or section 26, an occupation by 
the landlord of any part of a building of which any premises 
let out by him forms a part shall not disentile him to 
recovery the possession of such premises,

Explanation III.- For the purposes of this clause," owner of 
the premises" includes a person who has been allotted such 
premises by the Delhi Development Authority or any other 
local authority by way of an agreement of hire- purchase, 
lease or sub- lease, even before the full ownership rights 
accrue to such hire- purchaser, lessee or sublessee, as the 
case may be.


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>40434</tid>
<number>3</number>In any proceeding for eviction under clause (e), (f), (g), 
 (h) or (r) of sub- section (2) of section 22 or section 23 or section 
 24 or section 25 or section 26, the Rent Authority may allow eviction 
from only a part of the premises if the landlord is agreeable to the 
same:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>20</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Provided that, in case of such part- eviction, the rent and other 
charges payable by the tenant will be decreased in proportion to the 
part vacated.


</section>

<section><tid>1125580</tid>
<number>4</number>No order for the recovery of possession in any proceeding 
under sub- section (2) shall be binding on any sub- tenant referred to 
in section 29 who has given notice of his sub- tenancy to the landlord 
under the provision of that section, unless the sub- tenant is made a 
party to the proceeding and the order for eviction is made binding on 
him.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1762886</tid>
<number> 23</number> Right to recover immediate possession of promises to accrue 
to certain persons.
<section><tid>1385232</tid>
<number>1</number>Where a person in occupation of any  
residential premises allotted to him by the Government or any local 
authority is required by, or in pursuance of, any general or special 
order made by that Government or authority to vacate such residential 
accommodation, or in default to incur certain obligations, on the 
ground that he or his spouse or his dependent son or daughter, as the 
case may be, owns, in the National Capital Territory of Delhi a 
residential accommodation, there shall accrue, on and from the date of 
such order, to such person, his spouse or his dependent son or 
daughter, as the case may be, notwithstanding anything contained 
elsewhere in this Act or in any other law for the time being in force 
or in any contract (whether express or implied), custom or usage to 
the contrary, a right to recover immediate possession of any premises 
let out by him, his spouse or his dependent son or daughter, as the 
case may be:
Provided that nothing in this section shall be construed as 
conferring a right on such person, his spouse or his dependent son or 
daughter, as the case may be, owning, in the National Capital 
Territory of Delhi; two or more dwelling houses, to recover the 
possession of more than one dwelling house and it shall be lawful for 
such person, his spouse or his dependent son or daughter, as the case 
may be, to indicate the dwelling house possession of which he intended 
to recover.

Explanation.- For the purposes of this sub- section, sections 24, 
 25 and 26, immediate possession shall mean possession recoverable on 
the expiry of sixty days from the date of order of eviction.


</section>

<section><tid>1048390</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a landlord exercises the right of recovery conferred 
on him by sub- section (1) or section 22, 24, 25 or 26 and he had 
received,-

<subsection><tid>1741206</tid>
<number>a</number>any rent in advance from the tenant, he shall, within a 
period of ninety days from the date of recovery of possession 
of the premises by him, refund to the tenant such amount as 
represents the rent payable for the unexpired portion of the 
contract, agreement or lease;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>176293</tid>
<number>b</number>any other payment, he shall, within the period 
aforesaid, refund to the tenant a sum which shall bear the 
same proportion to the total amount so received, as the 
unexpired portion of the contract, agreement or lease bears 
to the total period of contract, agreement or lease:
Provided that, if any default is made in making any refund as 
aforesaid, the landlord shall be liable to pay simple interest at the 
rate of fifteen per cent. per annum on the amount which he has omitted 
or failed to refund:


<pagefootnote><pagenum>21</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Provided further that it shall be permissible for the landlord to 
set off any amount which he is lawfully entitled to recover from the 
tenant against the refund due to the tenant.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>538586</tid>
<number> 24</number> Right to recover immediate possession of premises to accrue 
to members of the armed forces, etc.
<section><tid>95770</tid>
<number>1</number>Where a person- 

<subsection><tid>851165</tid>
<number>a</number>is a released or retired person from any armed forces 
and the premises let out by him, his spouse or his dependent 
son or daughter, as the case may be, are required for his own 
residence; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>127085</tid>
<number>b</number>is a dependent of a member of any armed forces who had 
been killed in action and the premises let out by such member 
are required for the residence of the family of such 
member, such person, his spouse or his dependent son or 
daughter, as the case may be, may, within one year from the 
date of his release or retirement from such armed forces or, 
as the case may be the date of death of such member, or 
within a period of one year from the date of commencement of 
this Act, whichever is later, apply to the Rent Authority for 
recovery of immediate possession of such premises

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1334440</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a person is a member of any of the armed forces and 
has a period of less than one year preceding the date of his 
retirement and the premises let out by him, his spouse or his 
dependent son or daughter, as the case may be, are required for his 
own residence after his retirement, he, his spouse or his dependent 
son or daughter, as the case may be, may, at any time, within a period 
of one year before the date of his retirement, apply to the' Rent 
Authority for recovery of immediate possession of such premises.

</section>

<section><tid>1182071</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the person, his spouse or his dependent son or daughter 
referred to in sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) has let out more 
than one premises, it shall be open to him, his spouse or his 
dependent son or daughter, as the case may be, to make an application 
under the sub- section in respect of only one at the premises chosen.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section," armed forces" 
means an armed force of the Union constituted under an Act of 
Parliament and includes a member of the police force constituted under 
section 3 of the Delhi Police Act, <year>1978</year>. (34 of <year>1978</year>.)




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>828425</tid>
<number> 25</number> Right to recover immediate possession of premises to to 
Central Government and State Government employees.
<section><tid>337481</tid>
<number>1</number>Where a  
person is a retired employee of the Central Government or of a State 
Government and the premises let out by him, his spouse or his 
dependent son or daughter are required for his own residence, such 
employee, his spouse or his dependent son or daughter, as the case may 
be, may, within one year from the date of his retirement or within a 
period of one year from the date of commencement of this Act, 
whichever is later, apply to the Rent Authority for recovery of 
immediate possession of such premises.

</section>

<section><tid>814315</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a person is an employee of the Central Government or 
of a State Government and has a period of less than one year preceding 
the date of his retirement and the premises let out by him or his 
spouse or dependent son or daughter are required by him for his own 
residence after his retirement, he, his spouse or his dependent son or 
daughter, as the case may be, may, at any time within a period of one 
year before the date of retirement, apply to the Rent Authority for 
recovery of immediate possession of such premises.

</section>

<section><tid>669939</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the person, his spouse or his dependent son or 
daughter referred to in sub- section (1) or in sub- section (2) has let 
out more than one

<pagefootnote><pagenum>22</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

premises, it shall be open to him, his spouse or his dependent son or 
daughter, as the case may be, to make an application under the sub- 
section in respect of only one of the premises chosen.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>924880</tid>
<number> 26</number> Right to recover immediate possession of premises to accrue 
to widows, handicapped persons and old persons.
<section><tid>138425</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the  
landlord is-

<subsection><tid>737753</tid>
<number>a</number>a widow and the premises let out by her, or by her 
husband,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>217964</tid>
<number>b</number>a handicapped person and the premises let out by him,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1543108</tid>
<number>c</number>a person who is of the age of sixty- five years or more 
and the premises lot out by him,
is required by her or him or for her or his family or for any one 
ordinarily living with her or him for residential or non- residential 
use, she or he may apply to the Rent Authority for recovery of 
immediate possession of such premises.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>645964</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the landlord referred to in sub- section (1) has let 
out more than one premises, it shall be open to him to make an 
application under that sub- section in respect of any one residential 
and one non- residential premises each chosen by him.
Explanation. I.-- For the purposes of this section," handicapped 
person" shall mean a person who is as if being an assessee entitled 
for the time being to the benefits of deduction under section 80U of 
the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year>. (43 of <year>1961</year>.)

Explanation II.- The right to recover possession under this 
section shall be exercisable only once in respect of each for 
residential and for non- residential use.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1557153</tid>
<number> 27</number> Payment of rent during eviction proceedings.
<section><tid>899125</tid>
<number>1</number>If, in any  
proceeding for the recovery of possession of any premises on any 
ground other than that referred to in clause (a) of sub- section (2) of 
section 22, the tenant contests the claim for eviction, the landlord 
may, at any stage of the proceeding, make an application to the Rent 
Authority for an order on the tenant to pay to the landlord the amount 
of rent legally recoverable from the tenant and the Rent Authority 
may, after giving the parties an opportunity of being heard, make an 
order directing the tenant to pay to the landlord or deposit with the 
Rent Authority within one month of the date of the order, an amount 
calculated at the rate of rent at which it was last paid for the 
period for which the arrears of the rent were legally recoverable from 
the tenant including the period subsequent thereto up to the end of 
the month previous to that in which payment or deposit is made and to 
continue to pay or deposit, month by month, by the fifteenth of each 
succeeding month, a sum equivalent to the rent at that rate.

</section>

<section><tid>1040043</tid>
<number>2</number>if, in any proceeding referred to in sub- section (7), there 
is any dispute as to the amount of rent payable by the tenant, the 
Rent Authority shall, within fifteen days of the date of the first 
bearing of the proceeding, fix an interim rent in relation to the 
premises to be paid or deposited in accordance with the provisions of 
sub- section (1), until the rent in relation thereto is determined 
having regard to the provisions of this Act, and the amount of 
arrears, if any, calculated on the basis of the rent so determined 
shall be paid or deposited by the tenant within one month of the date 
en which the standard rent is fixed or such further time as the Rent 
Authority may allow in this behalf.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>23</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1111697</tid>
<number>3</number>If, in any proceeding referred to in sub- section (1), there 
is any dispute as to the person or persons to whom the rent is 
payable, the Rent Authority may direct the tenant to deposit with the 
Rent Authority the amount payable by him under sub- section (1) or sub- 
section (2), as the case may be, and in such a case, no person shall 
be entitled to withdraw the amount in deposit until the Rent Authority 
decides the dispute and makes an order for payment of the same.

</section>

<section><tid>547728</tid>
<number>4</number>If the Rent Authority is satisfied that any dispute referred 
to in subsection (3) has been raised by a tenant for reasons which are 
false or frivolous, the Rent Authority may order the defence against 
eviction to be struck out and proceed with the hearing of the 
application.

</section>

<section><tid>439186</tid>
<number>5</number>If a tenant fails to make payment or deposit as required by 
this section, the Rent Authority may order the defence against 
eviction to be struck out and proceed with the hearing of the 
application.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>522965</tid>
<number> 28</number> Restrictions on subletting.
<section><tid>276676</tid>
<number>1</number>Where at any time before the  
 9th day of June, <year>1952</year>, a tenant has sub- let the whole or any part of 
the premises and the sub- tenant is, at the commencement of this Act, 
in occupation of such premises, then, notwithstanding that the consent 
of the landlord was not obtained for such sub- letting, the premises 
shall be deemed to have been lawfully sub- let.

</section>

<section><tid>392198</tid>
<number>2</number>No premises which have been sub- let either in whole or in 
part on or after the 9th day of June, <year>1952</year>, without obtaining the 
consent in writing of the landlord, shall be deemed to have been 
lawfully sub- let.

</section>

<section><tid>542375</tid>
<number>3</number>After the commencement of this Act, no tenant shall, without 
the previous consent in writing of the landlord,-

<subsection><tid>446958</tid>
<number>a</number>sub- let the whole or any part of the premises held by him 
as a tenant; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>890639</tid>
<number>b</number>transfer or assign his rights in the tenancy or in any 
part thereof.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1922056</tid>
<number>29</number>Notice of creation and termination of subtenancy. Where, 
after the commencement of this Act, any premises are sub- let either in 
whole or in part by the tenant with the previous consent in writing of 
the landlord, the tenant or the sub- tenant to whom the premises are 
sub- let may, in the prescribed manner, give notice to the landlord of 
the creation of the sub- tenancy within one month of the date of such 
sub- letting and notify the termination of such sub- tenancy within one 
month of such termination,


</article>



<article><tid>737378</tid>
<number>30</number>Subtenant to be tenant in certain cases. Where an order for 
eviction in respect of any premises is made under section 22 against a 
tenant but not against a sub- tenant referred to in section 29 and a 
notice of the sub- tenancy has been given to the landlord, the sub- 
tenant shall, with effect from the date of the order, be deemed to 
have become a tenant holding the premises in his occupation directly 
under the landlord on The same terms and conditions on which the 
tenant would have hold from the landlord, if the tenancy had 
continued.


</article>



<article><tid>1633810</tid>
<number> 31</number> Recovery of possession for occupation and re- entry.
<section><tid>850475</tid>
<number>1</number> 
When a landlord recovers possession of any premises from the tenant in 
pursuance of an order made under clause (r) of sub- section (2) of 
section 22, or under section 23, 24, 25, 26 or 33, the landlord shall 
not, except with the permission of the Rent Authority obtained in the 
prescribed manner, re- let the whole or any part of the premises within 
three years from the, date of obtaining such possession, and in 
granting such permission, the Rent Authority may direct the landlord 
to put such evicted tenant in possession of the premises:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>24</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Provided that where a landlord recovers possession of any 
premises from the tenant in pursuance of an order made under clause 
 (r) of sub- section (2) of section 22 for occupation after re- 
construction or re- building, the period of three years shall be 
reckoned from the date of completion of re- construction or re- 
building, as the case may be.


</section>

<section><tid>1221578</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a landlord recovers possession of any premises as 
aforesaid and the premises are not occupied by the landlord or by the 
person for whose benefit the premises are held, within two months of 
obtaining such possession, or the premises having been so occupied 
are, at any time within three years from the date of obtaining 
possession, re- let to any person other than the evicted tenant without 
obtaining the permission of the Rent Authority under subsection (1) or 
the possession of such premises is transferred to another person for 
reasons which do not appear to the Rent Authority to be bona fide, the 
Rent Authority may, on an application made to him in this behalf by 
such evicted tenant within such time as may be prescribed, direct the 
landlord to put the tenant in possession of the premises on the same 
terms and conditions if the premises are in the same form or on new 
terms and conditions if the premises have been re- constructed or re- 
built if he has not already built, acquired vacant possession of, or 
been allotted another premises or to pay him such compensation as the 
Rent Authority thinks fit or both, as the facts and circumstances of 
the case may warrant.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>500474</tid>
<number> 32</number> Recovery of possession for repairs and rebuilding and re- 
entry.
<section><tid>1037454</tid>
<number>1</number>In making any order on the grounds specified in clause (e),  
 (f)  (g), (h) or (i) of sub- section (2) of section 22 the Rent Authority 
shall fix the new rent and ascertain from the tenant whether he elects 
to be placed in occupation of the premises or part thereof from which 
he is to be evicted and if the tenant so elects, shall record the fact 
of the election in the order and specify therein the date on or before 
winch he shall deliver possession so as to enable the landlord to 
commence the work of repairs or' building or rebuilding, is the case 
may be, and the date before which the landlord shall deliver the 
possession of the said premises.

</section>

<section><tid>540056</tid>
<number>2</number>If the tenant delivers possession on or before the date 
specified in the order, the landlord shall, on the completion of the 
work of repairs or building or re- building, place the tenant in 
occupation of the premises or part thereof before the date specified 
in sub- section (1) or such extended date as may be specified by the 
Rent Authority by an order.

</section>

<section><tid>193777</tid>
<number>3</number>If, after the tenant has delivered possession on or before 
the date specified in the order, the landlord fails to commence the 
work of repairs or building or re- building within three months of the 
specified date, the Rent Authority may, on an application made to him 
in this behalf by the tenant, within such time as may be prescribed, 
order the landlord to place the tenant in occupation of the premises 
on the same terms and conditions and to pay to the tenant such 
compensation as the Rent Authority thinks fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1754557</tid>
<number>4</number>If the tenant has delivered possession on or before the date 
specified in the order and the landlord fails to place the tenant in 
occupation of the premises after repairs, building or re- building, as 
the case may be, in accordance with sub- section (2), the Rent 
Authority may, on an application made to him in this behalf by the 
tenant within such time as may be prescribed, order the landlord to 
place the in occupation of the premises on revised terms and 
conditions and to pay to the tenant such compensation as the Rent 
Authority thinks fit.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>25</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1465817</tid>
<number> 33</number> Recovery of possession in case of tenancies for limited 
period.
<section><tid>1430713</tid>
<number>1</number>Where a landlord does not require the whole or any part of  
any premises for a particular period, and after obtaining the 
permission of the Rent Authority in the, prescribed manner, lets the 
whole of the premises or part thereof as a residence for such period, 
not being more than five years, as may be agreed to in writing between 
the landlord and the tenant and the tenant does not, on the expiry of 
the said period, vacate such premises, then, notwithstanding anything 
contained in section 22 or in any other law, the Rent Authority may, 
on an application made to him in this behalf by the landlord within 
such time as may be prescribed, place the landlord in vacant 
possession of the premises or part thereof by evicting the tenant and 
every other person who may be in occupation of such Premises.

</section>

<section><tid>1155714</tid>
<number>2</number>The Rent Authority shall not-

<subsection><tid>855637</tid>
<number>i</number>grant permission under sub- section (1) in relation to a 
premises consecutively more than two times except for good 
and sufficient reasons to be recorded in writing.
Explanation.- A permission granted under sub- section (1) shall 
not be construed to be consecutive, if a period of five years 
or more has elapsed after the expiry of the last limited 
period tenancy;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1951318</tid>
<number>ii</number>entertain any application from the tenant calling in 
question the bonafides of the landlord in letting the 
premises under this secton.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>877481</tid>
<number>3</number>All applications made before the Rent Authority and appeals 
made before the Tribunal by the tenant shall abate on the expiry of 
period for which permission has been granted under sub- section (1).

</section>

<section><tid>1752068</tid>
<number>4</number>While making an order under sub- section (1), the Rent 
Authority may award to the landlord damages for the use or occupation 
of the premises at double the last rent paid by the tenant together 
with interest at the rate of fifteen per cent. per annum for the 
period from the date of such order till the date of actual vacation by 
the tenant.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1447961</tid>
<number> 34</number> Special provision for recovery of possession in certain 
cases. Where the landlord in respect of any premises is any 
company or other body corporate of any public institution, then 
notwithstanding anything contained in section 22 or in any other law, 
the Rent Authority may. on an application made to him in this behalf 
by such landlord. place the landlord in vacant possession of such 
premises, by evicting the tenant and every other person who may be in 
occupation thereof, if the Rent Authority is satisfied that-
' (a) the tenant to Whom such premises were let for use as a 
residence at a time when he was in the service or employment 
of the landlord, has ceased to be in such service. or 
employment and the premise,, are required for the use of 
employees of such landlord; or

<section><tid>1529177</tid>
<number>b</number>the tenant has acted in contravention of the terms, 
express or implied, under which he was authorised to occupy 
such premises; or

</section>

<section><tid>1652835</tid>
<number>c</number>any other person is in unauthorised occupation of such 
premises; or

</section>

<section><tid>607195</tid>
<number>d</number>the premises are required bonafide by the landlord for 
the use of employees of such landlord or. in the case of a 
public institution, for the furtherance of its activities.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>26</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Explanation.- For the purposes of this section," public 
institution" includes any educational institution, library, hospital 
and charitable dispensary but does no include any such institution set 
up by a private trust.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>904640</tid>
<number>35</number>Permission to construct additional structures. Where the 
landlord proposes to make any improvement in, or construct any 
additional structure on, any building which has been let, to a tenant 
and the tenant refuses to allow the landlord to make such improvement 
or construct such additional structure and the Rent Authority, on an 
application, made to him in this behalf by the landlord, is satisfied 
that the, landlord is ready and willing to commence the work and that 
such work will not cause any undue hardship to the tenant, Rent 
Authority may permit the landlord to do such Work and may make such 
other order as be thinks fit in the circumstances of the case.


</article>



<article><tid>1599225</tid>
<number> 36</number> Special provision regarding vacant building sites. 
Notwithstanding anything contained in section 22, where any premises 
which have been let comprise vacant land upon which it is permissible 
under the building regulations or municipal bye- laws, for the time 
being in force, to erect any building. whether for use as a residence 
or for any other purpose and the landlord proposing to erect such 
building is unable to obtain possession of the land from the tenant by 
agreement with him and the Rent Authority, on an application made to 
him in this behalf by the landlord, is satisfied that the landlord is 
ready and willing commence the work and that the severance of the 
vacant land from the rest of the premises will not cause undue 
hardship to the tenant, the Rent Authority may-
<section><tid>1048348</tid>
<number>a</number>direct such severance

</section>

<section><tid>962725</tid>
<number>b</number>place the landlord in possession of the vacant land;

</section>

<section><tid>20972</tid>
<number>c</number>determine the rent payable by the tenant in respect of 
the rest of the premises; and

</section>

<section><tid>19133</tid>
<number>d</number>make such other order as he thinks fit in the 
circumstances of the case.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1079609</tid>
<number>37</number>Vacant possession to land lord. Notwithstanding anything 
contained in any other law, where the interest of a tenant in any 
premises is determined for any reason Whatsoever and any order is made 
by the Rent Authority tinder this Act for the recovery of possession 
of such premises, the order shall, subject to the Provisions of 
section 30, be binding on all persons who may be in occupation of the 
premises and vacant possession thereof shall be given to the landlord 
by evicting all such persons therefrom:
Provided that nothing in this section shall apply to any person 
who has an independent title to such premises.

CHAP

HOTELS AND LODGING HOUSES

CHAPTER V

HOTELS AND LODGING HOUSES



</article>



<article><tid>725687</tid>
<number>38</number>Application of the Chapter. The provisions of this Chapter 
shall apply to all hotels and lodging houses in the areas which the 
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
specify:
Provided that if the Central Government is of opinion that it 
would not be desirable in the public interest to make the provisions 
of this Chapter applicable to any class of hotels or lodging houses, 
it may, by notification in the Official Gazette, exempt such class of 
hotels or lodging houses from the operation of this Chapter.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>27</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>586989</tid>
<number> 39</number> Fixing of fair rate.
<section><tid>973795</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the Rent Authority, on a  
written or otherwise, has reason to believe that the charges made for 
board or lodging or any other service provided in any hotel or lodging 
house are excessive, he may fix a fair rate to be charged for board, 
lodging or other services provided in the hotel or lodging house and 
in fixing such fair rate, specify separately the rate for lodging, 
board or other services.

</section>

<section><tid>786475</tid>
<number>2</number>In determining the fair rate under sub- section (1), the Rent 
Authority shall have regard to the circumstances of the, case and to 
the prevailing rate of charges for the same or similar accommodation, 
board and service, during the twelve months immediately preceding the 
 1st day of June, <year>1951</year>, and any general increase in the cost of living 
after that date.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>682820</tid>
<number>40</number>Revision of fair rate. On a written application from the 
manager of a hotel or the owner of a lodging house or otherwise, the 
Rent Authority may, from time tO time, revise the fair rate to be 
charged for board, lodging or other service in a hotel or lodging 
house, and fix such rate as he may deem fit having regard to any 
general rise or fall in the cost of living which may have occurred 
after the fixing of fair rate.,


</article>



<article><tid>9373</tid>
<number> 41</number> Charges in excess of fair rate not recoverable. When the 
Rent, Authority has determined the fair rate of charges in respect 
of a hotel or lodging houses,-
<section><tid>375956</tid>
<number>a</number>the manager of the hotel or the owner of the lodging 
house, as the case may be, shall not charge any amount in 
excess of the fair rate and shall not, except with tile 
previous Written permission of the Rent Authority, withdraw 
from the lodger any concession or services allowed at the 
time when Me Relic Authority determined the fair rate;

</section>

<section><tid>1935052</tid>
<number>b</number>any agreement for the payment of any charges in excess 
of such fair rate shall be void in respect of such excess and 
shall be construed as if it were an agreement for payment of 
the said fair rate;

</section>

<section><tid>1960748</tid>
<number>c</number>any sum paid' by a lodger in excess of the fair rate 
shall be recoverable by him at any time within a period of 
six months from the date of the payment from the manager of 
the hotel or the owner of the lodging house or Ills legal 
representatives and may, without prejudice to any other mode 
of recovery, be deducted by such lodger from any amount 
payable by him to such manager or owner.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1112236</tid>
<number> 42</number> Recovery of possession by manager of a hotel or the owner of 
a lodging house. Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, the 
manager of a hotel or the owner of a lodging house shall, be entitled 
to recover possession of the accommodation provided by him to a lodger 
on obtaining a certificate from the Rent Authority certifying---
<section><tid>1399657</tid>
<number>a</number>that the lodger has be 6n guilty of conduct which is a 
nuisance or which causes annoyance to any adjoining or 
neighbouring lodger.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this clause," nuisance" 
shall be deemed to include any act which constitutes an 
offence under the Immoral Traffic (Prevention) Act, <year>1956</year>; 
 (104 of <year>1956</year>.)


</section>

<section><tid>308604</tid>
<number>b</number>that the accommodation is reasonably and bona fide 
required by the owner of the hotel or lodging house, as the 
case may be, either for his own occupation or for the 
Occupation of any person for whose benefit the accommodation 
is held, or any other cause; which may be deemed satisfactory 
to the Rent Authority;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>28</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>714826</tid>
<number>c</number>that the lodger has failed to vacate the accommodation 
on the termination of the period of the agreement in respect 
thereof;

</section>

<section><tid>703425</tid>
<number>d</number>that the lodger has done any act which is inconsistent 
with the purpose for which the accommodation was given to him 
or which is likely to affect adversely or substantially the 
owner' s interest therein;

</section>

<section><tid>347266</tid>
<number>e</number>that the lodger has failed to pay the rent due from 
him.
CHAP

RENT AUTHORITIES

CHAPTER VI

RENT AUTHORITIES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1922856</tid>
<number> 43</number> Appointment of Rent Authorities and additional Rent 
Authorities.
<section><tid>871494</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by notification in the  
Official Gazette, appoint as many Rent Authorities as it thinks fit; 
and define the local limits within which, or the hotelsa and lodging 
houses in respect of which, each Rent Authority, shall exercise the 
powers conferred, and perform[ lie duties imposed, on Rent Authorities 
by or under this Act and in respect of all tenancy matters relating to 
premises and tenancies covered under clauses (c) to (i) of sub- section 
 (1) of election 3 by or under the Transfer of Property Act, <year>1882</year>. (4  
  of <year>1882</year>.)

</section>

<section><tid>1613479</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may also, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, appoint as many additional Rent Authorities as it 
thinks fit and an additional Rent Authority shall perform such of the 
functions of the Rent Authority as may; subject to the control of the 
Central Government, be assigned to him in writing by the Rent 
Authority and in the discharge of these functions, an additional Rent 
Authority shall halve and shall exercise the same powers and discharge 
the same duties as the Rent Authority.

</section>

<section><tid>1629997</tid>
<number>3</number>A person shall not be qualified for appointment, as a Rent 
Authority or an additional Rent Authority unless he has for at least 
ten years held a judicial office in India or has for at least ten 
years been practising as an advocate or a pleader in India.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>709932</tid>
<number> 44</number> Powers of Rent Authority.
<section><tid>1439149</tid>
<number>1</number>The Rent Authority may- 

<subsection><tid>666813</tid>
<number>a</number>transfer any proceeding pending before him for disposal 
to any additional Rent Authority, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1128686</tid>
<number>b</number>withdraw any proceeding pending before any additional 
Rent Authority and dispose it of himself or transfer the 
proceeding for disposal to any other additional Rent 
Authority.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1335778</tid>
<number>2</number>The Rent Authority shall have the same powers as are vested 
in a civil court under the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year>, (5 of <year>1908</year>.) 
when trying a suit, in respect, of the following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>401261</tid>
<number>a</number>summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person 
and examining him on oath;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1467902</tid>
<number>b</number>requiring the discovery and production of documents;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>973167</tid>
<number>c</number>issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1587438</tid>
<number>d</number>any other matter which may be prescribed,
and any proceeding before the Rent Authority shall be deemed to be a 
Judicial proceeding within the meaning of section 193 and section 228, 
and for the purpose of section 196, of the Indian Penal Code, (45 of  
  <year>1860</year>.) and the Rent


<pagefootnote><pagenum>29</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Authority shall be deemed to be a civil court for the purpose of 
section 195 but not for the purposes of Chapter XXVI of the Code of 
Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year>. (2 of <year>1974</year>.)


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>751727</tid>
<number>3</number>For the purposes of holding any inquiry or discharging any 
duty under this Act, the Rent Authority may,-

<subsection><tid>451295</tid>
<number>a</number>after giving not less than twenty- flour hours' notice 
in writing, enter and inspect or authorise any officer 
subordinate to him to enter and inspect any premises at any 
time between sunrise and sunset; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1240716</tid>
<number>b</number>by written order, require any person to produle for his 
inspection all such accounts, books or other documents 
relevant to the inquiry at such time and at such place as may 
be specified in the order.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>440289</tid>
<number>4</number>The Rent Authority may, if he thinks fit, appoint one or 
more persons having special knowledge of the matter under 
consideration as an assessor or assessors to advise him, on the 
proceeding before him.

</section>

<section><tid>1538724</tid>
<number>5</number>Any fine imposed by a Rent Authority under this Act shall 
be, paid by the person fined Within such time as may be allowed by the 
Rent Authority and the Rent Authority may, for good and sufficient 
reason, extend the time, and in default of such payment, the amount 
shall be recoverable as fine under the provisions of the Code of 
Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year>, (2 of <year>1974</year>.) and the Rent Authority shall 
be deemed to be a magistrate under the said Code for the purposes of 
such recovery.

</section>

<section><tid>711725</tid>
<number>6</number>An order made by a Rent Authority or the Tribunal under this 
Act or an order made by a Controller, or an order passed on appeal, 
under the Delhi Rent Control Act, <year>1958</year> (2 of <year>1958</year>.) shall be 
executable by a Rent Authority designated by the Tribunal in this 
behalf and for', the purpose the Rent Authority so designated shall 
have all the powers of a civil court.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1746765</tid>
<number> 45</number> Procedure to be followed by Rent Authority.
<section><tid>679933</tid>
<number>1</number>No order  
which prejudicially affects any person shall be made by the Rent 
Authority under this Act without giving him a reasonable opportunity 
of showing cause against the order proposed to be made and until his 
objections, if any, and any evidence he may produce in support If the 
same have been considered by the Rent Authority.

</section>

<section><tid>207784</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to any rules that may be made under this Act and the 
other provisions of this Act, the Rent Authority shall, while holding 
an inquiry in any proceeding before him, follow as far as may be the 
practice and procedure of a court of small causes, including the 
recording of evidence.

</section>

<section><tid>1853040</tid>
<number>3</number>The Rent Authority shall not ordinarily allow more than 
three adjournments at the request of a party throughout the 
proceedings and in case he decides to do so, he shall inform the 
Chairman the reasons therefor and order to pay the other party the 
reasonable cast.

</section>

<section><tid>1465470</tid>
<number>4</number>The Rent Authority shall issue summons in relation to every 
application under this Act in the form specified in Schedule IV.

</section>

<section><tid>819584</tid>
<number>5</number>The Rent Authority shall, in addition to, and simultaneously 
with the issue of summons for service on the opposite party, also 
direct the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>30</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

summons to be served by registered post, acknowledgment due, addressed 
to the opposite party or his agent empowered to accept the service at 
the place where the opposite party or his agent actually and 
voluntarily resides or carries on business or personally works for 
gain and may, if the circumstances of the case so require, also direct 
the publication of the summons in a newspaper circulating in the 
locality in which the opposite party is last known to have resided or 
carried on business or personally worked for gain.


</section>

<section><tid>895145</tid>
<number>6</number>When an acknowledgment purporting to be signed by the 
opposite party or his agent is received by the Rent Authority or the 
registered article containing the summons is received back with an 
endorsement purporting to have been made by a postal employee to the 
effect that the opposite party or his agent had refused to take 
delivery of the registered article, the Rent Authority may declare 
that there has been a valid service of summons.

</section>

<section><tid>482289</tid>
<number>7</number> (a) An application under section 21 shall be dealt with in, 
accordance with the procedure specified in this sub- section.

<subsection><tid>858911</tid>
<number>b</number>The Rent Authority shall commence the hearing of the 
application within seven days of the filing thereof and shall, dispose 
of the same within thirty days of starting of such hearing, failing 
such commencement of hearing or disposal of application within such 
time, the Rent Authority shall inform the Chairman of the Tribunal the 
reasons therefor.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1664014</tid>
<number>8</number> (a) Every application by a landlord for the recovery of 
possession of any premises on the ground specified in clause (e) or 
clause or clause (r) of sub- section (2) of section 22, or under 
section 23, or under section 24, or under section 25, or under section 
26, or under sect- Ion 33, shall be dealt with in accordance with the 
procedure specified in this sub- section.

<subsection><tid>1616326</tid>
<number>b</number>The tenant on whom the summons is duly served (whether in  
  the ordinary way or by registered post) in the form specified in 
Schedule IV shall not contest the prayer for eviction from the 
premises unless he files an affidavit stating the grounds on which he 
seeks to con. test the application for eviction and obtains leave from 
the Rent Authority as hereinafter provided; and in default of his 
appearance in Pursuance of the summons or his obtaining such leave, 
the statement made by the landlord in the application for eviction 
shall be deemed to be admitted by the tenant and the applicant shall 
be entitled to an order for eviction on the ground aforesaid.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>488885</tid>
<number>c</number>The Rent Authority shall give to the tenant leave to contest 
the application if the affidavit filed by the tenant discloses such 
facts as would desentitle the landlord from obtaining an order for the 
recovery of possession of the premises.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>747614</tid>
<number>d</number>Where leave is granted to the tenant to contest the 
application the Rent Authority shall ordinarily commence the hearing 
of the application within seven days of the grant of such leave and 
shall provide day to day hearing and shall dispose of the application 
within thirty days of starting of such hearing, failing such 
commencement of hearing or disposal of application within such time, 
the Rent Authority shall inform the Chairman of the Tribunal the 
reasons therefor.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>31</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>560184</tid>
<number>e</number>Where the leave to contest under clause is denied to the 
tenant, he may file an application for review before the Rent 
Authority Within ten days of such denial and the Rent Authority shall 
endeavour to dispose of such application within seven days of its 
filing.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1411454</tid>
<number>9</number>Every application made to the Rent Authority shall be heard 
as expeditiously or, possible and, subject lo the provisions of sub- 
sections (7) and (8), endeavour shall be made to conclude the hearing 
and to dispose of the application within six months of it being filed.

</section>

<section><tid>1945823</tid>
<number>10</number>In all proceedings before him, the Rent Authority shall 
consider the question of costs and award such costs to or against any 
party as that Rent Authority considers reasonable.
CHAP

DELHI RENT TRIBUNAL

CHAPTER VII

DELHI RENT TRIBUNAL




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1816252</tid>
<number>46</number>Establishment of Delhi Rent Tribunal. The Central Government 
shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, establish a Tribunal, 
to be known as the Delhi Rent Tribunal to exercise the jurisdiction, 
powers and authority conferred on it by or under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1001848</tid>
<number> 47</number> Composition of Tribunal and Benches thereof.
<section><tid>710773</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Tribunal shall consist of a Chairman and such number of other Members, 
being not less than three, as the Central Government may deem fit and, 
subject to the other provisions of this Act, the jurisdiction, powers 
and authority of the Tribunal may be exercised by the Benches thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>329339</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the other provisions of this Act, a Bench shall 
consist of one or more Members, as the Chairman may decide in 
accordance with the, rules as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>153254</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), the 
Chairman may transfer other Member from one Bench to another Bench.

</section>

<section><tid>1770994</tid>
<number>4</number>Subject to the other provisions of this Act, the Benches of 
the Tribunal shall ordinarily sit at such places in the National 
Capital Territory of Delhi as the Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, specify.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>856129</tid>
<number> 48</number> Qualifications for appointment as Chairman and Members.
<section><tid>461121</tid>
<number>1</number> 
A person shall not be qualified for appointment as the Chairman unless 
he-

<subsection><tid>746200</tid>
<number>a</number>is, or has been, a Judge of a High Court; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1945118</tid>
<number>b</number>has, for- at least three years, held the office of a 
Member; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>225676</tid>
<number>c</number>is, or has been, a Member of the Indian Legal Service 
and has held, for at least three years, a post in Grade I of 
that Service; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>801626</tid>
<number>d</number>has, for at least three years, held the post of a 
Secretary in the Law Department of a State Government.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1684171</tid>
<number>2</number>A person shall not be qualified for appointment as a Member, 
unless be-

<subsection><tid>1030749</tid>
<number>a</number>has for at least eight years, held the Post of Rent 
Authority; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>349416</tid>
<number>b</number>has, for at least five years, held the post of a District 
Judge; or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>32</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1249979</tid>
<number>c</number>is, or has been, a Member of the Indian Legal Service 
in Grade I of that Service; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>986168</tid>
<number>d</number>has, for at least two years, held the post of a 
Secretary in me Law Department of a State Government; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>289738</tid>
<number>e</number>has, for at least ten years, been an Advocate.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1892925</tid>
<number>3</number>Subject to the provisions of sub- sections (4) and (5), the 
Chairman and other Members of the Tribunal shall be appointed by the 
President of India after consultation with the Chief Justice of India.

</section>

<section><tid>787799</tid>
<number>4</number>The Chairman and other Members shall be appointed by the 
President of India on the recommendation of a Selection Committee ap- 
pointed by the Central Government consisting of the following, 
namely:--

<subsection><tid>406066</tid>
<number>a</number>Chief Justice of the High Court of Delhi or his nominee 
who shall be a sitting Judge of the High Court;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1950753</tid>
<number>b</number>Chairman of the Tribunal (except in case of the  
  appointment of the Chairman);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1827871</tid>
<number>c</number>Secretary to the Government of India in the Ministry 
dealing with Legal Affairs;.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>753094</tid>
<number>d</number>Secretary to the Government of India in Ministry 
dealing with Urban Development;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1005811</tid>
<number>e</number>Chief Secretary to the Government of the National 
Capital Territory of Delhi.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1230561</tid>
<number>5</number>The Selection Committee shall recommend a person for 
appointment as Chairman or other Member from amongst the persons on 
the list of candidates prepared by the Ministry dealing with Urban 
Development in consultation with the Department dealing with Justice 
of the Government of India in accordance with the procedure as may be 
prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1225833</tid>
<number> 49</number> Term of office. The Chairman or any other Member shall bold 
office as such for a term of five years from the date on which he 
enters upon his office, but shall be eligible for re- appointment for 
another term of five years:
Provided that no Chairman, or any other Member shall hold office 
as such after he has attained,-

<section><tid>1704294</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of the Chairman, the age of sixty- five 
years; and

</section>

<section><tid>1663681</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of any other Member, the age of sixty- two 
years.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1516208</tid>
<number> 50</number> Senior most Member to act as Chairman or discharge his 
functions in certain circumstances.
<section><tid>293459</tid>
<number>1</number>In the, event of occurrence of  
any vacancy in the office of the Chairman by reason of his death, 
resignation or' Otherwise, the seniormost Member shall act as Chairman 
until the date on which a new Chairman, appointed in accordance with 
the provisions; of this Act to fill such vacancy, enters upon his 
office.

</section>

<section><tid>1649003</tid>
<number>2</number>When the Chairman is unable to discharge his functions owing 
to his absence, illness or any other cause, the seniormost Member 
shall discharge the function of the Chairman until the date on which 
the Chairman resumes his office.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>33</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1425476</tid>
<number>51</number>Salaries allowances and other terms and conditions of 
services of Chairman and other Members. The salaries and allowances 
payable to, the other terms and conditions of service (inmcluding,  
  pensions, gratuity and other retirement benefits) of, the Chairman and 
other Mambers shall be such as may he prescribed:
Provided that neither the salary and allowances nor the other 
terms and conditions of service of the Chairman or any other Members 
shall be varied to his disadvantage after his appointment.



</article>



<article><tid>1370038</tid>
<number> 52</number> Resignation and removal.
<section><tid>393163</tid>
<number>1</number>The Chair or any other Member  
may, by notice in writing under his hand addressed to the President of 
India, resign his office:
Provided that the Chairman or any other Member shall, unless he 
is permitted by the President of India to relinquish his office 
sooner, continue to hold office until the expiry of three months from 
the date of receipt of such notice or until a person duly appointed as 
his successor enters upon his office or until the expiry of his term 
of office, whichever is the earliest.


</section>

<section><tid>903489</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chairman or any other Member shall not be removed from 
his office except by an order made by the President of India on the 
ground of proved misbehaviour or incapacity after an inquiry made by a 
Judge of the Supreme Court in which such Chairman or other Member had 
been informed of the charges against him and given a reasonable 
opportunity of being heard in respect of those charges.

</section>

<section><tid>425888</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government may, by rules, regulate the procedure 
for the investigation of misbehaviour or incapacity of the Chairman or 
other Member referred to in sub- section (2).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1170963</tid>
<number> 53</number> Provision as to the holding of offices by Chairman and 
Member on ceasing to be such Chairman or Member. On ceasing to hold 
office,-
<section><tid>1766738</tid>
<number>a</number>the Chairman of the Tribunal shall be ineligible for 
further employment either under the Government of India or 
under the Government of a State;

</section>

<section><tid>1249059</tid>
<number>b</number>a Member, other than the Chairman, of the Tribunal 
shall, subject to the other provisions of this Act, be 
eligible for appointment as the Chairman or Member of any 
other tribunal, but not for any other employment either under 
the Government of India of under the Government of a State;

</section>

<section><tid>1476462</tid>
<number>c</number>the Chairman or other Member shall not appear, act or 
plead before the Tribunal.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section, employment under the 
Government of India or under the Government of a State includes 
employment under any local or other authority within the territory of 
India or under the control of the Government of India or under any 
corporation or society owned or controlled by the Government.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>34</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1791090</tid>
<number>54</number>Financial--------------------------- Chairman. The Chairman 
shall exercise such financial and administrative powers over the 
Benches as may be prescribed:
Provided that the Chairman shall have authority to delegate such 
of his financial and administrative powers as be may think fit to any 
other Member or any officer of the Tribunal, subject to the condition 
that such Member or officer shall, while exercising such delegated 
powers, continue to act under the direction, control and supervision 
of the Chairman.



</article>



<article><tid>1790026</tid>
<number> 55</number> Staff of the tribunal.
<section><tid>467110</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government shall  
determine the nature and categories of the officers and other 
employees required to assist the Tribunal in the discharge of its 
functions and provide the Tribunal with such officers and other 
employees as it may think fit.

</section>

<section><tid>657772</tid>
<number>2</number>The salaries and allowances and conditions of service of the 
officers and other employees of the Tribunal shall be such as may be 
prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>410788</tid>
<number>3</number>The officers and other employees of the Tribunal shall 
discharge their functions under the general superintendence of the 
Chairman.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1264260</tid>
<number>56</number>Distribution of business among the Benches. The Chairman may 
make provisions as to the distribution of the business of the Tribunal 
among its Benches.


</article>



<article><tid>708451</tid>
<number> 57</number> Jurisdiction, Powers and Authority of the Tribunal.
<section><tid>1971927</tid>
<number>1</number>Save  
as otherwise expressly provided in this Act, the Tribunal shall 
exercise, on and from the date with effect from which it is establish- 
ed under section 46, all the jurisdiction, powers and authority 
exercisable immediately before that date by all courts (except the  
  Supreme Court) In relation to--

<subsection><tid>79235</tid>
<number>a</number>all appeals from the orders of the Rent Authority under 
this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1420638</tid>
<number>b</number>any other matter arising from the provisions of this 
Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>153347</tid>
<number>c</number>review of its own orders and decisions.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1671072</tid>
<number>2</number>The Tribunal may, either on its own motion or on application 
of any of the parties and after notice to the parties and after 
hearing such of them as it may desire to be heard, call for records of 
any case pending before the; Rent Authority under this Act, and either 
itself try the case or give direction for disposal of the case by such 
Rent Authority.

</section>

<section><tid>1280820</tid>
<number>3</number>The Tribunal shall have powers to effect a conciliation 
between the parties in any case pending before It.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1962483</tid>
<number> 58</number> Power to punish for contempt. The Tribunal shall have, and 
exercise, the same, jurisdiction, powers and authority in respect of 
contempt of itself or of the Rent Authority under this Act as a High 
Court has and may exercise and, for this purpose, the provisions of 
the Contempt of Courts Act, <year>1971</year>, (70 of <year>1971</year>.) shall have effect 
subject to the modification that-
<section><tid>1994012</tid>
<number>a</number>the references therein to a High Court shall be 
construed as including a reference to the Tribunal;

</section>

<section><tid>1937081</tid>
<number>b</number>in section, 15 of the said Act, the references to the 
Advocate- General shall be construed as a reference to the 
Attorney- General or the Solicitor- General or the Additional 
Solicitor- General;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>35</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1740668</tid>
<number>c</number>in sections 6, 10, 11A, 12, 15 and 17 of the said Act, 
the references therein to subordinate Court or Court 
subordinate, shall be construed as including a reference to 
Rent Authority under this Act; and

</section>

<section><tid>107087</tid>
<number>d</number>the references, in section 14 of the said Act, to Chief 
Justice, Judge or Judges shall be construed as including a 
reference to Chairman, Member or Members.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1341521</tid>
<number> 59</number> Application to Tribunal.
<section><tid>1694241</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the other provisions  
of this Act, a person aggrieved by any order pertaining to any matter 
within the jurisdiction of the Tribunal may make an application to the 
Tribunal for the redressal of his grievance.

</section>

<section><tid>776736</tid>
<number>2</number>Every application under sub- section (1) shall be in such 
form and be accompanied by such affidavits, documents or any other 
evidence and by such fee in respect of the filing or such 
application and by such other fees for the service or execution of, 
processes as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>428247</tid>
<number>3</number>On receipt of an application under sub- section (1), the 
Tribunal shall, if satisfied after such inquiry as it may deem 
necessary, that the application is a fit case for adjudication or 
trial by it, admit such application: but where the Tribunal is not so 
satisfied; it may summarily reject the application after recording its 
reasons.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1308883</tid>
<number> 60</number> Procedure of Tribunal.
<section><tid>738519</tid>
<number>1</number>The Tribunal shall not be bound  
by the procedure laid down in the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year>, (5 of  
  <year>1908</year>.) but shall be guided by the principles of natural justice and, 
subject to the other provisions of this Act and of any rules made by 
the Central Government, the Tribunal shall have power to lay down and 
regulate its own procedure, including the fixing of places and times 
of its inquiry and deciding whether to sit in public or in private.

</section>

<section><tid>744499</tid>
<number>2</number>The Tribunal shall decide every application made to it as 
expeditiously as possible and on a persual of documents, affidavits 
and written representations and after hearing such oral arguments as 
may be advanced:
Provided that where the Tribunal deems it necessary, for reasons 
to be recorded in writing, it may allow oral evidence to be adduced.


</section>

<section><tid>602629</tid>
<number>3</number>The Tribunal shall, have,' for the purposes of discharging 
its functions under this Act, the same powers as are vested in a civil 
court under the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year>, (5 of <year>1908</year>.) while 
trying a suit, in respect of the following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>249493</tid>
<number>a</number>summoning and enforcing the attendance of any parson 
and examining him on oath;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1746853</tid>
<number>b</number>requiring the discovery and production of documents;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>959892</tid>
<number>c</number>receiving evidence on affidavits;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1301006</tid>
<number>d</number>subject to the provisions of sections 123 and 12A of 
the Indian Evidence Act, <year>1872</year>, (1 of <year>1872</year>.) requisitioning 
any public record or document or copy of such record or 
document from any office;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>89929</tid>
<number>e</number>issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses or 
documents;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>36</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>242201</tid>
<number>f</number>reviewing its orders and decisions;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1420541</tid>
<number>g</number>dismissing an application or appeal for default or 
deciding it ex parte;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1427210</tid>
<number>h</number>setting aside any order of dismissal of any application 
or appeal for default or any order passed by it ex parte;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>998438</tid>
<number>i</number>for the execution of its orders and decisions and 
orders and decisions of Rent Authority under this Act, like 
decree of a civil court without reference to any civil court; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>781954</tid>
<number>j</number>any other matter which may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1233233</tid>
<number>4</number>No adjournment shall be granted by the Tribunal without 
recording the reasons justifying the grant of such adjournment in the 
case and costs shall be awarded, if a party asks for adjournment for 
third and subsequent times.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1535727</tid>
<number> 61</number> Appeal to the Tribunal.
<section><tid>29443</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person aggrieved by an order  
passed or a decision made by the Rent Authority may, within thirty 
days from the date of such order or decision, prefer an appeal in 
writing to the Tribunal in the prescribed form and accompanied by a 
certified copy of the order or decision appealed against and by such 
fees as may be prescribed:
Provided that an appeal may be admitted after the expiry of the 
said period of thirty days, if the appellant satisfies the Tribunal 
that he had sufficient cause for not preferring the appeal within the 
specified period


</section>

<section><tid>1329377</tid>
<number>2</number>In computing the aforesaid period of thirty days, the time 
taken in obtaining a certified copy of the order or decision appealed 
against shall be excluded.

</section>

<section><tid>959516</tid>
<number>3</number>An appeal shall lie to the Tribunal from every order or 
decision of Rent Authority made under this Act both on question of law 
and facts:
Provided that no appeal shall lie from an order or decision of 
the Rent Authority made under section 11, section 12, section 21 or 
section 33 of this Act.


</section>

<section><tid>360984</tid>
<number>4</number>On receipt of an appeal under sub- section (1), the Tribunal 
shall, if satisfied after such inquiry as it may deem necessary, that 
the appeal is a fit case for adjudication by it admit such appeal; but 
where the Tribunal is not so satisfied, it may summarily reject the 
appeal after recording its reason.

</section>

<section><tid>1739703</tid>
<number>5</number>The Tribunal shall endeavour to dispose of an appeal against 
the order or decision of the Rent Authority under clause (e), clause 
 (f) or clause (r) of sub- section (2) of section 22 or a section 23, 
24, 25, 26 or, 33 within one month of filing of such appeal.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>153006</tid>
<number> 62</number> Conditions as to making of interim orders. Notwithstanding 
anything contained in any other provisions of this Act or in any other 
law for the time being in force, no interim order (whether by way of  
  injunction or stay or in any other manner) shall be made on, or in any 
proceeding relating to, an application or appeal unless-
<section><tid>1949805</tid>
<number>a</number>copies of such application or appeal and of all 
documents in support of the plea for such interim order are 
furnished to the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>37</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

party against whom such application is made or appeal is 
preferred; and


</section>

<section><tid>1602511</tid>
<number>b</number>opportunity is given to such party to be heard in the 
matter:
Provided that the Tribunal may dispense with the requirements of 
clauses (a) and (b) and make an interim order as an exceptional 
measure if it is satisfied, for reasons to be recorded in writing that 
it is necessary so to do for preventing any loss being caused to the 
applicant or the appellant, as the case may be, which cannot be 
adequately compensated in money; but any such interim order shall, if 
it is not sooner vacated, cease to have effect on the expiry of a 
period of fourteen days from the date on which it is made unless the 
said requirement' s have been complied with before the expiry of that 
period and the Tribunal has continued the operation of the interim 
order.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1855484</tid>
<number>63</number>Right of applicant to take assistance of legal practitioner. 
A person making an application or preferring an appeal to the Tribunal 
under this Act may either appear in person or take the assistance of a 
legal practitioner of his choice to present his case before the 
Tribunal


</article>



<article><tid>220490</tid>
<number>64</number>Power of Chairman to transfer cases from one Bench to 
another. On the application of any of the parties and after notice to 
the parties, and after hearing such of them as he may desire to be 
heard, or on his own motion without such notice, the Chairman may 
transfer any case pending before one Bench, for disposal, to any other 
Bench.


</article>



<article><tid>180708</tid>
<number>65</number>Decision to be try majority. The decision of a Bench 
consisting of more than one Member on any point shall, where there is 
a majority, be according to the opinion of the majority, and where 
there is no majority and the Members are equally divided in their 
opinion, they shall draw up a statement of" the case setting forth the 
point or points on which they differ and make a reference to the 
Chairman, and on receipt of such reference, the Chairman may arrange 
for the hearing of such point or points by one or more of the other 
Members (including, if be did not preside over such Bench, himself) 
and such point or points shall be decided according to the opinion by 
the majority of the Members who have heard the case, including those 
who had first heard it.


</article>



<article><tid>590280</tid>
<number>66</number>Exclusion of jurisdiction of courts except the Supreme 
Court. On and from the date from which any jurisdiction, powers and 
authority becomes exercisable under this Act by the Tribunal in 
relation to any matter, no court (except the Supreme Court) shall 
have, or be entitled to exercise any jurisdiction,, powers or 
authority in relation, to much matter.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>38</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>28560</tid>
<number> 67</number> Transfer of pending cases. On the Commencement of this Act, 
all cases pertaining to the matters in respect of which the Tribunal 
shall have jurisdiction under this Act including the cages under the 
Transfer of Property Act, <year>1882</year> (4 of <year>1882</year>.) in respect of premises and 
tenancies covered under clauses, (c) to (i) of subsection
<section><tid>538088</tid>
<number>1</number>of  
section 3 and pending in the High Court and all cases pending in the 
Rent Control Tribunal or additional Rent Control Tribunal, constituted 
under the Delhi Rent Control Act, <year>1958</year> (59 of <year>1958</year>.) shall stand 
transferred to the Tribunal and the Tribunal may proceed with the 
matter either de novo or from the stage it was so transferred.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>624729</tid>
<number>68</number>Proceedings before the Tribunal to be judicial proceedings. 
All proceedings before the Tribunal shall be deemed to be judicial 
proceedings within the meaning of sections 193, 219 and 228 of the 
Indian Penal Code. (45 of <year>1860</year>.)


</article>



<article><tid>871696</tid>
<number>69</number>Members and staff of Tribunal to be public servants. The 
Chairman and other Members and the officers and other employees 
provided under section 55 to the Tribunal shall be deemed to be public 
servants wit- bin the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code. 
 (45 of <year>1860</year>.)


</article>



<article><tid>780662</tid>
<number>70</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit. 
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central 
Government or against the Chairman or other Member of the Tribunal, or 
any other person authorised by such Chairman or other Member, for 
anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in 
pursuance of this Act or any rule or order made thereunder.


</article>



<article><tid>664370</tid>
<number> 71</number> Criminal Jurisdiction of the Tribunal.
<section><tid>903546</tid>
<number>1</number>No court other  
than the Tribunal shall try any offence punishable under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1207079</tid>
<number>2</number>The Tribunal shall not take cognizance of an offence 
punishable under this Act, unless the complaint in respect of the 
offence has been made within three months from the date of the 
commission of the offence.

</section>

<section><tid>1987321</tid>
<number>3</number>Every complaint referred to in sub- section (2) shall set 
forth the facts which constitute the offence alleged', the nature of 
such offence and such other particulars as are reasonably sufficient 
to summon the accused and to give him notice of the offence alleged to 
have been committed and to notify the Public Prosecutor to conduct the 
prosecution.

</section>

<section><tid>1548279</tid>
<number>4</number>The Tribunal shall observe the same procedure for the trial 
of offences under this Act as the High Court would observe if it were 
trying the case under section 474 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 
 <year>1973</year> and for that purpose the Tribunal shall be deemed to be High 
Court under the said Code. (2 of <year>1974</year>.)



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>744212</tid>
<number>72</number>Amendment of orders. Clerical or arithmetical mistakes in 
any order passed by the Tribunal or Rent Authority or errors arising 
therein from any accidental slip or ommission may. at any time, be 
corrected by the Tribunal or, as the case may be, the Rent Authority 
on an application received in this behalf from any of the parties or 
otherwise.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>39</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1715477</tid>
<number>73</number>Finality of orders. Save as otherwise expressly provided in 
this Act, every order made by the Rent Authority or an order passed on 
appeal under this Act shall be final and shall not be called in 
question in any original suit, application or execution proceeding.
CHAP

PENALTIES

CHAPTER VIII

PENALTIES



</article>



<article><tid>833028</tid>
<number> 74</number> Penalties.
<section><tid>1900502</tid>
<number>1</number>In a case where the tenant, applies for  
fixation of standard rent under section 11 for the premises the 
standard rent of which had been fixed in a previous tenancy under the 
Delhi Rent Control Act, <year>1958</year> (59 of <year>1958</year>.) or under this Act, the, 
landlord shall, on a request from the tenant, intimate in writing to 
such tenant the standard rent so fixed and in case the landlord fails 
to do so, be shall be punishable with fine of one thousand rupees or 
double the standard rent, fixed in the previous tenancy, whichever is 
more.

</section>

<section><tid>1789204</tid>
<number>2</number>If any landlord or tenant contravenes the provisions of sub- 
section (1) of section 21, he shall be punishable with fine equivalent 
in amount to the rent for three months or with one month' s 
imprisonment, or with both, and shall also be liable to fine of one 
hundred rupees for each day commencing on the date of cutting off or 
with holding essential supply or service till. the date the essential 
supply or service is restored.

</section>

<section><tid>31615</tid>
<number>3</number>If any tenant sub- lets, assigns or otherwise parts 
with the possession of the whole or part of any premises in 
contravention of the provisions of clause (b) of sub- section (2) 
of section 22, he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to 
five thousand rupees, or double the rent received by the tenant for 
sub- letting for every month till such time the cause of complaint 
ceases, whichever is more or with imprisonment for a term of one 
month.

</section>

<section><tid>305006</tid>
<number>4</number>If any landlord, makes a false statement in his affidavit 
under paragraph (i) of Explanation I to clause (r) of sub- section (2) 
of section 22, he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to 
five thousand rupees, or double the rent receivable for a period of 
three years in case it has been re- let, whichever is more.

</section>

<section><tid>1381485</tid>
<number>5</number>If any landlord re- lets the whole or any part of any 
premises in contravention of sub- section (1) of section 31, he shall 
be punishable with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees or 
double the rent the landlord receives after re- letting whichever is 
more, or imprisonment which may extend to one month.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this sub- section and sub- section 
 (3) in cases where it is difficult to prove the 
rent which the landlord or the tenant, as the case may be, is 
receiving after re- letting on sub- letting, the fine may extend to 
five thousand rupees.


</section>

<section><tid>705770</tid>
<number>6</number>If, after the tenant has delivered possession, the landlord 
fails to commerce the work of repairs or building or re- building, as 
the case may be., within three: months of the specified date under 
sub- section (3) of section 32, he shall be punishable with fine 
equivalent to rent for three months

<pagefootnote><pagenum>40</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>483923</tid>
<number>7</number>If a landlord contravenes the provisions of subsection (2) 
of section 32, he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to 
six months' rent of the premises.

</section>

<section><tid>1254120</tid>
<number>8</number>If a tenant fails to make re- entry under sub- section (2) of 
section 32 within three months from the date of the completion of 
repairs or building or rebuilding, as the case may be, intimated in 
writing by the landlord without reasonable excuse, he shall forfeit 
his right to re- entry and shall be punishable with fine equivalent to 
three months' rent of the premises.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER IX

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1907058</tid>
<number>75</number>Jurisdiction of civil courts barred in respect of certain 
matters. Save as otherwise expressly provided in this Act, no civil 
court shall entertain any suit or proceedings in so far as it relates 
to any matter to which this Act applies or to any other matter which 
the Rent Authority is empowered by or under this Act to decide, and no 
injunction in respect of any action taken or to be taken by the Rent 
Authority or the Tribunal under this Act shall be granted by any civil 
court or other authority.


</article>



<article><tid>357647</tid>
<number>76</number>Rent Authorities to be public servants. All Rent Authorities 
and additional Rent Authorities appointed under this Act shall he 
deemed to be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the 
Indian Penal Code. (45 of <year>1860</year>.)


</article>



<article><tid>1689845</tid>
<number>77</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit, 
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any Rent 
Authority or additional Rent Authority In respect of anything which is 
in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>89886</tid>
<number>78</number>Special provision regarding decrees affected by the Delhi 
Tenants (Temporary Protection) Act, <year>1956</year> and the Delhi Rent Control 
Act, <year>1958</year>. Where any decree or order for the recovery of possession of 
any premises to which the Delhi Tenants (Temporary Protection) Act, 
 <year>1956</year> (97 of <year>1956</year>.) or the Delhi Rent Control Act, <year>1958</year>, (59 of <year>1958</year>.) 
applies is sought to be executed on the cesser of operation of any of 
those Acts in relation to those premises, the Rent Authority executing 
the decree or order may, on the application of the person against whom 
the decree or order has been passed or otherwise, reopen the case and 
if it is satisfied that' the decree or order could not have been 
passed if this Act had been in force on the date of the decree or 
order the Rent Authorty may, having regard to the provisions of this 
Act, set aside the decree or order or pass such other order in 
relation thereto as he thinks fit.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>41</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1143785</tid>
<number>79</number>Transfer of pending cases to Rent Authority. On the 
commencement of this Act, all cases pertaining to the matters in 
respect of which the Rent Authority shall have jurisdiction under this 
Act and pending before the Controller under the Delhi Rent Control 
Act, <year>1958</year> (59 of <year>1958</year>.) or any other court shall stand transferred to 
the Rent Authority and tile Rent Authority shall proceed with the 
matter either de novo or from the stage it was transferred.


</article>



<article><tid>490593</tid>
<number> 80</number> Powers of Central Government to remove difficulties.
<section><tid>399156</tid>
<number>1</number>If  
any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, 
the Central Government may, by order published in the Official 
Gazette, make such provisions not inconsistent with the provisions of 
this Act as may appear to be necessary for removing the difficulty.
Provided that no order shall be made under this section after the 
expiry of two years from the commencement of this Act.


</section>

<section><tid>1907362</tid>
<number>2</number>Every order made under this section shall, as soon as may be 
after it is made, be laid before each House of Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1031986</tid>
<number> 81</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>75296</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for the purpose of 
carrying out the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>60141</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of 
the foregoing powers, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>439561</tid>
<number>a</number>the period within which agreements shall be registered 
under sub- section (2) of section 4;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>247601</tid>
<number>b</number>the authority before whom, the form and the manner in 
which and the period within which the landlord and the tenant 
shall separately file the particulars about the tenancy under 
the proviso to sub- section (3) of section 4;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1888759</tid>
<number>c</number>the manner of making application under sub- section (1) 
of section 11;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>804902</tid>
<number>d</number>the valuer whose assistance may be taken by the Rent 
Authority and the manner of assessment to be carried out by 
him tinder sub- section (2) of section 11;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1912719</tid>
<number>e</number>the manner of depositing rent or other charges under 
subsection (1) of section 16;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>256325</tid>
<number>f</number>the particulars under clause (e) of sub- section (2) of 
section 16;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>636698</tid>
<number>g</number>the manner of sending copy of application to landlord 
under sub- section (3) of section 16;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1871734</tid>
<number>h</number>the manner in which the deposited rent or other charges 
to be paid to the applicant under Sub- section (4) of section 
16;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1782824</tid>
<number>i</number>the manner of giving notice to the tenant under sub- 
section (3) of section 20;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>305372</tid>
<number>j</number>the manner in which the application under sub- section 
 (2) of section 22 shall be made to the Rent Authority:

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1187967</tid>
<number>k</number>the manner in which a notice shall be given under 
proviso to clause (c) of sub- section (2) of section 22;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>42</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1550647</tid>
<number>l</number>the Manner in which notices to the landlord shall be 
give by the tenant or sub- tenant under section 29;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1076179</tid>
<number>m</number>the manner in which permission of tile Rent Authority 
shall be obtained by the landlord under section 31;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>763389</tid>
<number>n</number>the time within which applications to be made under 
sub- section (2) of section 31 or sub- section (3) and sub- 
section (4) of section 32;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>43888</tid>
<number>o</number>the manner in which the permission of the Rent 
Authority shall be obtained by the landlord under section 33;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1716982</tid>
<number>p</number>the time within which the application shall be made to 
the Rent Authority by the landlord under section 33;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1685668</tid>
<number>q</number>the powers of a civil court which may be vested in the 
Rent Authority under clause (d) of sub- section (2) of section 
44;-

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1535673</tid>
<number>r</number>the number of Members in the Benches to be decided by 
the Chairman under sub- section (2) of section 47;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1520513</tid>
<number>s</number>the procedure in accordance with which a list of 
candidates shall be prepared by the Ministry dealing with 
Urban Development in consultation with the Department dealing 
with Justice of the Government of India under sub- section (5) 
of section 48;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>387549</tid>
<number>t</number>the salaries and allowances payable to, land the other 
terms and conditions of service (including pension, gratuity  
  and other retirement benefits) of, the Chairman and other 
Members under section 51;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>95222</tid>
<number>u</number>procedure under sub- section (3) of section 52, for the 
Investigation of misbehaviour or incapacity of the Chairman 
or other Member referred to in sub- section (2) of the said 
section;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1296592</tid>
<number>v</number>the financial and administrative powers of the Chairman 
under section 54;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>132929</tid>
<number>w</number>the salaries and allowances and conditions of service 
of the officers and other employees of the Tribunal under 
sub- section (2) of section 55;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1917730</tid>
<number>x</number>the form of application under sub- section (1) of 
section 59 and the affidavits, documents or any other 
evidence and the fee in respect of filing of the said 
application and the other fees for the service or execution 
of Processes as mentioned In sub- section (2) of the said 
section;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>93240</tid>
<number>y</number>the to be prescribed under clause (j) of sub- section 
 (3) of section 60;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1829872</tid>
<number>z</number>the form of appeal and the fee payable under sub- 
section (1) of section 61;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>225267</tid>
<number>za</number>any other matter which has to be, or may be, prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1193034</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made under this Act shall be laid,. as soon, as 
may be after it is made before each House of Parliament, while it is 
in session,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>43</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one 
session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the 
expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be: so. however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>24823</tid>
<number> 82</number> Repeal and savings.
<section><tid>750275</tid>
<number>1</number>The Delhi Rent Control Act, <year>1958</year>,  
 (59 of <year>1958</year>.) is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1457034</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal and subject to the provisions of 
section 67 and section 79 all cases and other proceedings under the 
said Act pending, at the commencement of this Act, shall be continued 
and disposed of in accordance with the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1506493</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding such repeal all leases relating to the 
premises taken by the Government on lease under section 47 of the 
Delhi Rent Control Act, <year>1958</year> (59 of <year>1958</year>.) shall cease on the 
expiration of a period of six months from the date of commencement of 
this Act, unless sooner determined by the Government.


</section>

</article>



 </act>