<act><title>

THE HINDU SUCCESSION ACT, 1956</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and extent.—
<section><number>1</number> This Act may 
    be called the Hindu Succession Act, 1956.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends 
    to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Application of Act.—
<section><number>1</number> This Act 
    applies—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    to any person, who is a Hindu by 
    religion in any of its forms or developments including a Virashaiva, a 
    Lingayat or a follower of the Brahmo, Prarthana or Arya Samaj;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    to any person who is a Buddhist, Jaina 
    or Sikh by religion; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    to any other person who is not a 
    Muslim, Christian, Parsi or Jew by religion unless it is proved that any 
    such person would not have been governed by the Hindu law or by any custom 
    or usage as part of that law in respect of any of the matters dealt with 
    herein if this Act had not been passed. 
 
Explanation.—The 
    following persons are Hindus, Buddhists, Jainas or Sikhs by religion, as the 
    case may be:— 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>a</number>    any child, legitimate or illegitimate, 
    both of whose parents are Hindus, Buddhists, Jainas or Sikhs by religion; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    any child, legitimate or illegitimate 
    one of whose parents is a Hindu, Buddhist, Jaina or Sikh by religion and who 
    is brought up as a member of the tribe, community, group or family to which 
    such parent belongs or belonged; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    any person who is a convert or 
    re-convert to the Hindu, Buddhist, Jaina or Sikh religion. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), nothing contained in 
    this Act shall apply to the members of any Scheduled Tribe within the 
    meaning of clause (25) of Article 366 of the Constitution unless the Central 
    Government, by notification in the Official Gazette, otherwise directs. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    expression “Hindu” in any portion of this Act shall be construed as if it 
    included a person who, though not a Hindu by religion, is, nevertheless, a 
    person to whom this Act applies by virtue of the provisions contained in 
    this section. 
  
 
STATE AMENDMENTS
 
Pondicherry:  
 
In section 2, after 
    sub-section (2) insert—  
 
                        “(2A) 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), nothing contained in 
    this Act shall apply to the Renouncants of the Union territory of 
    Pondicherry.”
 
[Regulation 7 of 1963, 
    sec. 3 and First Sch. (w.e.f. 1-10-1963).]  
  





 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Definitions and interpretation </title>.—
<section><number>1</number> In this 
Act, unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> “agnate”—one person is said to be an “agnate” of another if the two are 
  related by blood or adoption wholly through males; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> “aliyasantana law” means the system of law applicable to 
  persons who, if this Act had not been passed, would have been governed by the 
  Madras Aliyasantana Act, 1949, or by the customary Aliyasantana law 
  with respect to the matter for which provision is made in this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> “cognate” — one person is said to be a cognate of another if the two 
  are related by blood or adoption but not wholly through males; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> the expression “custom” and “usage” signify any rule which having been 
  continuously and uniformly observed for a long time, has obtained the force of 
  law among Hindus in any local area, tribe, community, group or family: 
 Provided that the rule is certain and not unreasonable or opposed to public 
  policy; and 
 Provided further that in the case of a rule applicable only to a family it 
  has not been discontinued by the family; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> “full blood”, “half blood” and “uterine blood”— 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> two persons are said to be related to each other by full blood when 
    they are descended from a common ancestor by the same wife, and by half 
    blood when they are descended from a common ancestor but; by different 
    wives; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> two persons are said to be related to each other by uterine blood 
    when they are descended from a common ancestress but by different husbands; 
    </subsubsection></subsection>
 Explanation.— In this clause “ancestor” includes the father and 
“ancestress” the mother; 
 
 <subsection><number>f</number> “heir” means any person, male or female, who is entitled to succeed to 
  the property of an intestate under this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> “intestate”—a person is deemed to die intestate in respect of property 
  of which he or she has not made a testamentary disposition capable of taking 
  effect; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> “marumakkattayam law” means the system of law applicable to 
  persons— 
 
 </subsection><subsection><number>a</number> who, if this Act had not been passed, would have been governed by the 
    Madras Marumakkattayam Act, 1932 (Madras Act XXII of 1933); the Travancore 
    Nayar Act (II of 1100K); the Travancore Ezhava Act (III of 1100K); the (VII 
    of 1108K) Travancore Nanjinad Vellala Act (IV of 1101K); the Travancore 
    Kshatriya Act (VII of 1108K); the Travancore Krishnanvaka Marumakkathayee 
    Act (VII of 1115K); the Cochin Marumakkathayam Act (XXXIII of 1113K); or the 
    Cochin Nayar Act (XXIX of 1113K); with respect to the matters for which 
    provision is made in this Act; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> who belong to any community, the members of which are largely 
    domiciled in the State of Travancore-Cochin or Madras <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[as it 
    existed immediately before the 1st November, 1956,] and who, if this Act had 
    not been passed, would have been governed with respect to the matters for 
    which provision is made in this Act by any system of inheritance in which 
    descent is traced through the female line; </subsection>
 but does not include the aliyasantana law; 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> “nambudri law” means the system of law applicable to persons 
  who, if this Act had not been passed, would have been governed by the Madras 
  Nambudri Act, 1932 (Madras Act XXI of 1933); the Cochin Nambudri Act (XVII of 
  1113); or the Travancore Malayala Brahmin Act with respect to the matters for 
  which provision is made in this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> “related” means related by legitimate kinship: 
 Provided that illegitimate children shall be deemed to be related to their 
  mothers and to one another, and their legitimate descendants shall be deemed 
  to be related to them and to one another; and any word expressing relationship 
  or denoting a relative shall be construed accordingly. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires, words importing the 
masculine gender shall not be taken to include females. 






</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Over-riding effect of Act.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Save as otherwise expressly provided in this Act,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    any text, rule or interpretation of 
    Hindu law or any custom or usage as part of that law in force immediately 
    before the commencement of this Act shall cease to have effect with respect 
    to any matter for which provision is made in this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    any other law in force immediately 
    before the commencement of this Act shall cease to apply to Hindus in so far 
    as it is inconsistent with any of the provisions contained in this Act. 
 
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[***]
 







 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>5</number> Act not to apply to certain 
      properties.—This Act shall not 
      apply to— 
 <section><number>i</number>    any property 
      succession to which is regulated by the Indian Succession Act, 1925, by 
      reason of the provisions contained in section 21 of the Special Marriage 
      Act, 1954; 
    
 </section><section><number>ii</number>    any estate 
      which descends to a single heir by the terms of any covenant or agreement 
      entered into by the Ruler of any Indian State with the Government of India 
      or by the terms of any enactment passed before the commencement of this 
      Act; 
 </section><section><number>iii</number>    the 
      Valiamma Thampuran Kovilagam Estate and the Palace Fund administered by 
      the Palace Administration Board by reason of the powers conferred by 
      Proclamation (IX of 1124) dated 29th June, 1949, promulgated by the 
      Maharaja of Cochin. 
  
 State amendment 
 <subsection><number>a</number> Kerala 
      State has passed an Act for the partition of the valiamma Thampuran Kovilegam 
      Estate and the Palace Fund: Kerala Act 16 of 1961, sec. 10.  
                         
      “10. Amendment of the Hindu Succession Act, 1956.—Clause (iii) of 
      section 5 of the Hindu Succession Act, 1956 (Central Act 30 of 1956), 
      shall be omitted with effect on and from the date of execution of the 
      partition deed under  section 6.”
 
  </subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<title><number>6</number> Devolution of interest in coparcenary property. 
</title>—
<section><number>1</number> On and from the commencement of the Hindu Succession (Amendment) 
Act, 2005*, in a Joint Hindu family governed by the Mitakshara law, the daughter 
of a coparcener shall,— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> by birth become a coparcener in her own right in the same manner as the 
  son; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> have the same rights in the coparcenary property as she would have had 
  if she had been a son; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> be subject to the same liabilities in respect of the said coparcenary 
  property as that of a son, </subsection>
 and any reference to a Hindu Mitakshara coparcener shall be deemed to include 
a reference to a daughter of a coparcener: 
 Provided that nothing contained in this sub-section shall affect or 
invalidate any disposition or alienation including any partition or testamentary 
disposition of property which had taken place before the 20th day of December, 
2004. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any property to which a female Hindu becomes entitled by virtue of 
sub­-section (1) shall be held by her with the incidents of coparcenary 
ownership and shall be regarded, notwithstanding anything contained in this Act 
or any other law for the time being in force in, as property capable of being 
disposed of by her by testamentary disposition. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where a Hindu dies after the commencement of the Hindu Succession 
(Amendment) Act, 2005*, his interest in the property of a Joint Hindu family 
governed by the Mitakshara law, shall devolve by testamentary or intestate 
succession, as the case may be, under this Act and not by survivorship, and the 
coparcenary property shall be deemed to have been divided as if a partition had 
taken place and,— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the daughter is allotted the same share as is allotted to a son; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the share of the pre-deceased son or a pre-deceased daughter, as they 
  would have got had they been alive at the time of partition, shall be allotted 
  to the surviving child of such pre-deceased son or of such pre-deceased 
  daughter; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the share of the pre-deceased child of a pre-deceased son or of a 
  pre­-deceased daughter, as such child would have got had he or she been 
  alive at the time of the partition, shall be allotted to the child of such 
  pre-deceased child of the pre-deceased son or a pre-deceased daughter, as the 
  case may be. </subsection>
 Explanation. —For the purposes of this sub-section, the interest of 
a Hindu Mitakshara coparcener shall be deemed to be the share in the property 
that would have been allotted to him if a partition of the property had taken 
place immediately before his death, irrespective of whether he was entitled to 
claim partition or not. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> After the commencement of the Hindu Succession (Amendment) Act, 2005*, no 
court shall recognise any right to proceed against a son, grandson or 
great­-grandson for the recovery of any debt due from his father, 
grandfather or great-grandfather solely on the ground of the pious obligation 
under the Hindu law, of such son, grandson or great-grandson to discharge any 
such debt: 
 Provided that in the case of any debt contracted before the commencement of 
the Hindu Succession (Amendment) Act, 2005*, nothing contained in this 
sub-section shall affect— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the right of any creditor to proceed against the son, grandson or 
  great-grandson, as the case may be; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> any alienation made in respect of or in satisfaction of, any such debt, 
  and any such right or alienation shall be enforceable under the rule of pious 
  obligation in the same manner and to the same extent as it would have been 
  enforceable as if the Hindu Succession (Amendment) Act, 2005 had not been 
  enacted. </subsection>
 Explanation. —For the purposes of clause (a), the expression “son”, 
“grandson” or “great-grandson” shall be deemed to refer to the son, grandson or 
great-grandson, as the case may be, who was born or adopted prior to the 
commencement of the Hindu Succession (Amendment) Act, 2005*. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Nothing contained in this section shall apply to a partition, which has 
been effected before the 20th day of December, 2004. 
 Explanation. —For the purposes of this section “partition” means any 
partition made by execution of a deed of partition duly registered under the 
Registration Act, 1908 (16 of 1908) or partition effected by a decree of a 
court.] 
 Statement of Objects and Reasons [The Hindu Succession (Amendment) Act, 2005] 

 Section 6 of the Act deals with devolution of interest of a male Hindu in 
coparcenary property and recognises the rule of devolution by survivorship among 
the members of the coparcenary. The retention of the Mitakshara coparcenary 
property without including the females in it means that the females cannot 
inherit in ancestral property as their male counterparts do. The law by 
excluding the daughter from participating in the coparcenary ownership not only 
contributes to her discrimination on the ground of gender but also has led to 
oppression and negation of her fundamental right of equality guaranteed by the 
Constitution having regard to the need to render social justice to women, the 
States of Andhra Pradesh, Tamil Nadu, Karnataka and Maharashtra have made 
necessary changes in the law giving equal right to daughters in Hindu Mitakshara 
coparcenary property. The Kerala Legislature has enacted the Kerala Joint Hindu 
Family System (Abolition) Act, 1975. 
 It is proposed to remove the discrimination as contained in section 6 of the 
Hindu Succession Act, 1956 by giving equal rights to daughters in the Hindu 
Mitakshara coparcenary property as the sons have. 
  
 <title>State Amendment </title><title></title>
 <title>Sections 6A to 6C </title>
 <title>Karnataka: </title>
 After section 6 the following sections shall be inserted, namely:— 
 "6A. Equal rights to daugher in co-parcenary property.— 
Notwithstanding anything contained in section 6 of this Act— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> in a joint Hindu family governed by Mitakshara law, the 
  daughter of a co-parcener shall by birth become a co-parcener in her own right 
  in the same manner as the son and have the same rights in the co-parcenary 
  property as she would have had if she had been a son inclusive of the right to 
  claim by survivorship and shall be subject to the same liabilities and 
  disabilities in respect thereto as the son; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> at a partition in such a joint Hindu family the co-parcenary property 
  shall be so divided as to allot to a daughter the same share as is allotable 
  to a son: 
 Provided that the share which a predeceased son or a predeceased daughter 
  would have got at the partition if he or she had been alive at the time of the 
  partition, shall be allotted to the surviving child of such predeceased son or 
  of such predeceased daughter: 
 Provided further that the share allotable to the predeceased child of a 
  predeceased son or of a predeceased daughter, if such child had been alive at 
  the time of the partition, shall be allotted to the child of such predeceased 
  child of the predeceased son or of such predeceased daughter, as the case may 
  be; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> any property to which a female Hindu becomes entitled by virtue of the 
  provisions of clause (a) shall be held by her with the incidents of 
  co-parcenary ownership and shall be regarded, notwithstanding anything 
  contained in this Act or any other law for the time being in force, as 
  property capable of being disposed of by her by will or other testamentary 
  disposition; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> nothing in clause (b) shall apply to a daughter married prior to or to 
  a partition which had been effected before the commencement of Hindu 
  Succession (Karnataka Amendment) Act, 1990. </subsection>
 </section></article><article><title><number>6B</number> Interest to devolve by survivorship on death.</title>— 
When a female Hindu dies after the commencement of the Hindu Succession 
(Karnataka Amendment) Act, 1990, having at the time of her death an interest in 
a Mitakshara co-parcenary property, her interest in the property shall 
devolve by survivorship upon the surviving members of the co-parcenary and not 
in accordance with this Act: 
 Provided that if the deceased had left any child or child of a pre-deceased 
child, the interest of the deceased in the Mitakshara co-parcenary property 
shall devolve by testamentary or intestate succession as the case may be under 
this Act and not by survivorship. 
 <section><number>Explanations</number>— (1) For the purposes of this section the interest of 
female Hindu Mitakshara co-parcenary shall be deemed to be the share in 
the property that would have been allotted to her if a partition of the property 
had taken place immediately before her death, irrespective of whether she was 
entitled to claim partition or not. 
 <subsection><number>2</number> Nothing contained in the proviso to this section shall be construed as 
enabling a person who, before the death of the deceased had separated himself or 
herself from the co-parcenary, or any of his or her heirs to claim on intestacy 
a share in the interest referred to therein. 
 </subsection></section></article><article><title><number>6C</number> Preferential right to acquire property in certain 
cases.</title>— 
<section><number>1</number> Where, after the commencement of Hindu Succession 
(Karnataka Amendment) Act, 1990 an interest in any immovable property of an 
intestate or in any business carried by him or her, whether solely or in 
conjunction with others devolves under sections 6A or 6B upon two or more heirs 
and any one of such heirs proposes to transfer his or her interest in the 
property or business, the other heirs shall have a preferential right to acquire 
the interest proposed to be transferred. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The consideration for which any interest in the property of the deceased 
may be transferred under sub-section (1) shall in the absence of any agreement 
between the parties, be determined by the court, on application, being made to 
it in this behalf, and if any person proposing to acquire the interest is not 
willing to acquire it for the consideration so determined, such person shall be 
liable to pay all costs of or incidental to the application. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> If there are two or more heirs proposing to acquire any interest under 
this section, that heir who offers the highest consideration for the transfer 
shall be preferred. 
 Explanation.— In this section 'court' means the court within the 
limits of whose jurisdiction the immovable property is situate or the business 
is carried on, and includes any other court which the State Government may by 
notification in the Official Gazette specify in this behalf. 
 [ Vide Karnataka Act 23 of 1994, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 30-7-1994).] 




 
 <subsection><number>i</number> The contention of the petitioners that there was automatic partition 
  amongst the heirs of the deceased Karta on his death has been 
  negatived because it is only when the deceased had left his surviving female 
  heirs as provided in proviso to section 6 of the Act, a notional partition is 
  deemed to have taken place in the joint family property for the purpose of 
  ascertaining the share of the deceased in the joint family properties which 
  comes to the share of the female heirs. If there are male heirs there is no 
  automatic partition; Shivgonda Balgonda Patil v. Director of 
  Resettlement, AIR 1992 Bom 72. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> The heirs will get his or her share in the interest which the deceased 
  had in the coparcenary property at the time of his death in addition to the 
  share which he or she received or must be deemed to have received in the 
  notional partition; Gurupad v. Hirabai, AIR 1978 SC 1239. 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> The fiction in the explanation of section 6 of the Act should be 
  carried to a narrow extent only with a new point to implement the purpose for 
  which it was introduced. When there were only two coparceners and one of them 
  died, then if any person other then the coparcener is entitled to a share as a 
  result of severance of the share of the deceased coparcener, the share of such 
  other person will become fixed; Shushilabai v. Naraynarao , 
  AIR 1975 Bom 257. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> The deceased coparcener's share gets fixed on the date of his death, 
  subsequent fluctuations in the fortunes of the coparceners do not affect it; 
  Karuppa v. Palaniammal; AIR 1963 Mad 254. </subsection>







</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Devolution of interest in the property of a tarwad, tavazhi, 
kutumba, kavaru or illom </title>. —
<section><number>1</number> When a Hindu to whom the 
marumakkattayam or nambudri law would have applied if this Act 
had not been passed, dies after the commencement of this Act, having at the time 
of his or her death an interest in the property of a tarwad, 
tavazhi or illom, as the case may be, his or her interest 
in the property shall devolve by testamentary or intestate succession, as the 
case may be, under this Act and not according to the marumakkattayam or 
nambudri law. <title></title>
 Explanation.— For the purposes of this sub-section, the interest of 
a Hindu in the property of a tarwad, tavazhi or illom shall be 
deemed to be the share in the property of the tarwad, tavazhi or 
illom, as the case may be, that would have fallen to him or her if a 
partition of that property per capita had been made immediately before 
his or her death among all the members of the tarwad, tavazhi or 
illom, as the case may be, then living, whether he or she was entitled 
to claim such partition or not under the marumakkattayam or 
nambudri law applicable to him or her, and such share shall be deemed 
to have been allotted to him or her absolutely. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> When a Hindu to whom the aliyasantana law would have applied if 
this Act had not been passed, dies after the commencement of this Act, having at 
the time of his or her death an undivided interest in the property of a 
kutumba or kavaru, as the case may be, his or her interest in 
the property shall devolve by testamentary or intestate succession, as the case 
may be, under this Act and not according to the aliyasantana law. 
 Explanation.— For the purposes of this sub-section, the interest of 
a Hindu in the property of a kutumba or a kavaru shall be 
deemed to be the share in the property of the kutumba or kavaru 
as the case may be that would have fallen to him or her if a partition of 
that property per capita had been made immediately before his or her 
death among all the members of the kutumba or kavaru, as the 
case may be, then living, whether he or she was entitled to claim such partition 
or not under the aliyasantana law, and such share shall be deemed to 
have been allotted to him or her absolutely. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), when a 
sthanamdar dies after the commencement of this Act, sthanam 
property held by him shall devolve upon the members of the family to which 
the sthanamdar belonged and the heirs of the sthanamdar as if 
the sthanam property had been divided per capita immediately 
before the death of the sthanamdar among himself and all the members of 
his family then living, and the shares falling to the members of his family and 
the heirs of the sthanamdar shall be held by them as their separate 
property. 
 Explanation.— For the purposes of this sub-section, the family of a 
sthanamdar shall include every branch of that family, whether divided 
or undivided, the male members of which would have been entitled by any custom 
or usage to succeed to the position of sthanamdar if this Act had not 
been passed. 
 <title>State Amendment </title><title></title>
 <title>Kerala: </title>
 In section 7, in sub-section (3)— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number>  between the words “him” and “shall”, the words “or her”, between 
  the words “himself” and “and”, the words “or herself” and between the words 
  “his” and “family” in the two places where they occur the words “or her” shall 
  be respectively inserted; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> in the e xplanation , the word “male” shall be omitted; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the existing Explanation shall be numbered as Explanation 
  I and the following Explanation shall be added, namely:— 
</subsection>
  “Explanation II.— The devolution of Sthanam 
properties under sub-section (3) and their division among the members of 
the family and heirs shall not be deemed to have conferred upon them in respect 
of immovable properties any higher rights than the sthanamdar regarding 
eviction or otherwise as against tenants who were holding such properties under 
the sthani .” 
 [ Vide Kerala Act 28 of 1958, sec. 27 (w.e.f. 18-5-1958).] 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>8</number> General 
    rules of succession in the case of males.—The 
    property of a male Hindu dying intestate shall devolve according to the 
    provisions of this Chapter— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    firstly, upon the heirs, being the 
    relatives specified in class I of the Schedule;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    secondly, if there is no heir of class 
    I, then upon the heirs, being the relatives specified in class II of the 
    Schedule; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    thirdly, if there is no heir of any of 
    the two classes, then upon the agnates of the deceased; and 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    lastly, if there is no agnate, then 
    upon the cognates of the deceased.
  







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>9</number> Order of 
    succession among heirs in the Schedule.—Among 
    the heirs specified in the Schedule, those in class I shall take 
    simultaneously and to the exclusion of all other heirs; those in the first 
    entry in class II shall be preferred to those in the second entry; those in 
    the second entry shall be preferred to those in the third entry; and so on 
    in succession. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Distribution of property among heirs in class I of the Schedule.—The 
    property of an intestate shall be divided among the heirs in class I of the 
    Schedule in accordance with the following rules:— 
 
Rule 1.—  
    The intestate’s widow, or if there are more widows than one, all the widows 
    together, shall take one share.
 
Rule 2.—  
    The surviving sons and daughters and the mother of the intestate shall each 
    take one share.
 
Rule 3.—  
    The heirs in the branch of each pre-deceased son or each pre-deceased 
    daughter of the intestate shall take between them one share.
 
Rule 4.—  
    The distribution of the share referred to in Rule 3—
 <section>
<number>i</number>    among the heirs in the branch of the 
    pre-deceased son shall be so made that his widow (or widows together) and 
    the surviving sons and daughters gets equal portions; and the branch of his 
    predeceased sons gets the same portion; 
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    among the heirs in the branch of the 
    pre-deceased daughter shall be so made that the surviving sons and daughters 
    get equal portions. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Distribution of property among heirs in class II of the Schedule.—The 
    property of an intestate shall be divided between the heirs specified in any 
    one entry in class II of the Schedule so that they share equally. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>12</number> Order of 
    succession among agnates and cognates.—The 
    order of succession among agnates or cognates, as the case may be, shall be 
    determined in accordance with the rules of preference laid down hereunder: 
 
Rule 1.—  
    Of two heirs, the one who has fewer or no degrees of ascent is preferred.
 
Rule 2.—  
    Where the number of degrees of ascent is the same or none, that heir is 
    preferred who has fewer or no degrees of descent.
 
Rule 3.—  
    Where neither heirs is entitled to be preferred to the other under Rule 1 or 
    Rule 2 they take simultaneously.
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Computation of degrees.—
<section><number>1</number> For 
    the purposes of determining the order of succession among agnates or 
    cognates, relationship shall be reckoned from the intestate to the heir in 
    terms of degrees of ascent or degrees of descent or both, as the case may 
    be. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Degrees of 
    ascent and degrees of descent shall be computed inclusive of the intestate. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every 
    generation constitutes a degree either ascending or descending. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>14</number> Property 
    of a female Hindu to be her absolute property.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any property possessed by a female Hindu, whether acquired before or after 
    the commencement of this Act, shall be held by her as full owner thereof and 
    not as a limited owner. 
 
Explanation.—In 
    this sub-section, “property” includes both movable and immovable property 
    acquired by a female Hindu by inheritance or devise, or at a partition, or 
    in lieu of maintenance or arrears of maintenance, or by gift from any 
    person, whether a relative or not, before, at or after her marriage, or by 
    her own skill or exertion, or by purchase or by prescription, or in any 
    other manner whatsoever, and also any such property held by her as 
    stridhana immediately before the commencement of this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Nothing 
    contained in sub-section (1) shall apply to any property acquired by way of 
    gift or under a will or any other instrument or under a decree or order of a 
    civil court or under an award where the terms of the gift, will or other 
    instrument or the decree, order or award prescribe a restricted estate in 
    such property. 
  




















 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>15</number> General 
    rules of succession in the case of female Hindus.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The property of a female Hindu dying intestate shall devolve according to 
    the rules set out in section 16,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> firstly, upon the sons and 
    daughters (including the children of any pre-deceased son or daughter) and 
    the husband;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    secondly, upon the heirs of the 
    husband; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> thirdly, upon the mother and 
    father; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    fourthly, upon the heirs of the father; 
    and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number> lastly, upon the heirs of the 
    mother. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1),— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    any property inherited by a female 
    Hindu from her father or mother shall devolve, in the absence of any son or 
    daughter of the deceased (including the children of any pre-deceased son or 
    daughter) not upon the other heirs referred to in sub-section (1) in the 
    order specified therein, but upon the heirs of the father; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    any property inherited by a female 
    Hindu from her husband or from her father-in-law shall devolve, in the 
    absence of any son or daughter of the deceased (including the children of 
    any pre-deceased son or daughter) not upon the other heirs referred to in 
    sub-section (1) in the order specified therein, but upon the heirs of the 
    husband. 
  











 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>16</number> Order of 
    succession and manner of distribution among heirs of a female Hindu.—The 
    order of succession among the heirs referred to in section 15 shall be, and 
    the distribution of the intestates property among those heirs shall take 
    place according to the following rules, namely:— 
 
Rule 1.—Among 
    the heirs specified in sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 15, those in one entry 
    shall be preferred to those in any succeeding entry and those included in 
    the same entry shall take simultaneously. 
 
Rule 2.—If 
    any son or daughter of the intestate had pre-deceased the intestate leaving 
    his or her own children alive at the time of the intestate’s death, the 
    children of such son or daughter shall take between them the share which 
    such son or daughter would have taken if living at the intestate’s death. 
 
Rule 3.—The 
    devolution of the property of the intestate on the heirs referred to in 
    clauses (b), (d) and (e) of sub-section (1) and in sub-section (2) to 
    section 15 shall be in the same order and according to the same rules as 
    would have applied if the property had been the father’s or the mother’s or 
    the husband’s as the case may be, and such person had died intestate in 
    respect thereof immediately after the intestate’s death. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>17</number> Special 
    provisions respecting persons governed by marumakkattayam and 
    aliyasantana laws.—The 
    provisions of sections 8, 10, 15 and 23 shall have effect in relation to 
    persons who would have been governed by the marumakkattayam law or 
    aliyasantana law if this Act had not been passed as if—
 <section>
<number>i</number>    for sub-clauses (c) and (d) of section 
    8, the following had been substituted, namely:—
 
            “(c)    thirdly, if there is no 
    heir of any of the two classes, then upon his relatives, whether agnates or 
    cognates.”;
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    for clauses (a) to (e) of sub-section 
    (1) of section 15, the following had been substituted, namely:—
 
“(a)    firstly, upon the sons and daughters 
    (including the children of any pre-deceased son or daughter) and the mother;
 <subsection>
<number>b</number>    secondly, upon the father and the 
    husband;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    thirdly, upon the heirs of the mother;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    fourthly, upon the heirs of the father; 
    and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    lastly, upon the heirs of the 
    husband.”;
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>iii</number>    clause (a) of sub-section (2) of 
    section 15 had been omitted; 
 </section><section>
<number>iv</number> section 23 had been omitted. 
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>18</number> Full 
    blood preferred to half blood.—Heirs 
    related to an intestate by full blood shall be preferred to heirs related by 
    half blood, if the nature of the relationship is the same in every other 
    respect. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>19</number> Mode of 
    succession of two or more heirs.—If 
    two or more heirs succeed together to the property of an intestate, they 
    shall take the property,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    save as otherwise expressly provided in 
    this Act, per capita and not per stirpes; and 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    as tenants-in-common and not as joint 
    tenants. 
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>20</number> Right of 
    child in womb.—A child who was in 
    the womb at the time of the death of an intestate and who is subsequently 
    born alive shall have the same right to inherit to the intestate as if he or 
    she had been born before the death of the intestate, and the inheritance 
    shall be deemed to vest in such a case with effect from the date of the 
    death of the intestate. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>21</number> 
    Presumption in cases of simultaneous deaths.—Where 
    two persons have died in circumstances rendering it uncertain whether either 
    of them, and if so which, survived the other then, for all purposes 
    affecting succession to property, it shall be presumed, until the contrary 
    is proved, that the younger survived the elder. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Preferential right to acquire property in certain cases.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where, after the commencement of this Act, an interest in any immovable 
    property of an intestate, or in any business carried on by him or her, 
    whether solely or in conjunction with others, devolves upon two or more 
    heirs specified in class I of the Schedule, and any one of such heirs 
    proposes to transfer his or her interest in the property or business, the 
    other heirs shall have a preferential right to acquire the interest proposed 
    to be transferred. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    consideration for which any interest in the property of the deceased may be 
    transferred under this section shall, in the absence of any agreement 
    between the parties, be determined by the court on application being made to 
    it in this behalf, and if any person proposing to acquire the interest is 
    not willing to acquire it for the consideration so determined, such person 
    shall be liable to pay all costs of or incident to the application. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If there 
    are two or more heirs specified in class I of the Schedule proposing to 
    acquire any interest under this section, that heir who offers the highest 
    consideration for the transfer shall be preferred. 
 

    Explanation.—In this section, 
    “court” means the court within the limits of whose jurisdiction the 
    immovable property is situate or the business is carried on, and includes 
    any other court which the State Government may, by notification in the 
    Official Gazette, specify in this behalf. 

 
  


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>23</number> Special provision respecting dwelling houses. 
</title>—[ Rep. by the Hindu Succession (Amendment) Act, 2005 (39 of 2005), 
sec. 4 (w.e.f. 9-9-2005) .]] 
 <title>Statement of Objects and Reasons [The Hindu Succession (Amendment) 
Act, 2005] </title>
 Section 23 of the Act disentitles a female heir to ask for partition in 
respect of a dwelling house wholly occupied by a joint family until the male 
heirs choose to divide their respective shares therein. It is also proposed to 
omit the said section so as to remove the disability on female heirs contained 
in that section. 



</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>24</number> Certain widows re-marrying may not inherit as 
widows. </title>—[ Rep. by the Hindu Succession (Amendment) Act, 2005 (39 of 
2005), sec. 5 (w.e.f. 9-9-2005) .]] 


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>25</number> Murderer 
    disqualified.—A person who commits 
    murder or abets the commission of murder shall be disqualified from 
    inheriting the property of the person murdered, or any other property in 
    furtherance of the succession to which he or she committed or abetted the 
    commission of the murder. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>26</number> 
    Convert’s descendants disqualified.—Where, 
    before or after the commencement of this Act, a Hindu has ceased or ceases 
    to be a Hindu by conversion to another religion, children born to him or her 
    after such conversion and their descendants shall be disqualified from 
    inheriting the property of any of their Hindu relatives, unless such 
    children or descendants are Hindus at the time when the succession opens. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>27</number> 
    Succession when heir disqualified.—If 
    any person is disqualified from
    inheriting any property under this Act, it shall devolve as if such person 
    had died before the intestate.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>28</number> Disease, 
    defect, etc., not to disqualify.—No 
    person shall be disqualified from succeeding to any property on the ground 
    of any disease, defect or deformity, or save as provided in this Act, on any 
    other ground whatsoever. 
  

 
  


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>29</number> Failure of heirs </title>.—If an intestate has left no heir 
qualified to succeed to his or her property in accordance with the provisions of 
this Act, such property shall devolve on the government; and the government 
shall take the property subject to all the obligations and liabilities to which 
an heir would have been subject. 
 <title>State Amendments </title><title></title>
 <title>Chapter IIA </title>
 <title>Andhra Pradesh: </title>
 After Chapter II, insert the following Chapter, namely:— 
 <title>"Chapter IIA </title>
 <title>Succession by survivorship 
</title><title></title>
 </article><article><title><number>29A</number> Equal rights to daughter in coparcenary property.</title>— 
Notwithstanding anything contained in section 6 of this Act— 
 
 <section><number>i</number> in a joint Hindu family governed by Mitakshara Law, the 
  daughter of a coparcener shall by birth, become a coparcener in her own right 
  in the same manner as the son and have the same rights in the coparcenary 
  property as she would have had if she had been a son, inclusive of the right 
  to claim by survivorship; and shall be subject to the same liabilities and 
  disabilities in respect thereto as the son; 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> at a partition in such a joint Hindu family the coparcenary property 
  shall be so divided as to allot to a daughter the same share as is allotable 
  to a son: </section>
 Provided that the share which a pre-deceased son or a pre-deceased daughter 
would have got at the partition if he or she had been alive at the time of the 
partition shall be allotted to the surviving child of such pre-deceased son or 
of such pre-deceased daughter: 
 Provided further that the share allotable to the pre-deceased child of a 
pre-deceased son or of a pre-deceased daughter, if such child had been alive at 
the time of the partition, shall be allotted to the child of such pre-deceased 
child of the pre-deceased son or of the pre-deceased daughter as the case may 
be; 
 
 <section><number>iii</number> any property to which a female Hindu becomes entitled by virtue of 
  the provisions of clause (i) shall be held by her with the incidents of 
  coparcenary ownership and shall be regarded, notwithstanding anything 
  contained in this Act or any other law for the time being in force, as 
  property capable of being disposed of by her by will or other testamentary 
  disposition; 
 </section><section><number>iv</number> Nothing in clause (ii) shall apply to a daughter married prior to or 
  to a partition which had been effected before the commencement of the Hindu 
  Succession (Andhra Pradesh Amendment) Act, 1986. </section>
 </article><article><title><number>29B</number> Interest to devolve by survivorship on death</title>.— 
When a female Hindu dies after the commencement of the Hindu Succession 
(Andhra Pradesh Amendment) Act, 1986 having at the time of her death an interest 
in a Mitakshara coparcenary property, her interest in the property 
shall devolve by survivorship upon the surviving members of the coparcenary and 
not in accordance with this Act: 
 Provided that if the deceased had left any child or child of a pre-deceased 
child, the interest of the deceased in the Mitakshara coparcenary 
property shall devolve by testamentary or intestate succession as the case may 
be, under this Act and not by survivorship. 
 Explanation I .—For the purposes of this section the interest of a 
female Hindu Mitakshara coparcener shall be deemed to be the share in 
the property that would have been allotted to her if a partition of the property 
had taken place immediately before her death irrespective of whether she was 
entitled to claim partition or not. 
 Explanation II .—Nothing contained in the proviso this section shall 
be construed as enabling a person who before the death of the deceased, had 
separated himself or herself from the coparcenary or any of his or her heirs to 
claim on intestacy a share in the interest referred to therein. 
 </article><article><title><number>29C</number> Preferential right to acquire property in certain 
cases</title>.— 
<section><number>1</number> Where, after the commencement of the Hindu Succession 
(Andhra Pradesh Amendment) Act, 1986 an interest in any immovable property of an 
intestate or in any business carried on by him or her, whether solely or in 
conjunction with others, devolves under section 29A or section 29B upon two or 
more heirs, and any one of such heirs proposes to transfer his or her interest 
in the property or business, the other heirs shall have a preferential right to 
acquire the interest proposed to be transferred. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The consideration for which any interest in the property of the deceased 
may be transferred under this section shall, in the absence of any agreement 
between the parties, be determined by the court on application being made toit 
in this behalf, and if any person proposing to acquire the interest is not 
willing to acquire it for the consideration so determined, such person shall be 
liable to pay all costs of or incidental to the application. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> If there are two or more heirs proposing to acquire any interest under 
this section, that heir who offers the highest consideration for the transfer 
shall be preferred. 
 Explanation. —In his section 'court' means the court within the 
limits of whose jurisdiction the immovable property is situate or the business 
is carried on, and includes any other court which the State Government may, by 
notification in the Andhra Pradesh Gazette, specify in this behalf." 
 [ Vide Andhra Pradesh Act 13 of 1986, sec. 2 (w.r.e.f. 5-9-1985).] 

 <title>Maharashtra </title>: 
 After Chapter II, insert the following Chapter, namely:— 
 “CHAPTER IIA <title></title>
 <title>SUCCESSION BY SURVIVORSHIP 
</title><title></title>
 </section></article><article><title><number>29A</number> Equal rights of daughter in coparcenary property</title>.— 
Notwithstanding anything contained in section 6 of this Act— 
 
 <section><number>i</number> in a joint Hindu family governed by the Mitakshara Law, the 
  daughter of a coparcener shall, by birth, become a coparcener in her own right 
  in the same manner as a son and have the same rights in the coparcenary 
  property as she would have had if she had been a son inclusive of the right to 
  claim by survivorship; and shall be subject to the same liabilities and 
  disabilities in respect thereto as the son; 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> at a partition in a joint Hindu family referred to in clause (i), the 
  coparcenary property shall be so divided as to allot to a daughter the same 
  share as is allotable to a son: </section>
 Provided that the share which a pre-deceased son or a pre-deceased daughter 
would have got at the partition if he or she had been alive at the time of the 
partition, shall be allotted to the surviving child of such pre-deceased son or 
of such pre-deceased daughter: 
 Provided further that the share allotable to the pre-deceased child of a 
pre-deceased son or of a pre-deceased daughter, if such child had been alive at 
the time of the partition, shall be allotted to the child of such pre-deceased 
child of the pre-deceased son or of the pre-deceased daughter as the case may 
be; 
 
 <section><number>iii</number> any property to which a female Hindu becomes entitled by virtue of 
  the provisions of clause (i) shall be held by her with the incidents of 
  coparcenary ownership and shall be regarded, notwithstanding anything 
  contained in this Act or any other law for the time being in force, as 
  property capable of being disposed of by her by will or other testamentary 
  disposition; 
 </section><section><number>iv</number> nothing in this Chapter shall apply to a daughter married before the 
  date of the commencement of the Hindu Succession (Maharashtra Amendment) Act, 
  1994; 
 </section><section><number>v</number> nothing in clause (ii) shall apply to a partition which has been 
  effected before the date of the commencement of the Hindu Succession 
  (Maharashtra Amendment) Act, 1994; </section>
 </article><article><title><number>29B</number> Interest to devolve by survivorship on death</title>.— 
When a female Hindu dies after the date of the commencement of the Hindu 
Succession (Maharashtra Amendment) Act, 1994, having, at the time of her death, 
an interest in a Mitakshara coparcenary property by virtue of the 
provisions of section 29A, her interest in the property shall devolve by 
survivorship upon the surviving members of the coparcenary and not in accordance 
with this Act: 
 Provided that, if the deceased had left any child or child of a pre-deceased 
child, the interest of the deceased in the Mitakshara coparcenary 
property shall devolve by testamentary or intestate succession, as the case may 
be, under this Act and not by survivorship. 
 Explanation I.—For the purposes of this section, the interest of a 
female Hindu in Mitakshara coparcener property shall be deemed to be 
the share in the property that would have been allotted to her if a partition of 
the property had taken place immediately before her death, irrespective of 
whether she was entitled to claim partition or not. 
 Explanation II.—Nothing contained in the proviso to this section 
shall be construed as enabling a person who, before the death of the deceased, 
had separated himself or herself from the coparcenary or any of his or her heirs 
to claim on intestacy a share in the interest referred to therein. 
 </article><article><title><number>29C</number> Preferential right to acquire property in certain 
cases</title>.— 
<section><number>1</number> Where, after the date of the commencement of the Hindu 
Succession (Maharashtra Amendment) Act, 1994 an interest in any immovable 
property of any intestate or in any business carried on by him or her, whether 
solely or in conjunction with others, devolves under section 29A or section 29B 
upon two or more heirs, and any one of such heirs proposes to transfer his or 
her interest in the property or business, the other heirs shall have a 
preferential right to acquire the interest proposed to be transferred. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The consideration for which any interest in the property of the deceased 
may be transferred under this section shall, in the absence of any agreement 
between the parties, be determined by the court on application being made to it 
in this behalf, and if any person proposing to acquire the interest is not 
willing to acquire it for the consideration so determined, such person shall be 
liable to pay all costs of or incidental to the application. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> If there are two or more heirs proposing to acquire any interest under 
this section, then, the heir who offers the highest consideration for the 
transfer shall be preferred. 
 Explanation .—In this section "court" means the court within the 
limits of whose jurisdiction the immovable property is situate or the business 
is carried on, and includes any other court which the State Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf." 
 [ Vide Maharashtra Act 39 of 1994, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 22-6-1994).] 
 <title>Tamil Nadu: </title>
 After Chapter II, insert the following Chapter, namely:— 
 <title>"Chapter IIA </title>
 <title>Succession by survivorship 
</title><title></title>
 </section></article><article><title><number>29A</number> Equal rights to daughter in coparcenary property</title>.— 
Notwithstanding anything contained in section 6 of this Act,— 
 
 <section><number>i</number> in a joint Hindu family governed by Mitakshara Law, the 
  daughter of a coparcener shall by birth become a coparcener in her own right 
  in thesame manner as a son and have the same rights in the coparcenary 
  property as she would have had if she had been a son, inclusive of the right 
  to claim by survivorship; and shall be subject to the same liabilities and 
  disabilities in respect thereto as the son; 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> at a partition in such a Joint Hindu Family the coparcenary property 
  shall be so divided as to allot to a daughter the same share as is allotable 
  to son: </section>
 Provided that the share which a pre-deceased son or a pre-deceased daughter 
would have got at the partition if he or she had been alive at the time of the 
partition shall be allotted to the surviving child of such pre-deceased son or 
of such pre-deceased daughter: 
 Provided further that the share allotable to the pre-deceased child of 
pre-deceased son or of a pre-deceased daughter, if such child had been alive at 
the time of the partition, shall be allotted to the child of such pre-deceased 
child of the pre-deceased son or of the pre-deceased daughter, as the case may 
be; 
 
 <section><number>iii</number> any property to which a female Hindu becomes entitled by virtue of 
  the provisions of clause (i) shall be held by her with the incidents of 
  coparcenary ownership and shall be regarded, notwithstanding anything 
  contained in this Act or any other law for the time being in force, as 
  property capable of being disposed of by her by will or other testamentary 
  disposition: 
 </section><section><number>iv</number> nothing in this Chapter shall apply to a daughter married before the 
  date of the commencement of the Hindu Succession (Tamil Nadu Amendment) Act, 
  1989; 
 </section><section><number>v</number> nothing in clause (ii) shall apply to a partition which had been 
  effected before the date of the commencement of the Hindu Succession (Tamil 
  Nadu Amendment) Act, 1989. </section>
 </article><article><title><number>29B</number> Interest to devolve by survivorship on death</title>.— 
When a female Hindu dies after the date of the commencement of the Hindu 
Succession (Tamil Nadu Amendment) Act, 1989, having at the time of her death, an 
interest in a Mitakshara coparcenary property by virtue of the 
provisions of section 29A, her interest in the property shall devolve by 
survivorship upon the surviving members of the coparcenary and not in accordance 
with this Act: 
 Provided that if the deceased had left any child or child of a pre-deceased 
child, the interest of the deceased in the Mitakshara coparcenary 
property shall devolve by testamentary or intestate succession, as the case may 
be, under this Act and not by survivorship. 
 Explanation I.— For the purposes of this section, the interest of a 
female Hindu Mitakshara coparcener shall be deemed to be the share in 
the property that would have been allotted to her if a partition of the property 
had taken place immediately before her death, irrespective of whether she was 
entitled to claim partition or not. 
 Explanation II.— Noting contained in the proviso to this section 
shall be construed as enabling a person who, before the death of the deceased 
had separated himself or herself from the coparcenary or any of his or her heirs 
to claim on intestacy a share in the interest referred to therein. 
 </article><article><title><number>29C</number> Preferential right to acquire property in certain 
cases.</title>— 
<section><number>1</number> Where, after the date of the commencement of the Hindu 
Succession (Tamil Nadu Amendment) Act, 1989, an interest in any immovable 
property of an intestate or in any business carried on by him or her, whether 
solely or in conjunction with others, devolves under section 29A or section 29B 
upon two or more heirs, and any one of such heirs proposes to transfer his or 
her interest in the property or business, the other heirs shall have a 
preferential right to acquire the interest proposed to be transferred. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The consideration for which any interest in the property of the deceased 
may be transferred under this section shall, in the absence of any agreement 
between the parties, be determined by the court on application being made to it 
in this behalf, and if any person proposing to acquire the interest is not 
willing to acquire it for the consideration so determined, such person shall be 
liable to pay all costs of, or incidental to, the application. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> If there are two or more heirs proposing to acquire any interest under 
this section, that heir who offers the highest consideration for the transfer 
shall be preferred. 
 Explanation.— In this section "court" means the court within the 
limits of whose jurisdiction the immovable property is situate or the business 
is carried on and includes any other court which the s tate Government may, by 
notification in the Tamil Nadu Government Gazette, specify in this behalf. 
 [ Vide Tamil Nadu Act 1 of 1990 sec. 2 (w.r.e.f. 25-3-1989).] 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>30</number> Testamentary succession. </title>— <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[***] Any Hindu 
may dispose of by will or other testamentary disposition any property, which is 
capable of being so <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[disposed of by him or by her], in accordance 
with the provisions of the Indian Succession Act, 1925 (39 of 1925), or any 
other law for the time being in force and applicable to Hindus. 
 Explanation.— The interest of a male Hindu in a Mitakshara 
coparcenary property or the interest of a member of a tarwad, tavazhi, 
illom, kutumba or kavaru in the property of the tarwad, 
tavazhi, illom, kutumba or kavaru shall notwithstanding anything 
contained in this Act or in any other law for the time being in force, be deemed 
to be property capable of being disposed of by him or by her within the meaning 
of this <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[section.] 
 <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[***] 




</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>31</number> Repeals </title>.—[ Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1960 
(58 of 1960), sec. 2 and Sch. I (w.e.f. 26-12-1960). ] </article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



THE HINDU SUCCESSION ACT, 1956
 



 



 



 


THE SCHEDULE
 



(See section 8)
 


HEIRS IN CLASS I AND CLASS II
 

 
 


Class 
    I
 


Son; daughter; widow; mother; son of a 
    pre-deceased son; daughter of a pre-deceased son; son of a pre-deceased 
    daughter; daughter of a pre-deceased daughter; widow of a pre-deceased son; 
    son of a pre-deceased son of a pre-deceased son; daughter of a pre-deceased 
    son of a pre-deceased son; widow of a pre-deceased son of a pre-deceased 
    son; 1[son of a pre-deceased 
    daughter of a pre-deceased daughter; daughter of a pre-deceased daughter of 
    a pre-deceased daughter; daughter of a pre-deceased son of a pre-deceased 
    daughter; daughter of a pre-deceased daughter of a pre-deceased son].
 

 
 


Class 
    II
 
 
 
 


Father.
 
 


(1) Son’s daughter’s son, (2) son’s 
        daughter’s daughter, (3) brother, (4) sister.
 
 


(1) Daughter’s son’s son, (2) daughter’s 
        son’s daughter, (3) daughter’s daughter’s son, (4) daughter’s daughter’s 
        daughter.
 
 


(1) Brother’s son, (2) sister’s son, (3) 
        brother’s daughter, (4) sister’s daughter.
 
 


Father’s father; father’s mother.
 
 


Father’s widow; brother’s widow.
 
 


Father’s brother; father’s sister.
 
 


Mother’s father; mother’s mother.
 
 


Mother’s brother; mother’s sister.


 


Explanation.—In this Schedule, 
    references to a brother or sister do not include references to a brother or 
    sister by uterine blood.
 


 
 


-------------------------------
 


            1.         
    Added by Act 39 of 2005, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 9-9-2005).
 


-------------------------------
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Ins. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, 
1956.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>  Sub-section (2) omitted 
    by Act 39 of 2005, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 9-9-2005). Sub-section (2), before 
    omission, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Subs. by Act 39 of 2005, sec. 3, for section 6 (w.e.f. 
9-9-2005). Section 6, before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Section 23, before repeal by Act 39 of 2005, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Section 24, before repeal by Act 39 of 2005, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> The brackets and figure “(1)” omitted by Act 58 of 1960, sec. 
3 and Sch. II (w.e.f. 26-12-1960).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Subs. by Act 39 of 2005, sec. 6, for “disposed of by him” 
(w.e.f. 9-9-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Subs. by Act 56 of 1974, sec. 3 and Sch. II, for 
“sub-section”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> Sub-section (2) omitted by Act 78 of 1956, sec. 29 (w.e.f. 
21-12-1956).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>