<act><tid>686232</tid>
<title>THE APPROPRIATION (No. 3) ACT, <year>1996</year></title>

ACT NO. 31 OF <year>1996</year>
[ 23rd September, <year>1996</year>]

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- seventh Year of 
the 
Republic of India as follows:-

An Act to authorise payment and appropriation of certain 
sums 
from and out of the Consolidated Fund of India for the services of 
the 
financial year <year>1996</year>- 97.





<article><tid>1231054</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Appropriation (No.  
  3) Act, <year>1996</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>869544</tid>
<number>2</number>Issue of Rs. 465857, 03, 00, 000 out of the Consolidated Fund 
of India for the year <year>1996</year>- 97. From and out of the Consolidated Fund 
of India there may be paid and applied sums not exceeding those 
specified in column 3 of the Schedule amounting in the aggregate 
[ inclusive of the sums specified in column 3 of the Schedule to the 
Appropriation (Vote on Account) No. 2 Act, <year>1996</year>] (18 of <year>1996</year>). to 
the sum of four lakh sixty- five thousand eight hundred and fifty- seven 
crores and three lakh rupees towards defraying the several charges 
which will come in course of payment during the financial year <year>1996</year>- 97 
in respect of the services specified in column 2 of the Schedule.


</article>



<article><tid>795529</tid>
<number>3</number>Appropriation. The sums authorised to be paid and applied 
from and out of the Consolidated Fund of India by this Act shall be 
appropriated for the services and purposes expressed in the Schedule 
in relation to the said year.


</article>



<article><tid>395753</tid>
<number>4</number>Construction of references to Ministries and Departments in 
the Schedule. References to Ministries or Departments in the 
Schedule are to such Ministries or Departments as existing immediately 
before the 28th June, <year>1996</year> and shall, on or after that date, be 
construed as references to the appropriate Ministries or Departments 
as reconstituted from time to time.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</article>



 </act>