<act><title>


The Disaster Management (National Institute of Disaster Management) Rules, 20061</title> 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Disaster Management (National Institute of 
Disaster Management) Rules, 2006.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 



</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  “Act” means 
the Disaster Management Act, 2005 (53 of 2005);
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  “chairperson” 
means the chairperson of the governing body;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  “executive 
director” means the executive director of the institute appointed by the Central 
Government;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  “governing 
body” means the governing body of the institute;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  “institute” 
means the National Institute of Disaster Management;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  “president” 
means the president of the institute;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>g</number>  “secretary” 
means the secretary of the institute and the governing body;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>h</number>  “section” 
means a section of the Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>i</number>  
“vice-chairperson” means the vice-chairperson of the governing body of the 
institute;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>j</number>  
“vice-president” means the vice-president of the institute;
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Words and expressions 
used herein and not defined but defined in the Act shall have the meanings 
respectively assigned to them in the Act.
</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> Composition of the 
institute.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The institute shall consist of the following members, namely:—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  the Minister 
in charge of the Ministry or Department of the Central Government having 
administrative control of disaster management, who shall be the President, ex 
officio;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  the 
Vice-Chairperson of the National Authority who shall be the vice-president, 
ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number>  one member 
of the National Authority;   
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iv</number>  Chairperson 
of the National Executive Committee, that is, the Secretary to the Government of 
India in charge of the Ministry or Department of the Central Government having 
administrative control of disaster management, ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>v</number>  the Secretary 
to the Government of India in charge of the Ministry or Department of the 
Central Government having administrative control of expenditure, ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>vi</number>  the Secretary 
to the Government of India in charge of the Ministry or Department of the 
Central Government having administrative control of agriculture, ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection>
 
<number>vii</number>  the Secretary to 
the Government of India in charge of the Ministry or Department of the Central 
Government having administrative control of External Affairs, ex 
officio;
 </subsection><subsection>
     <number>viii</number>  the Secretary 
to the Government of India in charge of the Ministry or Department of the 
Central Government having administrative control of health, ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>ix</number>  the Secretary 
to the Government of India in charge of the Ministry or Department of the 
Central Government having administrative control of science and technology, 
ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>x</number>  the Secretary 
to the Government of India in charge of the Ministry or Department of the 
Central Government having administrative control of atomic energy, ex 
officio;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>xi</number>  the Secretary 
to the Government of India in charge of the Ministry or Department of the 
Central Government having administrative control of space, ex officio;
 <subsubsection>
      <number>xii</number>  the Secretary 
to the Government of India in charge of the Ministry or Department of the 
Central Government having administrative control of ocean development, ex 
officio;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
      <number>xiii</number>  the 
Secretary or Special Secretary or Additional-Secretary or Joint-Secretary, as 
the case may be, to the Government of India dealing with disaster management in 
the Ministry or Department of the Central Government having administrative 
control of disaster management, ex officio;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
     <number>xiv</number>  the Additional 
Secretary and Financial Advisor or Joint Secretary and Financial Advisor, as the 
case may be, to the Government of India dealing with finance of the Ministry or 
Department of the Central Government having administrative control of disaster 
management, ex officio;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
      <number>xv</number>  the Secretary 
or Additional Secretary, as the case may be, of the National Disaster Management 
Authority, ex officio;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
     <number>xvi</number> the 
Director-General of the National Disaster Response Force, ex officio;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
     <number>xvii</number>  the Deputy 
Chief of Integrated Defence Staff, Doctrine Organisation and Training (DOT), 
Head Quarters Integrated Defence Staff, Ministry of Defence ex officio;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>xviii</number>  two 
Secretaries of State Governments in charge of disaster management; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
     <number>xix</number>  one 
vice-chancellor from the universities;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
      <number>xx</number>  the Director, 
Lal Bahadur Shastri National Academy of Administration, Mussorrie;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
     <number>xxi</number>  the Director, 
Sardar Vallabah Bhai Patel National Police Academy, Hyderabad; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
     <number>xxii</number>  the Director 
General, India Meteorological Department, ex officio: 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>xxiii</number>  two 
Directors, one each, from any Indian Institute of Management and any Indian 
Institute of Technology;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>xxiv</number>  the Chairman 
of the Central Water Commission, ex officio; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>xxv</number>  the Director of 
Indian-Institute of Public Administration, ex officio; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>xxvi</number>  the Director 
General of Indian Council of Agriculture Research, ex officio; 

 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>xxvii</number>  one Director 
General from the Administrative Training Institutes or State Institutes of Rural 
Development;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>xxviii</number>  the Director 
General of Indian Council of Medical Research, ex officio; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
 
<number>xxix</number>  two eminent 
persons in the field of disaster management, public administration, information 
technology, medicine etc.;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
     <number>xxx</number>  two experts, 
one each from banking and insurance sector;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>xxxi</number>  two presidents 
or heads, by whatever name called, from the industry associations or federations 
of all-India-level which in the opinion of the Central Government are capable of 
representing the industry, trade or commerce;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>xxxii</number>  two presidents 
or heads, by whatever name called, from non-governmental organisations which in 
the opinion of the Central Government are active and effective in the disaster 
management activities, or are capable of representing such activities;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>xxxiii</number>  one head from 
science and technology institutions; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
  <number>xxxiv</number>  one head from 
medical or health institutions; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>xxxv</number>  one professor 
of the National Institute of Disaster Management; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
  <number>xxxvi</number>  the Executive 
Director of the Institute, ex officio.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Central Government 
shall nominate the members of the Institute, other than the ex officio 
members in such manner as it may consider appropriate.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Vice-Chairperson 
of the National Authority shall nominate the member of the National Authority 
for the institute.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Save as otherwise 
provided in this sub-rule, the term of office of—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  an ex 
officio member of the institute shall continue so long as he holds the 
office by virtue of which he is such a member; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  a nominated 
member of the institute shall be two years from the date of his nomination:
 
Provided that a member 
other than an ex officio member of the institute may resign from the 
office of such member, by writing under his hand addressed to the Central 
Government, but he shall continue in office until his resignation is accepted by 
that Government.
</subsection></section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> Filling up of 
vacancies.—All 
vacancies by reason of resignation, death or otherwise among members (other than
ex officio members) of the Institute shall be filled as soon as may be 
after the occurrence of the vacancy by a fresh nomination.
</article> 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> Meetings of the 
institute.—The 
institute shall hold its first meeting at such time and place as may be 
appointed by the Central Government and observe such rules of procedure in 
regard to the transaction of business at the first meeting as may be laid down 
by that Government and thereafter the institute shall meet at such times and 
places and observe such rules of procedure in regard to the transaction of 
business at its meetings as may be determined by regulations.
</article> 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> Governing body of 
the institute.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Governing body of the institute shall consist of the following members, 
namely:—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  The 
Vice-Chairperson of the National Authority who shall be the chairperson, ex 
officio;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  the 
Secretary to the Government of India in-charge of the Ministry or Department of 
the Central Government having administrative control of disaster management, who 
shall be the vice-chairperson, ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number>  the 
Secretary or Special Secretary or Additional-Secretary or Joint- Secretary, as 
the case may be, to the Government of India dealing with disaster management in 
the Ministry or Department of the Central Government having administrative 
control of disaster management, ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iv</number>  the Secretary 
to the Government of India in-charge of the Ministry or Department of the 
Central Government having administrative control of expenditure, ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>v</number>  the Secretary 
or Additional Secretary, as the case may be, of the National Authority; ex 
officio;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>vi</number>  the 
Additional Secretary and Financial Advisor or Joint-Secretary and Financial 
Advisor, as the case may be, to the Government of India dealing with finance of 
the Ministry or Department of the Central Government having administrative 
control of disaster management, ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>vii</number>  one member 
from amongst the members of the institute representing the State Governments;
 </subsection><subsection>
     <number>viii</number>  one member of 
the institute representing the university;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>ix</number> two members of 
the institute representing the Indian Institute of Technology and the Indian 
Institute of Management; 
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>x</number>  one member of 
the institute representing a science and technology institution;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>xi</number>  two members 
from amongst the members of the institute representing the Department of Space, 
the Department of Atomic Energy, the Department of Science and Technology, the 
Central Water Commission and the Indian Council of Agriculture Research; and
 <subsubsection>
      <number>xii</number>  the executive 
director of the institute, ex officio.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The governing body 
shall be the executive committee of the institute and  shall exercise such 
powers and perform such functions as the institute may, by regulations made in 
this behalf, confer or impose upon it.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The procedure to be 
followed in the exercise of its powers and performance of its functions by the 
governing body, and the term of office of, and the manner of filling up 
vacancies, among the members of the governing body, shall be such as may be made 
by regulations.
</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number> Executive Director 
of the institute.—
<section><number>1</number> 
There shall be an Executive Director of the institute who shall be appointed by 
the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Executive Director 
of the institute shall act as the Secretary to the institute as well as the 
governing body of the institute.
</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>8</number> Powers and functions 
of the Executive Director.—The 
Executive Director of the institute shall exercise such powers and perform such 
functions as may be made by regulations.
</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>