<act><tid>689121</tid>
<title>THE JUDICIAL COMMISSIONERS' COURTS (DECLARATION AS HIGH COURTS) 
ACT, <year>1950</year></title>

ACT NO. 15 OF <year>1950</year> AN ACT TO DECLARE <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> CERTAIN JUDICIAL COMMISSIONERS' COUR 
TS] TO BE HIGH COURT
[ 10th March, <year>1950</year>.]

BE it enacted by Parliament as follows:-





<article><tid>719754</tid>
<number> 1</number> 
<section><tid>1842769</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title and commencement. This Act may be called the  
Judicial Commissioners' Courts (Declaration as High Courts) Act, <year>1950</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1442618</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 26th day 
of January, <year>1950</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1125621</tid>
<number>2</number>Definition. In this Act," article" means an article of 
the, Constitution.


</article>



<article><tid>1747421</tid>
<number>3</number>Declaration of certain Judicial Commissioner' s Courts as 
High Courts for certain purposes. The Courts of the Judicial 
Commissioners for <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Manipur and Tripura (each of which is  
  hereinafter referred to as a Judicial Commissioner' s Court) is hereby 
declared to be a High Court for the purposes of articles 132, 133 and 
134.]


</article>



<article><tid>1616687</tid>
<number>4</number>Appeals to the Supreme Court not to be barred on ground of 
judgment etc., being of a single Judge. An appeal shall lie to the 
Supreme Court under the provisions of article 133 from any judgment, 
decree or final order of a Judicial Commissioner' s Court 
notwithstanding that such judgment, decree or final order is that of a 
single Judge.


</article>



<article><tid>625550</tid>
<number>5</number>Appeals to lie to the Supreme Court from judgment, decree, 
etc., whether passed or made before or after the commencement of the 
Act. Subject to any rules made under article 145 or any other law as 
to the time within which appeals to the Supreme Court are to be 
entered, an appeal shall lie to that Court from a judgment, decree or 
final order of a Judicial Commissioner' s Court, under the provisions 
of article 132 or article 133, or from a judgment, final order or 
sentence of such Court under the provisions of article 134 whether 
such judgment, decree, final order or sentence, as the case may be, 
was passed or made before or after the commencement of this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>96</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" the 
Judicial Commissioners' Courts in Part C States".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs., ibid., for the original section.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>The words" Himachal Pradesh" omitted by Act 26 of <year>1966</year>, s. 19 and 
Sch. (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1967</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>907448</tid>
<number> 6</number> Exceptions and modifications subject to which the 
provisions of Chapter V of Part VI of the Constitution apply to the 
Judicial Commissioner' s Courts. The provisions of Chapter V of Part VI 
of the Constitution shall in their application to a Judicial 
Commissioner' s Court have effect subject to the following exceptions 
and modifications, namely:-
<section><tid>372974</tid>
<number>a</number>the provisions of articles 216, 217, 218, 220, 221, 222, 
223, 224 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 230 and 231] shall not apply;

</section>

<section><tid>76621</tid>
<number>b</number>references in article 219, in the proviso to clause (3) 
of article 227 and in article 229 to the Governor shall be 
construed as references to <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the administrator of the Union 
territory] in relation to which that Court exercises 
jurisdiction.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>97</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order. <year>1956</year>, for 230, 
231 and 232".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs., ibid., for" the Chief Commissioner of the State".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>