<act><tid>690021</tid>
<title>THE DEPARTMENTAL INQUIRIES (ENFORCEMENT OF ATTENDANCE OF WITNESSES  
  ANDPRODUCTION OF DOCUMENTS) ACT, <year>1972</year></title>

ACT NO. 18 OF <year>1972</year>
[ 31st May, <year>1972</year>.]

An Act to provide for the enforcement of attendance of witnesses 
and production of documents in certain departmental inquiries and for 
matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.

Be it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- third Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-





<article><tid>295025</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>1368037</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Departmental Inquiries (Enforcement of Attendance of Witnesses and  
  Production of Documents) Act, <year>1972</year>

</section>

<section><tid>294198</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and 
Kashmir.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>551511</tid>
<number> 2</number> Departmental inquiries to which the Act shall apply. The 
provisions of this Act shall apply to every departmental inquiry made 
in relation to-
<section><tid>1796950</tid>
<number>a</number>persons appointed to public services or posts in 
connection with the affairs of the Union;

</section>

<section><tid>954172</tid>
<number>b</number>persons who, having been appointed to any public 
service or post in connection with the affairs of the Union, 
are in service or pay of,-

<subsection><tid>44049</tid>
<number>i</number>any local authority in any Union territory,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>767437</tid>
<number>ii</number>any corporation established by or under a Central 
Act and owned or controlled by the Central 
Government,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>745766</tid>
<number>iii</number>any Government company within the meaning of 
section 617 of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), in 
which not less than fifty- one per cent. of the paid- up 
share capital is held by the Central Government or any 
company which is a subsidiary of such Government 
company,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1548126</tid>
<number>iv</number>any society registered under the Societies 
Registration Act, <year>1860</year>, (21 of <year>1860</year>.) which is subject 
to the control of the Central Government.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>86</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>878467</tid>
<number> 3</number> Definitions. For the purposes of this Act,-
<section><tid>176395</tid>
<number>a</number>" departmental inquiry" means an inquiry held under and 
in accordance with-

<subsection><tid>380054</tid>
<number>i</number>any law made by Parliament or any rule made thereunder, 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1009776</tid>
<number>ii</number>any rule made under the proviso to article 309, or 
continued under article 313, of the Constitution of India,
into any allegation of lack of integrity against any person 
to whom this Act applies;


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>225303</tid>
<number>b</number>" inquiring authority" means an officer or authority 
appointed by the Central Government or by any officer or 
authority subordinate to that Government to hold a 
departmental inquiry and includes any officer or authority 
who is empowered by or under any law or rule for the time 
being in force to hold such inquiry;

</section>

<section><tid>185815</tid>
<number>c</number>" lack of integrity" includes bribery or corruption.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>509380</tid>
<number> 4</number> Power of Central Government to authorise the exercise of powers 
specified in section 5.
<section><tid>1070477</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the Central Government is of opinion  
that for the purposes of any departmental inquiry it is necessary to 
summon as witnesses, or call for any document from, any class or 
category of persons it may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
authorise the inquiring authority to exercise the power specified in 
section 5 in relation to any person within such class or category and 
thereupon the inquiring authority may exercise such power at any stage 
of the departmental inquiry.

</section>

<section><tid>943024</tid>
<number>2</number>The power conferred on the Central Government by sub- section 
 (1) may also be exercised by such authority, not being an authority 
inferior to the appointing authority in relation to the person against 
whom the departmental inquiry is being held, as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1594370</tid>
<number> 5</number> Power of authorised inquiring authority to enforce attendance 
of witnesses and production of documents.
<section><tid>901746</tid>
<number>1</number>Every inquiring  
authority authorised under section 4 (hereafter referred to as the  
 " authorised inquiring authority") shall have the same powers as are 
vested in a civil court under the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year>, while 
trying a suit, in respect of the following matters, 5 of <year>1908</year> namely:-

<subsection><tid>275873</tid>
<number>a</number>the summoning and enforcing the attendance of any 
witness and examining him on oath;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>678351</tid>
<number>b</number>requiring the discovery and production of any document 
or other material which is producible as evidence;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>799414</tid>
<number>c</number>the requisitioning of any public record from any court 
or office.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>87</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1383953</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), the 
authorised inquiring authority shall not compel the Reserve Bank of 
India, the State Bank of India, any subsidiary bank as defined in 
clause (k) of sectionII" of the State Bank of India (Subsidiary Banks) 
Act, <year>1959</year> (38 of <year>1959</year>), or any corresponding new bank constituted 
under section 3 of the Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of  
  Undertakings) Act, <year>1970</year>, (5 of <year>1970</year>).

<subsection><tid>363251</tid>
<number>a</number>to produce any books of account or other documents 
which the Reserve Bank of India, the State Bank of India, the 
subsidiary bank or the corresponding new bank claims to be of 
a confidential nature, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>776929</tid>
<number>b</number>to make any such books or documents a part of the 
record of the proceedings of the departmental inquiry, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>568854</tid>
<number>c</number>to give inspection of any such books or documents, if 
produced, to any party before it or to any other person.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1883053</tid>
<number>3</number>Every process issued by an authorised inquiring authority 
for the attendance of any witness or for the production of any 
document shall be served and executed through the District Judge 
within the local limits of whose jurisdiction the witness or other 
person, on whom the process is to be served or executed, voluntarily 
resides or carries on business or personally works for gain, and, for 
the purpose of taking any action for the disobedience of any such 
process, every such process shall be deemed to be a process issued 
by the District Judge.

</section>

<section><tid>961587</tid>
<number>4</number>Every authorised inquiring authority making any departmental 
inquiry under this Act shall be deemed to be a civil court for the 
purposes of sections 480 and 482 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 
<year>1898</year>. (5 of <year>1898</year>.)



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1636935</tid>
<number>6</number>Territorial limits in which powers specified In may be 
exercised. For the purpose of exercising the powers specified in 
section 5, the territorial jurisdiction of every authorised inquiring 
authority shall extend to the limits of the territory to which this 
Act extends.


</article>



<article><tid>1111278</tid>
<number> 7</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1441549</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, be  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for the purpose of 
giving effect to the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>974139</tid>
<number>2</number>Every rule made by the Central Government under this section 
shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House 
of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty days 
which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive 
sessions,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>88</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the 
session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in 
making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule 
should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, 
that the modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.



</section>

</article>



 </act>