<act><title>THE MEDICAL TERMINATION OF PREGNANCY RULES, 1975 </title> 

  
  
<title>1. Short title and commencement</title>.—(1) These rules may be called the Medical Termination of Pregnancy Rules, 1975. 
(2) They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>2</number> Definitions.In 
    these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,
 <section>


    <number>a</number>    Act means the Medical Termination of Pregnancy Act, 1971 (34 of 
    1971);
 </section><section>


    <number>b</number>    Chief Medical Officer of the District means the Chief Medical 
    Officer of a District, by whatever name called;
 </section><section>


    <number>c</number>    Form means a form appended to these rules;
 </section><section>


    <number>d</number>    owner, in relation to a place, means any person who is the 
    administrative head or otherwise responsible for the working or maintenance 
    of such hospital or clinic, by whatever name called;
 </section><section>


    <number>e</number>    place means such building, tent, vehicle or vessel, or part 
    thereof, as is used for the establishment or maintenance therein of a 
    hospital or clinic which is used, or intended to be used, for the 
    termination of any pregnancy;
 </section><section>


    <number>f</number>    section means a section of the Act.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>3</number> Experience or training, etc.For 
    the purpose of clause (d) of section 2, a registered medical practitioner 
    shall have one or more of the following experience or training in 
    gynaecology and obstetrics, namely:  
 <section>


    <number>a</number>    in the case of a medical practitioner who was registered in a State 
    Medical Register immediately before the commencement of the Act, experience 
    in the practice of gynaecology and obstetrics for a period of not less than 
    three years;  
 </section><section>


    <number>b</number>    in the case of a medical practitioner who was registered in a State 
    Medical Register on or after the date of the commencement.  
 <subsection>


    <number>i</number>    if he has completed six months of house surgency in gynaecology and 
    obstetrics; or   
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>ii</number>    where he has not done any such house surgery, if he had experience 
    at any hospital for a period of not less than one year in the practice of 
    obstetrics and gynaecology; or   
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>iii</number>    if he has assisted a registered medical practitioner in the 
    performance of twenty-five cases of medical termination of pregnancy in a 
    hospital established or maintained, or a training institute approved for 
    this purpose, by the Government;  
 </subsection></section><section>


    <number>c</number>    in the case of a medical practitioner who has been registered in a 
    State Medical Register and who holds a postgraduate degree or diploma in 
    gynaecology and obstetrics, the experience or training gained during the 
    course of such degree or diploma.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>4</number> Approval of a place.
<section><number>1</number> 
    No place shall be approved under clause (b) of section 4,-  
 <subsection>


                   <number>i</number>    unless the Government is satisfied that termination of 
    pregnancies may be done therein under safe and hygienic conditions; and
      
 </subsection><subsection>


                 <number>ii</number>    unless the following facilities are provided therein, 
    namely:  
 <subsubsection>


    <number>a</number>    an operation table and instruments for performing abdominal or 
    gynaecological surgery;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>


    <number>b</number>    anaesthetic equipment, resuscitation equipment and sterilization 
    equipment;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>


    <number>c</number>    drugs and parenteral fluids for emergency use.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>


    <number>2</number> Every application for the approval of a place shall be in Form A and 
    shall be addressed to the Chief Medical Officer of the District;  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> On receipt of an application referred to in sub-rule (2), the Chief 
    Medical Officer of the District shall verify or enquire any information 
    contained in any such application or inspect any such place with a view to 
    satisfy himself that the facilities referred to in sub-rule (1) are provided 
    therein, and that termination of pregnancies may be made therein under safe 
    and hygienic conditions.  
 </section><section>


    <number>4</number> Every owner of the place which is inspected by the Chief Medical Officer 
    of the District shall afford all reasonable facilities for the inspection of 
    the place.  
 </section><section>


    <number>5</number> The Chief Medical Officer of the District may, if he is satisfied after 
    such verification, enquiry or inspection, as may be considered necessary, 
    that termination of pregnancies may be done under safe and hygienic 
    conditions, at the place, recommend the approval of such place to the 
    Government.  
 </section><section>


    <number>6</number> The Government may after considering the application and the 
    recommendations of the Chief Medical Officer of the District approve such 
    place and issue a certificate of approval in Form B.  
 </section><section>


    <number>7</number> The certificate of approval issued by the Government shall be 
    conspicuously displayed at the place to be easily visible to persons 
    visiting the place.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>5</number> Inspection of a place.
<section><number>1</number> 
    A place approved under rule 4 may be inspected by the Chief Medical Officer 
    of the District, as often as may be necessary with a view to verify whether 
    termination of pregnancies is being done therein under safe and hygienic 
    conditions.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> If the Chief Medical Officer has reason to believe that there has been 
    death of, or injury to, a pregnant woman at the place or that termination of 
    pregnancies is not being done at the place under safe and hygienic 
    conditions, he may call for any information or may seize any article, 
    medicine, ampule, admission register or other document, maintained, kept 
    found at the place.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> The provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), 
    relating to seizure shall, so far as may be, apply to seizures made under 
    sub-rule (2).

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>6</number> Cancellation or suspension of certificate of approval.
<section><number>1</number> 
    If, after inspection of any place approved under rule 4, the Chief Medical 
    Officer of the District is satisfied that the facilities specified in rule 4 
    are not being properly maintained therein and the termination of pregnancy 
    at such place cannot be made under safe and hygienic conditions, he shall 
    make a report of the fact to the Government giving the detail of the 
    deficiencies or defects found at the place. On receipt of such report the 
    Government may after giving the owner of the place a reasonable port unity 
    of being heard either cancel the certificate of approval or suspend the same 
    for such period as it may think fit.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> Where a certificate issued under rule 4 is cancelled or suspended, the 
    owner of the place may make such additions or improvements in the place as 
    he may think fit and thereafter, he may make an application to the 
    Government for the issue to him of a fresh certificate of approval under 
    rule 4 or, as the case may be, for the revival of the certificate which was 
    suspended under sub-rule (1).  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> The provisions of rule 4 shall, as far as may, apply to an application 
    for the issue of a fresh certificate of approval in relation to a place, or 
    as the case may be, for the revival of a suspended certificate as they apply 
    to an application for issue of a certificate of approval under that rule.  
 </section><section>


    <number>4</number> In the event of suspension of certificate, of approval, the place shall 
    not be deemed to be an approved place for the purposes of termination of 
    pregnancy from the date of communication of the order of suspension.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>7</number> Review.
<section><number>1</number> 
    The owner of a place who is aggrieved by an order made under rule 6, may 
    make an application for review of the order to the Government within a 
    period of sixty days from the date of such order.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> The Government may, after giving the owner an opportunity of being 
    heard, confirm, modify or reverse the order.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>8</number> Form of consent.The 
    consent referred to in sub-section (4) of section 3 shall be given in Form 
    C.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>9</number> Repeal and saving.The 
    Medical Termination of Pregnancy Rules, 1972, are hereby repealed except as 
    respects things done or omitted to be done before such repeal.  
  

 
  


</article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




    THE MEDICAL TERMINATION OF PREGNANCY RULES, 1975
 



 



 




    FORM A
 




    [See sub-rule (2) of rule 4] 
 




    Form of application for the approval of a place  

    under clause (b) of section 4
 

 
 




    1. Name of the place (in capital letters)   
    ...........................................................................
 




    2. Address in full................................................................................................................
 




    3. Non-Government/Private/Nursing Home/Other 
    institutions*.................................
 




    4. State, if the following facilities are available at the place:
 




                (1)  An operation table and instruments for performing abdominal 
    or gynaecological surgery.
 




                (2)  Drugs and parenteral fluid in sufficient supply for 
    emergency cases.
 




                (3)  Anaesthetic equipment, resuscitation equipment and 
    sterilization equipment.
 





 




    Signature of the owner of the place
 




    Place: .....................                
 




    Date: ......................
 




    *Strike out whichever is not applicable.
 

 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




    THE MEDICAL TERMINATION OF PREGNANCY RULES, 1975
 



 



 




    FORM B
 




    [See sub-rule (6) of rule 4]
 




    Certificate of approval
 




    The place described below is herby approved for the purpose of the Medical 
    Termination of Pregnancy Act, 1971 (34 of 1971).
 
 
 
 



        Name of the place 
 

        Address and other Description
 Name of the 
        Owner


 

 
 




    Place: .........................
 




    Date: ..........................            
 




    to the Government of the.....................
 

 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 
 

 
 
 

THE 
      MEDICAL TERMINATION OF PREGNANCY RULES, 1975
 

 
 

 
 

FROM 
      C
 

(See rule 
      8)
 

I, 
      ............................................... daughter/wife of 
      .............................. aged about ................................ 
      years of ................................................. At resent 
      residing at ..................................... do hereby give my 
      consent to the termination of my pregnancy 
      at.......................................................................................
 

                        
      (State the name of place where the pregnancy is to be 
      terminated)
 

Place: 
      .........................            
      
 

Date: 
      .........................
 

Signature
 

 
 

(To be filled in 
      by guardian where the woman is a lunatic or minor)
 

I,..........................................., 
      son/daughter/wife of.................................................... 
      aged about........................................... years 
      of........................................................................................ 
      (here state the permanent address) at present residing 
      at................................................. 
      ......................................................................... 
      do hereby give my consent to the termination of the pregnancy of my 
      ward.................................................................................... 
      who is a minor/lunatic 
      at....................................................................................................................
 

(place of 
      termination of pregnancy)
 

 
 

Place: 
      .........................
 

Date: 
      .........................             
      
 

Signature
 
 

 </form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>