<act><title>


The Bio-Medical Waste (Management and Handling) 
Rules, 19981</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Bio-Medical Waste (Management and Handling) Rules, 
1998.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date
 of their 
publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Application.—These 
rules apply to all persons who generate, collect, receive, store, transport, 
treat, dispose, or handle bio-medical waste in any form.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>

      <number>1</number> “Act” means the Environment (Protection) Act, 1986 (29 of 1986);
 </section><section>

      <number>2</number> “animal house” means a place where animals are reared/kept for 
experiments or testing purposes;
 </section><section>

      <number>3</number> “authorisation” means permission granted by the prescribed authority 
for the generation, collection, reception, storage, transportation, treatment, 
disposal and/or any other form of handling of bio-medical waste in accordance 
with these rules and any guidelines issued by the Central Government;
 </section><section>

      <number>4</number> “authorised person” means an occupier or operator authorised by the 
prescribed authority to generate, collect, receive, store, transport, treat, 
dispose, and/or handle bio-medical waste in accordance with these rules and any 
guidelines issued by the Central Government;
 </section><section>

      <number>5</number> “bio-medical waste” means any waste which is generated during the 
diagnosis, treatment or immunisation of human beings or animals or in research 
activities pertaining thereto or in the production or testing of biologicals, 
and including categories  mentioned in Schedule I;
 </section><section>

      <number>6</number> “biologicals” means any preparation made from organisms or 
micro-organisms or product of metabolism and biochemical reactions intended for 
use in the diagnosis, immunisation or the treatment of human beings or animals 
or in research activities pertaining thereto;
 </section><section>

      <number>7</number> “bio-medical waste treatment facility” means any facility wherein 
treatment, disposal of bio-medical waste or process incidental to such treatment 
or disposal is carried out 

1[and 
includes common treatment facilities];
 

  2[(7a) 
“Form” means Form appended to these rules.]
 </section><section>

      <number>8</number> “occupier” in relation to any institution generating bio-medical 
waste, which includes a hospital, nursing home, clinic, dispensary, veterinary 
institution, animal house, pathological laboratory, blood bank by whatever name 
called, means a person who has control over that institution and/or its 
premises;
 </section><section>

      <number>9</number> “operator of a bio-medical waste facility” means a person who owns or 
controls or operates a facility for the collection, reception, storage, 
transport, treatment, disposal or any other form of handling of bio-medical 
waste;
 </section><section>
    
<number>10</number> “Schedule” means Schedule appended to these rules.
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Duty of occupier.—It 
shall be the duty of every  occupier of an institution generating bio-medical 
waste which includes a hospital, nursing home, clinic, dispensary, veterinary 
institution, animal house, pathological laboratory, blood bank by whatever name 
called to take all steps to ensure that such waste is handled without any 
adverse effect to human health and the environment.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Treatment and 
disposal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Bio-medical waste shall be treated and disposed of in accordance with Schedule 
I, and in compliance with the standards prescribed in Schedule V.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every occupier, where 
required, shall set up in accordance with the time-schedule in Schedule VI, 
requisite bio-medical waste treatment facilities like incinerator, autoclave, 
microwave system for the treatment of waste, or, ensure requisite treatment of 
waste at a common waste treatment or any other waste treatment facility.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Segregation, 
packaging, transportation and storage.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Bio-medical waste shall not be mixed with other wastes.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Bio-medical waste 
shall be segregated into containers/bags at the point of generation in 
accordance with Schedule II prior to its storage, transportation, treatment and 
disposal. The containers shall be labelled according to Schedule III.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If a container is 
transported from the premises where bio-medical waste is generated to any waste 
treatment facility outside the premises, the container shall, apart from the 
label prescribed in Schedule III, also carry information prescribed in Schedule 
IV.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in the Motor Vehicles Act, 1988, or rules thereunder, 
untreated bio-medical waste shall be transported only in such vehicle as may be 
authorised for the purpose by the competent authority as specified by the 
Government.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> No untreated 
bio-medical waste shall be kept stored beyond a period of 48 hours:
 
Provided that if for any 
reason it becomes necessary to store the waste beyond such period, the 
authorised person must take permission of the prescribed authority and take 
measures to ensure that the waste does not adversely affect human health and the 
environment.
 

1[(6) The Municipal 
body of the area shall continue to pick up the transport segregated non 
bio-medical solid waste generated in hospitals and nursing homes, as well as 
duly treated bio-medical wastes for disposal at municipal dump site.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Prescribed 
authority.—1[
<section><number>1</number>


2[Save as otherwise 
provided, the prescribed authority for enforcement] of the provisions of these 
rules shall be the State Pollution Control Boards in respect of States and the 
Pollution Control Committees in respect of the Union territories and all pending 
cases with a prescribed authority appointed earlier shall stand transferred to 
the concerned State Pollution Control Board, or as the case may be, the 
Pollution Control Committees.]
 

3[(1A) The 
prescribed authority for enforcement of the provisions of these rules in respect 
of all health care establishments including hospitals, nursing homes, clinics, 
dispensaries, veterinary institutions, Animal houses, pathological laboratories 
and blood banks of the Armed Forces under the Ministry of Defence shall be the 
Director General, Armed Forces Medical Services.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The prescribed 
authority for the State or Union Territory shall be appointed within one month 
of the coming into force of these rules.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The prescribed 
authority shall function under the supervision and control of the respective 
Government of the State or Union Territory.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The prescribed 
authority shall on receipt of Form I make such enquiry as it deems fit and if it 
is satisfied that the applicant possesses the necessary capacity to handle 
bio-medical waste in accordance with these rules, grant or renew an 
authorisation as the case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> An authorisation shall 
be granted for a period of three years, including an initial trial period of one 
year from the date of issue. Thereafter, an application shall be made by the 
occupier/operator for renewal. All such subsequent authorisation shall be for a 
period of three years. A provisional authorisation will be granted for the trial 
period, to enable the occupier/operator to demonstrate the capacity of the 
facility.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The prescribed 
authority may after giving reasonable opportunity of being heard to the 
applicant and for reasons thereof to be recorded in writing, refuse to grant or 
renew authorisation.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Every application for 
authorisation shall be disposed of by the prescribed authority within ninety 
days from the date of receipt of the application.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> The prescribed 
authority may cancel or suspend an authorisation, if for reasons, to be recorded 
in writing, the occupier/operator has failed to comply with any provision of the 
Act or these rules:
 
Provided that no 
authorisation shall be cancelled or suspended without giving a reasonable 
opportunity to the occupier/operator of being heard.
 
 





</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Authorisation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every occupier of an institution generating, collecting, receiving, storing, 
transporting, treating, disposing and/or handling bio-medical waste in any other 
manner, except such occupier of clinics, dispensaries, pathological 
laboratories, blood banks providing treatment/service to less than 1000 (one 
thousand) patients per month, shall make an application in Form I to the 
prescribed authority for grant of authorisation.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every operator of a 
bio-medical waste facility shall make an application in Form I to the prescribed 
authority for grant of authorisation.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every application in 
Form I for grant of authorisation shall be accompanied by a fee as may be 
prescribed by the Government of the State or Union Territory.
 

1[(4) The 
authorization to operate a facility shall be issued in Form IV, subject to 
conditions laid therein and such other condition, as the prescribed authority, 
may consider it necessary.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Advisory committee.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
The Government of every State/Union  Territory shall constitute an Advisory 
Committee. The Committee will include experts in the field of medical and 
health, animal husbandry and veterinary sciences, environmental management, 
municipal administration, and any other related department or organisation 
including non-governmental organisations. 

2[***] As and when 
required, the Committee shall advise the Government of the State/Union Territory 
and the prescribed authority about matters related to the implementation of 
these rules.
 

3[(2) 
Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rule (1), the Ministry of Defence 
shall constitute in that Ministry, an Advisory Committee consisting of the 
following in respect of all health care establishments including hospitals, 
nursing homes, clinics, dispensaries, veterinary institutions, animal houses, 
pathological laboratories and blood banks of the Armed Forces under the Ministry 
of Defence, to advise the Director General, Armed Forces Medical Services and 
the Ministry of Defence in matters relating to implementation of these rules, 
namely:—
 </section><section>
   
<number>1</number> Additional Director General of Armed Forces
 

        Medical Services                                                    ... 
Chairman
 </section><section>
   
<number>2</number> A representative of the Ministry of Defence not
 

        below the rank of Deputy Secretary, to be
 

        nominated by that Ministry                                         ... 
Member
 </section><section>
   
<number>3</number> A representative of the Ministry of Environment
 

        and Forests not below the rank of Deputy Secretary
 

        to be nominated by that Ministry                                 ... 
Member
 </section><section>
   
<number>4</number> A representative of the Indian Society of Hospitals
 

        Waste Management, Pune                                         ... 
Member]
 
 





</section></article> 

  
 <article>1[<number>9A</number> Monitoring of implementation 
of the rules in Armed Forces Health Care Establishments.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Pollution Control 
Board shall monitor the implementation of these rules in respect of all the 
Armed Forces health care establishments under the Ministry of 
Defence.
 </section><section><number>2</number> After giving prior notice to 
the Director General Armed Forces Medical Services, the Central Pollution 
Control Board along with one or more representatives of the Advisory Committee 
constituted under sub-rule (2) of rule 9  may, if it considers it 
necessary, inspect any Armed Forces health care establishments.]
  


</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Annual report.—Every 
occupier/operator shall submit an annual report to the prescribed authority in 
Form II by 31st January every year, to include information about the categories 
and quantities of bio-medical wastes handled during the preceding year. The 
prescribed authority shall send this information in a compiled form to the 
Central Pollution Control Board by 31st March every year.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Maintenance of 
records.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every authorised person shall maintain records related to the generation, 
collection, reception, storage, transportation, treatment, disposal and/or any 
form of handling of bio-medical waste in accordance with these rules and any 
guidelines issued.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> All records shall be 
subject to inspection and verification by the prescribed authority at any time.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Accident reporting.—When 
any accident occurs at any institution or facility or any other site where 
bio-medical waste is handled or during transportation of such waste, the 
authorised person shall report the accident in Form III to the prescribed  
authority forthwith.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Appeal.—1[
<section><number>1</number>]


2[Save as otherwise 
provided in sub-rule (2), any person] aggrieved by an order made by the 
prescribed authority under these rules may, within thirty days from the date on 
which the order is communicated to him, prefer an appeal 

3[in Form V] to 
such authority as the Government of State/Union Territory may think fit to 
constitute:
 
Provided that the 
authority may entertain the appeal after the expiry of the said period of thirty 
days if it is satisfied that the appellant was prevented by sufficient cause 
from filing the appeal in time.
 

4[(2) Any person 
aggrieved by an order of the Director General, Armed Forces Medical Services 
under these rules may, within thirty days from the date on which the order is 
communicated to him prefer an appeal to the Central Government in the Ministry 
of Environment and Forests.]
 
 






</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>14</number>
Common disposal/incineration sites.—Without prejudice to rule 5 of these 
rules, the Municipal Corporations, Municipal Boards or Urban Local Bodies, as 
the case may be, shall be responsible for providing suitable common 
disposal/incineration sites for the biomedical wastes generated in the area 
under their jurisdiction and in areas outside the jurisdiction of any municipal 
body, it shall be the responsibility of the occupier generating bio-medical 
waste/operator of a bio medical waste treatment facility to arrange for suitable 
sites individual or in association, so as to comply with the provisions of these 
rules.]
 
 




</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>