<act><title> THE RAILWAYS (PUNITIVE CHARGES FOR OVERLOADING OF WAGON) RULES, 20071 </title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be called the Railways (Punitive Charges for Overloading of Wagon) Rules, 2007. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of their publication in the Official Gazette. 




</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires, 
 
 <section><number>a</number> Act means the Railways Act, 1989 (24 of 1989); 
 </section><section><number>b</number> class rate means the freight rate applicable to a commodity as per the class assigned to that commodity; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> Normal freight means the freight charge recoverable on a commodity at the class rate for the weight of the commodity loaded upto permissible carrying capacity plus 1 tonne or 2 tonnes, as the case may be, as specified in the Schedule; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> Permissible carrying capacity means the normal carrying capacity determined under sub­-section (2) or (3) of section 72 or where a railway administration has determined a varied carrying capacity under sub-section (4) of section 72, such varied carrying capacity, whichever is higher; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> Schedule means the Schedule to these rules; 
 </section><section><number>f</number> section means the section of the Act; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> Words and expressions used and not defined in these rules, but defined in the Act, shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act. 
</section>
</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Punitive charges for overloading. </title>Where the commodities are over-loaded in Railway wagon, the railway administration shall recover punitive charges as provided in Parts I, II and III of the Situation A' &amp; B' of <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[the Schedule I], from the consignor, the consignee or the endorsee as the case may be, for the entire distance to be travelled by the train hauling the wagon from the originating station to the destination point, irrespective of the point of detection of overloading: 
  
 Provided that no punitive charges will be levied if the customer carries out load adjustment at the originating station itself in case of detection of overloading at originating point. 



</article> 

  
 <article><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<title>4</title>. Notwithstanding anything contained in rule 3, where the commodities are overloaded in railway wagons on certain routes, the railway administration shall recover punitive charges as provided in the Schedule II.]



</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Came into force on 15-6-2007.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 595(E), dated 1st August, 2011, for the Schedule (w.e.f. 1-8-2011).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 595(E), dated 1st August, 2011 (w.e.f. 1-8-2011).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>