<act><tid>727141</tid>
<title>THE NAGA HILLS- TUENSANG AREA ACT, <year>1957</year></title>

ACT NO. 42 OF <year>1957</year>
[ 29th November, <year>1957</year>.]

An Act to provide for the formation of the Naga Hills- Tuensang Area of 
Assam as an administrative unit.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Eighth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:--





<article><tid>1145923</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>639819</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Naga Hills- Tuensang Area Act, <year>1957</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1433838</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> date as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>51747</tid>
<number>2</number>Formation of Naga Hills- Tuensang Area. As from the 
commencement of this Act, there shall be formed a new administrative 
unit in the State of Assam by the name of Naga Hills- Tuensang Area 
comprising the tribal areas which at such commencement were known as 
the Naga Hills District and Tuensang Frontier Division of the North 
East Frontier Agency.


</article>



<article><tid>1047648</tid>
<number> 3</number> Amendment of the Sixth Schedule to the Constitution. In the 
Sixth Schedule to the Constitution, in paragraph 20,--
<section><tid>1312422</tid>
<number>a</number>after sub- paragraph (2A), the following sub- paragraph 
shall be inserted, namely:--
" (2B) The Naga Hills- Tuensang Area shall 
comprise the areas which at the commencement of 
this Constitution were known as the Naga Hills 
District and the Naga Tribal Area.";


</section>

<section><tid>1320872</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- paragraph (3), after the words" administrative 
area", the brackets and words" (other than the Naga  
  Hills- Tuensang Area)" shall be inserted;

</section>

<section><tid>1750803</tid>
<number>c</number>in Part A of the Table, item 4 shall be omitted; and

</section>

<section><tid>1371387</tid>
<number>d</number>in Part B of the Table, for item 2, the following item 
shall be substituted, namely:--
" 2. The Naga Hills- Tuensang Area."




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>594572</tid>
<number> 4</number> Amendment of the Delimitation Order. In the Delimitation of 
Parliamentary and Assembly Constituencies Order, <year>1956</year>,--
<section><tid>167986</tid>
<number>a</number>in the First Schedule, in the entry in column 3 against 
serial No. 37, the words" Naga Hills", shall be 
omitted; and
<pagefootnote><pagenum>514</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1st December, <year>1957</year>, vide Notification No. S. R. O. 3843, dated 
30th November, <year>1957</year>, see Gazette of India, Extraordinary, Pt. II, Sec. 
3, p. 2877.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1084102</tid>
<number>b</number>in the Second Schedule, in the part relating to Assam, 
the heading" Naga Hills District" and all entries 
against serial Nos. 16, 17 and 18 shall be omitted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>265620</tid>
<number>5</number>[ Amendment of the Representation of the People Act, <year>1950</year>.] 
Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, <year>1960</year> (58 of <year>1960</year>), s. 2 and 
Sch. I.


</article>



<article><tid>1551649</tid>
<number>6</number>Provision as to the sitting member of Parliament. 
Notwithstanding the alteration in the extent of the Autonomous 
Districts Parliamentary constituency in Assam effected by section 4, 
the sitting member of the House of the People representing that 
constituency shall be deemed to have been elected to the House of the 
People by that constituency as so altered.


</article>



<article><tid>674570</tid>
<number>7</number>Territorial extent of laws not to be affected. The provisions 
of section 2 shall not be deemed to have effected any change in the 
areas to which any law in force immediately before the commencement of 
this Act extends or applies, and territorial references in any such 
law to the Naga Hills District, the Naga Tribal Area or the Tuensang 
Frontier Division shall, until otherwise provided by a competent 
legislature or other competent authority, continue to have the same 
meaning.
Explanation.-- In this section, law means any law, ordinance, 
regulation, order, bye- law, rule, scheme, notification or other 
instrument having the force of law in India or any part thereof.


</article>



 </act>