<act><title>


Board for Industrial and Financial 
    Reconstruction (Financial and Administrative Powers) Rules, 19871</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Board for Industrial and Financial Reconstruction 
    (Financial and Administrative Powers), Rules, 1987.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “Act” means the Sick Industrial 
    Companies (Special Provisions) Act, 1985 (1 of 1986);
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “Board” means the Board for Industrial 
    and Financial Reconstruction;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “Chairman” means the Chairman of the 
    Board;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    “Secretary” means the Secretary of the 
    Board.
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> Powers 
    of the Chairman and the Secretary.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Chairman shall have the same powers as are conferred on a Department of 
    the Central Government in respect of the Delegation of Financial Powers 
    Rules, 1978, the General Financial Rules, 1963, the Fundamental and 
    Supplementary Rules, the Central Civil Services (Leave) Rules, 1972, the 
    Central Civil Services (Joining Time) Rules, 1979, the Civil Services 
    (Pension) Rules, 1972, the Central Civil Services (Conduct) Rules, 1964, the 
    Central Civil Services (Classification, Control and Appeal) Rules, 1965, and 
    the General Provident Fund (Central Services) Rules, 1960, as amended from 
    time to time.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Secretary shall have the same powers as are conferred on a head of the 
    department in respect of the Delegation of the Financial Powers Rules, 1978, 
    the General Financial Rules, 1963, the Fundamental and Supplementary Rules, 
    the Central Civil Services (Leave) Rules, 1972, the Central Civil Services 
    (Joining Time) Rules, 1979, the Civil Services (Pension) Rules, 1972, the 
    Central Civil Services (Conduct) Rules, 1964, the Central Civil Services 
    (Classification, Control and Appeal) Rules, 1965, and the General Provident 
    Fund (Central Services) Rules, 1960, as amended from time to time:
 
Provided that 
    the exercise of the powers by the Chairman or Secretary under these rules 
    shall be subject to such instructions as may be issued from time to time by 
    the Central Government.
  
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>