<act><tid>728827</tid>
<title>THE DISPUTED ELECTIONS (PRIME MINISTER ANDSPEAKER) ACT, <year>1977</year></title>

ACT NO. 16 OF <year>1977</year>
[ 18th. April., <year>1977</year>.]

An Act to provide for Authorities to deal with disputed elections 
to Parliament in the case of Prime Minister and Speaker of the House 
of the People and for matters connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- eighth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY


<pagefootnote><pagenum>1</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Short title and commencement.



<article><tid>34002</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1460995</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Disputed Elections (Prime Minister and Speaker) Act, <year>1977</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1113139</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 3rd day of 
February, <year>1977</year>.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Definitions.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>623367</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definition. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>1836364</tid>
<number>a</number>" Authority" means an Authority constituted under 
section 4 for the trial of a petition;

</section>

<section><tid>1619995</tid>
<number>b</number>" candidate" means a person who has been or claims to 
have been duly nominated as a candidate at any election;

</section>

<section><tid>221134</tid>
<number>c</number>" costs" means all costs, charges and expenses of, or 
incidental to, trial of a petition under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>830619</tid>
<number>d</number>" election" means an election in the case of Prime 
Minister or in the case of Speaker;

</section>

<section><tid>1496163</tid>
<number>e</number>" election in the case of Prime Minister" means an 
election to either House of Parliament of a person who holds 
the office of Prime Minister at the time of such election or 
is appointed as Prime Minister after such election;

</section>

<section><tid>302291</tid>
<number>f</number>" election in the case of Speaker" means an election to 
the House of the People of a person who holds the office of 
Speaker at the time of such election or is chosen as the 
Speaker for that House after such election;

</section>

<section><tid>1293654</tid>
<number>g</number>" Petition" means a petition calling in question an 
election;

</section>

<section><tid>1604150</tid>
<number>h</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1975519</tid>
<number>i</number>" returned candidate" means a candidate whose name has 
been published under section 67 of the Representation of the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>182</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

People Act, <year>1951</year>, (43 of <year>1951</year>) as duly elected at an election 
in the case of 43 of <year>1951</year>. Prime Minister or, as the case 
may be, an election in the case of Speaker;


</section>

<section><tid>504571</tid>
<number>j</number>each of the expressions defined in the Representation of 
the People Act, <year>1951</year>, 43 of <year>1951</year>. but not defined in this Act 
shall have the same meaning as in that Act.
CHAP

AUTHORITIES FOR DISPUTED ELECTIONS

CHAPTER II

AUTHORITIES FOR DISPUTED ELECTIONS


<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Petitions on respect of disputed elections.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>415603</tid>
<number>3</number>Petitions on respect of disputed elections. No election shall 
be called in question except by a petition presented in accordance 
with the provisions of this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Authority to try a petition.

</article>



<article><tid>1421186</tid>
<number> 4</number> Authority to try a petition.
<section><tid>1137817</tid>
<number>1</number>Every petition shall be  
tried by an Authority, constituted for the purpose by the Central 
Government by notification in the official Gazette.

</section>

<section><tid>1052557</tid>
<number>2</number>The Authority shall consist of a single member, who is a 
Judge of the Supreme Court, to be nominated in this behalf by the 
Chief Justice of India.

</section>

<section><tid>1169752</tid>
<number>3</number>If for any reason a vacancy occurs in the office of member 
aforesaid, the Chief Justice shall, as soon as practicable, nominate a 
person to fill the vacancy, and thereupon the trial of the petition 
shall be continued as if that member had been the Authority from the 
commencement of the trial of such petition:
Provided that the Authority may, if it thinks fit, recall and re- 
examine any of the witnesses already examined.

CHAP

PRESENTATION Of PETITIONS IN RESPECT OF DISPUTED ELECTIONS

CHAPTER III

PRESENTATION Of PETITIONS IN RESPECT OF DISPUTED ELECTIONS


<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Presentation of petition.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1468325</tid>
<number> 5</number> Presentation of petition.
<section><tid>1642878</tid>
<number>1</number>A petition palling in question  
any election may be presented on one or more of the grounds specified 
in sub- section (1) of section 100 and section 101 of the 
Representation of the People Act, <year>1951</year>, (43 of <year>1951</year>) to the Election 
Commission by any candidate at such election or any elector within 
fortyfive days from, but not earlier than, the date of election of the 
returned candidate, or if there ire more returned candidates than one 
at the election and the dates of their election are different, the 
last of those dates:
Provided that a petition calling in question the election of a 
person who does not hold the office of Prime Minister or, as the case 
may be, Speaker of the House of the People at the time of such 
election and who is appointed or chosen to that office after such 
election but before the expiry of the time for presenting such 
election petition, may be presented within forty-


<pagefootnote><pagenum>183</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

five days from the date on which such person was appointed as the 
Prime Minister or chosen as the Speaker of the House of the People.

Explanation.- In this sub- section," elector" means a person who 
was entitled to vote at the election to which the petition relates, 
whether he has voted at such election or not.


</section>

<section><tid>1039724</tid>
<number>2</number>A petition shall be deemed to have been presented to the 
Election Commission when it is delivered to the Election Commission or 
to such other officer as may be appointed by it in this behalf-

<subsection><tid>923243</tid>
<number>a</number>by the person making the petition, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1549824</tid>
<number>b</number>by a person authorised in writing in this behalf by the 
person making the petition.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>406995</tid>
<number>3</number>Every petition shall be accompanied by as many copies 
thereof as there are respondents mentioned in the petition and one 
more copy for the use of the Election Commission, and every such copy 
shall be attested by the petitioner under his own signature to be a 
true copy of the petition.

</section>

<section><tid>328217</tid>
<number>4</number>At the time of presenting a petition, the petitioner shall 
deposit with the Election Commission in such manner as may be 
prescribed a sum of two thousand rupees as security for costs.

</section>

<section><tid>1764418</tid>
<number>5</number>The Authority trying a petition may at any time during the 
course of the trial of the petition call upon petitioner to give such 
further security for costs as it may direct.

</section>

<section><tid>1405115</tid>
<number>6</number>No person shall be entitled to be joined as a respondent to 
a petition under sub- section (3) of section 10 unless he has given 
such security for costs as the Authority may direct.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>6</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Parties to the petition.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1373967</tid>
<number> 6</number> Parties to the petition. A petitioner shall join as respondents 
to his petition-
<section><tid>306449</tid>
<number>a</number>where the petitioner, in addition to claiming a 
declaration that the election of all or any of the returned 
candidates is void, claims a further declaration that he 
himself or any other candidate has been duly elected, all the 
contesting candidates other than the petitioner, and where no 
such further declaration is claimed, all the returned 
candidates; and

</section>

<section><tid>1706545</tid>
<number>b</number>any other candidate against whom allegations of any 
corrupt practice are made in the petition.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>7</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Contents of petition.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1120134</tid>
<number> 7</number> 
<section><tid>717957</tid>
<number>1</number>Contents of petition. A petition- 

<subsection><tid>892493</tid>
<number>a</number>shall contain a concise statement of the material facts 
on which the petitioner relies;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1770896</tid>
<number>b</number>shall set forth full particulars of any corrupt 
practice that the petitioner alleges, including as full a 
statement as possible of the names of the parties alleged to 
have committed such cor-

<pagefootnote><pagenum>184</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

rupt practice and the date and place of the commission of 
each such practice; and


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1881763</tid>
<number>c</number>shall be signed by the petitioner and verified in the 
manner laid down in the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year>, (5  
  of <year>1908</year>) for the verification of pleadings:
Provided that where the petitioner alleges any corrupt practice, 
the petition shall also be accompanied by an affidavit in the 
prescribed form in support of the allegation of such corrupt practice 
and the particulars thereof.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1390094</tid>
<number>2</number>Any schedule or annexure to the petition shall also be 
signed by the petitioner and verified in the same manner as the 
petition.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>8</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Relief that may be claimed by the petitioner.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1474713</tid>
<number>8</number>Relief that may be claimed by the petitioner. A petitioner may, 
in addition to claiming a declaration that the election of all or any 
of the returned candidates is void, claim a further declaration that 
he himself or any other candidate has been duly elected.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>9</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Procedure on receiving petitions.

</article>



<article><tid>1232694</tid>
<number> 9</number> Procedure on receiving petitions.
<section><tid>295551</tid>
<number>1</number>The Election Commission  
shall, as soon as may be after the receipt of a petition under section 
5, forward it to the Authority for trying the petition.

</section>

<section><tid>696352</tid>
<number>2</number>Where more petitions than one have been received under 
section 5 in respect of the same election, the Election Commission 
shall forward them to the Authority and such Authority may, in its 
discretion, try them separately or in one or more groups.
CHAP

TRIAL OF PETITIONS

CHAPTER IV

TRIAL OF PETITIONS


<pagefootnote><pagenum>10</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Trial of petitions.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>925577</tid>
<number> 10</number> Trial of petitions.
<section><tid>566901</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to any rules made in this  
behalf, the Authority for the trial of any petition shall hold the 
trial at New Delhi.

</section>

<section><tid>1262650</tid>
<number>2</number>The Authority shall dismiss the petition-

<subsection><tid>1619558</tid>
<number>a</number>if the petition has not been presented within the 
period specified in sub- section (1) of section 5;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1340688</tid>
<number>b</number>if the petition does not comply with the provisions of 
sub- section (3) or sub- section (4) of section 5 or section 6.
Explanation.- An order dismissing a petition under this sub- 
section shall be deemed to be an order made under clause (a) of 
section 16.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1669338</tid>
<number>3</number>Any candidate not already a respondent to a petition shall, 
upon application made by him to the Authority within fourteen days 
from the date of commencement of the trial and subject to any order as 
to security for costs which may be made by the Authority, be entitled 
to be joined as a respondent.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>185</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Explanation.- For the purposes of this sub- section and of section 
 15 the trial of a petition shall be deemed to commence on the date 
fixed for the respondents to appear before the Authority and answer 
the claim or claims made in the petition.


</section>

<section><tid>343021</tid>
<number>4</number>The Authority may, upon such terms as to costs and otherwise 
as it may deem fit, allow the particulars of any corrupt practice 
alleged in the petition to be amended or amplified in such manner as 
may in its opinion be necessary for ensuring a fair and effective 
trial of the petition, but shall not allow any amendment of the 
petition which will have the effect of introducing particulars of a 
corrupt practice not previously alleged in the petition.

</section>

<section><tid>1824646</tid>
<number>5</number>The trial of a petition shall, so far as is practicable 
consistently with the interests of justice in respect of the trial, be 
continued from day to day until its conclusion, unless the Authority 
finds the adjournment of the trial beyond the following day to be 
necessary for reasons to be recorded.

</section>

<section><tid>1196782</tid>
<number>6</number>Every petition shall be tried as expeditiously as possible 
and endeavour shall be made to conclude the trial within six months 
from the date of commencement of the trial.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>11</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Procedure before the Authority.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1101991</tid>
<number> 11</number> Procedure before the Authority.
<section><tid>1298116</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions  
of this Act and of any rules made thereunder, every petition shall be 
tried by the Authority, as nearly as may be, in accordance with the 
procedure applicable under the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of  
  <year>1908</year>) to the trial of suits:
Provided that the Authority shall have the discretion to refuse, 
for reasons to be recorded in writing, to examine any witness or 
witnesses, if it is of the opinion that the evidence of such witness 
or witnesses is not material for the decision of the petition or that 
the party tendering such witness or witnesses is doing so on frivolous 
grounds or with a view to delay the proceedings.


</section>

<section><tid>468904</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes of any such trial, the Authority shall have 
all the powers of a Civil Court while trying a suit under the Code of 
Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year>, (5 of <year>1908</year>) in respect of the following 
matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1938378</tid>
<number>a</number>summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person 
and examining him on oath;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>206695</tid>
<number>b</number>requiring the discovery and production of any document;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1212631</tid>
<number>c</number>receiving evidence on affidavits;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1951893</tid>
<number>d</number>requisitioning any public record or copy thereof from 
any court or office;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>905879</tid>
<number>e</number>issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses or 
documents;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1808859</tid>
<number>f</number>such other matters as may be prescribed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>186</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1692053</tid>
<number>3</number>The provisions of the Indian Evidence Act, <year>1872</year>, (1 of  
  <year>1872</year>) shall, subject to the provisions of this Act, be deemed to apply 
in all respects to the trial of a petition.

</section>

<section><tid>306882</tid>
<number>4</number>Any proceeding before the Authority shall be deemed to be a 
judicial proceeding within the meaning of section 193 of the Indian 
Penal Code. (45 of <year>1860</year>)

<pagefootnote><pagenum>12</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Secrecy of voting not to be infringed.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>277702</tid>
<number>12</number>Secrecy of voting not to be infringed. No witness or other 
person shall be required to state for whom he has voted at an 
election.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>13</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Answering of criminating questions and certificate of indemnity.

</article>



<article><tid>1718362</tid>
<number> 13</number> Answering of criminating questions and certificate of 
indemnity.
<section><tid>19823</tid>
<number>1</number>No witness shall be excused from answering any question  
as to any matter relevant to a matter in issue in the trial of a 
petition upon the ground that the answer to such question may 
criminate or may tend to criminate him, or that it may expose or may 
tend to expose him to any penalty or forfeiture:
Provided that-


<subsection><tid>1226098</tid>
<number>a</number>a witness, who answers truly all questions which he is 
required to answer shall be entitled to receive a certificate 
of indemnity from the Authority; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1371128</tid>
<number>b</number>an answer given by a witness to a question put by or 
before the Authority shall not, except in the case of any 
criminal proceeding for perjury in respect of the evidence, 
be admissible in evidence against him in any civil or 
criminal proceeding.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>806387</tid>
<number>2</number>When a certificate of indemnity has been granted to any 
witness, it may be pleaded by him in any court and shall be a full and 
complete defence to or upon any charge under Chapter IXA of the Indian 
Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>) Part VII of the Representation of the People 
Act, <year>1951</year>, (43 of <year>1951</year>) arising out of the matter to which such 
certificate relates, but it shall not be deemed to relieve him from 
any disqualification in connection with an election imposed by this 
Act or any other law.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>14</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Expenses of witnesses.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>49380</tid>
<number>14</number>Expenses of witnesses. The reasonable expenses incurred by any 
person in attending to give evidence before the Authority may be 
allowed by it to such person, and shall, unless the Authority 
otherwise directs, be deemed to be part of the costs.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>15</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Recrimination when seat claimed.

</article>



<article><tid>1190322</tid>
<number> 15</number> Recrimination when seat claimed.
<section><tid>1121345</tid>
<number>1</number>When in a petition a  
declaration that any candidate other than the returned candidate has 
been duly elected is claimed, the returned candidate or any other 
party may give evidence to prove that the election of such candidate 
would have been void if he had been the returned candidate and a 
petition had been presented calling in question his election:
Provided that the returned candidate or such other party, as 
aforesaid shall not be entitled to give such evidence unless he his, 
within fourteen


<pagefootnote><pagenum>187</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

days from the date of commencement of the trial, given notice to 
the. Authority of his intention to do so and has also given the 
security and the further security referred to in sub- sections (4), (5) 
and (6) respectively of section 5.


</section>

<section><tid>1056447</tid>
<number>2</number>Every notice referred to in sub- section (1) shall be 
Accompained by the statement and particulars required by section 7 in 
the case of a petition and shall be signed and verified in like 
manner.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>16</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Decision of the Authority.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>505218</tid>
<number> 16</number> Decision of the Authority. At the conclusion of the trial of a 
petition the Authority shall make an order-
<section><tid>1865701</tid>
<number>a</number>dismissing the petition; or

</section>

<section><tid>1758949</tid>
<number>b</number>declaring the election of all or any of the returned 
candidates to be void; or

</section>

<section><tid>814350</tid>
<number>c</number>declaring the election of all or any of the returned 
candidates to be void and the petitioner or any other 
candidate to have been duly elected.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>17</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Other orders to be made by the Authority.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>559355</tid>
<number> 17</number> Other orders to be made by the Authority.
<section><tid>710668</tid>
<number>1</number>At the time of  
making an order under section 16, the Authority shall also make an 
order-

<subsection><tid>676146</tid>
<number>a</number>Where any charge is made in the petition of any corrupt 
practice having been committed at the election, recording-

<subsubsection><tid>1612707</tid>
<number>i</number>a finding whether any corrupt practice has or has 
not been proved to have been committed at the election, 
and the nature of that corrupt practice; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>417262</tid>
<number>ii</number>the names of all persons, if any, who have been 
proved at the trial to have been guilty of any corrupt 
practice and the nature of that practice; and

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1079442</tid>
<number>b</number>fixing the total amount of costs payable and specifying 
the persons by and to whom costs shall be paid:
Provided that a person who is not a party to the petition shall 
not be named in the order tinder sub- clause (ii) of clause (a) unless-


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>676146</tid>
<number>a</number>he has been given notice to appear before the Authority 
and to show cause why he should not be so named; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1079442</tid>
<number>b</number>if he appears in pursuance of the notice, he has been 
given an opportunity of cross- examining any witness who has 
already been examined by the Authority and has given evidence 
against him, of calling evidence in his defence and of being 
heard.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1101698</tid>
<number>2</number>In this section and in section 18, the expression" agent" 
has the same meaning as in section 123 of the Representation of the 
People Act, <year>1951</year>. (43 of <year>1951</year>)

<pagefootnote><pagenum>188</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


<pagefootnote><pagenum>18</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Grounds for declaring election to be void.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1581926</tid>
<number> 18</number> Grounds for declaring election to be void.
<section><tid>1077252</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the  
provisions of sub- section (2), if the Authority is of opinion-

<subsection><tid>1135764</tid>
<number>a</number>that on the date of his election a returned candidate 
was not qualified, or was disqualified, to be chosen to fill 
the seat under the Constitution or the Representation of the 
People Act, <year>1951</year>, (43 of <year>1951</year>) or this Act or the Government 
of Union Territories Act, <year>1963</year>; 20 of <year>1963</year> or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1197299</tid>
<number>b</number>that any corrupt practice has been committed by a 
returned candidate or his election agent or by any other 
person with the consent of a returned candidate or his 
election agent; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1574901</tid>
<number>c</number>that any nomination has been improperly rejected; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>588687</tid>
<number>d</number>that the result of the election, in so far as it 
concerns the returned candidate, has been materially 
affected-

<subsubsection><tid>494923</tid>
<number>i</number>by the improper acceptance of any 
nomination, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>861867</tid>
<number>ii</number>by any corrupt practice committed in the interests 
of the returned candidate by an agent other than his 
election agent, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>418504</tid>
<number>iii</number>by the improper reception, refusal or 
rejection of any vote or the reception of any vote which 
is void, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1041175</tid>
<number>iv</number>by any non- compliance with the provisions of 
the Constitution or of this Act or of any rules or 
orders made under this Act, the Authority shall declare 
the election of the returned candidate to be void.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1075246</tid>
<number>2</number>If in the opinion of the Authority a returned candidate has 
been guilty by an agent, other than his election agent, of any corrupt 
practice but the Authority is satisfied-

<subsection><tid>1677606</tid>
<number>a</number>that no such corrupt practice was committed at the 
election by the candidate or his election agent, and every 
such corrupt practice was committed contrary to the orders, 
and without the consent, of the candidate or his election 
agent;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>936712</tid>
<number>b</number>that the candidate and his election agent took all 
reasonable means for preventing the commission of corrupt 
practices at the election; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1495920</tid>
<number>c</number>that in all other respects the election was free from 
any corrupt practice on the part of the candidate or any of 
his agents, then the Authority may decide that the election 
of the returned candidate is not void.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>19</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Grounds for which a candidate other than the returned candidate may bedeclared 
to have been elected.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>484993</tid>
<number> 19</number> Grounds for which a candidate other than the returned 
candidate may be declared to have been elected. If any person who has 
lodged a petition has, in addition to calling in question the election 
of the returned candidate, claimed a declaration

<pagefootnote><pagenum>189</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

that he himself or any other candidate has been duly elected and the 
Authority is of opinion--

<section><tid>1328931</tid>
<number>a</number>that in fact the petitioner or such other candidate 
received a majority of the valid votes; or

</section>

<section><tid>1681576</tid>
<number>b</number>that but for the votes obtained by the returned 
candidate by corrupt practices the petitioner or such other 
candidate would have obtained a majority of the valid votes, 
the Authority shall after declaring the election of the 
returned candidate to be void declare the petitioner or such 
other candidate, as the case may be, to have been duly 
elected.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>20</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Communication of orders of the Authority.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1289089</tid>
<number>20</number>Communication of orders of the Authority. The Authority shall, 
as soon as may be after the conclusion of the trial of a petition, 
intimate the substance of the decision to the Election Commission and 
the Speaker or the Chairman, as the case may be, of the House of 
Parliament and, as soon as may be thereafter, shall send to the 
Election Commission an authenticated copy of the decision.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>21</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Costs.

</article>



<article><tid>650425</tid>
<number>21</number>Costs. Costs shall be in the discretion of the Authority:
Provided that where a petition is dismissed under clause (a) of 
section 16, the returned candidate shall be entitled to the costs 
incurred by him in contesting the petition and accordingly the 
Authority shall make an order for costs in favour of the returned 
candidate.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>22</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Ordersof Authority to be final. 22. Orders of Authority to be final. No 
order made by an Authorityunder this Act shall be called in question in any 
court.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>23</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Effect of orders of Authority.

</article>



<article><tid>451087</tid>
<number> 23</number> Effect of orders of Authority.
<section><tid>1716241</tid>
<number>1</number>An order made by an  
Authority under this Act shall take effect as soon as it is pronounced 
by the Authority.

</section>

<section><tid>1145370</tid>
<number>2</number>Where by an order under section 16 the election of a 
returned candidate is declared to be void, acts and proceedings in 
which that returned candidate has, before the date thereof, 
participated as a member of Parliament or, as the Prime Minister or as 
the Speaker of the House of the People shall not be invalidated by 
reason of that order, nor shall such candidate be subjected to any 
liability or penalty on the ground of such participation.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER V

MISCELLANEOUS


<pagefootnote><pagenum>24</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Withdrawal and abatement of petitions.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>821534</tid>
<number>24</number>Withdrawal and abatement of petitions. The provisions of 
sections 109 to 116 (both inclusive) of the Representation of the 
People Act, <year>1951</year>, (43 of <year>1951</year>) relating to withdrawal and abatement 
of election petitions shall, so far as may be, apply in relation to

<pagefootnote><pagenum>190</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

withdrawal and abatement of petitions under this Act subject to the 
modifications that the references therein to an election petition, 
High Court and petitioner shall be construed as references to a 
petition under this Act, the Authority for hearing such petition and 
the petitioner in respect of such petition respectively.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>25</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Payment of costs out of security deposits and return of such deposits.

</article>



<article><tid>664263</tid>
<number> 25</number> Payment of costs out of security deposits and return of 
such deposits.
<section><tid>123523</tid>
<number>1</number>If in any order as to costs under the provisions  
of this Act there is a direction for payment of costs by any party to 
any person, such costs shall, if they have not been already paid, be 
paid in full, or so far as possible, out of the security deposit and 
the further security deposit, if any, made by such party under this 
Act on an application made in writing in that behalf within a period 
of one year, from the date of such order to the Election Commission by 
the person in whose favour the costs have been awarded.

</section>

<section><tid>596023</tid>
<number>2</number>If there is any balance left of any of the said security 
deposits after payment under sub- section (1) of the costs referred to 
in that sub- section, such balance, or where no costs have been awarded 
or no application as aforesaid has been made within the said period of 
one year, the whole of the said security deposits may, on an 
application made in that behalf in writing to the Election Commission 
by the person by whom the deposits have been made, or if such person 
dies after making such deposits, by the legal representative of such 
person, be returned to the said person or to his legal representative, 
as the case may be.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>26</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Execution of orders as to costs.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1027937</tid>
<number>26</number>Execution of orders as to costs. Any order as to costs under 
the provisions of this Act may be produced before the principal civil 
court of original jurisdiction within the local limits of whose 
jurisdiction any person directed by such order to pay any sum of money 
has a place of residence or business or where such place is within a 
presidency- town before the court of small causes having jurisdiction 
there, and such court shall execute the order or cause the same to be 
executed in the same manner and by the same procedure as if it were a 
decree for the payment of money made by itself in a suit:
Provided that where any such costs or any portion thereof may be 
recovered by an application made under sub- section (1) of section 25, 
no application shall lie under this section within a period of one 
year from the date of such order unless it is for the recovery of the 
balance of any costs which has been left unrealised after an 
application has been made under that sub- section owing to the 
insufficiency of the amount of the security deposits referred to in 
that sub- section.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>27</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Power to make rules.

</article>



<article><tid>1541158</tid>
<number> 27</number> Power to make rule.
<section><tid>779776</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may make  
rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>191</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>196821</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1563898</tid>
<number>a</number>the deposit or further deposit to be made by the 
petitioner as security for the costs;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>558252</tid>
<number>b</number>the appointment of officers and other employees for 
assisting the Authorities in the discharge of their functions 
and the conditions of service of such officers and other 
employees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>351125</tid>
<number>c</number>the custody of deposits made under this Act, the 
payment of costs out of such deposits on an application made 
under section 25 and other matters relating to the disposal 
of such application;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>988010</tid>
<number>d</number>the fees, if any, payable in respect of any petition or 
application under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1548355</tid>
<number>e</number>any other matter which has to be prescribed by or 
provided for by rules made under this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1863083</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act 
shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House 
of Parliament while it is in session, for a total period of thirty 
days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session, or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything pre- 
viously done under that rule.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>28</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Repeal and saving.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1011096</tid>
<number> 28</number> Repeal and saving.
<section><tid>106509</tid>
<number>1</number>The Disputed Elections (Prime Minister   
  and Speaker) Ordinance, <year>1977</year>, (4 of <year>1977</year>) is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>916066</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action 
taken under the provisions of the said Ordinance shall be deemed to 
have been done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this 
Act.


</section>

</article>



 </act>