<act><tid>737311</tid>
<title>THE UNION TERRITORIES (DIRECT ELECTION TO THEHOUSE OF THE PEOPLE) 
ACT, <year>1965</year></title>

ACT NO. 49 OF <year>1965</year>
[ 22nd December, <year>1965</year>.]

An Act to provide for direct election in certain Union 
territories for filling the seats allotted to them in the House of the 
People and for matters connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Sixteenth Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-


<pagefootnote><pagenum>1</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Short title.



<article><tid>1800852</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Union Territories 
 (Direct Election to the House of the People) Act, <year>1965</year>.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Definitions.

</article>



<article><tid>1404083</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act-
<section><tid>1112243</tid>
<number>a</number>" parliamentary constituency" has the same meaning as in 
the Representation of the People Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of <year>1950</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>394701</tid>
<number>b</number>" sitting member" means a person who immediately before 
the commencement of this Act is a member of the House of the 
People;

</section>

<section><tid>200810</tid>
<number>c</number>" Union territory" means any of the Union territories of 
the Andaman and Nicobar Islands, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Lakshadeep] and Dadra and 
Nagar Haveli.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Direct election to fill the seats in the House of the People allottedto 
certain Union Territories.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1371849</tid>
<number>3</number>Direct election to fill the seats in the House of the People 
allotted to certain Union Territories. At the next general election 
to the House of the People and thereafter, the seats allotted under 
section 3 of the Representation of the People Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of <year>1950</year>) 
to the Union territories in the House of the People shall be seats to 
be filled by persons chosen by direct election and for that purpose 
each Union territory shall form one parliamentary constituency.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

[ Amendment of Act 43 of <year>1950</year>.]

</article>



<article><tid>837653</tid>
<number>4</number>[ Amendment of Act 43 of <year>1950</year>.] Not printed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

[ Amendment of Act 43 of <year>1951</year>.]

</article>



<article><tid>1069497</tid>
<number>5</number>[ Amendment of Act 43 of <year>1951</year>.] Not printed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>6</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Provision as to sitting member.

</article>



<article><tid>418449</tid>
<number>6</number>Provision as to sitting member. The sitting member representing 
each Union territory shall continue to represent that Union territory 
until the dissolution of the present House of the People and if before 
such dissolution the seat allotted to a Union territory in the House 
of the People becomes vacant it shall be filled by a person nominated 
by the President and that person shall represent the Union territory 
in the present House of the People until its dissolution.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>7</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the Laccadive. Minicoy and Amindivi Islands, (Alteration  
  of Name) Adaptation of Laws Order, <year>1974</year> (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1973</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>