<act><title>

THE SCHEDULED CASTES AND THE SCHEDULED TRIBES
    
    (PREVENTION OF ATROCITIES) RULES, 19951</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled Tribes 
    (Prevention of Atrocities) Rules, 1995.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In the rules, unless 
    the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “Act” means the 
    Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled Tribes (Prevention of Atrocities) Act, 
    1989 (33 of 1989);
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “Dependent”, with its 
    grammatical variations and cognate expressions, includes wife, children, 
    whether married or unmarried, dependent parents, widowed sister, widow and 
    children of pre-deceased son of a victim of atrocity;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “identified area” means 
    such area where State Government has reason to believe that atrocity may 
    take place or there is an apprehension of reoccurrence of an offence under 
    the Act or an area prone to atrocities;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    “Non-Government 
    Organisation” means a voluntary organisation engaged in the welfare 
    activities relating to the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled Tribes and 
    registered under the Societies Registration Act, 1860 (21 of 1860) or under 
    any law for the registration of documents or such organisation for the time 
    being in force;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    “schedule” means the 
    Schedule annexed to these rules;
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    “section” means section 
    of the Act;
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    “State Government”, in 
    relation to a Union territory, means the Administrator of that Union 
    territory appointed by the President under article 239 of the Constitution;
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>    words and expressions 
    used herein and not defined but defined in the Act shall have the meanings 
    respectively assigned to them in the Act.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Precautionary and preventive measures.—With 
    a view to prevent atrocities on the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled 
    Tribes, the State Government shall:—  
 <section>
<number>i</number>    identify the area where 
    it has reason to believe that atrocity may take place or there is an 
    apprehension of reoccurrence of an offence under the Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    order the District 
    Magistrate and Superintendent of Police or any other officer to visit the 
    identified area and review the law and order situation;  
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>    if deem necessary, in 
    the identified area cancel the arms licences of the persons, not being 
    member of the Scheduled Castes or Scheduled Tribes, their near relations, 
    servants or employees and family friends and get such arms deposited in the 
    Government Armoury;  
 </section><section>
<number>iv</number>    seize all illegal fire 
    arms and prohibit any illegal manufacture of fire arms;  
 </section><section>
<number>v</number>    with a view to ensure 
    the safety of person and property, if deem necessary, provide arms licences 
    to the members of the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled Tribes;  
 </section><section>
<number>vi</number>    constitute a high power 
    State-level committee, district and divisional level committees or such 
    number of other committees as deem proper and necessary for assisting the 
    Government in implementation of the provisions of the Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>vii</number>    set-up a vigilance and 
    monitoring committee to suggest effective measures to implement the 
    provisions of the Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>viii</number>    set-up Awareness 
    Centres and organise Workshops in the identified area or at some other place 
    to educate the persons belonging to the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled 
    Tribes about their rights and the protection available to them under the 
    provisions of various Central and State enactments or rules, regulations and 
    schemes framed thereunder;  
 </section><section>
<number>ix</number>    encourage 
    Non-Government Organisations for establishing and maintaining Awarenes 
    Centres and organising workshops and provide them necessary financial and 
    other sort of assistance;  
 </section><section>
<number>x</number>    deploy special police 
    force in the identified area;  
 </section><section>
<number>xi</number>    by the end of every 
    quarter, review the law and order situation, functioning of different 
    committees, performance of Special Public Prosecutors, Investigating 
    Officers and other Officers responsible for implementing the provisions of 
    the Act and the cases registered under the Act.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Supervision of Prosecution and Submission of Report.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government on the recommendation of the District Magistrate shall 
    prepare for each District a panel of such number of eminent Senior Advocates 
    who have been in practice for not less than seven years, as it may deem 
    necessary for conducting cases in the Special Courts. Similarly, in 
    consultation with the Director of Prosecution/in-charge of the prosecution, 
    a panel of such number of Public Prosecutors as it may deem necessary for 
    conducting cases in the Special Court, shall also be specified. Both these 
    panels shall be notified in the Official Gazette of the State and shall 
    remain in force for a period of three years.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    District Magistrate and the Director of Prosecution/in-charge of the 
    prosecution shall review at least twice in a calendar year, in the months of 
    January and July, the performance of Special Public Prosecutors so specified 
    or appointed and submit a report to the State Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If the 
    State Government is satisfied or has reason to believe that a Special Public 
    Prosecutor so appointed or specified has not conducted the case to the best 
    of his ability and with due care and caution, his name may be, for reasons 
    to be recorded in writing, denotified.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    District Magistrate and the officer-in-charge of the prosecution at the 
    District level, shall review the position of cases registered under the Act 
    and submit a monthly report on or before 20th day of each subsequent month 
    to the Director of Prosecution and the State Government. This report shall 
    specify the actions taken/proposed to be taken in respect of investigation 
    and prosecution of each case.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rule (1) the District Magistrate 
    or the Sub-Divisional Magistrate may, if deem necessary or if so desired by 
    the victims of atrocity engage an eminent Senior Advocate for conducting 
    cases in the Special Courts on such payment of fee as he may consider 
    appropriate.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Payment of 
    fee to the Special Public Prosecutor shall be fixed by the State Government 
    on a scale higher than the other panel advocates in the State.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Information to Police Officer in-charge of a Police Station.—
<section><number>1</number>Every 
    information relating to the commission of an offence under the Act, if given 
    orally to an officer incharge of a police station shall be reduced to 
    writing by him or under his direction, and be read over to the informant, 
    and every such information, whether given in writing or reduced to writing 
    as aforesaid, shall be signed by the persons giving it, and the substance 
    thereof shall be entered in a book to be maintained by that police station.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A copy of 
    the information as so recorded under sub-rule (1) above shall be given 
    forthwith, free of cost, to the informant.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any person 
    aggrieved by a refusal on the part of an officer in-charge of a police 
    station to record the information referred to in-sub-rule (1) may send the 
    substance of such information, in writing and by post, to the Superintendent 
    of Police concerned who after investigation either by himself or by a police 
    officer not below the rank of Deputy Superintendent of Police, shall make an 
    order in writing to the officer in-charge of the concerned police station to 
    enter the substance of that information to be entered in the book to be 
    maintained by that police station.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Spot 
    inspection by officers.—
<section><number>1</number>Whenever 
    the District Magistrate or the Sub-Divisional Magistrate or any other 
    Executive Magistrate or any police officer not below the rank of Deputy 
    Superintendent of Police receives an information from any person or upon his 
    own knowledge that an atrocity has been committed on the members of the 
    Scheduled Castes or the Scheduled Tribes within his jurisdiction, he shall 
    immediately himself visit the place of occurrence to assess the extent of 
    atrocity, loss of life, loss and damage to the property and submit a report 
    forthwith to the State Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    District Magistrate or the Sub-District Magistrate or any other Executive 
    Magistrate and the Superintendent of Police/Deputy Superintendent of Police 
    after inspecting the place or area shall on the spot—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number> draw a list of victims, their family 
    members and dependents entitled for relief;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number> prepare a detailed report of the extent 
    of atrocity, loss and damage to the property of the victims;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number> order for intensive police patrolling in 
    the area;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number> take effective and necessary steps to 
    provide protection to the witnesses and other sympathisers of the victims;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number> provide immediate relief to the victims.  
  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Investigating Officer.—
<section><number>1</number> An 
    offence committed under the Act shall be investigated by a police officer 
    not below the rank of a Deputy Superintendent of Police. The investigating 
    officer shall be appointed by the State Government/Director General of 
    Police/Superintendent of Police after taking into account his past 
    experience, sense of ability and justice to perceive the implications of the 
    case and investigate it alongwith right lines within the shortest possible 
    time.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    investigating officer so appointed under sub-rule (1) shall complete the 
    investigation on top priority basis within thirty days and submit the report 
    to the Superintendent of Police who in turn will immediately forward the 
    report to the Director General of Police of the State Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Home 
    Secretary and the Social Welfare Secretary to the State Government, Director 
    of Prosecution, the officer in-charge of Prosecution and the Director 
    General of Police shall review by the end of every quarter the position of 
    all investigations done by the investigating officer.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Setting 
    up of the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled Tribes Protection Cell.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government shall set up a Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled 
    Tribes Protection Cell at the State headquarter under the charge of Director 
    General of Police/Inspector General of Police. This Cell shall be 
    responsible for—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    conducting survey of the 
    identified area;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    maintaining public 
    order and tranquility in the identified area;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    recommending to the 
    State Government for deployment of special police force or establishment of 
    special police post in the identified area;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    making investigations 
    about the probable causes leading to an offence under the Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>    restoring the feeling of 
    security amongst the members of the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled 
    Tribes;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vi</number>    informing the nodal 
    officer and special officer about the law and order situation in the 
    identified area;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vii</number>    making enquiries about 
    the investigation and spot inspections conducted by various officers;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>viii</number>    making enquiries 
    about the action taken by the Superintendent of Police in the cases where an 
    officer in-charge of the police station has refused to enter an information 
    in a book to be maintained by that police station under sub-rule (3) of rule 
    5;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ix</number>    making enquiries about 
    the wilful negligence by a public servant;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>x</number>    reviewing the position 
    of cases registered under the Act; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>xi</number>    submitting a monthly 
    report on or before 20th day of each subsequent month to the State 
    Government/nodal officer about the action taken/proposed to be taken in 
    respect of the above.  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Nomination of Nodal Officer.—The 
    State Government shall nominate a nodal officer of the level of a Secretary 
    to the State Government preferably belonging to the Scheduled Castes or the 
    Scheduled Tribes, for co-ordinating the functioning of the District 
    Magistrates and Superintendent of Police or other officers authorised by 
    them, investigating officers and other officers responsible for implementing 
    the provisions of the Act. By the end of every quarter, the nodal officer 
    shall review—  
 <section>
<number>i</number> the reports received by the State 
    Government under sub-rules (2) and (4) of rule 4, rule 6, clause (xi) of 
    rule 8;
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> the position of cases registered under 
    the Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number> law and order situation in the 
    identified area;  
 </section><section>
<number>iv</number> various kinds of measures adopted for 
    providing immediate relief in cash or kind or both to the victims of 
    atrocity or his or her dependent;  
 </section><section>
<number>v</number> adequacy of immediate facilities like 
    rationing, clothing, shelter, legal aid, travelling allowance, daily 
    allowance and transport facilities provided to the victims of atrocity or 
    his/her dependants;  
 </section><section>
<number>vi</number> performance of Non-Governmental 
    Organisations, the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled Tribes Protection 
    Cell, various committees and the public servants responsible for 
    implementing the provisions of the Act.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Appointment of a Special Officer.—In 
    the identified area a Special Officer not below the rank of a Additional 
    District Magistrate shall be appointed to coordinate with the District 
    Magistrate, Superintendent of Police or other officers responsible for 
    implementing the provisions of the Act, various committees and the Scheduled 
    Castes and the Scheduled Tribes Protection Cell.  
 
The Special 
    Officer shall be responsible for—  
 <section>
<number>i</number> providing immediate relief and other 
    facilities to the victims of atrocity and initiate necessary measures to 
    prevent or avoid re-occurrence of atrocity;  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> setting up an awareness centre and 
    organising workshop in the identified area or at the district headquarters 
    to educate the persons belonging to the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled 
    Tribes about their rights and the protection available to them under the 
    provisions of various Central and State enactments or rules and schemes 
    etc. framed therein;
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number> co-ordinating with the Non-Governmental 
    Organisations and providing necessary facilities and financial and other 
    types of assistance to Non-Governmental Organisations for maintaining 
    centres or organising workshops.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Travelling allowance, daily allowance, maintenance expenses and transport 
    facilities to the victim of atrocity, his or her dependent and witnesses.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every victim of atrocity or his/her dependent and witnesses shall be paid to 
    and fro rail fare by second class in express/mail/passenger train or actual 
    bus or taxi fare from his/her place of residence or place of stay to the 
    place of investigation or hearing of trial of an offence under the Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    District Magistrate or the Sub-Divisional Magistrate or any other Executive 
    Magistrate shall make necessary arrangements for providing transport 
    facilities or reimbursement of full payment thereof to the victims of 
    atrocity and witnesses for visiting the investigating officer, 
    Superintendent of Police/Deputy Superintendent of Police, District 
    Magistrate or any other Executive Magistrate.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every 
    woman witness, the victim of atrocity or her dependent being a woman or a 
    minor, a person more than sixty years of age and a person having 40 per cent 
    or more disability shall be entitled to be accompanied by an attendant of 
    her/his choice. The attendant shall also be paid travelling and maintenance 
    expenses as applicable to the witness or the victim of atrocity when called 
    upon during hearing, investigation and trial of an offence under the Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    witness, the victim of atrocity or his/her dependent and the attendant shall 
    be paid daily maintenance expenses, for the days he/she is away from the 
    place of his/her residence or stay during investigation, hearing and trial 
    of an offence, at such rates but not less than the minimum wages, as may be 
    fixed by the State Government for the agricultural labourers.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> In 
    addition to daily maintenance expenses the witness, the victim of atrocity 
    (or his/her dependant) and the attendant shall also be paid diet expenses at 
    such rates as may be fixed by the State Government from time to time.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    payment of travelling allowance, daily allowance, maintenance expenses and 
    reimbursement of transport facilities shall be made immediately or not later 
    than three days by the District Magistrate or the Sub-Divisional Magistrate 
    or any other Executive Magistrate to the victims, their 
    dependants/attendants and witnessess for the days they visit the 
    investigating officer or in-charge of police station or hospital authorities 
    or Superintendent of Police/Deputy Superintendent of Police or District 
    Magistrate or any other officer concerned or the special court.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> When an 
    offence has been committed under section 3 of the Act, the District 
    Magistrate or the Sub-Divisional Magistrate or any other Executive 
    Magistrate shall reimburse the payment of medicines, special medical 
    consultation, blood transfusion, replacement of essential clothing, meals 
    and fruits provided to the victim (s) of atrocity.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Measures to be taken by the District Administration.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The District Magistrate and the Superintendent of Police shall visit the 
    place or area where the atrocity has been committed to assess the loss of 
    life and damage to the property and draw a list of victims, their family 
    members and dependents entitled for relief.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Superintendent of Police shall ensure that the First Information Report is 
    registered in the book of the concerned police station and effective measure 
    for apprehending the accused are taken.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Superintendent of Police, after spot inspection, shall immediately appoint 
    an investigating officer and deploy such police force in the area and take 
    such other preventive measures as he may deem proper and necessary.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    District Magistrate or the Sub-Divisional Magistrate or any other Executive 
    Magistrate shall make arrangements for providing immediate relief in cash or 
    in kind or both to the victims of atrocity, their family members and 
    dependents according to the scale as in the Schedule annexed to these rules 
    (Annexure I read with Annexure II). Such immediate relief shall also include 
    food, water, clothing, shelter, medical aid, transport facilities and other 
    essential items necessary for human beings.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The relief 
    provided to the victim of the atrocity or his/her dependent under sub-rule 
    (4) in respect of death, or injury to, or damage to property shall be in 
    addition to any other right to claim compensation in respect there of under 
    any other law for the time being in force.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The relief 
    and rehabilitation facilities mentioned in sub-rule (4) above shall be 
    provided by the District Magistrate or Sub-Divisional Magistrate or any 
    other Executive Magistrate in accordance with the scales provided in the 
    Schedule annexed to these rules.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> A report 
    of the relief and rehabilitation facilities provided to the victims shall 
    also be forwarded to the Special Court by the District Magistrate or the 
    Sub-Divisional Magistrate or the Executive Magistrate of Superintendent of 
    Police. In case the Special Court is satisfied that the payment of relief 
    was not made to the victim or his/her dependent in time or the amount of 
    relief or compensation was not sufficient or only a part of payment of 
    relief or compensation was made it may order for making in full or part the 
    payment of relief or any other kind of assistance.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Selection of officers and other staff members for completing the work 
    relating to atrocity.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    State Government shall ensure that the administrative officers and other 
    staff members to be appointed in an area prone to atrocity shall have the 
    right aptitude and understanding of the problems of the Scheduled Castes and 
    the Scheduled Tribes.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It shall 
    also be ensured by the State Government that person from the Scheduled 
    Castes and the Scheduled Tribes are adequately represented in the 
    administration and in the police force at all levels, particularly at the 
    level of police posts and police station.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Specific responsibility of the State Government.—The 
    State Government shall make necessary provisions in its annual budget for 
    providing relief and rehabilitation facilities to the victims of atrocity. 
    It shall review atleast twice in a calendar year, in the month of January 
    and July the performance of the Special Public Prosecutor specified or 
    appointed under section 15 of the Act, various reports received, 
    investigation made and preventive steps taken by the District Magistrate, 
    Sub-Divisional Magistrate and Superintendent of Police, relief and 
    rehabilitation facilities provided to the victims and the reports in respect 
    of lapses on behalf of the Concerned officers.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Contingency plan by the State Government.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government shall prepare a model contingency plan for implementing 
    the provisions of the Act and notify the same in the Official Gazette of the 
    State Government. It should specify the role and responsibility of various 
    departments and their officers at different levels, the role and 
    responsibility of Rural/Urban Local Bodies and Non-Government Organisations.
    Inter alia this plan shall contain a package of relief measures 
    including the following :—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    scheme to provide 
    immediate relief in cash or in kind or both;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    allotment of 
    agricultural land and house sites;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the rehabilitation 
    packages;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    scheme for employment in 
    Government or Government undertaking to the dependant or one of the family 
    members of the victim;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    pension scheme for 
    widows, dependant children of the deceased, handicapped or old age victims 
    of atrocity;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>)    mandatory compensation 
    for the victims;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    scheme for strengthening 
    the socio-economic condition of the victim;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    provisions for providing 
    brick/stone masonary house to the victims;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    such other elements as 
    health care, supply of essential commodities, electrification, adequate 
    drinking water facility, burial/cremation ground and link road to the 
    Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled Tribes habitats.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The State 
    Government shall forward a copy of the contingency plan or a summary thereof 
    and a copy of the scheme, as soon as may be, to the Central Government in 
    the Ministry of Welfare and to all the District Magistrates, Sub-Divisional 
    Magistrates, Inspectors General of Police and Superintendents of Police.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Constitution of State-level vigilance and monitoring committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government shall constitute a high power vigilance and monitoring 
    committee of not more than 25 members consisting of the following:—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    Chief 
    Minister/Administrator—Chairman (in case of a State under President’s Rule 
    Governor—Chairman);
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    Home Minister, Finance 
    Minister and Welfare Minister—Members (in case of a State under the 
    President’s Rule Advisors—Members);
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    all elected Members of 
    Parliament and State Legislative Assembly and Legislative Council from the 
    State belonging to the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled Tribes—Members;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    Chief Secretary, the 
    Home Secretary, the Director General of Police, Director/Deputy Director 
    National Commission for the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled Tribes—Members;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>    the Secretary in-charge 
    of the welfare and development of the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled 
    Tribes—Convenor.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The high 
    power vigilance and monitoring committee shall meet at least twice in a 
    calendar year, in the month of January and July to review the implementation 
    of the provisions of the Act, relief and rehabilitation facilities provided 
    to the victims and other matters connected therewith, prosecution of cases 
    under the Act, role of different officers/agencies responsible for 
    implementing the provisions of the Act and various reports received by the 
    State Government.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Constitution of District-level vigilance and monitoring committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In each district within the State, the District Magistrate shall set up a 
    vigilance and monitoring committee in his district to review the 
    implementation of the provisions of the Act, relief and rehabilitation 
    facilities provided to the victims and other matters connected therewith, 
    prosecution of cases under the Act, role of different officers/agencies 
    responsible for implementing the provisions of the Act and various reports 
    received by the District Administration.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    district-level vigilance and monitoring committee shall consist of the 
    elected Members of the Parliament and State Legislative Assembly and 
    Legislative Council, Superintendent of Police, three group ‘A’ officers/Gazetted 
    officers of the State Government belonging to the Scheduled Castes and the 
    Scheduled Tribes, not more than 5 non-official members belonging to the 
    Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled Tribes and not more than 3 members from 
    the categories other than the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled Tribes 
    having association with Non-Government Organizations. The District 
    Magistrate and District Social Welfare Officer shall be Chairman and 
    Member-Secretary respectively.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    district-level committee shall meet at least once in three months.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Material for annual report.—The 
    State Government shall every year before the 1st July, forward the report to 
    the Central Government about the measures taken for implementing provisions 
    of the Act and various schemes/plans framed by it during the previous 
    calendar year.  
  
 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>