<act><title>


The Working Journalists (Fixation of Rates of 
    Wages) Act, 1958 </title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title.—This 
    Act may be called the Working Journalists (Fixation of Rates of Wages) Act, 
    1958.  

 
  

 
  
  
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>   “Committee” means the Committee 
    constituted under section 3;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   “prescribed” means prescribed by 
    rules made under this Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   “Wage Board” means the Wage Board 
    constituted under the Working Journalists Act by Notification No. S.R.O. 
    1075 of the Government of India in the Ministry of Labour, dated the 2nd 
    May, 1956;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   “Wage Board decision” means the 
    decisions of the Wage Board published in the Gazette of India, 
    Extraordinary, Part II, Section 3, dated the 11th May, 1957;  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   “wages” means wages as defined in 
    the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 (14 of 1947);  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   “Working Journalists Act” means 
    the Working Journalists (Conditions of Service) and Miscellaneous Provisions 
    Act, 1955 (45 of 1955);  
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>   words and expressions used but not 
    defined in this Act, and defined in the Working Journalists Act, shall have 
    the meanings respectively assigned to them to in that Act.  

 
  

 
  
  
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
        Constitution of Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    For the purpose of enabling the Central Government to fix rates of wages in 
    respect of working journalists in the light of the Judgment of the Supreme 
    Court, dated the 19th day of March, 1958, relating to the Wage Board 
    decision, and in the light of all other relevant circumstances, the Central 
    Government shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute a 
    Committee consisting of the following persons, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   an officer of the Ministry of Law 
    not below the rank of Joint Secretary, nominated by the Central Government, 
    who shall be the Chairman of the Committee,  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   three persons nominated by the 
    Central Government from among the officers of each of the Ministries of Home 
    Affairs, Labour and Employment and Information and Broadcasting,  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   a chartered accountant nominated 
    by the Central Government.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    for any reason a vacancy (other than a vacancy by reason of temporary 
    absence) occurs in the office of the Chairman or any other member of the 
    Committee, the Central Government may appoint another person in accordance 
    with the provisions of sub-section (1) to fill the vacancy, and the inquiry 
    before the Committee may be continued from the stage which had been reached 
    when the vacancy arose.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Central Government may appoint a Secretary to the Committee, and may also 
    provide the Committee with such other staff as may be necessary.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Secretary shall perform such functions of a ministerial or other nature as 
    the Committee or the Chairman thereof may assign or delegate to him.  
 

 
  

 
  
  
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Functions of Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Committee shall, by notice published in such manner as it thinks fit, 
    call upon newspaper establishments and working journalists and other persons 
    interested in the Wage Board decision to make such representations as they 
    may think fit as respects the Wage Board decision and the rates of wages 
    which may be fixed under this Act in respect of working journalists.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every such representation shall be in writing and shall be made within such 
    period not exceeding thirty days, as the Committee may specify in the 
    notice, and shall state—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the specific grounds of objection, 
    if any, to the Wage Board decision,  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   the rates of wages which, in the 
    opinion of the person making the representation, would be reasonable, having 
    regard to the capacity of the employer to pay the same or to any other 
    circumstance, whichever may seem relevant to the person making the 
    representation in relation to his representation,  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   the alterations or modifications, 
    if any, which, in the opinion of the person making the representation, 
    should be made in the Wage Board decision and the reasons therefor.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Committee shall take into account the representations aforesaid, if any, and 
    after examining the materials placed before the Wage Board and such further 
    materials as have since been obtained by or made available to it under this 
    Act, make such recommendations, as it thinks fit, to the Central Government 
    for the fixation of rates of wages in respect of working journalists, 
    whether by way of modification or otherwise, of the Wage Board decision; and 
    any such recommendation may specify, whether prospectively or 
    retrospectively, the date from which the rates of wages should take effect.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> In 
    making any recommendations to the Central Government, the Committee shall 
    have regard to all the matters set out in sub-section (1) of section 9 of 
    the Working Journalists Act.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Committee may, if it thinks fit, take up for consideration separately groups 
    or classes of newspaper establishments, whether on the basis of regional 
    classification or on any other basis, and made recommendations from time to 
    time in regard to each such group or class.  

 
  

 
  
  
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Powers of Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions contained in sub-section (2), the Committee may 
    exercise all or any of the powers which an industrial tribunal, constituted 
    under the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 (14 of 1947), exercises for the 
    adjudication of an industrial dispute referred to it and shall, subject to 
    the provisions contained in this Act and the rules, if any, made thereunder, 
    have power to regulate its own procedure.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any 
    representations made to the Committee and any documents furnished to it by 
    way of evidence, shall be open to inspection on payment of such fee as may 
    be prescribed by any person interested in the matter.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If 
    in the course of any inquiry it appears to the Committee that it is 
    necessary to examine any accounts or documents or obtain any statements from 
    any person, the Committee may authorise any officer of the Central 
    Government (hereinafter referred to as the authorised officer) in that 
    behalf; and the authorised officer shall, subject to the directions of the 
    Committee, if any, examine the accounts or documents or obtain the 
    statements from the person.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    authorised officer may, subject to the directions of the Committee, if any, 
    exercise all or any of the powers which an industrial tribunal may exercise 
    under sub-section (2) or sub-section (3) of section 11 of the Industrial 
    Disputes Act, 1947 (14 of 1947).  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> 
    Nothing in sub-section (1) of section 54 of the Indian Income-tax Act, 1922 
    (11 of 1922), or in any corresponding provision in any other law for the 
    time being in force relating to the levy of any tax shall apply to the 
    disclosure of any of the particulars referred to therein in any report made 
    to the Committee by an authorised officer.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Any 
    information obtained by an authorised officer in the exercise of any of his 
    powers and any report made by him shall, notwithstanding anything contained 
    in this Act, be treated as confidential but nothing in this sub-section 
    shall apply to the disclosure of any such information or report to the 
    Central Government or to a court in relation to any matter concerning the 
    execution of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The 
    authorised officer shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning 
    of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).  
 

 
  

 
  
  
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Power of Central Government to enforce recommendations of Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    As soon as may be, after the receipt of the recommendations of the 
    Committee, the Central Government shall make an order in terms of the 
    recommendations or subject to such modifications, if any, as it thinks fit, 
    being modifications which, in the opinion of the Central Government, do not 
    effect important alterations in the character of the recommendations.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), the Central 
    Government may, if it thinks fit,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   make such modifications in the 
    recommendations not being modifications of the nature referred to in 
    sub-section (1) as it thinks fit:
 
Provided that before making any such 
    modifications, the Central Government shall cause notice to be given to all 
    persons likely to be affected thereby in such manner as may be prescribed, 
    and shall take into account any representations which they may make in this 
    behalf in writing, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   refer the recommendations or any 
    part thereof to the Committee, in which case the Central Government shall 
    consider its further recommendations and make an order either in terms of 
    the recommendations or with such modifications of the nature referred to in 
    sub-section (1) as it thinks fit.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Every order made by the Central Government shall be published in the 
    Official Gazette together with the recommendations of the Committee relating 
    to the order, and the order shall come into operation on the date of 
    publication or on such date, whether prospectively or retrospectively, as 
    may be specified in the order.  

 
  

 
  
  
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Working journalists entitled to wages at rates not less than those specified 
    in the order.—Subject 
    to the provisions contained in section 11, on the coming into operation of 
    an order of the Central Government, every working journalist shall be 
    entitled to be paid by his employer wages at a rate which shall in no case 
    be less than the rate of wages specified in the order.  

 
  

 
  
  
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Review of order of Central Government.—[Rep. 
    by the Working Journalists (Amendment) Act, 1962, sec. 10 (w.e.f. 
    15-1-1963)].  

 
  

 
  
  
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Recovery of money due to working journalists.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where any amount is due under this Act to a working journalist from an 
    employer, 

    1[the working 
    journalist himself, or any other person authorised by him in writing in this 
    behalf or in the case of the death of the working journalist, any member of 
    his family may,] without prejudice to any other mode of recovery, make an 
    application to the State Government for the recovery of the money due to 
    him, and if the State Government, or such authority as the State Government 
    may specify in this behalf, is satisfied that any money is so due, it shall 
    issue a certificate for that amount to the Collector, and the Collector 
    shall proceed to recover that amount in the same manner as an arrear of land 
    revenue.  
 


    2[(2) If any question 
    arises as to the amount due under this Act to a working journalist from his 
    employer, the State Government may on its own motion or upon application 
    made to it, refer the question to any Labour Court constituted by it under 
    the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 (14 of 1947), or under any corresponding 
    law relating to investigation and settlement of industrial disputes in force 
    in the State and the said Act or law shall have effect in relation to the 
    Labour Court as if the question so referred were a matter referred to the 
    Labour Court for adjudication under that Act or law.]  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    decision of the Labour Court shall be forwarded by it to the State 
    Government which made the reference, and any amount found due by the Labour 
    Court may be recovered in the manner provided in sub-section (1).  
 
 






 


 
  
  
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Authentication of orders, letters, etc., of the Committee.—All 
    notices, letters authorisations, orders or other documents to be issued or 
    made by the Committee under this Act may be authenticated by the Chairman or 
    the Secretary thereof or any other officer authorised by the Committee in 
    this behalf and any notice, letter authorisation, order or other document so 
    authenticated shall be presumed to have been duly issued or made by the 
    Committee.  

 
  

 
  
  
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Effect of Act on Working Journalists Act, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Sections 8, 10, 11, 12 and 13 of the Working Journalists Act shall have no 
    effect in relation to the Committee.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
    inconsistent therewith in the terms of any award, agreement or contract of 
    service, whether made before or after the commencement of this Act:  
 
Provided 
    that where under any such award, agreement, contract of service or 
    otherwise, a working journalist is entitled to benefits in respect of any 
    matter which are more favourable to him than those to which he would be 
    entitled under this Act, the working journalist shall continue to be 
    entitled to the more favourable benefits in respect of that matter, 
    notwithstanding that he receives benefits in respect of other matters under 
    this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Nothing contained in this Act shall be construed to preclude any working 
    journalist from entering into any agreement with an employer for granting 
    him rights or privileges in respect of any matter which are more favourable 
    to him than those to which he would be entitled under this Act.  

 
  

 
  
  
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Vacancies, etc., not to invalidate proceedings of Committee.—No 
    act or proceeding of the Committee shall be invalid merely by reason of the 
    existence of any vacancy among its members or any defect in the constitution 
    thereof.  
 

 
  

 
  
  
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>12A</number> Penalty.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any employer who contravenes the provisions of section 7 shall be punishable 
    with fine which may extend to two hundred rupees.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Whoever, having been convicted of any offence under sub-section (1), is 
    again convicted of an offence under that sub-section, shall be punishable 
    with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Where an offence has been committed by a company, every person who, at the 
    time the offence was committed, was in charge, of and was responsible to, 
    the company for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as the 
    company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to 
    be proceeded against and punished accordingly:  
 
Provided 
    that nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person 
    liable to any punishment provided in this section if he proves that the 
    offence was committed without his knowledge or that he exercised all due 
    diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (3), where an offence 
    under this section has been committed by a company and it is proved that the 
    offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or that the 
    commission of the offence is attributable, to any gross negligence on the 
    part of any director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, 
    such director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to 
    be guilty of such offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and 
    punished accordingly.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> For 
    the purposes of this section,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   “company” means any body corporate 
    and includes a firm or other association of individuals; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   “director” in relation to a firm 
    means a partner in the firm.]
 
 
 
 




 


 
  
  
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make 
    rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the manner in which notices under 
    this Act may be published;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   the procedure to be followed by 
    the Committee in the exercise of its powers under this Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   the powers and functions of the 
    Committee which may be delegated to any of its members;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   the fees to be paid for inspection 
    of documents furnished to the Committee.  
 


    1[(3) Every rule made 
    under this Act, shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made before each 
    House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty 
    days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive 
    sessions and if before the expiry of the session immediately following the 
    sessions or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making 
    any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
    be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or 
    be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however that any such modification 
    or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
    previously done under that rule.]  
 
 




 


 
  
  
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Repeal and saving.—[Rep. 
    by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1960, sec. 2 and Sch. I].  
  
 
  

 
  
  
  


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>