<act><tid>761918</tid>
<title>THE LOK SAHAYAK SENA ACT, <year>1956</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum></title>

ACT NO. 53 OF <year>1956</year>
[ 15th September, <year>1956</year>.]

An Act to provide for the constitution of Lok Sahayak Sena for 
imparting military training to citizens of India

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Seventh Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>1671469</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>1650496</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Lok  
Sahayak Sena Act, <year>1956</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1737938</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1184162</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>43509</tid>
<number>a</number>" camp" means any place established under section 4 as a 
camp where any body of volunteers is for the time being 
undergoing training;

</section>

<section><tid>1031720</tid>
<number>b</number>" Force" means the Lok Sahayak Sena constituted under 
this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>341223</tid>
<number>c</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1899627</tid>
<number>d</number>" superior officer" means any officer, junior 
commissioned officer, warrant officer or non- commissioned 
officer of the regular Army or of the Territorial Army;

</section>

<section><tid>188219</tid>
<number>e</number>" volunteer" means a person enrolled in the Force under 
this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>150075</tid>
<number>f</number>all words and expressions used in this Act and not 
defined but defined in the Army Act, <year>1950</year> (46 of <year>1950</year>), or in 
the Territorial Army Act, <year>1948</year> (56 of <year>1948</year>), shall have the 
meanings respectively assigned to them in the said Acts.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1606776</tid>
<number>3</number>Construction of the Lok Sahayak Sena. There shall be raised 
and maintained by the Central Government a force to be designated the 
Lok Sahayak Sena by the enrolment of volunteers in the manner 
hereinafter provided.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>292</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been extended to and comes into force in 
Pondicherry vide Reg. 7 of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch. I (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1963</year>).






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>224832</tid>
<number>4</number>Establishment of camps. The Central Government may establish 
such number of camps for the purposes of the Force as it thinks fit 
and may close down or re- establish any such camps.


</article>



<article><tid>355233</tid>
<number>5</number>Enrolment. Any citizen of India not below the age of eighteen 
years and not above the age of forty years may offer himself for 
enrolment as a volunteer and may, if he satisfies the prescribed 
conditions, be enrolled in the prescribed manner by the prescribed 
authority for such period and subject to such conditions as may be 
prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>122165</tid>
<number>6</number>Duties of volunteers. No person shall, on the ground only of 
being a volunteer be liable for military service, but subject thereto 
a volunteer may be called upon to undergo such training as may be 
prescribed, and while undergoing such training shall perform such 
duties and discharge such obligations as the prescribed authority may, 
be general or special order, direct.


</article>



<article><tid>24567</tid>
<number>7</number>Discharge. Every volunteer shall be entitled to receive his 
discharge from the Force on the expiration of the period for which he 
was enrolled, but may, prior to the expiration of that period, be dis- 
charged from the Force by such authority and subject to such con- 
ditions as may be prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>1339703</tid>
<number> 8</number> Officers and penalties.
<section><tid>1844586</tid>
<number>1</number>If any volunteer commits any of  
the following offences, that is to say,-

<subsection><tid>1870390</tid>
<number>i</number>without sufficient cause fails to attend at any place 
when duly required to do so; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1457282</tid>
<number>ii</number>while in camp on duty-

<subsubsection><tid>9960</tid>
<number>a</number>absents himself from the camp without leave;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1404358</tid>
<number>b</number>uses criminal force or uses threatening or in- 
subordinate language to a superior officer or assaults a 
superior officer;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1166897</tid>
<number>c</number>disobeys any lawful command of a superior officer;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>763321</tid>
<number>d</number>neglects to obey any standing, general or other 
orders by the officer commanding the camp;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>25061</tid>
<number>e</number>uses criminal force to, or assaults, any volunteer 
or any person subject to the Army Act, <year>1950</year> (46 of  
  <year>1950</year>), or the Territorial Army Act, <year>1948</year> (56 of <year>1948</year>);

<pagefootnote><pagenum>292A</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1810523</tid>
<number>f</number>knowingly does any act which is prejudicial to the 
maintenance of good order or military discipline in 
camp;
he shall be punishable summarily by order of the prescribed authority 
with fine which may extend to fifty rupees or, in default, by being 
confined to barracks for a term which may extend to seven days.


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>759419</tid>
<number>2</number>Any fine imposed by order of the prescribed authority under 
sub- section (1) may, on application made in this behalf by the pre-

<pagefootnote><pagenum>293</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

scribed authority to a magistrate having jurisdiction in the place 
where the volunteer resides or has a place of business, be recovered 
in accordance with the provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 
 <year>1898</year> (5 of <year>1898</year>), as if it were a fine imposed by such magistrate.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>86576</tid>
<number>9</number>Liability for causing loss of, or damage to, Government 
property. If any volunteer wilfully or negligently causes loss of, or 
damage to, any property of the Government, the prescribed authority 
may, after giving him an opportunity of being heard and after making 
such inquiry into the matter as it thinks fit, make an order requiring 
him to make good the loss or damage within such time as may be 
specified in the order or within such further time as may be allowed 
by the prescribed authority in this behalf, and where the amount 
thereof as determined by the prescribed authority is not paid within 
the time allowed, it shall, on application made by the prescribed 
authority to the Collector of the district in which the volunteer 
resides or has a place of business, be recovered from him in the same 
manner as an arrears of land revenue.


</article>



<article><tid>329631</tid>
<number>10</number>Presumption as to certain documents. Where a volunteer is 
required by or in pursuance of any rule made under this Act to attend 
at any place, a certificate purporting to be signed by the prescribed 
officer stating that the volunteer so required to attend failed to do 
so, in accordance with such requirement shall, without proof of the 
signature or appointment of such officer, be evidence of the matters 
stated therein.


</article>



<article><tid>478763</tid>
<number> 11</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>707279</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the 
purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>268008</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of 
the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>871345</tid>
<number>a</number>the authorities by which, the manner in which, the 
period for which, and the conditions subject to which, any 
person may be enrolled as a volunteer;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>771328</tid>
<number>b</number>the training, discipline, duties and obligations which 
a volunteer has to undergo, observe, perform or discharge 
under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1190639</tid>
<number>c</number>the authorities by which, and the conditions subject to 
which, a volunteer may be discharged;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1159506</tid>
<number>d</number>the manner in which, and the conditions subject to 
which, volunteer may be called out for training or duties;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1779275</tid>
<number>e</number>the determination of authorities for the purposes of 
this Act;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>294</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>23365</tid>
<number>f</number>the officers by whom certificates may be signed under 
section 10; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>242236</tid>
<number>g</number>any other matter which under this Act is to be or may 
be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>751426</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon 
as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it 
is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be com- 
prised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, 
before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or 
the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>295</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 4 of <year>1986</year>, s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 15. 5. <year>1986</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>