<act><tid>763062</tid>
<title>THE SMUGGLERS AND FOREIGN EXCHANGE MANIPULATORS (FORFEITURE  
  OFPROPERTY ACT <year>1976</year>),</title>

ACT NO. 13 OF <year>1976</year>
[ 25th January, <year>1976</year>.]

An Act to provide for the forfeiture of illegally acquired 
properties of smugglers and foreign exchange manipulators and for 
matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.

WHEREAS for the effective prevention of smuggling activities and 
foreign exchange manipulations which are having a deleterious effect 
on the national economy it is necessary to deprive persons engaged in 
such activities and manipulations of their ill- gotten gains;

AND WHEREAS such persons have been augmenting such gains by 
violations of wealth- tax, income- tax or other laws or by other means 
and have thereby been increasing their resources for operating in a 
clandestine manner;

AND WHEREAS such persons have in many cases been holding the pro- 
perties acquired by them through such gains in the names of their 
relatives, associates and confidants;

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- sixth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-





<article><tid>1827614</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>870445</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Smugglers and Foreign Exchange Manipulators (Forfeiture of  
  Property) Act, <year>1976</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>318294</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu 
and Kashmir.

</section>

<section><tid>1785059</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 5th day of 
November, <year>1975</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1651179</tid>
<number> 2</number> Application.
<section><tid>1501399</tid>
<number>1</number>The provisions of this Act shall apply only to  
the persons specified in sub- section (2).

</section>

<section><tid>279476</tid>
<number>2</number>The persons referred to in sub- section (1) are the 
following, namely:-

<subsection><tid>669258</tid>
<number>a</number>every person-

<subsubsection><tid>1017640</tid>
<number>i</number>who has been convicted under the Sea Customs Act, 
 <year>1878</year> (8 of <year>1878</year>), or the Customs Act, <year>1962</year> (52 of <year>1962</year>), of 
an offence in relation to goods of a value exceeding one lakh 
of rupees; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1121872</tid>
<number>ii</number>who has been convicted under the Foreign Exchange 
Regulation Act, <year>1947</year> (7 of <year>1947</year>), or the Foreign Exchange 
Regulation Act,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1104</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

 <year>1973</year> (46 of <year>1973</year>), of an offence, the amount or value 
involved in which exceeds one lakh of rupees; or


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>478958</tid>
<number>iii</number>who having been convicted under the Sea Customs Act, 
 <year>1878</year> (8 of <year>1878</year>), or the Customs Act, <year>1962</year> (52 of <year>1962</year>), has 
been convicted subsequently under either of those Acts; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>453804</tid>
<number>iv</number>who having been convicted under the Foreign Exchange 
Regulation Act, <year>1947</year> (7 of <year>1947</year>), or the Foreign Exchange 
Regulation Act, <year>1973</year> (46 of <year>1973</year>), has been convicted 
subsequently under either of those Acts;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1979284</tid>
<number>b</number>every person in respect of whom an order of detention 
has been made under the Conservation of Foreign Exchange and 
Prevention of Smuggling Activities Act, <year>1974</year> (52 of <year>1974</year>);
Provided that-


<subsubsection><tid>1653335</tid>
<number>i</number>such order of detention, being an order to which the 
provisions of section 9 or section 12A of the said Act do not 
apply, has not been revoked on the report of the Advisory 
Board under section 8 of the said Act or before the receipt 
of the report of the Advisory Board or before making a 
reference to the Advisory Board; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1042676</tid>
<number>ii</number>such order of detention, being an order to which the 
provisions of section 9 of the said Act apply, has not been 
revoked before the expiry of the time for, or on the basis 
of, the review under sub- section (3) of section 9, or on the 
report of the Advisory Board under section 8, read with sub- 
section (2) of section 9, of the said Act; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1337786</tid>
<number>iii</number>such order of detention, being an order to which, the 
provisions of section 12A of the said Act apply, has not been 
revoked before the expiry of the time for, or on the basis 
of, the first review under sub- section (3) of that section, 
or on the basis of the report of the Advisory Board under 
section 8, read with sub- section (6) of section 12A, of that 
Act; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>344011</tid>
<number>iv</number>such order of detention has not been set aside by a 
court of competent jurisdiction;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1336950</tid>
<number>c</number>every person who is a relative of a person referred to 
in clause (a) or clause (b);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>463743</tid>
<number>d</number>every associate of a person referred to in clause (a) 
or clause (b);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1940503</tid>
<number>e</number>any holder (hereafter in this clause referred to as the  
  present holder) of any property which was at any time 
previously held by a person referred to in clause (a) or 
clause (b) unless the present holder or, as the case may be, 
any one who held

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1105</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

such property after such person and before the present 
holder, is or was a transferee in good faith for adequate 
consideration.

Explanation 1.- For the purposes of sub- clause (i) of clause (a), 
the value of any goods in relation to which a person has been 
convicted of an offence shall be the wholesale price of the goods in 
the ordinary course of trade in India as on the date of the commission 
of the offence.

Explanation 2.-- For the purposes of clause (c)," relative", in 
relation to a person, means-


<subsubsection><tid>1642479</tid>
<number>i</number>spouse of the person;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>654369</tid>
<number>ii</number>brother or sister of the person;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1364253</tid>
<number>iii</number>brother or sister of the spouse of the person;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1377296</tid>
<number>iv</number>any lineal ascendant or descendant of the person;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>544572</tid>
<number>v</number>any lineal ascendant or descendant of the spouse of the 
person;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1752209</tid>
<number>vi</number>spouse of a person referred to in clause (ii), clause 
 (iii), clause (iv) or clause (v);

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1151731</tid>
<number>vii</number>any lineal descendant of a person referred to in clause 
 (ii) or clause (iii).
Explanation 3.- For the purposes of clause (d)," associate", in 
relation to a person, means-


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1642479</tid>
<number>i</number>any individual who had been or is residing in the 
residential premises (including outhouses) of such person;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>654369</tid>
<number>ii</number>any individual who had been or is managing the affairs 
or keeping the accounts of such person;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1364253</tid>
<number>iii</number>any association of persons, body of individuals, 
partnership firm, or private company within the meaning of 
the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), of which such person 
had been or is a member, partner or director;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1377296</tid>
<number>iv</number>any individual who had been or is a member, partner or 
director of an association of persons, body of individuals, 
partnership firm or private company referred to in clause 
 (iii) at any time when such person had been or is a member, 
partner or director of such association, body, partnership 
firm or private company;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>544572</tid>
<number>v</number>any person who had been or is managing the affairs, or 
keeping the accounts, of any association of persons, body of

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1106</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

individuals, partnership firm or private company referred to 
in clause (iii);


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1752209</tid>
<number>vi</number>the trustee of any trust, where-

<subsubsubsection><tid>712412</tid>
<number>a</number>the trust has been created by such person; or

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1599027</tid>
<number>b</number>the value of the assets contributed by such person 
 (including the value of the assets, if any, contributed by  
  him earlier) to the trust amounts, on the date on which the 
contribution is made, to not less than twenty per cent. of 
the value of the assets of the trust on that date;

</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1151731</tid>
<number>vii</number>where the competent authority, for reasons to be 
recorded in writing, considers that any properties of such 
person are held on his behalf by any other person, such other 
person.
Explanation 4.- For the avoidance of doubt, it is hereby provided 
that the question whether any person is a person to whom the 
provisions of this Act apply may be determined with reference to any 
facts, circumstances or events (including any conviction or detention) 
which occurred or took place before the commencement of this Act.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>2A</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Act not to apply to certain persons. Act not to apply to certain 
persons. <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 2A. On and from thecommencement of the provisions of Chapter VA of 
the Narcotic Drugs andPsychotropic Substance




</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>420621</tid>
<number> 3</number> Definitions.
<section><tid>1085132</tid>
<number>1</number>In this Act, unless the context otherwise  
requires-

<subsection><tid>1408704</tid>
<number>a</number>" Appellate Tribunal" means the Appellate Tribunal for 
Forfeited Property constituted under section 12;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>756070</tid>
<number>b</number>" competent authority" means an officer of the Central 
Government authorised by it under sub- section (1) of section 
 5 to perform the functions of a competent authority under 
this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>568215</tid>
<number>c</number>" illegally acquired property", in relation to any 
person to whom this Act applies, means-

<subsubsection><tid>1896134</tid>
<number>i</number>any property acquired by such person, whether before or 
after the commencement of this Act, wholly or partly out of 
or by means of any income, earnings or assets derived or 
obtained from or attributable to any activity prohibited by 
or under any law for the time being in force relating to any 
matter in respect of which Parliament has power to make laws; 
or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1128126</tid>
<number>ii</number>any property acquired by such person, whether before or 
after the commencement of this Act, wholly or partly out of 
or by means of any income, earnings or assets in respect of 
which any such law has been contravened; or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1106A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 2 of <year>1989</year>, s. 22 (w. e. f. 29- 05- <year>1989</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>865714</tid>
<number>iii</number>any property acquired by such person, whether before or 
after the commencement of this Act, wholly or partly out of 
or by means of any income, earnings or assets the source of 
which cannot be proved and which cannot be shown to be 
attributable to any act or thing done in respect of any 
matter in relation to which Parliament has no power to make 
laws; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1590472</tid>
<number>iv</number>any property acquired by such person, whether before or 
after the commencement of this Act, for a consideration,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1107</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

or by any means, wholly or partly traceable to any property 
referred to in sub- clauses (i) to (iii) or the income or 
earnings from such property;

and includes-


<subsubsubsection><tid>269406</tid>
<number>A</number>any property held by such person which would have been, 
in relation to any previous holder thereof, illegally ac- 
quired property under this clause if such previous holder had 
not ceased to hold it, unless such person or any other person 
who held the property at any time after such previous holder 
or, where there are two or more such previous holders, the 
last of such previous holders is or was a transferee in good 
faith for adequate consideration;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1370405</tid>
<number>B</number>any property acquired by such person, whether before or 
after the commencement of this Act, for a consideration, or 
by any means, wholly or partly traceable to any property 
falling under item (A), or the income or earnings therefrom;

</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>68116</tid>
<number>d</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act; 
 (e)" property" includes any interest in property, movable 
or immovable;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>244268</tid>
<number>f</number>" trust" includes any other legal obligation.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>748493</tid>
<number>2</number>Any reference in this Act to any law which is not in force 
in any area shall, in relation to that area, be construed as a 
reference to the corresponding law, if any, in force in that area.

</section>

<section><tid>1728336</tid>
<number>3</number>Any reference in this Act to any officer or authority shall, 
in relation to any area in which there is no officer or authority with 
the same designation, be construed as a reference to such officer or 
authority as may be specified by the Central Government by 
notification in the Official Gazette.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>729978</tid>
<number> 4</number> Prohibition of holding illegally acquired property.
<section><tid>1645514</tid>
<number>1</number>As from  
the commencement of this Act, it shall not be lawful for any person to 
whom this Act applies to hold any illegally acquired property either 
by himself or through any other person on his behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>125545</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any person holds any illegally acquired property in 
contravention of the provisions of sub- section (1), such property 
shall be liable to be forfeited to the Central Government in 
accordance with the provisions of this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>364631</tid>
<number> 5</number> Competent authority.
<section><tid>1090056</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by order  
published in the Official Gazette, authorise as many officers of the 
Central Government (not below the rank of a Joint Secretary to the  
  Government), as it thinks fit, to Perform the functions of the 
competent authority under this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1108</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>523636</tid>
<number>2</number>The competent authorities shall perform their functions in 
respect of such persons or classes of persons as the Central 
Government may, by order, direct.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1223435</tid>
<number> 6</number> Notice of forfeiture.
<section><tid>1492740</tid>
<number>1</number>If, having regard to the value of  
the properties held by any person to whom this Act applies, either by 
himself or through any other person on his behalf, his known 
sources of income, earnings or assets, and any other information or 
material available to it as a result of action taken under section 18 
or otherwise, the competent authority has reason to believe (the  
  reasons for such belief to be recorded in writting) that all or any of 
such properties are illegally acquired properties. it may serve a 
notice upon such person (hereinafter referred to as the person  
  affected) calling upon him within such time as may be specified in the 
notice, which shall not be ordinarily less than thirty days, to 
indicate the sources of his income, earnings or assets, out of which 
or by means of which he has acquired such property, the evidence on 
which he relies and other relevant information and particulars, and to 
show cause why all or any of such properties, as the case may be, 
should not be declared to be illegally acquired properties and 
forfeited to the Central Government under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1017970</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a notice under sub- section (1) to any specifies any 
property as being held on behalf of such person by any other person. a 
copy of the notice shall also be served upon such other person.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>916683</tid>
<number> 7</number> Forfeiture of property in certain cases.
<section><tid>1104280</tid>
<number>1</number>The competent  
authority may, after considering the explanation, if any, to the show- 
cause notice issued under section 6, and the materials available 
before it and after giving to the person affected (and in a case where  
the person affected holds any property specified in the notice through 
  any other person, to such other person also) a reasonable opportunity 
of being heard, by order, record a finding whether all or any of the 
properties in question are illegally acquired properties.

</section>

<section><tid>722049</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the competent authority is satisfied that some of the 
properties referred to in the show- cause notice are illegally acquired 
properties but is not able to identify specifically such 
properties then, it shall be lawful for the competent authority to 
specify the. properties which, to the best of its judgment, are 
illegally acquired properties and record a finding accordingly under 
sub- section (1).

</section>

<section><tid>535008</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the competent authority records a finding under this 
section to the effect that any property is illegally acquired 
property, it shall declare that such property shall, subject to the 
provisions of this Act, stand forfeited to the Central Government free 
from all encumbrances.

</section>

<section><tid>1831067</tid>
<number>4</number>where any shares in a company stand forfeited to the Central 
Government under this Act, then, the company shall, notwithstanding 
anything contained in the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), or the art- 
icles of asso-

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1109</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

ciation of the company, forthwith register the Central Government as 
the transferee of such shares.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1890862</tid>
<number>8</number>Burden of proof. In any proceedings under this Act, the burden 
of proving that any property specified in the notice served under 
section 6 is not illegally acquired property shall be on the person 
affected.


</article>



<article><tid>1571474</tid>
<number> 9</number> Fine in lieu of forfeiture.
<section><tid>88640</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the competent authority  
makes a declaration that any property stands forfeited to the Central 
Government under section 7 and it is a case where the source of only a 
part, being less than one- half of the income, earnings or assets with 
which such property was acquired has not been proved to the 
satisfaction of the competent authority, it shall make an order giving 
an option to the person affected to pay, in lieu of forfeiture, a fine 
equal to one and one- fifth times the value of such part.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this sub- section, the value of 
any part of income, earnings or assets, with which any property has 
been acquired, shall be,-


<subsection><tid>1298775</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of any part of income or earnings, the 
amount of such part of income or earnings;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>315148</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of any part of assets, the proportionate 
part of the full value of the consideration for the 
acquistion of such assets.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1928814</tid>
<number>2</number>Before making an order imposing a fine under sub- section 
 (1), the per- son affected shall be given a reasonable opportunity 
of being heard,

</section>

<section><tid>314074</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the person affected pays the fine due under sub- 
section (1), within such time as may be allowed in that behalf, the 
competent authority may, by order, revoke the declaration of 
forfeiture under section 7 and thereupon such property shall stand 
released.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>646890</tid>
<number> 10</number> Procedure in relation to certain trust properties. In the case 
of any person referred to in clause (vi) of Explanation 3 to sub- 
section (2) of section 2, if the competent authority, on the the basis 
of the information and materials available to it, has reason to 
believe (the reason for such belief to be recorded in writing) that 
any property held in trust in illegally acquired property, it may 
serve a notice upon the author of the trust or, as the case may be, 
the contributor of the assets out of or by means of which such 
property was acquired by the trust and the trustees, calling upon them 
within such time as may be specified in the notice which shall not 
ordinarily be less than thirty days, to explain the source of the 
money or other assets out of or by means of which property was 
acquired or, as the case may be, the source of the money or other 
assets which were contributed to the trust for acquiring such property 
and thereupon such notice shall be deemed to be a notice served under 
section 6 and all the other provisions of this Act shall apply 
accordingly.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1110</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Explanation.- For the purposes of this section" illegally acquired 
property", in relation to any property held in trust, includes-

<section><tid>68041</tid>
<number>i</number>any property which if it had continued to be held by 
the author of the trust or the contributor of such property 
to the trust would have been illegally acquired property in 
relation to such author or contributor;

</section>

<section><tid>974739</tid>
<number>ii</number>any property acquired by the trust out of any 
contributions made by any person which would have been 
illegally acquired property in relation to such person had 
such person acquired such property out of such contributions.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>973439</tid>
<number>11</number>Certain transfers to be null and void. Where after the issue 
of a notice under section 6 or under section 10, any property referred 
to in the said notice is transferred by any mode whatsoever such 
transfer shall, for the purposes of the proceedings under this Act, be 
ignored and if such property is subsequently forfeited to the Central 
Government under section 7, then, the transfer of such property shall 
be deemed to be null and void.


</article>



<article><tid>582313</tid>
<number> 12</number> Constitution of Appellate Tribunal.
<section><tid>1997245</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government  
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute an Appellate 
Tribunal to be called the Appellate Tribunal for Forfeited Property 
consisting of a Chairman and such number of other members (being  
officers of the Central Government not below the rank of a Joint 
  Secretary to the Government) as the Central Government thinks fit, to 
be appointed by that Government for hearing appeals against the orders 
made under section 7, sub- section (1) of section 9 or section 10.

</section>

<section><tid>1484639</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chairman of the Appellate Tribunal shall be a person who 
is or has been or is qualified to be a Judge of the Supreme Court or 
of a High Court.

</section>

<section><tid>427482</tid>
<number>3</number>The terms and conditions of service of the Chairman and 
other members shall be such as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1267634</tid>
<number>4</number>Any person aggrieved by an order of the competent authority 
made under section 7, sub- section (1) of section 9 or section 10, may, 
within forty- five days from the date on which the order is served on 
him, prefer an appeal to the Appellate Tribunal:
Provided that the Appellate Tribunal may entertain any appeal 
after the said period of forty- five days, but not after sixty days, 
from the date aforesaid if it is satisfied that the appellant was 
prevented by sufficient cause from filing the appeal in time.


</section>

<section><tid>918818</tid>
<number>5</number>On receipt of an appeal under sub- section (4), the Appellate 
Tribunal may, after giving an opportunity to the appellant to be 
heard if he so desires, and after making such further enquiry as it 
deems fit, confirm, modify or set aside the order appealed against.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1111</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1379667</tid>
<number>6</number>The powers and functions of the Appellate Tribunal may be 
exercised and discharged by Benches consisting of three members and 
constituted by the Chairman of the Appellate Tribunal.

</section>

<section><tid>856372</tid>
<number>6A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (6), where 
the Chairman considers it necessary so to do for the expeditious 
disposal of appeals under this section, he may constitute a Bench of 
two members and a Bench so constituted may exercise and discharge the 
powers and functions of the Appellate Tribunal:
Provided that if the members of a Bench so constituted differ on 
any point or points, they shall state the point or points on which 
they differ and refer the same to a third member (to be specified by  
  the Chairman) for hearing on such point or points and such point or 
points shall be decided according to the opinion of that member.]


</section>

<section><tid>933141</tid>
<number>7</number>the Appellate Tribunal may regulate its own procedure.

</section>

<section><tid>326542</tid>
<number>8</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> On application to the Appellate Tribunal and on payment of the 
prescribed fee, the Tribunal may allow a party to any appeal or any 
person authorised in this behalf by such party to inspect at any time 
during office hours, any relevant records and registers of the 
Tribunal and obtain a certified copy of any art thereof.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1488604</tid>
<number>13</number>Notice or order not to be invalid for error in description. No 
notice issued or served, no declaration made, and no order 
passed, under this Act shall be deemed to be invaild by reason of any 
error in the description of the property or person mentioned therein 
if such property or person is identifiable from the description so 
mentioned.


</article>



<article><tid>256032</tid>
<number>14</number>Bar of jurisdiction. No order passed or declaration made under 
this Act shall be appealable except as provided therein and no civil 
court shall have jurisdiction in respect of any matter which the 
Appellate Tribunal or any competent authority is empowered by or under 
this Act to determine and no injunction shall be granted by any court 
or other authority in respect of any action taken or to be taken in 
pursuance of any power conferred by or under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>948373</tid>
<number> 15</number> Competent authority and Appellate Tribunal to have powers of 
civil court. The competent authority- and the Appellate Tribunal shall 
have all the powers of a civil court while trying a suit under the 
Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>), in respect of the 
following matters, namely:-
<section><tid>1764596</tid>
<number>a</number>summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person an 
examining him on oath;

</section>

<section><tid>1797844</tid>
<number>b</number>requiring the discovery and production of documents;

</section>

<section><tid>1741280</tid>
<number>c</number>receiving evidence on affidavits;

</section>

<section><tid>828183</tid>
<number>d</number>requisitioning any public record or copy thereof from 
any court or office;

</section>

<section><tid>1254310</tid>
<number>e</number>issuing commissions for examination of witnesses or 
documents;

</section>

<section><tid>744327</tid>
<number>f</number>any other matter which may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>920341</tid>
<number> 16</number> Information to competent authority.
<section><tid>1076778</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding  
anything contained in any other law, the competent authority shall 
have power to require any officer or authority of the Central 
Government or a State Government or a local authority to furnishing 
information in relation to such persons, points or matters as in the 
opinion of the competent authority will be useful for, or relevant to, 
the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1299925</tid>
<number>2</number>Any officer of the Income- tax Department, the Customs Depart- 
ment or the Central Excise Department or any officer of enforcement 
appointed under the Foreign Exchange Regulation Act, <year>1973</year> (46 of <year>1973</year>), 
may furnish

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1112</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 55 of <year>1980</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1981</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

suo motu any information available with him to the competent authority 
if in the opinion of the officer such information will be useful to 
the competent authority for the purposes of this Act.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1723703</tid>
<number> 17</number> Certain officers to assist competent authority and Appellate 
Tribunal. For the purposes of any proceedings under this Act, the 
following officers are hereby empowered and required to assist the 
competent authority and the Appellate Tribunal, namely:-
<section><tid>1744467</tid>
<number>a</number>officers of the Customs Department;

</section>

<section><tid>1343349</tid>
<number>b</number>officers of the Central Excise Department;

</section>

<section><tid>433393</tid>
<number>c</number>officers of the Income- tax Department;

</section>

<section><tid>952331</tid>
<number>d</number>officers of enforcement appointed under the Foreign 
Exchange Regulation Act, <year>1973</year>; (46 of <year>1973</year>)

</section>

<section><tid>636239</tid>
<number>e</number>officers of police;

</section>

<section><tid>76288</tid>
<number>f</number>such other officers of the Central or State Government 
as are specified by the Central Government in this behalf by 
notification in the Official Gazette.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1416542</tid>
<number> 18</number> Power of competent authority to require certain officers to 
exercise certain powers.
<section><tid>1834926</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purposes of any proceedings under  
this Act or the initiation of any such proceedings, the competent 
authority shall have power to cause to be conducted any inquiry, 
investigation or survey in respect of any person, place, property, 
assets, documents, books of account or any other relevant matters.

</section>

<section><tid>642908</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes referred to in sub- section (1), the 
competent authority may, having regard to the nature of the inquiry, 
investigation or survey, require an officer of the Income- tax 
Department to conduct or cause to be conducted such inquiry, 
investigation or survey.

</section>

<section><tid>997923</tid>
<number>3</number>Any officer of the Income- tax Department who is conducting 
or is causing to be conducted any inquiry, investigation or survey 
required to be conducted under sub- section (2), may, for the purpose 
of such inquiry, investigation or survey, exercise any power 
 (including the power to authorise the exercise of any power) which may 
be exercised by him for any purpose under the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> (43  
  of <year>1961</year>), and the provisions of the said Act shall, so far as may 
be, apply accordingly.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1874166</tid>
<number> 19</number> Power to take possession.
<section><tid>164220</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any property has been  
declared to be forfeited to the Central Government under this Act, or 
where the person affected has failed to pay the fine due under sub- 
section (1) of section 9 within the time allowed therefor under sub- 
section (3) of that section, the competent authority may order the 
person affected as well as any other person who may be in possession 
of the property to surrender or deliver possession thereof to the 
competent authority or to any person duly authorised by it in this 
behalf within thirty days of the service of the order.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1113</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>890359</tid>
<number>2</number>If any person refuses or fails to comply with an order made 
under sub- section (1), the competent authority may take possession of 
the property and may for that purpose use such force as may be 
necessary.

</section>

<section><tid>1418335</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (2), the 
competent authority may, for the purpose of taking possession of any 
property referred to in sub- section (1), requisition the service of 
any police officer to assist the competent authority and it shall be 
the duty of such officer to comply with such requisition.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1071319</tid>
<number>20</number>Rectification of mistakes. With a view to rectifying any 
mistakes apparent from record, the competent authority or the 
Appellate Tribunal, as the case may be, may amend any order made 
by it within a period of one year from the date of the order:
Provided that if any such amendment is likely to affect any 
person prejudicially, it shall not be made without giving to such 
person a reasonable opportunity of being heard.



</article>



<article><tid>667392</tid>
<number>21</number>Findings under other laws not conclusive for proceedings 
under this Act. No finding of any officer or authority under any other 
law shall be conclusive for the purpose of any proceedings under this 
Act.


</article>



<article><tid>964958</tid>
<number> 22</number> Service of notices and orders. Any notice or order issued or 
made under this Act shall be served-
<section><tid>56247</tid>
<number>a</number>by tendering the notice or order or sending it by 
registered post to the person for whom it is intended or to 
his agent;

</section>

<section><tid>50921</tid>
<number>b</number>if the notice or order cannot be served in the manner 
provided in clause (a), by affixing it on a conspicuous place 
in the property in relation to which the notice or order is 
issued or made, or on some conspicuous part of the premises 
in which the person for whom it is intended is known to have 
last resided or carried on business or personally worked for 
gain.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>807832</tid>
<number>23</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit, prosecution 
or other proceeding shall lie against the Central Government or any 
officers of the Central or State Government for anything which is 
done or intended to be done, in good faith in pursuance of this Act 
or the rules made thereunder.


</article>



<article><tid>1962759</tid>
<number>24</number>Act to have overiding effect. The provisions of this Act shall 
have effect notwithstanding any thing inconsistent therewith contained 
in any other law for the time being in force.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1114</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>72542</tid>
<number> 25</number> Provisions of the Act not to apply to certain properties held 
in trust. Nothing contained in this Act shall apply in relation to any 
property held by a trust or an institution created or established 
wholly for public religious or charitable purposes if-
<section><tid>483605</tid>
<number>i</number>such property has been so held by such trust or 
institution from a date prior to the commencement of this Act; 
or

</section>

<section><tid>1273233</tid>
<number>ii</number>such property is wholly traceable to any property held 
by such trust or institution prior to the commencement of 
this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1657152</tid>
<number> 26</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>977024</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the 
provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1114326</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1503589</tid>
<number>a</number>the terms and conditions of service of the Chairman and 
other members of the Appellate Tribunal under sub- section (3) 
of section 12;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1867215</tid>
<number>aa</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the fees which shall be paid for the inspection of the 
records and registers of the Appellate Tribunal or for 
obtaining a certified copy of any part thereof under sub- 
section (8) of section 12];

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>211837</tid>
<number>b</number>the powers of a civil court that may be exercised by 
the competent authority and the Appellate Tribunal under 
clause of section 15;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1871482</tid>
<number>c</number>any other matter which has to be, or may be, 
prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1484375</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may 
be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in 
session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the 
expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule, or both Houses agree that the rule should 
not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, 
that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to 
the validity of anything previously done under that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1951892</tid>
<number> 27</number> Repeal and saving.
<section><tid>721518</tid>
<number>1</number>The Smuggler and Foreign Exchange  
Manipulators (Forfeiture of Property) Ordinance, <year>1975</year> (20 of <year>1975</year>), is 
hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1729837</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action 
taken under the Ordinance so repealed shall be deemed to have been 
done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1115</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act of <year>1980</year> (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1981</year>).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>