<act><tid>763689</tid>
<title>THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES (BANKING COMPANIES) DECISION ACT, <year>1955</year></title>

ACT NO. 41 OF <year>1955</year>
[ 21st October, <year>1955</year>.]

An Act to provide for the modification of the decision of the Labour 
Appellate Tribunal, dated the 28th day of April, <year>1954</year>, in accordance 
with the recommendations of the Bank Award Commission and for giving 
effect to the award accordingly.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Sixth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:--





<article><tid>1930231</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title.- This Act may be called the Industrial Disputes 
 (Banking Companies) Decision Act, <year>1955</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1834633</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>765067</tid>
<number>a</number>" appellate decision" means the decision of the Labour 
Appellate Tribunal, dated the 28th day of April, <year>1954</year>, 
in the matter of the appeals filed before it against 
the award of the All- India Industrial Tribunal (Bank  
  Disputes), Bombay;

</section>

<section><tid>532646</tid>
<number>b</number>" award" means the award of the All- India Industrial 
Tribunal (Bank Disputes), Bombay, constituted by the 
notification of the Government of India in the Ministry 
of Labour No. S. R. O. 35, dated the 5th day of January, 
<year>1952</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>1419375</tid>
<number>c</number>" Bank Award Commission" means the person appointed by 
the Resolution of the Government of India in the 
Ministry of Labour No. LR. 100 (9) 55, dated the 25th 
day of February, <year>1955</year>, to enquire into and report upon 
the terms of reference specified in the Resolution of 
the Government of India in the Ministry of Labour No. 
LR. 100 (56) 54, dated the 17th day of September, <year>1954</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>1756559</tid>
<number>d</number>" modification order" means the order of the Government 
of India in the Ministry of Labour No. S. R. O. 2732, 
dated the 24th day of August, <year>1954</year>, modifying the 
appellate decision under section 15 of the Industrial 
Disputes (Appellate Tribunal) Act, <year>1950</year> (48 of <year>1950</year>),

<pagefootnote><pagenum>320</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>297341</tid>
<number> 3</number> Appellate decision to have effect subject to the modifications 
recommended by the Bank Award Commission.- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<section><tid>681095</tid>
<number>1</number>] The appellate  
decision shall have effect as if the modifications recommended in 
Chapter XI of the Report of the Bank Award Commission, dated the 25th 
day of July, <year>1955</year>, had actually been made therein, and the appellate 
decision as so modified shall be the decision of the Appellate 
Tribunal within the meaning of the Industrial Disputes (Appellate  
  Tribunal) Act, <year>1950</year> (48 of <year>1950</year>), and the award shall have effect 
accordingly.

</section>

<section><tid>959912</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), the 
recommendations in Chapter XI of the Report of the Bank Award 
Commission in relation to the banking companies incorporated in the 
former State of Travancore- Cochin specified in that Chapter shall be 
modified and shall be deemed to have been modified--

<subsection><tid>831579</tid>
<number>a</number>with effect from the 1st January, <year>1955</year>, in relation to 
the C Class banks known as the South Indian Bank 
Limited, Trichur, and the Catholic Syrian Bank Limited, 
Trichur, as if--

<subsubsection><tid>1885694</tid>
<number>1</number>in clause (1) of the said recommendations--

<subsubsubsection><tid>552469</tid>
<number>i</number>under the heading C Class', after the 
entry (viii), Travancore Bank', the entries (ix), 
South Indian Bank, Trichur' and (x), Catholic 
Syrian Bank, Trichur', had been inserted;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1276527</tid>
<number>ii</number>items (i) and (ii) under sub- clause (b) 
had been omitted; and

</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1022013</tid>
<number>2</number>in clause (2) thereof, after the words 
Travancore Bank', the words the South Indian 
Bank, Trichur, and the Catholic Syrian Bank, 
Trichur' had been inserted; and

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>499588</tid>
<number>b</number>with effect from the 1st January, <year>1956</year>, in relation to 
the C Class banks known as the Palai Central Bank 
Limited, Palai, and the Travancore Forward Bank 
Limited, Kottayam, and the D Class banks, as if in 
clause (1) of the said recommendations, items (i) and 
 (ii) under sub- clause (b) had been omitted.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1074174</tid>
<number>3</number>The arrears of emoluments payable to the workmen of the 
banking companies specified in sub- section (2) by reason of the 
modifications effected by that sub- section shall be paid as follows:--

<subsection><tid>410767</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of the banking companies specified in clause 
 (a) of that sub- section--

<subsubsection><tid>1026774</tid>
<number>i</number>the arrears for the year <year>1955</year> shall be 
paid in two equal instalments of which the first 
shall be paid within
<pagefootnote><pagenum>320A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>S. 3 renumbered as sub- section (1) of that section by Act 40 of 
<year>1957</year>, s. 2. 
2. Ins. by s. 2, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


thirty days from the commencement of the 
Industrial Disputes (Banking Companies) Decision 
Amendment Act, <year>1957</year> (40 of <year>1957</year>), and the second 
within six months after such commencement; and


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1912264</tid>
<number>ii</number>the arrears for the period from the 1st 
January, <year>1956</year>, to such commencement shall be paid 
within thirty days thereof;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>718483</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of the banking companies specified in clause 
 (b) of that sub- section, the arrears for the period 
from the 1st January, <year>1956</year>, to such commencement shall 
be paid within thirty days thereof.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>432955</tid>
<number>4</number>For the purposes of this section, the expression the former 
State of Travancore- Cochin' means the State of Travancore- Cochin as it 
existed immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>.]

</section>

<section><tid>1583653</tid>
<number>5</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing 
provisions of this section, the Central Government may, from time to 
time by notification in the Official Gazette, make in lieu of the 
adjustment of the dearness allowance recommended in clause 1 (e) of 
Chapter XI of the Report of the Bank Award Commission, such adjustment 
there- of as it thinks fit for any period subsequent to the 31st 
December, <year>1957</year>, with reference to the rise or fall, as compared to 144 
<year>1944</year> 100, of the average all- India cost of living index for any 
period immediately preceding that period; and upon the issue of such 
notification the adjustment of dearness allowance so made for any 
period shall be deemed to have been recommended in clause 1 (e) of the 
Report of that Commission:
Provided that any adjustment so made shall, so far as may be, 
bear to the rise or fall of the cost of living index the same ratio as 
is indicated between the adjustment of dearness allowance and the rise 
or fall of the cost of living index in the formula recommended in that 
clause.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1107713</tid>
<number>4</number>Duration of the award.- Notwithstanding anything contained in 
the Industrial Disputes Act, <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>), or the Industrial 
Disputes (Appellate Tribunal) Act <year>1950</year> (48 of <year>1950</year>), the award as 
now modified by the decision of the Appellate Tribunal in the manner 
referred to in section 3 shall remain in force until the 31st day of 
March, <year>1959</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>141581</tid>
<number>5</number>Modification order to have no effect except in certain cases.- 
The provisions of the modification order shall not have, and shall be 
deemed never to have had, any force or effect except in so far as any 
of such provisions has become incorporated in the award by reason of 
the provisions contained in section 3.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>320B</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 38 of <year>1958</year>, s. 2.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>751858</tid>
<number> 6</number> Power to remove difficulties.-
<section><tid>529141</tid>
<number>1</number>If in the opinion of the  
Central Government any difficulty or doubt has arisen as to the 
interpretation of any provision of the award as now modified by the 
decision of the Appellate Tribunal in the manner referred to in 
section 3, it shall refer for decision the matter in respect of which 
such difficulty or doubt has arisen to a single member of the Labour 
Appellate Tribunal constituted under the Industrial Disputes 
 (Appellate Tribunal) Act, <year>1950</year> (48 of <year>1950</year>), or to such Industrial 
Tribunal constituted under the Industrial Disputes Act, <year>1947</year> (14 of  
  <year>1947</year>), as it may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify in 
this behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>1817336</tid>
<number>2</number>The tribunal to which such matter is referred shall, after 
giving the parties a reasonable opportunity of being heard, decide 
such matter and its decision shall be final and binding on all such 
parties.


</section>

</article>



 </act>