<act><tid>76600</tid>
<title>THE CENTRAL BOARDS OF REVENUE ACT, <year>1963</year></title>

ACT NO. 54 OF <year>1963</year>
[ 30th December, <year>1963</year>.]

An Act to provide for the constitution of separate Boards of 
Revenue for Direct Taxes and for Excise and Customs and to amend 
certain enactments for the purpose of conferring powers and imposing 
duties on the said Boards.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fourteenth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-





<article><tid>1782077</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>30414</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Central Boards of Revenue Act, <year>1963</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1885138</tid>
<number>2</number>it shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1671337</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>1066298</tid>
<number>a</number>Board" means the Central Board of Direct Taxes or the 
Central Board of Excise and Customs constituted under section 
 3;

</section>

<section><tid>1739591</tid>
<number>b</number>Central Board of Revenue" means the Central Board of 
Revenue constituted under the Central Board of Revenue Act, 
 <year>1924</year> (4 of <year>1924</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1457925</tid>
<number>c</number>" direct tax" means-

<subsection><tid>305835</tid>
<number>1</number>any duty leviable or tax chargeable under-

<subsubsection><tid>1925250</tid>
<number>i</number>the Estate Duty Act, <year>1953</year> (34 of <year>1953</year>);

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>131996</tid>
<number>ii</number>the Wealth- tax Act, <year>1957</year> (27 of <year>1957</year>);

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1191265</tid>
<number>iii</number>the Expenditure- tax Act, <year>1957</year> (29 of <year>1957</year>);

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>998061</tid>
<number>iv</number>the Gift- tax Act, <year>1958</year> (18 of <year>1958</year>);

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1039873</tid>
<number>v</number>the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> (43 of <year>1961</year>);

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1693968</tid>
<number>vi</number>the Super Profits Tax Act, <year>1963</year> (14 of <year>1963</year>) <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>;]

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>707765</tid>
<number>vii</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Interest- tax Act, <year>1974</year> (45 of <year>1974</year>) <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>;]

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>474054</tid>
<number>viii</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> the Hotel- Receipts Tax Act, <year>1980</year> (54 of <year>1980</year>) <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>;]

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>474054</tid>
<number>viii</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Hotel- Receipts Tax Act, <year>1980</year>; and"]

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>264115</tid>
<number>2</number>any other duty of tax which, having regard to its 
nature or incidence, may be declared by the Central

<subsubsection><tid>1913737</tid>
<number>ix</number><footcitenum>7</footcitenum> the Expenditure- tax Act, <year>1987</year>; and"]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>1266</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1st January, <year>1964</year>; vide Notification No. S. O. 3606, dated 
30- 12- <year>1963</year> Gazette of India, Extraordinary, Pt. 11, See. 3 (ii), p. 
897.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Omitted and ins. by Act 45 of <year>1974</year>, S. 30.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by s. 30. ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Omitted and ins. by Act 54 of <year>1980</year>, S. 37.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Ins. by s. 37. ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Omitted and ins. by Act 35 <year>1987</year>, S. 33 (w. e. f. 1. 11. <year>1987</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>7</number>Ins. by s. 33. ibid.






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Government, by notification in the Official Gazette, to be a 
direct tax.




</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>370655</tid>
<number> 3</number> Constitution of separate Central Boards for Direct Taxes and 
for Excise and Customs.
<section><tid>630436</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government shall, in place of  
the Central Board of Revenue, constitute two separate Boards of Revenue 
to be called the Central Board of Direct Taxes and the Central Board of 
Excise and Customs, and each such Board shall, subject to the control 
of the Central Government, exercise such powers and perform such 
duties, as may be entrusted to that Board by the Central Government or 
by or under any law.

</section>

<section><tid>96108</tid>
<number>2</number>Each Board shall consist of such number of persons <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> not 
exceeding seven] as the Central Government may think fit to appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1379804</tid>
<number> 4</number> Procedure of the Board.
<section><tid>1007817</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may make  
rules for the purpose of regulating the transaction of business by 
each Board and every order made or act done in accordance with such 
rules shall be deemed to be the order or act, as the case may be, of 
the Board.

</section>

<section><tid>1033340</tid>
<number>2</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as 
may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is in 
session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or in two successive sessions, and if, before the expiry 
of the session in which it is so laid or the session immediately 
following, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be, so however, that any modification or annulment 
shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done 
under that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>397332</tid>
<number> 5</number> Amendment of certain enactments.
<section><tid>613747</tid>
<number>1</number>In the Estate Duty Act,  
<year>1953</year>, (34 of <year>1953</year>) the Wealth- tax Act, <year>1957</year>, (27 of <year>1957</year>) the 
Expenditure- tax Act, <year>1957</year>, (29 of <year>1957</year>) the Gift- tax Act, <year>1958</year>, (18 of  
  <year>1958</year>) the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> (43 of <year>1961</year>) and the Super Profits Tax 
Act, <year>1963</year>, (14 of <year>1963</year>) for the words and figures" Central Board of 
' Revenue constituted under the Central Board of Revenue Act, <year>1924</year>" (4  
  of <year>1924</year>) or" Central Board of Revenue", wherever they occur, the 
words and figures" Central Board of Direct Taxes constituted under the 
Central Boards of Revenue Act, <year>1963</year>" shall be substituted.

</section>

<section><tid>1301493</tid>
<number>2</number>In the Central Excises and Salt Act, <year>1944</year>, (1 of <year>1944</year>) and 
the Customs Act, <year>1962</year>, (52 of <year>1962</year>) for the words and figures" Central 
Board of Revenue constituted under the Central Board of Revenue Act, 
 <year>1924</year> (4 of <year>1924</year>)" or" Central Board of Revenue" wherever they 
occur, the words and figures" Central Board of Excise and Customs 
constituted under the Central Boards of Revenue Act, <year>1963</year> shall be 
substituted.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1267</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 25 of <year>1978</year>, S. 27 (w. e. f 21. 6. <year>1978</year>).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>159222</tid>
<number>3</number>The functions entrusted to the Central Board of Revenue by 
or under any other enactment shall--

<subsection><tid>98094</tid>
<number>a</number>if such functions relate to matters connected with direct 
taxes, be discharged by the Central Board of Direct Taxes; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1380946</tid>
<number>b</number>if such functions relate to any other matter, unless they 
are entrusted by the Central Government to the Central Board 
of Direct Taxes, be discharged by the Central Board of Excise 
and Customs.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>427387</tid>
<number> 6</number> Transfer of certain proceedings.
<section><tid>1088057</tid>
<number>1</number>Every proceeding pending  
at the commencement of this Act, before the Central Board of Revenue 
shall--

<subsection><tid>707202</tid>
<number>a</number>if it is a proceeding relating to direct taxes, stand 
transferred to the Central Board of Direct Taxes; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>299498</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, stand transferred to the Central Board 
of Excise and Customs.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>256273</tid>
<number>2</number>If any question arises as to whether any proceeding stands 
transferred to the Central Board of Direct Taxes or to the Central 
Board of Excise and Customs, it shall be referred to the Central 
Government whose decision thereon shall be final.

</section>

<section><tid>1999470</tid>
<number>3</number>In any legal proceeding pending at the commencement of this 
Act to which the Central Board of Revenue is a party,--

<subsection><tid>1218873</tid>
<number>a</number>if it is a proceeding relating to direct taxes, the 
Central Board of Direct Taxes shall be deemed to be substituted for 
the Central Board of Revenue in such proceeding; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>811859</tid>
<number>b</number>if it is a proceeding relating to any other matter, the 
Central Board of Excise and Customs shall be deemed to be substituted 
for the Central Board of Revenue in such proceeding.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>268671</tid>
<number> 7</number> Power to remove difficulties.
<section><tid>37340</tid>
<number>1</number>If any difficulty arises  
in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions 
not inconsistent with the purposes of this Act, as appear to it to be 
necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty.

</section>

<section><tid>969685</tid>
<number>2</number>An order under sub- section (1) may be made so as to have 
retrospective effect from a date not earlier than the date of the 
commencement of this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1268</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1137579</tid>
<number> 8</number> Repeal and saving.
<section><tid>1603394</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Board of Revenue Act, <year>1924</year>,  
 (4 of <year>1924</year>) is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1412748</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing contained in sub- section (1) shall affect any appoint- 
ment, assessment, order (including quasi- judicial order) or rule made, 
or exemption, approval or recognition granted, or any notice, 
notification, direction or instruction issued, or any duty levied, or 
penalty or fine imposed, or confiscation adjudged, or any form 
prescribed, or any other thing done or action taken by the Central 
Board of Revenue under any law and any such appointment, assessment, 
order, rule, exemption, approval, recognition, notice, notification, 
direction, instruction, duty, penalty, fine, confiscation, form, thing 
or action shall be deemed to have been made, granted, issued, levied, 
imposed, adjudged, prescribed, done or taken by the Central Board of 
Direct Taxes, or as the case may be, by the Central Board of Excise 
and Customs and shall continue to be in force unless and until it is 
revised, withdrawn or superseded by the concerned Board.


</section>

</article>



 </act>