<act><title>The 
      PREVENTION OF MONEY-LAUNDERING (the MANNER OF FORWARDING A COPY OF THE 
      ORDER OF PROVISIONAL ATTACHMENT OF PROPERTY ALONG WITH THE MATERIAL, AND 
      COPY OF the reasons along with the MATERIAL IN RESPECT OF SURVEY, TO THE 
      ADJUDICATING AUTHORITY AND ITS PERIOD OF RETENTION) RULES, 
      20051</title> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be called the Prevention of 
      Money-laundering (the Manner of Forwarding a Copy of the Order of 
      Provisional Attachment of Property along with the Material, and Copy of 
      the Reasons along with the Material in respect of Survey, to the 
      Adjudicating Authority and its Period of Retention) Rules, 
      2005.
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date of 
      their publication in the Official Gazette. 
 



 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> “Act” means the Prevention of Money-laundering Act, 2002 (15 of 2003); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> “Adjudicating Authority” means an Adjudicating Authority appointed under sub-section (1) of section 6 of the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> “authorised officer' means an officer authorised by the Director under sub-section (1) of section 20 of the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> “designated officer” means an officer designated by the Adjudicating Authority for the purpose of sub-rule (1) of rule 4; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> “Form” means forms appended to these rules; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>f</number> “material” means any material in possession of the officer authorized under sub-section (1) of section 20 of the Act including,— 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> a report forwarded to a Magistrate under section 157 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) or a complaint filed before a Magistrate or a court by a person authorized to investigate the scheduled offence for taking cognizance of such scheduled offence; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> report forwarded to a Magistrate under section 173 of Code of Criminal Procedure 1973 (2 of 1974) or a complaint filed before a Magistrate or a court by a person authorized to investigate the scheduled offence for taking cognizance of such scheduled offence.] 
</subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> “order” means the order for retention of the property for the purposes of adjudication; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> “seized property” means any property seized under section 17 or section 18 of the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> “Schedule” means the Schedule to the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> “section” means a section of the Act. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> All other words and expressions used and not defined in these rules but defined in the Act shall have the meaning respectively assigned to them in the Act. 




 
 <subsection><number>i</number> a report forwarded to the Magistrate under section 173 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) in relation to an offence under paragraph 1 of Part A, or paragraph 1 or paragraph 2 or paragraph 3 or paragraph 4 or paragraph 5 of Part B, of the Schedule; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> a police report or a complaint filed for taking cognizance of an offence by the Special Court constituted under sub-section (1) of section 36 of the Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances Act, 1985 (61 of 1985) in relation to an offence under paragraph 2 of Part A of the Schedule;'. 
</subsection>
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Manner of forwarding the copy of the order of retention of seized property along with the material to the Adjudicating Authority. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The authorised officer shall prepare the index of the copy of the order of retention of the seized property and the material and sign each page of such index of the copy of the order and the material and shall also write a letter while forwarding such index of the copy of the order and the material to the Adjudicating Authority in a sealed envelope. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The authorised officer shall place an acknowledgement slip in Form I appended to these rules inside the envelope before sealing it. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The authorised officer shall indicate a reference number and date of despatch on the sealed envelope. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The sealed envelope shall be marked “Confidential” and “To be opened by the addressee only”, the complete address of the Adjudicating Authority including his name shall be mentioned on the sealed envelope, with official seal. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The authorised officer shall place the sealed envelope inside an outer envelope, along with an acknowledgement slip in Form II appended to these rules. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The outer envelope shall be sealed and complete address of the Adjudicating Authority shall be mentioned on the sealed outer envelope. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> The authorised officer shall maintain registers and other records such as acknowledgement slip register, dak register for the purposes of this rule and shall ensure that necessary entries are made in the register immediately as soon as the copy of the order and the material are forwarded to the Adjudicating Authority. 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>4</number> Manner of forwarding a copy of the reasons 
      along with the material in respect of survey under sub-section (2) of 
      section 16 of the Act, to the Adjudicating Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> The authority shall prepare an index of a 
      copy of the reasons and the material in respect of survey and sign each 
      page of such index, reasons and the material and shall also write a letter 
      while forwarding such index, reasons and the material to the Adjudicating 
      Authority in a sealed envelope.  
 </section><section><number>2</number> The authority shall place an acknowledgement 
      slip in Form II appended to these rules inside the envelope before sealing 
      it.  
 </section><section><number>3</number> The authority shall indicate a reference 
      number and date of despatch on the sealed envelope.  
 </section><section><number>4</number> The sealed envelope shall be marked 
      “Confidential” and “To be opened by the addressee only”, the complete 
      address of the Adjudicating Authority including his name, shall be 
      mentioned on the sealed envelope with official seal.  
 </section><section><number>5</number> The authority shall place the sealed 
      envelope inside an outer envelope along with an acknowledgement slip in 
      Form III appended to these rules.  
 </section><section><number>6</number> The outer envelope shall be sealed and the 
      complete address of the Adjudicating Authority shall be mentioned on the 
      sealed outer envelope.  
 </section><section><number>7</number> The authority shall maintain registers and 
      other records such as acknowledgement slip register, dak register for the 
      purposes of this rule and shall ensure that necessary entries are made in 
      the register immediately as soon as a copy of the reasons along with the 
      material in respect of survey are forwarded to the Adjudicating 
      Authority.  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>5</number> Acknowledgement of receipt of a copy of the 
      order of provisional attachment of property and the material and a copy of 
      the reasons and the material in respect of survey by the Adjudicating 
      Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> On receipt of 
      the outer sealed envelope along with Form II, the Adjudicating Authority 
      or in his absence, the designated officer  of the office of 
      Adjudicating Authority, shall forward Form II duly filled in, signed and 
      his name legibly written below his signature. The seal of the office of 
      the Adjudicating Authority shall be affixed before forwarding Form II to 
      the Director or the authorized officer or the authority, as the case may 
      be, as a token of receipt of the sealed envelope.  
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Adjudicating Authority shall, on opening 
      of the sealed envelope, forward Form I duly filled in, signed and his name 
      legibly written below his signature. The seal of the office of the 
      Adjudicating Authority shall be affixed before forwarding of Form I to the 
      Director or the authorized officer or the authority, as the case may be, 
      as a token of receipt of the copy of the order of provisional attachment 
      of property along with the material and a copy of the reasons along with 
      the material in respect of survey.  
 </section><section><number>3</number> Adjudicating Authority shall maintain 
      registers and other records such as acknowledgement slip register, dak 
      register and register showing details of receipt of a copy of the order of 
      the Director or the authorized officer or the authority, as the case may 
      be, along with the material for the purposes of this rule and shall ensure 
      that necessary entries are made in the registers immediately on receipt of 
      such order and the material and reasons and the material in respect of 
      survey.  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>6</number> Period of retention of a copy of the order of 
      provisional attachment of property and the material and a copy of the 
      reasons and the material in respect of survey by the Adjudicating 
      Authority.—The Adjudicating 
      Authority shall retain a copy of the order of provisional attachment of 
      property and the material and a copy of the reasons and the material for a 
      period of ten years, or, if before the expiry of the said period of ten 
      years,—  
 <section><number>i</number>    any 
      proceedings under section 8 of the Act have been commenced, until the 
      disposal of such proceedings; or  
 </section><section><number>ii</number>    where an 
      appeal has been preferred to the Appellate Tribunal under section 26 of 
      the Act, until the disposal of such appeal by the Appellate Tribunal; or  
 </section><section><number>iii</number>    where an 
      appeal has been filed in the High Court under section 42 of the Act, until 
      the disposal of such appeal by the High Court;  
 whichever is later.  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>7</number> Interpretation.—If any question arises relating to the 
      interpretation of these rules, the matter shall be referred to the Central 
      Government and the decision of the Central Government shall be 
      final.  
  
 
  </article><form>
 
 
 
 
 

 
 
 

The 
      PREVENTION OF MONEY-LAUNDERING (the MANNER OF FORWARDING A COPY OF THE 
      ORDER OF PROVISIONAL ATTACHMENT OF PROPERTY ALONG WITH THE MATERIAL, AND 
      COPY OF the reasons along with the MATERIAL IN RESPECT OF SURVEY, TO THE 
      ADJUDICATING AUTHORITY AND ITS PERIOD OF RETENTION) RULES, 
      2005
 

 
 

FORM I
 

[See sub-rule (2) of rule 
      3]
 

Acknowledgement Slip
 

 
 

Serial Number.....................  
 
 

Received a copy of the provisional 
      Attachment Order bearing number .................................. dated 
      ...................... along with the material containing ............. 
      pages from the Director/the authorised officer on 
      ........................[date] at .....................[time].  
 

 
 

Signature of the Adjudicating 
      Authority
 

Date........................
 

                                                                                                        
      .................................................................
 

                                                                                                       Name 
      of the Adjudicating Authority
 

                                                                                                        
      Office seal
 

To
 

...........................................................
 

[Director or the authorised 
      officer]
 

Address 
      ...............................................
 

...........................................................
 

...........................................................
 

 
 
 

 </form><form>
 

The PREVENTION OF 
MONEY-LAUNDERING (the MANNER OF FORWARDING A COPY OF THE ORDER OF PROVISIONAL 
ATTACHMENT OF PROPERTY ALONG WITH THE MATERIAL, AND COPY OF the reasons along 
with the MATERIAL IN RESPECT OF SURVEY, TO THE ADJUDICATING AUTHORITY AND ITS 
PERIOD OF RETENTION) RULES, 2005
 

 
 

FORM 
II
 

[See sub-rule (2) of rule 
4]
 

ACKNOWLEDGEMENT 
SLIP
 

Serial 
Number.....................
 

Received a copy of 
letter No. .................................. dated ...................... along 
with the reasons and the material containing ............. pages from the 
.................................................... [designation of 
the authority from whom received] on 
........................[date] at...............[time].
 

 
 

Signature of the Adjudicating Authority 
 

Date........................
 

                                                                                 
..................................................
 

                                                                                 
Name of the Adjudicating Authority
 

                                                                                 
Office seal
 

To
 

...........................................................
 

[Authority]
 

Address................................................
 

...........................................................
 

...........................................................
 

 </form><form>
 
 
 
 
 

 
 
 

The 
      PREVENTION OF MONEY-LAUNDERING (the MANNER OF FORWARDING A COPY OF THE 
      ORDER OF PROVISIONAL ATTACHMENT OF PROPERTY ALONG WITH THE MATERIAL, AND 
      COPY OF the reasons along with the MATERIAL IN RESPECT OF SURVEY, TO THE 
      ADJUDICATING AUTHORITY AND ITS PERIOD OF RETENTION) RULES, 
      2005
 

 
 

FORM III
 

[See sub-rule (5) of rule 3 
      and sub-rule (5) of rule 4]
 

ACKNOWLEDGEMENT SLIP
 

 
 

Serial 
      Number.....................
 

Received a sealed envelope 
      bearing No. .............................. dated....................... 
      from   ...................................................................[Director 
      or the authorised officer or the authority from whom received as the case 
      may be] on ........................[date] at............ [time]. 
 

 
 

 
 

Signature of the Adjudicating 
      Authority/ 
designated officer of the office 
      of          
       
                                                            Adjudicating 
      Authority.                        
      
 

....................................................
 

Name of the Adjudicating 
      Authority/ 
                                                                               designated 
      officer of the office of     
       
                                                                  Adjudicating 
      Authority.                   
      
 

Office seal 
 

To
 

.......................................................
 

[Director or the authorised 
officer 
 

or the authority as the case may 
      be] 
 

Address............................................ 
 

.......................................................
 

......................................................
 

 
 
 

 </form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 20(E), dated 7th January, 2010, for clause (f) (w.e.f. 7-1-2010). Clause (f), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>