<act><title>
The
Payment of Wages (Deductions for National Defence 
Fund and Defence Savings
Scheme) Rules, 19721</title> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number>
Short title, application and extent.—
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be called the
Payment of Wages (Deductions for National Defence Fund and Defence Savings
Scheme) Rules, 1972. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>
These rules shall apply to persons employed on railways, mines and oil-fields.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>
They extend to the whole of India.
 





  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number>
Definitions.—In these rules,—
 <section><number>a</number>
‘Act’ means the Payment of Wages Act, 1936 (4 of 1936); 
 </section><section><number>b</number>
‘section’ means a section of the Act. 
  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number>
Conditions for making deductions.—The conditions for making deductions in
pursuance of clause (ii) of sub-section (2) of section 7 from the wage of the
employed persons for contribution to the National Defence Fund or to any Defence
Savings Scheme approved by the State Government with the written authorisation
of the president or secretary of the registered trade union of which the
employed person is a member shall be as follows:— 
 


 <section><number>a</number>
the President or, in his absence, the secretary of such trade union shall
forward,— 


 <subsection><number>i</number> in
duplicate to the employer, a copy of the list of the employed persons who are
members of the trade union indicating therein the amount or extent of deductions
which are to be made from the wages of each employed person and also, where the
deductions are to continue for more than one wage-period, the total period
during which such deductions are to be made and a copy of the resolution adopted
at a meeting of such trade union authorising such deductions; and 


 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> a
copy of the said list and resolution to the person who acts as an Inspector for
the purposes of the Act; 


 </subsection></section><section><number>b</number>
the employer shall display in a conspicuous place of the establishment
one of the two copies of the said list and resolution received from the
president or secretary as the case may be, of the trade union, for at least a
period of three consecutive days immediately preceding the day on which the
deductions are to be made from the wages of the employed person; and 


 </section><section><number>c</number>
if an employed person objects in writing to deductions being made from
his wages upto the amount or extent of deductions indicated in the list
displayed by the employer, no deduction shall be made from his wages except in
accordance with the written authorisation of such employed person. 



  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>