<act><tid>773809</tid>
<title>THE RAILWAY COMPANIES (EMERGENCY PROVISIONS) ACT, <year>1951</year></title>

ACT NO. 51 OF <year>1951</year>
[ 14th September, <year>1951</year>.]

An Act to make provision for the proper management and administration 
of railway companies in certain special cases.





<article><tid>369911</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and application.
<section><tid>190168</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Railway Companies (Emergency Provisions) Act, <year>1951</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>375460</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu 
and Kashmir.

</section>

<section><tid>362187</tid>
<number>3</number>It applies to every railway company in respect of which a 
notified order has been issued under section 3.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1702368</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>293100</tid>
<number>a</number>" Companies Act" means the Indian Companies Act, <year>1913</year> (7  
  of <year>1913</year>.);

</section>

<section><tid>1432783</tid>
<number>b</number>" directors" means the directors appointed under section 
3;

</section>

<section><tid>978720</tid>
<number>c</number>" notified order" means an order notified in the Official 
Gazette;

</section>

<section><tid>434507</tid>
<number>d</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>772866</tid>
<number>e</number>" railway company" means any company registered under the 
Companies Act or any law repealed thereby for the 
purpose of making and working or making or working a 
railway, whether alone or in conjunction with other 
purposes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>491467</tid>
<number> 3</number> Power of Central Government to apply Act to any railway 
company and to appoint directors thereof.
<section><tid>405337</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the Central  
Government is of opinion that a situation has arisen in the affairs of 
a railway company which--

<subsection><tid>1758582</tid>
<number>a</number>has prejudicially affected the convenience of persons 
using the railway administered by the railway company, 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1960235</tid>
<number>b</number>has caused serious dislocation in any trade or industry 
using the railway, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>263148</tid>
<number>c</number>has caused serious unemployment amongst a section of the 
community,
or when, in the opinion of the Central Government, it is necessary in 
the national interest the Central Government may, by notified

The Act comes into force in Pondicherry on 1. 10. <year>1963</year> vide Reg. 7 of 
<year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch. I.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>128</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

order, apply the provisions of this Act to the railway company and 
appoint as many persons as it thinks fit to be directors of the 
railway company for the purpose of taking over its management and 
administration.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1946416</tid>
<number>2</number>The power to appoint directors under this section includes 
the power to appoint any individual, firm or company to be the 
managing agent of the railway company on such terms and conditions as 
to the Central Government may seem fit.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>17995</tid>
<number> 4</number> Effect of notified order appointing directors or managing 
agents. On the issue of a notified order under section 3,--
<section><tid>1047172</tid>
<number>a</number>all persons holding office as directors of the railway 
company immediately before the issue of the notified 
order shall be deemed to have vacated their offices as 
such;

</section>

<section><tid>563719</tid>
<number>b</number>any contract of management between the railway company 
and any managing agent thereof holding office as such 
immediately before the issue of the notified order 
shall be deemed to have terminated;

</section>

<section><tid>1475774</tid>
<number>c</number>the managing agent, if any, appointed under this Act 
shall be deemed to have been duly appointed in 
pursuance of the Companies Act and the memorandum and 
articles of association of the railway company, and the 
provisions of the Companies Act and of the memorandum 
and articles shall, subject to the other provisions 
contained in this Act, apply accordingly, but no such 
managing agent shall be removed from office except with 
the previous consent of the Central Government;

</section>

<section><tid>1233413</tid>
<number>d</number>the directors shall take such steps as may be necessary 
to take into their custody or under their control all 
the property, effects and actionable claims to which 
the railway company is, or appears to be, entitled, and 
all the property and effects of the railway company 
shall be deemed to be in the custody of the directors 
as from the date of the notified order;

</section>

<section><tid>914565</tid>
<number>e</number>the directors shall be for all purposes the directors of 
the railway company duly constituted under the 
Companies Act, and shall alone be entitled to exercise 
all the powers of the directors of the railway company, 
whether such powers are derived from the Companies Act 
or from the memorandum or articles of association of 
the railway company or from any other source.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1803397</tid>
<number> 5</number> Powers and duties of directors.
<section><tid>1478948</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the control of  
the Central Government, the directors shall take such steps as may be 
necessary for the purpose of efficiently managing the business of the 
railway company and, in

<pagefootnote><pagenum>129</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

particular, the directors shall have power, notwithstanding anything 
contained in the Companies Act or in the memorandum or articles of 
association of the railway company,--


<subsection><tid>1964757</tid>
<number>a</number>to choose one of their number to be the chairman, and to 
delegate to him or to any one or more of the directors 
all or any of their powers;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>291870</tid>
<number>b</number>with the previous approval of the Central Government and 
subject to such conditions as that Government may think 
fit to impose, to raise funds in such manner and offer 
such security therefor as they think fit;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1641957</tid>
<number>c</number>to carry out such repairs as may be necessary in respect 
of any machinery, rolling- stock, buildings, works or 
other property in their custody;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>551713</tid>
<number>d</number>to do all acts necessary for making, maintaining, 
altering or repairing and using the railway of the 
railway company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1256377</tid>
<number>e</number>to employ such persons as may be necessary for enabling 
them to efficiently discharge their duties, and define 
the conditions of service of such employees.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>524216</tid>
<number>2</number>The directors may, with the previous sanction of the Central 
Government, cancel or vary, either unconditionally or subject to such 
conditions as they think fit to impose, any contract or agreement 
entered into between the railway company and any other person at any 
time before the issue of the notified order under section 3, if such 
contract or agreement had been entered into in bad faith and is 
detrimental to the interests of the railway company.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1708906</tid>
<number> 6</number> Statement of affairs to be made to directors.
<section><tid>344775</tid>
<number>1</number>On the issue  
of a notified order under section 3, there shall be made out and 
submitted to the directors a statement as to the affairs of the 
railway company, verified by affidavit and containing the following 
particulars, namely:--

<subsection><tid>835415</tid>
<number>a</number>the assets of the railway company, stating separately 
the cash balance in hand and at the bank, if any;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>828895</tid>
<number>b</number>the debts and liabilities;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1666922</tid>
<number>c</number>the names, residences and occupations of the creditors, 
stating separately the amount of secured debts and 
unsecured debts and, in the case of secured debts, the 
particulars of the securities, their value and the 
dates when they were given;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1316621</tid>
<number>d</number>the debts due to the railway company and the names, 
residences and occupations of the persons from whom 
they are due and the amount likely to be realised 
therefrom;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>130</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1827016</tid>
<number>e</number>such other particulars as may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1582706</tid>
<number>2</number>The statement shall be submitted by one or more of the 
persons who was or were holding office as a director or as directors 
of the railway company immediately before the issue of the notified 
order under section 3 or by the secretary, manager or other chief 
officer of the railway company who was holding office as such before 
the issue of the notified order as the directors may require in each 
case, and the statement shall be submitted within such time as may be 
so required.

</section>

<section><tid>1212586</tid>
<number>3</number>If any person, without any reasonable excuse, knowingly and 
wilfully makes default in complying with the requirements of this 
section, he shall be punishable with imprisonment which may extend to 
three months, or with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, or 
with both.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1798974</tid>
<number>7</number>Statements by beneficial owners of shares of railway company. 
Any person who has any interest in any share of the railway company 
which stands in the name of another person in the register of 
shareholders of the railway company shall, within such period as may 
be specified by the Central Government by notified order, make a 
declaration in such form as may be prescribed (which shall be  
  countersigned by the person in whose name the share is registered) to 
the railway company declaring his interest in the share, and 
notwithstanding anything contained in any other law or in any contract 
to the contrary, a person who fails to make a declaration as aforesaid 
in respect of any share shall be deemed to have no right or title 
whatsoever in or to that share:
Provided that nothing in this section shall affect the right of 
any person who has an interest in any such share to establish in a 
Court his right thereto if the person in whose name the share is 
registered refuses to sign that declaration as required by this 
section.



</article>



<article><tid>602892</tid>
<number> 8</number> Power of directors to institute proceedings against past 
directors, etc., for damages.
<section><tid>283990</tid>
<number>1</number>The directors may, if they are  
satisfied that it is necessary in the interests of the railway company 
or in the public interest so to do, institute in the name of the 
railway company such proceedings as they think fit for the recovery of 
damages for any fraud, misfeasance or other misconduct in connection 
with the management of the affairs of the railway company committed by 
any person before the issue of the notified order under section 3 or 
for the recovery of any property of the railway company which has been 
misapplied or wrongfully retained by any person.

</section>

<section><tid>685915</tid>
<number>2</number>No director shall be personally liable for any costs or 
expenses incurred in connection with any proceedings instituted by 
virtue of this section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1637731</tid>
<number>9</number>Penalties. If any person wilfully destroys or fails to deliver 
to the directors when required any books of account, registers or any 
other documents

<pagefootnote><pagenum>131</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

in his custody relating to the business of the railway company or 
retains any property of the railway company, he shall be punishable 
with imprisonment which may extend to six months, or with fine which 
may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both.



</article>



<article><tid>1665267</tid>
<number> 10</number> Filling up of vacancies among directors.
<section><tid>1239816</tid>
<number>1</number>Casual vacancies  
occurring in the body of directors, whether caused by death, 
resignation or otherwise, shall be filled by nomination by the Central 
Government.

</section>

<section><tid>606680</tid>
<number>2</number>No act of the directors shall be called in question on the 
ground merely of the existence of any vacancy among the directors or 
any defect in the appointment of any of them.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>599080</tid>
<number> 11</number> No right to compensation for termination of contract of 
managing agent or any other contract.
<section><tid>1833670</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything  
contained in the Companies Act or in any other law for the time being 
in force, no managing agent shall be entitled to any compensation for 
the premature termination under this Act of any contract of management 
entered into by him with the railway company, and no person shall be 
entitled to compensation in respect of the cancellation or variation 
under this Act of any other contract or agreement.

</section>

<section><tid>636171</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing contained in sub- section (1) shall affect the right 
of any such managing agent or person to recover from the railway 
company moneys recoverable otherwise than by way of such compensation.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>948477</tid>
<number> 12</number> Cancellation of appointment of directors.
<section><tid>1012651</tid>
<number>1</number>If at any time  
it appears to the Central Government that the purpose of the notified 
order appointing the directors has been fulfilled or that for any 
other reason it is unnecessary that the notified order should remain 
in force, the Central Government may, by notified order, cancel the 
appointment of directors made under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1502911</tid>
<number>2</number>On the cancellation of any such appointment as is referred to 
in sub- section (1), the Central Government may--

<subsection><tid>535127</tid>
<number>a</number>direct that all the property, effects and actionable 
claims of the railway company shall revest in the 
persons in whom they were vested before the issue of 
the notified order under section 3; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1775</tid>
<number>b</number>reconstitute by fresh appointment a new body of persons 
to take charge of the management and administration of 
the whole affairs of the railway company, whether as 
directors or managers or in any other capacity:
Provided that no such direction or fresh appointment shall be 
made except in pursuance of a resolution passed by the shareholders of 
the railway company at a meeting called for the purpose by the 
directors appointed under section 3.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>595330</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government may, at any time before the issue of 
the notified order under sub- section (1), take such action as may be

<pagefootnote><pagenum>132</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

necessary under clause (b) of sub- section (2) for the purpose of 
making any fresh appointments.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>55831</tid>
<number> 13</number> Application of the Companies Act.
<section><tid>651639</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding  
anything contained in the Companies Act or in the memorandum or 
articles of association of the railway company, but subject to the 
other provisions contained in this Act,--

<subsection><tid>53957</tid>
<number>a</number>it shall not be lawful for the shareholders of the 
railway company or any other person to nominate or 
appoint any person to be a director of the railway 
company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1494056</tid>
<number>b</number>no resolution passed at any meeting of the shareholders 
of the railway company shall be given effect to unless 
approved by the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>915384</tid>
<number>c</number>no proceeding for the winding- up of the railway company 
or for the appointment of a receiver in respect thereof 
shall lie in any Court, unless by or with the sanction 
of the Central Government.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1617589</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions contained in sub- section (1) and to 
the other provisions contained in this Act and subject to such 
exceptions, restrictions and limitations as the Central Government may 
by notified order specify, the Companies Act shall continue to apply 
to the railway company in the same manner as it applied thereto before 
the issue of the notified order under section 3.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1671853</tid>
<number>14</number>Effect of Act on other laws. The provisions of this Act and 
of any notified order made thereunder shall have effect 
notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith in any other law for 
the time being in force or in the memorandum or articles of 
association of the railway company or in any other instrument having 
effect by virtue of any law other than this Act, but save as aforesaid 
the provisions of this Act shall be in addition to, and not in 
derogation of, any other law for the time being applicable to the 
railway company.


</article>



<article><tid>828725</tid>
<number>15</number>Directors to be public servants. Every director appointed 
under section 3 shall be deemed to be a public servant within the 
meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code. (45 of <year>1860</year>)


</article>



<article><tid>99313</tid>
<number>16</number>Delegation of powers. The Central Government may, by notified 
order, direct that all or any of the powers exercisable by it under 
this Act, except the powers given to it under section 3 to apply the 
provisions of this Act to any railway company or the powers given to 
it under section 12 or section 18, may be exercised by any State 
Government, and where any powers are so delegated, they shall be 
exercised subject to such directions as the Central Government may 
issue from time to time.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>133</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>728602</tid>
<number> 17</number> Protection of action taken under Act.
<section><tid>268041</tid>
<number>1</number>No suit,  
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any director 
in respect of anything which is in good faith done or intended to be 
done in pursuance of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>430726</tid>
<number>2</number>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the 
Central Government or any State Government or any director for any 
damage caused or likely to be caused by anything which is in good 
faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>180870</tid>
<number> 18</number> Power of Central Government to acquire railway of railway 
company.
<section><tid>1040711</tid>
<number>1</number>Where under any instrument, having effect by virtue of  
any law other than this Act or by virtue of an agreement arrived at 
between the parties, provision is made for the purchase by a person or 
local authority or the State Government of a railway which is the 
property of a railway company on payment of the value thereof 
calculated in the manner and subject to the conditions specified in 
the instrument, the Central Government shall also have the same right 
to purchase the railway on the same terms and subject to the same 
conditions as the person, local authority or the State Government has 
under the instrument.

</section>

<section><tid>1315890</tid>
<number>2</number>If in respect of any railway the Central Government exercises 
its right of purchase under this section, any person, local authority 
or State Government, in whom or in which a similar right is vested 
under the instrument, shall be deemed to have become disentitled to 
exercise the same.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1160212</tid>
<number> 19</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>882740</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may by  
notified order, make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>92657</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, any rules made under sub- section (1) may provide for- 
-

<subsection><tid>1388325</tid>
<number>a</number>the manner in which or the conditions subject to which 
the directors or managing agents of a railway company 
may exercise their powers under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1341295</tid>
<number>b</number>the additional particulars which a statement under 
section 6 should contain;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1079673</tid>
<number>c</number>the form in which a declaration under section 7 may be 
made;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1498158</tid>
<number>d</number>the appointment of a Railway Local Advisory Committee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1681817</tid>
<number>e</number>the manner in which books of account shall be maintained 
by the directors and audited;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>200170</tid>
<number>f</number>the submission of specified or periodical returns and 
reports by the directors to any specified authority in 
connection with the affairs of the railway company;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>134</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>479307</tid>
<number>g</number>the conduct of business of the directors appointed by 
notified order and for the recruitment and employment 
of officers and staff.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>971818</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as 
may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is 
in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised 
in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the year session or 
the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should 
not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, 
that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to 
the validity of anything previously done under that rule.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>857215</tid>
<number> 20</number> Repeal of Ordinance 2 of <year>1951</year>. The Railway Companies 
 (Emergency Provisions) Ordinance, <year>1951</year> (2 of <year>1951</year>.) is hereby 
repealed:
Provided that the repeal shall not affect--

<section><tid>1363483</tid>
<number>a</number>the previous operation of the said Ordinance, or

</section>

<section><tid>323647</tid>
<number>b</number>any penalty, forfeiture or punishment incurred in 
respect of any offence committed against the said 
Ordinance, or

</section>

<section><tid>622537</tid>
<number>c</number>any investigation, legal proceeding or remedy in respect 
of any such penalty, forfeiture or punishment, and any 
such investigation, legal proceeding or remedy may be 
instituted, continued or enforced, and any such 
penalty, forfeiture, or punishment may be imposed as if 
this Act had not been passed:
Provided further that, subject to the preceding proviso, anything 
done or any action taken (including any notified order issued,  
  appointment made or direction given under the said Ordinance) shall be 
deemed to have been done or taken under the corresponding provision of 
this Act and shall continue in force accordingly, unless and until 
superseded by anything done or any action taken under this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>135</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 4 of <year>1986</year>, s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 15. 5. <year>1986</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>