<act><tid>774283</tid>
<title>THE CENSUS ACT, <year>1948</year></title>

ACT NO. 37 OF <year>1948</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 3rd September, <year>1948</year>.]

An Act to provide for certain matters in connection with the taking of 
census.





<article><tid>1653376</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.-
<section><tid>1165065</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Census  
Act, <year>1948</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1890042</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1566345</tid>
<number> 2</number> <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1762543</tid>
<number>a</number>" premises" means any land, building or part of a 
building and includes a hut, shed or other structure or any part 
thereof;

</section>

<section><tid>1359912</tid>
<number>b</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>372583</tid>
<number>c</number>" vehicle" means any vehicle used or capable of being 
used for the purpose of road transport, whether propelled by 
mechanical power or otherwise.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>930316</tid>
<number>2A</number>Rule of construction respecting enactments not extending to 
Jammu and Kashmir.- Any reference in this Act to the Indian Penal Code 
 (45 of <year>1860</year>), the Indian Evidence Act, <year>1872</year> (1 of <year>1872</year>), or the Code 
of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>), shall, in relation to the 
State of Jammu and Kashmir, be construed as a reference to the 
corresponding enactment in force in that State.]


</article>



<article><tid>84306</tid>
<number>3</number>Central Government to take census.- The Central Government may, 
by notification in the Official Gazette, declare its intention of 
taking a census in the whole or any part of the territories to which 
this Act extends, whenever it may consider it necessary or desirable 
so to do, and thereupon the census shall be taken.


</article>



<article><tid>1797362</tid>
<number> 4</number> Appointment of census staff.-
<section><tid>1520927</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may  
appoint a Census Commissioner to supervise the taking of the census 
throughout the area in which the census is intended to be taken, and 
 <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Directors of Census Operations] to supervise the taking of the 
census within the several States.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The Act has been extended to:--

Goa, Daman and Diu by Reg. 11 of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch. with 
modifications to the whole of the Union territory of Lakshadweep, 
vide Reg. 8 of <year>1965</year>, s 3 and Sch. (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1967</year>).

the State of Sikim vide Notification No. 3465, dated 21- 9- <year>1976</year> 
 (w. e. f., 13- 9- <year>1976</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The words" the Provinces and Acceding States" were rep. by the A. 
O. <year>1950</year>. 
3. Subs., ibid. for the former sub- section. 
4. The words" except the State of Jammu and Kashmir" omitted by Act 
22 of <year>1959</year>, s. 2. 
5. Subs. by Act 11 of <year>1994</year>, s. 2, for s. 2. 
6. Subs. by Act 56 of <year>1974</year>, s. 3 and Second Sch., for 
" Superintendents of Census Operations" (w. e. f. 20- 12- <year>1974</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>980132</tid>
<number>2</number>The State Government may appoint persons as census- officers 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> with such designations as that Government may deem necessary] to 
take, or aid in, or supervise the taking of, the census within any 
specified local area and such persons, when so appointed, shall be 
bound to serve accordingly.

</section>

<section><tid>798132</tid>
<number>3</number>A declaration in writing, signed by any authority authorised 
by the State Government in this behalf, that any person has been duly 
appointed a census- officer for any local area shall be conclusive 
proof of such appointment.

</section>

<section><tid>317147</tid>
<number>4</number>The State Government may delegate to such authority as it 
thinks fit the power of appointing census- officers conferred by sub- 
section (2).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>291893</tid>
<number>4A</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Staff of every local authority to be made available for 
taking census.- Every local authority in a State shall, when so 
directed by a written order by the Central Government or by an 
authority appointed by that Government in this behalf, make available 
to any Director of Census Operations such staff as may be necessary 
for the performance of any duties in connection with the taking of 
census.]


</article>



<article><tid>1610217</tid>
<number>5</number>Status of census authorities as public servants.- The Census 
Commissioner, all <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Directors of Census Operations] and all census- 
officers shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of 
the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>901810</tid>
<number> 6</number> Discharge of duties of census- officers in certain cases.-
<section><tid>762320</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Where the District Magistrate, or such authority as the State 
Government may appoint in this behalf, by a written order so directs--

<subsection><tid>1254458</tid>
<number>a</number>every officer in command of any body of men belonging to 
the naval, military or air forces, or of any vessel of 
war, of India,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1862683</tid>
<number>b</number>every person (except a pilot or harbourmaster) having 
charge or control of a vessel,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>248964</tid>
<number>c</number>every person in charge of a lunatic asylum, hospital, 
work- house, prison, reformatory or lock- up or of any 
public, charitable, religious or educational 
institution,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>90111</tid>
<number>d</number>every keeper, secretary or manager of any sarai, hotel, 
boarding- house, lodging- house, emigration depot or 
club,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>130769</tid>
<number>e</number>every manager or officer of a railway or any commercial 
or industrial establishment, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1628834</tid>
<number>f</number>every occupant of immovable property wherein at the time 
of the taking of the census persons are living,
shall perform such of the duties of a census- officer in relation to 
the persons who at the time of the taking of the census are under his 
command or charge, or are inmates of his house, or are present on or 
in such immovable property or are employed under him as may be 
specified in the order.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 11 of <year>1994</year>, s. 3. 
2. Ins. by s. 4, ibid. 
3. Subs. by Act 56 of <year>1974</year>, s. 3 and Second Sch., for 
" Superintendent of Census Operations" (w. e. f. 20- 12- <year>1974</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1538895</tid>
<number>2</number>All the provisions of this Act relating to census- officers 
shall apply, so far as may be, to all persons while performing such 
duties under this section, and any person refusing or neglecting to 
perform any duty which under this section he is directed to perform 
shall be deemed to have committed an offence under section 187 of the 
Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1420029</tid>
<number> 7</number> Power to call upon certain persons to give assistance.- The 
District Magistrate, or such authority as the State Government may 
appoint in this behalf for any local area, may, by written order which 
shall have effect throughout the extent of his district or of such 
local area, as the case may be, call upon--
<section><tid>1233637</tid>
<number>a</number>all owners and occupiers of land, tenure- holders, and 
farmers and assignees of land revenue, or their agents,

</section>

<section><tid>1943185</tid>
<number>b</number>all members of the district, municipal, panchayat and 
other local authorities and officers and servants of 
such authorities, and

</section>

<section><tid>962429</tid>
<number>c</number>all officers and members of staff of any factory, firm 
or establishment,
to give such assistance as shall be specified in the order towards the 
taking of a census of the persons who are, at the time of the taking 
of the census, on the lands of such owners, occupiers, tenure- holders, 
farmers and assignees, or in the premises of factories, firms and 
other establishments, or within the areas for which such local 
authorities are established, as the case may be, and the persons to 
whom an order under this section is directed shall be bound to obey it 
and shall, while acting in pursuance of such order, be deemed to be 
public servants within the meaning of the Indian Penal Code (45 of  
  <year>1860</year>).




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1840781</tid>
<number> 7A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Requisitioning premises, vehicles, etc., for taking of a 
census.-
<section><tid>1262963</tid>
<number>1</number>If it appears to the Central Government that, in  
connection with taking of a census,--

<subsection><tid>1536145</tid>
<number>a</number>any premises are needed or are likely to be needed, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>975287</tid>
<number>b</number>any vehicle, vessel or animal is needed or is likely to 
be needed,
that Government may by order in writing requisition such premises, or 
vehicle, vessel or animal, as the case may be, and make such further 
orders as may appear to it to be necessary or expedient in connection 
with the requisitioning.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1624391</tid>
<number>2</number>The requisition shall be effected by an order in writing 
addressed to the person deemed by the Central Government to be the 
owner or person in possession of the property, and such order, shall 
be served in the prescribed manner on the person to whom it is 
addressed.

</section>

<section><tid>1304565</tid>
<number>3</number>Whenever any property is requisitioned under sub- section (1), 
the period of such requisition shall not extend beyond the period for 
which such property is required for any of the purposes mentioned in 
that sub- section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1145070</tid>
<number> 7B</number> Payment of compensation.-
<section><tid>1758447</tid>
<number>1</number>Whenever in pursuance of section  
 7A the Central Government requisitions any premises, there shall be 
paid to the persons interested compensation the amount of which shall 
be determined by taking into consideration the following, namely:--



</section>

</article>



 </act>