<act><title>

The
Public provident fund act, 1968</title> 

 

 

 <article><number>1</number>
Short title and extent.—
<section><number>1</number> This Act
may be called the Public Provident Fund Act, 1968.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
It extends to the whole of India.
  
</section></article> 

 

 

 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In this Act, unless the
context otherwise requires,—
 <section><number>a</number>
“Fund” means the Public Provident Fund established under the Scheme;
 </section><section><number>b</number>
“minor” means a person who is not deemed to have attained majority
under the Indian Majority Act, 1875 (9 of 1875);

 </section><section><number>c</number>
“Scheme” means the Public Provident Fund Scheme framed under sub-
section (1) of section 3;
 </section><section><number>d</number>
“subscriber” means an individual who makes subscription to the Fund
under section 4 and where such subscription is made by an individual on behalf
of a minor, of whom he is the guardian, such minor;
 </section><section><number>e</number>
“year” means the financial year.
</section></article> 

 

 

 <article><number>3</number>
Public Provident Fund Scheme.—
<section><number>1</number>
The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, frame a
scheme to  be called the Public Provident Fund Scheme for the establishment
of a provident fund for the general public and there shall be
     established, as soon as may be after the framing of the
Scheme, a Fund in accordance with the provisions of this Act and the Scheme.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Scheme may provide for all or any of
the matters specified in the Schedule.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
The Scheme shall have effect notwithstanding anything contained in any law for
the time being in force other than this Act or in any instrument having effect
by virtue of any law other than this Act.
 </section><section><number>4</number>
The Central Government may, from time to time, by notification in the Official
Gazette, add to, amend or vary the Scheme.
</section></article> 

 

 

 <article><number>4</number>
Subscriptions to Fund.— Any
individual may, on his own behalf or on behalf of a minor, of whom he is the
guardian, subscribe to the Fund in such manner and subject to such maximum and
minimum limits as may be specified in the Scheme.
</article> 

 

 

 <article><number>5</number>
Interest.—All subscription made
under section 4 shall bear interest at such rate as may be notified by the
Central Government in the Official Gazette, from time to time, and the interest
shall be calculated in such manner as may be specified in the Scheme.
  


</article> 

 

 

 <article><number>6</number>
Withdrawals.—
<section><number>1</number> A subscriber shall
be entitled to make withdrawals from the amount standing to his credit in the
Fund (including any interest accrued thereon) to such extent and subject to such
terms and conditions as may be specified in the Scheme:
 Provided
that such withdrawals shall be allowed only after the expiry of a period of five
years from the end of the year in which he makes the initial subscription to the
Fund.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), a subscriber shall be
entitled to withdraw the entire balance standing to his credit in the Fund after
the expiry of a period of fifteen years from the end of the year in which he
makes the initial subscription to the Fund.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
Subject to the provisions of sub-sections (1) and (2), an individual who has
made subscriptions to the Fund on behalf of a minor, of whom he is the guardian,
shall be entitled to withdraw any amount from the Fund only for the use of the
minor.
  


</section></article> 

 

 

 <article><number>7</number>
Grant of loans.—A subscriber may be
granted loans out of the amount standing to his credit in the Fund on such terms
and conditions as may be specified in the Scheme and where the subscriber is a
minor, such loans shall be granted to his guardian only for the use of the
minor.
  


</article> 

 

 

 <article><number>8</number>
Payment on death of subscriber.—
<section><number>1</number>
If a subscriber dies and there is in force at the time of his death a nomination
in favour of any person, all amounts standing to his credit in the Fund shall be
payable to the nominee.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Where the nominee is a minor, the amounts referred to in sub-section (1) shall
be payable to any guardian of the property of the minor appointed by a competent
court, or where no such guardian has been so appointed, to either parent of the
minor, or where neither parent is alive, to any other guardian of the minor.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
Where there is no nomination in force at the time of the death of the
subscriber, the amounts referred to in sub-section (1) shall be payable to his
legal heirs.
  


</section></article> 

 

 

 <article><number>9</number>
Protection against attachment.—The
amount standing to the credit of any subscriber in the Fund shall not be liable
to attachment under any decree or order of any court in respect of any debt or
liability incurred by the subscriber.
  


</article> 

 

 

 <article><number>10</number>
Protection of action taken in good faith.—No
suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any person for
anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or
the Scheme.
</article> 

 

 

 <article><number>11</number>
Power to remove difficulties.—
<section><number>1</number> If
any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act or the
Scheme, the Central Government may, by order published in the Official Gazette,
make such provisions not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as appear
to it to be necessary or expedient for the removal of the difficulty:
 Provided
that no such order shall be made after the expiration of three years from the
commencement of this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Every order made under sub-section (1) shall be laid as soon as may be after it
is made before each House of Parliament.
</section></article> 

 

 

 <article><number>12</number>
Scheme to be laid before Parliament.—The
Scheme shall be laid, as soon as may be, after it is framed before each House of
Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be
comprised in one session or in two successive sessions, and if, before the
expiry of the session in which it is so laid or the session immediately
following, both Houses agree in making any modification in any provision of the
Scheme or both Houses agree that any provision in the Scheme should not be made,
the provision of the Scheme shall thereafter have effect only in such modified
form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so, however, that any such
modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything
previously done under that provision.
 

</article><form>
 



The
Public provident fund act, 1968
 



 



 



THE SCHEDULE
 


 [See section 3 (2)]
 

Matters
for which provision may be made in the Scheme— 
 

(1)   The manner in which subscriptions to the Fund may be made and the maximum
and minimum limits of such subscriptions.
 

(2)
The manner in which interest on subscriptions to the Fund may be
calculated.
 

(3)
The documents to be issued to subscribers as evidence of the
subscriptions made by them to the Fund.
 

(4)
The extent to which and the terms and conditions under which withdrawals
may be made by subscribers from the amount standing to their credit in the Fund.
 

(5)
The authority or authorities by or through whom subscriptions to the Fund
may be collected or withdrawals therefrom may be made.
 

(6) The terms and conditions under which loans may be granted to subscribers
out of the amounts standing to their credit in the Fund and the authority or
authorities by whom such loans may be granted.
 

(7)
The accounts to be maintained with respect to subscriptions to the Fund,
and withdrawals and final payment made and loans granted therefrom and the
authority or authorities by whom such accounts shall be maintained.
 

(8)
The nomination of any person to receive the amount standing to the credit
of a subscriber in the Fund in the event of his death and the cancellation or
change of such nomination.
 

(9)
The issue of duplicate of any document issued as evidence of any
subscription to the Fund in the event of damage, loss or destruction of the
original and the fee on the payment of which such duplicate may be issued.
 

(10) Any other matter which is to be provided for in the Scheme or which may
be necessary or proper for the purpose of implementing the Scheme.
 

  


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>