<act><tid>783396</tid>
<title>THE OIL AND NATURAL GAS COMMISSION ACT, <year>1959</year></title>

ACT NO. 43 OF <year>1959</year>
[ 18th September, <year>1959</year>.]

An Act to provide for the establishment of a Commission for the 
development of petroleum resources and the production and sale of 
petroleum and petroleum products produced by it and for matters 
connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Tenth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I 
PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1819549</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title extent and commencement.
<section><tid>136006</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called  
the Oil and Natural Gas Commission Act, <year>1959</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1655217</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>.

</section>

<section><tid>1946262</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date 2 as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Definitions.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1736463</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>1427843</tid>
<number>a</number>" Chairman" means the chairman of the Commission

</section>

<section><tid>1365800</tid>
<number>b</number>" Commission" means the Oil and Natural Gas Commission 
established under section 3;

</section>

<section><tid>1091929</tid>
<number>c</number>" existing Organisation" means the body set up in pursuance 
of the resolution of the Government of India, No. 22 29 55-ONG, dated 
the 14th August, <year>1956</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>1087719</tid>
<number>d</number>" Fund" means the fund referred to in section 19

</section>

<section><tid>864913</tid>
<number>e</number>" member" means a member of the Commission and includes the 
chairman;

<subsection><tid>538116</tid>
<number>F</number>" petroleum" has the same meaning as in the Petroleum Act, 
<year>1934</year>, and includes natural gas; (30 of <year>1934</year>).

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>814871</tid>
<number>g</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>110</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words," except the State of Jammu and Kashmir" omitted by Act 38 
of <year>1962</year> s. 2.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number> 15th October, <year>1959</year>, see Notification No. S. O. 2302, dated 14th 
October, <year>1959</year>, Gazette of India, Extraordinary, <year>1959</year>, Pt. II, Sec. 
3 (ii), p. 515.

This Act came into force in Pondicherry on the lst October, <year>1963</year>, vide 
Reg. 7 of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch. I.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

CHAP

THE OIL AND NATURAL GAS COMMISSION

CHAPTER II 
THE OIL AND NATURAL GAS COMMISSION




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1230328</tid>
<number> 3</number> 
<section><tid>604923</tid>
<number>1</number>Establishment and incorporation of the Commission. With  
effect from such date' as the Central Government may, by notification 
in the Official Gazette, appoint in this behalf, there shall be 
established a Commission to be called the Oil and Natural Gas 
Commission.

</section>

<section><tid>1135596</tid>
<number>2</number>The Commission shall be a body corporate having perpetual 
succession and a common seal with power to acquire, hold and dispose 
of property and to contract and shall by the said name sue and be 
sued.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>206322</tid>
<number>4</number>Composition of the Commission. The Commission shall consist 
of a chairman and not less than two, and not more than eight, other 
members appointed by the Central Government and the members may be 
required to render whole- time or part- time service, as the Central 
Government may direct;
Provided that one of the members shall be a whole- time Finance 
Member in charge of the financial matters relating to the Commission:

Provided further that the Central Government may, if it thinks 
fit, appoint one of the members as vice- chairman of the Commission.



</article>



<article><tid>578883</tid>
<number> 5</number> 
<section><tid>982659</tid>
<number>1</number>Term of office and conditions of service of members. The  
term of office and conditions of service of the chairman and other 
members shall be such as may be prescribed:
[ Provided that the Central Government may-


<subsection><tid>944087</tid>
<number>a</number>terminate the appointment of any whole- time member, who 
is not a servant of the Government, after giving him notice 
for a period of not less than three months or in lieu thereof 
on payment of an amount equal to his salary and allowances, 
if any, for a period of three months;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>42419</tid>
<number>b</number>terminate the appointment of any part- time member who 
is not a servant of the Government after giving him notice 
for such period as may be prescribed; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>199465</tid>
<number>c</number>terminate at any time the appointment of any member who 
is servant of the Government.]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1952848</tid>
<number>2</number>Any member may resign his office by giving notice in writing 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> for such period as may be prescribed,] to the Central Government,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>111</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 15th October, <year>1959</year>, see Notification No. S. O. 2303, dated 14th 
October., <year>1959</year>. Gazette of India, Extraordinary, 1059, Pt. 11, Sec. 
3 (ii), p. 515.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 17 of <year>1981</year>, s. 2, for the proviso. 
3 Ins. by s. 2, ibid.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

and on such resignation being notified in the Official Gazette by that 
Government, shall be deemed to have vacated his office.


</section>

<section><tid>1387509</tid>
<number>3</number>A casual vacancy created by the resignation of a member 
under sub- section (2) or for any other reason may be filled by fresh 
appointment,



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1603674</tid>
<number>6</number>Disqualifications for beining appointed, or for continuing, 
as member of the Commission. A person shall be disqualified for being 
appointed or for continuing as a member, if he has, directly or 
indirectly, any interest in a subsisting contract made with, or in any 
work being done for, the Commission.


</article>



<article><tid>258212</tid>
<number>7</number>Temporary absence of member. If any member is by infirmity 
or otherwise rendered temporarily incapable of carrying out his duties 
or is absent on leave or otherwise in circumstances not involving the 
vacation of his appointment the Central Government may appoint another 
person to act in his place during his absence.


</article>



<article><tid>1317818</tid>
<number>8</number>Vacancies, etc., not to invalidate acts and proceeding of the 
Commission. No act or proceeding of the Commission shall be invalid by 
reason only of the existence of any vacancy among its members or any 
defect in, the constitution thereof.


</article>



<article><tid>1372075</tid>
<number> 9</number> 
<section><tid>976509</tid>
<number>1</number>Meetings of the Commission. The Commission shall meet at  
such times and places and shall, subject to the provisions of sub- 
sections (2) and (3), observe such rules of procedure in regard to the 
transaction of business at its meetings (including the quorum at  
  meetings) as may be provided by regulations made under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>24466</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chairman or, in his absence, the vice- chairman, if any, 
or in the absence of the chairman and of the vice- chairman if any, any 
member chosen by the members from among themselves, shall preside at a 
meeting of the Commission.

</section>

<section><tid>1259361</tid>
<number>3</number>All questions at a meeting of the Commission shall be 
decided by a majority of the votes of the members present and voting, 
and in the case of an equality of votes, the chairman or, in his 
absence, the person presiding, shall have a second or casting vote:
Provided that the person presiding may in his discretion, reserve 
any matter for the consideration of the Central Government.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>406404</tid>
<number> 10</number> 
<section><tid>1620087</tid>
<number>1</number>Temporary association of persons with the commission for  
particular purpose. The Commission may associate with itself in such 
manner and for such purposes, as may be provided by regulations made 
under this
<pagefootnote><pagenum>112</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


Act, any person whose assistance or advice it may desire in 
performing any of its functions under this Act.


</section>

<section><tid>1397749</tid>
<number>2</number>A person associated with it by the Commission under sub- 
section (1) for any purpose shall have a right to take part in the 
discussions of the Commission relevant to that purpose, but shall not 
have a right to, vote at a meeting of the Commission, and shall not be 
a member for any other purpose.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>11</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Authentication of orders and other instruments of the Commission.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>314374</tid>
<number>11</number>Authentication of orders and other instruments of the 
Commission. All orders and decisions of the Commission shall be 
authenticated by the signature of the chairman or any other member 
authorised by the Commission in this behalf, and all other instruments 
issued by the Commission shall be authenticated by the signature of an 
officer of the Commission authorised in like manner in this 
behalf.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>12</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Staff of the Commission.

</article>



<article><tid>1449906</tid>
<number> 12</number> 
<section><tid>79596</tid>
<number>1</number>Staff of the Commission. Subject to the provisions of  
section 15, the Commission may, for the purpose of enabling it 
efficiently to perform its functions or exercise its powers under this 
Act, appoint such number of employees as it may consider necessary

</section>

<section><tid>584180</tid>
<number>2</number>The functions and the terms and conditions of service of 
such employees shall be such as may be provided by regulations made 
under this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>13</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Transfer of service of existing employees to the Commission.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1882227</tid>
<number> 13</number> 
<section><tid>622226</tid>
<number>1</number>Transfer of service of existing employees to the  
Commission. Subject to the provisions of this Act, every person 
employed by the existing Organisation immediately before the date of 
establishment of the Commission shall, on and from such date, become 
an employee of the Commission with such designation as the Commission 
may determine and shall hold his office or service therein by the same 
tenure, at the same remuneration and upon the same terms and 
conditions as he would have held the same on such date if the 
Commission had not been established and shall continue to do so unless 
and until his employment in the Commission is terminated or until such 
tenure, remuneration and terms and conditions are duly altered by the 
Commission
Provided that-


<subsection><tid>1196510</tid>
<number>a</number>the tenure, remuneration and terms and conditions of 
service of any such person shall not be altered to his 
disadvantage without the previous approval of the Central 
Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1885490</tid>
<number>b</number>any service rendered in the existing Organisation by 
any such person shall be deemed to be service under the 
Commission; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1997891</tid>
<number>c</number>all persons employed by the Commission on the date of 
its establishment, who, immediately before such date, hold, 
in a permanent or quasi- permanent capacity, posts in 
connection

<pagefootnote><pagenum>113</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

with the affairs of the Union or of any State, but not posts 
in the existing Organisation, shall be treated as Government 
servants on foreign service with the Commission.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>258157</tid>
<number>2</number>The Commission may employ any person who has become its 
employee under sub- section (1), in such capacity as it thinks fit, and 
every such employee shall be bound to discharge his functions 
accordingly.
CHAP

POWERS AND FUNCTIONS OF THE COMMISSION

CHAPTER III 
POWERS AND FUNCTIONS OF THE COMMISSION


<pagefootnote><pagenum>14</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Functions of the Commission.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>647489</tid>
<number> 14</number> 
<section><tid>66036</tid>
<number>1</number>Functions of the Commission. Subject, to the provisions  
of this Act, the functions of the Commission shall generally be to 
plan, promote, organise and implement programmes for the development 
of petroleum resources and the production and sale of petroleum and 
petroleum products produced by it and to perform such functions as the 
Central Government may, from time to time, assign to the Commission.

</section>

<section><tid>531960</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing provision, the Commission may take such steps as it thinks 
fit-

<subsection><tid>525710</tid>
<number>a</number>for the carrying out of geological and geophysical 
surveys for exploration of petroleum;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1269904</tid>
<number>d</number>to undertake, assist or encourage and promote the 
production to prove and estimate the reserves of petroleum;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>78716</tid>
<number>c</number>to undertake encourage and promote such other activities as 
may lead to the establishment of such reserves;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1269904</tid>
<number>d</number>to undertake, assist or encourage and promote the 
production of petroleum from such reserves and its refining;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>802669</tid>
<number>e</number>for the transport and disposal of natural gas and 
refinery gases produced by the Commission;
Provided that no industry, which will use any of these gases 
as a raw materials shall be set up by the Commission without 
the previous approval of the Central Government;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>959300</tid>
<number>f</number>to undertake, encourage and, promote geological, chemical 
and other scientific investigations whether in or outside the 
laboratory;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1938094</tid>
<number>g</number>to undertake, assist or encourage the collection, 
maintenance and publication of statistics, bulletins and 
monographs;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>114</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>939885</tid>
<number>gg</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> to promoto and from companies in compliance with the 
requirements of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> for any of the purposes 
aforesaid;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1278832</tid>
<number>h</number>to perform any other function which is supplemental, 
incidental or consequential to any of the functions aforesaid 
or which may be prescribed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>15</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Powers of the Commission.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>743981</tid>
<number> 15</number> Powers of the Commission. The Commission may exercise all 
such powers as may be necessary or expedient for the purpose of 
carrying out its functions under this Act:
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Provided that before exercising its powers in respect of the 
following matters, it shall obtain the previous approval of the 
Central Government, namely:-

<section><tid>1850101</tid>
<number>a</number>the creation of any post, the salary or honorarium of 
which would either be more than such amount as may be pres- 
cribed, or where no such amount has been prescribed, more 
than rupees two thousand seven hundred and fifty or be on a 
scale the maximum of which exceeds such amount as may be 
prescribed or where no such amount has been prescribed, 
exceeds rupees two thousand seven hundred and fifty, and the 
appointment of'[ any person other than the person referred to 
in clause (aa)] to any such post;

</section>

<section><tid>52192</tid>
<number>aa</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> the employment, whether by fresh appointment, re- 
employment, extension of service or otherwise, of any person 
who has attained the age of fifty- eight years to a post, 
where the pay (including pension and pensionary equivalent of  
  retirement benefits) of the post exceeds 2, 500 rupees per 
mensem or where the minimum of the pay scale of the post, 
proposed to be given to such person is 2, 500 rupees or more 
per mensem;]

</section>

<section><tid>227614</tid>
<number>b</number>the implementation of any scheme or proposal which will 
involve a capital expenditure exceeding such amount as may be 
prescribed, or where no such amount has been prescribed, 
exceeding fifty lakhs of rupees;

</section>

<section><tid>1367264</tid>
<number>c</number>the disposal of any property, right or privilege the 
original or book value of which exceeds such amount as may be

<pagefootnote><pagenum>115</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 38 of <year>1962</year>, s. 3. 
2 Sub- section (3) omitted by Act 23 of <year>1977</year>, s. 2. 
3 Subs. by s. 3. ibid., for the proviso. 
4 Subs. by Act 17 of <year>1981</year>, s. 3, for" any person". 
5 Ins. by s. 3, ibid.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

prescribed, or where no such amount has been prescribed, 
exceeds ten lakhs of rupees.]

CHAP

FINANCE, ACCOUNTS, AUDIT AND REPORTS

CHAPTER IV 
FINANCE, ACCOUNTS, AUDIT AND REPORTS


<pagefootnote><pagenum>16</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Capital of the Commission.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>440685</tid>
<number> 16</number> 
<section><tid>396323</tid>
<number>1</number>Capital of the Commission. All non- recurring expenditure  
incurred by the Central Government for or in connection with the 
existing Organisation up to the date of establishment of the 
Commission and declared to be capital expenditure by that Government, 
shall be treated as capital expenditure provided by that Government to 
the commission, and shall be brought into the books of the Commission.

</section>

<section><tid>1581511</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may, after due appropriation made by 
Parliament in this behalf, provide any further capital that may be re- 
quired by the- Commission for the carrying on of the business of the 
Commission or for any purpose connected therewith on such terms and 
conditions as that Government may determine,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>17</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Vesting of property in the Commission.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1671411</tid>
<number>17</number>Vesting of property in the Commission. All property acquired 
and all works constructed or under construction by or on behalf of the 
Central Government for the purposes of the existing Organisation up to 
the date of establishment, of the Commission shall, on such date, vest 
in the Commission and all income derived and all expenditure incurred 
in this behalf shall be brought into the books of the Commission.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>18</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Commission to have rights liabilitions and obligations of the 
CentralGovernment in certain cases.

</article>



<article><tid>1273011</tid>
<number>18</number>Commission to have rights liabilitions and obligations of the 
Central Government in certain cases. All rights, liabilities arid, 
obligations of the Central Government which, whether arising out of 
any contract or otherwise, were acquired or incurred by it in 
connection with the existing Organisation or for any of the purposes 
referred to in this Act, before the date of establishment of the 
Commission shall be deemed to have been acquired or incurred by the 
Commission and shall be the rights, liabilities and obligations res- 
pectively of the Commission.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>19</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Fund of the Commission.

</article>



<article><tid>1862</tid>
<number> 19</number> 
<section><tid>1333587</tid>
<number>1</number>Fund of the Commission. The Commission shall have its own  
Fund and all receipts of the Commission, whether from grants made by 
the Central Government or otherwise, shall be carried thereto and all 
payments by the Commission made therefrom.

</section>

<section><tid>248901</tid>
<number>2</number>The Commission may expend such sums as it thinks fit for 
performing its functions under this Act and such sums shall be treated 
as expenditure payable out of the Fund.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>116</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1629466</tid>
<number>3</number>All monies of the Commission shall be deposited in the 
Reserve Bank of India or with the agents of that Bank <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or in a 
corresponding new bank constituted under the Banking Companies 
 (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings) Act, <year>1970</year> or in such other 
bank as may be prescribed, or] in a Government Treasury, or be 
invested in such securities as may be approved by the Central 
Government.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>20</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Browing of money.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>814056</tid>
<number>20</number>Browing of money. The Commission may, with the previous 
approval of the Central Government borrow money in the open market or 
otherwise for the purposes of carrying out its functions under this 
Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>21</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Budget.

</article>



<article><tid>802691</tid>
<number> 21</number> 
<section><tid>815745</tid>
<number>1</number>Budget. (a) The Commission shall, by such date in each  
year as may be prescribed, submit to the Central Government for 
approval a budget in the prescribed form for the next financial year, 
showing the estimated receipts and expenditure, and the sums which 
would be required from the Central Government, during that financial 
year.

<subsection><tid>214698</tid>
<number>b</number>If any sum granted by the Central Government remains wholly 
or partly unspent in any financial year, the unspent sum may be 
carried forward to the next financial year and taken into account in 
determining the sum to be provided by the Central Government for that 
year.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>328082</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (3), no sum shall 
be expended by or on behalf of the Commission unless the 
expenditure is covered by provision in the budget approved by the 
Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1291258</tid>
<number>3</number>The Commission may sanction any re- appropriation from one 
head of expenditure to another or from a provision made for one scheme 
to that for another:
Provided that, except with the previous approval of the Central 
Government-


<subsection><tid>1594332</tid>
<number>a</number>no re- appropriation from the head" loan" to another 
head of expenditure and vice versa in the budget shall be 
sanctioned by the Commission;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>549439</tid>
<number>b</number>no re- appropriation which has the effect of augmenting 
the provision under any head of expenditure as approved by 
the Central Government by more than twenty per cent <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> shall 
be made.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>22</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Annual reports, accounts and audit.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>595223</tid>
<number> 22</number> 
<section><tid>1515179</tid>
<number>1</number>Annual reports, accounts and audit. The Commission shall  
maintain proper accounts and other relevant records and prepare an 
annual statement of accounts, including profit and loss account and 
balance sheet in accordance with such general

<pagefootnote><pagenum>117</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 23 of <year>1977</year>, s. 4, for certain words. 
2 The words" or seven and a half lakhs of rupees, whichever is less, 
Omitted by Act 38 of <year>1962</year>, s. 5.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

directions as may be issued, and in such form as may be prescribed, by 
the Central Government in consultation with the Comptroller and 
Auditor- General of India.


</section>

<section><tid>1180868</tid>
<number>2</number>The accounts of the Commission shall be audited annually by 
the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any expenditure in- 
curred by him in connection with such audit shall be payable by the 
Commission to the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.

</section>

<section><tid>373133</tid>
<number>3</number>The Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any person 
appointed by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the 
Commission shall have the same rights and privileges and authority in 
connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor- General has 
in connection with the audit of Government accounts, and in 
particular, shall have the right to demand the production of books, 
accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and to 
inspect any of the offices of the Commission.

</section>

<section><tid>593014</tid>
<number>4</number>The accounts of the Commission as certified by the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General of India or any other person appointed 
by him in this behalf, together with the audit report thereon, shall 
be forwarded annually to the Central Government and that Government 
shall cause the same to be laid before each House of Parliament.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>23</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Returns and reports.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1030954</tid>
<number> 23</number> 
<section><tid>26156</tid>
<number>1</number>Returns and reports. The Commission shall furnish to the  
Central Government at such time and in such form and in such manner, 
as may be prescribed or as the Central Government may direct, such 
returns and statements and such particulars in regard to any proposed 
or existing programme for the development of petroleum resources and 
the production and sale of petroleum and petroleum products produced 
by the Commission as the Central Government may, from time to time, 
require.

</section>

<section><tid>1178593</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the provisions of sub- section (1), the 
Commission shall as soon as possible after the commencement of each 
financial year, submit to the Central Government a report in such form 
and before such date as may be prescribed, giving a true and full 
account of its activities, policy and programme during the previous 
financial year and an account of the activities likely to be 
undertaken during the current financial year.

</section>

<section><tid>1358018</tid>
<number>3</number>A copy of the report received under sub- section (2) shall be 
laid before each House of Parliament.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>118</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER V 
MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>602899</tid>
<number>24</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Compulsory acquisition of land for the Commission, Any land 
- required by the Commission for carrying out its functions under this 
Act shall be deemed to be needed for a public purpose and such land 
shall be acquired for the Commission under the provisions of the Land 
Acquisition Act, <year>1894</year>.]


</article>



<article><tid>57394</tid>
<number>25</number>Power of entry. Any employee of the Commission, generally or 
specially authorised by it, may at all reasonable times enter upon any 
land or premises and there do such things as may be reasonably 
necessary for the purpose of lawfully carrying out any of its works or 
of making any survey, examination or investigation preliminary or 
incidental to the exercise of powers or the performance of functions 
by the Commission under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>815273</tid>
<number>26</number>Deligation of powers and duties. The Commission may, by 
general or special order in writing, direct that all or any of the 
powers or duties which may be exercised or discharged by it shall, in 
such circumstances and under such conditions, if any, as may be 
specified in the order, be exercised or discharged also by any person 
specified in this behalf in the order.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>27</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Members and employees of the Commission to be public servants.

</article>



<article><tid>546722</tid>
<number>27</number>Members and employees of the Commission to be public 
servants. All members and employees of the Commission, shall, when 
acting or purporting to act in pursuance of the provisions of this 
Act, or of any rule or regulation made thereunder, be deemed to be 
public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal 
Code.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>28</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Protection of action taken under Act.

</article>



<article><tid>916300</tid>
<number>28</number>Protection of action taken under Act. No suit, prosecution or 
other legal proceeding shall lie against the Commission or any member 
or employee of the Commission for anything which is in good faith done 
or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or of any rule or 
regulation made thereunder.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>29</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Liability of Commission to pay taxes and fees.

</article>



<article><tid>443815</tid>
<number>29</number>Liability of Commission to pay taxes and fees. The Commission 
shall be deemed to be a company within the meaning of any enactment 
for the time being in force providing for the levy of any tax or fee 
by the Central Government or a State Government and shall be liable to 
pay such tax or fee accordingly.


</article>



<article><tid>624890</tid>
<number> 30</number> 
<section><tid>824840</tid>
<number>1</number>Dissolution of the Commission. The Central Government  
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that the 
Commission shall be dissolved from such date as may be specified in 
the notification and thereupon the Commission shall be deemed to be 
dissolved accordingly.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>119</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 19 of <year>1964</year>, s, 2, for s, 24.





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>736945</tid>
<number>2</number>On and from the said date-

<subsection><tid>1492423</tid>
<number>a</number>all assets, liabilities and obligations acquired or 
incurred by the Commission for purposes of the Commission or 
for any of the purposes referred to in this Act shall vest in 
the Central Government, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1370573</tid>
<number>b</number>all members shall vacate their offices as members of 
the Commission.

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1894290</tid>
<number>30A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Commission to comply with direction. The Commission shall 
be bound by such directions, including directions regarding 
reservation of posts for the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled 
Tribes, as the Central Government may, from time to time, for reasons 
to be recorded in writing, give to the Commission in respect of its 
affairs.]


</article>



<article><tid>1231117</tid>
<number> 31</number> 
<section><tid>260696</tid>
<number>1</number>Power of Central Government to make rules. The Central  
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to 
give effect to the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>615175</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing provision, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1589870</tid>
<number>a</number>the term of office of, and the manner of filling casual 
vacancies among, the members, and their conditions of service 
including the salaries, remuneration and allowances to be 
paid to them and the travelling and daily allowances to be 
drawn by them when they are on tour;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1958704</tid>
<number>b</number>the disqualifications for membership of the Commission 
and the procedure to be followed in removing a member who is 
or becomes subject to any disqualification;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1881829</tid>
<number>c</number>the procedure to be followed in the discharge of 
functions by members;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1926522</tid>
<number>d</number>the date by which, and the form in which, the budget 
shall be submitted in each year under sub- section (1) of 
section 21

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1884877</tid>
<number>e</number>the procedure to be followed for placing the Commission 
in possession of funds;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>849512</tid>
<number>f</number>the procedure to be followed and the conditions to be 
observed in borrowing moneys or in granting loans;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>120</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 23 of <year>1977</year>, s, 5.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1614201</tid>
<number>g</number>the conditions subject to which, and the mode in which, 
contracts may be entered into by or on behalf of the Commis- 
sion;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1089986</tid>
<number>gl</number>the amount of salary, or honorarium, or the 
maximum of the scale of pay of any post, the creation of 
which requires the previous approval of the Central 
Government under section 15;
 (g 2) the amount of capital expenditure in respect of any 
scheme or proposal the implementation of which would require 
the previous approval of the Central Government under section 
15, or the original or book value of any property, right or 
privilege the disposal of which would require such, approval;

 (g 3) any bank in which the monies of the Commission may be 
deposited as provided in section 19;]


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1742911</tid>
<number>h</number>the form and manner in which the accounts of the 
Commission shall be maintained under sub- section (1) of 
section 22;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>624645</tid>
<number>i</number>the form and manner in which returns, reports or 
statements shall be submitted under section 23;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1046279</tid>
<number>j</number>any other matter which has to be, or may be, 
prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>792804</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as 
may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is in 
session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> in two or more successive sessions, and if before the 
expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid], both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only] in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however that any such 
modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity 
of anything previously done under that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1891296</tid>
<number> 32</number> 
<section><tid>412942</tid>
<number>1</number>Power of Commission to make regulations. The Commission  
may, with the previous approval of the Central Government, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, make regulations, not 
inconsistent with this Act and the rules made thereunder, for enabling 
it to discharge its functions under this Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>120A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 23 of <year>1977</year>, s. 6. 
2 Subs. by s. 6, ibid., for certain words.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1794457</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing provision, such regulations may provide for all or any of 
the following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>527954</tid>
<number>a</number>the terms and conditions of appointment and service and 
the scales of pay of- employees of the Commission, including 
payment of travelling and daily allowances in respect of 
journeys undertaken by such employees for the purposes of 
this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1142063</tid>
<number>b</number>the time and place of meetings of the Commission, the 
procedure to be followed in regard to the transaction of 
business at such meetings and the quorum necessary for the 
transaction of business at a meeting;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>861233</tid>
<number>c</number>the maintenance of minutes of meetings of the 
Commission and the transmission of copies thereof to the 
Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1072435</tid>
<number>d</number>the persons by whom, and the manner in which payments, 
deposits and investments may be made on behalf of the Com- 
mission;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1112526</tid>
<number>e</number>the custody of monies required for the current 
expenditure of the Commission and the investment of monies 
not so required;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>484221</tid>
<number>f</number>the maintenance of accounts.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>731031</tid>
<number>2A</number>The power to make regulations conferred by this section with 
respect to terms and conditions of appointment and service and the 
scales of pay of employees of the Commission shall include power to 
give retrospective effect from a date not earlier than the 
commencement of the Act, to such regulations or any of them but no 
retrospective effect shall be given to any such regulation so as to 
prejudicially affect the interests of any person to whom such 
regulations may be applicable.]

</section>

<section><tid>528667</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, amend, vary or rescind any regulation which it has approved; 
and thereupon the regulation shall have effect accordingly but without 
prejudice to the exercise of the powers of the Commission under sub- 
section (1).

</section>

<section><tid>796771</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Every regulation made under this section and every 
notifications issued under sub- section (3) of this section shall be 
laid, as soon as may be after it is made or issued, before each House 
of Parliament, while it

<pagefootnote><pagenum>120B</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 17 of <year>1981</year>, s. 4.







</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be 
comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and 
if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session 
or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the regulation or notification or both Houses agree 
that the regulation or notification should not be made or issued, the 
regulation or notification shall thereafter have effect only in such 
modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, 
that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to 
the validity of anything previously done under that regulation or by 
virtue of that notification.]


<pagefootnote><pagenum>999999</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>