<act><tid>784050</tid>
<title>THE WHITE PHOSPHORUS MATCHES PROHIBITION ACT, <year>1913</year></title>

ACT NO. 5 OF <year>1913</year>
[ 7th March, <year>1913</year>.]

An Act to prohibit the importation, manufacture and sale of matches 
made with white phosphorus.

WHEREAS, it is expedient to prohibit the importation, manufacture 
and sale of matches made with white phosphorus; It is hereby enacted 
as follows:--





<article><tid>9439</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1193373</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the White Phosphorus Matches Prohibition Act, <year>1913</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>295286</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India except <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the territories 
which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in 
Part B States]; and

</section>

<section><tid>1965605</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on the first day of July, <year>1913</year>, with 
the exception of section 6, which shall come into force on the first 
day of July, <year>1914</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1440778</tid>
<number>2</number>Definition. In this Act," white phosphorus" means the 
substance commonly known as white or yellow phosphorus.


</article>



<article><tid>698192</tid>
<number>3</number>[ Prohibition of Importation by addition to section 18, Act 8 
of <year>1878</year>.] Rep. by the Repealing Act, <year>1938</year> (1 of <year>1938</year>), s. 2 and Sch.


</article>



<article><tid>871983</tid>
<number> 4</number> Prohibition of use of white phosphorus in manufacture of 
matches.
<section><tid>651752</tid>
<number>1</number>No person shall use white phosphorus in the manufacture  
of matches.

</section>

<section><tid>290500</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person who uses, or permits the use by any person under 
his control of, white phosphorus in the manufacture of matches, shall 
be punishable with fine which may extend to two hundred rupees.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1394477</tid>
<number> 5</number> Power of Inspector of Factories to take samples of material 
used in manufacture.
<section><tid>621334</tid>
<number>1</number>Every person who manufactures matches shall  
allow an Inspector of Factories appointed under the Indian Factories 
Act, <year>1911</year> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>, (12 of <year>1911</year>.) at any time to take for analysis 
sufficient samples of any material in use or mixed for use, in such 
manufacture:
Provided that any such person may, at the time the sample is 
taken, and on providing the necessary appliances, require the 
Inspector to divide the sample so taken into two parts, and to mark, 
seal and deliver to him one part.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" Part B 
States". 
2. See now the Factories Act, <year>1948</year> (63 of <year>1948</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>498093</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person who refuses to permit any such Inspector of 
Factories as aforesaid to take a sample, in accordance with the 
provisions of sub- section (1), shall be punishable with fine which may 
extend to two hundred rupees.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1475997</tid>
<number> 6</number> Prohibition of sale.
<section><tid>1791367</tid>
<number>1</number>No person shall sell, or offer or  
expose for sale, or have in his possession for the purposes of sale, 
any matches made with white phosphorus.

</section>

<section><tid>1706386</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person who contravenes the provisions of sub- section (1) 
may, on complaint to a Presidency Magistrate, Sub- divisional 
Magistrate or Magistrate of the first class, be ordered to forfeit any 
such matches in his possession, and any matches so forfeited shall be 
destoryed or otherswise dealt with as the Magistrate may direct.

</section>

</article>



 </act>