<act><title>


THE PETROLEUM Concession RULES, 19491</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title, extent 
and commencement.—
<section><number>i</number> 
These rules may be called the Petroleum Concession Rules, 1949.
 <subsection>
<number>ia</number> They extend to the 
whole of India, except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>ii</number> They shall come into 
force on the fifth day of January, 1950.
 
 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>2</number> Saving of Act of 
1934.—Nothing in 
these rules shall affect the provisions of Petroleum Act, 
1934.</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,—
 
           
“petroleum,” wherever the word occurs, includes also natural gas;
 
           
“railway” and “railway administration” have the meaning respectively assigned ‘ 
to them in the Indian Railways Act, 1890;1
 
           
“geophysical 
survey” means the search by instruments of the presence of suitable underground 
geological structures and includes the sinking of bore‑holes for detonating 
explosives necessary for the purpose, but not the drilling of deep bore‑holes or 
the sinking of trial shafts, trenches, or other kinds of large and deep 
excavations connected with prospecting as defined hereinafter;
 
           
“prospecting” means the operations necessary to ascertain whether any geological 
structures favourable for accumulation of oil are present and are capable of 
yielding petroleum or natural gas in commercially workable quantities. It 
includes the drilling of deep test wells in such number as would be necessary to 
verify the geological structure of the oil and gas‑bearing formations and their 
productive extent;
 
           
“exploring licence” means a licence conferring the sole right on the 
licensee to search, by geological or geophysical surveys, for oil bearing 
formations and their underground structure and includes trenching, pitting and 
drilling of bore‑holes for geological information, but not test drilling for 
petroleum;
 
           
“prospecting licence” means a licence conferring the sole right on the 
licensee to conduct all or any of the operations included under prospecting;
 
           
“mining lease” means a lease conferring the sole right on the lessee to 
mine, bore, dig, drill, search for, win, work and extract in any quantity, 
petroleum or natural gas and carry away the crude or refined products as 
provided in these rules.
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Grant of certificate 
of approval for petroleum.—A 
certificate of approval for petroleum shall be granted only by the Central 
Government and shall be valid for the whole of the State.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Person to whom 
certificate may be granted.—A 
certificate of approval for petroleum may be granted to any person, who, in the 
opinion of the Central Government, is financially and technically competent to 
carry on the operations of searching for, drilling and producing petroleum and 
natural gas in a proper workmanlike manner according to the standards of modern 
oilfield practice.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Application for 
certificate of approval for petroleum.—An 
application for the grant or renewal of a certificate of approval for petroleum 
shall be submitted to the Central Government. An application for the grant of 
such a certificate shall contain the following particulars:—
 <section>
    <number>a</number> (i)  
If the applicant is an individual, his name, nationality, profession and 
residence; and
 <subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  if the applicant is a company, syndicate, partnership or private 
firm, its name, nature and place of business, and, if the place of business is 
outside India, the name and residence of a member or duly authorized agent 
resident in India;
 </subsection></section><section>
        
<number>b</number>  a statement showing the previous experience of the applicant in the 
search for and development of petroleum and such other particulars as may be 
necessary to satisfy the State Government of the applicant’s financial and 
technical competence to hold the certificate.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Period of 
certificate of approval for petroleum.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A certificate of approval for petroleum shall have effect from the date on which 
it is granted and shall expire at midnight on the 31st December next following:—
 
Provided that a 
certificate issued in the last quarter of the year shall be valid until 31st 
December of the year next following.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Only one person shall 
be named in the certificate and the fee payable for the grant thereof shall be 
Rs. 500 (rupees five hundred).
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Renewal of 
certificate of approval for petroleum.—A 
certificate of approval for petroleum may be renewed on payment of a fee of Rs. 
250 if the application for renewal is received within three months of the date 
of expiry of the certificate. After the expiry of three months no renewal shall 
be granted but an application for a fresh certificate may be made.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Notification of 
grant of certificate of approval for petroleum.—The 
name and address of the person to whom a Certificate of Approval for petroleum 
has been granted or renewed shall be published by the Central Government in the 
Official Gazette.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Holder of a 
concession need not renew his certificate.—The 
expiry of a certificate of approval for petroleum shall not affect the validity 
of a licence or lease already granted to the holder of such a certificate, or 
the right of the holder of an exploring licence to apply for or obtain a 
prospecting licence or mining lease or the right of the holder of a prospecting 
licence to apply for or obtain a mining lease.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Eligibility.—An 
exploring licence may be granted by the Central Government to any person holding 
a certificate of approval for petroleum.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Application for 
exploring licence.—An 
application for an exploring licence shall be made to the State Government 
concerned and shall contain the following particulars:—
 <section>
    <number>a</number> (i)  
If the applicant is an individual, his name, profession, residence and 
nationality;
 <subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  If the applicant is a company, syndicate, partnership or private 
firm, its name, nature and place of business and if the place of business is 
outside India, the name and residence of a duty authorized agent resident in 
India;
 </subsection></section><section>
        
<number>b</number>  the number and date of the notification of granting or renewing the 
certificate of approval for petroleum to the applicant;
 </section><section>
        
<number>c</number>  whether the applicant proposes to employ any commercial firm for 
purposes of geophysical survey and, if so, the name of the firm, its place of 
registration or incorporation and its experience in the carrying out of 
geophysical surveys;
 </section><section>
        
<number>d</number>  a description, illustrated by a map or plan showing as accurately as 
possible the situation, boundaries and area of the land in respect of which the 
licence is required;
 </section><section>
        
<number>e</number>  the period for which the licence is required.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Application fee.—Every 
application for an exploring licence shall be accompanied by a fee of Rs. 1,000 
(rupees one thousand).
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Acknowledgment of 
application.—On 
receipt of the application, the receiving officer shall not thereon the date and 
hour of its receipt and shall give to the applicant an acknowledgment stating 
the date and time of receipt.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Central Government 
may grant or refuse a licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to rule 11, the Central Government may grant or refuse the licence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In case of refusal, 
intimation of the same shall be given to the applicant in writing and the fee 
paid under rule 13 shall be refunded.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Priority.—If 
more than one application regarding the same land is received, preference shall 
be given to the application received first, unless the Central Government, for 
any special reason, decides to the contrary.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Security deposit—The 
applicant shall, before the licence is issued to him, deposit as security for 
the observance of the terms and conditions of the licence a sum of Rs. 50 per 
100 square miles, or part thereof of the area covered by the licence, subject to 
a minimum of Rs. 2000, (rupees two thousand).
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Register of 
exploring licences.—A 
register of applications for exploring licences shall be maintained by the 
Central Government specifying—
 <section>
        
<number>1</number>  Serial No.
 </section><section>
        
<number>2</number>  Name of the applicant.
 </section><section>
        
<number>3</number>  Residence of the applicant.
 </section><section>
        
<number>4</number>  Date and No. of the certificate of approval for petroleum granted to 
the applicant.
 </section><section>
        
<number>5</number>  Date of application.
 </section><section>
        
<number>6</number>  Situation and boundaries of the land.
 </section><section>
        
<number>7</number>  Estimated total area.
 </section><section>
        
<number>8</number>  Date of grant of the licence.
 </section><section>
        
<number>9</number>  Period for which granted, renewed or extended.
 </section><section>
      
<number>10</number>  Exploring fee payable.
 </section><section>
      
<number>11</number>  Amount of security deposit.
 </section><section>
      
<number>12</number>  Particulars of disposal or refund of deposit.
 </section><section>
      
<number>13</number>  Date of assignment or transfer of the licence, if any, and fees paid 
therefor and the names of the parties thereto.
 </section><section>
      
<number>14</number>  Date of application for prospecting licence or mining lease (if any).
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Inspection of 
register.—The 
register shall be open for inspection by any holder of a valid certificate of 
approval for petroleum or of an exploring or prospecting licence or mining lease 
for petroleum, or his duly authorised agent, on payment of such fee as the 
Central Government may fix.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Period of grant or 
renewal of a prospective licence.—
<section><number>1</number>
The term for which an exploring licence may be granted shall be two years, 
but may be shorter if the applicant himself so desires. The licensee shall be 
entitled to two renewals of one year each, but the Central Government may 
decline to grant him one or both renewals.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the licensee, 
before the termination of the period of his licence, applies for the grant of a 
prospecting licence or mining lease, the period shall be further extended till 
the prospecting licence or the mining lease, as the case may be, is granted.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Conditions of an 
exploring licence.—Every 
exploring licence shall, in addition to such other conditions as may be found 
necessary in any particular case, contain the following conditions:—
 <section>
         
<number>i</number>  The licensee shall pay annually, in advance, an exploring fee of Re. 1 
per square mile of land covered by the licence for each year or portion of a 
year for which the licence is granted.
 </section><section>
        
<number>ii</number>  The licence shall not confer upon the licensee any right to win or 
carry away petroleum:
 
                 
Provided that for experimental purposes, the licensee may carry away petroleum 
from the surface seepages, if any, up to a maximum quantity of 1,000 gallons, 
free of royalty.
 </section><section>
        
<number>iii</number>  The licensee shall make a reasonable satisfaction and pay such 
compensation as may be assessed by lawful authority in accordance with the law 
on the subject applying to lands over which the licence has been granted, for 
any damage, injury or disturbance which may be done by him in exercise of the 
powers granted by the licence, and shall indemnify the Government against all 
claims which may be made by third parties in respect of any such damage, injury 
or disturbance.
 </section><section>
       
<number>iv</number>  The licensee shall not, without the permission in writing of the 
proper authority, cut or injure any tree on unoccupied and unreserved land nor 
disturb the surface of any road, or enter on any public pleasure, ground, 
burning or buying ground or place held sacred by any class of persons or 
interfere with any right‑of way, well or tank.
 </section><section>
        
<number>v</number>  The licensee may, with the previous consent of the Central Government, 
transfer his licence or any right or interest to person, holding a certificate 
of approval for petroleum, on payment to the Central Government of a fee of 
rupees one hundred.
 </section><section>
       
<number>vi</number>  The licensee shall not be controlled by any trust, syndicate, 
corporation, firm or person, except with the written consent of the Central 
Government.
 </section><section>
       
<number>vii</number>  The licensee shall be at liberty to determine the licence or 
surrender or relinquish any part of the licensed area on giving not less than 
one month’s notice in writing to the Central Government.
 </section><section>
      
<number>viii</number>  In case of breach of any of the conditions of the licence may, 
where it is satisfied that the breach is such as cannot be remedied, on giving 
thirty days notice to the licensee or his transferee or assignee, forfeit the 
whole or part of the deposit made under rule 17 or determine the licence. In 
case the Central Government considers the breach to be of a remediable nature, 
it shall give notice to the licensee, transferee or assignee, as the case, may 
be, requiring him to remedy the breach within thirty days from the date of 
receipt of the notice, and informing him of the penalty proposed to be inflicted 
if such remedy is not made within such period:
 
                 
Provided that if the licensee or his transferee or assignee claims that he has 
not committed any such breach, or that the penalty proposed therefor is unduly 
severe, or that the breach is of a remediable nature, he may submit the dispute 
to arbitration as provided in rule 64, within thirty days from the date of 
receipt of the notice and if he does so the Central Government shall not take 
any action under this clause till the award of the arbitration is announced, 
and, in case the arbitrators or the umpire find that a breach has been committed 
and that it is of a remediable nature, the thirty days’ time for remedying the 
same shall run from the date of announcement of the award.
 </section><section>
        
<number>ix</number>  Save in the case of land over which the licensee has been granted a 
prospecting licence or mining lease, he shall, within three months following the 
determination of the licence or the date of abandonment of the undertaking, 
whichever, shall occur first, securely plug any bore‑holes and fill up or fence 
any excavations or ditches that he may have made on the land:
 
                 
Provided that he shall not be required to restore that surface of the land in 
respect of which full and proper compensation has already been paid under 
condition (iii) above.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Operations within a 
reserved or protected forest.—All 
operations conducted under the authority of these rules within a reserved or 
protected forest shall be subject to such conditions as the Central Government 
may prescribe.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Right to 
prospecting licence.—On 
or before the determination of his licence, the licensee shall have the 
exclusive right to a prospecting licence for petroleum or natural gas over such 
part of the land covered by the licence as he may desire, but subject to the 
rules in force at the time of grant to him of the exploring licence.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>24</number> Reports of 
information obtained by licensee.—The 
licensee shall, before the deposit made under rule 17 is returned to him submit 
confidentially to the State Government a full report of the work done by him, 
and disclose all information acquired in the course of the operations carried on 
under the licence, regarding the geology and mineral resources of the area 
covered by the licence.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Eligibility.—A 
prospecting licence may be granted by the Central Government to any person—
 <section>
         
<number>i</number>  holding a certificate of approval for petroleum; or
 </section><section>
        
<number>ii</number>  referred to in rule 10.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Application for 
prospecting licence.—An 
application for a prospecting licence shall be made to the State Government 
concerned and shall contain the following particulars:—
 <section>
    <number>a</number> (i)  
If the applicant is an individual, his name, nationality, profession and 
residence; and
 <subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  If the applicant is a company, syndicate, partnership or private 
firm, its name, nature and place of business, and if the place of business is 
outside India, the name and residence of a member or duly authorized agent 
resident in India;
 </subsection></section><section>
        
<number>b</number>  the number and date of the notification granting or renewing the 
certificate of approval for petroleum to the applicant;
 </section><section>
        
<number>c</number>  a description, illustrated by a map or plan showing as accurately as 
possible the situation, boundaries, and area of the land in respect of which the 
licence is required;
 </section><section>
        
<number>d</number>  the period for which the licence is required;
 </section><section>
        
<number>e</number>  whether the applicant holds or held an exploring licence over the land 
for which the prospecting licence is required by him, and, if so, the 
particulars thereof.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Application fee.—Every 
application for a prospecting licence shall be accompanied by a fee of Rs. 2000 
(rupees two thousand).
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Acknowledgment of 
application.—On 
receipt of the application the receiving officer shall note thereon the date and 
time of its receipt and shall give the applicant an acknowledgment stating the 
date and hour of receipt.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>29</number> Central Government 
may grant or refuse a licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to rules 23 and 25, the Central Government may grant or refuse the 
licence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In case of refusal, 
intimation of the same shall be given to the applicant in writing and the fee 
paid under rule 27 shall be refunded.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>30</number> Priority.—Subject 
to rule 23, if more than one application regarding the same land is received, 
preference shall be given to the application received first, unless the Central 
Government, for any special reason, decides to the contrary.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>31</number> Security deposit.—The 
applicant shall, before the licence is issued to him, deposit as security for 
due observance of the terms and conditions of the licence, a sum of Rs. 50 for 
each square mile or part thereof covered by the licence, subject to a minimum of 
Rs. 5000 (rupees five thousand).
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>32</number> Register of 
prospecting licences.—A 
register of prospecting licences shall be maintained by the Central Government, 
specifying—
 <section>
        
<number>1</number>  Serial No.
 </section><section>
        
<number>2</number>  Name of the applicant.
 </section><section>
        
<number>3</number>  Residence of the applicant.
 </section><section>
        
<number>4</number>  Date and No. of the Certificate of Approval for petroleum granted to 
the applicant.
 </section><section>
        
<number>5</number>  Date of application,
 </section><section>
        
<number>6</number>  Situation and boundaries of the land.
 </section><section>
        
<number>7</number>  Estimated total area.
 </section><section>
        
<number>8</number>  Date of grant of the licence.
 </section><section>
        
<number>9</number>  Period for which granted, renewed or extended.
 </section><section>
      
<number>10</number>  Prospecting fee and royalty.
 </section><section>
      
<number>11</number>  Amount of security deposit.
 </section><section>
      
<number>12</number>  Particulars of disposal or refund of security deposit.
 </section><section>
      
<number>13</number>  Date of assignment or transfer of the licence, if any, and fees paid 
therefor and the names of the parties thereto.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>33</number> Inspection of 
register.—The 
register shall be open for inspection by any holder of a valid certificate of 
approval for petroleum or an exploring or prospecting licence, or a mining lease 
for petroleum, or his duly authorized agent, on payment of such fee as the 
Central Government may fix.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>34</number> Period of grant of 
renewal of a prospecting licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The period for which a prospecting licence may be granted shall be three years 
but may be shorter if the applicant himself so desires. The licensee shall be 
entitled to two renewals of one year each, but the Central Government may, for 
special reasons, decline to grant one or both the renewals.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Central Government 
may, in cases where the licensee holds prospecting licences over two or more 
geologically related areas, extend the period referred to in (1) above by such 
further period as may be considered necessary.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If the licensee, 
before the termination of the period of his licence, applies for the grant of 
mining lease, the period shall be further extended till the mining lease is 
granted.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>36</number> Operations within a 
reserved or protected forest.—All 
operations conducted under the authority of these rules within a reserved or 
protected forest shall be subject to such conditions as the Central Government 
may prescribe.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>37</number> Right to a mining 
lease.­—On or 
before the determination of his licence, the licensee shall have the exclusive 
right to a mining lease or leases for petroleum or natural gas over such part of 
the land covered by the licence as he may desire, but subject to the rules in 
force at the time of grant to him of the exploring licence, it any, or the 
prospecting licence.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>38</number> Reports of 
information obtained by licensee.—The 
licensee shall, before the deposit made under rule 31 is returned to him or 
transferred to any other account, submit confidentially to the State Government 
a full report of the work done by him, and disclose all information acquired in 
the course of the operations carried on under the licence, regarding the geology 
and mineral resources of the area covered by tile licence.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>39</number> Eligibility.—A 
mining lease may be granted by the Central Government to any person—
 <section>
         
<number>i</number>  holding a certificate of approval for petroleum;
 </section><section>
        
<number>ii</number>  referred to in rule 10.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>40</number> Application for 
mining lease.—An 
application for mining lease shall be made to the State Government concerned and 
shall contain the following particulars:—
 <section>
    <number>a</number> (i)  
If the applicant is an individual, his name, nationality, profession and 
residence.
 <subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  If the applicant is a company, syndicate, private firm or 
partnership, its nature and place of business and if the place of business is 
outside India, the name and residence of a member or duly authorized agent 
resident in India.
 </subsection></section><section>
        
<number>b</number>  the No. and date of the notification granting or renewing the 
certificate of approval for petroleum to the applicant;
 </section><section>
        
<number>c</number>  a description, illustrated by a map or plan, showing as accurately as 
possible, the situation, boundaries and area of the land in respect of which the 
lease is required;
 </section><section>
        
<number>d</number>  the period for which the lease is required;
 </section><section>
        
<number>e</number>  particulars of any other mining lease for petroleum held by the 
applicant in any other State;
 </section><section>
         
<number>f</number>  whether the applicant holds or held an exploring or a prospecting 
licence over land for which the mining lease is required and, if so, the 
particulars thereof.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>41</number> Application fee.—The
application shall be accompanied by a fee grant of Rs. 5,000 (rupees five 
thousand). If, subject to rule 37, the Central Government refuse to grant the 
lease applied for, the fee shall be refunded.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>42</number> Acknowledgment of 
applications.—On 
receipt of the application the receiving officer shall note thereon the date and 
time of its receipt and shall give to the applicant an acknowledgment stating 
the date and time of receipt.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>43</number> Priority.—Subject 
to rule 37, if more than one application regarding the same land is received, 
preference shall be given to the application received first, unless the Central 
Government, for any special reason, decides to the contrary.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>44</number> Area of mining 
lease.—A mining 
lease may be granted for such area as may be desired by the applicant, but 
subject to the conditions that no mining lease shall be granted under these 
rules so as to cause the total area held under mining lease for petroleum by the 
lessee himself or with person joint in interest with him to exceed 1,000 square 
miles within India.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>45</number> Security deposit.—The 
applicant shall, before the lease is issued, deposit as security a sum of Rs. 
20,000 (rupees twenty thousand) for the due observance of terms and conditions 
of the lease.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>46</number> Deposit for 
preliminary expenses.—The 
applicant shall, before the lease is issued, also deposit for meeting the 
preliminary expenses, such sum not exceeding Rs. 2,000 (rupees two thousand), as 
the Central Government may determine.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>47</number> Survey of leased 
area.—When a 
lease is granted by the Central Government, it shall, at the expense of the 
lessee, arrange for the survey and demarcation of the area granted under the 
lease.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>48</number> Register of mining 
leases.—A 
register of applications for mining leases shall be maintained by the Central 
Government specifying—
 <section>
        
<number>1</number>  Serial No.
 </section><section>
        
<number>2</number>  Name of the applicant.
 </section><section>
        
<number>3</number>  Residence of the applicant.
 </section><section>
        
<number>4</number>  Date and No. of the certificate of approval for petroleum granted to 
the applicant.
 </section><section>
        
<number>5</number>  Date of application.
 </section><section>
        
<number>6</number>  Situation and boundaries of the land.
 </section><section>
        
<number>7</number>  Estimated total area.
 </section><section>
        
<number>8</number>  Date of grant of the lease.
 </section><section>
        
<number>9</number>  Period for which granted, renewed or extended.
 </section><section>
      
<number>10</number>  Dead rent and royalty payable.
 </section><section>
      
<number>11</number>  Particulars of the refund or disposal of the deposits made under 
rules 45 and 46.
 </section><section>
      
<number>12</number>  Date of assignment or transfer of the lease, if any, and fees paid 
therefor and the names of the parties thereto.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>49</number> Inspection of 
register.—The 
register shall be open to inspection by any holder of a certificate of approval 
for petroleum of an exploring or prospecting licence, or a mining lease for 
petroleum, or his duly authorised agent, on payment of such fee as the Central 
Government may fix.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>50</number> Transfer of lease.—The 
lessee may, with the previous sanction of the Central Government and subject to 
the provision of rule 45, transfer his lease or any right or interest therein to 
a person holding a certificate of approval for petroleum, on payment of a fee of 
Rs. 500 to the Central Government.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>51</number> Period of lease.—
<section><number>1</number> 

<subsection><number>a</number> The period for which mining lease may be granted shall be twenty years, 
unless the applicant asks for a shorter period.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> The lease may be 
renewed at the option of the lessor for such period or periods as he may deem 
fit, but any such period shall not exceed the term of the original lease.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> When a renewal is 
granted, royalty, dead rent and surface rent shall be charged at the rates in 
force at the time of the renewal.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>52</number> Refining of crude 
oil.—The 
Central Government may require that mining lease shall contain a condition that 
any crude petroleum produced the lessee shall not be exported form India until 
it has been converted into refined products:
 
Provided that in any case 
in which it is proved to the satisfaction of the Central Government that any 
practical or economic difficulty is involved in giving effect to this rule it 
may pass such order or take such action as it deems fit to remove such 
difficulty:
 
Provided further that the 
lessee shall not at any time be required to refine in India more crude oil than 
is sufficient to meet India’s total indigenous requirements at that time, and 
the decision of the Central Government as to what quantity is sufficient to meet 
such requirements shall be final.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>53</number> Piping of crude 
oil.—The lessee 
shall be free to construct or operate such pipelines as may be necessary for the 
purpose of carrying away cured oil or natural gas or the products thereof from 
the leased area to any part of India:
 
Provided that the pipeline 
shall not pass through any non‑Indian territory except with the written 
permission of the Central Government.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>54</number> Conditions of 
mining lease.—Every 
mining lease shall, in addition to such other conditions as may in any 
particular case be found necessary, contain the following conditions:—
 <section>
         
<number>i</number>  The lessee shall pay royalty on all crude oil or natural gas won and 
saved from the leased area, at the rate specified in the Schedule to these 
rules.
 </section><section>
        
<number>ii</number>  The lessee shall pay, for every year except the first year of the 
lease, a fixed yearly dead rent at the following rates:—
 <subsection>
                   
<number>Rs</number> 2 per acre for the first 10 square miles;
 </subsection><subsection>
                   
<number>Rs</number> 3 per acre for the next 40 square miles;
 </subsection><subsection>
                   
<number>Rs</number> 5 per acre for the next 40 square miles;
 </subsection><subsection>
                   
<number>Rs</number> 10 per acre for area exceeding the first 100 square miles.
 
                 
 Provided that the lessee shall be liable to pay only the dead rent or the 
royalty, whichever be higher in amount but not both.
 </subsection></section><section>
        
<number>iii</number>  The lessee shall also pay for the surface area actually used by him 
for the purposes of the operations conducted under the lease surface rent at 
such rate not exceeding the land revenue and cesses assessable on the land, as 
may be specified by the State Government in the lease.
 </section><section>
       
<number>iv</number>  The lessee shall make reasonable satisfaction and pay such 
compensation, as may be assessed by lawful authority in accordance with the law 
in force on the subject applying to the lands over which the lease has been 
granted for any damage, injury of disturbance which may be done by him in 
exercise of the powers granted by the lease, and shall indemnify the Government 
against all claims which may be made by third parties in respect of any such 
damage, injury or disturbance.
 </section><section>
        
<number>v</number>  Unless the Central Government for good cause permits otherwise the 
lessee shall commence operations within one year from the date of execution of 
the lease, and shall thereafter carry them on in a proper, skilful and 
workmanlike manner.
 

Explanation.—For the purposes of this clause, operations shall include 
the erection of machinery, laying of a tramway or construction of a road in 
connection with the oilfield.
 </section><section>
       
<number>vi</number>  The lessee shall, at his own expense, erect and all times maintain 
and keep in repair boundary marks and pillars necessary to indicate the 
demarcation shown in the plan annexed to his lease.
 </section><section>
       
<number>vii</number>  The lease shall contain such restrictions and conditions with regard 
to the cutting and use of reserved timber as may be agreed upon between the 
Central Government and the lessee.
 </section><section>
      
<number>viii</number>  The lessee shall not, without the previous permission of the proper 
authority, erect any building or carry on any surface operations upon any public 
pleasure ground, burning or burying ground or place held sacred by any class of 
persons, or any village site, or public road, nor shall he interfere with any 
right of way, well or tank.
 </section><section>
        
<number>ix</number>  The lessee shall not carry on or allow to be carried on any boring 
operations at any point within a distance of 50 yards from any railway line, 
except with the written permission of the railway administration concerned, or 
from any reservoir, canal or other public works or buildings except with the 
previous permission of the Central Government. The railway administration or the 
Central Government may, in granting such permission, impose such conditions as 
it may deem fit.
 </section><section>
        
<number>x</number>  The lessee shall not intentionally cause any boring to deviate from 
the vertical in such a way as to cross a vertical plane passing through a 
boundary of the land covered by the lease or employ any method of drilling which 
is causing or is likely to cause a boring to deviate to such extent and in such 
direction as to cross such a vertical plane.
 </section><section>
        
<number>xi</number>  The lessee shall provide properly constructed and efficient 
tankmeters and other suitable means for measuring the quantity and volume of 
petroleum or natural gas produced.
 <subsection>
       
<number>xii</number>  The lessee shall keep correct accounts showing the quantity and 
other particulars of petroleum or natural gas obtained and dispatched from the 
oilfield, the number of persons employed therein, and complete plans of the 
oilfield, and shall allow any officer authorized by the Central Government in 
that behalf to examine at any time, nay accounts, plans and records maintained 
by him, and shall finish the Central Government, with such information and 
returns as it may prescribe.
 </subsection><subsection>
      
<number>xiii</number>  The lessee shall keep accurate records of the drilling, deepening, 
plugging or abandonment of all bore‑holes and wells and of any alterations to 
the casings thereof, and shall allow any officer authorized by the Central 
Government to inspect the same. Such records shall contain the following 
particulars:—
 </subsection><subsection>
             
<number>a</number>  The strata and sub‑soil through which the bore‑hole or well was 
drilled.
 </subsection><subsection>
             
<number>b</number>  The casing inserted in any bore‑hole or well and any alteration to 
such casing.
 </subsection><subsection>
             
<number>c</number>  Any petroleum or water‑bearing strata, coal‑seams, seam and veins of 
any other mineral substance encountered.
 </subsection><subsection>
             
<number>d</number>  Such other matter as the Central Government may from time to time 
require.
 </subsection><subsection>
      
<number>xiv</number>  The lessee shall strengthen and support to the satisfaction of the 
railway administration concerned, or the Central Government, as the case may be, 
any part of the mine which in its opinion requires such strengthening or support 
for the safety of any railway, reservoir, canal, road or any other public works 
or structures.
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>xv</number>  The lessee shall allow any officer authorized by the Central 
Government to enter upon any building, excavation or land comprised in the lease 
for the purpose of inspecting the same.
 </subsection><subsection>
      
<number>xvi</number>  The lessee shall allow reasonable facilities of access to existing 
or future holders of licences or leases over any land which is comprised in or 
adjoins or is reached by the land held by him.
 </subsection><subsection>
     
<number>xvii</number>  The lessee shall, without delay, report to the State Government the 
discovery in the area comprised in this lease, of any mineral other than 
petroleum or natural gas.
 </subsection><subsection>
     
<number>xviii</number>  The lessee shall not be controlled by any trust, syndicate, 
corporation, firm or person, except with the written consent of the State 
Government.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>xix</number> (1)  In case of 
a national emergency in respect of petroleum the Central Government shall, at 
all time, have the right of pre­-emption of the refined petroleum or petroleum 
products produced from the oil crude extracted from the area held under lease, 
or of the crude oil where the lessee is permitted to sell, export or dispose of 
it without refining:
 
                 
Provided that the fair market price prevailing at the time of pre-emption shall 
be paid to the lessee, for the petroleum or petroleum products taken in 
pre‑emption.
 <subsubsection>
        
<number>2</number>  Notwithstanding anything contained in rule 64, the Central Government 
shall be the sole judge as to what constitutes a national emergency in respect 
of petroleum, and its decision in this respect shall be final.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
       
<number>xx</number>  Should the royalty or rent payable by the lessee be not paid within 
two months next after the date fixed in the lease for the payment of the same, 
the Central Government may enter upon the premises comprised in the lease and 
distrain any moveable property therein, and may order the sale of the property 
so distrained or so much of it as will suffice for the satisfaction of the 
royalty or rent due and all costs and expenses occasioned by the non‑payment 
thereof: and if any royalty or rent remains at any time unpaid for six calendar 
months next after the date on which it is due the Central Government may 
determine the lease and take possession of the premises demised therein:
 
                 
Provided that if any dispute regarding the royalty or rent shall have been 
submitted to arbitration the period of two months or of six months, as the case 
may be, shall run from the date of announcement of the award.
 </subsection><subsection>
      
<number>xxi</number>  In cases of breach of any of the conditions of the lease by the 
lessee of his transferee or assignee, the Central Government may, where it is 
satisfied that the breach is such as cannot be remedied, on giving thirty day’s 
notice to the lessee or his transferee or assignee, forfeit the whole or part of 
deposit made under rule 45 or determine the lease. In case the Central 
Government considers the breach to be of a remediable nature, it shall give 
notice to the lessee, or his transferee or assignee, as the case may be, 
requiring him to remedy the breach within sixty days from the date of receipt of 
the notice and informing him of the penalty proposed to be inflicted if such 
remedy is not made within such period:
 
                 
Provided that, if the lessee, or his transferee or assignee, claims that he has 
not committed any such breach or that, the penalty proposed therefor is unduly 
sever, or that the breach is of a remediable nature, be may submit the dispute 
to arbitration as provided in rule 64, within thirty days from the date of 
receipt of the notice and if he does so, the Central Government shall not take 
any action under this clause till the award of the arbitration is announced and, 
in case the arbitrators of the umpire find that a breach as been committed and 
that it is of a remediable nature, the sixty days’ time for remedying the same 
shall run from the date of announcement of the award.
 </subsection><subsection>
      
<number>xxii</number>  The lessee shall be at liberty to, determine the lease or surrender 
or relinquish any part of the leased area, giving not less than twelve calendar 
months’ notice in writing to the Central Government.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>55</number> Operations within a 
reserved or protected forest.—All 
operations conducted under the authority of these rules within a reserved or 
protected forest shall be subject to such conditions as the Central Government 
may prescribe.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>56</number> Reserve forest.—Every 
mining lease which includes any portion of a reserved forest shall, if it 
authorizes the lessee to fell timber for the purpose of his operations, specify 
the terms and conditions upon which he may exercise that authority.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>57</number> Direct application 
for prospecting licence or mining lease.—Any 
person holding a certificate of approval for petroleum may apply directly for a 
prospecting licence or a mining lease.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>58</number> Rights of lessee.—An 
exploring of prospecting licence or mining lease for petroleum or natural gas 
shall contain, consistent with these rules, such covenants regarding the 
liberties, powers and privileges to be exercised or enjoyed by the licensee or 
lessee as may be necessary.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>59</number> Force majeure.—Failure 
on the part of a licensee or lessee to fulfil any of the terms and conditions of 
his licence or lease shall not give the Central Government any claim against the 
licensee or lessee or be deemed a breach of the licence or lease on so far as 
such failure arises from force majeure, and if through force majeure 
the fulfilment by the licensee or lessee or any of the terms and conditions 
of his licence or lease be delayed, the period of such delay shall be added to 
the period fixed by the licence or lease.
 
Explanation—This 
expression force majeure, an act of God, war, insurrection, riot, civil 
commotion, tide, storm, tidal wave, flood, lightning, explosion, fire, 
earthquake, and any other happening which the licensee or lessee could not 
reasonably prevent or control.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>60</number> Stipulations in 
case of an alien or Company incorporated outside India.—In 
granting a licence, or a lease where a licence has not previously been held, to 
a person who is not a citizen of India, or a company which is not incorporated 
in India, the Central Government may—
 <section>
         
<number>i</number>  require the licensee or lessee to associate Indian capital in the 
enterprise to such extent as may be agreed upon between him and the Central 
Government;
 </section><section>
        
<number>ii</number>  require the licensee, or lessee to employ citizens of India at all 
levels in his organization to such extent as may be agreed upon between him and 
the Central Government and to arrange for their training in India and abroad to 
enable them to occupy those appointments.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>61</number> Application of these rules to 
all renewals.—Where an exploring or prospecting 
licence or a mining lease granted before the commencement of these rules is 
renewed after such commencement, these rules shall apply in relation to such 
renewal as they apply in relation to the renewal of an exploring or prospecting 
licence or a mining lease granted after such 
commencement.</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>62</number> Forwarding of 
copies of reports.—The 
State Government shall send copies of all reports received by under rules 24, 38 
and clause (xvii) of rule 54 to the Director, Indian Bureau of Mines.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>63</number> Fair market price.—For
the purpose of clause (xix) of rules 54, fair market price at any time shall 
mean the published price at that time of similar commodities in a substantial 
free market in any part of the world, with such adjustments as may be necessary.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>64</number> Arbitration for 
breaches, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In case of any dispute between the Central Government and the licensee or lessee 
regarding—
 <subsection>
        
<number>a</number>  any right claimed by the licensee or lessee under the licence or 
lease;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>b</number>  any breach alleged to have been committed by the licensee or lessee of 
any covenant contained in his licence or lease, or any penalty proposed to be 
inflicted therefor;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>c</number>  the amount of royalty or rent payable under the licence or lease;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>d</number>  the amount of compensation payable to the lessee in the event of 
acquisition of his property;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>e</number>  any other matter or thing connected with the licence or lease;
 
the matter in dispute 
shall be settled by two arbitrators, one to be nominated by the Central 
Government and the other by the licensee or lessee; or in case of disagreement 
between the arbitrators, by an umpire appointed by the arbitrators by writing 
under their hands before proceeding with the arbitration, and the decision of 
such arbitrators or umpire shall be final.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The arbitrators or the 
umpire will also determine which party shall bear the expenses of the 
arbitration or whether the expenditure shall be divided between the two parties 
and, if so, in what proportion.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>65</number> Arbitration for 
pre‑emption.—In 
case of any dispute regarding the price to be paid for petroleum or natural gas 
taken in pre-emption by the Central Government, the matter in dispute shall be 
settled by two arbitrators, one to be nominated by the Central Government and 
the other by the lessee; or in case of disagreement between the arbitrators, by 
an umpire appointed by the arbitrators by writing under their hands before 
proceeding with the arbitration and the decision of such arbitrators or umpire 
shall be final. The arbitrators or the umpire will also determine which party 
shall bear the expenses of the arbitration or whether the expenditure shall be 
divided between the two parties, and if so, in what proportion.
</article> 

 
 
  
 [***]


<form>
 




THE PETROLEUM Concession RULES, 1949
 


 
 




Schedule
 




Royalty
 


Petroleum.—Ten 
per cent on the well‑head value, convertible at the option of the Central 
Government to an equivalent charge to be fixed annually, subject to a minimum of 
fifty paise per 40 imperial gallons, excluding water and foreign substance.
 


Natural gas.—If 
sold by the licensee or lessee or if utilized by him for any other purposes than 
the production of natural petroleum or natural gas—10 per cent on the well‑head 
value.
 


Gasoline from gas.—On 
gas converted into gasoline the well‑head value shall be calculated on the 
volume of gasoline manufactured; it shall be deemed to be equivalent to the 
selling value of the gasoline less the cost of manufacture, and the royalty 
shall be subject to a minimum of fifty paise per 40 imperial gallons of gasoline 
manufactured:
 


Provided that the 10 per 
cent, royalty rate shall be convertible at the option of the Central Government 
to an equivalent charge per 40 imperial gallons of gasoline (not being less than 
fifty paise) or per 1,000 cubic feet of gas, as the case may be, to be fixed 
annually.
 


Explanation—”Well 
head value” shall be the published price of crude oil of similar type and 
quality in a substantial free market in any part of the world, where such market 
may exist, with suitable adjustments to bring the price back to the well‑head 
value of the crude oil.
 


Oil shale.—To 
be fixed by negotiation between the lessee and the Central Government.
 


 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>