<act><tid>78925</tid>
<title>THE INSTITUTES OF TECHNOLOGY ACT, <year>1961</year></title>

ACT NO. 59 OF <year>1961</year>
[ 19th December, <year>1961</year>.]

An Act to declare certain institutions of technology to be 
institutions of national importance and to provide for certain matters 
connected with such institutions and the Indian Institute of 
Technology, Kharagpur.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twelfth Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1087446</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>361303</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Institutes of Technology Act, <year>1961</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1287681</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint, and 
different dates may be appointed for different provisions of this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>684814</tid>
<number>2</number>Declaration of certain institutions as institutions of 
national importance. Whereas the objects of the institutions known as 
the Indian Institute of Technology, Bombay, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the College of 
Engineering and Technology, Delhi, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> The Indian Institute of 
technogys Guwahati, Assam] the Indian Institute of Technology, Kanpur 
and the Indian Institute of Technology, Madras are such as to make 
them institutions of national importance, it is hereby declared that 
each such institution is an institution of national importance.


</article>



<article><tid>1038979</tid>
<number> 3</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>75607</tid>
<number>a</number>" Board", in relation to any Institute, means the Board 
of Governors thereof;

</section>

<section><tid>1035068</tid>
<number>b</number>" Chairman" means the Chairman of the Board;

</section>

<section><tid>1937242</tid>
<number>c</number>" corresponding Institute" means,-

<subsection><tid>592292</tid>
<number>i</number>in relation to the society known as the 
Indian Institute of Technology, Bombay, the Indian 
Institute of Technology, Bombay.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>150</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1st April, <year>1962</year>; vide Notification No. S. O. 929, dated the 23rd 
March, <year>1962</year> Gazette of India. Pt. II. Sec. 3 (ii) p. 867. 
2 Ins. by Act 29 of <year>1963</year>, s. 2. (w. e. f. 13- 9- <year>1963</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>620975</tid>
<number>ia</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in relation to the society known as 
the College of Engineering and Technology, Delhi, 
the Indian Institute of Technology, Delhi,]

</section>

<section><tid>566573</tid>
<number>ib</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> in relation to the society known as 
the Indian Institute of Technology, Guwahati, 
Assam, the indian Institute of Technology, 
Guwahati;"]

<subsection><tid>1249706</tid>
<number>ii</number>in relation to the society known as the 
Indian Institute of Technology (Kanpur) Society, 
the Indian Institute of Technology, Kanpur, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>823447</tid>
<number>iii</number>in relation to the society known as the 
Indian Institute of Technology, Madras, the Indian 
Institute of Technology, Madras;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>194729</tid>
<number>d</number>" Council" means the Council established under sub- 
section (1) of section 31;

</section>

<section><tid>998950</tid>
<number>e</number>" Deputy Director", in relation to any Institute, means 
the Deputy Director thereof;

</section>

<section><tid>711905</tid>
<number>f</number>" Director", in relation to any Institute, means the 
Director thereof;

</section>

<section><tid>1440959</tid>
<number>g</number>" Institute" means any of the Institutions mentioned in 
section 2 and includes the Indian Institute of 
Technology, Kharagpur, incorporated under the Indian 
Institute of Technology (Kharagpur) Act, <year>1956</year> (5 of  
  <year>1956</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1257474</tid>
<number>h</number>" Registrar", in relation to any Institute, means the 
Registrar thereof;

</section>

<section><tid>1095355</tid>
<number>i</number>" Senate", in relation to any Institute, means the 
Senate thereof;

</section>

<section><tid>917750</tid>
<number>j</number>" society" means any of the following societies 
registered under the Societies Registration Act, <year>1860</year> 
 (21 of <year>1860</year>), namely:-

<subsection><tid>100109</tid>
<number>i</number>the Indian Institute of Technology, 
Bombay;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>620975</tid>
<number>ia</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the College of Engineering and 
Technology, Delhi;]

</section>

<section><tid>566573</tid>
<number>ib</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the Indian Institute of Technology, 
Guwahati, Assam;"]

<subsection><tid>1249706</tid>
<number>ii</number>the Indian Institute of Technology 
 (Kanpur) Society;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>823447</tid>
<number>iii</number>the Indian Institute of Technology, 
Madras;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>241906</tid>
<number>k</number>" Statutes" and" Ordinances", in relation to any 
Institute, mean the Statutes and Ordinances of the 
Institute made under this Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>150A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 29 of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 13- 9- <year>1963</year>). 
2. Ins by Act 35 of <year>1994</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 1- 9- <year>1994</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


CHAP

THE INSTITUTES

CHAPTER II

THE INSTITUTES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1585254</tid>
<number> 4</number> Incorporation of institutes.
<section><tid>27249</tid>
<number>1</number>Each of the Institutes  
mentioned in section 2 shall be a body corporate having perpetual 
succession and a common seal and shall, by its name, sue and be sued.

</section>

<section><tid>1206480</tid>
<number>1A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The College of Engineering and Technology, Delhi shall, 
on such incorporation, be called the Indian Institute of Technology, 
Delhi.]

</section>

<section><tid>1210206</tid>
<number>1B</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> The Indian Institute of Technology, Guwahati, Assam 
shall, on such incorporation, be called the Indian Institute of 
Technology, Guwahati."]

</section>

<section><tid>1068450</tid>
<number>2</number>The body corporate constituting each of the said Institutes 
shall consist of a Chairman, a Director and other members of the Board 
for the time being of the Institute.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>151</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 29 of <year>1963</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 13- 9- <year>1963</year>). 
2. Ins by Act 35 of <year>1994</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 1- 9- <year>1994</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>950871</tid>
<number> 5</number> Effect of incorporation of institutes. On and from the 
commencement of this Act,--
<section><tid>1977420</tid>
<number>a</number>any reference to a society in any law (other than this  
  Act) or in any contract or other instrument shall be 
deemed as a reference to the corresponding Institute;

</section>

<section><tid>305587</tid>
<number>b</number>all property, movable and immovable, of or belonging to 
a society shall vest in the corresponding Institute;

</section>

<section><tid>1240776</tid>
<number>c</number>all the rights and liabilities of a society shall be 
transferred to, and be the rights and liabilities of, 
the corresponding Institute; and

</section>

<section><tid>194200</tid>
<number>d</number>every person employed by a society immediately before 
such commencement shall hold his office or service in 
the corresponding Institute by the same tenure, at the 
same remuneration and upon the same terms and 
conditions and with the same rights and privileges as 
to pension, leave, gratuity, provident fund and other 
matters as he would have held the same if this Act had 
not been passed, and shall continue to do so unless and 
until his employment is terminated or until such 
tenure, remuneration and terms and conditions are duly 
altered by the Statutes:
Provided that if the alteration so made is not 
acceptable to such employee, his employment may be 
terminated by the Institute in accordance with the 
terms of the contract with the employee or, if no 
provision is made therein in this behalf, on payment to 
him by the Institute of compensation equivalent to 
three months' remuneration in the case of permanent 
employees and one month' s remuneration in the case of 
other employees.

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Explanation.-- The reference in this section to the ccommence- 
ment of this Act shall be construed in relation to the Indian 
Institute of Technology, Guwahati as the reference to the date on 
which the provisions of the Institutes of Technology (Amendment) Act, 
 <year>1994</year> come into force."]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>191382</tid>
<number> 6</number> Powers of Institutes.
<section><tid>1768678</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of this  
Act, every Institute shall exercise the following powers and perform 
the following duties, namely:-

<subsection><tid>186207</tid>
<number>a</number>to provide for instruction and research in such 
branches of engineering and technology, sciences and 
arts, as the Institute may think fit, and for the 
advancement of learning and dissemination of knowledge 
in such branches;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>771749</tid>
<number>b</number>to hold examinations and grant degrees, diplomas and 
other academic distinctions or titles;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>151089</tid>
<number>c</number>to confer honorary degrees or other distinctions; 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1087446</tid>
<number> 1</number> Ins. by Act 35 of <year>1994</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 1- 9- <year>1994</year>).

<pagefootnote><pagenum>152</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

<section><tid>1721370</tid>
<number>d</number>to fix, demand and receive fees and other charges;

</section>

<section><tid>251135</tid>
<number>e</number>to establish, maintain and manage halls and hostels for 
the residence of students;

</section>

<section><tid>602848</tid>
<number>f</number>to supervise and control the residence and regulate the 
discipline of students of the Institute and to make 
arrangements for promoting their health, general 
welfare and cultural and corporate life;

</section>

<section><tid>1184870</tid>
<number>g</number>to provide for the maintenance of units of the National 
Cadet Corps for the students of the Institute;

</section>

<section><tid>566290</tid>
<number>h</number>to institute academic and other posts and to make 
appointments thereto (except in the case of the  
  Director);

</section>

<section><tid>237754</tid>
<number>i</number>to frame Statutes and Ordinances and to alter, modify 
or rescind the same;

</section>

<section><tid>1079835</tid>
<number>j</number>to deal with any property belonging to or vested in the 
Institute in such manner as the Institute may deem fit 
for advancing the objects of the Institute;

</section>

<section><tid>1235202</tid>
<number>k</number>to receive gifts, grants, donations or benefactions 
from the Government and to receive bequests, donations 
and transfers of movable or immovable properties from 
testators, donors or transferors, as the case may be;

</section>

<section><tid>813055</tid>
<number>l</number>to co- operate with educational or other institutions in 
any part of the world having objects wholly or partly 
similar to those of the Institute by exchange of 
teachers and scholars and generally in such manner as 
may be conducive to their common objects;

</section>

<section><tid>1845400</tid>
<number>m</number>to institute and award fellowships, scholarships, 
exhibitions, prizes and medals; and

</section>

<section><tid>679358</tid>
<number>n</number>to do all such things as may be necessary, incidental 
or conducive to the attainment of all or any of the 
objects of the Institute.

<subsection><tid>789157</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), an 
Institute shall not dispose of in any manner any immovable property 
without the prior approval of the Visitor.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>314217</tid>
<number> 7</number> Institutes to be open to all races, creeds and classes.
<section><tid>778106</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Every Institute shall be open to persons of either sex and of whatever 
race, creed, caste or class, and no test or condition shall be imposed 
as to religious belief or profession in admitting or appointing 
members, students, teachers or workers or in any other connection 
whatsoever.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>153</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>721769</tid>
<number>2</number>No bequest, donation or transfer of any property shall be 
accepted by any Institute which in the opinion of the Council involves 
conditions or obligations opposed to the spirit and object of this 
section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1388525</tid>
<number>8</number>Teaching at Institute. All teaching at each of the Institutes 
shall be conducted by or in the name of the Institute in accordance 
with the Statutes and Ordinances made in this behalf.


</article>



<article><tid>1104256</tid>
<number> 9</number> Visitor.
<section><tid>1051427</tid>
<number>1</number>The President of India shall be the Visitor of  
every Institute.

</section>

<section><tid>471818</tid>
<number>2</number>The Visitor may appoint one or more persons to review the 
work and progress of any Institute and to hold inquiries into the 
affairs thereof and to report thereon in such manner as the Visitor 
may direct.

</section>

<section><tid>1996522</tid>
<number>3</number>Upon receipt of any such report, the Visitor may take such 
action and issue such directions as he considers necessary in respect 
of any of the matters dealt with in the report and the Institute shall 
be bound to comply with such directions.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>576365</tid>
<number> 10</number> Authorities of Institutes. The following shall be the 
authorities of an Institute, namely:-
<section><tid>548048</tid>
<number>a</number>a Board of Governors;

</section>

<section><tid>1500227</tid>
<number>b</number>a Senate; and

</section>

<section><tid>1447549</tid>
<number>c</number>such other authorities as may be declared by the 
Statutes to be the authorities of the Institute.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1073145</tid>
<number> 11</number> Board of Governors. The Board of an Institute shall consist 
of the following persons, namely:-
<section><tid>999690</tid>
<number>a</number>the Chairman, to be nominated by the Visitor;

</section>

<section><tid>252175</tid>
<number>b</number>the Director, ex officio;

</section>

<section><tid>743977</tid>
<number>c</number>one person to be nominated by the Government of each of 
the States comprising the zone in which the Institute 
is situated, from among persons who, in the opinion of 
that Government, are technologists or industrialists of 
repute;

</section>

<section><tid>1500003</tid>
<number>d</number>four persons having special knowledge or practical 
experience in respect of education, engineering or 
science, to be nominated by the Council; and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>154</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>489793</tid>
<number>e</number>two professors of the Institute, to be nominated by the 
Senate.
Explanation.-- In this section, the expression" zone" means a zone 
as for the time being demarcated by the All- India Council for 
Technical Education for the purposes of this Act.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1585216</tid>
<number> 12</number> Term of office of, vacancies among, and allowances payable 
to, members of Board.
<section><tid>1995890</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as otherwise provided in this section,  
the term of office of the Chairman or any other member of the Board 
shall be three years from the date of his nomination.

</section>

<section><tid>56091</tid>
<number>2</number>The term of office of an ex officio member shall continue so 
long as he holds the office by virtue of which he is a member.

</section>

<section><tid>23574</tid>
<number>3</number>The term of office of a member nominated under <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> clause (e)] 
of section 11 shall be two years from the 1st day of January of the 
year in which he is nominated.

</section>

<section><tid>125968</tid>
<number>4</number>The term of office of a member nominated to fill a casual 
vacancy shall continue for the remainder of the term of the member in 
whose place he has been nominated.

</section>

<section><tid>62022</tid>
<number>5</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, an 
outgoing member shall, unless the Council otherwise directs, continue 
in office until another person is nominated as a member in his place.

</section>

<section><tid>240919</tid>
<number>6</number>The members of the Board shall be entitled to such 
allowances, if any, from the Institute as may be provided for in the 
Statutes but no member other than the persons referred to in clauses 
 (b) and (e) of section 11 shall be entitled to any salary by reason of 
this sub- section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>974355</tid>
<number> 13</number> Functions of Board.
<section><tid>736870</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of this  
Act, the Board of any Institute shall be responsible for the general 
superintendence, direction and control of the affairs of the Institute 
and shall exercise all the powers of the Institute not otherwise 
provided for by this Act, the Statutes and the Ordinances, and shall 
have the power to review the acts of the Senate.

</section>

<section><tid>1510481</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the provisions of sub- section (1), the 
Board of any Institute shall-

<subsection><tid>1678312</tid>
<number>a</number>take decisions on questions of policy relating to the 
administration and working of the Institute;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>4374</tid>
<number>b</number>institute courses of study at the Institute;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>352619</tid>
<number>c</number>make Statutes;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>155</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 29 of <year>1963</year>, s. 5, for" clause (c)" 
 (retrospectively).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>314413</tid>
<number>d</number>institute and appoint persons to academic as well as 
other posts in the Institute;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>450295</tid>
<number>e</number>consider and modify or cancel Ordinances;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1569194</tid>
<number>f</number>consider and pass resolutions on the annual report, the 
annual accounts and the budget estimates of the 
Institute for the next financial year as it thinks fit 
and submit them to the Council together with a 
statement of its development plans;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>566016</tid>
<number>g</number>exercise such other powers and perform such other 
duties as may be conferred or imposed upon it by this 
Act or the Statutes.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>760457</tid>
<number>3</number>The Board shall have the power to appoint such committees as 
it considers necessary for the exercise of its powers and the 
performance of its duties under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1808686</tid>
<number> 14</number> Senate. The Senate of each Institute shall consist of the 
following persons, namely:-
<section><tid>807947</tid>
<number>a</number>the Director, ex officio, who shall be the Chairman of 
the Senate;

</section>

<section><tid>1922752</tid>
<number>b</number>the Deputy Director, ex officio;

</section>

<section><tid>486083</tid>
<number>c</number>the professors appointed or recognised as such by the 
Institute for the purpose of imparting instruction in 
the Institute;

</section>

<section><tid>1520439</tid>
<number>d</number>three persons, not being employees of the Institute, to 
be nominated by the Chairman in consultation with the 
Director, from among educationists of repute, one each 
from the fields of science, engineering and humanities; 
and

</section>

<section><tid>1661657</tid>
<number>e</number>such other members of the staff as may be laid down in 
the Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1287851</tid>
<number>15</number>Functions of Senate. Subject to the provisions of this Act, 
the Statutes and the Ordinances, the Senate of an Institute shall have 
the control and general regulation, and be responsible for the 
maintenance, of standards of instruction, education and examination in 
the Institute and shall exercise such other powers and perform such 
other duties as may be conferred or imposed upon it by the Statutes.


</article>



<article><tid>1497516</tid>
<number> 16</number> Chairman of Board.
<section><tid>1242714</tid>
<number>1</number>The Chairman shall ordinarily preside  
at the meetings of the Board and at the Convocations of the Institute.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>156</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>798775</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be the duty of the Chairman to ensure that the 
decisions taken by the Board are implemented.

</section>

<section><tid>1800564</tid>
<number>3</number>The Chairman shall exercise such other powers and perform 
such other duties as may be assigned to him by this Act or the 
Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1975046</tid>
<number> 17</number> Director.
<section><tid>450897</tid>
<number>1</number>The Director of each Institute shall be  
appointed by the Council with the prior approval of the Visitor.

</section>

<section><tid>937484</tid>
<number>2</number>The Director shall be the principal academic and executive 
officer of the Institute and shall be responsible for the proper 
administration of the Institute and for the imparting of instruction 
and maintenance of discipline therein.

</section>

<section><tid>122907</tid>
<number>3</number>The Director shall submit annual reports and accounts to the 
Board.

</section>

<section><tid>989723</tid>
<number>4</number>The Director shall exercise such other powers and perform 
such other duties as may be assigned to him by this Act or the 
Statutes or Ordinances.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>54171</tid>
<number>18</number>Deputy Director. The Deputy Director of each Institute shall 
be appointed on such terms and conditions as may be laid down by the 
Statutes and shall exercise such powers and perform such duties as may 
be assigned to him by this Act or the Statutes or by the Director.


</article>



<article><tid>611039</tid>
<number> 19</number> Registrar.
<section><tid>878580</tid>
<number>1</number>The Registrar of each Institute shall be  
appointed on such terms and conditions as may be laid down by the 
Statutes and shall be the custodian of records, the common seal, the 
funds of the Institute and such other property of the Institute as the 
Board shall commit to his charge.

</section>

<section><tid>1889447</tid>
<number>2</number>The Registrar shall act as the Secretary of the Board, the 
Senate, and such committees as may be prescribed by the Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>1428727</tid>
<number>3</number>The Registrar shall be responsible to the Director for the 
proper discharge of his functions.

</section>

<section><tid>929750</tid>
<number>4</number>The Registrar shall exercise such other powers and perform 
such other duties as may be assigned to him by this Act or the 
Statutes or by the Director.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>405486</tid>
<number>20</number>Other authorities and officers. The powers and duties of 
authorities and officers other than those hereinbefore mentioned shall 
be determined by the Statutes.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>157</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1030781</tid>
<number>21</number>Grants by Central Government. For the purpose of enabling the 
Institutes to discharge their functions efficiently under this Act, 
the Central Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament 
by law in this behalf, pay to each Institute in each financial year 
such sums of money and in such manner as it may think fit.


</article>



<article><tid>1536192</tid>
<number> 22</number> Fund of the Institute.
<section><tid>41129</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Institute shall maintain a  
Fund to which shall be credited-

<subsection><tid>226401</tid>
<number>a</number>all moneys provided by the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>223840</tid>
<number>b</number>all fees and other charges received by the Institute;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1259946</tid>
<number>c</number>all moneys received by the Institute by way of grants, 
gifts, donations, benefactions, bequests or transfers; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>979725</tid>
<number>d</number>all moneys received by the Institute in any other 
manner or from any other source.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1707679</tid>
<number>2</number>All moneys credited to the Fund of any Institute shall be 
deposited in such Banks or invested in such manner as the Institute 
may, with the approval of the Central Government, decide.

</section>

<section><tid>513137</tid>
<number>3</number>The Fund of any Institute shall be applied towards meeting 
the expenses of the Institute including expenses incurred in the 
exercise of its powers and discharge of its duties under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>208958</tid>
<number> 23</number> Accounts and audit.
<section><tid>359162</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Institute shall maintain proper  
accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual statement of 
accounts, including the balance- sheet, in such form as may be 
prescribed by the Central Government in consultation with the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.

</section>

<section><tid>816651</tid>
<number>2</number>The accounts of every Institute shall be audited by the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any expenditure incurred 
by him in connection with such audit shall be payable by the Institute 
to the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.

</section>

<section><tid>954047</tid>
<number>3</number>The Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any person 
appointed by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of any 
Institute shall have the same rights, privileges and authority in 
connection with such audit as the comptroller and Auditor- General of 
India has in connection with the audit of the Government accounts, 
and, in particular, shall have the right to demand the production of 
books, accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and 
to inspect the offices of the Institute.

</section>

<section><tid>115236</tid>
<number>4</number>The accounts of every Institute as certified by the 
comptroller and Auditor- General of India or any other person appointed 
by

<pagefootnote><pagenum>158</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

him in this behalf together with the audit report thereon shall be 
forwarded annually to the Central Government and that Government shall 
cause the same to be laid before each House of Parliament.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1720499</tid>
<number> 24</number> Pension and provident fund.
<section><tid>1610476</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Institute shall  
constitute for the benefit of its employees, including the Director, 
in such manner and subject to such conditions as may be prescribed by 
the Statutes, such pension, insurance and provident funds as it may 
deem fit.

</section>

<section><tid>530074</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any such provident fund has been so constituted, the 
Central Government may declare that the provisions of the Provident 
funds Act, <year>1925</year> (19 of <year>1925</year>) shall apply to such fund as if it were a 
Government Provident Fund.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1486102</tid>
<number> 25</number> Appointments. All appointments on the staff of any Institute, 
except that of the Director, shall be made in accordance with the 
procedure laid down in the Statutes, by-
<section><tid>973104</tid>
<number>a</number>the Board, if the appointment is made on the academic 
staff in the post of Lecturer or above or if the 
appointment is made on the non- academic staff in any 
cadre the maximum of the pay- scale for which exceeds 
six hundred rupees per month;

</section>

<section><tid>1988908</tid>
<number>b</number>by the Director, in any other case.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>696289</tid>
<number> 26</number> Statutes. Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Statutes 
may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:-
<section><tid>1217416</tid>
<number>a</number>the conferment of honorary degrees;

</section>

<section><tid>141291</tid>
<number>b</number>the formation of departments of teaching;

</section>

<section><tid>1475835</tid>
<number>c</number>the fees to be charged for courses of study in the 
Institute and for admission to the examinations of 
degree and diplomas of the Institute;

</section>

<section><tid>1031898</tid>
<number>d</number>the institution of fellowships, scholarships, 
exhibitions, medals and prizes;

</section>

<section><tid>1414132</tid>
<number>e</number>the term of office and the method of appointment of 
officers of the Institute;

</section>

<section><tid>1703461</tid>
<number>f</number>the qualifications of teachers of the Institute;

</section>

<section><tid>611582</tid>
<number>g</number>the classification, the method of appointment and the 
determination of the terms and conditions of service 
of, teachers and other staff of the Institute;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>159</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>136120</tid>
<number>h</number>the constitution of pension, insurance and provident 
funds for the benefit of the officers, teachers and 
other staff of the Institute;

</section>

<section><tid>1590207</tid>
<number>i</number>the constitution, powers and duties of the authorities 
of the Institute;

</section>

<section><tid>1351349</tid>
<number>j</number>the establishment and maintenance of halls and hostels;

</section>

<section><tid>1028533</tid>
<number>k</number>the conditions of residence of students of the 
Institute and the levying of fees for residence in the 
halls and hostels and of other charges;

</section>

<section><tid>1381008</tid>
<number>l</number>the manner of filling vacancies among members of the 
Board;

</section>

<section><tid>1436081</tid>
<number>m</number>the allowances to be paid to the Chairman and members 
of the Board;

</section>

<section><tid>1408250</tid>
<number>n</number>the authentication of the orders and decisions of the 
Board;

</section>

<section><tid>959643</tid>
<number>o</number>the meetings of the Board, the Senate, or any 
Committee, the quorum at such meetings and the 
procedure to be followed in the conduct of their 
business;

</section>

<section><tid>436410</tid>
<number>p</number>any other matter which by this Act is to be or may be 
prescribed by the Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>429955</tid>
<number> 27</number> Statutes how made.
<section><tid>80415</tid>
<number>1</number>The first Statutes of each Institute  
shall be framed by the Council with the previous approval of the 
Visitor and a copy of the same shall be laid as soon as may be before 
each House of Parliament.

</section>

<section><tid>782491</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board may, from time to time, make new or additional 
Statutes or may amend or repeal the Statutes in the manner hereafter 
in this section provided.

</section>

<section><tid>1877994</tid>
<number>3</number>Every new Statute or addition to the Statutes or any 
amendment or repeal of a Statute shall require the previous approval 
of the Visitor who may assent thereto or withhold assent or remit it 
to the Board for consideration.

</section>

<section><tid>1590392</tid>
<number>4</number>A new Statute or a Statute amending or repealing an existing 
Statute shall have no validity unless it has been assented to by the 
Visitor.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>13407</tid>
<number> 28</number> Ordinances. Subject to the provisions of this Act and the 
Statutes, the Ordinances of each Institute may provide for all or any 
of the following matters, namely:-
<section><tid>1589243</tid>
<number>a</number>the admission of the students to the Institute;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>160</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1793976</tid>
<number>b</number>the courses of study to be laid down for all degrees 
and diplomas of the Institute;

</section>

<section><tid>1277805</tid>
<number>c</number>the conditions under which students shall be admitted 
to the degree or diploma courses and to the 
examinations of the Institute, and shall be eligible 
for degrees and diplomas;

</section>

<section><tid>1011574</tid>
<number>d</number>the conditions of award of the fellowships, 
scholarships, exhibitions, medals and prizes;

</section>

<section><tid>1150775</tid>
<number>e</number>the conditions and mode of appointment and duties of 
examining bodies, examiners and moderators;

</section>

<section><tid>706499</tid>
<number>f</number>the conduct of examinations;

</section>

<section><tid>284155</tid>
<number>g</number>the maintenance of discipline among the students of the 
Institute; and

</section>

<section><tid>388266</tid>
<number>h</number>any other matter which by this Act or the Statutes is 
to be or may be provided for by the Ordinances.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>789958</tid>
<number> 29</number> Ordinances how made.
<section><tid>1912710</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as otherwise provided in this  
section, Ordinances shall be made by the Senate.

</section>

<section><tid>1530001</tid>
<number>2</number>All Ordinances made by the Senate shall have effect from such 
date as it may direct, but every Ordinance so made shall be submitted, 
as soon as may be, to the Board and shall be considered by the Board 
as its next succeeding meeting.

</section>

<section><tid>512053</tid>
<number>3</number>The Board shall have power by resolution to modify or cancel 
any such Ordinance and such Ordinance shall from the date of such 
resolution stand modified accordingly or cancelled, as the case may 
be.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>560639</tid>
<number> 30</number> Tribunal of Arbitration.
<section><tid>1514170</tid>
<number>1</number>Any dispute arising out of a  
contract between an Institute and any of its employees shall, at the 
request of the employee concerned or at the instance of the Institute, 
be referred to a Tribunal of Arbitration consisting of one member 
appointed by the Institute, one member nominated by the employee, and 
an umpire appointed by the Visitor.

</section>

<section><tid>1011262</tid>
<number>2</number>The decision of the Tribunal shall be final and shall not be 
questioned in any court.

</section>

<section><tid>1597504</tid>
<number>3</number>No suit or proceeding shall lie in any court in respect of 
any matter which is required by sub- section (1) to be referred to the 
Tribunal of Arbitration.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>161</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1689791</tid>
<number>4</number>Tribunal of Arbitration shall have power to regulate its own 
procedure.

</section>

<section><tid>687084</tid>
<number>5</number>Nothing in any law for the time being in force relating to 
arbitration shall apply to arbitrations under this section.
CHAP

THE COUNCIL

CHAPTER III

THE COUNCIL




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>174185</tid>
<number> 31</number> Establishment of Council.
<section><tid>1300354</tid>
<number>1</number>With effect from such date as  
the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
specify in this behalf, there shall be established a central body to 
be called the Council.

</section>

<section><tid>1840784</tid>
<number>2</number>The Council shall consist of the following members, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1706301</tid>
<number>a</number>the Minister in charge of technical education in the 
Central Government, ex officio, as Chairman;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1630577</tid>
<number>b</number>the Chairman of each Institute, ex officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1185734</tid>
<number>c</number>the Director of each Institute, ex officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>921218</tid>
<number>d</number>the Chairman, University Grants Commission, ex officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1153699</tid>
<number>e</number>the Director- General, Council of Scientific and 
Industrial Research, ex officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1172315</tid>
<number>f</number>the Chairman of the Council of the Indian Institute of 
Science, Bangalore, ex officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>102348</tid>
<number>g</number>the director of the Indian Institute of Science, 
Bangalore, ex officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1168549</tid>
<number>h</number>three persons to be nominated by the Central 
Government, one to represent the Ministry concerned 
with technical education, another to represent the 
Ministry of Finance and the third to represent any 
other Ministry;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>177911</tid>
<number>i</number>one person to be nominated by the All- India Council for 
Technical Education;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>911165</tid>
<number>j</number>not less than three, but not more than five, persons to 
be nominated by the Visitor, who shall be persons 
having special knowledge or practical experience in 
respect of education, industry, science or technology;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>238417</tid>
<number>k</number>three Members of Parliament, of whom two shall be 
elected by the House of the People from among its 
members and one by the Council of States from among its 
members.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>162</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>910505</tid>
<number>3</number>An officer of the Ministry of the Central Government 
concerned with technical education shall be nominated by that 
Government to act as the Secretary of the Council.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1888921</tid>
<number> 32</number> Term of office of, vacancies among, and allowances payable 
to, members of Council.
<section><tid>1927335</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as otherwise provided in this  
section, the term of office of a member of the Council shall be three 
years from the date of his nomination or election, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>159801</tid>
<number>2</number>The term of office of an ex officio member shall continue so 
long as he holds the office by virtue of which he is a member.

</section>

<section><tid>1117037</tid>
<number>3</number>A member of the Council referred to in clause (h) of sub- 
section (2) of section 31 shall hold office during the pleasure of the 
Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1094461</tid>
<number>4</number>The term of office of a member elected under clause (k) of 
sub- section (2) of section 31 shall expire as soon as he ceases to be 
a member of the House which elected him.

</section>

<section><tid>1463267</tid>
<number>5</number>The term of officer of a member nominated or elected to fill 
a casual vacancy shall continue for the remainder of the term of the 
member in whose place he has been nominated or elected.

</section>

<section><tid>1363611</tid>
<number>6</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this section an 
outgoing member shall, unless the Central Government otherwise 
directs, continue in office until another person is nominated or 
elected as a member in his place.

</section>

<section><tid>1337612</tid>
<number>7</number>The members of the Council shall be paid such travelling and 
other allowances by the Central Government as may be determined by 
that Government, but no member shall be entitled to any salary by 
reason of this sub- section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>670203</tid>
<number> 33</number> Functions of Council.
<section><tid>38112</tid>
<number>1</number>It shall be the general duty of the  
Council to co- ordinate the activities of all the Institutes.

</section>

<section><tid>1269506</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the provisions of sub- section (1), the 
Council shall perform the following functions, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1610741</tid>
<number>a</number>to advise on matters relating to the duration of the 
courses, the degrees and other academic distinctions to 
be conferred by the Institutes, admission standards and 
other academic matters;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1007204</tid>
<number>b</number>to lay down policy regarding cadres, methods of 
recruitment and conditions of service of employees, 
institution of scholarships and freeships, levying of 
fees and other matters of common interest;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>163</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>144199</tid>
<number>c</number>to examine the development plans of each Institute and 
to approve such of them as are considered necessary and 
also to indicate broadly the financial implications of 
such approved plans;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>394460</tid>
<number>d</number>to examine the annual budget estimates of each 
Institute and to recommend to the Central Government 
the allocation of funds for that purpose;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1816114</tid>
<number>e</number>to advise the Visitor, if so required, in respect of 
any function to be performed by him under this Act; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>564316</tid>
<number>f</number>to perform such other functions as are assigned to it 
by or under this Act.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>404032</tid>
<number> 34</number> Chairman of Council.
<section><tid>1424575</tid>
<number>1</number>The Chairman of the Council shall  
ordinarily preside at the meetings of the Council.

</section>

<section><tid>510787</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be the duty of the Chairman of the Council to ensure 
that the decisions taken by the Council are implemented.

</section>

<section><tid>1800932</tid>
<number>3</number>The Chairman shall exercise such other powers and perform 
such other duties as are assigned to him by this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1400995</tid>
<number> 35</number> Power to make rules in respect of matters in this Chapter.

<section><tid>875858</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> by notification in the Official  
Gazette,] make rules to carry out the purposes of this Chapter.

</section>

<section><tid>80318</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1572254</tid>
<number>a</number>the manner of filling vacancies among the members of 
the Council;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1368091</tid>
<number>b</number>the disqualifications for being chosen as, and for 
being, a member of the Council;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>776452</tid>
<number>c</number>the circumstances in which, and the authority by which, 
members may be removed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1860124</tid>
<number>d</number>the meetings of the Council and the procedure of 
conducting business thereat;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>514080</tid>
<number>e</number>the travelling and other allowances payable to members 
of the Council; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1823277</tid>
<number>f</number>the functions of the council and the manner in which 
such functions may be exercised.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>87655</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Every rule made by the Central Government under this 
Chapter shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each 
House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of 
thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule."]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>164</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 4 of <year>1986</year>, s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 15. 5. <year>1986</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER IV

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1500758</tid>
<number> 36</number> Acts and proceedings not to be invalidated by vacancies, etc. 
No act of the Council, or any Institute or Board or Senate or any 
other body set up under this Act or the Statutes, shall be invalid 
merely by reason of-
<section><tid>764592</tid>
<number>a</number>any vacancy in, or defect in the constitution thereof, 
or

</section>

<section><tid>1484804</tid>
<number>b</number>any defect in the election, nomination or appointment 
of a person acting as a member thereof, or

</section>

<section><tid>1209170</tid>
<number>c</number>any irregularity in its procedure not affecting the 
merits of the case.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>532095</tid>
<number>37</number>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in 
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such provision 
or give such direction not inconsistent with the purposes of this Act, 
as appears to it to be necessary or expedient for removing the 
difficulty.


</article>



<article><tid>815310</tid>
<number> 38</number> Transitional provisions. Notwithstanding anything contained 
in this Act,-
<section><tid>138877</tid>
<number>a</number>the Board of Governors of an Institute functioning as 
such immediately before the commencement of this Act 
shall continue to so function until a new Board is 
constituted for that Institute under this Act, but on 
the constitution of a new Board under this Act, the 
members of the Board holding office before such 
constitution shall cease to hold office:

</section>

<section><tid>931840</tid>
<number>b</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Staff Committee constituted in relation to the 
College of Engineering and Technology, Delhi and any 
Academic Council constituted in relation to any other 
Institute] before the commencement of this Act shall be 
deemed to be the Senate constituted under this Act 
until a Senate is constituted under this Act for that 
Institute;

</section>

<section><tid>1550045</tid>
<number>c</number>until the first Statutes and the Ordinances are made 
under this Act, the Statutes and Ordinances of the 
Indian Institute of Technology, Kharagpur as in force 
immediately before the commencement of this Act shall 
continue to apply to that Institute and shall, with the 
necessary modifications and adaptations, also apply to 
any other Institute, in so far as they are not 
inconsistent with the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>185425</tid>
<number>d</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> until the first Statutes and the Ordinances in relation 
to the Indian Institute of Technology, Guwahati are made under this 
Act, the Statutes and Ordinances of the indian Institute of Techno- 
logy, Kharagpur as in force immediately before the commencement of 
the Institutes of Technology (Amendment) Act, <year>1994</year> shall apply to the 
Indian Institute of Technology, Guwahati with the necessary modifi- 
cation and adaptations in so far as they are not inconsistent with 
the provisions of this Act.
Explanation-- The reference in clause (a) of this section to the 
commencement off this Act shall be construed in relation to the Indian 
Institute of Technology, Guwahati as the reference to the date on 
which the provisions of the Instittutes of Technology (Amendment) Act, 
 <year>1994</year> come into force."]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>165</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 29 of <year>1963</year>, s. 6, for certain words (w. e. f 13- 9-  
  <year>1963</year>). 
2. Added by Act 35 of <year>1994</year>, s. 6 (w. e. f. 1- 9- <year>1994</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>318844</tid>
<number> 39</number> Repeal an savings.
<section><tid>876259</tid>
<number>1</number>The Indian Institute of Technology  
 (Kharagpur) Act, <year>1956</year> (5 of <year>1956</year>) is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>607306</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, the provisions of the said Act 
set out in the Schedule shall continue to have effect:
Provided that in the said provisions, the expression" this Act" 
means the said provisions.

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1087446</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>361303</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Institutes of Technology Act, <year>1961</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1287681</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Govern- 
ment may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint, and 
different dates may be appointed for different provisions of this Act,



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>684814</tid>
<number>2</number>Declaration of certain institutions as institution 5 of 
national importance. Whereas the objects of the institutions known as 
the Indian Institute of Technology, Bombay, the Indian Institute of 
Technology, Kanpur and the Indian Institute of Technology, Madras are 
such as to make them institutions of national importance, it is hereby 
declared that each such institution is an institution of national 
importance.


</article>



<article><tid>1038979</tid>
<number> 3</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>75607</tid>
<number>a</number>" Board", in relation to any Institute, means the Board 
of Governors thereof;

</section>

<section><tid>1035068</tid>
<number>b</number>" Chairman" means the Chairman of the Board;

</section>

<section><tid>1937242</tid>
<number>c</number>" corresponding Institute" means,-

<subsection><tid>592292</tid>
<number>i</number>in relation to the society known as the Indian Insti- 
tute of Technology, Bombay, the Indian Institute of 
Technology, Bombay;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>582</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>999999</number>  1- 4- <year>1962</year>, vide Notifn. No. S. O. 926, dated 23- 3- <year>1962</year>. Gazette of India, 
Part. II, Sec. 3 (ii), p. 867.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>68230</tid>
<number>ii</number>in relation to the society known as the Indian Insti- 
tute of Technology (Kanpur) Society, the Indian Institute of 
Technology, Kanpur, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>110524</tid>
<number>iii</number>in relation to the society known as the Indian Insti- 
tute of Technology, Madras, the Indian Institute of Techno- 
logy, Madras;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>194729</tid>
<number>d</number>" Council" means the Council established under sub- 
section (1) of section 31;

</section>

<section><tid>998950</tid>
<number>e</number>" Deputy Director", in relation to any Institute, means 
the Deputy Director thereof;

</section>

<section><tid>711905</tid>
<number>f</number>" Director", in relation to any Institute, means the 
Director thereof;

</section>

<section><tid>1440959</tid>
<number>g</number>" Institute" means any of the Institutions mentioned in 
section 2 and includes the Indian Institute of Technology, 
Kharagpur, incorporated under the Indian Institute of 
Technology (Kharagpur) Act, <year>1956</year>; (5 of <year>1956</year>.)

</section>

<section><tid>1257474</tid>
<number>h</number>" Registrar", in relation to any Institute, means the 
Registrar thereof;

</section>

<section><tid>1095355</tid>
<number>i</number>" Senate", in relation to any Institute- means the 
Senate thereof;

</section>

<section><tid>917750</tid>
<number>j</number>" society" means any of the following societies 
registered under the Societies Registration Act, <year>1860</year>, (21 of  
  <year>1860</year>.) namely:-

<subsection><tid>100109</tid>
<number>i</number>the Indian Institute of Technology, Bombay;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>28805</tid>
<number>ii</number>the Indian Institute of Technology (Kanpur) Society;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1646384</tid>
<number>iii</number>the Indian Institute of Technology, Madras;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>241906</tid>
<number>k</number>" Statutes" and" Ordinances", in relation to any 
Institute, mean the Statutes and Ordinances of the Institute 
made under this Act.
CHAP

THE INSTITUTES

CHAPTER II

THE INSTITUTES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1585254</tid>
<number> 4</number> Incorporation of institutes.
<section><tid>27249</tid>
<number>1</number>Each of the Institutes  
mentioned in section 2 shall be a body corporate having perpetual 
succession and a common seal and shall, by its name, sue and be sued.

</section>

<section><tid>1068450</tid>
<number>2</number>The body corporate constituting each of the said Institutes 
shall consist of a Chairman, a Director and other members of the Board 
fox the time being of the Institute.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>583</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>950871</tid>
<number> 5</number> Effect of incorporation of institutes. On and from the 
commencement of this Act,-
<section><tid>1977420</tid>
<number>a</number>any reference to a society in any law (other than this  
  Act) or in any contract or other instrument shall be deemed 
as a reference to the corresponding Institute;

</section>

<section><tid>305587</tid>
<number>b</number>all property, movable and immovable, of or belonging to 
a society shall vest in the corresponding Institute;

</section>

<section><tid>1240776</tid>
<number>c</number>all the rights and liabilities of a society shall be 
trans" erred to, and be the rights and liabilities of, the 
corresponding Institute; and

</section>

<section><tid>194200</tid>
<number>d</number>every person employed by a society immediately before 
such commencement shall hold his office or service in the 
corresponding Institute by the same tenure, at the same 
remuneration and upon the same terms and conditions and with 
the same rights and privileges as to pension, leave, 
gratuity, provident fund and other matters as he would have 
held the same if this Act had not been passed, and shall 
continue to do so unless and until his employment is 
terminated or until such tenure, remuneration and terms and 
conditions are duly altered by the, Statutes:
Provided that if the alteration so made is not acceptable to such 
employee, his employment may be terminated by the Institute in 
accordance with the terms of the contract with the employee or, if no 
provision is made therein in this behalf, on payment to him by the 
Institute of compensation equivalent to three months' remuneration in 
the case of permanent employees and one month' s remuneration in the 
case of other employees.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>191382</tid>
<number> 6</number> Powers of Institutes.
<section><tid>1768678</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of this  
Act, every Institute shall exercise the following powers and Perform 
the following duties, namely:-

<subsection><tid>186207</tid>
<number>a</number>to provide for instruction and research in such 
branches of engineering and technology, sciences and arts, as 
the Institute may think fit, and for the advancement of 
learning and dissemination of knowledge in such branches;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>771749</tid>
<number>b</number>to hold examinations and grant degrees, diplomas and 
other academic distinctions or titles;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>151089</tid>
<number>c</number>to confer honorary degrees or other distinctions;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>700874</tid>
<number>d</number>to fix, demand and receive fees and other charges;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1645454</tid>
<number>e</number>to establish, maintain and manage halls and hostels for 
the residence of students;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>584</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1353305</tid>
<number>f</number>to supervise and control the residence and regulate the, 
discipline of students of the Institute and to make 
arrangements for promoting their health, general welfare and 
cultural and corporate life;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>61652</tid>
<number>g</number>to provide for the maintenance of units of the National 
Cadet Corps for the students of the Institute;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1951025</tid>
<number>h</number>to institute academic and other posts and to make 
appointments thereto (except in the case of the Director);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1869311</tid>
<number>i</number>to frame Statutes and Ordinances and to alter, modify 
or 
rescind the same;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1729415</tid>
<number>j</number>to deal. with any property belonging to or vested in 
the 
Institute in such manner as the Institute may deem fit for 
advancing the objects of the Institute;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1479762</tid>
<number>k</number>to receive gifts, grants, donations or benefactions 
from the Government and to receive bequests, donations and 
transfers of movable or immovable properties from testators, 
donors or transferors, as the case may be;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>260299</tid>
<number>l</number>to co- operate with educational or other institutions in 
any part of the world having objects wholly or partly similar 
to those of the Institute by exchange of teachers and 
scholars and generally in such manner as may be conducive to 
their common objects;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>966908</tid>
<number>m</number>to institute and award fellowships, scholarships, 
exhibitions, prizes and medals; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>615265</tid>
<number>n</number>to do all such things as may be necessary, incidental 
or conducive to the attainment of all or any of the objects 
of the Institute.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>738151</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), an 
Institute shall not dispose of in any manner any immovable property 
without the prior approval of the Visitor.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>314217</tid>
<number> 7</number> Institutes to be open to all races, creeds and classes.
<section><tid>778106</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Every Institute shall be open to persons of either sex and of whatever 
race, creed, caste or class, and no test or condition shall be imposed 
as to religious belief or profession in admitting or appointing 
members, students, teachers or workers or in any other connection 
whatsoever.

</section>

<section><tid>721769</tid>
<number>2</number>No bequest, donation or transfer of any property shall be 
accepted by any Institute which in the opinion of the Council involves 
conditions or obligations opposed to the spirit and object of this 
section.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>585</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1388525</tid>
<number>8</number>Teaching at Institute. All teaching at each of the Institutes 
shall be conducted by or in the name of the Institute in accordance 
with the Statutes and Ordinances made in this behalf.


</article>



<article><tid>1104256</tid>
<number> 9</number> Visitor.
<section><tid>1051427</tid>
<number>1</number>The President of India shall be the Visitor of  
every Institute.

</section>

<section><tid>471818</tid>
<number>2</number>The Visitor may appoint one or more persons to review the 
work and progress of any Institute and to hold inquiries into the 
affairs, thereof and to report thereon in such manner as the Visitor 
may direct.

</section>

<section><tid>1996522</tid>
<number>3</number>Upon receipt of any such report, the Visitor may take such 
action and issue such directions as he considers necessary in respect 
of any of the matters dealt with in the report and the Institute shall 
be bound to comply with such directions.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>576365</tid>
<number> 10</number> Authorities of Institutes. The following shall be the 
authorities of an Institute, namely:
<section><tid>548048</tid>
<number>a</number>a Board of Governors;

</section>

<section><tid>1500227</tid>
<number>b</number>a Senate; and

</section>

<section><tid>1447549</tid>
<number>c</number>such other authorities as may be declared by the 
Statutes to be the authorities of the Institute.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1073145</tid>
<number> 11</number> Board of Governors. The Board of an Institute shall consist 
of the following persons, namely:-
<section><tid>999690</tid>
<number>a</number>the Chairman, to be nominated by the Visitor;

</section>

<section><tid>252175</tid>
<number>b</number>the Director, ex officio;

</section>

<section><tid>743977</tid>
<number>c</number>one person to be nominated by the Government of each of 
the States comprising the zone in which the Institute is 
situated, from among persons who, in the opinion of that 
Government, are technologists or industrialists of repute;

</section>

<section><tid>1500003</tid>
<number>d</number>four persons having special knowledge or practical 
experience in respect of education, engineering or science, 
to be nominated by the Council; and

</section>

<section><tid>489793</tid>
<number>e</number>two professors of the Institute, to be nominated by the 
Senate.
Explanation.- In this section, the expression" zone" means a zone 
as, for the time being demarcated by the All- India Council for Techni- 
cal' Education for the purposes of this Act.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>586</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1585216</tid>
<number> 12</number> Term of office of, vacancies among, and allowances payable to, 
members of Board.
<section><tid>1995890</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as otherwise provided in this section,  
the term of office of the Chairman or any other member of the 
Board shall be three years from the date of his nomination.

</section>

<section><tid>56091</tid>
<number>2</number>The term of office of an ex officio member shall continue so 
long as he holds the office by virtue of which he is a member.

</section>

<section><tid>23574</tid>
<number>3</number>The term of office of a member nominated under clause (c) of 
section 11 shall be two years from the 1st day of January of the year 
in which he is nominated.

</section>

<section><tid>125968</tid>
<number>4</number>The term of office of a member nominated to fill a casual 
vacancy shall continue for the remainder of the term of the member in 
whose place he has been nominated.

</section>

<section><tid>62022</tid>
<number>5</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, an out- 
going member shall, unless the Council otherwise directs, continue in 
office until another person is nominated as a member in his place.

</section>

<section><tid>240919</tid>
<number>6</number>The members of the Board shall be entitled to such allow- 
ances, if any, from the Institute as may be provided for in the 
Statutes but no member other than the persons referred to in clauses 
 (b) and (e) of section 11 shall be entitled to any salary by reason of 
this sub- section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>974355</tid>
<number> 13</number> Functions of Board.
<section><tid>736870</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of this  
Act, the Board of any Institute shall be responsible for the general 
superintendence, direction and control of the affairs of the Institute 
and shall exercise all the powers of the Institute not otherwise 
provided for by this Act, the Statutes and the Ordinances, and shall 
have the power to review the acts of the Senate.

</section>

<section><tid>1510481</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the provisions of sub- section (1), the 
Board of any Institute shall-

<subsection><tid>1678312</tid>
<number>a</number>take decisions on questions of policy relating to the 
administration and working of the Institute;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>4374</tid>
<number>b</number>institute courses of study at the Institute;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>352619</tid>
<number>c</number>make Statutes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>314413</tid>
<number>d</number>institute and appoint persons to academic as well as 
other posts in the Institute;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>450295</tid>
<number>e</number>consider and modify or cancel Ordinances;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1569194</tid>
<number>f</number>consider and pass resolutions on the annual report, the 
annual accounts and the budget estimates of the Institute 
for the next financial year as it thinks fit and submit them 
to the Council together with a statement of its development 
plans-,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>587</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>566016</tid>
<number>g</number>exercise such other powers and perform such other 
duties as may be conferred or imposed upon it by this Act or 
the Statutes.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>760457</tid>
<number>3</number>The Board shall have the power to appoint such committees an 
it considers necessary for the exercise of its powers and the per- 
formance of its duties under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1808686</tid>
<number> 14</number> Senate. The Senate of each Institute shall consist of the 
following persons, namely:
<section><tid>807947</tid>
<number>a</number>the Director, ex officio, who shall be the Chairman of 
the Senate,'

</section>

<section><tid>1922752</tid>
<number>b</number>the Deputy Director, ex officio;

</section>

<section><tid>486083</tid>
<number>c</number>the professors appointed or recognised as such by the 
Institute for the purpose of imparting instruction in the 
Institute;

</section>

<section><tid>1520439</tid>
<number>d</number>three persons, not being employees of the Institute, to 
be nominated by the Chairman in consultation with the 
Director, from among educationists of repute, one each from 
the fields of science, engineering and humanities; and

</section>

<section><tid>1661657</tid>
<number>e</number>such other members of the staff as may be laid down in 
the Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1287851</tid>
<number>15</number>Functions of Senate. Subject to the provisions of this Act, 
the Statutes and the Ordinances, the Senate of an Institute shall have 
the control and general regulation, and be responsible for the 
maintenance, of standards of instruction, education and examination in 
the Institute and shall exercise such other powers and perform such 
other duties as may be conferred or imposed upon it by the Statutes.


</article>



<article><tid>1497516</tid>
<number> 16</number> Chairman of Board.
<section><tid>1242714</tid>
<number>1</number>The Chairman shall ordinarily preside  
at the meetings of the Board and at the Convocations of the Institute.

</section>

<section><tid>798775</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be the duty of the Chairman to ensure that the 
decisions taken by the Board are implemented.

</section>

<section><tid>1800564</tid>
<number>3</number>The Chairman shall exercise such other powers and perform 
such other duties as may be assigned to him by this Act or the 
Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1975046</tid>
<number> 17</number> Director.
<section><tid>450897</tid>
<number>1</number>The Director of each Institute shall be  
appointed by the Council with the prior approval of the Visitor.

</section>

<section><tid>937484</tid>
<number>2</number>The Director shall be the principal academic and executive 
officer of the Institute and shall be responsible for the proper 
administration of the Institute and, for the imparting of instruction 
and maintenance of discipline therein.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>588</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>122907</tid>
<number>3</number>The Director shall submit annual reports and accounts to the 
Board.

</section>

<section><tid>989723</tid>
<number>4</number>The Director shall exercise such other powers and perform 
such other duties as may be assigned to him by this Act or the Sta- 
tutes or Ordinances.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>54171</tid>
<number>18</number>Deputy Director. The Deputy Director of each Institute shall 
be appointed on such terms and conditions as may be laid down by the 
Statutes and shall exercise such powers and perform such duties as may 
be assigned to him by this Act or the Statutes or by the Director.


</article>



<article><tid>611039</tid>
<number> 19</number> Registrar.
<section><tid>878580</tid>
<number>1</number>The Registrar of each Institute shall be  
appointed on such terms and conditions as may be laid down by the 
Statutes and shall be the custodian of records, the common seal, the 
funds of the Institute and such other property of the Institute as the 
Board shall commit to his charge.

</section>

<section><tid>1889447</tid>
<number>2</number>The Registrar shall act as the Secretary of the Board, the 
Senate, and such committees as may be prescribed by the Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>1428727</tid>
<number>3</number>The Registrar shall be responsible to the Director for the 
proper discharge of his functions.

</section>

<section><tid>929750</tid>
<number>4</number>The Registrar shall exercise such other powers and perform 
such other duties as may be assigned to him by this Act or the 
Statutes or by the Director.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>405486</tid>
<number>20</number>Other authorities and officers. The powers and duties of 
authorities and officers other than those hereinbefore mentioned shall 
be determined by the Statutes.


</article>



<article><tid>1030781</tid>
<number>21</number>Grants by Central Government. For the purpose of enabling the 
Institutes to discharge their functions efficiently under this Act, 
the Central Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament 
by law in this behalf, pay to each Institute in each financial year 
such sums of money and in such manner as it may think fit.


</article>



<article><tid>1536192</tid>
<number> 22</number> Fund of the Institute.
<section><tid>41129</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Institute shall maintain a  
Fund to which shall be credited-

<subsection><tid>226401</tid>
<number>a</number>all moneys provided by the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>223840</tid>
<number>b</number>all fees and other charges received by the Institute;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1259946</tid>
<number>c</number>all moneys received by the Institute by way of grants, 
gifts, donations, benefactions, bequests or transfers; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>979725</tid>
<number>d</number>all moneys received by the Institute in any other 
manner or from any other source.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1707679</tid>
<number>2</number>All moneys credited to the Fund of any Institute shall be 
deposited in such Banks or invested in such manner as the Institute 
may, with the approval of the Central Government, decide.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>589</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>513137</tid>
<number>3</number>The Fund of any Institute shall be applied towards meeting 
the expenses of the Institute including expenses incurred in the 
exercise of its powers and discharge of its duties under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>208958</tid>
<number> 23</number> Accounts and audit.
<section><tid>359162</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Institute shall maintain proper  
accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual statement of 
accounts, including the balance- sheet, in such form as may be 
prescribed by the Central Government in consultation with the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.

</section>

<section><tid>816651</tid>
<number>2</number>The accounts of every Institute shall be audited by the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any expenditure incurred 
by him in connection with such audit shall be payable by the Institute 
to the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.

</section>

<section><tid>954047</tid>
<number>3</number>The Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any person 
appointed by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of any 
Institute shall have the same rights, privileges and authority in 
connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor- General of 
India has in connection with the audit of the Government accounts, 
and, in particular, shall have the right to demand the Production of 
books, accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and 
to inspect the offices of the Institute.

</section>

<section><tid>115236</tid>
<number>4</number>The accounts of every Institute as certified by the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General of India or any other person appointed 
by him in this behalf together with the audit report thereon shall be 
forwarded annually to the Central Government and that Government shall 
cause the same to be laid before each House of Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1720499</tid>
<number> 24</number> Pension and provident fund.
<section><tid>1610476</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Institute shall  
constitute for the benefit of its employees, including the Director, 
in such manner and subject to such conditions as may be prescribed by 
the Statutes, such pension, insurance and provident funds as it may 
deem fit.

</section>

<section><tid>530074</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any such provident fund has been so constituted, the 
Central Government may declare that the provisions of the Provident 
Funds Act, <year>1925</year> (19 of <year>1925</year>.) shall apply to such fund as if it were a 
Government Provident Fund.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1486102</tid>
<number> 25</number> Appointments. All appointments on the staff of any Institute, 
except that, of the Director, shall be made in accordance with the 
procedure laid down in the Statutes, by-
<section><tid>973104</tid>
<number>a</number>the Board, if the appointment is made on the academic 
staff in the post of Lecturer or above or if the appointment 
is

<pagefootnote><pagenum>590</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

' made on the non- academic staff in any cadre the maximum of 
the pay- scale for which exceeds six hundred rupees per month;


</section>

<section><tid>1988908</tid>
<number>b</number>by the Director,- in any other case.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>696289</tid>
<number> 26</number> Statutes. Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Statutes 
may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:-
<section><tid>1217416</tid>
<number>a</number>the conferment of honorary degrees;

</section>

<section><tid>141291</tid>
<number>b</number>the formation of departments of teaching;

</section>

<section><tid>1475835</tid>
<number>c</number>the fees to be charged for courses of study in the 
Institute and for admission to the examinations of degree and 
diplomas of the Institute;

</section>

<section><tid>1031898</tid>
<number>d</number>the institution of fellowships, scholarships, 
exhibitions, medals and prizes;

</section>

<section><tid>1414132</tid>
<number>e</number>the term of office and the method of appointment of 
officers of the Institute;

</section>

<section><tid>1703461</tid>
<number>f</number>the qualifications of teachers of the Institute;

</section>

<section><tid>611582</tid>
<number>g</number>the classification, the method of appointment and the 
determination of the terms and conditions of service of, 
teachers and other staff of the Institute;

</section>

<section><tid>136120</tid>
<number>h</number>the constitution of pension, Insurance and provident 
funds for the benefit of the officers, teachers and other 
staff of the Institute;

</section>

<section><tid>1590207</tid>
<number>i</number>the constitution, powers and duties of the authorities of 
the Institute;

</section>

<section><tid>1351349</tid>
<number>j</number>the establishment and maintenance of halls and hostels;

</section>

<section><tid>1028533</tid>
<number>k</number>the conditions of residence of students of the 
Institute and the levying of fees for residence in the halls 
and hostels and of other charges;

</section>

<section><tid>1381008</tid>
<number>l</number>the manner of filling vacancies among members of the 
Board;

</section>

<section><tid>1436081</tid>
<number>m</number>the allowances to be paid to the Chairman and members 
of the Board;

</section>

<section><tid>1408250</tid>
<number>n</number>the authentication of the orders and decisions of the 
Board;

</section>

<section><tid>959643</tid>
<number>o</number>the meetings of the Board, the Senate, or any Com- 
mittee, the quorum aft such meetings and the procedure to be 
followed in the conduct of their business;

</section>

<section><tid>436410</tid>
<number>p</number>any other matter which by this Act is to be or may be 
prescribed by the Statutes.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>591</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>429955</tid>
<number> 27</number> Statutes how made.
<section><tid>80415</tid>
<number>1</number>The first Statutes of each Institute  
shall be framed by the Council with the previous approval of the 
Visitor and a copy of the same shall be laid as soon as may be before 
each House of Parliament.

</section>

<section><tid>782491</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board may, from time to time, make new or additional 
Statutes or may amend or repeal the Statutes in the manner hereafter 
in this section provided.

</section>

<section><tid>1877994</tid>
<number>3</number>Every new Statute or addition to the Statutes or any amend- 
ment or repeal of a Statute shall require the previous approval of the 
Visitor who may assent thereto or withhold assent or remit it to the 
Board for consideration.

</section>

<section><tid>1590392</tid>
<number>4</number>A new Statute or a Statute amending or repealing an existing 
Statute shall have no validity unless it has been assented to by the 
Visitor.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>13407</tid>
<number> 28</number> Ordinances. Subject to the provisions of this Act and the 
Statutes, the Ordinances of each Institute may provide for all or any 
of the following matters, namely:-
<section><tid>1589243</tid>
<number>a</number>the admission of the students to the Institute;

</section>

<section><tid>1793976</tid>
<number>b</number>the courses of study to be laid down for all degrees 
and diplomas of the Institute;

</section>

<section><tid>1277805</tid>
<number>c</number>the conditions under which students shall be admitted to 
the degree or diploma courses and to the examinations of the 
Institute, and shall be eligible for degrees and diplomas;

</section>

<section><tid>1011574</tid>
<number>d</number>the conditions of award of the fellowships, 
scholarships, exhibitions, medals and prizes;

</section>

<section><tid>1150775</tid>
<number>e</number>the conditions and mode of appointment and duties of 
examining bodies, examiners and moderators;

</section>

<section><tid>706499</tid>
<number>f</number>the conduct of examinations;

</section>

<section><tid>284155</tid>
<number>g</number>the maintenance of discipline among the students of the 
Institute; and

</section>

<section><tid>388266</tid>
<number>h</number>any other matter which by this Act or the Statutes is 
to be or may be provided for by the Ordinances.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>789958</tid>
<number> 29</number> Ordinances how made.
<section><tid>1912710</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as otherwise provided in this  
section, Ordinances shall be made by the Senate.

</section>

<section><tid>1530001</tid>
<number>2</number>All Ordinances made by the Senate shall have effect from 
such date as it may direct, but every Ordinance so made shall be 
submitted as soon as may be, to the Board and shall be considered by 
the Board at its next succeeding meeting.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>592</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>512053</tid>
<number>3</number>The Board shall have power by resolution to modify or cancel 
any such Ordinance and such- Ordinance shall from the date of such 
resolution stand modified accordingly or cancelled, as the case may 
be.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>560639</tid>
<number> 30</number> Tribunal of Arbitration.
<section><tid>1514170</tid>
<number>1</number>Any dispute arising out of a  
contract between an Institute and any of its employees shall, at the 
request of the employee concerned or at the instance of the Institute, 
be referred to a Tribunal of Arbitration consisting of one member 
appointed by the Institute, one member nominated by the employee, and 
an umpire appointed by the Visitor.

</section>

<section><tid>1011262</tid>
<number>2</number>The decision of the Tribunal shall be final and shall not be 
questioned in any court.

</section>

<section><tid>1597504</tid>
<number>3</number>No suit or proceeding shall lie in any court in respect of 
any matter which is required by sub- section (1) to be referred to the 
Tribunal of Arbitration.

</section>

<section><tid>1689791</tid>
<number>4</number>The Tribunal of Arbitration shall have power to, regulate 
its own procedure.

</section>

<section><tid>687084</tid>
<number>5</number>Nothing in any law for the time being in force relating to 
arbitration shall apply to arbitrations under this section.
CHAP

THE COUNCIL

CHAPTER III

THE COUNCIL




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>174185</tid>
<number> 31</number> Establishment of Council.
<section><tid>1300354</tid>
<number>1</number>With effect from such date as  
the Central Government, may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
specify in this behalf, there shall be established a central body to 
be called the Council.

</section>

<section><tid>1840784</tid>
<number>2</number>The Council shall consist of the following members, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1706301</tid>
<number>a</number>the Minister in charge of technical education in the 
Central Government, ex officio, as Chairman;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1630577</tid>
<number>b</number>the Chairman of each Institute, ex officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1185734</tid>
<number>c</number>the Director of each Institute, ex officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>921218</tid>
<number>d</number>the Chairman, University Grants Commission, ex officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1153699</tid>
<number>e</number>the Director- General, Council of Scientific and Indus- 
trial Research, ex officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1172315</tid>
<number>f</number>the Chairman of the Council of the Indian Institute of 
Science, Bangalore ex officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>102348</tid>
<number>g</number>the Direct or of the Indian Institute of Science, 
Bangalore, ex officio;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>593</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1168549</tid>
<number>h</number>three persons to be nominated by the Central 
Government, one to represent the Ministry concerned with 
technical education, another to represent the Ministry of 
Finance and the third th represent any other Ministry;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>177911</tid>
<number>i</number>one person to be nominated by the All- India Council for 
Technical Education-

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>911165</tid>
<number>j</number>not less than three, but not more than five, persons to 
be, nominated by the Visitor, who shall be persons having 
special knowledge or practical experience in respect of 
education', industry, science or technology;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>238417</tid>
<number>k</number>three Members of Parliament, of whom two shall be 
elected by the House of the People from among its members and 
one by the Council of States from among its members.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>910505</tid>
<number>3</number>An officer of the Ministry of the Central Government con- 
cerned with technical education shall be nominated by that Government 
to act as the Secretary of the Council.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1888921</tid>
<number> 32</number> Term of office of, vacancies among, and allowances payable 
to, members of Council.
<section><tid>1927335</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as otherwise provided in this  
section, the term of 
office of a member of the Council shall be three years from the date 
of his nomination or election, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>159801</tid>
<number>2</number>The term of office of an ex officio member shall continue so 
long as he holds the office by virtue of which he is a member.

</section>

<section><tid>1117037</tid>
<number>3</number>A member of the Council referred to in clause (h) of sub- 
section (2) of section 31 shall hold office during the pleasure of 
the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1094461</tid>
<number>4</number>The term of office of a member elected under clause (k) 
of subsection (2) of section 31 shall expire as soon as he ceases to 
be a member of the House which elected him.

</section>

<section><tid>1463267</tid>
<number>5</number>The term of office of a member nominated or elected to fill 
a casual vacancy shall continue for the remainder of the term of the 
member in whose place he, has been nominated or elected.

</section>

<section><tid>1363611</tid>
<number>6</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this section an out- 
going member shall, unless the Central Government otherwise directs, 
continue in office until another person is nominated or elected as a 
member in his place.

</section>

<section><tid>1337612</tid>
<number>7</number>The members of the Council shall be paid such travelling and 
other allowances by the Central Government as may be determined by 
that Government, but no member shall be entitled to any salary by, 
reason of this sub- section.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>594</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>670203</tid>
<number> 33</number> Functions of Council.
<section><tid>38112</tid>
<number>1</number>It shall be the general duty of  
the Council to co- ordinate the activities of all the Institutes.

</section>

<section><tid>1269506</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the provisions of sub- section (1), the 
Council shall perform the following functions, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1610741</tid>
<number>a</number>to advise on matters relating to the duration of the 
courses, the degrees and other academic distinctions to be 
conferred by the Institutes, admission standards and other 
academic matters;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1007204</tid>
<number>b</number>to lay down policy regarding cadres, methods of 
recruitment and conditions of service of employees, 
institution of scholarships and freeships, levying of fees 
and other matters of common interest;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>144199</tid>
<number>c</number>to examine the development plans of each Institute and 
to approve such of them as are considered necessary and also 
to indicate broadly the financial implications of such 
approved plans;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>394460</tid>
<number>d</number>to examine the annual budget estimates of each 
Institute and to recommend to the Central Government the 
allocation of funds for that purpose;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1816114</tid>
<number>e</number>to advise the Visitor, if so required, in respect of 
any function to be performed by him under this Act; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>564316</tid>
<number>f</number>to perform such other functions as are assigned to it 
or under this Act.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>404032</tid>
<number> 34</number> Chairman of Council.
<section><tid>1424575</tid>
<number>1</number>The Chairman of the Council shall  
ordinarily preside at the meetings of the Council.

</section>

<section><tid>510787</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be the duty of the Chairman of the Council to 
ensure that the decisions taken by the Council are implemented.

</section>

<section><tid>1800932</tid>
<number>3</number>The Chairman shall exercise such other powers and perform 
such other duties as are assigned to him by this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1400995</tid>
<number> 35</number> Power to make rules in respect of matters in this Chapter.

<section><tid>875858</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may make rules to carry out the purposes of  
this Chapter.

</section>

<section><tid>80318</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the follow- 
ing matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1572254</tid>
<number>a</number>the manner of filling vacancies among the members of 
the Council;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>595</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1368091</tid>
<number>b</number>the disqualifications for being chosen as, and for 
being a member of the Council;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>776452</tid>
<number>c</number>the circumstances in which, and the authority by which, 
members may be removed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1860124</tid>
<number>d</number>the meetings of the Council and the procedure of con- 
ducting business thereat;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>514080</tid>
<number>e</number>the travelling and other allowances payable to members 
of the Council; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1823277</tid>
<number>f</number>the functions of the Council and the manner in which 
such functions may be exercised.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER IV

MISCELLANEOUS




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1500758</tid>
<number> 36</number> Acts and proeedings not to be invalidated by vacancies. No 
act of the Council, or any Institute or Board or Senate or any other 
body set up under this Act or the Statutes, shall be invalid merely by 
reason of-
<section><tid>764592</tid>
<number>a</number>any vacancy in, or defect in the constitution thereof, 
or

</section>

<section><tid>1484804</tid>
<number>b</number>any defect in the election, nomination or appointment 
of person acting as a member thereof, or

</section>

<section><tid>1209170</tid>
<number>c</number>any irregularity in its procedure not affecting the 
merits of the case.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>532095</tid>
<number>37</number>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in 
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such provision 
or give such direction not inconsistent with the purposes of this Act, 
as appears to it to be necessary or expedient for removing the 
difficulty.


</article>



<article><tid>815310</tid>
<number> 38</number> Transitional provisions. Notwithstanding anything contained 
in this Act,-
<section><tid>138877</tid>
<number>a</number>the Board of Governors of an Institute functioning as 
such immediately before the commencement of this Act shall 
continue to so function until a new Board is constituted for 
that Institute under this Act, but on the constitution of a 
new Board under this Act, the members of the Board holding 
office before such constitution shall cease to hold office;

</section>

<section><tid>931840</tid>
<number>b</number>any Academic Council constituted in relation to any 
Institute before the commencement of this Act shall be deemed 
to be the Senate constituted under this Act until a Senate is 
constituted Under this Act for that Institute;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>596</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1550045</tid>
<number>c</number>until the first Statutes and the Ordinances are made 
under this Act, the Statutes and Ordinances of the Indian 
Institute of Technology, Kharagpur as in force immediately 
before the commencement of this Act shall continue to apply 
to that Institute and shall, with the necessary modifications 
and adaptations, also apply to any other Institute, in so far 
as they are not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>318844</tid>
<number> 39</number> Repeal and savings.
<section><tid>876259</tid>
<number>1</number>The Indian Institute of Technology  
 (Kharagpur) Act, <year>1956</year> is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>607306</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, the provisions of the said Act 
set out in the Schedule shall continue to have effect:
Provided that in the said provisions, the expression" this Act" 
means the said provisions.



</section>

</article>



 </act>