<act><title>THE PRASAR BHARATI (BROADCASTING CORPORATION 
OF INDIA ) INVESTMENT OF MONEYS RULES, 20071</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the Prasar Bharati (Broadcasting Corporation of India ) Investment of 
Moneys Rules, 2007. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the 
Official Gazette. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, unless the context 
otherwise requires, 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> Act means the Prasar Bharati (Broadcasting Corporation of India ) 
  Act, 1990 (25 of 1990); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> committee means the Investment Committee, referred to in rule 5; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> credit rating agency means an agency recognised by Securities and 
  Exchange Board of India and Reserve Bank of India for the purpose of rating 
  companies based on their debt servicing capacity; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> debt investment means any instrument through which loan is advanced 
  to third party like loan, debentures, etc.; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> short-term means a period not exceeding one year. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Words and expressions used in these rules and not defined but defined in 
the Act shall have the meanings assigned to them in the Act. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Investment of moneys in securities, etc. </title>The Corporation 
may invest its moneys in one or more of the following instruments subject, 
however, to the principles laid down in rule 4, namely: 
 
 <section><number>i</number> term deposits with any nationalised banks, having a net-worth of at 
  least rupees 100 crores, fulfilling the capital adequacy norms, as specified 
  by the Reserve Bank of India, and as reflected in the last published balance 
  sheet; 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> investments which have been rated by an established credit rating 
  agency and have been accorded the highest safety such as, certificate of 
  deposits issued by nationalised banks; 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> any debt instrument which has obtained highest rating from an 
  established credit rating agency; 
 </section><section><number>iv</number> public accounts with the Government of India with the facility for 
  withdrawal at any time; 
 </section><section><number>v</number> securities of the Central Government or any State Government. 
</section>

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Principles Governing Investment. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The principles 
governing the investment shall be safety, returns, transparency and 
accountability. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Term deposits for the chosen period shall be made from amongst the 
nationalised banks for the highest rate of interest and return. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Debt instruments carrying the maximum return amongst the eligible 
instruments of highest safety rating by the established credit rating agencies 
shall be selected. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Investments in Government securities through primary dealers charging the 
lowest commission shall be preferred. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> For obtaining maximum returns and achieving transparency and 
accountability, three competitive quotations from the eligible nationalised 
banks shall be chosen. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> All investment decisions shall be taken in accordance with the rules, 
regulations and directions issued by the Central Government, as applicable. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> The Corporation shall, in making investments of short-terms surplus 
funds, be guided by the following principles, namely: 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> investment shall be made only in instruments with maximum safety; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> there shall be no element of speculation on the yield obtaining from 
  the invest­ment; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> the surplus availability may be worked out for a minimum one year at 
  any point of time, in consultation with the Ministry of Information and 
  Broadcasting; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> there shall be a proper commercial appreciation before any investment 
  decision on surplus funds is taken; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> funds shall not be invested at a particular rate of interest for a 
  particular period of time, if the Corporation is resorting to borrowing at an 
  equal or higher rate of interest for its requirements for the same period of 
  time; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vi</number> investment decisions shall be based on commercial judgment; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vii</number> the availability should be worked out based on cash-flow estimates 
  taking into account working capital requirements, replacement of assets and 
  other demands; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>viii</number> the investment shall be only of temporary nature using temporary 
  idle cash including refundable deposits and it shall not be used for investing 
  from the funds kept outside the internal extra budgetary resources 
  calculation; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ix</number> the final maturity of investment shall not exceed one year from the 
  date of investment. </subsection>

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Investment Committee. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Decisions on investment of 
surplus funds shall be taken by an Investment Committee, consisting of the 
Executive Member, Member (Finance) and Member (Personnel). 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The decision on investments shall be taken by the committee comprising a 
minimum of two Members. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Decision made under sub-rule (1) shall be placed before the Prasar 
Bharati Board for approval, in its next meeting. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Internal audit. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Proper internal audit of the funds 
and investments shall be developed and the reports of the internal audit shall 
be reviewed by the Executive Member of the Corporation, from time to time. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Important observations shall be placed before the Prasar Bharati Board 
for approval. 

</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>