<act><title>THE PROHIBITION OF CHILD MARRIAGE ACT, 2006</title> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title, extent and commencement. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> This Act may 
be called the Prohibition of Child Marriage Act, 2006. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir; 
and it applies also to all citizens of India without and beyond India: 
 Provided that nothing contained in this Act shall apply to the Renoncants of 
the Union territory of Pondicherry. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, appoint; and different dates<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 
may be appointed for different States and any reference in any provision to the 
commencement of this Act shall be construed in relation to any State as a 
reference to the coming into force of that provision in that State. 

</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.-In 
this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-
 <section>
       <number>a</number> "child" means a 
person who, if a male, has not completed twenty-one years of age, and if a 
female, has not completed eighteen years of age;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number> "child 
marriage" means a marriage to which either of the contracting parties is a 
child;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number> "contracting 
party", in relation to a marriage, means either of the parties whose marriage is 
or is about to be thereby solemnised;
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number> "Child Marriage 
Prohibition Officer" includes the Child Marriage Prohibition Officer appointed 
under sub-section (1) of section 16;
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number> "district 
court" means, in any area for which a Family Court established under section 3 
of the Family Courts Act, 1984 (66 of 1984) exists, such Family Court, and in 
any area for which there is no Family Court but a city civil court exists that 
court and in any other area, the principal civil court of original jurisdiction 
and includes and other civil court which may be specified by the State 
Government, by notification in the Official Gazette, as having jurisdiction in 
respect of the matters dealt with in this Act;
 </section><section>
        <number>f</number> "minor" means 
a person who, under the provisions of the Majority Act, 1875 (9 of 1875) is to 
be deemed not to have attained his majority.
 
 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>3</number> Child marriages to be voidable 
at the option of contracting party being a child.-
<section><number>1</number> Every child marriage, whether 
solemnised before or after the commencement of this Act, shall be voidable at 
the option of the contracting party who was a child at the time of the 
marriage:
 Provided that a petition for 
annulling a child marriage by a decree of nullity may be filed in the district 
court only by a contracting party to the marriage who was a child at the time of 
the marriage.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If at the time of filing a 
petition, the petitioner is a minor, the petition may be filed through his or 
her guardian or next friend alongwith the Child Marriage Prohibition 
Officer.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The petition under this 
section may be filed at any time but before the child filing the petition 
completes two years of attaining majority.
 </section><section><number>4</number> While granting a decree of 
nullity under this section, the district court shall make an order directing 
both the parties to the marriage and their parents or their guardians to return 
to the other party, his or her parents or guardian, as the case may be, the 
money, valuables, ornaments and other gifts received on the occasion of the 
marriage by them from the other side, or an amount equal to the value of such 
valuables, ornaments, other gifts and money:
 Provided that no order under this 
section shall be passed unless the concerned parties have been given notices to 
appear before the district court and show cause why such order should not be 
passed.
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><number>4</number> Provision for maintenance and 
residence to female contracting party to child marriage.-
<section><number>1</number> While granting a decree under 
section 3, the district court may also make an interim or final order directing 
the male contracting party to the child marriage, and in case the male 
contracting party to such marriage is a minor, his parent or guardian to pay 
maintenance to the female contracting party to the marriage until her 
remarriage.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The quantum of maintenance 
payable shall be determined by the district court having regard to the needs of 
the child, the lifestyle enjoyed by such child during her marriage and the means 
of income of the paying party.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The amount of maintenance may 
be directed to be paid monthly or in lump sum.
 </section><section><number>4</number> In case the party making the 
petition under section 3 is the female contracting party, the district court may 
also make a suitable order as to her residence until her remarriage.


</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Custody and 
maintenance of children of child marriages.-
<section><number>1</number> 
Where there are children born of the child marriage, the district court shall 
make an appropriate order for the custody of such children.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> While making an order 
for the custody of a child under this section, the welfare and best interests of 
the child shall be the paramount consideration to be given by the district 
court.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An order for custody 
of a child may also include appropriate directions for giving to the other party 
access to the child in such a manner as may best serve the interests of the 
child, and such other orders as the district court may, in the interest of the 
child, deem proper.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The district court may 
also make an appropriate order for providing maintenance to the child by a party 
to the marriage or their parents or guardians.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Legitimacy of 
children born of child marriages.-Notwithstanding 
that a child marriage has been annulled by a decree of nullity under section 3, 
every child begotten or conceived of such marriage before the decree is made, 
whether born before or after the commencement of this Act, shall be deemed to be 
a legitimate child for all purposes.



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Power of district 
court to modify orders issued under section 4 or section 5.-The 
district court shall have the power to add to, modify or revoke any order made 
under section 4 or section 5 and if there is any change in the circumstances at 
any time during the pendency of the petition and even after the final disposal 
of the petition.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Court to which 
petition should be made.-For 
the purpose of grant of reliefs under sections 3, 4 and 5, the district court 
having jurisdiction shall include the district court having jurisdiction over 
the place where the defendant or the child resides, or where the marriage was 
solemnised or where the parties last resided together or the petitioner is 
residing on the date of presentation of the petition.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Punishment for male 
adult marrying a child.-Whoever, 
being a male adult above eighteen years of age, contracts a child marriage shall 
be punishable with rigorous imprisonment which may extend to two years or with 
fine which may extend to one lakh rupees or with both.



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Punishment for 
solemnising a child marriage.-Whoever 
performs, conducts or directs or abets any child marriage shall be punishable 
with rigorous imprisonment which may extend to two years and shall be liable to 
fine which may extend to one lakh rupees unless he proves that he had reasons to 
believe that the marriage was not a child marriage.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Punishment for 
promoting or permitting solemnisation of child marriages.-
<section><number>1</number> 
Where a child contracts a child marriage, any person having charge of the child, 
whether as parent or guardian or any other person or in any other capacity, 
lawful or unlawful, including any member of an organization or association of 
persons who does any act to promote the marriage or permits it to be solemnised, 
or negligently fails to prevent it from being solemnised, including attending or 
participating in a child marriage, shall be punishable with rigorous 
imprisonment which may extend to two years and shall also be liable to fine 
which may extend upto one lakh rupees:
 
Provided that no woman 
shall be punishable with imprisonment.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> For the purposes of 
this section, it shall be presumed, unless and until the contrary is proved, 
that where a minor child has contracted a marriage, the person having charge of 
such minor child has negligently failed to prevent the marriage from being 
solemnised.



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Marriage of a minor 
child to be void in certain circumstances.-Where 
a child, being a minor-
 <section>
       <number>a</number> is taken or 
enticed out of the keeping of the lawful guardian; or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number> by force 
compelled, or by any deceitful means induced to go from any place; or
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number> is sold for the 
purpose of marriage; and made to go through a form of marriage or if the minor 
is married after which the minor is sold or trafficked or used for immoral 
purposes, 
 
such marriage shall be 
null and void.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Power of court to 
issue injunction prohibiting child marriages.-
<section><number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in this Act, if, on an 
application of the Child Marriage Prohibition Officer or on receipt of 
information through a complaint or otherwise from any person, a Judicial 
Magistrate of the first class or a Metropolitan Magistrate is satisfied that a 
child marriage in contravention of this Act has been arranged or is about to be 
solemnised, such Magistrate shall issue an injunction against any person 
including a member of an organization or an association of persons prohibiting 
such marriage.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A complaint under 
sub-section (1) may be made by any person having personal knowledge or reason to 
believe, and a non-governmental organization having reasonable information, 
relating to the likelihood of taking place of solemnisation of a child marriage 
or child marriages.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Court of the 
Judicial Magistrate of the first class or the Metropolitan Magistrate may also 
take suo motu cognizance on the basis of any reliable report or 
information.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> For the purposes of 
preventing solemnisation of mass child marriages on certain days such as 
Akshaya Trutiya, the District Magistrate shall be deemed to be the Child 
Marriage Prohibition Officer with all powers as are conferred on a Child 
Marriage Prohibition Officer by or under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The District 
Magistrate shall also have additional powers to stop or prevent solemnisation of 
child marriages and for this purpose, he may take all appropriate measures and 
use the minimum force required.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> No injunction under 
sub-section (1) shall be issued against any person or member of any organization 
or association of persons unless the Court has previously given notice to such 
person, members of the organization or association of persons, as the case may 
be, and has offered him or them an opportunity to show cause against the issue 
of the injunction:
 
Provided that in the case 
of any urgency, the Court shall have the power to issue an interim injunction 
without giving any notice under this section.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> An injunction issued 
under sub-section (1) may be confirmed or vacated after giving notice and 
hearing the party against whom the injunction was issued.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> The Court may either 
on its own motion or on the application of any person aggrieved, rescind or 
alter an injunction issued under sub-section (1).
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> Where an application 
is received under sub-section (1), the Court shall afford the applicant an early 
opportunity of appearing before it either in person or by an advocate and if the 
Court, after hearing the applicant rejects the application wholly or in part, it 
shall record in writing its reasons for so doing.
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> Whoever knowing that 
an injunction has been issued under sub-section (1) against him disobeys such 
injunction shall be punishable with imprisonment of either description for a 
term which may extend to two years or with fine which may extend to one lakh 
rupees or with both:
 
Provided that no woman 
shall be punishable with imprisonment.



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Child marriages in 
contravention of injunction orders to be void.-Any 
child marriage solemnised in contravention of an injunction order issued under 
section 13, whether interim or final, shall be void ab initio.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Offences to be 
cognizable and non-bailable.-Notwithstanding 
anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), an 
offence punishable under this Act shall be cognizable and non-bailable.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Child Marriage 
Prohibition Officers.-
<section><number>1</number> 
The State Government shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint for 
the whole State, or such part thereof as may be specified in that notification, 
an officer or officers to be known as the Child Marriage Prohibition Officer 
having jurisdiction over the area or areas specified in the notification.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The State Government 
may also request a respectable member of the locality with a record of social 
service or an officer of the Gram Panchayat or Municipality or an officer of the 
Government or any public sector undertaking or an office bearer of any 
non­-governmental organization to assist the Child Marriage Prohibition Officer 
and such member, officer or office bearer, as the case may be, shall be bound to 
act accordingly.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall be the duty 
of the Child Marriage Prohibition Officer-
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> to prevent 
solemnisation of child marriages by taking such action as he may deem fit;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> to collect 
evidence for the effective prosecution of persons contravening the provisions of 
this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number> to advise 
either individual cases or counsel the residents of the locality generally not 
to indulge in promoting, helping, aiding or allowing the solemnisation of child 
marriages;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number> to create 
awareness of the evil which results from child marriages;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number> to sensitize 
the community on the issue of child marriages;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number> to furnish 
such periodical returns and statistics as the State Government may direct; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>g</number> to discharge 
such other functions and duties as may be assigned to him by the State 
Government.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The State Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, subject to such conditions and 
limitations, invest the Child Marriage Prohibition Officer with such powers of a 
police officer as may be specified in the notification and the Child Marriage 
Prohibition Officer shall exercise such powers subject to such conditions and 
limitations, as may be specified in the notification.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Child Marriage 
Prohibition Officer shall have the power to move the Court for an order under 
sections 4, 5 and 13 and along with the child under section 3.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Child Marriage 
Prohibition Officers to be public servants.-The 
Child Marriage Prohibition Officers shall be deemed to be public servants within 
the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Protection of 
action taken in good faith.-No 
suit, prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against the Child 
Marriage Prohibition Officer in respect of anything in good faith done or 
intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any rule or order made 
thereunder.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Power of State 
Government to make rules.-
<section><number>1</number> 
The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules 
for carrying out the provisions of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every rule made under 
this Act shall, as soon as may be after it is made, be laid before the State 
Legislature.



</section></article> 

   

   

 <article><number>20</number> Amendment of Act No. 25 of 1955.-In the Hindu Marriage Act, 
1955, in section 18, for clause 
<section><number>a</number>, the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:- 20. Amendment of Act No. 25 of 1955.-In the Hindu Marriage Act, 1955, in section 18, for
clause (a), the following clause shall be substituted, namely\:-" 
 
 </section><section> <number>a</number>
in the case of contravention of the condition specified in clause (iii) 
of section 5, with rigorous imprisonment which may extend to two years or with 
fine which may extend to one lakh rupees, or with both. </section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Repeal and savings.-
<section><number>1</number> 
The Child Marriage Restraint Act, 1929 (19 of 1929) is hereby repealed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding such 
repeal, all cases and other proceedings pending or continued under the said Act 
at the commencement of this Act shall be continued and disposed of in accordance 
with the provisions of the repealed Act, as if this Act had not been passed.
 
 
  
</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Came into force in the State of Himachal Pradesh on 
1-11-2007,  vide  S.O. 1786(E), dated 19th October, 2007.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>