<act><title>

The
Partition Act, 1893</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>1</number>
Title, extent and saving.—
<section><number>1</number>
This Act may be called the Partition Act, 1893. 
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[except
the State of Jammu and Kashmir] <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[***].

 


 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[***]
 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
But nothing herein contained shall be deemed to affect any local law providing
for the partition of immovable property paying revenue to Government. 
 


   









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>2</number>
Power to court to order sale instead of division in partition suits.—Whenever
in any suit for partition in which, if instituted prior to the commencement of
this Act, a decree for partition might have been made, it appears to the court
that, by reason of the nature of the property to which the suit relates, or of
the number of the shareholders therein, or of any other special circumstance, a
division of the property cannot reasonably or conveniently be made, and that a
sale of the property and distribution of the proceeds would be more beneficial
for all the shareholders, the court may, if it thinks fit, on the request of any
of such shareholders interested individually or collectively to the extent of
one moiety or upwards, direct a sale of the property and a distribution of the
proceeds.
   



 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>3</number>
Procedure when sharer undertakes to buy.—
<section><number>1</number>
If, in any case in which the court is requested under the last foregoing section
to direct a sale, any other shareholder applies for leave to buy at a valuation
the share or shares of the party or parties asking for a sale, the court shall
order a valuation of the share or shares in such manner as it may think fir and
offer to sell the same to such shareholder at the price so ascertained, and may
give all necessary and proper directions in that behalf.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
If two or more shareholders severally apply for leave to buy as provided in
sub-section (1), the court shall order a sale of the share or shares to the
shareholder who offers to pay the highest price above the valuation made by the
court. 
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
If no such shareholder is willing to buy such share or shares at the price so
ascertained, the applicant or applicants shall be liable to pay all costs of or
incident to the application or applications. 
 


  
   



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>4</number>
Partition suit by transferee of share in dwelling-house.—
<section><number>1</number>
Where a share of a dwelling-house belonging to an undivided family has been
transferred to a person who is not a member of such family and such transferee
sues for partition, the court shall, if any member of the family being a
shareholder shall undertake to buy the share of such transferee, make a
valuation of such share in such manner as it thinks fit and direct the sale of
such share to such shareholder, and may give all necessary and proper directions
in that behalf.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
If in any case described in sub-section (1) two or more members of the family
being such shareholders severally undertake to buy such share, the court shall
follow the procedure prescribed by sub-section (2) of the last foregoing
section.
 


  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>5</number>
Representation of parties under disability.—In
any suit for partition a request for sale may be made or an undertaking, or
application for leave, to buy may be given or made on behalf of any party under
disability by any person authorised to act on behalf of such party in such suit,
but the court shall not be bound to comply with any such request, undertaking or
application unless it is of opinion that the sale or purchase will be for the
benefit of the party under such disability.
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>6</number>
Reserved bidding and bidding by shareholders.—
<section><number>1</number>
Every sale under Section 2 shall be subject to a reserved bidding, and the
amount of such bidding shall be fixed by the Court in such manner as it may
think fit and may be varied from time to time.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
On any such sale any of the shareholders shall be at liberty to bid at the sale
on such terms as to non-payment of deposit or as to setting off or accounting
for the purchase-money or any part thereof instead of paying the same as to the
court may seem reasonable.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
If two or more persons, of whom one is a shareholder in the property,
respectively advance the same sum at any bidding at such sale, such bidding
shall be deemed to be the bidding of the shareholder.
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>7</number>
Procedure to be followed in case of sale.—Save
as herein before provided, when any property is directed to be sold under this
Act, the following procedure shall, as far as practicable, be adopted,
namely:—
 <section><number>a</number>
if the property be sold under a decree or order of the High Court of
Calcutta, Madras or Bombay, in the exercise of its original jurisdiction, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[***]
the procedure of such court in its original civil jurisdiction for the sale of
property by the Registrar;

 </section><section><number>b</number>
if the property be sold under a decree or order of any other court, such
procedure as the High Court may form time to time by rules prescribe in this
behalf, and until such rules are made the procedure prescribed in the Code of
Civil Procedure<footcitenum>4</footcitenum> in
respect of sales in execution of decrees.
   








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>8</number>
Orders For Sale To Be Deemed Decrees.—Any
order for sale made by the court under section 2, 3 or 4 shall be deemed to be a
decree within the meaning of section 2 of the Code of Civil Procedure, (14 of
1882).
   



 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>9</number>
Saving of power to order partly partition and partly sale.—In
any suit for partition the Court may, if it shall think fit, make a decree for a
partition of part of the property to which the suit relates and a sale of the
remainder under this Act.
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>10</number> Application of act to pending 
      suits.—This Act shall apply to 
      suits instituted before the commencement thereof, in which no scheme for 
      the partition of the partition has been finally approved by the 
      court.
 
  </article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>
Subs. By Act 3 of 1951, sec. 3 and Sch. for “except Part B States”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>
The word “and” at the end of sub-section (2), and sub-section (3)
omitted by Act 10 of 1914, sec. 3 and Sch. II.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>  The
words “or of the Court of the Recorder of Rangoon” omitted by the Government
of India (Adaptation of Indian Laws) Order, 1937.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>  See
now the Code of Civil procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>