<act><title>


The National Environment appellate Authority 
act, 1997</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
This Act may be called the National Environment Appellate Authority Act, 1997.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It shall be deemed to 
have come into force on the 30th day of January, 1997.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
       
<number>a</number>  “Act” means the Environment (Protection) Act, 1986 (29 of 1986);
 </section><section>
       
<number>b</number>  “Authority” means the National Environment Appellate Authority 
established under sub-section (1) of section 3;
 </section><section>
       
<number>c</number>  “Chairperson” means the Chairperson of the Authority;
 </section><section>
       
<number>d</number>  “Member” means a Member of the Authority;
 </section><section>
       
<number>e</number>  “prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act;
 </section><section>
        
<number>f</number>  “Vice-Chairperson” means the Vice-Chairperson of the Authority.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Establishment of 
Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, establish 
a body to be known as the National Environment Appellate Authority to exercise 
the powers conferred upon, and to perform the functions assigned to, it under 
this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The head office of the 
Authority shall be at Delhi.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Composition of 
Authority.—The 
Authority shall consist of a Chairperson, a Vice-Chairperson and such other 
Members not exceeding three, as the Central Government may deem fit.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Qualifications for 
appointment as Chairperson, Vice-Chairperson or Member.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A person shall not be qualified for appointment as a Chairperson unless he has 
been—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  a Judge of the Supreme Court; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  the Chief Justice of a High Court.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A person shall not be 
qualified for appointment as a Vice-Chairperson unless he has—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  for at least two years held the post of a Secretary to the Government 
of India or any other post under the Central or State Government carrying a 
scale of pay which is not less than that of a Secretary to the Government of 
India; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  expertise or experience in administrative, legal, managerial or 
technical aspects of problems relating to environment.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> A person shall not be 
qualified for appointment as a Member unless he has professional knowledge or 
practical experience in the areas pertaining to conservation, environment 
management, law or planning and development.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Chairperson, the 
Vice-Chairperson and the Members shall be appointed by the President.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>6</number> Vice-Chairperson to act as 
Chairperson or to discharge his functions in certain 
circumstances.—
<section><number>1</number> In the event of the 
occurrence of any vacancy in the office of the Chairperson by reason of his 
death, resignation or otherwise, the Vice-Chairperson shall act as the 
Chairperson until the date on which a new Chairperson appointed in accordance 
with the provisions of this Act to fill such vacancy enters upon his 
office.
 </section><section><number>2</number> When the Chairperson is unable 
to discharge his functions owing to absence, illness or any other cause, the 
Vice-Chairperson or, as the case may be, such one of the Member as the Central 
Government may, by notification, authorise in this behalf, shall discharge the 
functions of the Chairperson until the date on which the Chairperson resumes his 
duties.</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Term of office.—The 
Chairperson, the Vice-Chairperson or a Member shall hold office as such for a 
term of three years from the date on which he enters upon his office, but shall 
be eligible for re-appointment for another term of three years:
 
Provided that no 
Chairperson, Vice-Chairperson or Member shall hold office as such after he has 
attained,—
 <section>
       
<number>a</number>  in the case of the Chairperson, the age of seventy years; and
 </section><section>
       
<number>b</number>  in the case of the Vice-Chairperson or a Member, the age of sixty-five 
years.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Resignation and 
removal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chairperson, the Vice-Chairperson or a Member may, by notice in writing 
under his hand addressed to the President, resign his office:
 
Provided that the 
Chairperson, the Vice-Chairperson or a Member shall, unless he is permitted by 
the President to relinquish his office sooner, continue to hold office until the 
expiry of three months from the date of receipt of such notice or until a person 
duly appointed as his successor enters upon his office or until the expiry of 
his term of office, whichever is the earliest.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Chairperson, the 
Vice-Chairperson or a Member shall not be removed from his office except by an 
order made by the President on the ground of proved misbehaviour or incapacity 
after an inquiry made by a Judge of the Supreme Court in which such Chairperson, 
the Vice-Chairperson or a Member had been informed of the charges against him 
and given a reasonable opportunity of being heard in respect of those charges.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The President may 
suspend from office the Chairperson, the Vice-Chairperson or a Member in respect 
of whom a reference has been made to the Supreme Court under sub-section (2) 
until the President has passed orders on receipt of the report of the Supreme 
Court on such reference.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Central Government 
may, by rules, regulate the procedure for the investigation of misbehaviour or 
incapacity of the Chairperson, the Vice-Chairperson or a Member referred to in 
sub-section (2).
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Salaries and 
allowances and other terms and conditions of service of Chairperson, 
Vice-Chairperson and Members.—The 
salaries and allowances payable to, and the other terms and conditions of 
service (including pension, gratuity and other retirement benefits) of, the 
Chairperson, the Vice-Chairperson and the Members shall be such as may be 
prescribed by the Central Government.
</article> 

  
 <article><number>10</number> Vacancy in Authority not to 
invalidate acts or proceedings.—No act or proceedings of the 
Authority shall be questioned or shall be invalid merely on the ground of 
existence of any vacancy or defect in the establishment of the 
Authority.</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Appeals to 
Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any person aggrieved by an order granting environmental clearance in the areas 
in which any industries, operations or processes or class of industries, 
operations and processes shall not be carried out or shall be carried out 
subject to certain safeguards may, within thirty days from the date of such 
order, prefer an appeal to the Authority in such form as may be prescribed:
 
Provided that the 
Authority may entertain any appeal after the expiry of the said period of thirty 
days but not after ninety days from the date aforesaid if it is satisfied that 
the appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from filing the appeal in time.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> For the purposes of 
sub-section (1), “person” means—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  any person who is likely to be affected by the grant of environmental 
clearance;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  any person who owns or has control over the project with respect to 
which an application has been submitted for environmental clearance;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>c</number>  any association of persons (whether incorporated or not) likely to be 
affected by such order and functioning in the field of environment;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>d</number>  the Central Government, where the environmental clearance is granted 
by the State Government and the State Government, where the environmental 
clearance is granted by the Central Government; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>e</number>  any local authority, any part of whose local limits is within the 
neighbourhood of the area wherein the project is proposed to be located.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> On receipt of an 
appeal preferred under sub-section (1), the Authority shall, after giving the 
appellant an opportunity of being heard, pass such orders, as it thinks fit.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Authority shall 
dispose of the appeal within ninety days from the date of filing the appeal:
 
Provided that the 
Authority may for reasons to be recorded in writing dispose of the appeal within 
a further period of thirty days.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Procedure and 
powers of Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Authority shall not be bound by the procedure laid down in the Code of Civil 
Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), but shall be guided by the principles of natural 
justice and subject to the other provisions of this Act and of any rules made by 
the Central Government, the Authority shall have power to regulate its own 
procedure including the fixing of places and times of its inquiry and deciding 
whether to sit in public or in private.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Authority shall 
have, for the purposes of discharging its functions under this Act, the same 
powers as are vested in a civil court under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 
of 1908), while trying a suit, in respect of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person and examining him 
on oath;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  requiring the discovery and production of documents;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>c</number>  receiving evidence on affidavits;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>d</number>  subject to the provisions of sections 123 and 124 of the Indian 
Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872), requisitioning any public record or document or 
copy of such record or document from any office;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>e</number>  issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses or documents;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>f</number>  reviewing its decisions;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>g</number>  dismissing a representation for default or deciding it, ex parte;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>h</number>  setting aside any order of dismissal of any representation for default 
or any order passed by it ex parte; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>i</number>  any other matter which is required to be, or may be, prescribed by the 
Central Government.




</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Financial and 
administrative powers of Chairperson.—The 
Chairperson shall exercise such financial and administrative powers as may be 
vested in him under the rules:
 
Provided that the 
Chairperson shall have authority to delegate such of his financial and 
administrative powers as he may think fit to the Vice-Chairperson or any other 
officer subject to the condition that the Vice-Chairperson or such other officer 
shall, while exercising such delegated powers, continue to act under the 
direction, control and supervision of the Chairperson.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Staff of Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government shall determine the nature and categories of the officers 
and other employees required to assist the Authority in the discharge of its 
functions and provide the Authority with such officers and other employees as it 
may think fit.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The officers and other 
employees of the Authority shall discharge their functions under the general 
superintendence of the Chairperson.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The salaries and 
allowances and conditions of service of the officers and other employees shall 
be such as may be prescribed.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Bar of 
jurisdiction.—With 
effect from the date of establishment of the Authority, no civil court or other 
authority shall have jurisdiction to entertain any appeal in respect of any 
matter with which the Authority is so empowered by or under this Act.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Proceedings before 
the Authority to be judicial proceedings.—All 
proceedings before the Authority shall be deemed to be judicial proceedings 
within the meaning of sections 193, 219 and 228 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 
1860).








</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Members and staff 
of Authority to be public servants.—The 
Chairperson, the Vice-Chairperson and the Members and the officers and other 
employees of the Authority shall be deemed to be public servants within the 
meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Protection of 
action taken in good faith.—No 
suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central 
Government or against the Chairperson, the Vice-Chairperson or a Member of the 
Authority or any other person authorised by the Chairperson, the 
Vice-Chairperson or a Member for anything which is in good faith done or 
intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any rule or order made 
thereunder.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Penalty for failure 
to comply with orders of Authority.—Whoever 
fails to comply with any order made by the Authority, he shall be punishable 
with imprisonment for a term which may extend to seven years, or with fine which 
may extend to one lakh rupees, or with both.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Offences by 
companies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where any offence under this Act has been committed by a company, every person 
who, at the time the offence was committed, was directly in charge of, and was 
responsible to, the company for the conduct of the business of the company, as 
well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be 
liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
 
Provided that nothing 
contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to any 
punishment provided in this Act, if he proves that the offence was committed 
without his knowledge or that he has exercised all due diligence to prevent the 
commission of such offence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence under this Act has been 
committed by a company and it is proved that the offence has been committed with 
the consent or connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, 
any director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such director, 
manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of that 
offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.
 
Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this section,—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  “company” means any body corporate and includes a firm or other 
association of individuals; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  “director”, in relation to a firm, means a partner in the firm.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Power to remove 
difficulties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the 
Central Government may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such 
provisions, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as appear to it to 
be necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty:
 
Provided that no such 
order shall be made after the expiry of the period of three years from the date 
on which this Act receives the assent of the President.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every order made under 
this section shall, as soon as may be after it is made, be laid before each 
House of Parliament.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Power to make 
rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
Central Government may, by notification, make rules for carrying out the 
provisions of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular, and 
without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may 
provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  the procedure under sub-section (4) of section 8 for the investigation 
of misbehaviour or incapacity of the Chairperson, the Vice-Chairperson or a 
Member;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  the salaries and allowances payable to and the other terms and 
conditions of service of the Chairperson, the Vice-Chairperson and the Members 
under section 9;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>c</number>  the form which an appeal shall contain under sub-section (1) of 
section 11;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>d</number>  financial and administrative powers of the Chairperson under section 
13;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>e</number>  the salaries and allowances and conditions of service of the officers 
and other employees of the Authority;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>f</number>  any other matter which is required to be, or may be, prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Every rule made under 
this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of 
Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may 
be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, 
before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in 
the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the 
case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be 
without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Repeal and saving.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The National Environment Appellate Authority Ordinance, 1997 (12 of 1997) is 
hereby repealed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding such 
repeal, anything done or any action taken under the said Ordinance, shall be 
deemed to have been done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this 
Act.
 
 
 
 
</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>