<act><title>THE ENERGY CONSERVATION (FORM AND MANNER AND TIME 
FOR FURNISHING INFORMATION WITH REGARD TO ENERGY CONSUMED AND ACTION TAKEN ON 
RECOMMENDATIONS OF ACCREDITED ENERGY AUDITOR) RULES, 20081</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>혰
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the Energy Conservation (Form and Manner and Time for Furnishing 
Information With Regard to Energy Consumed and Action Taken on Recommendations 
of Accredited Energy Auditor) Rules, 2008. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of their publication 
in the Official Gazette. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, unless the context 
otherwise requires,- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> "Act" means the Energy Conservation Act, 2001; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> "Form" means the forms specified under rule 3; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> "year" means the financial year beginning on the 1st day of April and 
  ending on the 31st March following; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> words and expression used herein and not defined, but defined in the 
  Act shall have the meanings assigned to them in the Act. </subsection>


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Form and time limit for furnishing of information by the 
designated consumers with regard to energy consumed and action taken on the 
recommendations of the accredited energy auditor. </title>혰
<section><number>1</number> Every designated 
consumer within three months of the submission of energy audit report by the 
accredited energy auditor shall, furnish in electronic form as well as in a hard 
copy, to the designated agency,혰 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> details of information on energy consumed during the year preceding to 
  the year for which energy audit was undertaken as verified by the accredited 
  energy auditor, in Form 1; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> details of specific energy consumption product-wise for the period 
  referred to in clause (a), in Form 1; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> details of the action taken on the recommendations made by the 
  accredited energy auditor in the energy audit report submitted under the Act, 
  in Form 2; </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every designated consumer shall furnish to the designated agency every 
year, the details of progress made in consequence of the action taken by it as 
per clause (c) of sub-rule (1) of rule 3 together with the details of energy 
efficiency improvement measures implemented and consequent savings achieved in 
Form 3, within three months of the close of that year. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Manner of furnishing information. </title>혰
<section><number>1</number> Every designated 
consumer shall furnish the information under rule 3 after getting the same 
authenticated by its energy manager appointed or designated in terms of 
notification number S.O. 318(E), dated the 2nd March, 2007. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The information under sub-rule (1) shall be strictly in accordance with 
the energy audit report of the accredited energy auditor. 

</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Came into force on 30-6-2008.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>