<act><title>THE CYBER APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (PROCEDURE FOR 
INVESTIGATION OF MISBEHAVIOUR OR INCAPACITY OF CHAIRPERSON AND MEMBERS) RULES, 
20091</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the Cyber Appellate Tribunal (Procedure for Investigation of Misbehaviour 
or Incapacity of Chairperson and Members) Rules, 2009. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date<title><footcitenum>1</footcitenum></title> of 
their publication in the Official Gazette. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, unless the context 
otherwise requires, 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> Act means the Information Technology Act, 2000 (21 of 2000); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> Chairperson means the Chairperson of the Cyber Appellate Tribunal 
  appointed under section 49 of the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> Committee means a Committee constituted under subrule (2) of rule 3; 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> Member means the Member of a Cyber Appellate Tribunal appointed under 
  section 49 of the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> Tribunal means the Cyber Appellate Tribunal established under 
  sub-section (1) of section 48 of the Act. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> All other words and expressions used but not defined in these rules shall 
have the meaning respectively assigned to them in the Act. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Committee for investigation of complaints. </title>
<section><number>1</number> If a 
written complaint, alleging any definite charges of misbehaviour or incapacity 
to perform the functions of the offices in respect of the Chairperson or the 
Member, as the case may be, is received by the Central Government, it shall make 
a preliminary scrutiny of such complaint. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> If, on preliminary scrutiny, the Central Government considers it 
necessary to investigate into the allegation, it shall place the complaint 
together with other material as may be available, before a Committee consisting 
of the following officers to investigate the charges of allegations made in the 
complaint, namely: 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> the Secretary (Co-ordination and Public Grievances) in the Cabinet 
  Secretariat, Government of India  Chairman; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> the Secretary, Department of Information Technology, Government of 
  India  Member; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> the Secretary, Department of Legal Affairs, Ministry of Law and 
  Justice, Government of India  Member. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Committee shall devise its own procedure and method of investigation, 
which may include recording of evidence of the complainant and collection of 
material under rule 4, which may be relevant to the conducted of inquiry. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Committee shall submit its findings to the President as early as 
possible within a period that may be specified by the President in this behalf. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Judge to conduct inquiry. </title>
<section><number>1</number> If, the President, on 
receipt of the report of the Committee under sub-rule (4) of rule 3, is of the 
opinion that there are reasonable grounds for making an inquiry into the truth 
of any imputation of misbehaviour or incapacity of the Chairperson or the 
Member, as the case may be then, he shall make a reference to the Chief Justice 
of India requesting him to nominate a Judge of the Supreme Court to conduct the 
inquiry. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The President shall, by order, appoint the Judge of the Supreme Court 
nominated by the Chief Justice of India (hereinafter referred to as Judge) for 
the purpose of conducting the inquiry. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Notice of appointment of a Judge under sub-rule (2) shall be given to the 
Chairperson or the Member, as the case may be. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The President shall forward to the Judge a copy of 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the articles of charges against the Chairperson or the Member, as the 
  case may be, and the statement of imputations; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the statement of witnesses, if any; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> material documents relevant to the inquiry. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Judge appointed under sub-rule (2) shall complete the inquiry within 
such time or further time as may be specified by the President. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Chairperson or the Member, as the case may be, shall be given a 
reasonable opportunity of presenting a written statement of defence within such 
time as may be specified in this behalf by the Judge. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> Where it is alleged that the Chairperson or Member, as the case may be, 
is unable to discharge the duties of his office efficiently due to any physical 
or mental incapacity and the allegation is denied, the Judge may arrange for the 
medical examination of the Chairperson or the Member, as the case may be, by 
such Medical Board as may be appointed for the purpose by the President and the 
Chairperson or the Member, as the case may be, shall submit himself to such 
medical examination within the time specified in this behalf by the Judge. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> The Medical Board shall undertake such medical examination of the 
Chairperson or the Member, as the case may be, as may be considered necessary to 
and submit a report to the Judge stating therein whether the incapacity is such 
as to render the Chairperson or the Member, as the case may be, unfit to 
continue in office. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> If the Chairperson or the Member, as the case may be, refuses to undergo 
such medical examination as considered necessary by the Medical Board, the Board 
shall submit a report to the Judge stating therein the examination which the 
Chairperson or the Member, as the case may be, has refused to undergo, and the 
Judge may, on receipt of such report, presume that the Chairperson or the 
Member, as the case may be, suffers from such physical or mental incapacity as 
is alleged in the article of charges referred to clause (a) of sub-rule (4). 

 </section><section><number>10</number> The Judge may, after considering the written statement of the 
Chairperson or the Member, as the case may be, and the Medical Board, if any, 
amend the article of charges referred to in clause (a) of sub-rule (4) and in 
such case, the Chairperson or the Member, as the case may be, shall be given a 
reasonable opportunity of presenting a fresh written statement of defence. 
 </section><section><number>11</number> The Central Government shall appoint an officer of that Government or an 
advocate to present the case against the Chairperson or the Member, as the case 
may be, before the Judge. 
 </section><section><number>12</number> Where the Central Government has appointed an advocate to present its 
case before the Judge, the Chairperson or the Member, as the case may be, shall 
also be allowed to present his case by an advocate chosen by him. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Application of the Departmental Inquiries (Enforcement of Witness 
and Production of Documents) Act, 1972 to inquiries under these rules. 
</title>The provisions of the Departmental Inquiries (Enforcement of Witness 
and Production of Documents) Act, 1972 (18 of 1972), shall apply to the 
inquiries made under these rules as they apply to departmental inquiries. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Powers of Judge. </title>The Judge shall not be bound by the 
procedure laid down by the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) but shall 
be guided by the principles of natural justice and shall have power to regulate 
his own procedure including the fixing of places and times of his inquiry. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Suspension of Chairperson or Member. </title>Notwithstanding 
anything contained in rule 4, and without any prejudice to any action being 
taken in accordance with the said rule, the President, keeping in view the 
gravity of charges may suspend the Chairperson or the Member, as the case may 
be, of the Tribunal against whom a complaint is under investigation or inquiry. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number> Subsistence allowance. </title>The payment of subsistence 
allowance to the Chairperson or the Member, as the case may be, under suspension 
shall be regulated in accordance with the rules and orders for the time being 
applicable to a Secretary to the Government of India belonging to the Indian 
Administrative Service. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>9</number> Inquiry Report. </title>After the conclusion of the 
investigation, the Judge shall submit his report to the President stating 
therein his findings and the reasons therefore on each of the articles of 
charges separately with such observations on the whole case as he thinks fit. 


</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Came into force on 27-10-2009.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>