<act><tid>796154</tid>
<title>THE ALL- INDIA INSTITUTE OF MEDICAL SCIENCES (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 24 OF <year>2002</year>
[ 24th May, <year>2002</year>.]

An Act further to amend the All- India Institute of Medical Sciences 
Act, <year>1956</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>543980</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>1324806</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
All- India Institute of Medical Sciences (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1093570</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>195074</tid>
<number> 2</number> Substitution of new section for section 23.- For section 23 of the 
All- India Institute of Medical Sciences Act, <year>1956</year> (25 of <year>1956</year>) 
 (hereinafter referred to as the principal Act), the following section 
shall be substituted, namely:-
" 23. Recognition of medical, dental and nursing qualifications 
granted by the Institute.- Notwithstanding anything contained in the 
Indian Medical Council Act, <year>1956</year> (102 of <year>1956</year>), the Dentists Act, <year>1948</year> 
 (16 of <year>1948</year>) and the Indian Nursing Council Act, 194 (48 of <year>1947</year>), the 
medical, dental or nursing degrees or diplomas, as the case may be, 
granted by the Institute under this Act shall be recognized-

<section><tid>84125</tid>
<number>a</number>medical qualifications for the purpose of the Indian Medical 
Council Act, <year>1956</year> (102 of <year>1956</year>) and shall be deemed to be included in 
the First Schedule to that Act;

</section>

<section><tid>572987</tid>
<number>b</number>dental qualifications for the purpose of the Dentists Act, <year>1948</year> 
 (16 of <year>1948</year>) and shall be deemed to be included in the Scheduled to 
that Act; and

</section>

<section><tid>188979</tid>
<number>c</number>nursing qualifications for the purpose of the Indian Nursing 
Council Act, <year>1947</year> (48 of <year>1947</year>) and shall be deemed to be included in 
the Schedule to that Act,".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>522305</tid>
<number>3</number>Substitution of new section for section 24.- For section 24 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
" 24. Grant of medical, dental or nursing degrees, diplomas, etc., by 
the Institute.- Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for 
the time being in force, the Institute shall have power to grant 
medical, dental or nursing degrees, diplomas and ther academic 
distinctions and titles under this Act.".

SUBHASH C. JAIN, 
Secy. to the Govt. of India.


</article>



 </act>