<act><title>


the Insurance Regulatory And Development Authority (Annual Report - Furnishing 
of ReturnS, Statements 
and Other particulars) Rules, 20001</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority 
(Annual Report - Furnishing of Returns, Statements and Other Particulars) Rules, 
2000.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date of their publication.
 
 


</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  “Act” means 
the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority Act, 1999;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  “Appendix” 
means an Appendix annexed to these rules;
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  All other 
words and expressions used in these rules but not defined, and defined in the 
Act shall have the same meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>3</number> Form, manner and the time of 
furnishing of returns, statements and other particulars.—
<section><number>1</number> The Authority shall furnish 
to the Central Government the Annual  Report-Returns, Statements and other 
particulars in regard to any proposed or existing programme for the promotion 
and the development of the insurance industry giving a true and full account of 
its activities in the form and manner prescribed in the appendix.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Annual Report - Returns, 
Statements and other particulars of the previous financial year referred to in 
sub-rule (1) above shall be submitted by the Authority to the Central Government 
within 9 months after the close of each financial year.
  </section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Form, manner and the 
time of furnishing of returns, statements and other particulars.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Authority shall furnish to the Central Government the Annual  
Report-Returns, Statements and other particulars in regard to any proposed or 
existing programme for the promotion and the development of the insurance 
industry giving a true and full account of its activities in the form and manner 
prescribed in the appendix.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Annual Report - 
Returns, Statements and other particulars of the previous financial year 
referred to in sub-rule (1) above shall be submitted by the Authority to the 
Central Government within 9 months after the close of each financial year.
 
 
</section></article><form>
 




the Insurance Regulatory And Development Authority (Annual Report - Furnishing 
of ReturnS, Statements  

and Other particulars) Rules, 2000
 


 
 




Appendix
 


[See rule 3]
 


Form of (Annual report - 
Returns, Statements and Other Particulars) of  

Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority
 



Part I
 




Policies and 
Programmes
 


     
(a)   Review of General Economic Environment
 


     
(b)   Appraisal of Insurance Market
 


     
(c)   Number and details of Authorised insurers/re-insurers
 


     
(d)   Policies and measures to develop Insurance Market
 


     
(e)   Research &amp; Development activities undertaken by the insurers
 


      
(f)   Review of:—
 


                   
(i)  protection of interests of policyholders
 


                  
(ii)  maintenance of solvency margins of insurers
 


                 
(iii)  monitoring of re-insurance
 


                 
(iv)  monitoring investments of the insurers
 


                  
(v)  health insurance
 


                 
(vi)  specified percentage of business to be done in rural sector
 


                
(vii)  pensions
 


                
(viii)  accounts and actuarial standards
 


                 
(ix)  directions, orders and regulations given by the Authority
 


                  
(x)  powers and functions delegated by the Authority
 


                 
(xi)  other policies and programmes having bearing on the working of the 
insurance market.
 



Part II
 




Review of working 
and operations of the Insurance Regulatory and  

Development Authority in respect of
 


         
(i)  Regulation of insurance/re-insurance companies
 


        
(ii)  Intermediaries associated with insurance business
 


        
(iii)  Professional institutes connected with insurance education
 


       
(iv)  Litigations, Appeals and Court pronouncements
 


        
(v)  International Cooperation in insurance
 


       
(vi)  Public Complaints
 


       
(vii)  Functioning of the Advisory Committee
 


      
(viii)  Functioning of Ombudsman
 


       
(ix)  Review of performance of various Committees set up from time to time  
by the IRDA
 


        
(x)  Review of the Advisory functions performed by the Authority from time 
to time
 


       
(xi)  Other activities having a bearing on the insurance market.
 



Part III
 




Statutory functions 
of the authority enshrined in the section 14 of the  

Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority Act, 1999
 



Part IV
 




Organisational 
matters of the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority
 


 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>