<act><tid>80115</tid>
<title>THE LEADERS AND CHIEF WHIPS OF RECOGNISED PARTIES AND GROUPS 
INPARLIAMENT (FACILITIES) ACT, <year>1998</year></title>

ACT NO. 5 OF <year>1999</year>
[ 7th January, <year>1999</year>.]

An Act to provide for facilities to Leaders and Chief Whips of 
recognised parties and groups in Parliament.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- ninth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-





<article><tid>1361064</tid>
<number> 1</number> 
<section><tid>446524</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title and commencement.- (1) This Act may be called  
the Leaders and Chief Whips of Recognised Parties and Groups in 
Parliament (Facilities) Act, <year>1998</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>496908</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1565574</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>1479055</tid>
<number>a</number>" recognised group" means,-

<subsection><tid>1275533</tid>
<number>i</number>in relation to the Council of States, every group of parties 
recognised for the purposes of this Act by the Chairman under the 
rules regulating the procedure of that House;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>476360</tid>
<number>ii</number>in relation to the House of the People, every group of 
parties recognised for the purposes of this Act by the Speaker 
under the rules regulating the procedure of that House;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1915083</tid>
<number>b</number>" recognised party" means,-

<subsection><tid>973209</tid>
<number>i</number>in relation to the Council of States, every party which is 
recognised for the purposes of this Act by the Chairman under the 
rules regulating the procedure of that House;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>231438</tid>
<number>ii</number>in relation to the House of the People, every party which is 
recognised for the purposes of this Act by the Speaker under the 
rules regulating the procedure of that House.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1833261</tid>
<number>3</number>Facilities to the Leaders and Chief Whips of recognised 
groups and parties.- Subject to any rules made in this behalf by 
the Central overnment, each leader (other than the Leader of the  
Opposition as defined in section 2 of the Salary and Allowances 
  of Leaders of Opposition in Parliament Act, <year>1977</year>)  (33 of <year>1977</year>) 
and each Chief Whip of a reconised group and a recognised party 
shall be entitled to telephone and secretarial facilities.


</article>



<article><tid>684080</tid>
<number> 4</number> Power to make rules.-
<section><tid>1877845</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out 
the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1937069</tid>
<number>2</number>Every rule made under sub- section (1) shall be laid, as soon 
as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, 
while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which 
may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive 
sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both 
Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both 
Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no 
effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such 
modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>240313</tid>
<number> 5</number> Amendment of section 3 of Act 10 of <year>1959</year>.- In the Parliament 
 (Prevention of Disqualification) Act, <year>1959</year>, in section 3,-
<section><tid>1210758</tid>
<number>i</number>after clause (ab), the following clause shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" (ac) the office of each leader of a recognised party and a 
recognised group in either House of Parliament;";


</section>

<section><tid>1816298</tid>
<number>ii</number>after Explanation 2, the following Explanation shall be 
inserted, namely:-
Explanation 3.- In clause (ac), the expressions" recognised 
party" and" recognised group" shall have the meanings assigned to 
them in the Leaders and Chief Whips of Recognised Parties and 
Groups in Parliament (Facilities) Act, <year>1998</year>.'.



</section>

</article>



 </act>