<act><title>THE
EMPLOYEES’ STATE INSURANCE
(CENTRAL) RULES, 19501


</title> 

   


   


 <article><number>1</number>
Short title and extent.—
<section><number>1</number>
These Rules may be called the Employees’ State Insurance (Central) Rules,
1950. 


 </section><section><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>2</number>
They extend to the whole of India <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[***]]. 


   






</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>—In these rules, unless there is anything repug­nant in the subject or context,— 
 <section><number>1</number> “the Act” means the Employees' State Insurance Act, 1948 (Act XXXIV of 1948); 
 
 
 Provided that where an employee receives wages without working on any day during such wage period, he shall be deemed to have worked for 26, 13, 6 or 1 days or day if the wage period, be a month, a fortnight, a week or a day respectively. 
 Explanation.— Where any night shift continues beyond midnight, the period of the night shift after midnight shall be counted for reckoning the day worked as part of the day preceding;] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>1A</number> “average daily wages during a contribution period” in respect of an employee, means the aggregate amount of wages payable to him during that period divided by the number of days for which such wages were payable;] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>1B</number> “Average daily wages during a wage period” means— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> in respect of an employee who is employed on time-rate basis, the amount of wage which would have been payable to him for the complete wage period had he worked on all the working days in that wage period, divided by 26 if he is monthly rated, 13 if he is fortnightly rated, 6 if he is weekly rated and 1 if he is daily rated; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> in respect of an employee employed on any other basis, the amount of wages earned during the complete wages period in the contribution period divided by the number of days in full or part for which he has worked for wages in that wage period: 
</subsection>
</section><section><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>1C</number> “benefit period” means the period not exceeding six consecu­tive months corresponding to the contribution period, as may be specified in the regulations;] 
 </section><section><number>2</number> “Chairman” means the Chairman of the Corporation, the Stand­ing Committee or the Medical Benefit Council, as the case may be; 
 </section><section><footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<number>2A</number> “Contribution period” means the period not exceeding six consecutive months, as may be specified in the regulations;] 
 </section><section><number>3</number> “Form” means a form appended to these Rules; 
 </section><section><number>4</number> “Fund” means the Employees' State Insurance Fund; 
 </section><section><number>5</number> “Government Securities” means Government Securities as de­fined in the Indian Securities Act, 1920; 
 </section><section><number>6</number> “immovable property” includes land, benefit to arise out of land, things attached to the earth, or permanently fastened to anything attached to the earth; 
 </section><section><number>7</number> “movable property” means property of every description except immovable property; 
 </section><section><footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<number>7A</number> “standard benefit rate” means average daily wages obtained by dividing the total wages paid during the contribution period by the number of days for which these wages were paid;] 
 </section><section><number>8</number> “State Medical Commissioner” means a duly registered medical practitioner including a medical officer in the service of a State Government appointed as such by the Corporation; 
 </section><section><number>9</number> “year” shall mean the financial year, that is to say, the period beginning from the first of April and ending with the thirty first of March of the year following; 
 </section><section><footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<number>10</number> all other words and expressions shall have the meaning respectively assigned to them in the Act.] 



 
 ‘(1A) “Average daily wages during a contribution period” means, in respect of any employee for the purpose of the daily rate of sickness benefit, maternity benefit, disablement benefit and dependant's benefit, the sum equal to one hundred and fifteen percent of the aggregate amount of wages payable to him during that period, divided by the number of days (including paid holi­days and leave days) for which such wages were payable.'. 




 
 ‘(7A) “Standard benefit rate” means the daily rate of benefit specified in Rule 54;'. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>—In these rules, unless there is anything repug­nant in the subject or context,— 
 <section><number>1</number> “the Act” means the Employees' State Insurance Act, 1948 (Act XXXIV of 1948); 
 
 
 Provided that where an employee receives wages without working on any day during such wage period, he shall be deemed to have worked for 26, 13, 6 or 1 days or day if the wage period, be a month, a fortnight, a week or a day respectively. 
 Explanation.— Where any night shift continues beyond midnight, the period of the night shift after midnight shall be counted for reckoning the day worked as part of the day preceding;] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>1A</number> “average daily wages during a contribution period” in respect of an employee, means the aggregate amount of wages payable to him during that period divided by the number of days for which such wages were payable;] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[<number>1B</number> “Average daily wages during a wage period” means— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> in respect of an employee who is employed on time-rate basis, the amount of wage which would have been payable to him for the complete wage period had he worked on all the working days in that wage period, divided by 26 if he is monthly rated, 13 if he is fortnightly rated, 6 if he is weekly rated and 1 if he is daily rated; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> in respect of an employee employed on any other basis, the amount of wages earned during the complete wages period in the contribution period divided by the number of days in full or part for which he has worked for wages in that wage period: 
</subsection>
</section><section><footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[<number>1C</number> “benefit period” means the period not exceeding six consecu­tive months corresponding to the contribution period, as may be specified in the regulations;] 
 </section><section><number>2</number> “Chairman” means the Chairman of the Corporation, the Stand­ing Committee or the Medical Benefit Council, as the case may be; 
 </section><section><footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[<number>2A</number> “Contribution period” means the period not exceeding six consecutive months, as may be specified in the regulations;] 
 </section><section><number>3</number> “Form” means a form appended to these Rules; 
 </section><section><number>4</number> “Fund” means the Employees' State Insurance Fund; 
 </section><section><number>5</number> “Government Securities” means Government Securities as de­fined in the Indian Securities Act, 1920; 
 </section><section><number>6</number> “immovable property” includes land, benefit to arise out of land, things attached to the earth, or permanently fastened to anything attached to the earth; 
 </section><section><number>7</number> “movable property” means property of every description except immovable property; 
 </section><section><footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[<number>7A</number> “standard benefit rate” means average daily wages obtained by dividing the total wages paid during the contribution period by the number of days for which these wages were paid;] 
 </section><section><number>8</number> “State Medical Commissioner” means a duly registered medical practitioner including a medical officer in the service of a State Government appointed as such by the Corporation; 
 </section><section><number>9</number> “year” shall mean the financial year, that is to say, the period beginning from the first of April and ending with the thirty first of March of the year following; 
 </section><section><footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[<number>10</number> all other words and expressions shall have the meaning respectively assigned to them in the Act.] 



 
 ‘(1A) “Average daily wages during a contribution period” means, in respect of any employee for the purpose of the daily rate of sickness benefit, maternity benefit, disablement benefit and dependant's benefit, the sum equal to one hundred and fifteen percent of the aggregate amount of wages payable to him during that period, divided by the number of days (including paid holi­days and leave days) for which such wages were payable.'. 




 
 ‘(7A) “Standard benefit rate” means the daily rate of benefit specified in Rule 54;'. 

</section></article> 

 


 <article>


1[<number>2A</number> Election of 
members of Parliament to the Corporation.—The 
House of the People (Lok Sabha) and the Council of States (Rajya Sabha) shall 
elect, in such manner as the Speaker of the House of the People or as the case 
may be, the Chairman of the Council of States may direct, two Members of the 
House of the People (Lok Sabha) and one Member of the Council of State (Rajya 
Sabha) to be Members of the Corporation.]
 
 



</article> 

 


 <article>
<number>3</number> Election of members 
of the Standing Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chair­man of the meeting shall, at a meeting of the Corporation at which it 
is proposed to elect members for the Standing Committee under clause (c) of 
section 8, invite members to propose names from among members of the Corporation 
belonging to the group from which election is to be made. The names proposed 
shall be duly seconded by another member of the Corporation.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the number proposed 
from any group for election does not exceed the number of vacancies to be filled 
from that group, the persons whose names have been so proposed shall be declared 
elected to the Standing Committee.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If the number proposed 
for election from a group exceeds the number of vacancies to be filled therefrom, 
each member of the Corporation present at the meeting shall be given a ballot 
paper containing the names of all the candidates proposed and he shall be 
required to vote thereon for as many candidates from group as there are 
vacancies to be filled up. Not more than one vote shall be given in favour of 
any one candidate. If any member votes for more candidates than there are 
vacancies in the group or gives more than one vote in favour of any one 
candidate, all his votes shall be deemed to be invalid.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The persons getting 
the highest number of votes shall be declared by the Chairman, at the meeting or 
as soon thereafter as possible, as duly elected to the Standing Committee:
 
Provided that where an 
equality of votes is found to exist bet­ween any candidates and the addition of 
one vote will entitle any of the candidates to be declared to be elected, the 
determination of the person or persons to whom such one additional vote shall be 
deemed to have been given shall be made by lot to be drawn in the presence of 
the Chairman and in such manner as he may deter­mine.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If any question shall 
arise as to the validity of any election it shall be referred to the Central 
Government whose decision in the matter shall be final.
</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>4</number> Restoration to 
membership.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A member of the Corporation, the Standing Committee or the Medical Benefit 
Council, who ceases to be a member by virtue of section 12, shall be informed of 
such cessation by a letter sent to him by registered post. The letter shall also 
indicate that if he desires restoration to membership, he may apply therefor 
within thirty days from the receipt of the letter.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The application under 
sub-rule (1) indicate the reasons which prevented him from attending three 
consecutive meetings and shall be addressed to the chairman concerned.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The application shall 
be placed before the next meeting of the Corporation, the Standing Committee or 
the Medical Benefit Council, as the case may be, and if a majority of the 
members present at such meeting are satisfied that the reasons for fai­lure to 
attend three consecutive meetings are adequate, he shall be restored to 
membership immediately after a restoration to that effect is adopted.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The benefit of 
restoration to membership as provided for in this rule shall be allowed to a 
member only once during any one term as a member.
</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>5</number> Fees and allowances 
of members.—


1[
<section><number>1</number> Subject to 
the provi­sions of sub-rules 2 and 3, every non-official member of the 
Corporation, Standing Committee or the Medical Benefit Council shall be allowed 
travelling and daily allowance for attending the meetings of the Corporation or 
the Standing Committee or the Medical Benefit Council, as the case may be, at 
the following rates:—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number> Travelling Allowance:
 <subsubsection>
         <number>A</number>  A 
non-official member residing at the place where a meeting is held shall be 
allowed the actual expenditure incurred by him on conveyance subject to the 
maximum of rupees fifty for each day on which he attends one or more meetings;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
         <number>B</number>  a 
non-official member, not residing at the place where a meeting is held, shall be 
allowed to draw—
 <subsubsubsection>
              <number>a</number>  actual 
expenditure incurred by him on air journey by economy (Tourist) class; or
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
              <number>b</number>  actual 
expenditure incurred by him on journey by rail by 2nd Class A.C. two tier 
sleeper or First Class, as the case may be;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
              <number>c</number>  actual 
fare or expenditure incurred on road journey by taxi or own car or auto-rickshaw 
or bus (other than an air conditioned bus) but not exceeding the rates notified 
by the concerned Direc­tor of Transport for journey by taxi or auto-rickshaw. 
When the journey is performed between places connected by railway, mileage would 
be limited to what would have been admissible to the member under clause (b) of 
this item.
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number> Daily Allowance:
 <subsubsection>
         <number>A</number>  A 
non-official member residing at a place where a meeting is held shall not be 
entitled to any daily allowance;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
         <number>B</number>  A 
non-official member, not residing at a place where a meet­ing is held shall be 
paid daily allowance at the rate of Rs. 150 (Rupees one hundred and fifty only) 
per day if the member stays in a hotel and Rs. 100 (Rupees one hundred only) per 
day if the member does not stay in a hotel:
 
                 Provided 
that the daily allowance shall be calculated for the entire absence from the 
normal place of residence of the non-official member on calendar day basis; 
i.e., midnight to midnight as under:
 
              For absence 
not exceeding 6 hours ...................................................................................... Nil
 
              For absence 
exceeding 6 hours but not exceeding 12 hours..................................................... 70%
 
              For absence 
exceeding 12 hours ...................................................................................... 100%
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A non-official member 
of the Corporation, of Standing Commit­tee or the Medical Benefit Council who is 
a Member of Parliament or a Member of State Legislature shall be paid travelling 
allow­ance and daily allowance in accordance with the provisions of the salary, 
allowances and pension of Members of Parliament Act, 1954 (30 of 1954) or the 
respective provision of the law pertaining to the members of the concerned State 
Legislature.
 </section><section>
<number>2A</number> Travelling and daily 
allowance shall be allowed if a member certifies that he has not drawn any 
travelling or daily allowance from any other source in respect of the journey 
and halt for which the claim is made.
 </section><section>
<number>2B</number> The daily and 
travelling allowance shall also be payable in respect of the meetings of any 
sub-committee set up by the Corpo­ration, the Standing Committee or the Medical 
Benefit Council].
 

2[(3) For attending 
meeting of the Corporation, the Standing Com­mittee, Medical Benefit Council or 
meetings of Sub-Committee set up by the Corporation, Standing Committee or the 
Medical Benefit Council, an official member of the Central Government shall draw 
his travelling allowance from his department on a scale admissi­ble to him under 
the Central Government rules and the amount so drawn shall, on a demand being 
made therefor by the Central Government be re-imbursed by the Corporation to 
that Government. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Payments shall not be 
made to a non-official member earlier than the last date upon which the 
allowance is claimed. The travelling allowance for both the onward and return 
journeys will be includ­ed in the travelling allowance bill and the payment made 
thereof treated as final, irrespective of the date of completion of the journey. 
The Director-General, Employees’ State Insurance Corporation, will however, 
obtain a formal intimation from the non-official member to the effect that the 
return journey has, in fact, been completed.]
 
 




</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>6</number> Minimum number of 
meetings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Corporation 

1[and the Medical 
Benefit Council] shall meet at least twice each year. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Standing Committee


2[***] shall meet 
at least four times each year. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Chairman may, 
whenever he thinks fit, and shall, within fifteen days of the receipt of a 
requisition in writing from not less than one-half of the members of the body 
concerned, call a meeting thereof.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Any requisition made 
under this rule shall specify the object of the meeting proposed to be called.

 
 




</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>7</number> Roll of Members.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Corporation shall maintain a Roll of Members separately for the Corporation, 
the Standing Committee and the Medical Benefit Council. The name and the address 
of each member shall be stated therein. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If a member changes 
his address, he shall notify such change to the Corporation for the correction 
of his address in the Roll. 
</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>8</number> Notice of meeting 
and list of business.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chairman shall decide the date, time and place of every meeting. A notice of 
not less than twenty-one days from the date of issue shall ordinarily be given 
to every member, of each meeting of the Corporation, the Standing Committee or 
the Medical Benefit Council, as the case may be. Such notice may be sent to 
every member by post or in any other suitable manner. A list of business 
proposed to be transacted shall, after approval by the Chairman, be posted 
alongwith the notice. Brief notes on each item of the agenda shall be sent along 
with the agenda or as soon thereafter as possible. If it is necessary to convene 
an emergency meeting, a reasonable notice thereof shall be given to every 
member. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No business other than 
that for which a meeting is convened shall be considered at that meeting, except 
with the permission of the Chairman of the meeting. 
</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>9</number> Chairman of the 
meeting.—The 
Chairman, or in his absence the Vice-Chairman, if any of the Corporation, the 
Standing Committee or the Medical Benefit Council, as the case may be, shall 
preside at the meetings. In the event of the absence of both the Chair­man and 
the Vice-Chairman, if any, the members present may elect one from amongst 
themselves to preside. 
</article> 

 


 <article>
<number>10</number> Quorum.—No 
business shall be transacted at any meeting unless a quorum of 

1[fifteen] members 
in the case of the Corpora­tion, five members in the case of the Standing 
Committee and seven members in the case of the Medical Benefit Council, is 
present: 
 
Provided that if at any 
meeting there is not a sufficient number of members present to form a quorum, 
the Chairman of the meeting may adjourn the meeting to a date not later than 
seven days from the date of the original meeting and it shall thereupon be 
lawful to dispose of the business at such adjourned meeting irrespective of the 
number of members attending. 
 
 



</article> 

 


 <article>
<number>11</number> Disposal of 
business.—Any 
business which requires considera­tion by the Corporation, the Standing 
Committee or the Medical Benefit Council shall be considered at a meeting 
thereof: 
 
Provided that the Chairman 
may, if he thinks fit, direct that the necessary papers may be referred for 
opinion to all members: 
 
Provided further that the 
decision on any question which is so re­ferred shall be acted upon if supported 
by not less than a two-third majority of the members of the body concerned. In 
other cases or where the Chairman so decides, the question shall be considered 
at a duly convened meeting.
</article> 

 


 <article>
<number>12</number> Proceedings of the 
meetings.—The 
proceedings of each meeting showing inter alia the name of the members 
present thereat, shall be forwarded to each member of the Corporation, the 
Standing Committee or the Medical Benefit Council, as the case may be, and to 
the Central Government as soon after the meeting as possible and in any case not 
later than four weeks after the meeting. 
 <section>
<number>2</number> The minutes of each 
meeting shall be confirmed with such modifications as may be considered 
necessary at the next meeting.
</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>13</number> Minute-books.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The minutes of a meeting of the Corpora­tion the Standing Committee and the 
Medical Benefit Council shall be kept in separate books (hereinafter referred to 
as minute-books) and shall be signed by the Chairman of the meeting at which 
proceedings are confirmed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A copy of the minutes 
so confirmed shall be forwarded to the Central Government within fifteen days 
from the date of such confirmation.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The minute-books shall 
be kept open at the principal office of the Corporation during office hours on 
working days for inspection free of charge by any member of the Corporation.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The minute-books of 
the Medical-Benefit Council shall be kept open at the principal office of the 
Corporation during office hours on workings days for inspection free of charge 
by any member of the Medical Benefit Council.
</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>14</number> Powers and duties 
of the Medical Benefit Council.—The 
powers and duties of the Medical Benefit Council shall be–
 <section>
<number>1</number> to advise the 
Corporation in regard to the constitution, setting up duties and powers of the 
Regional and Local Medical Benefit Councils.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> to make 
recommendations to the Corporation in regard to—
 <subsection>
          <number>i</number>  the scale 
and nature of medical benefit provided at hospitals, dispensaries, clinics and 
other institutions and the nature and extent of the medicines, staff and 
equipment which shall be maintained at such institutions and the extent to which 
these fall short of the desired standard;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>ii</number>  the medical 
formulary for use in connection with the medical benefit provided under the Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>iii</number>  medical 
certification, including the procedure and the forms for such certification, 
statistical returns, registers and other medical records;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>iv</number>  measures 
undertaken for the improvement of the health and welfare of insured persons, and 
the rehabilitation and re-employment of insured persons, disabled or injured.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> to advise the 
Corporation on any matter relating to the professional conduct of any medical 
practitioner employed for the purpose of providing medical benefit under the 
Act.
</section></article> 

 


 



 <article>

1[<number>15</number> Salaries, 
allowances and conditions of service of the Direc­tor-General and Financial 
Commissioner.—
<section><number>1</number> Director-General shall be in the scale of pay of Rs.


2[22400-24500] and 
the Financial Commissioner shall be in the scale of pay of Rs. 

2[18400-22400].
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Director-General 
and the Financial Commissioner shall receive dearness allowance, city 
compensatory allowance, house rent allowance, travelling allowance and other 
allowances, at such rates, and such provident fund, leave and medical benefits 
as may be sanctioned for the officers of the Central Government drawing similar 
salary at the place where they are posted: 
 
Provided that where the 
Director-General or the Financial Commis­sioner is a person already in the 
service of the Corporation, he shall be entitled to pension, gratuity and other 
superannuation benefits to which he would have been otherwise entitled but for 
his appointment as the Director-General or the Financial Commis­sioner: 

 
Provided further that the 
pay, allowances and other conditions of service of the Director-General or the 
Financial Commissioner, if he is a person already in the service of the 
Government, shall be such as may be determined by the Central Government in each 
individual case.]
 
 




</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>16</number> Powers and duties 
of the Director-General.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The powers and duties of the Director-General shall be— 
 <subsection>
          <number>i</number>  to act as 
the Chief Executive Officer of the Corporation;
 
 

1[***]
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>iii</number>  to 
convene, under the orders of the Chairman, meetings of the Corporation, the 
Standing Committee and the Medical Benefit Council in accordance with the Act 
and the Rules and to implement the decisions reached at the meetings; 

 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>iv</number>  to enter 
into contracts on behalf of the Corporation in accordance with the Act or the 
Rules or Regulations made thereun­der, or the general or special instructions of 
the Corporation or the Standing Committee; 
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>v</number>  to furnish 
all returns and documents required by the Act or the Rules to the Central 
Government and to correspond with the Central Government and the State 
Governments upon all matters concerning the Corporation;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>vi</number>  to undertake 
such other duties and to exercise such other powers as may, from time to time be 
entrusted or delegated to him. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Director-General 
may, with the approval of the Standing Committee, by general or special order, 
delegate any of his powers or duties under the Rules or the regulations or under 
any resolu­tion of the Corporation or the Standing Committee, as the case may 
be, to any person subordinate to him. The exercise or dis­charge of any of the 
powers or duties so delegated shall be subjected to such restrictions, 
limitations and conditions, if any, as the Director-General may, with the 
approval of the Standing Committee, impose.
 
 



</section></article> 

 


 

1[***]
 
 



 

 


 

1[***]
 
 



 

 


 <article>
<number>19</number> Powers and duties 
of the 

1[Financial 
Commissioner].—The 
powers and duties of the 

1[Financial 
Commissioner] shall, subject to the control of the Director-General be—
 <section>
          <number>i</number>  to maintain 
the accounts by the Corporation and to arrange for the compilation of accounts 
by the collection of returns from the Centres and Regions;
 </section><section>
         <number>ii</number>  to prepare 
the budget of the Corporation;
 </section><section>
         <number>iii</number>  to arrange 
for internal audit of the accounts of the Cen­tres and Regions and of the 
receipts and payments thereat;
 </section><section>
        <number>iv</number>  to make 
recommendations for the investment for the funds of the Corporation; and
 </section><section>
         <number>v</number>  to undertake 
such other duties and to exercise such other powers as may, from time to time, 
be entrusted or delegated to him.
 
 



</section></article> 

 


 <article>

1[<number>20</number> Creation 
of posts by the Corporation.—The powers for creation of posts vested in the 
Corporation under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 17 of the Act shall be exercised by 
the Corporation in relation to posts carrying maximum scale of pay of Rs. 

2[14300-18300.]
 
 





</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[<number>20A</number> 
Appeals to Medical Appeal Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If the insured person or the Corporation is not satisfied with the decision of 
the Medical Board, the insured person or the Corporation may appeal against such 
decision to the Medical Appeal Tribunal referred to in sub-section (2) of 
section 54A by presenting an application within three months from the date of 
communication of the said decision to the insured person or the Corporation as 
the case may be:
 
Provided that the Medical 
Appeal Tribunal may entertain an application after the period of three months, 
if it is satisfied that the applicant had sufficient reason for not presenting 
the application within the said period.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The application, 
referred to in sub-rule (1) shall be in form2 and shall contain a statement of 
the grounds upon which the appeal is made.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The application may be 
sent to the Chairman of the Medical Appeal Tribunal by registered post or may be 
presented personal­ly.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[<number>20B</number> 
Appeals to Employees’ Insurance Court.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The insured person or the Corporation may appeal to the Employees’ Insurance 
Court by presenting an application within three months of the date of 
communication of the decision of the Medical Board or of the Medical Appeal 
Tribunal to the insured person or the Corporation, as the case may be:
 
Provided that the 
Employees’ Insurance Court may entertain an application after the period of 
three months, if it is satisfied that the applicant had sufficient reason for 
not presenting the application within the said period.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The rules made by the 
State Government in respect of the forms and manner to be followed in presenting 
applications to the Employees’ Insurance Court, shall be applicable to the 
appli­cations presented under this rule.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[<number>20B</number> 
Appeals to Employees’ Insurance Court.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The insured person or the Corporation may appeal to the Employees’ Insurance 
Court by presenting an application within three months of the date of 
communication of the decision of the Medical Board or of the Medical Appeal 
Tribunal to the insured person or the Corporation, as the case may be:
 
Provided that the 
Employees’ Insurance Court may entertain an application after the period of 
three months, if it is satisfied that the applicant had sufficient reason for 
not presenting the application within the said period.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The rules made by the 
State Government in respect of the forms and manner to be followed in presenting 
applications to the Employees’ Insurance Court, shall be applicable to the 
appli­cations presented under this rule.]
 
 



</section></article> 

   


 <article><number>21</number>
Bank or banks for depositing the Fund.—
<section><number>1</number>
All moneys accru­ing or payable to the Fund shall be received by such officers
of the Corporation as may be authorised by it in this behalf. The amount so
received shall as soon as practicable be acknowledged by a receipt in Form I and
deposited in the Reserve or the <footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[State
Bank of India or any of its subsidiaries] <footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[or
the Nationalised Banks] to the account of the Fund: 


 Provided
that any moneys may also be paid directly to the account of the Fund in any such
bank. 


 <footcitenum>20</footcitenum>[Explanation.—‘Nationalised
Bank’ means a corresponding new bank specified in the First Schedule to the
Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings) Act, 1970 (5 of
1970) or a corresponding new bank specified in the First Schedule to the Banking
Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings) Act, 1980 (40 of 1980).] 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The receipt book in Form I shall be numbered serially by machine and the unused
forms shall be kept in the custody of the<footcitenum>21</footcitenum>[Financial
Commissioner] or such other officer of the Corpora­tion as may be authorised by
the Corporation in this behalf.  


   








</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>22</number> Procedure for 
crediting moneys to the Banks.—
<section><number>1</number> 
All moneys accruing or payable to the Corporation shall be credited to the 
approved bank and not utilised directly for any purpose.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The bank or banks 
shall be required at the end of every calendar month to furnish to the 
Corporation or such officer as may be authorised by it in this behalf, a 
statement of the amounts deposited in and withdrawn from the Fund during the 
month. These statements shall be examined by the Director-General before the 
expiry of a period of two months following the period to which the statements 
relate.
</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>23</number> Purpose and manner 
of payment out of the Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The accounts of the Fund shall be operated on by such officers as may be 
authorised by the Standing Committee with the approval of the Corporation.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No payment shall be 
made by the bank or banks out of the Fund except on a cheque signed by such 
officers as may be authorised under sub-rule (1).
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any payment in excess 
on one hundred rupees shall be made by means of a cheque signed as aforesaid and 
not in any other way unless specifically authorised by the Standing Committee:
 
Provided that payment of 
salaries to the employees of the Corpo­ration drawing a basic salary not 
exceeding rupees two hundred and fifty a month may be made in cash.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> No payment shall be 
made out of the Fund unless the expendi­ture is covered by a current budget 
grant:
 
Provided that in the 
absence of a current budget grant, the Corporation may authorise payments either 
generally or for any particular case:
 
Provided further that the 
payment of benefits to insured person under the provisions of the Act and of the 
pay and allowances of duly sanctioned posts shall not be withheld for want of a 
sanc­tioned budget grant.
</section></article> 

 


 <article>


1[<number>23A</number> Promotion of 
measures for the improvement of health and welfare of insured persons.—For 
the promotion of measures for the improvement of health and welfare of insured 
persons, and for the rehabilitation and re-employment of insured persons who 
have been disabled or injured, the Corporation may incur an expendi­ture upto a 
limit of 

2[rupees three 
hundred crores] per year from the Employees’ State Insurance Fund.]
 
 




</article> 

 


 <article>
<number>24</number> Circumstances in 
which cheques may be drawn.—Before 
any person authorised under rule 23 signs a cheque, he shall satisfy himself 
that the sum for which the cheque is drawn is:—
 <section>
          <number>i</number> required for 
a purpose or work specifically sanctioned by the proper authority and covered by 
a current budget grant, and
 </section><section>
         <number>ii</number> required for 
any payment referred to and specified under section 28:
 
Provided that in the 
absence of a current budget grant, the Corporation may authorise payment either 
generally or for any particular case:
 
Provided further that the 
payment of benefits to insured persons under the provisions of the Act and of 
the pay and allowances of duly sanctioned posts shall not be withheld for want 
of a sanc­tioned budget grant.
</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>25</number> Acquisition of 
property.—Subject 
to the provisions of rule 29 and such conditions, as may, from time to time, be 
laid down by the Corporation, the Director-General may, for the purposes of this 
Act, require on behalf of the Corporation movable or immova­ble property:
 
Provided that sanction of 
the Standing Committee shall be re­quired for the exchange of any immovable 
property, for taking of any property on lease for a term exceeding twelve 
months, or for the acceptance of any gift or bequest of property burdened by an 
obligation.
</article> 

 


 <article>
<number>26</number> Disposal of 
property.—Subject 
to the provisions of rule 29 and such conditions as may be laid down by the 
Corporation from time to time, the Director-General may—
 <section>
          <number>i</number> dispose of, 
by sale or exchange, any movable property belong­ing to the Corporation, the 
value of which does not exceed ten thousand rupees in each case, or grant for 
any term not exceeding twelve months a lease of any immovable property belonging 
to the Corporation;
 </section><section>
         <number>ii</number> with the 
sanction of the Standing Committee, lease, sell or otherwise dispose of any 
movable or immovable property belonging to the Corporation.
</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>27</number> Investment, 
transfer or realisation of the Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> 
All moneys belonging to the Fund which are not immediately required for expenses 
properly defrayable under the Act, may, subject to the approval of the Standing 
Committee, be invested by the Direc­tor-General—
 <subsection>
          <number>i</number> in 
Government securities including Treasury Deposit Receipt; or
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>ii</number> in 
securities mentioned or referred to in clauses (a) to (d) of section 20 of the 
Indian Trusts Act, 1882 (II of 1882); or
 

          1[(iii)  
as fixed deposit in the Reserve or the State Bank of India or any of its 
subsidiaries or a corresponding new bank constituted under section 3 of the 
Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings Act, 1970 (5 of 
1970).]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Money belonging to the 
Fund shall not be invested in any other manner except with the prior approval of 
the Central Gov­ernment.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any investment made 
under this rule may, subject to the provisions of sub-rules (1) and (2), be 
varied, transposed or realised from time to time:
 
Provided, however, that if 
such variation, transposition or realisation is likely to result in a loss, the 
prior approval of the Central Government shall be obtained.
 

2[Explanation.—The 
approval of the Central Government shall not be required merely on the ground 
that the value of the security on its maturity is less than the price at which 
it was purchased.]
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Central Government 
may, at any time, direct the vacation in part or in whole, or prohibit 
investment, in any security or class of securities or any land or building.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> All dividends, 
interest or other sums received in respect of any investment shall, as soon as 
possible after receipt, be paid into or credited to the account of the Fund.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The expenses of, or 
the loss, if any, arising from any in­vestment shall be charged to the Fund and 
the profit, if any, from the sale or any investment shall also accrue to the 
Fund.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The approval under 
sub-rules (1) and (2) of the Standing Committee or the Central Government, as 
the case may be, may be given with or without any conditions either generally or 
in any particular case.
 
 




</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>28</number> Raising and 
repayment of loans.—
<section><number>1</number> 
(i) The Corporation may, in pursuance of a resolution passed at a meeting of the 
Standing Committee, and with the prior approval of the Central Government, raise 
loans for the purposes of the Act.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> In particular and 
without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, the Corporation may 
raise loans—
 <subsubsection>
         <number>a</number> for the 
acquisition of land/or the raising of buildings thereon; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
         <number>b</number> to repay a 
loan raised under this rule; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
         <number>c</number> for any other 
purpose approved by the Central Government.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> All loans under this 
rule shall be obtained—
 <subsection>
          <number>i</number> from the 
Central Government on such rates of interest and on such terms as to the time 
and method of repayment as the Central Government may specify; or
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>ii</number> with the 
approval of the Central Government, from the Re­serve or the 

1[State Bank of 
India or any of its subsidiaries] or any other scheduled bank.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Where a loan is 
obtained from the Reserve or the State Bank of India or any of its subsidiaries 
as provided in clause (ii) of sub-rule (2), the Corporation may, with the 
approval of the Central Government, grant mortgages of all or any of the 
property vested in it for securing the repayment of the sums so advanced, with 
interest.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> All payments due from 
the Corporation for interest on the repayment of loans shall be made in such 
manner and at such time as may have been agreed upon:
 
Provided that the 
Corporation may apply any sums which can be so applied, in repaying any amount 
due in respect of the principal of any loan although in repayment of the same 
may not be due.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> No expenditure 
incurred out to loan shall be charged by the Corporation to capital, except with 
the previous sanction (or under the direction) of the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The Corporation shall 
submit to the Central Government an annual statement by the thirtieth of April 
each year showing the loans raised and repayments made during the preceding 
year.
 
 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>29</number> Procedure for execution of 
contracts.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Corporation may enter into and perform all such contracts as it may consider 
necessary or expedient for carrying into effect the provisions of the 
Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every contract made under or 
for any purpose of the Act shall be made on behalf of the 
Corporation—
 <subsection>          
<number>i</number>  by the Director-General; or
 </subsection><subsection>         
<number>ii</number> subject to such conditions as it may specify by such member or officer of 
the Corporation as it may authorise:
 Provided that the prior sanction 
of the Standing Committee shall be obtained in respect of any contract involving 
an expenditure exceeding 1[rupees five lakhs].
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> Every contract entered into by 
any person as provided in sub-rule (2) shall be entered into in such manner and 
form as would bind him if it were made on his own behalf and may in like manner 
and form be varied or discharged:
 Provided that the common or 
official seal, as the case may be, of the Corporation shall be affixed to every 
contract for amounts exceeding one thousand rupees.
  


</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>30</number> Seal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The common seal of the Corporation shall remain in the custody of the 
Director-General and shall not be affixed to any instrument except in the 
presence of the Director-General or two members of the Standing Committee, and 
the Director-General or the said two members shall sign the contract in token of 
the fact that the same was sealed in his or their presence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Corporation shall 
have for use at each of such other of its offices, as it may specify, an 
official seal which shall be a facsimile of the common seal of the Corporation 
with addition of the name of the office where it is to be used.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The official seal 
shall not be affixed to any instrument except in the presence of such person or 
persons as the Standing Committee may authorise in this behalf and such person 
or persons shall sign the instrument in token of the fact that the same was 
sealed in his or their presence.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> An instrument to which 
an official seal is duly affixed shall bind the Corporation as if it had been 
sealed with the common seal of the Corporation.
</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>31</number> Preparation and 
submission of annual budget estimates.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Budget estimates of the Corporation for each financial year beginning on the 
first of April and ending on the thirty-first of March next shall be prepared by 
the Chief Accounts Officer in such form as the Central Government may, from time 
to time, direct and shall be submitted with his recommendations by the 
Director-General to the Standing Committee for approval at a meeting of the 
Standing Committee to be held before the first of 

1[February] of the 
preceding year.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A copy of the budget 
estimates shall be sent to each member of the Standing Committee and of the 
Corporation at least seven clear days before the meeting of the Standing 
Committee or the Corporation at which these estimates are to be considered.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Standing Committee 
shall consider and approve the budget estimates with such changes as it may 
consider necessary.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The budget estimates 
as approved by the Standing Committee shall be placed before a meeting of the 
Corporation to be held before the twentieth of February of the preceding year.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The budget estimates 
as passed by the Corporation shall be authenticated by affixing the common seal 
of the Corporation and shall be submitted to the Central Government under 
section 32, not later than the first day of March next following.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> It shall be open to 
the Central Government to make such alterations in the budget estimates as may 
be considered neces­sary before according approval.
 

2[(7) The budget 
estimates as finally adopted by the Corporation and as approved by the Central 
Government shall be placed before the Parliament by the administrative Ministry 
concerned in the month of March preceding the financial year to which the 
esti­mates relate and shall be published in the Official Gazette].
 
 




</section></article> 

 


 <article>

1[<number>31A</number> 
Administrative expenses.—
<section><number>1</number> The expenditure incurred by the Corporation on 
the following items shall be termed as admin­istrative expenses under section 28 
of the Act, namely:—
 <subsection>
          <number>i</number>  Payment of 
fees and allowances to members of the Corporation, the Standing Committee and 
the Medical Benefit Council, the Regional Boards, Local Committees;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>ii</number>  Payment of 
salaries, leave and joining time allowances, travelling and compensatory and 
other allowances, bonus, gratui­ties and compassionate allowances, pension, 
contributions to the provident fund or other benefit funds of officers and 
employees of the corporation;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>iii</number>  Defraying 
expenses on depreciation and maintenance of staff car, office buildings, staff 
quarters, hiring of accommodation, purchase of furniture, office equipment, 
stationery, printing and other expenditure in respect of offices of the 
corporation;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>iv</number>  Defraying 
expenses towards membership subscription to Inter­national Organisation, and 
other services for the purposes of giving effect to the provisions of the Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>v</number>  Defraying 
the cost (including all expenses) of the auditing accounts of the corporation 
and of the valuation of its assets and liabilities;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>vi</number>  Defraying 
the cost (including all expenses) of the Em­ployees’ State Insurance Courts set 
up under the Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>vii</number>  Payment of 
any sums under any contract entered into for the purposes of this Act by the 
corporation or the Standing Committee or by any officer duly authorised by the 
Corporation or the Standing Committee in this behalf;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>viii</number>  Payment of 
sums under any decree, order or award of any court or Tribunal against the 
corporation or any of its officers or servants for any act done in the execution 
of his duty or under a compromise or settlement of any suit or other legal 
proceedings or claim instituted or made against the corporation;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ix</number>  Defraying 
the cost and other charges of instituting or defending any civil or criminal 
proceedings arising out of any action taken under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>x</number>  Defraying 
the expenditure in connection with publicity, of the Employees’ State Insurance 
Scheme, including printing of publicity materials, courses relevant to the 
purposes of the Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>xi</number>  Defraying 
the expenditure on conducting evaluation studies on various aspects of 
functioning of the Employees’ State In­surance Scheme.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The percentage of the 
total revenue income of the corporation which may be spent every year on its 
administrative expenses beginning with the year 1997-98 shall not exceed fifteen 
per cent.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>32</number> Supplementary 
estimates.—The 
Standing Committee may cause a supplementary estimate to be prepared and 
submitted to the Corpo­ration, if in respect of any financial year further 
expenditure is likely to be incurred. Every such supplementary estimate shall be 
considered and sanctioned by the Corporation and submitted to the Central 
Government in the same manner as if it were an origi­nal annual estimate, not 
later than the fifteenth of February of the Financial year to which it relates. 
The provisions of rule 31 shall, so far as may be, apply to such supplementary 
estimate.
</article> 

 


 <article>
<number>33</number> Re-appropriation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If the Director-General finds in the course of the year that there is likely to 
be an excess of expen­diture over the sanctioned budget estimate under any head, 
he shall examine the allotment under each head of the budget esti­mate with the 
object of discovering probable savings under any other head and effecting a 
re-appropriation. Where such re-appropriation is feasible, he may sanction the 
re-appropriation subject to such conditions as may be laid down by the Central 
Government from time to time.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Funds shall not be 
re-appropriated to meet expenditure on a new service not contemplated in the 
budget estimates except with the prior approval of the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No re-appropriation 
shall be permitted between the grant sanctioned for administrative expenses, 
two-thirds of which shall be met by the Central Government, and a grant 
sanctioned for any other expenditure.
</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>34</number> Maintenance of 
accounts.—The 
Corporation shall maintain complete and accurate accounts in such form as the 
Standing Committee may, with the approval of the Central Government, specify 
from time to time. The books shall be balanced on the thirty-first of March each 
year.
</article> 

 


 <article>
<number>35</number> Revenue Accounts.—The 
Corporation shall prepare Revenue Accounts for the financial year ended on the 
thirty-first March and Balance Sheet as on the thirty-first March, by the 
thirty-first of May:
 
Provided that on the 
application of the Corporation, the Central Government may extend the said date 
by a period not exceeding thirty days:
 
Provided further that the 
Corporation may, and if so required by the Central Government shall, cause to be 
prepared the Revenue Accounts and the Balance Sheet for any other period or as 
on any other date.
</article> 

 


 

1[***]
 
 



 

 


 <article>
<number>37</number> Production of 
accounts before the 

1[Comptroller and 
Auditor General of India].—The 
annual accounts shall be set out and produced before the 

1[Comptroller and 
Auditor General of India] for scrutiny on or before the fifteenth of June each 
year follow­ing the close of the financial year to which they relate:
 
Provided that on the 
application of the Corporation the Central Government may extend the said date 
by a period not exceeding thirty-days.
 
 



</article> 

 


 <article>
<number>38</number> Powers of 

1[Comptroller and 
Auditor General of India].—The 
Corporation shall submit all accounts to the 

1[Comptroller and 
Auditor General of India] as required by them. The 

1[Comptroller and 
Auditor General of India] may—
 <section>
          <number>i</number> by written 
notice, require the production before them or before any officer subordinate to 
them, of any document which they may consider necessary for the proper conduct 
of their audit;
 </section><section>
         <number>ii</number>  by written 
notice, require any person accountable for, or having the custody or control of, 
any such document, to appear in person before them or before any officer 
subordinate to them; and 
 </section><section>
         <number>iii</number> require any 
person so appearing before them or before any officer subordinate to them to 
make and sign a declaration with respect to such document or to answer any 
question or prepare and submit any statement.
 
 



</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>39</number> Report of 

1[Comptroller and 
Auditor General of India].—The


1[report of the 
Comptroller and Auditor General of India] on the annual accounts shall be 
submitted to the Corporation on such date and in such form as the Central 
Government may specify in this behalf and they shall state whether in their 
opinion the Balance Sheet is a fully and fair Balance Sheet containing all 
necessary particulars and properly drawn up so as to exhibit a true and correct 
view of the state of the Corporation’s affairs and in case they have called for 
any explanation or information from the Corporation or any of its officers, 
whether it has been given and whether it is satisfactory.
 
 



</article> 

 


 <article>


1[<number>40</number> Consideration 
of reports.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The annual report on the work and activities of the Corporation (excluding the 
unaudited ac­counts for the year incorporated therein) shall be considered by 
the Standing Committee and shall be placed for adoption at a meeting of the 
Corporation to be held before the 

2[tenth of 
December] following the close of the financial year concerned.
 

3[(2) The Annual 
Account relating to a financial year duly authenticated by the Financial 
commissioner and the Director General and approved by the Standing Committee 
shall be submitted for audit to the Comptroller and Auditor General of India and 
the Audited accounts together with the report of the Comptroller and Auditor 
General of India shall be placed for adoption at a meeting of the corporation to 
be held before the tenth of December following the close of the financial year 
concerned:
 
Provided that the report 
of the Comptroller and Auditor General of India is received by the twentieth 
November, following the year to which it pertains.]]
 
 






</section></article> 

 


 <article>


1[<number>41</number> 
Authentication of annual accounts and reports.—The 
annual accounts together with the 

2[report of the 
Comptroller and Audi­tor General of India] thereon and the annual report on the 
work and activities of the Corporation as adopted by the Corporation shall be 
authenticated by affixing the common seal of the Corpo­ration and four copies 
thereof 

3[together with the 
comments of the Corporation on the report of the Comptroller and Auditor 
General] shall be submitted to Central Government not later than the 

4[twentieth 
December] following the close of the financial year concerned for being placed 
before the Parliament:
 
Provided that if the


5[report of the 
Comptroller and Auditor General of India] is not received by the 

6[twentieth of 
November] following the financial year to which it pertains, the annual accounts 
together with the 

5[report of the 
Comptroller and Audi­tor General of India] thereon shall be submitted to the 
Central Government separately from the annual report on the work and activities 
of the Corporation.]
 
 








</article> 

 


 <article>
<number>42</number> Cost of Audit.—The 
cost of audit shall be paid by the Corpo­ration by such date as may be specified 
by the Central Govern­ment.
</article> 

 


 

1[***]
 
 



 

 


 <article>
<number>44</number> Impropriety or 
irregularity in accounts.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The auditors shall submit to the Corporation and the Central Government, a 
separate statement, if necessary, in regard to—
 <subsection>
          <number>i</number>  any 
material impropriety or irregularity which they may ob­serve in the expenditure, 
or in the recovery of moneys due to, or in the accounts of the Corporation, or
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>ii</number>  any loss or 
waste of money or other property owned by or vested in the Corporation which has 
been caused by neglect or misconduct, with the names of the persons who in their 
opinion are directly or indirectly responsible for such loss or waste.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Standing Committee 
shall forthwith remedy any defect or irregularity that may be pointed out by the 
auditors and shall report to the Central Government the action taken by it 
thereon within ninety days of the receipt of the report of the auditors:
 
 Provided that if there is 
a difference of opinion between the Standing Committee and the auditors, or if 
the Standing Committee does not remedy any defect or irregularity within a 
reasonable period, the Central Government may, and on a reference specifi­cally 
made thereof, shall, pass such orders thereon as they think fit and the Standing 
Committee shall thereafter take action in accordance therewith within such time 
as may be specified by the Central Government.
</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>45</number> Disallowance of 
expenditure incurred and surcharge for loss or deficiency.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Standing Committee or any authority authorised by it in this behalf may, 
after giving the person concerned an opportunity to submit an explanation, and 
after considering any such explanation, disallow any item of account contrary to 
the provisions of the Act or of the rules or regula­tions made thereunder, and 
surcharge the same on the person making or authorising the making of payment of 
such account and shall charge against any person accounting, the amount of any 
deficiency or loss incurred by the negligence or misconduct of that person, or 
of any sum which ought to have been but is not brought into account by that 
person, and shall in every such case certify the amount due from such person:
 
Provided that no 
certificate made by the authority authorised by the Standing Committee shall 
have effect unless it is approved by the Standing Committee.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Standing Committee 
shall state in writing its reasons for every disallowance, surcharge or charge 
made or approved by it and shall serve a certificate of the amount due and a 
copy of the reasons for its decision on the person against whom the certifi­cate 
is made and shall also furnish copies thereof to the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any person aggrieved 
by a certificate made under this rule, may, within one month from the date of 
the service of certificate on him under sub-rule (2), file an application to the 
Central Government for setting aside or modifying the disallowance, surcharge or 
charge in respect of which the certificate was made.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> On receipt of 
application under sub-rule (3) or on its own motion, the Central Government may, 
after making such inquiry as may be necessary, pass such order as it thinks fit 
either con­firming, modifying or setting aside the disallowance, surcharge or 
charge in respect of which the certificate was made, and the Standing Committee 
shall thereupon take action in accordance with such order within such time as 
may be specified by the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Central Government 
may by order direct that all further action under the certificate made under 
this rule shall be stayed until the disposal of the matter pending before it 
under sub-rule (4).
</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>46</number> Recovery of amounts 
certified to be due.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every sum certified to be due from any person by the Standing Committee or if 
the certificate has been modified by the Central Government, the sum shown to be 
due from such person in the modified certifi­cate, shall be paid by such person 
to the Corporation within three months after he has been served with the 
certificate of the Standing Committee, or within such longer time as may be 
allowed by the Central Government, any such sum, if not so paid, shall be 
recovered as if it were an arrear of land revenue.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any sum or part of a 
sum so paid or recovered, the certifi­cate in respect of which is set aside or 
modified, shall as the case may require, be wholly or partly refunded to the 
person who paid it.
</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>47</number> Establishment of 
Provident Fund.—The 
Corporation shall establish, maintain and contribute to a Provident Fund called 
the Employees’ State Insurance Corporation Provident Fund (hereina­fter referred 
to as the Provident Fund) in respect of its em­ployees other than those whose 
services are placed at the dispo­sal of the Corporation by the Central or State 
Government.
</article> 

 


 <article>
<number>48</number> Administration of 
the Provident Fund.—The 
Provident Fund shall be administered by the Standing Committee of the 
Corpora­tion or by any other Committee approved by it for the purpose and 
subject to such conditions as it may deem fit to impose.
</article> 

 


 <article>
<number>49</number> Framing of 
Provident Fund Regulations.—The 
Corporation may, subject to the previous approval of the Central Government, 
make regulations to provide for all other matters incidental to or necessary for 
the Provident Fund.
</article> 

    
   

 <article><footcitenum>44</footcitenum>[<number>50</number> Wage limit for coverage of employee under the 
Act.—The wage limit for coverage of an employee under sub-clause (b) of 
clause (9) of section 2 of the Act shall be <footcitenum>45</footcitenum>[ten thousand] rupees a month: 

 Provided that an employee whose wages 
(excluding remuneration for overtime work) exceed <footcitenum>45</footcitenum>[ten thousand] rupees a month at any time after and 
not before the beginning of the contribution period, shall continue to be an 
employee until the end of that period.]
  


</article> 

 


 <article>

1[<number>51</number> Rates of 
contribution.—The amount of contribution for a wage period shall be in 
respect of,—
 <section>
         <number>a</number> employer’s 
contribution, a sum (rounded to the next higher rupee) equal to four and 
three-fourth per cent of the wages payable to an employee; and
 </section><section>
         <number>b</number> employee’s 
contribution, a sum (rounded to the next higher rupee) equal to one and 
three-fourth per cent of the wages payable to an employee.]
 
 






</section></article> 

  
 <article><footcitenum>48</footcitenum>[<title><number>52</number> Exemption from payment of employee's contribution. </title>—The average daily wages during a wage period for exemption from payment of employee's contribution under section 42 shall be upto and inclusive of <footcitenum>49</footcitenum>[rupees one hundred].] 




  
</article> 

 


 <article>

1[<number>53</number> Writing 
off of losses.—
<section><number>1</number> Where the Corporation is of the opinion that the amount 
of contribution, interest and damages due to the Corporation has become 
irrecoverable, the Corporation or any other officer authorized by it in this 
behalf may sanction the writing off of the said amount, subject to the following 
conditions, namely:—
 <subsection>
          <number>i</number>  
establishment or factory has been closed for more than five years and the 
whereabouts of the employer cannot be ascertained, despite all possible efforts;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>ii</number>  decree 
obtained by the Corporation could not be executed successfully for want of 
sufficient assets of the defaulting employer; or
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>iii</number>  claim for 
contribution is not fully met by—
 <subsubsection>
              <number>a</number>  the 
Official Liquidator in the event of factories establis­hment having gone into 
liquidation; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
              <number>b</number>  the 
Commissioner of payments in the event of unit being nationalised or taken over 
by the Government.]
 
 




</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><footcitenum>52</footcitenum>[<title><number>55</number> Sickness benefit. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Subject to the provisions of the Act and the regulations, a person shall be qualified to claim sick­ness benefit for sickness occurring during any benefit period if the contributions in respect of him were payable for not less than <footcitenum>53</footcitenum>[seventy eight days] the corresponding contribution period and shall be entitled to receive such benefit at the daily standard benefit rate for the period of his sickness: 
 Provided that he shall not be entitled to the benefits for the first two days of sickness in the case of a spell of sickness following, at an interval of not more than fifteen days, the spell of sickness for which sickness benefits were last paid: 
 Provided further that sickness benefits shall not be paid to any person for more than ninety one days in any two consecutive benefit periods. 
 <footcitenum>54</footcitenum>[Provided that in case of a person who becomes an employee within the meaning of the Act for the first time and for whom a shorter contribution period of less than 156 days is available, he shall be qualified to claim sickness benefit if the contribution in respect of him were payable for not less than half the number of days available for working in such contribution period.] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>55</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> The daily rate of sickness benefit in respect of a person during any benefit period shall be seventy per cent. of the standard benefit rate of that person during the corresponding contribution period rounded to the next higher rupee.]] 






 
 “(2) The daily rate of sickness benefits in respect of a person during any benefit period shall be twenty per cent more than ‘the standard benefit rate' specified in rule 54 corresponding to the average daily wages of that person during the corresponding contribution period.”. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><footcitenum>57</footcitenum>[<title><number>56</number> Maternity benefits. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> An insured woman shall be qualified to claim maternity benefits for a confinement occurring or ex­pected to occur in a benefit period, if the contributions in respect of her were payable for not less than <footcitenum>58</footcitenum>[seventy] days in the immediately preceding two consecutive contribution periods. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Subject to the provisions of the Act and the regulations, if any, an insured woman who is qualified to claim maternity bene­fits in accordance with sub-rule (1) shall be entitled to receive it at the daily rate specified in sub-rule (5) for all days on which she does not work for remuneration during a period of twelve weeks of which not more than six weeks shall precede the expected date of confinement: 
 Provided that where the insured woman dies <footcitenum>59</footcitenum>[during her delivery or during the period immediately following the date of her deliv­ery] for which she is entitled to maternity benefits, leaving behind in either case, the child, maternity benefits shall be paid for the whole of that period but if the child also dies during the said period, then for the days up to and including the day of the death of the child, to the person nominated by the insured woman, in such manner as may be specified in the regula­tions, and if there is no such nominee, to her legal representa­tive. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> An insured woman who is qualified to claim maternity benefits in accordance with sub-rule (1) shall, in case of miscarriage or medical termination of pregnancy, be entitled, on production of such proof, as may be required under the regulations, to materni­ty benefits at the rates specified in sub-rule (5), for all days on which she does not work for remuneration during a period of six weeks immediately following the date of the miscarriage or medical termination of pregnancy. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> An insured woman who is qualified to claim maternity benefits in accordance with sub-rule (1), in case of sickness arising out of pregnancy, confinement, premature birth of child or miscar­riage or medical termination of pregnancy, shall, on production of such proof, as may be required under the regulations, be entitled, in addition to the maternity benefits payable to her under any other provisions of the Act, for all days on which she does not work for remuneration to maternity benefits at the rates specified in the sub-rule (5) for all days on which she does not work for remuneration during an additional period not exceeding one month. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>60</footcitenum>[<number>5</number> The daily rate of maternity benefit payable in respect of confinement occurring or expected to occur during any benefit period shall be equal to the standard benefit rate in respect of the insured woman during the corresponding contribution period, rounded to the next higher rupee, or rupees twenty-five, whichever is higher.] 






 
 ‘(5) The daily rate of maternity benefits payable in respect of confinement occurring or expected to occur during any benefit period shall be equal to twice the “standard benefit rate” speci­fied in rule 54 corresponding to the average daily wages in respect of the insured woman during the corresponding contribu­tion period or rupees twenty, whichever is higher'. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><footcitenum>62</footcitenum>[<title><number>56</number> Maternity benefits. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> An insured woman shall be qualified to claim maternity benefits for a confinement occurring or ex­pected to occur in a benefit period, if the contributions in respect of her were payable for not less than <footcitenum>63</footcitenum>[seventy] days in the immediately preceding two consecutive contribution periods. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Subject to the provisions of the Act and the regulations, if any, an insured woman who is qualified to claim maternity bene­fits in accordance with sub-rule (1) shall be entitled to receive it at the daily rate specified in sub-rule (5) for all days on which she does not work for remuneration during a period of twelve weeks of which not more than six weeks shall precede the expected date of confinement: 
 Provided that where the insured woman dies <footcitenum>64</footcitenum>[during her delivery or during the period immediately following the date of her deliv­ery] for which she is entitled to maternity benefits, leaving behind in either case, the child, maternity benefits shall be paid for the whole of that period but if the child also dies during the said period, then for the days up to and including the day of the death of the child, to the person nominated by the insured woman, in such manner as may be specified in the regula­tions, and if there is no such nominee, to her legal representa­tive. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> An insured woman who is qualified to claim maternity benefits in accordance with sub-rule (1) shall, in case of miscarriage or medical termination of pregnancy, be entitled, on production of such proof, as may be required under the regulations, to materni­ty benefits at the rates specified in sub-rule (5), for all days on which she does not work for remuneration during a period of six weeks immediately following the date of the miscarriage or medical termination of pregnancy. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> An insured woman who is qualified to claim maternity benefits in accordance with sub-rule (1), in case of sickness arising out of pregnancy, confinement, premature birth of child or miscar­riage or medical termination of pregnancy, shall, on production of such proof, as may be required under the regulations, be entitled, in addition to the maternity benefits payable to her under any other provisions of the Act, for all days on which she does not work for remuneration to maternity benefits at the rates specified in the sub-rule (5) for all days on which she does not work for remuneration during an additional period not exceeding one month. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>65</footcitenum>[<number>5</number> The daily rate of maternity benefit payable in respect of confinement occurring or expected to occur during any benefit period shall be equal to the standard benefit rate in respect of the insured woman during the corresponding contribution period, rounded to the next higher rupee, or rupees twenty-five, whichever is higher.] 






 
 ‘(5) The daily rate of maternity benefits payable in respect of confinement occurring or expected to occur during any benefit period shall be equal to twice the “standard benefit rate” speci­fied in rule 54 corresponding to the average daily wages in respect of the insured woman during the corresponding contribu­tion period or rupees twenty, whichever is higher'. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article>1[<number>56A</number>—2[Confinement Expenses] to an 
insured woman and an insured person in respect of his wife shall be paid a sum 
of rupees 3[one thousand] per case as medical 
bonus on account of confinement expenses:
 Provided that the confinement 
occurs at a place where necessary medical facilities under the Employees’ State 
Insurance Scheme are not available:]
 4[Provided further that confinement 
expenses shall be paid for two confinements only.]
  





</article> 

  
 <article><footcitenum>71</footcitenum>[<title><number>57</number> Disablement benefits. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> A person shall be qualified to claim disablement benefits for temporary disablement for not less than three days (excluding the day of accident) for the period of such disablement sustained as an employee under the Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> A person shall be qualified to claim periodical payment for permanent disablement sustained as an employee under the Act, whether total or partial, for such disablement: 
 Provided that where permanent disablement, whether total or partial, has been assessed provisionally for a limited period or finally, the benefit provided under this rule shall be payable for that limited period, or as the case may be, for life. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>72</footcitenum>[<number>3</number> The daily rate of disablement benefit shall be ninety per cent. of the standard benefit rate in the contribution period corresponding to the benefit period in which the employment injury occurs, rounded to the next higher rupee: 
 Provided that where an employment injury occurs before commencement of the first benefit period in respect of a person, the daily rate of disablement benefit shall be— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> where a person sustains employment injury after the expiry of the first wage period in the contribution period in which the injury occurs, ninety per cent. of his average daily wages in that wage period, rounded to the next higher rupee; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> where a person sustains employment injury before the expiry of the first wage period in the contribution period in which the injury occurs, ninety per cent. of his wages actually earned or which would have been earned, had he worked for a full day on the date of accident, rounded to the next higher rupee. 
</subsection>
 Explanation.— The disablement benefit calculated as aforesaid shall be called the “full rate”.] 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The disablement benefits shall be payable to the insured person as follows— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> for temporary disablement, at the full rate; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> for permanent total disablement, at the full rate; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> for permanent partial disablement resulting from an injury specified in Part II of the Second Schedule, at the such percent­age of the full rate which would have been payable in the case of permanent total disablement, as specified in the said Schedule as being the percentage of the loss of earning capacity caused by the injury; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> for permanent partial disablement resulting from an injury not specified in Part II of the Second Schedule, at such percentage of the full rate payable in the case of permanent total disablement as is proportionate to the loss of earning capacity permanently caused by the injury. 
</subsection>
 Explanation.— Where more injuries than one are caused by the same accident, the rate of benefit payable under clauses (c) and (d) shall be aggregated but not so in any case as to exceed the full rate and in cases of disablement not covered by clauses (a), (b), (c) and (d) at such rate, not exceeding the full rate as may be provided in the regulations.] 




 
 “(3) (a) The daily rate of disablement shall be, fifty per cent more than the standard benefit rate specified in rule 54 rounded to the next higher multiple of five paise corresponding to the average daily wages in the contribution period corresponding to the benefit period in which the employment injury occurs. 
 <subsection><number>b</number> Where an employment injury occurs before the commencement of the first benefit period in respect of a person, the daily rate of disablement shall be— 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> where a person sustains employment injury after the expiry of the first wage period in the contribution period in which the injury occurs, the rate, fifty per cent more than the standard benefit rate rounded to the next higher multiple of five paise corresponding to the wage group in which his average daily wages during that wage period fall; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> where a person sustains employment injury before the expiry of the first wage period in the contribution period in which the injury occurs, the rate, fifty per cent more than the standard benefit rate, rounded to the next higher multiple of five paise corresponding to the group in which wages are actually earned or which would have been earned, had he worked for a full day on the date of accident, fall. 
</subsubsection>
</subsection>

</section></article> 

  
 <article><footcitenum>74</footcitenum>[<title><number>58</number> Dependant's benefits. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Dependant's benefit shall be paid to the dependants of the insured person who dies as a result of an employment injury, in the following manner:— 
 
 <subsection><number>A</number> In the case of death of the insured person, the dependants' benefits shall be payable to his <footcitenum>75</footcitenum>[widow, children and widowed mother] as follows— 
 
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> to the widow during life until remarriage, an amount equiva­lent to three-fifths of the full rate and, if there are two or more widows, the amount payable to the widow as aforesaid shall be divided equally between the widows; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> to each legitimate or adopted son, an amount equivalent to two-fifth of the full rate until he attains the age of <footcitenum>76</footcitenum>[twenty-five years]: 
</subsubsection>
</subsection>
 Provided that in the case of a <footcitenum>75</footcitenum>[legitimate or adopted son] who is infirm and who is wholly dependant on the earnings of the insured person at the time of his death, dependants' benefits shall continue to be paid while the infirmity lasts; 
 
 <subsection><number>c</number> to each legitimate or adopted unmarried daughter an amount equivalent to two-fifths of the full rate <footcitenum>77</footcitenum>[***]: 
</subsection>
 <footcitenum>78</footcitenum>[Provided that in the case of legitimate or adopted daughter who is inform and is wholly dependant on the earnings of the insured person at the time of his death, dependants' benefit shall continue to be paid while the infirmity lasts:] 
 Provided further that if the total of the dependants' benefits distributed among the widow or widows and legitimate or <footcitenum>79</footcitenum>[adopted children and widowed mother] of the deceased person as aforesaid exceeds at any time the full rate, the share of each of the dependants shall be proportionately reduced, so that the total amount payable to them does not exceed the amount to disablement benefits at the full rate. 
 
 <subsection><footcitenum>80</footcitenum>[<number>d</number> to the widowed mother during life an amount equivalent to two-fifth of the full rate.] 
 <subsubsection><number>B</number> In case the deceased person does not leave a widow or legiti­mate or <footcitenum>81</footcitenum>[adopted child or widowed mother] dependants' benefit shall be payable to other dependants as follows— 
 
 <subsubsubsection><footcitenum>81</footcitenum>[<number>a</number> to a parent other than the widowed mother or grand-parent, for life, at an amount equiva­lent to three-tenths of the full rate and if there are two or more parents (other than widowed mother) or grand-parents the amount payable to the parents (other than widowed mother) or grand-parents as aforesaid shall be equally divided between them;] 
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>b</number> to any other— 
 
 (i) male dependant, until he attains the age of eighteen years, 
 (ii) female dependant until she attains the age of eighteen years or until marriage whichever is earlier or if widowed, until she attains eighteen years of age or remarriage, whichever is earli­er, at an amount equivalent to two-tenths of the full rate: 

</subsubsubsection>
</subsubsection></subsection>
 Provided that if there be more than one dependant under clause (b) the amount payable under this clause shall be equally divided between them. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>82</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> The daily rate of dependant's benefit shall be ninety per cent. of the standard benefit rate in the contribution period corresponding to the benefit period in which the employment injury occurs: 
 Provided that where an employment injury occurs before the commencement of the first benefit period in respect of a person, the daily rate of dependants' benefit shall be— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> where a person sustains employment injury after the expiry of the first wage period in the contribution period in which the injury occurs, ninety per cent. of his average daily wages during that wage period rounded to the next higher rupee; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> where a person sustains employment injury before the expiry of the first wage period in the contribution period in which the injury occurs, ninety per cent. of wages actually earned or which would have been earned had he worked for a full day on the date of accident, rounded to the next higher rupee.] 
</subsection>







 
 “Provided that in the case of legitimate or adopted unmarried daughter who is infirm and is wholly dependant on the earnings of the insured person at the time of his death, dependants' benefit shall continue to be paid while the infirmity lasts and she continues to be unmarried:”. 






 
 <subsection><number>b</number> Where an employment injury occurs before the commencement of the first benefit period in respect of a person, the daily rate of dependant's benefit shall be:— 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> where a person sustains employment injury after the expiry of the first wage period in the contribution period in which the injury occurs, the rate, fifty per cent more than the standard benefit rate rounded to the next higher multiple of five paise corre­sponding to the wage group in which his average daily wages during that wage period fall; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> where a person sustains employment injury before the expiry of the first wage period in the contribution period in which the injury occurs, the rate, fifty per cent more than the standard benefit rate, rounded to the next higher multiple of five paise corresponding to the group in which wages actually earned or which have been earned had he worked for a full day on the date of accident fall. 
</subsubsection>
</subsection>

</section></article> 

  
 <article><footcitenum>84</footcitenum>[<title><number>59</number> Funeral expenses. </title>—The amount of funeral expenses for the purpose of clause (f) of sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 46 of the Act shall be <footcitenum>85</footcitenum>[ten thousand rupees].





</section></article> 

 


 <article>

1[<number>60</number> Medical 
benefits to insured person who ceases to be in an insurable employment on 
account of permanent disablement.—An insured person who ceases to be in an 
insurable employment on account of permanent disablement caused due to an 
employment injury shall be eligible to receive medical benefits for himself and 
his spouse at the scale prescribed under the Act and the regulations made 
thereunder till the date on which he would have vacated the employment on 
attaining the age of superannuation, had he not sustained such permanent 
disablement, subject to—
 <section>
          <number>i</number>  the 
production of proof by such an insured person that he ceased to be in an 
insurable employment on account of permanent disablement due to employment 
injury to the satisfaction of such officer as may be authorized by the 
Corporation; and
 </section><section>
         <number>ii</number>  the payment 
of contribution at the rate of ten rupees per month in lump sum for one year at 
a time in advance to the con­cerned office of the Corporation in the manner 
prescribed by it.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 


 <article>

1[<number>61</number> Medical 
benefits to retired insured persons.—An insured person who leaves the 
insurable employment on attaining the age of superannuation after being insured 
for not less than five years, shall be eligible to receive medical benefits for 
himself and his spouse at the scale prescribed under the Act and the regulations 
made thereunder, subject to—
 <section>
          <number>i</number>  the 
production of proof if his superannuation and having been in the insurable 
employment for a minimum of five years to the satisfaction of such officer as 
may be authorized by the Corpora­tion; and
 </section><section>
         <number>ii</number>  the payment 
of contribution at the rate of ten rupees per month in lump sum for one year at 
a time in advance to the concerned office of the Corporation in the manner 
prescribed by it.]
 
 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><footcitenum>89</footcitenum>[<title><number>61A</number> Income limit of dependent parents for eligibility to medical benefit. </title>—The income of dependent parents for eligibility to medical benefit under sub-clause (v) of clause (11) of section 2 of the Act from all sources should not exceed five thousand rupees in a month.] 



</article> 

 


 <article>

1[<number>62</number> Bar on 
grant of cash benefits.—Where an insured person is convicted under section 
84 of the Act, he shall not be entitled to any cash benefit admissible under the 
Act for a period of three months for first conviction and six months for each 
subse­quent conviction from the date of receipt of judgment of the court in the 
concerned office of the Corporation.]
 
 




</article><form>
 

THE EMPLOYEES’ 
STATE INSURANCE 
(CENTRAL) RULES, 1950 

 

 
 

FORM 
I
 
 

(See rule 21)  
 

  

 

Book No........Receipt No............   Book No............Receipt No............ 
  
 

Received from............................................. 
Received from............................  
 

the sum of Rs...............................................  the sum of Rs............................

 

(in words)....................................................   (in 
words).................................
 
 

on account of...............................................  
on account of............................
 
 

  
 


Chief Accounts Officer 

 
Chief Accounts Offic
 
 
 
 

Authorised Officer  
Authorised 
      Officer.
 
 

Entered in Cash Book, Page Number........ 
 
The Employees’ State Insurance 
Accountant
  Corporation
 
 

   
 

  </form><form>
 




THE EMPLOYEES’ STATE INSURANCE (CENTRAL) RULES, 1950
 




 




1[FORM 
II
 


[See 
rule 20A (2)]
 




Application to Medical Appeal Tribunal
 


Insurance 
No...................
 


I,......................, 
(full name of appellant) of................. (address of appellant) appeal 
against the decision on................(date) of the Medical Board at 
......................................... (address) notified to me by letter 
from................... dated..................... that—
 


*(1)   there is no 
appreciable disablement;
 


*(2)   the disablement 
should continue to be treated as temporary and the next date when the case 
should be referred to the Medical Board is; or
 


*(3)   the disablement can 
be declared to be of a permanent nature and—
 


(i)   the extent of loss of 
earning capacity can be assessed provi­sionally or finally;
 


(ii)  the assessment of the 
proportion of loss of earning capacity whether provisional or final; and
 


(iii) in case of a 
provisional assessment, the period for which such assessment shall hold good.
 


The following are the 
grounds of my appeal:
 


List of documents, if any.
 



Date........................                                                                                                                            Signature of appellant
 


*Delete whichever does not 
apply.
 


The statement of facts 
contained in this application is to the best of my knowledge and belief true and 
correct.
 


Signature of appellant
 


To 
 


Chairman of Medical Appeal 
Tribunal.]
 


 
 


—————
 


1.  Ins. by G.S.R. 2113, 
dated 28th November, 1968.
 


 
 


 
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>
Subs. by S.R.O. 891, dated 12th May, 1952.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>
Omitted by G.S.R. 129, dated 9th February, 1987 (w.e.f. 28-2-1987).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 454(E), dated 15th June, 2011, for clause (1A) (w.e.f. 1-7-2011). Earlier clause (1A) was inserted by G.S.R. 76, dated 22nd January, 1991 (w.e.f. 1-2-1991). Clause (1A), before substitution by G.S.R. 454(E), stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 76, dated 22nd January, 1991 (w.e.f. 1-2-1991).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 76, dated 22nd January, 1991 (w.e.f. 1-2-1991).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 454(E), dated 15th June, 2011, for clause (7A) (w.e.f. 1-7-2011). Earlier clause (7A) was inserted by G.S.R. 76, dated 22nd January, 1991 (w.e.f. 1-2-1991). Clause (7A), before substitution by G.S.R. 454(E), stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 454(E), dated 15th June, 2011, for clause (1A) (w.e.f. 1-7-2011). Earlier clause (1A) was inserted by G.S.R. 76, dated 22nd January, 1991 (w.e.f. 1-2-1991). Clause (1A), before substitution by G.S.R. 454(E), stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 76, dated 22nd January, 1991 (w.e.f. 1-2-1991).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 76, dated 22nd January, 1991 (w.e.f. 1-2-1991).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 454(E), dated 15th June, 2011, for clause (7A) (w.e.f. 1-7-2011). Earlier clause (7A) was inserted by G.S.R. 76, dated 22nd January, 1991 (w.e.f. 1-2-1991). Clause (7A), before substitution by G.S.R. 454(E), stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 1082, 
dated 29th June, 1966.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>  Omitted by G.S.R. 199, 
dated 6th March, 1990 (w.r.e.f. 1-1-1990).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 210, 
dated 27th March, 2001 (w.r.e.f. 1-10-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 129, 
dated 29th March, 2000 (w.e.f. 8-4-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 2113, 
dated 28th November, 1968</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 2113, 
dated 28th November, 1968</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 2113, 
dated 28th November, 1968</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number>
Subs. by G.S.R. 231, dated 20th January, 1964.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number>
Subs. by G.S.R. 129, dated 9th February, 1987 (w.e.f. 28-2-1987).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number>
Ins. by G.S.R. 129, dated 9th February, 1987 (w.e.f. 28-2-1987).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number>
Subs. by G.S.R. 76, dated 22nd January, 1991 (w.e.f. 1-2-1991).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 240, 
dated 6th February, 1964.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 322(E), 
dated 17th May, 2005, for “rupees fifteen lakhs” (w.e.f. 1-5-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 306, 
dated 7th March, 1974.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 677, 
dated 29th March, 1968.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 131, 
dated 20th January, 1964.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 594, dated 
29th March, 1963.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>28</number>  Subs. by S.R.O. 1173, 
dated 15th May, 1956.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>29</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 1834, 
dated 18th December, 1964.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>30</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 226, 
dated 22nd April, 1997 (w.e.f. 1-5-1997).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>31</number>  Rule 36 omitted by 
G.S.R. 76, dated 22nd January, 1991 (w.e.f. 1-2-1991).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>32</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 76, 
dated 22nd January, 1991 (w.e.f. 1-2-1991).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>33</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 76, 
dated 22nd January, 1991 (w.e.f. 1-2-1991).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>34</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 76, 
dated 22nd January, 1991 (w.e.f. 1-2-1991).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>35</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 1834, 
dated 18th December, 1964.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>36</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 199, 
dated 6th March, 1990 (w.r.e.f. 1-1-1990).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>37</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 57, 
dated 31st January, 2005, for “(2) The annual accounts relating to a financial 
year together with the report of the Comptroller and Auditor General of India 
thereon shall be considered by the Standing Committee and shall be placed for 
adoption at a meeting of the Corporation to be held before the tenth of December 
following the close of the financial year concerned:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>38</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 1834, 
dated 18th December, 1964.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>39</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 76, 
dated 22nd January, 1991 (w.e.f. 1-2-1991).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>40</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 76, 
dated 22nd January, 1991 (w.e.f. 1-2-1991).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>41</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 60, 
dated 4th January, 1982.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>42</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 76, 
dated 22nd January, 1991 (w.e.f. 1-2-1991).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>43</number>  Rule 43 omitted by 
G.S.R. 76, dated 22nd January, 1991 (w.e.f. 1-2-1991).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>44</number>. Ins. by G.S.R. 76, dated 22nd January, 1991 
(w.e.f. 1-2-1991).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>45</number>Subs. by G.S.R. 591(E), 
dated 22nd September, 2006, for “seven thousand and five hundred” (w.e.f. 
1-10-2006). Earlier it was substituted by G.S.R. 172(E), dated 4th March, 2004, 
for “six thousand and five hundred” (w.e.f. 1-4-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>46</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 316, 
dated 26th August, 2004 and as corrected by G.S.R. 58, dated 19th January, 2005, 
for rule 51, before  substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>47</number> Vide S.R.O. 212, dated 22nd June, 1950.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>48</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 76, dated 22nd January, 1991 (w.e.f. 1-2-1991).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>49</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 454(E), dated 15th June, 2011, for “rupees seventy” (w.e.f. 1-7-2011). Earlier these words were substituted by G.S.R. 465(E), dated 4th July, 2007 (w.e.f. 1-8-2007), G.S.R. 172(E), dated 4th March, 2004 (w.e.f. 1-4-2004) and G.S.R. 582(E), dated 23rd December, 1996 (w.e.f. 
  23-12-1996).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>50</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 76, 
dated 22nd January, 1991 (w.e.f. 1-2-1991).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>51</number> Vide S.R.O. 212, dated 22nd June, 1950.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>52</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 76, dated 22nd January, 1991 (w.e.f. 1-2-1991).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>53</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 185, dated 1st September, 1998 (w.e.f. 19-9-1998).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>54</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 129, dated 29th March, 2000 (w.e.f. 8-4-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>55</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 454(E), dated 15th June, 2011, for sub-rule (2) (w.e.f. 1-7-2011). Earlier sub- 
  rule (2) was substituted by G.S.R. 685(E), dated 31st October, 2007 (w.e.f. 1-12-2007). Sub-</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>56</number> Vide S.R.O. 212, dated 22nd June, 1950.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>57</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 76, dated 22nd January, 1991 (w.e.f. 1-2-1991).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>58</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 185, dated 1st September, 1998 (w.e.f. 19-9-1998).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>59</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 522, dated 15th October, 1996 (w.e.f. 16-11-1996).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>60</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 454(E), dated 15th June, 2011, for sub-rule (5) (w.e.f. 1-7-2011). Earlier sub- 
rule (5) was amended by G.S.R. 522, dated 15th October, 1996 (w.e.f. 16-11-1996). Sub-rule (5), before substitution by G.S.R. 454(E), stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>61</number> Vide S.R.O. 212, dated 22nd June, 1950.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>62</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 76, dated 22nd January, 1991 (w.e.f. 1-2-1991).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>63</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 185, dated 1st September, 1998 (w.e.f. 19-9-1998).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>64</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 522, dated 15th October, 1996 (w.e.f. 16-11-1996).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>65</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 454(E), dated 15th June, 2011, for sub-rule (5) (w.e.f. 1-7-2011). Earlier sub- 
rule (5) was amended by G.S.R. 522, dated 15th October, 1996 (w.e.f. 16-11-1996). Sub-rule (5), before substitution by G.S.R. 454(E), stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>66</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 522, dated 
15th October, 1996 (w.e.f. 16-11-1996).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>67</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 28, dated 
2nd January, 2004 for “Medical bonus” (w.e.f. 24-1-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>68</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 28, dated 
2nd January, 2004 for “two hundred and fifty” (w.e.f. 24-1-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>69</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 28, dated 
2nd January, 2004 for (w.e.f. 24-1-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>70</number> Vide S.R.O. 212, dated 22nd June, 1950.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>71</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 76, dated 22nd January, 1991 (w.e.f. 1-2-1991).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>72</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 454(E), dated 15th June, 2011, for sub-rule (3) (w.e.f. 1-7-2011). Earlier sub- 
  rule (3) was amended by G.S.R. 685(E), dated 31st October, 2007 (w.e.f. 1-12-2007). Sub-rule (3), before substitution by G.S.R. 454(E), stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>73</number> Vide S.R.O. 212, dated 22nd June, 1950.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>74</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 76, dated 22nd January, 1991 (w.e.f. 1-2-1991).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>75</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 210, dated 27th March, 2001 (w.r.e.f. 1-10-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>76</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 229(E), dated 23rd March, 2011, for “eighteen years” (w.e.f. 1-4-2011).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>77</number> The words “until she attains the age of eighteen years or until marriage, whichever is earlier” omitted by G.S.R. 229(E), dated 23rd March, 2011 (w.e.f. 1-4-2011).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>78</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 229(E), dated 23rd March, 2011, for proviso (w.e.f. 1-4-2011). The proviso, before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>79</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 210, dated 27th March, 2001 (w.r.e.f. 1-10-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>80</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 210, dated 27th March, 2001 (w.r.e.f. 1-10-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>81</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 210, dated 27th March, 2001 (w.r.e.f. 1-10-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>82</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 454(E), dated 15th June, 2011, for sub-rule (2) (w.e.f. 1-7-2011). Earlier sub- 
  rule (2) was amended by by G.S.R. 685(E), dated 31st October, 2007 (w.e.f. 1-12-2007). Sub-</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>83</number>   Vide   S.R.O. 212, dated 22nd June, 1950.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>84</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 76, dated 22nd January, 1991 (w.e.f. 1-2-1991).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>85</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 229(E), dated 23rd March, 2011, for “five thousand rupees” (w.e.f. 1-4-2011). Earlier these words were substituted by G.S.R. 136, dated 14th September, 2009, for “three thousand rupees” (w.r.e.f. 1-9-2009), by G.S.R. 685(E), dated 31st October, 2007 (w.e.f. 1-12-2007), by G.S.R. 210(E), dated 27th March, 2001 (w.r.e.f. 1-10-2000) and G.S.R. 522(E), dated 15th October, 1996 (w.e.f. 16-11-1996).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>86</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 76, 
dated 22nd January, 1991 (w.e.f. 1-2-1991).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>87</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 76, 
dated 22nd January, 1991 (w.e.f. 1-2-1991).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>88</number>   Vide   S.R.O. 212, dated 22nd June, 1950.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>89</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 229(E), dated 23rd March, 2011 (w.e.f. 1-4-2011).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>90</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 76, 
dated 22nd January, 1991 (w.e.f. 1-2-1991).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>