<act><tid>8167</tid>
<title>THE FOREIGNERS LAW (APPLICATION AND AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>1962</year></title>

ACT NO. 42 OF <year>1962</year>
[ 24th November, <year>1962</year>.]

An Act to apply the Registration of Foreigners Act, <year>1939</year> and the 
Foreigners Act, <year>1946</year> to certain persons to whom they do not at present 
apply and further to amend the Foreigners Act, <year>1946</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirteenth Year of the Repub- 
lic of India as follows:-





<article><tid>1250554</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Foreigners Law 
 (Application and Amendment) Act, <year>1962</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>121672</tid>
<number>2</number>Application of Act 16 of <year>1930</year> and Act 31 of <year>1946</year> to certain 
persons. Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the 
time being in force, the provisions of the Registration of Foreigners 
Act, <year>1939</year>, and the Foreigners Act, <year>1946</year>, and of the rules and orders 
made thereunder shall apply to and in relation to any person who, or 
either of whose parents, or any of whose grand- parents was at any time 
a citizen or subject of any country at war with, or committing 
external aggression against, India or of any other country assisting 
the country at war with, or committing such aggression against, India, 
as they apply to and in relation to foreigners as defined for the 
purposes of those Acts.


</article>



<article><tid>470623</tid>
<number>3</number>[ Amendment of Act 31 of <year>1946</year>.] Rep. by Act 56 of <year>1974</year>, s. 2 
and Sch. I.


</article>



<article><tid>877685</tid>
<number> 4</number> Repeal and saving.
<section><tid>165381</tid>
<number>1</number>The Foreigners Law (Application and   
  Amendment) Ordinance, <year>1962</year> (5 of <year>1962</year>) is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>258980</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action 
taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or 
taken under this Act, as if this Act had commenced on the 26th 
October, <year>1962</year>.


</section>

</article>



 </act>