<act><title>


    The Child Labour 
    (Prohibition and Regulation) Rules, 19881</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Child Labour (Prohibition and Regulation) Rues, 
    1988.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   “Act” means the Child Labour 
      (Prohibition and Regulation) Act, 1986 (61 of 1986);
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   “Committee” means the Child Labour 
      Technical Advisory Committee constituted under sub-section (1) of section 
      3 of the Act;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   “Chairman” means the Chairman of the 
      Committee appointed under sub-section (2) of section 5 of the Act;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   “Form” means a Form appended to these 
      rules;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   “register” means the register required 
      to be maintained under section 11 of the Act;
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   “Schedule” means the Schedule appended 
      to the Act;
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>   “section” means a section of the Act.
</section>
  
  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Term of 
    office of the members of the Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The term of office of the members of the Committee shall be one year from 
    the date on which their appointment is notified in the Official Gazette:
 
Provided that 
    the Central Government may extend the term of office of the member of the 
    Committee for a maximum period of two years:
 
Provided 
    further that the member shall, notwithstanding the expiration of his term, 
    continue to hold office until his successor enters upon his office.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    members appointed under sub-rule (1) shall be eligible for re-appointment.
  
  
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Secretary to the Committee.—The 
    Central Government may appoint an officer not below the rank of an Under 
    Secretary to the Government of India as Secretary of the Committee.
  
  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Allowances to non-official members.—The 
    non-official members and Chairman of the Committee shall be paid such fees 
    and allowances as may be admissible to the officers of the Central 
    Government drawing a pay of rupees four thousand and five hundred or above.
  
  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Resignation.—
<section><number>1</number> A member may 
    resign his office by writing under his hand addressed to the Chairman.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Chairman may resign his office by writing under his hand addressed to the 
    Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    resignation referred to in sub-rule (1) and sub-rule (2) shall take effect 
    from the date of its acceptance or on the expiry of thirty days from the 
    date of receipt of such resignation, whichever is earlier, by the Chairman 
    or the Central Government, as the case may be.
  
  
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Removal 
    of Chairman or member of the Committee.— 
    The Central Government may remove the Chairman or any member of the 
    Committee at any time before the expiry of the term of office after giving 
    him a reasonable opportunity of showing cause against the proposed removal.
  
  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Cessation of membership.—If a 
    member—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   is absent without leave of the 
      Chairman for three or more consecutive meetings of the Committee; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   is declared to be of unsound mind by a 
      competent court; or
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   is or has been convicted of any 
      offence which, in the opinion of the Central Government, involves moral 
      turpitude; or
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   is, or at any time, has been 
      adjudicated insolvent or has suspended his debts or has compounded with 
      his creditors,
 
shall cease to be member of the Committee.
</section>
  
  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Filling 
    up of casual vacancies.—In case a 
    member resigns his office under rule 6 or ceases to be member under rule 8, 
    the casual vacancy thus caused shall be filled up by the Central Government 
    and the member so appointed shall hold office for the unexpired portion of 
    the term of his predecessor.
  
  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Time 
    and place of meetings.—The 
    Committee shall meet at such times and places as the Chairman may fix in 
    this behalf.
  
  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> Notice 
    of meetings.— The Secretary to 
    the Committee shall give at least seven days’ notice to every member of the 
    Committee of the time and place fixed for each meeting alongwith the list of 
    business to be transacted at the said meeting.
  
  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 

   

 <article><number>2</number> 
Definitions.—In these rules, unless 
the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>  “Act” means 
the Child Labour (Prohibition and Regulation) Act, 1986 (61 of 1986);  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>  “Committee” 
means the Child Labour Technical Advisory Committee constituted under 
            sub-section 
(1) of section 5 of the Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>  “Chairman” 
means the Chairman of the Committee appointed under sub-section (2) of 
             section 
5 of the Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>  “Form” means 
a Form appended to these rules;  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>  “register” 
means the register required to be maintained under section 11 of the Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>  “Schedule” 
means the Schedule appended to the Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>g</number> 
“section” means a section of the Act.
 </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> Quorum.—No 
    business shall be transacted at a meeting of the Committee unless at least 
    three members of the Committee other than the Chairman and the Secretary are 
    present:
 
Provided that 
    at any meeting in which less than three of the total members are present, 
    the Chairman may adjourn the meeting to a date as he deems fit and inform 
    the members present and notify other members that the business of the 
    scheduled meeting shall be disposed of at the adjourned meeting irrespective 
    of the quorum and it shall be lawful to dispose of the business at such 
    adjourned meeting irrespective of the number of members attending the 
    meeting.
  
  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Decision by majority.—All 
    questions considered at a meeting of the Committee shall be decided by a 
    majority of votes of the members present and voting and in the event of 
    equality of votes, the Chairman, or in the absence of Chairman, the member 
    presiding at the meeting, as the case may be, shall have a second or casting 
    vote.
  
  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Sub-Committees.—The Committee may 
    constitute one or more Sub-Committees, whether consisting only of members of 
    the Committee or partly of members of the Committee and partly of other 
    persons as it thinks fit, for such purposes, as it may decide and any 
    Sub-Committee so constituted shall discharge such functions as may be 
    delegated to it by the Committee.
  
  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>16</number> Register to be maintained under section 11 
      of the Act.—
<section><number>1</number> Every occupier 
      of an establishment shall maintain a register in respect of children 
      employed or permitted to work, in Form A.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The register shall be maintained on a yearly 
      basis but shall be retained by the employer for a period of three years 
      after the date of the last entry made therein.
  
  
  
  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Certificate of age.—
<section><number>1</number> All young 
    persons in employment in any of the occupations set-forth in Part A of the 
    Schedule or in any workshop wherein any of the processes setforth in Part B 
    of the Schedule is carried on, shall produce a certificate of age from the 
    appropriate medical authority, whenever required to do so by an Inspector.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    certificate of age referred to in sub-rule (1) shall be issued in Form B.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    charges payable to the medical authority for the issue of such certificate 
    shall be the same as prescribed by the State Government or the Central 
    Government, as the case may be, for their respective Medical Boards.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    charges payable to the medical authority shall be borne by the employer of 
    the young person whose age is under question.
 
Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of sub-rule (1), the appropriate “Medical Authority” shall be 
    Government medical doctor not below the rank of an Assistant Surgeon of a 
    District or a regular doctor of equivalent rank employed in Employees’ State 
    Insurance dispensaries or hospitals.
  
  
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article><form>
 
 
 
 
 

 
 
 

The 
      Child Labour  
(Prohibition and Regulation) Rules, 
1988
 

 
 

 
 

Form A 
[See rule 
      16(1)]
 

Year...................................
 

Name and address of 
      employer.......................Place of 
      work..............................   
Nature of work being done by 
      the 
      establishment.....................................................
 
 
 
 
 

Sl. No.
 
 

Name of Child
 
 

Father's Name
 
 

Date of Birth
 
 

Permanent Address
 
 

Date of joining the establishment
 
 
 

(1)
 
 

(2)
 
 

(3)
 
 

(4)
 
 

(5)
 
 

(6)
 
 
 

 
 

 
 
 

 
 
 

 
 
 

 
 
 

 
 
 

 
 

 
 

 
 

 
 
 
 
 
 

Name of the work on which employer 
 
 

Daily hours of working
 
 

Interval of rest
 
 

wage paid
 
 

Remarks
 
 
 

(7)
 
 

(8)
 
 

(9)
 
 

(10)
 
 

(11)
 
 
 

 
 
 

 
 

 
 

 
 
 

 
 
 

 
 
 

 
 

  
 

 
 
 

 </form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




    The Child Labour  

    (Prohibition and Regulation) Rules, 1988
 

 
 

 
 

 
 

Form B 

    [See rule 17 (2)]
 


Certificate of Age
 


    Certificate No...............................
 

I hereby 
    certify that I have personally examined 
    (name).................................son/daughter 
    of......................................residing 
    at........................................and that he/she has completed 
    his/her fourteenth year and his/her age, as nearly as can be ascertained 
    from my examination, 
    is................................................................. years 
    (completed). His/her descriptive marks 
    are................................................................................................... 
    Thumb impression/signature of child....................................
 
 
 
 


        Place........................... 
 
 

Medical 
        Authority

 
 
 


        Date............................       
 
 

Designation


 


 
 

  


  
 

 
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>