<act><tid>826323</tid>
<title>THE EVACUEE INTEREST (SEPARATION) ACT, <year>1951</year></title>

ACT NO. 64 OF <year>1951</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 31st October, <year>1951</year>.]

An Act to make special provisions for the separation of the interests 
of evacuees from those of other persons in property in which such 
other persons are also interested and for matters connected therewith.

WHEREAS it is expedient to make special provisions for the 
separation of the interests of evacuees from those of other persons in 
property in which such other persons are also interested and for 
matters connected therewith;

AND WHEREAS some of the aforesaid provisions may relate to 
certain matters in the State List and Parliament is empowered, in 
pursuance of a Resolution passed under Article 249 of the 
Constitution, to make such laws;

BE it therefore enacted by Parliament as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1931506</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>604714</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Evacuee  
Interest (Separation) Act, <year>1951</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>639990</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India except <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the territories 
which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in 
the States] of Assam, West Bengal, Tripura, Manipur and Jammu and 
Kashmir.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1378857</tid>
<number> 2</number> In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-
<section><tid>1641625</tid>
<number>a</number>" appellate officer" means an officer appointed as such 
by the State Government under section 13;

</section>

<section><tid>1651430</tid>
<number>b</number>" claim" means the assertion by any person, not being an 
evacuee, of any right, title or interest in any 
property--

<subsection><tid>933024</tid>
<number>i</number>as a co- sharer or partner of an evacuee in the 
property; or 
 (ii) as a mortgagee of the interest of an evacuee 
in the property; or
Supplemented in:- 
 (a) Am., in Panjab by Punjab Act 15 of <year>1960</year>. 
 (b) Kerala in Kerala Act 15 of <year>1960</year>. 
 (c) Andhra Pradesh by Andhra Pradesh Act 28 of <year>1960</year>. 
 (d) U. P by U. P. Act 5 of <year>1961</year>. 
 (e) Bihar by Bihar Act 20 of <year>1960</year>. 
 (f) Madras by Madras 3 of <year>1961</year>. 
 (g) Rajasthan by Rajasthan Act 1 of <year>1961</year>. 
 (h) Mysore by Mysore Act 3 of <year>1961</year>.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>44</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The Act has been supplemented in Uttar Pradesh by U. P. Act 13 of 
<year>1953</year> and in Orissa by Orissa Act 11 of <year>1953</year> and in the Punjab by 
Punjab Act XXI of <year>1953</year>, Amended in Panjab by Punjab Act 15 of <year>1960</year>, 
Kerala in Kerala Act 15 of <year>1960</year>, Andhra Pradesh by Andhra Pradesh Act 
28 of <year>1960</year>, U. P by U. P. Act 5 of <year>1961</year>, Bihar by Bihar Act 20 of <year>1960</year>, 
Madras by Madras 3 of <year>1961</year>, Rajasthan by Rajasthan Act 1 of <year>1961</year>, 
Mysore by Mysore Act 3 of <year>1961</year>. 
2. Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 4) Order, <year>1957</year>, for" the 
States" (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1956</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1312785</tid>
<number>iii</number>as a mortgagor having mortgaged the property 
or any interest therein in favour of an evacuee;
and includes any other interest which such person may 
have jointly with an evacuee and which is notified in 
this behalf by the Central Government in the Official 
Gazette;


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>768091</tid>
<number>c</number>" competent officer" means an officer appointed as such 
by the State Government under section 4;

</section>

<section><tid>728</tid>
<number>d</number>" composite property" means any property which, or any 
property in which an interest, has been declared to be 
evacuee property or has vested in the Custodian under 
the Administration of Evacuee Property Act, <year>1950</year> (31 of  
  <year>1956</year>), and--

<subsection><tid>165585</tid>
<number>i</number>in which the interest of the evacuee consists 
of an undivided share in the property held by him as a 
co- sharer or partner of any other person, not being an 
evacuee; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1532605</tid>
<number>ii</number>in which the interest of the evacuee is 
subject to mortgage in any form in favour of a person, 
not being an evacuee; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>240361</tid>
<number>iii</number>in which the interest of a person, not being 
an evacuee, is subject to mortgage in any form in 
favour of an evacuee; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1788307</tid>
<number>iv</number>in which an evacuee has such other interest 
jointly with any other person, not being an evacuee, as 
may be notified in this behalf by the Central 
Government, in the Official Gazette;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1672381</tid>
<number>e</number>" evacuee interest", in relation to a composite 
property, means the right, title and interest of an 
evacuee in that property;

</section>

<section><tid>117838</tid>
<number>f</number>" mortgage debt" means any liability in respect of a 
property due under any form of mortgage (including any  
  usufructuary mortgage or mortgage by conditional sale) 
whether such liability is payable presently or in 
future, or under any decree or order of a Court or 
otherwise, or whether ascertained or not, which--

<subsection><tid>1700756</tid>
<number>i</number>in any case where it is incurred by an 
evacuee, is secured by the mortgage of the interest of 
the evacuee in the property in favour of a person, not 
being an evacuee;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>45</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>287931</tid>
<number>ii</number>in any case where it is incurred by a person 
not being an evacuee, is secured by the mortgage of the 
interest of such person in the property in favour of an 
evacuee;
but does not include any such liability of an evacuee 
arising out of any transaction entered into after the 
 14th day of August, <year>1947</year> unless such transaction has 
been confirmed by the Custodian under the 
Administration of Evacuee Property Act, <year>1950</year> (31 of  
  <year>1950</year>);


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1154982</tid>
<number>g</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>668244</tid>
<number>h</number>" principal money", in relation to a mortgage deed 
executed by an evacuee, means--

</section>

<section><tid>1750937</tid>
<number>i</number>in the case of a mortgage deed which has not 
been executed by way of renewal of a prior mortgage 
deed, the sum of money advanced by way of loan at the 
time of the execution of the mortgage deed;

<subsection><tid>1768899</tid>
<number>ii</number>in the case of a mortgage deed which has been 
executed at any time before the 1st day of January, 
<year>1940</year>, by way of renewal of a prior mortgage deed, the 
consideration for which the renewed mortgage deed was 
executed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>166993</tid>
<number>iii</number>in the case of a mortgage deed which has 
been executed at any time after the 1st day of January, 
<year>1940</year>, by way of renewal of a prior mortgage deed 
executed before that date, the sum of money which 
became due on the 1st day of January, <year>1940</year>, on account 
of the money advanced on the prior mortgage deed and 
interest thereon up to the said date;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1171143</tid>
<number>iv</number>in the case of a mortgage deed which was 
executed at any time after the 1st day of January, 
<year>1940</year>, by way of renewal of a prior mortgage deed which 
was also executed after that date, the sum of money 
advanced by way of loan at the time of the execution of 
the prior mortgage deed;
Explanation.-- For the purpose of calculating the 
principal money in relation to any mortgage deed which 
has been executed by way of renewal of a prior mortgage 
deed, any sum of money advanced at the time of such 
renewal in addition to the sum of money which


<pagefootnote><pagenum>46</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

was due on the prior mortgage deed shall also be taken 
into account.


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>931885</tid>
<number>i</number>all words and expressions used, but not defined in this 
Act and defined in the Administration of Evacuee 
Property Act, <year>1950</year> (31 of <year>1950</year>), shall have the 
meanings assigned to them in that Act.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>178802</tid>
<number>3</number>Act to override other laws. Save as otherwise expressly 
provided in this Act, the provisions of this Act and of the rules and 
orders made thereunder shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
inconsistent therewith contained in any other law for the time being 
in force or in any instrument having effect by virtue of any such law.
CHAP

SEPARATION OF EVACUEE INTEREST IN COMPOSITE PROPERTY

CHAPTER II

SEPARATION OF EVACUEE INTEREST IN COMPOSITE PROPERTY



</article>



<article><tid>1588912</tid>
<number> 4</number> Power to appoint competent officers.
<section><tid>195319</tid>
<number>1</number>The State Government  
may, with the approval of the Central Government, by notification in 
the Official Gazette, appoint as many competent officers as may be 
necessary for the purpose of performing the functions assigned to them 
by or under this Act, and a competent officer may perform his 
functions in such local area or areas as may be specified in the 
notification.

</section>

<section><tid>1664338</tid>
<number>2</number>No person shall be qualified to be appointed as a competent 
officer under this Act unless he has held a judicial office for at 
least five years, or has been an advocate or a pleader for at least 
seven years.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1119263</tid>
<number>5</number>Jurisdiction of competent officers. A competent officer shall 
have jurisdiction to decide any claim relating to any composite 
property situate within the limits of the local area of his 
jurisdiction and such cases or classes of cases as may, by general or 
special order, be transferred to him under section 19 by the Central 
Government or the appellate officer.


</article>



<article><tid>1243430</tid>
<number> 6</number> Notice to submit claims.
<section><tid>1919186</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purpose of determining or  
separating the evacuee interest in a composite property, any competent 
officer having jurisdiction over such property may, either on 
information received in this behalf from the Custodian or on an 
application from a claimant, issue, in such form and manner as may be 
prescribed,--

<subsection><tid>807148</tid>
<number>a</number>a general notice requiring all persons who claim 
interest in such property, and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>47</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>72620</tid>
<number>b</number>also a notice on every person who, in the opinion of 
the competent officer, may have a claim in such 
property, to submit claims, if any, in respect of that 
property.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>216505</tid>
<number>2</number>An application under sub- section (1) shall be in such form 
and manner as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1786622</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> No application under this section shall be entertained if 
filed after the expiry of one year from the commencement of the 
Evacuee Interest (Separation) Amendment Act, <year>1960</year> (27 of <year>1960</year>).]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1789976</tid>
<number> 7</number> Submission of claims.
<section><tid>657695</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person claiming an interest in a  
composite property may, within sixty days of the date of the issue of 
the general notice or service of individual notice under section 6, 
whichever is later, submit to the competent officer a statement of his 
claim in writing and signed and verified in the prescribed manner.
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>


</section>

<section><tid>77543</tid>
<number>2</number>A statement of claim under sub- section (1) shall be drawn up, 
as far as may be, in the form of pleadings under the Code of Civil 
Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>) and shall include the following 
particulars, namely:-

<subsection><tid>153321</tid>
<number>a</number>the nature of the interest of the claimant in the 
composite property;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1017852</tid>
<number>b</number>the estimated money value of the composite property;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>134397</tid>
<number>c</number>where the claim is made by a co- sharer or partner, the 
extent of the share of the claimant and the money value 
of such share;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1240840</tid>
<number>d</number>where the claim is made by a mortgagee,--

<subsubsection><tid>1239424</tid>
<number>i</number>the principal money and the rate of interest 
chargeable under the mortgage deed;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>144676</tid>
<number>ii</number>payments made towards the mortgage debt after 
the principal money was advanced or deemed to have been 
advanced;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1336353</tid>
<number>iii</number>the history of the mortgage debt in so far 
as it is relevant to the determination of the principal 
money;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>88022</tid>
<number>iv</number>particulars of the property mortgaged and the 
estimated value of such property;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1886613</tid>
<number>v</number>particulars of any property the possession of 
which has been taken by the mortgagee as security for, 
or in lieu of payment of, the mortgage debt;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>48</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 27 of <year>1960</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 15- 10- <year>1960</year>). 
2. Proviso omitted by s. 3, ibid. (w. e. f. 15- 10- <year>1960</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1720886</tid>
<number>vi</number>the total amount claimed under the mortgage 
debt in accordance with the provisions of this Act;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>870203</tid>
<number>e</number>where the claim is made by a mortgagor, the total 
amount due under the mortgage debt and the particulars 
necessary to determine the same;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>896783</tid>
<number>f</number>the order of preference in which the claimant desires 
to have his interest separated from that of the evacuee 
under section 10;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1820114</tid>
<number>g</number>any other particulars which may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>686262</tid>
<number>3</number>The claimant shall, along with the submission of claim under 
sub- section (1), file true copies of all documents in his possession 
or power on which the claim is based and a list of any other documents 
 (whether in his possession or power or not) on which he intends to 
rely as evidence in support of his claim; and the claimant shall, 
whenever required to do so by the competent officer, produce all the 
documents of which true copies have been filed and also the documents 
in his possession or power which have been entered in the list.

</section>

<section><tid>1755212</tid>
<number>4</number>No document which should have been but has not been filed in 
accordance with the requirements of sub- section (3), shall be received 
at any stage of the proceedings without the leave of the competent 
officer.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1508185</tid>
<number> 8</number> Decision by competent officer.
<section><tid>1285405</tid>
<number>1</number>On receipt of a statement  
of claim under section 7, the competent officer shall, subject to the 
provisions of sub- sections (2) and (3), hold an inquiry into the claim 
in accordance with the procedure laid down in section 17 and pass an 
order determining the interest of the evacuee and the claimant in the 
property in question and the order shall contain all or any of the 
following particulars, namely:-

<subsection><tid>961455</tid>
<number>a</number>the money value of the property;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1756316</tid>
<number>b</number>in any case where the evacuee and the claimant are co- 
sharers or partners, their respective shares in the 
property and the money value of such shares;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>834020</tid>
<number>c</number>in any case where the claim is made by a mortgagor, the 
amount due to the evacuee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1774490</tid>
<number>d</number>in any case where the claim is made by a mortgagee, the 
amount due under the claim in accordance with the 
provisions of section 9.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>465258</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the Custodian under the Administration of Evacuee 
Property Act, <year>1950</year> (31 of <year>1950</year>), has determined that the property in 
question or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>49</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

any interest therein is evacuee property, the decision of the 
Custodian shall be binding on the competent officer:

Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall debar 
the competent officer from determining the mortgage debt in respect of 
such property or any interest therein or from separating the interest 
of the evacuee from that of the claimant under section 10.


</section>

<section><tid>1756782</tid>
<number>3</number>If there is any dispute as to whether a liability is a 
mortgage debt or not or whether any claim submitted under section 7 
exists, the competent officer shall decide such dispute:
Provided that a decree of a Civil Court (other than an ex- parte  
  decree passed after the 14th day of August, <year>1947</year>) shall, subject to 
the provisions of sections 9 and 10, be binding on the competent 
officer in respect of any matter which has been finally decided by 
such decree; and where any matter was decided by an ex- parte decree 
passed by a Civil Court after the 14th day of August, <year>1947</year>, the 
competent officer may decide such matter afresh and on such decision 
being made, the ex- parte decree shall be deemed to have no effect.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>116019</tid>
<number> 9</number> Certain reliefs in respect of mortgaged property of evacuees.

<section><tid>1391464</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything to the contrary in any law or contract or  
any decree or order of a Civil Court or other authority, where the 
claim is made by a mortgagee, no mortgaged property of an evacuee 
shall, subject to the provisions of sub- section (2), be liable for the 
payment of interest at a rate exceeding five per cent. per annum 
simple on the principal money advanced or deemed to have been 
advanced.

</section>

<section><tid>1568636</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a mortgagee has taken possession on any terms 
whatsoever of any agricultural land and is entitled to receive profits 
accruing from the land and to appropriate the same, every such 
mortgage shall be deemed to have taken effect as a complete 
usufructuary mortgage period mentioned in the mortgage deed or twenty 
years, whichever is less, from the date of the execution of the 
mortgage deed; and if the aforesaid period has not expired and the 
mortgage debt has not been extinguished, the competent officer shall 
determine the mortgage debt due having regard to the proportion which 
the unexpired portion of that period bears to the total of that 
period.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1547866</tid>
<number> 10</number> Separation of the interests of evacuees from those of 
claimants in composite property. Notwithstanding anything to the 
contrary in any law or contract or any decree or order of a Civil 
Court or other authority, the competent officer may, subject to any 
rules that may be made in this behalf, take all such measures as he 
may consider necessary for the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>50</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

purpose of separating the interests of the evacuees from those of the 
claimants in any composite property, and in particular may,--

<section><tid>1289595</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of any claim of a co- sharer or partner,--

<subsection><tid>927283</tid>
<number>i</number>direct the Custodian to pay to the claimant 
the amount of money assessed in respect of his share in 
the composite property or deposit the same in a Civil 
Court having jurisdiction over such property and 
deliver possession of the property to the Custodian and 
the claimant may withdraw the amount in deposit in the 
Civil Court; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>700387</tid>
<number>ii</number>transfer the property to the claimant on 
payment by him of the amount of money assessed in 
respect of the share of the evacuee in the property; 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>644323</tid>
<number>iii</number>sell the property and distribute the sale 
proceeds thereof between the Custodian and the claimant 
in proportion to the share of the evacuee and of the 
claimant in the property; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>518195</tid>
<number>iv</number>partition the property according to shares of 
the evacuee and the claimant and deliver possession of 
the shares allotted to the evacuee and the claimant to 
the Custodian and the claimant respectively;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1923430</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of any claim of a mortgagor or a 
mortgagee,--

<subsection><tid>1755896</tid>
<number>i</number>pay to the Custodian or the claimant the 
amount payable under the mortgage debt and redeem the 
mortgaged property; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1776956</tid>
<number>ii</number>sell the mortgaged property for satisfaction 
of the mortgage debt and distribute the sale proceeds 
thereof; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1392819</tid>
<number>iii</number>partition the property between the mortgagor 
and the mortgagee having regard to the share to which 
the mortgagee would be entitled in lieu of his claim;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1745386</tid>
<number>c</number>adopt a combination of all or some of the aforesaid 
measures:
Provided that before taking any measure under this section, the 
competent officer shall take into account the order of preference 
filed by the claimant under clause (f) of sub- section (2) of section 7 
; and in any case where the claimant is a mortgagor and tenders the 
amount due, the competent officer shall accept the same in full 
satisfaction of the mortgage debt.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1925476</tid>
<number> 11</number> Vesting of evacuee interest in the Custodian free from 
encumbrances and payments, etc., to be valid discharge from all 
claims.
<section><tid>1142372</tid>
<number>1</number>Where in respect of any property, notice under section 6  
is issued but no claim is filed or found to exist or where any claim 
in

<pagefootnote><pagenum>51</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

respect of such property is found to exist and the competent officer 
separates the evacuee interest therein under section 10, the whole 
property, or, as the case may be, the evacuee interest in the property 
thus separated shall vest in the Custodian free from all encumbrances 
and liabilities and any payment, transfer or partition made or 
effected under section 10, in satisfaction of any claim in respect of 
the property shall be a full and valid discharge of all claims in 
respect of the property.


</section>

<section><tid>778343</tid>
<number>2</number>The Custodian may take possession of any such property by 
evicting the claimant and other persons who may be in occupation 
thereof and may, for that purpose, use or cause to be used such force 
as may be necessary:
Provided that the Custodian shall not disturb the possession of 
any person (other than the claimant) who was in lawful possession of 
the property at the commencement of this Act and has continued in such 
possession.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1414835</tid>
<number>12</number>Rights of claimants inter se and by other persons against 
claimants not to be affected. Nothing in this Chapter shall prejudice 
any rights in respect of the property transferred or delivered, or 
payment made, to a claimant under the provisions of this Act which any 
other claimant or other person may be entitled by due process of law 
to enforce against the claimant to whom the property is delivered or 
transferred or the payment is made.
CHAP

APPEAL, REVISION AND POWERS AND PROCEDURE OF COMPETENT OFFICERS ANDAPPELLATE 
OFFICERS

CHAPTER III

APPEAL, REVISION AND POWERS AND PROCEDURE OF COMPETENT OFFICERS 
AND APPELLATE OFFICERS



</article>



<article><tid>184264</tid>
<number> 13</number> Power to appoint appellate officers.
<section><tid>1578823</tid>
<number>1</number>The State Government  
with the approval of the Central Government may, by notification in 
the Official Gazette, appoint as many appellate officers as may be 
necessary for the purpose of hearing appeals against the orders of the 
competent officers and an appellate officer shall have jurisdiction 
over such local area or areas as may be specified in the notification.

</section>

<section><tid>426170</tid>
<number>2</number>No person shall be qualified to be appointed as an appellate 
officer under this Act unless such person--

<subsection><tid>1446327</tid>
<number>a</number>is, or has been, or is qualified for appointment as, a 
Judge of a High Court; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1142430</tid>
<number>b</number>is, or has been, a District Judge.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>52</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>523773</tid>
<number> 14</number> Appeals.
<section><tid>321151</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person aggrieved by an order of the  
competent officer made under section 8 or section 10 may, within sixty 
days from the date of the order, prefer an appeal to the appellate 
officer in such form and manner as may be prescribed:
Provided that the appellate officer may entertain the appeal 
after the expiry of the said period of sixty days if he is satisfied 
that the appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from filing the 
appeal in time.


</section>

<section><tid>433642</tid>
<number>2</number>The appellate officer may, after hearing the appeal, confirm, 
vary or reverse the order appealed from and may pass such orders as he 
deems fit.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>932982</tid>
<number>15</number>Power of revision of the appellate officer. The appellate 
officer may at any time call for the record of any proceeding in which 
the competent officer has passed an order for the purpose of 
satisfying himself as to the legality or propriety of any such order 
and may pass such order in relation thereto as he thinks fit:
Provided that the appellate officer shall not pass an order under 
this section prejudicially to any person without giving him a 
reasonable opportunity of being heard.



</article>



<article><tid>806246</tid>
<number>16</number>Amendment of orders. Clerical or arithmetical mistakes in 
orders passed by a competent officer or an appellate officer or errors 
arising therein from any accidental slip or omission, may, at any 
time, be corrected by the competent officer or the appellate officer 
either of his own motion or on an application received in this behalf 
from any of the parties.


</article>



<article><tid>1268366</tid>
<number> 17</number> Powers and procedure of competent officers and appellate 
officers.
<section><tid>1026340</tid>
<number>1</number>A competent officer or an appellate officer shall, for  
the purpose of holding any inquiry or hearing any appeal under this 
Act, have the same powers as are vested in a Civil Court under the 
Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>), when trying a suit in 
respect of the following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1704556</tid>
<number>a</number>summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person 
and examining him on oath;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1578343</tid>
<number>b</number>requiring the discovery and production of documents;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>792991</tid>
<number>c</number>issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1001038</tid>
<number>d</number>any other matter which may be prescribed;
and any proceeding before the competent officer or the appellate 
officer shall be deemed to be a judicial proceeding within the meaning 
of section 193 and 228 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>), and the 
competent


<pagefootnote><pagenum>53</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

officer or the appellate officer shall be deemed to be a Civil Court 
within the meaning of sections 480 and 482 of the Code of Criminal 
Procedure, <year>1898</year> (5 of <year>1898</year>).


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>966212</tid>
<number>2</number>An appellate officer shall, subject to the provisions of this 
Act, have such further powers as are vested in a Court under the Code 
of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>), when hearing an appeal.

</section>

<section><tid>1744920</tid>
<number>3</number>Subject to any rules made in this behalf, the competent 
officer and appellate officer shall follow the same procedure as a 
Civil Court does in regard to civil suits including recording of 
evidence and the provisions of the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of  
  <year>1908</year>) shall, as far as may be, apply to such proceedings.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1172193</tid>
<number>18</number>Finality of orders. Save as otherwise expressly provided in 
this Act, every order made by any appellate officer or competent 
officer shall be final and shall not be called in question in any 
Court by way of an appeal or revision or in any original suit, 
application or execution proceedings.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER IV

MISCELLANEOUS



</article>



<article><tid>1971122</tid>
<number> 19</number> Power to transfer cases.
<section><tid>1411077</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government or the  
appellate officer may, by order in writing at any time, transfer any 
case pending before a competent officer to another competent officer 
for holding the inquiry and the competent officer to whom the case is 
so transferred may proceed either de novo or from the stage at which 
it was transferred.

</section>

<section><tid>844781</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government or the State Government may, by order 
in writing at any time, transfer any appeal pending before an 
appellate officer to another appellate officer for hearing the appeal 
and the appellate officer to whom the appeal is so transferred may 
proceed either de novo or from the stage at which it was transferred.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>607897</tid>
<number> 20</number> Jurisdiction of Civil Courts barred in certain matters.
<section><tid>1682727</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Save as otherwise expressly provided in this Act, no Civil or Revenue 
Court shall entertain any suit or proceeding in so far as it relates 
to any claim to composite property which the competent officer is 
empowered by or under this Act to decide, and no injunction in respect 
of any action taken or to be taken by the competent officer in respect 
of the composite property shall be granted by any Civil Court or other 
authority.

</section>

<section><tid>169709</tid>
<number>2</number>All suits and proceedings pending before a Civil or Revenue 
Court at the commencement of this Act shall, in so far as they relate

<pagefootnote><pagenum>54</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

to any claim filed before a competent officer under section 7, be 
stayed during the pendency of any proceeding under this Act.


</section>

<section><tid>394395</tid>
<number>3</number>Nothing in sub- section (1) shall prevent any Civil or Revenue 
Court from entertaining any suit or proceeding relating to any right 
in respect of any payment made, or property transferred or delivered, 
to a claimant under the provisions of this Act which any other 
claimant or other person may be entitled by due process of law to 
enforce against the claimant to whom the payment is made or the 
property is delivered or transferred.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1810958</tid>
<number>21</number>Competent officer and appellate officer to be a public 
servant. Every competent officer and appellate officer shall be deemed 
to be a public servant within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian 
Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>778955</tid>
<number>22</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit, 
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the appellate 
officer or the competent officer in respect of anything which is in 
good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or of 
any rules or orders made thereunder.


</article>



<article><tid>676434</tid>
<number> 23</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1470322</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> to carry out the 
purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>676358</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1693367</tid>
<number>a</number>the form of any notice and the manner of its service;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>454504</tid>
<number>b</number>the form and manner in which an application may be 
filed under section 6;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1807918</tid>
<number>c</number>the form and manner in which claims may be submitted 
and the particulars which a statement of claim may 
contain;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1886343</tid>
<number>d</number>the manner in which inquiries under this Act may be 
held and the procedure to be followed by competent 
officers in such proceedings;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>101627</tid>
<number>e</number>the form and manner in which appeals may be preferred 
against the order of competent officers and the 
procedure to be followed by appellate officers;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1775901</tid>
<number>f</number>the powers vested in a Civil Court which may be 
exercised by the competent officers and appellate 
officers while
<pagefootnote><pagenum>55</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>For the Evacuee Interest (Separation) Rules, <year>1951</year>, see Gazette of 
India, <year>1952</year>, Pt. II, Sec. 3, p. 109.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


holding an inquiry or hearing an appeal, as the case 
may be, under this Act;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1316810</tid>
<number>g</number>the manner of separating the interests of the evacuees 
from those of claimants in any composite property;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>820407</tid>
<number>h</number>any other matter which has to be, or may be, prescribed 
under this Act.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



 </act>