<act><title>

The
Press Council Rules, 19791</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>1</number>
Short title.—
<section><number>1</number>
These rules may be called the Press Council Rules, 1979.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official
Gazette.
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>3</number>
Conditions of service of the Chairman.—
<section><number>1</number>
the Headquarters of the Chairman shall be the same as that of the Council.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The leave admissible to the Chairman shall be as admissible to Central
Government Officers under the Central Civil Services (Leave) Rules, 1972.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
(i) If a person belonging to a pensionable service is nominated as Chairman, he
shall be entitled to pension and shall also subscribe to the General Provident
Fund.
 


 <subsection><number>ii</number>
If a retired person or any person other than a person belonging to a pensionable
service, is nominated as Chairman he shall contribute to the Contributory
Provident Fund from the date of such employment. However, the Council’s
contribution, with interest, shall be credited after the completion of one
year’s service.
 


 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number>
The Chairman shall be entitled to travel by air on journeys performed in
connection with the work of the Council or by rail by first class
air-conditioned accommodation and shall be entitled to be paid travelling and
daily allowance in accordance with the pay drawn by him.
 


 </section><section><number>5</number>
The Chairman shall be his own controlling officer for the purpose of travelling
allowances.
 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>3</number> Conditions of service of the 
      Chairman.—
<section><number>1</number> the Headquarters 
      of the Chairman shall be the same as that of the Council.
 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The leave admissible to the Chairman shall 
      be as admissible to Central Government Officers under the Central Civil 
      Services (Leave) Rules, 1972.
 
 </section><section><number>3</number> (i) If a person belonging to a pensionable 
      service is nominated as Chairman, he shall be entitled to pension and 
      shall also subscribe to the General Provident Fund.
 
 <subsection><number>ii</number> If a retired person or any person other 
      than a person belonging to a pensionable service, is nominated as Chairman 
      he shall contribute to the Contributory Provident Fund from the date of 
      such employment. However, the Council’s contribution, with interest, shall 
      be credited after the completion of one year’s service.
 
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number> The Chairman shall be entitled to travel by 
      air on journeys performed in connection with the work of the Council or by 
      rail by first class air-conditioned accommodation and shall be entitled to 
      be paid travelling and daily allowance in accordance with the pay drawn by 
      him.
 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Chairman shall be his own controlling 
      officer for the purpose of travelling allowances.
 
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>4</number>
Allowances to be paid to members other than the Chairman.—
<section><number>1</number> A member of
the Council, other than the Chairman shall, on journeys performed in connection
with the work of the Council, be entitled to travel by air or by rail by first
class air-conditioned accommodation by the shortest route and shall be entitled
to reimbursement of single room rent and daily allowance at the following
rates:—
 


 <subsection><number>i</number>
reimbursement of rent in any State Guest House or for single room in
medium range Indian Tourism Development Corporation hotels or State Government
run Tourist hotel/hotels or residential accommodation provided by registered
societies;
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>
room rent for stay in private lodges/hotels will continue to be allowed
up to the limits specified from time to time;
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number>
daily allowance at the rate of 90% of ordinary rates of daily allowance
as admissible to officers in the pay range of Rs. 5,100/- and above for boarding
purpose; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number>
In addition to the above, the outstation, non-official members will be
entitled to a sitting fee at the rate of Rs. 300/- per day irrespective of the
class of city.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
Those members of the Council who attend the work of the Council locally, shall
be entitled to actual conveyance subject to a ceiling of Rs. 100/- per day in
‘A’ and ‘B-1’ class cities and Rs. 75/- per day in other cities.] 


   


  






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>5</number>
Method of recruitment.—
<section><number>1</number>
Recruitment to the posts under the Council may be made by adopting any of the
following methods, namely:—
 


 <subsection><number>a</number>
by direct recruitment by advertising the post: 
 

 Provided
that in respect of posts corresponding to Groups ‘C’ and ‘D’ posts under
the Central Government the recruitment shall be made through the Employment
Exchange; or 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
by promotion; or 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
by deputation or transfer of persons employed in Government Offices or
bodies whether incorporated or not, wholly or substantially owned or controlled
by Government: 
 

 Provided
that the regular officers and employees of the erstwhile Press Council of India
which was dissolved with effect from January 1, 1976 may also be absorbed in the
Secretariat of the first Council.
 


 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
the Council shall constitute such Selection Committees as may be considered
necessary for the purpose of recommending suitable candidates for the posts.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
the Council may make appointments to the posts taking into account the
recommendations of the Selection Committees:
 


 Provided
that if a vacancy is required to be filled urgently the Chairman may make a
temporary appointment in any post on ad hoc basis for a period not
exceeding six months, so, however, that every appointment so made, shall be
reported to the Council before the expiry of that period for its approval; and,
where in a case any appointment so made is not approved by the Council, the
person so appointed shall cease to hold the post from such date as the Council
may specify in that behalf.
 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>6</number>
Reservation of posts for Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes.—The
Council shall, except in the case of the officers requiring special
qualifications to be decided by the Council with the previous approval of the
Central Government, observe the rules relating to reservation of posts for the
Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled Tribes as laid down by the Central Government
from time to time in this behalf.
 



 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>7</number> Production of medical certificate and 
      verification of character and antecedents.—Recruitment to all posts under the council 
      shall normally be made subject to the production of a medical certificate 
      of physical fitness in accordance with such standards as may be laid down 
      for posts of corresponding status under the Central Government and after 
      due verification of the character and antecedents of the persons 
      concerned.
 
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>8</number>
Terms and conditions of Service.—Until
the Council makes regulations in this behalf, the terms and conditions of
service governing the employees of the Central Government and the rights and
privileges enjoyed by them shall, so far as may be, apply to the employees of
the Council, provided that the employees of the Council shall be entitled to
subscribe to the Contributory Provident Fund (India) with effect from the date
of appointment in the Council in accordance with the orders issued by the
Ministry of Finance on the subject from time to time.
 



 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>9</number>
Annual Report.—The Annual Report
required to be prepared under section 20 of the Act shall be prepared by the
Council within four months from the expiry of the year to which it relates.
 


 Explanation.—For
purpose of this rule the ‘year’ means ‘calender year’.
 



 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>10</number>
Levy of Fees.—
<section><number>1</number> The Council may
for the purpose of performing its functions under the Act, levy and collect fees
from registered newspapers and news agencies during each financial year as
specified below:
 


 <subsection><number>a</number>
Rs. 1,500 per annum from each registered newspaper with a circulation
range of above one lakh; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
Rs. 1,000 per annum from each registered newspaper with a circulation
range above 50,000 but below one lakh; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
Rs. 500 per annum from each registered newspaper with a circulation range
above 15,000 but below 50,000; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
Rs. 100 per annum from each registered newspaper with a circulation range
above 5,000 but below 15,000; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>
Rs. 1,500 per annum from each Class I or Class II news agency, and 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>
Rs. 1,000 per annum each from all other news agencies. 
 

 Explanation.—For
the purposes of this rule, the circulation range of registered newspapers shall
be such as indicated in the Annual Report of the Registrar of Newspapers for
India (Press in India) last published before April 1 every year, and the
criteria for classification of news agencies shall be such as indicated in the
Report of the Wage Board for Working Journalists.
 


 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
The Council shall send during the course of every financial year notices of
demand under registered A.D. covers to registered newspapers and news agencies
calling for the remittance to it of the fees as indicated in sub-rule (1) and
such registered newspapers and news agencies shall remit the amount of fees so
demanded within thirty days of the receipt of such notices by means of Demand
Drafts payable to the Council.
 



 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 
Subs. by G.S.R. 37 (E), dated 27th January, 1997.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>