<act><title>


THE Petroleum AND NATURAL GAS RULES, 19591</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Petroleum and Natural Gas Rules, 1959.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the 25th day of November, 1959.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Savings.—Nothing 
in these rules shall affect the provisions of the Petroleum Act, 1934 (30 of 
1934), or the rules made thereunder.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
        
<number>a</number>  “bore‑hole” includes an oil well or gas well;
 
     
1[***]
 
      
2[(ab)  “coal 
bed methane” means natural gas obtained from bore holes occurring to coal or 
lignite seams and consisting primarily of hydrocarbons;
 </section><section>
      
<number>ac</number>  “condensate” means those low vapour pressure hydrocarbons obtained 
form natural gas through condensation of extraction which are in the form of 
liquid at normal surface temperature and pressure conditions;
 </section><section>
      
<number>ad</number>  “continental shelf” shall have the same meaning as assigned to it in 
the Territorial Waters, Continental Shelf, Exclusive Economic Zone and Other 
Maritime Zones Act, 1976 as amended from time to time;
 </section><section>
      
<number>ae</number>  “contract” means an agreement entered into between the Government of 
India and any other party in relation to exploration and exploitation of 
hydrocarbon and/or coal bed methane for relevant area;]
 



3[(b)  “crude 
oil” means petroleum in its natural state in liquid, viscous or solid form 
refined or otherwise treated from which water and foreign substances have been 
extracted;]
 </section><section>
        
<number>c</number>  “drilling” or “boring” means perforation of the earth’s surface crust 
by mechanical means (irrespective of whether the hole caused by the perforation 
is vertical, inclined, or horizontal) and includes all operations for preventing 
collapse of the sides of such hole or for preventing such hole from being filled 
with extraneous materials including water;
 
 

4[(ca)  
“exclusive economic” zone shall have the same meaning as assigned to it in the 
Territorial Waters, Continental Shelf, Exclusive Economic Zone and Other 
Maritime Zones Act, 1976 as amended from time to time;]
 </section><section>
        
<number>d</number>  “field” means the general area which is underlaid, or appears to be 
underlaid, by at least one pool and shall include the underground reservoir or 
reservoirs containing petroleum or natural gas or both;
 </section><section>
        
<number>e</number>  “gas well” means any well the production from which is predominantly 
natural gas or condensate, or both in quantity;
 
 

4[(ea)  “gas 
hydrates” means naturally occurring solids composed of water molecules  
forming a rigid lattice of cages each containing a molecule of natural gas;]
 </section><section>
         
<number>f</number>  “geological survey” includes the examination of exposed rocks in the 
field the collection of the necessary specimens of rocks and other materials, 
investigations in the laboratory, the preparations of geological maps and 
geological sections and all other operations essential for the determination of 
the geological nature, age and structure of rocks in any area;
 </section><section>
        
<number>g</number>  “geophysical survey” means the search, by instruments for the presence 
of suitable underground geological structures and includes the sinking of 
bore‑holes for detonating explosives necessary for the purpose, but not the 
drilling of deep core‑holes or the sinking of trial shafts, trenches, or other 
kinds of large and deep excavations connected with prospecting;
 
 

4[(ga)  
“hydrocarbons” means any organic compound of hydrogen and carbon;]
 </section><section>
        
<number>h</number>  “information drilling” means the drilling of bore‑holes, for the 
purpose of procuring scientific information and not with the immediate object if 
obtaining petroleum;
 



5[(i)  
“natural gas” or gas means gas obtained from bore‑holes and consisting primarily 
of hydrocarbons but does not includes helium occurring in association with such 
hydrocarbons;]
 </section><section>
         
<number>j</number>  “oil well” means any well which is capable of producing crude 
oil and which is not a gas well;
 </section><section>
        
<number>k</number>  “petroleum” means naturally occurring hydrocarbons in a free state, 
whether in the form of natural gas or in a liquid viscous or solid form but does 
not include helium occurring in association with petroleum or coal, or shale, or 
any substance which may be extracted from coal, shale, or other rock by the 
application of heat or by a chemical process;
 </section><section>

<number>l</number>  
“petroleum deposit” means any accumulation of petroleum on or below the surface 
of the earth;
 </section><section>
       
<number>m</number>  “pool” means an underground reservoir containing a common accumulation 
of petroleum or natural gas or both and includes each zone of a general 
structure which is completely separated from any other zone in the structure;
 </section><section>
        
<number>n</number>  “petroleum product” means any commodity made from petroleum or natural 
gas and shall include refined crude oil, processed crude petroleum, residuum 
from crude petroleum, cracking stock, uncracked fuel oil, fuel oil, treated 
crude oil residuum casinghead gasoline natural gas gasoline, naphtha, 
distillate, gasoline, kerosene, waste oil, blended gasoline, lubricating oil, 
blends or mixture of oil with one or more liquid products or by products derived 
from oil or gas, and blends or mixtures of two or more liquids products or 
by‑products derived from oil condensate gas or petroleum hydrocarbons, whether 
herein enumerated or not;
 </section><section>
        
<number>o</number>  “prospect” with its grammatical variations means search for a 
petroleum deposit;
 </section><section>
        
<number>p</number>  “stratum” means a layer of rock more or less similar throughout a 
lithological unit;
 </section><section>
        
<number>q</number>  “the Act” means the Oilfields (Regulation and Development) Act, 1948 
(53 of 1948); and
 
 

6[(qq)  
“territorial waters” shall have the same meaning as assigned to it in the 
Territorial Waters, Continental Shelf, Exclusive Economic Zone and Other 
Maritime Zones Act, 1976 as amended from time to time;]
 </section><section>
         
<number>r</number>  “Waste” includes the following:—
 <subsection>
              
<number>i</number>  the inefficient, excessive, or improper use or dissipation of 
reservoir energy and the locating, spacing, drilling, equipping, operating or 
producing of any oil or gas well in a manner which results or tends to result in 
reducing the quantity of oil or gas ultimately to be recovered from any pool;
 </subsection><subsection>
             
<number>ii</number>  the inefficient storing of petroleum; and the locating, spacing, 
drilling, equipping, operating or producing of any oil or gas well in a manner 
causing or tending to cause unnecessary or excessive surface loss or destruction 
of petroleum or natural gas;
 </subsection><subsection>
             
<number>iii</number>  producing petroleum or natural gas in such a manner as to cause 
unnecessary channeling of water or gas or both, or coming of water;
 </subsection><subsection>
            
<number>iv</number>  the submerging with water of any stratum or part thereof capable of 
producing petroleum or natural gas;
 </subsection><subsection>
             
<number>v</number>  the creation of unnecessary fire hazards;
 </subsection><subsection>
            
<number>vi</number>  the escape into the open air, from a well producing both petroleum 
and natural gas, of gas in excess of the amount which is necessary for efficient 
production from the well; and
 </subsection><subsection>
            
<number>vii</number>  permitting gas produced from a gas well to escape into open air.
 
 








</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> No prospecting or 
mining except under a licence or a lease.—No 
person shall prospect for petroleum except in pursuance of a petroleum 
exploration licence (hereinafter referred to as a licence) granted under these 
rules and no person shall mine petroleum except in pursuance of a petroleum 
mining lease (hereinafter referred to as a lease) granted under these rules. 
Every holder of a licence and every holder of a lease shall in these rules be 
referred to as the licensee and the lessee, respectively.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>5</number> Grant of 
licences and leases.—2[
<section><number>1</number> 
A licence or lease in respect of—
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  any land or mineral underlying the ocean within the territorial waters 
or the continental shelf 

3[or the exclusive 
economic zone] of India and vested in the Union, shall be granted by the Central 
Government, and
 



4[(ii)  any 
land vested in a State Government, shall be granted by the State Government with 
the previous approval of the State Government.]]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every licence and 
lease shall contain such of the terms, covenants and conditions prescribed by 
these rules as are applicable and such additional terms, covenants and 
conditions as may be provided in the agreement between the Central Government 
and the licensee or the lessee:
 
Provided that 

5[where the licence 
or lease has been or is to be granted by the State Government] the Central 
Government shall consult the State Government before agreeing to such additional 
terms, covenants and conditions.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Central 
Government, if it deems fit, may from time to time notify in the Official 
Gazette, particulars regarding the basis on which the Central Government may be 
prepared to consider proposals for prospecting or mining operations in any 
specified area or areas.
 
 







</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Initial licence or 
lease fee.—A
fee amounting to 
<section><number>i</number> 

1[Rs. 25000 (Rupees 
twenty five thousand)] in the case of a licence, and (ii) 

1[Rs. 50,000 
(Rupees fifty thousand)] in the case of a lease, shall be paid 

2[to the Central 
Government or the State Government, as the case may be] by the licensee or the 
lessee prior to the formal grant of a licence or a lease.
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Rights of the 
licensee and the lessee.—Subject 
to the Act or any rules made thereunder and subject also to terms of the 
agreement that may be 

1[arrived at 
between the Central Government and the licensee or the lessee or, where the land 
is vested in a State Government between the Central Government and the licensee 
or lessee after consultation with the State Government].
 <section>
         
<number>i</number>  every licensee shall have the exclusive right to carry out, in 
addition to geological and geophysical surveys, information drilling and 
test‑drilling operations for petroleum in the area covered by the licence and 
shall have the exclusive right to a lease to a lease over such part of the


2[area] covered by 
the licence as he may desire;
 </section><section>
        
<number>ii</number>  every lessee shall have the exclusive right to conduct mining 
operations for petroleum and natural gas in and on the land demised by such 
lease together with the right to construct and maintain in and on such 

2[area] such works, 
buildings, plant, 

2[platform] 
waterways, roads, pipelines, dams, reservoirs, tanks, pumping stations, 
tramways, railways, telephone lines, electric power lines and other structures 
and equipment 

2[and other 
facilities] as are necessary for the full enjoyment of the lease or for 
fulfilling his obligations under the lease.
 
 





</section></article> 

 
 
 

1[***]
 
 



 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Date of effect of 
licences and leases.—Every 
licence and every lease shall be effective from the date specified in this 
behalf in the licence or the lease.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>10</number> Area and 
term of licence.—The area covered by licence shall be specified therein and 
the licence shall in the first instance be valid for a period of four years, 
which may be extended for 

2[***] further 
periods of one year each 

3[till the expiry 
of the exploration period(s) provided under the agreement if any, or unless 
otherwise specified by the Central Government in this regard.]
 
 





</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Security deposit, 
annual licence fee and shedding of areas.—­
<section><number>1</number>


1[2[***] 
The applicant for a licence shall,] before the licence is granted to him, 
deposit with 

1[the Central 
Government or where the licence is to be or has been granted by the State 
Government, the State Government] as security for due observance of the terms, 
covenants and conditions of the licence, a sum of 

3[Rs. 1,00,000 
(Rupees one lakh).]
 

4[(2) 

2[***], the 
licensee shall pay yearly in advance by way of licence fee in respect of his 
licence a sum calculated for each square kilometre or part thereof covered by 
the licence at the following rates:—
 



3[(i)  Rs. 50 
(Rupees fifty) for the first year licence.
 <subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  Rs. 100 (Rupees one hundred) for the second year licence.
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>iii</number>  Rs. 500 (Rupees five hundred) for the third year licence.
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iv</number>  Rs. 700 (Rupees seven hundred) for the fourth year licence.
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>v</number>  Rs. 1000 (Rupees one thousand) for the each subsequent year of 
renewal.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The licensee shall be 
at liberty to determine the licence or relinquish any part of the area covered 
by the licence on giving not less than two months notice in writing to the


5[the Central 
Government or where the licence is to be or has been granted by the State 
Government, the State Government] and the Central Government.
 
 








</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Area and term of a 
lease.—1[***] 
The area covered by a lease shall ordinarily be 

2[250 square 
kilometers] and the term of a lease shall ordinarily be twenty years: 

 

3[Provided that the 
Central Government may, if satisfied that it is necessary in public interest so 
to do, by notification, relax the condition regarding area of aforesaid, in 
relation to any application for lease.]
 
 





</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Mining lease fees, 
rent.—
<section><number>1</number> 
1[2[***] 
The applicant for a lease shall,] before the lease is granted to him,—
 <subsection>
        
<number>a</number>  deposit with 

1[the Central or 
the State Government, as the case may be] as security, a sum of 

3[Rs. 2,00,000 
(Rupees two lakh)], for due observance of the terms and conditions of the lease;
 



1[(b)  also 
deposit with the Central Government or the State Government, as the case may be, 
for meeting the preliminary expenses such sum, not exceeding 

3[Rs. 30,000 
(rupees thirty thousand)], as the Central Government or the State Government 
with the approval of the Central Government, may determine;]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 

1[2[***] 
On the grant of a lease, the lessee],—
 <subsection>
        
<number>a</number>  shall pay 

1[to the Central 
Government or the State Government, as the case may be] for every year a fixed 
yearly dead rent at the following rates:—
 
                             
4[Rs. 25.00 per 
hectare] or part thereof for the first 

1[100 square 
kilometres]; and 

4[Rs. 50.00 per 
hectare] or part thereof for area exceeding the first 

1[100 square 
kilometres] provided that the lessee shall be liable to pay only the dead rent 
of the royalty, whichever is higher in amount but not both;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>b</number>  shall also pay to the State Government, for the surface area of the 
land actually used by him for the purpose of the operations conducted under the 
lease, surface rent at such rate, not exceeding the land revenue and cesses 
assessed or assessable on the land, as may be specified by the State Government 
with the approval of the Central Government.
 
 






</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Royalty on 
petroleum and furnishing of return and particulars.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 

<subsection><number>a</number> Notwithstanding anything in any agreement, a lessee shall—
 <subsubsection>
         
<number>i</number>  where the lease has been granted by the Central Government, pay to 
that Government, and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  where the lease has been granted by the State Government, pay to that 
Government, 

2[a royalty in 
respect of any mineral oil mined, quarried excavated or collected by him from 
the leased area at the rate specified in Schedule of the Act from time to time. 
The royalty shall be payable on monthly basis, as may be provided for in the 
lease and shall be paid by the last day of the month succeeding the period in 
respect of which it is payable]:
 
Provided that the Central 
Government or, as the case may be, the State Government with the approval of the 
Central Government, may direct that such royalty be paid in petroleum and 
natural gas:
 

3[Provided further 
that such royalty shall not be payable in respect of any crude oil, casing head 
condensate or natural gas which is unavoidably lost or is returned to the 
reservoir or is used for drilling or other operations relating to the production 
of petroleum or natural gas or both.]
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> Every lessee shall pay 
to the State Government, where the lease has been granted by that Government, 
royalty for the period of the lease before the 1st November, 1962, at the rate 
specified in the lease deed.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The lessee shall, 
within the first seven days of every month or within such further time as 

4[the Central 
Government or the State Government, as the case may be] may allow, furnish or 
cause to be furnished to 

4[the Central 
Government or the State Government, as the case may be,] a full and proper 
return showing the quantity 

5[***] of all crude 
oil, casinghead condensate and natural gas obtained during the preceding month 
from mining operations conducted pursuant to the lease. The monthly return 
required to be furnished shall be, as nearly as may be, in the form specified in 
the Schedule annexed to these rules.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If 

4[the Central 
Government or the State Government, as the case may be] is not satisfied with 
any return furnished in accordance with sub‑rule (2), it may require the person 
furnishing the same to furnish such further particulars as it may demand with 
respect to the crude oil, casing head condensate or natural gas obtained as 
aforesaid, and may appoint an officer in this behalf to make all necessary 
enquiries in relation to such crude oil, casing head condensate or natural gas. 
The officer so appointed may make all such enquiries and may require the lessee 
or the manager or person acting as manager or secretary of such lessee to 
produce for his inspection at the office of such lessee any books, accounts, 
documents, writings, papers or instruments in his possession or under his 
control which such officer may consider necessary to enable him to ascertain the 
quantity 

5[***] of the crude 
oil, casinghead condensate and natural gas obtained as aforesaid and may make 
copies of any entries or matters contained in such books, accounts, documents, 
writings, papers or instruments and upon completion of such enquiries such 
officer shall report thereon to 

4[the Central 
Government or the State Government as the case may be.]
 

6[On receipt of 
such report, 

7[the Central 
Government or the State Government, as the case may be,] if it is of the opinion 
that the quantity of any crude oil, casing‑head condensate or natural gas 
declared in the return furnished in accordance with this rule is too low; may 
determine the quantity of such crude oil, casing‑head condensate or natural gas 
and royalty shall be paid on the quantity so assessed.]
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every officer in


6[the Central or 
State Government service] shall preserve and aid in preserving secrecy with 
regard to the contents of any return made under this rule which have come to his 
knowledge in his official capacity and shall not communicate such matter to any 
other person unless required in the performance of his official duties or under 
the authority of a court of competent jurisdiction,
 
 









</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Survey.—If 
at the time of the grant, or at any time during the term, of a lease, the State 
Government is of the opinion that survey or re‑survey 

1[a fee of Rs. 
10,000 (Rupees ten thousand)] of the land covered by such lease or any part of 
such land is necessary, such land or part thereof shall be surveyed by a 
qualified surveyor and the lessee shall within the period specified by the State 
Government pay to the State Government, for such survey or re‑survey 

1[a fee of Rs. 
10,000 (Rupees ten thousand)] such fee as the State Government may, with the 
approval of the Central Government, determine.
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Identification of 
areas.—Within 
three months from the date referred to in rule 9, the licensee or the lessee 
shall display notices at all conspicuous points on the area covered by the 
licence or the lease so as to indicate its boundaries and shall thereafter, 
during the term of such licence or lease, maintain such notices to the 
satisfaction of the State Government.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Transfer or 
assignment.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
The licensee or the lessee shall not assign or transfer his right, title 
and interest in respect of the licence or the lease or 

2[in respect of the 
land or mineral underlying the ocean within the territorial waters or the 
continental shelf of India covered by such licence or lease granted by the 
Central Government, without the consent in writing of the Central Government, 
and in the case of land covered by a licence or lease granted by the State 
Government, without the consent in writing of the Central Government being first 
obtained through the State Government:]
 

1[Provided that in 
case where a contract has been signed between the licensee/lessee and the 
Central Government, the transfer or the assignment, as the case may be, shall be 
governed by the terms and conditions of the contract, and will be effected in 
the manner laid down in such contract.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Upon receipt of the 
consent of the Central Government referred to in sub-rule (1) the licence or 
lease, as the case may be, shall be issued in name of the transferee or the 
assignee, severally or jointly, to the extent of the transfer or the assignment, 
with effect from the date from which such transfer or assignment is made 
effective.]
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Pre‑emption.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In the case of a national emergency in respect of petroleum, the Central 
Government shall, at all times, during such emergency, have the right of 
pre‑emption of the refined petroleum or petroleum products produced from the 
crude oil or natural gas extracted from the area held under a lease, or of the 
crude oil or natural gas where the lessee is permitted to sell, export or 
dispose of it without its being refined within India: provided that the fair 
market price prevailing at the time of pre‑emption shall be paid to the lessee 
by the Central Government, for the petroleum or petroleum products or the crude 
oil or natural gas taken in pre‑emption.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Central Government 
shall be the sole judge as to what constitutes a national emergency in respect 
of petroleum, and its decision in this respect shall be final.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> General provisions.—The 
licensee or the lessee shall—
 <section>
        
<number>a</number>  maintain in good repair and condition all apparatus, appliances and 
wells capable of producing petroleum on the 

1[area] covered by 
the licence or the lease;
 </section><section>
        
<number>b</number>  execute all prospecting or mining operations on such 

1[area] in a proper 
and workmanlike manner in accordance with such methods and practice as are 
customarily use in modern oilfield practice and abide by all instructions, 
directions and orders that may be give pursuant to any rules under Chapter VI; 
and
 </section><section>
        
<number>c</number>  upon the determination of the licence or the lease or upon the 
relinquishment of any’ area covered by it shall furnish to the Central 
Government 

2[where a licence 
or lease is granted by that Government and to the Central Government through the 
State Government where a licence or lease is granted by the State Government] 
confidentially complete records of all the data such as surface geological maps, 
and sections, magnetic and gravity measurements and anomaly maps, seismic 
profiles, sections and structure contour maps, electrical and telluric current 
survey data, and other information which have a direct or indirect bearing on 
the petroleum and mineral possibilities in the area, collected by the licensee 
or the lessee or his agents or contractors.
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>19A</number> Recovery 
of helium from natural gas.—
<section><number>1</number> Nothing contained in these rules or the 
terms of a licence or a lease or a contract will give right to a licensee or a 
lessee to use, sell or otherwise dispose of Helium which may be produced with 
natural gas and the licensee/lessee shall dispose of such helium in accordance 
with such directions as may be issued in this behalf by the Central Government 
or by an officer or an agency duly authorised for this purpose by the Central 
Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the Central 
Government desires to extract Helium from natural gas, the licensee/lessee, in 
order to enable the Government to install and operate equipment and facilities 
for carrying out helium recovery operations, shall make available to the Central 
Government or its nominee the area and utilities required for such operations 
and in such a case the licensee/lessee shall be entitled for compensation based 
on the internal company accounting practices to be mutually agreed between the 
licensee/lessee and the Central Government/its nominee.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Suspension of 
conditions of licence or lease.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Upon written application being made by the licensee or the lessee, or, where 
there are two or more of them, by not less than one‑half of their number, 

1[the Central 
Government, where the licence or the lease has been granted by it, or the State 
Government with the prior approval of the Central Government where the licence 
or the lease has been granted by the State Government may, from time to time, if 
it considers that adequate reason have been furnished, authorise], for periods 
not on any occasion exceeding six months, suspension of any or all of the terms, 
covenants or conditions relating to the working of the 

2[area] covered by 
the licence or the lease.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 

1[The Central 
Government or the State Government, as the case may be,] if it authorises; 
suspension as aforesaid, impose such conditions as it may think fit for the 
protection of any bore‑holes, equipment or works on such 

2[area], or for the 
protection of any petroleum deposits, water or minerals in such 

2[area] or in any 
adjacent 

2[area], or for any 
other purpose whatsoever and the licensee or the lessee shall comply with such 
conditions as if they are incorporated in the licence or the lease.
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Cancellation of 
licences and leases.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If the licensee or the lessee or his executors, administrators or assigns at any 
time during the term of the licence or the lease—
 <subsection>
        
<number>a</number>  fails to fulfil, or contravenes, any of the terms, covenants and 
conditions contained therein, or
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>b</number>  fails to use the 

1[area] covered by 
in bona fide for the purpose for which it has been granted, or
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>c</number>  uses such 

1[area] for a 
purpose other than that for which it has been granted.
 

2[the Central 
Government, or, as the case may be, the State Government with the prior approval 
of the Central Government], 

3[may, after 
considering the representation, if any, made by such person impose the penalty 
aforesaid], where it is satisfied that the failure, contravention or user is 
such as cannot be remedied, on giving thirty days’ notice to such person, 

4[and after 
considering the representation if any, made by him] forfeit the whole or any 
part of the security deposit made under rule 11(1) or rule 13(1)(a) and may 
cancel the licence or the lease. Such cancellation shall be published in the 
Official Gazette and shall take effect from the date of such publication. If the 
failure, contravention or user is considered to be of a remediable nature 

5[the Central 
Government or the State Government, as the case may be, shall give notice] to 
such person requiring him to remedy the same within sixty days from the date of 
receipt of the notice and informing him that the penalty as aforesaid may be 
imposed if such remedy is not provided within such period. 

5[The Central 
Government, or, as the case may be, the State Government with the prior approval 
of the Central Government], 

6[may, after 
considering the representations if any, made by such person, impose the penalty 
aforesaid], if such person fails to so remedy within such period:
 
Provided that the failure 
on the part of such a person to fulfil any of the terms, covenants and 
conditions of the licence or the lease shall not give the State Government any 
power to impose the penalty as aforesaid in so far as such failure arises from
force majeure; and if through force majeure the fulfilment of any 
of the terms, covenants and conditions of the licence or the lease be delayed, 
the period of such delay shall be added to the period fixed by the licence or 
the lease for the performance of any act. “Force majeure” includes an act 
of God, war, insurrection, riot, civil commotion, tide, storm, tidal wave, 
flood, lightning, explosion, fire, earthquake, and any other happening which the 
licensee or the lessee could not reasonably prevent or control.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A licence or a lease 
may be cancelled either wholly or in part 

5[by the Central 
Government where such licence or lease has been granted by it and by the State 
Government, after the approval of the Central Government, where such licence or 
lease has been granted by it] upon the written request of the licensee or the 
lessee or, where there are two or more of them, of not less than one‑half of 
their number and such cancellation shall be published in the Official Gazette 
and shall take effect from the date of such publication: Provided that in the 
case of a request for cancellation in part of a licence or a lease, if the State 
Government is of the opinion that survey or re‑survey is necessary such survey 
or re‑survey shall be carried out by a mining surveyor and the licensee or the 
lessee shall within the period specified by the State Government pay to the 
State Government for such survey or re‑survey such fee as the State Government 
may, with the approval of, the Central Government, determine.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If during the term of 
a licence or a lease any part of the land covered by it is required for any 
public purpose, 

5[the Central 
Government or as the case may be the State Government after approval of the 
Central Government, may] upon one month’s notice, 

7[and after 
considering representation, if any, made by the person concerned] cancel such 
licence or lease in so far as it relates to the said part of the land subject to 
such restrictions and conditions as it may impose and such cancellation shall be 
published in the Official Gazette and shall take effect from the date of such 
publication.
 

8[(4) Where the 
Central Government has entered into an agreement with the licensee, licence and 
the lease, as the case may be, shall automatically stand cancelled upon the 
expiry or termination of such contract.]
 
 










</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>22</number> Delivery 
of premises upon determination of licence or lease.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Upon determination or cancellation or relinquishment in part or in full of a 
licence, the licensee shall deliver the area released on account of the 
determination or cancellation or relinquishment after restoring it in good order 
and condition in accordance with international practices within six months from 
the date of such determination or cancellation or relinquishment, or within such 
further time as the Central Government or the State Government, as the case may 
be, may allow.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In the event of lessee 
opting not to continue mining operations and opts to relinquish the leased area 
in part or in full, or a lease is to be determined, the lessee shall deliver up 
the area released by such relinquishment or determination of lease after 
restoring it in good order and condition in accordance with the abandonment plan 
approved by the Central Government. However, lessee shall have to give prior 
written notice of at least one year before the date of intended relinquishment 
or determination as the case may be, to the Central Government along with an 
abandonment plan incorporating all actions and steps necessary to restore the 
area in accordance with international practices, for approval of the Central 
Government.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Upon cancellation of a 
mining lease under these rules, the lessee shall deliver up the area covered by 
such lease after restoring it in good order and condition in accordance with an 
abandonment plan, prepared in accordance with established international 
practices and approval by the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Upon determination or 
cancellation or relinquishment of a licence or a lease, the holder of such 
licence or lease, as the case may be, shall take all necessary steps to prevent 
consequent hazards to human life, property, environment, marine resources or 
navigation, to the satisfaction of the Central Government or the State 
Government as the case may be.
 

2[(5) The licensee 
or lessee after determination, cancellation or relinquishment of his licence or 
lease shall immediately remove and dispose of any petroleum, all stores, 
equipment, tools, machinery from such area.]
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> If such petroleum, 
stores, equipment, tools, machinery and improvements are not removed or disposed 
off and the area restored to good order and condition within six months prior to 
the determination, relinquishment or cancellation of the licence or lease, the 
Central Government or the State Government as the case may be, shall proceed 
with the removal and disposal of such petroleum, stores, equipments tools, 
machinery and restore the area at the risk and cost of the licensee or lessee.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The net proceeds of 
such sale shall be held by the Central Government, or the State Government, as 
the case may be, until applied for and obtained by the licensee or the lessee.]
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Fees, etc., payable 
by due date.—
<section><number>1</number> 
All licence fees, lease fees, royalties and other payments under these rules 
shall, if not paid to 

1[the Central 
Government or the State Government, as the case may be] within the time 
specified for such payment, be increased by 

2[a penal rate of 
200 (two hundred) basis points over the prime lending rate of State Bank of 
India for the delayed period.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to these 
rules, if any licence fee, lease fee, royalty or other payment due in respect of 
a licence or a lease is in arrears for more than three months, 

3[the Central 
Government or, as the case may be, the State Government with the prior approval 
of the Central Government, may] cancel such licence or lease and such 
cancellation shall be published in the Official Gazette and shall take affect 
from the date of such publication.
 
 





</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>24</number> Preservation of 
cores and samples for examination, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every licensee or lessee shall—
 <subsection>
        
<number>a</number>  so far as is reasonably practicable collect, label and preserve for 
reference for a period of at least twelve months all bore‑cores and 
characteristic samples of the strata encountered in any bore‑hole on the 

1[area] covered by 
the licence or the lease and samples of any petroleum or water discovered in any 
bore‑hole on such 

1[area], and
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>b</number>  furnish to the Central Government detailed reports of all examinations 
made of such cores and samples.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Cores and samples 
preserved as aforesaid shall at all times be made available for examination to 
the agent authorised by the Central Government and may be taken for the purpose 
of analysis or other examination but no information obtained as a result of such 
analysis or examination shall be published without the consent of the licensee 
or the lessee unless the Central Government sees fit to direct otherwise.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Directions to 
prevent waste.—The 
lessee shall comply with such directions as the Central Government, 

1[where the lease 
has been granted by that Government or where the lease has been granted by the 
State Government, as the Central Government, or the State Government, with the 
prior consent of the Central Government] may issue restricting the use of 
petroleum or 

2[oil or gas or 
coal bed methane or gas hydrate] for any purpose which the Central Government or 
the State Government may consider to be uneconomical or conductive to waste.
 
 




</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Spacing of wells.—The 
Central Government may issue instructions for—
 <section>
        
<number>a</number>  the spacing of oil wells; and
 </section><section>
        
<number>b</number>  the spacing of gas wells:
 
Provided that no such well 
shall be drilled at any point, within a minimum distance, to be prescribed by 
the Central Government, of any railway, pipeline or other right of way, surveyed 
road, dwellings, industrial plant, air‑craft runway, buildings used for military 
or public purposes, or within 

1[three kilometres] 
of any mine, whether active or abandoned, unless the special permission of the 
Central Government is obtained in advance.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Restriction of 
production.—The
Central Government may in the interests of conservation of mineral oils by 
general or special order, restrict the amount of petroleum or 

1[or oil or gas or 
coal bed methane or gas from gas hydrate] that may be produced by a lessee in a 
particular field.
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Regulation of 
operations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may by notification in the Official Gazette prescribe 
conditions to regulate the conduct of operations by a lessee 

1[or licensee] in a 
field or area where it has reason to believe that the petroleum deposit extends 
beyond the boundary of the leased 

1[or licenced] area 
into areas worked by other lessees 

1[or licensee or 
into areas not covered by any licence or lease] and may require the lessee


1[or licensee] to 
undertake any operation or prohibit any operation or permit it to be undertaken 
subject to such conditions as it may deem fit.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any order under rule 
27 or notification issued by the Central Government under sub‑rule (1) of this 
rule shall be deemed to be a condition of the lease.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>29</number> Control of 
operations to prevent escape of petroleum or access of water.—The 
Central Government may after reasonable notice to the lessee,—
 <section>
        
<number>a</number>  assume control of the operation of an oil well or gas well and adopt 
such means as may appear to it necessary or expedient to prevent the escape of 
petroleum or water from the well, if the lessee fails to do so appears unable to 
do so;
 </section><section>
        
<number>b</number>  assume control of the operation of an oil well or gas well and adopt 
such means as may appear to it necessary or expedient to prevent the access of 
water to such well or to the petroleum bearing or 

1[oil bearing or to 
both or gas bearing or coal bed methane bearing or gas hydrate being strata;]
 </section><section>
        
<number>c</number>  for the above purpose appoint such agents as may be deemed necessary 
and authorise them to enter upon the premises and perform the work and for this 
purpose to take possession of and use any drilling rig, derrick, tools, 
machinery, and other appliances or materials necessary for the performance of 
the work which may be upon the location or which may be in the possession or 
control of the lessee; and
 </section><section>
        
<number>d</number>  recover from the lessee all the costs and expenses incurred in the 
performance of the operations so undertaken by the Central Government.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>30</number> Suspension, etc., 
of operations.—No
licensee or lessee shall—
 <section>
         
<number>i</number>  suspend normal drilling;
 </section><section>
        
<number>ii</number>  suspend normal producing operations;
 </section><section>
        
<number>iii</number>  abandon an oil well or gas well;
 </section><section>
       
<number>iv</number>  re‑condition such a well;
 </section><section>
        
<number>v</number>  resume drilling operations after a previous completion, suspension or 
abandonment of such a well; or
 </section><section>
       
<number>vi</number>  resume producing operations after a previous suspension by giving to 
the Central Government at least a fortnight’s notice of any or all of the 
aforesaid actions, provided that, if normal drilling or normal producing 
operations have to be suspended immediately due to any unforeseen reason, notice 
thereof shall be given to the Central Government within twenty four hours of 
such suspension 

1[under intimation 
to the State Government.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>31</number> Shutting down of 
wells.—
<section><number>1</number>
If the Central Government is satisfied after holding an enquiry that an oil 
well or gas well is being operated in such a way that any provision of these 
rules or any order of the Central Government pursuant to these rules has been or 
is being contravened, the Central Government may order that, on and after a date 
to be fixed by the order, no production is to be permitted from the well and 
that it is to be shut down and kept shut down until such time as the Central 
Government may specify.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If, the opinion of the 
Central Government, waste, damage to property, or pollution can thereby be 
prevented, the Central Government may order the well to be shut down pending an 
enquiry under sub‑rule (1), which enquiry shall be held within fifteen days of 
the making of such order.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>32</number> Agency for 
supervision.—
<section><number>1</number> 
For the purpose of ascertaining whether the provisions contained in rules 24 to 
28 and 30 and any orders, instructions and directions issued thereunder have 
been or are being, complied with by the licensee or the lessee and whether the 
prospecting or mining operations are being carried on by him in accordance with 
these rules, the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, constitute a suitable agency consisting of such number of persons as 
the Central Government thinks fit.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It shall be the duty 
of such agency for the purposes aforesaid to supervise from time to time any oil 
well or gas well or any drilled hole or information well in the process of 
drilling and submit its report to the Central Government accordingly.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The agency may, in 
order to carry out its functions under these rules, depute any person authorised 
by it in this behalf to enter into and inspect an oil well or gas well, or any 
drilled hole or information well in the process of drilling.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>32A</number> Penalties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If the holder of a Petroleum Exploration Licence or Mining Lease or his 
transferee or assignee fails, without sufficient cause, to furnish the 
information or returns or acts in any manner in contravention of sub‑rule (2) of 
rule 14, rule 19 

2[rule 21] and rule 
24, or to allow any authorised person as provided in rule 32 to enter into and 
inspect any oil well or gas well or any drilled hole or information well in the 
process of drilling, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which 
may extend to six months or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees or 
with both.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Whoever, after having 
been convicted of any offence referred to in sub‑rule (1), continues to commit 
such offence shall be punishable for each day after the date of the first 
conviction during which he continues so to offend, with fine which may extend to 
one hundred rupees.]
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>33</number> Arbitration 
of disputes.—Every 
licence or lease shall be subject to the following term, namely:—
 
Any dispute [including


1[***] a dispute 
regarding the market price referred to in rule 18] between the Government and 
the licensee or the lessee regarding—
 <section>
        
<number>a</number>  any right claimed by the licensee or the lessee under the licence or 
the lease, or
 </section><section>
        
<number>b</number>  any breach alleged to have been committed by the licensee or the 
lessee of any of the terms, covenants or conditions of the licence or the lease, 
or any penalty proposed to be inflicted therefor, or
 </section><section>
        
<number>c</number>  the fees, royalty or rents payable under the licence or the lease, or
 </section><section>
        
<number>d</number>  any other matter or thing connected with the licence or the lease,
 

2[shall be settled 
through arbitration and conciliation proceedings under the provisions of the 
Arbitration and Conciliation Act, 1996 and the rules made thereunder as are 
applicable to such proceedings.]
 

3[The arbitrators 
or the umpires, as the case may be, may, from time to time, with the consent of 
all the parties to the contract, enlarge the time, for making the award, subject 
as aforesaid, the provisions of the Arbitration Act, 1940, and the rules 
thereunder for the time being in force shall apply to the arbitration 
proceedings under this clause.]
 
 





</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>34</number> Saving of existing 
licences and leases.—Notwithstanding 
the supersession of Petroleum Concession Rules, 1949, all licences and leases 
granted thereunder, which are still in force on the commencement of these rules, 
shall 

1[subject to the 
provisions contained in sub‑rule 1 
<section><number>a</number> of rule 141] continue to be in force and 
such supersession shall not affect—
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  any right, privilege, obligation or liability acquired, accrued or 
incurred under the said Petroleum Concession Rules, 1949, or
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  any penalty, forfeiture or punishment incurred in respect of any 
contravention of the provisions of the said Petroleum Concession Rules, 1949, or 
the said licences and leases:
 

2[Provided that any 
such licence or lease may be modified by mutual agreement between the Central 
Government and the licensee or the lessee where such licence or lease has been 
granted by the Central Government, or between the State Government and the 
licensee or the lessee, with the approval of the Central Government, where such 
licence or lease has been granted by the State Government.]
 
 




</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article>1[<number>35</number> Power to exempt from 
operation of certain rules.—
<section><number>i</number> The Central Government may grant exemption 
under section 12 of the said Act, subject to specified conditions to a licensee 
or lessee from the provisions of rule 6(i) and (ii), rule 11, sub-rules (1) and 
(2) of rule 13, where it is in the public interest to do so.
 </section><section><number>ii</number> The Central Government, may 
consult the State Government in the matter of granting exemptions in respect of 
onland areas under sub-rule (i).]
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>