<act><tid>852644</tid>
<title>THE GOVERNMENT TRADING TAXATION ACT, <year>1926</year></title>

ACT NO. 3 OF <year>1926</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 24th February, <year>1926</year>.]

An Act to determine the liability of certain Governments to taxation 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> in respect of trading operations.

WHEREAS it is expedient to determine the liability to taxation 
for the time being in forcs <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> of the Government of any part of His 
Majesty' s Dominions, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> in respect of any trade or business 
carried on by or on behalf of such Government;

It is hereby enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>593717</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1743348</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Government Trading Taxation Act, <year>1926</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1152293</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>811177</tid>
<number> 2</number> Liability of certain Governments to taxation in respect of 
trading operations.
<section><tid>871508</tid>
<number>1</number>Where a trade or business of any kind is  
carried on by or on behalf of the Government of any part of His 
Majesty' s Dominions, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> that Government shall, in respect of the 
trade or business and of all operations connected therewith, all 
property occupied in <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> India] and all goods owned in <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> India] for 
the purposes thereof, and all income arising in connection therewith, 
be liable-

<subsection><tid>1182724</tid>
<number>a</number>to taxation under the Indian Income- tax Act, <year>1922</year>, (11  
  of <year>1922</year>) in the same manner and to the same extent as 
in the like case a company would be liable;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1596081</tid>
<number>b</number>to all other taxation for the time being in force in 
 <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> India] in the same manner as in the like case any 
other person would be liable.
<footcitenum>7</footcitenum>


<pagefootnote><pagenum>14</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>999999</number> Extended to Dadra and Nagar Haveli, Goa, Daman and Diu, and 
Pondicherry (w. e. f. 1. 4. <year>1963</year>)- by Reg. 3 of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 (1) and Sch.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>1</number>The Act has been extended to the whole of India except the State 
of Jammu and Kashmir by the Opium and Revenue Laws (Extension  
  of Application) Act, <year>1950</year> (33 of <year>1950</year>), s. 2. This Act has also 
been extended to the State of Jammu and Kashmir by the Taxation 
Laws (Extension to Jammu and Kashmir) Act, <year>1954</year> (41 of <year>1954</year>), s. 2. 
2. The words" in the Provinces of India" omitted by the A. O. <year>1950</year>. 
3. The words" exclusive of India" omitted, ibid. 
4. The words" or the Government of any Acceding State or other 
Indian State" omitted by Act 33 of <year>1950</year>, s. 2 and Sch. 
5. Ist April, <year>1926</year>; see Gazette of India, Extraordinary, <year>1926</year>, p. 
60. 
6. Subs, by Act 33 of <year>1950</year>, s. 2 and Sch. for" Part A States and 
Part C States". 
7. Sub- section (1A) ins. by the A. O. <year>1948</year> omitted by Act 33 of 
<year>1950</year>, s. 2 and Sch.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1614638</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes of the levy and collection of income- tax 
under the Indian Income- tax Act, <year>1922</year> (11 of <year>1922</year>), in accordance with 
the provisions of sub- section (1), any Government to which that sub- 
section applies shall be deemed to be a company within the meaning of 
that Act, and the provisions of that Act shall apply accordingly.

</section>

<section><tid>35441</tid>
<number>3</number>In this section the expression" His Majesty' s Dominions" 
includes any territory which is under His Majesty' s protection or in 
respect of which a mandate is being exercised by the Government of any 
part of His Majesty' s Dominions <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>361810</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Application of the Act to existing liability of Acceding or 
other Indian States. Where any Acceding State or other Indian State 
was liable for any tax under this Act in respect of any period before 
the 26th day of January, <year>1950</year>, and such liability has, after that 
date, devolved <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> upon a Part B State], the provisions of section 2 
shall apply in relation to that Part B State as they applied in 
relation to the corresponding Acceding State or other Indian State.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>15</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words' and" India" means the territory of India excluding the 
State of Jammu and Kashmir' ins by Act 33 of <year>1950</year>, s. 2 and Sch. 
omitted by Act 41 of <year>1954</year>, s. 2 and Sch. 
2. Ins. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>. 
3. Subs. by Act 33 of <year>1950</year>, s. 2 and Sch., for" upon an Acceding 
State or other Indian State".

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>