<act><tid>853406</tid>
<title>THE ALLIANZ UND STUTTGARTER LIFE INSURANCE BANK (TRANSFER) ACT, <year>1950</year></title>

ACT NO. 62 OF <year>1950</year>
[ 1st December, <year>1950</year>.]

An Act to provide for the transfer of the business of the Allianz 
Und Stuttgarter Life Insurance Bank, Limited, to the United India Life 
Assurance Company, Limited, and for matters connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament as follows:-





<article><tid>1801102</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>392143</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Allianz Und Stuttgarter Life Insurance Bank (Transfer) Act, <year>1950</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1284850</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 1st day 
of September, <year>1950</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>513917</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>635775</tid>
<number>a</number>" the Act" means the Insurance Act, <year>1938</year> (4 of  
  <year>1938</year>.);

</section>

<section><tid>266927</tid>
<number>b</number>" transferee company" means the United India Life 
Assurance Company, Limited, having its registered office in 
Madras;

</section>

<section><tid>313116</tid>
<number>c</number>" transferor company" means the Allianz Und Stuttgarter 
Life Insurance Bank, Limited.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>905543</tid>
<number>3</number>Transfer of assets and liabilities of the transferor company to 
the transferee company. All the assets and liabilities of the 
transferor company which relate to or arise out of the life insurance 
business of the transferor company carried on immediately before the 
commencement of this Act by Messrs. A. F. Ferguson and Company, 
Chartered Accountants of Bombay, under the Defence of India Rules 
shall, by virtue of this Act, stand transferred to and vest in the 
transferee company, subject to the provisions of this Act and to the 
terms and conditions specified in the First Schedule.


</article>



<article><tid>1339779</tid>
<number> 4</number> Effect of transfer of assets and liabilities to transferee 
company.
<section><tid>1151707</tid>
<number>1</number>Every contract of life insurance, entered into between the  
transferor company and the holder of any life policy before the com- 
mencement of this Act, shall have effect as from such commencement 
as if the transferee company had been a party to the contract instead 
of the transferor company, and for any reference (however worded and  
  whether express or implied) to the transferor company there were 
substituted as respects anything falling to be done on or after such

<pagefootnote><pagenum>10</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

commencement, a reference to the transferee company, and with such 
other modifications as may be necessary to transfer rights, 
liabilities and obligations under the contract so far as unperformed, 
from the transferor company to the transferee company:

Provided that no provision in any such contract for the payment 
of any bonus, profit, interest or dividend on any life policy shall 
have effect against the transferee company except on the basis of an 
actuarial valuation of the business of the transferor company made 
after the commencement of this Act and to the extent, if any, that may 
be recommended by the actuary.


</section>

<section><tid>1653699</tid>
<number>2</number>For the removal of doubts it is hereby declared that 
notwithstanding any decision or rule of law to the contrary, no 
contract of life insurance as is referred to in sub- section (1) shall 
be deemed to have been dissolved merely by reason of the declaration 
that war had broken out between the Government of the United Kingdom 
and Germany.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>897668</tid>
<number> 5</number> Cessation of payment of commission to past insurance agents.
<section><tid>656707</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in the Act or in 
any other law for the time being in force or in any contract, all 
contracts of agency entered into before the 31st day of July, <year>1942</year>, 
between an insurance agent, a special agent or a chief agent (by what-  
  ever name called) and the transferor company, and any appointment made 
before the said date whereby remuneration is payable to any person in 
the form of commission or bonus, shall be deemed to have been 
terminated with effect from the said date and no commission or bonus 
due to such agent or person, whether on renewal premiums or otherwise, 
shall be payable to him in respect of any life policies procured by or 
through him before the said date.

</section>

<section><tid>28324</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any 
law for the time being in force, no compensation shall be payable to 
any person for the termination, in pursuance of this section, of any 
contract of agency or other appointment.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1925194</tid>
<number> 6</number> Provision for facilitating transfer. The Central Government may, 
by order notified in the Official Gazette, make such incidental, 
supplementary or consequential provisions as, in its opinion, are 
necessary to secure that the transfer of the assets and liabilities of 
the transferor company to the transferee company are fully and 
effectively carried out, and in particular and, without prejudice to 
the generality of such power, provision may be made by order notified 
in the Official Gazette-
<section><tid>1489213</tid>
<number>a</number>for adapting the terms of contracts entered into 
between the transferor company and any other person before 
the commencement of this Act, so as to conform to the changes

<pagefootnote><pagenum>11</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Consequent on the passing of this Act in the circumstances in 
which the contracts will fall to be performed after such 
commencement;


</section>

<section><tid>363616</tid>
<number>b</number>for requiring any person concerned with the keeping of 
the register of the holders of any securities or investments 
now transferred to the transferee company, to forthwith 
register the transferee company therein and to issue to the 
transferee company the appropriate documents of title 
relating to the securities or investments transferred to it;

</section>

<section><tid>884126</tid>
<number>c</number>for the continuation by or against the transferee 
company of any legal proceedings pending by or against the 
transferor company.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1092532</tid>
<number> 7</number> Power to give directions.
<section><tid>1316240</tid>
<number>1</number>If any difficulty arises in giving  
effect to the Provisions of this Act, the Controller of Insurance may, 
with the approval of the Central Government, give such directions to 
the transferee company as he may consider necessary and the transferee 
company shall be bound to comply with such directions.

</section>

<section><tid>164551</tid>
<number>2</number>If the transferee company fails to comply with any direction 
given to it under sub- section (1) it shall be deemed to have committed 
an offence punishable under section 102 of the Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1298619</tid>
<number> 8</number> Repeals.
<section><tid>1679115</tid>
<number>1</number>The Allianz Und Stuttgarter Life Insurance Bank  
 (Transfer) Ordinance, <year>1950</year>, (24 of <year>1950</year>.) is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>439512</tid>
<number>2</number>The notifications specified in the Second Schedule shall 
cease to have effect on the commencement of this Act, except as 
respects things done or omitted to be done before such commencement.


</section>

</article>



 </act>