<act><tid>854063</tid>
<title>THE BENGAL, AGRA AND ASSAM CIVIL COURTS ACT, <year>1887</year></title>

ACT NO. 12 OF <year>1887</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> AN ACT TO CONSOLIDATE AND AMEND THE LAW RELATING TO CI 
VIL COURTSIN BENGAL
[ 11th March, <year>1887</year>.]

WHEREAS it is expedient to consolidate and amend the law relating 
to Civil Courts in Bengal, the North- Western Provinces and Assam; It 
is hereby enacted as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1779809</tid>
<number> 1</number> Title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1437418</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called  
the Bengal, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Agra] and Assam Civil Courts Act, <year>1887</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>179547</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the territories <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> which were on the 11th 
March, <year>1887</year>,] respectively administered by the Lieutenant- Governor of 
Bengal, the Lieutenant- Governor of the North- Western Provinces and the 
Chief Commissioner of Assam, except such portions of those territories 
as for the time being are not subject to the ordinary civil 
jurisdiction of the High Courts <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>; and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>72</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been declared by notification under the Scheduled 
Districts Act, <year>1874</year> (14 of <year>1874</year>), s. 3, to be in force in the 
following Scheduled Districts namely:- the districts of Hazaribagh, 
Ranchi, Palamau and Manbhum, and Parganas Dhalbhum, the Chaibbassa 
Municipality, and the Porahat Estate in the district of Singhbhum in 
the Chota Nagpur Division. It has also been declared in force in the 
Angul District by the Angul Laws Regulation <year>1936</year> (5 of <year>1936</year>), s. 3 and 
Sch.

It is in force in the Sonthal Parganas for certain purposes; see 
the Sonthal Parganas Justice Regulation, <year>1893</year> (5 of <year>1893</year>).

It has been extended to. the Sambalpur district by the Sambalpur 
Civil Courts Act, <year>1906</year> (Ben. 4 of <year>1906</year>); to the areas transferred to 
the Province of Orissa from the Madras Presidency and the Central 
Provinces by the Orissa Laws Regulation, <year>1936</year> (1 of <year>1936</year>), s. 4; and 
to the District of Koraput and certain areas of the Ganjam Agency, by 
the Koraput and Ganjam Agency Repealing and Extension of Laws 
Regulation, <year>1951</year> (Orissa Regu. 5 of <year>1951</year>).

It has been amended in its application to-

West Bengal, by Ben. Act 19 of <year>1935</year> and West Ben. Act 59 
of <year>1950</year>; West Bengal Act 16 of <year>1956</year>.

Bihar and Orissa, by B. and O. Act 4 of <year>1922</year>;


Agra, by U. P. Acts 5 of <year>1925</year> and 4 of <year>1936</year>; and

Assam, by Assam Act 6 of <year>1935</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 16 of <year>1911</year>, s. 2, for" North- Western Provinces".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for" for the time being".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>The words" and except the Jhansi Division" rep. by Act 20 of 
<year>1890</year>, s. 9.

Amended in Bihar by Bihar Act 12 of <year>1960</year>.

Amended in Assam by Assam Act 17 of <year>1974</year>.

Amended in West Bengal by W. B. Act 26 of <year>1969</year>.

Amended in Uttar Pradesh by U. P. Act 14 of <year>1970</year>.

Amended in Uttar Pradesh by U. P. Act 57 of <year>1976</year>.

Amended in West Bengal by W. B. Acts 55 and 58 of <year>1978</year>.

Amended in Assam by Assam Act 1 of <year>1979</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>342083</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on the first day of July, <year>1887</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>447119</tid>
<number> 2</number> Repeal. <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1756350</tid>
<number>2</number>All Courts constituted, appointments, nominations, 
rules and orders made, jurisdiction and powers conferred and lists 
published under the Bengal Civil Courts Act, <year>1871</year>, (6 of <year>1871</year>) 2, or any 
enactment thereby repealed, or purporting expressly or impliedly to 
have been so constituted, made, conferred and published, shall be 
deemed to have been respectively constituted, made, conferred and 
published under this Act; and

</section>

<section><tid>1679564</tid>
<number>3</number>Any enactment or document referring to the Bengal Civil 
Courts Act, <year>1871</year>, (6 of <year>1871</year>) 2, or to any enactment thereby repealed, 
shall be construed to refer to this Act or to the corresponding 
portion thereof.
CHAP

CONSTITUTION OF CIVIL COURTS

CHAPTER II

CONSTITUTION OF CIVIL COURTS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1504752</tid>
<number> 3</number> Classes of Courts. There shall be the following classes of 
Civil Courts under this Act, namely--
<section><tid>1610768</tid>
<number>1</number>the Court of the District Judge;

</section>

<section><tid>934087</tid>
<number>2</number>the Court of the Additional Judge;

</section>

<section><tid>533623</tid>
<number>3</number>the Court of the Subordinate Judge; and

</section>

<section><tid>233131</tid>
<number>4</number>the Court of the Munsif.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1791015</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Number of District Judges, subordinate Judges and Munsifs. 
The State Government may alter the number of District Judges, 
Subordinate Judges and Munsifs now fixed.]


</article>



<article><tid>55182</tid>
<number>5</number>[ Number of Munsifs.] Rep. by the Decentralization Act, <year>1914</year> 
 (4 of <year>1914</year>), s. 2 and Sch., Part I.


</article>



<article><tid>1764690</tid>
<number> 6</number> Vacancies among Districts or Subordinate Judges.
<section><tid>1667512</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Whenever the office of District Judge or Subordinate Judge is vacant 
by reason of the death, resignation or removal of

<pagefootnote><pagenum>73</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Sub- section (1) and the word" But" at the beginning of sub- 
section (2) were rep. by Act 12 of <year>1891</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Act 6 of <year>1871</year> was rep. by s. 2 (1) of this Act.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by the Devolution Act, <year>1920</year> (38 of <year>1920</year>), s. 2 and Sch. 
I, for the original section.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

the Judge or other cause, or whenever <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> an increase in the number of 
District or Subordinate Judges has been made under the provisions of 
section 4], the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> State Government or, as the case may be, the High 
Court] may fill up the vacancy or appoint the Additional District 
Judges or Subordinate Judges <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>.


</section>

<section><tid>743473</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing in this section shall be construed to prevent a 
State Government from appointing a District Judge or Subordinate Judge 
to discharge, for such period as it thinks fit, in addition to the 
functions devolving on him as such District Judge or Subordinate 
Judge, all or any of the functions of another District Judge or 
Subordinate Judge, as the case may be.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1614132</tid>
<number>7</number>[ Vacancies among Munsifs.] Rep. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>745668</tid>
<number> 8</number> Additional Judges.
<section><tid>471178</tid>
<number>1</number>When the business pending before any  
District Judge requires the aid of Additional Judges for its speedy 
disposal, the State Government may, <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> having consulted the High Court 
 <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> appoint such Additional Judges as may be requisite.

</section>

<section><tid>164166</tid>
<number>2</number>Additional Judges so appointed shall discharge any of the 
functions of a District Judge which the District Judge may assign to 
them, and, in the discharge of those functions, they shall exercise 
the same powers as the District Judge.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>98538</tid>
<number>9</number>Administrative Control of Courts. Subject to the 
superintendence of the High Court, the District Judge shall have 
administrative control over all the Civil Courts under this Act within 
the local limits of his jurisdiction.


</article>



<article><tid>496633</tid>
<number> 10</number> Temporary charge of district Court.
<section><tid>1274750</tid>
<number>1</number>In the event of the  
death, resignation or removal of the District Judge, or of his being 
incapacitated by illness or otherwise for the performance of his 
duties, or of his absence from the place at which his Court is held, 
the Additional Judge, or, if an Additional Judge is not present at 
that place, the senior Subordinate Judge present thereat, shall, 
without relinquishing his ordinary duties, assume charge of the office 
of the District Judge, and shall, continue in charge thereof until the 
office is resumed by the District Judge or assumed by an officer 
appointed thereto.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>74</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 38 of <year>1920</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I, for" the G. G. in 
C. has sanctioned an increase of the number of District Judges or 
Subordinate Judges".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for" L. G.".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>The words" as the case may be" were rep., ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs., ibid., for" upon the recommendation of".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>The words" and with the previous sanction of the G. G. in C." 
were rep. by Act 16 of <year>1911</year>, s. 3,





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>104841</tid>
<number>2</number>While in charge of the office of the District Judge, the Addi- 
tional Judge or Subordinate Judge, as the case may be, may, subject 
to any rules which the High Court may make in this behalf, exercise 
any of the powers of the District Judge.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1114235</tid>
<number> 11</number> Transfer of proceedings on vacation of office of Subordinate 
Judge.
<section><tid>794018</tid>
<number>1</number>In the event of the death, resignation or removal of a 
Subordinate Judge, or of his being incapacitated by illness or other- 
wise for the performance of his duties, or of his absence from the 
place at which his Court is held, the District Judge may transfer all 
or any of the proceedings pending in the Court of the Subordinate 
Judge either to his own Court or to any Court under his administrative 
control competent to dispose of them.

</section>

<section><tid>1258393</tid>
<number>2</number>Proceedings transferred under sub- section (1) shall be 
disposed of as if they had been instituted in the Court to which they 
are so transferred:

</section>

<section><tid>1353332</tid>
<number>3</number>Provided that the District Judge may re- transfer to the Court 
of the Subordinate Judge or his successor any proceedings transferred 
under sub- section (1) to his own or any other Court.

</section>

<section><tid>420100</tid>
<number>4</number>For the purposes of proceedings which are not pending in the 
Court of the Subordinate Judge on the occurrence of an event referred 
to in sub- section (1), and with respect to which that Court has exclu- 
sive jurisdiction, the District Judge may exercise all or any of the 
jurisdiction of that Court.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1935189</tid>
<number>12</number>[ Temporary charge of office of Munsif.] Rep. by the A. O. 
<year>1937</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1090911</tid>
<number> 13</number> Power to fix local limits of jurisdiction of Courts.
<section><tid>1077340</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, fix and 
alter the local limits of the jurisdiction of any Civil Court under 
this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1674368</tid>
<number>2</number>If the same local jurisdiction is assigned to two or more 
Subordinate Judges or to two or more Munsifs, the District Judge may 
assign to each of them such civil business cognizable by the Sub- 
ordinate Judge or Munsif, as the case may be, as, subject to any 
general or special orders of the High Court, he thinks fit.

</section>

<section><tid>668483</tid>
<number>3</number>When civil business arising in any local area is assigned by 
the District Judge under sub- section (2) to one of two or more Sub- 
ordinate Judges, or to one of two or more Munsifs, a decree or order 
passed by the Subordinate Judge or Munsif shall not be invalid by 
reason only of the case in which it was made having arisen wholly or 
in part in a place beyond the local area if that place is within the 
local limits fixed by the State Government under sub- section (1).

<pagefootnote><pagenum>75</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>163692</tid>
<number>4</number>A Judge of a Court of Small Causes appointed to be also a 
Subordinate Judge or Munsif is a Subordinate Judge or Munsif, as the 
case may be, within the meaning of this section.

</section>

<section><tid>693395</tid>
<number>5</number>The present local limits of the jurisdiction of every Civil 
Court under this Act shall be deemed to have been fixed under this 
section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1038358</tid>
<number> 14</number> Place of sitting of Courts.
<section><tid>452858</tid>
<number>1</number>The State Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, fix and alter the place or 
places at which any Civil Court under this Act is to be held.

</section>

<section><tid>308195</tid>
<number>2</number>All places at which any such Courts are now held shall be 
deemed to have been fixed under this section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>563774</tid>
<number> 15</number> Vacations of Courts.
<section><tid>1343397</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to such orders as may be made  
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> by the State Government <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>] the High Court shall 
prepare a list of days to be observed in each year as close holidays 
in the Civil Courts.

</section>

<section><tid>805963</tid>
<number>2</number>The list shall be published in the Official Gazette.

</section>

<section><tid>1816125</tid>
<number>3</number>A judicial act done by a Civil Court on a day specified in 
the list shall not be invalid by reason only of its having been done 
on that day.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>29629</tid>
<number>16</number>Seals of Courts. Every Civil Court under this Act shall use 
a seal of such form and dimensions as are prescribed by the State 
Government.


</article>



<article><tid>1368851</tid>
<number> 17</number> Continuance of proceeding of Courts ceasing to have 
jurisdiction.
<section><tid>1192752</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any Civil Court under this Act has from any  
cause ceased to have jurisdiction with respect to any case, any 
proceeding in relation to that case which, if that Court had not 
ceased to have jurisdiction, might have been had therein may be had in 
the Court to which the business of the former Court has been 
transferred.

</section>

<section><tid>1260304</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing in this section applies to cases for which provision 
is made in section 623 or section 649 of the Code of Civil Procedure 4 
 (14 of <year>1882</year>), or in any other enactment for the time being in 
force.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>76</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" by the G. G. in C., in the case of the High Court 
at Calcutta, and" were rep. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The words" in the case of the High Court at Calcutta, and by 
the Local Government in other cases," had been ins. by Act 38 of <year>1920</year>, 
s. 2 and Sch. I.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>The words" in other cases" were rep. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>In Bengal and Assam, for the words and figures" in s. 623 
or s. 649 of the Code of Civil Procedure" the words and figures" in 
ss. 36, 37 and 114 of, and rule 1 of Order XLVII in Sch. I to, the 
Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year>," have been subs. by Bengal Act 19 of 
<year>1935</year> and Assam Act 6 of <year>1935</year>, respectively. In Agra, Bihar and 
Orissa, also, the reference to the old enactment should be construed 
in the same way; see the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (Act 5 of <year>1908</year>) 
S. 158.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


CHAP

ORDINARY JURISDICTION

CHAPTER III

ORDINARY JURISDICTION




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1852882</tid>
<number>18</number>Extent of original jurisdiction of District or Subordinate 
Judge. Save as otherwise provided by any enactment for the time being 
in force, the jurisdiction of a District Judge or Subordinate Judge 
extends, subject to the provisions of section 15 of the Code of Civil 
Procedure 1 (14 of <year>1882</year>), to all original suits for the time being cog- 
nizable by Civil Courts.


</article>



<article><tid>1942591</tid>
<number> 19</number> Extent of jurisdiction of Munsif.
<section><tid>1071665</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as aforesaid,  
and subject to the provisions of sub- section (2), the jurisdiction of a 
Munsif extends to all like suits of which the value does not exceed 
one thousand rupees.

</section>

<section><tid>1954217</tid>
<number>2</number>The State Government may, on the recommendation of the High 
Court, direct, by notification in the Official Gazette, with respect 
to any Munsif named therein, that his jurisdiction shall extend to all 
like suits of such value not exceeding two thousand rupees as may be 
specified in the notification:
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Provided that the State Government may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, delegate to the High Court its powers under this 
section.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>614124</tid>
<number> 20</number> Appeals from District and Additional Judges.
<section><tid>765269</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as 
otherwise provided by any enactment for the time being in force, an 
appeal from a decree or order of a District Judge or Additional Judge 
shall lie to the High Court.

</section>

<section><tid>4066</tid>
<number>2</number>An appeal shall not lie to the High Court from a decree or 
order of an Additional Judge in any case in which, if the decree or 
order had been made by the District Judge, an appeal would not lie to 
that Court.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1854719</tid>
<number> 21</number> Appels from Subordinate Judges and Munsifs.
<section><tid>1143060</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as  
aforesaid, an appeal from a decree or order of a Subordinate Judge 
shall lie-

<subsection><tid>125167</tid>
<number>a</number>to the District Judge where the value of the original 
suit in which or in any proceeding arising out of which the 
decree or order was made did not exceed five thousand rupees, 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1844555</tid>
<number>b</number>to the High Court in any other case.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>77</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>In Bengal and Assam, the figures", <year>1908</year>," have been ins. at 
this place by Bengal Act 19 of <year>1935</year> and Assam Act 6 of <year>1935</year>, 
respectively. In Agra, Bihar and Orissa, also, the reference to the 
old enactment should be construed in the same way: see the Code of 
Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (Act 5 of <year>1908</year>), s. 158.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>S. 19 does not apply to Honorary Munsifs and Benches in the U. 
P.; see the U. P. Honorary Munsifs Act, <year>1896</year> (U. P. 2 of <year>1896</year>), s. 
13. This section has been diversely amended in Bengal, Bihar and 
Orissa, Agra and Assam by Ben. Act 19 of <year>1935</year>, s. 5, B. and O. Act 4 of 
<year>1922</year>, s. 2, U. P. Act 5 of <year>1925</year>, ss. 2 and 3, and Assam Act 6 of <year>1935</year>, 
s. 5, respectively.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by Act 4 of <year>1914</year>, s. 2 and Sch., Pt. I



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>567829</tid>
<number>2</number>Save as aforesaid, an appeal from a decree or order of a 
Munsif shall lie to the District Judge.

</section>

<section><tid>1944054</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the function of receiving any appeals which lie to the 
District Judge under sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) has been 
assigned to an Additional Judge, the appeals may be preferred to the 
Additional Judge.

</section>

<section><tid>1488665</tid>
<number>4</number>The High Court may, with the previous sanction of the State 
Government, direct, by notification in the Official Gazette, that 
appeals lying to the District Judge under sub- section (2) from all or 
any of the decrees or orders of any Munsif shall be preferred to the 
Court of such Subordinate Judge as may be mentioned in the noti- 
fication, and the appeals shall thereupon be preferred accordingly.
CHAP

SPECIAL JURISDICTION

CHAPTER IV

SPECIAL JURISDICTION




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>651181</tid>
<number> 22</number> Power to transfer to Subordinate Judges appeals from 
Munsifs.
<section><tid>977483</tid>
<number>1</number>A District Judge may transfer to any Subordinate Judge 
under his administrative control any appeals pending before him from 
the decrees or orders of Munsifs.

</section>

<section><tid>1074432</tid>
<number>2</number>The District Judge may withdraw any appeal so transferred, 
and either hear and dispose of it himself or transfer it to a Court 
under his administrative control competent to dispose of it.

</section>

<section><tid>561079</tid>
<number>3</number>Appeals transferred under this section shall be disposed of 
subject to the rules applicable to like appeals when disposed of by 
the district Judge.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1435946</tid>
<number> 23</number> Exercise by Subordinate Judge or Munsif of jurisdiction of 
District Court in certain proceedings.
<section><tid>1902667</tid>
<number>1</number>The High Court may, by 
general or special order, authorize any Subordinate Judge or Munsif to 
take cognizance of, or any District Judge to transfer to a Subordinate 
Judge or Munsif under his administrative control, any of the 
proceedings next hereinafter mentioned or any class of those 
proceedings specified in the order.

</section>

<section><tid>101480</tid>
<number>2</number>The proceedings referred to in sub- section (1) are the 
following, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1189279</tid>
<number>a</number>proceedings under Bengal Regulation 5, 1799 (to limit  
the Interference of the Zillah and City Courts of Dewanny

<pagefootnote><pagenum>78</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>S. 23 does not apply to Honorary Munsifs and Benches in the U. 
P.; see the U. P. Honorary Munsifs Act, <year>1896</year> (U. P. 2 of <year>1896</year>), s. 
13.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

Adawlut in the Execution of Wills and Administration to the 
  Estates of persons dying intestate)

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>

<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>771562</tid>
<number>d</number>proceedings under the Indian Succession Act, <year>1865</year> (10  
  of <year>1865</year>) 3, and the Probate and Administration Act, <year>1881</year> (5 of  
  <year>1881</year>) 3, which cannot be disposed of by District Delegates; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1100624</tid>
<number>e</number>references by Collectors under section 322C of the Code 
of Civil Procedure. 4 (14 of <year>1882</year>)

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>438751</tid>
<number>3</number>The District Judge may withdraw any such proceedings taken 
cognizance of by, or transferred to, a Subordinate Judge or Munsif, 
and may either himself dispose of them or transfer them to a Court 
under his administrative control competent to dispose of them.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>640128</tid>
<number> 24</number> Disposal of proceedings referred to in last foregoing 
section.
<section><tid>690665</tid>
<number>1</number>Proceedings taken cognizance of by, or transferred to, a  
Subordinate Judge or Munsif, as the case may be, under the last 
foregoing section shall be disposed of by him subject to the rules 
applicable to like proceedings when disposed of by the District Judge:
Provided that an appeal from an order of the Munsif in any such 
proceedings shall lie to the District Judge.


</section>

<section><tid>687018</tid>
<number>2</number>An appeal from the order of the District Judge on the appeal 
from the order of a munsif under this section shall lie to the High 
Court if a further appeal from the order of the District Judge is 
allowed by the law for the time being in force.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>578577</tid>
<number>25</number>Power to invest Subordinate Judges and Munsifs with Small 
Cause court jurisdiction. The State Government may, by notification in 
the Official Gazette, confer, within such local limits as it thinks 
fit, upon any Subordinate Judge or Munsif the jurisdiction of a Judge 
of a Court
<pagefootnote><pagenum>79</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Cl. (b) relating to proceedings under Act 40 of <year>1858</year> or Act 9 
of <year>1861</year> was rep. by Act 8 of <year>1890</year>, s. 2 and Sch.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Cl. (c) relating to applications for certificates under Act 27 
of <year>1860</year> was rep. by Act 7 of <year>1889</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>See now the Indian Succession Act, <year>1925</year> (39 of <year>1925</year>). In 
Bengal and Assam, this cl. has been formally amended by Ben. Act 19 
of <year>1935</year> and Assam Act 6 of <year>1935</year>, respectively.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>See now the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (Act 5 of <year>1908</year>), Sch. 
III. This cl. has been omitted in Bengal by Ben. Act 19 of <year>1935</year> and 
formally amended in Assam by Assam Act 6 of <year>1935</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Ss 24 and 25 do not apply to Honorary Munsifs and Benches in 
the U. P. see the U. P. Honorary Munsifs Act, <year>1896</year> (U. P. 2 of <year>1896</year>), 
s. 13.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


of Small Causes under the Provincial Small Cause Courts Act, <year>1887</year> 
 (9 of <year>1887</year>) for the trial of suits, cognizable by such Courts, up to 
such value not exceeding five hundred 1 rupees in the case of a Subord- 
inate Judge or <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> two hundred and fifty 1 rupees] in the case of a Mun- 
sif as it thinks fit, and may withdraw any jurisdiction so conferred:

<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Provided that the State Government may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, delegate to the High Court its powers under this 
section.]

CHAP

Misfeasance.

CHAPTER V.-[ Misfeasance.] Rep. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>.

CHAP

Ministerial Officers.

CHAPTER VI.-[ Ministerial Officers.] Rep., ibid.

CHAP

SUPPLEMENTAL PROVISIONS

CHAPTER VII

SUPPLEMENTAL PROVISIONS



</article>



<article><tid>236149</tid>
<number> 36</number> Power to confer powers of Civil Courts on officers.
<section><tid>967141</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
State Government may invest with the powers of any Civil Court under 
this Act, by name or in virtue of office,-

<subsection><tid>641262</tid>
<number>a</number>any officer in the Chutia Nagpur, <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Sambalpur,] 
Jalpaiguri or Darjeeling District, or in any part of the 
territories administered by the Chief Commissioner of Assam 
except the district of Sylhet, or,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>193264</tid>
<number>b</number>after consultation with the High Court, any officer 
serving in any other part of the territories to which this 
Act extends and belonging to a class defined in this behalf 
by the State Government <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1125082</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing in <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> sections 4, 5, 6, 8, 10 or 11] applies to any 
officer so invested, but all the other provisions of this Act shall, 
so far as
<pagefootnote><pagenum>80</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>In Bengal and Assam the limits are seven hundred and fifty and 
three hundred, respectively: see Ben. Act 19 of <year>1935</year> and Assam Act 6 
of <year>1935</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 16 of <year>1911</year>, s. 4, for" one hundred rupees".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by the Decentralization Act, <year>1914</year> (4 of <year>1914</year>), s. 2 and 
Sch., Pt. 1.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Ins. by the Sambalpur Civil Courts Act, <year>1906</year> (Ben. 4 of <year>1906</year>), 
s. 6.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>The words" with the previous sanction of the G. G. in C." were 
rep. by Act 38 of <year>1920</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I, Pt. I.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" sections 4 to 8 (both inclusive), 
or sections 10 to 12 (both inclusive), or sections 27 to 35 (both  
  inclusive)".




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


those provisions can be made applicable, apply to him as if he were a 
Judge of the Court with the powers of which he is invested.


</section>

<section><tid>195374</tid>
<number>3</number>Where, in the territories mentioned in clause (a) of sub- 
section (1), the same local jurisdiction is assigned to two or more 
officers invested with the powers of a Munsif, the officer invested 
with the powers of a District Judge may, with the previous sanction of 
the State Government, delegate his functions under sub- section (2) of 
section 13 to an officer invested with the powers of a Subordinate 
Judge or to one of the officers invested with the powers of a Munsif.

</section>

<section><tid>334619</tid>
<number>4</number>Where the place at which the Court of an officer invested 
with powers under sub- section (1) is to be held has not been fixed 
under section 14, the Court may be held at any place within the local 
limits of its jurisdiction.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>20936</tid>
<number> 37</number> Certain decisions to be according to Native law.
<section><tid>1089487</tid>
<number>1</number>Where  
in any suit or other proceeding it is necessary for a Civil Court to 
decide any question regarding succession, inheritance, marriage or 
caste, or any religious usage or institution, the Muhammadan law in 
cases where the parties are Muhammadans, and the Hindu law in cases 
where the parties are Hindus, shall form the rule of decision except 
in so far as such law has, by legislative enactment, been altered or 
abolished.

</section>

<section><tid>1933386</tid>
<number>2</number>In cases not provided for by sub- section (1) or by any other 
law for the time being in force, the Court shall act according to 
justice, equity and good conscience.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1654939</tid>
<number> 38</number> Judges not to try suits in which they are interested.
<section><tid>1686984</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The presiding officer of a Civil Court shall not try any suit or other 
proceeding to which he is a party or in which he is personally 
interested.

</section>

<section><tid>554472</tid>
<number>2</number>The presiding officer of an appellate Civil Court under this 
Act shall not try an appeal against a decree or order passed by him 
self in another capacity.

</section>

<section><tid>1287426</tid>
<number>3</number>When any such suit, proceeding or appeal as is referred to 
in sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) comes before any such officer, 
the officer shall forthwith transmit the record of the case to the 
Court to which he is immediately subordinate, with a report of the 
circumstances attending the reference.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>81</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The provisions of this section, in so far as they are 
inconsistent with the provisions of the Muslim Personal Law (Shariat) 
Application Act, <year>1937</year> (26 of <year>1937</year>), were rep. by s. 6 of that Act, but 
have been revived by s. 3 of Act 16 of <year>1943</year>.






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1203711</tid>
<number>4</number>The superior Court shall thereupon dispose of the case under 
section 25 of the Code (14 of <year>1882</year>) of Civil Procedure. 1

</section>

<section><tid>1380191</tid>
<number>5</number>Nothing in this section shall be deemed to affect the extra- 
ordinary original civil jurisdiction of the High Court.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1868194</tid>
<number>39</number>Subordination of Courts to District Court. For the purposes of 
the last foregoing section the Presiding officer of a Court subject to 
the administrative control of the District Judge shall be deemed to be 
immediately subordinate to the Court of the District Judge, and, for 
the purposes of the Code of Civil Procedure (14 of <year>1882</year>), the Court of 
such an officer shall be deemed to be of a grade inferior to that of 
the Court of the District Judge.


</article>



<article><tid>1710720</tid>
<number> 40</number> Application of Act to State Courts of Small Causes.
<section><tid>338660</tid>
<number>1</number>This  
section and sections 15, 32, 37, 38 and 39 apply to Courts of Small 
Causes constituted under the Provincial Small Cause Courts Act, 
 <year>1887</year> (9 of <year>1887</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>1635552</tid>
<number>2</number>Save as provided by that Act, the other sections of this Act 
do not apply to those Courts.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>82</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>See now s. 24 of the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (Act 5 of  
  <year>1908</year>). In Bengal and Assam, that reference has been formally subs. by 
Ben. Act 19 of <year>1935</year> and Assam Act 6 of <year>1935</year> respectively.

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>