<act><title>


    The Central Apprenticeship Council rules, 19621</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title  and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These Rules may be called the Central Apprenticeship Council Rules, 1962.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    They shall come into force at once.
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>  “Act” means the 
    Apprentices Act, 1961 (52 of 1961); 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>  “Chairman” means the 
    Chairman of the Central Apprenticeship Council; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>  “Council” means the 
    Central Apprenticeship Council established under sub-section (1) of section 
    24 of the Act; 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>  “Member” means a 
    member of the Council; 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>  “Secretary” means 
    Secretary to the Council. 
 
 
 
 
 
  


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Constitution of Council. </title>—The Council shall consist of a 
Chairman <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[and a Vice-Chairman] who shall be appointed by the Central 
Government and the following other members who shall also be appointed by the 
Central Government, namely:— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> not more than 9 representatives of employers in establishments in the 
  public sector, 
 </section><section><number>b</number> not more than 9 representatives of employers in establishments in the 
  private sector, 
 </section><section><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>c</number> not more than 18 representatives of the Central 
  Government,] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>d</number> not more than <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[22] representatives of the 
  State Governments,] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>e</number> not more than 4 persons having special knowledge and 
  experience on matters relating to industry and technical education, 
 </section><section><number>f</number> not more than 5 persons having special knowledge and experience on 
  matters relating to labour, 
 </section><section><number>g</number> two representatives of the All India Council and one representative 
  each of the Regional Boards.] </section>






</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Term of office.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The  Council shall be constituted for a period of three years and thereafter 
    it shall be reconstituted at the end of every three years. *All the members 
    appointed to it shall accordingly hold office for a period of three years: 
 

    Provided that a member  of Council shall, notwithstanding the expiry of the 
    said period of three years, continue to hold office until his successor is 
    appointed. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where a person is chosen as a member of the Council by virtue of the office 
    or appointment he holds, he shall cease to be a member if he ceases to hold 
    that office or appointment. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Cessation of membership.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A member of the Council shall cease to be a member if he dies, resigns, 
    becomes of unsound mind, is declared insolvent or is convicted of a criminal 
    offence involving moral turpitude. 
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> 
    The office of a member of the Council shall fall vacant from the date on 
    which his resignation is accepted or on the expiry of 30 days from the date 
    of receipt of letter of resignation, whichever is earlier.] 
  
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Filling of vacancies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any vacancy in the membership of the Council caused by reasons mentioned in 
    sub-rule (1) of rule 5, shall be filled by the Central Government. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    member appointed to fill a casual vacancy shall hold office for so long as 
    the member whose place he fills would have been entitled to hold office if 
    the vacancy had not occurred. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Time and place of meeting.—The 
    council shall meet as often as may be necessary and at least once a year on 
    such date, time and place as may be determined by the Chairman. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Notice of meeting.— 
The Secretary shall give a 
    notice of not less than fifteen days for a meeting of the  Council to each 
    member but a shorter notice may be given for holding an emergency meeting. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Quorum for the Council.—One-third 
    of the number of members of the Council shall constitute the quorum for any 
    meeting of the Council. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Decision by majority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    All questions to be decided by the Council shall be in accordance with the 
    opinion of the majority of the members present and voting. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Each member shall have one vote. If there is equality of votes, the Chairman 
    shall have and exercise the casting vote. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Business by circulation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Chairman may, in special circumstances, instead of convening a meeting 
    of the Council, obtain the opinion of the members on any item of business 
    individually by circulation of papers and such item shall be decided in 
    accordance with the opinion of the majority. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Proceedings of the Council.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Copies of all proceedings of the Council shall be furnished to the Secretary 
    of the National Council for Training in Vocational Trades. Any views 
    expressed or suggestions made thereon by the said National Council shall be 
    duly considered by the Council. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    all other matters, the Council shall follow such procedure as it may 
    determine. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Power to co-opt members.—The 
    Council may, at any time, invite any person to attend its meetings to give 
    advice or assist in any matter. The person to be invited shall, however, not 
    be entitled to vote on any question coming before the Council. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Committees of Council.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Council shall have the power to appoint such Standing or Special 
    Committees  for  assisting it in the discharge of its functions as may be 
    considered expedient by it.
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> 
    The functions of the Standing or Special Committees shall be determined by 
    the <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[Central Government].
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    The composition of the Standing or Special Committees shall be determined  
    by the <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[Central Government].]
  
  





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Fees and allowances to members.—The 
    Chairman and the representatives of the Central and the State Governments 
    will draw travelling and  daily allowances for attending the meetings of the 
    Council or of its Committees from the respective Governments in accordance 
    with the rules of those Governments. All other members of the Council will 
    be paid travelling and daily allowances by the Central Government for 
    attending the meetings of the Council or of its Committees at the rate 
    admissible to a Government Officer of the first grade in accordance with the 
    relevant rules. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>16</number> Authentication of acts and 
      proceedings.—
<section><number>1</number> All acts and proceedings 
      of the Council shall be authenticated by the Chairman, or with the 
      approval of the Chairman, by the Secretary.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Secretary shall carry 
      out the decision of the Council.
  
 
  </section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 200, dated 4th February, 1975 .</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 895(E), dated 29th December, 2008 (w.e.f. 
30-12-2008 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 1250, dated 25th June, 1968 .</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 200, dated 4th February, 1975 .</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 216, dated 5th May, 2003 (w.e.f. 24-5-2003 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 1465, 
    dated 31st August, 1963.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 187, 
    dated 10th April, 1996 (w.e.f. 27-4-1996).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 216, 
    dated 5th May, 2003 (w.e.f. 24-5-2003).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>