<act><tid>855945</tid>
<title>THE ACQUISITION OF CERTAIN AREA AT AYODHYA ACT, <year>1993</year></title>

NO. 33 OF <year>1993</year> 
[ 3rd April,
An Act to provide for the acquisition of certain area at Ayodhya 
and for matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.

WHEREAS there has been a long- standing dispute relating to the 
structure (including the premises of the inner and outer courtyards of  
  such structure), commonly known as the Ram Janma Bhumi- Babri Masjid, 
situated in village Kot Ramchandra in Ayodhya, in Pargana Haveli 
Avadh, in tehsil Faizabad Sadar, in the district of Faizabad of the 
State of Uttar Pradesh;

AND WHEREAS the said dispute has affected the maintenance of 
public order and harmony between different communities in the 
country;

AND WHEREAS it is necessary to maintain public order and to 
promote communal harmony and the spirit of common brotherhood amongst 
the people of India;

AND WHEREAS with a view to achieving the aforesaid objectives, it 
is necessary to acquire certain areas in Ayodhya;

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- fourth Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-

CHAP 
PRELIMINARY.

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY




<article><tid>331976</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>513081</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Acquisition of Certain Area at Ayodhya Act, <year>1993</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1389414</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 7th day of 
January, <year>1993</year>.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>169869</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>264693</tid>
<number>a</number>" area" means the area (including all the buildings,  
  structures or other properties comprised therein) specified 
in the Schedule;

</section>

<section><tid>1991827</tid>
<number>b</number>" authorised person" means a person or body of persons 
or trustees of any trust authorised by the Central Government 
under section 7;

</section>

<section><tid>1435599</tid>
<number>c</number>" Claims Commissioner" means the Claims Commissioner ap- 
pointed under subsection (2) of section 8;

</section>

<section><tid>1526331</tid>
<number>d</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act.
CHAP 
ACQUISITION OF THE AREA IN AYODHYA.

CHAPTER II

ACQUISITION OF THE AREA IN AYODHYA



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1507776</tid>
<number>3</number>Acquisition of rights in respect of certain area. On and from 
the commencement of this Act, the right, title and interest in 
relation to the area shall, by virtue of this Act, stand transferred 
to, and vest in, the Central Government,

</article>



<article><tid>416288</tid>
<number> 4</number> General effect of vesting.
<section><tid>616962</tid>
<number>1</number>The area shall be deemed to  
include all assets, rights, leaseholds, powers, authority and 
privileges and all property, movable and immovable, including lands, 
buildings, structures, shops of whatever nature or other properties 
and all other rights and interests in, or arising out of, such 
properties as were immediately before the commencement of this Act in 
the ownership, possession, power or control of any person or the State 
Government of Uttar Pradesh, as the case may be, and all registers, 
maps, plans, drawings and other documents of whatever nature relating 
thereto.

</section>

<section><tid>1986915</tid>
<number>2</number>All properties aforesaid which have vested in the Central 
Government under section 3 shall, by force of such vesting, be freed 
and discharged from any trust, obligation, mortgage, charge, lien and 
all other encumbrances affecting them and any attachment, injunction, 
decree or order of any court or tribunal or other authority 
restricting the use of such properties in any manner or appointing any 
receiver in respect of the whole or any part of such properties shall 
cease to have any effect.

</section>

<section><tid>766778</tid>
<number>3</number>If, on the commencement of this Act, any suit, appeal or 
other proceeding in respect of the right, title and interest relating 
to any property which has vested in the Central Government under 
section 3, is pending before any court, tribunal or other authority, 
the same shall abate.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>422666</tid>
<number> 5</number> Duty of person or State Government in charge of the management 
of the area to deliver all assets, etc.
<section><tid>1858833</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may  
take all necessary steps to secure possession of the area which is 
vested in that Government under section 3.

</section>

<section><tid>621213</tid>
<number>2</number>On the vesting of the area in the Central Government under 
section 3, the person or State Government of Uttar Pradesh, as the 
case may be, in charge of the management of the area immediately 
before such vesting shall be bound to deliver to the Central 
Government or the authorised person, all assets, registers and other 
documents in their custody relating to such vesting or where it is not 
practicable to deliver such registers or documents, the copies of such 
registers or documents authenticated in the prescribed manner.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>361596</tid>
<number> 6</number> Power of Central Government to direct vesting of the area in 
another authority or body or trust.
<section><tid>1849036</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything  
contained in sections 3, 4, 5 and 7, the Central Government may, if it 
is satisfied that any authority or other body, or trustees of any 
trust, set up on or after the commencement of this Act is or are 
willing to comply with such terms and conditions as that Government 
may think fit to impose, direct by notification in the Official 
Gazette, that the right, title and interest or any of them in relation 
to the area or any part thereof, instead of continuing to vest in the 
Central Government, vest in that authority or body or trustees of that 
trust either on the date of the notification or on such later date as 
may be specified in the notification.

</section>

<section><tid>969174</tid>
<number>2</number>When any right, title and interest in relation to the area 
or part thereof vest in the authority or body or trustees referred to 
in sub- section (1), such rights of the Central Government in relation 
to such area or part thereof, shall, on and from the date of such 
vesting, be deemed to have become the rights of that authority or 
body or trustees of that trust.

</section>

<section><tid>1812298</tid>
<number>3</number>The provisions of sections 4, 5, 7 and 11 shall, so far as 
may be, apply in relation to such authority or body or trustees as 
they apply in relation to the Central Government and for this purpose 
references therein to the Central Government shall be construed as 
references to such authority or body or trustees.
CHAP 
MANAGEMENT AND ADMINISTRATION OF PROPERTY.

CHAPTER III

MANAGEMENT AND ADMINISTRATION OF PROPERTY



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>280120</tid>
<number> 7</number> Management of property by Government.
<section><tid>1538937</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding  
anything contained in any contract or instrument or order of any 
court, tribunal or other authority to the contrary, on and from the 
commencement of this Act, the property vested in the Central Govern- 
ment under section 3 shall be managed by the Central Government or by 
a person or body of persons or trustees of any trust authorised by 
that Government in this behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>19144</tid>
<number>2</number>In managing the property vested in the Central Government 
under section 3, the Central Government or the authorised person 
shall ensure that the position existing before the commencement of 
this Act in the area on which the structure including the premises of 
the inner and outer courtyards of such structure commonly known as the 
Ram Janma Bhumi- Babri Masjid, stood in village Kot Ramchandra in 
Ayodhya, in Pargana Haveli Avadh, in tehsil Faizabad Sadar, in the dis- 
trict of Faizabad of the State of Uttar Pradesh is maintained.
CHAP 
MISCELLANEOUS.

CHAPTER IV

MISCELLANEOUS



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1884087</tid>
<number> 8</number> Payment of amount.
<section><tid>1687247</tid>
<number>1</number>The owner of any land, building,  
structure or other property comprised in the area shall be given by 
the Central Government, for the transfer to and vesting in that 
Government under section 3 of that land, building, structure or other 
property, in cash an amount equivalent to the market value of the 
land, building, structure or other property.

</section>

<section><tid>155365</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government shall, for the purpose of deciding 
the claim of the owner or any person having a claim against the owner 
under sub- section (1), by notification in the Official Gazette, 
appoint a Claims Commissioner.

</section>

<section><tid>393210</tid>
<number>3</number>The Claims Commissioner shall regulate his own procedure for 
receiving and deciding the claims.

</section>

<section><tid>1052632</tid>
<number>4</number>The owner or any person having a claim against the owner may 
make a claim to the Claims Commissioner within a period of ninety days 
from the date of commencement of this Act:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Provided that if the Claims Commissioner is satisfied that the 
claimant was prevented by sufficient cause from preferring the claim 
within the said period of ninety days, the Claims Commissioner may 
entertain the claim, within a further period of ninety days and not 
thereafter.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1213112</tid>
<number>9</number>Act to override all other enactments. The provisions of this 
Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith 
contained in any other law for tile time being in force or any 
instrument having effect by virtue of any law other than this Act or 
any decree or order of any court, tribunal or other authority.

</article>



<article><tid>805996</tid>
<number>10</number>Penalties. Any person who is in charge of the management of 
the area and fails to deliver to the Central Government or the 
authorised person any asset, register or other document in his custody 
relating to such area or, as the case may be, authenticated copies of 
such register or document, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a 
term which may extend to three years or with fine which may extend to 
ten thousand rupees or with both.

</article>



<article><tid>1155830</tid>
<number>11</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit, prosecution 
or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central Government or 
the authorised person or any of the officers or other employees of 
that Government or the authorised person for anything which is in good 
faith done or intended to be done under this Act.

</article>



<article><tid>1967878</tid>
<number> 12</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>865447</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the 
provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1381130</tid>
<number>2</number>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act 
shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House 
of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty 
days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule 
or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect duly in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1349202</tid>
<number> 13</number> Repeal and saving.
<section><tid>1235197</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of sub-  
section (2), the Acquisition of Certain Area at Ayodhya Ordinance, 
 <year>1993</year> (Ord. 8 of <year>1993</year>), is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1332169</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the said Ordinance,-

<subsection><tid>844893</tid>
<number>a</number>the right, title and interest in relation to plot No. 
 242 situated in village Kot Ramchandra specified against SI. 
No. 1 of the Schedule to the said Ordinance shall be deemed 
never to have been transferred to, and vested in, the Central 
Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1761666</tid>
<number>b</number>any suit, appeal or other proceeding in respect of the 
right, title and interest relating to the said plot No. 242, 
pending before any court, tribunal or other authority, shall 
be deemed never to have abated and such suit, appeal or other 
proceeding (including the orders or interim orders of any  
  court thereon) shall be deemed to have been restored to the 
position existing immediately before the commencement of the 
said Ordinance;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1372681</tid>
<number>c</number>any other action taken or thing done under that Ordinance 
in relation to the said plot No. 242 shall be deemed never to 
have been taken or done.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>153778</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action 
taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or 
taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



 </act>