<act><title>


THE ENVIRONMENT (PROTECTION) RULES, 19861</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>i</number> 
These rules may be called the Environ-ment (Protection) Rules, 1986.
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> They shall come into 
force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  “Act” means 
the Environment (Protection) Act, 1986 (29 of 1986);
 

    1[(aa)  “areas” 
means all areas where the hazardous substances are handled;]
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number> “Central 
Board” means the Central Board for the Prevention and Control of Water Pollution 
constituted under section 3 of the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) 
Act, 1974 (6 of 1974);
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number> “form” means a 
form set forth in Appendix A to these rules;
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number> “Government 
Analyst” means a person appointed or recognized as such under section 13;
 </section><section>
        <number>e</number> “person” in 
relation to any factory or premises means a person or occupier or his agent who 
has control over the affairs of the factory or premises and includes in relation 
to any substance, the person in possession of the substance;
 

    1[(ee) 
“prohibited substance” means the substance prohibited for handling;]
 </section><section>
         <number>f</number> “recipient 
system” means the part of the environment, such as, soil, water, air or other 
which receives the pollutants;
 

     1[(ff) 
“restricted substance” means the substance restricted for handling;]
 </section><section>
        <number>g</number> “section” 
means a section of the Act;
 </section><section>
        <number>h</number> “schedule” 
means a schedule appended to these rules;
 </section><section>
         <number>i</number> “standards” 
means standards prescribed under these rules;
 </section><section>
         <number>j</number> “State Board” 
means a State Board for the Prevention and Control of Water Pollution 
constituted under section 4 of the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) 
Act, 1974 (6 of 1974), or a State Board for the Prevention and Control of Air 
Pollution constituted under section 5 of the Air (Prevention and Control of 
Pollution) Act, 1981 (14 of 1981).
 
 



</section></article> 

 <title> </title>
 <article><title><number>3</number> Standards for emission or discharge of environmental pollutants. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> For the purposes of protecting and improving the quality of the environment and preventing and abating environmental pollution, the standards for emission or discharge of environmental pollutants from the industries, operations or processes shall be as specified in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[Schedules I to IV]. 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[***] 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rule (1), the Central Board or a State Board may specify more stringent standards from those provided in <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[Schedules I to IV] in respect of any specific industry, operation or process depending upon the quality of the recipient system and after recording reasons, therefor, in writing. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>3</number> The standards for emission or discharge of environmental pollutants specified under sub-rule (1) or sub-rule (2) shall be complied with by an industry, operation or process within a period of one year of being so specified.] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>3A</number> (i) Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rules (1) and (2), on and from the 1st day of January, 1994, emission or discharge of environmental pollutants from the <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[industries, operations or processes other than those industries, operations or processes for which standards have been specified in Schedule I shall] not exceed the relevant parameters and standards specified in Schedule VI: 
 Provided that the State Boards may specify more stringent standards for the relevant parameters with respect to specific industry or locations after recording reasons thereof in writing; 
 
 <subsection><number>ii</number> The State Board shall while enforcing the standards specified in Schedule VI follow the guidelines specified in Annexures I and II in that Schedule.] 
</subsection>
 </section><section><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>3B</number> The combined effect of emission or discharge of environmental pollutants in an area, from industries, operations, processes, automobiles and domestic sources, shall not be permitted to exceed the relevant concentration in ambient air as specified against each pollutant 7 [in columns (4) and (5) of Schedule VII].] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>4</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rule (3),— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the Central Board or a State Board, depending on the local conditions or nature of discharge of environment pollutants, may, by order, specify a lesser period than a period specified under sub-rule (3) within which the compliance of standards shall be made by an industry, operation or process; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the Central Government in respect of any specified industry, operation or process, by order, may specify any period other than a period specified under sub-rule (3) within which the compliance of standards shall be made by such industry, operation or process.] 
</subsection>
 </section><section><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>5</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rule (3), the standards for emission or discharge of environmental pollutants specified under sub-rule (1) or sub-rule (2) in respect of an industry, operation or process before the commencement of the Environment (Protection) Amendment Rules, 1991, shall be complied with by such industry, operation or process by the 31st day of December, 1991.] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[<number>6</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rule (3), an industry, operation or process which has commenced production on or before 16th May, 1981 and has shown adequate proof of at least commencement of physical work for establishment of facilities to meet the specified standards within a time-bound programme, to the satisfaction of the concerned, State Pollution Control Board, shall comply with such standards latest by the 31st day of December, 1993.] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[<number>7</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rule (3) or sub-rule (6) an industry, operation or process which has commenced production after the 16th day of May, 1981 but before the 31st day of December, 1991 and has shown adequate proof of at least commencement of physical work for establishment of facilities to meet the specified standards within a time-bound programme, to the satisfaction of the concerned State Pollution Control Board, shall comply with such standards latest by the 31st day of December, 1992.] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[<number>8</number> <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[On and from the 1st day of June, 2002], the following coal based thermal power plants shall use <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[raw or blended or beneficiated coal with an ash content not exceeding thirty-four per cent on an annual average basis], namely:— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> any thermal power plant located beyond one thousand kilometres from the pit-head; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> any thermal power plant located in urban area or sensitive area or critically polluted area irrespective of their distance from pit-head except any pit-head power plant: 
</subsection>
 <footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[Provided that any thermal power plant using Fluidised Bed Combustion or Circulating Fluidised Bed Combustion or Atmospheric Fluidised Bed Combustion or Pressurised Fluidised Bed Combustion or Integrated Gasification Combined Cycle technologies or any other clean technologies as may be notified by the Central Government in the Official Gazette shall be exempted from clauses (a) and (b)]. 
 Explanation. —For the purpose of this rule— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> ‘beneficiated coal' means coal containing higher calorific value but lower ash than the original ash content in the raw coal obtained through physical separation or washing process; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> ‘pit-head power plant' means power stations having captive transportation system for its exclusive use for transportation of coal from the loading point at the mining end up to the unloading point at the power station without using the normal public transportation system; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> ‘sensitive area' means an area whose ecological balance is prone to be easily disturbed; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> ‘critically polluted area' means the area where pollution level has reached or likely to reach to the critical level and which has been identified as such by the Central Government or Central Pollution Control Board or a State Pollution Control Board.] 
</subsection>
 <subsection><footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[<number>e</number> ‘urban area' means an area limit of a city having a population of more than 1 million according to 1991 census.] 















</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Directions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any direction issued under section 5 shall be in writing.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The direction shall 
specify the nature of action to be taken and the time within which it shall be 
complied with by the person, officer or the authority to whom such direction is 
given.
 

1[(3-a)] The 
person, officer or authority to whom any direction is sought to be issued shall 
be served with a copy of the proposed direction and shall be given an 
opportunity of not less than fifteen days from the date of service of a notice 
to file with an officer designated in this behalf the objections, if any, to the 
issue of the proposed direction.
 

2[(3-b) Where the 
proposed direction is for the stoppage or regulation of electricity or water or 
any other service affecting the carrying on any industry, operation or process 
and is sought to be issued to an officer or an authority, a copy of the proposed 
direction shall also be endorsed to the occupier of the industry, operation or 
process, as the case may be, and objections, if any, filed by the occupier with 
an officer designated in this behalf shall be dealt with in accordance with the 
procedures under sub-rules (3-a) and (4) of this rule:
 
Provided that no 
opportunity of being heard shall be given to the occupier if he had already been 
heard earlier and the proposed direction referred to in sub-rule (3-b) above for 
the stoppage or regulation of electricity or water or any other service was the 
resultant decision of the Central Government after such earlier hearing.]
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Central Government 
shall within a period of 45 days from the date of receipt of the objections, if 
any, or from the date up to which an opportunity is given to the person, officer 
or authority to file objections whichever is earlier, after considering the 
objections, if any, received from the person, officer or authority sought to be 
directed and for reasons to be recorded in writing, confirm, modify or decide 
not to issue the proposed direction.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> In a case where the 
Central Government is of the opinion that in view of the likelihood of a grave 
injury to the environment it is not expedient to provide an opportunity to file 
objections against the proposed direction, it may, for reasons to be recorded in 
writing, issue directions without providing such an opportunity.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Every notice or 
direction required to be issued under this rule shall be deemed to be duly 
served—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  where the 
person to be served is a company, if the document is addressed in the name of 
the company at its registered office or at its principal office or place of 
business and is either,—
 <subsubsection>
              <number>i</number> sent by 
registered post; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>ii</number> 
delivered at its registered office or at the principal office or place of 
business;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number> where the 
person to be served is an officer serving Government, if the document is 
addressed to the person and a copy thereof is endorsed to the Head of the 
Department and also to the Secretary to the Government, as the case may be, 
incharge of the Department in which for the time being the business relating to 
the Department in which the officer is employed is transacted and is either,—
 <subsubsection>
              <number>i</number> sent by 
registered post; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>ii</number> is given 
or tendered to him;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  in any other 
case, if the document is addressed to the person to be served and—
 <subsubsection>
              <number>i</number> is given 
or tendered to him; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>ii</number> if such 
person cannot be found, is affixed on some conspicuous part of his last known 
place of residence or business or is given or tendered to some adult member of 
his family or is affixed on some conspicuous part of the land or building, if 
any, to which it relates; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>iii</number> is sent 
by registered post to that person.
 
Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this sub-rule,—
 <subsubsubsection>
        <number>a</number> “company” 
means any body corporate and includes a firm or other association of 
individuals;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
        <number>b</number> “a servant” is 
not a member of the family.
 
 




</subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Prohibition and 
restriction on the location of industries and the carrying on processes and 
operations in different areas.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may take into consideration the following factors while 
prohibiting or restricting the location of industries and carrying on of 
processes and operations in different areas:—
 <subsection>
         <number>i</number> Standards for 
quality of environment in its various aspects laid down for an area.
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number> The maximum 
allowable limits of concentration of various environment pollutants (including 
noise) for an area.
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>iii</number> The likely 
emission or discharge of environmental pollutants from an industry, process or 
operation proposed to be prohibited or restricted.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iv</number> The 
topographic and climatic features of an area.
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>v</number> The biological 
diversity of the area which, in the opinion of the Central Government, needs to 
be preserved.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>vi</number> 
Environmentally compatible land use.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>vii</number> Net adverse 
environmental impact likely to be caused by an industry, process or operation 
proposed to be prohibited or restricted.
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>viii</number> Proximity to 
a protected area under the Ancient Monuments and Archaeological Sites and 
Remains Act, 1958 or a sanctuary, National Park, game reserve or closed area 
notified, as such under the Wild Life (Protection) Act, 1972, or places 
protected under any treaty, agreement or convention with any other country or 
countries or in pursuance of any decision made in any international conference, 
association or other body.
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ix</number> Proximity to 
human settlements.
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>x</number> Any other 
factors as may be considered by the Central Government to be relevant to the 
protection of the environment in an area.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> While prohibiting or 
restricting the location of industries and carrying on of processes and 
operations in an area, the Central Government shall follow the procedure 
hereinafter laid down.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> (a) Whenever it 
appears to the Central Government that it is expedient to impose prohibition or 
restrictions on the location of an industry or the carrying on of processes and 
operations in an area, it may, by notification in the Official Gazette and in 
such other manner as the Central Government may deem necessary from time to 
time, given notice of its intention to do so.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> Every notification 
under clause (a) shall give a brief discription of the area, the industries, 
operations processes in that area about which such notification pertains and 
also specify the reasons for the imposition of prohibition or restrictions on 
the location of the industries and carrying on of processes or operations in 
that area.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> Any person interested 
in filing an objection against the imposition of prohibition or restriction on 
carrying on of processes or operations as notified under clause (a) may do so in 
writing to the Central Government within sixty days from the date of publication 
of the notification in the Official Gazette.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> The Central Government 
shall, within a period of one hundred and twenty days from the date of 
publication of the notification in the Official Gazette, consider all the 
objections received against such notification and may
1[within
2[three hundred and 
sixty-five days] from such date of publication,] impose prohibition or 
restrictions on location of such industries and the carrying on of any process 
or operation in an area.
 

3[(4) 
Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rule (3), whenever it appears to the 
Central Government that it is in public interest to do so, it may dispense with 
the requirement of notice under clause (a) of sub-rule (3).]
 
 





</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>6</number> Procedure 
for taking samples.—The 
Central Government or the officer empowered to take samples under section 11 
shall collect the sample in sufficient quantity to be divided into two uniform 
parts and effectively seal and suitably mark the same and permit the person from 
whom the sample is taken to add his own seal or mark to all or any of the 
portions so sealed and marked. In case where the sample is made up in containers 
or small volumes and is likely to deteriorate or be otherwise damaged if 
exposed, the Central Government or the officer empowered shall take two of the 
said samples without opening the containers and suitably seal and mark the same. 
The Central Government or the officer empowered shall dispose of the samples so 
collected as follows:—
 <section>
         <number>i</number> one portion 
shall be handed over to the person from whom the sample is taken under 
acknowledgement; and
 </section><section>
        <number>ii</number> the other 
portion shall be sent forthwith to the environmental laboratory for analysis.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Service of notice.—The 
Central Government or the officer empowered shall serve on the occupier or his 
agent or person in charge of the place a notice then and there in Form I of his 
intention to have the sample analysed.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Procedure for 
submission of samples for analysis, and the form of laboratory report thereon.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Sample taken for analysis shall be sent by the Central Government or the officer 
empowered to the environmental laboratory by registered post or through special 
messenger along with Form II.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Another copy of Form 
II together with specimen impression of seals of the officer empowered to take 
samples along with the seals/marks, if any, of the person from whom the sample 
is taken shall be sent separately in a sealed cover by registered post or 
through a special messenger to the environmental laboratory.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The findings shall be 
recorded in Form III in triplicate and signed by the Government Analyst and sent 
to the officer from whom the sample is received for analysis.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> On receipt of the 
report of the findings of the Government Analyst, the officer shall send one 
copy of the report to the person from whom the sample was taken for analysis, 
the second copy shall be retained by him for his records and the third copy 
shall be kept by him to be produced in the Court before which proceedings, if 
any are, instituted.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Functions of 
environmental laboratories.—The 
following shall be the functions of environmental laboratories:—
 <section>
         <number>i</number> to evolve 
standardised methods for sampling and analysis of various types of environmental 
pollutants;
 </section><section>
        <number>ii</number>  to analyse 
samples sent by the Central Government or the officers empowered under 
sub-section (1) of section 11;
 </section><section>
        <number>iii</number>  to carry 
out such investigations as may be directed by the Central Government to lay down 
standards for the quality of environment and distcharge of environmental 
pollutants, to monitor and to enforce the standards laid down;
 </section><section>
       <number>iv</number> to send 
periodical reports regarding its activities to the Central Government;
 </section><section>
        <number>v</number> to carry out 
such other functions as may be entrusted to it by the Central Government from 
time to time.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Qualifications of 
Government Analyst.—A 
person shall not be qualified for appointment or recognised as a Government 
Analyst unless he is a—
 <section>
        <number>a</number> graduate in 
science from a recognised university with five years’ experience in a laboratory 
engaged in environmental investigations, testing or analysis; or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number> post-graduate 
in science or a graduate in engineering or a graduate in medicine or equivalent 
with two years’ experience in a laboratory engaged in environmental 
investigations, testing or analysis; or
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number> post-graduate 
in environmental science from a recognized university with two years’ experience 
in a laboratory engaged in environmental investigations, testing or analysis.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Manner of giving 
notice.—The 
manner of giving notice under clause (b) of section 19 shall be as follows, 
namely:—
 <section>
        <number>1</number> The notice 
shall be in writing in Form IV.
 </section><section>
        <number>2</number> The person 
giving notice may send notice to,—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number> if the alleged 
offence has taken place in a Union territory:
 <subsubsection>
             <number>A</number> the 
Central Board; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>B</number> the 
Ministry of Environment and Forests (represented by the Secretary of the 
Government of India);
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number> if the alleged 
offence has taken place in a State:
 <subsubsection>
             <number>A</number> the State 
Board; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>B</number> the 
Government of the State (represented by the Secretary to the State Government 
incharge of environment); and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>C</number> the 
Ministry of Environment and Forests (represented by the Secretary to the 
Government of India).
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
        <number>3</number> The notice 
shall be sent by registered post-acknowledgement due.
 </section><section>
        <number>4</number> The period of 
sixty days mentioned in clause (b) of section 19 of the Environment (Protection) 
Act, 1986 shall be reckoned from the date it is first received by one of the 
authorities mentioned above.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>12</number> Furnishing 
of information to authorities and agencies in centain cases.— 
Where the discharge of environmental pollutant in excess of the prescribed 
standard occurs or is apprehended to occur due to any accident or other 
unforeseen act or event, the person in charge of the place at which such 
discharge occurs or is apprehended to occur shall forthwith intimate the fact of 
such occurrence or apprehension of such occurrence to all the following 
authorities or agencies, namely:—
 <section>
         <number>i</number> The 
officer-in-charge of emergency or disaster relief operations in a district or 
other region of a State or Union territory specified by whatever designation, by 
the Government of the said State or Union territory, and in whose jurisdiction 
the industry, process or operation is located;
 </section><section>
        <number>ii</number> The Central 
Board or a State Board, as the case may be, and its regional officer having 
local jurisdiction who have been delegated powers under sections 20, 21, 23 of 
the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1974 (6 of 1974), and 
section 24 of the Air (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1981 (14 of 
1981);
 </section><section>
        <number>iii</number> The 
statutory authorities or agencies specified in column 3 in relation to places 
mentioned in column 2 against thereof of] in
2[Schedule V].
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>13</number> 
Prohibition and restriction on the handling of hazardous substances in different 
areas.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
Central Government may take into consideration the following factors while 
prohibiting or restricting the handling of hazardous substances in different 
areas:—
 <subsection>
         <number>i</number> the hazardous 
nature of the substance (either in qualitative or quantitative terms) as far as 
may be in terms of its damage causing potential to the environment, human 
beings, other living creatures, plants and property;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number> the 
substances that may be or likely to be or readily available as substitutes for 
the substances proposed to be prohibited or restricted;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>iii</number>  the 
indigenous availability of the substitute, or the state of technology available 
in the country for developing a safe substitute;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iv</number> the gestation 
period that may be necessary for gradual introduction of a new substitute with a 
view to bringing about a total prohibition of the hazardous substance in 
question; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>v</number> any other 
factor as may be considered by the Central Government to be relevant to the 
protection of environment.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> While prohibiting or 
restricting the handling of hazardous substances in an area including their 
imports and exports the Central Government shall follow the procedure 
hereinafter laid down:—
 <subsection>
         <number>i</number> Whenever it 
appears to the Central Government that it is expedient to impose prohibition or 
restriction on the handling of hazardous substances in an area, it may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette and in such other manner as the Central 
Government may deem necessary from time to time, give notice of its intention to 
do so.
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  Every 
notification under clause (i) shall give a brief description of the hazardous 
substances and the geographical region or the area to which such notification 
pertains and also specify the reasons for the imposition of prohibition or 
restriction on the handling of such hazardous substances in that region or area.
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>iii</number>  Any person 
interested in filing an objection against the imposition of prohibition or 
restrictions on the handling of hazardous substances as notified under clause (i) 
may do so in writing to the Central Government within thirty days from the date 
of publication of the notification in the Official Gazette.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iv</number> The Central 
Government shall within a period of sixty days from the date of publication of 
the notification in the Official Gazette consider all the objections received 
against such notification and may impose prohibition or restrictions on the 
handling of hazardous substances in a region or an area.]
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>14</number> Submission 
of environment 2[statement].—Every 
person carrying on an industry, operation or process requiring consent under 
section 25 of the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1974 (6 of 
1974) or under section 21 of the Air (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 
1981 (14 of 1981) or both or authorisation under the Hazardous Waters 
(Management and Handling) Rules, 1989 issued under the Environment (Protection) 
Act, 1986 (29 of 1986) shall submit an environmental
2[statement] for the 
financial year ending on the 31st March in Form V to the concerned State 
Pollution Control Board on or before the
2[thirtieth day of 
September] every year, beginning 1993.]
 
 




</article><form>
 




THE ENVIRONMENT (PROTECTION) RULES, 1986
 


 
 



1[2[***]]
 


 
 


—————
 


1.  Schedule II (relating 
to rule 12) re-numbered as Schedule V by G.S.R. 422(E), dated 15th May, 1998 (w.e.f. 
15-5-1998). Earlier Schedule II (relating to rule 12) was inserted by S.O. 
82(E), dated 16th February, 1987 (w.e.f. 16-2-1987).
 


2. Schedule II (relating to 
rule 3) omitted by G.S.R. 801(E), dated 31st December, 1993 (w.e.f. 31-12-1993). 
Earlier Schedule II (relating to rule 3) was inserted by G.S.R. 919(E), dated 
12th September, 1988.
 


 
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Proviso omitted by S.O. 23(E), dated 16th January, 1991 (w.e.f. 16-1-1991).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 422(E), dated 19th May, 1993 (w.e.f. 19-5-1993).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Ins. by S.O. 23(E), dated 16th January, 1991 (w.e.f. 16-1-1991).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 422(E), dated 19th May, 1993 (w.e.f. 19-5-1993).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 801(E), dated 31st December, 1993 (w.e.f. 31-12-1993).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 7, dated 22nd December, 1998, for sub-rule (3B) (w.e.f. 2-1-1999). Earlier sub-rule (3B) was inserted by G.S.R. 176(E), dated 2nd April, 1996 (w.e.f. 3-4-1996).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 826(E), dated 16th November, 2009, for "in columns (3) to (5) of Schedule VII" (w.e.f. 16-11-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Added by G.S.R. 95(E), dated 12th February, 1992 (w.e.f. 12-2-1992).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 560(E), dated 19th September, 1997 (w.e.f. 19-9-1997).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 407(E), dated 31st May, 2001 (w.e.f. 31-5-2001).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 378(E), dated 30th June, 1998 (w.e.f. 3-7-1998).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 378(E), dated 30th June, 1998 (w.e.f. 3-7-1998).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 378(E), dated 30th June, 1998 (w.e.f. 3-7-1998).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number> Ins. by S.O. 64(E), 
dated 18th January, 1988 (w.e.f. 18-1-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 884(E), 
dated 20th November, 1992</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 320(E) 
dated 16th March, 1994 (w.e.f. 16-03-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 422(E), 
dated 19th May, 1993 (w.e.f. 19-5-1993).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 386(E), 
dated 22nd April, 1993 (w.e.f. 28-4-1993</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>