<act><title>


THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL OF 
    POLLUTION) ACT, 1974</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title, application and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 
    1974. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    applies in the first instance to the whole of the States of Assam, Bihar, 
    Gujarat, Haryana, Himachal Pradesh, Jammu and Kashmir, Karnataka, Kerala, 
    Madhya Pradesh, Rajasthan, Tripura and West Bengal and the Union 
    territories; and it shall apply to such other State which adopts this Act by 
    resolution passed in that behalf under clause (1) of article 252 of the 
    Constitution. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It 
    shall come into force, at once in the States of Assam, Bihar, Gujarat, 
    Haryana, Himachal Pradesh, Jammu and Kashmir, Karnataka, Kerala, Madhya 
    Pradesh, Rajasthan, Tripura and West Bengal and in the Union territories, 
    and in any other State which adopts this Act under clause (1) of article 252 
    of the Constitution on the date of such adoption and any reference in this 
    Act to the commencement of this Act shall, in relation to any State or Union 
    territory, mean the date on which this Act comes into force in such State or 
    Union territory.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “Board” means the Central Board 
    or a State Board;  
 

1[(b) 
       “Central Board” means the Central Pollution Control Board constituted 
    under section 3;]  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “member” means a member of a 
    Board and includes the chairman thereof;  
 

2[(d) 
       “occupier”, in relation to any factory or premises, means the person who 
    has control over the affairs of the factory or the premises, and includes, 
    in relation to any substance, the person in possession of the substance;]  
 

3[(dd) 
       “outlet” includes any conduit pipe or channel, open or closed, carrying 
    sewage or trade effluent or any other holding arrangement which causes, or 
    is likely to cause, pollution;]  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    “pollution” means such 
    contamination of water or such alteration of the physical, chemical or 
    biological properties of water or such discharge of any sewage or trade 
    effluent or of any other liquid, gaseous or solid substance into water 
    (whether directly or indirectly) as may, or is likely to, create a nuisance 
    or render such water harmful or injurious to public health or safety, or to 
    domestic, commercial, industrial, agricultural or other legitimate uses, or 
    to the life and health of animals or plants or of aquatic organisms;  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    “prescribed” means prescribed by 
    rules made under this Act by the Central Government or, as the case may be, 
    the State Government;  
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    “sewage effluent” means effluent 
    from any sewerage system or sewage disposal works and includes sullage from 
    open drains;  
 

3[(gg) 
       “sewer” means any conduit pipe or channel, open or closed, carrying 
    sewage or trade effluent;]  
 

4[(h) 
       “State Board” means a State Pollution Control Board constituted under 
    section 4;]  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    “State Government” in relation to 
    a Union territory means the Administrator thereof appointed under article 
    239 of the Constitution;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>    “stream” includes—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    river;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    water course (whether flowing or 
    for the time being dry);  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>    inland water (whether natural 
    or artificial);  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iv</number>    sub-terranean waters;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>v</number>    sea or tidal waters to such 
    extent or, as the case may be, to such point as the State Government may, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf;  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>    “trade effluent” includes any 
    liquid, gaseous or solid substance which is discharged from any premises 
    used for carrying on any 
5[industry, 
    operation or process, or treatment and disposal system], other than domestic 
    sewage.
 
 
 
 









 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Constitution of Central Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government shall, with effect from such date (being a date not 
    later than six months of the commencement of this Act in the States of 
    Assam, Bihar, Gujarat, Haryana, Himachal Pradesh, Jammu and Kashmir, 
    Karnataka, Kerala, Madhya Pradesh, Rajasthan, Tripura and West Bengal and in 
    the Union territories) as it may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    appoint, constitute a Central Board to be called the 

    1[Central Pollution 
    Control Board] to exercise the powers conferred on and perform the functions 
    assigned to that Board under this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Central Board shall consist of the following members, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    a full-time chairman, being a 
    person having special knowledge or practical experience in respect of 
2[matters 
    relating to environmental protection] or a person having knowledge and 
    experience in administering institutions dealing with the matters aforesaid, 
    to be nominated by the Central Government;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> 
     3[such 
    number of officials, not exceeding five,] to be nominated by the Central 
    Government to represent that Government;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    such number of persons, not 
    exceeding five to be nominated by the Central Government, from amongst the 
    members of the State Boards, of whom not exceeding two shall be from those 
    referred to in clause (c) of sub-section (2) of section 4;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> 
     4[such 
    number of non-officials, not exceeding three,] to be nominated by the 
    Central Government, to represent the interests of agriculture, fishery or 
    industry or trade or any other interest which, in the opinion of the Central 
    Government, ought to be represented;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    two persons to represent the 
    companies or corporations owned, controlled or managed by the Central 
    Government, to be nominated by that Government;
 

5[(f) 
       a full-time member-secretary, possessing qualifications, knowledge and 
    experience of scientific, engineering or management aspects of pollution 
    control, to be appointed by the Central Government.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Central Board shall be a body corporate with the name aforesaid having 
    perpetual succession and a common seal with power, subject to the provisions 
    of this Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of property and to contract, and 
    may, by the aforesaid name, sue or be sued.  
 
 

 










 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Constitution of State Boards.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government shall, with effect from such date 

    1[***] as it may, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, appoint, constitute a 

    2[State Pollution 
    Control Board], under such name as may be specified in the notification, to 
    exercise the powers conferred on and perform the functions assigned to that 
    Board under this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    State Board shall consist of the following members, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    a 
3[***] 
    chairman, being a person having special knowledge or practical experience in 
    respect of 
4[matters 
    relating to environmental protection] or a person having knowledge and 
    experience in administering institutions dealing with the matters aforesaid, 
    to be nominated by the State Government:
 

5[Provided 
    that the chairman may be either whole-time or part-time as the State 
    Government may think fit;]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> 
     6[such 
    number of officials, not exceeding five,] to be nominated by the State 
    Government to represent that Government;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> 
     7[such 
    number of persons, not exceeding five,] to be nominated by the State 
    Government from amongst the members of the local authorities functioning 
    within the State;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> 
     8[such 
    number of non-officials, not exceeding three,] to be nominated by the State 
    Government to represent the interests of agriculture, fishery or industry or 
    trade or any other interest which, in the opinion of the State Government, 
    ought to be represented;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    two persons to represent the 
    companies or corporations owned, controlled or managed by the State 
    Government, to be nominated by that Government;
 

9[(f) 
       a full-time member-secretary, possessing qualifications, knowledge and 
    experience of scientific, engineering or management aspects of pollution 
    control, to be appointed by the State Government.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Every State Board shall be a body corporate with the name specified by the 
    State Government in the notification under sub-section (1), having perpetual 
    succession and a common seal with power, subject to the provisions of this 
    Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of property and to contract, and may, by 
    the said name, sue or be sued.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, no State Board shall be 
    constituted for a Union territory and in relation to a Union territory, the 
    Central Board shall exercise the powers and perform the functions of a State 
    Board for that Union territory:  
 
Provided 
    that in relation to any Union territory the Central Board may delegate all 
    or any of its powers and functions under this sub-section to such person or 
    body of persons as the Central Government may specify.  
 
 













 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Terms and conditions of service of members.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Save as otherwise provided by or under this Act, a member of a Board, other 
    than a member-secretary, shall hold office for a term of three years from 
    the date of his nomination:  
 
Provided 
    that a member shall, notwithstanding the expiration of his term, continue to 
    hold office until his successor enters upon his office.  
 


    1[(2) The term of 
    office of a member of a Board nominated under clause (b) or clause (e) of 
    sub-section (2) of section 3 or clause (b) or clause (e) of sub-section (2) 
    of section 4 shall come to an end as soon as he ceases to hold the office 
    under the Central Government or the State Government or, as the case may be, 
    the company or corporation owned, controlled or managed by the Central 
    Government or the State Government, by virtue of which he was nominated.]  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Central Government or, as the case may be, the State Government may, if it 
    thinks fit, remove any member of a Board before the expiry of his term of 
    office, after giving him a reasonable opportunity of showing cause against 
    the same.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A 
    member of a Board, other than the member-secretary, may at any time resign 
    his office by writing under his hand addressed—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    in the case of the chairman, to 
    the Central Government or, as the case may be, the State Government; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    in any other case, to the 
    chairman of the Board,  
 
and the seat of the chairman or such other 
    member shall thereupon become vacant.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> A 
    member of a Board, other than the member-secretary, shall be deemed to have 
    vacated his seat if he is absent without reason, sufficient in the opinion 
    of the Board, from three consecutive meetings of the Board, 

    2[or where he is 
    nominated under clause (c) or clause (e) of sub-section (2) of section 3 or 
    under clause (c) or clause (e) of sub-section (2) of section 4, if he ceases 
    to be a member of the State Board or of the local authority or, as the case 
    may be, of the company or corporation owned, controlled or managed by the 
    Central Government or the State Government and such vacation of seat shall, 
    in either case, take effect from such date as the Central Government or, as 
    the case may be, the State Government may, by notification in the Official 
    Gazette, specify.]  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> A 
    casual vacancy in a Board shall be filled by a fresh nomination and the 
    person nominated to fill the vacancy shall hold office only for the 
    remainder of the term for which the member in whose place he was nominated.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> A 
    member of a Board 

    3[shall be eligible 
    for re-nomination.]  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> The 
    other terms and conditions of service of a member of a Board, other than the 
    chairman and member-secretary, shall be such as may be prescribed.  
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> The 
    other terms and conditions of service of the chairman shall be such as may 
    be prescribed.  
 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Disqualifications.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No person shall be a member of Board, who—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    is, or at any time has been 
    adjudged insolvent or has suspended payment of his debts or has compounded 
    with his creditors, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    is of unsound mind and stands so 
    declared by a competent court, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    is, or has been, convicted of an 
    offence which, in the opinion of the Central Government or, as the case may 
    be, of the State Government, involves moral turpitude, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    is, or at any time has been, 
    convicted of an offence under this Act, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    has directly or indirectly by 
    himself or by any partner, any share or interest in any firm or company 
    carrying on the business of manufacture, sale or hire of machinery, plant, 
    equipment, apparatus or fittings for the treatment of a sewage or trade 
    effluents, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    is a director or a secretary, 
    manager or other salaried officer or employee of any company or firm having 
    any contract with the Board, or with the Government constituting the Board, 
    or with a local authority in the State, or with a company or corporation 
    owned, controlled or managed by the Government, for the carrying out of 
    sewerage schemes or for the installation of plants for the treatment of 
    sewage or trade effluents, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    has so abused, in the opinion of 
    the Central Government or as the case may be, of the State Government, his 
    position as a member, as to render his continuance on the Board detrimental 
    to the interest of the general public.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> No 
    order of removal shall be made by the Central Government or the State 
    Government, as the case may be, under this section unless the member 
    concerned has been given a reasonable opportunity of showing cause against 
    the same.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-sections (1) and (7) of section 5, 
    a member who has been removed under this section shall not be eligible for 
    renomination as a member.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Vacation of seats by members.—If 
    a member of a Board becomes subject to any of the disqualifications 
    specified in section 6, his seat shall become vacant.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Meetings of Boards.—A 
    Board shall meet at least once in every three months and shall observe such 
    rules of procedure in regard to the transaction of business at its meetings 
    as may be prescribed:  
 
Provided 
    that if, in the opinion of the chairman, any business of an urgent nature is 
    to be transacted, he may convene a meeting of the Board at such time as he 
    thinks fit for the aforesaid purpose.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Constitution of committees.— 
    
<section><number>1</number> A Board may constitute as many committees consisting wholly of members 
    or wholly of other persons or partly of members and partly of other persons, 
    and for such purpose or purposes as it may think fit.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    committee constituted under this section shall meet at such time and at such 
    place, and shall observe such rules of procedure in regard to the 
    transaction of business at its meetings, as may be prescribed.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    members of a committee (other than the members of the Board) shall be paid 
    such fees and allowances, for attending its meetings and for attending to 
    any other work of the Board as may be prescribed.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Temporary association of persons with Board for particular purposes.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A Board may associate with itself in such manner, and for such purposes, as 
    may be prescribed any person whose assistance or advice it may desire to 
    obtain in performing any of its functions under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    person associated with the Board under sub-section (1) for any purpose shall 
    have a right to take part in the discussions of the Board relevant to that 
    purpose, but shall not have a right to vote at a meeting of the Board, and 
    shall not be a member for any other purpose.  
 


    1[(3) A person 
    associated with the Board under sub-section (1) for any purpose shall be 
    paid such fees and allowances, for attending its meetings and for attending 
    to any other work of the Board, as may be prescribed.]  
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Vacancy in Board not to invalidate acts or proceedings.—No 
    act or proceeding of a Board or any committee thereof shall be called in 
    question on the ground merely of the existence of any vacancy in, or any 
    defect in the constitution of, the Board or such committee, as the case may 
    be.  
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>11A</number> 
    Delegation of powers to Chairman.—The Chairman of a Board shall exercise 
    such powers and perform such duties as may be prescribed or as may, from 
    time to time, be delegated to him by the Board.]  
 
 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Member-secretary and officers and other employees of Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The terms and conditions of service of the member-secretary shall be such as 
    may be prescribed.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    member-secretary shall exercise such powers and perform such duties as may 
    be prescribed or as may, from time to time, be delegated to him by the Board 
    or its chairman.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Subject to such rules as may be made by the Central Government or, as the 
    case may be, the State Government in this behalf, a Board may appoint such 
    officers and employees as it considers necessary for the efficient 
    performance of its functions 

    1[***].  
 


    2[(3A) The method of 
    recruitment and the terms and conditions of service (including the scales of 
    pay) of the officers (other than the member-secretary) and other employees 
    of the Central Board or a State Board shall be such as may be determined by 
    regulations made by the Central Board or, as the case may be, by the State 
    Board:  
 
Provided 
    that no regulation made under this sub-section shall take effect unless,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    in the case of a regulation made 
    by the Central Board, it is approved by the Central Government; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    in the case of a regulation made 
    by a State Board, it is approved by the State Government.]
 


    3[(3B) The Board may, 
    by general or special order, and subject to such conditions and limitations, 
    if any, as may be specified in the order, delegate to any officer of the 
    Board such of its powers and functions under this Act as it may deem 
    necessary.]  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> Subject to 
    such conditions as may be prescribed, a Board may from time to time appoint 
    any qualified person to be a consulting engineer to the Board and pay him 
    such salaries and allowances and subject him to such other terms and 
    conditions of service as it thinks fit.
 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Constitution of Joint Boards.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, an agreement may be entered 
    into—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    by two or more Governments of 
    contiguous States, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    by the Central Government (in 
    respect of one or more Union territories) and one or more Governments of 
    States contiguous to such Union territory or Union territories,  
 
to be in force for such period and to be 
    subject to renewal for such further period, if any, as may be specified in 
    the agreement to provide for the constitution of a Joint Board,—
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    in a case referred to in clause 
    (a), for all the participating States, and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    in a case referred to in clause 
    (b), for the participating Union territory or Union territories and the 
    State or States.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> An 
    agreement under this section may—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    provide, in a case referred to in 
    clause (a) of sub-section (1), for the apportionment between the 
    participating States and in a case referred to in clause (b) of that 
    sub-section, for the apportionments between the Central Government and the 
    participating State Government or State Governments, of the expenditure in 
    connection with the Joint Board;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    determine, in a case referred to 
    in clause (a) of sub-section (1), which of the participating State 
    Governments and in a case referred to in clause (b) of that sub-section, 
    whether the Central Government or the participating State Government (if 
    there are more than one participating State, also which of the participating 
    State Governments) shall exercise and perform the several powers and 
    functions of the State Government under this Act and the references in this 
    Act to the State Government shall be construed accordingly;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    provide for consultation, in a 
    case referred to in clause (a) of sub-section  (1), between the 
    participating State Governments and in a case referred to in clause (b) of 
    that sub-section, between the Central Government and the participating State 
    Government or State Governments either generally or with reference to 
    particular matters arising under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    make such incidental and 
    ancillary provisions, not inconsistent with this Act, as may be deemed 
    necessary or expedient for giving effect to the agreement.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> An 
    agreement under this section shall be published, in a case referred to in 
    clause (a) of sub-section (1), in the Official Gazette of the participating 
    States and in a case referred to in cause (b) of that sub-section, in the 
    Official Gazette of the participating Union territory or Union territories 
    and participating State or States.  
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Composition of Joint Boards.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A Joint Board constituted in pursuance of an agreement entered into under 
    clause 
<subsection><number>a</number> of sub-section (1) of section 13 shall consist of the following 
    members, namely:—  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>a</number>    a full-time chairman, being a 
    person having special knowledge or practical experience in respect of 
1[matters 
    relating to environmental protection] or a person having knowledge and 
    experience in administering institutions dealing with the matters aforesaid, 
    to be nominated by the Central Government;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    two officials from each of the 
    participating States to be nominated by the concerned participating State 
    Government to represent that Government;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    one person to be nominated by 
    each of the participating State Governments from amongst the members of the 
    local authorities functioning within the State concerned;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    one non-official to be nominated 
    by each of the participating State Governments to represent the interests of 
    agriculture, fishery or industry or trade in the State concerned or any 
    other interest which, in the opinion of the participating State Government, 
    is to be represented;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    two persons to be nominated by 
    the Central Government to represent the companies or corporations owned, 
    controlled or managed by the participating State Governments;
 

2[(f) 
       a full-time member-secretary, possessing qualifications, knowledge and 
    experience of scientific, engineering or management aspects of pollution 
    control, to be appointed by the Central Government.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    Joint Board constituted in pursuance of an agreement entered into under 
    clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 13 shall consist of the following 
    members, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    a full-time chairman, being a 
    person having special knowledge or practical experience in respect of 
3[matters 
    relating to environmental protection] or a person having knowledge and 
    experience in administering institutions dealing with the matters aforesaid, 
    to be nominated by the Central Government;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    two officials to be nominated by 
    the Central Government from the participating Union territory or each of the 
    participating Union territories, as the case may be, and two officials to be 
    nominated, from the participating State or each of the participating States, 
    as the case may be, by the concerned participating State Government;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    one person to be nominated by the 
    Central Government from amongst the members of the local authorities 
    functioning within the participating Union territory or each of the 
    participating Union territories, as the case may be, and one person to be 
    nominated, from amongst the members of the local authorities functioning 
    within the participating State or each of the participating States, as the 
    case may be, by the concerned participating State Government;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    one non-official to be nominated 
    by Central Government and one person to be nominated by the participating 
    State Government or State Governments to represent the interests of 
    agriculture, fishery or industry or trade in the Union territory or in each 
    of the Union territories or the State or in each of the States, as the case 
    may be, or any other interest which in the opinion of the Central Government 
    or, as the case may be, of the State Government is to be represented;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    two persons to be nominated by 
    the Central Government to represent the companies or corporations owned, 
    controlled or managed by the Central Government and situate in the 
    participating Union territory or territories and two persons to be nominated 
    by the Central Government to represent the companies or corporations owned, 
    controlled or managed by the participating State Governments;
 

4[(f) 
       a full-time member-secretary, possessing qualifications, knowledge and 
    experience of scientific, engineering or management aspects of pollution 
    control, to be appointed by the Central Government.]  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> When 
    a Joint Board is constituted in pursuance of an agreement under clause (b) 
    of sub-section (1) of section 13, the provisions of sub-section (4) of 
    section 4 shall cease to apply in relation to the Union territory for which 
    the Joint Board is constituted.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of sub-section (3), the provisions of sub-section 
    (3) of section 4 and sections 5 to 12 (inclusive) shall apply in relation to 
    the Joint Board and its member-secretary as they apply in relation to a 
    State Board and its member-secretary.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Any 
    reference in this Act to the State Board shall, unless the context otherwise 
    requires, be construed as including a Joint Board.  
 
 








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Special provision relating to giving of directions.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in this Act where any Joint Board is constituted under 
    section 13,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    the Government of the State for 
    which the Joint Board is constituted shall be competent to give any 
    direction under this Act only in cases where such direction relates to a 
    matter within the exclusive territorial jurisdiction of the State;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    the Central Government alone 
    shall be competent to give any direction under this Act where such direction 
    relates to a matter within the territorial jurisdiction of two or more 
    States or pertaining to a Union territory.
 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Functions of Central Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of this Act, the main function of the Central 
    Board shall be to promote cleanliness of streams and wells in different 
    areas of the States.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
    function, the Central Board may perform all or any of the following 
    functions, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    advise the Central Government on 
    any matter concerning the prevention and control of water pollution;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    co-ordinate the activities of the 
    State Boards and resolve disputes among them;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    provide technical assistance and 
    guidance to the State Boards, carry out and sponsor investigations and 
    research relating to problems of water pollution and prevention, control or 
    abatement of water pollution; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    plan and organise the training of 
    persons engaged or to be engaged in programmes for the prevention, control 
    or abatement of water pollution on such terms and conditions as the Central 
    Board may specify;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    organise through mass media a 
    comprehensive programme regarding the prevention and control of water 
    pollution;
 

1[(ee) 
       perform such of the functions of any State Board as may be specified in 
    an order made under sub-section (2) of section 18;]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    collect, compile and publish 
    technical and statistical data relating to water pollution and the measures 
    devised for its effective prevention and control and prepare manuals, codes 
    or guides relating to treatment and disposal of sewage and trade effluents 
    and disseminate information connected therewith;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    lay down, modify or annul, in 
    consultation with the State Government concerned, the standards for a stream 
    or well:
 
Provided that different standards may be 
    laid down for the same stream or well or for different streams or wells, 
    having regard to the quality of water, flow characteristics of the stream or 
    well and the nature of the use of the water in such stream or well or 
    streams or wells;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    plan and cause to be executed a 
    nation-wide programme for the prevention, control or abatement of water 
    pollution;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    perform such other functions as 
    may be prescribed.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Board may establish or recognize a laboratory or laboratories to enable the 
    Board to perform its functions under this section efficiently, including the 
    analysis of samples of water from any stream or well or of samples of any 
    sewage or trade effluents.  
 
 

 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Functions of State Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of this Act, the functions of a State Board shall 
    be—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    to plan a comprehensive programme 
    for the prevention, control or abatement of pollution of streams and wells 
    in the State and to secure the execution thereof;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    to advise the State Government on 
    any matter concerning the prevention, control or abatement of water 
    pollution;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    to collect and disseminate 
    information relating to water pollution and the prevention, control or 
    abatement thereof;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    to encourage, conduct and 
    participate investigations and research relating to problems of water 
    pollution and prevention, control or abatement of water pollution;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    to collaborate with the Central 
    Board in organizing the training of persons engaged or to be engaged in 
    programmes relating to prevention, control or abatement of water pollution 
    and to organise mass education programmes relating thereto;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    to inspect sewage or trade 
    effluents, works and plants for the treatment of sewage and trade effluents 
    and to review plans, specifications or other data relating to plants set up 
    for the treatment of water, works for the purification thereof and the 
    system for the disposal of sewage or trade effluents or in connection with 
    the grant of any consent as required by this Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    to lay down, modify or annul 
    effluent standards for the sewage and trade effluents and for the quality of 
    receiving waters (not being water in an inter-State stream) resulting from 
    the discharge of effluents and to classify waters of the State;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    to evolve economical and reliable 
    methods of treatment of sewage and trade effluents, having regard to the 
    peculiar conditions of soils, climate and water resources of different 
    regions and more especially the prevailing flow characteristics of water in 
    streams and wells which render it impossible to attain even the minimum 
    degree of dilution;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    to evolve methods of utilisation 
    of sewage and suitable trade effluents in agriculture;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>    to evolve efficient methods of 
    disposal of sewage and trade effluents on land, as are necessary on account 
    of the predominant conditions of scant stream flows that do not provide for 
    major part of the year the minimum degree of dilution;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>    to lay down standards of 
    treatment of sewage and trade effluents to be discharged into any particular 
    stream taking into account the minimum fair weather dilution available in 
    that stream and the tolerance limits of pollution permissible in the water 
    of the stream, after the discharge of such effluents;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>    to make, vary or revoke any 
    order—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    for the prevention, control or 
    abatement of discharges of waste into streams or wells;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    requiring any person concerned 
    to construct new systems for the disposal of sewage and trade effluents or 
    to modify, alter or extend any such existing system or to adopt such 
    remedial measures as are necessary to prevent, control or abate water 
    pollution;  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number>    to lay down effluent standards to 
    be complied with by persons while causing discharge of sewage or sullage or 
    both and to lay down, modify or annul effluent standards for the sewage and 
    trade effluents;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>n</number>    to advise the State Government 
    with respect to the location of any industry the carrying on of which is 
    likely to pollute a stream or well;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>o</number>    to perform such other functions 
    as may be prescribed or as may, from time to time, be entrusted to it by the 
    Central Board or the State Government.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Board may establish or recognise a laboratory or laboratories to enable the 
    Board to perform its functions under this section efficiently, including the 
    analysis of samples of water from any stream or well or of samples of any 
    sewage or trade effluents.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Powers to give directions.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
    In the performance of its functions under this Act—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the Central Board shall be bound 
    by such directions in writing as the Central Government may give to it; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    every State Board shall be bound 
    by such directions in writing as the Central Board or the State Government 
    may give to it:  
 
Provided 
    that where a direction given by the State Government is inconsistent with 
    the direction given by the Central Board, the matter shall be referred to 
    the Central Government for its decision.  
 


    2[(2) Where the 
    Central Government is of the opinion that any State Board has defaulted in 
    complying with any directions given by the Central Board under sub-section 
    (1) and as a result of such default a grave emergency has arisen and it is 
    necessary or expedient so to do in the public interest, it may, by order, 
    direct the Central Board to perform any of the functions of the State Board 
    in relation to such area for such period and for such purposes, as may be 
    specified in the order.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Where the Central Board performs any of the functions of the State Board in 
    pursuance of a direction under sub-section (2), the expenses, if any, 
    incurred by the Central Board with respect to the performance of such 
    functions may, if the State Board is empowered to recover such expenses, be 
    recovered by the Central Board with interest (at such reasonable rate as the 
    Central Government may, by order, fix) from the date when a demand for such 
    expenses is made until it is paid from the person or persons concerned as 
    arrears of land revenue or of public demand.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> For 
    the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that any directions to perform 
    the functions of any State Board given under sub-section (2) in respect of 
    any area would not preclude the State Board from performing such functions 
    in any other area in the State or any of its other functions in that area.]  
 
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Power of State Government to restrict the application of the Act to certain 
    areas.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, if the State Government, 
    after consultation with, or on the recommendation of, the State Board, is of 
    opinion that the provisions of this Act need not apply to entire State, it 
    may, by notification in the Official Gazette, restrict the application of 
    this Act to such area or areas as may be declared therein as water 
    pollution, prevention and control area or areas and thereupon the provisions 
    of this Act shall apply only to such area or areas.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Each 
    water pollution, prevention and control area may be declared either by 
    reference to a map or by reference to the line of any watershed or the 
    boundary of any district or partly by one method and partly by another.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    alter any water pollution, 
    prevention and control area whether by way of extension or reduction; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    define a new water pollution, 
    prevention and control area in which may be merged one or more water 
    pollution, prevention and control areas, or any part or parts thereof.  
 

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> 
    Power to obtain information.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    For the purpose of enabling a State Board to perform the functions conferred 
    on it by or under this Act, the State Board or any officer empowered by it 
    in that behalf, may make surveys of any area and gauge and keep records of 
    the flow or volume and other characteristics of any stream or well in such 
    area, and may take steps for the measurement and recording of the rainfall 
    in such area or any part thereof and for the installation and maintenance 
    for those purposes of gauges or other apparatus and works connected 
    therewith, and carry out stream surveys and may take such other steps as may 
    be necessary in order to obtain any information required for the purposes 
    aforesaid.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    State Board may give directions requiring any person who in its opinion is 
    abstracting water from any such stream or well in the area in quantities 
    which are substantial in relation to the flow or volume of that stream or 
    well or is discharging sewage or trade effluent into any such stream or 
    well, to give such information as to the abstraction or the discharge at 
    such times and in such form as may be specified in the directions.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Without prejudice to the provisions of sub-section (2), a State Board may, 
    with a view to preventing or controlling pollution of water, give directions 
    requiring any person in charge of any establishment where any 

    1[industry, operation 
    or process, or treatment and disposal system] is carried on, to furnish to 
    it information regarding the construction, installation or operation of such 
    establishment or of any disposal system or of any extension or addition 
    thereto in such establishment and such other particulars as may be 
    prescribed.  
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>21</number> 
    Power to take samples of effluents and procedure to be followed in 
    connection therewith.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A State Board or any officer empowered by it in this behalf shall have power 
    to take for the purpose of analysis samples of water from any stream or well 
    or samples of any sewage or trade effluent which is passing from any plant 
    or vessel or from or over any place into any such stream or well.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    result of any analysis of a sample of any sewage or trade effluent taken 
    under sub-section (1) shall not be admissible in evidence in any legal 
    proceeding unless the provisions of sub-sections (3), (4) and (5) are 
    complied with.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of sub-sections (4) and (5), when a sample 
    (composite or otherwise as may be warranted by the process used) of any 
    sewage or trade effluent is taken for analysis under sub-section (1), the 
    person taking the sample shall—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    serve on the person in charge of, 
    or having control over, the plant or vessel or in occupation of the place 
    (which person is hereinafter referred to as the occupier) or any agent of 
    such occupier, a notice, then and there in such form as may be prescribed of 
    his intention to have it so analysed;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    in the presence of the occupier 
    or his agent, divide the sample into two parts;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    cause each part to be placed in a 
    container which shall be marked and sealed and shall also be signed both by 
    the person taking the sample and the occupier or his agent;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    send one container forthwith,—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    in a case where such sample is 
    taken from any area situated in a Union territory, to the laboratory 
    established or recognised by the Central Board under section 16; and  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    in any other case, to the 
    laboratory established or recognised by the State Board under section 17;  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    on the request of the occupier or 
    his agent, send the second container,—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    in a case where such sample is 
    taken from any area situated in a Union territory, to the laboratory 
    established or specified under sub-section (1) of section 51; and  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    in any other case, to the 
    laboratory established or specified under sub-section (1) of section 52.  
 


    1[(4) When a sample of 
    any sewage or trade affluent is taken for analysis under sub-section (1) and 
    the person taking the sample serves on the occupier or his agent, a notice 
    under clause (a) of sub-section (3) and the occupier or his agent wilfully 
    absents himself, then,—  
 <subsubsubsection>
<number>a</number>    the sample so taken shall be 
    placed in a container which shall be marked and sealed and shall also be 
    signed by the person taking the sample and the same shall be sent forthwith 
    by such person for analysis to the laboratory referred to in sub-clause (i) 
    or sub-clause (ii), as the case may be, of clause (e) of sub-section (3) and 
    such person shall inform the Government analyst appointed under sub-section 
    (1) or sub-section (2), as the case may be, of section 53, in writing about 
    the wilful absence of the occupier or his agent; and  
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
<number>b</number>    the cost incurred in getting such 
    sample analysed shall be payable by the occupier or his agent and in case of 
    default of such payment, the same shall be recoverable from the occupier or 
    his agent, as the case may be, as an arrear of land revenue or of public 
    demand:  
 
Provided that no such recovery shall be 
    made unless the occupier or, as the case may be, his agent has been given a 
    reasonable opportunity of being heard in the matter.]  
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> When 
    a sample of any sewage or trade effluent is taken for analysis under 
    sub-section (1) and the person taking the sample serves on the occupier or 
    his agent a notice under clause (a) of sub-section (3) and the occupier or 
    his agent who is present at the time of taking the sample does not make a 
    request for dividing the sample into two parts as provided in clause (b) of 
    sub-section (3), then, the sample so taken shall be placed in a container 
    which shall be marked and sealed and shall also be signed by the person 
    taking the sample and the same shall be sent forthwith by such person for 
    analysis to the laboratory referred to in sub-clause (i) or sub-clause (ii), 
    as the case may be, of clause (d) of sub- 
    section (3).  
 
 

 
 

 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Reports of the result of analysis on samples taken under section 21.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where a sample of any sewage or trade effluent has been sent for analysis to 
    the laboratory established or recognised by the Central Board or, as the 
    case may be, the State Board, the concerned Board analyst appointed under 
    sub-section (3) of section 53 shall analyse the sample and submit a report 
    in the prescribed form of the result of such analysis in triplicate to the 
    Central Board or the State Board as the case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On 
    receipt of the report under sub-section (1), one copy of the report shall be 
    sent by the Central Board or the State Board, as the case may be, to the 
    occupier or his agent referred to in section 21, another copy shall be 
    preserved for production before the court in case any legal proceedings are 
    taken against him and the other copy shall be kept by the concerned Board.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Where a sample has been sent for analysis under clause (e) of sub-section 
    (3) or sub-section (4) of section 21 to any laboratory mentioned therein, 
    the Government analyst referred to in that sub-section shall analyse the 
    sample and submit a report in the prescribed form of the result of the 
    analysis in triplicate to the Central Board or, as the case may be, the 
    State Board which shall comply with the provisions of sub-section (2).  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If 
    there is any inconsistency or discrepancy between, or variation in the 
    results of, the analysis carried out by the laboratory established or 
    recognised by the Central Board or the State Board, as the case may be, and 
    that of the laboratory established or specified under section 51 or section 
    52, as the case may be, the report of the latter shall prevail.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Any 
    cost incurred in getting any sample analysed at the request of the occupier 
    or his agent shall be payable by such occupier or his agent and in case of 
    default the same shall be recoverable from him as arrears of land revenue or 
    of public demand.  
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> 
    Power of entry and inspection.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of this section, any person empowered by a State 
    Board in this behalf shall have a right at any time to enter, with such 
    assistance as he considers necessary, any place—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    for the purpose of performing any 
    of the functions of the Board entrusted to him;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    for the purpose of determining 
    whether and if so in what manner, any such functions are to be performed or 
    whether any provisions of this Act or the rules made thereunder or any 
    notice, order, direction or authorisation served, made, given, or granted 
    under this Act is being or has been complied with;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    for the purpose of examining any 
    plant, record, register, document or any other material object or for 
    conducting a search of any place in which he has reason to believe that an 
    offence under this Act or the rules made thereunder has been or is being or 
    is about to be committed and for seizing any such plant, record, register, 
    document or other material object, if he has reason to believe that it may 
    furnish evidence of the commission of an offence punishable under this Act 
    or the rules made thereunder:  
 
Provided 
    that the right to enter under this sub-section for the inspection of a well 
    shall be exercised only at reasonable hours in a case where such well is 
    situated in any premises used for residential purposes and the water thereof 
    is used exclusively for domestic purposes.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    provisions of 

    1[the Code of Criminal 
    Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974)], or, in relation to the State of Jammu and 
    Kashmir, the provisions of any corresponding law in force in that State, 
    shall, so far as may be, apply to any search or seizure under this section 
    as they apply to any search or seizure made under the authority of a warrant 
    issued under 

    2[section 94] of the 
    said Code, or, as the case may be, under the corresponding provisions of the 
    said law.  
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section, “place” includes vessel.  
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Prohibition on use of stream or well for disposal of polluting matter, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of this section,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    no person shall knowingly cause 
    or permit any poisonous, noxious or polluting matter determined in 
    accordance with such standards as may be laid down by the State Board to 
    enter (whether directly or indirectly) into any 
1[stream 
    or well or sewer or on land]; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    no person shall knowingly cause 
    or permit to enter into any stream any other matter which may tend, either 
    directly or in combination with similar matters, to impede the proper flow 
    of the water of the stream in a manner leading or likely to lead to a 
    substantial aggravation of pollution due to other causes or of its 
    consequences.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    person shall not be guilty of an offence under sub-section (1), by reason 
    only of having done or caused to be done any of the following acts, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    constructing, improving or 
    maintaining in or across or on the bank or bed of any stream any building, 
    bridge, weir, dam, sluice, dock, pier, drain or sewer or other permanent 
    works which he has a right to construct, improve or maintain;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    depositing any materials on the 
    bank or in the bed of any stream for the purpose of reclaiming land or for 
    supporting, repairing or protecting the bank or bed of such stream provided 
    such materials are not capable of polluting such stream;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    putting into any stream any sand 
    or gravel or other natural deposit which has flowed from or been deposited 
    by the current of such stream;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    causing or permitting, with the 
    consent of the State Board, the deposit accumulated in a well, pond or 
    reservoir to enter into any stream.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    State Government may, after consultation with, or on the recommendation of, 
    the State Board, exempt, by notification in the Official Gazette, any person 
    from the operation of sub-section (1) subject to such conditions, if any, as 
    may be specified in the notification and any condition so specified may by a 
    like notification be altered, varied or amended.  
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Restrictions on new outlets and new discharges.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of this section, no person shall, without the 
    previous consent of the State Board,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    establish or take any steps to 
    establish any industry, operation or process, or any treatment and disposal 
    system or any extension or addition thereto, which is likely to discharge 
    sewage or trade effluent into a stream or well or sewer or on land (such 
    discharge being hereafter in this section referred to as discharge of 
    sewage); or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    bring into use any new or altered 
    outlet for the discharge of sewage; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    begin to make any new discharge 
    of sewage:  
 
Provided 
    that a person in the process of taking any steps to establish any industry, 
    operation or process immediately before the commencement of the Water 
    (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Amendment Act, 1988, for which no 
    consent was necessary prior to such commencement, may continue to do so for 
    a period of three months from such commencement or, if he has made an 
    application for such consent, within the said period of three months, till 
    the disposal of such application.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> An 
    application for consent of the State Board under sub-section (1) shall be 
    made in such form, contain such particulars and shall be accompanied by such 
    fees as may be prescribed.]  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    State Board may make such inquiry as it may deem fit in respect of the 
    application for consent referred to in sub-section (1) and in making any 
    such inquiry shall follow such procedure as may be prescribed.  
 


    2[(4) The State Board 
    may—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    grant its consent referred to in 
    sub-section (1), subject to such conditions as it may impose, being—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    in cases referred to in clauses 
    (a) and (b) of sub-section (1) of section 25, conditions as to the point of 
    discharge of sewage or as to the use of that outlet or any other outlet for 
    discharge of sewage;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    in the case of a new discharge, 
    conditions as to the nature and composition, temperature, volume or rate of 
    discharge of the effluent from the land or premises from which the discharge 
    or new discharge is to be made; and  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>    that the consent will be valid 
    only for such period as may be specified in the order,  
 
and any such conditions imposed shall be 
    binding on any person establishing or taking any steps to establish any 
    industry, operation or process, or treatment and disposal system of 
    extension or addition thereto, or using the new or altered outlet, or 
    discharging the effluent from the land or premises aforesaid; or 
 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    refuse such consent for reasons 
    to be recorded in writing.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> 
    Where, without the consent of the State Board, any industry, operation or 
    process, or any treatment and disposal system or any extension or addition 
    thereto, is established, or any steps for such establishment have been taken 
    or a new or altered outlet is brought into use for the discharge of sewage 
    or a new discharge of sewage is made, the State Board may serve on the 
    person who has established or taken steps to establish any industry, 
    operation or process, or any treatment and disposal system or any extension 
    or addition thereto, or using the outlet, or making the discharge, as the 
    case may be, a notice imposing any such conditions as it might have imposed 
    on an application for its consent in respect of such establishment, such 
    outlet or discharge.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> 
    Every State Board shall maintain a register containing particulars of the 
    conditions imposed under this section and so much of the register as relates 
    to any outlet, or to any effluent, from any land or premises shall be open 
    to inspection at all reasonable hours by any person interested in, or 
    affected by such outlet, land or premises, as the case may be, or by any 
    person authorised by him in this behalf and the conditions so contained in 
    such register shall be conclusive proof that the consent was granted subject 
    to such conditions.]  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The 
    consent referred to in sub-section (1) shall, unless given or refused 
    earlier, be deemed to have been given unconditionally on the expiry of a 
    period of four months of the making of an application in this behalf 
    complete in all respects to the State Board.  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> For 
    the purposes of this section and sections 27 and 30,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the expression “new or altered 
    outlet” means any outlet which is wholly or partly constructed on or after 
    the commencement of this Act or which (whether so constructed or not) is 
    substantially altered after such commencement;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the expression “new discharge” 
    means a discharge which is not, as respects the nature and composition, 
    temperature, volume, and rate of discharge of the effluent substantially a 
    continuation of a discharge made within the preceding twelve months (whether 
    by the same or a different outlet), so however that a discharge which is in 
    other respects a continuation of previous discharge made as aforesaid shall 
    not be deemed to be a new discharge by reason of any reduction of the 
    temperature or volume or rate of discharge of the effluent as compared with 
    the previous discharge.
 
 
 
 







 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>26</number> 
    Provision regarding existing discharge of sewage or trade effluent.—Where 
    immediately before the commencement of this Act any person was discharging 
    any sewage or trade effluent into a 

    1[stream or well or 
    sewer or on land], the provisions of section 25 shall, so far as may be, 
    apply in relation to such person as they apply in relation to the person 
    referred to in that section subject to the modification that the application 
    for consent to be made under sub-section (2) of that section 

    2[shall be made on or 
    before such date as may be specified by the State Government by notification 
    in this behalf in the Official Gazette].  
 
 

 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>27</number> 
    Refusal or withdrawal of consent by State Board.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    A State Board shall not grant its consent under sub-section (4) of section 
    25 for the establishment of any industry, operation or process, or treatment 
    and disposal system or extension or addition thereto, or to the bringing 
    into use of a new or altered outlet unless the industry, operation or 
    process, or treatment and disposal system or extension or addition thereto, 
    or the outlet is so established as to comply with any conditions imposed by 
    the Board to enable it to exercise its right to take samples of the 
    effluent.]  
 


    2[(2) A State Board 
    may from time to time review—  
 

3[(a) 
       any condition imposed under section 25 or section 26 and may serve on the 
    person to whom a consent under section 25 or section 26 is granted a notice 
    making any reasonable variation of or revoking any such condition;]
 <subsection>
<number>b</number>    the refusal of any consent 
    referred to in sub-section (1) of section 25 or section 26 or the grant of 
    such consent without any condition, and may make such orders as it deems 
    fit.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Any 
    condition imposed under section 25 or section 26 shall be subject to any 
    variation made under sub-section (2) and shall continue in force until 
    revoked under that sub-section.  
 
 








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>28</number> 
    Appeals.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person aggrieved by an order made by the State Board under section 25, 
    section 26 or section 27 may, within thirty days from the date on which the 
    order is communicated to him, prefer an appeal to such authority 
    (hereinafter referred to as the appellate authority) as the State Government 
    may think fit to constitute:  
 
Provided 
    that the appellate authority may entertain the appeal after the expiry of 
    the said period of thirty days if such authority is satisfied that the 
    appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from filing the appeal in time.  
 


    1[(2) An appellate 
    authority shall consist of a single person or three persons as the State 
    Government may think fit, to be appointed by that Government.]  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    form and manner in which an appeal may be preferred under sub-section  (1), 
    the fees payable for such appeal and the procedure to be followed by the 
    appellate authority shall be such as may be prescribed.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> On 
    receipt of an appeal preferred under sub-section (1), the appellate 
    authority shall, after giving the appellant and the State Board an 
    opportunity of being heard, dispose of the appeal as expeditiously as 
    possible.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If 
    the appellate authority determines that any condition imposed, or the 
    variation of any condition, as the case may be, was unreasonable, then,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    where the appeal is in respect of 
    the unreasonableness of any condition imposed, such authority may direct 
    either that the condition shall be treated as annulled or that there shall 
    be substituted for it such condition as appears to it to be reasonable;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    where the appeal is in respect of 
    the unreasonableness of any variation of a condition, such authority may 
    direct either that the condition shall be treated as continuing in force 
    unvaried or that it shall be varied in such manner as appears to it to be 
    reasonable.
 
 
 
 






 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>29</number> 
    Revision.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government may at any time either of its own motion or on an 
    application made to it in this behalf, call for the records of any case 
    where an order has been made by the State Board under section 25, section 26 
    or section 27 for the purpose of satisfying itself as to the legality or 
    propriety of any such order and may pass such order in relation thereto as 
    it may think fit:  
 
Provided 
    that the State Government shall not pass any order under this sub-section 
    without affording the State Board and the person who may be affected by such 
    order a reasonable opportunity of being heard in the matter.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    State Government shall not revise any order made under section 25, 
    section 26, or section 27 where an appeal against that order lies to the 
    appellate authority, but has not been preferred or where an appeal has been 
    preferred such appeal is pending before the appellate authority.  
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>30</number> 
    Power of State Board to carry out certain works.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where under this Act, any conditions have been imposed on any person while 
    granting consent under section 25 or section 26 and such conditions require 
    such person to execute any work in connection therewith and such work has 
    not been executed within such time as may be specified in this behalf, the 
    State Board may serve on the person concerned a notice requiring him within 
    such time (not being less than thirty days) as may be specified in the 
    notice to execute the work specified therein.]  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    the person concerned fails to execute the work as required in the notice 
    referred to in sub-section (1), then, after the expiration of the time 
    specified in the said notice, the State Board may itself execute or cause to 
    be executed such work.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All 
    expenses incurred by the State Board for the execution of the aforesaid 
    work, together with interest, at such rate as the State Government may, by 
    order, fix, from the date when a demand for the expenses is made until it is 
    paid, may be recovered by that Board from the person concerned, as arrears 
    of land revenue, or of public demand.  
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>31</number> 
    Furnishing of information to State Board and other agencies in certain 
    cases.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    If at any place where any industry, operation or process, or any treatment 
    and disposal system or any extension or addition thereto is being carried 
    on, due to accident or other unforeseen act or event, any poisonous, noxious 
    or polluting matter is being discharged, or is likely to be discharged into 
    a stream or well or sewer or on land and, as a result of such discharge, the 
    water in any stream or well is being polluted, or is likely to be polluted, 
    then the person in charge of such place shall forthwith intimate the 
    occurrence of such accident, act or event to the State Board and such other 
    authorities or agencies as may be prescribed.]  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where any local authority operates any sewerage system or sewage works, the 
    provisions of sub-section (1) shall apply to such local authority as they 
    apply in relation to the person in charge of the place where any industry or 
    trade is being carried on.  
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>32</number> 
    Emergency measures in case of pollution of stream or well.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where it appears to the State Board that any poisonous, noxious or polluting 
    matter is present in 

    1[any stream or well 
    or on land by reason of the discharge of such matter in such stream or well 
    or on such land] or has entered into that stream or well due to any accident 
    or other unforeseen act or event, and if the Board is of opinion that it is 
    necessary or expedient to take immediate action, it may for reasons to be 
    recorded in writing, carry out such operations, as it may consider necessary 
    for all or any of the following purposes, that is to say,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    removing that matter from the
    2[stream 
    or well or on land] and disposing it of in such manner as the Board 
    considers appropriate;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    remedying or mitigating any 
    pollution caused by its presence in the stream or well;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    issuing orders immediately 
    restraining or prohibiting the person concerned from discharging any 
    poisonous, noxious or polluting matter 
3[into 
    the stream or well or on land] or from making insanitary use of the stream 
    or well.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    power conferred by sub-section (1) does not include the power to construct 
    any works other than works of a temporary character which are removed on or 
    before the completion of the operations.  
 
 
 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>33</number> 
    Power of Board to make application to courts for restraining apprehended 
    pollution of water in streams or wells.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where it is apprehended by a Board that the water in any stream or well is 
    likely to be polluted by reason of the disposal or likely disposal of any 
    matter in such stream or well or in any sewer or on any land, or otherwise, 
    the Board may make an application to a court, not inferior to that of a 
    Metropolitan Magistrate or a Judicial Magistrate of the first class, for 
    restraining the person who is likely to cause such pollution from so 
    causing.]  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On 
    receipt of an application under sub-section (1) the court may make such 
    order as it deems fit.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Where under sub-section (2) the court makes an order restraining any person 
    from polluting the water in any stream or well, it may in that order—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    direct the person who is likely 
    to cause or has caused the pollution of the water in the stream or well, to 
    desist from taking such action as is likely to cause pollution or, as the 
    case may be, to remove from such stream or well, such matter, and 

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    authorise the Board, if the 
    direction under clause (i) (being a direction for the removal of any matter 
    from such stream or well) is not complied with by the person to whom such 
    direction is issued, to undertake the removal and disposal of the matter in 
    such manner as may be specified by the court.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> All 
    expenses incurred by the Board in removing any matter in pursuance of the 
    authorisation under clause (ii) of sub-section (3) or in the disposal of any 
    such matter may be defrayed out of any money obtained by the Board from such 
    disposal and any balance outstanding shall be recoverable from the person 
    concerned as arrears of land revenue or of public demand.  
 
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>33A</number> Power to 
    give directions.—Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law, 
    but subject to the provisions of this Act, and to any directions that the 
    Central Government may give in this behalf, a Board may, in the exercise of 
    its powers and performance of its functions under this Act, issue any 
    directions in writing to any person, officer or authority, and such person, 
    officer or authority shall be bound to comply with such directions.  
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the avoidance of doubts, it is hereby declared that the power to issue 
    directions under this section includes the power to direct—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    the closure, prohibition or 
    regulation of any industry, operation or process; or  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    the stoppage or regulation of supply of 
    electricity, water or any other service.]
 
 






 



</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>33B</number> Appeal to National Green Tribunal. </title>—Any person aggrieved by,— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> an order or decision of the appellate authority under section 28, made on or after the commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010; or 
 </section><section><number>b</number> an order passed by the State Government under section 29, on or after the commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010; or 
 </section><section><number>c</number> directions issued under section 33A by a Board, on or after the commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, 
</section>
 may file an appeal to the National Green Tribunal established under section 3 of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, in accordance with the provisions of that Act.] 


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>34</number> 
    Contributions by Central Government.—The 
    Central Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in 
    this behalf, make in each financial year such contributions to the Central 
    Board as it may think necessary to enable the Board to perform its functions 
    under this Act.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>35</number> 
    Contributions by State Government.—The 
    State Government may, after due appropriation made by the Legislature of the 
    State by law in this behalf, make in each financial year such contributions 
    to the State Board as it may think necessary to enable that Board to perform 
    its functions under this Act.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>36</number> 
    Fund of Central Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Board shall have its own fund, and all sums which may, from time 
    to time, be paid to it by the Central Government and all other receipts (by 
    way of gifts, grants, donations, benefactions 

    1[fees] or otherwise) 
    of that Board shall be carried to the fund of the Board and all payments by 
    the Board shall be made therefrom.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Central Board may expend such sums as it thinks fit for performing its 
    functions under this Act, 

    2[and, where any law 
    for the time being in force relating to the prevention, control or abatement 
    of air pollution provides for the performance of any function under such law 
    by the Central Board, also for performing its functions under such law] and 
    such sums shall be treated as expenditure payable out of the fund of the 
    Board.  
 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>37</number> 
    Fund of State Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Board shall have its own fund, and the sums which may, from time 
    to time, be paid to it by the State Government and all other receipts (by 
    way of gifts, grants, donations, benefactions 

    1[fees] or otherwise) 
    of that Board shall be carried to the fund of the Board and all payments by 
    the Board shall be made therefrom.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    State Board may expend such sums as it thinks fit for performing its 
    functions under this Act, 

    1[and, where any law 
    for the time being in force relating to the prevention, control or abatement 
    of air pollution provides for the performance of any function under such law 
    by the State Board, also for performing its functions under such law] and 
    such sums shall be treated as expenditure payable out of the fund of that 
    Board.  
 









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>37A</number> Borrowing 
    powers of Board.—A Board may, with the consent of, or in accordance 
    with, the terms of any general or special authority given to it by the 
    Central Government or, as the case may be, the State Government, borrow 
    money from any source by way of loans or issue of bonds, debentures or such 
    other instruments, as it may deem fit, for the performance of all or any of 
    its functions under this Act.]  
 
 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>38</number> 
    Budget.— 
    The Central Board or, as the case may be, the State Board shall, during each 
    financial year, prepare, in such form and at such time as may be prescribed, 
    a budget in respect of the financial year next ensuing showing the estimated 
    receipt and expenditure, and copies thereof shall be forwarded to the 
    Central Government or, as the case may be, the State Government.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>39</number> Annual 
    report.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Board shall, during each financial year, 
    prepare, in such form as may be prescribed, an annual report giving full 
    account of its activities under this Act during the previous financial year 
    and copies thereof shall be forwarded to the Central Government within four 
    months from the last date of the previous financial year and that Government 
    shall cause every such report to be laid before both Houses of Parliament 
    within nine months from the last date of the previous financial year.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every State Board shall, during each financial year, prepare, in such form 
    as may be prescribed, an annual report giving full account of its activities 
    under this Act during the previous financial year and copies thereof shall 
    be forwarded to the State Government within four months from the last date 
    of the previous financial year and that Government shall cause every such 
    report to be laid before the State Legislature within a period of nine 
    months from the last date of the previous financial year.]  
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>40</number> 
    Accounts and audit.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every Board shall maintain proper accounts and other relevant records and 
    prepare an annual statement of accounts in such form as may be prescribed by 
    the Central Government or, as the case may be, the State Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    accounts of the Board shall be audited by an auditor duly qualified to act 
    as an auditor of companies under section 226 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 
    of 1956).  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    said auditor shall be appointed by the Central Government or, as the case 
    may be, the State Government on the advice of the Comptroller and 
    Auditor-General of India.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Every auditor appointed to audit the accounts of the Board under this Act 
    shall have the right to demand the production of books, accounts, connected 
    vouchers and other documents and papers and to inspect any of the offices of 
    the Board.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> 
    Every such auditor shall send a copy of his report together with an audited 
    copy of the accounts to the Central Government or, as case may be, the State 
    Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    Central Government shall, as soon as may be after the receipt of the audit 
    report under sub-section (5), cause the same to be laid before both Houses 
    of Parliament.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The 
    State Government shall, as soon as may be after the receipt of the audit 
    report under sub-section (5), cause the same to be laid before the State 
    Legislature.  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>41</number> Failure to 
    comply with directions under sub-section (2) or sub-section (3) of section 
    20, or orders issued under clause (c) of sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 32 or 
    directions issued under sub-section (2) of section 33 or section 33A.—(1) 
    Whoever fails to comply with the direction given under sub-section (2) or 
    sub-section (3) of section 20 within such time as may be specified in the 
    direction shall, on conviction, be punishable with imprisonment for a term 
    which may extend to three months or with fine which may extend to ten 
    thousand rupees or with both and in case the failure continues, with an 
    additional fine which may extend to five thousand rupees for every day 
    during which such failure continues after the conviction for the first such 
    failure.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Whoever fails to comply with any order issued under clause (c) of 
    sub-section (1) of section 32 or any direction issued by a court under 
    sub-section (2) of section 33 or any direction issued under section 33A 
    shall, in respect of each such failure and on conviction, be punishable with 
    imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than one year and six months 
    but which may extend to six years and with fine, and in case the failure 
    continues, with an additional fine which may extend to five thousand rupees 
    for every day during which such failure continues after the conviction for 
    the first such failure.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If 
    the failure referred to in sub-section (2) continues beyond a period of 
    one year after the date of conviction, the offender shall, on conviction, be 
    punishable with imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than two 
    years but which may extend to seven years and with fine.]  
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>42</number> 
    Penalty for certain acts.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whoever—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    destroys, pulls down, removes, 
    injures or defaces any pillar, post or stake fixed in the ground or any 
    notice or other matter put up, inscribed or placed, by or under the 
    authority of the Board, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    obstructs any person acting under 
    the orders or directions of the Board from exercising his powers and 
    performing his functions under this Act, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    damages any works or property 
    belonging to the Board, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    fails to furnish to any officer 
    or other employee of the Board any information required by him for the 
    purpose of this Act, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    fails to intimate the occurrence 
    of any accident or other unforeseen act or event under section 31 to the 
    Board and other authorities or agencies as required by that section, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    in giving any information which 
    he is required to give under this Act, knowingly or wilfully makes a 
    statement which is false in any material particular, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    for the purpose of obtaining any 
    consent under section 25 or section 26, knowingly or wilfully makes a 
    statement which is false in any material particular,  
 
shall be punishable with imprisonment 
    for a term which may extend to three months or with fine which may extend to
    1[ten 
    thousand rupees] or with both.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where for the grant of a consent in pursuance of the provisions of section 
    25 or section 26 the use of meter or gauge or other measure or monitoring 
    device is required and such device is used for the purposes of those 
    provisions, any person who knowingly or wilfully alters or interferes with 
    that device so as to prevent it from monitoring or measuring correctly shall 
    be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three months 
    or with fine which may extend to 

    1[ten thousand rupees] 
    or with both.  
 
 

 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>43</number> 
    Penalty for contravention of provisions of section 24.—Whoever 
    contravenes the provisions of section 24 shall be punishable with 
    imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than 

    1[one year and six 
    months] but which may extend to six years and with fine.  
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>44</number> 
    Penalty for contravention of section 25 or section 26.—Whoever 
    contravenes the provisions of section 25 or section 26 shall be punishable 
    with imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than 

    1[one year and six 
    months] but which may extend to six years and with fine.  
 
 

 
 

 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>45</number> 
    Enhanced penalty after previous conviction.—If 
    any person who has been convicted of any offence under section 24 or section 
    25 or section 26 is again found guilty of an offence involving a 
    contravention of the same provision, he shall, on the second and on every 
    subsequent conviction, be punishable with imprisonment for a term which 
    shall not be less than 

    1[two years] but which 
    may extend to seven years and with fine:  
 
Provided 
    that for the purpose of this section no cognizance shall be taken of any 
    conviction made more than two years before the commission of the offence 
    which is being punished.  
 
 
 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>45A</number> Penalty for 
    contravention of certain provisions of the Act.—Whoever contravenes any 
    of the provisions of this Act or fails to comply with any order or direction 
    given under this Act, for which no penalty has been elsewhere provided in 
    this Act, shall be punishable with imprisonment which may extend to three 
    months or with fine which may extend to ten thousand rupees or with both, 
    and in the case of a continuing contravention or failure, with an additional 
    fine which may extend to five thousand rupees for every day during which 
    such contravention or failure continues after conviction for the first such 
    contravention or failure.]  
 
 

 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>46</number> 
    Publication of names of offenders.—If 
    any person convicted of an offence under this Act commits a like offence 
    afterwards it shall be lawful for the court before which the second or 
    subsequent conviction takes place to cause the offender’s name and place of 
    residence, the offence and the penalty imposed to be published at the 
    offender’s expense in such newspapers or in such other manner as the court 
    may direct and the expenses of such publication shall be deemed to be part 
    of the cost attending the conviction and shall be recoverable in the same 
    manner as a fine.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>47</number> 
    Offences by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where an offence under this Act has been committed by a company, every 
    person who at the time the offence was committed was in charge of, and was 
    responsible to the company for the conduct of, the business of the company, 
    as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and 
    shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:  
 
Provided 
    that nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person 
    liable to any punishment provided in this Act if he proves that the offence 
    was committed without his knowledge or that he exercised all due diligence 
    to prevent the commission of such offence.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence 
    under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the 
    offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is 
    attributable to any neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary 
    or other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary or other 
    officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be 
    liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.  
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “company” means any body 
    corporate, and includes a firm or other association of individuals; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    “director” in relation to a firm 
    means a partner in the firm.
 

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>48</number> 
    Offences by Government Departments.—Where 
    an offence under this Act has been committed by any Department of 
    Government, the Head of the Department shall be deemed to be guilty of the 
    offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished 
    accordingly:  
 
Provided 
    that nothing contained in this section shall render such Head of the 
    Department liable to any punishment if he proves that the offence was 
    committed without his knowledge or that he exercised all due diligence to 
    prevent the commission of such offence.  
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>49</number> 
    Cognizance of offences.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    No court shall take cognizance of any offence under this Act except on a 
    complaint made by—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    a Board or any officer authorised 
    in this behalf by it; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    any person who has given notice 
    of not less than sixty days, in the manner prescribed, of the alleged 
    offence and of his intention to make a complaint, to the Board or officer 
    authorised as aforesaid,  
 
and no court inferior to that of a 
    Metropolitan Magistrate or a Judicial Magistrate of the first class shall 
    try any offence punishable under this Act.]
 


    2[2) Where a complaint 
    has been made under clause (b) of sub-section (1), the Board shall, on 
    demand by such person, make available the relevant reports in its possession 
    to that person:  
 
Provided 
    that the Board may refuse to make any such report available to such person 
    if the same is, in its opinion, against the public interest.]  
 


    3[(3)] Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in section 

    4[29 of the Code of 
    Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974)], it shall be lawful for any 


    4[Judicial Magistrate 
    of the first class or for any Metropolitan Magistrate] to pass a sentence of 
    imprisonment for a term exceeding two years or of fine exceeding two 
    thousand rupees on any person convicted of an offence punishable under this 
    Act.  
 
 

 








 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>50</number> 
    Members, officers and servants of Boards to be public servants.—All 
    members, officers and servants of a Board when acting or purporting to act 
    in pursuance of any of the provisions of this Act and the rules made 
    thereunder shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of 
    section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>51</number> 
    Central Water Laboratory.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    establish a Central Water 
    Laboratory; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    specify any laboratory or 
    institute as a Central Water Laboratory, to carry out the functions 
    entrusted to the Central Water Laboratory under this Act.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Central Government may, after consultation with the Central Board, make 
    rules prescribing—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the functions of the Central 
    Water Laboratory;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the procedure for the submission 
    to the said laboratory of samples of water or of sewage or trade effluent 
    for analysis or tests, the form of the laboratory’s report thereunder and 
    the fees payable in respect of such report;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    such other matters as may be 
    necessary or expedient to enable that laboratory to carry out its functions.

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>52</number> 
    State Water Laboratory.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    establish a State Water 
    Laboratory; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    specify any laboratory or 
    institute as a State Water Laboratory, to carry out the functions entrusted 
    to the State Water Laboratory under this Act.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    State Government may, after consultation with the State Board, make rules 
    prescribing—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the functions of the State Water 
    Laboratory;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the procedure for the submission 
    to the said laboratory of samples of water or of sewage or trade effluent 
    for analysis or tests, the form of the laboratory’s report thereon and the 
    fees payable in respect of such report;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    such other matters as may be 
    necessary or expedient to enable that laboratory to carry out its functions.  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>53</number> 
    Analysts.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint 
    such persons as it thinks fit and having the prescribed qualifications to be 
    Government analysts for the purpose of analysis of samples of water or of 
    sewage or trade effluent sent for analysis to any laboratory established or 
    specified under sub-section (1) of section 51.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint such 
    persons as it thinks fit and having the prescribed qualifications to be 
    Government analysts for the purpose of analysis of samples of water or of 
    sewage or trade effluent sent for analysis to any laboratory established or 
    specified under sub-section (1) of section 52.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Without prejudice to the provisions of sub-section (3) of section 12, the 
    Central Board or, as the case may be, the State Board may, by notification 
    in the Official Gazette, and with the approval of the Central Government or 
    the State Government, as the case may be, appoint such persons as it thinks 
    fit and having the prescribed qualifications to be Board analysts for the 
    purpose of analysis of samples of water or of sewage or trade effluent sent 
    for analysis to any laboratory established or recognised under section 16, 
    or, as the case may be, under section 17.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>54</number> 
    Reports of analysts.—Any 
    document purporting to be a report signed by a Government analyst or, as the 
    case may be, a Board analyst may be used as evidence of the facts stated 
    therein in any proceeding under this Act.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>55</number> 
    Local authorities to assist.—All 
    local authorities shall render such help and assistance and furnish such 
    information to the Board as it may require for the discharge of its 
    functions, and shall make available to the Board for inspection and 
    examination such records, maps, plans and other documents as may be 
    necessary for the discharge of its functions.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>56</number> 
    Compulsory acquisition of land for the State Board.—Any 
    land required by a State Board for the efficient performance of its 
    functions under this Act shall be deemed to be needed for a public purpose 
    and such land shall be acquired for the State Board under the provisions of 
    the Land Acquisition Act, 1894 (1 of 1894), or under any other corresponding 
    law for the time being in force.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>57</number> 
    Returns and reports.—The 
    Central Board shall furnish to the Central Government, and a State Board 
    shall furnish to the State Government and to the Central Board such reports, 
    returns, statistics, accounts and other information with respect to its fund 
    or activities as that Government, or, as the case may be, the Central Board 
    may, from time to time, require.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>58</number> 
    Bar of jurisdiction.—No 
    civil court shall have jurisdiction to entertain any suit or proceeding in 
    respect of any matter which an appellate authority constituted under this 
    Act is empowered by or under this Act to determine, and no injunction shall 
    be granted by any court or other authority in respect of any action taken or 
    to be taken in pursuance of any power conferred by or under this Act.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>59</number> 
    Protection of action taken in good faith.—No 
    suit or other legal proceedings shall lie against the Government or any 
    officer of Government or any member or officer of a Board in respect of 
    anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of 
    this Act or the rules made thereunder.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>60</number> 
    Overriding effect.—The 
    provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
    inconsistent therewith contained in any enactment other than this Act.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>61</number> 
    Power of Central Government to supersede the Central Board and Joint Boards.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If at any time the Central Government is of opinion—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    that the Central Board or any 
    Joint Board has persistently made default in the performance of the 
    functions imposed on it by or under this Act; or 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    that circumstances exist which 
    render it necessary in the public interest so to do,  
 
the Central Government may, by notification in 
    the Official Gazette, supersede the Central Board or such Joint Board, as 
    the case may be, for such period, not exceeding one year, as may be 
    specified in the notification:
 
Provided 
    that before issuing a notification under this sub-section for the reasons 
    mentioned in clause (a), the Central Government shall give a reasonable 
    opportunity to the Central Board or such Joint Board, as the case may be, to 
    show cause why it should not be superseded and shall consider the 
    explanations and objections, if any, of the Central Board or such Joint 
    Board, as the case may be.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Upon 
    the publication of a notification under sub-section (1) superseding the 
    Central Board or any Joint Board,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    all the members shall, as from 
    the date of supersession vacate their offices as such;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    all the powers, functions and 
    duties which may, by or under this Act, be exercised, performed or 
    discharged by the Central Board or such Joint Board shall, until the Central 
    Board or the Joint Board, as the case may be, is reconstituted under 
    sub-section (3) be exercised, performed or discharged by such person or 
    persons as to Central Government may direct;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    all property owned or controlled 
    by the Central Board or such Joint Board shall, until the Central Board or 
    the Joint Board, as the case may be, is reconstituted under sub-section (3) 
    vest in the Central Government.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> On 
    the expiration of the period of supersession specified in the notification 
    issued under sub-section (1), the Central Government may—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    extend the period of supersession 
    for such further term, not exceeding six months, as it may consider 
    necessary; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    reconstitute the Central Board or 
    the Joint Board, as the case may be, by fresh nomination or appointment, as 
    the case may be, and in such case any person who vacated his office under 
    clause (a) of sub-section (2) shall not be deemed disqualified for 
    nomination or appointment:
 
Provided 
    that the Central Government may at any time before the expiration of the 
    period of supersession, whether originally specified under sub-section (1) 
    or as extended under this sub-section, take action under clause (b) of this 
    sub-section.
 

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>62</number> 
    Power of State Government to supersede State Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If at any time the State Government is of opinion—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    that the State Board has 
    persistently made default in the performance of the functions imposed on it 
    by or under this Act; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    that circumstances exist which 
    render it necessary in the public interest so to do,  
 
the State Government may, by notification in 
    the Official Gazette, supersede the State Board for such period, not 
    exceeding one year, as may be specified in the notification:
 
Provided 
    that before issuing a notification under this sub-section for the reasons 
    mentioned in clause (a), the State Government shall give a reasonable 
    opportunity to the State Board to show cause why it should not be superseded 
    and shall consider the explanations and objections, if any, of the State 
    Board.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Upon 
    the publication of a notification under sub-section (1) superseding the 
    State Board, the provisions of sub-sections (2) and (3) of section 61 shall 
    apply in relation to the supersession of the State Board as they apply in 
    relation to the supersession of the Central Board or a Joint Board by the 
    Central Government.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>63</number> 
    Power of Central Government to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, simultaneously with the constitution of the 
    Central Board, make rules in respect of the matters specified in sub-section 
    (2):  
 
Provided 
    that when the Central Board has been constituted, no such rule shall be 
    made, varied, amended or repealed without consulting the Board.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the terms and conditions of 
    service of the members (other than the chairman and member-secretary) of the 
    Central Board under sub-section (8) of section 5;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the intervals and the time and 
    place at which meetings of the Central Board or of any committee thereof 
    constituted under this Act, shall be held and the procedure to be followed 
    at such meetings, including the quorum necessary for the transaction of 
    business under section 8, and under sub-section (2) of section 9;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the fees and allowances to be 
    paid to such members of a committee of the Central Board as are not members 
    of the Board under sub-section (3) of section 9;  
 

1[(d) 
       the manner in which and the purposes for which persons may be associated 
    with the Central Board under sub-section (1) of section 10 and the fees and 
    allowances payable to such persons;]  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the terms and conditions of 
    service of the chairman and the member-secretary of the Central Board under 
    sub-section (9) of section 5 and under sub-section (1) of section 12;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    conditions subject to which a 
    person may be appointed as a consulting engineer to the Central Board under 
    sub-section (4) of section 12;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    the powers and duties to be 
    exercised and performed by the chairman and the member-secretary of the 
    Central Board;  
 


    2[***]  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>    the form of the report of the 
    Central Board analyst under sub-section (1) of section 22;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>    the form of the report of the 
    Government analyst under sub-section (3) of section 22;  
 

3[(l) 
       the form in which and the time within which the budget of the Central 
    Board may be prepared and forwarded to the Central Government under section 
    38;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ll</number>    the form in which the annual 
    report of the Central Board may be prepared under section 39;]  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number>    the form in which the accounts of 
    the Central Board may be maintained under section 40;  
 

4[(mm) 
       the manner in which notice of intention to make a complaint shall be 
    given to the Central Board or officer authorised by it under section 49;]  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>n</number>    any other matter relating to the 
    Central Board, including the powers and functions of that Board in relation 
    to Union territories;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>o</number>    any other matter which has to be, 
    or may be, prescribed.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act shall be laid, as 
    soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament while it is 
    in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one 
    session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, 

    5[before the expiry of 
    the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
    aforesaid], both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both 
    Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter 
    have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may 
    be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without 
    prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.  
 
 

 
 

 










 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>64</number> 
    Power of State Government to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government may, simultaneously with the constitution of the State 
    Board, make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act in respect of 
    matters not falling within the purview of section 63:  
 
Provided 
    that when the State Board has been constituted, no such rule shall be made, 
    varied, amended or repealed without consulting that Board.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the terms and conditions of 
    service of the members (other than the chairman and the member-secretary) of 
    the State Board under sub-section (8) of section 5;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the time and place of meetings of 
    the State Board or of any committee of that Board constituted under this Act 
    and the procedure to be followed at such meeting, including the quorum 
    necessary for the transaction of business under section 8 and under 
    sub-section (2) of section 9;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the fees and allowances to be 
    paid to such members of a committee of the State Board as are not members of 
    the Board under sub-section (3) of section 9;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the manner in which and the 
    purposes for which persons may be associated with the State Board under 
    sub-section (1) of section 10 
1[and 
    the fees and allowances payable to such persons];  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the terms and conditions of 
    service of the chairman and the member-secretary of the State Board under 
    sub-section (9) of section 5 and under sub-section (1) of section 12;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    the conditions subject to which a 
    person may be appointed as a consulting engineer to the State Board under 
    sub-section (4) of section 12;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    the powers and duties to be 
    exercised and discharged by the chairman and the member-secretary of the 
    State Board;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    the form of the notice referred 
    to in section 21;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    the form of the report of the 
    State Board analyst under sub-section (1) of section 22;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>    the form of the report of the 
    Government analyst under sub-section (3) of section 22;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>    the form of application for the 
    consent of the State Board under sub-section (2) of section 25, and the 
    particulars it may contain;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>    the manner in which inquiry under 
    sub-section (3) of section 25 may be made in respect of an application for 
    obtaining consent of the State Board and the matters to be taken into 
    account in granting or refusing such consent;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number>    the form and manner in which 
    appeals may be filed, the fees payable in respect of such appeals and the 
    procedure to be followed by the appellate authority in disposing of the 
    appeals under sub-section (3) of section 28;  
 

2[(n) 
       the form in which and the time within which the budget of the State Board 
    may be prepared and forwarded to the State Government under section 38;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>nn</number>    the form in which the annual 
    report of the State Board may be prepared under section 39;]  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>o</number>    the form in which the accounts of 
    the State Board may be maintained under sub-section (1) of section 40;  
 

3[(oo) 
       the manner in which notice of intention to make a complaint shall be 
    given to the State Board or officer authorised by it under section 49;]  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>p</number>    any other matter which has to be, 
    or may be, prescribed.  
 
  







 



</subsection></section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Ins. by Act 19 of 2010, sec. 36 and Sch.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Ins. by Act 44 
    of 1978, sec. 16. tc 
    " 2. Ins. by Act 44 of 1978, sec. 16."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   Ins. by Act 44 
    of 1978, sec. 17. tc 
    " 2. Ins. by Act 44 of 1978, sec. 17."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   Ins. by Act 53 
    of 1988, sec. 19 (w.e.f. 29-9-1988). tc 
    " 3. Ins. by Act 53 of 1988, sec. 19 (w.e.f. 
    29-9-1988)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>   Subs. by Act 53 
    of 1988, sec. 20, for section 39 (w.e.f. 29-9-1988). tc 
    " 4. Subs. by Act 53 of 1988, sec. 20, 
    for section 39 (w.e.f. 29-9-1988)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>   Subs. by Act 53 
    of 1988, sec. 21, for section 41 (w.e.f. 29-9-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>   Subs. by Act 53 
    of 1988, sec. 22, for “one thousand rupees” (w.e.f. 29-9-1988). tc 
    " 1. Subs. by Act 53 of 1988, sec. 22, 
    for “one thousand rupees” (w.e.f. 29-9-1988)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>   Subs. by Act 53 
    of 1988, sec. 23, for “six months” (w.e.f. 29-9-1988). tc 
    " 1. Subs. by Act 53 of 1988, sec. 23, 
    for “six months” (w.e.f. 29-9-1988)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>   Subs. by Act 53 
    of 1988, sec. 23, for “six months” (w.e.f. 29-9-1988). tc 
    " 1. Subs. by Act 53 of 1988, sec. 23, 
    for “six months” (w.e.f. 29-9-1988)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>   Subs. by Act 53 
    of 1988, sec. 24, for “one year” (w.e.f. 29-9-1988). tc 
    " 2. Subs. by Act 53 of 1988, sec. 24, 
    for “one year” (w.e.f. 29-9-1988)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>   Ins. by Act 53 
    of 1988, sec. 25 (w.e.f. 29-9-1988). tc 
    " 3. Ins. by Act 53 of 1988, sec. 25 (w.e.f. 
    29-9-1988)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>   Subs. by Act 53 
    of 1988, sec. 26, for sub-section (1) (w.e.f. 29-9-1988).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>   Subs. by Act 44 
    of 1978, sec. 20, for clause (d). tc 
    " 1. Subs. by Act 44 of 1978, sec. 20, 
    for clause (d)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>   Ins. by Act 44 of 
    1978, sec. 21.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>