<act><tid>888150</tid>
<title>THE COAL MINES PROVIDENT FUND AND MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS 
 (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>1996</year></title>

ACT NO. 23 OF <year>1996</year>
[ 13th August, <year>1996</year>.]

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- seventh Year of 
the 
Republic of India as follows:-

An Act further to amend the Coal Mines Provident Fund 
and 
Miscellaneous Provisions Act, <year>1948</year>.





<article><tid>1717606</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1619808</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Coal Mines Provident Fund and Miscellaneous Provisions (Amendment) 
Act, <year>1996</year>,

</section>

<section><tid>686460</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint,



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1269297</tid>
<number>2</number>Amendment of long title of Act 46 of <year>1948</year>. In the long title 
to the Coal Mines Provident Fund and Miscellaneous Provisions Act, 
 <year>1948</year> (hereinafter referred to as the principal Act), for the words 
" Family Pension Scheme", the words" Pension Scheme" shall be 
substituted.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1112378</tid>
<number> 3</number> Amendment of section 2. In section. 2 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1555450</tid>
<number>a</number>clause (ee) shall be omitted;

</section>

<section><tid>1971883</tid>
<number>b</number>after clause (g), the following Rowing clauses shall be 
inserted, namely:-
' (h)" Pension Fund" means the Pension Fund established 
under sub- section (2) of section 3E;


<subsection><tid>1776204</tid>
<number>i</number>" Pension Scheme" means the Coal Mines Pension 
Scheme framed under sub- section (1) of section 3E;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>90415</tid>
<number>j</number>" superannuation", in relation to an employee who 
is a member of the Pension Scheme, means the attainment, by 
the said employee, of such age as is fixed in the contract or 
conditions of service as the age on the attainment of which 
such employee shall vacate the employment.'.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>787060</tid>
<number>4</number>Substitution of references to certain expressions by certain 
other expressions. In the principal Act, for the expressions" Family 
Pension"," Family Pension Fund"," Family Pension Scheme" and" Coal 
Mines Family Pension Scheme", wherever they occur, the expressions 
" Pension"," Pension Fund"," Pension. Scheme" and" Coal Mines Pension 
Scheme" shall respectively be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1123693</tid>
<number>5</number>Substitution of new section for section 3E. For section 3E of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-


</article>



<article><tid>1259759</tid>
<number> 3E</number> Coal Mines Pension Scheme.
<section><tid>1970369</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may, by notification- in the Official Gazette, 
frame a scheme to be called the Coal Mines Pension Scheme for 
the purpose of providing for-

<subsection><tid>309402</tid>
<number>a</number>superannuation pension, retiring pension, or 
permanent total disablement pension to the persons 
employed in any coal mine or class of coal mines to 
which this Act applies; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>172547</tid>
<number>b</number>widow or widower pension, children pension or 
orphan pension and life assurance benefits, payable to 
the beneficiaries of such employees.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1451772</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in section 
3, there shall be established, as soon as may be after framing 
of the Pension Scheme, a Pension Fund into which there shall 
be paid, from time to time, in respect of every employee who 
is a member of the Pension Scheme,-

<subsection><tid>598089</tid>
<number>a</number>such sums, not exceeding one- fourth, of the 
amount payable to the Fund under sub- section (1) of 
section 10D as the employer' s contribution as well as 
the employee' s contribution, as may be specified in the 
Pension Scheme;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>143927</tid>
<number>b</number>such sums as the Central Government may, after 
due appropriation made by Parliament by law in this 
behalf, specify;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>276615</tid>
<number>c</number>the net assets of the Family Pension Fund as 
existed immediately before the establishment of the 
Pension Fund; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1290168</tid>
<number>d</number>any other contribution which may be made to 
the Pension Fund with the previous approval of the 
Central Government.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>508738</tid>
<number>3</number>On the establishment of the Pension Fund, the Family Pension 
Scheme (hereinafter referred to as the ceased scheme) shall cease to 
operate and all assets of the ceased scheme shall vest in, and shall 
stand transferred to, and all liabilities under the ceased scheme 
shall be enforceable against, the Pension" Fund and the beneficiaries 
under the ceased scheme shall be entitled to draw the benefits. riot 
less than the benefits, they were entitled to under the ceased scheme, 
from the Pension Fund.

</section>

<section><tid>519862</tid>
<number>4</number>The Pension Fund shall vest in and be administered by the 
Board in such manner as may be specified in the Pension Scheme.

</section>

<section><tid>1444575</tid>
<number>5</number>A scheme trained under the provisions of sub- section (1) may 
provide for all or any of the matters specified in the Second 
Schedule.".

<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>179085</tid>
<number>6</number>Substitute--- new section-- section 4-- For section 4 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-


</article>



<article><tid>787060</tid>
<number>4</number>Fund to-- recognise under act of <year>1961</year>. For the 
purposes of the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year>, the Fund shall be deemed to be a 
recognised Provident Fund within the meaning of Part A of the Fourth 
Schedule to that Act.".


</article>



<article><tid>1282244</tid>
<number> 7</number> Amendment section 10. In section 10 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (2B),-
<section><tid>755923</tid>
<number>a</number>for the words and figures" the Code of Criminal 
Procedure, <year>1898</year>", (5 of <year>1898</year>) the words and figures" the Code 
of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year>" (2 of <year>1974</year>) shall be 
substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1837805</tid>
<number>b</number>for the word and figures" section 98", the word 
and figures" section 94" shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>748521</tid>
<number>8</number>Amendment of section. In section 11 of the principal Act, for 
the words and figures" section 230 of the Indian Companies Act, <year>1913</year>", 
 (7 of <year>1913</year>) the words and figures" section 530 of the Companies Act, 
<year>1956</year>" (1 of <year>1956</year>) shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1101225</tid>
<number>9</number>Substitution of new schedule the Second Schedule. For the 
Second Schedule to the principal Act, the following Schedule shall be 
substituted, namely:-

</article>



 </act>