<act><tid>889904</tid>
<title>THE SPECIAL PROTECTION GROUP (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2003</year></title>

ACT NO. 20 OF <year>2003</year>
[ 13th March, <year>2003</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Special Protection Group Act, <year>1988</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- fourth Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>1676905</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title.- This Act may be called the Special Protection Group 
 (Amendment) Act, <year>2003</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>821240</tid>
<number> 2</number> Amendment of section 4.- In the Special Protection Group Act, <year>1988</year> 
 (34 of <year>1988</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the prinicpal Act), in 
sub- section
<section><tid>1034575</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 4, for clause (ii), the following clause  
shall be substituted, namely:-
" (ii) any former Prime Minister or to the members of his immediate 
family-


<subsection><tid>103929</tid>
<number>a</number>for a period of one year from the date on which the former Prime 
Minister ceased to hold office and beyond one year based on the level 
of threat as decided by the Central Government, so however that not 
more than twelve months shall elapse between tw consecutive 
assessments made in regard to the need for proximate security:
Provided that while deciding the level of threat, the Central 
Government shall take into account, among other things, the following 
factors, namely:-


<subsubsection><tid>552402</tid>
<number>A</number>that the threat emanates from any militant or terrorist 
organisation or any other source; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>959282</tid>
<number>B</number>that the threat is of a grave and continuing nature;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1861141</tid>
<number>b</number>on their visits abroad, based on entitlement to proximate security 
and the level of threat as assessed by the Central Government;".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>422763</tid>
<number>3</number>Amendment of section 5.- In section 5 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (2), for the words" Deputy Directors, Assistant Directors, 
Joint Assistant Directors", the words" Inspectors General, Deputy 
Inspectors General, Assistant Inspectors General" sh ll be 
substituted.
----

SUBHASH C. JAIN,

Secy. to the Govt. of India.


</article>



 </act>