<act><tid>903170</tid>
<title>THE INDIAN MEDICINE CENTRAL COUNCIL (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2003</year></title>

NO. 58 OF <year>2003</year>
[ 30th December, <year>2003</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Indian Medicine Central Council Act, <year>1970</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- fourth Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>931051</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>264444</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Indian  
Medicine Central Council (Amendment) Act, <year>2003</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1604101</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 7th day of 
November, <year>2003</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>112167</tid>
<number>2</number>Amendment of section 2.- In the Indian Medicine Central Council Act, 
 <year>1970</year> (48 of <year>1970</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the principal Act), in 
section 2, after clause (e), the following clause shall be inserted, 
namely:-
' (ea)" medical college" means a college of Indian medicine, whether 
known as such or by any other name, in which a person may undergo a 
course of study or training including any post- graduate course of study 
or training which will qualify him for the award of a recognised 
medical qualification;'.



</article>



<article><tid>1519133</tid>
<number>3</number>Substitution of new Chapter for Chapter IIA.- For Chapter IIA of the 
principal Act, the following Chapter shall be substituted, namely:-
CHAPTER IIA

PERMISSION FOR NEW MEDICAL COLLEGE, COURSE, ETC.

' CHAPTER IIA

PERMISSION FOR NEW MEDICAL COLLEGE, COURSE, ETC.



</article>



<article><tid>1900091</tid>
<number> 13A</number> Permission for establishment of new medical college, new course of 
study, etc.-
<section><tid>707485</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act or any  
other law for the time being in force,-

<subsection><tid>744661</tid>
<number>a</number>no person shall establish a medical college; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1183696</tid>
<number>b</number>no medical college shall-

<subsubsection><tid>108987</tid>
<number>i</number>open a new or higher course of study or training, including a post- 
graduate course of study or training, which would enable a student of 
such course or training to qualify himself for the award of any 
recognised medical qualification; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>542444</tid>
<number>ii</number>increase its admission capacity in any course of study or training 
including a post- graduate course of study or training,
except with the previous permission of the Central Government obtained 
in accordance with the provisions of this section.

Explanation 1.- For the purposes of this section," person" includes any 
University or a trust, but does not include the Central Government.

Explanation 2.- For the purposes of this section," admission capacity", 
in relation to any course of study or training, including post- graduate 
course of study or training, in a medical college, means the maximum 
number of students as may be fixed by the Central Government from time 
to time for being admitted to such course or training. 
 (2) Every person or medical college shall, for the purpose of obtaining 
permission under sub- section (1), submit to the Central Government a 
scheme in accordance with the provisions of sub- section (3) and the 
Central Government shall refer the scheme to the Central Council for 
its recommendations.


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>722815</tid>
<number>3</number>The scheme referred to in sub- section (2), shall be in such form 
and contain such particulars and be preferred in such manner and 
accompanied with such fee, as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>554414</tid>
<number>4</number>On receipt of a scheme from the Central Government under sub- 
section (2), the Central Council may obtain such other particulars as 
may be considered necessary by it from the person or the medical 
college concerned, and thereafter, it may,-

<subsection><tid>1457658</tid>
<number>a</number>if the scheme is defective and does not contain necessary 
particulars, give a reasonable opportunity to the person or medical 
college concerned for making a written representation and it shall be 
open to such person or medical college to rectify the defects, if any, 
specified by the Central Council;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1167224</tid>
<number>b</number>consider the scheme, having regard to the factors referred to in 
sub- section (8) and submit it to the Central Government together with 
its recommendations thereon within a period not exceeding six months 
from the date of receipt of the reference from the Central Government.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>83017</tid>
<number>5</number>The Central Government may, after considering the scheme and 
recommendations of the Central Council under sub- section (4) and after 
obtaining, where necessary, such other particulars as may be considered 
necessary by it from the person or medical college concerned and having 
regard to the factors referred to in sub- section (8), either approve 
the scheme with such conditions, if any, as it may consider necessary 
or disapprove the scheme and any such approval shall constitute as a 
permission under sub- section (1):
Provided that no scheme shall be disapproved by the Central Government 
except after giving the person or medical college concerned a 
reasonable opportunity of being heard:

Provided further that nothing in this sub- section shall prevent any 
person or medical college whose scheme has not been approved by the 
Central Government to submit a fresh scheme and the provisions of this 
section shall apply to such scheme as if such scheme had been submitted 
for the first time under sub- section (2).


</section>

<section><tid>1553074</tid>
<number>6</number>Where, within a period of one year from the date of submission of 
the scheme to the Central Government under sub- section (2), no order is 
communicated by the Central Government to the person or medical college 
submitting the scheme, such scheme shall be deemed to have been 
approved by the Central Government in the form in which it was 
submitted, and, accordingly, the permission of the Central Government 
required under sub- section (1) shall also be deemed to have been 
granted.

</section>

<section><tid>634225</tid>
<number>7</number>In computing the time- limit specified in sub- section (6), the time 
taken by the person or medical college concerned submitting the scheme, 
in furnishing any particulars called for by the Central Council, or by 
the Central Government, shall be excluded.

</section>

<section><tid>1396053</tid>
<number>8</number>The Central Council while making its recommendations under clause 
 (b) of sub- section (4) and the Central Government while passing an 
order, either approving or disapproving the scheme under sub- section 
 (5), shall have due regard to the following factors, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1452647</tid>
<number>a</number>whether the proposed medical college or the existing medical 
college seeking to open a new or higher course of study or training, 
would be in a position to offer the minimum standards of medical 
education as prescribed by the Central Council under section 22;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>88071</tid>
<number>b</number>whether the person seeking to establish a medical college or the 
existing medical college seeking to open a new or higher course of 
study or training or to increase its admission capacity has adequate 
financial resources;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>613397</tid>
<number>c</number>whether necessary facilities in respect of staff, equipment, 
accommodation, training, hospital or other facilities to ensure proper 
functioning of the medical college or conducting the new course of 
study or training or accommodating the increased admission capacity 
have been provided or would be provided within the time- limit specified 
in the scheme;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1698309</tid>
<number>d</number>whether adequate hospital facilities, having regard to the number 
of students likely to attend such medical college or course of study or 
training or the increased admission capacity have been provided or 
would be provided within the time- limit specified in the scheme;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>92231</tid>
<number>e</number>whether any arrangement has been made or programme drawn to impart 
proper training to students likely to attend such medical college or 
the course of study or training by persons having recognised medical 
qualifications;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1997348</tid>
<number>f</number>the requirement of manpower in the field of practice of Indian 
medicine in the medical college;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>95557</tid>
<number>g</number>any other factors as may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>99671</tid>
<number>9</number>Where the Central Government passes an order either approving or 
disapproving a scheme under this section, a copy of the order shall be 
communicated to the person or medical college concerned.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1396375</tid>
<number> 13B</number> Non- recognition of medical qualifications in certain cases.-
<section><tid>162912</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Where any medical college is established without the previous 
permission of the Central Government in accordance with the provisions 
of section 13A, medical qualification granted to any student of such 
medical college shall not be deemed to be a recognised medical 
qualification for the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1489824</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any medical college opens a new or higher course of study or 
training including a post- graduate course of study or training without 
the previous permission of the Central Government in accordance with 
the provisions of section 13A, medical qualification granted to any 
student of such medical college on the basis of such study or training 
shall not be deemed to be a recognised medical qualification for the 
purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1134736</tid>
<number>3</number>Where any medical college increases its admission capacity in any 
course of study or training without the previous permission of the 
Central Government in accordance with the provisions of section 13A, 
medical qualification granted to any student of such medical college on 
the basis of the increase in its admission capacity shall not be deemed 
to be a recognised medical qualification for the purposes of this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>295803</tid>
<number> 13C</number> Time for seeking permission for certain existing medical 
colleges.-
<section><tid>1604639</tid>
<number>1</number>If any person has established a medical college or any  
medical college has opened a new or higher course of study or training 
or increased the admission capacity on or before the commencement of 
the Indian Medicine Central Council (Amendment) Act, <year>2003</year>, such person 
or medical college, as the case may be, shall seek, within a period of 
three years from the said commencement, permission of the Central 
Government in accordance with the provisions of section 13A.

</section>

<section><tid>794772</tid>
<number>2</number>If any person or medical college, as the case may be, fails to seek 
permission under sub- section (1), the provisions of section 13B shall 
apply, so far as may be, as if permission of the Central Government 
under section 13A has been refused.'.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1472969</tid>
<number> 4</number> Repeal and saving.-
<section><tid>1764581</tid>
<number>1</number>The Indian Medicine Central Council  
 (Amendment) Ordinance, <year>2003</year> is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1502445</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding the repeal of the Indian Medicine Central Council 
 (Amendment) Ordinance, <year>2003</year>, anything done or any action taken under 
the principal Act, as amended by the said Ordinance shall be deemed to 
have been done or taken under the principal Act, as amended by this Act.
T. K. VISWANATHAN,

Secy. to the Govt. of India.





</section>

</article>



 </act>