<act><tid>909402</tid>
<title>THE REPRESENTATION OF THE PEOPLE (MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS) ACT, <year>1956</year></title>

ACT NO. 88 OF <year>1956</year>
[ 28th December, <year>1956</year>.]

An Act to provide for the removal of disqualifications for 
membership of, and voting at elections to, Parliament and State 
Legislatures, and for certain miscellaneous matters in connection with 
such elections.

[ 28th December, <year>1956</year>.]

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Seventh Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>1566528</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title.
<section><tid>570265</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Representation of the  
People (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act, <year>1956</year>.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Removal of disqualifications.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1134157</tid>
<number> 2</number> Removal of disqualifications.-
<section><tid>1095193</tid>
<number>1</number>Every disqualification for  
membership of Parliament or of the Legislature of a State incurred by 
any person under the Representation of the People Act, <year>1951</year> (43 of  
  <year>1951</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the principal Act) before the 
commencement of the Representation of the People (Second Amendment) 
Act, <year>1956</year>, (27 of <year>1956</year>) for failure to lodge a return of election 
expenses as required by clause (c) of section 7 of the principal Act 
is hereby removed.

</section>

<section><tid>772637</tid>
<number>2</number>Every disqualification for membership of Parliament or of 
the Legislature of a State or for voting at an election incurred by 
any person under the principal Act before the commencement of the 
Representation of the People (Second Amendment) Act, <year>1956</year>, for any 
illegal practice or for any corrupt practice, other than the corrupt 
practice of bribery or undue influence is hereby removed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

[ Amendment of section 7 of Act 43 of <year>1951</year>.]


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1303639</tid>
<number>3</number>[ Amendment of section 7 of Act 43 of <year>1951</year>. 1 Rep. by the 
Repealing and Amending Act, <year>1960</year> (58 of <year>1960</year>), s. 2 and Sch. I.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

[ Special provision for nomination in case of prisoners in 
Portugueseterritory.]

</article>



<article><tid>1467064</tid>
<number>4</number>[ Special provision for nomination in case of prisoners in 
Portuguese territory.] Rep. by s. 2 and Sch. 1, ibid.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Prevention of dispualification for membership of Parliament in certaincases.

</article>



<article><tid>355331</tid>
<number>5</number>Prevention of dispualification for membership of Parliament in 
certain cases. It is hereby declared that the office of member of the 
Council of Advisers associated with the Chief Commissioner of Manipur 
or with the Chief Commissioner of Tripura shall not disqualify the 
holder thereof for being chosen as, or for being, a member of 
Parliament.

</article>



 </act>