<act><tid>9160</tid>
<title>THE MYSORE HIGH COURT (EXTENSION OF JURISDICTION TO COORG) ACT, <year>1952</year></title>

ACT NO. 72 OF <year>1952</year> AN ACT TO EXTEND THE JURISDICTION OF THE HIGH COURT OF MY 
SORE TOTHE STATE OF
[ 18th December, <year>1952</year>.]

BE it enacted by Parliament as follows:-





<article><tid>712160</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1755535</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Mysore High Court (Extension of Jurisdiction to Coorg) Act, <year>1952</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1964726</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date 1 as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>147544</tid>
<number> 2</number> definitions. In this Act,-
<section><tid>1277882</tid>
<number>a</number>appointed day" means the date appointed under sub 
section (2) of section 1 for the coming into force of 
this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>605422</tid>
<number>b</number>Coorg Order" means the Madras High Court 
 (Extension of Jurisdiction to Coorg) Order, <year>1948</year>, made 
by the Governor General on the 28th day of February, 
 <year>1948</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>1831742</tid>
<number>c</number>proceeding in relation to Coorg" means any appeal 
or other proceeding from, or in respect of, any 
judgment, decree or order of any Court or tribunal 
within the State of Coorg.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1662359</tid>
<number> 3</number> Extension of jurisdiction of Mysore High Court to, and 
exclusion of the jurisdiction of madras High Court from, coorg. Save as 
otherwise expressly provided in any other enactment, as from the 
appointed day,-
<section><tid>424035</tid>
<number>a</number>the jurisdiction of the High Court of Mysore shall 
extend to the whole of the State of Coorg; and

</section>

<section><tid>993501</tid>
<number>b</number>the, jurisdiction of the High Court at Madras to 
entertain, or dispose of, any proceeding in relation to 
Coorg, whether such jurisdiction is exercisable by virtue of 
the Coorg Order or of any enactment specified in the 
Schedule, shall cease.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>622415</tid>
<number>4</number>Transfer of pending proceedings to Mysore High Court. Save 
as otherwise expressly provided in any other enactment, all 
proceedings in relation to Coorg pending in the High Court at Madras 
immediately before the appointed day shall by virtue of this

<pagefootnote><pagenum>122</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1st April, <year>1953</year>, vide Notification No. S. R. O. 469, dated the 6th 
March, <year>1953</year>, Gazette of India, <year>1953</year>, Pt. II, See. 3, p. 294.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

Act stand transferred to the High Court of Mysore and shall be dis- 
posed of by it in exercise of the jurisdiction conferred on it by this 
Act.



</article>



<article><tid>663708</tid>
<number>5</number>Effect of orders of Madras High Court. Any judgment, decree 
or order in any proceeding in relation to Coorg made before the 
appointed day by the High Court at Madras shall, for all purposes have 
effect, not only as a judgment, decree or order of that Court, but 
also as if it were a judgment, decree or order made by the High Court 
of Mysore in the exercise of the jurisdiction conferred on it by this 
Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1123618</tid>
<number>6</number>Amendment of certain enactments. The enactments specified in 
the Schedule shall be amended in the manner specified therein.


</article>



<article><tid>1983997</tid>
<number>7</number>Coorg Order to cease to have effect. As from the appointed 
day, the Coorg Order shall cease to have effect.

</article>



 </act>