<act><title>THE NATIONAL GREEN TRIBUNAL ACT, 2010 </title> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> This Act may be called 
the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> It shall come into force on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central Government 
may, by notification, in the Official Gazette, appoint. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> In this Act, unless the 
context otherwise requires,- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> "accident" means an accident involving a fortuitous or sudden or 
  unintended occurrence while handling any hazardous substance or equipment, or 
  plant, or vehicle resulting in continuous or intermittent or repeated exposure 
  to death, of, or, injury to, any person or damage to any property or 
  environment but does not include an accident by reason only of war or civil 
  disturbance; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> "Chairperson" means the Chairperson of the National Green Tribunal; 

 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> "environment" includes water, air and land and the inter-relationship, 
  which exists among and between water, air and land and human beings, other 
  living creatures, plants, micro-organism and property; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> "Expert Member" means a member of the Tribunal who, is appointed as 
  such, and holds qualifications specified in sub-section (2) of  section 5, 
  and, is not a Judicial Member; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> "handling", in relation to any hazardous substance, means the 
  manufacture, processing, treatment, package, storage, transportation, use, 
  collection, destruction, conversion, offering for sale, transfer or the like 
  of such hazardous substance; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> "hazardous substance" means any substance or preparation which is 
  defined as hazardous substance in the Environment (Protection) Act, 1986 (29 
  of 1986), and exceeding such quantity as specified or may be specified by the 
  Central Government under the Public Liability Insurance Act, 1991 (6 of 1991); 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> "injury" includes permanent, partial or total disablement or 
  sickness resulting out of an accident; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> "Judicial Member" means a member of the Tribunal who is qualified to be 
  appointed as such under sub-section (1) of section 5 and includes the 
  Chairperson; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> "notification" means a notification published in the Official Gazette; 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> "person" includes- 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> an individual, 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> a Hindu undivided family, 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number> a company, 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iv</number> a firm, 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>v</number> an association of persons or a body of individuals, whether 
    incorporated or not, 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>vi</number> trustee of a trust, 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>vii</number> a local authority, and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>viii</number> every artificial juridical person, not falling within any of the 
    preceding sub-clauses; </subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number> "prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act; 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number> "Schedule" means Schedules I, II and III appended to this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>m</number> "substantial question relating to environment" shall include an 
  instance where,- 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> there is a direct violation of a specific statutory environmental 
    obligation by a person by which,- 
 
 <subsubsubsection><number>A</number> the community at large other than an individual or group of 
      individuals is affected or likely to be affected by the environmental 
      consequences; or 
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>B</number> the gravity of damage to the environment or property is 
      substantial; or 
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>C</number> the damage to public health is broadly measurable; </subsubsubsection>
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> the environmental consequences relate to a specific activity or a 
    point source of pollution; </subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>n</number> "Tribunal" means the National Green Tribunal established under section 
  3; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>o</number> "workman" has the meaning assigned to it in the Workmen's 
  Compensation Act, 1923 (8 of 1923). </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The words and expressions used in this Act but not defined herein and 
defined in the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1974 (6 of 
1974), the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Cess Act, 1977 (36 of 
1977), the Forest (Conservation) Act, 1980 (69 of 1980), the Air (Prevention and 
Control of Pollution) Act, 1981 (14 of 1981), the Environment (Protection) Act, 
1986 (29 of 1986), the Public Liability Insurance Act, 1991 (6 of 1991) and the 
Biological Diversity Act, 2002 (18 of 2003) and other Acts relating to 
environment shall have the meaning, respectively, assigned to them in those 
Acts. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Establishment of Tribunal. </title>-The Central Government shall, by notification, establish, with effect from such date as may be specified therein, a Tribunal to be known as the National Green Tribunal* to exercise the jurisdiction, powers and authority conferred on such Tribunal by or under this Act. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Composition of Tribunal. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> The Tribunal shall consist 
of,- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> a full-time Chairperson; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> not less than ten but subject not maximum of twenty full-time Judicial 
  Members as the Central Government may, from time to time, notify; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> not less than ten but subject to maximum of twenty full-time Expert 
  Members, as the Central Government may, from time to time notify. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Chairperson of the Tribunal may, if considered necessary, invite any 
one or more person having specialised knowledge and experience in a particular 
case before the Tribunal to assist the Tribunal in that case. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Central Government may, by notification, specify the ordinary place 
or places of sitting of the Tribunal, and the territorial jurisdiction falling 
under each such place of sitting. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Central Government may, in consultation with the Chairperson of the 
Tribunal, make rules regulating generally the practices and procedure of the 
Tribunal including:- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the rules as to the persons who shall be entitled to appear before the 
  Tribunal; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the rules as to the procedure for hearing applications and appeals and 
  other matters [including the circuit procedure for hearing at a place other 
  than the ordinary place of its sitting falling within the jurisdiction 
  referred to in sub-section (3)], pertaining to the applications and appeals; 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the minimum number of Members who shall hear the applications 
  and appeals in respect of any class or classes of applications and appeals: 
  
 Provided that the number of Expert Members shall, in hearing an application 
  or appeal, be equal to the number of judicial Members hearing such application 
  or appeal; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> rules relating to transfer of cases by the Chairperson from one place 
  of sitting (including the ordinary place of sitting) to other place of 
  sitting. 
 <title>Comments </title>
 (Based on Notes on Clauses of the Bill) </subsection>
 This section specifies the composition of the Tribunal. The Tribunal shall 
consist of a full-time Chairperson, such number of full-time Judicial Members 
and Expert Members as the Central Government may, from time to time, notify. 
Sub-section (2) provides that the Chairperson of the Tribunal may, if considered 
necessary, invite any one or more person having specialised knowledge and 
experience in a particular case before the Tribunal to assist the Tribunal in 
that case. Sub-section (3) provides that the Tribunal shall sit at such place or 
places as the Central Government may, by notification, specify. Sub-section (4) 
empowers the Central Government to make rules in consultation with the 
Chairperson of the Tribunal regulating generally the practices and procedure of 
the Tribunal including rules as to the persons who shall be entitled to appear 
before the Tribunal, the procedure for hearing applications and appeals and 
other matters pertaining to the applications and appeals, and the minimum number 
of members who shall hear the applications and appeals in respect of any class 
or classes of applications and appeals. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Qualifications for appointment of Chairperson, Judicial Member and 
Expert Member. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> A person shall not be qualified for appointment as 
the Chairperson or Judicial Member of the Tribunal unless he is, or has been, a 
Judge of the Supreme Court of India or Chief Justice of a High Court: 
 Provided that a person who is or has been a Judge of the High Court shall 
also be qualified to be appointed as a Judicial Member. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> A person shall not be qualified for appointment as an Expert Member, 
unless he,- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> has a degree in Master of Science (in physical sciences or life 
  sciences) with a Doctorate degree or Master of Engineering or Master of 
  Technology and has an experience of fifteen years in the relevant field 
  including five years practical experience in the field of environment and 
  forests (including pollution control, hazardous substance management, 
  environment impact assessment, climate change management; biological diversity 
  management and forest conservation) in a reputed national level institution or 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> has administrative experience of fifteen years including experience of 
  five years in dealing with environmental matters in the Central or a State 
  Government or in a reputed National or State level institution. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Chairperson, Judicial Member and Expert Member of the Tribunal shall 
not hold any other office during their tenure as such. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Chairperson and other Judicial and Expert Members shall not, 
for a period of two year from the date on which they cease to hold office, 
accept any employment in, or connected with the management or administration of, 
any person who has been a party to a proceeding before the Tribunal under this 
Act: 
 Provided that nothing contained in this section shall apply to any employment 
under the Central Government or a State Government or local authority or in any 
statutory authority or any corporation established by or under any Central, 
State or Provincial Act or a Government company as defined in section 617 of the 
Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956). </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Appointment of Chairperson, Judicial Member and Expert Member. 
</title>-
<section><number>1</number> Subject to the provisions of section 5, the Chairperson, Judicial 
Members and Expert Members of the Tribunal shall be appointed by the Central 
Government. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Chairperson shall be appointed by the Central Government in 
consultation with the Chief Justice of India. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Judicial Members and Expert Members of the Tribunal shall be 
appointed on the recommendations of such Selection Committee and in such manner 
as may be prescribed. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Term of office and other conditions of service of Chairperson, 
Judicial Member and Expert Member. </title>-The Chairperson, Judicial Member 
and Expert Member of the Tribunal shall hold office as such for a term of five 
years from the date on which they enter upon their office, but shall not be 
eligible for re-appointment: 
 Provided that in case a person, who is or has been a Judge of the Supreme 
Court, has been appointed as Chairperson or Judicial Member of the Tribunal, he 
shall not hold office after he has attained the age of seventy years: 
 Provided further that in case a person, who is or has been the Chief Justice 
of a High Court, has been appointed as Chairperson or Judicial Member of the 
Tribunal, he shall not hold office after he has attained the age of sixty-seven 
years: 
 Provided also that in case a person, who is or has been a Judge of a High 
Court, has been appointed as Judicial Member of the Tribunal, he shall not hold 
office after he has attained the age of sixty-seven years: 
 Provided also that no Expert Member shall hold office after he has attained 
the age of sixty-five years. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number> Resignation. </title>-The Chairperson, Judicial Member and Expert 
Member of the Tribunal may, by notice in writing under their hand addressed to 
the Central Government, resign their office. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>9</number> Salaries, allowances and other terms and conditions of service. 
</title>-The salaries and allowances payable to, and the other terms and 
conditions of service (including pension, gratuity and other retirement 
benefits) of, the Chairperson, Judicial Member and Expert Member of the Tribunal 
shall be such as may be prescribed: 
 Provided that neither the salary and allowances nor the other terms and 
conditions of service of the Chairperson, Judicial Member and Expert Member 
shall be varied to their disadvantage after their appointment. 
</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>10</number> Removal and suspension of Chairperson, Judicial Member and Expert 
Member. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government may, in consultation with the Chief 
Justice of India, remove from office of the Chairperson or Judicial Member of 
the Tribunal, who,- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> has been adjudged an insolvent; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> has been convicted of an offence which, in the opinion of the Central 
  Government, involves moral turpitude; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> has become physically or mentally incapable; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> has acquired such financial or other interest as is likely to affect 
  prejudicially his functions; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> has so abused his position as to render his continuance in office 
  prejudicial to the public interest. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Chairperson or Judicial Member shall not be removed from his office 
except by an order made by the Central Government after an inquiry made by a 
Judge of the Supreme Court in which such Chairperson or Judicial Member has been 
informed of the charges against him and given a reasonable opportunity of being 
heard in respect of those charges. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Central Government may suspend from office the Chairperson or 
Judicial Member in respect of whom a reference of conducting an inquiry has been 
made to the Judge of the Supreme Court under sub-section (2), until the Central 
Government passes an order on receipt of the report of inquiry made by the Judge 
of the Supreme Court on such reference. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Central Government may, by rules, regulate the procedure for inquiry 
referred to in sub-section (2). 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Expert Member may be removed from his office by an order of the 
Central Government on the grounds specified in sub-section (1) and in accordance 
with the procedure as may be notified by the Central Government: 
 Provided that the Expert Member shall not be removed unless he has been given 
an opportunity of being heard in the matter. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>11</number> To act as Chairperson of Tribunal or to discharge his functions 
in certain circumstances. </title>-In the event of the occurrence of any 
vacancy in the office of the Chairperson of the Tribunal, by reason of his 
death, resignation or otherwise, such Judicial Member of the Tribunal as the 
Central Government may, by notification, authorised in this behalf, shall act as 
the Chairperson until the date on which a new Chairperson is appointed in 
accordance with the provisions of this Act. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>12</number> </title><title>Staff of Tribunal. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
Government shall determine the nature and categories of the officers and other 
employees required to assist the Tribunal in the discharge of its functions. 

 </section><section><number>2</number> The recruitment of the officers and other employees of the Tribunal shall 
be made by the Chairperson in such manner as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The officers and other employees of the Tribunal shall discharge their 
functions under the general superintendence of the Chairperson. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The salaries and allowances and conditions of service of the officers and 
other employees of the Tribunal shall be such as may be prescribed. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>13</number> Financial and administrative powers of Chairperson. </title>-The 
Chairperson of the Tribunal shall exercise such financial and administrative 
powers as may be vested in him under the rules made by the Central Government: 
Provided that the Chairperson may delegate such of his financial and 
administrative powers, as he may think fit, to any Judicial Member or Expert 
Member or officer of the Tribunal subject to the condition that the Member or 
such officer, while exercising such delegated power, continues to act under the 
direction, control and supervision of the Chairperson. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>14</number> Tribunal to settle disputes. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> The Tribunal shall 
have the jurisdiction over all civil cases where a substantial question relating 
to environment (including enforcement of any legal right relating to 
environment), is involved and such question arises out of the implementation of 
the enactments specified in  Schedule I. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Tribunal shall hear the disputes arising from the questions referred 
to in sub-section (1) and settle such disputes and pass order thereon. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> No application for adjudication of dispute under this section shall be 
entertained by the Tribunal unless it is made within a period of six months from 
the date on which the cause of action for such dispute first arose: 
Provided that the Tribunal may, if it is satisfied that the 
applicant was prevented by sufficient cause from filing the application within 
the said period, allow it to be filed within a further period not exceeding 
sixty days. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>15</number> Relief, compensation and restitution. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> The Tribunal 
may, by an order, provide,- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> relief and compensation to the victims of pollution and other 
  environmental damage arising under the enactments specified in the Schedule I 
  (including accident occurring while handling any hazardous substance); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> for restitution of property damaged; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> for restitution of the environment for such area or areas, as the 
  Tribunal may think fit. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The relief and compensation and restitution of property and environment 
referred to in clauses (a), (b) and (c) of sub-section (1) shall be in addition 
to the relief paid or payable under the Public Liability Insurance Act, 1991 (6 
of 1991). 
 </section><section><number>3</number> No application for grant of any compensation or relief or restitution of 
property or environment under this section shall be entertained by the Tribunal 
unless it is made within a period of five years from the date on which the cause 
for such compensation or relief first arose: 
 Provided that the Tribunal may, if it is satisfied that the applicant was 
prevented by sufficient cause from filing the application within the said 
period, allow it to be filed within a further period not exceeding sixty days. 

 </section><section><number>4</number> The Tribunal may, having regard to the damage to public health, 
property and environment, divide the compensation or relief payable under 
separate heads specified in Schedule II so as to provide compensation or relief 
to the claimants and for restitution of the damaged property or environment, as 
it may think fit. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Every claimant of the compensation or relief under this Act shall 
intimate to the Tribunal about the application filed to, or, as the case may be, 
compensation or relief received from, any other court or authority. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>16</number> Tribunal to have appellate jurisdiction. </title>-Any person 
aggrieved by,- 
 
 <section><number>a</number> an order or decision, made, on or after the commencement of the 
  National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, by the appellate authority under section 28 
  of the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1974 (6 of 1974); 
 </section><section><number>b</number> an order passed, on or after the commencement of the National Green 
  Tribunal Act, 2010, by the State Government under section 29 of the Water 
  (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1974 (6 of 1974); 
 </section><section><number>c</number> directions issued, on or after the commencement of the National Green 
  Tribunal Act, 2010, by a Board, under section 33A of the Water (Prevention and 
  Control of Pollution) Act, 1974 (6 of 1974); 
 </section><section><number>d</number> an order or decision made, on or after the commencement of the National 
  Green Tribunal Act, 2010, by the appellate authority under section 13 of the 
  Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Cess Act, 1977 (36 of 1977); 
 </section><section><number>e</number> an order or decision made, on or after the commencement of the National 
  Green Tribunal Act, 2010, by the State Government or other authority under 
  section 2 of the Forest (Conservation) Act, 1980 (69 of 1980); 
 </section><section><number>f</number> an order or decision, made, on or after the commencement of the 
  National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, by the Appellate Authority under section 31 
  of the Air (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1981 (14 of 1981); 
 </section><section><number>g</number> any direction issued, on or after the commencement of the National 
  Green Tribunal Act, 2010, under section 5 of the Environment (Protection) Act, 
  1986 (29 of 1986); 
 </section><section><number>h</number> an order made, on or after the commencement of the National 
  Green Tribunal Act, 2010, granting environmental clearance in the area in 
  which any industries, operations or processes or class of industries, 
  operations and processes shall not be carried out or shall be carried out 
  subject to certain safeguards under the Environment (Protection) Act, 1986 (29 
  of 1986); 
 </section><section><number>i</number> an order made, on or after the commencement of the National Green 
  Tribunal Act, 2010, refusing to grant environmental clearance for carrying out 
  any activity or operation or process under the Environment (Protection) Act, 
  1986 (29 of 1986); 
 </section><section><number>j</number> any determination of benefit sharing or order made, on or after the 
  commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, by the National 
  Biodiversity Authority or a State Biodiversity Board under the provisions of 
  the Biological Diversity Act, 2002 (18 of 2003), may, within a period of 
  thirty days from the date on which the order or decision or direction or 
  determination is communicated to him, prefer an appeal to the Tribunal: 
</section>
 Provided that the Tribunal may, if it is satisfied that the appellant was 
prevented by sufficient cause from filing the appeal within the said period, 
allow it to be filed under this section within a further period not exceeding 
sixty days. 



</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>17</number> Liability to pay relief or compensation in certain cases. 
</title>-
<section><number>1</number> Where death of, or injury to, any person (other than a workman) or 
damage to any property or environment has resulted from an accident or the 
adverse impact of an activity or operation or process, under any enactment 
specified in Schedule I, the person responsible shall be liable to pay such 
relief or compensation for such death, injury or damage, under all or any of the 
heads specified in Schedule II, as may be determined by the Tribunal. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> If the death, injury or damage caused by an accident or the 
adverse impact of an activity or operation or process under any enactment 
specified in Schedule I cannot be attributed to any single activity or operation 
or process but is the combined or resultant effect of several such activities, 
operations and processes, the Tribunal may, apportion the liability for relief 
compensation amongst those responsible for such activities, operations and 
processes on an equitable basis. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Tribunal shall, in case of an accident, apply the principle of no 
fault. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>18</number> </title><title>Application or appeal to Tribunal. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> 
Each application under sections 14 and 15 or an appeal under section 16 shall, 
be made to the Tribunal in such form, contain such particulars, and, be 
accompanied by such documents and such fees as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Without prejudice to the provisions contained in section 16, an 
application for grant of relief or compensation or settlement of dispute may be 
made to the Tribunal by- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the person, who has sustained the injury; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the owner of the property to which the damage has been caused; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> where death has resulted from the environmental damage, by all or any 
  of the legal representatives of the deceased; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> any agent duly authorised by such person or owner of such property or 
  all or any of the legal representatives of the deceased, as the case may be; 
  or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> any person aggreived, including any representative 
  body or organisation; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> the Central Government or a State Government or a Union territory 
  Administration or the Central Pollution Control Board or a State Pollution 
  Control Board or a Pollution Control Committee or a local authority, or any 
  environmental authority constituted or established under the Environment 
  (Protection) Act, 1986 (29 of 1986) or any other law for the time being in 
  force: </subsection>
 Provided that where all the legal representatives of the deceased have not 
joined in any such application for compensation or relief or settlement of 
dispute, the application shall be made on behalf of, or, for the benefit of all 
the legal representatives of the deceased and the legal representatives who have 
not so joined shall be impleaded as respondents to the application: 
 Provided further that the person, the owner, the legal representative, agent, 
representative body or organisation shall not be entitled to make an application 
for grant of relief or compensation or settlement of dispute if such person, the 
owner, the legal representative, agent, representative body or organisation have 
preferred an appeal under section 16. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The application, or as the case may be, the appeal filed before the 
Tribunal under this Act shall be dealt with by it as expeditiously as possible 
and endeavour shall be made by it to dispose of the application, or, as the case 
may be, the appeal, finally within six months from the date of filing of the 
application, or as the case may be, the appeal, after providing the parties 
concerned an opportunity to be heard. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>19</number> Procedure and powers of Tribunal. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> The Tribunal 
shall not be bound by the procedure laid down by the Code of Civil Procedure, 
1908 (5 of 1908) but shall be guided by the principles of natural justice. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Tribunal shall have power to 
regulate its own procedure. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Tribunal shall also not be bound by the rules of evidence contained 
in the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872). 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Tribunal shall have, for the purposes of discharging its functions 
under this Act, the same powers as are vested in a civil court under the Code of 
Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), while trying a suit, in respect of the 
following matters, namely:- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person and 
  examining him on oath; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> requiring the discovery and production of documents; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> receiving evidence on affidavits; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> subject to the provisions of sections 123 and 124 of the Indian 
  Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872), requisitioning any public record or document 
  or copy of such record or document from any office; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses or 
  documents; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> reviewing its decision; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> dismissing an application for default or deciding its ex parte; 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> setting aside any order of dismissal of any 
  application for default or any order passed by it ex parte; 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> pass an interim order (including granting an 
  injunction or stay) after providing the parties concerned an opportunity to be 
  heard, on any application made or appeal filed under this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> pass an order requiring any person to cease and desist from committing 
  or causing any violation of any enactment specified in Schedule I; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number> any other matter which may be prescribed. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>5</number> All proceedings before the Tribunal shall be deemed to be the judicial 
proceedings within the meaning of sections 193, 219 and 228 for the purposes of 
section 196 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860) and the Tribunal shall be 
deemed to be a civil court for the purposes of section 195 and Chapter XXVI of 
the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974). 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>20</number> </title><title>Tribunal to apply certain principles. 
</title>-The Tribunal shall, while passing any order or decision or award, 
apply the principles of sustainable development, the prescautionary principle 
and the polluter pays principle. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>21</number> Decision to be taken by majority. </title>-The decision of the 
Tribunal by majority of Members shall be binding: 
 Provided that if there is a difference of opinion among the Members hearing 
an application or appeal, and the opinion is equally divided, the Chairperson 
shall hear (if he has not heard earlier such application or appeal) such 
application or appeal and decide: 
 Provided further that where the Chairperson himself has heard such 
application or appeal along with other Members of the Tribunal, and if there is 
a difference of opinion among the Members in such cases and the opinion in 
equally devided, he shall refer the matter to other Members of the Tribunal who 
shall hear such application or appeal and decide. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>22</number> Appeal to Supreme Court. </title>-Any person aggrieved by any 
award, decision or order of the tribunal, may, file an appeal to the Supreme 
Court, within ninety days from the date of communication of the award, decision 
or order of Tribunal, to him, on any one or more of the grounds specified in 
section 100 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908): 
 Provided that the Supreme Court may, entertain any appeal after the expiry of 
ninety days, if it is satisfied that the appellant was prevented by sufficience 
cause from preferring the appeal. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>23</number> Cost. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> While disposing of an application or an 
appeal under this Act, the Tribunal shall have power to make such order as to 
costs, as it may consider necessary. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where the Tribunal holds that a claim is not maintainable, or is false or 
vexatious, and such claim is disallowed, in whole or part, the Tribunal may, if 
it so thinks fit, after recording its reasons for holding such claim to be false 
or vexatious, make an order to award costs, including lost benefits due to any 
interim injunction. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>24</number> Deposit of amount payable for damage to environment. 
</title>-
<section><number>1</number> Where any amount by way of compensation or relief is ordered to be 
paid under any award or order made by the Tribunal on the ground of any damage 
to environment, that amount shall be remitted to the authority specified under 
sub-section (3) of section 7A of the Public Liability Insurance Act, 1991 (6 of 
1991) for being credited to the Environmental Relief Fund established under that 
section. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The amount of compensation or relief credited to the Environmental Relief 
Fund under sub-section (1), may, notwithstanding anything contained in the 
Public Liability Insurance Act, 1991 (6 of 1991), be utilised by such persons or 
authority, in such manner and for such purposes relating to environment, as may 
be prescribed. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>25</number> Execution of award or order or decision of Tribunal. 
</title>-
<section><number>1</number> An award or order or decision of the Tribunal under this Act shall 
be executable by the Tribunal as a decree of a civil court, and for this 
purpose, the Tribunal shall have all the powers of a civil court. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), the Tribunal may 
transmit any order or award made by it to a civil court having local 
jurisdiction and such civil court shall execute the order or award as if it were 
a decree made by that court. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where the person responsible, for death of, or injury to any person or 
damage to any property and environment, against whom the award or order is made 
by the Tribunal, fails to make the payment or deposit the amount as directed by 
the Tribunal within the period so specified in the award or order, such amount, 
without prejudice to the filing of complaint for prosecution for an offence 
under this Act or any other law for the time being in force, shall be 
recoverable from the aforesaid person as arrears of land revenue or of public 
demand. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>26</number> Penalty for failure to comply with orders of Tribunal. 
</title>-
<section><number>1</number> Whoever, fails to comply with any order or award or decision of 
the Tribunal under this Act, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term 
which may extend to three years, or with fine which may extend to ten crore 
rupees, or with both and in case the failure or contravention continues, with 
additional fine which may extend to twenty-five thousand rupees for every day 
during which such failure or contravention continues after conviction for the 
first such failure or contravention: 
 Provided that in case a company fails to comply with any order or award or a 
decision of the Tribunal under this Act, such company shall be punishable with 
fine which may extend to twenty-five crore rupees, and in case the failure or 
contravention continues, with additional fine which may extend to one lakh 
rupees for every day during which such failure or contravention continues after 
conviction for the first such failure or contravention. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal 
Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), every offence under this Act shall be deemed to be 
non-cognizable within the meaning of the said Code. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>27</number> Offences by companies. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> Where any offence under this 
Act has been committed by a company, every person who, at the time the offence 
was committed, was directly in charge of, and was responsible to the company for 
the conduct of the business of the company, as well as the company, shall be 
deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against 
and punished accordingly: 
 Provided that nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such 
person liable to any punishment provided in this Act, if he proves that the 
offence was committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised all due 
diligence to prevent the commission of such offence. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence 
under this Act has been committed by the company and it is proved that the 
offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is attributable 
to any neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary or other officer 
of the company, such director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be 
deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against 
and punished accordingly. 
 Explanation. -For the purposes of this section,- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> "company" means any body corporate and includes a firm or other 
  association of individuals; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> "director" in relation to a firm means a partner in the firm. 
</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>28</number> Offences by Government Department. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> Where any 
Department of the Government fails to comply with any order or award or decision 
of the Tribunal under this Act, the Head of the Department shall be deemed to be 
guilty of such failure and shall be liable to be proceeded against for having 
committed an offence under this Act and punished accordingly: 
 Provided that nothing contained in this section shall render such Head of the 
Department liable to any punishment if he proves that the offence was committed 
without his knowledge or that he exercised all due diligence to prevent the 
commission of such offence. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence 
under this Act has been committed by a Department of the Government and it is 
proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or 
is attributable to any neglect on the part of any officer, other than the Head 
of the Department, such officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of that 
offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly. 




</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>29</number> Bar of jurisdiction. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> With effect from the date of 
establishment of the Tribunal under this Act, no civil court shall have 
jurisdiction to entertain any appeal in respect of any matter, which the 
Tribunal is empowered to determine under its appellate jurisdiction. (2) No 
civil court shall have jurisdiction to settle dispute or entertain any question 
relating to any claim for granting any relief or compensation or restitution of 
property damaged or environment damaged which may be adjudicated upon by the 
Tribunal, and no injunction in respect of any action taken or to be taken by or 
before the Tribunal in respect of the settlement of such dispute or any such 
claim for granting any relief or compensation or restitution of property damaged 
or environment shall be granted by the civil court. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>30</number> Cognizance of offences. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> No court shall take 
cognizance of any offence under this Act except on a complaint made by,- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the Central Government or any authority or officer authorised in this 
  behalf by that Government; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> any person who has given notice of not less than sixty days in such 
  manner as may be prescribed, of the alleged offence and of his intention to 
  make a complaint, to the Central Government or the authority or officer 
  authorised as aforesaid. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> No court inferior to that of a Metropolitan Magistrate or, a Judicial 
Magistrate of the first class shall try any offence punishable under this Act. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>31</number> Members and staff of Tribunal to be public servants. 
</title>-The Chairperson, the Judicial and Expert Members, officers and other 
employees of the Tribunal shall be deemed to be public servants within the 
meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860). </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>32</number> Protection of action taken in good faith. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> No suit 
or other legal proceeding shall lie against the employees of the Central 
Government or a State Government or any statutory authority, for anything which 
is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any 
rule or order made thereunder. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the 
Chairperson or, Judicial Member or Expert Member of the Tribunal or any other 
person authorised by the Chairperson or Judicial Member or the Expert Member for 
anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this 
Act or any rule or order made thereunder. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>33</number> Act to have overriding effect. </title>-The provisions of this 
Act, shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent contained in any 
other law for the time being in force or in any instrument having effect by 
virtue of any law other than this Act. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>34</number> Power to amend Schedule I. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government 
may, by notification, amend the Schedule I by including therein any other Act, 
enacted by Parliament having regard to the objective of environmental protection 
and conservation of natural resources, or omitting therefrom any Act already 
specified therein and on the date of publication of such notification, such Act 
shall be deemed to be included in or, as the case may be, omitted from the 
Schedule I. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> A copy of every notification proposed to be issued under 
sub-section (1), shall be laid in draft before each House of Parliament, while 
it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of 
the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in disapproving the issue of the notification or 
both Houses agree in making any modification in the notification, the 
notification shall not be issued or, as the case may be, shall be issued only in 
such modified form as may be agreed upon by both the Houses. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>35</number> Power to make rules. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the provisions 
of this Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:- 

 
 <subsection><number>a</number> rules as to the persons who shall be entitled to appear before the 
  Tribunal under clause (a) of sub-section (4) of section 4; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the procedure for hearing applications and appeals and other matters 
  pertaining to the applications and appeals under clause (b) of sub-section (4) 
  of section 4; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the minimum number of members who shall hear the applications and 
  appeals in respect of any class or classes of applications and appeals under 
  clause (c) of sub-section (4) of section 4; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> the transfer of cases by the Chairperson from one place of sitting 
  (including the ordinary place of sitting) to other place of sitting; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> such selection committee and the manner of appointment of the Judicial 
  Member and Expert Member of the Tribunal under sub-section (3) of section 6; 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> the salaries and allowances payable to, and other terms and conditions 
  of service (including pension, gratuity and other retirement benefits) of, the 
  Chairperson, Judicial Member and Expert Member of the Tribunal under section 
  9; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> the procedure for inquiry of the charges against the Chairperson or 
  Judicial Member of the Tribunal under sub-section (4) of section 10; 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> the recruitment of officers and other employees of the 
  Tribunal under sub­-section (2) section 12; and the salaries and 
  allowances and other conditions of service of the officers and other employees 
  of the Tribunal under sub-section (4) of that section; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> the financial and administrative powers to be exercised by the 
  Chairperson of the Tribunal under section 13; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> the form of application or appeal, the particulars which it shall 
  contain and the documents to be accompanied by and the fees payable under 
  sub-section (1) of section 18; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number> any such matter in respect of which the Tribunal shall have powers of a 
  civil court under clause (k) of sub-section (4) of section 19; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number> the manner and the purposes for which the amount of compensation or 
  relief credited to the Environment Relief Fund shall be utilised under 
  sub-section (2) of section 24; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>m</number> the manner of giving notice to make a complaint under clause (b) 
  of sub-­section (1) of section 30; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>n</number> any other matter which is required to be, or may be, 
  specified by rules or in respect of which provision is to be made by rules. 
  </subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every rule made under this Act by the Central Government shall 
be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, 
while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised 
in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry 
of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both 
Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have 
effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, 
however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to 
the validity of anything previously done under that rule. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>36</number> Amendment of certain enactments. </title>-The enactments 
specified in the Schedule III to this Act shall be amended in the manner 
specified therein and such amendments shall take effect on the date of 
establishment of the Tribunal. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>37</number> Power to remove difficulties</title>.-
<section><number>1</number> If any difficulty 
arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government, 
may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions, not 
inconsistent with the provisions of this Act as may appear to it to be necessary 
for removing the difficulty: Provided that no such order shall be made after 
the expiry of a period of two years from the commencement of this Act. (2) 
Every order made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is 
made, before each House of Parliament.</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>38</number> Repeal and savings. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> The National Environment 
Tribunal Act, 1995 (27 of 1995) and the National Environment Appellate Authority 
Act, 1997 (22 of 1997) are hereby repealed (hereinafter referred to as the 
repealed Act). 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken under the 
said Acts shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the corresponding 
provisions of this Act. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The National Environment Appellate Authority established under 
sub-section (1) of section 3 of the National Environment Appellate Authority 
Act, 1997 (22 of 1997), shall, on the establishment of the National Green 
Tribunal under the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, stand dissolved. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> On the dissolution of the National Environment Appellate Authority 
established under sub-section (1) of section 3 of the National Environment 
Appellate Authority Act, 1997 (22 of 1997), the persons appointed as the 
Chairperson, Vice-chairperson and every other person appointed as Member of the 
said National Environment Appellate Authority and holding office as such 
immediately before the establishment of the National Green Tribunal under the 
National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, shall vacate their respective offices and no 
such Chairperson, Vice-chairperson and every other person appointed as Member 
shall be entitled to claim any compensation for the premature termination of the 
term of his office or of any contract of service. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> All cases pending before the National Environment Appellate Authority 
established under sub-section (1) of section 3 of the National Environment 
Appellate Authority Act, 1997 (22 of 1997) on or before the establishment of the 
National Green Tribunal under the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, shall, on 
such establishment, stand transferred to the said National Green Tribunal and 
the National Green Tribunal shall dispose of such cases as if they were cases 
filed under that Act. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The officers or other employees who have been, immediately before the 
dissolution of the National Environment Appellate Authority appointed on 
deputation basis to the National Environment Appellate Authority, shall, on such 
dissolution, stand reverted to their parent cadre, Ministry or Department, as 
the case may be. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> On the dissolution of the National Environment Appellate Authority, the 
officers and other employees appointed on contract basis under the National 
Environment Appellate Authority and holding office as such immediately before 
such dissolution, shall vacate their respective offices and such officers and 
other employees shall be entitled to claim compensation for three months' pay 
and allowances or pay and allowances for the remaining period of service, 
whichever is less, for the premature termination of term of their office under 
their contract of service. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> The mention of the particular matters referred to in 
sub-sections (2) to (7) shall not be held to prejudice or affect the general 
application of section 6 of the General Clauses Act, 1897 (10 of 1897) with 
regard to the effect of repeal. </section></article><form>
 

THE NATIONAL GREEN TRIBUNAL ACT, 2010 
 

 
 

SCHEDULE I 
 

[ See sections 14(1), 15(1), 17(1)(a), 17(2), 19(4)(j) and 34(1)] 

 

1. The Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1974; 
 

2. The Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Cess Act, 1977; 
 

3. The Forest (Conservation) Act, 1980; 
 

4. The Air (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1981; 
 

5. The Environment (Protection) Act, 1986; 
 

6. The Public Liability Insurance Act, 1991; 
 

7. The Biological Diversity Act, 2002. </form><form>
 

THE NATIONAL GREEN TRIBUNAL ACT, 2010 
 

 
 

SCHEDULE II 
 

[ See sections 15(4) and 17(1)] 
 

HEADS UNDER WHICH COMPENSATION OR RELIEF  
FOR DAMAGE 
MAY BE CLAIMED 
 

(a) Death; 
 

(b) Permanent, temporary, total or partial disability or other injury or 
sickness; 
 

(c) Loss of wages due to total or partial disability or permanent or 
temporary disability; 
 

(d) Medical expenses incurred for treatment of injuries or sickness; 
 

(e) Damages to private property; 
 

(f) Expenses incurred by the Government or any local authority in providing 
relief, aid and rehabilitation to the affected persons; 
 

(g) Expenses incurred by the Government for any administrative or legal 
action or to cope with any harm or damage, including compensation for 
environmental degradation and restoration of the quality of environment; 
 

(h) Loss to the Government or local authority arising out of, or 
connected with, the activity causing any damage; 
 

(i) Claims on account of any harm, damage or destruction to the fauna 
including milch and draught animals and aquatic fauna; 
 

(j) Claims on account of any harm, damage or destruction to flora including 
aquatic flora, crops, vegetables, trees and orchards; 
 

(k) Claims including cost of restoration on account of any harm or 
damage to environment including pollution of soil, air, water, land and 
eco-systems; 
 

(l) Loss and destruction of any property other than private property; 
 

(m) Loss of business or employment or both; 
 

(n) Any other claim arising out of, or connected with, any activity 
of handling of hazardous substance. </form><form>
 

THE NATIONAL GREEN TRIBUNAL ACT, 2010 
 

 
 

SCHEDULE III 
 

(See section 36) 
 

AMENDMENT TO CERTAIN ENACTMENTS 
 

PART I 
 

AMENDMENT TO THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL OF 
POLLUTION) ACT, 1974 
 

(6 of 1974) 
 

Insertion of new section 33B. -After section 33A, the 
following section shall be inserted, namely:- 
 

33B. Appeal to National Green Tribunal .-Any person aggrieved by,- 

 

(a) an order or decision of the appellate authority under section 28, made on 
or after the commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010; or 
 

(b) an order passed by the State Government under section 29, on or after the 
commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010; or 
 

(c) directions issued under section 33A by a Board, on or after the 
commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, 
 

may file an appeal to the National Green Tribunal established under section 3 
of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, in accordance with the provisions of 
that Act.". 
 

PART II 
 

AMENDMENTS TO THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL OF 
POLLUTION) CESS ACT, 1977 
 

(36 of 1977) 
 

1. Amendment of section 13. -In section 13 in sub-section 
(4), for the words "shall be final", the words, figures and letters 
"shall, if no appeal has been filed under section 13A, be final" shall be 
substituted. 
 

2. Insertion of new section 13A. -After 
section 13, the following section shall be inserted, namely:- 
 

" 13A. Appeal to National Green Tribunal.- Any person aggrieved, by 
an order or decision of the appellate authority made under section 13, on or 
after the commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, may file an 
appeal to the National Green Tribunal established under section 3 of the 
National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, in accordance with the provisions of that 
Act.". 
 

PART III 
 

AMENDMENT TO THE FOREST (CONSERVATION) ACT, 1980 

 

(69 of 1980) 
 

Insertion of new section 2A. -After section 2, the following 
section shall be inserted, namely:- 
 

"2A. Appeal to National Green Tribunal .-Any person 
aggrieved, by an order or decision of the State Government or other authority 
made under section 2, on or after the commencement of the National Green 
Tribunal Act, 2010, may file an appeal to the National Green Tribunal 
established under section 3 of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, in 
accordance with the provisions of that Act.". 
 

PART IV 
 

AMENDMENT TO THE AIR (PREVENTION AND CONTROL OF 
POLLUTION) ACT, 1981 
 

(14 of 1981) 
 

Insertion of new section 31B. -After section 31A, the 
following section shall be inserted, namely:- 
 

" 31B. Appeal to National Green Tribunal .-Any person aggrieved by 
an order or decision of the Appellate Authority under section 31, made on or 
after the commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, may file an 
appeal to the National Green Tribunal established under section 3 of the 
National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, in accordance with the provisions of that 
Act.". 
 

PART V 
 

AMENDMENT TO THE ENVIRONMENT (PROTECTION) ACT, 1986 

 

(29 of 1986) 
 

Insertion of new section 5A. -After section 5, the following 
section shall be inserted, namely:- 
 

" 5A. Appeal to National Green Tribunal .-Any person aggrieved by 
any directions issued under section 5, on or after the commencement of the 
National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, may file an appeal to the National Green 
Tribunal established under section 3 of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, 
in accordance with the provisions of that Act.". 
 

PART VI 
 

AMENDMENTS TO THE BIOLOGICAL DIVERSITY ACT, 2002 

 

(18 of 2003) 
 

1. Amendment of section 52. -In section 52, after the 
proviso, the following provisos shall be inserted, namely:- 
 

"Provided further that nothing contained in this section shall apply on and 
from the commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010: 
 

Provided also that any appeal pending before the High Court, before the 
commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, shall continue to be 
heard and disposed of by the High Court as if the National Green Tribunal had 
not been established under section 3 of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010.". 

 

2. Insertion of new section 52A. -After section 52, the 
following section shall be inserted, namely:- 
 

" 52A. Appeal to National Green Tribunal .-Any person aggrieved by 
any determination of benefit sharing or order of the National Biodiversity 
Authority or a State Biodiversity Board under this Act, on or after the 
commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, may file an appeal to the 
National Green Tribunal established under section 3 of the National Green 
Tribunal Act, 2010, in accordance with the provisions of that Act.". 
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Came into force on 18-10-2010, vide S.O. 2569(E), dated 18th October, 2010.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>