<act><title>THE COPYRIGHT RULES, 1958 </title> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title, extent and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Copyright Rules, 1958.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They extend to the 
whole of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> They shall come into 
force on the date on which the Act comes into force.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Interpretations.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  “Act” means the Copyright Act, 
1957 (14 of 1957);
 

      1[(aa) “Copyright business” 
means the business of issuing or granting licence in respect of any class of 
works in which copyright or any other right conferred by the Act subsists, and 
includes the functions referred to in sub-section (3) of section 34;]
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number> “Form” means a form set out in 
the First Schedule;
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  “Schedule” means a Schedule to 
these rules; and
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number> “Section” means a section of the 
Act.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Terms and conditions of 
office of the Chairman and members of the Copyright Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chairman and other members of the Copyright Board shall be appointed for 
such period not exceeding five years as the Central Government may in each case 
deem fit.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Chairman and other 
members of the Copyright Board shall, on the expiry of the period of their 
appointment, be eligible for reappointment.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Chairman or any 
other member of the Copyright Board may resign his office by giving three 
months’ notice in writing to the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Chairman and other 
members of the Copyright Board shall be paid such salary or honorarium as may be 
determined by the Central Government in each case.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> A non-official 
appointed as the Chairman or other member of the Copyright Board shall be 
entitled to travelling allowances for journeys performed on duty and to daily 
allowances for the period spent on duty on the scale provided in the rules 
applicable to the class of officers to which the Central Government may declare 
him to correspond in status:
 
Provided that it shall be 
competent for the Central Government to provide a different scale of such 
allowance if the circumstances of any case so require.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> An official appointed 
as the Chairman or other member of the Copyright Board shall be entitled to such 
travelling allowances for journeys performed on duty and to such daily 
allowances for the period spent on duty as may be admissible to him as such 
official.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The other conditions 
of service of the Chairman and other members of the Copyright Board shall be 
regulated by orders made in that behalf by the Central Government from time to 
time.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Functions of the 
Secretary of the Copyright Board.—The 
Registrar of Copyrights shall perform all secretarial functions relating to the 
Copyright Board under the direction and control of the Chairman of the Copyright 
Board.
 
 
</article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Notice of 
relinquishment.—The 
author of a work desiring to relinquish under section 21 all or any of the 
rights comprised in the copyright in the work shall give notice to the Registrar 
of Copyright in accordance with Form I.
 
 
</article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Application for licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An application for a licence under section 32 to produce and publish a 
translation of a literary or dramatic work in any language shall be made in 
triplicate in accordance with Form II and shall be accompanied by the fee 
prescribed in the Second Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every such application 
shall be in respect of one work only and for translation of that work into one 
language only.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Notice of application.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When any such application has been made, the Copyright Board shall, as soon as 
possible, give notice of the application in the Official Gazette and also, if 
the Copyright Board thinks fit, in one or two newspapers and shall send a copy 
of the notice to the owner of the copyright, wherever practicable.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every such notice 
shall contain the following particulars:—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number> the date of the application;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number> the name, address and nationality 
of the applicant;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number> particulars of the work which is 
to be translated;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number> the date and country of the first 
publication of the work;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>e</number> the name, address and nationality 
of the owner of the copyright as stated in the application;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>f</number> the language in which the work 
is to be translated; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>g</number> the Registration Number of the 
work in the Register of Copyrights, if any.
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number> Consideration of the application. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The Copyright Board shall consider the application after the expiry of not less than one hundred and twenty days from the date of the publication of the notice in the Official Gazette. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Copyright Board shall give an opportunity to the applicant and also, wherever practicable, to any person claiming any interest in the copyright of the work, to be heard and may take such evidence in respect of the application as it thinks fit. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> If more than one application for translation of the work in the same language is pending before the Copyright Board at the expiry of one hundred and twenty days after the publication in the Official Gazette of the application first received, all such applications shall be considered together. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> If the Copyright Board is satisfied that the licence for a translation of the work in the language applied for may be granted to the applicant, or if there are more applicants than one, to such one of the applicants as, in the opinion of the Copyright Board, would best serve the interest of the general public, it shall grant a licence accordingly. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Every such licence shall be subject to the condition provided in sub-section (4) of section 32 relating to the payment of royalties and shall specify— 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the period within which the translation shall be produced and published; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the language in which the translation shall be produced and published; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the rate at which royalties in respect of the copies of the translation of the work sold to the public shall be paid to the owner of the copyright in the work; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> the person or persons to whom such royalties shall be payable. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>6</number> The grant of every such licence shall, as soon as possible, be notified in the Official Gazette and in the newspapers, if any, in which the notice under rule 7 was published and a copy of the licence shall be sent to the other parties concerned. 
</section></article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Manner of determining 
royalties.—The 
Copyright Board shall determine the royalties payable to the owner of the 
Copyright under sub-section (4) of section 32 after taking into consideration—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  the proposed retail price of a 
copy of the translation of the work;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  the prevailing standards of 
royalties in regard to translation of works; and
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  such other matters as may be 
considered relevant by the Copyright Board.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Extension of the 
period of licence.—The 
Copyright Board may, on the application of the licensee and after notice to the 
owner of the copyright, wherever practicable, if it is satisfied that the 
licensee was for sufficient reasons unable to produce and publish the 
translation within the period specified in the li­cence, extend such period.
 
 
</article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Cancellation of 
licence.—The 
Copyright Board may, after giving the licensee an opportunity of being heard, 
cancel the licence on any of the following grounds, namely:—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  that the licensee has failed to 
produce and publish the translation within the time specified in the licence or 
within the time extended on the application of the licensee;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  that the licence was obtained by 
fraud or misrepresentation as to any essential fact;
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  that the licensee has 
contravened any of the terms and conditions of the licence.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 <article><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>11A</number> 
Application for licence.—An application for a licence under section 31A, 
sub-section (1A) of section 32 and section 32A to publish any unpublished work 
or to translate any work in any language or to reproduce any published work 
shall be made in triplicate in accordance with Form 11A and shall be accompanied 
by the fee prescribed in the Second Schedule.]
 
 




</article> 
 The Copyright Rules, 1958
  
 <article><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>11B</number> Every such 
application shall be in respect of one work only and in respect of translation 
of a work into one language only.]
  



</article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>11C</number> 
Notice of application.—
<section><number>1</number> A copy of such application shall be served by 
registered mail on the owner of copyright and if the owner of such copyright is 
not known or is not traceable, a copy of the application shall be served on the 
publisher whose name appears on the work.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Copyright Board 
shall give an opportunity to the applicant and also, wherever practicable, to 
any person claiming any interest in the copyright of the work, to be heard and 
may take such evidence in respect of the application as it thinks fit.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If more than one 
application for translation of the work in the same language or for reproduction 
of the work or for publication of any unpublished work is pending before the 
Copyright Board, all such applications shall be considered together.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If the Copyright Board 
is satisfied that the licence for a translation of the work in the language or 
for reproduction of the work or for publication of unpublished work, applied for 
may be granted to the applicant, or if there are more applicants than one, to 
such one of the applicants, as in the opinion of the Copyright Board, would best 
serve the interests of the general public, it shall grant a licence accordingly.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Every such licence 
shall be subject to the conditions provided in sub-section (7) of section 31A, 
clause (i) of sub-section (4) of section 32 and clause (i) of sub-section (4) of 
section 32A relating to payment of royalties and shall specify—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  the period within which such 
work shall be published;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  the rate at which royalties in 
respect of the copies of such work sold to the public shall be paid to the owner 
of the copyright in the work;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  in a case of translation of the 
work, the language in which the translation shall be produced and published; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  the person or persons to whom 
such royalties shall be payable.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>6</number> The grant of every 
such licence shall, as soon as possible, be notified in the Official Gazette and 
a copy of the licence shall be sent to the other parties concerned.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>11D</number> 
Manner of determining royalties.—The Copyright Board shall determine the 
royalties payable to the owner of the copyright under sub-section (7) of section 
31A, clause 
<section><number>i</number> of sub-section (4) of section 32 and clause (i) of sub-section 
(4) of section 32A after taking into consideration:
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  the proposed retail price of a 
copy of such work;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  the prevailing standards of 
royalties in regard to such works; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  such other matters as may be 
considered relevant by the Copyright Board.]
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>11E</number> 
Extension of the period of licence.—The Copyright Board may, on the 
application of the licensee and after notice to the owner of the copyright, 
wherever practicable, if it is satisfied that the licensee was for sufficient 
reasons unable to produce and publish the translation or reproduce the work or 
publish the unpublished work within the period specified in the licence, extend 
such period.]
 
 



</article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article><footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<number>11F</number> 
Cancellation of licence.—The Copyright Board may, after giving the licensee 
an opportunity of being heard, cancel the licence on any of the following 
grounds, namely:—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  that the licensee has failed to 
produce and publish such work within the time specified in the licence or within 
the time extended on the application of the licensee;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  that the licence was obtained by 
fraud or misrepresentation as to any essential fact;
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  that the licensee has 
contravened any of the terms and conditions of the licence.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>11G</number> 
Notice for termination of licence.—Notice for termination of licence under 
proviso to sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> or sub-section (2) of section 32B shall be served on 
the person holding the licence by the owner of copyright in Form IIB of the 
First Schedule to these rules.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
*<number>12</number> Conditions for 
submission of applications for registration of copyright societies.—
<section><number>1</number> Any 
association of persons, whether incorporated or not, comprising seven or more 
owners of copyright (hereinafter referred to as “the Applicant”) formed for the 
purpose of carrying on the business of issuing or granting li­cences in respect 
of any class of works in which copyright sub­sists or in respect of any other 
right conferred by the Act may file with the Registrar of Copyrights an 
application in Form II-C for submission to the Central Government for grant of 
permission to carry on such business and for its registration as a copyright 
society.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An application under 
sub-rule (1) shall be signed by all the members of the Governing Body (by 
whatever name called) and the Chief Executive of the Applicant (who need not be 
a member of the Applicant).
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
*<number>13</number> Application for 
registration by performing right societies.—A performing right society 
functioning in accordance with the provisions of section 33 on the date 
immediately before the coming into force of the Copyright (Amendment) Act, 1994 
(38 of 1994), and desirous of carrying on the business as a copyright society 
under the Act shall submit an application in Form II-C to the Registrar of 
Copyrights as early as possible but not later than ten months from the date of 
commencement of the said Act.
 
 



</article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
*<number>14</number> Conditions for 
grant of permission to carry on copyright business.—An Applicant including a 
performing right society referred to in rule 13 for registration of it as a 
copyright society shall not be eligible to be considered for such registration 
unless—
 <section>
         <number>i</number>  the instrument by which the 
Applicant is established or incorporated creates a commitment on it to deal with 
only copyright business and other activities ancillary thereto; and
 </section><section>
        <number>ii</number>  the Applicant is willing to 
comply with the provisions of the Act and the rules made thereunder.
 
Explanation.—In 
this rule, and in rule 14A, “instrument” means the memorandum and articles of 
association.
 
 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[<number>14A</number> Documents accompanying applications. </title>—Every application made under rule 12 or rule 13 shall be accompanied by— 
 <section><number>a</number> a true copy of the instrument by which the Applicant is established or incorporated; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> the consent in writing of the individuals named in the application to act as members of the Governing Body (by whatever name called) of the Applicant; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> a declaration containing the objectives of the Applicant, the bodies through which it will function and arrangements for accounting and auditing; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> an undertaking to the effect that the instrument by which the application is established or incorporated provides for conforming the same to the provisions of the Act and these rules. 
  


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[<number>14B</number> Conditions for registration of a copyright society. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> When an application for registration is submitted to the Central Government through the Registrar of Copyrights, that Government may, within sixty days from the date of its receipt by the Registrar of Copyrights either register the Applicant as a Copyright society or, if— 
 <subsection><number>i</number> the Applicant has no professional competence to carry on its business or has not sufficient funds to manage its affairs; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> there exists another copyright society registered under the Act for administering the same class of works and it is functioning well; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> the Central Government has reason to believe that the members of the Applicant are not bona fide  copyright owners or they have not voluntarily signed the instrument setting up the Applicant and the application for registration; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> the application is found to be incomplete in any respect, reject the applications: 
 Provided that no such application shall be rejected without giving the Applicant an opportunity of being heard. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Upon the registration of a copyright society by the Central Government, the Registrar of Copyrights shall issue a Certificate of Registration in Form II-D under his hand and seal. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> On and from the date of its registration as specified in the Certificate of Registration, the copyright society shall be entitled to commence and carry on the permitted copyright business in the name by which it has been so registered. 
  


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[<number>14C</number> Procedure for holding inquiry. </title>—If the Central Government, on a complaint of the Registrar of Copyrights or of any owner of rights, has reason to believe that a copyright society is being managed in a manner detrimental to the interests of the owners of rights concerned, it may after making an inquiry in the following manner, cancel or suspend the registration of the copyright society made under these rules, namely:— 
 <section><number>i</number> The Central Government shall provide a copy of the complaint to the society and require the society to submit within such time as may be specified by the Central Government a written statement of its defence and to state whether it desires to be heard. 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> If, after considering the written statement furnished by the society, the Central Government is satisfied that a prima facie  case is established, it shall order an inquiry into the allegations and appoint an Inquiry Officer not below the rank of a Deputy Secretary to the Government of India for holding the inquiry. 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> On being appointed as such, the Inquiry Officer shall conduct the inquiry having regard to the principles of natural justice. 
 </section><section><number>iv</number> The Inquiry Officer may, if he consider it necessary, engage a Chartered Accountant or an Audit Officer in the office of the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India to assist him in the inquiry. The concerned copyright society shall render all as­sistance and shall make available all such documents as may be called for by the Inquiry Officer to enable him to complete the inquiry within a period of three months or such further time as may be allowed by the Central Government. 
 </section><section><number>v</number> If, according to the findings of the Inquiry Officer, the complaints against the copyright society are found to be true or if the society fails to co-operate with the Inquiry Officer, the Central Government shall cancel the registration of the copyright society. 
  


</section></article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
*<number>14D</number> Suspension of 
registration and appointment of administrator.—If, pending inquiry under 
sub-section (4) of section 33, the Central Government is of the opinion that in 
the interests of the owners of rights concerned, it is necessary so to do, it 
may, by order, suspend the registration of the society for a period not 
exceeding one year as may be specified in that order and shall appoint an 
administrator to discharge the functions of the copyright society.
 
 



</article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
*<number>14E</number> Powers and 
functions of the administrator.—
<section><number>1</number> On the appointment of the administrator 
referred to in rule 14D under sub-section (5) of section 33, all powers of the 
copyright society shall vest in him and all other representative bodies or 
committees of the copyright society other than the General Body shall stand 
dissolved.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The administrator 
shall, within six months before the expiry of the period of suspension, arrange 
election for reconstituting the dissolved bodies failing which, the bodies so 
superseded shall stand revived at the end of the period of suspension for their 
remaining term, excluding the period of suspension.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
*<number>14F</number> Cancellation of 
registration of a copyright society.—The registration of a copyright society 
as such may be cancelled by the Central Government, if—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  any of the particulars furnished 
in the application for registration is, at any time, found to be untrue or 
incorrect and misleading in any manner;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  after holding an inquiry by an 
officer duly appointed by the Central Government and giving the copyright 
society a reasonable opportunity of being heard, the Central Government is 
satisfied that the copyright society is being managed in a manner detrimental to 
the interests of the owners of rights concerned or if the copyright society 
persistently fails to manage its affairs properly or if it persistently fails to 
properly maintain its accounts and get them audited or it uti­lises its funds 
for purposes other than the copyright business.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
*<number>14G</number> Conditions 
subject to which a copyright society may accept authorisation and an owner of 
rights may withdraw such authorisation.—
<section><number>1</number> Copyright society may accept 
from an owner of rights or his duly authorised agent, exclusive authorisation to 
administer any right in a work if such owner or such agent enters into an 
agreement, in writing with the copyright society specifying the rights to be 
administered, the duration for which such rights are authorised to be 
administered the quantum of fees agreed to and the frequency at which such fees 
shall be paid by the copyright society in accordance with its scheme of Tariff 
and Distribution.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The owner of 
copyrights shall without prejudice to the rights under the agreement and subject 
to the condition of a prior notice of sixty days, be free to withdraw such 
authorisation in case the copyright society fails to fulfil its commitments as 
laid down in the agreement.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
*<number>14H</number> Conditions 
subject to which a copyright society may issue licences, collect fees and 
distribute such fees.—
<section><number>1</number> A copyright society may issue licences and collect 
fees in accordance with its Scheme of Tariff in relation to only such works as 
it has been authorised to administer in writing by the owners of rights and for 
the period for which it has been so authorised.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The distribution of 
fees collected shall be subject to a deduction not exceeding fifteen per cent. 
of the collection on account of administrative expenses incurred by the 
copyright society.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article></article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
*<number>14J</number> Tariff Scheme.—As 
soon as may be, but in no case later than three months from the date on which a 
copyright society has become entitled to commence its copyright business, it 
shall frame a scheme of tariff to be called the “Tariff Scheme” setting out the 
nature and quantum of fees or royalties which it proposes to collect in respect 
of such copyright or other rights administered by it.
 
 



</article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
*<number>14K</number> Distribution 
Scheme.—
<section><number>1</number> As soon as may be, but in no case later than three months from 
the date on which a copyright society has become entitled to commence its 
copyright business, it shall frame a scheme to be called the “Distribution 
Scheme” setting out the procedure for collection and distribution of the fees or 
royalties specified in the Tariff Scheme among the owners of copyright or other 
rights whose names are borne on its Register of Owners [maintained under clause 
(i) of rule 14-I] for the approval of such owners.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any distribution under 
the Distribution Scheme shall, as far as possible, be in proportion to the 
income of the copyright society from actual use of the work or works of each 
owner of rights.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
*<number>14L</number> Meeting of 
copyright societies.—
<section><number>1</number> As soon as the Tariff Scheme and the Distribution 
Scheme have been prepared, the copy­right society shall call a general meeting 
of the owners of rights whose names are recorded in the Register of Owners to 
approve the same.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A notice of not less 
than twenty-one clear days shall be given to every such owner of rights of the 
meeting and a copy each of the proposed Tariff Scheme and Distribution Scheme 
shall be annexed to the notice.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The notice under 
sub-rule (2) shall specify that any owner of rights who objects to the Tariff 
Scheme or Distribution Scheme shall be entitled to withdraw the authorisation 
given to the copyright society to administer any right in his work.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The copyright society 
shall keep a record of the owners of rights who have given their approval and 
those who have objected thereto.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Approval by owner of 
rights for the Schemes shall be by a majority of such owners present in person.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The quorum for a 
general meeting shall be one-third of the members.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The copyright society 
shall not amend an approved Tariff Scheme or Distribution Scheme except with the 
consent of the owners obtained at a subsequent general meeting called for the 
purpose.
 
 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[<number>14M</number> Accounts and audit. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Every copyright society shall maintain proper accounts of the fees and royalties collected in a financial year, payments made out of such collections to the owners of rights and other expenditure incurred for meeting administrative expenses and related matters with the approval of the owners of rights: 
 Provided that a copyright society shall not spend more than fifteen per cent. of its collection towards its administrative expenses. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every copyright society shall get its accounts audited by a Chartered Accountant annually. 
  


</section></article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
*<number>14N</number> Annual general 
meeting of owners of rights.—
<section><number>1</number> Every copyright society shall, within a 
period of twelve months from the holding of a meeting in pursuance of sub-rule 
(1) of rule 14L, hold a general meeting of owners of rights, herein called the 
annual general meeting of owners:
 
Provided that a special 
meeting of the owners of rights may also be held, if considered necessary.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The meetings of owners 
of rights shall be held in the town or city in which its Registered or 
Administrative Office is situated and the notice calling the meeting shall 
specify the time, date and address of the venue of the meeting.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
*<number>14-O</number> Documents to be 
presented in the annual general meeting of owners of rights.—Every copyright 
society shall place before its annual general meeting the following documents, 
namely:—
 <section>
         <number>i</number>  an up-to-date list of the 
owners of rights, their names and addresses as recorded in the Register of 
Owners maintained by the copyright society, as provided in sub-rule (1) of rule 
14-I;
 </section><section>
        <number>ii</number>  audited accounts of the society 
for the previous year;
 </section><section>
        <number>iii</number>  the Tariff Scheme;
 </section><section>
       <number>iv</number>  the Distribution Scheme;
 </section><section>
        <number>v</number>  a statement approved by its 
Governing Body (by whatever name called) setting out a full and detailed account 
of all its activities during the previous year; and
 </section><section>
       <number>vi</number>  details of budget estimates for 
the succeeding year and a programme of action for the succeeding year.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
*<number>14P</number> Returns to be 
filed by the copyright societies with the Registrar of Copyrights.—Every 
copyright society shall file a return called the Annual Return with the 
Registrar of Copyrights within one month from the conclusion of each annual 
general meeting of owners setting out the following details, namely:—
 <section>
              <number>i</number>  the date of the annual 
meeting of owners held immediately preceding the filing of the Annual Return, 
the number of owners who attended the meeting in person or by proxy, and the 
minutes of such meeting;
 </section><section>
             <number>ii</number>  the up-to-date list of the 
owners of rights, their names and addresses as recorded in the Register of 
Owners main­tained by the copyright society, as provided in rule 14-I;
 </section><section>
             <number>iii</number>  audited accounts of the 
copyright society;
 </section><section>
            <number>iv</number>  the Tariff Scheme;
 </section><section>
             <number>v</number>  the Distribution Scheme; 
and
 </section><section>
            <number>vi</number>  a statement approved by its 
Governing Body or Board of Directors setting out a full and detailed account of 
all its activities during the year in relation to the rights of the owners.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Form of Register of 
Copyrights.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
The Register of Copyrights shall be kept in six parts as follows:
 
        Part I.  Literary works other than 
computer programmes, tables and compilations including computer data bases and 
Dramatic Works.
 
       Part II.  Musical Works.
 
      Part III.  Artistic Works.
 
       Part IV.  Cinematograph Films.
 
        Part V.  Sound Recordings.
 
       Part VI.  Computer Programmes, tables 
and compilations including computer data bases.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Register of 
Copyrights shall contain the particulars specified in Form III.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Application for 
Registration of Copyright.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every application for registration of copyright shall be made in ac­cordance 
with Form IV and every application for registration of changes in the 
particulars of copyright entered in the Register of Copyrights shall be made in 
accordance with Form V.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every such application 
shall be in respect of one work only, shall be made in triplicate and shall be 
accompanied by the fee specified in the Second Schedule in this behalf.
 

1[(3) The person 
applying for registration shall give notice of his application to every person 
who claims or has any interest in the subject-matter of the copyright or 
disputes the rights of the applicant to it.]
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If no objection to 
such registration is received by the Registrar of Copyrights within thirty days 
of the receipt of the application by him, he shall, if satisfied about the 
correctness of the particulars given in the application, enter such particu­lars 
in the Register of Copyrights.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If the Registrar of 
Copyrights receives any objection for such registration within the time 
specified in sub-rule (4), or, if he is not satisfied about the correctness of 
the particulars given in the application he may, after holding such inquiry as 
he deems fit, enter such particulars of the work in the Register of Copyrights 
as he considers proper.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The Registrar of 
Copyrights shall, as soon as may be, send, wherever practicable, a copy of the 
entries made in the Register of Copyrights to the parties concerned.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Correction of entries 
in the Register of Copyrights.—The 
Registrar of Copyrights may, on his own motion or on an application of any 
interested person, amend or alter the Register of Copyrights in the manner 
specified in section 49 after giving, wherever practicable, to the person 
affected by such amendment or alteration, an opportunity to show cause against 
such amendment or alteration and communicate to such person the amendment or 
alteration made.
 
 
 
 
</article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Indexes.—
<section><number>1</number> 
There shall be kept at the Copyright Office the following indexes for each part 
of the Register of Copyrights, namely:—
 <subsection>
         <number>i</number>  a general Author Index;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  a general Title Index;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>iii</number>  an Author Index of works in 
each language; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iv</number>  a Title Index of works in each 
language.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every index shall be 
arranged alphabetically in the form of cards.
 
 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>19</number> Inspection of the Register of Copyrights and Indexes. </title>—The Register of Copyrights and indexes thereof shall at all reasonable times be open to inspection by any person in such manner and subject to such conditions as the Registrar of Copyrights may specify. 
</article> 
 The Copyright Rules, 1958
  
 <article><number>20</number> Copies and extracts of the 
Register of Copyrights and index­es.—
<section><number>1</number> Any person shall be 
entitled to take copies of, or make extracts from, the Register of Copyrights or 
indexes on payment of the fee specified in the Second Schedule subject to such 
supervision as the Registrar of Copyrights may arrange.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Registrar of Copyrights 
shall, on an application made in that behalf and on payment of the fee specified 
in the Second Schedule, furnish a certified copy of any entries made in the 
Register of Copyrights and indexes thereof.
  </section></article> 
 The Copyright Rules, 1958
  
 <article><number>20</number> Copies and extracts of the 
Register of Copyrights and index­es.—
<section><number>1</number> Any person shall be 
entitled to take copies of, or make extracts from, the Register of Copyrights or 
indexes on payment of the fee specified in the Second Schedule subject to such 
supervision as the Registrar of Copyrights may arrange.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Registrar of Copyrights 
shall, on an application made in that behalf and on payment of the fee specified 
in the Second Schedule, furnish a certified copy of any entries made in the 
Register of Copyrights and indexes thereof.
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>21</number> Making of records. </title>— <footcitenum>14</footcitenum> [
<section><number>1</number> Any person intending to make sound recordings under clause (j) of sub-section (1) of section 52 shall give a notice of such intention to the owner of the copy­right and to the Registrar of Copyrights at least fifteen days in advance of making of the sound recordings and shall pay to the owner of the copyright, along with the notice, the amount of royalties due in respect of all the sound recordings to be made at the rate fixed by the Copyright Board in this behalf and provide copies of all covers and labels with which the sound recordings are to be sold.] 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Such notice shall contain the following information, namely:— 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the particulars of the work in respect of which <footcitenum>14</footcitenum> [sound recording] are to be made; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> alterations <footcitenum>15</footcitenum> [***], if any, which are proposed to be made for the adaptation of the work to the <footcitenum>14</footcitenum> [sound recording]; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the name, address and nationality of the owner of the copyright in the work; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> particulars of the <footcitenum>14</footcitenum> [sound recording] made previously recording the work; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> the number of <footcitenum>14</footcitenum> [sound recording] intended to be made; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> the amount paid to the owner of the copyright in the work by way of royalties and the manner of payment. 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Importation of 
infringing copies.—Every 
application under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 53, shall be made in accordance 
with Form VI and shall be accompanied by the fee specified in the Second 
Schedule.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Procedure for 
examination of infringing copies.—The 
Registrar of Copyrights or the person authorised by him in this behalf shall, in 
taking action under sub-section (2) of section 53, act in collaboration with 
Customs authorities.
 
 
</article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
<number>24</number> Mode of making 
applications, etc.—Every 
application, notice, statement or any other document to be made, given, filed, 
or sent under the Act or under these Rules may, unless otherwise directed by the 
authority concerned, be sent by hand or pre-paid registered post.
 
 
</article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Mode of communication 
by the Copyright Board, etc.—Every 
written intimation from the Copyright Board, the Copyright Office or the 
Registrar of Copyrights shall be deemed to have been duly communicated to any 
person if such intimation is sent to the known address of such person by 
pre-paid registered post.
 
 
</article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Fees.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The fees payable under this Act in respect of any matter shall be as specified 
in the Second Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The fees may be paid 
to the Registrar of Copyrights, New Delhi, by a postal order or Bank draft 
issued by a Scheduled Bank as defined in the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 
of 1934), or by deposit into a Government Treasury or a branch of the Reserve 
Bank of India or the State Bank of India under the head of Account: Major 
Head—“XLVI-Miscellaneous”, Minor Head ‘Naturalisation, Passport and Copyright 
Fees’.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Postal orders and bank 
drafts shall be crossed and drawable in New Delhi.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Payment by bank drafts 
shall not be valid unless the amount of bank commission is included therein.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where payment is made 
by deposit in a Government Treasury or a branch of the Reserve Bank of India or 
the State Bank of India, the challan evidencing the payment shall be sent to the 
authority concerned by pre-paid registered post.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Right of audience.—In 
any proceedings before the Copyright Board or the Registrar of Copyrights any 
party may appear and be heard either in person or by a pleader or other person 
duly authorised by such party.
 
 
</article> 
 
The Copyright Rules, 1958
 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Costs.—The 
costs of, and incidental to, the proceedings before the Copyright Board or the 
Registrar of Copyrights shall be in the discretion of the Copyright Board or the 
Registrar of Copyrights, as the case may be.
 
 
</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>  Rule 11A ins. by 
G.S.R. 602(E), dated 9th August, 1984 (w.e.f. 9-8-1984).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>  Rule 11B ins. 
by G.S.R. 602(E), dated 9th August, 1984 (w.e.f. 9-8-1984).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>  Rule 11C ins. by 
G.S.R. 602(E), dated 9th August, 1984 (w.e.f. 9-8-1984).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>  Rule 11D ins. by 
G.S.R. 602(E), dated 9th August, 1984 (w.e.f. 9-8-1984).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>  Rule 11E ins. by 
G.S.R. 602(E), dated 9th August, 1984 (w.e.f. 9-8-1984).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>  Rule 11F ins. by 
G.S.R. 602(E), dated 9th August, 1984 (w.e.f. 9-8-1984).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>  Rule 11G ins. by 
G.S.R. 602(E), dated 9th August, 1984 (w.e.f. 9-8-1984).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>subs. by G.S.R. 383(E), dated 5th May, 1995, (w.e.f. 10-5-1995).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>subs. by G.S.R. 383(E), dated 5th May, 1995, (w.e.f. 10-5-1995).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>subs. by G.S.R. 383(E), dated 5th May, 1995, (w.e.f. 10-5-1995).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>subs. by G.S.R. 383(E), dated 5th May, 1995, (w.e.f. 10-5-1995).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>  Subs. by  G.S.R. 
383(E), dated 5th May, 1995 (w.e.f. 10-5-1995).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 
435(E), dated 27th April, 1992.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>Subs. by G.S.R. 383(E), dated 5th May, 1995 (w.e.f. 10-5-1995).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>Omitted by G.S.R. 383(E), dated 5th May, 1995 (w.e.f. 10-5-1995).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>