<act><tid>933499</tid>
<title>THE PUNJAB REORGANISATION ACT, <year>1966</year></title>

ACT NO. 31 OF <year>1966</year>
[ 18th September, <year>1966</year>.]

An Act to provide for the reorganisation of the existing State of 
Punjab and for matters connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Seventeenth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--

PART

PRELIMINARY

PART I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1508589</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Punjab Reorganisation 
Act, <year>1966</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>792775</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>234484</tid>
<number>a</number>" Administrator" means the administrator of a Union 
territory appointed by the President under article 239 
of the Constitution;

</section>

<section><tid>1518305</tid>
<number>b</number>" appointed day" means the 1st day of November, <year>1966</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>92327</tid>
<number>c</number>" article" means an article of the Constitution;

</section>

<section><tid>1448793</tid>
<number>d</number>" assembly constituency"," council constituency" and 
" parliamentary constituency" have the same meanings as 
in the Representation of the People Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of  
  <year>1950</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1840763</tid>
<number>e</number>" Delimitation Commission" means the Delimitation 
Commission constituted under section 3 of the 
Delimitation Commission Act, <year>1962</year> (61 of <year>1962</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>612007</tid>
<number>f</number>" existing State of Punjab" means the State of Punjab as 
existing immediately before the appointed day;

</section>

<section><tid>94220</tid>
<number>g</number>" law" includes any enactment, ordinance, regulation, 
order, bye- law, rule, scheme, notification or other 
instrument having, immediately before the appointed 
day, the force of law in the whole or in any part of 
the existing State of Punjab;

</section>

<section><tid>1853557</tid>
<number>h</number>" notified order" means an order published in the 
Official Gazette;

</section>

<section><tid>851046</tid>
<number>i</number>" population ratio", in relation to the States of Haryana 
and Punjab and the Union, means the ratio of 37. 38 to 
54. 84 to 7. 78;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>770</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>450653</tid>
<number>j</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>129076</tid>
<number>k</number>" sitting member", in relation to either House of 
Parliament or of the Legislature of the existing State 
of Punjab, means a person who immediately before the 
appointed day is a member of that House;

</section>

<section><tid>1015370</tid>
<number>l</number>" State of Punjab" means the State with the same name, 
comprising the territories referred to in sub- section 
 (1) of section 6;

</section>

<section><tid>269731</tid>
<number>m</number>" successor State", in relation to the existing State of 
Punjab, means the State of Punjab or Haryana, and 
includes also the Union in relation to the Union 
territory of Chandigarh and the transferred territory;

</section>

<section><tid>1371747</tid>
<number>n</number>" transferred territory" means the territory which on the 
appointed day is transferred from the existing State of 
Punjab to the Union territory of Himachal Pradesh;

</section>

<section><tid>1893351</tid>
<number>o</number>" treasury" includes a sub- treasury; and

</section>

<section><tid>1647298</tid>
<number>p</number>any reference to a district, tahsil or other territorial 
division of the existing State of Punjab shall be 
construed as a reference to the area comprised within 
that territorial division on the 1st day of July, <year>1966</year>.
PART

REORGANISATION OF THE STATE OF PUNJAB

PART II

REORGANISATION OF THE STATE OF PUNJAB




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1650739</tid>
<number> 3</number> Formation of Haryana State.
<section><tid>940795</tid>
<number>1</number>On and from the appointed day,  
there shall be formed a new State to be known as the State of Haryana 
comprising the following territories of the existing State of Punjab, 
namely:--

<subsection><tid>1468869</tid>
<number>a</number>Hissar, Rohtak, Gurgaon, Karnal and Mahendragarh 
districts;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>225106</tid>
<number>b</number>Norwana and Jind tahsils of Sangrur district;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1861945</tid>
<number>c</number>Ambala, Jagadhri and Naraingarh tahsils of Ambala 
district;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>626880</tid>
<number>d</number>Pinjore kanungo circle of Kharar tahsil of Ambala 
district; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>835525</tid>
<number>e</number>the territories in Manimajra kanungo circle of Kharar 
tahsil of Ambala district specified in the First 
Schedule,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>771</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

and thereupon the said territories shall cease to form part of the 
existing State of Punjab.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1328276</tid>
<number>2</number>The territories referred to in clause (b) of sub- section (1) 
shall form a separate district known as the Jind district in the State 
of Haryana.

</section>

<section><tid>468776</tid>
<number>3</number>The territories referred to in clauses (c), (d) and (e) of 
sub- section (1) shall form a separate district to be known as Ambala 
district in the State of Haryana and in that district,--

<subsection><tid>1972895</tid>
<number>i</number>the territories referred to in clauses (d) and (e) of 
sub- section (1) shall be included in, and form part of, 
the Naraingarh tahsil, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1131342</tid>
<number>ii</number>the territories referred to in clause (e) of sub- 
section (1) shall be included in, and form part of, 
Pinjore kanungo circle in the Naraingarh tahsil.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1485878</tid>
<number>4</number>Formation of Union territory of Chandigarh. On and from the 
appointed day, there shall be formed a new Union territory to be known 
as the Union territory of Chandigarh comprising such of the 
territories of Manimajra and Manauli kanungo circles of Kharar tahsil 
of Ambala district in the existing State of Punjab as are specified in 
the Second Schedule and thereupon the territories so specified shall 
cease to form part of the existing State of Punjab.


</article>



<article><tid>1558795</tid>
<number> 5</number> Transfer of territory from Punjab to Himachal Pradesh.
<section><tid>66727</tid>
<number>1</number>On  
and from the appointed day, there shall be added to the Union 
territory of Himachal Pradesh the territories in the existing State of 
Punjab comprised in--

<subsection><tid>410419</tid>
<number>a</number>Simla, Kangra, Kulu and Lahaul and Spiti districts;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>855938</tid>
<number>b</number>Nalagarh tahsil of Ambala district;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1989906</tid>
<number>c</number>Lohara, Amb and Una kanungo circles of Una tahsil of 
Hoshiarpur district;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>665449</tid>
<number>d</number>the territories in Santokhgarh kanungo circle of Una 
tahsil of Hoshiarpur district specified in Part I of 
the Third Schedule;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1160028</tid>
<number>e</number>the territories Una tahsil of Hoshiarpur district 
specified in Part II of the Third Schedule; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1718479</tid>
<number>f</number>the territories of Dhar Kalan kanungo circle of 
Pathankot tahsil of Gurdaspur district specified in 
Part III of the Third Schedule,
and thereupon the said territories shall cease to form part of the 
existing State of Punjab.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>772</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1251899</tid>
<number>2</number>The territories referred to in clause (b) of sub- section (1) 
shall be included in, and form part of, Simla district.

</section>

<section><tid>610937</tid>
<number>3</number>The territories referred to in clauses (c), (d) and (e) of 
sub- section (1) shall be included in, and form part of, Kangra 
district, and

<subsection><tid>1784085</tid>
<number>i</number>the territories referred to in clauses (c) and (d) shall 
form a separate tahsil known as Una tahsil in that 
district and in that tahsil the territories referred to 
in clause (d) shall form a separate kanungo circle 
known as the Santokhgarh kanungo circle; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>701196</tid>
<number>ii</number>the territories referred to in clause (e) shall form 
part of the Hamirpur tahsil in the said district.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>690811</tid>
<number>4</number>The territories referred to in clause (f) of sub- section (1) 
shall be included in, and form part of, the Bhattiyat tahsil of Chamba 
district in the Union territory of Himachal Pradesh and in that 
tahsil, the villages Dalhousie and Balun shall be included in, and 
form part of, Banikhet kanungo circle and the village Bakloh shall 
form part of Chowari kanungo circle.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1398738</tid>
<number> 6</number> State of Punjab and territorial divisions thereof.
<section><tid>488171</tid>
<number>1</number>On and  
from the appointed day, the State of Punjab shall comprise the 
territories of the existing State of Punjab other than those specified 
in sub- section (1) of section 3, section 4 and sub- section (1) of 
section 5.

</section>

<section><tid>1752536</tid>
<number>2</number>The territories which immediately before the appointed day 
were part of Ambala district in the existing State of Punjab but are 
not transferred by virtue of sections 3, 4 and 5, shall, together with 
the territories which immediately before that day were part of the Una 
tahsil of Hoshiarpur district in the existing State of Punjab but are 
not transferred by virtue of section 5, form a separate district known 
as the Rupar district in the State of Punjab and in that district--

<subsection><tid>392330</tid>
<number>i</number>the territories which immediately before the appointed 
day were part of Manimajra kanungo circle of Kharar 
tahsil of Ambala district but are not transferred by 
virtue of sections 3 and 4, shall form in that tahsil a 
separate kanungo circle called the Mullanpur kanungo 
circle;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1735465</tid>
<number>ii</number>the territories which immediately before the appointed 
day were part of Una tahsil of Hoshiarpur district but 
are not transferred by virtue of section 5, shall form 
a separate tahsil known as Anandpur Sahib tahsil, and 
in that tahsil,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>773</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

the territories which immediately before the appointed 
day were part of Santokhgarh kanungo circle of Una 
tahsil of Hoshiarpur district but are not transferred 
by virtue of section 5, shall be included in, and form 
part of Nurpur Bedi kanungo circle.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1034707</tid>
<number> 7</number> Amendment of the First Schedule to the Constitution. On and 
from the appointed day, in the First Schedule to the Constitution,--
<section><tid>1492142</tid>
<number>a</number>under the heading" I. THE STATES",--

<subsection><tid>1645666</tid>
<number>i</number>in the paragraph relating to the 
territories of the State of Punjab, the following 
shall be added at the end, namely:--
" and the territories specified in sub- section (1) 
of section 3, section 4 and sub- section (1) of 
section 5 of the Punjab Reorganisation Act, <year>1966</year>";


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>305233</tid>
<number>ii</number>after entry 16, the following entry 
shall be inserted, namely:--
" 17. Haryana: The territories specified in sub- 
section (1) of section 3 of the Punjab 
Reorganisation Act <year>1966</year>";


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1334589</tid>
<number>b</number>under the heading" II. THE UNION TERRITORIES",--

<subsection><tid>1718806</tid>
<number>i</number>in the paragraph relating to the extent 
of the Union territory of Himachal Pradesh, the 
following shall be added at the end, namely:--
" and the territories specified in sub- section 
 (1) of section 5 of the Punjab Reorganisation Act, 
<year>1966</year>";


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>985812</tid>
<number>ii</number>after entry 9, the following entry shall 
be inserted, namely:--
" 10. Chandigarh: The territories specified 
in section 4 of the Punjab 
Reorganisation Act, <year>1966</year>.".




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>452580</tid>
<number>8</number>Saving powers of Government. Nothing in the foregoing 
provisions of this Part shall be deemed to affect the power of the 
Government of Punjab or Haryana or the Administrator of the Union 
territory of Himachal Pradesh to alter, after the appointed day, the 
name, area or boundaries of any district or other territorial division 
in the State or Union territory, as the case may be.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>774</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

PART

REPRESENTATION IN THE LEGISLATURES

PART III

REPRESENTATION IN THE LEGISLATURES

The Council of States



</article>



<article><tid>455164</tid>
<number> 9</number> Amendment of the Fourth Schedule to the Constitution. On and 
from the appointed day, in the Fourth Schedule to the Constitution, in 
the Table,--
<section><tid>881243</tid>
<number>a</number>entries 5 to 21 shall be re- numbered as entries 6 to 22 
respectively;

</section>

<section><tid>92113</tid>
<number>b</number>after entry 4, the following entry shall be inserted, 
namely:--
" 5. Haryana.... 5";


</section>

<section><tid>634058</tid>
<number>c</number>in entry 12 as so re- numbered, for the figures" 11", the 
figure" 7" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1505867</tid>
<number>d</number>in entry 19 as so re- numbered, for the figure" 2", the 
figure" 3" shall be substituted; and

</section>

<section><tid>1642779</tid>
<number>e</number>for the figures" 226", the figures" 228" shall be 
substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1732751</tid>
<number> 10</number> Allocation of sitting members.
<section><tid>1323085</tid>
<number>1</number>On and from the appointed  
day, the eleven sitting members of the Council of States representing 
the existing State of Punjab shall be deemed to have been elected to 
fill the seats allotted to the States of Haryana and Punjab and the 
Union territory of Himachal Pradesh, as specified in the Fourth 
Schedule.

</section>

<section><tid>1570415</tid>
<number>2</number>The term of office of such sitting members shall remain 
unaltered.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>32846</tid>
<number> 11</number> Filling up of vacancies.
<section><tid>590065</tid>
<number>1</number>As soon as may be after the  
appointed day, bye- elections shall be held to fill the vacancies 
existing on the appointed day in the seats allotted to the State of 
Haryana.

</section>

<section><tid>1036024</tid>
<number>2</number>The term of office of such one of the two members so elected 
as the Chairman of the Council of States may determine by drawing lot, 
shall expire on the 2nd day of April, <year>1968</year>, and the term of office of 
the other member shall expire on the 2nd day of April, <year>1972</year>.
The House of the People




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1409621</tid>
<number>12</number>Provision as to existing House. Nothing in Part II shall be 
deemed to affect the constitution or duration of the existing House of 
the People or the extent of the constituency of any sitting member of 
that House.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>775</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

The Legislative Assemblies



</article>



<article><tid>1631656</tid>
<number> 13</number> Provision as to Legislative Assemblies.
<section><tid>642107</tid>
<number>1</number>The number of  
seats as on the appointed day in the Legislative Assemblies of the 
States of Haryana and Punjab and the Union territory of Himachal 
Pradesh shall be fifty- four, eighty- seven and fifty- six respectively.

</section>

<section><tid>586804</tid>
<number>2</number>In the Second Schedule to the Representation of the People 
Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of <year>1950</year>)--

<subsection><tid>1797960</tid>
<number>a</number>after entry 4, the following entry shall be inserted, 
namely:--
" 4A. Haryana... 54";


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1814695</tid>
<number>b</number>in entry 11, for the figures" 154", the figures" 87" 
shall be substituted; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>812872</tid>
<number>c</number>in entry 16, for the figures" 40", the figures" 54" 
shall be substituted.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1876332</tid>
<number>14</number>Amendment of Delimitation Orders. On and from the appointed 
day, Part B of Schedule XI to the Delimitation of Parliamentary and 
Assembly Constituencies Order, <year>1961</year>, and the Schedule to the 
Delimitation of Territorial Council Constituencies (Himachal Pradesh) 
Order, <year>1962</year>, shall stand amended as directed in the Fifth Schedule to 
this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1625524</tid>
<number> 15</number> Allocation of sitting members.
<section><tid>53909</tid>
<number>1</number>Every sitting member of  
the Legislative Assembly of Punjab elected to fill a seat in that 
Assembly from a constituency which on the appointed day by virtue of 
the provisions of section 14 stands allotted, with or without 
alteration of boundaries, to the State of Haryana or to the Union 
territory of Himachal Pradesh, shall, on and from that day, cease to 
be a member of the Legislative Assembly of Punjab and shall be deemed 
to have been elected to fill a seat in the Legislative Assembly of 
Haryana or in the Legislative Assembly of Himachal Pradesh, as the 
case may be, from that constituency as so allotted.

</section>

<section><tid>1077308</tid>
<number>2</number>All other sitting members of the Legislative Assembly of 
Punjab shall continue to be members of the Legislative Assembly of 
that State and any such sitting member representing a constituency the 
extent, or the name and extent, of which are altered by virtue of the 
provisions of section 14 shall be deemed to have been elected to the 
legislative Assembly of Punjab by that constituency as so altered.

</section>

<section><tid>1571558</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the 
time being in force, the Legislative Assemblies of Haryana, Punjab

<pagefootnote><pagenum>776</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

and Himachal Pradesh shall be deemed to be duly constituted on the 
appointed day.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>715025</tid>
<number> 16</number> Duration of Legislative Assemblies of Haryana. The period of 
five years referred to in clause
<section><tid>1765876</tid>
<number>1</number>of article 172 shall, in the case  
of the Legislative Assembly of Haryana, be deemed to have commenced on 
the date on which it actually commenced in the case of the Legislative 
Assembly of Punjab.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1855584</tid>
<number>17</number>Duration of Legislative Assembly of Punjab and Himachal 
Pradesh. The changes in the composition of the Legislative Assemblies 
of Punjab and Himachal Pradesh shall not affect the duration of either 
of those Assemblies.


</article>



<article><tid>815637</tid>
<number> 18</number> Speakers and Deputy Speakers.
<section><tid>1680729</tid>
<number>1</number>The person who immediately  
before the appointed day is the Speaker of the Legislative Assembly of 
Punjab shall continue to be the Speaker of that Assembly on and from 
that day.

</section>

<section><tid>442180</tid>
<number>2</number>As soon as may be after the appointed day, the Legislative 
Assembly of Haryana shall choose a member of that Assembly to be 
Speaker of that Assembly.

</section>

<section><tid>997758</tid>
<number>3</number>The person who immediately before the appointed day is the 
Deputy Speaker of the Legislative Assembly of Punjab shall be the 
Deputy Speaker of the Legislative Assembly of Haryana.

</section>

<section><tid>828359</tid>
<number>4</number>As soon as may be after the appointed day, the Legislative 
Assembly of Punjab shall choose a member of that Assembly to be Deputy 
Speaker of that Assembly.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>574348</tid>
<number> 19</number> Rules of procedure. The rules of procedure and conduct of 
business of the Legislative Assembly of Punjab as in force immediately 
before the appointed day shall, until rules are made under clause
<section><tid>1794768</tid>
<number>1</number> 
of article 208, be the rules of procedure and conduct of business of 
the Legislative Assembly of Haryana, subject to such modifications and 
adaptations as may be made therein by the Speaker thereof.
The Legislative Council




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1572765</tid>
<number>20</number>Legislative Council of Punjab. On and from the appointed day, 
there shall be forty seats in the Legislative Council of Punjab, and 
in the Third Schedule to the Representation of the People Act, <year>1950</year> 
 (43 of <year>1950</year>), for the existing entry 7, the following entry shall be 
substituted, namely:--
" 7. Punjab. 40 14 3 3 14 6".


<pagefootnote><pagenum>777</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>634051</tid>
<number>21</number>Council Constituencies. On and from the appointed day, the 
Delimitation of Council Constituencies (Punjab) Order, <year>1951</year>, shall 
stand amended as directed in the Sixth Schedule.


</article>



<article><tid>1167900</tid>
<number> 22</number> Provision as to certain sitting members.
<section><tid>396538</tid>
<number>1</number>On the appointed  
day, the sitting members of the Legislative Council of Punjab 
specified in the Seventh Schedule shall cease to be members of that 
Council.

</section>

<section><tid>1555790</tid>
<number>2</number>On and from the appointed day, all sitting members of the 
Legislative Council of Punjab, other than those referred to in sub- 
section (1), shall continue to be members of that Council.

</section>

<section><tid>204884</tid>
<number>3</number>Any of the sitting members continuing as aforesaid, 
representing a council constituency the extent of which is altered by 
virtue of the provisions of section 21 shall be deemed to have been 
elected to the Legislative Council of Punjab by that constituency as 
so altered.

</section>

<section><tid>1111551</tid>
<number>4</number>Every sitting member of the said Council representing 
immediately before the appointed day any of the council constituencies 
specified in column (1) of the Table below shall be deemed to have 
been elected to the said Council by the council constituency specified 
against that constituency in column (2) of the said Table:-- 
TABLE 
 (1)  (2) 
Punjab West Central Graduates Punjab Central Graduates.
Punjab East Central Graduates Punjab South Graduates.

Punjab West Central Teachers Punjab Central Teachers.

Punjab East Central Teachers Punjab South Teachers.

Patiala Local Authorities Patiala- cum- Rupar Local 
Authorities.


</section>

<section><tid>440212</tid>
<number>5</number>The term of office of the members referred to in sub- section 
 (2) shall remain unaltered.

</section>

<section><tid>223707</tid>
<number>6</number>As soon as may be after the appointed day, elections shall be 
held to fill the vacancies existing on the appointed day in the seats

<pagefootnote><pagenum>778</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

allotted to the several council constituencies by the Delimitation of 
Council Constituencies (Punjab) Order, <year>1951</year>, as amended by this Act 
and to fill the vacancy existing on that day in the seats to be filled 
by persons elected by the members of the Legislative Assembly.


</section>

<section><tid>1736849</tid>
<number>7</number>The term of office of the three members so elected from 
Ferozepur Local Authorities' constituency, Jullundur Local 
Authorities' constitutency and Ludhiana Local Authorities' 
constituency and of the member so elected by the members of the 
Legislative Assembly shall expire on the 26th day of April, <year>1968</year>, and 
the term of office of the member so elected from Patiala- cum- Rupar 
Local Authorities' constituency shall expire on the 26th day of April, 
<year>1972</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>842460</tid>
<number>8</number>The person who immediately before the appointed day is the 
Chairman of the Legislative Council of Punjab shall continue to be the 
Chairman of that Council on and from that day.

</section>

<section><tid>630700</tid>
<number>9</number>As soon as may be after the appointed day, the Legislative 
Council of Punjab shall choose one of its members to be the Deputy 
Chairman thereof.
Delimitation of Constituencies




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1220158</tid>
<number> 23</number> Allocation of seats in the House of the People. In the House 
of the People to be constituted after the commencement of this Act, 
there shall be allotted,--
<section><tid>267131</tid>
<number>a</number>nine seats to the State of Haryana of which two seats 
shall be reserved for the Scheduled Castes;

</section>

<section><tid>1671663</tid>
<number>b</number>thirteen seats to the State of Punjab of which three 
seats shall be reserved for the Scheduled Castes;

</section>

<section><tid>1976311</tid>
<number>c</number>six seats to the Union territory of Himachal Pradesh of 
which one seat shall be reserved for the Scheduled 
Castes; and

</section>

<section><tid>346372</tid>
<number>d</number>one seat to the Union territory of Chandigarh which 
shall form one Parliamentary Constituency.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1411823</tid>
<number> 24</number> Allocation of seats in the Legislative Assembly.
<section><tid>855409</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
total number of seats in the Legislative Assembly of Haryana to be 
constituted at any time after the appointed day, to be filled by 
persons chosen by direct election from territorial constituencies, 
shall be eighty- one of which fifteen seats shall be reserved for the 
Scheduled Castes.

</section>

<section><tid>343114</tid>
<number>2</number>The total number of seats in the Legislative Assembly of 
Punjab to be constituted at any time after the appointed day, to be 
filled by persons chosen by direct election from territorial consti-

<pagefootnote><pagenum>779</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

tuencies, shall be one hundred and four of which twenty- three seats 
shall be reserved for the Scheduled Castes.


</section>

<section><tid>115054</tid>
<number>3</number>The total number of seats in the Legislative Assembly of 
Himachal Pradesh to be constituted at any time after the appointed 
day, to be filled by persons chosen by direct election from 
territorial constituencies, shall be sixty of which fourteen seats 
shall be reserved for the Scheduled Castes and three seats shall be 
reserved for the Scheduled Tribes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1537727</tid>
<number> 25</number> Delimitation of constituencies.
<section><tid>1258715</tid>
<number>1</number>The Delimitation  
Commission shall, in the manner herein provided, distribute the seats 
in the House of the People allotted to Haryana, Punjab and Himachal 
Pradesh under section 23 and the seats assigned to the Legislative 
Assembly of each of them under section 24 to single- member territorial 
constituencies and delimit them on the basis of the latest census 
figures, having regard to the provisions of the Constitution and to 
the following provisions, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1747374</tid>
<number>a</number>all constituencies shall, as far as practicable be 
geographically compact areas, and in delimiting them 
regard shall be had to physical features, existing 
boundaries of administrative units, facilities of 
communication and public convenience;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>148370</tid>
<number>b</number>every assembly constituency shall be so delimited as to 
fall wholly within one parliamentary constituency;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>906639</tid>
<number>c</number>constituencies in which seats are reserved for the 
Scheduled Castes shall be distributed in different 
parts of the State or Union territory, as the case may 
be, and located, as far as practicable, in those areas 
where the proportion of their population to the total 
population is comparatively large; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1732548</tid>
<number>d</number>constituencies in which seats are reserved for the 
Scheduled Tribes shall, as far as practicable, be 
located in areas where the proportion of their 
population to the total population is the largest.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>217190</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purpose of assisting it in the performance of its 
functions under sub- section (1), the Delimitation Commission shall 
associate with itself in respect of each State and Union territory 
such six persons as the Central Government may by order specify, being 
persons who are members either of the House of the People or of the 
Legislative Assembly of Haryana, Punjab or Himachal Pradesh:
Provided that such persons shall be chosen, as far as 
practicable, from among those members who were associated before the 
com-


<pagefootnote><pagenum>780</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

mencement of this Act with the Delimitation Commission in delimiting 
constituencies of Punjab or Himachal Pradesh:

Provided further that none of the associate members shall have a 
right to vote or to sign any decision of the Delimitation Commission.


</section>

<section><tid>888106</tid>
<number>3</number>The Delimitation Commission shall, by one or more orders, 
determine the delimitation of the parliamentary and assembly 
constituencies referred to in sub- section (1).

</section>

<section><tid>1282057</tid>
<number>4</number>The provisions of sections 7, 10 and 11 of the Delimitation 
Commission Act, <year>1962</year> (61 of <year>1962</year>), shall apply in relation to the 
delimitation of parliamentary and assembly constituencies under this 
Part as they apply in relation to the delimitation of parliamentary 
and assembly constituencies under the said Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1603422</tid>
<number>5</number>Upon publication in the Gazette of India of the order or 
orders of the Delimitation Commission made under sub- section (3), the 
orders previously made by it delimiting the parliamentary and assembly 
constituencies of Punjab and Himachal Pradesh shall stand cancelled.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>97108</tid>
<number>26</number>Amendment of article 371 of the Constitution. On and from the 
appointed day, in article 371 of the Constitution, in clause 1, the 
words" or Punjab" shall be omitted.


</article>



<article><tid>767951</tid>
<number> 27</number> Amendment of Scheduled Castes Orders.
<section><tid>1880884</tid>
<number>1</number>On and from the  
appointed day, the Constitution (Scheduled Castes) Order, <year>1950</year>, shall 
stand amended as directed in the Eighth Schedule.

</section>

<section><tid>502318</tid>
<number>2</number>On and from the appointed day, the Constitution (Scheduled  
  Castes)  (Union Territories) Order, <year>1951</year>, shall stand amended as; 
directed in the Ninth Schedule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>546827</tid>
<number> 28</number> Amendment of Scheduled Tribes Orders.
<section><tid>770678</tid>
<number>1</number>On and from the  
appointed day, the Constitution (Scheduled Tribes) Order, <year>1950</year>, shall 
stand amended as directed in the Tenth Schedule.

</section>

<section><tid>681591</tid>
<number>2</number>On and from the appointed day, the Constitution (Scheduled  
  Tribes)  (Union Territories) Order, <year>1951</year>, shall stand amended as 
directed in the Eleventh Schedule.
PART

HIGH COURT

PART IV

HIGH COURT




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1230932</tid>
<number> 29</number> Common High Court for Punjab, Haryana and Chandigarh.
<section><tid>1354619</tid>
<number>1</number>On  
and from the appointed day,--

<subsection><tid>25348</tid>
<number>a</number>there shall be a common High Court for the States of 
Punjab and Haryana and for the Union territory of Chan-

<pagefootnote><pagenum>781</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

digarh to be called the High Court of Punjab and 
Haryana (hereinafter referred to as the common High  
  Court);


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>625001</tid>
<number>b</number>the Judges of the High Court of Punjab holding office 
immediately before that day shall, unless they have 
elected otherwise, become on that day the Judges of the 
common High Court.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>718543</tid>
<number>2</number>The expenditure in respect of salaries and allowances of the 
Judges of the common High Court shall be allocated amongst the States 
of Punjab and Haryana and the Union in such proportion as the 
President may, by order, determine.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1341702</tid>
<number>30</number>Jurisdiction of the common High Court. On and from the 
appointed day, the common High Court shall have, in respect of the 
territories comprised in the States of Punjab and Haryana and the 
Union territory of Chandigarh, all such jurisdiction, powers and 
authority as, under the law in force immediately before the appointed 
day, are exercisable in respect of those territories by the High Court 
of Punjab and shall, save as otherwise provided in this Part, have no 
jurisdiction in respect of the transferred territory.


</article>



<article><tid>411489</tid>
<number> 31</number> Special provision relating to Bar Council and Advocates.
<section><tid>1330550</tid>
<number>1</number> 
On and from the appointed day,--

<subsection><tid>1357318</tid>
<number>a</number>in the Advocates Act, <year>1961</year> (25 of <year>1961</year>), in sub- section 
 (1) of section 3, for clause (d), the following clause 
shall be substituted, namely:--
" (d) for the States of Punjab and Haryana and the 
Union territories of Chandigarh and Himachal Pradesh, 
to be known as the Bar Council of Punjab and Haryana";


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>55308</tid>
<number>b</number>the Bar Council of Punjab shall be deemed to be the Bar 
Council of Punjab and Haryana with the Advocate- General 
of the State of Haryana also as an ex officio member.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>782650</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person who immediately before the appointed day is an 
advocate entitled to practise in the High Court of Punjab shall be 
entitled to practise as an advocate in the common High Court.

</section>

<section><tid>361107</tid>
<number>3</number>All persons who immediately before the appointed day are 
advocates on the roll of the Bar Council of Punjab shall, as from that 
day, become advocates on the roll of the Bar Council of Punjab and 
Haryana.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>782</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>703055</tid>
<number>4</number>The right of audience in the common High Court shall be 
regulated in accordance with the like principles as immediately before 
the appointed day are in force with respect to the right of audience 
in the High Court of Punjab:
Provided that as between the Advocate- General of Punjab and the 
Advocate- General of Haryana, the right of audience shall be determined 
with reference to their dates of enrolment as advocates.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>943891</tid>
<number>32</number>Practice and procedure in common High Court. Subject to the 
provisions of this Part, the law in force immediately before the 
appointed day with respect to practice and procedure in the High Court 
of Punjab shall, with the necessary modifications, apply in relation 
to the common High Court.


</article>



<article><tid>11589</tid>
<number>33</number>Custody of seal of common High Court. The law in force 
immediately before the appointed day with respect to the custody of 
the seal of the High Court of Punjab shall, with the necessary 
modifications, apply with respect to the custody of the seal of the 
common High Court.


</article>



<article><tid>1466055</tid>
<number>34</number>Form of writs and other processes. The law in force 
immediately before the appointed day with respect to the form of writs 
and other processes used, issued or awarded by the High Court of 
Punjab shall, with the necessary modifications, apply with respect to 
the form of writs and other processes used, issued or awarded by the 
common High Court.


</article>



<article><tid>842670</tid>
<number>35</number>Powers of Judges. The law in force immediately before the 
appointed day with respect to the powers of the Chief Justice, single 
Judges and division courts of the High Court of Punjab and with 
respect to all matters ancillary to the exercise of those powers 
shall, with the necessary modifications, apply in relation to the 
common High Court.


</article>



<article><tid>867080</tid>
<number> 36</number> Principal seat and other places of sitting of the common High 
Court.
<section><tid>346204</tid>
<number>1</number>The principal seat of the common High Court shall, unless  
otherwise determined by the President after consultation with the 
Chief Justice of that High Court and the Governors of Punjab and 
Haryana, be at the same place as the principal seat of the High court 
of Punjab immediately before the appointed day.

</section>

<section><tid>308259</tid>
<number>2</number>The President may, after consultation with the Chief Justice 
of the common High Court and the Governors of the States of Punjab and 
Haryana, by notified order, provide for the establishment of a 
permanent bench or benches of that High Court at one or more places 
within the territories to which the jurisdiction of the High Court 
extends, other than the principal seat of the High Court, and for any 
matters connected therewith.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>783</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>882582</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1) or sub- 
section (2), the Judges and division courts of the common High Court 
may also sit at such other place or places in the States of Punjab and 
Haryana as the Chief Justice may, with the approval of the Governors 
of the States of Punjab and Haryana, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>591475</tid>
<number>37</number>Procedure as to appeals to Supreme Court. The law in force 
immediately before the appointed day relating to appeals to the 
Supreme Court from the High Court of Punjab and the Judges and 
division courts thereof, shall, with the necessary modifications, 
apply in relation to the common High Court.


</article>



<article><tid>446015</tid>
<number>38</number>Extension of jurisdiction of the Court of Judicial 
Commissioner for Himachal Pradesh. On and from the appointed day, the 
jurisdiction of the Court of the Judicial Commissioner for Himachal 
Pradesh shall extend to the transferred territory.


</article>



<article><tid>184718</tid>
<number> 39</number> Transfer of pending proceedings.
<section><tid>1852114</tid>
<number>1</number>All proceedings pending  
in the High Court of Punjab immediately before the appointed day 
shall, on that day, stand transferred to the common High Court.

</section>

<section><tid>1499939</tid>
<number>2</number>Such proceedings which stand transferred to the common High 
Court under sub- section (1) as are certified by the Chief Justice of 
the common High Court, having regard to the place of accrual of the 
cause of action and other circumstances, to be proceedings which ought 
to be heard and decided by the Court of the Judicial Commissioner for 
Himachal Pradesh shall, as soon as may be after such certification, be 
transferred to the Court of the Judicial Commissioner for Himachal 
Pradesh.

</section>

<section><tid>1540166</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing 
provisions of this Part, but save as hereinafter provided, the common 
High Court shall have, and the Court of the Judicial Commissioner for 
Himachal Pradesh shall not have, jurisdiction to entertain, hear or 
dispose of appeals, applications for leave to appeal to the Supreme 
Court, applications for review and other proceedings where any such 
proceedings seek any relief in respect of any order passed by the High 
Court of Punjab before the appointed day:
Provided that if, after any such proceedings have been 
entertained by the common High Court, it appears to the Chief Justice 
of that High Court that they ought to be transferred to the Court of 
the Judicial Commissioner for Himachal Pradesh, he shall order that 
they


<pagefootnote><pagenum>784</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

shall be so transferred, and such proceedings shall thereupon be 
transferred accordingly.


</section>

<section><tid>1327195</tid>
<number>4</number>Any order--

<subsection><tid>250796</tid>
<number>a</number>made by the High Court of Punjab before the appointed 
day, in any proceeding transferred to the Court of the 
Judicial Commissioner for Himachal Pradesh by virtue of 
sub- section (2), or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>171431</tid>
<number>b</number>made by the common High Court in any proceeding with 
respect to which that High Court has jurisdiction by 
virtue of sub- section (3),
shall for all purposes have effect not only as an order of the High 
Court of Punjab or, as the case may be, of the common High Court, but 
also as an order made by the Court of the Judicial Commissioner for 
Himachal Pradesh.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1177988</tid>
<number> 40</number> Interpretation. For the purposes of this Part,--
<section><tid>1576156</tid>
<number>a</number>proceedings shall be deemed to be pending in a court 
until that court has disposed of all issues between the 
parties including any issues with respect to the 
taxation of the costs of the proceedings and shall 
include appeals, applications for leave to appeal to 
the Supreme Court, applications for review, petitions 
for revision and petitions for writs; and

</section>

<section><tid>127828</tid>
<number>b</number>references to a High Court shall be construed as 
including references to a Judge or division court 
thereof, and references to an order made by a court or 
a Judge shall be construed as including references to a 
sentence, judgment or decree passed or made by that 
court or Judge.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1661096</tid>
<number>41</number>Savings. Nothing in this Part shall affect the application to 
the common High Court of any provisions of the Constitution, and this 
Part shall have effect subject to any provision that may be made on or 
after the appointed day with respect to that High Court by any 
Legislature or other authority having power to make such provision.
PART

AUTHORISATION OF EXPENDITURE AND DISTRIBUTION OF REVENUES

PART V

AUTHORISATION OF EXPENDITURE AND DISTRIBUTION OF REVENUES



</article>



<article><tid>1361871</tid>
<number>42</number>Authorisation of expenditure of the State of Haryana. The 
Governor of the existing State of Punjab may at any time, before the 
appointed day, authorise such expenditure from the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>785</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Consolidated Fund of the State of Haryana as he deems necessary for 
any period not extending beyond the 31st day of March, <year>1967</year>, pending 
the sanction of such expenditure by the Legislative Assembly of 
Haryana:

Provided that the Governor of Haryana may, after the appointed 
day, authorise such further expenditure from the Consolidated Fund of 
the State as he deems necessary for the said period pending such 
sanction.



</article>



<article><tid>1799151</tid>
<number> 43</number> Appropriation of moneys for expenditure in transferred 
territory.
<section><tid>1065451</tid>
<number>1</number>On and from the appointed day, any Act passed by the  
Legislative Assembly of the Union territory of Himachal Pradesh before 
that day for the appropriation of any money out of the Consolidated 
Fund of that Union territory to meet any expenditure in respect of any 
part of the financial year <year>1966</year>- 67 shall have effect also in relation 
to the transferred territory and it shall be lawful for the Government 
of Himachal Pradesh to spend any amount in the transferred territory 
out of the amount authorised by such Act to be expended for any 
service in that Union territory.

</section>

<section><tid>1349798</tid>
<number>2</number>The Administrator of Himachal Pradesh may, after the 
appointed day, authorise such expenditure from the Consolidated Fund 
of the Union territory as he deems necessary for any purpose or 
service in the transferred territory for any period not extending 
beyond the 31st day of March, <year>1967</year>, pending the sanction of such 
expenditure by the Legislative Assembly of Himachal Pradesh.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1858293</tid>
<number> 44</number> Reports relating to the accounts of the existing State of 
Punjab.
<section><tid>913851</tid>
<number>1</number>The reports of the Comptroller and Auditor- General of  
India referred to in clause (2) of article 151 relating to the 
accounts of the existing State of Punjab in respect of any period 
prior to the appointed day, shall be submitted to the Governor of each 
of the States of Punjab and Haryana and the Administrator of Himachal 
Pradesh who shall cause them to be laid before the Legislature of that 
State or Union territory, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1025785</tid>
<number>2</number>The President may by order--

<subsection><tid>1566913</tid>
<number>a</number>declare any expenditure incurred out of the Consolidated 
Fund of Punjab on any service in respect of any period 
prior to the appointed day during the financial year 
<year>1966</year>- 67 or in respect of any earlier financial year in 
excess of the amount granted for that service and for 
that year as disclosed in the reports referred to in 
sub- section (1) to have been duly authorised, and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>786</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1955803</tid>
<number>b</number>provide for any action to be taken on any matter arising 
out of the said reports.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1108813</tid>
<number>45</number>Allowances and privileges of Governor of Haryana. The 
allowances and privileges of the Governor of Haryana shall, until 
provision in that behalf is made by Parliament by law under clause (3) 
of article 158, be such as the President may, by order, determine.


</article>



<article><tid>1681698</tid>
<number>46</number>Distribution of revenues. The Constitution (Distribution of  
  Revenues) Order, <year>1965</year>, the Union Duties of Excise (Distribution) Act, 
 <year>1962</year> (3 of <year>1962</year>), the Additional Duties of Excise (Goods of Special  
  Importance) Act, <year>1957</year> (58 of <year>1957</year>), and the Estate Duty (Distribution) 
Act <year>1962</year> (9 of <year>1962</year>), shall on and from the appointed day, stand 
amended as directed in the Twelfth Schedule.
PART

APPORTIONMENT OF ASSETS AND LIABILITIES

PART VI

APPORTIONMENT OF ASSETS AND LIABILITIES



</article>



<article><tid>465524</tid>
<number>47</number>Application of Part. The provisions of this Part shall apply 
in relation to the apportionment of the assets and liabilities of the 
existing State of Punjab immediately before the appointed day.


</article>



<article><tid>480680</tid>
<number> 48</number> Land and goods.
<section><tid>864840</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the other provisions of this  
Part, all land and all stores, articles and other goods belonging to 
the existing State of Punjab shall,--

<subsection><tid>17683</tid>
<number>a</number>if within that State, pass to the successor State in 
whose territories they are situated; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>841711</tid>
<number>b</number>if outside that State, pass to the State of Punjab:
Provided that where the Central Government is of the opinion that 
any goods or class of goods should be distributed among the successor 
States otherwise than according to the situation of the goods, the 
Central Government may issue such directions as it thinks fit for a 
just and equitable distribution of the goods and the goods shall pass 
to the successor States accordingly.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>735543</tid>
<number>2</number>Stores held for specific purposes, such as use or utilisation 
in particular institutions, workshops or undertakings or on particular 
works under construction, shall pass to the successor State in whose 
territories such institutions, workshops, undertakings or works are 
located.

</section>

<section><tid>1362036</tid>
<number>3</number>Stores relating to the Secretariat and offices of Heads of 
Departments having jurisdiction over the whole of the existing State

<pagefootnote><pagenum>787</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

of Punjab shall be divided between the successor States in accordance 
with such directions as the Central Government may think fit to issue 
for a just and equitable distribution of such stores.


</section>

<section><tid>1851037</tid>
<number>4</number>Any other unissued stores of any class in the existing State 
of Punjab shall be divided between the successor States in proportion 
to the total stores of that class purchased in the period of three 
years ending with the 31st day of March, <year>1966</year>, for the territories of 
the existing State of Punjab included respectively in each of the 
successor States:
Provided that where such proportion cannot be ascertained in 
respect of any class of stores or where the value of any class of such 
stores does not exceed rupees ten thousand, that class of stores shall 
be divided between the successor States according to the population 
ratio.


</section>

<section><tid>1578284</tid>
<number>5</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, the lands 
specified in the Thirteenth Schedule which were acquired by the 
Government of the existing State of Punjab--

<subsection><tid>1473664</tid>
<number>i</number>for the sewerage scheme of Chandigarh,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1593886</tid>
<number>ii</number>for soil conservation measures in the catchment area of 
Sukhna lake, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>616973</tid>
<number>iii</number>for the setting up of brick kilns of the Chandigarh 
Capital Project,
together with all connected works in or over such land (including any  
  plant, machinery or implements) shall vest in the Union.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1095631</tid>
<number>6</number>In this section, the expression" land" includes immovable 
property of every kind and any rights in or over such property, and 
the expression" goods" does not include coins, bank notes and currency 
notes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1716163</tid>
<number>49</number>Treasury and bank balances. The total of the cash balances in 
all treasuries of the existing State of Punjab and the credit balances 
of that State with the Reserve Bank of India, the State Bank of India 
or any other bank immediately before the appointed day shall be 
divided between the successor States according to the population 
ratio:
Provided that for the purposes of such division, there shall be 
no transfer of cash balances from any treasury to any other treasury 
and the apportionment shall be effected by adjusting the credit


<pagefootnote><pagenum>788</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

balances of the successor States in the books of the Reserve Bank of 
India on the appointed day:

Provided further that if any successor State has no account with 
the Reserve Bank of India, the adjustment shall be made in such manner 
as the Central Government may by order, direct.



</article>



<article><tid>1037092</tid>
<number>50</number>Arrears of taxes. The right to recover arrears of any tax or 
duty on property, including arrears of land revenue, shall belong to 
the successor State in whose territories the property is situated, and 
the right to recover arrears of any other tax or duty shall belong to 
the successor State in whose territories the place of assessment of 
that tax or duty is included.


</article>



<article><tid>1947926</tid>
<number> 51</number> Right to recover loans and advances.
<section><tid>969452</tid>
<number>1</number>The right to recover  
any loans or advances made before the appointed day by the existing 
State of Punjab to any local body, society, agriculturist or other 
person in an area within that State shall belong to the successor 
State in whose territories that area is included:
Provided that the right to recover loans or advances of pay and 
travelling allowance to a Government servant made before the appointed 
day by the existing State of Punjab shall pass to the successor State 
to which such Government servant is allotted.


</section>

<section><tid>1333835</tid>
<number>2</number>The right to recover any loans or advances made before the 
appointed day by the existing State of Punjab to any person or 
institution outside that State shall belong to the State of Punjab:
Provided that any sum recovered in respect of any such loan or 
advance shall be divided between all the successor States according to 
the population ratio.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>409487</tid>
<number> 52</number> Investments and credits in certain funds.
<section><tid>1031892</tid>
<number>1</number>The investments  
made from the Cash Balance Investment Account, the Famine Relief Fund 
and any other general fund of the existing State of Punjab, the sums 
at the credit of that State in the Central Road Fund and the sums held 
in the Defence and Security Relief Fund shall be divided between the 
successor States according to the population ratio; and the 
investments in any special fund the objects of which are confined to a 
local area in the existing State of Punjab shall pass to the successor 
State in whose territories that area is included.

</section>

<section><tid>1795102</tid>
<number>2</number>The investments of the existing State of Punjab immediately 
before the appointed day in any private commercial or industrial 
undertaking, in so far as such investments have not been made or are 
deemed not to have been made from the Cash Balance Investment

<pagefootnote><pagenum>789</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Account, shall pass to the successor State in whose territories the 
principal seat of business of the undertaking is located and where on 
that day the principal seat of business of the undertaking is located 
outside the territories of the existing State of Punjab such 
investments shall be divided between all the successor States in the 
population ratio.


</section>

<section><tid>356278</tid>
<number>3</number>Where any body corporate constituted under a Central Act, 
State Act or Provincial Act for the existing State of Punjab or any 
part thereof has, by virtue of the provisions of Part II, become an 
inter- State body corporate, the investments in, or loans or advances 
to, any such body corporate by the existing State of Punjab made 
before the appointed day shall, save as otherwise expressly provided 
by or under this Act, be divided between the successor States in the 
same proportion in which the assets of the body corporate are divided 
under the provisions of Part VII.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>435469</tid>
<number> 53</number> Assets and liabilities of State undertakings.
<section><tid>916262</tid>
<number>1</number>The assets  
and liabilities relating to any commercial or industrial undertaking 
of the existing State of Punjab shall pass to the successor State in 
whose territories the undertaking is located.

</section>

<section><tid>11401</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a depreciation reserve fund is maintained by the 
existing State of Punjab for any commercial or industrial undertaking, 
the securities held in respect of investments made from that fund 
shall pass to the successor State in whose territories the undertaking 
is located.

</section>

<section><tid>1768074</tid>
<number>3</number>Where any such undertaking is located in more than one 
successor State, the assets and liabilities and the securities 
referred to in sub- sections (1) and (2) respectively shall be divided 
in such manner as may be agreed upon between the successor States 
before the 1st day of November, <year>1967</year>, or in default of such agreement, 
as the Central Government may by order direct.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1210792</tid>
<number> 54</number> Public debt.
<section><tid>1011416</tid>
<number>1</number>The public debt of the existing State of  
Punjab attributable to loans raised by the issue of Government 
securities and outstanding with the public immediately before the 
appointed day shall, on and from that day, be the debt of the State of 
Punjab, and--

<subsection><tid>1201602</tid>
<number>a</number>the other successor States shall be liable to pay to the 
State of Punjab their shares of the sums due from time 
to time for the servicing and repayment of the debt, 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>490457</tid>
<number>b</number>for the purpose of determining the said shares, the debt 
shall be deemed to be divided between the successor 
States as if it were a debt referred to in sub- section 
 (4).

<pagefootnote><pagenum>790</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>879640</tid>
<number>2</number>The public debt of the existing State of Punjab attributable 
to loans taken from the Central Government, the National Co- operative 
Development Corporation or the Khadi and Village Industries Commission 
or from any other source for the purpose of re- lending the same to a 
specific institution or class of institutions and outstanding 
immediately before the appointed day shall--

<subsection><tid>152952</tid>
<number>a</number>if re- lent to any local body, body corporate or other 
institution in any local area, be the debt of the 
successor State in whose territories the local area is 
included on the appointed day; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1883816</tid>
<number>b</number>if re- lent to the Punjab State Electricity Board or any 
other institution which becomes an inter- State 
institution on the appointed day, be divided between 
the successor States in the same proportion in which 
the assets of such body corporate or institution are 
divided under the provisions of Part VII.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1352685</tid>
<number>3</number>The public debt of the existing State of Punjab attributable 
to loans taken from the Central Government for the Beas Project and 
the Bhakra- Nangal Project as defined in sub- section (4) of section 78 
shall be divided between the successor States in such proportion as 
may be agreed upon between them, or if no agreement is entered into 
within two years from the appointed day, as may be fixed by order of 
the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>863125</tid>
<number>4</number>The remaining public debt of the existing State of Punjab 
attributable to loans taken from the Central Government, the Reserve 
Bank of India or any other body or bank before the appointed day shall 
be divided between the successor States in proportion to the total 
expenditure on all capital works and other capital outlays incurred 
or deemed to have been incurred up to the appointed day in the 
territories of the existing State of Punjab included respectively in 
each of those successor States:
Provided that in computing such expenditure, the expenditure on 
the Beas Project and the Bhakra- Nangal Project as defined in sub- 
section (4) of section 78 shall be excluded and the expenditure on 
other assets for which capital accounts have been kept shall be taken 
into account.

Explanation.-- Where any expenditure on capital works or other 
capital outlays cannot be allocated between the territories included 
in the successor States, such expenditure shall, for the purposes of 
this sub- section, be deemed to have been incurred in those territories 
according to the population ratio.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>791</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>16197</tid>
<number>5</number>Where a sinking fund or depreciation fund is maintained by 
the existing State of Punjab for repayment of any loan referred to in 
sub- section (3), the securities held in respect of the investments 
made from that fund shall be divided between the successor States in 
the same proportion and in the same manner as the public debt referred 
to in sub- section (3).

</section>

<section><tid>450360</tid>
<number>6</number>Where a sinking fund or depreciation fund is maintained by 
the existing State of Punjab for the repayment of any loan raised by 
it other than a loan referred to in sub- section (3), the securities 
held in respect of the investments made from that fund shall be 
divided between the successor States in the same proportion as the 
public debt referred to in sub- section (4).

</section>

<section><tid>1459653</tid>
<number>7</number>In this section, the expression" Government security" means a 
security created and issued by a State Government for the purpose of 
raising a public loan and having any of the forms specified in, or 
prescribed under clause (2) of section 2 of the Public Debt Act, <year>1944</year> 
 (8 of <year>1944</year>).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>182186</tid>
<number>55</number>Refund of taxes collected in excess. The liability of the 
existing State of Punjab to refund any tax or duty on property, 
including land revenue, collected in excess shall be the liability of 
the successor State in whose territories the property is situated, and 
the liability of the existing State of Punjab to refund any other tax 
or duty collected in excess shall be the liability of the successor 
State in whose territories the place of assessment of that tax or duty 
is included.


</article>



<article><tid>1863248</tid>
<number> 56</number> Deposits, etc.
<section><tid>956224</tid>
<number>1</number>The liability of the existing State of  
Punjab in respect of any civil deposit or local fund deposit shall, on 
and from the appointed day, be the liability of the successor State in 
whose territories the deposit has been made:
Provided that if the deposit is made in any area outside the 
existing State, the liability shall be that of the State of Punjab in 
the first instance and shall be adjusted between the successor States 
according to the population ratio.


</section>

<section><tid>664287</tid>
<number>2</number>The liability of the existing State of Punjab in respect of 
any charitable or other endowment shall, on and from the appointed 
day, be the liability of the successor State in whose territories the 
institution entitled to the benefit of the endowment is located or of 
the successor State to which the objects of the endowment, under the 
terms thereof, are confined.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>792</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>301056</tid>
<number> 57</number> Provident fund.
<section><tid>431949</tid>
<number>1</number>The liability of the existing State of  
Punjab in respect of the provident fund account of a Government 
servant in service on the appointed day shall, on and from that day, 
be the liability of the successor State to which that Government 
servant is permanently allotted.

</section>

<section><tid>896868</tid>
<number>2</number>The liability of the existing State of Punjab in respect of 
the provident fund account of a Government servant who has retired 
from service before the appointed day shall be the liability of the 
State of Punjab in the first instance and shall be adjusted between 
the successor States according to the population ratio.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1072701</tid>
<number>58</number>Pensions. The liability of the existing State of Punjab in 
respect of pensions shall pass to, or be apportioned between, the 
successor States in accordance with the provisions contained in the 
Fourteenth Schedule.


</article>



<article><tid>1331895</tid>
<number> 59</number> Contracts.
<section><tid>1665998</tid>
<number>1</number>Where before the appointed day the existing  
State of Punjab has made any contract in the exercise of its executive 
power for any purpose of the State, that contract shall be deemed to 
have been made in the exercise of the executive power--

<subsection><tid>1560850</tid>
<number>a</number>if the purposes of the contract are, on and from the 
appointed day, exclusively purposes of any one of the 
successor States,-- of that State; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1980089</tid>
<number>b</number>if the purposes of the contract are, on and from that 
day, not exclusively purposes of any one of the 
successor States,-- of the State of Punjab,
and all rights and liabilities which have accrued, or may accrue, 
under any such contract shall, to the extent to which they would have 
been rights or liabilities of the existing State of Punjab, be rights 
or liabilities of the successor State or, as the case may be, the 
State of Punjab specified above:

Provided that in any such case as is referred to in clause (b), 
the initial allocation of rights and liabilities made by this sub- 
section shall be subject to such financial adjustment as may be agreed 
upon between all the successor States concerned, or in default of such 
agreement, as the Central Government may by order direct.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>272616</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes of this section, there shall be deemed to be 
included in the liabilities which have accrued or may accrue under any 
contract--

<subsection><tid>1117855</tid>
<number>a</number>any liability to satisfy an order or award made by any 
court or other tribunal in proceedings relating to the 
contract; and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>793</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>421254</tid>
<number>b</number>any liability in respect of expenses incurred in or in 
connection with any such proceedings.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>253909</tid>
<number>3</number>This section shall have effect subject to the other 
provisions of this Part relating to the apportionment of liabilities 
in respect of loans, guarantees and other financial obligations; and 
bank balances and securities shall, notwithstanding that they partake 
of the nature of contractual rights, be dealt with under those 
provisions.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>202907</tid>
<number> 60</number> Liability in respect of actionable wrong. Where, immediately 
before the appointed day, the existing State of Punjab is subject to 
any liability in respect of an actionable wrong other than breach of 
contract, that liability shall,--
<section><tid>759731</tid>
<number>a</number>if the cause of action arose wholly within the 
territories which on and from that day are the 
territories of one of the successor States, be a 
liability of that successor State; and

</section>

<section><tid>1090186</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, be initially a liability of the State 
of Punjab, but subject to such financial adjustment as 
may be agreed upon between all the successor States 
concerned, or in default of such agreement, as the 
Central Government may by order direct.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1205689</tid>
<number> 61</number> Liability as guarantor. Where, immediately before the 
appointed day, the existing State of Punjab is liable as guarantor in 
respect of any liability of a registered co- operative society or other 
person, that liability of the existing State of Punjab shall--
<section><tid>825432</tid>
<number>a</number>if the area of the operations of such society or person 
is limited to the territories which on and from that 
day are the territories of one of the successor States, 
be a liability of that successor State; and

</section>

<section><tid>1453659</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, be a liability of the State of 
Punjab:
Provided that in any such case as is referred to in clause (b) 
the initial allocation of liabilities under this section shall be 
subject to such financial adjustment as may be agreed upon between all 
the successor States, or in default of such agreement, as the Central 
Government may by order direct.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1284526</tid>
<number>62</number>Items in Suspense. If any item in suspense is ultimately 
found to affect an asset or liability of the nature referred to in any 
of the foregoing provisions of this Part, it shall be dealt with in 
accordance with that provision.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>794</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>601086</tid>
<number>63</number>Residuary provision. The benefit or burden of any assets or 
liabilities of the existing State of Punjab not dealt with in the 
foregoing provisions of this Part shall pass to the State of Punjab in 
the first instance, subject to such financial adjustment as may be 
agreed upon between all the successor States before the 1st day of 
November, <year>1967</year>, or in default of such agreement, as the Central 
Government may by order direct.


</article>



<article><tid>1046152</tid>
<number>64</number>Apportionment of assets or liabilities by agreement. Where 
the successor States agree that the benefit or burden of any 
particular asset or liability should be apportioned between them in a 
manner other than that provided for in the foregoing provisions of 
this Part, then, notwithstanding anything contained therein, the 
benefit or burden of that asset or liability shall be apportioned in 
the manner agreed upon.


</article>



<article><tid>1413001</tid>
<number>65</number>Power of Central Government to order allocation or adjustment 
in certain cases. Where, by virtue of any of the provisions of this 
Part, any of the successor States becomes entitled to any property or 
obtains any benefits or becomes subject to any liability, and the 
Central Government is of opinion, on a reference made within a period 
of three years from the appointed day by any State that it is just and 
equitable that that property or those benefits should be transferred 
to, or shared with, one or more of the other successor States, or that 
a contribution towards that liability should be made by one or more of 
the other successor States, the said property or benefits shall be 
allocated in such manner, or the other successor State or States shall 
make to the State primarily subject to the liability such contribution 
in respect thereof, as the Central Government may, after consultation 
with State Governments concerned by order determine.


</article>



<article><tid>1735644</tid>
<number>66</number>Certain expenditure to be charged on the Consolidated Fund. 
All sums payable by the Union to any State or by any State to any 
other State or to the Union by virtue of the provisions of this Part, 
or sub- section (4) of section 72, or section 77, or Part VIII shall be 
charged on the Consolidated Fund of India, or as the case may be, the 
Consolidated Fund of the State by which such sums are payable:
Provided that where any sums are payable as aforesaid by the 
Union in relation to the transferred territory, the Central Government 
may by order direct that sums payable in respect of such liabilities 
as may be specified therein shall be charged on the Consolidated Fund 
of the Union territory of Himachal Pradesh.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>795</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

PART

PROVISIONS AS TO CERTAIN CORPORATIONS

ART VII

PROVISIONS AS TO CERTAIN CORPORATIONS



</article>



<article><tid>992994</tid>
<number> 67</number> Provisions as to certain Corporations.
<section><tid>1265926</tid>
<number>1</number>The following  
bodies corporate constituted for the existing State of Punjab, 
namely:--

<subsection><tid>1020270</tid>
<number>a</number>the State Electricity Board constituted under the 
Electricity Supply Act, <year>1948</year>; (54 of <year>1948</year>.) and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>852851</tid>
<number>b</number>the State Warehousing Corporation established under the 
Warehousing Corporations Act, <year>1962</year>, (58 of <year>1962</year>.)
shall, on and from the appointed day, continue to function in those 
areas in respect of which they were functioning immediately before 
that day subject to the provisions of this section and to such 
directions as may, from time to time, be issued by the Central 
Government.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1797991</tid>
<number>2</number>Any directions issued by the Central Government under sub- 
section (1) in respect of the Board or the Corporation may include a 
direction that the Act under which the Board or the Corporation was 
constituted shall, in its application to that Board or Corporation, 
have effect subject to such exceptions and modifications as the 
Central Government thinks fit.

</section>

<section><tid>118645</tid>
<number>3</number>The Board or the Corporation referred to in sub- section (1) 
shall cease to function as from, and shall be deemed to be dissolved 
on, the 1st day of November, <year>1967</year>, or such earlier date as the Central 
Government may, by order, appoint; and upon such dissolution, its 
assets, rights and liabilities shall be apportioned between the 
successor States in such manner as may be agreed upon among them 
within one year of the dissolution of the Board or the Corporation, as 
the case may be, or if no agreement is reached, in such manner as the 
Central Government may, by order, determine.

</section>

<section><tid>1347033</tid>
<number>4</number>Nothing in the preceding provisions of this section shall be 
construed as preventing the Government of any of the successor States 
from constituting at any time on or after the appointed day, a State 
Electricity Board or a State Warehousing Corporation for that State 
under the provisions of the Act relating to such Board or Corporation; 
and if such a Board or a Corporation is so constituted in any of the 
successor States before the dissolution of the Board or the 
Corporation referred to in sub- section (1),--

<subsection><tid>275378</tid>
<number>a</number>provision may be made by order of the Central Government 
enabling the new Board or the new Corporation to take 
over from the existing Board or Corporation all or any 
of its undertakings, assets, rights and liabilities in 
that State, and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>796</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1435281</tid>
<number>b</number>upon the dissolution of the existing Board or 
Corporation, any assets, rights and liabilities which 
would otherwise have passed to that State by or under 
the provisions of sub- section (3) shall pass to the new 
Board or the new Corporation instead of to that State.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>460527</tid>
<number>68</number>Continuance of arrangements in regard to generation and 
supply of electric power and supply of water. If it appears to the 
Central Government that the arrangement in regard to the generation or 
supply of electric power or the supply of water for any area or in 
regard to the execution of any project for such generation or supply 
has been or is likely to be modified to the disadvantage of that area 
by reason of the fact that it has been transferred by the provisions 
of Part II from the State in which the power stations and other 
installations for the generation and supply of such power, or the 
catchment area, reservoirs and other works for the supply of water, as 
the case may be, are located, the Central Government may give such 
directions as it deems fit, to the State Government or other authority 
concerned for the maintenance, so far as practicable, of the previous 
arrangement.


</article>



<article><tid>1425744</tid>
<number> 69</number> Provisions as to Punjab State Financial Corporation.
<section><tid>284253</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Punjab State Financial Corporation established under the State 
Financial Corporations Act, <year>1951</year> (63 of <year>1951</year>), shall on and from the 
appointed day continue to function in those areas in respect of which 
it was functioning immediately before that day subject to the 
provisions of this section and to such directions, as may from time to 
time, be issued by the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1503374</tid>
<number>2</number>Any directions issued by the Central Government under sub- 
section (1) in respect of the Corporation may include a direction that 
the said Act, in its application to the Corporation, shall have effect 
subject to such exceptions and modifications as may be specified in 
the direction.

</section>

<section><tid>1257338</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1) or sub- 
section (2), the Board of Directors of the Corporation may, with the 
previous approval of the Central Government and shall, if so required 
by the Central Government, convene at any time after the appointed day 
a meeting for the consideration of a scheme for the reconstitution or 
reorganisation or dissolution, as the case may be, of the Corporation, 
including proposals regarding the formation of new corporations and 
the transfer thereto of the assets, rights and liabilities of the 
existing Corporation, and if such a scheme is approved at a general 
meeting by a resolution passed by a majority of the shareholders 
present and voting, the scheme shall be submitted to the Central 
Government for its sanction.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>797</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1539737</tid>
<number>4</number>If the scheme is sanctioned by the Central Government either 
without modifications or with modifications which are approved at a 
general meeting, the Central Government shall certify the scheme, and 
upon such certification the scheme shall, notwithstanding anything to 
the contrary contained in any law for the time being in force, be 
binding on the Corporations affected by the scheme as well as the 
shareholders and creditors thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>1498963</tid>
<number>5</number>If the scheme is not so approved or sanctioned, the Central 
Government may refer the scheme to such Judge of the High Court of 
Punjab and Haryana as may be nominated in this behalf by the Chief 
Justice thereof and the decision of the Judge in regard to the scheme 
shall be final and shall be binding on the Corporations affected by 
the scheme as well as the shareholders and creditors thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>1136531</tid>
<number>6</number>Nothing in the preceding provisions of this section shall be 
construed as preventing the Government of the State of Haryana or 
Punjab from constituting, at any time after the appointed day and with 
the approval of the Central Government, a State Financial Corporation 
for that State under the State Financial Corporations Act, <year>1951</year> (63  
  of <year>1951</year>).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1657702</tid>
<number>70</number>Amendment of Act 6 of <year>1942</year>. In the Multi- Unit Co- operative 
Societies Act, <year>1942</year>, after section 5C, the following section shall be 
inserted, namely:--
Transitional provision relating to certain multiunit co- operative 
societies.

</article>



<article><tid>1532036</tid>
<number> 5D</number> 
<section><tid>1469296</tid>
<number>1</number>Where, in respect of any co- operative society  
specified in the Fifteenth Schedule to the Punjab 
Reorganisation Act, <year>1966</year>, which under the provisions of 
sub- section (1) of section 5A would become a multi- unit 
co- operative society, the Board of Directors adopts, by 
a majority of not less than three- fourths of the 
directors, any scheme for the reconstitution, 
reorganisation or dissolution of the society, including 
proposals regarding--

<subsection><tid>112054</tid>
<number>a</number>the formation of new co- operative 
societies and the transfer thereto, in whole or in 
part, of the assets and liabilities and employees 
of that society; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1305221</tid>
<number>b</number>the transfer, in whole or in part, of the 
assets and liabilities and employees of that 
society to any other co- operative society in the 
existing State of Punjab or in the Union territory 
of Himachal Pradesh;
and the State Government of Punjab certifies the scheme at 
any time before the 1st day of November, <year>1966</year>, then, 
notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (2) or 
sub- section


<pagefootnote><pagenum>798</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1756674</tid>
<number>3</number>or sub- section (4) of the said section or any other law, 
regulation or bye- law for the time being in force in 
relation to that society, the scheme so certified shall be 
binding on all societies affected by the scheme, as well as 
the shareholders, creditors and employees of all such 
societies, subject to such financial adjustments as may be 
directed in this behalf under sub- section (3), but no such 
scheme shall be given effect to before the said day:
Provided that where a scheme includes any proposal regarding 
the transfer of assets and liabilities and employees to 
any co- operative society referred to in clause (b), the 
scheme shall not be binding on that existing society or 
the shareholders and creditors thereof, unless the 
proposal relating to such transfer is accepted by the 
existing society by a resolution passed by a majority 
of the members present at a meeting of its general 
body.


</section>

<section><tid>1883401</tid>
<number>2</number>When a scheme in respect of a co- operative society is so 
certified, the Central Registrar shall place the scheme 
at a meeting, held in such manner as may be prescribed 
by rules made under this Act, of all the persons who, 
immediately before the date of certification of the 
scheme, were members of the society, and the scheme may 
be approved by a resolution passed by a majority of the 
members present and voting at the said meeting.

</section>

<section><tid>1756674</tid>
<number>3</number>If the scheme is not so approved or is approved with 
modifications, the Central Registrar may refer the 
scheme to such Judge of the High Court of Punjab and 
Haryana as may be nominated in this behalf by the Chief 
Justice thereof and the Judge may direct such financial 
adjustments to be made among the societies affected as 
he deems necessary, and the scheme shall be deemed to 
be approved subject to those financial adjustments.

</section>

<section><tid>1579582</tid>
<number>4</number>If, in consequence of the directions given under sub- 
section (3), a society becomes liable to pay any sum of 
money, the successor State within whose area the 
society is located shall be deemed to be guarantor in 
respect of the payment of such money and shall be 
liable as such.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1977049</tid>
<number>71</number>Provision as to co- operative banks. Notwithstanding anything 
contained in section 22 of the Banking Regulation Act, <year>1949</year> (10 of  
  <year>1949</year>), where on account of the reorganisation of the existing State of 
Punjab, a co- operative bank is newly formed

<pagefootnote><pagenum>799</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

on the appointed day or within three months thereof in any of the 
successor States, it may commence and conduct banking business without 
obtaining a licence under that section from the Reserve Bank of India, 
until it is granted such a licence or until it is informed by the 
Reserve Bank of India that such a licence cannot be granted to it;

Provided that such bank applies to the Reserve Bank of India for 
such a licence within a period of three months from the date of 
formation of the bank.



</article>



<article><tid>1712331</tid>
<number> 72</number> General provisions as to statutory corporations.
<section><tid>185408</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as  
otherwise expressly provided by the foregoing provisions of this Part, 
where any body corporate constituted under a Central Act, State Act or 
Provincial Act for the existing State of Punjab or any part thereof 
serves the needs of the successor States or has, by virtue of the 
provisions of Part II, become an inter- State body corporate, then, the 
body corporate shall, on and from the appointed day, continue to 
function and operate in those areas in respect of which it was 
functioning and operating immediately before that day, subject to such 
directions as may from time to time be issued by the Central 
Government, until other provisions is made by law in respect of the 
said body corporate.

</section>

<section><tid>206216</tid>
<number>2</number>Any direction issued by the Central Government under sub- 
section (1) in respect of any such body corporate may include a 
direction that any law by which the said body corporate is governed 
shall, in its application to that body corporate, have effect, subject 
to such exceptions and modifications as may be specified in the 
direction. 
 (3) For the removal of doubt it is hereby declared that the 
provisions of this section shall apply also to the Punjab University 
constituted under the Punjab University Act, <year>1947</year> (East Punjab Act 7  
  of <year>1947</year>), the Punjab Agricultural University Act, <year>1961</year> (Punjab Act  
  32 of <year>1961</year>), and the Board constituted under the provisions of Part 
III of the Sikh Gurdwaras Act, <year>1925</year> (Punjab Act 8 of <year>1925</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>1195617</tid>
<number>4</number>For the purpose of giving effect to the provisions of this 
section in so far as it relates to the Punjab University and the 
Punjab Agricultural University referred to in sub- section (3) the 
successor States shall make such grants as the Central Government may, 
from time to time, by order, determine.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>379014</tid>
<number> 73</number> Provision as to certain companies.
<section><tid>1624325</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding  
anything contained in the foregoing provisions of this Part, each of 
the following companies, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1012758</tid>
<number>i</number>the Punjab Export Corporation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>429544</tid>
<number>ii</number>the Punjab State Small Industries Corporation;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>800</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1398793</tid>
<number>iii</number>the Punjab Dairy Development Corporation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>533143</tid>
<number>iv</number>the Punjab Poultry Corporation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1606010</tid>
<number>v</number>the Land Development and Seed Corporation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1994665</tid>
<number>vi</number>the Industrial Development Corporation; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1753265</tid>
<number>vii</number>the Agro- Industrial Corporation,
shall, on and from the appointed day and until otherwise provided for 
in any law, or in any agreement among the successor States, or in any 
direction issued by the Central Government, continue to function in 
the areas in which it was functioning immediately before that day; and 
the Central Government may from time to time issue such directions in 
relation to such functioning as it may deem fit, notwithstanding 
anything to the contrary contained in the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of  
  <year>1956</year>), or in any other law.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>936623</tid>
<number>2</number>Any directions issued under sub- section (1) in respect of a 
company referred to in that sub- section, may include directions--

<subsection><tid>1445131</tid>
<number>a</number>regarding the division of the interests and shares of 
the existing State of Punjab in the company among the 
successor States;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>632619</tid>
<number>b</number>requiring the reconstitution of the Board of Directors 
of the company so as to give adequate representation to 
all the successor States.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1981130</tid>
<number> 74</number> Temporary provisions as to continuance of certain existing 
road transport permits.
<section><tid>626496</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in  
section 63 of the Motor Vehicles Act, <year>1939</year> (4 of <year>1939</year>), a permit 
granted by the State or a Regional Transport Authority in the existing 
State of Punjab shall, if such permit was, immediately before the 
appointed day, valid and effective in any area therein, be deemed to 
continue to be valid and effective in that area after that day subject 
to the provisions of that Act as for the time being in force in that 
area and it shall not be necessary for any such permit to be 
countersigned by any State or Regional Transport Authority for the 
purpose of validating it for use in such area:
Provided that the Central Government may, after consultation with 
the State Government or Governments concerned, add to, amend or vary 
the conditions attached to the permit by the authority by which the 
permit was granted.


</section>

<section><tid>902899</tid>
<number>2</number>No tolls, entrance fees or other charges of a like nature 
shall be levied after the appointed day in respect of any transport 
vehicle for its operations in any of the successor States under any 
such permit, if such vehicle was immediately before that day exempt 
from

<pagefootnote><pagenum>801</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

the payment of any such toll, entrance fees or other charges for its 
operations within the existing State of Punjab:

Provided that the Central Government may, after consultation with 
the State Government or Governments concerned, authorise the levy of 
any such toll, entrance fees or other charges, as the case may be.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>356888</tid>
<number> 75</number> Special provision relating to re- trenchment compensation in 
certain cases. Where, on account of the reorganisation of the existing 
State of Punjab under this Act, any body corporate constituted under a 
Central Act, State Act or Provincial Act, any co- operative society 
registered under any law relating to co- operative societies or any 
commercial or industrial undertaking of that State is reconstituted or 
reorganised in any manner whatsoever or is amalgamated with any other 
body corporate, co- operative society or undertaking, or is dissolved, 
and in consequence of such reconstitution, reorganisation, 
amalgamation or dissolution, any workman employed by such body 
corporate or any such co- operative society or undertaking, is 
transferred to, or re- employed by any other body corporate, or in any 
other co- operative society or undertaking then notwithstanding 
anything contained in section 25F, 25FF or 25FFF, of the Industrial 
Disputes Act, <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>), such transfer or re- employment shall 
not entitle him to any compensation under that section:
Provided that--

<section><tid>1500692</tid>
<number>a</number>the terms and conditions of service applicable to the 
workman after such transfer or re- employment are not 
less favourable to the workman than those applicable to 
him immediately before the transfer or re- employment; 
and

</section>

<section><tid>700718</tid>
<number>b</number>the employer in relation to the body corporate, the 
cooperative society or the undertaking where the 
workman transferred or re- employed is, by agreement or 
otherwise, legally liable to pay to the workman, in the 
event of his retrenchment, compensation under section 
25F, 25FF or 25FFF of the Industrial Disputes Act, 
 <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>), on the basis that his service has 
been continuous and has not been interrupted by the 
transfer or re- employment.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1292420</tid>
<number>76</number>Special provision as to income- tax. Where the assets, rights 
and liabilities of any body corporate carrying on business are, under 
the provisions of this Part, transferred to any other bodies corporate 
which after the transfer carry on the same business, the losses of 
pofits or gains sustained by the body corporate first mentioned which, 
but for such transfer, would have been allowed to be carried forward 
and set off in accordance

<pagefootnote><pagenum>802</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

with the provisions of Chapter VI of the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> (43 of  
  <year>1961</year>), shall be apportioned amongst the transferee bodies corporate in 
accordance with the rules to be made by the Central Government in this 
behalf and, upon such apportionment, the share of loss allotted to 
each transferee body corporate shall be dealt with in accordance with 
the provisions of Chapter VI of the said Act as if the transferee body 
corporate had itself sustained such loss in a business carried on by 
it in the years in which these losses were sustained.



</article>



<article><tid>559899</tid>
<number> 77</number> Continuance of facilities in certain State institutions.
<section><tid>144221</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The Government of the State of Haryana or Punjab, or, as the case may 
be, the Central Government in relation to the transferred territory or 
the Union territory of Chandigarh, shall in respect of the 
institutions specified in the Sixteenth Schedule located in the State 
or territory aforesaid continue to provide facilities to any other 
Government aforesaid and the people of the States and territories 
aforesaid which shall not, in any respect, be less favourable to such 
Government and people than what were being provided to them before the 
appointed day for such period and upon such terms and conditions 
 (including those relating to any contributions to be made for the  
  provision of such facilities) as may be agreed upon between the said 
Governments before the 1st day of April, <year>1967</year>, or if no agreement is 
reached by the said date, as may be fixed by order of the Central 
Government.

</section>

<section><tid>237585</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may, at any time before the 1st day of 
April, <year>1967</year>, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify in the 
Sixteenth Schedule any other institution existing on the appointed day 
in the said States and territories and on the issue of such 
notification, the Schedule shall be deemed to be amended by the 
inclusion of the said institution therein.
PART

BHAKRA- NANGAL AND BEAS PROJECTS

PART VIII

BHAKRA- NANGAL AND BEAS PROJECTS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1285253</tid>
<number> 78</number> Rights and liabilities in regard to Bhakra- Nangal and Beas 
Projects.
<section><tid>1920156</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act but  
subject to the provisions of sections 79 and 80, all rights and 
liabilities of the existing State of Punjab in relation to Bhakra- 
Nangal Project and Beas Project shall, on the appointed day, be the 
rights and liabilities of the successor States in such proportion as 
may be fixed, and subject to such adjustments as may be made, by 
agreement entered into by the said States after consultation with the 
Central Government or, if no such agreement is entered into within two

<pagefootnote><pagenum>803</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

years of the appointed day, as the Central Government may by order 
determine having regard to the purposes of the Projects:

Provided that the order so made by the Central Government may be 
varied by any subsequent agreement entered into by the successor 
States after consultation with the Central Government.


</section>

<section><tid>1822219</tid>
<number>2</number>An agreement or order referred to in sub- section (1) shall, 
if there has been an extension or further development of either of the 
projects referred to in that sub- section after the appointed day, 
provide also for the rights and liabilities of the successor States in 
relation to such extension or further development.

</section>

<section><tid>1376167</tid>
<number>3</number>The rights and liabilities referred to in sub- sections (1) 
and (2) shall include--

<subsection><tid>164904</tid>
<number>a</number>the rights to receive and to utilise the water available 
for distribution as a result of the projects, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1349456</tid>
<number>b</number>the rights to receive and to utilise the power generated 
as a result of the projects,
but shall not include the rights and liabilities under any contract 
entered into before the appointed day by the Government of the 
existing State of Punjab with any person or authority other than 
Government.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>356580</tid>
<number>4</number>In this section and in sections 79 and 80,--

<subsection><tid>1016764</tid>
<number>A</number>" Beas Project" means the works which are either under 
construction or are to be constructed as components of 
the Beas- Sutlej Link Project (Unit I) and Pong Dam 
Project on the Beas river (Unit II) including--

<subsubsection><tid>1499686</tid>
<number>i</number>Beas- Sutlej Link Project (Unit I) comprising--

<subsubsubsection><tid>1460690</tid>
<number>a</number>Pandoh Dam and works appurtenant thereto,

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>683082</tid>
<number>b</number>Pandoh- Baggi Tunnel,

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1776036</tid>
<number>c</number>Sundernagar Hydel Channel,

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>874114</tid>
<number>d</number>Sundernagar- Sutlej Tunnel,

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1393656</tid>
<number>e</number>By- pass Tunnel,

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1573487</tid>
<number>f</number>four generating units each of 165 M. W. 
capacity at Dehar Power House on the right side of 
Sutlej river,

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1522815</tid>
<number>g</number>fifth generating unit of 120 M. W. 
capacity at Bhakra Right Bank Power House,

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>920396</tid>
<number>h</number>transmission lines,

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1166239</tid>
<number>i</number>Balancing Reservoir;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>804</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1602732</tid>
<number>ii</number>Pong Dam Project (Unit II) comprising--

<subsubsubsection><tid>1891426</tid>
<number>a</number>Pong Dam and works appurtenant thereto,

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>369112</tid>
<number>b</number>Outlet Works,

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1197965</tid>
<number>c</number>Penstock Tunnels,

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>760691</tid>
<number>d</number>Power plant with four generating units of 
 60 M. W. each;

</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>608670</tid>
<number>iii</number>such other works as are ancillary to the 
works aforesaid and are of common interest to more than 
one State;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1853578</tid>
<number>B</number>" Bhakra- Nangal Project" means--

<subsubsection><tid>398403</tid>
<number>i</number>Bhakra Dam, Reservoir and works appurtenant 
thereto;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>543437</tid>
<number>ii</number>Nangal Dam and Nangal- Hydel Channel;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1676610</tid>
<number>iii</number>Bhakra Main Line and canal system;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>845763</tid>
<number>iv</number>Bhakra Left Bank Power House, Ganguwal Power 
House and Kotla Power House, switchyards, sub- stations 
and transmission lines;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>954241</tid>
<number>v</number>Bhakra Right Bank Power House with four units 
of 120 M. W. each.



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1252251</tid>
<number> 79</number> Bhakra Management Board.
<section><tid>1688037</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government shall  
constitute a Board to be called the Bhakra Management Board for the 
administration, maintenance and operation of the following works, 
namely:--

<subsection><tid>104274</tid>
<number>a</number>Bhakra Dam and Reservior and works appurtenant thereto;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>382518</tid>
<number>b</number>Nangal Dam and Nangal- Hydel Channel up to Kotla Power 
House;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1781016</tid>
<number>c</number>the irrigation headworks at Rupar, Harike and Ferozepur;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1150418</tid>
<number>d</number>Bhakra Power Houses:
Provided that the administration, maintenance and operation 
by the said Board of the generating units of the Right 
Bank Power House as have not been commissioned shall 
commence as and when any such unit has been 
commissioned;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1042056</tid>
<number>e</number>Ganguwal and Kotla Power Houses;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>994293</tid>
<number>f</number>Sub- stations at Ganguwal, Ambala, Panipat, Delhi, 
Ludhiana, Sangrur and Hissar and the main 220 KV 
transmission lines connecting the said sub- stations 
with the power stations specified in clauses (d) and 
 (e); and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>805</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1926008</tid>
<number>g</number>such other works as the Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, specify.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1402272</tid>
<number>2</number>The Bhakra Management Board shall consist of--

<subsection><tid>815002</tid>
<number>a</number>a whole- time Chairman and two whole- time members to be 
appointed by the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>871665</tid>
<number>b</number>a representative each of the Governments of the States 
of Punjab, Haryana and Rajasthan and the Union 
territory of Himachal Pradesh to be nominated by the 
respective Governments or Administrator, as the case 
may be;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1791329</tid>
<number>c</number>two representatives of the Central Government to be 
nominated by that Government.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1407544</tid>
<number>3</number>The functions of the Bhakra Management Board shall include--

<subsection><tid>561110</tid>
<number>a</number>the regulation of the supply of water from the Bhakra- 
Nangal Project to the States of Haryana, Punjab and 
Rajasthan having regard to--

<subsubsection><tid>459649</tid>
<number>i</number>any agreement entered into or arrangement 
made between the Governments of the existing State 
of Punjab and the State of Rajasthan, and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>890062</tid>
<number>ii</number>the agreement or the order referred to 
in sub- section (1) of section 78;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>569438</tid>
<number>b</number>the regulation of the supply of power generated at the 
power houses referred to in sub- section (1) to any 
Electricity Board or other authority in charge of the 
distribution of power having regard to--

<subsubsection><tid>1434433</tid>
<number>i</number>any agreement entered into or arrangement 
made between the Governments of the existing State 
of Punjab and the State of Rajasthan,

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>490972</tid>
<number>ii</number>the agreement or the order referred to 
in sub- section (1) of section 78; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>427435</tid>
<number>iii</number>any agreement entered into or 
arrangement made by the existing State of Punjab 
or the Punjab Electricity Board or the State of 
Rajasthan or the Rajasthan Electricity Board with 
any other Electricity Board or authority in charge 
of distribution of power before the appointed day 
in relation to the supply of power generated at 
the power houses specified in sub- section (1);

<pagefootnote><pagenum>806</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1774013</tid>
<number>c</number>the construction of such of the remaining works 
connected with the Right Bank Power House as the 
Central Government may specify;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1924214</tid>
<number>d</number>such other functions as the Central Government may, 
after consultation with the Governments of the States 
of Haryana, Punjab and Rajasthan, entrust to it.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1999496</tid>
<number>4</number>The Bhakra Management Board may employ such staff as it may 
consider necessary for the efficient discharge of its functions under 
this Act:
Provided that every person who immediately before the 
constitution of the said Board was engaged in the construction, 
maintenance or operator of the works in sub- section (1) shall continue 
to be so employed under the Board in connection with the said works on 
the same terms and conditions of service as were applicable to him 
before such constitution until the Central Government by order directs 
otherwise:

Provided further that the said Board may at any time in 
consultation with State Government or the Electricity Board concerned 
and with the previous approval of the Central Government return any 
such person for service under that Government or Board.


</section>

<section><tid>710934</tid>
<number>5</number>The Governments of the successor States and of Rajasthan 
shall at all times provide the necessary funds to the Bhakra 
Management Board to meet all expenses (including the salaries and  
  allowances of the staff) required for the discharge of its functions 
and such amounts shall be apportioned among the successor States, the 
State of Rajasthan and Electricity Boards of the said States in such 
proportion as the Central Government may, having regard to the 
benefits to each of the said States or Boards, specify.

</section>

<section><tid>1319926</tid>
<number>6</number>The Bhakra Management Board shall be under the control of the 
Central Government and shall comply with such directions, as may from 
time to time, be given to it by that Government.

</section>

<section><tid>559078</tid>
<number>7</number>The Bhakra Management Board may with the approval of the 
Central Government delegate such of its powers, functions and duties 
as it may deem fit to the Chairman of the said Board or to any officer 
subordinate to the Board.

</section>

<section><tid>791545</tid>
<number>8</number>The Central Government may, for the purpose of enabling the 
Bhakra Management Board to function effectively, issue such directions 
to the State Governments of Haryana, Punjab and Rajasthan and the 
Administrator of the Union territory of Himachal

<pagefootnote><pagenum>807</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Pradesh or any other authority, and the State Governments, 
Administrator or authority shall comply with such directions.


</section>

<section><tid>1751105</tid>
<number>9</number>The Bhakra Management Board may, with the previous approval 
of the Central Government and by notification in the Official Gazette, 
make regulations consistent with this Act and the rules made 
thereunder, to provide for--

<subsection><tid>976012</tid>
<number>a</number>regulating the time and place of meetings of the Board 
and the procedure to be followed for the transaction of 
business at such meetings;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>210679</tid>
<number>b</number>delegation of powers and duties to the Chairman or any 
officer of the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>737923</tid>
<number>c</number>the appointment, and the regulation of the conditions of 
service, of the officers and other staff of the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>524454</tid>
<number>d</number>any other matter for which regulations are considered 
necessary by the Board.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>478762</tid>
<number> 80</number> Construction of Beas Project.
<section><tid>1257153</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything  
contained in this Act or in any other law, the construction (including  
  the completion of any work already commenced) of the Beas Project 
shall, on and from the appointed day, be undertaken by the Central 
Government on behalf of the successor States and the State of 
Rajasthan:
Provided that the Governments of the successor States and the 
State of Rajasthan shall at all times provide the necessary funds to 
the Central Government for the expenditure on the project[ including 
the expenses of the Board referred to in sub- section (2)] and such 
amounts shall be apportioned among the successor States and the State 
of Rajasthan in such proportion as may be fixed by the Central 
Government after consultation with the Governments of the said States.


</section>

<section><tid>1359697</tid>
<number>2</number>For the discharge of its functions under sub- section (1), the 
Central Government may--

<subsection><tid>1368563</tid>
<number>a</number>by notification in the Official Gazette and in 
consultation with the Governments of the successor 
States and the State of Rajasthan, constitute a Board 
to be called the Beas Construction Board with such 
members as it may deem fit and assign to the Board such 
functions as it may consider necessary; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>541689</tid>
<number>b</number>issue such directions to the State Governments of 
Haryana, Punjab and Rajasthan and the Administrator of 
the Union territory of Himachal Pradesh or any other 
authority,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>808</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

and the State Governments, Administrator or other 
authority shall comply with such directions.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1213080</tid>
<number>3</number>The notification constituting a Board under clause (a) of 
sub- section (2) may empower the Board to appoint such staff as may be 
necessary for the efficient discharge of its functions:
Provided that every person who immediately before the 
constitution of the Board was engaged in the construction or any work 
relating to the Beas Project shall continue to be so employed by the 
Board in connection with the said works on the same terms and 
conditions of service as were applicable to him before such 
constitution until the Central Government by order directs otherwise:

Provided further that the Board may at any time in consultation 
with the State Government or the Electricity Board concerned and with 
the previous approval of the Central Government return any such person 
for service under that Government or Board.


</section>

<section><tid>133135</tid>
<number>4</number>Nothing contained in this section shall be construed as 
enabling the Central Government to reduce or enlarge the scope of the 
Beas Project as agreed to between the Governments of the State of 
Rajasthan and the existing State of Punjab except after consultation 
with the Governments of the States of Haryana, Punjab and Rajasthan.

</section>

<section><tid>558117</tid>
<number>5</number>Any component of the Beas Project in relation to which the 
construction has been completed after the appointed day may be 
transferred by the Central Government to the Board constituted under 
section 79 whereupon the provisions of that section shall apply as if 
it were a work included in sub- section (1) of that section.

</section>

<section><tid>721382</tid>
<number>6</number>The Bhakra Management Board constituted under section 79 
shall be re- named as the Bhakra Beas Management Board when any of the 
components of the Beas Project has been transferred under sub- section 
 (5), and the Beas Construction Board shall cease to exist when all the 
components of the Beas Project have been so transferred.
PART

PROVISIONS AS TO SERVICES

PART IX

PROVISIONS AS TO SERVICES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1799227</tid>
<number> 81</number> Provisions relating to All- India Services.
<section><tid>823620</tid>
<number>1</number>In this  
section, the expression" State cadre"--

<subsection><tid>537668</tid>
<number>a</number>in relation to the Indian Administrative Service, has 
the meaning assigned to it in the Indian Administrative 
Service (Cadre) Rules, <year>1954</year>, and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>809</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>492993</tid>
<number>b</number>in relation to the Indian Police Service, has the 
meaning assigned to it in the Indian Police Service 
 (Cadre) Rules, <year>1954</year>.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1551869</tid>
<number>2</number>In place of the cadres of the Indian Administrative Service 
and the Indian Police Service for the existing State of Punjab, there 
shall, on and from the appointed day, be two separate cadres, one for 
the State of Punjab and the other for the State of Haryana, in respect 
of each of these Services.

</section>

<section><tid>1114676</tid>
<number>3</number>The initial strength and composition of each of the State 
cadres for the States of Punjab and Haryana and the strength and 
composition of the Delhi- Himachal Pradesh State cadres shall be such 
as the Central Government may, by order, determine before the 
appointed day.

</section>

<section><tid>1436481</tid>
<number>4</number>The members of each of the said Services borne on the State 
cadres for the existing State of Punjab immediately before the 
appointed day shall be allocated to the State cadres of the same 
Service for each of the States of Punjab and Haryana and to the Delhi- 
Himachal Pradesh State cadres in such manner and with effect from such 
date or dates as the Central Government may, by order, specify.

</section>

<section><tid>593223</tid>
<number>5</number>Nothing in this section shall be deemed to affect the 
operation, on or after the appointed day, of the All- India Services 
Act, <year>1951</year> (61 of <year>1951</year>), or the rules made thereunder in relation to 
the State cadres of the said Services referred to in sub- section (3) 
and in relation to the members of those Services borne on the said 
cadres.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1150315</tid>
<number> 82</number> Provisions relating to other Services.
<section><tid>784454</tid>
<number>1</number>Every person who  
immediately before the appointed day is serving in connection with the 
affairs of the existing State of Punjab shall, on and from that day, 
provisionally continue to serve in connection with the affairs of the 
State of Punjab unless he is required, by general or special order of 
the Central Government, to serve provisionally in connection with the 
affairs of any other successor State.

</section>

<section><tid>1729138</tid>
<number>2</number>As soon as may be after the appointed day, the Central 
Government shall, by general or special order, determine the successor 
State to which every person referred to in sub- section (1) shall be 
finally allotted for service and the date with effect from which such 
allotment shall take effect or be deemed to have taken effect.

</section>

<section><tid>868720</tid>
<number>3</number>Every person who is finally allotted under the provisions of 
sub- section (2) to a successor State shall, if he is not already 
serving therein, be made available for serving in the successor State 
from such date as may be agreed upon between the Governments

<pagefootnote><pagenum>810</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

concerned or in default of such agreement, as may be determined by the 
Central Government.


</section>

<section><tid>406492</tid>
<number>4</number>The Central Government may, by order, establish one or more 
advisory committees for the purpose of assisting it in regard to--

<subsection><tid>1650564</tid>
<number>a</number>the division and integration of the services among the 
successor States; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1889990</tid>
<number>b</number>the ensuring of fair and equitable treatment to all 
persons affected by the provisions of this section and 
the proper consideration of any representations made by 
such persons.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1509127</tid>
<number>5</number>The foregoing provisions of this section shall not apply in 
relation to any person to whom the provisions of section 81 apply.

</section>

<section><tid>1308535</tid>
<number>6</number>Nothing in this section shall be deemed to affect on or after 
the appointed day the operation of the provisions of Chapter I of Part 
XIV of the Constitution in relation to the determination of the 
conditions of service of persons serving in connection with the 
affairs of the Union or any State:
Provided that the conditions of service applicable immediately 
before the appointed day to the case of any person referred to in sub- 
section (1) or sub- section (2) shall not be varied to his disadvantage 
except with the previous approval of the Central Government.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1154030</tid>
<number>83</number>Provisions as to continuance of officers in the same posts. 
Every person who immediately before the appointed day is holding or 
discharging the duties of any post or office in connection with the 
affairs of the existing State of Punjab in any area which on that day 
falls within any of the successor States shall continue to hold the 
same post or office in that successor State and shall be deemed, on 
and from that day, to have been duly appointed to the post or office 
by the Government of, or other appropriate authority in, that 
successor State:
Provided that nothing in this section shall be deemed to prevent 
a competent authority on or after the appointed day from passing in 
relation to such person any order affecting his continuance in such 
post or office.



</article>



<article><tid>747616</tid>
<number>84</number>Power of Central Government to give directions. The Central 
Government may give such directions to the State Governments of Punjab 
and Haryana and to the Administra-

<pagefootnote><pagenum>811</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

tors of the Union terriories of Himachal Pradesh and Chandigarh as may 
appear to it to be necessary for the purpose of giving effect to the 
foregoing provisions of this Part and the State Governments and the 
Administrators shall comply with such directions.



</article>



<article><tid>408322</tid>
<number> 85</number> Provisions as to State Public Service Commissions.
<section><tid>3255</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Public Service Commission for the existing State of Punjab shall, on 
and from the appointed day, cease to exist.

</section>

<section><tid>34023</tid>
<number>2</number>The person holding office immediately before the appointed 
day as Chairman of the Public Service Commission for the existing 
State of Punjab shall become the Chairman of the Public Service 
Commission for the State of Haryana or Punjab as the President shall, 
by order, specify and every other person holding office immediately 
before that day as member of that Commission shall become a member, or 
if so specified by the President, the Chairman, of such one of the 
said Commissions as the President shall, by order, specify.

</section>

<section><tid>588920</tid>
<number>3</number>Every person who becomes the Chairman or other member of a 
Public Service Commission on the appointed day under sub- section (2) 
shall--

<subsection><tid>1872259</tid>
<number>a</number>be entitled to receive from the Government of the State 
conditions of service not less favourable than those to 
which he was entitled under the provisions applicable 
to him immediately before the appointed day;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>47111</tid>
<number>b</number>subject to the proviso to clause (2) of article 316, 
hold office or continue to hold office until the 
expiration of his term of office as determined under 
the provisions applicable to him immediately before the 
appointed day.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1396642</tid>
<number>4</number>The report of the Punjab Public Service Commission as to the 
work done by the Commission in respect of any period prior to the 
appointed day shall be presented under clause (2) of article 323 to 
the Governors of Punjab and Haryana, and the Governor of Punjab shall, 
on receipt of such report, cause a copy thereof together with a 
memorandum explaining as far as possible, as respects the cases, if 
any, where the advice of the Commission was not accepted, the reasons 
for such non- acceptance to be laid before the Legislature of the State 
of Punjab and it shall not be necessary to cause such report or any 
such memorandum to be laid before the Legislative Assembly of Haryana.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>812</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

PART

LEGAL AND MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS

PART X

LEGAL AND MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>108501</tid>
<number> 86</number> Amendment of Act 37 of <year>1956</year>. In clause (a) of section 15 of 
the States Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year>,--
<section><tid>854302</tid>
<number>i</number>for the word" Punjab", the words" Haryana, Punjab" shall 
be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1672045</tid>
<number>ii</number>for the words" and Himachal Pradesh", the words 
" Himachal Pradesh and Chandigarh" shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1026771</tid>
<number>87</number>Power to extend enactments to Chandigarh. The Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, extend with 
such restrictions or modifications as it thinks fit, to the Union 
territory of Chandigarh any enactment which is in force in a State at 
the date of the notification.


</article>



<article><tid>737021</tid>
<number>88</number>Territorial extent of laws. The provisions of Part II shall 
not be deemed to have effected any change in the territories to which 
any law in force immediately before the appointed day extends or 
applies, and territorial references in any such law to the State of 
Punjab shall, until otherwise provided by a competent Legislature or 
other competent authority, be construed as meaning the territories 
within that State immediately before the appointed day.


</article>



<article><tid>1519308</tid>
<number> 89</number> Power to adapt laws. For the purpose of facilitating the 
application in relation to the State of Punjab or Haryana or to the 
Union territory of Himachal Pradesh or Chandigarh of any law made 
before the appointed day, the appropriate Government may, before the 
expiration of two years from that day, by order, make such adaptations 
and modifications of the law, whether by way of repeal or amendment, 
as may be necessary or expedient, and thereupon every such law shall 
have effect subject to the adaptations and modifications so made until 
altered, repealed or amended by a competent Legislature or other 
competent authority.
Explanation.-- In this section, the expression" appropriate 
Government" means--

<section><tid>72613</tid>
<number>a</number>as respects any law relating to a matter enumerated in 
the Union List, the Central Government; and

</section>

<section><tid>1523831</tid>
<number>b</number>as respects any other law,--

<subsection><tid>1672302</tid>
<number>i</number>in its application to a State, the State 
Government, and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>813</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>713722</tid>
<number>ii</number>in its application to a Union territory, the 
Central Government.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>615530</tid>
<number> 90</number> Power to construe laws.
<section><tid>1947474</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding that no provision  
or insufficient provision has been made under section 89 for the 
adaptation of a law made before the appointed day, any court, tribunal 
or authority, required or empowered to enforce such law may, for the 
purpose of facilitating its application in relation to the State of 
Punjab or Haryana, or to the Union territory of Himachal Pradesh or 
Chandigarh construe the law in such manner, without affecting the 
substance, as may be necessary or proper in regard to the matter 
before the court, tribunal or authority.

</section>

<section><tid>183054</tid>
<number>2</number>Any reference to the High Court of Punjab in any law shall, 
unless the context otherwise requires, be construed, on and from the 
appointed day, as a reference to the High Court of Punjab and Haryana.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>841041</tid>
<number>91</number>Power to name authorities, etc., for exercising statutory 
functions. The Central Government, as respects the Union territory of 
Chandigarh or the transferred territory, and the Government of the 
State of Haryana as respects the territories thereof may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, specify the authority, officer 
or person who, on and from the appointed day, shall be competent to 
exercise such functions exercisable under any law in force on that day 
as may be mentioned in that notification and such law shall have 
effect accordingly.


</article>



<article><tid>1962065</tid>
<number>92</number>Legal proceedings. Where, immediately before the appointed 
day, the existing State of Punjab is a party to any legal proceedings 
with respect to any property, rights or liabilities subject to 
apportionment under this Act, the successor State which succeeds to, 
or acquires a share in, that property or those rights or liabilities 
by virtue of any provision of this Act shall be deemed to be 
substituted for the existing State of Punjab or added as a party to 
those proceedings, and the proceedings may continue accordingly.


</article>



<article><tid>222250</tid>
<number> 93</number> Transfer of pending proceedings.
<section><tid>1075263</tid>
<number>1</number>Every proceeding pending  
immediately before the appointed day before a court (other than a High  
  Court), tribunal, authority or officer in any area which on that day 
falls within a State or Union territory shall, if it is a proceeding 
relating exclusively to the territories which as from that day are the 
territories of another State or Union territory, stand transferred to 
the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>814</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

corresponding court, tribunal, authority or officer in that other 
State or Union territory, as the case may be.


</section>

<section><tid>1603821</tid>
<number>2</number>If any question arises as to whether any proceeding should 
stand transferred under sub- section (1), it shall be referred to the 
High Court having jurisdiction in respect of the area in which the 
court, tribunal, authority or officer before which or whom such 
proceeding is pending on the appointed day, is functioning, and the 
decision of that High Court shall be final.

</section>

<section><tid>1671101</tid>
<number>3</number>In this section--

<subsection><tid>423878</tid>
<number>a</number>" proceeding" includes any suit, case or appeal; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1950864</tid>
<number>b</number>" corresponding court, tribunal, authority or officer" in 
a State or a Union territory means--

<subsubsection><tid>1157953</tid>
<number>i</number>the court, tribunal, authority or officer in 
that State or a Union territory in which or before 
whom, the proceeding would have lain if it had been 
instituted after the appointed day; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>765956</tid>
<number>ii</number>in case of doubt, such court, tribunal, 
authority or officer in that State or Union territory, 
as may be determined after the appointed day by the 
Government of that State or the Central Government, as 
the case may be, or before the appointed day by the 
Government of the existing State of Punjab, to be the 
corresponding court, tribunal, authority or officer.



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>563222</tid>
<number>94</number>Right of pleaders to practise in certain cases. Any person 
who, immediately before the appointed day, is enrolled as a pleader 
entitled to practise in any subordinate courts in the existing State 
of Punjab shall, for a period of one year from that day, continue to 
be entitled to practise in those courts, notwithstanding that the 
whole or any part of the territories within the jurisdiction of those 
courts has been transferred to the State of Haryana or to a Union 
territory.


</article>



<article><tid>1202292</tid>
<number>95</number>Effect of provisions of the Act inconsistent with other laws. 
The provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
inconsistent therewith contained in any other law.


</article>



<article><tid>1675889</tid>
<number>96</number>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in 
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the President may, by 
order, do anything not inconsistent with such provisions which appears 
to him to be necessary or expedient for the purpose of removing the 
difficulty.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>815</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>531319</tid>
<number> 97</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>491248</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to give effect to the 
provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1797438</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1163355</tid>
<number>a</number>the procedure to be followed by the Bhakra Management 
Board and the Beas Construction Board for the conduct 
of business and for the proper functioning of the 
Boards and the manner of filling casual vacancies among 
the members of the said Boards;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1074364</tid>
<number>b</number>the salaries and allowances to be paid to the whole- time 
Chairman and whole- time members of the Bhakra Manage- 
ment Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>557285</tid>
<number>c</number>the salaries and allowances and other conditions of 
service of the members of the staff of the Bhakra 
Management Board or the Beas Construction Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1598486</tid>
<number>d</number>the maintenance of records of all business transacted at 
the meetings of the Bhakra Management Board or the Beas 
Construction Board and the submission of copies of such 
records to the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>179892</tid>
<number>e</number>the conditions subject to which, and the mode in which, 
contracts may be made on behalf of the successor States 
and the State of Rajasthan in relation to the functions 
of the Bhakra Management Board or the Beas Construction 
Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>724126</tid>
<number>f</number>the preparation of the budget estimates of the receipts 
and expenditure of the said Boards and the authority by 
which such estimates shall be approved;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1623739</tid>
<number>g</number>the conditions subject to which the said Boards may 
incur expenditure or re- appropriate funds from any 
budget head to another such head;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1940631</tid>
<number>h</number>the preparation and submission of annual reports;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>832283</tid>
<number>i</number>the maintenance of accounts of the expenditure incurred 
by the said Boards;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>153854</tid>
<number>j</number>any other matter which is to be, or may be, prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1065075</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as 
may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament while it is 
in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised

<pagefootnote><pagenum>816</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

in one session or <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in two or more successive sessions, and if, 
before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or 
the successive sessions aforesaid], both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so however that any such 
modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validly of 
anything previously done under that rule.



</section>

</article>



 </act>