<act><tid>941434</tid>
<title>THE FARIDABAD DEVELOPMENT CORPORATION ACT, <year>1956</year></title>

ACT NO. 90 OF <year>1956</year>
[ 28th December, <year>1956</year>.]

An Act to provide for the establishment and regulation of a trading 
Corporation for the purpose of carrying on and promoting trade and 
industry in the town of Faridabad, assisting in the rehabilitation of 
displaced persons settled therein and for matters connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Seventh Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>31987</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Faridabad Development 
Corporation Act, <year>1956</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1894938</tid>
<number>2</number>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context 
otherwiserequires,- (a)" Corporation" means the Faridabad Development 
Corpo- ration established under sec
CHAP

ESTABLISHMENT OF THE CORPORATION

CHAPTER II

ESTABLISHMENT OF THE CORPORATION



</article>



<article><tid>817525</tid>
<number> 3</number> Incorporation.
<section><tid>648492</tid>
<number>1</number>With effect from such date as the Central  
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint in 
this behalf, there shall be established a Corporation by the name of 
the Faridabad Development Corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>149259</tid>
<number>2</number>The said Corporation shall be a body corporate having 
perpetual succession and a common seal, and shall by the said name sue 
and to be sued.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>130109</tid>
<number>4</number>Constitution of the Corporation. The Corporation shall consist 
of a Chairman and such other members, being not less than four and not 
more than eight, as the Central Government may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, appoint.


</article>



<article><tid>284480</tid>
<number> 5</number> Term and conditions of service of members.
<section><tid>1507628</tid>
<number>1</number>The term of  
office and conditions of service of the Chairman and other members 
shall be such as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1080409</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chairman or any other member may resign his office by 
writing under his hand addressed to the Central Government, but he 
shall continue in office until the appointment of his successor is 
notified in the Official Gazette.

</section>

<section><tid>1867615</tid>
<number>3</number>A casual vacancy created by the resignation of the Chairman 
or any other member under sub- section (2) or for any other reason 
shall be filled by fresh appointment.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1908554</tid>
<number>6</number>Disqualification for being appointed, or for continuing as, 
member of the Corporation. A person shall be disqualified for being 
appointed or for continuing as a member of the Corporation if he has, 
directly or indirectly, any interest in a subsisting contract made 
with, or in any work being done, for, the Corporation except as a 
shareholder (other than a director) in an incorporated company:
Provided that where he is a shareholder, he shall disclose to the 
Central Government the nature and extent of shares held by him in such 
company.



</article>



<article><tid>96265</tid>
<number>7</number>Temporary absence of any member. If any member of the 
Corporation is by infirmity or otherwise rendered temporarily 
incapable of carrying out his duties or is absent on leave or 
otherwise in circumstances not involving the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>105</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

vacation of his appointment, the Central Government may appoint 
another person to act in his place during his absence.



</article>



<article><tid>1290511</tid>
<number>8</number>Vacancies amongst members or defect in the constitution not to 
invalidate acts or proceedings of the Corporation. No act or 
proceeding of the Corporation shall be invalid by reason only of the 
existence of any vacancy amongst its members or any defect in the 
constitution thereof.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>105</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>801272</tid>
<number>9</number>Committees of the Corporation. The Corporation may constitute 
such committees for general or special purposes as the Corporation 
deems necessary to carry out the purposes of this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>524909</tid>
<number> 10</number> Meetings of the Corporation.
<section><tid>1853246</tid>
<number>1</number>The Corporation shall meet  
for the transaction of business at such times and places as may be 
prescribed:
Provided that the Chairman may, whenever he thinks fit, and 
shall, upon the written requisition of not less than two members, call 
a special meeting.


</section>

<section><tid>1494690</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chairman or, in his absence, any member chosen by the 
members present from among themselves, shall preside at a meeting of 
the Corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>1912641</tid>
<number>3</number>All questions which come before any meeting of the 
Corporation shall be decided by majority of votes of the members 
present, and in the case of an equality of votes, the Chairman, or in 
his absence, any other person presiding, shall have a second or 
casting vote.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1707111</tid>
<number>11</number>Authentication of orders and other instruments of theCorporation. All 
orders and decisions of the Corporation sha


</article>



<article><tid>1554533</tid>
<number> 12</number> Appointment of Administrator and other officer of the 
Corporation.
<section><tid>57318</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be an Administrator of the Corporation  
who shall be appointed by the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1816884</tid>
<number>2</number>The Administrator shall be the chief executive officer of the 
Corporation and all other officers of the Corporation shall be 
subordinate to him.

</section>

<section><tid>575411</tid>
<number>3</number>The Administrator shall have the right to take part in the 
discussions of the Corporation or of any of its committees but shall 
not have the right to vote at the meetings of the Corporation or of 
any of its committees:
Provided that when one of the members of the Corporation is 
appointed under sub- section (1) as the Administrator, such 
Administrator shall have all the rights and privileges of a member.


</section>

<section><tid>1473203</tid>
<number>4</number>The Corporation may appoint such other officers as it may 
consider necessary for the efficient performance of its functions 
under this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>106</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

CHAP

POWERS AND FUNCTIONS OF THE CORPORATION

CHAPTER III

POWERS AND FUNCTIONS OF THE CORPORATION




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1309262</tid>
<number>13</number>General duty of Corporation. It shall be the general duty of 
the Corporation to carry on and promote trade, business and industry 
in Faridabad, to assist in the rehabilitation of displaced persons 
settled therein and to manage and develop the property of the Union 
vested in the Corporation.


</article>



<article><tid>1124200</tid>
<number> 14</number> Powers of the Corporation.
<section><tid>1535422</tid>
<number>1</number>The Corporation may exercise  
all such powers as may be necessary or expedient for the purpose of 
carrying out its functions under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>722880</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
provision, such power shall include the power-

<subsection><tid>389638</tid>
<number>a</number>to acquire and hold such property, both movable and 
immovable, as the Corporation may deem necessary for 
efficiently performing its functions under this Act and 
to make improvements in such property and to transfer 
by way of sale, lease or otherwise any such property;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1989390</tid>
<number>b</number>to carry on or promote any trade, business or industry;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1684343</tid>
<number>c</number>to give financial or other assistance to persons to 
enable them to carry on trade, business or industry in 
Faridabad primarily with a view to providing employment 
to, and rehabilitating, displaced persons settled 
therein;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1782619</tid>
<number>d</number>to construct or cause to be constructed residential or 
other buildings and to sell or let such buildings or 
cause them to be sold or let, on such terms as may be 
prescribed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>465743</tid>
<number>e</number>to advance loans on such terms and for such purposes as 
may be prescribed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1032649</tid>
<number>f</number>to supply or cause to be supplied, in accordance with 
the law for the time being in force, electrical energy 
for domestic and industrial purposes at reasonable 
rates;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1085154</tid>
<number>g</number>to take such other measures as the Corporation may deem 
necessary for the rehabilitation of displaced persons 
settled in Faridabad;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1496773</tid>
<number>h</number>to take such steps as may be necessary for improving 
the economic and social conditions of the inhabitants 
of Faridabad.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>468</tid>
<number>3</number>Nothing in this section shall affect the exercise of any 
power or the performance of any function by any local authority having 
jurisdiction in Faridabad.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>107</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1577493</tid>
<number>15</number>Capital of the Corporation. All non- recurring expenditure 
incurred by the Central Government or the body known as the Faridabad 
Development Board for and in connection with the development of 
Faridabad or for any of the purposes referred to in this Act upto the 
date of the establishment of the Corporation and declared to be 
capital expenditure by the Central Government shall be treated as the 
capital provided by the Central Government to the Corporation.


</article>



<article><tid>695041</tid>
<number>16</number>Grants and loans to the Corporation. The Central Government 
may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in this behalf, 
make such grants and advance such loans to the Corporation as the 
Central Government may deem necessary for the performance of the 
functions of the Corporation under this Act; and all grants made and 
all loans advanced shall be on such terms and conditions as the 
Central Government may determine.


</article>



<article><tid>263700</tid>
<number>17</number>Vesting of property in the Corporation. All property, assets 
and funds owned or acquired by the Central Government or purporting to 
have been owned or acquired by the body known as the Faridabad 
Development Board for the purposes of the development of Faridabad or 
for any of the purposes referred to in this Act before the 
establishment of the Corporation shall, on such establishment, vest in 
the Corporation unless the Central Government otherwise directs in 
respects of any part of such property, assets or funds.


</article>



<article><tid>1954158</tid>
<number>18</number>Repayment of capital and loan with interest. The Corporation 
shall repay, at such intervals and on such terms as the Central 
Government may determine, the amount of capital provided under section 
 15 and all loans advanced under section 16 with interest at such rate 
as may, from time to time, be fixed by that Government and such 
repayment of capital or loan or payment of interest shall be deemed to 
be part of the expenditure of the Corporation.


</article>



<article><tid>1192076</tid>
<number> 19</number> Corporation to have rights and liabilities of the Central 
Government in certain case.
<section><tid>883536</tid>
<number>1</number>All rights, liabilities and  
obligations of the Central Government which, whether arising out of 
any contract or otherwise, were acquired or incurred by it in 
connection with any transaction for the development of Faridabad or 
for any of the purposes referred to in this Act before the 
establishment of the Corporation, shall be deemed to have been 
acquired or incurred by the Corporation and shall be the rights, 
liabilities and obligations, respectively, of the Corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>1830664</tid>
<number>2</number>All suits or other legal proceedings instituted or which 
might but for the issue of the notification under sub- section (1) of 
section 3

<pagefootnote><pagenum>108</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

have been instituted by or against the Central Government may be 
continued or instituted by or against the Corporation.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>864485</tid>
<number> 20</number> Fund of the Corporation.
<section><tid>433314</tid>
<number>1</number>The Corporation shall have its  
own Fund and all receipts of the Corporation shall be carried thereto 
and all payments by the Corporation shall be made therefrom.

</section>

<section><tid>264515</tid>
<number>2</number>All moneys belonging to the Fund shall be deposited in such 
bank or invested in such manner as may be decided by the Corporation.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>49915</tid>
<number> 21</number> Provision for depreciation and reserve and other funds.
<section><tid>811046</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The Corporation shall make such provision for depreciation and for 
reserve and other funds as the Central Government may from time to 
time direct.

</section>

<section><tid>1326143</tid>
<number>2</number>The management of these funds, the sums to be carried from 
time to time to the credit thereof and the application of the moneys 
comprised therein shall be determined in accordance with such 
directions as the Central Government may from time to time issue.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>569545</tid>
<number>22</number>Power of the Corporation to spend. The Corporation shall have 
power to spend such sums as it thinks fit for performing its functions 
under this Act, and such sums shall be treated as expenditure payable 
out of the Fund of the Corporation.


</article>



<article><tid>348670</tid>
<number>23</number>Budget. The Corporation shall prepare, in such form and at 
such time each year as may be prescribed, a budget in respect of every 
financial year next ensuing showing the estimated receipts and 
expenditure, and copies thereof shall be forwarded to the Central 
Government.


</article>



<article><tid>640624</tid>
<number>24</number>Annual report. The Corporation shall prepare in such form and 
at such time each year as may be prescribed an annual report giving a 
true and full account of its activities during the previous financial 
year and copies thereof shall be sent to the Central Government and 
the Government of the State of Punjab.


</article>



<article><tid>442546</tid>
<number> 25</number> Accounts and audit.
<section><tid>726873</tid>
<number>1</number>The Corporation shall cause to be  
maintained such books of account and other books in relation to its 
accounts in such form and in such manner as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1371300</tid>
<number>2</number>The accounts of the Corporation shall be audited at such 
times and in such manner as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1613879</tid>
<number> 26</number> Amount due to the Corporation to be first charge.
<section><tid>1029609</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law, where a loan has 
been advanced to any person for the construction of a building or 
where a building has been transferred to any person,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>109</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

the amount due to the Corporation on account of the loan or transfer 
together with interest thereon shall be a first charge on the building 
so constructed or transferred.


</section>

<section><tid>465343</tid>
<number>2</number>The Corporation may also take such further security as it may 
consider necessary for advancing any loan or for transferring any 
building.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER IV

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>948032</tid>
<number>27</number>Direction. For the purposes of this Act, the Central 
Government may, from time to time, give to the Corporation such 
general or special directions as the Central Government thinks fit and 
in the performance of the functions, the Corporation shall comply with 
such directions.


</article>



<article><tid>625624</tid>
<number>28</number>Returns and reports. The Corporation shall furnish to the 
Central Government such returns, statistics, accounts and other 
information with respect to its property or activities as the Central 
Government may from time to time require.


</article>



<article><tid>1924121</tid>
<number>29</number>Mode of recovery of moneys due to the Corporation. When any 
money is due to the Corporation from any person, then, without 
prejudice to any other mode of recovery, the Corporation may, after 
giving that person an opportunity of being heard, issue a certificate 
to the Collector of the amount due and the Collector shall proceed to 
recover that amount in the same manner as an arrear of land revenue.


</article>



<article><tid>127547</tid>
<number>30</number>Delegation of powers. The Corporation may, by general or 
special order in writing, delegate to the Chairman or any other member 
or any officer of the Corporation, subject to such conditions and 
limitations (if any) as may be specified in the order, such of its 
powers and duties under this Act as it may deem necessary for the 
efficient running of the day- to- day administration of the Corporation.


</article>



<article><tid>1328469</tid>
<number>31</number>Members and officers of the Corporation to be public 
servants. All members and officers of the Corporation shall, when 
acting or purporting to act in pursuance of any of the provisions of 
this Act, be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of 
section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>789012</tid>
<number>32</number>Removal of disqualification for membership of Parliament. It 
is hereby declared that the office of the member of the Corporation 
shall not disqualify its holder for being chosen as, or for being, a 
member of either House of Parliament.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>110</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1006624</tid>
<number>33</number>Bar of legal proceedings. No suit or other legal proceedings 
shall lie against any member or officer of the Corporation in respect 
of anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in 
pursuance of this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1717314</tid>
<number> 34</number> Validation of certain transactions. On the establishment of 
the Corporation under section 3,-
<section><tid>1278402</tid>
<number>a</number>all action purporting to have been taken, and all 
transactions purporting to have been made, by or with 
the body known as the Faridabad Development Board 
 (including any action or transaction by which any  
property, asset or right was purported to have been 
acquired or any liability or obligation, whether by 
contract or otherwise, was purported to have been 
  incurred) shall be deemed to have been validly and 
lawfully taken or made by or with the Corporation as if 
this Act were in force and the Corporation were in 
existence on the day on which such action was taken or 
transaction was made; and

</section>

<section><tid>335717</tid>
<number>b</number>in particular, and without prejudice to the generality 
of the foregoing provision,--

<subsection><tid>1835831</tid>
<number>i</number>all property and assets vesting in the body 
known as the Faridabad Development Board shall vest in 
the Corporation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>359438</tid>
<number>ii</number>all rights, liabilities and obligations of 
the body known as the Faridabad Development Board, 
whether arising out of any contract or otherwise, shall 
be the rights, liabilities and obligations, 
respectively, of the Corporation; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>547597</tid>
<number>iii</number>all leases granted by, all contracts made 
with, and all instruments executed on behalf of, the 
body known as the Faridabad Development Board shall be 
deemed to have been granted by, made with, or executed 
on behalf of, the Corporation and shall have effect 
accordingly.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>436976</tid>
<number>35</number>Power to remove difficulties. If any doubt or difficulty 
arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central 
Government may, by order, make such provision or give such direction, 
not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as may appear to it 
to be necessary or expedient for the removal of the doubt or 
difficulty, and the order of the Central Government, in such cases, 
shall be final.


</article>



<article><tid>1748793</tid>
<number> 36</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1290150</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the 
purposes of this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>111</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1385525</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>843219</tid>
<number>a</number>the term of office and other conditions of service of 
members;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1049150</tid>
<number>b</number>the terms and conditions of service of the 
Administrator and other officers of the Corporation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1299554</tid>
<number>c</number>meetings of the Corporation and the procedure for 
conducting business thereat;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1312168</tid>
<number>d</number>the intervals at which, and the terms on which, the 
capital provided or loan advanced by the Central 
Government to the Corporation may be repaid, and the 
rate at which interest may be paid on the capital 
provided or loan advanced by the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1940160</tid>
<number>e</number>the form and manner in which the budget and the annual 
report may be prepared;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1309783</tid>
<number>f</number>the manner in which the accounts of the Corporation may 
be maintained and audited;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1145837</tid>
<number>g</number>the form and manner in which returns, statistics, 
accounts and other information may be furnished to the 
Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1668048</tid>
<number>h</number>any other matter which has to be, or may be, prescribed 
under this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>507581</tid>
<number>3</number>All rules made under this section shall, as soon as may be 
after they are made, be laid before both Houses of Parliament.


</section>

</article>



 </act>