<act><title>
The
APPELLATE TRIBUNAL FOR Forfeited PROPERTY (Conditions OF SERVICE OF CHAIRMAN 
AND
MEMBERS)
RULES, 19891</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>1</number>
Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
These rules may be called the Appellate Tribunal for Forfeited Property
(Conditions of Service of Chairman and Members) Rules, 1989.
 </section></article><article><number>2</number>
They shall come into force from the date of their publication in the Official
Gazette.
  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In these rules, unless
the context otherwise requires,—
 <section><number>a</number>
“Act” means the Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances Act, 1985
(61 of 1985), as amended by the Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances
(Amendment) Act, 1988 (2 of 1989); 
 

 </section><section><number>b</number>
“Chairman” means the Chairman of the Tribunal; 
 

 </section><section><number>c</number>
“Tribunal” means the Appellate Tribunal constituted under sub- 
section (1) of section 68N of the Act; 
 

 </section><section><number>d</number>
“member” means a member of the Tribunal. 
 

  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>3</number>
Remuneration, allowances, etc., of the Chairman.—
<section><number>1</number>
A Judge of the Supreme Court or of High Court appointed as Chairman shall be
entitled to a monthly salary at the same rate as is admissible to him as a judge
of the Supreme Court or of a High Court, as the case may be. He shall be
entitled to such allowances and other benefits as are admissible to a Judge of
the Supreme Court or of a High Court, as the case may be. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Where the Chairman retires from services as Judge of the Supreme Court or of a
High Court during the term of office of such Chairman or a retired judge
of the Supreme Court or of a High Court is appointed as such, he shall be paid
for the period he serves as Chairman, such salary, which, together with his
pension and pension equivalent of any other form of retirement benefits shall
not exceed the last pay drawn by him before retirement. He shall be entitled to
such allowances and other benefits as are admissible to a serving Judge of the
Supreme Court or High Court, as the case may be.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[A
person not being a serving Judge or a retired Judge of the Supreme Court or of a
High Court appointed as Chairman shall receive a pay of Rs. 26,000 (fixed) per
mensem and shall be entitled to draw such allowances as are admissible to the
Central Government officers of equivalent pay:
 


 Provided
that if the pay scale of the officers of the Central Government of equivalent
pay [i.e., officers in the pay scale of Rs. 26,000 (fixed)] is revised,
the person appointed as Chairman referred to in this sub-rule shall be entitled
to the revised pay scale applicable to the said officers of the Central
Government of equivalent pay:
 


 Provided
further that if such a person at the time of this appointment as
Chairman is in receipt of a pension in respect of his previous service
under the Government or any local body or authority owned or controlled by the
Government, such salary shall be reduced by the amount of pension and pension
equivalent of any other form of retirement benefits.] 


   


   






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>4</number>
Remuneration, allowances, etc., of members.—A
person appointed as member shall receive pay in the scale of Rs.
22,400-525-24,500 and shall be entitled to draw such allowances as are
admissible to the Central Government officers of equivalent pay:
 


 Provided
that if the pay scale of the officers of the Central Government of equivalent
pay (i.e., officers in the pay scale of Rs. 22,400-525-24,500) is
revised, the person appointed as member shall be entitled to the revised pay
scale applicable to the said officers of the Central Government of equivalent
pay:
 


 Provided
further that if such a person at the time of his appointment as member is in
receipt of a pension in respect of his previous service under the Government or
any local body or authority owned or controlled by the Government, such salary
shall be reduced by the amount of pension and pension equivalent of any other
form of retirement benefits.] 


   






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>5</number>
Retirement during the term of member.—Where
a member retired from service under the Government or any local body/authority
owned or controlled by the Government during the term of office as such member,
his salary for the period he serves as members after such retirement shall be
reduced by the amount of pension and pension equivalent of any other form of
retirement benefits. 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>6</number>
Travelling allowances.—
<section><number>1</number>(i) If the
Chairman is a serving Judge of the Supreme Court or of a High Court he shall be
entitled to draw travelling allowance at the rates as are admissible to a Judge
of the Supreme Court or of a High Court under the Supreme Court Judges (Travelling
Allowances) Rules, 1959 or, as the case may be, the High Court Judges (Travelling
Allowances) Rules, 1956 in respect of journeys performed by him in connection
with the work of the Tribunal.
 <subsection><number>ii</number>
If the Chairman is a retired Judge of the Supreme Court or of a High Court, he
shall be entitled to draw travelling allowance or daily allowance according to
his entitlement at the rates in force at the time of his re-employment in
respect of journeys performed by him in connection with the work of the
Tribunal:
 


 Provided
that the retired Judge of the Supreme Court or of a High Court shall not be
entitled to the benefit of higher daily allowance admissible to a serving Judge
of the Supreme Court or of a High Court, as the case may be, for performing
functions outside his normal duties in localities away from his headquarters:
 


 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
The Chairman, not being a judge or
a retired Judge of the Supreme Court or of a High Court, or any member, shall be
entitled to draw travelling allowance in respect of journey performed by him in
connection with the work of the Tribunal at the same rates as are admissible to
a Central Government officer of equivalent pay.
 


   


  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>7</number>
Leave.—
<section><number>1</number> Where the Chairman is a
serving Judge of the Supreme Court or of a High Court, he shall be entitled to
such leave as may be admissible to him under the Supreme Court Judges
(Conditions of Service) Act, 1958, or as the case may be, the High Court Judges
(Conditions of Service) Act, 1954. The serving Judge of the Supreme Court or of
a High Court retiring during the tenure of appointment as Chairman, he would be
governed by Central Civil Services (Leave) Rules, 1972, with effect from his
date of retirement from service. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Where the Chairman is a retired Judge of the Supreme Court or of a High Court,
he shall be entitled to such leave as is admissible to an officer of the
Government under the Central Civil Services (Leave) Rules, 1972.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
A person appointed as a member shall be entitled to such leave as is admissible
to an officer of the Government under the Central Civil Services (Leave) Rules,
1972:
 


 Provided
that where a person to whom the Central Civil Services (Leave) Rules, 1972 are
not applicable, is appointed as the Chairman or a Member, he shall be eligible
for the grant of leave under the rules applicable to him before such
appointment.
 


   


  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>8</number>
Vacation.—
<section><number>1</number> Where the Chairman is
a serving Judge, he shall be entitled to vacation in accordance with the Supreme
Court Judges (Conditions of Service) Act, 1958 or as the case may be, the High
Court Judges (Conditions of Service) Act, 1954. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Chairman, who is not a serving Judge of the Supreme Court or of a High Court
and a member shall not be entitled to vacation.
   



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>9</number>
Accommodation.—
<section><number>1</number> A serving Judge
or a retired Judge of the Supreme Court or of a High Court, who is appointed as
Chairman, shall be entitled without payment of rent, to the use of an official
residence in accordance with the Supreme Court Judges (Conditions of Service)
Act, 1958, or as the case may be, the High Court Judges (Conditions of Service)
Act, 1954:
 Provided
that where a retired Judge of the Supreme court
or of a High Court, is not provided residence in accordance with this sub-rule,
house rent allowance at the rate of 12.5% of pay shall be payable to such
retired Judge of the Supreme Court or of a High Court.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Chairman, who is not a serving Judge or a retired Judge of the Supreme Court
or of a High Court, and a Member shall be entitled to Government accommodation
on payment of prescribed rent as admissible to a Central Government officer of
equivalent pay. 
 


  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>10</number>
Medical attendance.—
<section><number>1</number>(i) A serving
Judge of the Supreme Court or of a High Court shall be entitled to medical
attendance in accordance with the Supreme Court Judges (Conditions of Service)
Act, 1958, or as the case may be, the High Court Judges (Conditions of Service)
Act, 1954.
 <subsection><number>ii</number>
A retired Judge of the Supreme Court or of a High Court appointed as Chairman
shall be entitled to medical facilities as available under the Central
Government Health Scheme or where the Central Government Health Scheme is not
available, he shall be entitled to medical facilities as available to Cabinet
Ministers. 
 


 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
The Chairman, who is not a serving Judge of the Supreme Court or of a High Court
and a Member of the Tribunal shall be entitled to medical facilities admissible
to a Central Government officer of equivalent pay. 
 


  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>11</number>
Tenure.—
<section><number>1</number> 
<subsection><number>a</number> Where a serving
Judge of the Supreme Court or of a High Court is appointed as Chairman, he shall
hold office as Chairman for a period of three years or till he attains the age
of sixty-five years or sixty-two years, as the case may be, whichever happens
earlier:
 Provided
that where a retired Judge of the Supreme Court or of a High Court is appointed
or re-appointed as Chairman, beyond the age of sixty-five or sixty-two years, as
the case may be, he shall hold office as Chairman for such period not exceeding
three years, as may be determined by the Central Government at the time of
appointment or re-appointment.
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
Where a person not falling under clause (a) is appointed as Chairman, he shall
hold office for a period of three years, or till he attains the age of
sixty-five years, whichever happens earlier and shall not be eligible for
re-appointment.
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
Notwithstanding anything contained in clause (b) where a person appointed as
Chairman is due to retire on attaining the age of superannuation under the
relevant rules applicable to him within a period of one year after completion of
the period of three years referred to in that clause, such person shall continue
to hold office as Chairman till the date of his superannuation under the said
rules.
 


 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
A person appointed as member shall hold office till he attains the age of 60
years.
 


  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>11A</number>
Contributions of General Provident Fund and Contributory Provident Fund.—
<section><number>a</number>
The Chairman and members shall be entitled to make contributions towards General
Provident Fund Account under the General Provident Fund (Central Services)
Rules, 1960 in the same manner as any other Central Government servant.
 </section><section><number>b</number>
Such of the Chairman and members, as are re-employed after retirement from
Government service, shall be entitled to contribute towards the Contributory
Provident Fund Account under the Contributory Provident Fund Rules (India), 1962
subject to such conditions as are applicable to re-employed Central Government
servants.
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>12</number>
Oath of office.—Every person
appointed as the Chairman or as a member, not already in Government service
shall, before entering upon office, make and subscribe to an oath of office
before an officer of the Central Government not below the rank of Additional
Secretary in the form appended to these rules. 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>13</number>
Terms and conditions of service of Chairman and members who are Chairman and
member of the Appellate Tribunal for Forfeited Property constituted under Safemfopa.—The
Chairman or a member of the Tribunal shall not be entitled for any salary,
remuneration, allowance or any other benefits to which the Chairman or member is
entitled under these rules, if the Chairman or member is a sitting Chairman or
member, as the case may be, of the Appellate Tribunal for Forfeited Property
constituted under the Smugglers and Foreign Exchange Manipulators (Forfeiture of
Property) Act, 1976 (hereinafter referred to as “Safemfopa”)
and the terms of office of such Chairman or member shall be co-terminus with the
terms of office of the Chairman or member, as the case may be, of the Appellate
Tribunal for Forfeited Property constituted under Safemfopa. 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>14</number>
Saving.—In respect of any matter not
covered by these rules, the Chairman and a member shall be governed by such
rules or orders, as may be applicable to a Central Government officer of
equivalent pay.
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>15</number>
Interpretation.—If any question
arises relating to the interpretation of these rules, the matter shall be
referred to the Central Government, who shall decide the same.
  
 
  


</article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


The
APPELLATE TRIBUNAL FOR Forfeited PROPERTY (Conditions OF SERVICE OF CHAIRMAN  

AND
MEMBERS) RULES, 1989
 

 
 

 
 


Form
 


(See
rule 12)
 


Oath of Office
 

I...................,do
swear/solemnly affirm that I will be faithful and bear true allegiance to India
and to the Constitution of India, as by law established, that I will uphold the
sovereignty and integrity of India and that I will carry out duties of my office
loyally, honestly and with impartiality.
 

So
help me God.
 

Signature;
 

Chairman/Member
 

Appellate
Tribunal for Forfeited Property 

Officer before whom the oath was taken.
 

 
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>
Subs. by S.O. 1255 (E), dated 24th December, 2001 (w.e.f. 24-12-2001).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>
Subs. by S.O. 1255 (E), dated 24th December, 2001 (w.e.f. 24-12-2001).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>