<act><tid>954428</tid>
<title>THE EXPORT (QUALITY CONTROL AND INSPECTION) ACT, <year>1963</year></title>

ACT NO. 22 OF <year>1963</year>
[ 24th August, <year>1963</year>.]

An Act to provide for the sound development of the export trade of 
India through quality control and inspection and for matters connected 
therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fourteenth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--





<article><tid>470032</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1070302</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Export (Quality Control and Inspection) Act, <year>1963</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>243658</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.

</section>

<section><tid>1395655</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1145746</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>104138</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>" adjudicating authority" means the authority 
specified in, or under, section 10K;

</section>

<section><tid>1184882</tid>
<number>ab</number>" Appellate authority" means the Appellate authority 
referred to in section 10M;]

</section>

<section><tid>621147</tid>
<number>ac</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>]" Council" means the Export Inspection Council 
established under section 3;

</section>

<section><tid>1120335</tid>
<number>b</number>" export", with its grammatical variations and cognate 
expressions, means taking out of India to a place 
outside India;

</section>

<section><tid>1764862</tid>
<number>c</number>" inspection", in relation to a commodity, means the 
process of determining whether a batch of goods in that 
commodity complies with the standard specifications 
applicable to it or any other specifications stipulated 
in the export contract generally by inspecting either 
the whole batch or a selected sample or samples which 
purport to represent the whole batch;

</section>

<section><tid>189324</tid>
<number>d</number>" notified commodity" means any commodity notified under 
clause (a) of section 6;

</section>

<section><tid>1822461</tid>
<number>e</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>57799</tid>
<number>f</number>" quality control" means any activity having for its 
object the determination of the quality of a commodity 
 (whether during the process of manufacture or  
production or
<pagefootnote><pagenum>66</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1st January, <year>1964</year>; vide Notification No. S. O. 3604, dated 30- 12- 
<year>1963</year>, Gazette of India, Extraordinary, <year>1963</year>, Pt. II, Sec. 3 (ii), p. 
895. 
2 Re- lettered and Ins. by Act 40 of <year>1984</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 2- 7- <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


  subsequently) in order to ascertain whether it 
satisfies the standard specifications applicable to it 
or any other specifications stipulated in the export 
contract and whether it may be accepted for purposes of 
export.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1806522</tid>
<number> 3</number> Establishment of Export Inspection Council.
<section><tid>113886</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, establish, 
with effect from such date as may be specified in the notification, a 
Council to be known as the Export Inspection Council, which shall 
consist of--

<subsection><tid>48214</tid>
<number>a</number>a Chairman to be appointed by the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1988877</tid>
<number>b</number>the Director of Inspection and Quality Control, ex 
officio, who shall be the Secretary;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1177748</tid>
<number>c</number>the Honorary Adviser on Standardization to the 
Government of India and Director of Indian Standards 
Institution, ex officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1362725</tid>
<number>d</number>the Agricultural Marketing Adviser to the Government of 
India, ex officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>294385</tid>
<number>e</number>the Director- General of Commercial Intelligence and 
Statistics, ex officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>468214</tid>
<number>f</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> fifteen] other members nominated by the Central 
Government three of whom shall be persons representing 
the agencies referred to in section 7.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>189438</tid>
<number>2</number>The Council shall be a body corporate by the name aforesaid, 
having perpetual succession and a common seal, with power to acquire, 
hold and dispose of property and to contract, and shall by the said 
name sue and be sued.

</section>

<section><tid>14886</tid>
<number>3</number>The term of office of, and the manner of filling casual 
vacancies among, the members of the Council referred to in clauses (a) 
and (f) of sub- section (1) and the travelling and daily allowances 
payable to the members of the Council and the procedure to be followed 
in the discharge of its functions by the Council shall be such as may 
be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>480178</tid>
<number>4</number>No act or proceeding of the Council shall be invalidated 
merely by reason of any vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution 
of, the Council.

</section>

<section><tid>211237</tid>
<number>5</number>Subject to such rules as may be made by the Central 
Government in this behalf, the Council may appoint such officers and 
other employees as it considers necessary for the purpose of 
discharging its functions under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1770238</tid>
<number>4</number>Director of Inspection and Quality Control. The Central 
Government shall appoint a Director of Inspection and Quality Control 
to exercise such powers and perform such duties under this Act as may 
be prescribed.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>67</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 40 of <year>1984</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 2- 7- <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>1030351</tid>
<number> 5</number> Functions of the Conncil.
<section><tid>823171</tid>
<number>1</number>The functions of the Council  
shall generally be to advise the Central Government regarding measures 
for the enforcement of quality control and inspection in relation to 
commodities intended for export and to draw up programmes therefor, to 
make, with the concurrence of the Central Government, grants- in- aid to 
the agencies established or recognised under section 7 and to perform 
such other functions as may be assigned to it by or under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>290759</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purpose of performing its functions, the Council may 
co- opt as members such number of persons as it thinks fit who have 
special knowledge and practical experience in matters relating to any 
commodity or trade therein and any such person shall have the right to 
take part in the discussions of the Council but shall not have the 
right to vote and shall not be a member for any other purpose.

</section>

<section><tid>1965488</tid>
<number>3</number>The Council may also constitute specialist committees for 
conducting investigations on special problems connected with its 
functions.

</section>

<section><tid>563864</tid>
<number>4</number>In the performance of its functions under this Act, the 
Council shall be bound by such directions as the Central Government 
may give to it in writing from time to time.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1802475</tid>
<number> 6</number> Powers of the Central Government in regard to quality control 
and inspection. If the Central Government, after consulting the 
Council, is of opinion that it is necessary or expedient so to do for 
the development of the export trade of India, it may, by order 
published in the Official Gazette,--
<section><tid>1154469</tid>
<number>a</number>notify commodities which shall be subject to quality 
control or inspection or both prior to export;

</section>

<section><tid>387925</tid>
<number>b</number>specify the type of quality control or inspection which 
will be applied to a notified commodity;

</section>

<section><tid>673679</tid>
<number>c</number>establish, adopt or recognise one or more standard 
specifications for a notified commodity;

</section>

<section><tid>785032</tid>
<number>d</number>prohibit the export in the course of international trade 
of a notified commodity unless it is accompanied by a 
certificate issued under section 7 that the commodity 
satisfies the conditions relating to quality control or 
inspection, or it has affixed or applied to it a mark 
or seal recognised by the Central Government as 
indicating that it conforms to the standard 
specifications applicable to it under clause (c).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>633516</tid>
<number> 7</number> Machinery for quality control and inspections.
<section><tid>345802</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, establish, or 
recognise subject to such conditions as it may deem fit, agencies for 
quality control or inspection or both:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>68</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Provided that if the Central Government is of opinion that any 
recognition granted to any agency under this sub- section should, in 
the public interest, be withdrawn, the Central Government may, after 
giving a reasonable opportunity to that agency to make representations 
in the matter, withdraw, by like notification, the recognition granted 
to it.


</section>

<section><tid>153160</tid>
<number>2</number>Any agency referred to in sub- section (1) may, on application 
made to it or otherwise, hold or cause to be held such examination as 
it thinks fit relating to quality control or inspection of notified 
commodities, either at the time of export or earlier, in such testing 
houses or by such surveyors or samplers as are approved by the Central 
Government in this behalf and may charge such fees as may be 
prescribed for the purpose of such examination.

</section>

<section><tid>436199</tid>
<number>3</number>If, after the examination, the agency is of opinion that the 
commodity satisfies the standard specifications laid down in respect 
of it under section 6 or, as the case may be, any other specifications 
stipulated in the export contract, it may issue a certificate that the 
commodity satisfies the conditions relating to quality control and 
inspection.

</section>

<section><tid>1574228</tid>
<number>3A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Where the agency has reason to believe that a certificate 
issued under sub- section (3) has been obtained fraudulently or by 
misrepresentation, or the commodity in relation to which the 
certificate is issued has been changed or has deteriorated in quality, 
the agency may, by order amend, suspend or cancel the certificate in 
such manner and subject to such procedure as may be prescribed:
Provided that before amending, suspending or cancelling any such 
certificate the holder thereof shall be given a reasonable opportunity 
of being heard.];


</section>

<section><tid>1545252</tid>
<number>4</number>Any person aggrieved by the refusal of any agency referred to 
in sub- section (1) to issue a certificate <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>, or by the amendment, 
suspension or cancellation of a certificate under sub- section (3A),] 
may prefer an appeal within such time as may be prescribed to such 
authority as the Central Government may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, constitute for the purpose of hearing appeals.

</section>

<section><tid>1640395</tid>
<number>5</number>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (6), the decision of 
the agency where no appeal is filed, and the decision of the appellate 
authority where an appeal is filed, shall be final and shall not be 
questioned in any court of law.

</section>

<section><tid>46274</tid>
<number>6</number>The Central Government may, at any time, call for and examine 
the record of any proceeding relating to any decision of an agency or 
appellate authority under this section for the purpose of satisfying 
itself as to the legality or propriety of such decision and may pass 
such order thereon as it thinks fit.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1399699</tid>
<number> 8</number> Power to recognise or establish marks to denote conformity 
with standard specifications.
<section><tid>341661</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, recognise or establish any mark 
or seal in relation to a notified commodity for the purpose of 
denoting that such commodity conforms to a standard specification 
applicable to it.

</section>

<section><tid>237334</tid>
<number>2</number>Any such mark or seal affixed or applied to a notified 
commodity or to any covering containing, or label attached to, such 
commodity shall be deemed to be evidence of the commodity being in 
conformity with the standard specifications applicable to it under 
this Act:
<pagefootnote><pagenum>69</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 40 of <year>1984</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 2- 7- <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Provided that nothing in this sub- section shall prevent any 
officer of customs from examining any consignment of a notified 
commodity intended for export if he has reason to believe that the 
seal or mark is not genuine or has been affixed or applied 
fraudulently or if such an examination is necessary for the purpose of 
any other law for the time being in force.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>119544</tid>
<number> 9</number> Power to obtain information from exporters, etc. The Central 
Government or any officer or authority authorised by it in this behalf 
may, by notice published in the Official Gazette, require--
<section><tid>1431447</tid>
<number>i</number>persons manufacturing, dealing in or exporting notified 
commodities; and

</section>

<section><tid>1058969</tid>
<number>ii</number>such other persons as may be prescribed,
to furnish any information, return or report which the Central 
Government or such officer or authority may consider necessary for 
carrying out the purposes of this Act.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>44852</tid>
<number> 10</number> Finance, accounts and audit.
<section><tid>1742029</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purpose of enabling  
the Council to discharge its functions under this Act, the Central 
Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in 
this behalf, pay to the Council such sums of money as that Government 
considers necessary by way of grants, loans or otherwise.

</section>

<section><tid>784292</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purpose of discharging its functions under this Act, 
the Council may receive grants or donations from bodies and 
institutions approved by the Central Government in this behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>566082</tid>
<number>3</number>The Council shall have its own fund to which shall be 
credited the sums of money referred to in sub- sections (1) and (2) and 
the moneys in the fund shall be applied for--

<subsection><tid>1293558</tid>
<number>a</number>meeting the pay and allowances of the officers and other 
employees of the Council and other administrative 
expenses of the Council;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>523400</tid>
<number>b</number>carrying out the functions of the Council under this 
Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>868292</tid>
<number>4</number>The Council shall prepare, before the commencement of each 
financial year, a statement of programme of its activities during that 
year as well as a financial estimate in respect thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>335972</tid>
<number>5</number>A statement prepared under sub- section (4) shall, not later 
than three months before the commencement of each financial year, be 
submitted for approval to the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1096576</tid>
<number>6</number>The Council shall maintain such accounts and prepare the 
balance- sheet in such form as may, in consultation with the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General of India, be prescribed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>70</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>740669</tid>
<number>7</number>The accounts of the Council shall be audited in such manner 
and at such times as may, in consultation with the Comptroller and 
Auditor- General of India, be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1453673</tid>
<number> 10A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Power to enter and inspect. The Director of Inspection 
and Quality Control or any officer of the Central Government 
authorised by him in writing in this behalf (hereinafter referred to  
  as the" authorised officer") may enter at any reasonable time, any 
premises in which--
<section><tid>1724831</tid>
<number>a</number>any commodity which has been changed after inspection by 
any agency, referred to in sub- section (1) of section 7; or

</section>

<section><tid>209869</tid>
<number>b</number>any books of account or other documents or things which, 
in his opinion, will be useful for, or relevant to, any 
proceeding under this Act,
are suspected to have been kept or concealed, and inspect such 
commodity, books of account, other documents or things and may take 
such notes or extracts from such books of account or other documents 
as he may think fit.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1399270</tid>
<number> 10B</number> Power to search. If the authorised officer has any reason to 
believe that--
<section><tid>1919264</tid>
<number>a</number>any commodity which has been changed after inspection by 
any agency referred to in sub- section (1), of section 7; or

</section>

<section><tid>1415290</tid>
<number>b</number>any books of account or other documents or things which, 
in his opinion, will be useful for, or relevant to, any 
proceeding under this Act,
are secreted in any place, he may enter into and search such place or 
premises for such commodity, books of account, other documents or 
fsthings.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1485486</tid>
<number> 10C</number> Power to seize commodities, etc.
<section><tid>1926858</tid>
<number>1</number>If the authorised  
officer has any reason to believe that any commodity is liable to 
confiscation under this Act, he may seize such commodity together with 
the package, covering or receptacle, if any, in which such commodity 
is found and where such commodity is found to have been mixed with any 
other goods or materials, he may seize such commodity together with 
the goods or materials with which it is so mixed:
Provided that where it is not practicable to seize any such 
commodity, the authorised officer may serve on the owner of the 
commodity an order that he shall not remove, part with, or otherwise 
deal with, the commodity except with the previous permission of such 
authorised officer.


</section>

<section><tid>5085</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any commodity is seized under sub- section (1) and no 
notice in respect thereof is given under section 10L within six months 
of the seizure of such commodity, it shall be returned to the person 
from whose possession it was seized:
Provided that the aforesaid period of six months may, on 
sufficient cause being shown, be extended by the Director of 
Inspection and Quality Control by a further period not exceeding six 
months.


</section>

<section><tid>1439356</tid>
<number>3</number>The authorised officer may seize any documents or things 
which, in his opinion, will be useful for, or relevant to, any 
proceeding under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1648643</tid>
<number>4</number>The person from whose custody any documents are seized under 
sub- section (3) shall be entitled to make copies thereof or take 
extracts therefrom in the presence of the authorised officer.

</section>

<section><tid>1276526</tid>
<number>5</number>If any person legally entitled to the documents or things 
seized under sub- section (3) objects, for any reason, to the retention 
by the authorised officer of the documents or things, he may make an 
application to the Central Government stating therein the reasons for 
such objection and requesting for the return of the documents or 
things.

</section>

<section><tid>1366226</tid>
<number>6</number>On receipt of an application under sub- section (5), the 
Central Government may, after giving the applicant an opportunity of 
being heard, pass such order as it may think fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1149332</tid>
<number>7</number>Where any document--

<subsection><tid>195980</tid>
<number>a</number>is produced or furnished by any person or has been 
seized from the custody or control of any person under this Act 
or any other law for the time being in force; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>400751</tid>
<number>b</number>has been received from any place outside India (duly  
authenticated by such authority or person and in such manner as 
  may be prescribed) in the course of the investigation of any 
offence alleged to have been committed by any person against this 
Act,
and such document is tendered in evidence against the person by whom 
it is produced or from whom it was seized or against such person and 
any other person who is jointly tried, or proceeded against, with him, 
the court, or, as the case may be, the adjudicating authority shall, 
notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any other law 
for the time being in force,--


<subsubsection><tid>703743</tid>
<number>i</number>presume, unless the contrary is proved, that the signature 
and every other part of such document which purports to be in the 
handwriting of any particular person or which the court or the 
adjudicating authority may reasonably assume to have been signed by, 
or to be in the handwriting of, any particular person, is under that 
person' s handwriting, and, in the case of a document executed or 
attested, it was executed or attested by the person by whom it 
purports to have been so executed or attested;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1817205</tid>
<number>ii</number>admit the document in evidence notwithstanding that it is 
not duly stamped, if such document is otherwise admissible in 
evidence.



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1585908</tid>
<number> 10D</number> Power to stop and seize conveyances. Any authorise officer 
may, if he has any reason to suspect that any conveyance or animal is 
being, or is about to be, used for the transportation of any commodity 
which is liable to confiscation under this Act and that by such 
transportation any provision of this Act has been, is being, or is 
about to be, contravened, at any time, stop such conveyance or animal 
or, in the case of an aircraft, compel it to land, and
<section><tid>15040</tid>
<number>a</number>rummage and search the conveyance or any part thereof,

</section>

<section><tid>1221770</tid>
<number>b</number>examine and search any goods or materials in the 
conveyance or on the animal,

</section>

<section><tid>1626940</tid>
<number>c</number>if it becomes necessary to stop any conveyance or 
animal, he may use all lawful means for stopping it and 
where such means fail, the conveyance or animal may be 
fired upon,
and where he is satisfied that it is necessary so to do to prevent the 
contravention of any provision of this Act, he may seize such 
conveyance or animal.

Explanation.-- Any reference in this section to a conveyance 
shall, unless the context otherwise requires, be construed as 
including a reference to an aircraft, vehicle or vessel.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>562490</tid>
<number>10E</number>Search and seizure to be made in accordance with the Code of 
Criminal Procedure <year>1973</year>. The provisions of the Code of Criminal 
Procedure, <year>1973</year>, relating to searches and seizures shall, so far as 
may be, apply to every search or seizure made under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1585649</tid>
<number> 10F</number> Confiscation. Any commodity in respect of which--
<section><tid>486196</tid>
<number>a</number>a certificate has been obtained from an agency referred 
to in sub- section (1) of section 7 fraudulently or by 
misrepresentation, or

</section>

<section><tid>735785</tid>
<number>b</number>any provision of this Act has been, is being, or is 
attempted to be, contravened,
shall, together with any package, covering or receptacle in which such 
commodity is found, be liable to confiscation and, where such 
commodity is so mixed with any other goods or materials that it cannot 
be readily separated, such other goods or materials shall also be 
liable to confiscation:

Provided that where it is established to the satisfaction of the 
adjudicating authority that any commodity, which is liable to 
confiscation under this Act, belongs to a person other than the person 
who has, by any act or omission, rendered it liable to confiscation, 
and such act or omission was without the knowledge or connivance of 
the person to whom it belongs, such commodity shall not be ordered to 
be confiscated; but such other action as is authorised by this Act may 
be taken against the person who has, by such act or omission, rendered 
such commodity liable to confiscation.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1233251</tid>
<number>10G</number>Confiscation of conveyance. Any conveyance or animal which 
has been, is being, or is attempted to be, used for the transport of 
any commodity which is liable to confiscation under this Act, shall be 
liable to confiscation unless the owner of the conveyance or animal 
proves that it was, is being, or is about to be, so used without the 
knowledge or connivance of the owner himself, his agent, if any, and 
the person in charge of the conveyance or animal and that each of them 
had taken all reasonable precautions against such use:
Provided that in the case of a conveyance or animal used for the 
transport of goods or passengers for hire, the owner of the conveyance 
or animal shall be given an option to pay, in lieu of confiscation of 
the conveyance of animal, a fine not exceeding the value of the 
commodity which has been, is being, or is attempted to be, transported 
by such conveyance or animal.



</article>



<article><tid>72920</tid>
<number>10H</number>Option to pay fine in lieu of confiscation. Whenever 
confiscation of any commodity is authorised by this Act, the officer 
adjudging it shall, without prejudice to the provisions of the proviso 
to section 10G, give to the owner of the commodity an option to pay in 
lieu of confiscation such fine not exceeding the value of the 
commodity.


</article>



<article><tid>1227159</tid>
<number> 10I</number> Liability to penalty. Any person,--
<section><tid>162565</tid>
<number>a</number>who, in relation to any commodity, does or omits to do 
any act which act or omission would render such commodity liable 
to confiscation under this Act, or abets the doing or omission of 
such an act; or

</section>

<section><tid>1756575</tid>
<number>b</number>who acquires possession of or is in any way concerned in 
carrying, removing, depositing, keeping, concealing, selling or 
purchasing, or in any manner dealing with, any commodity which he 
knows or has reason to believe is liable to confiscation under 
this Act,
shall be liable to a penalty not exceeding five times the value of the 
commodity or five thousand rupees, whichever is more, whether or not 
such commodity has been confiscated or is available for confiscation.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1636344</tid>
<number>10J</number>Confiscation or penalty not to interfere with other 
punishments. No confiscation made or penalty imposed under the 
foregoing provisions of this Act shall prevent the infliction of any 
other punishment to which the person affected thereby is liable under 
the provisions of this Act or under any other law for the time being 
in force.


</article>



<article><tid>1211210</tid>
<number>10K</number>Adjudication Any confiscation may be adjudged or penalty, 
may be imposed under this Act by the Director of Inspection and 
Quality Control, or, where he so directs, by a general or special 
order, by any officer subordinate to him.


</article>



<article><tid>1358276</tid>
<number> 10L</number> Giving of opportunity to the owner of goods, etc. No order 
of adjudication of confiscation or imposing a penalty shall be made 
unless the owner of the commodity, conveyance or animal or other 
person concerned, is given a notice in writing--
<section><tid>1204658</tid>
<number>a</number>informing him of the grounds on which it is proposed to 
confiscate such commodity, conveyance or animal or to impose a 
penalty;

</section>

<section><tid>851246</tid>
<number>b</number>giving him a reasonable opportunity of making a 
representation in writing within such reasonable time as may be 
specified in the notice against the confiscation or imposition of 
penalty mentioned therein, and, if he so desires, of being heard 
in the matter.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1064240</tid>
<number> 10M</number> Appeal.
<section><tid>251409</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person aggrieved by any decision or order  
made under this Act may prefer an appeal,--

<subsection><tid>19996</tid>
<number>a</number>Where the decision or order has been made by the 
Director of Inspection and Quality Control, to the Central 
Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>267193</tid>
<number>b</number>where the decision or order has been made by any officer 
subordinate to the Director of Inspection and Quality Control, to 
the Director of Inspection and Quality Control,
within a period of forty- five days from the date on which the decision 
or order is served on such person:

Provided that the Appellate authority may, if it is satisfied 
that the appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from preferring 
the appeal within the aforesaid period of forty- five days, allow such 
appeal to be preferred within a further period of forty- five days:

Provided further that in the case of an appeal against an order 
imposing a penalty, no such appeal shall be entertained unless the 
amount of the penalty has been deposited by the appellant:

Provided also that where the Appellate authority is of the 
opinion that the deposit to be made will cause undue hardship to the 
appellant, it may, at its discretion, dispense with such deposit 
either unconditionally or subject to such conditions as it may impose.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1124295</tid>
<number>2</number>The Appellate authority may, after giving to the appellant a 
reasonable opportunity of being heard, if he so desires, and after 
making such further inquiries, if any, as it may consider necessary, 
pass such orders as it thinks fit, confirming, modifying or reversing 
the decision or order appealed against, or may send back the case, 
with such directions as it may think fit, for a fresh adjudication or 
decision, as the case may be, after taking additional evidence, if 
necessary:
Provided that an order enhancing or imposing a penalty or 
confiscating commodity of a greater value shall not be made under this 
section unless the appellant has had an opportunity of making a 
representation and, if he so desires, of being heard, in his defence.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>364056</tid>
<number> 10N</number> Powers of revision. The Central Government may, on its own 
motion or otherwise, call for and examine the records of any 
proceeding in which an order of adjudication of confiscation or 
imposing any penalty has been made by any officer under this Act and 
against which no appeal has been preferred, for the purpose of 
satisfying itself as to the correctness, legality or propriety of such 
order or decision and pass such orders thereon as it may think fit:
Provided that no decision or order shall be varied under this 
section so as to prejudicially affect any person unless such person--

<section><tid>1462117</tid>
<number>a</number>has, within a period of two years from the date of such 
decision or order, received a notice to show cause why such 
decision or order shall not be varied, and

</section>

<section><tid>566209</tid>
<number>b</number>has been given a reasonable opportunity of making a 
representation and, if he so desires, of being heard in his 
defence.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>271022</tid>
<number> 10O</number> Powers of adjudicating and other authorities.
<section><tid>1714720</tid>
<number>1</number>Every  
authority making any adjudication or hearing any appeal or exercising 
any powers of revision under this Act shall have all the powers of a 
civil court under the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year>, while trying a 
suit, in respect of the following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1481843</tid>
<number>a</number>summoning and enforcing the attendance of witnesses;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>843256</tid>
<number>b</number>requiring the discovery and production of any document;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>977990</tid>
<number>c</number>requisitioning any public record or copy thereof from 
any court or office;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1330757</tid>
<number>d</number>receiving evidence on affidavits; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>305362</tid>
<number>e</number>issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses or 
documents.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>405002</tid>
<number>2</number>Every authority making any adjudication or hearing any appeal 
or exercising any powers of revision under this Act shall be deemed to 
be a Civil Court for the purposes of sections 345 and 346 of the Code 
of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1116470</tid>
<number>3</number>Every authority making any adjudication or hearing any appeal 
or exercising any powers of revision under this Act shall have the 
power to make such orders of an interim nature as it may think fit and 
may also, for sufficient cause, order the stay of operation of any 
decision or order.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>117520</tid>
<number> 10P</number> Continuance of proceedings in the event of death or 
insolvency.
<section><tid>307571</tid>
<number>1</number>Where a penalty has been imposed by the adjudicating  
authority and--

<subsection><tid>1055167</tid>
<number>a</number>no appeal against the order imposing such penalty has 
been preferred to the Appellate authority and the person entitled 
to file such appeal dies or is adjudicated an insolvent before 
the expiry of the period within which the appeal can be 
preferred; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>944791</tid>
<number>b</number>an appeal has been preferred to the Appellate authority 
against the order imposing such penalty but the appellant dies or 
is adjudicated an insolvent during the pendency of the appeal,
then, it shall be lawful for the legal representatives of such person 
or the Official Assignee or the Official Receiver as the case may be, 
to prefer an appeal to the Appellate authority or as the case may be 
to continue the appeal before the Appellate authority in place of such 
person and the provisions of section 10M shall so far as may be, apply 
or continue to apply to such appeal.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>914274</tid>
<number>2</number>The powers of the Official Assignee or the Official Receiver 
under sub- section (1) shall be exercised by him subject to the 
provisions of the Presidency- towns Insolvency Act, <year>1909</year>, or the 
Provincial Insolvency Act, <year>1909</year>, or the Provincial Insolvency Act, 
<year>1920</year>, as the case may be.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>677272</tid>
<number> 11</number> Penalty.
<section><tid>735478</tid>
<number>1</number>If any person contravenes any order under clause  
 (d) of section 6, or fraudulently obtains a certificate under section 
7, or fraudulently affixes or applies any such mark or seal as is 
referred to in sub- section (1) of section 8, he shall, on conviction, 
be punishable--

<subsection><tid>192491</tid>
<number>i</number>for the first offence, with imprisonment for a term 
which may extend to two years, or with fine which may 
extend to five thousand rupees, or with both;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>916183</tid>
<number>ii</number>for the second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment 
for a term which may extend to <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> three years] and also 
with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees and 
in the absence of special and adequate reasons to be 
mentioned in the judgment of the court, such 
imprisonment shall not be less than three months.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1523706</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person who attempts to commit or abets the commission of 
an offence punishable under sub- section (1) shall be deemed to have 
committed such offence.

</section>

<section><tid>1941488</tid>
<number>3</number>If any person contravenes or attempts to contravene or abets 
the contravention of any other provision of this Act or any rules or 
orders made thereunder, he shall be punishable with fine which may 
extend to one thousand rupees.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>400217</tid>
<number>11A</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Penalty for contravention of order made by adjudicating 
authority or Appeallate authority. If any person fails to pay the 
penalty imposed by the adjudicating or the Appellate authority or 
fails to comply with any direction or order made, or deemed to have 
been made, under this Act, he shall, on conviction, be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years, or with fine, 
or with both.


</article>



<article><tid>1231802</tid>
<number> 11B</number> Offences by officers and employees of agency, etc.
<section><tid>1770216</tid>
<number>1</number>If  
any officer or employee of the Council or of any agency referred to in 
sub- section (1) of section 7, or any surveyor, sampler or employee of 
any testing house, referred to in sub- section (2) of that section 
enters into, or acquiesces in, any agreement to do, abstains from 
doing, permits, conceals or connives at, any act or thing whereby any 
provision of this Act is or may be contravened, he shall, on 
conviction, be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may 
extend to two years, or with fine which may extend to five thousand 
rupees, or with both.

</section>

<section><tid>589699</tid>
<number>2</number>If any officer searches or authorises any other officer of 
the Central Government to search any place without having reason to 
believe that any commodity, books of account or documents or things of 
the nature referred to in section 10B are secreted in that place, he 
shall, on conviction, be punishable with imprisonment for a term which 
may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to one 
thousand rupees, or with both.

</section>

<section><tid>1823049</tid>
<number>3</number>If any officer or employee of the Council or of any agency 
referred to in sub- section (1) of section 7, or any surveyor, sampler 
or employee of any testing house, referred to in sub- section (2) of 
that section, except in the discharge in good faith of his duty as 
such officer or employee or in compliance with any requisition made 
under any law for the time being in force discloses any particulars 
learnt by him in his official capacity in respect of any commodity, he 
shall on conviction be punishable with imprisonment for a term which 
may extend to six months or with fine which may extend to one thousand 
rupees or with both.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1034310</tid>
<number>11C</number>Correction of clerical or arithmetical mistakes. Clerical or 
arithmetical mistakes in any decision or order, or errors arising 
therein from any accidental slip or omission may, at any time, be 
corrected by the authority by which the decision or order was made 
either on its own motion or on the application of the aggrieved 
person:
Provided that where any correction proposed to be made under this 
section will have the effect of prejudicially affecting any person, no 
such correction shall be made except after giving to that person a 
reasonable opportunity of making a representation in the matter and no 
such correction shall be made after the expiry of a period of two 
years from the date on which such decision or order was made.]



</article>



<article><tid>1316209</tid>
<number> 12</number> Offences by companies.
<section><tid>1829912</tid>
<number>1</number>Where an offence under this Act  
has been committed by a company, every person who, at the time the 
offence was committed, was in charge of, and was responsible to, the 
company for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as the 
company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be 
liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the 
offence was committed without his knowledge or that he exercised all 
due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.


</section>

<section><tid>734453</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where 
an offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is 
proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or 
connivance of, or is attributable to any negligence on the part of, 
any director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such 
director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed
<pagefootnote><pagenum>71</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 40 of <year>1984</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 2. 7. <year>1984</year>). 
2 Subs. by s. 6 ibid (w. e. f. 2. 7. <year>1984</year>). 
3 Ins. by s. 7, ibid (w. e. f. 2. 7. <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded 
against and punished accordingly.

Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section--


<subsection><tid>971103</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means a body corporate and includes a firm or 
other association of individuals; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>78470</tid>
<number>b</number>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner in 
the firm.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1319326</tid>
<number> 13</number> Delegation of powers. The Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, direct that any power 
exercisable by it under this Act shall, in relation to such matters 
and subject to such conditions, if any, as may be specified in the 
direction, be exercisable also by--
<section><tid>867258</tid>
<number>a</number>the Council;

</section>

<section><tid>1174676</tid>
<number>b</number>such officer or authority subordinate to the Central 
Government, or such State Government or such officer or 
authority subordinate to a State Government as may be 
specified in the direction.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>350097</tid>
<number>14</number>Procedure for prosecution. No prosecution for an offence 
punishable under this Act shall be instituted except by or with the 
consent of an officer authorised by the Central Government by general 
or special order in this behalf.


</article>



<article><tid>114873</tid>
<number> 15</number> Officers and employees of agency to be public servants. All 
officers and employees of the Council or of any agency established or 
recognised under sub- section
<section><tid>1743805</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 7 and all surveyors,  
samplers and employees of testing houses, referred to in sub- section 
 (2) of that section shall, while acting or purporting to act in 
pursuance of the provisions of this Act or any rule or order made 
thereunder, be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of 
section 21 of the Indian Penal Code. (45 of <year>1860</year>.)



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1342095</tid>
<number> 16</number> Protection of action taken in good faith.
<section><tid>1073749</tid>
<number>1</number>No suit,  
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Council or 
any officer or employee of the Government or the Council or any agency 
referred to in sub- section (1) of section 7 for anything which is in 
good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any 
rule or order made thereunder.

</section>

<section><tid>405616</tid>
<number>2</number>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the 
Government for any damage caused or likely to be caused by anything 
which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of 
this Act or any rule or order made thereunder.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>865287</tid>
<number> 16A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Suspension, etc., of operation of the provisions of the 
Act.
<section><tid>913268</tid>
<number>1</number>If the Central Government is satisfied that circumstances  
exist which render it necessary or expedient so to do in the public 
interest, it may, by notification in the Official Gazette, suspend or 
relax to a specified extent the operation of all or any of the 
provisions of this Act in respect of such notified commodity or 
commodities generally or in respect of any area and for such period as 
may be specified in the notification.

</section>

<section><tid>151686</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the operation of any provision of this Act has, under 
sub- section (1), been suspended or relaxed, such suspension or 
relaxation may, at any time be removed by the Central Government by a 
like notification.

</section>

<section><tid>1647711</tid>
<number>3</number>Every notification issued under this section shall be laid, 
as soon as may be after it is issued before each House of Parliament, 
while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be 
comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and 
if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session 
or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the notification or both Houses agree that the 
notification should not be issued, the notification shall thereafter 
have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case 
may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be 
without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under 
that notification.].



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1705281</tid>
<number> 17</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1340180</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the 
purposes of this Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>72</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 40 of <year>1984</year>, s. 8 (w. e. f. 2- 7- <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1578388</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for--

<subsection><tid>1478892</tid>
<number>a</number>the travelling and daily allowances payable to members 
of the Council, persons co- opted under sub- section (2) 
of section 5, and members of specialist committees 
referred to in sub- section (3) of that section;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1519455</tid>
<number>b</number>the functions of the Council and the procedure to be 
followed by it;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>41507</tid>
<number>c</number>the appointment of officers and other employees of the 
Council;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1650531</tid>
<number>d</number>the procedure to be followed for various types of 
quality control and inspection;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>689921</tid>
<number>e</number>the conditions which a testing house, surveyor or 
sampler should satisfy for purposes of approval by the 
Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1092056</tid>
<number>f</number>the fees chargeable for purposes of examination and 
issue of certificates under section 7;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>664339</tid>
<number>ff</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the manner in which, and the procedure subject to 
which, any certificate issued under sub- section (3) of 
section 7 shall be amended, suspended or cancelled;];

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1540679</tid>
<number>g</number>the filing of appeals under section 7 and the fees 
payable therefor;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>177300</tid>
<number>gg</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the authority or person by which or by whom, and the 
manner in which, any document received from a place 
outside India shall be authenticated;];

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1360321</tid>
<number>h</number>the manner in which the accounts of the Council shall be 
maintained and audited;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1640940</tid>
<number>i</number>any other matter which is required to be, or may be, 
prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1710062</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made by the Central Government under this section 
shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made before each House of 
Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty days 
which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive 
sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> immediately 
following the session] or the successive sessions aforesaid, both 
Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses 
agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have 
effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may 
be; so however that any such modification or annulment shall be 
without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under 
that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1599801</tid>
<number>18</number>Act to override other enactments. As from the date on which a 
commodity is notified under clause (a) of section 6, the provisions of 
this Act or anything done or any action taken thereunder shall have 
effect in relation to that commodity notwithstanding any provisions 
 (relating to quality control and inspection prior to the export of  
  such commodity) contained in any enactment other than this Act or in 
any instrument having effect by virtue of any enactment other than 
this Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>73</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. and subs. by Act 4 of <year>1984</year>, s. 9 (w. e. f. 2. 7. <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>