<act><title>THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948 </title> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and extent.—
<section><number>1</number> 
This Act may be called the Dentists Act, 1948.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends to the 

1[whole of India 

2[***]].
 
 




</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Interpretation.—In 
this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  “the Council” means the Dental 
Council of India constituted under section 3;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  “dental hygienist” means a person 
not being a dentist or a medical practitioner, who scales, cleans or polishes 
teeth, or gives instructions in dental hygiene;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  “dental mechanic” means a person 
who makes or repairs denture and dental appliances;
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  “dentistry” includes—
 <subsection>
             <number>i</number>  the performance of any 
operation on, and the treatment on any disease, deficiency or lesion of, human 
teeth or jaws, and the performance of radiographic work in connection with human 
teeth or jaws or the oral cavity.
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>ii</number>  the giving of any 
anaesthetic in connection with any such operation or treatment;
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>iii</number>  the mechanical construction 
or the renewal of artificial dentures or restorative dental appliances;
 </subsection><subsection>
           <number>iv</number>  the performance of any 
operation on, or the giving of any treatment, advice or attendance to, any 
person preparatory to, or for the purpose of, or in connection with, the 
fitting, inserting, fixing, constructing, repairing or renewing of artificial 
dentures or restorative dental appliances, and the performance of any such 
operation and the giving of any such treatment, advice or attendance, as is 
usually performed or given by dentists;
 </subsection></section><section>
       <number>e</number>  “dentist” means a person who 
practises dentistry;
 </section><section>
        <number>f</number>  “medical practitioner” means a 
person who holds a qualification granted by an authority specified or notified 
under section 3 of the Indian Medical Degrees Act, 1916 (7 of 1916), or 
specified in the Schedules to the 

1[Indian Medical Council Act, 1956 (102 
of 1956)], 

2[or specified in any other law for the 
time being in force in any State,] or who practises any system of medicine and 
is registered or is entitled to be registered in any 

3[State] medical register by whatever 
name called;
 </section><section>
       <number>g</number>  “prescribed” means prescribed by 
rules or regulations made under this Act;
 </section><section>
       <number>h</number>  “3[State] 
Council” means a 

3[State] Dental Council constituted 
under section 21, and includes a Joint 

3[State] Council constituted in 
accordance with an agreement under section 22;
 </section><section>
        <number>i</number>  “register” means a register 
maintained under this Act;
 

       4[(j)  “recognised dental 
qualification” means any of the qualifications included in the Schedule;]
 </section><section>
       <number>k</number>  “recognised dental hygiene 
qualification” means a qualification recognised by the Coun­cil under section 
11:
 </section><section>
        <number>l</number>  “registered dentist”, “registered 
dental hygienist” and “registered dental mechanic” shall mean, respectively, a 
person whose name is for the time being registered in a register of dentists, a 
register of dental hygienists and a register of dental mechanics.
 </section><section>
       <number>m</number>  

5[***]
 









</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 


 <article>

1[<number>2A</number> 
Construction of references to laws not in force in Jammu and Kashmir.—Any 
reference in this Act to a law which is not in force in the State of Jammu and 
Kashmir shall, in relation to that State, be construed as a reference to the 
corresponding law, if any, in force in that State.]
  




</article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Constitution and 
composition of Council.—The 
Central Government shall, as soon as may be, constitute a Council consisting of 
the following members, namely:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  one registered dentist possessing 
a recognised dental qualification elected by the dentists registered in Part A 
of each 

1[State] register;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  one member elected from amongst 
themselves by the members of the Medical Council of India;
 

   2[3[(c)  
not more than four members elected from among themselves, by—
 </section><section>
            <number>a</number>  Principals, Deans, Directors 
and Vice-Principals of dental colleges in the States training students for 
recognised dental qualifications:
 
                  Provided that not more than 
one member shall be elected from the same dental college;
 </section><section>
            <number>b</number>  Heads of dental wings of 
medical colleges in the States training students for recognised dental 
qualifications;]
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  one member from each University 
established by law in the States which grants a recognised dental qualification, 
to be elected by the members of the Senate of the University, or in case the 
University has no Senate, by the members of the court, from amongst the members 
of the Dental Faculty of the University or in case the University has no Dental 
Faculty, from amongst the members of the Medical Faculty thereof;
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number>  one member to represent 

4[each State 

5[***], nominated by the Government of 
each such State from among persons registered either in a medical register or a 
dental register of the State;]
 



6[Explanation.—In this clause, 
“State” does not include a Union territory;]
 </section><section>
        <number>f</number>  six members nominated by the 
Central Government, of whom at least one shall be a registered dentist 
possessing a recognised dental qualification and practising or holding an 
appointment in an institution for the training of dentists in a 

7[Union territory], and at least two 
shall be dentists registered in Part B of a 

1[State] register;
 

      8[(g)  the Director-General of 
Health Services, ex officio:]
 
Provided that pending the 
preparation of registers the 

1[State] Governments 
may nominate to the first Council members referred to in parts (a) and (e) and 
the Central Government members referred to in part (f) out of persons who are 
eligible for registration in the respective registers and such persons shall 
hold office for such period as the 

1[State] or Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify.
 
 










</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Incorporation of Council.—The 
Council shall be a body corporate by the name of the Dental Council of India, 
having perpetual succession and a common seal, with power to acquire and hold 
property, both movable and immovable, and shall by the said name sue and be 
sued.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Mode of elections.—Elections 
under this Chapter shall be conducted in the prescribed manner, and where any 
dispute arises regarding any such election, it shall be referred to the Central 
Government whose decision shall be final.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Term of office and casual 
vacancies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to the provisions of this section an elected or nominated member shall 
hold office for a term of five years from the date of his election or nomination 
or until his successor has been duly elected or nominated, whichever is longer:
 

1[Provided that a member nominated under clause (e) or clause 
(f) of section 3, shall hold office during the pleasure of the authority 
nominating him.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An elected or nominated 
member may at any time resign his membership by writing under his hand addressed 
to the President, and the seat of such member shall thereupon become vacant.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An elected or nominated 
member shall be deemed to have vacated his seat if he is absent without excuse, 
sufficient in the opinion of the Council, from three consecutive ordinary 
meetings of the Council or, in the case of a member whose name is required to be 
included in a 

2[State] register, if 
his name is removed from such register, or if he has been elected under clause 
(c) of section 3 

3[if he ceases to hold 
his appointment as the 

4[Principal, Dean, 
Director or Vice-Prin­cipal] of a dental college, or as 

5[the Head of the 
dental wing] of a medical college], or if he has been elected under clause (b) 
or (d) of section 3, if he ceases to be a member of the Medical Council of India 
or 

6[the Dental or 
Medical Faculty] of the University, as the case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A casual vacancy in the 
Council shall be filled by fresh election or nomination, as the case may be, and 
the person elected or nominated to fill the vacancy shall hold office only for 
the remainder of the term for which the member whose place he takes was elected 
or nominated.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Members of the Council 
shall be eligible for re-election or re-nomination.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> No act done by the 
Council shall be called in question on the ground merely of the existence of any 
vacancy in, or defect in the constitution of, the Council.
 
 








</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> President and 
Vice-President of Council.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The President and Vice-President of the Council shall be elected by the members 
thereof from among themselves:
 
Provided that on the first 
constitution of the Council and until the President is elected, a member of the 
Council nominated by the Central Government in this behalf shall discharge the 
functions of the President:
 
Provided further that for 
five years from the first constitution of the Council, the President shall, if 
the Central Government so decides, be a person nominated by the Central 
Government who shall hold office during the pleasure of the Central Government, 
and where he is not already a member, shall be a member of the Council in 
addition to the members referred to in section 3.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An elected President or 
Vice-President shall hold office as such for a term not exceeding five years and 
not extending beyond the expiry of his term as member of the Council, but 
subject to his being a member of the Council, he shall be eligible for 
re-election.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Staff remuneration and 
allowances.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Council shall—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  appoint a Secretary who may also, 
if so decided by the Council, act as Treasurer;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  appoint such other officers and 
servants as the Council deems necessary to enable it to carry out its functions 
under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  require and take from the 
Secretary or from any other officer or servant such security for the due 
performance of his duties as the Council considers necessary; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  with the previous sanction of the 
Central Government, fix the fees and allowances of the President, Vice-President 
and other members of the Council, and the pay and allowances and other 
conditions of service of officers and servants of the Council.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in clause (a) of sub-section (1), for the first four years from the 
first constitution of the Council, the Secretary of the Council shall be a 
person appointed by the Central Government, who shall hold office during the 
pleasure of the Central Government.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> The Executive Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Council shall constitute from among its members an Executive Committee, and 
may so constitute other Committees for such general or special purposes as the 
Council considers necessary for carrying out its functions under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Executive Committee 
shall consist of the President and Vice-President ex officio 

1[and the Director-General of Health Services ex officio], 
and five other members elected by the Council.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The President and 
Vice-President of the Council shall be Chairman and Vice-Chairman, respectively, 
of the Executive Committee.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A member of the Executive 
Committee shall hold office as such until the expiry of his term of office as 
member of the Council but, subject to his being a member of the Council, he 
shall be eligible for re-election.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> In addition to the powers 
and duties conferred and imposed on it by this Act, the Executive Committee 
shall exercise and discharge such powers and duties as may be prescribed.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>10</number> 
Recognition of dental qualifications.—
<section><number>1</number> The dental qualifications, granted by any authority or 
institution in India, which are included in Part I of the Schedule shall be 
recognised dental qualifications for the purposes of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any authority or 
institution in India which grants a dental qualification not included in Part I 
of the Schedule may apply to the Central Government to have such qualification 
recognised and included in that Part, and the Central Government, after 
consulting the Council, and after such inquiry, if any, as it may think fit for 
the purpose, may, by notification in the Official Gazette, amend Part I of the 
Schedule so as to include such qualification therein, and any such notification 
may also direct that an entry shall be made in Part I of the Schedule against 
such dental qualification declaring that it shall be a recognised dental 
qualification only when granted after a specified date.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> (a) The dental 
qualifications, granted by any authority or institution outside India, which are 
included in Part II of the Schedule shall be recognised dental qualifications 
only for the purposes of the registration of citizens of India when the register 
is first prepared under this Act.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> Where any dental 
qualification granted by any authority or institution outside India, and held by 
a citizen of India, is recognised for the purposes of the register when it is 
first prepared, after the commencement of the Dentists (Amendment) Act, 1972 (42 
of 1972), the Central Government may, after consultation with the Council, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, amend Part II of the Schedule so as to 
include therein the dental qualification so recognised.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> (a) The dental 
qualifications granted by any authority or institution outside India, which are 
included in Part III of the Schedule, shall be recognised dental qualifications 
for the purposes of this Act, but no person possessing any such qualification, 
shall be entitled for registration unless he is a citizen of India.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> Where any dental 
qualification granted by any authority or institution outside India, and held by 
a citizen of India, is recognised, except on reciprocal basis, after the 
commencement of the Dentists (Amendment) Act, 1972 (42 of 1972), the Central 
Government may, after consultation with the Council, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, amend Part III of the Schedule so as to include therein the 
dental qualification so recognised.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> The Council may enter 
into negotiations with any authority or institution in any State or country 
outside India which, by law of any such State or country, is entrusted with the 
maintenance of a register of dentists, for the setling of a scheme of 
reciprocity for the recognition of dental qualifications and in pursuance of any 
such scheme, the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, declare that any such qualification granted by any authority or 
institution in any such State or country, or such qualification, only when 
granted after a specified date, shall be a recognised dental qualification for 
the purposes of this Act, and any such notification may provide for an amendment 
of the Schedule and may also direct that any such dental qualification as is 
specified in the notification shall be entered in the Schedule as so amended.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The Central Government 
may, after consultation with the Council, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, amend the Schedule by directing that an entry be made therein in 
respect of any dental qualification declaring that it shall be a recognised 
dental qualification only when granted before a specified date.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>10A</number> 
Permission for establishment of new dental college, new courses of study, etc.— 

<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act or any other law for the time 
being in force,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  no person shall establish an 
authority or institution for a course of study or training (including a 
post-graduate course of study or training) which would enable a student of such 
course or training to qualify himself for the grant of recognised dental 
qualification; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  no authority or institution 
conducting a course of study or training (including a post­graduate course of 
study or training) for grant of recognised dental qualification shall—
 <subsubsection>
             <number>i</number>  open a new or higher course 
of study or training (including a post-graduate course of study or training) 
which would enable a student of such course or training to qualify himself for 
the award of any recognised dental qualification; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>ii</number>  increase its admission 
capacity in any course of study or training (including a post-graduate course of 
study or training),
 
except with the previous permission of the 
Central Government obtained in accordance with the provisions of this section.
 
Explanation 1.—For 
the purposes of this section, ”person” includes any University or a trust but 
does not include the Central Government.
 
Explanation 2.—For 
the purposes of this section, “admission capacity”, in relation to any course of 
study or training (including a post-graduate course of study or training) in an 
authority or institution granting recognised dental qualification, means the 
maximum number of students that may be fixed by the Council from time to time 
for being admitted to such course or training.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> (a) Every person, 
authority or institution granting recognised dental qualification shall, for the 
purpose of obtaining permission under sub-section (1), submit, to the Central 
Government a scheme in accordance with the provisions of clause (b) and the 
Central Government shall refer the said scheme to the Council for its 
recommendations.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The scheme referred to in 
clause (b) shall be in such form and contain such particulars and be preferred 
in such manner and be accompanied with such fee as may be prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> On receipt of a scheme by 
the Council under sub-section (2), the Council may obtain such other particulars 
as may be considered necessary by it from the person, authority or institution 
concerned, granting recognised dental qualification and thereafter, it may,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  if the scheme is defective and 
does not contain any necessary particulars, give a reasonable opportunity to the 
person, authority or institution concerned for making a written representation 
and it shall be open to such person, authority or institution to rectify the 
defects, if any, specified by the Council;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  consider the scheme, having regard 
to the factors referred to in sub-section (7), and submit the scheme together 
with its recommendations thereon to the Central Government.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The Central Government 
may, after considering the scheme and the recommendations of the Council under 
sub-section (3) and after obtaining where necessary, such other particulars as 
may be considered necessary by it from the person, authority or institution 
concerned, and having regard to the factors referred to in sub-section (7), 
either approve (with such conditions, if any, as it may consider necessary) or 
disapprove the scheme and any such approval shall be a permission under 
sub-section (1):
 
Provided that no scheme shall 
be disapproved by the Central Government except after giving the person, 
authority or institution concerned granting recognised dental qualification a 
reasonable opportunity of being heard:
 
Provided further that nothing 
in this sub-section shall prevent any person, authority or institution whose 
scheme has not been approved to submit a fresh scheme and the provisions of this 
section shall apply to such scheme, as if such scheme has been submitted for the 
first time under sub-section (2).
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where, within a period of 
one year from the date of submission of the scheme to the Central Government 
under sub-section (2), no order passed by the Central Government has been 
communicated to the person, authority or institution submitting the scheme, such 
scheme shall be deemed to have been approved by the Central Government in the 
form in which it has been submitted, and accordingly, the permission of the 
Central Government required under sub-sec­tion (1) shall also be deemed to have 
been granted.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> In computing the 
time-limit specified in sub-section (5), the time taken by the person, authority 
or institution concerned submitting the scheme in furnishing any particulars 
called for by the Council or by the Central Government, shall be excluded.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The Council, while making 
its recommendations under clause (b) of sub-section (3) and the Central 
Government, while passing an order either approving or disapproving the scheme 
under sub-section (4), shall have due regard to the following factors, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  whether the proposed authority or 
institution for grant of recognised dental qualification or the existing 
authority or institution seeking to open a new or higher course of study or 
training, would be in a position to offer the minimum standards of dental 
education in conformity with the requirements referred to in section 16A and the 
regulations made under sub-section (1) of section 20;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  whether the person seeking to 
establish an authority or institution or the existing authority or institution 
seeking to open a new or higher course of study or training or to increase its 
admission capacity has adequate resources;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  whether necessary facilities in 
respect of staff, equipment, accommodation, training and other facilities to 
ensure proper functioning of the authority or institution or conducting the new 
course of study or training or accommodating the increased admission capacity 
have been provided or would be provided within the time-limit specified in the 
scheme;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  whether adequate hospital 
facilities, having regard to the number of students likely to attend such 
authority or institution or course of study or training or as a result of the 
increased admission capacity have been provided or would be provided within the 
time-limit specified in the scheme;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  whether any arrangement has been 
made or programme drawn to impart proper training to students likely to attend 
such authority or institution or course of study or training by persons having 
the recognised dental qualifications;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  the requirement of manpower in 
the field of practice of dentistry; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>g</number>  any other factors as may be 
prescribed.









</subsection></section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>10B</number> 
Non-recognition of dental qualifications in certain cases.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where any authority or institution is established for grant of recognised dental 
qualification except with the previous permission of the Central Government in 
accordance with the provisions of section 10A, no dental qualification granted 
to any student of such authority or institution shall be a recognised dental 
qualification for the purposes of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any authority or 
institution granting recognised dental qualification opens a new or higher 
course of study or training (including a post-graduate course of study or 
training) except with the previous permission of the Central Government in 
accordance with the provisions of section 10A, no dental qualification granted 
to any student of such authority or institution on the basis of such study or 
training shall be a recognised dental qualification for the purposes of this 
Act.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where any authority or 
institution granting recognised dental qualification increases its admission 
capacity in any course of study or training (including a post-graduate course of 
study or training) except with the previous permission of the Central Government 
in accordance with the provisions of section 10A, no dental qualification 
granted to any student of such authority or institution on the basis of the 
increase in its admission capacity shall be a recognised dental qualification 
for the purposes of this Act.
 
Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this section, the criteria for identifying a student who has 
been granted a dental qualification on the basis of such increase in the 
admission capacity shall be such as may be prescribed.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>10C</number> 
Time for seeking permission for certain existing authorities.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If, after the 1st day of June, 1992 and on and before the commencement of the 
Dentists (Amendment) Act, 1993 any person has established an authority or 
institution for grant of recognised dental qualification or any authority or 
institution granting recognised dental qualification has opened a new or higher 
course of study or training (including a post-graduate course of study or 
training) or increased its admission capacity, such person, authority or 
institution, as the case may be, shall seek, within a period of one year from 
the commencement of the Dentists (Amendment) Act, 1993, the permission of the 
Central Government in accordance with the provisions of section 10A.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any person or, as the 
case may be, any authority or institution granting recognised dental 
qualification fails to seek the permission under sub-section (1), the provisions 
of section 10B shall apply, so far as may be, as if permission of the Central 
Government under section 10A has been refused.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Qualifications of dental 
hygienists.—Any 
authority in a 

1[State] 

2[***] which grants a qualification for dental hygienists may 
apply to the Council to have such qualification recognised, and the Council may, 
after such inquiry, if any, as it thinks fit, and after consulting the 
Government and the 

3[State] Council of 
the 

1[State] in which the authority making the application is 
situated, declare that such qualification, or such qualification only when 
granted after a specified date, shall be a recognised dental hygiene 
qualification for the purposes of this Act.
 
 






</article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Qualifications of dental 
mechanics.—The 
Council may prescribe the period and nature of an apprenticeship or training 
which shall be undergone and the other conditions which shall be satisfied by a 
person before he is entitled to be registered under this Act as a dental 
mechanic.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Effect of recognition.—Notwithstanding 
anything contained in any other law, but subject to the provisions of this Act,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  any recognised dental or dental 
hygiene qualification shall be a sufficient qualification for enrolment in the 
appropriate register of any 

1[State];
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  no person shall, after the first 
registers are compiled under this Act, be entitled to be enrolled in any 
register as a dentist or dental hygienist unless he holds a recognised dental or 
dental hygiene qualification or as a dental mechanic unless he has undergone 
training which satisfies the prescribed requirements referred to in section 12.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Power to require 
information as to courses of study and training and examinations.—Every 
authority in a 

1[State] 

2[***] which grants 
any recognised dental or dental hygiene qualification shall furnish such 
information as the Council may from time to time require as to the courses of 
study and training and examinations to be undergone in order to obtain such 
qualification, as to the ages at which such courses of study and examinations 
are required to be undergone, and generally as to the requisites for obtaining 
such qualification.
 
 





</article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Inspections.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Executive Committee 

1[may, subject to regulations, if any, made by the Council 
appoint] such number of Inspectors as it deems necessary to attend at any 
examina­tions held by authorities in the 

2[States] 

3[***] which grant recognised dental or dental hygiene 
qualifications and to inspect any institution recognised as a training 
institution.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Inspectors appointed 
under this section shall not interfere with the course of any examina­tion but 
they shall report to the Executive Committee on the sufficiency of every 
examination at which they attend and of the courses of study and training at 
every institution which they inspect, and on any other matters with regard to 
which the Executive Committee may require them to report.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Executive Committee 
shall forward a copy of such report to the authority or institution concerned 
and shall also forward copies with remarks, if any, of the authority or 
institution concerned thereon to the Central Government and to the Government of 
the 

4[State] in which the authority or institution is situated.
 
 







</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>15A</number> 
Appointment of Visitors.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Council may appoint such number of Visitors as it may deem necessary to 
attend at any examination held by any authority or institution in a State which 
grants recognised dental qualifications and to inspect any institution training 
students for recognised dental qualifications.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person, whether he is 
a member of the Council or not, may be appointed as a Visitor under this 
section, but a person who is appointed as an Inspector under section 15 for any 
inspection or examination shall not be appointed as a Visitor for the same 
inspection or examination.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Visitor shall not 
interfere with the course of any examination but shall report to the President 
of the Council on the sufficiency of every examination at which he attends and 
of the courses of study and training at every institution which he inspects and 
on the adequacy of the standards of dental education including staff, equipment, 
accommodation and other facilities prescribed for giving dental education, and 
on any other matters with regard to which the Council may require him to report.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The report of a Visitor 
shall be treated as confidential unless in any particular case the President of 
the Council otherwise directs:
 
Provided that if the Central 
Government requires a copy of the report of a Visitor, the Council shall furnish 
the same.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Withdrawal of 
recognition.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When upon report by the Executive Committee it appears to the Council—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  that the courses of study and 
training or the examinations to be undergone in order to obtain a recognised


1[***] dental hygiene qualification 
from any authority in a 

2[State] 

3[***] or the conditions for admission 
to such courses or the standards of proficiency required from the candidates at 
such examinations are not in conformity with regulations made under this Act or 
fall short of the standards required thereby, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  that an institution does not 
satisfy the requirements of the Council,
 
the Council may send to the Government of the


2[States] in which the authority or 
institution is situated a statement to such effect, and the 

4[State] Government shall forward it, 
along with such remarks as it may think fit, to the authority or institution 
concerned with an intimation of the period within which the authority or 
institution may submit its explanation to the 

4[State] Government.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> On receipt of the 
explanation, or where no explanation is submitted within the period fixed, then 
on the expiry of the period, the 

4[State] Government 
shall after consulting the 

4[State] Council, 
forward its recommendations and those of the 

4[State] Council, if 
any, to the Council.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Council, after 
considering the recommendations of the 

4[State] Government 
and the 

4[State] Council and after such further inquiry, if any, as it 
may think fit to make, may declare that the qualification granted by the 
authority or institution shall be a recognised 

1[***] dental hygiene 
qualification only when granted before a specified date.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Council may declare 
that any recognised 

1[***] dental hygiene 
qualification granted outside the 

5[States] 

3[***] shall be recognised as such only if granted before a 
specified date.
 
 








</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>16A</number> 
Withdrawal of recognition of recognised dental qualification.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When, upon report by the Executive Committee or the Visitor, it appears to the 
Council—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  that the courses of study and 
training or the examination to be undergone in order to obtain a recognised 
dental qualification from any authority or institution in a State, or the 
conditions for admission to such courses or the standards of proficiency 
required from the candidates at such examinations are not in conformity with the 
regulations made under this Act or fall short of the standards required thereby, 
or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  that an institution does not, in 
the matter of staff, equipment, accommodation, training and other facilities, 
satisfy the requirements of the Council,
 
the Council shall send a statement to that 
effect to the Central Government.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> After considering such a 
statement, the Central Government may send it to the Govern­ment of the State in 
which the authority exercises power or the institution is situated, and the 
State Government shall forward it, along with such remarks as it may think fit 
to make, to the authority or institution concerned, with an intimation of the 
period within which the authority or institution may submit its explanation to 
the State Government.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> After considering the 
explanation, or where no explanation is submitted within the period fixed, then, 
on the expiry of that period, the State Government shall make its 
recommen­dations to the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Central Government 
may, after considering the recommendations of the State Government and after 
making such further inquiry, if any, as it may think fit, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, direct that an entry shall be made in Part I of the Schedule 
against the qualification granted by the authority or institution declaring that 
it shall be a recognised dental qualification only when granted before a 
specified date or that the said recognised dental qualification if granted to 
students of a specified college or institution affiliated to any University 
shall be a recognised dental qualification only when granted before a specified 
date or, as the case may be, that the said recognised dental qualification shall 
be a recognised dental qualification in relation to a specified college or 
institution affiliated to any University only when granted after a specified 
date.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Mode of declarations.—All 
declarations under 

1[***] section 11 or section 16 shall be made by a resolution 
passed at a meeting of the Council and shall forthwith be published in the 
Official Gazette.
 
 




</article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>17A</number> 
Professional conduct.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Council may prescribe standards of professional conduct and etiquette or the 
code of ethics for dentists.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Regulations made by the 
Council under sub-section (1) may specify which violations thereof shall 
constitute infamous conduct in any professional respect, that is to say, 
professional misconduct, and such provision shall have effect notwithstanding 
anything to the contrary contained in any other law for the time being in 
force].
 
 




</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> The Indian Register.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Council shall maintain a register of dentists to be known as the Indian 
Dentists Register and consisting of the entries in all the 

1[State] registers of 
dentists.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Each 

1[State] Council shall supply to the Council twenty printed 
copies of the 

1[State] register as 
soon as may be after the 1st day of April of each year, and each Registrar shall 
inform the Council without delay of all additions to and other amendments in the


1[State] register.







</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Information to be 
furnished.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
Council shall furnish copies of its minutes and of the minutes of the Executive 
Committee and an annual report of its activities together with an abstract of 
its accounts to the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Central Government 
may publish in such manner as it thinks fit any report, copy of abstract 
furnished to it under this section.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Power to make 
regulations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Council may, with the approval of the Central Government, 

1[by notification in 
the Official Gazette,] make regulations not inconsistent with the provisions of 
this Act to carry out the purposes of this Chapter.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular and without 
prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power such regula­tions may—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  provide for the management of the 
property of the Council 

2[***];
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  prescribe the manner in which 
elections under this Chapter shall be conducted;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  provide for the summoning and 
holding of meeting of the Council and the Executive Committee, the times and 
places at which such meetings shall be held, the conduct of business thereat and 
the number of members necessary to constitute a quorum;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  prescribe the functions of the 
Executive Committee;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  prescribe the powers and duties of 
the President and Vice-President;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  prescribe the tenure of office 
and the powers and duties of the Secretary, 

3[and other officers and servants of 
the Council, and Inspectors, and Visitors appointed by the Council];
 

     4[(fa)  prescribe the form of the 
scheme, the particulars to be given in such scheme, the manner in which the 
scheme is to be preferred and the fee payable with the scheme under clause (b) 
of sub-section (2) of section 10A;
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>fb</number>  prescribe any other factors under 
clause (g) of sub-section (7) of section 10A;
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>fc</number>  prescribe the criteria for 
identifying a student who has been granted a dental qualification referred to in 
the Explanation to sub-section (3) of section 10B;]
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>g</number>  prescribe the standard curricula 
for the training of dentists and dental hygienists, and the conditions for 
admission to courses of such training;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>h</number>  prescribe the standards of 
examinations and other requirements to be satisfied to secure for the 
qualifications recognition under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>i</number>  any other matter which is to be 
or may be prescribed under this Act:
 
Provided that regulations 
under clauses (g) and (h) shall be made after consultation with 

5[State] Governments.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> To enable the Council to 
be first constituted the Central Government may make regula­tions for the 
conduct of the elections to the Council, and any regulation so made may be 
altered or rescinded by the Council in exercise of its powers under this 
section.
 

6[(4) Every regulation made under this section shall be laid, 
as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is 
in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one 
session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the 
session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, 
both Houses agree in making any modification in the regulation or both Houses 
agree that the regulation should not be made, the regulation shall thereafter 
have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; 
so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice 
to the validity of anything previously done under that regulation.]












</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Constitution and 
composition of State Councils.—Except 
where a Joint 

1[State] Council is 
constituted in accordance with an agreement made under section 22, the 

1[State] Government shall constitute a 

1[State] Council consisting of the following members, namely:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  four members elected from among 
themselves by dentists registered in Part A of the 

1[State] register;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  four members elected from among 
themselves by dentists registered in Part B of the 

1[State] register;
 
 

3[(c)  the heads of dental colleges, if 
any, in the 

1[State] which train students for any 
of the recognised dental qualifications included in Part I of the Schedule, 
ex officio;]
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  one member elected from amongst 
themselves by the members of the Medical Council or the Council of Medical 
Registration of the 

4[State] as the case may be; 
5[***]
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number>  three members nominated by the


6[State] Government; 

7[and]
 
 

7[(f)  the Chief Medical Officer of the 
State, by whatever name called, ex officio:]
 

8[Provided that in the State of Saurashtra, 

9[as it existed before the 1st November, 1956], the State 
Dental Council constituted under Saurashtra Ordinance 25 of 1948, as amended by 
Saurashtra Ordinance 40 of 1949, shall be deemed to be the State Council 
constituted under this Act.]
 
 












</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Inter-State agreements.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Two or more 

1[State] Governments may enter into an agreement to be in force 
for such period and to be subject to renewal for such further periods, if any, 
as may be specified in the agreement, to provide—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  for the constitution of a Joint


1[State] Council for all the 
participating 

2[States], or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  for the 

1[State] Council of one 

1[State] to serve the needs of the 
other participating 

2[States].
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> In addition to such 
matters as are in this Act specified, an agreement under this section may—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  provide for the apportionment 
between the participating 

2[States] of the expenditure in 
connection with the 

1[State] Council or Joint 

1[State] Council;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  determine which of the 
participating 

1[State] Governments shall exercise the 
several functions of the 

1[State] Government under this Act, and 
the references in this Act to the 

1[State] Government shall be construed 
accordingly;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  provide for consultation between 
the participating 

1[State] Governments either generally 
or with reference to particular matters arising under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  make such incidental and ancillary 
provisions, not inconsistent with this Act, as may be deemed necessary or 
expedient for giving effect to the agreement.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> An agreement under this 
section shall be published in the Official Gazettes of the participating 

2[States].
 
 





</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Composition of Joint 
State Councils.—A 
Joint 

1[State] Council shall 
consist of the following members, namely:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  two members elected from among 
themselves by dentists registered in Part A of the register of each of the 
participating 

2[States];
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  two members elected from among 
themselves by dentists registered in Part B of the register of each of the 
participating 

2[States];
 

      3[(c)  the heads of dental 
colleges, if any, in all the participating States which train students for any 
of the recognised dental qualifications included in Part I of the Schedule, 
ex officio;]
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  one member elected by the Medical 
Council or the Council of Medical Registration, of each participating 

4[State], as the case may be;
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number>  two members nominated by each 
participating 

3[State] Government;
 

       5[(f)  the Chief Medical Officer 
of each participating State, by whatever name called, ex officio].
 
 









</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>24</number> Incorporation of State 
Councils.—Every


1[State] Council shall be a body corporate by such name as may 
be notified by the 

2[State] Government in 
the Official Gazette or, in the case of a Joint 

1[State] Council, as 
may be determined in the agreement, having perpetual succession and a common 
seal with power to acquire and hold property, both movable and immovable, and 
shall by the said name sue and be sued.
 
 




</article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> President and 
Vice-President of State Council.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The President and Vice-President of the 

1[State] Council shall 
be elected by the members from among themselves:
 
Provided that for five years 
from the first constitution of the 

1[State] Council, the 
President shall, if the 

1[State] Government so 
decides, be a person nominated by the 

1[State] Government 
who shall hold office during the pleasure of the 

1[State] Government, 
and where he is not already a member, shall be a member of the 

1[State] Council in addition to the members referred to in 
section 21 or 23, as the case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The President or 
Vice-President shall hold office as such for a term not exceeding five years and 
not extending beyond the expiry of his term as a member of the 

1[State] Council, but 
subject to his being a member of the 

1[State] Council, he shall be eligible, for re-election.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Mode of elections.—Elections 
under this Chapter shall be conducted in the prescribed manner, and where any 
dispute arises regarding any such election, it shall be referred to the 

1[State] Government whose decision shall be final.
 
 




</article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Term of office and casual 
vacancies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to the provisions of this section, an elected or nominated member shall 
hold office for a term of five years from the date of his election or nomination 
or until his successor has been duly elected or nominated whichever is longer:
 

1[Provided that a member nominated under clause (e) of section 
21 or clause (e) of section 23, shall hold office during the pleasure of the 
authority nominating him.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An elected or nominated 
member may at any time resign his membership by writing under his hand addressed 
to the President, and the seat of such member shall thereupon become vacant.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An elected or nominated 
member shall be deemed to have vacated his seat—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  if he is absent without excuse, 
sufficient in the opinion of the 

2[State] Council, from three 
consecutive ordinary meetings of the 

2[State] Council, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  in the case of a member whose name 
is required to be included in any 

2[State] register, if his name is 
removed from the register, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  where he has been elected under 
clause (d) of section 21 or under clause (d) of section 23, if he ceases to be a 
member of the Medical Council or the Council of Medical Registration of the


2[State] as the case may be.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> A casual vacancy in the


2[State] Council shall be filled by fresh election or 
nomination, as the case may be, and the person elected or nominated to fill the 
vacancy shall hold office only for the remainder of the term for which the 
member whose place he takes was elected or nominated.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Members of the 

2[State] Council shall be eligible for re-election or 
renomination.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> No act done by the 

2[State] Council shall be called in question on the ground 
merely of the existence of any vacancy in, or defect in the constitution of the


2[State] Council.
 
 





</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Staff, remuneration and 
allowances.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The 

1[State] Council may, 
with the previous sanction of the 

1[State] Government,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  appoint a Registrar, who shall 
also act as Secretary and if so decided by the 

1[State] Council also as its Treasurer;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  appoint such other officers and 
servants as may be required to enable the 

1[State] Council to carry out its 
functions under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  require and take from the 
Registrar or from any other officer or servant such security for the due 
performance of his duties as the 

1[State] Council considers necessary;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  fix the salaries and allowances 
and other conditions of service of the Registrar and other officers and servants 
of the 

1[State] Council;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  fix the rate of allowances payable 
to members of the 

1[State] Council.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in clause (a) of sub-section (1), for the first four years from the 
first constitution of the 

1[State] Council, the 
Registrar of the 

1[State] Council shall 
be a person appointed by the 

1[State] Government 
who shall hold office during the pleasure of the 

1[State] Government.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>29</number> Executive Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The 

1[State] Council shall constitute from among its members an 
Executive Committee consisting of the President and Vice-President ex officio


2[and the Chief Medical Officer of the State or the States 
concerned by whatever name called, ex officio,] and such number of other 
members elected by the 

1[State] Council as 
may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The President and 
Vice-President of the 

3[State] Council shall 
be Chairman and Vice-Chairman, respectively, of the Executive Committee.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A member of the Executive 
Committee shall hold office as such until the expiry of his term of office as 
member of the 

3[State] Council, but 
subject to his being a member of the 

3[State] Council, he 
shall be eligible for re-election.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Executive Committee 
shall exercise and discharge such powers and duties as may be prescribed.
 
 






</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>30</number> Information to be 
furnished.—
<section><number>1</number> The


1[State] Council shall furnish such reports, copies of its 
minutes and of the minutes of the Executive Committee, and abstracts of its 
accounts to the 

1[State] Government as 
the 

1[State] Government may from time to time require and shall 
forward copies of all material so furnished to the 

1[State] Government to the Council.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 

1[State] Government may publish in such manner as it thinks fit 
any report, copy or abstract furnished to it under this section.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>31</number> Preparation and 
maintenance of register.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The 

1[State] Government 
shall as soon as may be cause to be prepared in the manner hereinafter provided 
a register of dentists for the 

2[State].
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 

1[State] Council shall upon its constitution assume the duty of 
maintaining the register in accordance with the provisions of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The register of dentists 
shall be maintained in two Parts, A and B persons possessing recognised dental 
qualifications being registered in Part A and persons not possessing such 
qualifications being registered in Part B.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The register shall 
include the following particulars, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the full name, nationality and 
residential address of the registered person;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the date of his first admission to 
the register;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  his qualification for 
registration, and the date on which he obtained his degree or diploma in 
dentistry, if any, and the authority which conferred it;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  his professional address; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  such further particulars as may be 
prescribed.
 
 





</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>32</number> First preparation of register. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> For the purpose of first preparing the register of dentists, the <footcitenum>25</footcitenum> [State] Government shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute a Registration Tribunal consisting of three persons and shall also appoint a Registrar who shall act as Secretary of the Tribunal. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The <footcitenum>25</footcitenum> [State] Government shall, by the same or a like notification, appoint a date on or before which application for registration, which shall be accompanied by the prescribed fee, shall be made to the Registration  
  Tribunal. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Registration Tribunal shall examine every application received on or before the appointed date, and if it is satisfied that the applicant is qualified for registration under section 33, shall direct the entry of the name of the applicant on the register. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The register so prepared shall thereafter be published in such manner as the <footcitenum>25</footcitenum> [State] Government may direct, and any person aggrieved by a decision of the Registration Tribunal expressed or implied in the register as so published may within thirty days from the date of such publication, appeal to the authority appointed by the <footcitenum>25</footcitenum> [State] Government in this behalf by notification in the Official Gazette. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Registrar shall amend the register in accordance with the decisions of the authority appointed under sub-section (4) and shall thereupon issue to every person whose name is entered on the register a certificate of registration in the prescribed form. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> Upon the constitution of the <footcitenum>25</footcitenum> [State] Council, the register shall be given into its custody, and the <footcitenum>25</footcitenum> [State] Government may direct that all or any specified part of the application fees for registration in the first register shall be paid to the credit of the <footcitenum>25</footcitenum>[State] Council. 


</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>33</number> Qualifications for entry 
on first preparation of register.—
<section><number>1</number> A person shall be entitled on payment of the prescribed 
fee to have his name entered on the register when it is first prepared, if he 
resides or carriers on the profession of dentistry in the 

1[State] and if he—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  holds a recognised dental 
qualification, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  does not hold such a qualification 
but, being a 

2[citizen of India], has been engaged 
in practice as a dentist as his principal means of livelihood for a period of 
not less than five years prior to 

3[the date appointed under sub-section 
(2) of section 32]:
 
Provided that no person other 
than a 

2[citizen of India] 
shall be entitled to registration by virtue of a qualification—
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>a</number>  specified in Part I of the 
schedule unless by the law and practice of the State or country to which such 
person belongs persons of Indian origin holding dental qualifications 
registrable in that State or country are permitted to enter and practise the 
profession of dentistry in such State or country, or
 

      4[(b)  recognised, in pursuance 
of a scheme of reciprocity, under sub-section (5) of section 10]:
 
Provided further that a 
person shall be entitled to registration by virtue of a qualification specified 
in 

5[Part II] of the Schedule only if he is a 

2[citizen of India]:
 

6[Provided further that for the purpose of the first 
preparation of the register of dentists under this Act, a person shall be 
entitled to have his name entered in the appropriate part of the register 
without payment of any registration fee,—
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>a</number>  in the State of Saurashtra, 

7[as it existed before the 1st 
November, 1956], if he is registered on the register of dental practitioners 
maintained under Saurashtra Ordinance No. 25 of 1948, as amended by Saurashtra 
Ordinance No. 40 of 1949; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  in the State of Travancore-Cochin


7[as it existed before the 1st November, 1956], if he is registered on the register of dental practitioners 
maintained under the Travancore Medical Practitioners Act, 1119;] 

8[or]
 

      8[(c)  in the State of Jammu and 
Kashmir, if he is registered on the register of dental prac­titioners maintained 
under the Jammu and Kashmir Dentists Act, 1958 (J&amp;K Act 9 of 1958).]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A person domiciled in a


9[State] 

10[***] shall be 
entitled on payment of the prescribed fee to temporary registration as a dentist 
for a period of five years, if he has been engaged in practice as a dentist as 
his principal means of livelihood for a period of not less than two years during 
the five years prior to 

11[the date appointed 
under sub-section (2) of section 32], and a person so registered shall be 
entitled to permanent registration if 

12[for a period of 
five years from the date of his temporary registration he has been engaged in 
practice as a dentist.]
 
 















</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>34</number> Qualification for 
subsequent registration.—1[
<section><number>1</number> After the date appointed under sub-section (2) of section 
32 a person shall, on payment of the prescribed fee, be entitled to have his 
name entered on the register of dentists, if he resides or carries on the 
profession of dentistry in the 

2[State] and if he—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  holds recognised dental 
qualification, or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  does not hold such a 
qualification but, being a 

3[citizen of India], has been engaged 
in practice as a dentist as his principal means of livelihood for a period of 
not less than 

4[two years before the date appointed 
under sub-section (2) of section 32] and has passed, within a period of 

5[ten years after the said date], an 
examination recognised for this purpose by the 

6[Central Government]:
 
Provided that no person other 
than a 

7[citizen of India] 
shall be entitled to registration by virtue of a qualification:
 <subsubsection>
       <number>a</number>  specified in Part I of the 
Schedule unless by the law and practice of the State or country to which such 
person belongs persons of Indian origin holding dental qualifications 
registrable in that State or country are permitted to enter and practise the 
profession of dentistry in such State or country, or
 

      8[(b)  recognised in pursuance of 
a scheme of reciprocity, under sub-section (5) of section 10]:
 
Provided further that a 
person registered in Part B of the register shall be entitled to be registered 
in Part A thereof, if within a period of 

9[ten years after the 
date of his registration in Part B] he passes an examination recognized for the 
purpose by the 

10[Central 
Government].
 

11[(2) Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1),—
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>a</number>  a 

12[State Council] may during the period 
of two years immediately after the commence­ment of the Dentists (Amendment) 
Act, 

13[1955 (12 of 1955)], permit for 
sufficient reasons the registra­tion in the State register of any displaced 
person who does not hold a recognised dental qualification but has been actually 
practising the profession of dentistry as his principal means of livelihood from 
a date prior to the 29th day of March, 1948;
 
              Explanation.—In 
this clause “displaced person” means any person who, on account of the setting 
up of the Dominions of India and Pakistan or on account of civil disturbances or 
fear of such disturbances in any area now forming part of Pakistan has, after 
the 1st day of March, 1947, left or been displaced from, his place of residence 
in such area and who has since then been residing in India;
 

  14[(aa)  the State Council may, 
during the period of two years immediately after the commencement of the 
Dentists (Amendment) Act, 1972 (42 of 1972), permit, for sufficient reasons, the 
registra­tion in the State register of any displaced person or a repatriate who 
does not hold any recognised dental qualification but has been actually 
practising the profession of dentistry as his principal means of livelihood from 
a date prior to the 29th day of March, 1948.
 
              Explanation.—In 
this clause,—
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
             <number>i</number>  “displaced person” means any 
person who on account of civil disturbances or fear of such disturbances in any 
area now forming part of Bangladesh, has, after the 14th day of April, 1957 but 
before the 25th day of March, 1971, left, or has been displaced from, his place 
of residence in such area and who has since then been residing in India;
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>ii</number>  “repatriate” means any 
person who on account of civil disturbances or fear of such disturbances in any 
area now forming part of Burma or Ceylon, has, after the 14th day of April, 
1957, left or has been displaced from, his place of residence in such area and 
who has since then been residing in India;]
 <subsubsection>
       <number>b</number>  a person other than a citizen of 
India holding a reputable dental qualification and employed for teaching or 
research in a dental institution situated in any of the States may be permitted


15[***] temporary registration in the 
State register of dentists for the period of his employment or for a period of 
five years, whichever is shorter:
 
Provided that he does not 
practise the profession of dentistry for personal gain and his application for 
registration is approved by the President of the Council.]
 
 


















</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>35</number> Scrutiny of applications 
for registration.—
<section><number>1</number> 
After the date appointed for the receipt of applications for registration in the 
first register of dentists, all applications for registration shall be addressed 
to the Registrar of the 

1[State] Council and 
shall be accompanied by the prescribed fee.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If upon such application 
the Registrar is of opinion that the applicant is entitled to have his name 
entered on the register, he shall enter thereon the name of the applicant:
 
Provided that no person, 
whose name has under the provisions of this Act been removed from the register 
of any 

2[State] shall be entitled to have his name entered on the 
register except with the approval of the 

1[State] Council from 
whose register his name was removed.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any person whose 
application for registration is rejected by the Registrar may, within three 
months from the date of such rejection, appeal to the 

1[State] Council, and 
the decision of the 

1[State] Council 
thereon shall be final.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Upon entry in the 
register of a name under this section, the Registrar shall issue a certificate 
of registration in the prescribed form.
 
 





</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>35A</number> Special 
provision for amending the register of dentists.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in this Chapter, the Registrar may, by order, 
in writing, amend the register by deleting therefrom the name of any person who 
by reason of the formation of the State of Andhra, has ceased to reside or carry 
on the business or profession of dentistry in the State of Madras:
 
Provided that the Registrar 
shall, before passing an order, make such inquiry as he deems necessary.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person aggrieved by 
an order under sub-section (1) may appeal to such authority and within such 
time, as may be specified in this behalf by the State Government of Madras; and 
such authority shall pass such order on the appeal as it thinks fit.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An order of the Registrar 
under sub-section (1), or where an appeal has been preferred against it under 
sub-section (2), the order of the appellate authority shall be final.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The provision of this 
section shall cease to be in force from such date as the State Government of 
Madras may be notification in the Official Gazette appoint].
 
 




</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>36</number> Registers of dental 
hygienists and dental mechanics.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The 

1[State] Government 
may, by notification in the official Gazette, direct that the 

1[State] Council shall maintain a register of dental hygienists 
or a register of dental mechanics.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The provisions of section 
35 shall, so far as they may be made applicable, apply in respect of 
applications for registration in a register referred to in this section.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>37</number> Qualification for 
registration as a dental hygienist.—A 
person shall be entitled on payment of the prescribed fee to have his name 
registered on the register of dental hygienists, if he resides in the 

1[State] and holds a recognised dental hygiene qualification:
 
Provided that for the 
purposes of the first register of dental hygientists, a person shall be entitled 
to be registered, if he has been engaged as a dental hygienist as his principal 
means of livelihood for a period of not less than two years prior to the date of 
notification under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 36.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>38</number> Qualification for 
registration as a dental mechanic.—A 
person shall be entitled on payment of the prescribed fee to have his name 
entered in the register of dental mechanics, if he satisfies the prescribed 
requirements referred to in section 12:
 
Provided that for the 
purposes of the preparation of the first register of dental mechanics a person 
shall be entitled to be registered, if he has been engaged as a dental mechanic 
as his principal means of livelihood for a period of not less than two years 
prior to the date of notification under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 36.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>39</number> Renewal fees.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The 

1[State] Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, direct that for the retention of a name in a register after the 31st 
day of December of the year following the year in which the name is first 
entered in the register, there shall be paid annually to the 

1[State] Council such renewal fee as may be prescribed in 
respect of each register, and where such direction has been made, such renewal 
fee shall be due to be paid before the 1st day of April of the year to which it 
relates.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where a renewal fee is 
not paid before the due date, the Registrar shall remove the name of the 
defaulter from the register:
 
Provided that a name so 
removed may be restored to the register on payment in such manner as may be 
prescribed.
 

2[(3) On payment of the renewal fee, the Registrar shall issue 
a certificate of renewal and such certificate shall be proof of renewal of 
registration.]
 
 





</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>40</number> Entry of additional 
qualifications.—A 
registered dentist shall on payment of the prescribed fee be entitled to have 
entered in the register any further recognised 

1[dental] 
qualification which he may obtain.
 
 




</article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>41</number> Removal from register.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to the provisions of this section, the 

1[State] Council may 
order that the name of any person shall be removed from any register where it is 
satisfied, after giving that person a reasonable opportunity of being heard and 
after such further inquiry, if any, as it may think fit to make,—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  that his name has been entered in 
the register by error or on account of misrepresentation or suppression of a 
material fact, or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  that he has been convicted of 
any offence or has been guilty of any infamous conduct in any professional 
respect 

2[or has violated the standards of 
professional conduct and etiquette or the code of ethics prescribed under 
section 17A], which in the opinion of the 

1[State] Council renders him unfit to 
be kept in the register, 

3[or]
 

      3[(iii)  that he having been 
permitted temporary registration under clause (b) of sub-section (2) of section 
34 has, on such registration, been found to practise the profession of dentistry 
for personal gain.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> An order under 
sub-section (1) may direct that any person whose name is ordered to be removed 
from a register shall be ineligible for registration in the 

4[State] under this 
Act either permanently or for such period of years as may be specified.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An order under 
sub-section (1) shall not take effect until the expiry of three months from the 
date thereof.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A person aggrieved by an 
order under sub-section (1) may, within thirty days from the date thereof, 
appeal to the 

1[State] Government, 
and the order of the 

1[State] Government 
upon such appeal shall be final.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> A person whose name has 
been removed from the register under this section or under sub-section (2) of 
section 39 shall forthwith surrender his certificate of registration 

2[and certificate of renewal, if any,] to the Registrar, and 
the name so removed shall be published in the Official Gazette.
 

3[(6) A person whose name has been removed from the State 
register of dentists under this section or under sub-section (2) of section 39 
shall not be entitled to have his name registered in the register of dentists in 
any other State register of dentists except with the approval of the State 
Council from whose register his name has been removed.]










</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>42</number> Restoration to register.—The


1[State] Council may at any time, for reasons appearing to it 
sufficient and subject to the approval of the 

1[State] Government, 
order that upon payment of the prescribed fee the name of a person removed from 
a register shall be restored thereto.
 
 




</article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>43</number> Bar of jurisdiction.—No 
order refusing to enter a name in a register or removing a name from a register 
shall be called in question in any Court.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>44</number> Issue of duplicate 
certificates.—Where 
it is shown to the satisfaction of the Registrar that a certificate of 
registration 

1[or a certificate of 
renewal] has been lost or destroyed, the Registrar may, on payment of the 
prescribed fee, issue a duplicate certificate in the prescribed form.
 
 




</article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>45</number> Printing of registers.—As 
soon as may be after the 1st day of April in each year, the Registrar shall 
cause to be printed copies of the registers as they stood on the said date and 
such copies shall be made available to persons applying therefor on payment of 
the prescribed charge, and shall be evidence that on the said date the persons 
whose names are entered therein were registered dentists, registered dental 
hygienists or registered dental mechanics, as the case may be.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>46</number> Effect of registration.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any reference in any other law to a person recognised by law as a dentist shall 
be deemed to be a reference to a dentist registered under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No certificate required 
by or under any other law from a dentist shall be valid unless the person 
signing it is registered as a dentist under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> After the expiry of


1[three years] from 

2[the date appointed 
under sub-section (2) of section 32], a person who is not registered in Part A 
of the 

3[State] register of 
dentists shall not, except with the sanction of 

4[the Central 
Government or the State Government] hold any appointment as dentist in any 
dispensary, hospital or other institution 

5[***] which is 
supported wholly or partially from public or local funds:
 
Provided that the provisions 
of this sub-section shall not apply to any such person who is holding such an 
appointment 

6[immediately before 
the said date.]
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> After the expiry of two 
years from the publication of a register of dental hygienists in a 

3[State], no person whose name is not entered in that register 
shall hold appointment as dental hygienist in any dispensary, hospital or other 
institution in the 

7[State], which is 
supported wholly or partially from public or local funds.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Any person who is 
registered dentist, registered dental hygienist or registered dental mechanic in 
a 

7[State] may practise as such in any other 

7[State].
 
 










</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>46A</number> Transfer 
of registration.—Where a dentist registered in one State is practising 
dentistry in another State, he may, on payment of the prescribed fee which shall 
not exceed the renewal fee for registration in such other State, make an 
application in the prescribed form to the Council for the transfer of his name, 
from the register of the State where he is registered, to the register of the 
State in which he is practicing dentistry, and on receipt of any such 
application, the Council shall, notwithstanding anything contained elsewhere in 
this Act, direct that the name of such person be removed from the first 
mentioned register and entered in the register of the second-mentioned State and 
the State Councils concerned shall comply with such directions:
 
Provided that such a person 
shall be required to produce a certificate to the effect all dues in respect of 
his registration in the former State have been paid;
 
Provided further that where 
any such application for transfer is made by a dentist against whom any 
disciplinary proceeding is pending or where for any other reason it appears to 
the Council that the application for transfer has not been made bona fide 
and the transfer should not be made, the Council may, after giving the dentist a 
reasonable opportunity of making a representation in this behalf, reject the 
application.]
 
 




</article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>47</number> Penalty for falsely 
claiming to be registered.—If 
any person whose name is not for the time being entered in a register falsely 
represents that it is so entered, or uses in connection with his name or title 
any words or letters reasonably calculated to suggest that his name is so 
entered, he shall be punishable on first conviction with fine which may extend 
to five hundred rupees, and on any subsequent conviction with imprisonment which 
may extend to six months or with fine not exceeding one thousand rupees or with 
both.
 
 
</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>48</number> Misuse of titles. </title>—If any person— 
 <section><number>a</number> not being a person registered in a register of dentists, takes or uses, the description of dental practitioner, dental surgeon, surgeon dentist, or dentist, or 
 </section><section><number>b</number> not being a person whose name is entered on a register of dental hygienists, takes or uses in a <footcitenum>39</footcitenum> [State] where such register has been published, the title of dental hygienist, or 
 </section><section><number>c</number> not being a person whose name is entered on a register of dental mechanics, takes or uses in a <footcitenum>39</footcitenum> [State] where such register has been published, the title of dental mechanic, <footcitenum>40</footcitenum> [or] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>41</footcitenum> [<number>d</number> not possessing a recognised dental qualification, uses a degree or a diploma or an abbreviation indicating or implying a dental qualification]. 
 he shall be punishable on first conviction with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, and on any subsequent conviction with imprisonment which may extend to six months or with fine not exceeding one thousand rupees or with both. 
  




</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>49</number> Practice by unregistered 
persons.—
<section><number>1</number> After 
the expiry of 

1[three years] from


2[the date appointed under sub-section (2) of section 32] in 
the case of dentists, and in the 

3[States] where a 
register of dental hygienists or dental mechanics has been prepared under 
section 36 from such date as may be specified in this behalf by the 

4[State] Government by notification in the Official Gazette, in 
the case of dental hygienists or dental mechanics, no person, other than a 
registered dentist, registered dental hygienist or registered dental mechanic, 
shall practice dentistry or the art of scaling, cleaning or polishing teeth, or 
of making or repairing dentures and dental appliances, as the case may be, or 
indicate in any way that he is prepared to so practise:
 
Provided that the provisions 
of this section shall not apply to—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  practice of dentistry by a 
registered medical practitioner;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the extraction of a tooth by any 
person when the case is urgent and no registered dentist is available so, 
however, that the operation is performed without the use of any general or local 
anaesthetic;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  the performance of dental work or 
radiographic work in any hospital or dispensary maintained or supported from 
public or local funds.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If any person contravenes 
the provisions of sub-section (1), he shall be punishable on first conviction 
with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, and on any subsequent 
conviction with imprisonment which may extend to six months or with fine not 
exceeding one thousand rupees or with both.
 
 







</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>50</number> Failure to surrender 
certificate of registration.—If any person whose name has been removed from a register 
fails without sufficient cause forthwith to surrender his certificate of 
registration 

1[or certificate of 
renewal, or both] he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to fifty 
rupees per month of such failure and in the case of a continuing offence with an 
additional fine which may extend to two rupees per day after the first day 
during which the offence continues.
 
 




</article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>51</number> Companies not to engage 
in dentistry.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Except as hereinafter provided, the profession of dentistry shall not be carried 
on by a company or other corporate body.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The provisions of 
sub-section (1) shall not apply to—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  a company or other corporate body 
which carries on no business other than the profession of dentistry or some 
business ancillary to the profession of dentistry and of which the majority of 
the directors and all the operating staff are registered dentists;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the carrying on the profession of 
dentistry by employers who provide dental treatment for their employees by 
registered dentists otherwise than for profit;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  the carrying on of the profession 
of dentistry by any hospital or dispensary or institution for the training of 
dentists or dental hygienists or by any local authority or other body authorised 
or required by law to provide dental treatment:
 
Provided that any company or 
other corporate body carrying on the profession of dentistry 

1[immediately before the date appointed under sub-section (2) 
of section 32] may continue so to do until the expiry of three years from such 
date.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> If any person contravenes 
the provisions of sub-section (1), he shall be punishable with fine which may 
extend, on first conviction to five hundred rupees, or on any subsequent 
conviction with imprisonment which may extend to six months or with fine not 
exceeding one thousand rupees or with both.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>52</number> Cognizance of offences.—No 
Court shall take cognizance of any offence punishable under this Act except upon 
complaint made by order of the 

1[State] Government or the 

1[State] Council.
 
 




</article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>53</number> Payment of part of fees 
to Council.—The


1[State] Council shall before the end of June in each year pay 
to the Council a sum equivalent to one-fourth of the total fees realised by the


1[State] Council under 
this Act during the period of twelve months ending on the 31st day of March of 
that year.
 
 




</article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>53A</number> Accounts 
and audit.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
Council shall maintain appropriate accounts and other relevant records and 
prepare an annual statement of accounts including the balance-sheet, in 
accordance with such general directions as may be issued and in such form as may 
be specified by the Central Government in consultation with the Comptroller and 
Auditor-General of India.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The accounts of the 
Council shall be audited annually by the Comptroller and Auditor-General of 
India or any person appointed by him in this behalf and any expenditure incurred 
by him or any person so appointed in connection with such audit shall be payable 
by the Council to the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Comptroller and 
Auditor-General of India and any person appointed by him in connec­tion with the 
audit of the accounts of the Council shall have the same rights and privileges 
and authority in connection with such audit as the Comptroller and 
Auditor-General of India has in connection with the audit of Government 
accounts, and in particular, shall have the right to demand the production of 
books of accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papery and to 
inspect the office of the Council.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The accounts of the 
Council as certified by the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India or any 
person appointed by him in this behalf, together with the audit report thereon, 
shall be forwarded annually to the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> A copy of the accounts of 
the Council as so certified together with the audit report thereon shall be 
forwarded simultaneously to the Council.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 
THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948
 
 
 <article>
<number>54</number> Appointment of Commission 
of Enquiry.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Whenever it appears to the Central Government that the Council is not complying 
with any of the provisions of this Act, the Central Government may appoint a 
Commission of Enquiry consisting of three persons, two of whom shall be 
appointed by the Central Government, one being the Judge of a High Court, and 
one by the Council; and refer to it the matters on which the enquiry is to be 
made.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Commission shall 
proceed to enquire in a summary manner and report to the Central Government on 
the matters referred to it together with such remedies, if any, as the 
Commission may like to recommend.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Central Government 
may accept the report or remit the same to the Commission for modification or 
reconsideration.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> After the report is 
finally accepted, the Central Government may order the Council to adopt the 
remedies so recommended within such time as may be specified in the order and if 
the Council fails to comply within the time so specified, the Central Government 
may pass such order or take such action as may be necessary to give effect to 
the recommendations of the Commission.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Whenever it appears to 
the 

1[State] Government that the 

1[State] Council is 
not complying with any of the provisions of this Act, the 

1[State] Government may likewise appoint a similar Commission 
of Enquiry in respect of the 

1[State] Council to 
make enquiry in like manner and pass such order or take such action as specified 
in sub-sections (3) and (4).
 
 




</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>55</number> Power to make rules. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The <footcitenum>51</footcitenum> [State] Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the purposes of Chapters III, IV and V. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for— 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the management of the property of the <footcitenum>51</footcitenum> [State] Council, and the maintenance and audit of its accounts; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the manner in which elections under Chapter III shall be conducted; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the summoning and holding of meetings of the <footcitenum>51</footcitenum> [State] Council, the times and places at which such meetings shall be held, the conduct of business thereat and the number of members necessary to form a quorum; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> the powers and duties of the President and Vice-President of the <footcitenum>51</footcitenum> [State] Council; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> the constitution and functions of the Executive Committee, the summoning and holding of meetings thereof, the times and places at which such meetings shall be held, the number of members necessary to constitute a quorum; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> the term of office and the powers and duties of the Registrar and other officers and servants of the <footcitenum>51</footcitenum> [State] Council, including the amount and nature of the security to be given by the Treasurer. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> the particulars to be stated, and the proof of qualifications to be given in applications for registration under this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>52</footcitenum> [<number>gg</number> the form of application for transfer of registration from one State to another;] 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>53</footcitenum> [<number>h</number> the charge for supplying printed copies of the registers, and the fees payable for— 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> registration or renewal of registration; 
 <subsubsection><number>ii</number> supplying a duplicate certificate of registration or renewal; and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number> transfer of registration from one State to another; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>i</number> the forms of certificates of registration and renewal;] 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>j</number> any other matter which is to be or may be prescribed under  
  Chapters III, IV and V except sub-sections (1), (2), (3) and (4) of section 54. 
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section><footcitenum>54</footcitenum> [<number>3</number> Every rule made by the State Government under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before the State Legislature.] 





</section></article><form>
 

THE DENTISTS ACT, 1948 
 

 
 

THE SCHEDULE 
 

PART I 
 

[ See  sub-sections (1) and (2) of section 10] 
 

RECOGNISED DENTAL QUALIFICATIONS GRANTED BY  

  THE AUTHORITIES OR INSTITUTIONS IN INDIA 
 

 
 

PART II 
 

[See sub-section (3) of section 10] 
 

RECOGNISED DENTAL QUALIFICATIONS FOR  

  THE PURPOSES OF REGISTRATION WHEN  

  THE REGISTER IS FIRST PREPARED 
 

 
 

PART III 
 

[See sub-section (4) of section 10] 
 

RECOGNISED DENTAL QUALIFICATIONS GRANTED BY  

  AUTHORITIES OR INSTITUTIONS OUTSIDE INDIA ONLY  

  WHEN GRANTED TO A CITIZEN OF INDIA 
 

 
 

Ed. —For details please contact the Dental Council of India, New Delhi 
 

www.dciindia.org 
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>  Ins. by Act 30 of 1993, sec. 2 (w.r.e.f. 
27-8-1992).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>  Ins. by Act 30 of 1993, sec. 2 (w.r.e.f. 
27-8-1992).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>  Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for “Province”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>  Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for “Province”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>  Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for “Province”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>  Subs. by Act 12 of 1955, sec. 6, for 
“may appoint”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>  Ins. by Act 42 of 1972, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 
1-11-1972).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>  The words “dental or” omitted by Act 42 
of 1972, sec. 10 (w.e.f. 1-11-1972).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>  Ins. by Act 42 of 1972, sec. 11 (w.e.f. 
1-11-1972).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>  The word and figures “section 10” 
omitted by Act 42 of 1972, sec. 12 (w.e.f. 1-11-1972).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>  Ins. by Act 42 of 1972, sec. 13 (w.e.f. 
1-11-1972).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>  Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for 
“Provincial”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>  Ins. by Act 4 of 1986, sec. 2 and Sch. 
(w.e.f. 15-5-1986).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>  Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for 
“Provincial”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>  Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for 
“Provincial”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>  Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for 
“Provincial”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number>  Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for 
“Provincial”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number>  Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for 
“Provincial”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number>  Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for 
“Provincial”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number>  Added by Act 42 of 1972, sec. 17 (w.e.f. 
1-11-1972).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number>  Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for 
“Provincial”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number>  Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for 
“Provincial”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number>  Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for 
“Provincial”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number>  Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for 
“Provincial”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number>Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for “Provincial”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number>  Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for “Province”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number>  Section 34 renumbered as sub-section 
(1) thereof by Act, 12 of 1955, sec. 10.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>28</number>  Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for 
“Provincial”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>29</number>  Ins. by the Madras Adaptation of Laws 
Order, 1954.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>30</number>  Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for 
“Provincial”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>31</number>  Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for “Province”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>32</number>  Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for 
“Provincial”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>33</number>  Ins. by Act 12 of 1955, sec. 11.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>34</number>  Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for 
“Provincial”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>35</number>  Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for 
“Provincial”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>36</number>  Ins. by Act 42 of 1972, sec. 23 (w.e.f. 
1-11-1972).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>37</number>  Subs. by Act 58 of 1950, sec. 3, for 
“two years”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>38</number>  Ins. by Act 42 of 1972, sec. 24 (w.e.f. 
1-11-1972).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>39</number>Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for “Province”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>40</number>Ins. by Act 12 of 1955, sec. 14 (w.e.f. 15-4-1955).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>41</number>Ins. by Act 12 of 1955, sec. 14 (w.e.f. 15-4-1955).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>42</number>  Subs. by Act 58 of 1950, sec. 3 for 
“two years” (restrospectively).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>43</number>  Subs. by Act 12 of 1955, sec. 15, for 
the “the commencement of this Act”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>44</number>  Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for 
“Provinces”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>45</number>  Ins. by Act 42 of 1972, sec. 25 (w.e.f. 
1-11-1972).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>46</number>  Subs. by Act 12 of 1955, sec. 16, for 
“at the date of the commencement of the Act”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>47</number>  Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for 
“Provincial”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>48</number>  Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for 
“Provincial”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>49</number>  Ins. by Act 42 of 1972, sec. 26 (w.e.f. 
1-11-1972).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>50</number>  Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for 
“Provincial”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>51</number> Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for “Provincial”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>52</number> Ins. by Act 42 of 1972, sec. 27(a) (w.e.f. 1-11-1972).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>53</number> Subs. by Act 42 of 1972, sec. 27(b), for “clauses (h) and (i)” (w.e.f. 1-11-1972).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>54</number>Ins. by Act 4 of 1986, sec. 2. Sch. (w.e.f. 15-5-1986).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>