<act><title>


 The 
    Collection of Statistics 
    (Central) Rules, 19591</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Title.—These 
    rules may be called the Collection of Statistics (Central) Rules, 1959.
 



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>1</number>  ‘Act’ means the 
    Collection of Statistics Act, 1953 (32 of 1953);  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>  ‘notice’ means the 
    notice referred to in rule 3;  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>  ‘plantation’ means a 
    commercial concern referred to in sub-clause (ix) of clause (b) of section 2 
    of the Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number>  ‘statistics 
    authority’ means the officer appointed by the Central Government to be the 
    statistics authority under section 4 of the Act; and   
 </section><section>
<number>5</number>  ‘survey year’ means—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>  in relation to the 
    collection of statistics relating to a factory engaged in the sugar 
    industry, the twelve calendar months commencing from the 1st July of a year 
    and ending with the 30th June of the succeeding year;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>b</number>  
    in any other case, the accounting year of the factory ending on any date 
    between 1st April of the year in respect of which the statistics are being 
    collected and the 31st March of the preceding year.]  
  
  





 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Service of notice.—1[1] 
    For the purpose of the collection of statistics under these rules, the 
    statistics authority shall serve upon the owner of any factory, industrial 
    concern or plantation, a notice requiring the owner to furnish the 
    statistics authority with 

    2[***]—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>  one or more returns 
    in such manner and containing such particulars as may be specified in the 
    notice;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>  if the factory, 
    industrial concern or plantation is owned by a company as defined by the 
    Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), a copy of the annual balance sheet and 
    profit and loss account and of the Director’s report, if any, for the survey 
    year, or if the company’s accounting year does not correspond to the survey 
    year, then for the accounting year which corresponds as nearly as possible 
    to the survey year, for which the accounts have been closed:  
 

    Provided that it shall be lawful for the statistics authority to require the 
    owner to furnish more than one copy of a return or other document or 
    different returns or documents on different dates, or in respect of 
    different parts of the activities of the factory, industrial concern or 
    plantation.  
 


    3[(2) The return of 
    other document referred to in sub-rule (1) shall be furnished before a date 
    to be specified in the notice which date shall be—  
 </section><section>
<number>a</number>  in the case of an 
    annual return or other document, not earlier than three calender months;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>  in any other case, 
    not earlier than one calendar month, after the end of the period to which 
    the return or other document relates.]  
 








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Particulars to be furnished.—The 
    returns which the owner may be required to furnish under the notice shall 
    contain all or any of the following particulars, as indicated in the notice, 
    namely:—  
 <section>
<number>1</number>  Identification 
    particulars,   
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>  nature of 
    ownership and management,   
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>  value of and 
    expenditure on different components of fixed capital,   
 </section><section>
<number>4</number>  value of and 
    transactions on different components of working capital,   
 </section><section>
<number>5</number>  details of 
    employment including number of persons employed, man-hours worked and 
    payments made for different categories of employees,   
 </section><section>
<number>6</number>  value of 
    privileges or benefits accruing to different categories of employees, 
 
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> number and power of 
    different kinds of prime movers separately and for different types of motive 
    force,   
 </section><section>
<number>8</number>  number and 
    strength of motors,   
 </section><section>
<number>9</number>  installed 
    capacity,   
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> details of 
    consumption of fuel, electricity and lubricants and their quantity and 
    value,   
 </section><section>
<number>11</number> other materials, and 
    services consumed including raw materials, chemicals, packing materials and 
    stores and services purchased,   
 </section><section>
<number>12</number> value and quantity 
    of products meant for sale, including amount received for work done by the 
    factory for other concerns,   
 </section><section>
<number>13</number> sales to different 
    types of customers,   
 </section><section>
<number>14</number> stocks of fuels, 
    materials and products   
 </section><section>
<number>15</number> inventory of 
    equipment other than power equipment,   
 </section><section>
<number>16</number>  present age, 
    condition and service life of buildings, plant and machinery, and   
 </section><section>
<number>17</number>  any other 
    particulars on which information may be supplied at the discretion of the 
    owner.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Objections.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If the returns and other documents required from the owner cannot be 
    furnished by him in the manner in which or the period for which the notice 
    requires him to furnish, by reason of their not being capable of being 
    compiled from his accounts or other records or for any other reasonable 
    cause, he shall supply them in such manner and for such periods which 
    correspond as nearly as possible to the manner and period referred to in the 
    notice and shall apply to the statistics authority in writing within the 
    period allowed in the notice to treat such compliance as full compliance 
    with the notice.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where the statistics authority rejects an application made under sub-rule 
    (1), the time within which the owner is required by the notice to submit the 
    returns and other documents shall be deemed to have been extended by a 
    period equal to the interval between the date of the application and the 
    date of receipt by the owner, of the statistics authority’s order rejecting 
    the application.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Alteration of returns and extension of time.—On 
    an application by the owner or otherwise, it shall be competent for the 
    statistics authority to issue orders adding to or otherwise varying the 
    heads under which the owner has been required to furnish the returns and 
    other documents in any manner in which he has been asked to furnish in the 
    original notice and the owner shall thereupon be required to furnish such 
    revised returns and documents as if he had been required to furnish them in 
    the original notice:  
 

    Provided that where the order has been made otherwise than on the 
    application of the owner, the time limit for the submission of the revised 
    returns and other documents shall be deemed to have been extended to 

    1[three months or as 
    the case may be, one month] from the date of receipt of such order by the 
    owner:  
 

    Provided further that the statistics authority may extend the time limit 
    mentioned in the notice, in his discretion, in any other case also.  
  






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Interruption of ownership or working.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If at any time during the period in respect of which the returns or other 
    documents are called for in the notice, the owner ceases to be the owner, he 
    shall furnish to the statistics authority, the returns and documents in 
    respect of that part of the period for which he was the owner.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    a factory, an industrial concern or a plantation discontinues to function 
    during the period in respect of which returns and other documents relating 
    to it have been called for, the owner shall furnish to the statistics 
    authority the returns and other documents for the period up to the date on 
    which the factory, industrial concern or plantation discontinued to 
    function.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Mode of service of notice.—Any 
    notice or order required to be served on the owner under these rules may be 
    served by transmission through the post under registered cover with 
    acknowledgement due, or through a person authorised by the statistics 
    authority to serve such notice by delivering it at the place of business of 
    the owner and obtaining an acknowledgement for it.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Language in which information should be furnished.—All 
    information required to be furnished under these rules shall be furnished in 
    English or in such other language or languages as the Central Government may 
    by order specify.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Opportunity to show cause before sanction of prosecution.—The 
    statistics authority shall before sanctioning a prosecution under section 
    11, give a reasonable opportunity to the person to show cause why such 
    prosecution may not be sanctioned.   


 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>      Subs. by S.O. 
    2667, dated the 1st August, 1967.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>      Rule 3 re-numbered 
    as sub-rule (1) thereof by S.O. 1309, dated 26th April, 1962.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   Subs. by S.O. 1309, dated 26th April, 1962.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>