<act><title>THE TELECOMMUNICATION INTERCONNECTION USAGE CHARGES REGULATION, 20031</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title, extent and commencement. </title>-
<section><number>i</number> This Regulation shall be called the Telecommunication Interconnection Usage Charges Regulation 2003 (the Regulation) and supercedes the earlier Regulation dated 24th January, 2003 (1 of 2003) and its amendments dated 27th March, 2003 (1st amendment) and 16th June, 2003 (2nd amendment). 
 
 


</section><section><number>ii</number> The Regulation shall cover arrangements among service providers 
    for payment of Interconnection Usage Charges, for Telecommunication  
  Services, covering Basic Service that includes WLL(M) services, Cellular Mobile Services, and Long Distance Services (STD/ ISD) throughout the territory of India. 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> The Regulation shall be deemed to have come into force from the date of its notification in the Official Gazette. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>-In this Regulation, unless the context otherwise requires,- 
 
 <section><number>i</number> "Act" means the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India Act, 1997 as amended by TRAI (Amendment) Act, 2000. 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> "ADC" means Access Deficit Charge. 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> "Authority" means the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>iv</number> "BSO, CMSP, ILDO and NLDO and UASP" respectively mean the Basic Service Operator, Cellular Mobile Service Provider, International Long Distance Operator and National Long Distance Operator and Unified Access Service Provider.] 
 </section><section><number>v</number> "Ceiling(s)" mean(s) the upper limit(s) of a charge specified by the Authority from time to time over which such charges may not be offered. 
 </section><section><number>vi</number> "Floor" means the lower limit of a charge specified by the Authority from time to time below which such charges may not be offered. 
 </section><section><number>vii</number> "Forbearance" means that the Authority has not, for the time being, notified any charge for a particular telecommunication service and the service provider is free to fix any charge for such service. The Authority, however, has a right to intervene at any stage after the introduction of the charge. 
 </section><section><number>viii</number> "Interconnection" means the commercial and technical arrangements under which service providers connect their equipment, networks and services to enable their customers to have access to the customers services and networks of other service providers. 
 </section><section><number>ix</number> "Interconnection Charge" means the charge for interconnection levied by an interconnection provider on an interconnection seeker. 
 </section><section><number>x</number> "Interconnection Usage Charge (IUC)" means the charge payable by one service provider to one or more service providers for usage of the network elements for origination, transit or termination of the calls. 
 </section><section><number>xi</number> "Interconnection Provider" means the service provider to whose network an interconnection is sought for providing telecommunication services. 
 <subsection><number>xii</number> "Interconnection Seeker" means the service provider who seeks interconnection to the network of the interconnection provider. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>xiii</number> "International Subscriber Dialing" (ISD) means the facility by which a subscriber can have direct connection between him (in India ) with another end user in another country by means of direct dialing through licensed networks. This includes the coverage of the international sector by ILDO and the related national sector by NLDO and/or access provider. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>xiv</number> "LDCA/ LDCC" respectively mean Long Distance Charging Area/ Long Distance Charging Centre. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>xv</number> "Order" means the Telecommunication Tariff Order, 1999 as amended from time to time. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>xvi</number> "Originating Network" means the network to which an originator of a telecommunication message (voice and non-voice) is proximately connected to. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>xvii</number> "Originating/ Transit/ Terminating Service Provider" means the service provider whose network is used for originating/ transit/ terminating a telecommunication message (voice and non-voice) respectively. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>xviii</number> "Regulation" means The Telecommunication Interconnection Usage Charges (IUC) Regulation 2003 (2 of 2003). 
 </subsection><subsection><number>xix</number> "Reporting Requirement" means the obligation of a service provider to report to the Authority at least 45 working days before implementing any new Interconnection Usage Charge for telecommunication services under 'this Regulation' and any changes thereafter. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>xx</number> "SDCA/SDCC" respectively mean Short Distance Charging Area/ Short Distance Charging Centre. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>xxi</number> "Set Up Costs of Interconnection" means the initial cost of any system up-gradation needed to provide the specific interconnection facilities requested. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>xxii</number> "Settlement Period" is the period at the end of which the inter-carrier billing IUC/ADC payments among service providers are to be settled, based on the record reconciliation process as may be finalized through mutual arrangements among the service providers. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>xxiii</number> "Significant Market Power (SMP)" means "A Service Provider holding a share of at least 30% of total activity in a licensed telecommunication service area. These Services are categorized as Basic Service, Cellular Mobile Service, National Long Distance Service and International Long Distance Service." Where "Activity" would mean and include any one or more of the following: 
 
 
 </subsection><subsection><number>a</number> Subscriber Base 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> Turnover 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> Switching Capacity 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> Volume of Traffic 
</subsection><subsection><number>xxiv</number> "Subscriber Trunk Dialing" (STD) means the facility by which a subscriber can have direct connection between him and another end user in another SDCA within India by means of direct dialing through the public long distance networks. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>xxv</number> "Terminating Network" means the network to which a receiver of a telecommunication message (voice and non-voice) is proximately connected to. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>xxvi</number> "Transit Network" means the network through which telecommunication messages (voice or non-voice) from originating networks or other transit networks are transmitted and delivered to terminating or other transit networks. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>xxvii</number> "Usage Charge" means the charge levied by a service provider for carriage of telecommunication traffic on its network, i.e . for use of its network elements. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>xxviii</number> "WLL (M)" means limited mobility telephony service using wireless in local loop technology within a Short Distance Charging Area. 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>xxix</number> "Roaming" means the ability for a cellular subscriber to automatically make and receive voice calls, data and to access other services while travelling outside the geographical coverage area of the home network, by using the visited network. It is national roaming when visited network and the home network of the subscriber are in the same country and it is international roaming when visited network and home network of the subscriber are in different countries.] 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>xxx</number> Words and expressions used in this Regulation and not defined herein but defined in the Act shall have the same meanings assigned to them in the Act. 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>xxx</number> "Cellular" means fully mobile service provided by CMSPs and UASPs through GSM, CDMA or any other Technology.] 
</subsection></section>







</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Interconnection Charges. </title>-Interconnection Charges shall continue to be governed by "The Telecommunication Interconnection (Charges and Revenue Sharing) Regulation, 2001 (5 of 2001)" and The Telecommunication Interconnection (Port Charges) Regulation, 2001 (6 of 2001), except to the extent modified by this Regulation. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Interconnection Usage Charges (IUC). </title>-The Interconnection Usage Charges are specified in Schedules hereto. 
 Schedule I-Termination Charges 
 Schedule II-Carriage Charges 
 Schedule III-Access Deficit Charge (ADC) 
 <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[Schedule IV-Interconnect Usage Charge (IUC) for Short Message Service (SMS)]. 
 
 <section><number>i</number> Unless specifically provided in the Schedules to this Regulation, the Authority forbears with respect to other Interconnection Usage Charges. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<number>ii</number> The date of effect for actual implementation of IUC shall be 1st February, 2004.] 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> The existing Interconnection Usage Charges arrangement between the Interconnecting networks in respect of the items as specified in this Regulation shall hold good till the date on which this Regulation comes in force. 
 </section><section><number>iv</number> All existing interconnect agreements/arrangements as on date shall stand amended on the date of actual implementation of this Regulation so as to conform to the present framework of the IUC regime and these shall be submitted to TRAI for registration within 15 days of implementation of this Regulation, and for subsequent changes as per Reporting Requirement. 
 </section><section><number>v</number> IUC values specified in 'the Regulation' shall also be applicable for all Reference Interconnect Offers by Significant Market Powers (SMPs). 
</section>




</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Reporting Requirement. </title>-
<section><number>i</number> All service providers shall comply with the Reporting Requirement as defined in Section II in respect of Interconnection Usage Charges specified for the first time under 'the Regulation', as also all subsequent changes, subject to the provisions of Section IV above. 
 
 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> No service provider shall alter any Interconnection Usage Charge or any part thereof, without complying with the Reporting Requirement. 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> In respect of matters covered by the provisions of 'the Regulation', they shall have an overriding effect over any Regulation, Direction, Determination and Order of the Authority, Reference Interconnect Offer and existing Interconnect agreement/arrangement between Service Providers. 
</section><section><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>iv</number> Each service provider shall report to the Authority on quarterly basis, the ADC retained by it, wherever applicable, and also ADC paid by it to BSNL. In addition, BSNL shall report, on quarterly basis, ADC payments received by it from each operator. This shall include both the components of ADC, namely ADC paid in the form of percentage of Adjusted Gross Revenue and ADC on per minute basis for international incoming <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[***] calls. The quarterly report shall reach the Authority within 30 days of the end of the previous quarter:] 
 <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[Provided that the provisions of this clause shall, on and after the 1st day of April, 2008, have effect as if the words "ADC paid in the form of percentage of Adjusted Gross Revenue" had been omitted and the provisions in this clause relating to reporting requirement after the said date shall be construed accordingly: 
 Provided further that nothing contained in this clause shall apply on and after the 1st day of April, 2008.] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[<number>v</number> Reporting Requirement for carriage charges for long distance calls within India specified under paragraph (a) of Schedule II. -Every National Long Distance Operator shall, on quarterly basis, report to the Authority the per minute rate of carriage charge and the total amount of such carriage charge for long distance calls within India received by it from every BSO/CMSP/UASL/ ILDO, separately, and every BSO/CMSP/UASL/ILDO shall, on quarterly basis, report to the Authority, the per minute carriage charges for long distance calls within India and the total amount of such carriage charge for long distance calls within India paid by them to every National Long Distance Operator, separately, and such quarterly report shall be submitted to the Authority within thirty days of the end of the previous quarter.] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[<number>vi</number> Reporting Requirement of Interconnection Usage Charge for Short Message Service (SMS) specified under Paragraph (1) of Schedule IV. -Every BSO/CMSP/UASL/NLDO/ILDO shall, on quarterly basis, report to the Authority, the rate of Interconnect Usage Charge for SMS and the total amount of such Interconnect Usage Charge for SMS received by it from other BSO/ CMSP/UASL/NLDO/ILDO and paid by it to other BSO/CMSP/UASL/NLDO/ ILDO, separately, and such quarterly report shall be submitted to the Authority within thirty days of the end of the previous quarter.] 






</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Review. </title>- <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[
<section><number>i</number> The Authority may, from time to time, review and modify interconnection Usage Charge and Access Deficit Charge. 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> The Authority may also at any time, suo motu, or on the basis of reported information in terms of clause (iv) of Regulation (5) above or on reference from any affected party, and for good and sufficient reasons, review and modify any interconnection Usage Charge and Access Deficit Charge.] 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Explanatory Memorandum. </title>-This Regulation contains at Annex A, an explanatory memorandum to provide clarity and transparency to matters covered under 'the Regulation'. 



</article> 

  
 <title>SCHEDULE I </title>
 <article><title><number>8</number> Interpretation. </title>- <title><footcitenum>12</footcitenum></title>[In case of any doubt regarding any provision of this Regulation, the clarification given by the Authority shall be final.] 



</article><form>
 

THE TELECOMMUNICATION INTERCONNECTION USAGE CHARGES REGULATION, 20031
 

 
 

SCHEDULE I 
 

2[1. Termination Charges. -Termination charge for Local and National Long Distance voice calls to Fixed Wireline, Wireless in Local Loop (Fixed), Wireless in Local Loop (Mobile), Cellular Mobile Telephone Service (both 2G and 3G) shall be uniform at the rate of Re 0.20 (twenty paise only) per minute and the termination charge for incoming International Long Distance voice calls to such Fixed Wireline, Wireless in Local Loop (Fixed), Wireless in Local Loop (Mobile), Cellular Mobile Telephone Service (both 2G and 3G) shall be uniform at the rate of Re 0.40 (forty paise only) per minute.] 
 

2. Origination Charges 
 

Forbearance. 
 

The Originating Service Provider shall retain origination charges from the residual after payment of the charges for carriage, termination and access deficit. 
 

3. Carriage Charges 
 

Carriage charges have been specified in Schedule II. 
 

4. Access Deficit Charges 
 

Access Deficit Charge (ADC) has been specified in Schedule III. 
 

 -------- 
 

1. Vide Notification No. 409-5/2003-FN, dated 29th October, 2003. 
 

2. Subs. by Notification No. 409-8/2004-FN., dated 6th January, 2005 (w.e.f. 1-2-2005).
</form><form>
 

THE TELECOMMUNICATION INTERCONNECTION USAGE CHARGES REGULATION, 20031
 

 
 

2[SCHEDULE IV 
 

INTERCONNECT USAGE CHARGE (IUC) FOR SHORT MESSAGE SERVICE (SMS) 
 

Interconnect Usage Charge (IUC) for Short Message Service (SMS).-Interconnect Usage Charge (IUC) for Short Message Service (SMS) shall be under forbearance: 
 

Provided that such charges shall be transparent, reciprocal and non-discriminatory.] 
 

 -------- 
 

1. Vide Notification No. 409-5/2003-FN, dated 29th October, 2003. 
 

2. Ins. by Notification No. F. No. 409-12/2008-FN., dated 9th March, 2009 (w.e.f. 1-4-2009).
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by Notification No. F. No. 409-5/2003-(FN), dated 31st December, 2003, for clause (iv) (w.e.f. 7-1-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Ins. by Notification No. 409-8/2004-FN, dated 11th April, 2005.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Entry "(xxix)" renumbered as "(xxx)" by Notification No. 409-8/2004-FN, dated 11th April, 2005.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Ins. by Notification No. F. No. 409-5/2003-(FN), dated 31st December, 2003 (w.e.f. 7-1-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Ins. by Notification No. F. No. 409-12/2008-FN., dated 9th March, 2009 (w.e.f. 1-4-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Subs. by Notification No. 409-5/2003-FN, dated 31st December, 2003, for (ii) (w.e.f. 7-1-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Ins. by Notification No. 409-5/2005-FN, dated 23rd February, 2006 (w.e.f. 1-3-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> The words "and outgoing" omitted by Notification No. 409-2/2007-FN., dated 21st March, 2007 (w.e.f. 1-4-2007).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> Ins. by Notification No. F. No. 409-22/2007-F.N., dated 27th March, 2008 (w.e.f. 1-4-2008).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> Ins. by Notification No. F. No. 409-12/2008-FN., dated 9th March, 2009 (w.e.f. 1-4-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number> Subs. by Notification No. 409-5/2005-FN., dated 23rd February, 2006 (w.e.f. 1-3-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number> Subs. by Notification No. 409-8/2004-FN., dated 6th January, 2005 (w.e.f. 1-2-2005).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>