<act><title>

The 
    Telegraph Wires (Unlawful Possession) Act, 1950</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Telegraph Wires (Unlawful Possession) Act, 1950.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends 
    to the whole of India.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It 
    shall come into force in any State on such date1 as 
    the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint 
    for such State, and different dates may be appointed for different States.  
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In this Act,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “prescribed” means prescribed by rules 
    made under this Act;  
 

1[(b)    
    “telegraph wire” means any copper wire the diameter of which, in millimetres, 
    is—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    not less than 2.43 and not more than 
    2.53; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    not less than 2.77 and not more than 
    2.87; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    not less than 3.42 and not more than 
    3.52].  
 
 





 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Duty to 
    declare possession of telegraph wires.—Every 
    person in possession of telegraph wires shall, within six months from the 
    commencement of this Act, make a declaration in writing, in such form and to 
    such authority as may be prescribed stating the quantity of telegraph wires 
    in his possession.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Duty to 
    have telegraph wires converted or sold.—Every 
    person in possession of telegraph wires which exceed ten pounds in weight 
    shall, within one year from the commencement of this Act, have the whole of 
    the quantity as is in excess of ten pounds converted into ingots:  
 
Provided that 
    it shall be open to any such person to sell the whole or any part of the 
    telegraph wires in his possession at such price and to such authority as may 
    be prescribed.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>4A</number> Prohibition of 
    sale or purchase of telegraph wires.—No 
    person shall, after the commencement of the Telegraph Wires (Unlawful 
    Possession) Amendment Act, 1953 (53 of 1953), sell or purchase any quantity 
    of telegraph wires except with the permission of such authority as may be 
    prescribed.] 
 
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>5</number> Penalty for 
    unlawful possession of telegraph wires.—Whoever 
    is found or is proved to have been in possession of any quantity of 
    telegraph wires shall, unless he proves that the telegraph wires came into 
    his possession lawfully, be punishable,— 
 

2[
<section><number>a</number>    
    for the first offence, with imprisonment for a term which may extend to five 
    years, or with fine, or with both, and, in the absence of special and 
    adequate reasons to be recorded in the judgment of the Court, the term of 
    such imprisonment shall not be less than one year and such fine shall not be 
    less than one thousand rupees;]  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    for the second or a subsequent 
    offence, with imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years and 
    also with fine and in the absence of special and adequate reasons 
3[to 
    be recorded in the judgment of the court, the term of such imprisonment] 
    shall not be less than two years and such fine shall not be less than two 
    thousand rupees:  
 
Provided that where a person has made a 
    declaration under section 3 in relation to any quantity of telegraph wires, 
    the burden of proving, in respect of the quantity so declared, that it came 
    into his possession lawfully, shall not be on such person.]
 
 

 
 

 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Penalty for contravention of provisions of section 3, section 4 or section 
    4A.—Any 
    person who fails to make a declaration as required by section 3 or 


    1[contravenes the 
    provisions of section 4 or section 4A] shall be punishable with imprisonment 
    for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine, or with both.
 








 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>6A</number> Powers of search 
    and seizure.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A police officer not below the rank of a sub-inspector may seize, or search 
    any place and seize.—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    any telegraph wire; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    any conveyance or animal used for the 
    transport of such telegraph wire, 
 
if a reasonable suspicion exists that any 
    provision of this Act has been, or is being, or is about to be, contravened 
    in respect of such telegraph wire.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), relating to 
    searches and seizures shall, so far as may be, apply to searches and 
    seizures made under this section. 
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>6B</number> 
    Confiscation of telegraph wires, conveyances, etc.—Where 
    any person has been convicted for the contravention of any of the provisions 
    of this Act, the telegraph wires in relation to which the contravention has 
    been made, and any conveyance or animal used for the transport of such 
    telegraph wires, shall be liable to confiscation by the Court unless the 
    owner of the conveyance or animal proves that it was so used without the 
    knowledge or connivance of the owner himself, his agent, if any, and the 
    person in charge of the conveyance or animal and that each of them had taken 
    all reasonable precautions against such use:
 
Provided that 
    where any such conveyance or animal is used for the transport of goods or 
    passengers for hire, the owner of the conveyance or animal shall be given an 
    option to pay in lieu of the confiscation of the conveyance or animal, a 
    fine, not exceeding the market price of the conveyance or animal on the date 
    of seizure thereof or the value of the telegraph wires in relation to which 
    the contravention has been made, whichever is less:  
 
Provided 
    further that any telegraph wires, so seized and confiscated shall be handed 
    over by the court to such authority as may be specified by the Central 
    Government.]  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Cognizance of offences.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    No court shall take cognizance of any offence punishable under this Act 
    except on a report in writing of the facts constituting such offence made by 
    a person who is a public servant within the meaning of section 21 of the 
    Indian Penal Code (Act 45 of 1860).]  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No court 
    inferior to that of a presidency magistrate or a magistrate of the first 
    class shall try any offence punishable under this Act.  
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Power to 
    make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
    Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry 
    out the purposes of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the form in which, and the authorities 
    to which, declarations under section 3 may be made;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the authorities to which, and the 
    prices at which, telegraph wires may be sold under section 4.  
 


    1[(3) Every rule made 
    under this section shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made before 
    each House of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty 
    days which may be comprised in one session 

    2[or in two or more 
    successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
    following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid], both Houses 
    agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the 
    rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
    modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
    such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of 
    anything previously done under that rule.]  
 
 
 
 






 



</subsection></section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Ins. by Act 44 of 
    1975, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 7-8-1975).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Subs. by Act 44 
    of 1975, sec. 5, for sub-section (1) (w.e.f. 7-8-1975).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   Ins. by Act 15 
    of 1962, sec. 3.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>