<act><tid>98489</tid>
<title>THE INDIAN IRON AND STEEL COMPANY (TAKING OVER OF MANAGEMENT) 
ACT, <year>1972</year></title>

ACT NO. 50 OF <year>1972</year>
[ 3rd September, <year>1972</year>.]

An Act to provide for the taking over of the management of the 
undertaking of the Indian Iron and Steel Company Limited for a limited 
period in the public interest and in order to secure the proper 
management of the undertaking.

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1907468</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>332184</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Indian Iron and Steel Company (Taking over of Management) Act, <year>1972</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1697067</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 14th day of 
July, <year>1972</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1718814</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>657044</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means the 14th day of July, <year>1972</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>844679</tid>
<number>aa</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>" Board of management" means the Board of management 
constituted under section 4A;]

</section>

<section><tid>58552</tid>
<number>b</number>" company or" Indian Iron and Steel Company" means the 
Indian Iron and Steel Company Limited, being a company 
as defined in the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), 
having its registered office at Martin Burn House, 12, 
Mission Row, Calcutta;

</section>

<section><tid>1347762</tid>
<number>c</number>" Custodian" means the person appointed under section 4 
to take over the management of the undertaking of the 
company;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>190</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 36 of <year>1974</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 28- 6- <year>1974</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>438151</tid>
<number>d</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1215470</tid>
<number>e</number>" undertaking", in relation to the company, means the 
property and assets of the company referred to in sub- 
section (2) of section 3;

</section>

<section><tid>1027461</tid>
<number>f</number>words and expressions used but not defined in this Act 
and defined in the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), 
shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them 
in that Act.
CHAP

MANAGEMENT OF THE UNDERTAKING OF THE INDIAN IRON AND STEEL COMPANY

CHAPTER II

MANAGEMENT OF THE UNDERTAKING OF THE INDIAN IRON AND STEEL COMPANY




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>921859</tid>
<number> 3</number> Management of undertaking of the company to vest in Central 
Government.
<section><tid>1391376</tid>
<number>1</number>On and from the appointed day and for a period of  
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> five years] thereafter, the management of the undertaking of the 
company shall vest in the Central Government:
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Provided that if the Central Government is of opinion that it 
is expedient in the public interest that the management of the 
undertaking of the company should continue to vest in the Central 
Government after the expiry of the period of five years aforesaid, it 
may, from time to time, issue directions for such continuance for such 
further period, not exceeding two years at a time, as may be specified 
in the directions; so, however, that the total period of such 
continuance, including the period of five years aforesaid, shall not 
exceed ten years; and where any such direction is issued, a copy 
thereof shall be laid, as soon as may be, before both Houses of 
Parliament.]


</section>

<section><tid>1134728</tid>
<number>2</number>The undertaking of the company shall be deemed to include all 
assets, rights, leaseholds (including mining leases, if any), powers, 
authorities and privileges and all property, movable and immovable, 
including lands, buildings, works, mines, workshops, projects, 
washeries, smelters, ropeways, stores, instruments, machinery, 
aircraft, locomotives, automobiles and other vehicles, cash balances, 
reserve fund, investments and book debts and all other rights and 
interests arising out of such property as were immediately before the 
appointed day in the ownership, possession, power or control of the 
company in relation to the undertaking, whether within or without 
India, and
<pagefootnote><pagenum>191</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1974</year>, s. 3, for" two years" (w. e. f. 28- 6-  
  <year>1974</year>). 
2 Added by s. 3, ibid. (w. e. f. 28- 6- <year>1974</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


all books of account, registers, maps, plans, sections, drawings, 
records of survey and all other documents of whatever nature relating 
thereto.


</section>

<section><tid>872089</tid>
<number>3</number>Any contract, whether express or implied, or other 
arrangement, in so far as it relates to the management of the business 
and affairs of the company in relation to its undertaking and in force 
immediately before the appointed day, shall be deemed to have 
terminated on the appointed day.

</section>

<section><tid>1195494</tid>
<number>4</number>All persons in charge of the management, including persons 
holding offices as directors, managers or any other managerial 
personnel of the company immediately before the appointed day, shall 
be deemed to have vacated their offices as such on the appointed day.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>98997</tid>
<number> 4</number> Custodiarn of the company.
<section><tid>1013465</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government shall,  
as from the appointed day, appoint a person as the Custodian of the 
undertaking of the company for the npurpose of taking over the 
management thereof and the Custodian shall carry on the management of 
the undertaking of the company for and on behalf of the Central 
Government.

</section>

<section><tid>553485</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may issue such directions (including  
directions as to initiating, defending or continuing any legal 
  proceedings before any court, tribunal or other authority) to the 
Custodian as to his powers and duties as the Central Government deems 
desirable and the Custodian may apply to the Central Government at any 
time for instructions as to the manner in which the Custodian shall 
conduct the management of the undertaking of the company or in 
relation to any matter arising in the course of such management.

</section>

<section><tid>291595</tid>
<number>3</number>Subject to the other provisions of this Act and to the 
control of the Central Government, the Custodian shall be entitled, 
notwithstanding anything contained in the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of  
  <year>1956</year>), to exercise all the powers of the Board of Directors of the 
company (including the powers to dispose of any properties or assets  
  of the company) whether such powers are derived from the Companies 
Act, <year>1956</year>, or from the memorandum and articles of association of the 
company or from any other source.

</section>

<section><tid>822919</tid>
<number>4</number>Every person having possession, custody or control of any 
property forming part of the undertaking of the company shall deliver 
forthwith such property to the Custodian or to any officer or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>192</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

other employee of the Central Government or the company as may be 
authorised by the Central Government in this behalf.


</section>

<section><tid>712554</tid>
<number>5</number>Any person who, on the appointed day, has in his possession 
or under his control any books, papers or other documents relating to 
the undertaking of the company, including the minutes books containing 
the resolutions of the persons in charge of the management before the 
appointed day, the current cheque books relating to the undertaking of 
the company, any letters, memoranda, notes or other communications 
between him and the company shall, notwithstanding anything contained 
in any law for the time being in force, be liable to account for the 
books, papers and other documents (including such minutes books,  
  cheque books, letters, memoranda, notes or other communications) to 
the Custodian and shall deliver them up to the Custodian or to any 
such person (being an officer or other employee of the Central  
  Government or the company) as may be authorised by the Central 
Government in this behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>705983</tid>
<number>6</number>Every person in charge of the management of the undertaking 
of the company immediately before the appointed day shall, within ten 
days from that day or within such further period as the Central 
Government may allow in this behalf, furnish to the Custodian a 
complete inventory of all the properties and assets (including  
  particulars of book debts and investments and belongings) forming part 
of the undertaking of the company immediately before the appointed day 
and of all the liabilities and obligations of the company in relation 
to its undertaking subsisting immediately before that day and also of 
all agreements entered into by the company in relation to its 
undertaking and in force immediately before that day.

</section>

<section><tid>308745</tid>
<number>7</number>The Custodian shall receive from the funds of the undertaking 
of the company such remuneration as the Central Government may fix.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>719172</tid>
<number> 4A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Board of management.
<section><tid>1540198</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be a Board of  
management consisting of a Chairman and not less than four and not 
more than fourteen other members.

</section>

<section><tid>1959906</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chairman and the other members of the Board of management 
shall be appointed by the Central Government and shall hold office 
during the pleasure of that Government.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>193</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 36 of <year>1974</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 28- 6- <year>1974</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1881629</tid>
<number>3</number>Such of the members of the Board of management as may be 
specified by the Central Government as whole- time members may be 
placed in charge of such functions of management of the undertaking of 
the company as may be specified by that Government.

</section>

<section><tid>989828</tid>
<number>4</number>The Chairman and the other members of the Board of management 
shall receive from the funds of the undertaking of the company such 
allowances as may be prescribed for attending any meeting of the Board 
of management.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>369351</tid>
<number> 4B</number> Board of management to manage the undertaking of the company.

<section><tid>922201</tid>
<number>1</number>On the commencement of the Indian Iron and Steel Company (Taking   
  over of Management) Amendment Act, <year>1974</year> (36 of <year>1974</year>), the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that 
on and from such date as may be specified in the notification, the 
general superintendence, direction and management of the affairs and 
business of the undertaking of the company shall be carried on, for 
and on behalf of the Central Government, by the Board of management.

</section>

<section><tid>1133280</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the other provisions of this Act and to the 
direction, control and supervision of the Central Government, the 
Board of management shall be entitled, notwithstanding anything 
contained in the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), to exercise, in 
relation to the undertaking of the company, all the powers of the 
Board of Directors of a company (including powers to dispose of any  
  properties or assets of the company), whether such powers are derived 
from the Companies Act, <year>1956</year>, or from the memorandum or articles of 
association of the company or from any other source.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>39451</tid>
<number> 4C</number> Appointment of an Administrator.
<section><tid>514532</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be an  
Administrator, to be appointed by the Central Government, to assist 
the Board of management to manage the affairs of the undertaking of 
the company.

</section>

<section><tid>1801258</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chairman or any other member of the Board of management 
may be appointed by the Central Government as the Administrator.

</section>

<section><tid>1079332</tid>
<number>3</number>All officers and other persons employed in connection with 
the affairs of the undertaking of the company shall be subordinate to 
the Administrator.

</section>

<section><tid>240394</tid>
<number>4</number>The Administrator shall exercise, subject to the direction, 
control and supervision of the Board of management, such powers

<pagefootnote><pagenum>194</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

and discharge such functions of management in relation to the 
undertaking of the company as the Central Government may specify in 
this behalf.


</section>

<section><tid>533226</tid>
<number>5</number>The Administrator shall receive from the funds of the 
undertaking of the company such remuneration as the Central Government 
may fix.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1393875</tid>
<number> 4D</number> Custodian to vacate office.
<section><tid>926968</tid>
<number>1</number>The Custodian shall, on and  
from the date on which the management of the undertaking of the 
company is taken over by the Board of management, vacate his office as 
such; but nothing in this sub- section shall be construed as 
prohibiting his appointment as a member of the Board of management or 
as the Administrator.

</section>

<section><tid>1711659</tid>
<number>2</number>On the vacation of his office, the Custodian shall, where he 
is not appointed as the Administrator, forthwith deliver to the 
Administrator possession of all assets and properties of the company 
which are in his possession, custody and control on the date 
immediately preceding the date on which he vacates his office as the 
Custodian.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1250156</tid>
<number> 4E</number> Meetings, etc., of the Board of management.
<section><tid>70433</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board of  
management shall meet for the transaction of its business at such time 
and place as it may think fit:
Provided that the Chairman may, whenever he thinks fit, and 
shall, upon the written requisition of not less than two members, call 
a special meeting.


</section>

<section><tid>1487224</tid>
<number>2</number>The quorum for a meeting of the Board of management shall be 
one- third of its total strength (any fraction contained in that one-  
  third be rounded off as one) or three members, whichever is higher.

</section>

<section><tid>511673</tid>
<number>3</number>The Chairman, or in his absence, any member chosen by the 
members present from amongst themselves, shall preside at a meeting of 
the Board of management.

</section>

<section><tid>1895286</tid>
<number>4</number>All questions which come up before any meeting of the Board 
of management shall be decided by a majority of votes of the members 
present and voting, and in the case of an equality of votes, the 
Chairman, or, in his absence, the person presiding, shall have a 
second or casting vote.

</section>

<section><tid>1103151</tid>
<number>5</number>All orders and decisions of the Board of management shall be 
authenticated by the signature of the Chairman or any other member 
authorised by the Board of management in this behalf and all other 
instruments issued by the undertaking of the company shall be

<pagefootnote><pagenum>195</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

authenticated with the signature of the Administrator or any other 
officer of the undertaking of the company authorised by the Board of 
management in this behalf.


</section>

<section><tid>1091063</tid>
<number>6</number>The Board of management shall regulate its own procedure.]
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1105583</tid>
<number>6</number>No right to compensation for termination of contract on 
office. Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time 
being in force, no person in respect of whom any contract of 
management or other arrangement is terminated by reason of the 
provisions contained in sub- section (3) of section 3 or who ceases to 
hold any office by reason of the provisions contained in sub- section 
 (4) of that section, shall be entitled to claim any compensation for 
the premature termination of the contract of management or other 
arrangement or for the loss of office.


</article>



<article><tid>374645</tid>
<number> 7</number> Relinquishment of management of the undertaking of the 
company.
<section><tid>360712</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1) of  
section 3, if, at any time before the expiry of the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> period of five 
years referred to in that sub- section or the further period specified 
in any directions issued under the proviso thereto], it appears to the 
Central Government that the purposes of the vesting of the management 
of the undertaking of the company in that Government have been 
fulfilled or for any other reason it is not necessary that the 
management of the undertaking of the company should remain vested in 
that Government, it may by order published in the Official Gazette 
relinquish the management of the undertaking of the company with 
effect from such date as may be specified in the order.

</section>

<section><tid>523793</tid>
<number>2</number>On and from the date specified in the order published under 
sub- section (1), the undertaking of the company shall be managed in 
accordance with the provisions of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of  
  <year>1956</year>), so, however, that steps, if any, in relation to the management 
of the undertaking may be taken after the publication of the order 
under sub- section (1).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>262619</tid>
<number> 8</number> Application of Act 1 of <year>1956</year>.
<section><tid>1000036</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything  
contained in the Companies Act, <year>1956</year>, or in the memorandum or articles 
of association of the company, but subject to the provisions of sub- 
section (2) of section
<pagefootnote><pagenum>196</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Section 5 omitted by Act 36 of <year>1974</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 28- 6- <year>1974</year>). 
2 Subs. by s. 6, ibid., for certain words (w. e. f. 28- 6- <year>1974</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


 7, so long as the management of the undertaking of the company remains 
vested in the Central Government,--


<subsection><tid>575013</tid>
<number>a</number>it shall not be lawful for the shareholders of the 
company or any other person to nominate or appoint any 
person to be a director of the company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1510585</tid>
<number>b</number>no resolution passed at any meeting of the shareholders 
of the company on or after the appointed day shall be 
given effect to unless approved by the Central 
Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>561109</tid>
<number>c</number>no proceeding for the winding up of the company or for 
the appointment of a liquidator or receiver in respect 
thereof shall lie in any court except with the consent 
of the Central Government.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1650175</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions contained in sub- section (1), and 
to the other provisions contained in this Act and subject to such 
other exceptions, restrictions and limitations, if any, as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify in 
this behalf, the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), shall continue to 
apply to the company in the same manner as it applied thereto before 
the appointed day.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER III

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1331971</tid>
<number> 9</number> Penalties.
<section><tid>900648</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person, who-- 

<subsection><tid>1589987</tid>
<number>a</number>having in his possession or custody or under his control 
any property forming part of the undertaking of the 
company, wrongfully withholds such property from the 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Administrator, Board of management or Custodian] or 
any person authorised under this Act, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>336183</tid>
<number>b</number>wrongfully obtains possession of any such property, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1228086</tid>
<number>c</number>wilfully retains any property forming part of the 
undertaking of the company or removes or destroys it, 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1130147</tid>
<number>d</number>wilfully withholds or fails to deliver any books, papers 
or other documents which may be in his possession or 
custody or under his control to the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Administrator, 
Board of management or Custodian] or any person
<pagefootnote><pagenum>197</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1974</year>, s. 7, for the word" Custodian" (w. e. f.  
  28- 6- <year>1974</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


authorised under this Act, or


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>601875</tid>
<number>e</number>fails, without any reasonable cause, to furnish 
information or particulars as provided in sub- section 
 (6) of section 4,
shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
two years, or with fine which may extend to ten thousand rupees, or 
with both.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>573617</tid>
<number>2</number>No court shall take cognizance of an offence punishable under 
this section except with the previous sanction of the Central 
Government or of an officer authorised by the Central Government in 
this behalf.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>135400</tid>
<number> 10</number> Offences by companies.
<section><tid>742985</tid>
<number>1</number>Where an offence under this Act  
has been committed by a company, every person who at the time the 
offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible to, the 
company for the conduct of the business of the company as well as the 
company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be 
liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the 
offence was committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised 
all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.


</section>

<section><tid>1417774</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where 
any offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is 
proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or 
connivance of, or is attributable to, any neglect on the part of any 
director, manager, secretary or other officer shall be deemed to be 
guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and 
punished accordingly.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section,--


<subsection><tid>918127</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm 
or other association of individuals; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>820746</tid>
<number>b</number>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner in 
the firm.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1927082</tid>
<number>11</number>Exclusion of period of operation of Act. In computing the 
period of limitation prescribed by law for the time being in force for 
any suit or application against any person

<pagefootnote><pagenum>198</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

by the company in respect of any matter arising out of any transaction 
in relation to the undertaking of the company, the time during which 
this Act is in force shall be excluded.



</article>



<article><tid>1697881</tid>
<number>12</number>Act to have overriding effect. The provisions of this Act or 
any notification, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> direction,] order or rule made thereunder shall 
have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained 
in any law other than this Act or in any instrument having effect by 
virtue of any law other than this Act or in any decree or order of any 
court.


</article>



<article><tid>32094</tid>
<number> 13</number> Pretection of action taken in good faith.
<section><tid>464290</tid>
<number>1</number>No suit,  
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Administrator, Board of management or Custodian] or any officer or 
other employee of the Central Government or the company for anything 
which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>874709</tid>
<number>2</number>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the 
Central Government or the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Administrator, Board of management or 
Custodian] or any of the officers or other employees of the Central 
Government or the company for any damage caused or likely to be caused 
by anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under 
this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1726957</tid>
<number> 14</number> Contracts in bad faith may be cancelled or varied.
<section><tid>345579</tid>
<number>1</number>If the  
Central Government is satisfied, after such enquiry as it may think 
fit, that any contract or agreement entered into at any time within 
three years immediately preceding the appointed day, between the 
company or the managing agents of the company and any other person, in 
so far as such contract or agreement relates to the undertaking of the 
company, has been entered into in bad faith, or is detrimental to the 
interests of the undertaking of the company, it may make an order 
cancelling or varying (either unconditionally or subject to such  
  conditions as it may think fit to impose) such contract or agreement 
and thereafter the contract or agreement shall have effect 
accordingly:
Provided that no contract or agreement shall be cancelled or 
varied except after giving to the parties to the contract or agreement 
reasonable opportunity of being heard.


</section>

<section><tid>1992705</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person aggrieved by an order under sub- section (1) may 
make an application to the High Court at Calcutta for the variation
<pagefootnote><pagenum>199</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 36 of <year>1974</year>, s. 8 (w. e. f. 28- 6- <year>1974</year>). 
2 Subs. by s. 9, ibid., for the word" Custodian" (w. e. f. 28- 6-  
  <year>1974</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


or reversal of such order and thereupon such court may confirm, modify 
or reverse such order.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1163135</tid>
<number>15</number>Powers to terminate contract of employment. If the Custodian 
is of the opinion that any contract of employment entered into by the 
company or the managing agents of the company in relation to the 
undertaking of the company, at any time before the appointed day, is 
unduly onerous, he may, by giving to the employee one month' s notice 
in writing or the salary or wages for one month in lieu thereof, 
terminate such contract of employment.


</article>



<article><tid>252552</tid>
<number> 16</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1340459</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the 
purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1626489</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for--

<subsection><tid>1858091</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> allowances which may be received by the Chairman and 
other members of the Board of management for attending 
any meeting of the Board of management;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1056890</tid>
<number>b</number>the procedure to be followed by the said Board.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>357151</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act 
shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House 
of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty 
days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>265504</tid>
<number> 17</number> Repeal and savings.
<section><tid>203223</tid>
<number>1</number>The Indian Iron and Steel Company  
 (Taking over of Management) Ordinance, <year>1972</year> (Ord. 6 of <year>1972</year>), is 
hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>771557</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action 
taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or 
taken under the corresponding provision of this Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>200</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1974</year>, s. 10, for cl. (a)  (w. e. f. 28- 6- <year>1974</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>