<act><tid>988436</tid>
<title>THE ESTATE DUTY ACT, <year>1953</year></title>

ACT NO. 34 OF <year>1953</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 6th October, <year>1953</year>.]

An Act to provide for the levy and collection of an estate duty.

PART

PRELIMINARY

PART I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>870414</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>107293</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Estate Duty Act, <year>1953</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>157303</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>.

</section>

<section><tid>1371948</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1246869</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1220770</tid>
<number>1</number>" affidavit of valuation" means the affidavit of 
valuation made under section 19-I of the Court- fees 
Act, <year>1870</year>, (7 of <year>1870</year>) in connection with an 
application for the grant of representation;

</section>

<section><tid>1011656</tid>
<number>1A</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>" Appellate Controller" means a person appointed to 
be an Appellate Controller of Estate Duty under section 
4;

</section>

<section><tid>1339545</tid>
<number>1B</number>" Appellate Tribunal" means the Appellate Tribunal 
appointed under section 5A of the Indian Income- tax 
Act, <year>1922</year>; (11 of <year>1922</year>;)]

</section>

<section><tid>1737655</tid>
<number>2</number>" Board" means the <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Central Board of Direct Taxes 
constituted under the Central Boards of Revenue Act, 
<year>1963</year>]; (54 of <year>1963</year>)

</section>

<section><tid>1799892</tid>
<number>3</number>" company" includes any body corporate wheresoever 
incorporated;

</section>

<section><tid>963575</tid>
<number>4</number>" controlled company" means a company as defined in 
section 17;

</section>

<section><tid>970909</tid>
<number>5</number>" Controller" means a person appointed to be a Controller 
of Estate Duty under section 4 and includes a person 
appointed to be a Deputy Controller of Estate Duty or 
an Assistant Controller of Estate Duty;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>666</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been extended to the Union territories of Dadra and 
Nagar Haveli, Goa, Daman and Diu, and Pondicherry, with modifications, 
by Reg. 3 of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch. (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1963</year>). 
2 The words" except the State of Jammu and Kashmir" omitted by Act 
41 of <year>1954</year>, s. 2 (2) and Sch. 
3  15th October, <year>1953</year>, vide Notification No. S. R. O. <year>1882</year>, dated the 
8th October, <year>1953</year>, see Gazette of India, <year>1953</year>, Pt. II, Sec. 3, p. 
1595. 
4 Ins. by Act 33 of <year>1958</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1960</year>). 
5 Subs. by Act 54 of <year>1963</year>, s. 5, for certain words (w. e. f. 1- 1-  
  <year>1964</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>972414</tid>
<number>6</number>" deceased person" and" the deceased" mean a person 
dying after the commencement of this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>889747</tid>
<number>7</number>" estate duty" means estate duty under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>802138</tid>
<number>8</number>" executor" means the executor or administrator of a 
deceased person;

</section>

<section><tid>558402</tid>
<number>9</number>" general power" includes every power or authority 
enabling the donee or other holder thereof to appoint 
or dispose of property as he thinks fit, whether 
exercisable by instrument inter vivos or by will or 
both, but exclusive of any power exercisable in a 
fiduciary capacity under a disposition not made by 
himself or exercisable as mortgagee;

</section>

<section><tid>1318913</tid>
<number>10</number>" incumbrances" includes mortgages and terminable 
charges;

</section>

<section><tid>1210280</tid>
<number>11</number>" interest in expectancy" includes an estate in 
remainder or reversion and every other future interest 
whether vested or contingent, but does not include 
reversions expectant upon the determination of leases;

</section>

<section><tid>54714</tid>
<number>12</number>" legal representative" means a person who in law 
represents the estate of a deceased person, and 
includes--

<subsection><tid>1506816</tid>
<number>i</number>an executor,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>95524</tid>
<number>ii</number>as regards any obligation under this 
Act, any person who takes possession of, or 
intermeddles with, the estate of a deceased person 
or any part thereof, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1735938</tid>
<number>iii</number>where the deceased was a coparcener of 
a Hindu family, the manager for the time being of 
the family;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>266074</tid>
<number>12A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>" person accountable" or" accountable person" means 
the person accountable for estate duty within the 
meaning of this Act, and includes every person in 
respect of whom any proceeding under this Act has been 
taken for the assessment of the principal value of the 
estate of the deceased;]

</section>

<section><tid>65777</tid>
<number>13</number>" power to appoint property" means power to determine 
the disposition of property of which the person 
invested with the power is not the owner;

</section>

<section><tid>1999489</tid>
<number>14</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>667</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 33 of <year>1958</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1960</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>326046</tid>
<number>14A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>" principal officer", in relation to a company or a 
corporation established by a Central, State or 
Provincial Act, means the manager, managing director, 
managing agent or secretary, and includes any person 
connected with the management of the company or 
corporation upon whom the Controller has served a 
notice of his intention of treating him as the 
principal officer for the purposes of this Act;]

</section>

<section><tid>8712</tid>
<number>15</number>" property" includes any interest in property, movable 
or immovable, the proceeds of sale thereof and any 
money or investment for the time being representing the 
proceeds of sale and also includes any property 
converted from one species into another by any method;
Explanation 1.-- The creation by a person or 
with his consent of a debt or other right 
enforceable against him personally or against 
property which he was or might become competent to 
dispose of, or to charge or burden for his own 
benefit, shall be deemed to have been a 
disposition made by that person, and in relation 
to such a disposition the expression" property" 
shall include the debt or right created.

Explanation 2.-- The extinguishment at the 
expense of the deceased of a debt or other right 
shall be deemed to have been a disposition made by 
the deceased in favour of the person for whose 
benefit the debt or right was extinguished, and in 
relation to such a disposition the expression 
" property" shall include the benefit conferred by 
the extinguishment of the debt or right;


</section>

<section><tid>882973</tid>
<number>16</number>" property passing on the death" includes property 
passing either immediately on the death or after any 
interval, either certainly or contingently, and either 
originally or by way of substitutive limitation, and 
" on the death" includes" at a period ascertainable only 
by reference to the death";

</section>

<section><tid>223175</tid>
<number>17</number>" public charitable purpose" includes relief of the 
poor, education, medical relief and the advancement of 
any other object of general public utility within the 
territory of India;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>668</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 33 of <year>1958</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1960</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>262364</tid>
<number>18</number>" representation" means probate of a will or letters of 
administration;

</section>

<section><tid>330160</tid>
<number>19</number>" settled property" means property which stands limited 
to, or in trust for, any persons, natural or juridical, 
by way of succession, whether the settlement took 
effect before or after the commencement of this Act; 
and" settlement" means any disposition, including a 
dedication or endowment, whereby property is settled;

</section>

<section><tid>1497876</tid>
<number>20</number>" Valuer" means a Valuer appointed under section 4.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>832055</tid>
<number> 3</number> Interpretation.
<section><tid>405726</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purposes of this Act,-- 

<subsection><tid>466386</tid>
<number>a</number>a person shall be deemed competent to dispose of 
property if he has such an estate or interest therein 
or such general power as would, if he were sui juris, 
enable him to dispose of the property;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>375028</tid>
<number>b</number>a disposition taking effect out of the interest of the 
deceased shall be deemed to have been made by him, 
whether the concurrence of any other person was or was 
not required;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>203</tid>
<number>c</number>money which a person has a general power to charge on 
the property of another person shall be deemed to be an 
interest in that property of which the former has power 
to dispose;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1179264</tid>
<number>d</number>the domicile of a person shall be determined as if the 
provisions of the Indian Succession Act, <year>1925</year>, (39 of  
  <year>1925</year>) on the subject applied to him.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1305617</tid>
<number>2</number>In Parts II and III of this Act, any reference to any 
interest disposed of, policy of insurance effected, annuity or other 
interest purchased or provided or to any gift, settlement, disposition 
or transfer of property made, shall be construed as including any such 
interest, policy, annuity, gift, settlement, disposition or transfer, 
as the case may be, whether it was disposed of, effected, purchased or 
provided, or made before or after the commencement of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>129617</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> For the avoidance of doubt, it is hereby declared that 
references in this Act to property passing on the death of a person 
shall be construed as including references to property deemed to pass 
on the death of such person.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>669</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 17 of <year>1954</year>, s. 4 (with retrospective effect).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>993689</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Any reference in sections 9, 11 and 33 to public 
charitable purpose or purposes in relation to a gift made or 
disposition or determination of an interest effected or suffered on or 
after the 1st day of April, <year>1964</year> shall be construed as not including a 
purpose the whole or substantially the whole of which is of a 
religious nature.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>851290</tid>
<number> 4</number> Estate duty authorities.
<section><tid>591494</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be the following  
authorities for the purposes of this Act, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1610817</tid>
<number>a</number>the Board,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1363801</tid>
<number>b</number>Controllers of Estate Duty,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>43586</tid>
<number>bb</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Appellate Controllers of Estate Duty,]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1045482</tid>
<number>c</number>Valuers.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>606884</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may appoint as many Controllers of 
Estate Duty as it thinks fit and they shall, subject to the control of 
the Board, perform their functions in respect of such estates or 
classes of estates and such areas as are assigned to them by the 
Board:
Provided that, subject to such rules as may be made by the Board 
in this behalf, every Controller, within the local limits of whose 
jurisdiction any part of the estate of the deceased is situated, may 
exercise in relation to the whole estate or any part thereof any of 
the powers conferred on the Controller by this Act:

Provided further that the Board may, by general or special order, 
direct that any Controller specified by it in this behalf may exercise 
all or any of the powers conferred on the Controller by this Act to 
the exclusion of any other Controller.


</section>

<section><tid>1736939</tid>
<number>2A</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> The Central Government may appoint as many Appellate 
Controllers of Estate Duty as it thinks fit and they shall, subject to 
the control of the Board, perform their functions in respect of such 
estates or classes of estates or such areas as the Board may direct, 
and where such directions have assigned to two or more Appellate 
Controllers the same estate or classes of estates or the same area, 
they shall perform their functions in accordance with any orders which 
the Board may make for the distribution and allocation of the work to 
be performed.]

</section>

<section><tid>1049985</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government shall, within twelve months after the 
Commencement of this Act and may thereafter, from time to time,
<pagefootnote><pagenum>670</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 15 of <year>1965</year>, s. 19 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1964</year>). 
2 Ins. by Act 33 of <year>1958</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1960</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


appoint a sufficient number of qualified persons to act as Valuers for 
the purposes of this Act and shall fix a scale of charges for the 
remuneration of such persons.


</section>

<section><tid>742939</tid>
<number>4</number>Subject to the rules and orders of the Central Government 
regulating the conditions of service of persons in public services and 
posts, a Controller may appoint such executive or ministerial staff as 
may be necessary to assist him in the execution of his functions.

</section>

<section><tid>818071</tid>
<number>5</number>All officers and persons employed in the execution of this 
Act, other than Valuers, shall observe and follow the orders, 
instructions and directions of the Board:
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided that no such orders, instructions or directions shall 
be given by the Board so as to interfere with the discretion of the 
Appellate Controller of Estate Duty in the exercise of his appellate 
functions.]

PART

IMPOSITION OF ESTATE DUTY

PART II

IMPOSITION OF ESTATE DUTY

Extent of charge




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1138907</tid>
<number> 5</number> Levy of estate duty.
<section><tid>1295015</tid>
<number>1</number>In the case of every person dying  
after the commencement of this Act, there shall, save as hereinafter 
expressly provided, be levied and paid upon the principal value 
ascertained as hereinafter provided of all property, settled or not 
settled, including agricultural land situate in <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the territories 
which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in the 
States] specified in the First Schedule to this Act, which passes on 
the death of such person, a duty called" estate duty" at the rates 
fixed in accordance with section 35.

</section>

<section><tid>830187</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, add the names of any other States to the First Schedule in 
respect whereof resolutions have been passed by the Legislatures of 
those States adopting this Act under clause (1) of article 252 of the 
Constitution in respect of estate duty on agricultural lands situate 
in those States, and on the issue of any such notification the States 
so added shall be deemed to be States specified in the First Schedule 
within the meaning of sub- section (1).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1404377</tid>
<number> 5A</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Application in respect of estate duty on agricultural 
lands of Act amending this Act.
<section><tid>776275</tid>
<number>1</number>The amendments made to this Act  
by--

<subsection><tid>1525036</tid>
<number>i</number>the Finance Act, <year>1954</year>, (17 of <year>1954</year>.)
<pagefootnote><pagenum>670A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 33 of <year>1958</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1960</year>). 
2 Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year> for" the 
States". 
3 Ins. by Act 16 of <year>1960</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1960</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>962110</tid>
<number>ii</number>the Taxation Laws (Extension to Jammu and Kashmir) Act, 
<year>1954</year>, (41 of <year>1954</year>.) and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1377218</tid>
<number>iii</number>the Repealing and Amending Act, <year>1957</year>, (36 of <year>1957</year>)
shall apply, and shall be deemed to have applied, to estate duty in 
respect of agricultural lands situate in the territories comprised in 
the States, except those in the States of West Bengal and Jammu and 
Kashmir, but including those in the transferred territories, on and 
from the dates on which the amendments made by each of the amending 
Acts aforesaid respectively took effect:

Provided that where in respect of any part of the territories 
comprised in any of the said States the resolution of the Legislature 
concerned under clause (1) of article 252 of the Constitution was


<pagefootnote><pagenum>671</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

passed subsequently to the date on which the said amendments would 
otherwise have taken effect by virtue of the foregoing provision, the 
said amendments shall, in respect of estate duty on agricultural lands 
in that part of the said territories, be deemed to have taken effect 
only on the date on which this Act became applicable to estate duty in 
respect of agricultural lands.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1314920</tid>
<number>2</number>The amendments made to this Act by the Estate Duty 
 (Amendment) Act, <year>1958</year> (33 of <year>1958</year>), shall also apply to the levy of 
estate duty in respect of agricultural lands situate in the 
territories comprised in the States except those in the States of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 
West Bengal and Jammu and Kashmir

</section>

<section><tid>1526552</tid>
<number>2A</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> The amendments made to, or in relation to, this Act, by--

<subsection><tid>119170</tid>
<number>i</number>the Central Boards of Revenue Act, <year>1963</year> (54 of <year>1963</year>),

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1357944</tid>
<number>ii</number>the Finance Act, <year>1964</year> (5 of <year>1964</year>),

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1589054</tid>
<number>iii</number>The Taxation Laws (Continuation and Validation of  
  Recovery Proceedings) Act, <year>1964</year> (11 of <year>1964</year>),

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>326777</tid>
<number>iv</number>the Direct Taxes (Amendment) Act, <year>1964</year> (31 of <year>1964</year>),

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1099017</tid>
<number>v</number>the Finance Act, <year>1965</year> (10 of <year>1965</year>),

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1661363</tid>
<number>vi</number>the Finance (No. 2) Act, <year>1965</year> (15 of <year>1965</year>),

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1445363</tid>
<number>vii</number>the Taxation Laws (Amendment and Miscellaneous  
  Provisions) Act, <year>1965</year> (41 of <year>1965</year>), and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>301381</tid>
<number>viii</number>the Finance Act, <year>1966</year> (13 of <year>1966</year>),
shall apply, and shall be deemed to have applied, on and from the 
dates on which the amendments made by each of the Acts aforesaid 
respectively took effect, to estate duty in respect of agricultural 
lands situate in the territories comprised in--


<subsubsection><tid>342847</tid>
<number>a</number>the States of Gujarat, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Tamil Nadu], Maharashtra and 
Rajasthan; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>714381</tid>
<number>b</number>any other States which the Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this 
behalf after resolutions have been passed by the 
Legislatures of those States adopting the said 
amendments under clause (1) of article 252 of the 
Constitution.]

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>987968</tid>
<number>2B</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> The amendments made to this Act by sections 3 to 6 of 
the Estate Duty (Amendment) Act, <year>1982</year> (31 of <year>1982</year>), shall apply, and 
shall be deemed to have applied, on and from the 1st day of March, 
<year>1981</year>, to estate duty in respect of agricultural lands situate 
in the territories comprised in--

<subsection><tid>189175</tid>
<number>a</number>the States of Bihar, Gujarat, Haryana, Himachal Pradesh, 
Madhya Pradesh, Maharashtra, Orissa and Tamil Nadu; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>479923</tid>
<number>b</number>any other States which the Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf 
after resolutions have been passed by the Legislatures of those 
States adopting the proposals with respect to such amendments or 
the said amendments, as the case may be, under clause (1) of 
article 252 of the Constitution.]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1043962</tid>
<number>2C</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum> The amendments made to this Act by sections 3 to 5 of 
the Estate Duty (Amendment) Act, <year>1984</year> (53 of <year>1984</year>), shall apply to 
estate duty in respect of agricultural lands situate in the territories 
comprised in- 
-

<subsection><tid>1421516</tid>
<number>a</number>the States of Assam, Bihar, Gujarat, Haryana, Himachal 
Pradesh, Kerala, Madhya Pradesh, Maharashtra, Meghalaya, Orissa 
and Tamil Nadu and all the Union territories, on the expiration 
of two months from the date on which the said Act received the 
assent of the President;[ <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1505145</tid>
<number>aa</number><footcitenum>8</footcitenum> the States of Punjab and Tripura, on the 16th day 
of March, <year>1985</year>; and]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>154921</tid>
<number>b</number>any other States in respect whereof resolutions have 
been passed by the Legislatures of those States adopting the 
proposals with respect to such amendments or the said amendments, 
as the case may be, under clause (1) of article 252 of the 
Constituion, on the expiration of four months from the date of 
such adoption.]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>252415</tid>
<number>3</number>This Act shall cease to apply to the levy of estate duty in 
respect of agricultural lands situate <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> in the transferred
<pagefootnote><pagenum>672</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The word" Orissa," omitted by Act 5 of <year>1964</year>, s. 49 (w. e. f. 23- 9-  
  <year>1963</year>). 
2 Ins. by Act 22 of <year>1968</year>, s. 2. 
3 Subs. by the Madras State (Alteration of Name)  (Adaptation of  
  Laws on Union Subjects) Order, <year>1970</year>, for" Madras" (w. e. f. 14- 1- <year>1969</year>). 
4 The words" in the State of Orissa and" omitted by Act 5 of <year>1964</year>, 
s. 49 (w. e. f. 23- 9- <year>1963</year>). 
5 Ins. by Act 31 of <year>1982</year>, s. 2. 
6 Ins. by Act 53 of <year>1984</year>, s. 2. 
7 Omitted by Act 49 of <year>1986</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 16- 3- <year>1985</year>). 
8 Ins. by s. 2, ibid. (w. e. f. 16- 3- <year>1985</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


territories and, notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section 
 (1), shall be deemed to have so ceased on and from the 1st day of 
April, <year>1959</year>.

Explanation.--" Transferred territories" means the territories 
which as from the 1st day of November, <year>1956</year>, were added to the State 
of West Bengal by virtue of sub- section (1) of section 3 of the Bihar 
and West Bengal (Transfer of Territories) Act, <year>1956</year>. (40 of <year>1956</year>)]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>396059</tid>
<number>5B</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Act to cease to apply to estate duty in respect of 
agricultural land. Notwithstanding anything contained in section 5, 
this Act shall cease to apply to the levy of estate duty in respect of 
agricultural land.]


</article>



<article><tid>668855</tid>
<number>5C</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Discontinuance of levy of estate duty. Notwithstanding 
anything contained in section 5, this Act shall cease to apply to the 
levy of estate duty in respect of any property (other than  
  agricultural land) which passes on the death of any person on or after 
the 16th day of March, <year>1985</year>.]
Property which is deemed to pass



</article>



<article><tid>1332966</tid>
<number>6</number>Property within disposing capacity. Property which the 
deceased was at the time of his death competent to dispose of shall be 
deemed to pass on his death.


</article>



<article><tid>1120762</tid>
<number> 7</number> Interests ceasing on death.
<section><tid>1720918</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of  
this section, property in which the deceased or any other person had 
an interest ceasing on the death of the deceased shall be deemed to 
pass on the deceased' s death to the extent to which a benefit accrues 
or arises by the cesser of such interest, including, in particular, a 
coparcenary interest in the joint family property of a Hindu family 
governed by the Mitakshara, Marumakkattayam or Aliyasantana law.

</section>

<section><tid>1829000</tid>
<number>2</number>If a member of a Hindu coparcenary governed by the Mitakshara 
school of law dies, then the provisions of sub- section (1) shall apply 
with respect to the interest of the deceased in the coparcenary 
property only--

<subsection><tid>955926</tid>
<number>a</number>if the deceased had completed his eighteenth year at the 
time of his death, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>30500</tid>
<number>b</number>where he had not completed his eighteenth year at the 
time of his death, if his father or other male 
ascendant in the male line was not a coparcener of the 
same family at the time of his death.
Explanation.-- Where the deceased was also a member of a sub- 
coparcenary (within the coparcenary) possessing separate property of 
its own, the provisions of this sub- section shall have effect 
separately in respect of the coparcenary and the sub- coparcenary.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>325415</tid>
<number>3</number>If a member of any tarwad or tavazhi governed by the 
Marumakkattayam rule of inheritance or a member of a kutumba or kavaru 
governed by the Aliyasantana rule of inheritance dies, then the 
provisions of sub- section (1) shall not apply with respect to the 
interest of the deceased in the property of the tarwad, tavazhi, 
kutumba or kavaru, as the case may be, unless the deceased had 
completed his eighteenth year.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>673</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 53 of <year>1984</year>, s. 3. 
2 Ins. by Act 52 of <year>1985</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 16- 3- <year>1985</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1662476</tid>
<number>4</number>The provisions of sub- section (1) shall not apply to the 
property in which the deceased or any other person had an interest 
only as holder of an office or recipient of the benefits of a charity, 
or as a corporation sole.
Explanation.-- For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared 
that the holder of a Sthanam is neither the holder of an office nor a 
corporation sole within the meaning of this sub- section.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>826844</tid>
<number>8</number>Gifts mortis causa. Property taken as a gift made in 
contemplation of death shall be deemed to pass on the donor' s death.
Explanation.-- In this section, the expression" gift made in 
contemplation of death" has the same meaning as in section 191 of the 
Indian Succession Act, <year>1925</year> (39 of <year>1925</year>).



</article>



<article><tid>1522954</tid>
<number> 9</number> Gifts within a certain period before death.
<section><tid>116870</tid>
<number>1</number>Property taken  
under a disposition made by the deceased purporting to operate as an 
immediate gift inter vivos whether by way of transfer, delivery, 
declaration of trust, settlement upon persons in succession, or 
otherwise, which shall not have been bona fide made <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> two years] or 
more before the death of the deceased shall be deemed to pass on the 
death:
Provided that in the case of gifts made for public charitable 
purposes the period shall be six months.


</section>

<section><tid>1905200</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> The provisions of sub- section (1) shall not apply to--

<subsection><tid>427102</tid>
<number>a</number>gifts made in consideration of marriage, subject to a 
maximum of rupees ten thousand in value;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1594261</tid>
<number>b</number>gifts which are proved to the satisfaction of the 
Controller to have been part of the normal expenditure 
of the deceased, subject to a maximum of rupees ten 
thousand in value.]



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1126428</tid>
<number>10</number>Gifts whenever made where donor not entirely excluded. 
Property taken under any gift, whenever made, shall be deemed to pass 
on the donor' s death to the extent that bona fide possession and 
enjoyment of it was not immediately assumed by the donee and 
thenceforward retained to the entire exclusion of the donor or of any 
benefit to him by contract or otherwise:
Provided that the property shall not be deemed to pass by reason 
only that it was, not, as from the date of the gift, exclusively 
retained as aforesaid, if, by means of the surrender of the reserved 
benefit or otherwise, it is subsequently enjoyed to the entire 
exclusion of the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>674</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 13 of <year>1966</year>, s. 38, for" one year" (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1966</year>). 
2 Subs. by Act 33 of <year>1958</year>, s. 4, for sub- section (2)  (w. e. f. 1- 7-  
  <year>1960</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


donor or of any benefit to him for at least <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> two years] before the 
death:

<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Provided further that a house or part thereof taken under any 
gift made to the spouse, son, daughter, brother or sister, shall not 
be deemed to pass on the donor' s death by reason only of the residence 
therein of the donor except where a right of residence therein is 
reserved or secured directly or indirectly to the donor under the 
relevant disposition or under any collateral disposition.]



</article>



<article><tid>1139418</tid>
<number> 11</number> Limited interests disposed of within a certain period before 
death.
<section><tid>1242885</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of this section, where an  
interest limited to cease on a death has been disposed of or has 
determined, whether by surrender, assurance, divesting, forfeiture or 
in any other manner (except by the expiration of a fixed period at the  
  expiration of which the interest was limited to cease), whether wholly 
or partly, and whether for value or not, after becoming an interest in 
possession, and the disposition or determination (or any of them if  
  there are more than one) is not excepted by sub- section (2), then--

<subsection><tid>502869</tid>
<number>a</number>if, had there been no disposition or determination, as 
aforesaid of that interest and no disposition of any 
interest expectant upon or subject to that interest, 
the property in which the interest subsisted would have 
passed on the death under section 5, that property 
shall be deemed by virtue of this section to be 
included as to the whole thereof in the property 
passing on the death; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1861459</tid>
<number>b</number>if, had there been no disposition or determination as 
aforesaid of that interest and no disposition of any 
interest expectant upon or subject to that interest, 
the property in which the interest subsisted would have 
been deemed by virtue of section 7 to be included to a 
particular extent in the property passing on the death, 
the property in which the interest subsisted shall be 
deemed by virtue of this section to be included to that 
extent in the property passing on the death.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1298236</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a disposition or determination of an interest limited 
to cease on the death was bona fide effected or suffered not less than 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> two years] before the death (or, if it was effected or suffered for  
public charitable purposes, not less than six months before the 
  death),
<pagefootnote><pagenum>675</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 13 of <year>1966</year>, s. 38, for" one year" (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1966</year>). 
2 Ins. by Act 10 of <year>1965</year>, s. 69 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


the disposition or determination shall be excepted by this sub- 
section--


<subsection><tid>1586322</tid>
<number>a</number>if bona fide possession and enjoyment of the property in 
which the interest subsisted was assumed immediately 
thereafter by the person becoming entitled by virtue of 
or upon the disposition or determination and thence- 
forward retained to the entire exclusion of the person 
who immediately before the disposition or determination 
had the interest and of any benefit to him by contract 
or otherwise; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>656987</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of a partial determination, if the 
conditions specified in the preceding paragraph were 
not satisfied by reason only of the retention or 
enjoyment by the deceased of possession of some part of 
the property, or of some benefit, by virtue of the 
provisions of the instrument under which he had the 
interest:
Provided that where bona fide possession and enjoyment of the 
property referred to in clause (a) was not assumed immediately after 
the disposition or determination of the interest limited to cease on 
death, the disposition or determination shall be excepted by this sub- 
section, if, by means of the surrender of the reserved benefit or 
otherwise, the property is subsequently enjoyed for at least <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> two 
years] before the death, to the entire exclusion of the person who 
immediately before the disposition or determination had the interest 
and of any benefit to him by contract or otherwise:

<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Provided further that where the disposition or determination 
of an interest limited to cease on the death in a house or part 
thereof was effected or suffered in favour of the spouse, son, 
daughter, brother or sister, then, the disposition or determination 
shall, notwithstanding the residence therein of the person who 
immediately before the disposition or determination had the interest, 
be deemed to be excepted by this sub- section save where a right of 
residence therein is reserved or secured directly or indirectly to 
such person under the relevant disposition or under any collateral 
disposition:]

Provided further that nothing in this sub- section shall be 
construed as affecting any charge of estate duty arising otherwise 
than by virtue of the provisions of the preceding sub- section.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>387548</tid>
<number>3</number>In the application of sub- section (1) to a case in which an 
incumbrance on the property in which the interest in question subsist-
<pagefootnote><pagenum>676</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 13 of <year>1966</year>, s. 38, for" one year" (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1966</year>). 
2 Ins. by Act 10 of <year>1965</year>, s. 69 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


ed has been created by associated operations (as hereinafter defined  
  in section 27) which included a disposition of that interest, 
references to that property shall be construed as references to that 
property free from the incumbrance, except in a case in which the 
incumbrance was created for consideration in money or money' s worth 
which was applied for purposes calculated to maintain or increase the 
value of that property, and, in that case, shall be construed as 
references to that property subject to the incumbrance to the extent 
to which the consideration was so applied.


</section>

<section><tid>1299817</tid>
<number>4</number>Where an interest limited to cease on a death has been 
disposed of or has determined, bona fide possession and enjoyment of 
the property shall not be deemed for the purposes of sub- section (2) 
to be assumed immediately thereafter and thenceforward retained to the 
entire exclusion of a person who had the interest and of any benefit 
to him by contract or otherwise, if at any time thereafter he has a 
benefit by virtue of any operations associated with the disposition or 
determination, nor while he has such a benefit shall the property be 
deemed to be enjoyed to the entire exclusion as aforesaid for the 
purposes of the first proviso to sub- section (2).

</section>

<section><tid>860243</tid>
<number>5</number>In the preceding sub- section--

<subsection><tid>1165911</tid>
<number>a</number>the reference to any operations associated with the 
disposition shall be taken as referring to any 
associated operations as defined in section 27, of 
which the disposition is one; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1187293</tid>
<number>b</number>the reference to any operations associated with the 
determination shall be taken as referring to any 
associated operations as so defined of which any 
disposition resulting in, or effected in contemplation 
of or with reference to, the determination is one.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1669419</tid>
<number> 12</number> Settlements with reservation.
<section><tid>1541191</tid>
<number>1</number>Property passing under any  
settlement made by the deceased by deed or any other instrument not 
taking effect as a will whereby an interest in such property for life 
or any other period determinable by reference to death is reserved 
either expressly or by implication to the settlor or whereby the 
settlor may have reserved to himself the right by the exercise of any 
power, to restore to himself or to reclaim the absolute interest in 
such property shall be deemed to pass on the settlor' s death:
Provided that the property shall not be deemed to pass on the 
settlor' s death by reason only that any such interest or right was so


<pagefootnote><pagenum>676A</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

reserved if by means of the surrender of such interest or right the 
property is subsequently enjoyed to the entire exclusion of the 
settlor and of any benefit to him by contract or otherwise, for at 
least <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> two years] before his death:

<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Provided further that a house or part thereof comprised in 
such settlement made in favour of the spouse, son, daughter, brother 
or sister, shall not be deemed to pass on the settlor' s death by 
reason only of the residence therein of the settlor except where a 
right of residence is reserved or secured directly or indirectly to 
the settlor under the settlement or under any collateral disposition.]

Explanation.-- A settlor reserving an interest in the settled 
property for the maintenance of himself and any of his relatives (as  
  defined in section 27) shall be deemed to reserve an interest for 
himself within the meaning of this section.


</section>

<section><tid>1841829</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where 
property is settled by a person on one or more other persons for their 
respective lives and after their death, on the settlor for life and 
thereafter on other persons and the settlor dies before his interest 
in the property becomes an interest in possession, the property shall 
not be deemed to pass on the settlor' s death within the meaning of 
this section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1617480</tid>
<number>13</number>Joint investments. Where a person, having been absolutely 
entitled to any property or to the funds with which any property was 
purchased, has caused it to be transferred to or vested in himself and 
any other person jointly, whether by disposition or otherwise, either 
by himself alone, or in concert, or by arrangement, with any other 
person so that the beneficial interest in some part of that property 
passes or accrues by survivorship on his death to the other person, 
the whole of that property shall be deemed to pass on the death.


</article>



<article><tid>377729</tid>
<number> 14</number> Policies kept up for a donee.
<section><tid>1500309</tid>
<number>1</number>Money received under a  
policy of insurance effected by any person on his life, where the 
policy is wholly kept up by him for the benefit of a donee, whether 
nominee or assignee, or a part of such money in proportion to the 
premiums paid by him, where the policy is partially kept up by him for 
such benefit, shall be deemed to pass on the death of the assured.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>676B</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 13 of <year>1966</year>, s. 38, for" one year" (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1966</year>). 
2 Ins. by Act 10 of <year>1965</year>, s. 69 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Explanation.-- A policy of insurance on the life of a deceased 
person effected by virtue or in consequence of a settlement made by 
the deceased shall be treated as having been effected by the deceased.


</section>

<section><tid>1017226</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes of sub- section (1), so much of the premiums 
paid on any policy of insurance as was, by virtue or in consequence of 
a settlement made by the deceased, paid out of property, whether or 
not provided by the deceased, comprised in the settlement or out of 
income, whether or not provided by the deceased, arising under the 
settlement, shall be treated as having been paid by the deceased:
Provided that any payments which were not made either out of 
property provided directly or indirectly by the deceased for the 
purposes of the settlement, or out of property representing that 
property, or out of income provided directly or indirectly by the 
deceased whether arising from such property or otherwise, shall not be 
treated as having been made by the deceased if the Controller is 
satisfied that those payments were not made as part of any reciprocal 
arrangements between the deceased and any other person.


</section>

<section><tid>543306</tid>
<number>3</number>For the purposes of this section,--

<subsection><tid>1895432</tid>
<number>a</number>the expression" settlement" includes any disposition, 
trust, covenant, agreement or arrangement; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>140750</tid>
<number>b</number>a person shall be deemed to have made a settlement if he 
has made or entered into the settlement directly or 
indirectly, and in particular (but without prejudice to  
  the generality of the foregoing words of this clause) 
if he has

<pagefootnote><pagenum>677</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

provided or undertaken to provide funds directly or 
indirectly for the purposes of the settlement, or has 
made with any other person a reciprocal arrangement for 
that other person to make or enter into the settlement.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1372914</tid>
<number>15</number>Annuity or other interest purchased or provided by the 
deceased. Any annuity or other interest, purchased or provided by the 
deceased, either by himself alone or in concert or by arrangement with 
any other person shall be deemed to pass on his death to the extent of 
the beneficial interest accruing or arising, by survivorship or 
otherwise, on his death.
Explanation.-- The extent of the beneficial interest must be 
ascertained without regard to any interest in expectancy which the 
beneficiary may have had therein before the death.



</article>



<article><tid>1044274</tid>
<number> 16</number> Annuity or other interest purchased or provided out of 
property derived from the deceased.
<section><tid>1519186</tid>
<number>1</number>Section 15 shall have effect  
in relation to any annuity or other interest that was purchased or 
provided wholly or in part by any person who was at any time entitled 
to, or amongst whose resources there was at any time included, any 
property derived from the deceased, as if that annuity or other 
interest had been provided by the deceased, or, if it is proved to the 
satisfaction of the Controller that the application of all the 
property derived from the deceased would have been insufficient to 
provide the whole of that annuity or other interest, as if a similar 
annuity or interest of an amount reduced to an extent proportionate to 
the insufficiency proved had been provided by the deceased:
Provided that for the purpose of determining whether there would 
have been any such insufficiency as aforesaid, and the extent thereof, 
there shall be excluded from the property derived from the deceased 
any part thereof as to which it is proved to the satisfaction of the 
Controller that the disposition of which it, or the property which it 
represented, was the subject- matter, was not made with reference to, 
or with a view to enabling or facilitating, the purchase or provision 
of the annuity or other interest, or the recoupment in any manner of 
the cost thereof.


</section>

<section><tid>1725840</tid>
<number>2</number>In this section the following expressions have the meanings 
hereby assigned to them respectively, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1152694</tid>
<number>a</number>" property derived from the deceased" means any property 
which was the subject- matter of a disposition made by 
the deceased, either by himself alone or in concert or 
by arrangement with any other person, 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> notwithstanding
<pagefootnote><pagenum>678</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 33 of <year>1958</year>, s. 5, for" otherwise than for full 
consideration" (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1960</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


that the disposition was made for full consideration] 
in money or money' s worth paid to him for his own use 
or benefit, or which represented any of the subject- 
matter of such a disposition, whether directly or 
indirectly, and whether by virtue of one or more 
intermediate dispositions and whether any such 
intermediate disposition was or was not for full or 
partial consideration:

Provided that where the first- mentioned 
disposition was for full consideration in money or 
money' s worth paid to the deceased for his own use 
or benefit and it is proved to the satisfaction of 
the Controller that the disposition was not part 
of associated operations which included--


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1152694</tid>
<number>a</number>a disposition by the deceased, either by 
himself alone or in concert or by arrangement with 
any other person, otherwise than for full 
consideration in money or money' s worth paid to 
the deceased for his own use or benefit, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>294644</tid>
<number>b</number>a disposition by any other person 
operating to reduce the value of the property of 
the deceased; then, in considering whether estate 
duty should be charged the said first mentioned 
disposition shall be left out of account as if 
this provision did not apply in relation to it;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>294644</tid>
<number>b</number>" disposition" includes any trust, covenant, agreement or 
arrangement; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>850690</tid>
<number>c</number>" subject- matter" includes, in relation to any 
disposition, any annual or periodical payment made or 
payable under or by virtue of the disposition.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>661860</tid>
<number>3</number>For the purposes of section 34 the deceased shall be deemed 
to have had an interest in any property included by virtue of this 
section in the property passing on the death of the deceased.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>224911</tid>
<number>16A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Interest of the deceased in building allotted or leased 
to him by a co- operative society. Where at the time of his death, the 
deceased was a member of a co- operative society, being a co- operative 
housing society, and a building or part thereof allotted or leased to 
him under a house building scheme of the society, continued to remain 
allotted or leased to him at the time of his death, he shall, 
notwithstanding anything contained in this Act or any other law for 
the time being in force, be deemed to be the owner of such building or 
part at the time of his death and such building or part shall be 
deemed to pass on his death and, in determining the value of such 
building or part, the value of any outstanding instalments of the 
amount payable under such scheme by the deceased at the time of his 
death to the society towards the cost of such building or part and the 
land appurtenant thereto shall, whether the amount so payable is 
described as such or in any other manner in such scheme, be allowed as 
a debt owed by him in relation to such building or part.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section and section 33. 
" co- operative society" means a co- operative society registered under 
the Co- operative Societies Act, <year>1912</year> (2 of <year>1912</year>) or under any other 
law for the time being in force in any State for the registration of 
co- operative societies.]

Special provisions relating to transfers to companies



</article>



<article><tid>312961</tid>
<number> 17</number> Property transferred to a controlled company.
<section><tid>762016</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the  
deceased has made to a controlled company a transfer of any property 
 (other than an interest limited to cease on his death or property  
  which he transferred in a fiduciary capacity), and any benefits 
accruing to the deceased from the company accrued to him in the three 
years ending with his death, the assets of the company shall be deemed 
for the purposes of estate duty to be included in the property passing 
on his death to an extent determined in accordance with sub- section 
 (2).
<pagefootnote><pagenum>679</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 31 of <year>1982</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 1- 3- <year>1981</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>528993</tid>
<number>2</number>The extent to which the assets of the company are to be 
deemed to be included as aforesaid shall be the proportion ascertained 
by comparing the aggregate amount of the benefits accruing to the 
deceased from the company in the last three accounting years with the 
aggregate amount of the net income of the company for the said years:
Provided that--


<subsection><tid>938565</tid>
<number>a</number>where, in any of the said accounting years, the company 
sustained a loss, the amount of that loss shall be 
deducted in ascertaining the said aggregate net income 
of the company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>753108</tid>
<number>b</number>where the company came into existence in the last year 
but one, or in the last, of the said accounting years, 
the references in this sub- section to the said 
accounting years shall be construed as references to 
the last two, or, as the case may be, the last, of 
those years.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1313285</tid>
<number>3</number>The assets of the company which are deemed to be included in 
the property passing on the death of the deceased by virtue of this 
section shall include any assets thereof which have been disposed of 
or distributed by the company at any time between the beginning of the 
first of the accounting years aforesaid and the death of the deceased 
either--

<subsection><tid>1912681</tid>
<number>a</number>in or towards satisfaction of rights attaching to shares 
in or debentures of the company, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1640669</tid>
<number>b</number>otherwise howsoever except as follows, that is to say, 
by way of sale for full consideration in money or 
money' s worth received by the company for its own use 
and benefit, or in or towards discharge of taxes or 
rates or other liability imposed by or under an 
enactment, or in or towards discharge of a fine or 
penalty or a liability for tort incurred without 
collusion with the injured party, including assets 
which have been so disposed of or distributed in a 
winding up, whether continuing at or completed before 
the death:
Provided that this sub- section shall not apply to assets disposed 
of or distributed by way of payments from which income- tax was 
deductible or which were assessable to income- tax, of amounts not 
exceeding in the aggregate, as respects payments made in any 
accounting year or in the period between the end of the last 
accounting year and the death of the deceased, the amount of the 
income of the company for that year or period.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>680</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1439095</tid>
<number>4</number> (i) A controlled company is any company which at any relevant 
time, was or would, if these provisions had always been in force, have 
been deemed to be, under the control of not more than five persons and 
which is not a subsidiary company or a company in which the public are 
substantially interested.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this sub- section,--


<subsection><tid>495773</tid>
<number>a</number>a company shall be deemed to be a subsidiary company if, 
by reason of the beneficial ownership of shares 
therein, the control of the company is in the hands of 
a company not being a company to which the provisions 
of this sub- section apply, or of two or more companies 
none of which is a company to which the aforesaid 
provisions apply;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1439900</tid>
<number>b</number>a company shall be deemed to be a company in which the 
public are substantially interested if shares of the 
company (not being shares entitled to a fixed rate of  
dividend, whether with or without a further right to 
  participate in profits) carrying not less than twenty- 
five per cent. of the voting power have been allotted 
unconditionally to, or acquired unconditionally by, and 
are at the end of the year or other period for which 
the accounts of the company have been made up 
beneficially held by the public (not including a  
company to which the provisions of this sub- section 
  apply) and any such shares have, in the course of such 
year or other period, been the subject of dealings on a 
recognised stock exchange or are in fact freely 
transferable by the holders to other members of the 
public.

<subsubsection><tid>38941</tid>
<number>ii</number>A company shall be deemed to be under the control of not 
more than five persons--

<subsubsubsection><tid>1463548</tid>
<number>a</number>if any five or fewer persons together exercise, or are 
able to exercise or are entitled to acquire, control, 
whether direct or indirect, over the company' s affairs, 
and in particular, but without prejudice to the 
generality of the foregoing words, if any five or fewer 
persons together possess, or are entitled to acquire, 
the greater part of the share capital or voting power 
of the company; or

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1831054</tid>
<number>b</number>if any five or fewer persons together posses, or are 
entitled to acquire, either the greater part of the 
issued share capital of the company, or such part of 
that capital as would, if the whole of the income of 
the company were in

<pagefootnote><pagenum>681</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

fact distributed to the members, entitled them to 
receive the greater part of the amount so distributed; 
or


</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>576461</tid>
<number>c</number>if,--

</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1126583</tid>
<number>i</number>on the assumption that the company is a 
company to which this sub- section applies; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>38941</tid>
<number>ii</number>on the assumption that the company and 
any other company or companies are companies to 
which the said sub- section applies,
more than one half of the income of the company 
 (including any income which has been apportioned to it,  
or could on either of those assumptions be apportioned 
  to it, for the purposes of the said sub- section) could 
be apportioned for those purposes among not more than 
five persons.


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1794016</tid>
<number>iii</number>In determining whether a company is or is not under the 
control of not more than five persons, persons who are relatives of 
one another, persons who are nominees of any other persons together 
with that other person, persons in partnership, and persons interested 
in any shares or obligations of the company which are subject to any 
trust or are part of the estate of a deceased person, shall 
respectively be treated as a single person.
Explanation.-- For the purpose of this clause,--


<subsubsubsection><tid>770674</tid>
<number>a</number>the expression" relative" means a husband, wife, 
ancestor, lineal descendant, brother or sister;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>200545</tid>
<number>b</number>a person shall be deemed to be the nominee of another 
person, if, whether directly or indirectly, he 
possesses on behalf of that other person, or may be 
required to exercise on the direction of or on behalf 
of that other person, any right or power which, by 
virtue of any of the provisions of this sub- section, is 
material in determining whether a company is or is not 
to be deemed to be under the control of not more than 
five persons.

</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>664143</tid>
<number>iv</number>An investment company shall be deemed to be under the 
control of not more than five persons if any five or fewer persons 
would, if the company were wound up, be entitled as members or loan 
creditors of the company to receive more than half of the assets of 
the company which would be available for distribution to members and 
loan creditors.

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1592397</tid>
<number>v</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in clause (i), a company 
which is deemed for the purposes of that clause to be under the 
control of not more than five persons shall not be deemed to be a 
subsidiary company, unless it can be deemed to be under the control of

<pagefootnote><pagenum>682</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

not more than five persons only by including among the persons 
mentioned in sub- clause (a), (b) or (c) of clause (ii) or in clause 
 (iv) a company to which the provisions of the said clause (i) do not 
apply and which is not the nominee of any other person.


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1476441</tid>
<number>vi</number>The expression" relevant time" in this sub- section means any 
time during the period ending with the death of the deceased and 
beginning at the date of the disposition, transfer or other 
transaction or <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> event] relevant for the purposes of this Act, or, if 
that disposition, transfer or other transaction or event was one of 
associated operations, at the date of the earliest of those 
operations.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>242205</tid>
<number>5</number>For the purposes of section 34 the deceased shall be deemed 
to have had an interest in the property deemed by virtue of this 
section to be included in the property passing on his death.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1902509</tid>
<number> 18</number> Duty of company and officers of company to give information 
to Controller on death of transferor.
<section><tid>597879</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the deceased has made  
a transfer of property to a controlled company, the company shall be 
under obligation to inform the Controller within forty- five days from 
the date of the death of the deceased, of the death, of the fact that 
the deceased made a transfer of property to the company, and of the 
fact that benefits accrued to the deceased from the company, and every 
person who was a principal officer of the company at that date, or if 
the company has been wound up and dissolved before that date, who was 
a principal officer of the company at any time and who has been called 
upon to furnish any information under this section, shall be under the 
like obligation as respects such of the facts aforesaid as are within 
his knowledge, unless he knows, or has reasonable cause for believing, 
that the information in question has already been given to the 
Controller by the company or some other person.

</section>

<section><tid>888909</tid>
<number>2</number>If the company or any such person as aforesaid who is under 
obligation by virtue of the preceding sub- section to give any 
information to the Controller makes default in the performance of that 
obligation, the Controller may impose upon the defaulter a penalty not 
exceeding one thousand rupees.
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1377346</tid>
<number> 19</number> Collection and incidence of duty under section 17.
<section><tid>1427725</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
following persons shall be accountable for the duty payable on the 
death of the deceased by virtue of section 17, namely:--

<subsection><tid>268811</tid>
<number>a</number>the company;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>683</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 33 of <year>1958</year>, s. 6, for" even" (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1960</year>). 
2 Explanation omitted by s. 7, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1960</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>667086</tid>
<number>b</number>any person (other than a bona fide purchaser for full  
consideration in money or money' s worth received by the 
  company for its own use and benefit) who receives, 
whether directly from the company or otherwise, or 
disposes of, any assets which the company had, whether 
as capital or as income, at the death or at any time 
thereafter;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>408756</tid>
<number>c</number>any person who received any distributed assets of the 
company on their distribution:
Provided that a person shall not,--


<subsubsection><tid>1922246</tid>
<number>i</number>by virtue of clause (b), be accountable in respect of 
any assets for any duty in excess of the value of those 
assets, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1822342</tid>
<number>ii</number>by virtue of clause (c), be accountable in respect of 
any assets for more than a part of the duty bearing to 
the whole thereof the same proportion as the value of 
the distribution of those assets bears to the principal 
value of the assets of the company passing on the death 
by virtue of section 17.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this sub- section the 
expressions" distributed assets" and" assets of the company passing on 
the death" do not include any distributed assets of the company which 
the deceased received on their distribution; and a person who, having 
received any distributed assets of the company, has died before the 
deceased shall be deemed to have been a person accountable by virtue 
of clause (c).


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1878442</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a company incorporated <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> outside India] is accountable 
for any duty by virtue of the preceding sub- section or of this sub- 
section, every person who is a member of that company at the death 
shall also be accountable for a rateable part of that duty in 
proportion to the value of his interest in that company.

</section>

<section><tid>1726020</tid>
<number>3</number>A person accountable for any duty by virtue of this section 
shall, for the purpose of raising and paying the duty, have all the 
powers conferred on accountable parties.

</section>

<section><tid>1205275</tid>
<number>4</number>On a winding up of the company, sub- section (1) of <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> section 
 530 of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>)], shall have effect as if 
there were included in clause (a) of that sub- section a reference to 
any duty
<pagefootnote><pagenum>684</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 33 of <year>1958</year>, s. 8, for" outside the territories to 
which this Act extends" (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1960</year>). 
2 Subs. by s. 8, ibid., for" section 230 of the Indian Companies 
Act, <year>1913</year>" (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1960</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


payable in respect of assets of the company passing on a death by 
virtue of section <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 17] of this Act, and <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> section 123 of the 
Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>)] shall have effect accordingly.


</section>

<section><tid>741360</tid>
<number>5</number>The duty payable on the death of the deceased by virtue of 
section 17 shall be a first charge by way of floating security on the 
assets which the company had at the death or has at any time 
thereafter, and any part of the duty for which by virtue of clause (c) 
of sub- section (1) any person is accountable in respect of any 
distributed assets shall be a first charge also on those assets:
Provided that nothing in this sub- section shall operate to make 
any property chargeable as against a bona fide purchaser thereof for 
valuable consideration without notice.


</section>

<section><tid>1346616</tid>
<number>6</number>Where any duty has been--

<subsection><tid>1121169</tid>
<number>a</number>paid by a person accountable therefor by virtue only of 
clause (c) of sub- section (1); or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>653456</tid>
<number>b</number>raised by virtue of sub- section (5) out of any 
distributed assets charged therewith;
that person or, as the case may be, the person who was entitled to 
those assets subject to the charge, may (without prejudice to any  
right of contribution or indemnity which he may have apart from this 
  sub- section) recover the amount of the duty so paid or raised as 
aforesaid from any person who is accountable therefor otherwise than 
by virtue of the said clause (c).


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>469995</tid>
<number>7</number>No part of the duty paid by the company shall be recoverable 
by it from any person on the ground only that he is entitled to any 
interest in, or to any sum charged on, the assets which the company 
had at the death of the deceased.

</section>

<section><tid>997581</tid>
<number>8</number>The provisions of sub- sections (1) and (3) of section 53 
shall not have effect in relation to the duty payable by virtue of 
section 17.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1938445</tid>
<number> 20</number> Power to make rules respecting controlled companies 
generally.
<section><tid>444403</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board may make rules-- 

<subsection><tid>1670386</tid>
<number>a</number>prescribing the class of dispositions or operations 
which shall be deemed to be transfers to controlled 
companies within the meaning of section 17;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>685</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1957</year>, s. 3 and Sch. II, for" 16". 
2 Subs. by Act 33 of <year>1958</year>, s. 8, for" section 129 of the Indian 
Companies Act, <year>1913</year>," (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1960</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>311584</tid>
<number>b</number>prescribing the matters to be treated as benefits 
accruing to the deceased from any such controlled 
company, the manner in which their amount is to be 
determined, and the time at which they are to be 
treated as accruing;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>12305</tid>
<number>c</number>prescribing the manner in which the net income and the 
value of the assets of any such company are to be 
determined;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1418865</tid>
<number>d</number>prescribing the manner in which the accounting year of 
any such company is to be reckoned;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1803362</tid>
<number>e</number>prescribing the manner in which the shares and 
debentures of any such company passing upon the death 
of the deceased are to be valued for estate duty;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>785341</tid>
<number>f</number>providing an upper limit by reference to the value of 
the property transferred by the deceased to any such 
company and preventing duplication of charge where duty 
would otherwise be payable in respect of both the 
assets of any such company (or a proportion of them) 
and the deceased' s holding of shares and debentures in 
any such company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1918165</tid>
<number>g</number>prescribing the conditions upon which and the extent to 
which transactions in the name of any such company 
shall be deemed to be bona fide transactions for full 
consideration; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>904153</tid>
<number>h</number>generally for the purpose of checking the avoidance of 
estate duty through the machinery of any such company.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>849175</tid>
<number>2</number>All rules made under this section shall be laid before the 
House of the People for not less than fifteen days before the date of 
their final publication.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1340766</tid>
<number>20A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Duty and liability of companies incorporated outside 
India in certain cases. Where a company incorporated outside India 
which carries on business in India has been treated for the purposes 
of the Indian Income- tax Act, <year>1922</year> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>, (11 of <year>1922</year>.) as resident for 
two out of the three completed assessments for the years immediately 
preceding the date of death of any member of or debenture holder in 
the company, the company shall, within three months of the receipt of 
intimation of the death of the member or debenture holder, as the case 
may be, furnish to the controller such particulars as may be 
prescribed in respect of the interest
<pagefootnote><pagenum>686</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 33 of <year>1958</year>, s. 9 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1960</year>). 
2 Now see Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> (43 of <year>1961</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


of the deceased in the company, and the company shall be accountable 
for the estate duty which shall be levied at the rates mentioned in 
Part II of the Second Schedule on the principal value of the shares or 
debentures held by the deceased in the company except in cases where 
the deceased was a person domiciled in India and the person 
accountable under any of the other provisions of this Act has obtained 
a certificate from the Controller showing that either the estate duty 
in respect thereof has been paid or will be paid or that none is due, 
as the case may be.]

PART

EXCEPTIONS FROM THE CHARGE OF DUTY

PART III

EXCEPTIONS FROM THE CHARGE OF DUTY



</article>



<article><tid>1431541</tid>
<number> 21</number> Foreign property.
<section><tid>1497111</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall not be included in the  
property passing on the death of the deceased--

<subsection><tid>886987</tid>
<number>a</number>immovable property situated <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> outside India];

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>328506</tid>
<number>b</number>movable property situated <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> outside India] at the time 
of the death unless--

<subsubsection><tid>1169164</tid>
<number>i</number>in the case of any property, whether 
settled or not, the deceased was domiciled in 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> India] at the time of his death; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1765994</tid>
<number>ii</number>in the case of settled property of which 
the deceased was a life tenant, the settlor was 
domiciled in <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> India] at the date the settlement 
took effect.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>444592</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board may make rules regulating the manner in which the 
nature and locality of different classes of assets shall be determined 
for the purposes of this section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1970684</tid>
<number>22</number>Property held by the deceased as trustee. Property passing on 
the death of the deceased shall not be deemed to include property held 
by the deceased as trustee for another person under a disposition not 
made by the deceased or under a disposition made by the deceased where 
 (whether by virtue of the original disposition or of a subsequent  
surrender of any benefit originally reserved to the deceased or 
  otherwise) possession and enjoyment of the property was bona fide 
assumed by the beneficiary at least <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> two years] before the death and 
thenceforward retained by
<pagefootnote><pagenum>687</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 33 of <year>1958</year>, s. 10, for" outside the territories to 
which this Act extends" (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1960</year>). 
2 Subs. by s. 10, ibid., for" the said territories" (w. e. f. 1- 7-  
  <year>1960</year>). 
3 Subs. by Act 13 of <year>1966</year>, s. 38, for" one year" (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1966</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


him to the entire exclusion of the deceased or of any benefit to the 
deceased by contract or otherwise:

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided that a house or part thereof held by the deceased as 
trustee for another person under a disposition made by him in favour 
of the spouse, son, daughter, brother or sister, shall not be deemed 
to be included in the property passing on the death of the deceased by 
reason only of the residence therein of the deceased except where a 
right of residence therein is reserved or secured directly or 
indirectly to the deceased under the relevant disposition or under any 
collateral disposition.]



</article>



<article><tid>513957</tid>
<number>23</number>Interest failing before becoming an interest in possession. 
In the case of settled property where the interest of any person under 
the settlement fails or determines by reason of his death before it 
becomes an interest in possession, and one or more subsequent 
limitations under the settlement continue to subsist, the property 
shall not be deemed to pass on his death by reason only of the failure 
or determination of that interest.
Explanation 1.-- Where property is settled by a person on himself 
for life and after his death on any other person, with an ultimate 
reversion of an absolute interest or absolute power of disposition to 
the settlor, the property shall not be deemed to pass to the settlor 
on the death of such other person by reason only that the settlor 
being then in possession of the property as tenant for life becomes, 
in consequence of such death, entitled to the immediate reversion or 
acquires an absolute power to dispose of the whole property.

Explanation 2.-- Where the interest of a person in settled 
property consists of an interest in the residue or part of the residue 
of an estate of a testator or intestate and the said estate continues 
to be under administration until the death of the person, the said 
interest of the person in the residue or part of the residue shall be 
deemed to have become an interest in possession on the date as from 
which the income from the residue or part of the residue would have 
been attributable to that interest if the residue had been ascertained 
immediately after the death of the testator or intestate.



</article>



<article><tid>1789344</tid>
<number> 24</number> Property reverting to disponer.
<section><tid>1003247</tid>
<number>1</number>Where by a disposition of  
any property an interest is conferred on any person, other than the 
disponer for the life of
<pagefootnote><pagenum>688</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 10 of <year>1965</year>, s. 69, for the proviso (w. e. f. 1- 4-  
  <year>1965</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


such person or determinable on his death, the remainder being 
conferred upon the disponer absolutely, and such person enters into 
possession of the interest, and thenceforward retains possession of 
it, then, on the death of such person, the property shall not be 
deemed to pass by reason only of its reverter to the disponer in his 
life time.


</section>

<section><tid>1457647</tid>
<number>2</number>Where by a disposition of any property any such interest as 
is mentioned in sub- section (1) is conferred on two or more persons 
either severally or jointly or in succession, sub- section (1) shall 
apply in like manner as where the interest is conferred on one person:
Provided that sub- section (1) shall not apply where such person 
or persons taking the said life or determinable interest had at any 
time prior to the disposition been himself or themselves competent to 
dispose of the said property.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1370995</tid>
<number>25</number>Income of settled property acquired on death of spouse. Where 
a husband or wife is entitled, either solely or jointly with the 
other, to the income of any property settled by the other under a 
disposition which took effect before the commencement of this Act and 
on his or her death the survivor becomes entitled to the income of the 
property (as distinguished from the property itself) settled by such 
survivor, estate duty shall not be payable in respect of that property 
until the death of that survivor.


</article>



<article><tid>510645</tid>
<number> 26</number> Property passing by reason of a bona fide purchase for full 
or partial consideration in money.
<section><tid>668801</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of  
section 27 and section 46 estate duty shall not be payable in respect 
of property passing on the death of the deceased by reason only of a 
bona fide purchase from the person under whose disposition the 
property passes, nor in respect of the falling into possession of the 
reversion on any lease for lives, nor in respect of the determination 
of any annuity for lives, where such purchase was made, or such lease 
or annuity granted, for full consideration in money or money' s worth 
paid to the vendor or grantor for his own use or benefit, or in the 
case of a lease for the use or benefit of any person for whom the 
grantor was a trustee.

</section>

<section><tid>1057234</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any such purchase was made, or lease or annuity 
granted, for partial consideration in money or money' s worth paid to 
the vendor or grantor for his own use or benefit, or in the case of a 
lease for the use or benefit of any person for whom the grantor was a 
trustee, the value of the consideration shall be allowed as a 
deduction from the value of the property for the purpose of estate 
duty.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>688A</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>585229</tid>
<number> 27</number> Dispositions in favour of relatives.
<section><tid>1605960</tid>
<number>1</number>Any disposition made  
by the deceased in favour of a relative of his shall be treated for 
the purposes of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> this Act] as a gift unless--

<subsection><tid>1495752</tid>
<number>a</number>the disposition was made on the part of the deceased for 
full consideration in money or money' s worth paid to 
him for his own use or benefit; or
<pagefootnote><pagenum>689</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 33 of <year>1958</year>, s. 11, for" section 9" (w. e. f. 1- 7-  
  <year>1960</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1157358</tid>
<number>b</number>the deceased was concerned in a fiduciary capacity 
imposed on him otherwise than by a disposition made by 
him and in such a capacity only; and references to a 
gift in this Act shall be construed accordingly:
Provided that where the disposition was made on the part of the 
deceased for partial consideration in money or money' s worth paid to 
him for his own use or benefit, the value of the consideration shall 
be allowed as a deduction from the value of the property for the 
purpose of estate duty.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>392532</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the deceased has made a disposition of property in 
favour of a relative of his, the creation or disposition in favour of 
the deceased of an annuity or other interest limited to cease on the 
death of the deceased or of any other person shall not be treated for 
the purposes of this section as consideration for the disposition made 
by the deceased.

</section>

<section><tid>67365</tid>
<number>3</number>If a controlled company was concerned in a transaction in 
relation to which it is claimed that the provisions of clause (a) of 
or the proviso to sub- section (1) have effect, those provisions shall 
have effect in relation thereto if and only if, and to the extent only 
to which, the Controller is satisfied that those provisions would have 
had effect in the following circumstances, namely, if the assets of 
the company had been held by it on trust for the members thereof and 
any other person to whom it is under any liability incurred otherwise 
than for the purposes of the business of the company wholly and 
exclusively, in accordance with the rights attaching to the shares in 
and debentures of the company and the terms on which any such 
liability was incurred, and if the company had acted in the capacity 
of a trustee only with power to carry on the business of the company 
and to employ the assets of the company therein.

</section>

<section><tid>1440920</tid>
<number>4</number>Any gift made in favour of a relative of the deceased by a 
controlled company of which the deceased at the time of the gift had 
control within the meaning of section 17 shall be treated for the 
purposes of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> this Act] as a gift made by the deceased, and the 
property taken under the gift, shall be treated as included by virtue 
of that section in the property passing on the death of the deceased, 
if and to the extent to which the Controller is satisfied that they 
would fall to be so treated in the circumstances mentioned in the last 
foregoing sub- section.

</section>

<section><tid>1922012</tid>
<number>5</number>If the deceased has made in favour of a controlled company a 
disposition which, if it had been made in favour of a relative of
<pagefootnote><pagenum>690</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 33 of <year>1958</year>, s. 11, for" section 9" (w. e. f. 1- 7-  
  <year>1960</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


his, would have fallen within sub- section (2), this section shall have 
effect in like manner as if the disposition had been made in favour of 
a relative of his, unless it is shown to the satisfaction of the 
Controller that no relative of the deceased was, at the time of the 
disposition or subsequently during the life of the deceased, a member 
of the company.

Explanation.-- For the purposes of this sub- section a person who 
is, or is deemed by virtue of this provision to be, a member of a 
controlled company which is a member of another such company shall be 
deemed to be a member of that other company.


</section>

<section><tid>1786915</tid>
<number>6</number>Where there have been associated operations effected with 
reference to the receiving by the deceased of any payment in respect 
of such an annuity or other interest as is mentioned in sub- section 
 (2), or effected with a view to enabling him to receive or to 
facilitating the receipt by him of any such payment, this section 
shall have effect in relation to each of those associated operations 
as it has effect in relation to the creation or disposition in favour 
of the deceased of such an annuity or other interest.

</section>

<section><tid>334445</tid>
<number>7</number>In this section--

<subsection><tid>1653689</tid>
<number>i</number>" relative" means, in relation to the deceased,--

<subsubsection><tid>465957</tid>
<number>a</number>the wife or husband of the deceased,

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>803613</tid>
<number>b</number>the father, mother, children, uncles and aunts 
of the deceased, and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1644352</tid>
<number>c</number>any issue of any person falling within either 
of the preceding sub- clauses and the other party to a 
marriage with any such person or issue;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1238186</tid>
<number>ii</number>reference to" children" and" issue" include reference 
to illegitimate children and to adopted children;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>986065</tid>
<number>iii</number>" annuity" includes any series of payments, whether 
interconnected or not, whether of the same or of 
varying amounts, and whether payable at regular 
intervals or otherwise, and payments of dividends or 
interests on shares in or debentures of a company shall 
be treated for the purposes of this section as a series 
of payments constituting an annuity limited to cease on 
a death if the payments are liable to cease on the 
death, or the amounts thereof are liable to be reduced 
on the death, by reason directly or indirectly of the 
extinguishment or any alteration of rights attaching 
to, or of the issue of any shares in or debentures of a 
company;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>691</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1591664</tid>
<number>iv</number>" associated operations" means any two or more 
operations of any kind being--

<subsubsection><tid>1910170</tid>
<number>a</number>operations which affect the same property, or 
one of which affects some property and the other or 
others of which affect property which represents, 
whether directly or indirectly, that property, or 
income arising from that property, or any property 
representing accumulations of any such income; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1983855</tid>
<number>b</number>any two operations of which one is effected 
with reference to the other, or with a view to enabling 
it to be effected or to facilitating its being 
effected, and any third operation having a like 
relation to either of those two, and any fourth 
operation having a like relation to any of those three, 
and so on;
whether those operations are effected by the same person or 
by different persons, whether they are connected otherwise 
than as aforesaid or not, and whether they are 
contemporaneous or any of them precedes or follows any 
other.




</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1164311</tid>
<number> 28</number> Effect of new or increased rates of duty on certain prior 
sales and mortgages. Where an interest in expectancy in any property 
has, whether before or after the commencement of this Act, been bona 
fide sold or mortgaged for full consideration in money or money' s 
worth, and the rates of estate duty in force in the case of a person 
dying when the interest falls into possession are higher than the 
rates in force, if any, in the case of a person dying at the time of 
the sale or mortgage, then--
<section><tid>1390096</tid>
<number>a</number>no other duty on that property shall be payable by the 
purchaser or mortgagee when the interest falls into 
possession than the duty, if any, which would have been 
payable if the rates of estate duty applicable had been 
the rates in force, if any, in the case of a person 
dying at the time of the sale, or mortgage, and

</section>

<section><tid>1151035</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of a mortgage, any higher duty payable by 
the mortgagor shall rank as a charge subsequent to that 
of the mortgagee.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1968264</tid>
<number>29</number>Settled property in respect of which since the date of the 
settlement estate duty has been paid on the death of the deceased' s 
spouse. If estate duty has already been paid in respect of any settled 
property since the date of the settlement, on the death of one of the 
parties to a marriage, the estate duty shall not be payable in respect 
thereof on the death of the other party to the marriage,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>692</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

unless the latter was at the time of his death, or had been at any 
time during the continuance of the settlement, competent to dispose of 
such property, and, if on his death subsequent limitations under the 
settlement take effect in respect of such property, was sui juris at 
the time of his death, or had been sui juris at any time while so 
competent to dispose of the property.



</article>



<article><tid>1609373</tid>
<number> 29A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Exemption of pensions, etc., in certain cases. Estate 
duty shall not be payable in respect of--
<section><tid>1924372</tid>
<number>a</number>any pension accruing or arising on the death of the 
deceased to his widow or other dependants under the 
revised Pension Rules of the Central Government or 
under any similar scheme of a State Government, a local 
authority or a corporation established by a Central, 
State or Provincial Act, or under the New Pension Code 
applicable to the members of the Defence Services; or

</section>

<section><tid>968117</tid>
<number>b</number>any annuity or pension payable to such widow or 
dependants from--

<subsection><tid>1268394</tid>
<number>i</number>a superannuation fund approved under the 
Indian Income- tax Act, <year>1922</year>, (11 of <year>1922</year>) or the 
Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year>, (43 of <year>1961</year>) to the extent to 
which the amount of such annuity or pension does not 
exceed the equivalent of fifteen thousand rupees per 
annum, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>845243</tid>
<number>ii</number>a superannuation or pension fund established 
by such international organisations as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, specify in this behalf.]



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1107253</tid>
<number>30</number>Agreement for avoidance or relief of double taxation with 
respect to estate duty. The Central Government may enter into an 
agreement with the Government of any reciprocating country for the 
avoidance or relief of double taxation with respect to estate duty 
leviable under this Act and under the corresponding law in force in 
the reciprocating country and may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, make such provision as may be necessary for implementing the 
agreement.
Explanation.-- The expression" reciprocating country" for the 
purposes of this Act means any country which the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare to be a 
reciprocating country.



</article>



<article><tid>445862</tid>
<number>31</number>Allowance for quick succession to property. Where the Board 
is satisfied that estate duty has become payable on any property 
passing upon the death of any person, and
<pagefootnote><pagenum>693</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 10 of <year>1965</year>, s. 69 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


that subsequently within five years estate duty has again become 
payable on the same property or any part thereof passing on the death 
of the person to whom the property passed on the first death, the 
amount of estate duty payable on the second death in respect of the 
property so passing shall be reduced as follows:--

Where the second death occurs within one year of the first death, 
by fifty per cent.;

Where the second death occurs within two years of the first 
death, by forty per cent.;

Where the second death occurs within three years of the first 
death, by thirty per cent.;

Where the second death occurs within four years of the first 
death, by twenty per cent.;

Where the second death occurs within five years of the first 
death, by ten per cent.:

Provided that where the value on which the duty is payable of the 
property on the second death exceeds the value on which the duty was 
payable of the property on the first death, the latter value shall be 
substituted for the former for the purpose of calculating the amount 
of duty on which the reduction under this section is to be calculated.

Explanation 1.-- For the purposes of this section every death 
shall be deemed to be a second death in relation to the death 
immediately preceding.

Explanation 2.-- In computing any period for the purposes of this 
section, deaths occurring within a period of three months after the 
death of any person in respect of whose property estate duty has 
become payable, shall be treated as one death, and no estate duty 
shall again be payable on the same property by reason of the 
subsequent deaths occurring within the said period of three months.



</article>



<article><tid>666286</tid>
<number>32</number>Exemption of interest of a Hindu widow devolving upon 
reversioners in certain cases. Where on the death of any person 
governed by any school of Hindu law, his interest in any property has 
devolved on his widow, then, if the widow dies within seven years of 
her husband' s death and the interest aforesaid devolves upon the 
reversioners or any of them, no estate duty shall be leviable in 
respect of the passing of the interest aforesaid on the death of the 
widow, if and in so far as estate duty had been paid in respect of the 
passing of such interest on the death of her husband.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>694</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>318232</tid>
<number> 33</number> Exemptions.
<section><tid>1559807</tid>
<number>1</number>To the extent specified against each of the  
clauses in this sub- section, no estate duty shall be payable in 
respect of property of any of the following kinds belonging to the 
deceased which passes on his death--

<subsection><tid>1531402</tid>
<number>a</number>property taken <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> under one or more gifts] made by the 
deceased for a public charitable purpose within a 
period of six months before his death, to the extent of 
rupees two thousand and five hundred in value;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>131154</tid>
<number>b</number>property taken <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> under one or more gifts] made by the 
deceased for any other purpose within a period of 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> two years] before his death, to the extent of rupees 
one thousand and five hundred in value;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1488726</tid>
<number>c</number>household goods, including tools of artisans, 
agricultural implements or any other tools or 
implements as were necessary to the deceased to enable 
him to earn his livelihood, to the extent of rupees two 
thousand and five hundred in value;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1755995</tid>
<number>d</number>books not intended for sale;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>92554</tid>
<number>e</number>wearing apparel, but not including any precious or 
semiprecious stones or ornaments worked or sewn into 
the wearing apparel;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1410882</tid>
<number>f</number>moneys payable under one or more policies of insurance 
effected by the deceased on his life for the purpose of 
paying estate duty or assigned to the Government for 
the said purpose, to the extent of the amount of duty 
payable <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>898595</tid>
<number>g</number>moneys deposited with the Government in such manner as 
may be prescribed for the purpose of paying estate 
duty, together with the interest which has accrued due 
thereon at such rate as may be prescribed, to the 
extent of the amount of duty payable <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>:
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Provided that the moneys in respect whereof no 
estate duty shall be payable either under clause (f) or 
clause (g) or under both shall not exceed rupees fifty 
thousand in the aggregate;]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>695</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 33 of <year>1958</year>, s. 12, for" under a gift" (w. e. f. 1- 7-  
  <year>1960</year>). 
2 Subs. by Act 13 of <year>1966</year>, s. 38, for" one year" (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1966</year>). 
3 The words" but not exceeding rupees fifty thousand" omitted by 
Act 17 of <year>1954</year>, s. 4 (with retrospective effect). 
4 Ins. by s. 4, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1459396</tid>
<number>h</number>moneys payable under one or more policies of insurance 
effected by the deceased on his life, to the extent of 
rupees five thousand;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>161391</tid>
<number>i</number>drawings, paintings, prints, manuscripts, works of art 
or archaeological or scientific collections which are 
of national, scientific or historical interest and 
which are retained in the family of the deceased and 
dealt with or disposed of in accordance with such 
conditions as the Board may prescribe, or which are 
given absolutely or bequeathed to Government or to any 
University or other public institution;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>285467</tid>
<number>j</number>drawings, paintings, photographs, prints, manuscripts 
and any other heir- loom, not falling within clause (i), 
which are retained in the family of the deceased and 
are dealt with or disposed of in accordance with such 
conditions as the Board may prescribe and are not 
intended for sale;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>25638</tid>
<number>k</number>moneys earmarked under policies of insurance or 
declarations of trust or settlements effected or made 
by a deceased parent or natural guardian for the 
marriage of any of his female relatives dependent upon 
him for the necessaries of life, to the extent of 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> rupees ten thousand] in respect of the marriage of 
each of such relatives;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1759564</tid>
<number>l</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> any one building in the occupation of a Ruler 
declared by the Central Government as his official 
residence under Paragraph 13 of the Merged States 
 (Taxation Concessions) Order, <year>1949</year>, or Paragraph 15 of 
the Part B States (Taxation Concessions) Order, <year>1950</year>;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1515039</tid>
<number>m</number>property belonging to the deceased who was a member of 
the armed forces of the Union and who was killed in 
action during operations against an enemy;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1903740</tid>
<number>mm</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> property belonging to the deceased who was a member 
of any police force (including a border security force) 
and was killed in any action in protecting the border;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>645108</tid>
<number>n</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> one house or part thereof exclusively used by the 
deceased for his residence, to the extent the principal 
value
<pagefootnote><pagenum>696</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 33 of <year>1958</year>, s. 12, for" rupees five thousand" 
 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1960</year>). 
2 Ins. by s. 12, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1960</year>). 
3 Ins. by Act 13 of <year>1966</year>, s. 38 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
4 Ins. by Act 5 of <year>1964</year>, s. 49 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1964</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


thereof does not exceed rupees one lakh if such house 
is situate in a place with a population exceeding ten 
thousand, and the full principal value thereof in any 
other case;]


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1227225</tid>
<number>nn</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> any deposits with a co- operative society, being a 
co- operative housing society, made by the deceased who 
was a member of the society to whom a building or part 
thereof was allotted or leased under a house building 
scheme of the society, where such deposits had been 
made under such scheme;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1780231</tid>
<number>o</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> property taken under any gift made by the deceased to 
the spouse, son, daughter, brother or sister, beyond a 
period of five years before his death:
Provided that the property is either chargeable to 
gift- tax under the Gift- tax Act, <year>1958</year>, (18 of <year>1958</year>) or 
is not chargeable under section 5 of that Act, for any 
assessment year commencing after the 31st day of March, 
<year>1964</year>;]


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>408584</tid>
<number>p</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> National Defence Gold Bonds, <year>1980</year>, to the extent of 
the principal value of such Bonds for an aggregate 
weight of fifty kilogrammes of gold:
Provided that if such Bonds had passed on the 
death of any person, the exemption conferred by this 
clause shall not be available in respect of the same 
Bonds passing on any subsequent death.]


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>336732</tid>
<number>2</number>If the Central Government is of opinion that in respect of 
any class of property or class of persons the circumstances are such 
that some relief in addition to the reliefs provided in sub- section 
 (1) should be given, it may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
make any exemption, reduction in rate or other modification in respect 
of estate duty in favour of any such class of property or the whole or 
any part of the property of any class of persons, and any notification 
so issued shall be laid before both Houses of Parliament as soon as 
may be after it is issued.
PART

AGGREGATION OF PROPERTY AND RATES OF DUTY

PART IV

AGGREGATION OF PROPERTY AND RATES OF DUTY




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>156640</tid>
<number> 34</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Aggregation.
<section><tid>1326367</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purpose of determining the rate  
of the estate duty to be paid on any property passing on the death of 
the deceased,

<subsection><tid>829440</tid>
<number>a</number>all property so passing other than property exempted 
from estate duty under clauses (c), (d), (e), (i), (j), 
 (l) <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>, (m), <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> (mm)]], <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> (n), (o) and (p)] of sub- section (1) of 
section 33;[ and] <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>
<pagefootnote><pagenum>696A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 10 of <year>1965</year>, s. 69 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
2 Ins. by Act 41 of <year>1965</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 4- 12- <year>1965</year>). 
3 Subs. by Act 33 of <year>1958</year>, s. 13, for s. 34 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1960</year>). 
4 Subs. by Act 5 of <year>1964</year>, s. 49, for" (l) and (m)" (w. e. f. 1- 4-  
  <year>1964</year>). 
5 Ins. by Act 31 of <year>1982</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 1- 3- <year>1981</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1264354</tid>
<number>c</number>in the case of property so passing which consists of a 
coparcenary interest in the joint family property of a 
Hindu family governed by the Mitakshara, 
Marumakkattayam or Aliyasantana law, also the interests 
in the joint family property of all the lineal 
descendants of the deceased member;
shall be aggregated so as to form one estate and estate duty shall be 
levied thereon at the rate or rates applicable in respect of the 
principal value thereof.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>556423</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any such estate as is referred to in sub- section (1) 
includes any property exempt from estate duty, the estate duty 
leviable on the property not so exempt shall be an amount bearing to 
the total amount of duty which would have been payable on the whole 
estate had no part of it been so exempt, the same proportion as the 
value of the property not so exempt bears to the value of the whole 
estate.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this sub- section," property 
exempt from estate duty" means--


<subsection><tid>179851</tid>
<number>i</number>any property which is exempt from estate duty under 
section 33;
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>685995</tid>
<number>iii</number>the interests of all coparceners other than the 
deceased in the joint family property of a Hindu family 
governed by the Mitakshara, Marumakkattayam or 
Aliyasantana law.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>202477</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1) or sub- 
section (2), any property passing in which the deceased never had an 
interest, not being a right or debt or benefit that is treated as 
property by virtue of the Explanations to clause (15) of section 2, 
shall not be aggregated with any property, but shall be an estate by 
itself, and the estate duty shall be levied at the rate or rates 
applicable in respect of the principal value thereof.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>696B</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 13 of <year>1966</year>, s. 38 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>). 
2 Subs. by Act 41 of <year>1965</year>, s. 5, for" (n) and (o)" (w. e. f. 4- 12-  
  <year>1965</year>). 
3 Ins. by Act 53 of <year>1984</year>, s. 4. 
4 Omitted by s. 4, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>126641</tid>
<number>4</number>Every estate shall include all income accrued upon the 
property included therein down to and outstanding at the date of the 
death of the deceased.

</section>

<section><tid>1546793</tid>
<number>5</number>For the purposes of this section, no property shall be 
aggregated more than once nor shall estate duty in respect thereof be 
levied more than once on the same death.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1404055</tid>
<number> 35</number> Rates of estate duty on property including agricultural land.

<section><tid>59032</tid>
<number>1</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The rates of estate duty shall be as mentioned in the Second  
Schedule.]
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>


</section>

<section><tid>299033</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1) and the 
Second Schedule, where any property passing on the death of any person 
consists wholly or in part of agricultural land and the principal 
value of the estate does not exceed rupees two lakhs, there shall be 
allowed by way of rebate--

<subsection><tid>1877096</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of an estate which consists wholly of 
agricultural land, a sum representing one- fourth of the 
estate duty payable; and
<pagefootnote><pagenum>697</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 33 of <year>1958</year>, s. 14, for sub- section (1)  (w. e. f. 1- 7-  
  <year>1960</year>). 
2 Sub- section (2) omitted by s. 14, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1960</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>195984</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of an estate which consists in part only of 
agricultural land, a sum representing one- fourth of the 
estate duty payable on that part of the estate which 
consists of agricultural land, the duty on such part 
being a sum which bears to the total amount of estate 
duty the same proportion as the value of the 
agricultural land bears to the value of the estate.
PART

VALUE CHARGEABLE

PART V

VALUE CHARGEABLE




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>271103</tid>
<number> 36</number> Principal value how to be estimated.
<section><tid>1375872</tid>
<number>1</number>The principal value  
of any property shall be estimated to be the price which, in the 
opinion of the Controller it would fetch if sold in the open market at 
the time of the deceased' s death.

</section>

<section><tid>1697358</tid>
<number>2</number>In estimating the principal value under this section the 
Controller shall fix the price of the property according to the market 
price at the time of the deceased' s death and shall not make any 
reduction in the estimate on account of the estimate being made on the 
assumption that the whole property is to be placed on the market at 
one and the same time:
Provided that where it is proved to the satisfaction of the 
Controller that the value of the property has depreciated by reason of 
the death of the deceased, the depreciation shall be taken into 
account in fixing the price.


</section>

<section><tid>1186417</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1) or 
sub- section (2), the principal value of one residential house or part 
thereof belonging to the deceased (which the accountable person may at  
  his option specify in writing in this behalf) shall be.--

<subsection><tid>36269</tid>
<number>a</number>where the value of such house or part is included in 
computing the net wealth of the deceased for the purposes of 
making an assessment under the Wealth- tax Act, <year>1957</year> (27 of <year>1957</year>) 
 (hereafter in this sub- section referred to as the Wealth- tax Act) 
in respect of his net wealth on the valuation date immediately 
preceding the date of his death, the value as taken by the 
Wealth- tax Officer for the purposes of such assessment; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>580850</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, the value of such house or part,--

<subsubsection><tid>1892707</tid>
<number>i</number>on the said valuation date; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1643677</tid>
<number>ii</number>where such house or part was constructed, 
acquired or otherwise became the property of the 
deceased after the said valuation date, on the date of 
his death,
as determined by the Controller in accordance with the provisions of 
the Wealth- tax Act and the rules made thereunder; and, for this 
purpose, in a case where the provisions of sub- section (4) of section 
 7 of that Act apply, the provisions of that sub- section shall have 
effect as if the words" throughout the period of twelve months 
immediately preceding the valuation date", occurring therein, had been 
omitted and as if the references therein to the option of the assessee 
had been references to the option of the accountable person.

Explanation 1.-- Where the value adopted to be the value of a 
house or part in accordance with the provisions of clause (a) of this 
sub- section is subsequently varied by an order in any proceeding under 
the Wealth- tax Act, the value as so adopted shall be deemed to be a 
mistake apparent from the record within the meaning of section 61 and 
the Controller shall rectify the order, if any, passed by him, by 
substituting for the value as so adopted the value as so varied and 
the provisions of the said section shall apply accordingly, the period 
of five years specified in that section being reckoned from the date 
of the order under the Wealth- tax Act varying the value of the house 
or part.

Explanation 2.-- For the purposes of this sub- section, the 
expressions" net wealth"," valuation date" and" Wealth- tax Officer" 
shall have the same meanings as in the Wealth- tax Act.]




</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>873142</tid>
<number>37</number>Valuation of shares in a private company where alienation is 
restricted. Where the articles of association of a private company 
contain restrictive provisions as to the alienation of shares, the 
value of the shares, if not ascertainable by reference to the value of 
the total assets of the company, shall be estimated to be what they 
would fetch if they could be sold in the open market on the terms of 
the purchaser being entitled to be registered as holder subject to the 
articles, but the fact that a special buyer would for his own special 
reasons give a higher price than the price in the open market shall be 
disregarded.


</article>



<article><tid>1305204</tid>
<number> 38</number> Valuation of interests in expectancy. Where an estate 
includes an interest in expectancy, estate duty in respect of that 
interest shall be paid, at the option of the person accountable for 
the duty, either with the duty in respect of the rest of the estate or 
when the interest falls into possession, and if the duty is not paid 
with the estate duty in respect of the rest of the estate, then--
<section><tid>1994825</tid>
<number>a</number>for the purpose of determining the rate of estate duty 
in respect of the rest of the estate, the value of the 
interest
<pagefootnote><pagenum>698</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 31 of <year>1982</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 1- 3- <year>1981</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


shall be its value at the date of the death of the 
deceased; and


</section>

<section><tid>497574</tid>
<number>b</number>the rate of estate duty in respect of the interest when 
it falls into possession shall be calculated according 
to its value when it falls into possession, together 
with the value of the rest of the estate as previously 
ascertained.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1868746</tid>
<number> 39</number> Valuation of interest in coparcenary property ceasing on 
death.
<section><tid>946231</tid>
<number>1</number>The value of the benefit accruing or arising from the  
cesser of a coparcenary interest in any joint family property governed 
by the Mitakshara school of Hindu law which ceases on the death of a 
member thereof shall be the principal value of the share in the joint 
family property which would have been allotted to the deceased had 
there been a partition immediately before his death.

</section>

<section><tid>314604</tid>
<number>2</number>The value of the benefit accruing or arising from the cesser 
of an interest in the property of a tarwad or tavazhi governed by the 
Marumakkattayam rule of inheritance or of a kutumba or kavaru governed 
by the Aliyasantana rule of inheritance which ceases on the death of a 
member thereof shall be the principal value of the share in the 
property of the tarwad or tavazhi or, as the case may be, the kutumba 
or kavaru which would have been allotted to the deceased had a 
partition taken place immediately before his death.

</section>

<section><tid>1187393</tid>
<number>3</number>For the purpose of estimating the principal value of the 
joint family property of a Hindu family governed by the Mitakshara, 
Marumakkattayam or Aliyasantana law in order to arrive at the share 
which would have been allotted to the deceased had a partition taken 
place immediately before his death, the provisions of this Act, so far 
as may be, shall apply as they would have applied if the whole of the 
joint family property had belonged to the deceased.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1343998</tid>
<number> 40</number> Valuation of benefits from interests ceasing on death. The 
value of the benefit accruing or arising from the cesser of an 
interest ceasing on the death of the deceased shall--
<section><tid>1741035</tid>
<number>a</number>if the interest extended to the whole income of the 
property, be the principal value of that property; and

</section>

<section><tid>868011</tid>
<number>b</number>if the interest extended to less than the whole income 
of the property, be the principal value of an addition 
to the property equal to the income to which the 
interest extended.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1744502</tid>
<number>41</number>Valuation to be made by the Controller. Subject to the 
provisions of this Act, the value of any property for the purpose of 
estate duty shall be ascertained by the Controller in such manner and 
by such means as may be prescribed and if he authorises a person to 
inspect any property and to report the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>699</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

value thereof for the purposes of this Act, that person may enter upon 
the property and inspect it at such reasonable times as may be 
prescribed.



</article>



<article><tid>1031199</tid>
<number>42</number>Costs of valuation. Where the Controller requires any person 
to report on the value of any property for the purposes of this Act, 
the reasonable costs of such valuation shall be defrayed by the 
Controller.


</article>



<article><tid>1546018</tid>
<number>43</number>Controller may accept and certify valuation when convenient. 
The Controller on application from a person accountable for the duty 
on any property forming part of an estate shall, where he considers 
that it can conveniently be done, certify the amount of the valuation 
accepted by him for any class or description of property forming part 
of such estate.
PART

DEDUCTIONS

PART VI

DEDUCTIONS



</article>



<article><tid>1104171</tid>
<number> 44</number> Reasonable funeral expenses and, with some exceptions, debts 
and incumbrances to be allowed for in determining chargeable value of 
estate. In determining the value of an estate for the purpose of 
estate duty, allowance shall be made for funeral expenses (not  
  exceeding rupees one thousand) and for debts and incumbrances: but an 
allowance shall not be made--
<section><tid>138514</tid>
<number>a</number>for debts incurred by the deceased, or incumbrances 
created by a disposition made by the deceased, unless, 
subject to the provisions of section 27, such debts or 
incumbrances were incurred or created bona fide for 
full consideration in money or money' s worth wholly for 
the deceased' s own use and benefit and take effect out 
of his interest, or

</section>

<section><tid>650577</tid>
<number>b</number>for any debt in respect whereof there is right to 
reimbursement from any other estate or person, unless 
such reimbursement cannot be obtained, or

</section>

<section><tid>833961</tid>
<number>c</number>more than once for the same debt or incumbrance charged 
upon different portions of the estate, or

</section>

<section><tid>1078351</tid>
<number>d</number>for debts incurred by or on behalf of the deceased by 
way of dower, to the extent to which such debts are in 
excess of rupees five thousand,
and any debt or incumbrance for which an allowance is made shall be 
deducted from the value of the property liable thereto.

Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section," funeral 
expenses" include all expenses which may have to be incurred in 
connection with the sraddha or barsi ceremonies of the deceased for a 
period of one year from his death.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>700</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1105213</tid>
<number> 45</number> Limitations on debts deductible. Where a debt or incumbrance 
has been incurred or created in whole or in part for the purpose of or 
in consideration for the purchase or acquisition or extinction, 
whether by operation of law or otherwise of any interest in expectancy 
in any property passing or deemed to pass on the death of the deceased 
and any person whose interest in expectancy is so purchased, acquired, 
or extinguished becomes (under any disposition made by or through  
  devolution of law from, or under the intestacy of, the deceased) 
entitled to any interest in that property, then in determining the 
value of the estate of the deceased for the purpose of estate duty no 
allowance shall be made in respect of such debt or incumbrance, and 
any property charged with any such debt or incumbrance shall be deemed 
to pass freed from that debt or incumbrance:
Provided that--

<section><tid>1753143</tid>
<number>a</number>if part only of such debt or incumbrance was incurred or 
created for such purpose or as such consideration as 
aforesaid, this provision shall apply to that part of 
such debt or incumbrance only; and

</section>

<section><tid>1820091</tid>
<number>b</number>if a person whose interest in expectancy in the property 
so purchased, acquired or extinguished becomes entitled 
to an interest in part only of that property, this 
provision shall apply only to such part of the debt or 
incumbrance as bears the same proportion to the whole 
debt or incumbrance as the value of the part of the 
property to an interest in which he becomes entitled 
bears to the value of the whole of that property.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>3909</tid>
<number> 46</number> Further limitations.
<section><tid>1128210</tid>
<number>1</number>Any allowance which, but for this  
provision, would be made under section 44 for a debt incurred by the 
deceased as mentioned in clause (a) of that section, or for an 
incumbrance created by a disposition made by the deceased as therein 
mentioned, shall be subject to abatement to an extent proportionate to 
the value of any of the consideration given therefor which consisted 
of--

<subsection><tid>1657515</tid>
<number>a</number>property derived from the deceased; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>309324</tid>
<number>b</number>consideration not being such property as aforesaid, but 
given by any person who was at any time entitled to, or 
amongst whose resources there was at any time included, 
any property derived from the deceased:
Provided that if, where the whole or a part of the consideration 
given consisted of such consideration as is mentioned in clause (b) of 
this sub- section, it is proved to the satisfaction of the Controller 
that the value of the consideration given, or of that part thereof,


<pagefootnote><pagenum>701</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

as the case may be, exceeded that which could have been rendered 
available by application of all the property derived from the 
deceased, other than such (if any) of that property as is included in 
the consideration given or as to which the like facts are proved in 
relation to the giving of the consideration as are mentioned in the 
proviso to sub- section (1) of section 16 in relation to the purchase 
or provision of an annuity or other interest, no abatement shall be 
made in respect of the excess.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>221834</tid>
<number>2</number>Money or money' s worth paid or applied by the deceased in or 
towards satisfaction or discharge of a debt or incumbrance in the case 
of which sub- section (1) would have had effect on his death if the 
debt or incumbrance had not been satisfied or discharged, or in 
reduction of a debt or incumbrance in the case of which that sub- 
section has effect on his death, shall, unless so paid or applied 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> two years] before the death, be treated as property deemed to be 
included in the property passing on the death and estate duty shall, 
notwithstanding anything in section <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> 26], be payable in respect 
thereof accordingly.

</section>

<section><tid>1400972</tid>
<number>3</number>The provisions of sub- section (2) of section 16 shall have 
effect for the purpose of this section as they have effect for the 
purpose of that section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1124715</tid>
<number>47</number>Debts to persons resident in foreign country not to be 
deducted in first instance except from duty- paid property in that 
country. An allowance shall not be made in the first instance for 
debts due from the deceased to persons resident <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> out of India] 
 (unless contracted to be paid in <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> India] or charged on properties  
  situate within <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> India]) except out of the value of any property of 
the deceased situate out of <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> India] in respect of which estate duty 
is paid; and there shall be no repayment of estate duty in respect of 
any such debts, except to the extent to which it is shown to the 
satisfaction of the Controller that the property of the deceased 
situate in the foreign country in which the person to whom such debts 
are due resides is insufficient for their payment.


</article>



<article><tid>719168</tid>
<number>48</number>Cost of realising or administering foreign property may be 
allowed for within certain limits. Where the Controller is satisfied 
that any additional expense in administering or in realising property 
has been incurred by reason
<pagefootnote><pagenum>702</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 13 of <year>1966</year>, s. 38, for" one year" (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1966</year>). 
2 Subs. by Act 33 of <year>1958</year>, s. 15, for" 25" (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1960</year>). 
3 Subs. by s. 16, ibid., for" out of the territories to which this 
Act extends" (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1960</year>). 
4 Subs. by s. 16, ibid., for" the said territories" (w. e. f. 1- 7-  
  <year>1960</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


of the property being situate <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> out of India], he may make an 
allowance from the value of the property on account of such expense 
not exceeding in any case five per cent. on the value of the property.



</article>



<article><tid>259867</tid>
<number>49</number>Allowance for duty paid in a non- reciprocating country. Where 
any property passing on the death of the deceased is situate in a non- 
reciprocating country and the Controller is satisfied that by reason 
of such death any duty is payable in that country in respect of that 
property, he may, subject to such rules as may be made by the Board in 
this behalf, make an allowance of the whole or any part of the amount 
of that duty from the value of the property.
Explanation.-- In this section, the expression" non- reciprocating 
country" means any country other than India which has not been 
declared to be a reciprocating country for the purposes of this Act.



</article>



<article><tid>1250823</tid>
<number>50</number>Relief from estate duty where court- fees have been paid for 
obtaining representation to estate of deceased. Where any fees have 
been paid under any law relating to court- fees in force in any State 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> for obtaining probate, letters of administration or a succession 
certificate in respect of any property on which estate duty is 
leviable under this Act, the amount of the estate duty payable shall 
be reduced by <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> an amount which is equal to <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>] the court- fees so 
paid.


</article>



<article><tid>1344943</tid>
<number>50A</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Relief from estate duty where gift- tax has been paid. 
Where tax has been paid under the Gift- tax Act, <year>1958</year>, (18 of <year>1958</year>) in 
respect of a gift of any property and the property is also included in 
the estate of the donor as property passing under this Act, then, 
notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, the estate duty 
payable under this Act shall be reduced by an amount equal to the 
amount of gift- tax paid in respect of any such property under that 
Act.]


</article>



<article><tid>1796129</tid>
<number>50B</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Relief from estate duty where tax has been paid on 
capital gains. Where any property on which estate duty is leviable 
under this Act is transferred within a period of two years following 
the death of the deceased and tax under the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> (43  
  of <year>1961</year>) has
<pagefootnote><pagenum>702A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 33 of <year>1958</year>, s. 17, for" out of the territories to 
which this Act extends" (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1960</year>). 
2 The words" other than the State of Jammu and Kashmir" omitted by 
Act 41 of <year>1954</year>, s. 2 (2) and Sch. 
3 Subs. by Act 33 of <year>1958</year>, s. 18, for" an amount which is equal to" 
 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1960</year>). 
4 The words" one- half of" omitted by Act 5 of <year>1964</year>, s. 49 (w. e. f.  
  1- 4- <year>1964</year>). 
5 Ins. by Act 33 of <year>1958</year>, s. 19 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1960</year>). 
6 Ins. by Act 31 of <year>1964</year>, s. 19 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1964</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


been paid in respect of the capital gains arising from such transfer, 
the estate duty payable shall be reduced by a sum which bears to the 
total amount of tax so paid the same proportion as the amount paid 
towards estate duty out of the proceeds of the transfer bears to the 
gross proceeds of such transfer:

Provided that the Board may, on an application of the accountable 
person, extend the period of two years aforesaid if it is satisfied 
that the accountable person had sufficient cause for not effecting the 
transfer of the property within that period.]

PART

COLLECTION OF THE DUTY

PART VII

COLLECTION OF THE DUTY



</article>



<article><tid>358037</tid>
<number>51</number>Method of collection of duty. Estate duty may be collected by 
such means and in such manner as the Board may prescribe.


</article>



<article><tid>1102325</tid>
<number> 52</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Payment of duty by transfer of property.
<section><tid>1608166</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may, on an application of the person accountable for estate 
duty, accept in satisfaction of the whole or any part of such duty any 
property passing on the death of the deceased at such price as may be 
agreed upon between the Central Government and that person, and 
thereupon such person shall deliver possession of the property to such 
authority as may be specified by that Government in this behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>1705807</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the 
time being in force, on the date the possession of the property is 
delivered to the authority under sub- section (1)--

<subsection><tid>156888</tid>
<number>i</number>the property shall vest in the Central Government; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1027267</tid>
<number>ii</number>the Central Government shall, where necessary, intimate 
the registering authority concerned accordingly;
and the authority shall administer the property in such manner as the 
Central Government may direct.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1708039</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the price referred to in sub- section (1) exceeds the 
aggregate of the amounts due under this Act in respect of the estate 
of the deceasd, the excess shall be applied in the following order to 
the payment of any tax, penalty, interest or other amount--

<subsection><tid>131219</tid>
<number>i</number>which the legal representative of the deceased is liable 
to pay in respect of the income, expenditure or wealth 
of,
<pagefootnote><pagenum>702B</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 31 of <year>1964</year>, s. 19, for the original s. 52.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


or gift made by, the deceased under any of the Acts 
referred to in clause (c) of section 2 of the Central 
Boards of Revenue Act, <year>1963</year> (54 of <year>1963</year>);


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>544299</tid>
<number>ii</number>which the executor is liable to pay under any of the 
Acts aforesaid in respect of the estate of the deceased 
for the period of the administration of the estate;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1542879</tid>
<number>iii</number>which the person beneficially entitled to the property 
in question is liable to pay under any of those Acts;
and the balance, if any, shall be paid to the accountable person.]


<pagefootnote><pagenum>703</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1149782</tid>
<number> 53</number> Persons accountable, and their duties and liabilities.
<section><tid>666197</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Where any property passes on the death of the deceased--

<subsection><tid>831622</tid>
<number>a</number>every legal representative to whom such property so passes 
for any beneficial interest in possession or in whom any 
interest in the property so passing is at any time vested,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1639024</tid>
<number>b</number>every trustee, guardian, committee or other person in whom 
any interest in the property so passing or the management 
thereof is at any time vested, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1124132</tid>
<number>c</number>every person in whom any interest in the property so passing 
is vested in possession by alienation or other derivative 
title,
shall be accountable for the whole of the estate duty on the property 
passing on the death but shall not be liable for any duty in excess of 
the assets of the deceased which he actually received or which, but 
for his own neglect or default, he might have received:

Provided that nothing in this section shall render a person 
accountable for duty who acts merely as agent or bailiff for another 
person in the management of property.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1088361</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where 
an heir- at- law proves to the satisfaction of the Controller that some 
other person is in adverse possession of any assets of the deceased, 
the heir- at- law shall not be accountable for the portion of the estate 
duty payable in respect of such assets:
Provided that he shall become so accountable if, and to the 
extent that, he subsequently recovers possession of such assets.


</section>

<section><tid>752146</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Every person accountable for estate duty under this 
section shall, within six months of the death of the deceased, deliver 
to the Controller an account in the prescribed form and verified in 
the prescribed manner of all the properties in respect of which estate 
duty is payable:
Provided that the Controller may extend the period of six months 
aforesaid on such terms which may include payment of interest as may 
be prescribed.]


</section>

<section><tid>1909304</tid>
<number>4</number>Where the person accountable knows of any property which he 
has not included in his account because he does not know its amount or 
value, he may state that such property exists, but he does not know 
the amount or value thereof and that he undertakes, as soon as the 
amount and value are ascertained to bring a supplementary account 
thereof and to pay both the duty for which he may be
<pagefootnote><pagenum>704</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 33 of <year>1958</year>, s. 20, for sub- section (3)  (w. e. f. 1- 7-  
  <year>1963</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


liable in respect of such property and any further duty payable by 
reason thereof for which he may be liable in respect of the property 
mentioned in the original account.


</section>

<section><tid>1485990</tid>
<number>5</number>Where two or more persons are accountable, whether in the 
same capacity or in different capacities, for estate duty in respect 
of any property passing on the death of the deceased, they shall be 
liable jointly and severally for the whole of the estate duty on the 
property so passing.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>992644</tid>
<number> 54</number> Persons accountable may include trustees in certain cases.

<section><tid>594680</tid>
<number>1</number>Where an interest limited to cease on a death within the meaning  
of section 11 after becoming an interest in possession is disposed of 
or determines wholly or partly, then, whatever the nature of the 
property in which the interest subsisted, the following persons shall 
be accountable for any estate duty payable on the death by virtue of 
that section (in addition to any persons accountable therefor apart  
  from this section), that is to say--

<subsection><tid>1831109</tid>
<number>a</number>if the settlement under which the interest subsisted is 
in existence at the death, the trustees for the time 
being of that settlement; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1982765</tid>
<number>b</number>if it is not, the persons who were the last trustees of 
that settlement.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1243668</tid>
<number>2</number>Where--

<subsection><tid>1648608</tid>
<number>a</number>the trustees of a settlement may become accountable for 
estate duty payable by virtue of section 11 in respect 
of any property; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>929570</tid>
<number>b</number>it is intended that the property or any part thereof 
shall cease to be comprised in the settlement;
then if the trustees obtain from the Controller a certificate of the 
amount which in the opinion of the Controller may properly be treated 
as the prospective amount of the duty, and give the Controller all the 
information and evidence required by the Controller in connection with 
the application for the certificate, no person shall be accountable as 
trustee of the settlement for the duty to which the certificate 
relates to an amount in excess of the amount certified.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>439593</tid>
<number>3</number>It is hereby declared that a person who may become 
accountable as trustee of a settlement for estate duty payable by 
virtue of section 11 on property which is or has been comprised in the 
settlement has a lien for the prospective amount of the duty and the 
costs in respect thereof on any property in his hands which is so 
comprised.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>705</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Explanation.-- References in this section to the prospective 
amount of any duty are to be taken as referring to the prospective 
amount of the duty on the assumption that it will become chargeable.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1018417</tid>
<number>55</number>Every person believed to be in possession to deliver 
statement of particulars of property as required by Controller. Every 
person accountable for estate duty, every company to which, in the 
opinion of the Controller, a transfer of property has been made by the 
deceased as mentioned in section 17, every person who is or was at any 
time an officer or auditor of such a company, and every person whom 
the Controller believes to have taken possession of or administered 
any part of the estate in respect of which duty is leviable on the 
death of the deceased, or of the income of any part of such estate 
shall, if required by the Controller, deliver to him and verify, to 
the best of his knowledge and belief, a statement of such particulars 
together with such accounts, documents, evidence or information as the 
Controller may require relating to any property which he has reason to 
believe to form part of an estate in respect of which estate duty is 
leviable on the death of the deceased.


</article>



<article><tid>952773</tid>
<number> 56</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Grant of representation, etc., not to be made unless 
particulars are furnished to the Controller.
<section><tid>204828</tid>
<number>1</number>In all cases in which  
a grant of representation is applied for--

<subsection><tid>1513305</tid>
<number>a</number>the executor of the deceased shall, to the best of his 
knowledge and belief, specify in an appropriate account 
annexed to the affidavit of valuation filed in court 
under section 19-I of the Court- fees Act, <year>1870</year>, (7 of  
  <year>1870</year>) all the property in respect of which estate duty 
is payable upon the death of the deceased and shall 
deliver a copy of the affidavit with the account to the 
Controller, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>270257</tid>
<number>b</number>no order entitling the applicant to the grant of 
representation shall be made upon his application until 
he has delivered the account prescribed in clause (a) 
and has produced a certificate from the Controller 
under sub- section (2) of section 57 or section 67 that 
the estate duty payable in respect of the property 
included in the account has been or will be paid, or 
that none is due, as the case may be.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1190035</tid>
<number>2</number>In all cases in which a grant of a succession certificate is 
applied for, a copy of the application shall be furnished by the 
applicant to the Controller and no order entitling the applicant to 
the grant of such a certificate shall be made upon his application 
until he has produced a certificate from the Controller under sub-
<pagefootnote><pagenum>706</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 33 of <year>1958</year>, s. 21, for ss. 56 to 65 (w. e. f. 1- 7-  
  <year>1960</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


section (2) of section 57 or section 67 that the estate duty payable 
in respect of the property mentioned in the application has been or 
will be paid, or that none is due, as the case may be.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1236358</tid>
<number> 57</number> Power to make provisional assessment in advance of regular 
assessment.
<section><tid>912069</tid>
<number>1</number>Estate Duty shall be due from the date of the death of  
the deceased, and the Controller may, at any time after the receipt of 
account delivered under section 53 or section 56, proceed to make in a 
summary manner a provisional assessment of the estate duty payable by 
the person delivering the account on the basis of the account so 
delivered.

</section>

<section><tid>1484046</tid>
<number>2</number>Upon a provisional assessment being made under sub- section 
 (1), the person so assessed shall pay to the Controller, or furnish 
security to the satisfaction of the Controller for the payment of, the 
estate duty, if any, payable on the provisional assessment, and the 
Controller shall thereupon grant him a certificate that such duty has 
been or will be paid or that none is due, as the case may be, in 
respect of the property mentioned in the certificate.

</section>

<section><tid>224078</tid>
<number>3</number>After regular assessment has been made under section 58 any 
amount paid towards the provisional assessment made under sub- section 
 (1) shall be deemed to have been paid towards the regular assessment.

</section>

<section><tid>1373108</tid>
<number>4</number>No appeal shall lie against a provisional assessment made 
under sub- section (1), but nothing done or suffered by reason or in 
consequence of any such provisional assessment shall prejudice the 
determination on the merits of any issue which may arise in the course 
of the regular assessment under section 58.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1797853</tid>
<number> 58</number> Assessment.
<section><tid>692283</tid>
<number>1</number>If the Controller is satisfied without  
requiring the presence of the person accountable that an account 
delivered under section 53 or section 56 is correct and complete, he 
shall assess the principal value of the estate of the deceased, and 
shall determine the amount payable as estate duty.

</section>

<section><tid>87442</tid>
<number>2</number>If the Controller is not so satisfied, he shall serve a 
notice on the person accountable, either to attend in person at his 
office on a date to be specified in the notice, or to produce, or 
cause to be produced on that date, any evidence on which the person 
accountable may rely in support of his account.

</section>

<section><tid>643222</tid>
<number>3</number>The Controller, after hearing such evidence as the person 
accountable may produce and such other evidence as he may require on 
any specified points, shall, by order in writing, assess the principal 
value of the estate of the deceased and determine the amount payable 
as estate duty.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>707</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>379199</tid>
<number>4</number>In any case where no account has been delivered as required 
by section 53 or section 56, or the person accountable fails to comply 
with the terms of the notice served under sub- section (2), the 
Controller shall make the assessment to the best of his judgment and 
determine the amount payable as estate duty.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>504825</tid>
<number> 59</number> Property escaping assessment. If the Controller,--
<section><tid>1834963</tid>
<number>a</number>has reason to believe that by reason of the omission or 
failure on the part of the person accountable to submit 
an account of the estate of the deceased under section 
 53 or section 56 or to disclose fully and truly all 
material facts necessary for assessment, any property 
chargeable to estate duty has escaped assessment by 
reason of under- valuation of the property included in 
the account or of omission to include therein any 
property which ought to have been included or of 
assessment at too low a rate or otherwise, or

</section>

<section><tid>711971</tid>
<number>b</number>has, in consequence of any information in his 
possession, reason to believe notiwithstanding that 
there has not been such omission or failure as is 
referred to in clause (a) that any property chargeable 
to estate duty has escaped assessment, whether by 
reason of under- valuation of the property included in 
the account or of omission to include therein any 
property which ought to have been included, or of 
assessment at too low a rate or otherwise.
he may at any time, subject to the provisions of section 73A, require 
the person accountable to submit an account as required under section 
 53 and may proceed to assess or re- assess such property as if the 
provisions of section 58 applied thereto.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>546418</tid>
<number> 60</number> Penalty for default or concealment.
<section><tid>219856</tid>
<number>1</number>If the Controller,  
the Appellate Controller or the Appellate Tribunal, in the course of 
any proceedings under this Act, is satisfied that any person--

<subsection><tid>1758573</tid>
<number>a</number>has without reasonable cause failed to deliver the 
account of the property of the deceased under section 
 53 or section 56 or to comply with any requisition of 
the Controller under section 55 or section 59 or has 
without reasonable cause failed to deliver or submit 
any of the accounts or statements required under any of 
the sections aforesaid within the time allowed and in 
the manner required; or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>708</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1266312</tid>
<number>b</number>has without reasonable cause failed to comply with a 
notice under sub- section (2) of section 58; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>257197</tid>
<number>c</number>has concealed the particulars of the property of the 
deceased or deliberately furnished inaccurate 
particulars thereof; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1331843</tid>
<number>d</number>being a company referred to in section 20A, fails 
without reasonable cause, to pay the amount of estate 
duty due from the company under that section within the 
time specified in this behalf;
he or it may, by order in writing, direct that--

such person shall pay by way of penalty--


<subsubsection><tid>1731865</tid>
<number>i</number>in the case referred to in clause (a) or 
clause (d), in addition to the amount of the estate 
duty payable by him, a sum not exceeding twice the 
amount of such duty; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>434403</tid>
<number>ii</number>in the case referred to in clause (b) or 
clause (c), in addition to the amount of estate duty 
payable by him, a sum not exceeding twice the amount of 
the estate duty, if any, which would have been avoided 
if the principal value shown in the account of such 
person had been accepted as correct.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1516268</tid>
<number>2</number>No order shall be made under sub- section (1) unless the 
person concerned has been given a reasonable opportunity of being 
heard.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>664824</tid>
<number>61</number>Rectification of mistakes. At any time within five years from 
the date of any order passed by him or it, the Controller, the 
Appellate Controller or the Appellate Tribunal may, on his or its own 
motion rectify any mistake apparent from the record and shall, within 
a like period rectify any such mistake which has been brought to the 
notice of the Controller, the Appellate Controller or the Appellate 
Tribunal, as the case may be, by the person accountable:
Provided that no such rectification shall be made which has the 
effect of enhancing the estate duty payable unless the person 
accountable has been given a reasonable opportunity of being heard in 
the matter.



</article>



<article><tid>1316235</tid>
<number> 62</number> Appeal against orders of Controller.
<section><tid>1936853</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person-- 

<subsection><tid>1115571</tid>
<number>a</number>objecting--

<subsubsection><tid>361092</tid>
<number>i</number>to any valuation made by the Controller, or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>709</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>33302</tid>
<number>ii</number>to any order made by the Controller 
determining the estate duty payable under section 58 or 
section 59, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>39035</tid>
<number>iii</number>to any penalty levied by the Controller 
under section 60, section 72 or section 84, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1266701</tid>
<number>iv</number>to any penalty imposed by the Controller 
under sub- section (1) of section 46 of the Indian 
Income- tax Act, <year>1922</year>, (11 of <year>1922</year>) as applied under 
sub- section (5) of section 73 for the purposes of 
estate duty, or

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1136322</tid>
<number>b</number>denying his liability to the amount of estate duty 
payable in respect of any property,
may, within thirty days of the date of the receipt of the notice of 
demand under section 73, appeal to the Appellate Controller in the 
prescribed form which shall be verified in the prescribed manner:

Provided that no appeal shall lie under sub- clause (iv) of clause 
 (a) unless the duty has been paid before the appeal is filed.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>593889</tid>
<number>2</number>The Appellate Controller may admit an appeal after the expiry 
of the thirty days referred to in sub- section (1) if he is satisfied 
that there was sufficient cause for not presenting it within that 
period.

</section>

<section><tid>562074</tid>
<number>3</number>The Appellate Controller shall fix a day and place for the 
hearing of the appeal and may from time to time adjourn the hearing.

</section>

<section><tid>1381770</tid>
<number>4</number>The Appellate Controller may--

<subsection><tid>1541686</tid>
<number>a</number>at the hearing of an appeal, allow an appellant to go 
into any ground of appeal not specified in the grounds 
of appeal;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1562302</tid>
<number>b</number>before disposing of an appeal, make such further inquiry 
as he thinks fit or cause further inquiry to be made by 
the Controller.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1014587</tid>
<number>5</number>In disposing of an appeal, the Appellate Controller may pass 
such order as he thinks fit which may include an order enhancing the 
estate duty or penalty:
Provided that no order enhancing the estate duty payable or 
penalty shall be made unless the person affected thereby has been 
given a reasonable opportunity of showing cause against such 
enhancement.


</section>

<section><tid>25261</tid>
<number>6</number>The Appellate Controller shall, on the conclusion of the 
appeal, communicate the order passed by him to the appellant and to 
the Controller.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>710</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>482770</tid>
<number> 63</number> Appeal to the Appellate Tribunal from the order of the 
Appellate Controller.
<section><tid>1614696</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person accountable objecting to any  
order passed by an Appellate controller under section 62, may appeal 
to the Appellate Tribunal within sixty days of the date on which he is 
served with notice of such order.

</section>

<section><tid>1821535</tid>
<number>2</number>The Controller may, if he is not satisfied as to the 
correctness of any order passed by the Appellate Controller under 
section 62, appeal to the Appellate Tribunal against such order and 
such appeal may be made at any time before the expiry of sixty days of 
the date on which the order is communicated to the Controller.

</section>

<section><tid>501874</tid>
<number>3</number>The Tribunal may admit an appeal after the expiry of the 
sixty days referred to in sub- sections (1) and (2) if it is satisfied 
that there was sufficient cause for not presenting it within that 
period.

</section>

<section><tid>382197</tid>
<number>4</number>An appeal to the Appellate Tribunal shall be in the 
prescribed form and shall be verified in the prescribed manner and 
shall, except in the case of an appeal under sub- section (2), be 
accompanied by a fee of rupees one hundred.

</section>

<section><tid>685547</tid>
<number>5</number>The Appellate Tribunal may, after giving the parties to the 
appeal an opportunity of being heard, pass such orders thereon as it 
thinks fit, and any such orders may include an order enhancing the 
estate duty payable or penalty:
Provided that no order enhancing the estate duty payable or 
penalty shall be made unless the person affected thereby has been 
given a reasonable opportunity of showing cause against such 
enhancement.


</section>

<section><tid>227198</tid>
<number>6</number>Where the appellant objects to the valuation of any property, 
the Appellate Tribunal may, and if the appellant so requires, shall, 
refer the question of disputed value to the arbitration of two 
valuers, one of whom shall be nominated by the appellant and the other 
by the respondent, and the Tribunal shall, so far as that question is 
concerned pass its orders under sub- section (5) conformably to the 
decision of the valuers:
Provided that if there is a difference of opinion between the two 
valuers, the matter shall be referred to a third valuer nominated by 
agreement, or failing agreement, by the Appellate Tribunal, and the 
decision of that valuer on the question of valuation shall be final.


</section>

<section><tid>567667</tid>
<number>7</number>The costs of any arbitration proceeding under sub- section (6) 
shall be borne by the Central Government or the person accountable,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>711</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

as the case may be, at whose instance the question was referred to the 
valuers:

Provided that where the person accountable has been wholly or 
partially successful in any reference made at his instance, the extent 
to which the costs shall be borne by him shall be at the discretion of 
the Appellate Tribunal.


</section>

<section><tid>1958787</tid>
<number>8</number>The valuers may, in disposing of any matter referred to them 
for arbitration under sub- section (6), hold or cause to be held such 
inquiry as they think fit, and after giving the appellant and the 
respondent an opportunity of being heard, pass such orders thereon as 
they think fit and shall send a copy of such orders to the Appellate 
Tribunal.

</section>

<section><tid>1445412</tid>
<number>9</number>A copy of every order passed by the Appellate Tribunal under 
this section shall be forwarded to the person accountable and to the 
Controller.

</section>

<section><tid>117747</tid>
<number>10</number>Save as provided in section 64 any order passed by the 
Appellate Tribunal on appeal shall be final.

</section>

<section><tid>1093791</tid>
<number>11</number>The provisions of sub- sections (5), (7) and (8) of section 
 5A of the Indian Income- tax Act, <year>1922</year>, (11 of <year>1922</year>) shall apply to 
the Appellate Tribunal in the discharge of its functions under this 
Act as they apply to it in the discharge of its functions under that 
Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1425488</tid>
<number> 64</number> Reference to the High Court.
<section><tid>1462792</tid>
<number>1</number>Within ninety days of the  
date upon which he is served with an order under section 63, the 
person accountable or the Controller may present an application in the 
prescribed form and, where the application is by the person 
accountable, accompanied by a fee of one hundred rupees to the 
Appellate Tribunal requiring the Appellate Tribunal to refer to the 
High Court any question of law arising out of such order, and the 
Appellate Tribunal shall, if in its opinion a question of law arises 
out of such order, state the case for the opinion of the High Court.

</section>

<section><tid>195134</tid>
<number>2</number>An application under sub- section (1) may be admitted after 
the expiry of the period of ninety days aforesaid if the Appellate 
Tribunal is satisfied that there was sufficient cause for not 
presenting it within the said period.

</section>

<section><tid>1639724</tid>
<number>3</number>If, on an application made under sub- section (1), the 
Appellate Tribunal,--

<subsection><tid>341759</tid>
<number>a</number>refuses to state a case on the ground that no question 
of law arises; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>782670</tid>
<number>b</number>rejects it on the ground that it is time- barred;
the applicant may, within three months from the date on which he is 
served with a notice of refusal or rejection, as the case may be,


<pagefootnote><pagenum>712</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

apply to the High Court, and the High Court may, if it is not 
satisfied with the correctness of the decision of the Appellate 
Tribunal, require the Appellate Tribunal to state the case to the High 
Court, and on receipt of such requisition the Appellate Tribunal shall 
state the case:

Provided that, if in any case where the Appellate Tribunal has 
been required by a person accountable to state a case the Appellate 
Tribunal refuses to do so on the ground that no question of law 
arises, the person accountable may, within thirty days from the date 
on which he receives notice of refusal to state the case, withdraw the 
application, and if he does so, the fee paid by him under sub- section 
 (1) shall be refunded to him.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1928644</tid>
<number>4</number>The statement to the High Court shall set forth the facts, 
the determination of the Appellate Tribunal and the question of law 
which arises out of the case.

</section>

<section><tid>881006</tid>
<number>5</number>If the High Court is not satisfied that the case as stated is 
sufficient to enable it to determine the question of law raised 
thereby, it may require the Appellate Tribunal to make such 
modifications therein as it may direct.

</section>

<section><tid>1622741</tid>
<number>6</number>The High Court, upon hearing any such case, shall decide the 
question of law raised thereby, and in doing so, may, if it thinks 
fit, alter the form of the question of law and shall deliver judgment 
thereon containing the ground on which such decision is founded and 
shall send a copy of the judgment under the seal of the Court and the 
signature of the Registrar to the Appellate Tribunal and the Appellate 
Tribunal shall pass such orders as are necessary to dispose of the 
case conformably to such judgment.

</section>

<section><tid>1070660</tid>
<number>7</number>Where the amount of any assessment is reduced as a result of 
any reference to the High Court, the amount, if any, over- paid as 
estate duty shall be refunded with such interest as the Controller may 
allow unless the High Court, on intimation being given by the 
Controller within thirty days of the receipt of the result of such 
reference that he intends to ask for leave to appeal to the Supreme 
Court, makes an order authorising the Controller to postpone payment 
of such refund until the disposal of the appeal in the Supreme Court.

</section>

<section><tid>1650464</tid>
<number>8</number>The costs of any reference to the High Court shall be in the 
discretion of the High Court.

</section>

<section><tid>732036</tid>
<number>9</number>Section 5 of the Indian Limitation Act, <year>1908</year>, (9 of <year>1908</year>) 
shall apply to an application to the High Court under this section.

</section>

<section><tid>114430</tid>
<number>10</number>When a case has been stated to the High Court under this 
section, it shall be heard by a Bench of not less than two Judges of

<pagefootnote><pagenum>713</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

the High Court and shall be decided in accordance with the opinion of 
such Judges or of the majority (if any) of such Judges:

Provided that where there is no such majority, the Judges shall 
state the point of law upon which they differ, and the case shall then 
be heard upon that point only by one or more of the other Judges of 
the High Court, and such point shall be decided according to the 
opinion of the majority of the Judges who have heard the case, 
including those who first heard it.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>663390</tid>
<number> 65</number> Appeal to the Supreme Court.
<section><tid>548892</tid>
<number>1</number>An appeal shall lie to the  
Supreme Court from any judgment of the High Court delivered on a case 
stated under section 64 in any case which the High Court certifies as 
a fit case for appeal to the Supreme Court.

</section>

<section><tid>1130498</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the judgment of the High Court is varied or reversed on 
appeal under this section, effect shall be given to the order of the 
Supreme Court in the manner provided in sub- section (6) of section 64.

</section>

<section><tid>1484807</tid>
<number>3</number>The High Court may, on application made to it for the 
execution of any order of the Supreme Court in respect of any costs 
awarded by it, transmit the order for execution to any court sub- 
ordinate to the High Court.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1164497</tid>
<number>66</number>Grant of representation not to be delayed on reference to 
High Court. Where any grant of representation has been applied for, it 
shall not be delayed by reason of any reference to a High Court under 
section 64.


</article>



<article><tid>456473</tid>
<number>67</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Certificate of payment of estate duty. Where the amount of 
estate duty determined by the Controller as payable on an assessment 
made under section 58 has been paid by the person accountable, the 
Controller shall, on application by that person, grant to him a 
certificate to that effect.]


</article>



<article><tid>412416</tid>
<number>68</number>Commntation of duty in respect of interest in expectancy. The 
Controller in his discretion may, upon application by a person 
entitled to an interest in expectancy, commute the estate duty which 
would or might, but for the commutation, become payable in respect of 
such interest for a certain sum to be presently paid, and, for 
determining that sum, shall cause a present value to be set upon such 
duty, regard being had to the contingencies affecting the liability to 
and rate and amount of such duty, and interest being reckoned at three 
per cent,; and on the receipt of such sum the Controller shall give a 
certificate accordingly.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>714</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 33 of <year>1958</year>, s. 22, for s. 67 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1960</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>625798</tid>
<number>69</number>Assessment in complicated cases. Where by reason of the 
number of deaths upon which property has passed or of the complicated 
nature of the interests of different persons in property which has 
passed on death, or from any other cause, it is difficult to ascertain 
exactly the amount of estate duty payable in respect of any property 
or any interest therein or so to ascertain the same without undue 
expense in proportion to the value of the property or interest, the 
Board, on the application of any person accountable for the duty and 
upon his giving to the Board all the information in his power 
respecting the amount of the property and the several interests 
therein and other circumstances of the case, may by way of composition 
for all or any of the duties payable in respect of the property or 
interest and the various interests therein or any of them, assess such 
sum on the value of the property or interest, as having regard to the 
circumstances appears proper, and may accept payment of the sum so 
assessed in full payment of all claims for estate duty in respect of 
such property or interest, and shall give a certificate accordingly.


</article>



<article><tid>605792</tid>
<number> 70</number> Controller may allow postponement of payment on terms.
<section><tid>272856</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Where the Controller is satisfied that the estate duty leviable in 
respect of any property cannot, without excessive sacrifice, be raised 
at once, he may allow payment to be postponed for such period, to such 
extent, and on payment of such interest not exceeding four per cent. 
or any higher interest yielded by the property, and on such other 
terms as he may think fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1101496</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), estate 
duty in respect of immovable property may at the option of the person 
accountable be paid in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> four] equal yearly instalments or <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> eight] 
equal half- yearly instalments with interest at the rate of four per 
cent. per annum or any higher interest yielded by the property from 
the date on which the first instalment is payable and the interest on 
the unpaid portion of the duty shall be added to each instalment and 
paid accordingly; but the duty for the time being unpaid with such 
interest to the date of payment may be paid at any time and in case 
where the property is sold shall be paid on the completion of the sale 
and if not so paid shall be recovered in the manner specified in 
section 73.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>700713</tid>
<number>71</number>Board may remit duty and interest outstanding after twenty 
years from death. If after the expiration of twenty years from a death 
upon which estate duty became leviable any such duty remains unpaid, 
the Board may, if it thinks fit, on the application of any person
<pagefootnote><pagenum>715</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 33 of <year>1958</year>, s. 23, for" eight" (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1960</year>). 
2 Subs. by s. 23, ibid., for" sixteen" (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1960</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


accountable or liable for such duty or interested in the property, 
remit the payment of such duty or any part thereof or any interest 
thereon.



</article>



<article><tid>1477733</tid>
<number>72</number>Forms. All affidavits, accounts, certificates, statements and 
forms used for the purposes of this Part of this Act shall be in such 
form and contain such particulars as may be prescribed by the Board 
and, if so required by the Board, shall be in duplicate and accounts 
and statements shall be delivered and verified on oath and by 
production of books and documents in the manner prescribed by the 
Board and any person who wilfully fails to comply with the provisions 
of this section <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> shall be liable to pay by way of penalty a sum not 
exceeding rupees one thousand: provided that no penalty shall be 
imposed under this section unless the person concerned has been given 
a reasonable opportunity of being heard].


</article>



<article><tid>1965113</tid>
<number> 73</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Notice of demand and recovery of duty, penalty, etc.
<section><tid>1643007</tid>
<number>1</number> 
When any estate duty, penalty or interest is due in consequence of any 
order passed under this Act, the Controller shall serve upon the 
person accountable or other person liable to pay such duty, penalty or 
interest a notice of demand in the prescribed form specifying the sum 
so payable and the time within which it shall be payable.

</section>

<section><tid>593004</tid>
<number>2</number>Any amount specified as payable in a notice of demand issued 
under sub- section (1) shall be paid within the time, at the place and 
to the person mentioned in the notice, or if no time is so mentioned, 
then on or before the first day of the second month following the date 
of service of the notice and any person accountable failing so to pay 
shall be deemed to be in default.

</section>

<section><tid>921863</tid>
<number>3</number>Where a person accountable has been assessed in respect of 
assets located in a country outside India, the laws of which prohibit 
or restrict the remittance of money to India, the Controller shall not 
treat the person accountable as in default in respect of that part of 
the estate duty which is attributable to the assets in that country, 
and shall continue to treat the person accountable as not in default 
in respect of that part of the duty until the prohibition or 
restriction of remittance is removed.

</section>

<section><tid>1589044</tid>
<number>4</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, where the 
person accountable has presented an appeal under section 62 the 
Controller may in his discretion treat the person accountable as not 
being in default as long as such appeal has not been disposed of.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>716</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 33 of <year>1958</year>, s. 24, for" shall be liable to the 
penalty mentioned in section 56" (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1960</year>). 
2 Subs. by s. 25, ibid., for s. 73 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1960</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1403398</tid>
<number>5</number>The provisions of sub- sections (1), (1A), (2), (3), (4), (5), 
 (5A), (6) and (7) of section 46 and section 47 of the Indian Income- 
tax Act, <year>1922</year>, (11 of <year>1922</year>) shall apply as if the said provisions 
were provisions of this Act and referred to estate duty (including  
  estate duty provisionally assessed) and sums imposed by way of penalty 
or interest under this Act instead of to income- tax and sums imposed 
by way of penalty or interest under that Act and to Controller of 
Estate Duty instead of to Income- tax Officer.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1797950</tid>
<number> 73A</number> Limitation for commencing proceedings for assessment or 
re- assessment. No proceedings for the levy of any estate duty under 
this Act shall be commenced--
<section><tid>51071</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of a first assessment, after the expiration 
of five years from the date of death of the deceased in 
respect of whose property estate duty became payable; 
and

</section>

<section><tid>815135</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of a re- assessment, after the expiration of 
three years from the date of assessment of such 
property to estate duty under this Act.]
PART

CHARGE OF ESTATE DUTY ON PROPERTY AND FACILITIES FOR RAISING IT

PART VIII

CHARGE OF ESTATE DUTY ON PROPERTY AND FACILITIES FOR RAISING IT




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>760285</tid>
<number> 74</number> Estate duty a first charge on property liable thereto.
<section><tid>1123499</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Subject to the provisions of section 19, the estate duty payable in 
respect of property, movable or immovable, passing on the death of the 
deceased, shall be a first charge on the immovable property so passing 
 (including agricultural land) in whomsoever it may vest on his death 
after the debts and incumbrances allowable under Part VI of this Act; 
and any private transfer or delivery of such property shall be void 
against any claim in respect of such estate duty.

</section>

<section><tid>81835</tid>
<number>2</number>A rateable part of the estate duty on an estate, in 
proportion to the value of any beneficial interest in possession in 
movable property which passes to any person (other than the legal  
  representative of the deceased) on the death of the deceased shall be 
a first charge on such interest:
Provided that the property shall not be so chargeable as against 
a bona fide purchaser thereof for valuable consideration without 
notice.


</section>

<section><tid>1529829</tid>
<number>3</number>The Controller may release the whole or any part of any 
property, whether movable or immovable, from charge under this section 
in such circumstances and on such conditions as he thinks fit.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>716A</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1488351</tid>
<number>75</number>Discharge from estate duty in certain cases. A certificate 
granted by the Controller under section 67, or by the Board under 
section 69, shall discharge the property included therein and the 
grantee so far as regards that property from any further claim for 
estate duty, but shall not discharge any person or property from 
estate duty in case of fraud or failure to disclose material facts and 
shall not affect the duty payable in respect of any property 
afterwards shown to have passed on the death nor any further duty 
payable by reason thereof in respect of the property included in the 
certificate:
Provided nevertheless that a certificate purporting to be a 
discharge of the whole estate duty payable in respect of any property 
included in the certificate shall exonerate a bona fide purchaser for 
valuable consideration without notice from the duty notwithstanding 
any such fraud or failure.



</article>



<article><tid>576907</tid>
<number>76</number>Person accountable to be repaid by trustees and owners in 
certain cases. If a person accountable under section 53 pays any part 
of the estate duty in respect of any property not passing to him, it 
shall, where occasion requires, be repaid to him by the trustees or 
owners of the property.


</article>



<article><tid>727531</tid>
<number> 77</number> Facilities for paying duty or raising amount already paid.

<section><tid>524870</tid>
<number>1</number>A person authorised or required to pay estate duty in respect of  
any property shall, for the purposes of paying the duty, or raising 
the amount of the duty when already paid, have power, whether the 
property is or is not vested in him, to raise the amount of such duty 
and any interest and expenses properly paid or incurred by him in 
respect thereof, by the sale or mortgage of or a terminable charge on 
that property or any part thereof:
Provided that any sum payable under any such sale, mortgage or 
terminable charge may be paid (to the extent to which such sum or part  
  thereof represents the estate duty payable), not to the person raising 
the sum but to the Controller at the option of the person from whom 
the sum is being raised.


</section>

<section><tid>167961</tid>
<number>2</number>A person having an interest in any property, who pays the 
estate duty in respect of that property, shall be entitled to the like 
charge, as if the estate duty in respect of that property had been 
raised by means of a mortgage to him.

</section>

<section><tid>377193</tid>
<number>3</number>Any money arising from the sale of property comprised in a 
settlement or held upon trust to lay out upon the trusts of a 
settlement may be expended in paying any estate duty in respect of 
property comprised in the settlement and held upon the same trusts.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>716B</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

PART

MISCELLANEOUS

PART IX

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1489393</tid>
<number>78</number>Jurisdiction of Courts barred in certain cases. No suit shall 
be brought in any Civil Court to set aside or modify any estate duty 
determined under this Act and no prosecution suit or other proceedings 
shall lie against <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Government or] any officer of Government for 
anything in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>549382</tid>
<number> 79</number> Power to take evidence on oath, etc. Every authority 
specified in sub- section
<section><tid>761010</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 4, other than valuers, shall  
for the purposes of this Act have the same powers as are vested in a 
Court under the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year>, (5 of <year>1908</year>) when 
trying a suit in respect of the following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>145212</tid>
<number>a</number>enforcing the attendance of any person and examining him 
on oath;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1563917</tid>
<number>b</number>requiring the discovery and production of documents;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>56978</tid>
<number>c</number>receiving evidence on affidavit;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1171846</tid>
<number>d</number>issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses;
and any proceeding before any such authority under this Act shall be 
deemed to be a judicial proceeding within the meaning of sections 193 
and 228 of the Indian Penal Code. (45 of <year>1860</year>)




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>310017</tid>
<number>80</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Disclosure of information respecting assessments. Where a 
person makes an application to the Controller in the prescribed form 
for any information in respect of any assessment made under this Act, 
the Controller may, if he is satisfied that it is in the public 
interest so to do, furnish or cause to be furnished the information 
asked for in respect of that assessment only and his decision in this 
behalf shall be final and shall not be called in question in any court 
of law.


</article>



<article><tid>208903</tid>
<number> 80A</number> Publication of information respecting accountable persons.

<section><tid>861957</tid>
<number>1</number>If the Central Government is of opinion that it is necessary or  
expedient in the public interest to publish the names of any 
accountable persons and any other particulars relating to any 
proceedings under this Act in respect of such persons, it may cause to 
be published such names and particulars in such manner as it thinks 
fit.

</section>

<section><tid>232053</tid>
<number>2</number>No publication under this section shall be made in relation 
to any penalty imposed under this Act until the time for presenting
<pagefootnote><pagenum>718A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 5 of <year>1964</year>, s. 49 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1964</year>). 
2 Subs. by s. 49, ibid., for s. 80 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1964</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>717</number>- 718

an appeal to the Appellate Controller has expired without an appeal 
having been presented or the appeal, if presented, has been disposed 
of.]


</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>81</number>Arrangements with States to supply information. The Central 
Government may make arrangements with the Government of any State for 
exchange of such information as may be necessary for the purposes of 
levying or realising any estate duty under this Act or under any other 
law for the time being in force in that State.


</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>82</number>Service of Notices. Any notice or requisition under this Act 
may be served on the person therein named either by post or as if it 
were a summons issued by a Court under the Code of Civil Procedure, 
<year>1908</year>. (5 of <year>1908</year>)


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>126365</tid>
<number> 83</number> Appearance by authorised representatives. Any person 
accountable for estate duty who is entitled or required to attend 
before any authority specified in sub- section
<section><tid>968845</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 4 in  
connection with any proceeding under this Act, otherwise than when 
required under section 79 to attend in person, may attend by a person 
authorised by him in writing in this behalf, being a relative of or a 
person regularly employed by that person, or a legal practitioner or a 
chartered accountant <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or any other person having such qualifications 
as may be prescribed].
Explanation.-- In this section--


<subsection><tid>738311</tid>
<number>a</number>a person regularly employed by the accountable person 
shall include any officer of a Scheduled Bank with 
which the accountable person maintains a current 
account or has other regular dealings;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>254005</tid>
<number>b</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>" legal practitioner" means an advocate, vakil or 
attorney of any High Court, and includes a pleader in 
practice;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1382137</tid>
<number>c</number>" chartered accountant" means a chartered accountant as 
defined in the Chartered Accountants Act, <year>1949</year>. (38 of  
  <year>1949</year>)



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1160461</tid>
<number> 84</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Companies to furnish particulars of deceased persons to 
the Controller.
<section><tid>1895340</tid>
<number>1</number>Where a company within the meaning of the  
Companies Act, <year>1956</year>, (1 of <year>1956</year>) has knowledge through any of its 
principal officers of the death of any member of or debenture- holder 
in the company, it shall within three months of receipt of intimation 
of the death, furnish to the Controller such particulars as may be 
prescribed in respect of the interest of the deceased in the company; 
and it shall not be lawful for the company to register the transfer of 
any shares or debentures standing in the name of the deceased unless 
the transferee has acquired such shares or debentures for valuable 
consideration or a certificate from the Controller is produced before 
the company to the effect that the estate duty in respect of such 
shares or debentures has been paid or will be paid or that none is 
due, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>849039</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a corporation established by a Central, State or 
Provincial Act has knowledge through any of its principal officers of 
the death of any person who is a registered holder of stocks, shares 
or other securities in the corporation, it shall, within three months 
of the receipt of intimation of the death furnish to the Controller 
such particulars as may be prescribed in respect of the interest of 
the deceased in the corporation.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>718B</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 33 of <year>1958</year>, s. 26 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1960</year>). 
2 Subs. by s. 26, ibid., for cl. (b)  (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1960</year>). 
3 Subs. by s. 27, ibid., for s. 84 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1960</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1088330</tid>
<number>3</number>Any company or corporation which without reasonable cause 
fails to comply with the provisions of this section shall be liable to 
pay a penalty of rupees one thousand.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>942533</tid>
<number> 85</number> Rule- making powers of the Board.
<section><tid>1189197</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the condition  
of previous publication and subject to the control of the Central 
Government, the Board may make rules not inconsistent with this Act 
prescribing all matters which by this Act are required or permitted to 
be prescribed, or which are necessary or convenient to be prescribed 
for carrying out the purposes of or giving effect to this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1176752</tid>
<number>2</number>The power to make rules conferred by this section shall, on 
the first occasion of the exercise thereof, include the power to give 
retrospective effect to the rules or any of them from a date not 
earlier than the date of the commencement of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>65157</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as 
may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is 
in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised 
in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.]


</section>

</article>



 </act>