<act><title>
The
Kazis Act, 1880</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>1</number>
Short title.—This
Act may be called the Kazis Act, 1880;
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[***]
 Local
Extent.—It extends, in the first
instance, only to the territories administered by the Governor of Fort Saint
George in Council. <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[But
the Government of any other State] may, from time to time, by notification in
the Official Gazette, extend it to the whole or any part of the territories
under its administration<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>.
   









 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>2</number>
Power to appoint Kazis for any local area.—Wherever
it appears to the State Government that any considerable number of the
Muhammadans resident in any local area desire that one or more Kazis should be
appointed for such local area, the State Government may, if it thinks fit, after
consulting the principal Muhammadan residents of such local area, select one or
more fit persons and appoint him or them to be Kazis for such local area.
 If
any question arises whether any person has been rightly appointed Kazi under
this section, the decision thereof by the State Government shall be conclusive.
 The
State Government may, if it thinks fit, suspend or remove any Kazi appointed
under this section who is guilty of any misconduct in the execution of his
office, or who is for a continuous period of six months absent from the local
area for which he is appointed, or leaves such local area for the purpose of
residing elsewhere, or is declared an insolvent, or desires to be discharged
from the office, or who refuses or becomes in the opinion of the State
Government unfit, or personally incapable, to discharge the duties of the
office.
 
  
   



 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>3</number>
Naib Kazis.—Any Kazi appointed under
this Act may appoint one or more persons as his naib or naibs to act in his
place in all or any of the matters appertaining to his office throughout the
whole or in any portion of the local area for which he is appointed and may
suspend or remove any naib so appointed.
 When
any Kazi is suspended or removed under section 2, his naib or naibs (if any)
shall be deemed to be suspended or removed, as the case may be.
  
   



 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>4</number> 
      Nothing in Act to confer judicial or administrative powers; or to render 
      the presence of Kazi necessary; or to prevent any one acting as 
      Kazi.—Nothing herein contained, 
      and no appointment made hereunder, shall be deemed—
 <section><number>a</number>
to confer any judicial or administrative powers on any Kazi or Naib 
      Kazi appointed hereunder; or
 </section><section><number>b</number>
to render the presence of a Kazi or Naib Kazi necessary at the 
      celebration of any marriage or the performance of any rite or ceremony; or
 </section><section><number>c</number>
to prevent any person discharging any of the functions of a Kazi.
  
    
 
  </section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> The words “and it shall come into force at once” rep. by Act 10 of 1914,
sec. 3 and Sch. II.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Subs. by Act 3 of 1951, sec. 3 and Sch., for “But the Government of any other
Part A State or the Government of a Part C State” (w.e.f. 1-4-1951).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> The Act has been extended to certain places in the Bombay Presidency, West
Bengal, The U.P., The Punjab, The C.P., Assam, Union Territory of Pondicherry by
Act 26 of 1968 and Union Territory of Laccadive, Minicoy and Amindivi Islands
(now Lakshadweep) by Reg. 2 of 1970 (w.e.f. 15-10-1970).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>