<act><title>

    THE EMIGRATION ACT, 1983</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title, extent, application and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Emigration Act, 1983.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends 
    to the whole of India and applies also to citizens of India outside India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It 
    shall come into force on such date1 as 
    the Central Government may, by notification, appoint and different dates may 
    be appointed for different provisions of this Act and any reference in any 
    such provision to the commencement of this Act shall be construed as a 
    reference to the commencement of that provision. 
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> In this Act, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   “certificate” means a certificate of 
    registration issued under section 11;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   “conveyance” includes a vessel, vehicle, 
    country-craft and an aircraft; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   “dependent” means any person who is 
    related to an emigrant and is dependent on that emigrant; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   “emigrant” means any citizen of India 
    who intends to emigrate, or emigrates, or has emigrated but does not 
    include— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   a dependent of an emigrant, whether such 
    dependent accompanies that emigrant, or departs subsequently for the purpose 
    of joining that emigrant in the country to which that emigrant has lawfully 
    emigrated; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   any person who has resided outside 
    India at any time after attaining the age of eighteen years, for not less 
    than three years or the spouse or child of such person; 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   “emigrant conveyance” means any 
    conveyance specially chartered for conveyance of emigrants or for conveying 
    emigrants exceeding such number as may be prescribed: 
 
Provided that the Central Government may, by 
    notification, declare that any conveyance conveying emigrants to such place 
    as may be specified in the notification shall not be deemed to be an 
    emigrant conveyance; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   “emigrate” and “emigration” mean the 
    departure out of India of any person with a view to taking up any employment 
    (whether or not under an agreement or other arrangements to take up such 
    employment and whether with or without the assistance of a recruiting agent 
    or employer) in any country or place outside India; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>   “employer” means any person providing or 
    offering to provide, employment in any country or place outside India; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>   “employment” means any service, 
    occupation or engagement (not being service, occupation or engagement under 
    the Central Government or a State Government), in any kind of work within 
    the meaning of clause (o), for wages or for reward, and all its grammatical 
    variations and cognate expressions shall be construed accordingly; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>   “notification” means a notification 
    published in the Official Gazette; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>   “prescribed” means prescribed by rules 
    made under this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>   “Protector of Emigrants” means a 
    Protector of Emigrants appointed under section 3 and includes a person 
    authorised under section 5; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>   “recruiting agent” means a person 
    engaged in India in the business of recruitment for an employer and 
    representing such employer with respect to any matter in relation to such 
    recruitment including dealings with persons so recruited or desiring to be 
    so recruited; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number>   “recruitment” includes the issuing of 
    any advertisement for the purpose of recruitment, the offering by 
    advertisement to secure or assist in securing any employment in any country 
    or place outside India and the entering into any correspondence, 
    negotiation, agreement or arrangement with any individual for or in relation 
    to the employment of such individual in any country or place outside India; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>n</number>   “registering authority” means the 
    officer appointed under section 9 to be the registering authority for the 
    purposes of this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>o</number>   “work” means— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   any unskilled work, including any form 
    of industrial or agricultural labour; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   any domestic service; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>   any service, not being a service in a 
    managerial capacity, in any hotel, restaurant, tea-house or other place of 
    public resort; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iv</number>   work as a driver of a truck or other 
    vehicle, mechanic, technician or skilled labourer or artisan; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>v</number>   work as an office assistant or 
    accountant or typist or stenographer or salesman, or nurse or operator of 
    any machine; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>vi</number>   work in connection with, or for the 
    purposes of, any cinema, exhibition or entertainment; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>vii</number>   any such work of a professional or of 
    any other nature as the Central Government may, having regard to the need 
    for the protection of citizens of India who may be employed in such work 
    outside India and other relevant circumstances, specify by notification: 
 
Provided that the Central Government may, if 
    satisfied that it is necessary so to do having regard to the conditions of 
    service applicable with respect to employment in any of the aforementioned 
    categories of work or any sub-category thereof, whether generally or in 
    relation to any particular country or place and other relevant 
    circumstances, declare by notification that such category of work or 
    sub-category of work shall not be deemed to be work within the meaning of 
    this definition. 
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Any 
    reference in this Act to any law which is not in force in any area shall, in 
    relation to that area, be construed as a reference to the corresponding law, 
    if any, in force in that area. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Protectors of Emigrants.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Central Government may, by notification, appoint a Protector General of 
    Emigrants and as many Protectors of Emigrants, as it deems fit, for the 
    purposes of this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Central Government may, by general or special order, define the area to 
    which the authority of a Protector of Emigrants so appointed shall extend 
    and, where two or more Protectors of Emigrants are appointed for the same 
    area, also provide, by such order, for the distribution and allocation of 
    the work to be performed under this Act in relation to such area. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Protectors of Emigrants shall perform the functions assigned to them by or 
    under this Act under the general superintendence and control of the 
    Protector General of Emigrants. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Protector General of Emigrants may, in addition to the special functions 
    assigned to him by or under this Act, perform all or any of the functions 
    assigned to any Protector of Emigrants. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> General 
    duties of Protectors of Emigrants.—Subject 
    to the other provisions of this Act, every Protector of Emigrants shall, in 
    addition to the special duties assigned to him by or under this Act— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   protect and aid with his advice all 
    intending emigrants and emigrants; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   cause, so far as he can, all the 
    provisions of this Act and of the rules made thereunder to be complied with; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   inspect, to such extent and in such 
    manner as may be prescribed— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   any emigrant conveyance, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   any other conveyance if he has reason 
    to believe that any intending emigrants or emigrants are proceedings from, 
    or returning to, India to or from a place outside India by such other 
    conveyance; 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>d</number>   inquire into the treatment received by 
    emigrants during their voyage or journey to, and during the period of their 
    residence in the country to which they emigrated and also during the return 
    voyage or journey to India and report thereon to the Protector General of 
    Emigrants or such other authority as may be prescribed; 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   aid and advise, so far as he reasonably 
    can, emigrants who have returned to India. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Power to 
    authorise persons to exercise functions of a Protector.—The 
    Central Government may, if satisfied that it is necessary so to do in the 
    interest of emigrants or intending emigrants, authorise any person to 
    perform all or any of the functions of a Protector of Emigrants under this 
    Act. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Emigration check-posts.—
<section><number>1</number> Where 
    the Central Government considers that, with a view to preventing or checking 
    the contravention of the provisions of this Act, it is necessary so to do, 
    it may, by notification, set up such number of emigration check-posts at 
    such places as may be specified. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Central Government may, by general or special order made in this behalf, 
    appoint an officer of the Central Government or of a State Government to be 
    an officer in charge of an emigration check-post set up under sub- 
    section (1). 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An officer 
    in charge of an emigration check-post shall be subject to the general 
    control and supervision of the Protector of Emigrants within the local 
    limits of whose jurisdiction that emigration check-post is situated. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Other 
    emigration officers and staff.—The 
    Central Government may appoint such other officers and employees 
    (hereinafter referred to as the emigration officers and emigration 
    employees), as it may think fit, to assist the Protector General of 
    Emigrants and the Protector of Emigrants in the performance of their duties 
    under this Act. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Emigration officers to be public servants.—The 
    Protector General of Emigrants, Protectors of Emigrants, the officers in 
    charge of emigration check-posts, emigration officers and emigration 
    employees appointed under this Act shall be public servants within the 
    meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860). 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Registering authority.—The 
    Central Government may, by notification, appoint the Protector General of 
    Emigrants or any other officer of that Government of a rank higher than that 
    of a Protector of Emigrants to be the registering authority for the purposes 
    of this Act. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> No 
    person to function as recruiting agent without a valid certificate.—Save 
    as otherwise provided in this Act, no recruiting agent shall, after the 
    commencement of this Act, commence or carry on the business of recruitment 
    except under and in accordance with a certificate issued in that behalf by 
    the registering authority: 
 
Provided that 
    a person carrying on the business of recruiting agent immediately before the 
    commencement of this Act may continue to carry on such business without such 
    a certificate for a period of one month from such commencement, and if he 
    has made an application for such certificate under this Act within the said 
    period of one month and such application is in the prescribed form and 
    contains the prescribed particulars, till the disposal of such application 
    by the registering authority. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Application for registration.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    An application for registration shall be made to the registering authority 
    in such form and shall contain such particulars as to the applicant’s 
    financial soundness, trustworthiness, premises at which he intends to carry 
    on his business, facilities at his disposal for recruitment, his antecedents 
    (including information as to whether any certificate had been issued to him 
    under this Chapter earlier and if so, whether such certificate had been 
    cancelled) and previous experience, if any, of recruitment and other 
    relevant matters as may be prescribed and shall be accompanied by a receipt 
    evidencing the payment of the prescribed fee and an affidavit giving his 
    current financial standing and an undertaking in the form prescribed to the 
    effect that in the event of any information furnished in or along with the 
    application for registration being found to be false or incorrect in any 
    respect, the certificate shall be liable to be cancelled at any time in 
    accordance with the procedure prescribed: 
 
Provided that 
    no application shall be entertained under this sub-section from a person 
    disqualified under sub-section (6) of section 14 till the expiry of the 
    period of such disqualification. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On receipt 
    of such application, the registering authority shall,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   if the application is not in the 
    prescribed form or does not contain any of the prescribed particulars, 
    return the application to the applicant; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   if the application is in the prescribed 
    form and contains the prescribed particulars, inform the applicant that he 
    is eligible for the grant of the certificate applied for and, after giving 
    the applicant an opportunity to be heard, determine, under sub-section (3), 
    the amount of the security which the applicant shall furnish. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    registering authority shall, for securing the due performance of the terms 
    and conditions of the certificate proposed to be issued by it under 
    sub-section (2) to an applicant and for securing compliance with the 
    provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder and for meeting 
    expenses which may have to be incurred in the event of the repatriation to 
    India of any of the emigrants who may be recruited by the applicant, 
    determine, in accordance with the rules made in this behalf, the amount of 
    security (not being in any case less than one lakh of rupees) which shall be 
    furnished by the applicant. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If an 
    applicant furnishes in the prescribed manner the amount of security 
    determined under sub-section (3) within a period of one month from the date 
    on which the registering authority requires him to furnish such security, he 
    shall be issued the certificate applied for by him together with an 
    endorsement thereon to the effect that the security required has been 
    furnished by him. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If an 
    applicant fails to furnish the security required to be furnished by him 
    within the period specified in sub-section (4) his application shall be 
    deemed to have been rejected by the registering authority on the date of 
    expiry of that period. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Terms 
    and conditions of registration.—A 
    certificate issued under section 11 shall be— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   in such form as may be prescribed; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   valid for such period not exceeding five 
    years as may be prescribed: 
 
Provided that a certificate may be issued for 
    a period shorter than the prescribed period— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   if the person to whom it is issued so 
    desires; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   if the registering authority, for 
    reasons to be communicated in writing to the applicant for the certificate, 
    considers in any case that the certificate should be issued for a shorter 
    period; 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>c</number>   subject to such other terms and 
    conditions, including in particular, the maintenance by the holder of the 
    certificate of the prescribed records containing details of his financial 
    transactions in regard to recruitment, persons recruited or assisted to 
    emigrate by him, employers concerned, contracts and other arrangements 
    entered into in connection with recruitment, as may be prescribed: 
 
Provided that 
    a certificate may, contain, in addition to the prescribed terms and 
    conditions, such other terms and conditions as the registering authority 
    may, for securing the purposes of this Act, impose in any particular case. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> Renewal 
    of registration.—A certificate 
    may be renewed from time to time and the provisions of this Act and the 
    rules made thereunder (including provisions as to fees) shall apply to the 
    renewal of a certificate as they apply to the issue thereof: 
 
Provided that 
    no certificate shall be renewed unless the application for its renewal is 
    made not less than three months prior to the date on which the certificate, 
    would, but for such renewal, cease to be valid: 
 
Provided 
    further that the registering authority may entertain an application for the 
    renewal of a certificate which has been made at any time during the period 
    of three months prior to the date on which the certificate would, but for 
    such renewal, cease to be valid if the applicant satisfies the registering 
    authority that he had sufficient cause for not making such application 
    before the said period. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Cancellation, suspension, etc., of a certificate.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The registering authority may cancel any certificate on any one or more of 
    the following grounds and on no other ground, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   that having regard to the manner in 
    which the holder of the certificate has carried on his business or any 
    deterioration in his financial position, the facilities at his disposal for 
    recruitment, the holder of the certificate is not a fit person to continue 
    to hold the certificate; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   that the holder of the certificate has 
    recruited emigrants for purposes prejudicial to the interests of India or 
    for purposes contrary to public policy; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   that the holder of the certificate has, 
    subsequent to the issue of the certificate, been convicted in India for any 
    offence involving moral turpitude; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   that the holder of the certificate has, 
    subsequent to the issue of the certificate, been convicted by a court in 
    India for any offence under this Act, the Emigration Act, 1922 (7 of 1922), 
    or any other law relating to passports, foreign exchange, drugs, narcotics 
    or smuggling and sentenced in respect thereof to imprisonment for not less 
    than six months; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   that the certificate has been issued or 
    renewed on misrepresentation or suppression of any material fact; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   that the holder of the certificate has 
    violated any of the terms and conditions of the certificate; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>   that in the opinion of the Central 
    Government it is necessary in the interests of friendly relations of India 
    with any foreign country or in the interests of the general public to cancel 
    the certificate. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the 
    registering authority, for reasons to be recorded in writing, is satisfied 
    that pending the consideration of the question of cancelling any certificate 
    on any of the grounds mentioned in sub-section (1) it is necessary so to do, 
    the registering authority may, by order in writing, suspend the operation of 
    the certificate for such period not exceeding thirty days as may be 
    specified in the order and require the holder of the certificate to show 
    cause, within fifteen days from the date of receipt of such order, as to why 
    the suspension of the certificate should not be extended till the 
    determination of the question as to whether the registration should be 
    cancelled. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A court 
    convicting a holder of a certificate for an offence under this Act may also 
    cancel the certificate: 
 
Provided that 
    if the conviction is set aside in appeal or otherwise, the cancellation 
    under sub-section (3) shall become void. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> An order 
    of cancellation of a certificate may be made under sub-section (3) by an 
    appellate court or by a court exercising its powers of revision. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Before 
    passing an order cancelling or suspending a certificate the registering 
    authority or the court, as the case may be, shall consider the question as 
    to provisions and arrangements which should be made for safeguarding the 
    interests of emigrants and other persons with whom the holder of the 
    certificate had any transactions in the course of his business as recruiting 
    agent and may make such orders (including orders permitting the holder of 
    the certificate to continue to carry on his business with respect to all or 
    any of such emigrants and other persons) as it may consider necessary in 
    this behalf. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Where a 
    certificate issued to any person has been cancelled under this section, such 
    person shall not be eligible to make any application for another certificate 
    under this Chapter until the expiry of a period of two years from the date 
    of such cancellation. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Competent authority.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Central Government may, by notification, appoint the Protector General of 
    Emigrants or any other officer of that Government of a rank higher than that 
    of a Protector of Emigrants to be the authority (hereinafter referred to as 
    the competent authority) for issuing permits under this Chapter. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), the Central 
    Government may, by notification, authorise any person who is employed under 
    that Government in any country or place outside India to exercise the powers 
    of the competent authority, and issue permits under this Chapter to 
    employers who are not citizens of India for the purpose of recruiting any 
    citizen of India for employment in such country or place and a person so 
    authorised shall endorse a duly certified copy of every permit issued by him 
    under this Chapter to the Protector General of Emigrants. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Recruitment by employers to be through recruiting agent or under permit.—Save 
    as otherwise provided by or under this Act, no employer shall recruit any 
    citizen of India for employment in any country or place outside India 
    except— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   through a recruiting agent competent 
    under this Act to make such recruitment, or 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   in accordance with a valid permit issued 
    in this behalf under this Chapter. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Procedure for obtaining permits.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    An employer desiring to obtain a permit under this Chapter may make an 
    application in that behalf in the prescribed form to the competent 
    authority. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On receipt 
    of such application, the competent authority shall, subject to any rules 
    made in this behalf, make such inquiry as he may deem necessary and grant 
    the permit applied for or reject the application: 
 
Provided that 
    before granting a permit the competent authority may require the applicant 
    to comply with such conditions as may be prescribed, including conditions as 
    to furnishing of security and such other conditions as that authority may, 
    for reasons to be recorded in writing, deem necessary in the interests of 
    the citizens of India likely to be recruited by the applicant. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Subject to 
    the other provisions of this Act, the competent authority may reject an 
    application under sub-section (1) on any or more of the following grounds 
    and on no other ground, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   that the application is not complete in 
    all respects or that any of the material particulars furnished in the 
    application are not true; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   that the terms and conditions of 
    employment which the applicant proposes to offer to persons recruited or 
    proposed to be recruited by him are discriminatory or exploitative; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   that the employment which the applicant 
    proposes to offer involves work of a nature which is unlawful according to 
    the laws of India or offends against the public policy of India or is 
    violative of norms of human dignity and decency; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   that having regard to the antecedents of 
    the applicant, his financial standing, the facilities at his disposal, the 
    working and living conditions of persons employed by him in the past, it 
    would not be in the public interest or in the interest of the persons who 
    may be recruited by him, to issue a permit to him; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   that having regard to the prevailing 
    circumstances in the country or in the place where the applicant proposes to 
    employ the persons recruited by him, it would not be in the interests of any 
    citizen of India to emigrate for taking up such employment. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> Where the 
    competent authority makes an order under sub-section (2) rejecting an 
    application, he shall record in writing a brief statement of his reasons for 
    making such other and furnish the applicant, on demand, a copy of the same: 
 
Provided that 
    if the competent authority is of the opinion that it is necessary or 
    expedient in the interests of friendly relations with a foreign country or 
    in the interests of the general public so to do, he may refuse to provide 
    such copy, or, as the case may be, furnish a copy of only such parts of the 
    statement as he may deem fit. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> Period 
    of validity of permit.—A permit 
    issued under section 17 shall be valid till the expiry of such period, not 
    exceeding one year, as may be prescribed, from the date of issue thereof, or 
    till the recruitment of the persons for whose recruitment such permit is 
    issued is completed, whichever is earlier: 
 
Provided that 
    where the holder of the permit has been unable for sufficient cause, to 
    complete such recruitment before the expiry of the prescribed period, the 
    prescribed authority may, subject to rules made in this behalf, extend the 
    period of validity of the permit by such further period or periods, not 
    exceeding three months at a time. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Registration of certain permits.—Any 
    permit obtained from a person authorised under sub-section (2) of section 15 
    shall not be valid unless a certified copy thereof is filed in the 
    prescribed manner with the Protector General of Emigrants. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> 
    Cancellation or suspension of a permit.—The 
    provisions of section 14 relating to cancellation and suspension of a 
    certificate referred to therein shall, subject to such modifications as may 
    be necessary (including modifications for construing the references in that 
    section to registering authority as references to competent authority under 
    this Chapter), apply for the cancellation or suspension of a permit. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>21</number> Power 
    to exempt.—The Central Government 
    may, if satisfied that it is necessary or expedient so to do in the public 
    interest, by notification and subject to such conditions, if any, as may be 
    specified in the notification, exempt any class or classes of employers from 
    the requirement of obtaining a permit under this Chapter. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Requirement, etc., as to emigration clearance.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No citizen of India shall emigrate unless he obtains under this Chapter from 
    the Protector of Emigrants authorisation in the prescribed manner and form 
    (such authorisation being hereinafter referred to as emigration clearance) 
    for emigration. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An 
    application for emigration clearance shall be in the prescribed form, shall 
    contain the prescribed particulars and shall be made by the emigrant 
    concerned to the Protector of Emigrants: 
 
Provided that 
    such application may be made through the recruiting agent, if any, through 
    whom the emigrant has been recruited or through the employer concerned. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every 
    application under sub-section (2) shall be accompanied by— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   a true copy (verified and authenticated 
    in the prescribed manner) of the agreement with respect to the employment 
    for the taking up of which the applicant proposes to emigrate and where such 
    agreement does not provide for all or any of the prescribed matters, also a 
    statement (verified and authenticated in the prescribed manner) setting out 
    the particulars with respect to such matters; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   a statement (verified and authenticated 
    in the prescribed manner) as to the provision by way of security for meeting 
    the expenses which may be incurred in case it becomes necessary to arrange 
    for the repatriation to India of the applicant; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   a receipt evidencing the payment of the 
    prescribed fee; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   such other relevant documents or copies 
    of relevant documents as may be prescribed. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Protector of Emigrants shall, after satisfying himself about the accuracy of 
    the particulars mentioned in the application and in the other documents 
    submitted along with the application, authorise in the prescribed manner and 
    form, the emigration of the applicant or intimate by order in writing the 
    applicant or, as the case may be, the recruiting agent or employer through 
    whom the applications have been made about the deficiencies and require him 
    to make good such deficiencies within such time as may be specified in the 
    order or reject the application. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Subject to 
    the other provisions of this Act, the Protector of Emigrants may reject an 
    application for emigration clearance under this section on any one or more 
    of the following grounds and on no other ground, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   that the terms and conditions of 
    employment which the applicant proposes to take up are discriminatory or 
    exploitative; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   that the employment which the applicant 
    proposes to take up involves work of a nature which is unlawful according to 
    the laws of India or offends against the public policy of India or is 
    violative of norms of human dignity and decency; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   that the applicant will have to work or 
    live in sub-standard working or living conditions; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   that having regard to the prevailing 
    circumstances in the country or place where the applicant proposes to take 
    up employment or the antecedents of the employer under whom the applicant 
    proposes to take up employment or any other relevant circumstances, it would 
    not be in the interests of the applicant to emigrate; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   that no provision or arrangement has 
    been made for meeting the expenses which may be incurred in case it becomes 
    necessary to arrange for the repatriation to India of the applicant, or that 
    the provisions or arrangements made in this behalf are not adequate for the 
    purpose. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>6</number> Every 
    order rejecting an application for emigration clearance shall set out 
    clearly the ground or grounds on which the order has been made and the facts 
    or circumstances on which such ground or grounds are based. 
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> 
    Appeals.—
<section><number>1</number> Any person aggrieved 
    by— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   an order of the registering authority 
    rejecting his application for registration or requiring him to furnish any 
    security or to comply with any term or condition (not being a prescribed 
    term or condition) specified in the certificate issued to him or suspending 
    or cancelling or refusing to renew the certificate issued to him; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   an order of the competent authority 
    rejecting his application for a permit or requiring him to comply with any 
    terms or conditions (not being a prescribed term or condition) specified in 
    the permit issued to him, or suspending or cancelling or refusing to extend 
    the period of the validity of the permit issued to him; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   an order of the Protector of Emigrants 
    rejecting his application for emigration clearance; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   an order of the registering authority or 
    the competent authority or the Protector of Emigrants or the prescribed 
    authority requiring him to furnish any security, additional security or 
    fresh security under this Act, or forfeiting or rejecting his claim for 
    refund (whether wholly or partly in either case) of the security, the 
    additional security or the fresh security furnished by him, 
 
may prefer an appeal against such order to the 
    Central Government within such period as may be prescribed. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> No appeal 
    shall be admitted if it is preferred after the expiry of the period 
    prescribed therefor: 
 
Provided that 
    an appeal may be admitted after the expiry of the period prescribed therefor 
    if the appellant satisfies the Central Government that he had sufficient 
    cause for not preferring the appeal within that period. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The period 
    prescribed for an appeal shall be computed in accordance with the provisions 
    of the Limitation Act, 1963 (36 of 1963), with respect to the computation of 
    periods thereunder. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every 
    appeal under this section shall be made in such form as may be prescribed 
    and shall be accompanied by a copy of the order appealed against and by such 
    fee as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    procedure for disposing of an appeal (including remand of the matter for 
    further consideration to the authority whose order has been appealed 
    against) shall be such as may be prescribed: 
 
Provided that 
    before disposing of an appeal, the appellant shall be given a reasonable 
    opportunity of representing his case. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Every 
    order made on an appeal under this section confirming, modifying or 
    reversing the order appealed against shall be final. 
  
  
  
  
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Offences and penalties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whoever— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   except in conformity with the provisions 
    of this Act emigrates; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   contravenes the provisions of section 10 
    or section 16; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   by intentionally furnishing any false 
    information or suppressing any material information obtains a certificate or 
    a permit or an emigration clearance under this Act; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   without lawful authority makes or causes 
    to be made any alteration in any certificate or permit or in any document or 
    endorsement by way of emigration clearance issued or made under this Act; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   disobeys or neglects to comply with any 
    order of the Protector of Emigrants under this Act; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   collects from an emigrant any charges in 
    excess of the limits prescribed under this Act; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>   cheats any emigrant, 
 
shall be punishable with imprisonment for a 
    term which may extend to two years and with fine which may extend to two 
    thousand rupees: 
 
Provided that 
    in the absence of any special and adequate reasons to the contrary to be 
    mentioned in the judgment of the court, such imprisonment shall not be less 
    than six months and such fine shall not be less than one thousand rupees. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Whoever 
    attempts to commit any offence under sub-section (1) shall be punishable 
    with the punishment provided for such offence under that sub-section. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Whoever 
    contravenes any term or condition subject to which any emigration clearance 
    has been given under this Act, shall, if no other punishment is provided 
    elsewhere in this Act for such contravention, be punishable with 
    imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year or with fine which may 
    extend to two thousand rupees or with both. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Whoever 
    abets any offence punishable under this Act shall, if the act abetted is 
    committed in consequence of the abetment, be punishable with the punishment 
    provided for that offence. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Whoever, 
    having been convicted of an offence under any provision of this Act is again 
    convicted of an offence under the same provision, shall be punishable, for 
    the second and for each subsequent offence, with double the penalty provided 
    for that offence. 
  
  
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Offences by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> Where 
    an offence under this Act has been committed by a company, every person who, 
    at the time of the offence was committed, was in charge of, and was 
    responsible to, the company for the conduct of the business of the company, 
    as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and 
    shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly: 
 
Provided that 
    nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to 
    any punishment, if he proves that the offence was committed without his 
    knowledge or that he had exercised all due diligence to prevent the 
    commission of such offence. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where any offence 
    under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the 
    offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is 
    attributable to any neglect on the part of any director, manager, secretary 
    or other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary or other 
    officer shall be deemed to be guilty of that offence, and shall be liable to 
    be proceeded against and punished accordingly. 
 
Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   “company” means any body corporate and 
    includes a firm or other association of individuals; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   “director”, in relation to a firm, means 
    a partner in the firm. 
  
  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>26</number> 
    Offences to be cognizable.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), all 
    offences under this Act shall be cognizable. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>27</number> 
    Previous sanction of Central Government necessary.—No 
    prosecution shall be instituted against any person in respect of any offence 
    under this Act without the previous sanction of the Central Government or 
    such officer or authority as may be authorised by that Government by order 
    in writing in this behalf: 
 
Provided that 
    no sanction shall be required when an offence has been committed in respect 
    of an emigrant or an intending emigrant and the complaint is filed by such 
    emigrant or intending emigrant, or on behalf of such emigrant or intending 
    emigrant, by the father, mother, husband, wife, son, daughter, brother, 
    sister or guardian of such emigrant or intending emigrant or if such 
    emigrant or intending emigrant is a member of a joint Hindu family, by the 
    manager of that family. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>28</number> Punishment to be without prejudice to any 
      other action.—The award of 
      punishment for an offence under this Act shall be without prejudice to any 
      other action which has been or which may be taken under this Act with 
      respect to such contravention. 
 
  </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>29</number> Determination of question as to whether a person is an emigrant. </title>—Where a question arises before a Protector of Emigrants as to whether a person intending to depart from India is or is not an emigrant, the Protector of Emigrants shall decide the question after holding an inquiry in such manner and upon considering such evidence as may be prescribed and such other evidence as may be relevant, and communicate the decision to such person in the prescribed manner. 
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>30</number> Power 
    to prohibit emigration to any country in interests of the general public, 
    etc.—
<section><number>1</number> Where the Central 
    Government has reason to believe that sufficient grounds exist for 
    prohibiting emigration to any country, having regard to the sovereignty and 
    integrity of India, the security of India, friendly relations of India with 
    any foreign country or the interests of the general public, if may, by 
    notification, prohibit emigration to that country. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    notification issued under sub-section (1) shall have effect for such period 
    not exceeding six months as may be specified in the notification: 
 
Provided that 
    if the Central Government has reason to believe that the grounds mentioned 
    in sub-section (1) continues to exist, it may, from time to time, by 
    notification, prohibit emigration to that country for such further period, 
    not exceeding six months on each occasion, as may be specified in the 
    notification. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>31</number> Power 
    to prohibit emigration due to outbreak of epidemics, civil disturbances, 
    etc., in a country.—
<section><number>1</number> Where the 
    Central Government has reason to believe— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   that intending emigrants if allowed to 
    emigrate to any country would be exposed to serious risk to life on arrival 
    there by reason of— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   outbreak of any disease or grave 
    pollution of environment in such country; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   outbreak of hostilities or civil war or 
    civil commotion or political disturbances; 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   that by reason of India not being in 
    diplomatic relations with that country it is not possible to protect the 
    emigrants from discrimination, maltreatment and exploitation,  
    
 
it may, by notification, prohibit emigration 
    to that country. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    notification issued under sub-section (1) shall have effect for such period 
    not exceeding six months as may be specified in the notification: 
 
Provided that 
    if the Central Government has reason to believe that any ground mentioned in 
    sub-section (1) continues to exist, it may, from time to time, by 
    notification, prohibit emigration to that country for such further period, 
    not exceeding six months on each occasion, as may be specified in the 
    notification. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>32</number> Power 
    to prohibit emigration of any class or category of persons.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the Central Government considers that in the interests of the general 
    public, emigration of any class or category of persons, having regard to 
    their age, sex or other relevant factors, to any country should be 
    prohibited, it may, by notification, prohibit the emigration to such country 
    of such class or category of persons as may be specified in the 
    notification.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    notification issued under sub-section (1) shall have effect for such period 
    not exceeding six months as may be specified in the notification: 
 
Provided that 
    if the Central Government has reason to believe that any of the grounds 
    mentioned in sub-section (1) continues to exist, it may, from time to time, 
    by notification, prohibit emigration of such class or category of persons to 
    that country for such further period, not exceeding six months on each 
    occasion, as may be specified in the notification. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>33</number> 
    Provision as to security.—
<section><number>1</number> Any 
    security or other financial provision which may be required to be made under 
    this Act shall be reasonable having regard to the purpose for which such 
    security or other financial provision is required to be made. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    prescribed authority may, after giving notice in the prescribed manner to a 
    person who has furnished any security for any purpose and after giving to 
    such person an opportunity to represent his case, by order in writing, 
    direct that the whole or any part of such security may be forfeited for 
    being utilised for such purpose and in such manner as may be specified in 
    the order. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where it 
    appears to the prescribed authority that the security furnished by any 
    person under this Act for any purpose has, for any reason, become 
    inadequate, or has ceased to be available for any reason whatsoever, the 
    prescribed authority may, after giving him an opportunity to represent his 
    case, by order in writing, require such person to furnish such additional 
    security or, as the case may be, such fresh security as may be specified in 
    the order. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>34</number> Refund 
    of security.—Any security 
    furnished under this Act shall be refunded or, as the case may be, released, 
    when no longer required for the purpose for which it has been furnished and 
    the other circumstances in which and the manner in which any security 
    furnished under this Act may be released or refunded shall be such as may be 
    prescribed. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>35</number> Power 
    to search, seize and detain persons, conveyance, etc.—All 
    the powers for the time being conferred by the Customs Act, 1962 (52 of 
    1962), on officers of customs with regard to the searching and detention of 
    persons, vessels or aircraft or any other conveyance, or seizure of any 
    document or thing or arrest of any person or otherwise for the purpose of 
    prevention or detection of any offence under that Act or for apprehending a 
    person suspected to have committed any offence under that Act may be 
    exercised for the purpose of prevention or detection of any offence under 
    this Act or for apprehending a person suspected to have committed any 
    offence under this Act, by— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   any such officer of customs, or  
    
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   the Protector General of Emigrants or a 
    Protector of Emigrants, or  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   an officer in charge of an emigration 
    check-post. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>36</number> Returns 
    and registers.—
<section><number>1</number> Every 
    recruiting agent shall maintain such registers and other records and shall 
    submit to the prescribed authorities such periodical or other returns as may 
    be prescribed. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Protector General of Emigrants, the registering authority, the competent 
    authority or a Protector of Emigrants may, by order, call for any other 
    return or information from a recruiting agent. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Protector General of Emigrants, the registering authority, the competent 
    authority or a Protector of Emigrants or an officer in charge of an 
    emigration check-post may inspect any register or other record maintained by 
    a recruiting agent under sub-section (1) and for the purpose of such 
    inspection, enter, at any reasonable time, the business premises of a 
    recruiting agent.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>37</number> 
    Authorities and officers to have certain powers of civil court.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Protector General of Emigrants, the registering authority, the competent 
    authority and every Protector of Emigrants shall, for the purpose of 
    discharging their functions under this Act, have the same powers as are 
    vested in a court under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) while 
    trying a suit, in respect of the following matters, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   summoning and enforcing the attendance 
    of witnesses; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   requiring the discovery and production 
    of any document; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   requisitioning any public record or copy 
    thereof from any court or office; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   receiving evidence on affidavits; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   issuing commissions for the examination 
    of witnesses or documents. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    proceeding before the Protector General of Emigrants, or the registering 
    authority or the competent authority or a Protector of Emigrants shall be a 
    judicial proceeding within the meaning of sections 193 and 228 of the Indian 
    Penal Code (45 of 1860) and the Protector General of Emigrants, the 
    registering authority, the competent authority, and every Protector of 
    Emigrants shall be deemed to be a civil court for the purposes of section 
    195 and Chapter XXVI of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974). 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>38</number> Power 
    to give directions.—The Central 
    Government may give directions to the Protector General of Emigrants, the 
    registering authority, the competent authority or any Protector of Emigrants 
    as to the carrying into execution of any provision of this Act. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>39</number> Effect 
    of other laws.—
<section><number>1</number> The provisions 
    of this Act or any rule made thereunder shall have effect notwithstanding 
    anything inconsistent therewith contained in any enactment other than this 
    Act or in any agreement or other instrument having effect by virtue of any 
    enactment other than this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Save as 
    provided in sub-section (1), the provisions of this Act shall be in addition 
    to, and not in derogation of, any other law for the time being in force. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>40</number> 
    Delegation.—The Central 
    Government may, by notification direct that any power or function— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   which may be exercised or performed by 
    it under this Act, or 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   which may be exercised or performed by a 
    registering authority, competent authority or a Protector of Emigrants under 
    this Act, 
 
may, in relation to such matters, and subject 
    to such conditions, if any, as it may specify in the notification, be also 
    exercised or performed— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   by such officer or authority subordinate 
    to the Central Government, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   by any State Government or by any 
    officer or authority subordinate to such State Government, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   in any foreign country in which there 
    is no diplomatic mission of India, by such foreign consular office, 
 
as may be specified in the notification. 
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>41</number> Power 
    to exempt.—
<section><number>1</number> Where the Central 
    Government, on a reference made to it or otherwise, is satisfied that having 
    regard to— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the friendly relations with any foreign 
    country; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   the known reputation of any foreign 
    employer or class of foreign employers, for providing to emigrants standard 
    conditions of living and working, and their methods of recruitment and 
    conditions of employment; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   the methods of recruitment followed and 
    the conditions of employment provided by a public undertaking or an approved 
    concern for the execution of its projects abroad; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   the facilities and conditions of service 
    provided by Government officers posted abroad to their domestic servants 
    accompanying such Government officers, where the expenditure in respect of 
    the passage of such domestic servants is borne by the Government; and  
    
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   all other relevant considerations, 
 
it is necessary or expedient in the public 
    interest so to do the Central Government may, by notification, and subject 
    to such conditions, if any, as may be specified in the notification, exempt 
    from the operation of all or any of the provisions of this Act, such foreign 
    dignitary or class of foreign employers, public undertaking, approved 
    concern or Government officers. 
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    this sub-section— 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>a</number>   “public undertaking” means— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   an undertaking owned and controlled by 
    Government; or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   a Government company as defined in 
    section 617 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956); or  
    
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>   a body corporate established by or 
    under any Central, Provincial or State Act; 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   “approved concern” means such company 
    incorporated under the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) or partnership firm 
    registered under the Indian Partnership Act, 1932 (9 of 1932) or society 
    registered under the Societies Registration Act, 1860 (21 of 1860) or any 
    other law relating to societies for the time being in force in any State, or 
    co-operative society registered under any Central, Provincial or State law, 
    as the Central Government may, by notification, approve for the purposes of 
    this section. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If the 
    Central Government is satisfied that it is necessary for implementing any 
    treaty, agreement or convention between India and a foreign country or 
    foreign countries so to do, it may, by notification, and subject to such 
    conditions, if any, as may be specified in the notification, exempt from the 
    operation of all or any of the provisions of this Act, recruitment by such 
    authorities, agencies or persons as may be specified in the notification 
    either generally or for such purposes as may be specified in the 
    notification. 
 
 
Section 617 of the Companies 
      Act, 1956 is reproduced below:— 
 
 

 
  


</section><section>
    <number>617</number> 
      Definition of “Government Company”.—For the purposes of this Act, 
      Government Company means any company in which not less than fifty-one per 
      cent. of the paid-up share capital is held by the Central Government, or 
      by any State Government or Governments, or partly by the Central 
      Government and partly by one or more State Governments and includes a 
      Company which is a subsidiary of a Government Company as thus defined. 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>42</number> Act not to apply to certain 
      emigrants.—Nothing contained in 
      this Act shall be deemed to apply to— 
 <section><number>a</number>   the recruitment or 
      emigration of any person who is not a citizen of India; 
 </section><section><number>b</number>   the control of 
      recruiting in India for the service of foreign States to which the Foreign 
      Recruiting Act, 1874 (4 of 1874) applies. 
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>43</number> Power 
    to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
    Government may, by notification, make rules to carry out the provisions of 
    this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the powers and duties of officers and 
    employees appointed for the purposes of this Act and the terms and 
    conditions of their service; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   the form of— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   a certificate to commence or carry on 
    the business of recruitment, and of an application for the issue or renewal 
    thereof;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   a permit for the recruitment of persons 
    for employment outside India, and of an application for the issue thereof; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>   an application for emigration 
    clearance; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iv</number>   an appeal to be preferred to the 
    Central Government; 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   the manner and form in which an 
    authorisation by way of emigration clearance may be given; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   particulars to be contained in an 
    application for a certificate or a permit or for an emigration clearance; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   the manner in which different inquiries 
    required to be held under this Act may be held; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   the manner in which the amount of 
    security for securing the due performance of the terms and conditions of the 
    certificate of permit or for compliance with the provisions of this Act 
    shall be furnished; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>   the manner of verifying or 
    authenticating documents and copies of documents for the purposes of this 
    Act; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>   the procedure to be followed in hearing 
    an appeal preferred to the Central Government; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>   the fees to be paid in respect of 
    applications and other matters under this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>   the charges which a recruiting agent may 
    recover from an emigrant in respect of services rendered and the scales and 
    limits of such charges; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>   the terms and conditions subject to 
    which a certificate or a permit or an emigration clearance may be issued 
    under this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>   the period of the validity of a 
    certificate or a permit issued under this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number>   the authority competent to extend the 
    period of validity of a permit or to forfeit security or to require any 
    additional security or fresh security under this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>n</number>   the accommodation, the provisions, the 
    medical stores and staff, the life saving and sanitary arrangements and 
    other provisions and arrangement for the well-being, security and protection 
    of emigrants which shall be provided and the records which shall be 
    maintained in any emigrant conveyance. 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>o</number>   any other matter which is required to 
    be, or may be, prescribed. 
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>44</number> 
    Notifications and rules to be laid before Parliament.—Every 
    notification issued under clause (o) of sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 2, 
    section 30, section 31 or section 32 and every rule made under section 43 
    shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is issued or made, before each 
    House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty 
    days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive 
    sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the 
    session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making 
    any modification in the notification or the rule or both Houses agree that 
    the notification or the rule should not be issued or made, the notification 
    or the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of 
    no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
    annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously 
    done under that notification or rule. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>45</number> Repeal of Act 7 of 1922.—The Emigration Act, 1922 is hereby 
      repealed. 
  
  
  
 
  </article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>