<act><tid>996519</tid>
<title>THE MARRIED WOMEN' S PROPERTY (EXTENSION) ACT, <year>1959</year></title>

NO. 61 OF <year>1959</year>
[ 24th December, <year>1959</year>.]

An Act to provide for the extension of the Married Women' s Property 
Act, <year>1874</year>, to parts of India in which it is not now in force.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the TenthYear of the Republic of India 
as follows:-





<article><tid>639503</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>1704288</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Married Women' s Property (Extension) Act, <year>1959</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>380090</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date, as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1989686</tid>
<number>2</number>Amendment of section 2.- In section 2 of the Married Women' s 
Property Act, <year>1874</year> (3 of <year>1874</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the  
  principal Act), for the sentence" It extends to the whole of India 
except the territories which, immediately before the 1st Nove ber, 
<year>1956</year>, were comprised in Part B States.", the sentence" It extends to 
the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir." Shall be 
substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1123740</tid>
<number> 3</number> Amendment of section 6.- For sub- section (2) of section 6 of the 
principal Act, the following sub- section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (2) Notwithstanding anything contained in section 2, the provisions 
of sub- section (1) shall apply in the case of any policy of insurance 
such as is referred to therein which is effected-

<section><tid>332155</tid>
<number>a</number>by any Hindu, Muhammadan, Sikh or Jain-

<subsection><tid>828195</tid>
<number>i</number>in Madras, after the thirty- first day of December, <year>1913</year>, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1473376</tid>
<number>ii</number>in any other territory to which this Act extended immediately 
before the commencement of the Married Women' s Property (Extension) 
Act, <year>1959</year>, after the first day of April, <year>1923</year>, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1125089</tid>
<number>iii</number>in any territory to which this Act extends on and from the 
commencement of the Married Women' s Property (Extension) Act, <year>1959</year>, on 
or after such commencement;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>416007</tid>
<number>b</number>by a Buddhist in any territory to which this Act extends, on or 
after the commencement of the Married Women' s Property (Extension) 
Act, <year>1959</year>:
Provided that nothing herein contained shall affect any right or 
liability which has accrued or been incurred under any decree of a 
competent court passed-


<subsection><tid>1341473</tid>
<number>i</number>before the first day of April, <year>1923</year>, in any case to which 
sub- clause (i) or sub- clause (ii) of clause (a) applies; or 1. Ist 
March, <year>1960</year>, vide Notification No. S. O. 528, dated 29- 2- <year>1960</year>, see 
Gazette of India, Extraordinary, Part II, Section 3 (ii), page 77.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>942625</tid>
<number>ii</number>before the commencement of the Married Women' s Property 
 (Extension) Act, <year>1959</year>, in any case to which sub- clause (iii) of clause 
 (a) or clause (b) applies.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1362232</tid>
<number>4</number>Amendment of Act 30 of <year>1950</year>.- In Part A of the Schedule to the 
Union Territories (Laws) Act, <year>1950</year>, the entry relating to the Married 
Women' s Property Act, <year>1874</year>, shall be omitted.


</article>



<article><tid>1523848</tid>
<number> 5</number> Repeal and savings.- If immediately before the commencement of this 
Act, there is in force in any territory to which the principal Act is 
now extended any law corresponding to the principal Act, that law 
shall, save as otherwise expressly provided in his Act, stand repealed 
on such commencement:
Provided that the repeal shall not affect-

<section><tid>902214</tid>
<number>a</number>the previous operation of any law so repealed or anything duly 
done or suffered thereunder,

</section>

<section><tid>1159343</tid>
<number>b</number>any right, privilege, obligation or liability acquired, accrued or 
incurred under any law so repealed,

</section>

<section><tid>1130187</tid>
<number>c</number>any penalty, forfeiture or punishment incurred in respect of any 
offence committed against any law so repealed, or

</section>

<section><tid>168735</tid>
<number>d</number>any investigation, legal proceeding or remedy in respect of any 
such right, privilege, obligation, liability, penalty, forfeiture or 
punishment as aforesaid,
and any such investigation, legal proceeding or remedy may be 
instituted, continued or enforced, and any such penalty, forfeiture or 
punishment may be imposed as if this Act had not been passed:

Provided further that, subject to the preceding proviso, anything done 
or any action taken under any such law shall be deemed to have been 
done or taken under the corresponding provision of the principal Act, 
and shall continue to be in force accordingly unless and until 
superseded by anything done or any action taken under the principal 
Act.


</section>

</article>



 </act>