<act><title>THE OILFIELDS (REGULATION AND DEVELOPMENT) ACT, 
      1948</title> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> This Act may be 
      called the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[Oilfields] (Regulation and Development) Act, 
      1948.  
 </section><section><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> It extends to the whole of 
      India <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[***]. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> It shall come into force on such date<footcitenum>4</footcitenum> as the Central Government may, by notification 
      in the Official Gazette, appoint in this behalf.
 
    







 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>2</number> Declaration as to expediency of control by Central 
      Government.—[Rep. by the Mines and Minerals (Regulation 
      and Development) Act, 1957 (67 of 1957), sec. 32 and Sch. III (w.e.f. 
      1-6-1958).] 
    
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>3</number> Definitions.—In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant 
      in the subject or context,—
 <section><number>a</number> the expressions 
      “lessor” and “lessee”, respectively, include a licensor and licensee;  
      
 </section><section><number>b</number> “mine” means any 
      excavation for the purpose of searching for or obtaining [mineral oils] and 
      includes an oilwell;  
      
 </section><section><number>c</number> <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[“mineral oils”] include 
      natural gas and petroleum;  
      
 </section><section><number>d</number> “mining lease” 
      means a lease granted for the purpose of searching for, winning, working, 
      getting, making merchantable, carrying away or disposing away or disposing 
      of <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[mineral oils] 
      or for purposes connected therewith, and includes an exploring or a 
      prospecting licence;  
 </section><section><number>e</number> “oilfield” 
      means any area where any operation for the purpose of obtaining natural 
      gas and petroleum, crude oil, refined oil, partially refined oil and any 
      of the products of petroleum in a liquid or solid state, is to be or is 
      being carried on.  
  




 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>4</number> No mining lease to be valid unless it is in accordance with this 
      Act.—
<section><number>1</number> No mining lease shall be granted after the 
      commencement of this Act, otherwise than in accordance with the rules made 
      under this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any mining lease granted contrary to the provisions of 
      sub‑section (1) shall be void and of no effect.
    
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>5</number> Power to make rules as respects mining 
      leases.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government may, by notification 
      in the Official Gazette, make rules for regulating the grant of mining 
      leases or for prohibiting the grant of such leases in respect of any 
      <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[mineral oils] in any area.
 </section><section><number>2</number> In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
      foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following 
      matters, namely:—
 <subsection><number>a</number> the manner in which the 
      <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[mineral oils] or 
      area in respect of which, and the persons by whom, applications for mining 
      leases may be made and the fees to be paid on any such 
      applications;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the authority by which, 
      the terms on which, and the conditions subject to which, mining leases may 
      be granted;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the maximum or minimum 
      area and the period for which any mining lease may be granted, and the 
      terms on which leases in respect of contiguous area may be amalgamated;  
      
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> the fixing of the 
      maximum and minimum rent payable by a lessee, whether the mine is worked 
      or not.  
      
    





 
</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>6</number> Power to make rules as respects mineral 
      development.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government may, by notification 
      in the Official Gazette, make rules for the conservation and development 
      of <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[mineral oils].
 </section><section><number>2</number> In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
      foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following 
      matters, namely:—
 
 
<footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[***]
 <subsection><number>c</number> the development of any 
      <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[mineral oil resources] in any area by prescribing or 
      regulating the use of any engines, machinery or other 
equipment;
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> the regulation of the 
      drilling, re‑drilling, deepening, shutting down, plugging and abandoning 
      of oilwells in an oilfield and for the limitation or prohibition of such 
      operations and for the taking of remedial measures to prevent waste of or 
      damage to oil;
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> the regulation of the 
      methods of producing oil in any oilfield, and the limitation or 
      prohibition of such methods;
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> the compulsory 
      notifications of all new borings and shaft sinkings, and the preservation 
      of boring records and specimens of cores of all new bore‑holes;
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> the taking of samples 
      from mines and new bore‑holes;
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> the regulation of the 
      arrangements for the storage of 4[mineral oils] and the stocks 
      thereof that may be kept by any person;
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[<number>i</number> the collection of 
      royalties and the levy and collection of fees or taxes, in, respect of 
      mineral oils mined, quarried, excavated or collected;]
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number>
the submission by the owners or lesseses of mines of special or 
      periodical returns and reports; and the forms in which and the authorities 
      to whom such returns and reports shall be submitted.
    
  








 
</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[<number>6A</number> Royalties in respect of mineral 
      oils.—
<section><number>1</number> The holder of a mining lease granted 
      before the commencement of the Oilfields (Regulation and Development) 
      Amendment Act, 1969, shall, notwithstanding anything contained in the 
      instrument of lease or in any law in force at such commencement, pay 
      royalty in respect of any mineral oil mined, quarried, excavated, or 
      collected by him from the leased area after such commencement, at the rate 
      for the time being specified in the Schedule in respect of that mineral 
      oil.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The holder of a mining lease granted or on after the 
      commencement of the Oilfields (Regulation and Development) Amendment Act, 
      1969, shall pay royalty in respect of any mineral oil mined, quarried, 
      excavated or collected by him from the leased area at the rate for the 
      time being specified in the Schedule in respect of the mineral 
      oil.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub‑section (1) or 
      sub‑section (2) no royalty shall be Payable in respect of any crude oil, 
      casing‑head condensate or natural gas which is unavoidably lost or is 
      returned to the reservoir or is used for drilling or other operations 
      relating to the production of petroleum or natural gas, or 
      both.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Central Government may, by notification in the official 
      Gazette, amend the Schedule so as to enhance or reduce the rate at which 
      royalty shall be payable in respect of any mineral oil with effect from 
      such date as may be specified in the notification: 
 Provided that the Central Government shall not— 
 <subsection><number>a</number> fix the rate of royalty 
      in respect of any mineral oil so as to exceed twenty per cent. of the sale 
      price of the mineral oil at the oilfields or the oilwell‑head, as the case 
      may be, or
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> enhance the rate 
      of royalty in respect of any mineral oil more than once during any period 
      of <footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[three 
      years.]  
      
 </subsection></section><section><footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[<number>5</number> Notwithstanding anything 
      contained in sub‑section (4), the Central Government may, by notification 
      in the Official Gazette, amend the Schedule so as to enhance the rate of 
      royalty payable in respect of mineral oil, produced during the period 
      beginning on the 1st day of April, 1990 and ending on the 31st day of 
      March, 1993 to 24.52 per cent. of the sale price of mineral oil at the 
      oilfields or the oilwell‑head, as the case may be.]
   







 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>7</number> Power to make rules for modification of existing 
      leases.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government may, by notification 
      in the Official Gazette, make rules for the purpose of modifying or 
      altering the terms and conditions of any mining lease granted prior to the 
      commencement of this Act so as to bring such lease into conformity with 
      the rules made under sections 5 and 6:
 Provided that any rules so made which provide for the matters 
      mentioned in clause (c) of sub‑section (2) shall not come into force until 
      they have been approved, either with or without modifications, by 
      1[the House of the People].
 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The rules made under sub‑section (1) shall 
      provide—
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> for giving previous 
      notice of the modification or alteration proposed to be made thereunder to 
      the lessee; and where the lessor is not the Central Government, also to 
      the lessor and for affording them an opportunity of showing cause against 
      the proposal;  
      
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> for the payment of 
      compensation by the party who would be benefitted by the proposed 
      modification or alteration to the party whose rights under the existing 
      lease would thereby be adversely affected; and
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> for the principles on 
      which, the manner in which and the authority for which the said 
      compensation shall be determined.  
      
    




 
</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>8</number> Delegation.—The Central Government may, by notification in 
      the Official Gazette, direct that any power exercisable under this 
      Act shall be exercised, subject to such conditions, if any, as may be 
      specified therein by such officer or authority as may be specified in the 
      direction.
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>9</number> Penalties.—
<section><number>1</number> Any rule made under any of the 
      provisions of this Act may provide that any contravention thereof shall be 
      punishable with imprisonment which may provide that any contravention 
      thereof shall be punishable with imprisonment which may extend to six 
      months or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees or with 
      both. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Whoever, after having been convicted of any offence referred to 
      in sub‑section (2), continues to commit such offence shall be punishable 
      for each day after the date of the first conviction during which he 
      continues so to offend, with fine which may extend to one hundred 
      rupees.
  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[<number>10</number> Laying of rules and 
      notifications.—Every rule made under this Act and every 
      notification issued under sub-section (4) of section 6A shall be laid, as 
      soon as may be after it is made or issued, before each House of 
      Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days 
      which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive 
      sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following 
      the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in 
      making any modification in the rule or notification or both Houses agree 
      that the rule or notification should not be made or issued, the rule or 
      notification should not be made or issued, the rule or notification shall 
      thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as 
      the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment 
      shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done 
      under that rule or notification.]
  
    



 
</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>11</number> Power of inspection.—
<section><number>1</number> For the purpose of 
      ascertaining the position of the working actual or prospective, of any 
      mine or abandoned mine or for any other purpose mentioned in this Act or 
      the rules made thereunder, any officer authorized by the Central 
      Government in this behalf shall have the right to—
 <subsection><number>a</number> enter and inspect 
      any mine;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> order the 
      production of any document, book, register or record in the possession or 
      power of any person having the control of, or connected with, any mine;  
      
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> examine any 
      person having the control of, or connected with, any mine.  
      
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Any officer authorized by the Central Government under 
      sub‑section (1) shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning 
      of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code, 1860 (XLV of 
      1860).
 
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>12</number> Relaxation of rules in special cases.—The Central 
      Government may, if satisfied that it is in the public interest so to do, 
      authorize in any case the granting of any mining lease or the working of 
      any mine on terms and conditions different from those laid down in the 
      rules made under sections 5 and 6.
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>13</number> Act to be binding on the Government.—The provisions of 
      this Act shall be binding on the Government.
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>14</number> Protection of action taken in good 
      faith.—No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding 
      whatever shall lie against any person for anything which is in good faith 
      done or intended to be done under this Act. 
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 [THE 
      SCHEDULE
 (See section 6A)
 Rates of Royalty
 <article><number>1</number> Crude Oil
 <section><number>1</number> Production from areas outside 
      New Exploration Licensing Policy (NELP) regime
 <subsection><number>A</number>  Nomination Blocks:  
       
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> from 1-4-1993 to 31-3-1996: @ Rs. 
      539.20 per metric tonne
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> from 1-4-1996 to 31-3-1998: @ 
      603.95 per metric tonne
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>B</number>  Production from areas awarded 
      on nomination basis to National Oil Companies (NOCs), exploration blocks 
      awarded to Private/Joint Venture contractors prior to New Exploration 
      Licensing Policy (NELP) and onland discovered fields awarded to 
      Private/Joint Venture contractors:  
       
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> from 1-4-1998 to 31-3-2002: Monthly 
      average rate per metric tonne as per statement appended;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> With effect from 
      1-4-2002:
 <subsubsubsection><number>a</number> Onland areas: @ 
      20% of well head price
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>b</number> Shallow water 
      offshore areas (upto 400 mtr water depth): @ 10% of well head 
      price
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>c</number> Deep water 
      offshore areas (&gt; 400 mtr. water depth): @ 5% of well head price during 
      first 7 years after commercial production and normal rates as applicable 
      to shallow water areas (upto 400 mtr. water depth) during other 
      periods.
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>d</number> Heavier Crude 
      Oils of 25° API and less : 2.5% lesser than the applicable rates as 
      above
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>e</number> Reduced rates of 
      royalty, as may be notified by the Government form time to time, will be 
      levied on production from fields under Enhanced Oil Recovery 
      (EOR)/Impropved Oil Recovery (IOR).
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>C</number>  Production from offshore 
      discovered fields awarded to Private/Joint Venture contractors:  
       
 At the rates as specified in 
      respective Production Sharing Contracts (PSCs)  
       
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Production from areas under 
      nelp regime:
 At the rates determined in 
      accordance with the provisions under respective Production Sharing 
      Contracts (PSCs).
 </section></article><article><number>2</number> Casing Head 
      Condensate
 <section><number>1</number> Production from areas outside 
      New Exploration Licensing Policy (NELP) regime
 <subsection><number>A</number> Nomination Blocks:  
       
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> from 1-4-1993 to 31-3-1996: @ Rs. 
      539.20 per metric tonne
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> from 1-4-1996 to 31-3-1998: @ Rs. 
      603.95 per metric tonne
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>B</number> Production from areas awarded 
      on nomination basis to National Oil Companies (NOCs), Exploration blocks 
      awarded to Private/Joint Venture (Private/Joint Venture) contractors prior 
      to Nelp and onland 
      discovered fields awarded to Private/Joint Venture contractors:  
       
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> from 1-4-1998 to 
      31-3-2002: Monthly average rate per metric tonne as per statement 
      appended;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> With effect from 
      1-4-2002:
 <subsubsubsection><number>a</number> Onland areas: @ 
      20% of well head price
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>b</number> Shallow water 
      offshore areas (upto 400 mtr. water depth): @ 10% of well head 
      price
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>c</number> Deep water 
      offshore areas (&gt; 400 mtr. water depth): @ 5% of well head price during 
      first 7 years after commercial production and normal rates as applicable 
      to shallow water areas (upto 400 mtr. water depth) during other 
      periods.
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>d</number> Reduced rates of 
      royalty, as may be notified by the Government form time to time, will be 
      levied on production from fields under Enhanced Oil Recovery 
      (EOR)/Impropved Oil Recovery (IOR).
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>C</number> Production from offshore 
      discovered fields awarded to Private/Joint Venture contractors:  
       
 At the rates as specified in 
      respective Production Sharing Contracts (PSCs)  
       
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Production from areas under 
      Nelp regime:
 At the rates determined in 
      accordance with the provisions under respective Production Sharing 
      Contracts (PSCs).
 </section></article><article><number>3</number> Natural Gas
 Ten per cent of the value of the 
      natural gas obtained at well-head.
  
 Note 1.—Well Head Price of Crude Oil and Casing Head 
      Condensate for areas covered under 1, 
<section><number>1</number> B and 2(1) B, above will be 
      determined by deducting 7.5% and 10% of the Crude Oil and Casing Head 
      Condensate price considered for onland and offshore production 
      respectively.
 Royalty will be calculated on cum 
      – royalty basis as under:
 

Well Head Price x Royalty Rate
 Royalty amount 
      =       ————————————————
 

100 + Royalty Rate   
 Note 2.—Since consultations with the concerned State 
      Governments took some time, it has become necessary to revise the rate of 
      royalty with retrospective effect. The oil producing States stand to 
      benefit and other States are not likely to be adversely 
      affected.
  
 Statement of monthly average rates of royalty payable per metric 
       tonne on crude oil and casing head condensate as mentioned  at 1(1) 
      b(i) and 2. (1) B 
      (i) 
      above
 Details of Monthly Royalty 
      Rates
 
 
 
 Month
 Royalty Rates Rs / MT
  
 Month
 Royalty Rates Rs / MT
 
  
  
  
  
  
 
 Apr-98
 411.31
  
 Mar-00
 965.39
 
 May-98
 409.46
  
 Apr-00
 1055.88
 
 Jun-98
 414.09
  
 May-00
 1037.36
 
 July-98
 431.35
  
 Jun-00
 915.75
 
 Aug-98
 415.32
  
 Jul-00
 1100.28
 
 Sep-98
 450.01
 
 Aug-00
 1165.03
 
 Oct-98
 431.35
  
 Sep-00
 1126.65
 
 Nov-98
 483.15
  
 Oct-00
 1180.45
 
 Dec-98
 462.8
  
 Nov-00
 1331.39
 
 Jan-99
 409.53
  
 Dec-00
 1279.89
 
 Feb-99
 368.45
  
 Jan-01
 1298.23
 
 Mar-99
 398.67
  
 Feb-01
 973.71
 
 Apr-99
 374.77
  
 Mar-01
 1009.02
 
 May-99
 511.06
  
 Apr-01
 1104.29
 
 Jun-99
 569.64
  
 May-01
 1040.29
 
 1st 
            Jul,99 - 14th Jul-99
 569.64
  
 Jun-01
 1091.19
 
 15th Jul,99 - 31st Jul-99
 580.74
  
 Jul-01
 1165.5
 
 Aug-99
 602.17
  
 Aug-01
 1171.05
 
 Sep-99
 706.54
  
 Sep-01
 1066.21
 
 Oct-99
 769.29
  
 Oct-01
 1113.39
 
 Nov-99
 858.7
  
 Nov-01
 1106.76
 
 Dec-99
 846.99
  
 Dec-01
 904.03
 
 Jan-00
 942.11
  
 Jan-02
 808.29
 
 Feb-00
 958.91
  
 Feb-02
 815.23
 
  
  
  
 Mar-02
 851.77
  



 
</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by Act 67 of 1957, sec. 
      32 and Sch. III, for “mines and minerals” (w.e.f. 1-6-1958).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for 
      sub-section (2) (w.e.f. 26-1-1950).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> The words “except the State 
      of Jammu and Kashmir” omitted by Act 67 of 1957, sec. 32 and Sch. II 
      (w.e.f. 1-6-1958).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Came into force on 
      25-10-1949, vide Notification No. M-II-155(24)-1, dated 18th 
      October, 1949, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., 1949, p. 
      2075.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Subs. by Act 67 of 1957, sec. 
      32 and Sch. III, for “minerals” (w.e.f. 1-6-1958).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Subs. by Act 67 of 1957, sec. 
      32 and Sch. III, for “mineral” (w.e.f. 1-6-1958).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Subs. by Act 67 of 1957, sec. 
      32 and Sch. III, for “minerals” (w.e.f. 1-6-1958).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Subs. by Act 67 of 1957, sec. 
      32 and Sch. III, for “minerals” (w.e.f. 1-6-1958).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> Clauses (a) and (b) omitted 
      by Act 67 of 1957, sec. 32 and Sch. II (w.e.f. 1-6-1958).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> Subs. by Act 67 of 1957, sec. 
      32 and Sch. III, for “mineral resources” (w.e.f. 1-6-1958).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number> Subs. by Act 67 of 1957, sec. 
      32 and Sch. III, for “minerals” (w.e.f. 1-6-1958).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number> Subs. by Act 39 of 1969, sec. 
      2 for clause (i) (w.r.e.f. 1-1-1968).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number> Ins. by Act 39 of 1969, sec. 
      3 (w.r.e.f. 1-1-1968).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number> Subs. by Act 20 of 1984, sec. 
      2, for “four years” (w.e.f. 11-5-1984).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number> Ins. by Act 4 of 1993, sec. 2 
      (w.r.e.f. 30-1-1993).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number> Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for 
      “the Central Legislature” (w.e.f. 26-1-1950).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number> Subs. by Act 20 of 1984, sec. 
      3, for section 10 (w.e.f. 
      11-5-1984).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 
      814(E), dated 16th December, 
      2004.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>