<act><tid>997632</tid>
<title>THE HIMACHAL PRADESH AND BILASPUR (NEW STATE) ACT, <year>1954</year></title>

ACT NO. 32 OF <year>1954</year>
[ 28th May, <year>1954</year>.]

An Act to provide for the formation of the new State of Himachal 
Pradesh by uniting the existing States of Himachal Pradesh and 
Bilaspur, and for matters connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:--

PART

PRELIMINARY

PART I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1833890</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>844320</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Himachal Pradesh and Bilaspur (New State) Act, <year>1954</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1706772</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint in 
this behalf.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>875407</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>188367</tid>
<number>a</number>" article" means an article of the Constitution;
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>


</section>

<section><tid>1989785</tid>
<number>c</number>" existing States" mean the States specified as Bilaspur 
and Himachal Pradesh in Part C of the First Schedule to 
the Constitution immediately before the commencement of 
this Act, and" existing State" means either of the 
existing States;

</section>

<section><tid>245159</tid>
<number>d</number>" law" includes any enactment, ordinance, regulation, 
order, rule, scheme, notification, bye- law or other 
instrument having the force of law in the whole or in 
any part of either of the existing States;

</section>

<section><tid>1075090</tid>
<number>e</number>" Order" means an order published in the Official 
Gazette;

</section>

<section><tid>1050375</tid>
<number>f</number>" Parliamentary constituency" has the same meaning as in 
the Representation of the People Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of  
  <year>1950</year>);
<pagefootnote><pagenum>274</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1st July, <year>1954</year>, Gazette of India, <year>1954</year>, Extraordinary, Pt. II, 
Sec. 3, p. 1103. 
2. Cl. (b) omitted by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>43360</tid>
<number>g</number>" sitting member" in relation to either House of 
Parliament or in relation to the Legislature of the 
existing State of Himachal Pradesh, means a person who 
immediately before the commencement of this Act is a 
member of that House or that Legislature, as the case 
may be.
PART

FORMATION OF THE NEW STATE OF HIMACHAL PRADESH

PART II

FORMATION OF THE NEW STATE OF HIMACHAL PRADESH




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>733723</tid>
<number>3</number>Formation of the new State of Himachal Pradesh. As from the 
commencement of this Act there shall be formed by uniting the existing 
States a new Part C State to be known as the State of Himachal Pradesh 
 (hereafter in this Act referred to as the" new State").


</article>



<article><tid>754847</tid>
<number> 4</number> Amendment of the First Schedule to the Constitution. In the 
First Schedule to the Constitution, in Part C--
<section><tid>1625068</tid>
<number>a</number>under the heading" Names of States"--

<subsection><tid>728540</tid>
<number>i</number>entry" 3. Bilaspur" shall be omitted; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>784106</tid>
<number>ii</number>entries 4 to 10 shall be renumbered as 
entries 3 to 9 respectively;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1395251</tid>
<number>b</number>under the heading" Territories of States", after the 
first paragraph the following paragraph shall be 
inserted, namely:--
" The territory of the State of Himachal Pradesh 
shall comprise the territories which immediately before 
the commencement of the Himachal Pradesh and Bilaspur 
 (New State) Act, <year>1954</year> were comprised in the States of 
Bilaspur and Himachal Pradesh."

PART

REPRESENTATION IN THE LEGISLATURES

PART III

REPRESENTATION IN THE LEGISLATURES

Council of States




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>727274</tid>
<number> 5</number> Representation in the Council of States.
<section><tid>992966</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be  
allotted one seat to the new State in the Council of States.

</section>

<section><tid>1327811</tid>
<number>2</number>The sitting member of the Council of States representing the 
group of States comprising the existing States shall on and from the 
commencement of this Act represent the new State in the Council but 
the term of such sitting member shall remain unaltered, that is to 
say, shall expire on the 2nd of April, <year>1958</year>.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>275</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>134887</tid>
<number> 6</number> Amendment of the Fourth Schedule to the Constitution. In the 
Fourth Schedule to the Constitution, in the Table of Seats relating to 
the representatives of States specified in Part C of the First 
Schedule--
<section><tid>1745314</tid>
<number>i</number>for entries 4 and 5, the entry" 4. Himachal Pradesh 
.... 1" shall be substituted; and

</section>

<section><tid>1754800</tid>
<number>ii</number>entries 6 to 10 shall be renumbered as entries 5 to 9 
respectively.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1810531</tid>
<number> 7</number> Amendment of section 27A, Act 43 of <year>1950</year>. In section 27A of 
the Representation of the People Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of <year>1950</year>),--
<section><tid>1699592</tid>
<number>i</number>in sub- section (5), for the word" Delhi" the words 
" Delhi, Himachal Pradesh" shall be substituted; and

</section>

<section><tid>1492296</tid>
<number>ii</number>sub- section (6) shall be omitted.
House of the People




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>497478</tid>
<number>8</number>Representation in the House of the People. Until other 
provision is made by law, there shall be allotted 4 seats to the new 
State in the House of the People.


</article>



<article><tid>1059344</tid>
<number> 9</number> Amendment of the First Schedule, Act 43 of <year>1950</year>. In the First 
Schedule to the Representation of the People Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of <year>1950</year>), 
in the part relating to Part C States,--
<section><tid>1820362</tid>
<number>i</number>entry 3 shall be omitted;

</section>

<section><tid>1058682</tid>
<number>ii</number>entries 4 to 12 shall be renumbered as entries 3 to 11 
respectively; and

</section>

<section><tid>29446</tid>
<number>iii</number>for the figure" 3" in column 2 against Himachal 
Pradesh, the figure" 4" shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>611364</tid>
<number> 10</number> Parliamentary constituencies of the new State and their 
delimitation.
<section><tid>331469</tid>
<number>1</number>The new State shall, until other provision is made  
by law, consist of the following three Parliamentary constituencies, 
namely:--

<subsection><tid>561861</tid>
<number>i</number>the constituency of Bilaspur comprising the existing 
State of Bilaspur; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>862815</tid>
<number>ii</number>the two constituencies into which the existing State of 
Himachal Pradesh has been divided.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>10628</tid>
<number>2</number>The Delimitation of Parliamentary Constituencies (Part C  
  States) Order, <year>1951</year>, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> shall, until other provision is made by law, 
have effect subject to the amendments made in the First Schedule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>253890</tid>
<number> 11</number> Sitting members.
<section><tid>392258</tid>
<number>1</number>The sitting member of the House of the  
People representing the existing State of Bilaspur shall on and from 
the commencement of this Act represent the Bilaspur constituency of 
the new State
<pagefootnote><pagenum>276</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>See Notification No. S. R. O. 706, dated 15th May, <year>1951</year>, Gazette of 
India, Extraordinary, <year>1951</year>, Pt. II, Sec. 3, p. 587.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


and shall be deemed to have been elected to the House of the People by 
that constituency.


</section>

<section><tid>1702256</tid>
<number>2</number>Every sitting member of the House of the People representing 
a constituency of the existing State of Himachal Pradesh shall, on and 
from the commencement of this Act, represent the constituency of the 
same name in the new State and shall be deemed to have been elected to 
the House of the People by that constituency.
Legislative Assembly of the New State

Miscellaneous




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>212247</tid>
<number>17</number>Amendment of section 13, Act 43 of <year>1950</year>. In section 13 of the 
Representation of the People Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of <year>1950</year>), in clause (b) of 
sub- section 1, the word" Bilaspur" shall be omitted.


</article>



<article><tid>1072898</tid>
<number>18</number>[ Amendment of section 2, Act 49 of <year>1951</year>.] Rep. by the 
Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>.
</article>



<article><tid>1462977</tid>
<number>19</number>Amendment of the Constitution (Scheduled Castes)  (Part C  
  States) Order, <year>1951</year>. The Constitution (Scheduled Castes)  (Part C  
  States) Order, <year>1951</year>, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> shall be amended as shown in the Second 
Schedule.


</article>



<article><tid>734533</tid>
<number>20</number>Amendment of section 9, Act 81 of <year>1952</year>. In section 9 of the 
Delimitation Commission Act, <year>1952</year> (81 of <year>1952</year>), in sub- section (3), 
for the words" and the orders made under any of the said Acts" the 
words, brackets and figures" the Himachal Pradesh and Bilaspur (New  
  State) Act, <year>1954</year> and the orders made under any of the said Acts" shall 
be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>946095</tid>
<number>21</number>Construction of Act 43 of <year>1950</year>. Any reference to Himachal 
Pradesh in the Representation of the People Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of <year>1950</year>), 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>, as amended by this Act shall be construed as a reference to the 
new State.


</article>



<article><tid>478122</tid>
<number> 22</number> Electoral rolls of constituencies.
<section><tid>1953746</tid>
<number>1</number>The electoral rolls of  
the constituencies of the existing States shall, on and from the 
commencement of this Act, be deemed to be the electoral rolls of the 
constituencies of the same name in
<pagefootnote><pagenum>277</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>See C. O. 32, Gazette of India, <year>1951</year>, Pt. II, Sec. 3, p. 1198. 
2. The words" and the Government of Part C States Act, <year>1951</year>" omitted 
by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


the new State and shall continue in force until such rolls are 
revised, or fresh rolls are prepared, in accordance with law.

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>102977</tid>
<number>23</number>Power of Delimitation Commission to revise its orders. For 
the purpose of determination of the number of seats to be allotted to 
the new State in the House of the People in accordance with the 
provisions of sub- section 1, and distribution of those seats as well 
as the seats allotted to the Legislative Assembly of the new State to 
territorial constituencies and delimitation thereof in accordance with 
the provisions of sub- section (2) of section 8 of the Delimitation 
Commission Act, <year>1952</year> (81 of <year>1952</year>), it shall be lawful for the 
Delimitation Commission, notwithstanding anything contained in that 
Act, to amend, vary or rescind any of its final orders published under 
section 9 of that Act in so far as any such order relates to any or 
both of the existing States.


</article>



<article><tid>270638</tid>
<number>24</number>[ Rules of procedure of the Legislative Assembly of the new 
State.] Rep. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>.
PART

COURTS

PART IV

COURTS



</article>



<article><tid>627371</tid>
<number> 25</number> Court of the Judicial Commissioner for the new State. As from 
the commencement of this Act,--
<section><tid>428557</tid>
<number>a</number>the Courts of the Judicial Commissioner for the existing 
States (hereafter in this Part referred to as" the  
  existing Courts") shall be amalgamated and shall 
constitute the Court of the Judicial Commissioner for 
the new State (hereafter in this Part referred to as  
 " the new Court");

</section>

<section><tid>1125162</tid>
<number>b</number>the Judicial Commissioner and the Additional Judicial 
Commissioner, if any, for the existing State of 
Himachal Pradesh shall be respectively the Judicial 
Commissioner and the Additional Judicial Commissioner 
for the new State;

</section>

<section><tid>1732386</tid>
<number>c</number>every person who immediately before the commencement of 
this Act, is an officer or servant of either of the 
existing Courts shall be an officer or servant, as the 
case may be, of the new court deemed to have been 
appointed on the
<pagefootnote><pagenum>279</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Sub- section (2) omitted by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, 
<year>1956</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


same terms and conditions of service (or on terms and  
conditions as similar thereto as the changes effected 
  by this Act permit) as were applicable to him 
immediately before such commencement:

Provided that nothing in this clause shall be 
deemed to prevent the new Court from altering the 
designation or the duties of any office or post;


</section>

<section><tid>114932</tid>
<number>d</number>the new Court shall have all such original, appellate 
and other jurisdiction as under any law is exercisable 
immediately before the commencement of this Act by 
either of the existing Courts in respect of any area 
forming part of the new State;

</section>

<section><tid>228689</tid>
<number>e</number>the new Court shall have the same powers to admit, 
suspend and remove advocates, vakils and pleaders and 
to make rules with respect to advocates, vakils and 
pleaders in the whole of the new State as are 
immediately before the commencement of this Act, 
exercisable by either of the existing Courts:
Provided that subject to any rules made by the new 
Court in exercise of the powers conferred by this 
clause, any person who immediately before the 
commencement of this Act is an advocate, vakil or 
pleader entitled to practise in either of the existing 
Courts shall be recognised as an advocate, vakil or 
pleader entitled to practise in the new Court;


</section>

<section><tid>1166473</tid>
<number>f</number>subject to the provisions of this Part, the law in force 
immediately before the commencement of this Act with 
respect to the practice and procedure in the Court of 
the Judicial Commissioner for the existing State of 
Himachal Pradesh shall, until varied or altered by a 
competent authority, apply in relation to the new Court 
with such modifications as may be made by that Court;

</section>

<section><tid>1236301</tid>
<number>g</number>the Judicial Commissioners' Courts (Declaration as High  
  Courts) Act, <year>1950</year> (15 of <year>1950</year>) shall apply to the new 
Court as if the new Court were in existence at the 
commencement of that Act; and any other law in force 
immediately before the commencement of this Act 
relating to appeals to the Supreme Court from the Court 
of the Judicial Commissioner for the existing State of 
Himachal Pradesh shall, with necessary modifications, 
apply in relation to the new Court;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>280</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1406166</tid>
<number>h</number>all proceedings which immediately before the 
commencement of this Act are pending in either of the 
existing Courts shall by virtue of this Act stand 
transferred to the new Court and shall be continued as 
if they had been proceedings instituted in that Court;

</section>

<section><tid>672190</tid>
<number>i</number>any order made by either of the existing Courts in any 
such proceedings as aforesaid shall for all purposes 
have effect, not only as an order of that Court, but 
also as an order made by the new Court;

</section>

<section><tid>831893</tid>
<number>j</number>references in any law to either of the existing Courts 
by whatever name, shall, unless the context otherwise 
requires, be construed as references to the new Court.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>154038</tid>
<number>26</number>Subordinate Courts. All Courts which immediately before the 
commencement of this Act were exercising lawful powers, authority and 
jurisdiction under the superintendence and control of either of the 
existing Courts in any area forming part of the new State shall, until 
further provision is made by a competent legislature or authority, 
continue to exercise their respective powers, authority and 
jurisdiction in that area under the superintendence and control of the 
new Court.
PART

ADMINISTRATIVE AND MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS

PART V

ADMINISTRATIVE AND MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS



</article>



<article><tid>1230555</tid>
<number>27</number>Existing authorities and officers to continue to function in 
the new State. Save as otherwise provided in this Act, all authorities 
and all officers, judicial, executive and ministerial, who immediately 
before the commencement of this Act were exercising lawful functions 
in any area forming part of the new State, shall, until further 
provision is made by a competent authority, continue to exercise their 
respective functions as far as may be, in the same manner and to the 
same extent as they were doing before such commencement.


</article>



<article><tid>473851</tid>
<number>28</number>Existing laws to continue. Save as otherwise provided in this 
Act, all the law in force immediately before the commencement of this 
Act in any area forming part of the new State shall continue to be in 
force until repealed or amended by a competent legislature or 
authority.


</article>



<article><tid>1498228</tid>
<number>29</number>Power to construe laws. For the purpose of facilitating the 
application in relation to the new State of any law made before the 
commencement of this Act, any Court, tribunal or authority may, 
subject to any express provision of this Act, construe the law with 
such alterations not affecting

<pagefootnote><pagenum>281</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

the substance as may be necessary or proper to adapt it to the matter 
before the Court, tribunal or authority, as the case may be.



</article>



<article><tid>259360</tid>
<number>30</number>Existing taxes to continue. All taxes, duties, cesses and 
fees which immediately before the commencement of this Act were being 
lawfully levied in either of the existing States or any part thereof, 
shall continue to be levied in the same manner and to the same extent 
and to be applied for the same purposes until other provision is made 
by a competent legislature or authority.


</article>



<article><tid>515505</tid>
<number>31</number>Saving of the powers of the Central Government in relation to 
the Bhakra- Nangal Project. Nothing in this Act shall be deemed to 
derogate from the powers of the Central Government to make such 
arrangements or to take such action in relation to the Bhakra- Nangal 
Project as may, having due regard to the purposes of the Project, be 
necessary to ensure its proper administration and effective 
implementation.


</article>



<article><tid>817703</tid>
<number>32</number>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in 
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the President may make 
such orders not inconsistent with the said provisions, as appears to 
him to be necessary or expedient for the purpose of removing the 
difficulty:
Provided that no such power shall be exercised by the President 
after the expiry of one year from the commencement of this Act.


</article>



 </act>