<act><title>THE
SEMICONDUCTOR INTEGRATED CIRCUITS LAYOUT-DESIGN RULE, 2001


</title> 

   


 <article><number>1</number>
Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
These rules may be called the Semiconductor Integrated Circuits Layout-Design
Rules, 2001.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
They extend to the whole of India.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
They shall come into force on the date of the commencement of the Act.

</section></article> 

 
 


 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 
 


 <section> <number>a</number>
“Act” means the Semiconductor Integrated Circuits Layout-Design Act,
2000 (37 of 2000); 


 </section><section> <number>b</number>
“Form” means a form set out in the Schedule II; 


 </section><section> <number>c</number>
“journal” means the Semiconductor Integrated Circuits Layout-Design
Journal published by the Registrar of Semiconductor Integrated Circuits
Layout-Designs; 


 </section><section> <number>d</number>
“layout-design no.” means the Registration number of the
Layout-Design registered under the Act; 


 </section><section> <number>e</number>
“Registry” means the Semiconductor Integrated Circuits Layout-Design
Registry; 


 </section><section> <number>f</number>
“Schedule” means a Schedule to these rules; 


 </section><section> <number>g</number>
“section” means a section of the Act. 


</section></article> 

   


 
 


 <article><number>3</number>
Principal place of business in India.—“Principal
place of business in India” means,— 
 
 


 <section><number>i</number>
where a person carries on business of Semiconductor Integrated Circuits
or Layout-Design,— 


 <subsection>
<number>a</number>
if the business is carried on in India at only one place, that place; 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
if the business is carried on in India at more places than one, the place
mentioned by him as the principal place of business in India
 </subsection></section><section><number>ii</number>
where a person is not carrying on a business of Semiconductor Integrated
Circuits or Layout-Design,— 


 <subsection><number>a</number>
if he is carrying on any other business in India at only one place, that
place;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
if he is carrying on any other business in India at more places than one,
the place mentioned by him as the principal place of the business in India; and  


 </subsection></section><section><number>iii</number>
where a person does not carry on any business in India but has a place of
residence in India, then, such place of residence in India.
</section></article> 

   


 
 


 <article><number>4</number>
Appropriate office of the Semiconductor Integrated Circuits Layout-Design
Registry.—The “appropriate office
of the Semiconductor Integrated Circuits Layout-Design Registry” for the
purpose of making an application for registration of a layout-design shall be
the office of the Registry as specified in section 8 and for giving notice of
opposition under section 11 or for filing an application for rectification under
section 30 or for any other proceedings under the Act and the rules shall be,
 <section> <number>a</number>
in relation to a layout-design on the register, the office of the
Registry within whose territorial limits— 


 <subsection> <number>i</number>
the principal place of business in India of the registered proprietor of
the layout-design as entered in the register at such date is situate; 


 </subsection><subsection> <number>ii</number>
where there is no entry in the register as to the principal place of
business in India of the registered proprietor, the place mentioned in the
address for service in India as entered in the register at such date is situate; 


 </subsection><subsection> <number>iii</number>
in the case of jointly registered proprietors, the principal place of
business in India of the proprietor whose name is entered first in the register
as having such place of business in India at such date is situate; 


 </subsection><subsection> <number>iv</number>
where none of the jointly registered proprietors is shown in the register
as having a principal place of business in India, the place mentioned in the
address for service in India of the joint proprietors as entered in the register
at such date is situate; 


 </subsection><subsection> <number>v</number>
if no principal place of business in India of the registered proprietor
of the layout-design or in the case of joint registration, of any of the joint
proprietors of the layout-design, is entered in the register, and the register
does not contain any address for service in India, the place of the office of
the Registry where the application for registration of the layout-design was
made, is situate; and  


 </subsection></section><section> <number>b</number>
in relation to a layout-design for which an application for registration
is pending, the office of the Registry within whose territorial limits— 


 <subsection> <number>i</number>
the principal place of business in India of the applicant as disclosed in
his application or, in the case of joint applicants, the principal place of
business in India of the applicant whose name is first mentioned in the
application, as having such place of business is situate; 


 </subsection><subsection> <number>ii</number> where neither the applicant nor any of the joint applicants, as the
case may be, has a principal place of business in India, the place mentioned in
the address for service in India as specified in the application is situate. 


</subsection></section></article> 

   


 
 


 <article><number>5</number>
Jurisdiction of appropriate office not altered by change in the principal place
of business or address for service.—No
change in the principal place of business in India or in the address for service
in India, as the case may be,— 
 
 


 <section>
<number>a</number>
of a registered proprietor or of any of the jointly registered
proprietors in relation to any layout-design on the register, or 


 </section><section>
<number>b</number>
of an applicant for registration or of any of the joint applicants for
registration in relation to any layout-design for which an application for
registration is pending,  


 shall
effect the jurisdiction of the appropriate office of the Registry. 
 
 


</section></article> 

  
 


 <article><number>6</number>
Entry of the appropriate office in register.—In
respect of every layout-design on the register, the Registrar shall cause to be
entered in the register the appropriate office of the Registry and the Registrar
may, at any time, correct any error in the entry so made.
 


</article> 

   


 <article><number>7</number> Leaving of documents, etc.—
<section><number>1</number>
Save as otherwise provided in sub-rule (2), all applications, notices,
statements or other documents or any fees authorised or required by the Act or
the rules to be made, served, left or sent or paid at or to the Registry in
relation to a layout-design on the register for which an application for
registration is pending, shall be made, served, left or sent or paid to the
appropriate office of the Registry. 
 
 


 </section><section><number>2</number> Documents or fees authorised
or required by the Act or the rules to be sent or paid may be sent or paid at
either to the appropriate office or the head office of the Registry in the
following matters:— 
 
 


 <subsection><number>a</number>
communication and other documents including affidavits in relation to an
application filed for registration of a layout-design; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
application or request on forms LD-8, LD-9, LD-10, LD-11, LD-13, LD-14,
LD-15, LD-16, LD-17, LD-18, LD-19, LD-20, LD-21, LD-22, LD-25, LD-31.
 


</subsection></section></article> 

   


 <article><number>8</number> Documents, etc., filed or left not
at the appropriate office.—Subject
to the provisions of rule 7, where any application, notice, statement or other
document or any fee authorised or required by the Act or the rules is made,
served, left or sent or paid, at or to an office which is not the appropriate
office of the Registry, the Registrar shall return such application, notice,
statement or document or fee to the person concerned.
 


</article> 

   


 <article><number>9</number>
Issue of notices, etc.—Any
notice or communication relating to any application, matter or proceeding under
the Act or the rules shall ordinarily be issued from the appropriate office of
the Registry but may, nevertheless, be issued from any office of the Registry.
 


</article> 

   


 <article><number>10</number>
Fees.—
<section><number>1</number>
The fees to be paid in respect of applications, oppositions, registration and
other matters under the Act and the rules shall be those specified in Schedule
I, hereinafter referred to as the “prescribed fee”.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Where in respect of any matter a fee is required to be paid under the rules, the
form or the application or the request or the petition, therefor, shall be
accompanied by the prescribed fee.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
Fees may be paid in cash or sent by money order addressed to the Register or by
postal order or by a bank draft issued by, or by a cheque drawn
 on and guaranteed, by a scheduled bank as
defined in the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934) or at the discretion
of the Registrar by a cheque drawn on such bank even though not so guaranteed,
and if sent through post shall be deemed to have been paid at the time when the
money order or the properly addressed and prepaid letter containing the postal
order, or bank draft or cheque would be delivered in the ordinary course of
post.
 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
Postal orders shall be crossed and made payable to the Registrar at the
appropriate office of the Registry and bank drafts and cheque shall also be
similarly crossed and made payable to the Registrar but they shall be drawn on a
scheduled bank at the place where the appropriate office of the Registry is
situate.
 


 </section><section><number>5</number>
Where a fee is payable in respect of the filing of a document, the date on which
the entire fee is paid shall be deemed to be the date of filing of the document.
 


 </section><section><number>6</number>
Where any fee paid by a party is ordered to be returned by the Registrar under
any of the provisions of the Act or the rules the amount may be refunded by
money order in which event money order commission shall be deductible from such
amount.
 


</section></article> 

   


 <article><number>11</number>
Forms.—
<section><number>1</number>
The forms set forth in Schedules II and III shall be used in all cases to which
they are applicable and may be modified as directed by the Registrar to meet
other cases.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Any form, when filed at the Registry, shall be accompanied by prescribed fee.
 


</section></article> 

   


 <article><number>12</number>
Size, etc., of the documents.—
<section><number>1</number>
Subject to any other directions that may be given by the Registrar, all
applications, notices, statements, or other documents, authorised or required by
the Act or the rules to be made, served, left or sent, at or to the Registry or
with or to the Registrar or the Appellate Board, shall be written, typewritten
or printed in Hindi or in English in large and legible characters with deep
permanent ink upon strong paper, and except in the case of affidavits, on one
side only, of a size of approximately 33 centimeters by 20 centimeters and shall
have on the left hand part thereof a margin of less than 4 centimeters.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Duplicate documents including layout-designs shall be filed at the Registry, if
at any time required by the Registrar.
 


</section></article> 

   


 <article><number>13</number>
Signing of documents.—
<section><number>1</number>
A document purporting to be signed by a partnership shall be signed by at least
one of the partners and the document purporting to be singed by a body corporate
shall be signed by a director or by the secretary or other principal officer of
the body corporate. The capacity in which an individual signs a document on
behalf of a partnership or a body corporate shall be stated below his signature.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Signature to any documents if written in letters other than Roman, or if not
eligible shall be accompanied by a transliteration in English and in block
capital letters.
 


</section></article> 

   


 <article><number>14</number>
Service of documents.—
<section><number>1</number>
All applications, notices, statements, papers having representations affixed
thereto, or other documents authorised or required by the Act or the rules to be
made, served, left or sent, at or to the Registry or with to or the Registrar or
the Appellate Board, or any other person may be sent through the post by a
pre-paid letter.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Any application or any document so sent shall be deemed to have been made,
served, left or sent at the time when the letter containing the same would be
delivered in the ordinary course of post.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
In proving such sending it shall be sufficient to prove that the letter was
properly addressed and put into the post. 


   


   


</section></article> 

   


 <article> <number>15</number>
Particulars of address, etc., of applicants and other persons.—
<section><number>1</number>
Names and addresses of the applicants and other persons shall be given in full,
together with their nationality, calling, and such other particulars as are
necessary for identification.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
In the case of a firm the full name and nationality of every partner thereof
shall be stated.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
In the case of foreign applicants and persons having no principal place of
business in India, their addresses in their home country shall be given in
addition to their address for service in India.
 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
In the case of a body corporate or firm, the country of incorporation or the
nature of registration, if any, as the case may be, shall be given.

</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>16</number>
Statement of principal place of business in India in an application.—
<section><number>1</number> Every application for registration of a layout-design shall
state the principal place of business in India, if any, of the applicant or in
the case of joint applicants, of such of the joint applicants as have a
principal place of business in India.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Subject to the provisions of rules 17, 18 and 20 any written communication
addressed to an applicant, or in the case of joint applicants to a joint
applicant, in connection with the registration of a layout-design, at the
address of his principal place of business in India given by him in the
application shall be deemed to be properly addressed.

</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>17</number>
Address for service.—
<section><number>1</number> An address
for service in India shall be given,— 
 
 


 <subsection><number>a</number>
by every applicant for registration of a layout-design who has no
principal place of business in India; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
in the case of joint applicants, for registration of a layout-design if
none of them has a principal place of business in India;  


 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
by the proprietor of a layout-design who had his principal place of
business in India at the date of making the application for registration but has
subsequently ceased to have such place; and  


 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
by every applicant in any proceeding under the Act or the rules and every
person filing a notice of opposition, who does not have a principal place of
business in India. 


 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
Any written communication addressed to a person as aforesaid at an address for
service in India given by him shall be deemed to be properly addressed. 
 
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
Unless an address for service in India as required in sub-rule (1) is given, the
Registrar shall be under no obligation to send any notice that may be required
by the Act or the rules and no subsequent order or decision in the proceedings
shall be called in question on the ground of any lack or non-service of notice. 
 
 
 
 
 

</section></article> 

   


 <article><number>18</number>
Address for service in application and opposition proceedings.—An
applicant for registration of a layout-design or an opponent filing a notice of
opposition may, notwithstanding that he has a principal place of business in
India, if he so desires, furnish the Registrar with an address in India to which
communications in relation to the application or opposition proceedings only may
be sent. Such address of the applicant or the opponent shall be deemed, unless
subsequently cancelled, to be the actual address of the applicant or the
opponent, as the case may be, and all communications and documents in relation
to the application or notice of opposition may be served by leaving them at, or
sending them by post to such address of the applicant or the opponent, as the
case may be.

</article> 

   


 <article><number>19</number>
Non-availability of an address for service.—The
Registrar may, at any time when a doubt arises as to the continued availability
of an address for service in India entered in the register, request the person
for whom it is entered, by letter directed to any other address entered in the
register or if no such address is entered in the register to the address at
which the Registrar considers that the letter would reach him, to confirm the
address for service in India and if within three months of making such a request
the Registrar receives no such confirmation, he may strike the entry in the
register of the address for service in India and require such person to furnish
a fresh address for service in India, or his address at the principal place of
business in India, if he has, any, at that time.
 


</article> 

   


 <article><number>20</number>
Agency.—
<section><number>1</number>
The authorisation of an agent for the purpose of section 84 shall be executed on
Form LD-32 or in such other written form as the Registrar may deem sufficient
and proper.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
In the case of such authorisation, service upon the agent of any document
relating to the proceeding or matter shall be deemed to be service upon the
person so authorising him; all communications directed to be made to such person
in respect of the proceeding or matter may be addressed to such agent, and all
appearances before Registrar relating thereto may be made by or through such
agent.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
In any particular case the Registrar may require the personal signature or
presence of an applicant, opponent, proprietor, registered user or other person.

</section></article> 

   


 <article><number>21</number>
Preliminary advice by Registrar as to originality of the layout-design.—An
application for preliminary advice by the Registrar under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of
section 78 shall be made on Form LD-21 accompanied by prescribed fee.

</section></article> 

   


 <article><number>22</number>
Form and signing of application.—
<section><number>1</number>
An application to the Registrar for the registration of a layout-design under
sub-section (1) of section 8 shall be made on Form LD-1 accompanied by
prescribed fee and shall be signed by the applicant or his agent. 
 
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Three sets of one of the following items, which clearly describe the
layout-design, shall be attached. The size of the drawing or the photograph
shall not be less than 20 times the size of the semiconductor integrated circuit
fabricated using such layout-design, namely:— 
 
 


 <subsection>
<number>a</number>
three sets of drawings produced with a plotter which describes the
layout-design applied for registration; or
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
three sets of photographs of masks used for the fabrication of the
semiconductor integrated circuit by using of the layout-design applied for
registration, or drawings which describe the pattern of such masks.
 


 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number>
In the case the applicant for registration of layout-design makes a request in
writing for maintaining the secrecy of the layout-design, he may attach in place
of the drawings or photographs specified in sub-rule (2), the three sets of
partially blocked drawings or photographs of such layout-design to the
satisfaction of the Registrar. The Registrar may inspect the complete drawing or
photographs of such layout-design. The blocking of such drawing or photograph
shall be to the satisfaction of the Registrar such that it does not hamper the
identification of the applied-for layout-design. The blocked out area of such
drawing or photograph shall not be greater than the area of the remaining
portion of layout-design.

</section></article> 

   


 <article><number>23</number>
Application under reciprocal arrangements.—Every
application claiming priority under section 93 by reason of an application to
register the layout-design having been made in a convention country, so declared
under this section, which country shall be named, shall state the date of that
application and the applicant shall furnish a certificate by the registrar or
other registering authority of that country or shall otherwise verify the
application made therein to the satisfaction of the Registrar.

</article> 

   


   


 <article><number>24</number> Acknowledgement or receipt of
application.—Every
application for the registration of a layout-design shall, on receipt, be
acknowledged by the Registrar. The acknowledgement shall be by way of return of
one copy of the application on Form LD-1 with the official number of the
application duly entered thereon.
 


</article> 

   


   


 <article><number>25</number>
Objections to acceptance and hearing.—
<section><number>1</number>
If, on consideration of the application of any evidence of use or of originality
or of any other matter which the applicant may or may, be required to, furnish,
the Registrar has any objection to the acceptance of the application or proposes
to accept it subject to such amendments or modifications as he may think right
to impose, the Registrar shall communicate such objections or proposal in
writing to the applicant.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
If within three months from the date of the communication mentioned in sub-rule
(1), the applicant does not amend the application according to the proposal
aforesaid, or submit his observations to the Registrar or apply for a hearing,
the application shall be deemed to have been abandoned.
 


</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>26</number> Notice of withdrawal of the application for registration.—A
notice of withdrawal of application for registration of a layout-design under
sub-section (2) of section 78 for the purpose of obtaining repayment of any fee
paid on the filing of the application, shall be given in writing within three
months from the date of communication mentioned in sub-rule 
<section><number>1</number> of rule 25.
 


</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>27</number>
Decision of the Registrar.—
<section><number>1</number>
The decision of the Registrar under rule 25 or rule 29 after a hearing, or
without a hearing if the applicant has duly communicated his observation in
writing and has stated that he does not desire to be heard, shall be
communicated to the applicant in writing, and if the applicant intends to appeal
from such decision he may within one month from the date of such communication
apply on Form LD-5 accompanied by prescribed fee to the Registrar requiring him
to state in writing the grounds of, and materials used by him in arriving at,
his decision.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
In case where the Registrar makes any requirements to which the applicant does
not object, the applicant shall comply therewith before the Registrar issues a
statement in writing under sub-rule (1).
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
The date when the statement in writing under sub-rule (1) is received by the
applicant shall be deemed to be the date of communication of the Registrar’s
decision for the purpose of appeal.
 


</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>28</number> Correction and amendment of application.—An
applicant for registration of a layout-design, may, whether before or after
acceptance of his application but before the registration of the layout-design
apply on Form LD-6 accompanied by prescribed fee for the correction of any error
in or in connection with his application or any amendment of his application.
 


</article> 

   


   


 <article><number>29</number>
Withdrawal of acceptance by the Registrar.—
<section><number>1</number>
If, after the acceptance of an application but before the registration of the
layout-design, the Registrar has any objection to the acceptance of the
application on the ground that it was accepted in error, or that the
layout-design ought not to have been accepted in the circumstances of the case,
or proposes that the layout-design should be registered only subject to,
additional to or different from the amendments or modifications subject to which
the application has been accepted, the Registrar shall communicate such
objection in writing to the applicant.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Unless within two months from the date of the communication mentioned in
sub-rule (1), the applicant amends his application to comply with the
requirements of the Registrar or applies for a hearing, the acceptance of the
application shall be deemed to be withdrawn by the Registrar, and the
application shall proceed as if it has not been accepted. 
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
Where the applicant intimates the Registrar within the period mentioned in
sub-rule (2) that he desires to be heard, the Registrar shall give notice to the
applicant of a date when he shall hear him. Such appointment shall be for a date
at least fifteen days after the date of the notice, unless the applicant
consents to a shorter notice. The applicant may state that he does not desire to
be heard and submit such submission as he may consider desirable.
 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
The Registrar may, after hearing the applicant, or considering the submissions,
if any, of the applicant, pass such orders as he may deem fit.
 


</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>30</number>
Manner of advertisement.—An
application for the registration of a layout-design required to be advertised
under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 10 or to be re-advertised under sub-section (2)
of that section shall be advertised in the journal. The following details shall
be given in the advertisement, namely:— 
 
 


 <subsection> <number>i</number>
application No; 


 </subsection><subsection> <number>ii</number>
date of acceptance of application for registration of layout-design; 


 </subsection><subsection> <number>iii</number>
name and address of the proprietor as given in the application; 


 </subsection><subsection> <number>iv</number>
brief description of the layout-design; 


 </subsection><subsection> <number>v</number>
whether the layout-design has been commercially exploited, if so the
period of such exploitation. 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vi</number> the
address of the office of the Registry where the application is filed.
 


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>31</number> Notification of correction or 
    amendment of application.—In the case of an 
    application to which clause (b) of sub-section (2) of section 10 applies, 
    the Registrar may, if he so decides, instead of causing the application to 
    be advertised again, insert in the journal a notification setting out the 
    application number, the name and address of the principal place of business 
    in India, if any, of the applicant or address for service in India of the 
    applicant or where the applicant has no principal place of business in India 
    his address for service in India, and the correction or amendment made in 
    the application.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>32</number> Request to Registrar for 
    particulars of advertisement of layout-design.—Any 
    person may request the Registrar on Form LD-31 to be informed of the number, 
    date and page of the journal in which a layout-design specified in the form 
    was advertised and the Registrar shall furnish such particulars to the 
    person making the request.  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>33</number> Notice of opposition.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A notice of opposition to the registration of a layout-design under 
    sub-section (1) of section 11 shall be given in triplicate on Form LD-2 
    accompanied by prescribed fee within three months from the date of 
    advertisement or re-advertisement, as the case may be, of the application 
    for registration in the journal. The notice shall include a statement of the 
    grounds on which the opponent objects to the registration.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An application for an extension of 
    the period within which a notice of opposition to the registration of a 
    layout-design may be given, shall be made on a Form LD-30 accompanied by the 
    prescribed fee. Such period of extension shall not exceed one month in the 
    aggregate.  
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>34</number> Counter-statement.—The 
    counter-statement required by sub-section (2) of section 11 shall be sent in 
    triplicate on Form LD-3 accompanied by the prescribed fee within two months 
    from the receipt by applicant of the copy of the notice of opposition and 
    shall set out what facts, if any, alleged in the notice of opposition, are 
    admitted by the applicant. The Registrar, on the person giving notice of 
    opposition, shall serve a copy of the counter-statement.  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>35</number> Evidence in support of 
    opposition.—
<section><number>1</number> Within two months from the service 
    on him of a copy of the counter-statement by the Registrar, the opponent 
    shall either leave with the Registrar such evidence by way of affidavit as 
    he may desire to adduce in support of his opposition or shall intimate to 
    the Registrar and to the applicant in writing that he does not desire to 
    adduce evidence in support of his opposition but intends to rely on the 
    facts in the notice of opposition. He shall deliver to the applicant copies 
    of any evidence that he leaves with the Registrar under this sub-rule.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If an opponent takes no action under 
    sub-rule (1) within the time therein prescribed, he shall, unless the 
    Registrar otherwise directs, be deemed to have abandoned his opposition.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>36</number> Evidence in support 
      of opposition.—
<section><number>1</number> Within two months from the 
      service on him of a copy of the counter-statement by the Registrar, the 
      opponent shall either leave with the Registrar such evidence by way of 
      affidavit as he may desire to adduce in support of his opposition or shall 
      intimate to the Registrar and to the applicant in writing that he does not 
      desire to adduce evidence in support of his opposition but intends to rely 
      on the facts in the notice of opposition. He shall deliver to the 
      applicant copies of any evidence that he leaves with the Registrar under 
      this sub-rule.  
 </section><section><number>2</number> If an opponent takes no 
      action under sub-rule (1) within the time therein prescribed, he shall, 
      unless the Registrar otherwise directs, be deemed to have abandoned his 
      opposition.  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>37</number> Evidence in reply by opponent.—Within 
    one month from the receipt by the opponent of the copies of the applicant’s 
    affidavits, the opponent may leave with the Registrar evidence by affidavit 
    in reply and shall deliver to the applicant copies thereof. This evidence 
    shall be confined to matters strictly in reply.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>38</number> Further evidence.—No 
    further evidence shall be left on either side; but in any proceedings before 
    the Registrar, he may at any time, if he thinks fit, give leave to either 
    the applicant or the opponent to leave any evidence upon such terms as to 
    costs or otherwise as he may think fit.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>39</number> Exhibits.—Where 
    there are exhibits to affidavits filed in an opposition a copy of each 
    exhibit shall be sent to the other party on his request and at his expenses, 
    or, if such copies cannot conveniently be furnished the originals shall be 
    left with the Registrar in order that they may be open to inspection. The 
    original exhibits shall be produced at the hearing unless the Registrar 
    otherwise directs.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>40</number> Translation of documents.—Where 
    a document in a language other than Hindi or English referred to in the 
    notice of opposition, counter-statement or an affidavit filed in an 
    opposition, an attested translation thereof in Hindi or English shall be 
    furnished in duplicate.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>41</number> Hearing and decision.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Upon completion of the evidence (if any), the Registrar shall give notice to 
    the parties of a date when he shall hear the arguments in the case. Such 
    appointment shall be for a date at least one-month after the date of the 
    notice, unless the parties consent to a shorter notice. Within fourteen days 
    from the receipt of the notice, any party who intends to appear shall so 
    notify the Registrar on Form LD-4 accompanied by the prescribed fee. Any 
    party who does not so notify the Registrar within the time last aforesaid 
    may be treated as not desiring to be heard and the Registrar may act 
    accordingly.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The decision of the Registrar shall 
    be notified to the parties in writing.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>42</number> Security for costs.—The 
    security of costs which the Registrar may require under sub-section (6) of 
    section 11 may be fixed at any amount which he may consider proper, any such 
    amount may be further enhanced by him at any stage in the opposition 
    proceeding.  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>43</number> Procedure for giving notice.—The 
    notice which the Registrar is required by sub-section (3) of section 13 to 
    give to an applicant shall be sent on Form OLD-1 to the applicant at the 
    address of his principal place of business in India or if he has no 
    principal place of business in India at the address for service in India 
    stated in the application but if the applicant has authorised an agent for 
    the purpose of the application, the notice shall be sent to the agent and a 
    duplicate thereof to the applicant. The notice shall specify twenty-one 
    days’ time from the date thereof or such further time as the Registrar may 
    allow, for completion of the registration.  
  
 

 

 

 

 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>44</number> Entry in the Register.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    As soon as may be after the expiration of three months from the date of the 
    advertisement or re-advertisement, as the case may be, in the journal of any 
    application for the registration of a layout-design, the Registrar shall, 
    subject to the provisions of sub-section (1) of section 13, enter the 
    layout-design in the registrar.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The entry of layout-design in the 
    registrer shall specify the date of the registration of such layout-design, 
    and all particulars required by sub-section (1) of section 6 including—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   date of 
    acceptance of application for registration of layout-design under 
    sub-section (1) of section 10; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   name, 
    address and nationality of the registered proprietor;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   in case 
    the layout-design has been commercially exploited before date of 
    registration under section 13, the period of such exploitation and the place 
    of exploitation.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   office 
    of the Registry where the request for registration was filed;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   the 
    address of the principal place of business in India, if any, of the 
    proprietor of the layout-design or in case of a jointly owned layout-design, 
    of such of the joint proprietors of the layout-design as have a principal 
    place of business in India;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   where 
    the proprietor of the layout-design has no place of business in India his 
    address for service in India as entered in the application for registration 
    together with his address in his home country;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>   in case 
    of a jointly owned layout-design, where none of the joint proprietors has a 
    principal place of business in India, the address for service in India as 
    given in the application together with the address of each of the joint 
    proprietors in his home country.
 

 

 


 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>45</number> Death of applicant before 
    registration.—In case of death of any applicant 
    for the registration of a layout-design after the date of his application 
    and before the layout-design has been entered in the register, the Registrar 
    may on proof of the applicant’s death and on proof of the transmission of 
    the interest of the deceased person, substitute in the application his 
    successor in interest in place of the name of such deceased applicant and 
    the application may proceed thereafter as so amended.  
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>46</number> Certificate of registration.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Certificate of registration of a layout-design to be issued by the 
    Registrar under sub-section (2) of section 13 shall be on Form OLD-2 with 
    such modifications as the circumstances of any case may require.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Registrar may issue a duplicate 
    or further copies of the certificate of registration to be copy of entry in 
    register on request by the registered proprietor on Form LD-25 accompanied 
    by prescribed fee.  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>47</number> Application for entry of 
    assignment or transmission.—An application to 
    register the title of a person who becomes entitled by assignment or 
    transmission, to a registered layout-design shall be made on Form LD-10 or 
    Form LD-11 accompanied by prescribed fee according as it is made by such 
    person alone or conjointly with the registered proprietor.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>48</number> Particulars to be stated in 
    application.—An application under rule 47 shall 
    contain full particulars of the instrument, if any, under which the 
    application or in case of a joint application, the person other than the 
    registered proprietor claims to be entitled to the layout-design, and such 
    instrument or a duly certified copy thereof shall be produced at the 
    Registry for inspection at the time of application. The Registrar may 
    require and retain an attested copy of any instrument produced for 
    inspection in proof of title but such copy shall not be open to public 
    inspection.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>49</number> Case accompanying application.—Where 
    a person applying under rule 47 for registration of his title, does not 
    establish his claim under any document or instrument which is capable in 
    itself of furnishing proof of his title, he shall, unless the Registrar 
    otherwise directs, either upon or with the application, state a case setting 
    forth the full particulars of the facts upon which his claim to be 
    proprietor of the layout-design is based, and showing that the layout-design 
    has been assigned or transmitted to him. If the Registrar so requires, the 
    case shall be verified by an affidavit on Form LD-7. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>50</number> Proof of title.—The 
    Registrar may call upon any person who applies to be registered as 
    proprietor of a registered layout-design to furnish such proof or additional 
    proof of title as he may require for his satisfaction.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>51</number> Impounding of instruments.—If 
    in the opinion of the Registrar any instrument produced in proof of title of 
    a person is not properly or sufficiently stamped the Registrar shall impound 
    and deal with it in the manner provided by Chapter IV of the Indian Stamp 
    Act, 1899 (2 of 1899).  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>52</number> Assignments involving 
    transmission of moneys outside India.—If there is 
    in force any law regulating the transmission of moneys outside India, the 
    Registrar shall not register the title of a person who becomes entitled to a 
    layout-design by an assignment which involves such transmission except on 
    production of the permission of the authority specified in such law for such 
    transmission.  
 

 

 

 

 

 

 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>53</number> Application for Registrar’s 
    direction as to advertisement of an assignment of a layout-design without 
    goodwill of the business.—
<section><number>1</number> An application for 
    directions under section 22 shall be made on Form LD-8 accompanied by 
    prescribed fee and shall state the date on which the assignment was made. 
    The application shall give particulars of the registration of registered 
    layout-design including user of the registered layout-design. The Registrar 
    may call for any evidence or further information and if he is satisfied with 
    regard to the various matters he shall issue directions in writing with 
    respect to the advertisement of the assignment.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A request for an extension of the 
    period within which the application mentioned in sub-rule (1) may be made 
    shall be on Form LD-9 accompanied by prescribed fee.  
 

 

 

 

 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>53</number> Application for Registrar’s 
    direction as to advertisement of an assignment of a layout-design without 
    goodwill of the business.—
<section><number>1</number> An application for 
    directions under section 22 shall be made on Form LD-8 accompanied by 
    prescribed fee and shall state the date on which the assignment was made. 
    The application shall give particulars of the registration of registered 
    layout-design including user of the registered layout-design. The Registrar 
    may call for any evidence or further information and if he is satisfied with 
    regard to the various matters he shall issue directions in writing with 
    respect to the advertisement of the assignment.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A request for an extension of the 
    period within which the application mentioned in sub-rule (1) may be made 
    shall be on Form LD-9 accompanied by prescribed fee.  
 

 

 

 

 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>54</number> Application for entry of 
    assignment without goodwill.—An application under 
    rule 47 relating to an assignment of a layout-design shall state—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>   whether 
    the layout-design had been or was used in the business; and 

 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   whether 
    the assignment was made otherwise than in connection with the goodwill of 
    that business;
 
and if both those circumstances 
    subsisted, then, the applicant shall leave at the Registry a copy of the 
    directions to advertise the assignment, obtained upon application under rule 
    53, and such proof, including copies of advertisement or otherwise, as the 
    Registrar may require, to show that his directions have been fulfilled and 
    if the Registrar is not satisfied that the directions have been fulfilled, 
    he shall not proceed with the application.  
  
 

 

 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>55</number> Application for registration as 
    registered user.—
<section><number>1</number> An application to Registrar 
    for the registration under section 25 of a person as a registered user of a 
    registered layout-design shall be made jointly by that person and the 
    registered proprietor of the layout-design on Form LD-13 accompanied by 
    prescribed fee and shall also be accompanied by the following documents:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   
    the agreement in writing or a duly authenticated copy thereof, entered into 
    between the registered proprietor and the proposed registered user with 
    respect to the permitted use of the layout-design;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   
    the documents and correspondence, if any, mentioned in the agreement 
    referred to in clause (a) or duly authenticated copies thereof;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   
    Agreement if any or duly authenticated copies thereof, entered into between 
    the proposed registered user and the registered proprietor as regards the 
    price at which the semiconductor integrated circuit incorporating registered 
    layout-design or an article incorporate such a semiconductor integrated 
    circuit should be sold or the maintenance of particular price for such 
    semiconductor integrated circuits or articles.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> There shall also be filed along with 
    the application an affidavit made by the registered proprietor or by some 
    person authorised to the satisfaction of the Registrar to act on his behalf 
    giving—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   
    particulars and statements required by sub-clauses (i) to (iii) of clause 
    (b) of sub-section (1) of section 25;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   a 
    statement as to whether the layout-design which is the subject of the 
    application has been used by him in the course of trade before the date of 
    the application and if so the amount and duration of such use;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   a 
    statement as to whether the registered proprietor has acquired title to the 
    layout-design by way of assignment;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   a 
    statement as to whether the registered proprietor had, before the date of 
    the application for registration as registered user, allowed the use of the 
    layout-design by any person and if so by whom;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   a 
    statement whether or not the proposed permitted use is intended solely for 
    export from India.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The registered proprietor and the 
    proposed registered user shall also produce and file such other documents 
    and furnish such other evidence and information as may be required in that 
    behalf by the Registrar.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Notwithstanding anything contained 
    in sub-rule (1), where more than one application for registration as 
    registered user is made by the same registered proprietor and the same 
    proposed registered user in respect of layout-design covered by the same 
    agreement, the documents mentioned in sub-rule (1) may be filed with any one 
    of the applications and a cross reference to such documents given in other 
    application or applications.  
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>56</number> Entry in the Register.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whether the requirements of rule 55 have been complied with, the Registrar 
    shall register the proposed registered user.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The entry of a registered user in 
    the register shall state the date on which the application for registration 
    of registered user was made and the date of registration of the registered 
    user. The entry shall also state, in addition to the particulars and the 
    statements mentioned in clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 25, the 
    name, description and principal place of business in India of the registered 
    user and if he does not carry on business in India his address for service 
    in India.   

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>57</number> Notice of registration as 
    registered user.—A notice in writing of the 
    registration of the registered user of a layout-design shall be sent by the 
    Registrar to the registered proprietor of the layout-design, to the 
    registered user and to every other registered user whose name is entered in 
    relation to same layout-design on Form OLD-5. This Form shall also be 
    inserted in the journal.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>58</number> Cancellation of the registration 
    of the registered user.—An application for the 
    cancellation of the registration of a registered user under clause 
<section><number>a</number> or 
    clause (b) or clause (c) of sub-section (1) of section 26 shall be made on 
    Form LD-14 or Form LD-15, as the case may be, accompanied by prescribed fee 
    and shall be accompanied by a statement of grounds on which it is made.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>59</number> Registrar to require information 
    for enforcing of topographical dimensions of the layout-design.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Registrar may at any time or from time to time require the registered 
    proprietor or the registered user of a layout-design to furnish him with 
    such information as he may require for satisfying himself that the 
    stipulations in the agreements between the registered proprietor and the 
    registered user, regarding the topographical dimensions of the layout-design 
    are being enforced or complied with.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any such information as is 
    referred to in sub-rule (1) is not furnished within the stipulated time 
    allowed by the Registrar, the Registrar may presume that the stipulation in 
    the agreement regarding the topographical dimensions of the layout-design is 
    not being enforced or is not complied with.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>60</number> Notification for cancellation of 
    Registration.—The notice required for in respect 
    of every application under sub-section (2) of section 26 shall be made on 
    Form OLD-6 and shall be sent to the registered proprietor and each 
    registered user (not being the applicant) of the layout-design.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>61</number> Procedure on application to 
    cancel registration.—
<section><number>1</number> The Registrar shall 
    notify in writing applications under section 26 to the registered proprietor 
    and each registered user (not being the applicant in either case) of the 
    layout-design.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person notified under sub-rule 
    (1) who intends to intervene in the proceedings, shall within one month of 
    the receipt of such notification give notice to the Registrar on Form LD-16 
    accompanied by prescribed fee to the effect and shall send therewith a 
    statement of the grounds of his intervention. The Registrar shall thereupon 
    serve or cause to be served copies of such notice and statement on the other 
    parties, namely, the applicant, the registered proprietor, the registered 
    user whose registration is the subject-matter of the proceeding in question 
    and any other registered user who intervenes.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The applicant and any person 
    notified under sub-rule (1) may, within such time or times as the Registrar 
    may appoint, leave evidence in support of his case, and the Registrar after 
    giving the parties an opportunity of being heard, may accept or refuse the 
    application.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>62</number> Registered user’s application 
    under sub-section (2) of section 31.—Application 
    under sub-section (2) of section 31 shall be made on Form LD-6 or Form LD-17 
    or Form LD-18 or Form LD-19 accompanied by prescribed fee as may be 
    appropriate by a registered user of a layout-design and the Registrar may 
    require such evidence by affidavit or otherwise as he may think fit as to 
    the circumstances in which the application is made.  
  
 

 

 

 

 

 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>62</number> Registered user’s application 
    under sub-section (2) of section 31.—Application 
    under sub-section (2) of section 31 shall be made on Form LD-6 or Form LD-17 
    or Form LD-18 or Form LD-19 accompanied by prescribed fee as may be 
    appropriate by a registered user of a layout-design and the Registrar may 
    require such evidence by affidavit or otherwise as he may think fit as to 
    the circumstances in which the application is made.  
  
 

 

 

 

 

 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>63</number> Application to rectify the 
    register.—An application to the Appellate Board or 
    to the Registrar under section 30 or sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 48 for 
    making, expunging or varying of any entry relating to a layout-design in the 
    register shall be made in duplicate on Form LD-12 accompanied by prescribed 
    fee and shall be accompanied by a statement in duplicate setting out fully 
    the nature of the applicant’s interest and the facts upon which he bases his 
    case. Where the application is made by a person who is not the registered 
    proprietor to the layout-design in question, the application and the 
    statement aforesaid shall be left at the Registry in triplicate. In case 
    there are registered user, such application and statements shall be 
    accompanied by as many copies thereof as there are registered users. A copy 
    each of the application and statement shall to be transmitted forthwith by 
    the Registrar to the Registered proprietor and to each of the registered 
    user and to any other person who appears from the register to have an 
    interest in the layout-design.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>64</number> Further procedure.—Within 
    two months from the receipt by a registered proprietor of the copy of the 
    application mentioned in rule 63, he shall send to the Registrar on Form 
    LD-3 a counter-statement in triplicate of the grounds on which the 
    application is contested and if he does so the Registrar shall serve a copy 
    of the counter-statement on the person making the application. The 
    provisions of the rules 35 to 41 shall thereafter apply mutatis mutandis 
    to the further proceedings on the application. The Appellate Board or the 
    Registrar shall not, however, rectify the register merely because the 
    registered proprietor has not filed a counter-statement. In any case of 
    doubt, any party may apply to the Appellate Board or the Registrar, as the 
    case may be, for the directions.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>65</number> Rectification of the Register by 
    Appellate Board or the Registrar of its own motion.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The notice which the Appellate Board or the Registrar is required to give 
    under sub-section (3) of section 30, shall be sent in writing to the 
    registered proprietor, to each registered user, if any, to any other person 
    who appears from the register to have any interest in the layout-design, and 
    shall state the grounds on which the Appellate Board or the Registrar 
    proposes to rectify the register and shall also specify the time, not being 
    less than one month from the date of such notice, within which an 
    application for a hearing shall be made.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Unless within the time specified in 
    the notice aforesaid, any person so notified sends to the Appellate Board or 
    the Registrar a statement in writing setting out fully the facts upon which 
    he relies to meet the grounds stated in the notice or applies for a hearing, 
    he may be treated as not desiring to take part in the proceedings and the 
    Appellate Board or the Registrar may act accordingly.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If the Appellate Board or the 
    Registrar decides to rectify the register it shall communicate the decision 
    in writing to the registered proprietor and each registered user, if any.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>66</number> Order of the Appellate Board to 
    the Registrar.—Any order of the Appellate Board to 
    the Registrar for rectification of the register shall indicate the details 
    of making, expunging or varying an entry in the register. The Registrar upon 
    receipt of the notice in Form OLD-7 from the Appellate Board shall rectify 
    the register accordingly.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>67</number> Alteration of address in 
    register.—
<section><number>1</number> A registered proprietor or a 
    registered user of a layout-design, the address or whose principal place of 
    business in India or whose address in his home country, as the case may be, 
    is changed so that the entry in the register is rendered incorrect, shall 
    forthwith request the Registrar on Form LD-18 to make the appropriate change 
    of the address in the register, and the Registrar shall alter the register 
    accordingly, if he is satisfied in the matter.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A registered proprietor or a 
    registered user of a layout-design, whose address for service in India 
    entered in the register if changed, whether by discontinuance of the address 
    or otherwise, so that the entry in the register is rendered incorrect, shall 
    forthwith request the Registrar on Form LD-19 to make appropriate alteration 
    of the address in the register, and the Registrar shall alter the register 
    accordingly if he is satisfied in the matter.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A registered proprietor or a 
    registered user of a layout-design the address of whose principal place of 
    business in India or whose address for service in India is altered by a 
    public authority, so that the changed address designates the same premises 
    as entered in the register, may make the aforesaid request to the Registrar 
    on Form LD-18 or Form LD-19, as the case may be, and if he does so he shall 
    leave therewith a certificate of the alteration given by the said authority. 
    If the Registrar is satisfied as to the facts of the case, he shall alter 
    the register accordingly, but shall not require any fees to be paid on the 
    form, notwithstanding the provisions of sub-rule (2) of rule 10 or sub-rule 
    (2) of rule 11.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> (i) Where a registered proprietor 
    makes a request under sub-rule (1), (2) or (3), he shall serve a copy of the 
    request on the registered user or users, if any, and inform the Registrar 
    accordingly.  
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> When the request aforesaid is made 
    by a registered user, he shall serve a copy thereof on the registered 
    proprietor and other registered users, if any, and inform the Registrar that 
    he had done so.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> In case of the alteration of the 
    address of a person entered in the register as the address for service in 
    India of more than one registered proprietor or registered user of 
    layout-designs, the Registrar may, on proof that the said address is the 
    address of the applicant and if satisfied that it is just to do so, accept 
    an application from that person on Form LD-19 amended so as to suit the 
    case, for appropriate alteration of the entries of his address as the 
    address for service in the several registrations, particulars of which shall 
    be given in such form and may alter entries accordingly.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> All applications under this rule on 
    Form LD-19 shall be signed by the registered proprietor or the registered 
    user, as the case may be, or by an agent expressly authorised by him for the 
    purpose of such an application unless in exceptional circumstances the 
    Registrar otherwise allows.  
  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>68</number> Application under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> 
    of section 31.—Where an application has been made 
    by the registered proprietor under sub-section (1) of section 31 for the 
    alteration of the register by correction or change of any entry relating to 
    layout-design or cancellation of entry of layout-design in the register, the 
    Registrar may require the applicant to furnish such evidence by affidavit or 
    otherwise as the Registrar may think fit, as to the circumstances in which 
    the application is made. Such application shall be made on Form LD-6, LD-17, 
    LD-18, LD-19 or LD-20 accompanied by prescribed fee as may be appropriate 
    and a copy thereof shall be served by the applicant on the registered user 
    or users, if any, under the registration of the layout-design in question 
    and to any other person who appears from the register to have an interest in 
    the layout-design.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>69</number> Cancellation of registration or 
    of assignment or transmission of layout-design.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person may make application under sub-section (1) of section 41 to apply 
    for the cancellation of the registration or of assignment or transmission of 
    the layout-design to the Appellate Board on Form LD-33 accompanied by 
    prescribed fee. The Board shall give notice on Form OLD-8 to the opposite 
    parties.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Appellate Board shall on receipt 
    of replies, to the opposition to the application referred to in sub-rule (1) 
    within the time specified in the notices or where no such reply is filed 
    after the expiration of the period so specified, after giving opportunity of 
    being heard to the applicant and the opposite parties dispose of the 
    application.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>70</number> Board to permit certain uses of 
    the registered layout-design.—Subject to the 
    provisions of section 51 of the Act, the Appellate Board may permit the 
    Government or the person authorised by the Government to use the registered 
    layout-design. The application for such permission shall be made on the Form 
    LD-34 accompanied by prescribed fee.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>71</number> The time period for efforts under 
    first proviso to the sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 51.—The 
    person authorised under sub-section (1) of section 51 shall not be permitted 
    under that sub-section the use of a registered layout-design unless the 
    Appellate Board is satisfied that such person has made efforts to enter into 
    agreement with the registered proprietor of such layout-design on reasonable 
    commercial terms and conditions for permitted use of such layout-design and 
    such efforts had not been successful within a period of six months.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>72</number> Review of the decision of the 
    Appellate Board to permit use of registered layout-design.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The registered proprietor of a layout-design may request the Appellate Board 
    to review the permission granted under sub-section (1) of section 51, giving 
    details of the reasons for such a review. The request shall be filed on Form 
    LD-29 accompanied by prescribed fee.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Appellate Board, on receiving 
    application under sub-rule (1) for review of its decision, shall issue the 
    notice to the person authorised to use the registered layout-design under 
    sub-section (1) of section 51 on Form OLD-9. The date of hearing the 
    arguments of the case shall also be indicated in the notice.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Appointment for hearing of the 
    arguments in the case under sub-rule (2) shall be for a date at least one 
    month after the date of the notice, unless the parties consent for a shorter 
    notice. Within fourteen days from the receipt of the notice, any party who 
    intends to appear shall notify the Appellate Board. Any party who does not 
    so notify the Appellate Board within the time last aforesaid may be treated 
    as not desiring to be heard and Appellate Board may act accordingly.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The decision of the Appellate Board 
    shall be notified to the parties in writing.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>73</number> 
    Application to the Appellate Board for determining of royalty.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The application under sub-section (1) of section 40 for determining royalty 
    shall be made to the Appellate Board on Form LD-27. Such application shall 
    be accompanied by an affidavit supporting the facts and grounds stated in 
    the application and the copy of the document or other evidences in support 
    of the benefit accrued by performing or directing to perform any of the acts 
    referred to in clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 18 in respect of the 
    semiconductor integrated circuit or article, as the case may be, in respect 
    of which the royalty is claimed and fee in respect of filing and for the 
    service or execution of the processes amounting to two per cent of the 
    royalty claimed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On receipt 
    of an application under sub-rule (1) the Appellate Board shall give notice 
    to the opposite party on the Form OLD-3. The opposing party may file 
    opposition within thirty days from the date on which such notice is served 
    to him on Form LD-28.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Appellate Board shall on receipt of opposition under sub-rule (2) or where 
    no such opposition is filed after the expiration of the period of thirty 
    days referred to in sub-rule (2), after giving opportunity of being heard to 
    the applicant and the opposite party, dispose of the application.
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>74</number> Appeal to the Appellate Board.—An 
    appeal to the Appellate Board under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 42 shall be 
    preferred on Form LD-26 accompanied by prescribed fee and shall be verified 
    by the person preferring the appeal in the manner specified in such form.  
 
A copy of the order on decision against 
    which such appeal is preferred shall be accompanied with such form.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>75</number> Extension of time.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    An application for extension of time under section 76 not being a time 
    expressly provided in the Act or a time for extension of which provision is 
    made in these rules shall be made on Form LD-23 accompanied by prescribed 
    fee.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Upon an application made under 
    sub-rule (1) the Registrar, if satisfied that the circumstances are as to 
    justify the extension of the time applied for, may, subject to the 
    provisions of these rules where a maximum time limit is prescribed and 
    subject to such conditions as he may think fit to impose, extend the time 
    and notify the parties accordingly and the extension may be granted though 
    the time for doing the act or taking the proceeding for which it is applied 
    for has already expired or not.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>76</number> Exercise of discretionary power 
    of Registrar.—The time within which a person 
    entitled under section 72 to an opportunity of being heard shall exercise 
    his option of requiring to be heard shall, save as otherwise expressly 
    provided in the Act or these rules, be one month from the date of a notice 
    which the Registrar shall give to such person before determining the matter 
    with reference to which such person is entitled to be heard. If within that 
    month such person is required to be heard, the Registrar shall appoint a 
    date for the hearing and shall give ten days’ notice thereof.   

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>77</number> Notification of decision.—The 
    decision of the Registrar in the exercise of any discretionary power given 
    to him by the Act or these rules shall be notified to the person affected.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>78</number> Amendments and correction of 
    irregularity in procedure.—
<section><number>1</number> Any document or 
    drawing or other representation of a layout-design may be amended, and any 
    irregularity in procedure which, in the opinion of the Registrar may be 
    obviated without detriment to the interests of any person, might be 
    corrected, if the Registrar thinks fit on such terms as he may direct. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Registrar may require the 
    amendment of any application or representation of a layout-design or any 
    other document or the addition of any matter thereto in order to bring it in 
    accordance with the formal requirements of the Act. 
 

 

 

 

 

 

 

 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>79</number> Directions not otherwise 
    prescribed.—Where in the opinion of the Appellate 
    Board or the Registrar, it is necessary for the proper prosecution or 
    completion of any proceedings under the Act or these rules for a person to 
    perform an act, file a document or produce evidence, which is not provided 
    for by the Act or the rules, the Appellate Board or the Registrar may by 
    notice in writing require the person to perform the act, file the document 
    or produce the evidence, specified in the notice.  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>80</number> Hearings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In relation to a layout-design for which an application for registration is 
    made, the application as well as any proceeding under the Act and the rules 
    shall, in the event of a hearing becoming necessary, be heard at the office 
    of the Registry at which such application was made under sub-section (2) of 
    section 8 or at such place within the territorial jurisdiction of that 
    office as the Registrar may deem proper.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where an officer exercising the 
    powers of the Registrar who has heard any matter under the Act or these 
    rules has reserved order thereon, is transferred from one office of the 
    Registry to another office or reverts to another appointment before passing 
    an order or rendering decision thereon, he may, if the Registrar so directs, 
    pass the order or render the decision as if he had continued to be the 
    officer in the office of the Registry where the matter was heard.  
  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>81</number> Costs in uncontested cases.—Where 
    any opposition duly instituted under these rules is not contested by the 
    applicant, the Registrar in deciding whether costs should be awarded to the 
    opponent shall consider whether the proceedings might have been avoided if 
    reasonable notice had been given by the opponent to the applicant before the 
    notice of opposition was filed.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>82</number> Exception to rule 81.—Notwithstanding 
    the provisions of rule 81 costs in respect of fees specified under Forms 
    LD-2, LD-3 and LD-4 and of all stamps used on and affixed to affidavit used 
    in the proceedings shall follow the event.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>83</number> Scale of costs.—Subject 
    to the provisions of rules 81 and 82, in all proceedings before the 
    Registrar, the Registrar may, save as otherwise expressly provided by the 
    Act, award such costs, not exceeding the amount admissible thereof under 
    Schedule I, as he considers reasonable having regard to all the 
    circumstances of the cases.  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>84</number> Application for review of 
    Registrar’s decision.—An application to the 
    Registrar for the review of his decision under clause (c) of section 72 
    shall be made on Form LD-24 accompanied by prescribed fee within one month 
    from the date of such decision or within such further period not exceeding 
    one month thereafter as the Registrar may on request allow, and shall be 
    accompanied by the statement setting forth the grounds on which the review 
    is sought. Where the decision in question concern any other person in 
    addition to the applicant, such application and statement shall be left in 
    triplicate and the Registrar shall forthwith transmit a copy each of the 
    application and statement to the other person concerned. The Registrar may, 
    after giving the parties an opportunity of being heard, reject or grant the 
    application, either unconditionally or subject to any conditions or 
    limitations, as he thinks fit.  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>84</number> Application for review of 
    Registrar’s decision.—An application to the 
    Registrar for the review of his decision under clause (c) of section 72 
    shall be made on Form LD-24 accompanied by prescribed fee within one month 
    from the date of such decision or within such further period not exceeding 
    one month thereafter as the Registrar may on request allow, and shall be 
    accompanied by the statement setting forth the grounds on which the review 
    is sought. Where the decision in question concern any other person in 
    addition to the applicant, such application and statement shall be left in 
    triplicate and the Registrar shall forthwith transmit a copy each of the 
    application and statement to the other person concerned. The Registrar may, 
    after giving the parties an opportunity of being heard, reject or grant the 
    application, either unconditionally or subject to any conditions or 
    limitations, as he thinks fit.  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>85</number> Form, etc., of affidavits.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The affidavits required by the Act and these rules to be filed at the 
    Registry or furnished to the Appellate Board or the Registrar, unless 
    otherwise provided in Schedule II, shall be headed in the matter or matters 
    to which they relate, shall be drawn up in the first person, and shall be 
    divided into paragraphs consecutively numbered; and each paragraph shall, as 
    far as practicable, be confine to one subject. Every affidavit shall state 
    the description and the true place of abode of the person making the same, 
    shall bear the name and address of the person filing it and shall state on 
    whose behalf it is filed.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where two or more persons join in an 
    affidavit, each of them shall depose separately to such facts which are 
    within his personal knowledge and those facts shall be stated in separate 
    paragraphs.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Affidavits shall be taken—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   in India 
    before any court or person having by law authority to receive evidence, or 
    before any officer empowered by such court as aforesaid to administer oaths 
    or to take affidavits;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   in any 
    country or place outside India—before a diplomatic or counsellor officer, 
    within the meaning of the Diplomatic and Counsellor Officers (Oath and Fees) 
    Act, 1948, of such country, or place or before the Notary Public, or before 
    a Judge or Magistrate, of the country or place.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The person before whom affidavit is 
    taken shall state the date on which and the place where the same is taken 
    and shall affix his seal, if any, or the seal of the court to which he is 
    attached thereto and sign his name and description at the end thereof.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Any affidavit purporting to have 
    affixed, impressed or subscribed thereto or thereon the seal or signature of 
    any person authorised by sub-rule (3) to take an affidavit, in testimony of 
    the affidavit having been taken before him, may be admitted by the Registrar 
    without proof of the genuineness of the seal or signature, or of the 
    official character of that person.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Alterations and interlineations 
    shall, before an affidavit is sworn or affirmed, be authenticated by the 
    initials of the person before whom the affidavit is taken.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Where the deponent is unacquainted 
    with the language in which the affidavit is written, a certificate by the 
    person taking the affidavit that the affidavit was translated in his 
    presence to the deponent that the deponent seemed perfectly to understand it 
    and that the deponent made his signature in his presence, shall appear in 
    the jurat.  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> Every affidavit filed before the 
    Registrar in connection with any of the proceedings under the Act or these 
    rules shall be duly stamped under the law for the time being in force.  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>86</number> Inspection of documents.—The 
    documents mentioned in sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 87 shall be available for 
    inspection at the head office of the Registry. A copy of the register and 
    such of the other documents mentioned in section 87, and as the Central 
    Government may by notification in the Official Gazette, specify, shall be 
    available for inspection at each branch office of the Registry . The 
    inspection shall be made at such times on all the days on which the offices 
    of the Registry are not closed to the public, as be fixed by the Registrar.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>87</number> Distribution of copies of journal 
    and other documents.—The Central Government may 
    direct the Registrar to distribute the journal and any other document which 
    it may consider necessary, to such places as may be fixed by the Central 
    Government in consultation with the State Government and notified by the 
    Central Government from time to time in the Official Gazette.  
  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>88</number> Certified copies of documents.—The 
    Registrar may furnish certified copies of any entry in the register or 
    certified copies of any document referred to in sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 
    87 or of any decision or order of the Registrar, or give a certificate other 
    than a certificate under sub-section (2) of section 13, as to entry, matter 
    or thing which he is authorised or required by the Act or these rules to 
    make or do, upon receipt from any person of an application therefor on Form 
    LD-22 accompanied by prescribed fee.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>89</number> Certificate for use in obtaining 
    registration aboard.—Where a certificate relating 
    to the registration of a layout-design is desired for use in obtaining 
    registration in any territory outside India, Registrar may furnish the same. 
    The Registrar may state in the certificate such particulars concerning the 
    registration of the layout-design as may seem fit to him. The purpose for 
    which the certificate is issued shall be stated therein.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>90</number> Destruction of records.—Where 
    an application for the registration of a layout-design has been withdrawn, 
    abandoned or refused or a layout-design has been removed from the register, 
    the Registrar may, at the expiration of five years after the application is 
    withdrawn or is abandoned or is refused or after the layout-design is 
    removed from the register, as the case may be, destroy all or any of the 
    records relating to the application of the layout-design concerned.  
  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>91</number> Time for appeal.—An 
    appeal to a High Court from any decision or order of the Appellate Board 
    under the Act shall be made within three months from the date of such 
    decision or order, as the case may be, or within such further time as the 
    High Court may allow. The appeal shall be made on Form LD-35 accompanied by 
    prescribed fee. The appeal shall contain copy of the decision or order 
    against which the appeal is preferred and grounds on which the appeal is 
    preferred along with evidences, if any.  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>92</number> Application made to the High 
    Court to be served on the Appellate Board.—A copy 
    of every appeal to the High Court under the Act shall be served on the 
    Appellate Board.  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>93</number> Register of layout-design agents.—The 
    Registrar shall maintain a register of layout-design agents wherein shall be 
    entered the name, address of the place of residence, address of the 
    principal place of business, the nationality, qualifications and date of 
    registration of every registered layout-design agent.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>94</number> Qualification for registrations.—Subject 
    to the provisions of rule 95, a person shall be qualified to be registered 
    as layout-design agent if he—  
 <section>
<number>i</number>   is 
    a citizen of India;  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>   
    is not less than 21 years of age;  
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>   
    has passed the examination prescribed in rule 98;  
 </section><section>
<number>iv</number>   
    is a graduate of any university in India or possesses an equivalent 
    qualification; and  
 </section><section>
<number>v</number>   is 
    considered by the Central Government as a fit and proper person to be 
    registered as a layout-designs agent.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>95</number> Persons debarred from 
    registration.—A person shall not be eligible for 
    registration as a layout-design agent if he—
 <section>
<number>i</number>   has been 
    adjudged by a competent court to be of unsound mind;
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>   is an 
    undischarged insolvent;
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>   being 
    a discharged insolvent has not obtained from the court a certificate to the 
    effect that his insolvency was caused by misfortune without any misconduct 
    on his part;
 </section><section>
<number>iv</number>   has 
    been convicted by a competent court, whether within or without India of an 
    offence punishable with imprisonment, unless the offence of which he has 
    been convicted has been pardoned or unless on an application made by him, 
    the Central Government has, by order in this behalf, removed the disability;
 </section><section>
<number>v</number>   being a 
    legal practitioner has been held guilty of professional misconduct by any 
    High Court in India or by any court beyond the limits of India; or
 </section><section>
<number>vi</number>   being a 
    chartered accountant, has been guilty of negligence or misconduct by a High 
    Court.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>96</number> Manner of making application.—All 
    applications under the provisions of this Part shall be made in triplicate, 
    shall be sent to or left at that office of the Registry within whose 
    territorial limits the principal place of business of the applicant is 
    situate.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>97</number> Application for registration as a 
    layout-design agent.—
<section><number>1</number> Every person desiring to 
    be registered as a layout-design agent shall make an application on Form 
    LDA-1 accompanied by prescribed fee. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The applicant shall furnish such 
    further information bearing on his applications as may be required of him at 
    any time by the Registrar.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>98</number> Procedure on application and 
    qualifying requirements.—
<section><number>1</number> On receipt of an 
    application for the registration of a person as a layout-design agent, the 
    Registrar, if satisfied that the applicant fulfils the prescribed 
    qualifications, under the fore-going rules shall appoint a date in due 
    course on which the candidate shall appear before him for a written 
    examination in the Semiconductor Integrated Circuits Layout-Design Law and 
    practice followed by an interview. The candidate shall be expected to 
    possess a detailed knowledge of the provisions of the Act and rules and a 
    knowledge of the elements of the Semiconductor Integrated Circuits 
    Layout-Design Law.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The qualifying marks for the written 
    examination and for interview shall be 40 per cent and 60 per cent 
    respectively and a candidate shall be declared to have passed the 
    examination only if he obtains an aggregate of 50 per cent of the total 
    marks.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>99</number> Certificate of registration.—After 
    a candidate has been interviewed and any further information bearing on his 
    application, which the Registrar may consider necessary has been obtained 
    and if the Registrar considers the applicant eligible and qualified for 
    registration as a layout-design agent, he shall send an intimation to that 
    effect to the applicant and any person so intimated may inform in writing 
    for his registration as a layout-design agent. Upon receipt of the 
    information the Registrar shall cause the applicant’s name to be entered in 
    the register of layout-design agents and shall issue to him a certificate on 
    Form OLD-4 of his registration as a layout-design agent on payment of 
    prescribed fee.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>100</number> Continuance of a name in the 
    register of layout-design agents.—The continuance 
    of a person’s name in the register of layout-design agents shall be subject 
    to his payment of the fees prescribed in that behalf.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>101</number> Removal of agent’s name from the 
    register of layout-design agents.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Registrar shall remove from the register of layout-designs agents the name 
    of any registered layout-design agent—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   from 
    whom a request has been received to that effect; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   from 
    whom the annual fee has not been received on the expiry of three months from 
    the date on which it became due.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Registrar shall remove from the 
    register of layout-design agents the name of any registered layout-design 
    agent—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   who is 
    found to have been subject at the time of his registration or thereafter has 
    become subject, to any of the disabilities stated in clauses (i) to (vi) of 
    rule 95; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   whom the 
    Registrar has declared not be a fit and proper person to remain in the 
    register by reason of any act of negligence, misconduct or dishonesty 
    committed in his professional capacity;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   whose 
    name has been entered in the register by an error or on account of 
    misrepresentation or suppression of material fact:
 
Provided that 
    before making such declaration under clause (b), the Registrar shall call 
    upon the person concerned to show cause why his registration should not be 
    cancelled and shall make such further enquiry, if any, as he may consider 
    necessary.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The Registrar shall remove from the 
    register of layout-design agents, the name of any registered layout-designs 
    agent who is dead.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The removal of the name of any 
    person from the register of layout-design agents shall be notified in the 
    Official Gazette and in the journal and shall, wherever possible be 
    communicated to the person concerned.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>101</number> Removal of agent’s name from the 
    register of layout-design agents.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Registrar shall remove from the register of layout-designs agents the name 
    of any registered layout-design agent—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   from 
    whom a request has been received to that effect; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   from 
    whom the annual fee has not been received on the expiry of three months from 
    the date on which it became due.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Registrar shall remove from the 
    register of layout-design agents the name of any registered layout-design 
    agent—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   who is 
    found to have been subject at the time of his registration or thereafter has 
    become subject, to any of the disabilities stated in clauses (i) to (vi) of 
    rule 95; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   whom the 
    Registrar has declared not be a fit and proper person to remain in the 
    register by reason of any act of negligence, misconduct or dishonesty 
    committed in his professional capacity;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   whose 
    name has been entered in the register by an error or on account of 
    misrepresentation or suppression of material fact:
 
Provided that 
    before making such declaration under clause (b), the Registrar shall call 
    upon the person concerned to show cause why his registration should not be 
    cancelled and shall make such further enquiry, if any, as he may consider 
    necessary.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The Registrar shall remove from the 
    register of layout-design agents, the name of any registered layout-designs 
    agent who is dead.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The removal of the name of any 
    person from the register of layout-design agents shall be notified in the 
    Official Gazette and in the journal and shall, wherever possible be 
    communicated to the person concerned.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>102</number> Power of Registrar to refuse to 
    deal with certain agents.—
<section><number>1</number> The Registrar may 
    refuse to recognise—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   any 
    individual whose name has been removed from, and not restored to the 
    register of layout-design agents;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   any 
    person, not being registered as a layout-design agent, who in the opinion of 
    the Registrar is engaged wholly or mainly in acting as agent in applying for 
    layout-designs in India or elsewhere in the name or for the benefit of the 
    person by whom he is employed;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   any 
    company or firm, if any person whom the Registrar could refuse to recognise 
    as layout-design agent in respect of any business under these rules, is 
    acting as a director or manager of the company or is a partner in the firm.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Registrar shall also refuse to 
    recognise as layout-design agent in respect of any business under this rule 
    any person who neither resides nor has a place of business in India.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>103</number> Restoration of removed names.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Registrar may on an application made on Form LDA-2 accompanied by 
    prescribed fee within six months from the date of removal of his name from 
    the register of layout-design agents from a person whose name has been 
    removed under clause (b) of sub-rule (1) of rule 101, restore his name to 
    the register of layout-design agents and continue his name therein.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The restoration of a name to the 
    register of layout-designs agents shall be notified in the Official Gazette 
    and in the journal and shall be communicated to the person concerned.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>104</number> Alteration in the register of 
    layout-design agents.—
<section><number>1</number> A registered 
    layout-design agent may apply on Form LDA-3 accompanied by prescribed fee 
    for alteration of his name, address of the place of residence, address of 
    the principal place of business or qualifications entered in the register of 
    layout-design agents. On receipt of such application, the registrar shall 
    cause the necessary alteration to be made in the register of layout-design 
    agents.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every alteration made in the 
    register of layout-design agents shall be notified in the Official Gazette 
    and in the journal.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>105</number> Publication of the registrar of 
    layout-design agents.—The register of 
    layout-design agents shall be published from time to time, as the Registrar 
    may deem fit, the entries being arranged in the alphabetical order of the 
    surnames of the registered layout-designs agents and, copies thereof shall 
    be placed on sale. 
 

 

 


 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>