<act><title>

Aircraft (Public health) Rules, 19541</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    These Rules may be called the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[Aircraft 
    (Public Health) Rules, 1954].
 

 







 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    In these Rules, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or 
    context,—
 
 <section>
<number>1</number>   “airport” means 
      an airport designated by State in whose territory it is situated as an 
      airport of entry or departure for international traffic;
 
Explanation.—In 
      India an “Airport” corresponds to an aerodrome declared under rule 53 of 
      the Indian Aircraft Rules, 1920, to be a customs aerodrome.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>   “arrival” means 
      arrival at an airport;
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>   “baggage” means 
      the personal effects of a traveller or of a member of the crew;
 </section><section>
<number>4</number>   “Commander” means 
      the pilot-in-command or other person in-charge of an aircraft;
 </section><section>
<number>5</number>   “crew” means the 
      personnel of an aircraft who are employed for duties on board;
 </section><section>
<number>6</number>   “day” means an 
      interval of twenty-four hours;
 </section><section>
<number>7</number>   “direct transit 
      area” means a special area established in connection with an airport, 
      approved by the Health Officer concerned and under his direct supervision, 
      for accommodating direct transit traffic and, in particular, for 
      accommodating, in segregation, passengers and crews breaking their voyage 
      without leaving the airport;
 </section><section>
<number>8</number>   “Health Officer” 
      means in respect of an airport in India any person appointed by the 
      Central Government to be the Health Officer of the airport, and includes 
      an Additional, Deputy or Assistant Health Officer appointed by the Central 
      Government to perform the functions of a Health Officer;
 </section><section>
<number>8A</number>   “Infected 
      aircraft” means an aircraft which under rules 9(1), 16, 20(1), 24 or 30(1) 
      is regarded as an aircraft infected with an infectious disease;
 </section><section>
<number>9</number>   “Infected area” 
      in relation to a quarantinable or other infectious disease means any area 
      outside India, declared by the Central Government, by notification in the 
      Official Gazette, to be infected with such a disease;
 </section><section>
<number>10</number>   “infected 
      person” means a person who is suffering from a quarantinable or other 
      infectious disease, or who is believed to be infected with such a disease;
 </section><section>
<number>11</number>   “infectious 
      disease” means in addition to quarantinable diseases, a disease, declared 
      by the Central Government by notification in the Official Gazette to be an 
      infectious disease;
 </section><section>
<number>12</number>   “International 
      voyage” means—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   in the case of 
        an aircraft, a voyage between airports in the territories of more than 
        one State or a voyage between airports in the territory or territories 
        of the same State if the aircraft has relations with the territory of 
        any other State on its voyage but only as regards those relations;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   in the case of 
        a person, a voyage involving entry into the territory of State other 
        than the territory of the State in which that person commences his 
        voyage;
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>13</number>   “Isolation” when 
      applied to a person or group of persons means the separation of that 
      person or group of persons from other persons, except the health staff on 
      duty, in such a manner as to prevent the spread of infection;
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>13A</number>   
      “mainland” means the territory of India excluding the Andaman and Nicobar 
      Islands;
 </section><section>
<number>14</number>   “medical 
      examination” includes visit to and inspection of an aircraft and the 
      preliminary examination of persons on board;
 </section><section>
<number>15</number>   “period of 
      incubation” means (a) in respect of a quarantinable disease mentioned 
      below, the period specified against it—
 
 
 
Yellow 
          fever                                             6 days
 

          Plague                                                     6 days
 

          Cholera                                                    5 days
 

          Smallpox                                                  14 days
 

          Typhus                                                    14 days
 
Relapsing 
          fever                                          8 days

 
and (b) in respect of 
        other infectious diseases such period as may be declared by the Central 
        Government by notification in the Official Gazette to be the period of 
        incubation of that disease;

 </section><section>
<number>16</number>   “quarantinable 
      diseases” means yellow fever, plague, cholera, small pox, typhus and 
      relapsing fever;
 </section><section>
<number>17</number>   “relapsing 
      fever” means louse-borne relapsing fever;
 </section><section>
<number>18</number>   “suspect” means 
      a person who is considered by the Health Officer as having been exposed to 
      infection by a quarantinable to an infectious disease and is considered 
      capable of spreading that disease;
 </section><section>
<number>18A</number>   “suspected 
      aircraft” means an aircraft which under rules 9 (2), 20 (2), or 30 (2), is 
      regarded as an aircraft suspected of infection from an infectious disease;
 </section><section>
<number>19</number>   “typhus” means 
      louse-borne typhus;
 </section><section>
<number>20</number>   “valid 
      certificate”, when applied to vaccination, means a certificate which—
 
 <subsection>
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum><number>i</number>   
        conforms to the requirements and the model laid down in Schedules III, 
        IV, and V to these rules;]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   is issued only 
        to individuals and cannot in any circumstances be used collectively;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   is issued in 
        the case of children separately and is not incorporated in the mother’s 
        certificate;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   is completed 
        in English or in French;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>   is signed in 
        the case of an international certificate, by the parent or guardian of a 
        child who is unable to sign or which bears in the case of an illiterate 
        person, the mark of such illiterate person, duly attested by another 
        person to whom such illiterate person is personally known;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vi</number>   is signed, in 
        the case of an international certificate issued in India, in his own 
        hand by a qualified medical practitioner whose name is enrolled in the 
        Indian Medical Register maintained under section 21 of the Indian 
        Medical Council Act, 1956 (102 of 1956). In the case of certificates of 
        vaccination against cholera and smallpox issued in India, the approved 
        stamp to be affixed thereon shall be such as has been approved by the 
        Central Government and stamp shall be affixed on the certificates by 
        only those persons who are authorised, either by designation or by name, 
        for this purpose by the Central Government. In the case of certificates 
        of vaccination against yellow fever issued in India, the vaccinating 
        centres shall be approved by the Central Government.
</subsection>
</section>
 
 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number>
    
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Commander of an aircraft which is on its way to India from any place outside 
    India, shall send to officer in-charge of the airport, where he proposes to 
    land in India, a health report stating—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   whether any 
      person on board the aircraft is suffering from any illness, and if so, 
      what its signs and symptoms are, giving, if possible, the name of the 
      illness, and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   whether at any 
      time during the voyage there has occurred on board any case, or suspected 
      case of a quarantinable or any other infectious disease, and if so what 
      that case was.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The report referred to in sub-rule (1) shall be sent—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   if the aircraft 
      is not equipped with wireless, by means of cablegram from the last place 
      of landing before entering India, and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   if the aircraft 
      is equipped with wireless, by means of a wireless message, when it is not 
      less than two hours out from the airport in India, where it is proposed to 
      land the aircraft.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    The Health Officer of an airport may, if authorised by the general or 
    special orders of the Central Government, grant pratique by radio to an 
    aircraft when on the basis of information contained in the health report 
    received from it prior to its arrival, he is of the opinion that its arrival 
    will not result in the introduction or spread of a quarantinable or any 
    other infectious disease.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct 
    that aircraft shall, on entering India from any place outside India, land 
    only at such airport or airports as may be specified in the notification.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    
<section><number>1</number> If for any reasons beyond the control of the Commander an aircraft lands 
    elsewhere than at an airport, or at an airport specified under rule 4, it 
    shall proceed as soon as possible, without discharging any passenger, crew 
    or cargo to an airport specified under rule 4 or, where no such airport is 
    specified, to a conveniently situated airport.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    it is impracticable for the aircraft to comply with the provisions of 
    sub-rule (1), the Commander shall forthwith notify the Health Officer of the 
    nearest airport and also the nearest magistrate, Officer in-charge of a 
    Police Station or Government Medical Officer, who shall take such measures 
    to prevent the spread of infection, in accordance with the provisions of 
    these rules as he may consider necessary or expedient. The Commander shall 
    prevent any cargo being removed from, or any passenger or member of the crew 
    leaving the vicinity of, the aircraft except to such extent as may be 
    necessary to conform to, or to facilitate the measures taken under this 
    sub-rule. The Commander may take such emergency measures as may be necessary 
    for the health and safety of passengers and crew. On arrival at the airport 
    referred to in sub-rule (1) the Commander shall report the relevant facts to 
    the Health Officer of the airport.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    
<section><number>1</number> The Commander of an aircraft coming from any place outside India or his 
    authorised agent shall—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   arrange for all 
      persons on an international voyage on board to complete a Personal 
      Declaration of Origin and Health in the form shown in Schedule I to these 
      rules; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   complete and 
      deliver to the Health Officer of the airport <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[the 
      health part of the Aircraft General Declaration which shall conform to the 
      model specified in Schedule II];
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The Health Officer shall have the right to demand if he considers it 
    necessary, and on such a demand having been made it shall be incumbent on 
    the Commander or his authorised agent to produce the aircraft journey log 
    book. The Commander or his authorised agent shall also supply any further 
    information required by the Health Officer as to health conditions on board 
    during the voyage.





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    When an infected or suspected aircraft coming from a place outside India, or 
    a healthy aircraft coming from a yellow fever infected area arrives at an 
    airport, the Health Officer may, until such time as the appropriate measures 
    prescribed in the case of such aircraft have been taken, require that the 
    passengers and crew of the aircraft shall not go beyond such limits within 
    the airport as may be specified by him.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number>
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number>] The 
    Health Officer of an airport may, whenever he considers it desirable subject 
    to medical examination, inspect any aircraft and its passengers and crew on 
    its arrival at the airport. The further sanitary measures which may be 
    applied to the aircraft shall be determined by the conditions which existed 
    on board during the voyage or which exist at the time of the medical 
    examination, without prejudice to the measures which are permitted by these 
    rules to be applied to the aircraft if it arrives from an infected area.
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> Where 
    special problems constituting a grave danger to public health exist, a 
    person on an international voyage may, on arrival, be required to give a 
    destination address in writing.]






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>7</footcitenum><number>8A</number> 
    On arrival in an area where malaria or other mosquito-borne disease could 
    develop from imported vectors, the aircraft may be disinsected if the Health 
    Officer is not satisfied with disinsection carried out at a previous airport 
    in accordance with rule 39A or he finds live mosquitoes on board.]





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number>
    
<section><number>1</number> An aircraft 
    shall be regarded as infected with yellow fever—
 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   if it has a case 
      of yellow fever on board, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   if there has 
      been on board a case of yellow fever and, subsequent to the occurrence of 
      that case, all the measures specified in sub-rule (1) of rule 13 have not 
      been taken to the satisfaction of the Health Officer before arriving in 
      India.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An 
    aircraft shall be regarded as suspected of yellow fever infection if it has 
    started from or alighted in an airport in a yellow fever infected area and 
    has not been disinsected immediately before the departure from that airport 
    under control of the Health authority of the airport or in another airport 
    subsequent to such starting or alighting and has not obtained a certificate 
    of disinsectisation <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[from 
    any officer or body] stating that aircraft after leaving or alighting in the 
    yellow fever infected area and before arriving in India has been disinsected 
    in accordance with the procedure prescribed in Schedule VI to these rules,
    <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[or 
    recommended by the World Health Organisation,] or if live mosquitoes are 
    found on board.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Any other aircraft shall be regarded as healthy.






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

     <number>10</number> 
<section><number>1</number> Where 
    an aircraft, having started from, or during the course of the voyage 
    alighted in, a yellow fever infected area, is on its way to India, the 
    report referred to in sub-rule (1) of rule 3 shall also state—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the date of 
      departure of the aircraft from the yellow fever infected area, and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   whether the 
      aircraft has been disinsected immediately before or since leaving the 
      yellow fever infected area and if so, the place at which, and the 
      authority by which it was disinsected.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where an aircraft has on board any persons coming from a yellow fever 
    infected area, the report referred to in sub-rule (1) of rule 3 shall also 
    state the number of such persons, the dates of their respective departure 
    from such area, and the dates on which each of such persons has been 
    vaccinated against yellow fever.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number>
    No person shall 
    bring into India an aircraft which has started from, or alighted in, an 
    airport situated in a yellow fever infected area unless it has been 
    disinsected immediately before departure from that airport under the control 
    of the Health authority of that airport in accordance with the procedure 
    prescribed in Schedule VI to these rules <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[or with any 
    procedure recommended by the World Health Organisation].





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Any aircraft which, having started from or alighted in an airport situated 
    in a yellow fever infected area, attempts to enter India, without having 
    been disinsected immediately before departure from that airport under the 
    control of the Health authority of the airport in accordance with the 
    procedure prescribed in Schedule VI to these rules <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[, or with 
    any procedure recommended by the World Health Organisation,] may be refused 
    entry.






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    
<section><number>1</number> On the arrival of an aircraft infected with yellow fever or suspected of 
    yellow fever infection—
 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   the aircraft and 
      cargo shall be disinsected,
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   all infected 
      persons shall be disembarked and isolated for such period as the Health 
      Officer may consider necessary,
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   all persons on 
      board shall be medically examined either before disembarkation or under 
      such arrangements as may be made by the Health Officer to reduce to a 
      minimum the risk of spread of infection, and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   any passenger or 
      member of the crew who disembarks and is not in possession of a valid 
      certificate of vaccination against yellow fever shall be isolated until 
      his certificate becomes valid or until a period of not more than nine days 
      reckoned from the date of last possible exposure to infection has elapsed, 
      whichever occurs first:
 

      Provided that persons on an international voyage proceeding to an airport 
      in a yellow fever receptive area at which the means for securing 
      segregation provided for in Article 34 of the International Sanitary 
      Regulations do not yet exist shall be disembarked by the Health Officer 
      and isolated for the period specified in clause (iv).
</subsection>
 

    Explanation.—(1) 
    Yellow fever receptive area means an area in which yellow fever does not 
    exist but where conditions would permit its development if introduced.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The aircraft shall cease to be regarded as infected or suspected when the 
    measures required by the Health Officer in accordance with sub-rule (1) of 
    this rule have been effectively carried out, and it shall thereupon be given 
    free pratique.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number>
    
<section><number>1</number> On the 
    arrival of a healthy aircraft coming from a yellow fever infected area—
 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   the aircraft and 
      cargo may be disinsected:
 
Provided that, when the 
      aircraft on its voyage over the yellow fever infected areas has landed 
      only at a sanitary airport which is not itself a yellow fever infected 
      area, the aircraft may not be disinsected unless a person, other than a 
      person in possession of valid certificate of vaccination against yellow 
      fever, from the surrounding yellow fever infected areas has boarded the 
      aircraft and the aircraft reached India within a period during which such 
      a person is likely to spead yellow fever infection.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   all persons on 
      board shall be medically examined either before disembarkation or under 
      such arrangements as may be made by the Health Officer to reduce to a 
      minimum the risk of spread of infection; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   any passenger 
      or member of the crew who has come in transit through any airport situated 
      in a yellow fever infected area and who is unable to produce a valid 
      certificate of vaccination against yellow fever shall be isolated until 
      his certificate becomes valid, or until a period of not more than nine 
      days reackoned from the date of the last possible exposure to infection 
      has elapsed, whichever occurs first:
 
Provided that, if the 
      airport situated in the yellow fever infected area is a sanitary airport 
      equipped with a direct transit area and if the Health Officer is satisfied 
      that passenger or member of the crew during the period of his entire stay 
      in the airport remained within such passenger or member of the crew from 
      isolation.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On 
    the arrival of a healthy aircraft which, although not coming from a yellow 
    fever infected area, has on board a person who has come from such an area 
    and is unable to produce a valid certificate of vaccination against yellow 
    fever the aircraft and cargo may be disinsected.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Any person who has come from a yellow fever infected area and is unable to 
    produce a valid certificate of vaccination against yellow fever shall be 
    isolated until his certificate becomes valid, or until a period of not more 
    than nine days reckoned from the date of last possible exposure to infection 
    has elapsed, whichever occurs first. A person who boards an aircraft in a 
    sanitary airport, which itself is not a yellow fever infected area, shall be 
    treated as a person who has come from a yellow fever infected area unless he 
    is able to prove to the satisfaction of the Health Officer that he has not 
    come from such an area.
 

    Explanation.—(1) 
    Sanitary airport referred to in the proviso to clauses (i) and (iii) of 
    sub-rule (1) and in sub-rule (3) means an airport which is equipped in 
    accordance with the provisions of paragraph 2 of Article 19 and paragraph 3 
    of Article 20 of International Sanitary Regulations and which may be 
    approved from time to time by the Central Government for this purpose.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    person shall be regraded as coming from a yellow fever infected area unless 
    the Health Officer is satisfied, by reference to the Personal Declaration of 
    Origin and health, that he has not been in such an area within nine days of 
    arrival in India.
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number>
    All isolation 
    prescribed by sub-rule 
<section><number>1</number> of rule 13 and by sub-rules (1) and (3) of rule 
    14 shall be carried out in such manner as to preclude the access of 
    mosquitoes to the persons under isolation.
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number>
    
<section><number>1</number> An aircraft 
    shall be regarded as infected with plague—
 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   if it has a case 
      of human plague on board, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   if there has 
      been a case of human plague on board and subsequent to the occurrence of 
      that case all the measures prescribed in rule 17 have not been taken, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   if a plague 
      infected rodent is found on board.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Even when coming from a plague infected area or having on board a person 
    coming from such an area, an aircraft shall be regarded as healthy if on 
    medical examination, the Health Officer is satisfied that conditions 
    specified in sub-rule (1) of this rule do not exist.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number>
    
<section><number>1</number> On the 
    arrival of an aircraft, infected with plague—
 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   the aircraft and 
      all persons on board shall be medically examined by the Health Officer,
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   all infected 
      persons on board shall be disembarked and isolated for such period as the 
      Health Officer may consider necessary;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   suspects on 
      board may be disinfected and, if necessary, placed under surveillance for 
      a period of not more than six days reckoned from the date or arrival;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   the Health 
      Officer may disinsect and, if necessary, disinfect—
 
 <subsubsection>
<number>a</number>   any baggage of 
        any infected person or suspect; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>b</number>   any other 
        article such as used bedding or linen, and any part of the aircraft, 
        which is considered to be contaminated;
</subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>   if a rodent whch 
      has died of plague is found on board the aircraft, the aircraft shall be 
      deratted, if necessary in quarantine;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vi</number>   any unloading 
      shall be carried out under the control of the Health Officer, who shall 
      take all measures which in his opinion are necessary to prevent the 
      infection of the staff engaged on this work and may, for the purpose, 
      subject the staff to surveillance for a period not exceeding six days from 
      the time they have ceased to work at the unloading of the aircraft.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An 
    airccraft shall cease to be regarded as infected when the measures required 
    by the Health Officer in accordance with sub-rule (1) of this rule have been 
    effectively carried out. The aircraft shall thereupon be given free pratique.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number>
    A healthy 
    aircraft shall be given free pratique but, if it has come from a plague 
    infected area, the Health Officer may place under surveillance any suspect, 
    who disembarks, for a period of not more than six days reckoned from the 
    date on which the aircraft left the plague infected area.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number>
    In exceptional 
    circumstances of an epidemiological nature, when the Health Officer suspects 
    the presence of rodents on board, he may derat the aircraft.
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number>
    
<section><number>1</number> An aircraft 
    shall be regarded as infected with cholera if it has a case of cholera on 
    board.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An 
    aircraft shall be regarded as suspected of cholera infection if a case of 
    cholera has occurred on board during the voyage but the case has previously 
    been disembarked.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Even when coming from a cholera infected area or having on board a person 
    coming from a cholera infected area, an aircraft shall be regarded as 
    healthy, if on medical examination, the Health Officer is satisfied that no 
    case of cholera has occurred on board during the voyage.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>21</number> 
    
<section><number>1</number> On the arrival of an aircraft infected with cholera,—
 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   the aircraft and 
      all persons on board shall be medically examined by the Health Officer;
      
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   all infected 
      persons shall be disembarked and isolated for such period as the Health 
      Officer may consider necessary;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   other persons, 
      who disembark, may be placed under isolation for a period of not more than 
      five days reckoned from the date of disembarkation provided that any 
      person who produces a valid certificate of vaccination against cholera may 
      be placed only under surveillance for a like period;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   the Health 
      Officer may disinfect—
 
 <subsubsection>
<number>a</number>   any baggage of 
        any infected person or suspect, and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
(b)   
        any other article such as used bedding, or linen and any part of the 
        aircraft, which is considered to be contaminated;
</subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>   if, in the 
      opinion of the Health Officer, any water carried on board is contaminated, 
      he shall cause it to be emptied out after it has been disinfected and to 
      be replaced, after disinfection of the containers, by a supply of 
      wholesome drinking water;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vi</number>   the Health 
      Officer may require human dejecta, waste water, waste matter and any 
      matter which is considered to be contaminated be disinfected before they 
      are discharged from the aircraft or unloaded;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vii</number> (a)   the Health 
      Officer may prohibit the unloading of, or may remove, any fish, shell 
      fish, fruit or vegetables to be consumed uncooked or beverages, unless 
      such food or beverages are in sealed containers and he has no reason to 
      believe that they are contaminated:
 
Provided that if any 
      such food or beverage forms part of the cargo in a freight compartment of 
      the aircraft only the Health Officer for the airport at which such food or 
      beverage is to be unloaded may exercise the power to remove it:
 
Provided further that 
      any such food or beverage shall be removed by the Health Officer if the 
      Commander of the aircraft so desires;
 <subsubsection>
<number>b</number>   if any such food 
      or beverage is removed, arrangements shall be made by the Health Officer 
      for its safe disposal;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>viii</number>   any unloading 
      shall be carried out under the control of the Health Officer, who shall 
      take all measures which, in his opinion, are necessary to prevent the 
      infection of the staff engaged on this work and may, for that purpose, 
      subject the staff to surveillance for a period not exceeding five days 
      from the time they ceased to work at the unloading of the aircraft.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An 
    aircraft shall cease to be regarded as infected when the measures required 
    by the Health Officer in accordance with sub-rule (i) of this rule have been 
    effectively carried out. The aircraft shall thereupon be given free pratique.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>22</number>
    (A) On the 
    arrival of an aircraft suspected of cholera infection—
 
 <section>
<number>1</number>   The aircraft and 
      all persons on board shall be medically examined by the Health Officer; 
      and
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> (i)   any person 
      who disembarks and who within five days of arrival has been in a cholera 
      infected area may,—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   if he is in 
        possession of a valid certificate of vaccination against cholera, be 
        placed under surveillance for a period not exceeding five days reckoned 
        from the time of the last exposure to infection;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   if he is not in 
        possession of such a certificate, be placed in isolation for a like 
        period.
</subsection>
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number>   any other 
      passenger or member of the crew who disembarks may be placed under 
      surveillance for a period not exceeding five days reckoned from the date 
      of arrival.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number>   all or any of the 
      measures specified in clauses (vi) to (vii) of sub-rule (1) of rule 21, 
      and not already taken, may be taken at the discretion of the Health 
      Officer.
</section>
 <section>
<number>B</number> An 
    aircraft shall cease to be regarded as suspected when the measures required 
    by the Health Officer in accordance with sub-rule (A) of this rule have been 
    effectively carried out. The aircraft shall thereupon be given free pratique.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number>
    On arrival, a 
    healthy aircraft shall be given free pratique but, if it has come from a 
    cholera infected area, the measures specified in clause (vii) of sub-rule 
    
<section><number>1</number> of rule 21 and in sub-clause (i) of clause (2) of sub-rule (A) of rule 
    22 may be taken at the discretion of the Health Officer.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    
<section><number>1</number> An aircraft shall be regarded as infected with smallpox—
 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   if it has a case 
      of smallpox on board, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   if a case of 
      smallpox has occurred on board during the voyage.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Any other aircraft shall be regarded as healthy even though there may be 
    suspects on board, but any suspect on disembarking may be subjected to the 
    measures provided for in rule 25.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>25</number>
    
<section><number>1</number> On the 
    arrival of an aircraft infected with smallpox—
 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   the aircraft and 
      all persons on board shall be medically examined by the Health Officer;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   all infected 
      persons shall be disembarked and isolated for such period as the Health 
      Officer may consider necessary;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   other persons 
      who disembark and who in the opinion of the Health Officer are not 
      sufficiently protected by vaccination or by a previous attack of smallpox—
 
 <subsubsection>
<number>a</number>   if they are 
        willing to be vaccinated, or in the case of minors if their guardians or 
        those in charge of them consent to their vaccination, may be subjected 
        to vaccination free of charge, and also to isolation or surveillance for 
        a period not exceeding fourteen days reckoned from the time of the last 
        exposure to infection, and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>b</number>   if they are not 
        willing to be vaccinated, or in the case of minors if their guardians or 
        those in charge of them do not consent to their vaccination, shall be 
        subjected to isolation or surveillance for the aforesaid period;
</subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   the Health 
      Officer shall disinfect—
 
 <subsubsection>
<number>a</number>   any baggage of 
        any infected person, and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>b</number>   any other 
        baggage or article such as used bedding or linen, and any part of the 
        aircraft, which is considered to be contaminated.
</subsubsection>
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An 
    aircraft shall continue to be regarded as infected until every infected 
    person has been removed and until the measures required by the Health 
    Officer in accordance with sub-rule (1) of this rule have been effectively 
    carried out. The aircraft shall thereupon be given free pratique.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>26</number> 
    On arrival, a healthy aircraft, even when it has come from a smallpox 
    infected area, shall be given free pratique but the measures specified in 
    clause 
<section><number>i</number> of sub-rule (1) of the rule 25 shall be taken and the measures 
    specified in clause (iii) of that sub-rule may be taken by the Health 
    Officer.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>27</number> 
    
<section><number>1</number> The Health Officer may require any person on an international voyage who 
    does not show sufficient evidence or protection by a previous attack of 
    smallpox to possess, on arrival, a certificate of vaccination against 
    smallpox. Any such person who cannot produce such a certificate may be 
    vaccinated; if he refuses to be vaccinated, he may be placed under 
    serveillance for not more than fourteen days, reckoned from the date of his 
    departure from the last territory visited before arrival.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    person on an international voyage who during a period of fourteen days 
    before his arrival, has visited a smallpox infected area and who in the 
    opinion of the Health Officer, is not sufficiently protected by vaccination 
    or by a previous attack of smallpox may be required to be vaccinated or may 
    be placed under suveillance, or may be vaccinated and then placed under 
    surveillance; if he refuses to be vaccinated, he may be isolated. The period 
    of surveillance or isolation shall not be more than fourteen days, reckoned 
    from the date of his departure from the infected area.
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of clause (iii) of sub-rule (1) of rule 5 and sub-rule (2) of 
    rule 27 a valid certificate of vaccination aganist smallpox shall be 
    considered as evidence of sufficient protection.
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>28</number>
    On the arrival 
    of an aircraft having on board a person who is suffering from or is believed 
    to be infected with typhus or relapsing fever—
 <section>
<number>1</number>   the aircraft and 
    all persons on board shall be medically examined by the Health Officer;
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>   all infected 
    persons shall be disembarked and isolated for such period as the Health 
    Officer may consider necessary, and disinsected;
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>   any suspect may be 
    disinsected; and
 </section><section>
<number>4</number>   the accommodation 
    occupied by the infected person and by any suspect, together with the 
    clothes they are wearing, the baggage and any other article which in the 
    opinion of the Health Officer is likely to spread typhus or relapsing fever, 
    may be disinsected and, if necessary, disinfected.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>29</number>
    A person on an 
    international voyage, who has left a typhus infected area within the 
    previous fourteen days or a relapsing fever infected area within previous 
    eight days, may, if the Health Officer considers it necessary, be 
    disinsected and put under surveillance for a period of not more than 
    fourteen days in the case of typhus and not more than eight days in the case 
    of relapsing fever, reckoned from the date of disinsecting. The clothes 
    which such person is wearing, his baggage and any other article which in the 
    opinion of the Health Officer is likely to spread typhus or relapsing fever 
    may be disinsected and, if necessary, disinfected.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>30</number> 
    
<section><number>1</number> An aircraft shall be regarded as infected with an infectious disease 
    other than quarantinable diseases—
 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   if it has a case 
      of any infectious diseases on board, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   if there has 
      been a case of any such infectious disease on board and subsequent to the 
      occurrence of that case all the measures prescribed in rule 31 of these 
      rules have not been taken.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An 
    aircraft shall be regarded as suspected of infection from an infectious 
    disease other than quarantinable disease if it has on board any person who 
    within the incubation period in respect of such infectious disease has been 
    in contact with a case of that disease or has been otherwise exposed to 
    infection from that disease.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>31</number>
    On the arrival 
    of an aircraft infected with an infectious disease other than quarantinable 
    disease—
 <section>
<number>1</number>   the aircraft and 
    all persons on board shall be medically examined by the Health Officer;
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>   any infected 
    person—
 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   who, not being a 
      direct transit passenger, disembarks, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   who being a 
      direct transit passenger, leaves the airport otherwise than in the manner 
      prescribed in rule 38, may be isolated for such period as the Health 
      Officer may consider necessary;
</subsection>
 </section><section>
           <number>3</number>   persons 
    who have been exposed to infection may, if they disembark, be placed under 
    surveillance for a period not exceeding the incubation period of the 
    infectious disease to which they have been exposed, such period being 
    reckoned from the time of the last exposure to infection;
 </section><section>
           <number>4</number>   any 
    parts of the aircraft and any goods or personal effects on board which, in 
    the opinion of the Health Officer, are contaminated may be disinfected.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>32</number>
    On the arrival 
    of an aircraft suspected of infection from an infectious disease—
 
 <section>
<number>1</number>   the measures 
      specified in sub-rule (1) of rule 31 shall be taken; and
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>   the measures 
      specified in sub-rules (3) and (4) of rule 31 not already taken may be 
      taken at the discretion of the Health Officer.
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>33</number> 
    Except in case of an emergency constituting a grave danger to public health, 
    an aircraft shall not, on account of an infectious disease other than 
    quarantinable diseases, be prevented by the Health Officer of an airport 
    from discharging or loading cargo or stores, or taking on fuel or water.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>34</number> 
    The provisions of this Part shall apply to all aircraft leaving India on an 
    international voyage.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[<number>35</number> 
    All persons proposing to embark upon an aircraft leaving any airport in the 
    Andaman and Nicobar Islands or Lakshadweep Islands for any airport on the 
    mainland or vice versa shall be medically examined by the Health 
    Officer but they are not required to be in possession of valid certificates 
    of vaccination against cholera and smallpox.]





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>36</number> 
    
<section><number>1</number> [The Health 
    Officer shall, when brought to his notice,] prohibit the embarkation on any 
    aircraft of—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   any 
    person showing symptoms of any quarantinable disease, and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   any 
    person whom the Health Officer considers likely to transmit infection 
    because of his close contact with a person showing symptoms of a quarantinable disease:
 

    Provided that nothing in this sub-rule shall apply when a person suffering 
    from a quarantinable disease is to be transported in an aircraft specially 
    adapted or allocated for the purpose:
 
Provided further that a 
    person on an international voyage who on arrival is placed under 
    surveillance may be allowed to continue his voyage in which case the Health 
    Officer shall record this fact in the Aircraft General Declaration.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Health Officer 
    shall take all practicable measures to prevent the introduction on board an 
    aircraft of possible agents of infection or vectors of a quarantinable 
    disease.
 

 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>37</number> 
Subject to the special 
    provisions relating to yellow fever prescribed in Part II of these rules, 
    passengers and crew from a healthy aircraft who are in transit through India 
    and who remain in the direct transit area of an airport or, if the airport 
    is not yet provided with such an area, who submit to the measures for 
    segregation prescribed by the Health Officer in order to prevent the spread 
    of disease, shall not be subjected to any sanitary measure other than 
    medical examination, if such persons are obliged to leave the airport at 
    which they disembark solely in order to continue their voyage from another 
    airport in the vicinity of the first airport, no such measure shall be 
    applied to them if the transfer is made under the control of the Health 
    Officer concerned.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>38</number> 
Where there is an epidemic 
    of pulmonary plague in an airport every suspect shall, before departure on 
    an international voyage, be placed in isolation for a period of six days 
    reckoned from the date of the last exposure to infection,

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>39</number> 
When typhus or relapsing 
    fever exists in an airport, a person on an international voyage whom the 
    Health Officer considers is liable to spread typhus or relapsing fever, 
    shall be disinsected. The clothes which such person is wearing, his baggage, 
    and any other article likely to spread typhus or relapsing fever shall be 
    disinsected and if necessary, disinfected.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

    1[<number>39A</number> Every 
    aircraft leaving a local area where transmission of malaria or other 
    mosquito-borne disease is occurring, or where insecticide resistant mosquito 
    vectors of disease are present, shall be disinsected under the control of 
    the Health Officer as near as possible to the time of its departure but in 
    sufficient time to avoid delaying such departure.]
 

 

 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>40</number> 
No person shall be 
    permitted by the Health Officer to embark on an aircraft with a view to 
    proceeding by air to the Hedjaz unless such person produces valid 
    certificates of vaccination against cholera and smallpox.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>41</number> 
No person shall bring into 
    India any dead-body or human remains of persons who may have died of yellow 
    fever, plague, anthrax, glanders or such other diseases as may be notified 
    by the Central Government for this purpose:
 
Provided that nothing in 
    this rule shall apply to properly cremated ashes of dead bodies or human 
    remains.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>42</number> 
    The dead body human remains of a person who may have died of a disease other 
    than those specified in rule 41 may be brought into India subject to the 
    provisions of rules 43 to 47.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>43</number> 
    The consignee as well as the air transport service shall give to the Health 
    Officer of the airport of arrival advance intimation of at least 48 hours, 
    of the importation of the dead body or human remains or ashes of cremated 
    bodies:
 
Provided that nothing in 
    this rule or in rules 44 to 47 shall apply to the dead body of a person who 
    dies during fight before arrival of the aircraft in India. The Commander of 
    the aircraft shall send, if the aircraft is equipped with wireless, a radio 
    report to the Health Officer of the airport, where he proposes to land in 
    India, regarding the occurrence and, if possible, cause of death. On landing 
    of the aircraft no passenger or member of the crew shall disembark until 
    appropriate sanitary measures have been taken by the Health Officer of the 
    airport.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>44</number> 
Applications to bring dead 
    bodies or human remains or ashes of cremated bodies to India shall be made 
    to the Indian Diplomatic representatives in countries where such 
    representatives are functioning or where there is no such representative, to 
    the Health Officer of the airport at which the dead body is to be landed.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>45</number> 
    
<section><number>1</number> If the dead body or human remains have been properly cremated the 
    cremated ashes shall be placed in an urn or casket having an outer packing 
    of suitable material.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In the case of 
    uncremated remains, the following procedure shall be adopted:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   A corpse which has not been burried should be closed in a shell of zinc or other equally suitable metal 
    with all joints so soldered as to seal them hermetically and prevent the 
    escape of noxious gases or fluids. The shell should be enclosed in a stoutly 
    built teak or other hard wood coffin and the coffin should be enclosed in a 
    zinc or tin-lined wooden packing case filled with sawdust impregnated with 
    carbolic powder.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   Where a coffin has been 
    exhumed and proves on examination to be intact, sound and free from 
    offensive odour, it should be enclosed in a hermetically sealed zinc or 
    tin-lined wooden packing case filled with saw-dust impregnated with carbolic 
    powder.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   Where a coffin has been 
    exhumed and is not intact, sound and free from odour, its contents should be 
    dealt with in accordance with the requirements of clause (a) above.

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>46</number> 
A certificate issued by a 
    responsible Municipal or Governmental authority of the country from where 
    the package containing the dead-body, or human remains or ashes of cremated 
    bodies, as the case may be is imported and endorsed by the Indian Diplomatic 
    Representatives, if any, in that country shall accompany the package. The 
    certificate shall give the full name of the deceased, his age at the time of 
    death and the place, date and cause of death and shall indicate that the 
    package conforms to and has been sealed in accordance with the 
    specifications prescribed in rule 45.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>47</number> 
    The package containing the dead body or human remains or ashes of cremated 
    bodies shall not be opened during its transit and shall be in a sound sealed 
    condition at the time of arrival. It shall not be removed from the precincts 
    of the airport until the Health Officer has permitted in writing its 
    removal. After the Health Officer has accorded this permission, the 
    consignee shall remove and dispose of the package in accordance with the 
    general or special instructions which may be issued by the local 
    authorities, Governmental and/or Municipal in this behalf.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

    1[<number>48</number> For the 
    transmission of dead-body or human remains and ashes of cremated bodies from 
    India to any place outside India, the prior written permission of the 
    competent authority of the country of destination as also of the District 
    Magistrate or the Deputy Commissioner or the Chief Presidency Magistrate or 
    the Coroner within whose jurisdiction the death took place, shall be 
    obtained. The requirements laid down by the country of destination with 
    regard to the import of dead bodies, human remains or ashes or cremated 
    bodies into its territory shall be complied with by the consignor. In case 
    no such conditions have been prescribed, the provisions of rule 45 shall be 
    complied with the package and it shall bear an inscription to the effect 
    that it contains infected material and should be handled with care.]
 

 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>49</number> 
    Subject to the provision of rule 41, a package containing a dead body or 
    human remains or ashes or cremated remains, which is in transit through 
    India shall not be subject to any restrictions if it has been packed and 
    sealed in the manner prescribed in rule 45 or in a manner which, in the 
    opinion of the Health Officer, is considered to be equally satisfactory.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>50</number> 
    The sanitary measures permitted by these rules are the maximum measures 
    applicable to international traffic.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>51</number> 
    Sanitary measure and health formalities shall be initiated forthwith, 
    completed without delay, and applied without discrimination.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>52</number> 
    Any sanitary measures other than medical examination, which has been applied 
    to an aircraft at a previous airport shall not be repeated unless—
 <section>
<number>a</number>   after the departure of the 
    aircraft from the airport where the measures were applied, an incident of 
    epidemiological significance calling for a further application of any such 
    measure has occurred either in that airport or on board the aircraft; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   the Health Officer has reason 
    to believe that the individual measure so applied was not substantially 
    effective.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>53</number> 
    The Commander of an aircraft coming from a place outside India and 
    proceeding to a place outside India may, if he so desires, notify the Health 
    Officer of the airport in India where the aircraft first arrives, that he 
    does not wish to submit to any of the provisions, except the special 
    provisions relating to yellow fever, prescribed in part II of these rules; 
    and the aircraft shall thereupon be at liberty to continue its voyage, 
    without such submission, provided that it shall not during its voyage land 
    any where else in India except for the purpose of taking on fuel, water and 
    stores in quarantine.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>54</number> 
    The Health Officer shall when so requested issue free of charge to the 
    Commander of an aircraft a certificate specifying the measures applied to 
    the aircraft, the parts thereof treated, the methods employed and reasons 
    why the measures have been applied. This information shall, on request, be 
    entered in the Aircraft General Declaration.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>55</number> 
    The Health Officer shall, when so requested, issue free of charge—
 <section>
<number>a</number>   to any traveller a certificate specifying the date of his arrival or departure and 
    the measures applied to him and his baggage;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   to the 
    consignor, the consignee, and the carrier, or their respective agents, a 
    certificate specifying the measures applied to any goods.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>56</number> 
    Where any person is required under these rules to be disembarked and 
    isolated for any period, the Health Officer may remove or cause to be 
    removed, that person to a hospital or other place approved by the Health 
    Officer and detain him therein for that period. Persons who are under 
    isolation for a disease other than yellow fever may, however, in exceptional 
    circumstances at the discretion of the Health Officer, be allowed to 
    continue their voyage before the expiry of the isolation period.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>57</number>
    
<section><number>1</number> Whenever 
    surveillance is required or permitted by these rules, isolation shall not be 
    substituted for surveillance unless the Health Officer of the airport where 
    the suspect arrives or any other health authority to whom he is required to 
    report during the period of surveillance considers the risk of transmission 
    of the infection by the suspect to be exceptionally serious.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Apart from the provisions relating to quarantinable disease in Part II of 
    these Rules, the Health Officer may place under surveillance any suspect on 
    an international voyage arriving from an infected area. Such surveillance 
    may be continued until the end of the appropriate period of incubation 
    specified in rule 2 (15).

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>58</number> 
    A person under surveillance shall not be isolated and shall be permitted to 
    move about freely. The Health Officer may require such a person to report to 
    him, if necessary at specified intervals during the period of surveillance. 
    The Health Officer may also subject such a person to medical investigation 
    and make any enquiries which are necessary for ascertaining his state of 
    health. Rectal swabbing shall not be done, but a person showing symptoms 
    indicative of cholera may be required to submit to stool examination.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>59</number> 
    When the prson under surveillance departs for another place, he shall inform 
    the Health Officer who shall immediately inform the health authority for the 
    place to which the person is proceeding. On arrival the person shall report 
    to the health authority who may apply the measures provided for in rule 58.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>60</number> 
    Every person shall comply with all directions lawfully given and all 
    conditions lawfully imposed by the Health Officer in pursuance of these 
    Rules and shall give that Officer all reasonable facilities for the 
    discharge of any duty imposed on him by these rules.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>61</number>
    The Health 
    Officer may, whenever he considers it desirable, refuse entry into the 
    airport to any person, other than a person proceeding on an international 
    voyage, or remove or cause to be removed from the premises of the airport 
    any person who, in his opinion, is likely to spread any quarantinable or 
    other infectious disease.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>62</number> 
    
<section><number>1</number> Disinfection, disinfecting, deratting and other sanitary operations 
    shall be so carried out as—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   not to 
    cause undue discomfort to any person or injury to his health;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   not to 
    produce any deleterious effect on the structure of an aircraft or on its 
    operating equipment;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   to avoid all risk of fire.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> In carrying out such 
    operations on goods, baggage and other articles, every precaution shall be 
    taken to avoid any damage.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>63</number> 

<section><number>1</number> Goods shall be 
    submitted to sanitary measures provided for in these rules only when the 
    Health Officer has reason to believe that they may have become contaminated 
    by the infection of a quarantinable disease or may serve as a vehicle for 
    the spread of any such disease.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Apart from the measures 
    provided for in special provisions relating to cholera goods, other than 
    live animals, in transit without transhipment shall not be subjected to any 
    sanitary measures or detained at any airport.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>64</number> 
    Except in the case of an infected person or suspect, baggage may be 
    disinfected or disinsected only in the case of a person carrying infective 
    material or insect vectors of a quarantinable disease.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>65</number> 
    
<section><number>1</number> Mail, newspapers, books and other printed matter shall not be subject to 
    any sanitary measure.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Postal parcels may be 
    subjected to sanitary measures only if they contain—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   any of the foods referred to 
    in sub-rule (7) of rule 21 of these rules, which the Health Officer has 
    reason to believe comes from a cholera infected area; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   linen, wearing apparel, or 
    bedding which has been used or soiled and to which the provisions of Parts 
    II and III of these rules are applicable.

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>66</number> 
    No sanitary document other than those provided for in these rules, shall be 
    required by the Health Officer.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>67</number> 
    
<section><number>1</number> No charge shall be made by the Health Officer of an airport for—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   any medical examination 
    provided for in these rules or any supplementary examination, 
    bacteriological or otherwise which may be required to ascertain the state of 
    health of the person examined;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   any vaccination of a person on 
    arrival and any certificate thereof.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Charges for applying 
    the measures provided for in these rules, other than the measures referred 
    to in sub-rule (1) of this rule, shall conform with the tariff for such 
    charges as may be fixed from time to time by the Central Government. These 
    charges shall be rendered and they shall be levied without distinction as to 
    the nationality domicile or residence of the person concerned or as to the 
    nationality, flag registry or ownership of the aircraft. In particular there 
    shall be no distinction made between national and foreign persons and 
    aircraft.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The tariff, and any 
    amendment thereto, shall be published in the Official Gazette at least ten 
    days in advance of the levy thereunder.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If any person or member 
    of crew refuses or fails to pay any charges due from him then, without 
    prejudice to any proceedings that may be taken against him, such charges 
    shall be recoverable from the owner of the aircraft on which such person or 
    member of the crew arrives.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>68</number> 
    The Commander of an aircraft shall during the stay of the aircraft in an 
    airport, take such precautions as the Health Officer may specify in order to 
    prevent rodents gaining access to the aircraft.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>69</number> 
A vaccination document 
    issued by the Armed Forces to an active member of the Armed Forces shall be 
    accepted in lieu of an international certificate in the form shown in 
    Schedules III, IV or V if—
 <section>
<number>a</number>   it embodies medical 
    information substantially the same as that required by such form; and
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   it contains a statement in 
    English or in French recording the nature and date of the vaccination and to 
    the effect that it is issued in accordance with Article 99 of the 
    International Sanitary Regulations.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>70</number> 
No person shall throw or 
    let fall from any aircraft any matter capable of producing an outbreak of a 
    quarantinable or an infectious or any other epidemic disease.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>71</number> 
    Whoever contravenes any provision of these rules, or disobeys, or fails to 
    comply with, any order given in pursuance of these rules shall be punishable 
    with imprisonment for a term not exceeding three months or with fine which 
    may extend to one thousand rupees or with both.
  
  

 
  


</article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



Aircraft (Public health) Rules, 1954
 

 
 



 



1[Schedule 
    I
 



Personal Declaration of 
    Origin and Health
 



(See rule 6)
 



(For passengers on aircraft) 
 



Port of arrival
 


1. Name in full.
 


2. Permanent (Home) 
    Address.
 


3. (Precise address to 
    which immediately proceeding.
 


4. Please state where you 
    spent the nine days prior to arrival.
 
 
  
 Last Day
 Name of the countries 
        including transit places

 
  
  
  

 
  
 2 days ago
  

 
  
 3 days ago
  

 
  
 4 days ago
  

 
  
 5 days ago
  

 
  
 6 days ago
  

 
  
 7 days ago
  

 
  
 8 days ago
  

 
  
 9 days ago
  


 

 
 


I declare that the 
    information given above is correct to the best of my knowledge and belief.
 



 


  Signature.............................
 



        Date.....................................]
 


 
 


----------------------------------------------------------
 



     1. 
      Subs. by S.O. 2735, dated 28th August, 1965.
 


----------------------------------------------------------
 

 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



Aircraft (Public health) Rules, 1954
 

 
 

 
 




1[Schedule 
    II
 



Declaration of health
 



(See rule 6)
 



 


Persons on board known to 
    be suffering from illness other than air sickness or the effects of 
    accidents, as well as those cases of illness disembarked during the 
    flight..............
 


Any other condition on 
    board which may lead to the spread of diseases.......................
 


Details of each 
    disinsecting or sanitary treatment (place, date, time, method) during the 
    flight. If no disinsecting has been carried out during the flight give 
    details of most recent disinsecting............................................................................................................................ 
    .............................................................................................................SGD, 
    if required.
 


 
 



.........................................
 



Crew member concerned]
 



    --------------------------------------------------
 



     
    1.   Subs. by S.O. 2710, dated 3rd November, 1961.
 



    --------------------------------------------------
 


 
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



Aircraft (Public health) Rules, 1954
 

 
 

 
 



Schedule III
 



International Certificate 
    of Vaccination or  

    Re-vaccination against yellow Fever
 



(See rules 2 (20) and 14)
 



 


This is to certify 
    that...........................................Date of 
    birth.....................Sex.............
 


whose signature 
    follows..............................has on the date indicated been 
    vaccinated or revaccinated against yellow fever.
 
 
 
 
 
 Date
 
            Signature and professional Status of Vaccinator
 
            Origin and Batch No. of Vaccine
 
            Original Stamp of Vaccinating Center




 
  

 
  

 
  

 
  


 

 
 



1Note.—This 
    certificate is valid only if the vaccine used has been approved by the World 
    Health Organization and if the vaccinating centre has been designated by the 
    health administration for the territory in which the centre is situated.
 


The validity of this 
    certificate shall extend for a period of 10 years, begining ten days after 
    the date of vaccination or, in the event of a revaccination within such 
    period of 10 years from the date of that revaccination.
 


Any amendment of this 
    certificate, or erasure, or failure to complete any part of it, may render 
    it invalid.]
 


 
 



 



 



    ------------------------------------------------
 



      1   Subs. by S.O. 
    2735, dated 28th August, 1965.
 



    ------------------------------------------------
 


 
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



Aircraft (Public health) Rules, 1954
 

 
 


 
 



Schedule IV
 



International Certificate 
    of Vaccination or  

    Re-vaccination against Cholera
 



[See rules 2 (20), 21 and 22]
 



 


This is to certify 
    that.....................................Date of 
    birth...............................Sex................. whose signature 
    follows.........................has on the date indicated been vaccinated or 
    revaccinated against cholera.
 
 
 
 
 
 Date
            
 
            Signature and Professional Status of Vaccinator
 
            Approved Stamp.




 
 
 
 
  
  
  

 
 
1
 
1
 
2

 
 
2
  
  

 
 
3
 
3
 
4

 
 
4
  
  

 
 
5
 
5
 
6

 
 
6
  
  

 
 
7
 
7
 
8

 
 
 

8
  
  





 

 
 


The validity of this 
    certificate shall extend for a period of six months, beginning six days 
    after the first injection of the vaccine or in the event of a revaccination 
    within such period of six months, on the date of that revaccination.
 



1[***]
 


The approved stamp 
    mentioned above must be in a form prescribed by the health adminstration of 
    the territory in which the vaccination is performed.
 


Any amendment of this 
    certificate, or erasure, or failure to complete any part of it, may render 
    it invalid.
 

 
 

 
 



    ----------------------------------------------------
 



     
    1.   Omitted by S.R.O. 2284, dated 5th July, 1957.
 



    ----------------------------------------------------
 


 
 


 
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



Aircraft (Public health) Rules, 1954
 

 
 


 
 





1Schedule 
    V
 



International Certificate 
    of Vaccination or  

    Re-vaccination Against Smallpox
 



[See rules 2 (20) and 27]
 



 


This is to certify 
    that........................................Date of 
    birth............................ Sex............... whose signature 
    follows...........................has on the date indicated been vaccinated 
    or revaccinated against smallpox with a freeze dried or liquid vaccine 
    certified to fulfil the recommended requirements of the World Health 
    Organisation.
 
 
 
 
 
 Date
 Show by 'X' 

            Whether
 Signature and Professional Status of Vaccinator
 Origin and Batch no. of Vaccine
 Approved Stamp




 
 
 
 
  
  
  
  
  

 
 
(a) 1 
 
Primary vaccination Performed
  
 
a1
 
b1

 
 
(b) 1
 
Read as  

            Successful 

            Unsuccessful
  
  
  

 
 
2
 
Revaccination
  
 
2
 
3

 
 
3
 
Revaccination
  
  
  





 

 
 


The validity of this 
    certificate shall extend for a period of three years, beginning eight days 
    after the date of a successful primary vaccination or, in the event of a 
    revaccination, on the date of that revaccination.
 


The approved stamp 
    mentioned above must be in a form prescribed by the health administration of 
    the territory in which the vaccination is performed.
 


Any amendment of this 
    certificate, or erasure, or failure to complete any part of it, may render 
    it invalid.
 


Note.— 
    This revised Schedule V will come into force on 1st January, 1967.]
 

 
 

 
 



    ----------------------------------------------------
 



     
    1.   Subs. by S.O. 
    2735, dated 28th August, 1965 (w.e.f. 1-1-1967).
 



    ----------------------------------------------------
 


 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 


 

AIRCRAFT (PUBLIC HEALTH) RULES, 1954 
 

 
 

Schedule VI 
 

PROCEDURE FOR DISINSECTISATION OF AIRCRAFT 
 

[ See  rule 9(2)] 
 


 

The interior of the aircraft (inclusive of all places likely to harbour mosquitoes, such as cockpits, freight compartments, cabins) shall be sprayed with a pyrethrums—DDT aerosol containing not less than 0.4 per cent. pyrethrums and 3 per cent. DDT, 1[***] at a rate of not less than 2[8 to 10 seconds] per 1,000 cubic feet of free air space; the stopcock in the case of an aerosol dispense other than the Westinghouse type being kept open not less than half a turn during the operation and in the Westinghouse type the cap being removed completely. All openings into the aircraft shall be kept tightly closed during the spraying and for a period of not less than 2 [five minutes] thereafter. 
 

----------------
 

1.Omitted by S.O. 3126, dated 20th December, 1960. 
 

2. Subs. by S.R.O. 2084, dated 5th July, 1957. 
 

 

 




</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   
 Amended 
    by Notification No. F.34-1/64-1H, dated 7th November, 1969.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> 
 
Ins. by 
    S.R.O. 3650, dated 9th Novemeber, 1957.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> 
 
Subs. by 
    S.O. 984, dated 30th March, 1963.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   
    Subs. by S.O. 2710, dated 8th November, 1961.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> 
 
Rule 8 
    renumbered as sub-rule (1) thereof by S.O. 2741, dated 3rd September, 1966.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> 
 
Ins. by S.O. 2741, dated 3rd 
    September, 1966.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> 
 
Ins. by S.O. 2735, dated 28th 
    August, 1965.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> 
 
Subs. by S.O. 2741, dated 3rd 
    September, 1966.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> 
 
Ins. by S.O. 1475, dated 31st 
    May, 1960.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>   
    Added by S.O. 2741, dated 3rd September, 1966.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>   
    Added by S.O. 2741, dated 3rd September, 1966.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>   Subs. by S.O. 3417, dated 10th September, 1979.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>   
    Ins. by S.O. 2735, dated 28th August, 1965.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>   
    As amended by Notification No. F. 34-1/64-IH, dated 7th November, 1969.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>