<act><title>


Appellate Authority for Industrial and 
    Financial Reconstruction (Secretary’s Powers and Duties) Rules, 1988</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>i</number> These 
    rules may be called the Appellate Authority for Industrial and Financial 
    Reconstruction (Secretary’s Powers and Duties) Rules, 1988.
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> They 
    shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official 
    Gazette.
 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “Act” means the Sick Industrial 
    Companies (Special Provisions) Act, 1985 (1 of 1986);
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “Bench” means a Bench of the Appellate 
    Authority constituted under sub-section (2) of section 12 of the Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “Appellate Authority” means the 
    Appellate Authority for Industrial and Financial Reconstruction, constituted 
    under section 5 of the Act, and includes, where the context so requires, a 
    Bench exercising the jurisdiction, powers and authority of the Appellate 
    Authority;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    “Chairman” means the Chairman of 
    Appellate Authority;  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    “Secretary” means the Secretary to the 
    Appellate Authority appointed under sub-section (1) of section 8 of the Act.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> General.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Secretary shall be principal Officer of the Appellate Authority who 
    shall exercise his powers and perform his duties under the control of the 
    Chairman.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Appellate Authority, in discharge of its functions under the Act, may take 
    such assistance from the Secretary as it may deem fit and the Secretary 
    shall be bound to assist the Appellate Authority.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In 
    particular and without prejudice to the generality of the provisions of this 
    rule, the Secretary shall exercise the following powers and perform the 
    following duties, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    It shall be the duty of the Secretary 
    to assist the Appellate Authority in making such enquiry as it deems fit in 
    connection with any appeal before the Appellate Authority.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    The Secretary shall have the right to 
    collect from the Central Government, the Reserve Bank, any scheduled bank or 
    any other bank, public financial institutions or State level institutions or 
    other offices, institutions, companies, firms, such information as may be 
    considered useful for the purpose of discharge of the functions of the 
    Appellate Authority under the Act and place the said information before the 
    Appellate Authority.   
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    The official seal of the Appellate 
    Authority shall not be affixed to any order, summons, other process or any 
    certified copy issued by the Appellate Authority or any other document save 
    under the authority in writing of the Secretary.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    The Secretary shall have the custody of 
    the records of the Appellate Authority.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    The official seal of the Appellate 
    Authority shall be in the custody and control of the Secretary.  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Additional powers and duties of the Secretary.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In addition to his powers and duties specified in rule 3, the Secretary 
    shall have the following additional powers and perform the following duties, 
    namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    receive all references, applications, 
    reports, letters, representations and other documents;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    decide all questions arising out of 
    any reference to the Appellate Authority before the same is registered in 
    the office of the Appellate Authority;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    require any reference to be amended 
    in accordance with the Act, or the regulations made under section 13 of the 
    Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    subject to the directions of the 
    Chairman, or the respective Benches, as the case may be, fix dates for 
    hearing of references, applications or other proceedings;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>    direct formal amendment of records;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vi</number>    grant leave to inspect the records of 
    the Appellate Authority;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vii</number>    dispose of all matters relating to 
    the service of the notices, summons, other process, applications for issue 
    of fresh notices, summon or other process or for extending time for ordering 
    a particular mode of service including the substituted service by 
    publication of the notices, summons or other process by way of advertisement 
    in the newspapers.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> An appeal 
    against the decision of, or direction issued by, the Secretary under clauses 
    (ii), (iii), (v), (vi) and (vii) shall be made to the Chairman by the 
    aggrieved party within 15 days from the date on which such decision or 
    direction is communicated to him and the decision thereon of the Chairman 
    shall be final.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> Powers 
    exercisable under these rules to be in addition to other powers of the 
    Secretary.—
<section><number>1</number> The powers 
    exercisable and duties to be performed by the Secretary under these rules 
    shall be in addition to those prescribed under any other rules as have 
    already been made or as may be made from time to time, by the Central 
    Government under section 36 of the Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The powers 
    exercisable and duties to be performed by the Secretary under these rules 
    are without prejudice to those as may be specified by the Chairman or 
    delegated to the Secretary by the Appellate Authority under section 27 of 
    the Act. 

 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>