<act><title>


Board for Industrial and Financial 
    Reconstruction (Secretary’s Powers and Duties) Rules, 19871</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Board for Industrial and Financial Reconstruction 
    (Secretary’s Powers and Duties) Rules, 1987. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “Act” means the Sick 
    Industrial Companies (Special Provisions) Act, 1985 (1 of 1986);
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “Bench” means a Bench of 
    the Board constituted under sub-section (2) of section 12;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “Board” means the Board 
    for Industrial and Financial Reconstruction, established under section 4 of 
    the Act, and includes, where the context so requires, a Bench exercising the 
    jurisdiction, powers and authority of the Board;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    “Chairman” means the 
    Chairman of the Board;  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    “operating agency” means 
    any public financial institution specified by the Board, by general or 
    special order, as its agency;
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    “reference” means 
    reference made to the Board under section 15 of the Act;
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    “Secretary” means the 
    Secretary to the Board appointed under sub-section (1) of section 8 of the 
    Act.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> General.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Secretary shall be the principal officer of the Board who shall exercise 
    his powers and perform his duties under the control of the Chairman.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Board 
    in discharge of its functions under the Act, may take such assistance from 
    the Secretary, as it may deem fit, and the Secretary shall be bound to 
    assist the Board.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In 
    particular and without prejudice to the generality of the provisions of this 
    rule, the Secretary shall have the following powers and perform the 
    following duties, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    It shall be the duty of 
    the Secretary to scrutinise the report submitted by any operating agency, in 
    pursuance of the order of the Board made under sub-section (2) of section 16 
    of the Act and submit a report to the Board on the point as to whether the 
    said report is complete with respect to matters which the operating agency 
    was required by the Board to enquire into or not, and seek directions of the 
    Board as to carrying out of further inquiry, if any, by the operating agency 
    and submission by it of a further report.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    It shall be the duty of 
    the Secretary to scrutinise the scheme prepared by any operating agency in 
    pursuance of an order of the Board under sub-section (3) of section 17 or a 
    fresh scheme prepared by an operating agency in pursuance of the order of 
    the Board under sub-section (5) of section 18 of the Act, and submit a 
    report on the point as to whether the said scheme has been prepared in 
    accordance with the guidelines specified in the order of the Board.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    The Secretary shall have 
    the right to collect from the Central Government, the Reserve Bank, any 
    scheduled bank or any other bank, the public financial institutions or the 
    State level institutions, or other offices, institutions, companies, firms, 
    such information as may be considered useful for the purpose of efficient 
    discharge of the functions of the Board under the Act and place the said 
    information before the Board.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    The Secretary may call 
    upon any industrial company to furnish within such time, as may be specified 
    by him, information in relation to compliance by the company of the 
    provisions of sub-section (1) of section 23 and seek the directions of the 
    Chairman as to further action, if any, to be taken in the matter.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    The official seal of the 
    Board shall not be affixed to any order, summons, other process or any 
    certified copy issued by the Board or any other documents save under the 
    authority in writing of the Secretary.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    The Secretary shall have 
    the custody of the records of the Board.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    The official seal of the 
    Board shall be in the custody and control of the Secretary.

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Additional powers and duties of the Secretary.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In addition to his powers and duties specified in rule 3, the Secretary 
    shall have the following additional powers and perform the following duties, 
    namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    receive all references, 
    applications, reports, letters, representations and other documents;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    decide all questions 
    arising out of any reference to the Board before the same is registered in 
    the office of the Board;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    require any reference 
    to be amended in accordance with the Act or the regulations made under 
    section 13 of the Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    subject to the 
    directions of the Chairman, or the respective Benches, as the case may be, 
    fix dates for hearing of references, applications or other proceedings;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>    direct formal amendment 
    of records;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vi</number>    grant leave to inspect 
    the records of the Board;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vii</number>    dispose of all matters 
    relating to the service of the notice, summons, other process, applications 
    for issue of fresh notices, summons or other process, or for extending time 
    for ordering a particular mode of service including the substituted service 
    by publication of the notice, summons or other process by way of 
    advertisement in the newspapers.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> An appeal 
    against the decision of or direction issued by the Secretary under clauses 
    (ii), (iii), (v) (vi) and (vii) shall be made to the Chairman by the 
    aggrieved party within 15 days from the date on which such decision or 
    direction is communicated to him and the decision thereon of the Chairman 
    shall be final.  
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> Powers 
    exercisable under these rules to be in addition to other powers of the 
    Secretary.—
<section><number>1</number> The powers 
    exercisable and duties to be performed by the Secretary under these rules 
    shall be in addition to those prescribed under any other rules as have 
    already been made or as may be made from time to time, by the Central 
    Government under section 36 of the Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The powers 
    exercisable and duties to be performed by the Secretary under these rules 
    are without prejudice to those as may be specified by the Chairman or 
    delegated to the Secretary, by the Board under section 27 of the Act.  
 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>