<act><title>


Board for Industrial and Financial Reconstruction 
(Salaries and Allowances and Conditions of 
Service of Chairman and other Members) 
Rules, 1987</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Board for Industrial and Financial Reconstruction 
(Salaries and Allowances and Conditions of Service of Chairman and other 
Members) Rules, 1987.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
        
<number>a</number> “Act” means the Sick Industrial Companies (Special Provisions) Act, 1985 (1 
of 1986);
 </section><section>
        
<number>b</number> “Board” means the Board for Industrial and Financial Reconstruction, 
established under section 4 of the Act;
 </section><section>
        
<number>c</number> “Chairman” means the Chairman of the Board appointed under section 4 of the 
Act;
 </section><section>
        
<number>d</number> “Member” means a Member of the Board appointed under section 4 of the Act.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Pay.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chairman shall receive pay as admissible to a Judge of a High Court.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A Member shall receive 
pay as admissible to the Secretary to the Government of India:
 
Provided that in the case 
of an appointment of a person as a Chairman, or as a Member, who was retired as 
a Judge of a High Court or who has retired from service under the Central 
Government or a State Government and who is in receipt of or has received or has 
become entitled to receive any retirement benefit by way of pension, gratuity, 
employer’s contribution to the Contributory Provident Fund or other forms of 
retirement benefits, the pay of such Chairman or Member shall be reduced by the 
gross amount of pension and pension equivalent of gratuity or employer’s 
contribution to the Contributory Provident Fund or any other form of retirement 
benefits, if any, drawn or to be drawn by him.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Dearness allowance 
and city compensatory allowance.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chairman shall receive dearness allowance and city compensatory allowance at 
the rate admissible to a Judge of the Delhi High Court.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A Member shall receive 
dearness allowance and city compensatory allowance at the rate admissible to a 
Group ‘A’ officer of the Central Government drawing an equivalent pay.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Leave.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Person, on appointment in the Board as Chairman or a Member shall be entitled to 
have leave as follows:
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number> Earned leave at the rate of thirty days for every completed calendar year of 
service or a part thereof:
 
                 
Provided that the leave account shall be credited with earned leave in advance, 
in two instalments of fifteen days each on the first day of January and July of 
every calendar year:
 
                 
Provided further that the earned leave at the credit at the close of previous 
half year shall be carried forward to next half year, subject to the condition 
that the leave so carried forward plus credit for the half year do not exceed 
the maximum limit of one hundred and eighty days;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number> Half pay leave on medical certificate or on private affairs at the rate of 
twenty days in respect of each completed year of service and the leave salary 
for half pay leave shall be equivalent to half of the leave salary admissible 
during the earned leave;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>iii</number> Leave on half pay may be commuted to full pay leave at the discretion of 
the Chairman or a Member, provided it is taken on medical grounds and is 
supported by a medical certificate by a competent medical authority;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iv</number> Extraordinary leave without pay and allowances up to a maximum period of 
one hundred and eighty days in one term of office.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Leave sanctioning 
authority.—The 
Chairman shall be authority competent to sanction leave to a Member and the 
President of India shall be the authority competent to sanction leave to the 
Chairman.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Provident Fund.—The 
Chairman or a Member shall be entitled to subscribe to the General Provident 
Fund at his option and in case of his so opting, shall be governed by the 
provision of the General Provident Fund (Central Services) Rules.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Travelling 
Allowances.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chairman while on tour or on transfer (including the journey undertaken to 
join the Board or on the expiry of his term with Board to proceed to his home 
town) shall be entitled to the travelling allowances, daily allowances, 
transportation of personal effects and other similar matters at the same scale 
and the same rates as are prescribed in the High Court Judge (Travelling 
Allowances) Rules, 1956.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A Member while on tour 
or on transfer (including the journey undertaken to join the Board or on the 
expiry of his term with the Board to proceed to his home town) shall be entitled 
to the travelling allowances, daily allowances, transportation of personal 
effects and other similar matters at the same scales and at the same rates as 
are applicable to a Group ‘A’ officer of the Central Government drawing an 
equivalent pay.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Leave travel 
concession.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chairman shall be entitled to leave travel concession at the same rates and 
at the same scales as are applicable to a Judge of the Delhi High Court.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A Member shall be 
entitled to leave travel concession at the same rates and at the same scales as 
are applicable to Group ‘A’ officer of the Central Government drawing an 
equivalent pay.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Accommodation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every person appointed to the Board as a Chairman or a Member shall be eligible, 
subject to availability, to the use of official residence from the general pool 
accommodation of the type admissible to a Group ‘A’ officer of the Central 
Government drawing an equivalent pay and stationed at Delhi on payment of the 
licence fee at the rates specified by the Central Government from time to time.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where a Chairman or a 
Member occupies an official residence beyond permissible period he shall be 
liable to pay additional licence fee or penal rent, as the case may be, and he 
will be liable to eviction in accordance with the rules applicable to Central 
Government servants.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Facility of 
conveyance.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chairman shall be entitled to a staff car and one hundred and fifty litres 
of petrol every month or actual consumption of petrol per month whichever is 
less.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A Member shall be 
entitled to get a conveyance allowance of rupees seven hundred and fifty per 
mensem.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Facilities for 
medical treatment.—The 
Chairman or other Members shall be entitled to medical treatment and hospital 
facilities as provided in the Contributory Health Services Scheme Rules, 1954 
and in places where the Central Health Services Scheme is not in operation, the 
Chairman and Members shall be entitled to the facilities as provided in the 
Central Services Medical Attendance Rules.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Residuary 
provision.—Matter 
relating to the conditions of service of the Chairman or other Members with 
respect to which no express provision has been made in these rules shall be 
referred in each case to the Central Government for its decision and the 
decision of the Central Government thereon shall be binding on the Chairman or 
the other Member.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Powers to relax.—The 
Central Government shall have power to relax the provisions of any of these in 
respect of any class or categories of persons.
 
 
</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>