<act><tid>1737355</tid>
<title>DEHRA DUN</title>

ACT NO. 21 OF <year>1871</year>
[ 11th July, <year>1871</year>.]

An Act to give validity to the operation of the general 
Regulations and Acts within the Dehra dun.

Preamble.

WHEREAS it is necessary to give validity to the operation of the 
general Regulations and Acts within the district under the 
Superintendent of the Dehra Dun <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>; It is hereby enacted as 
follows:--





<article><tid>537664</tid>
<number>1</number>Extension of Regulations and Acts in force in Saharanpur to 
Dehra Dun. The Regulations and Acts now in force in the district 
Saharanpur are hereby declared to extend to the said district of Dehra 
Dun <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>.


</article>



<article><tid>853312</tid>
<number>2</number>Jurisdiction of High Court and Board of Revenue over Dehra 
Dun. The High Court and the Board of Revenue of <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Uttar Pradesh] 
shall exercise <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> respectively, in the said district, all the powers 
which the said High Court or Board of Revenue are at present, 
respectively, authorized to exercise in any part of <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Agra].


</article>



<article><tid>1983529</tid>
<number>3</number>District Court of Saharanpur to be District Court of Dehra 
Dun. The District Court of Saharanpur shall be <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> the District Court 
of such district until the State Government otherwise directs <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>.


</article>



<article><tid>1919455</tid>
<number>4</number>Exemption of Jaunsar Bawar. Nothing in this Act shall apply to 
that portion of the Dehra Dun district called <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> Jaunsar Bawar <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>999999</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" and to indemnify all officers and other persons who 
have acted in the said district under the said Regulations and Acts" 
rep. by Act 16 of <year>1874</year>. 
2. The words" and no judgment heretofore given, order passed or 
proceeding had in the said district, shall be deemed to have been or 
to be invalid merely because any Regulation or Act, under or in 
reference to which such judgment, order or proceeding was given, 
passed or had, was not in force at the time of such judgment, order or 
proceeding, or on the ground of a defect of jurisdiction in any Court 
or office" rep. by Act 12 of <year>1891</year>. 
3. Subs. by the O. <year>1950</year>, for" the North- Western Provinces". 
4. The words' and shall be deemed to have been heretofore authorized 
to exercise" rep., ibid. 
5. The words" deemed to have been heretofore the District Court of 
the said district of Dehra Dun and" rep., ibid. 
6. The words" and may subject to the provisions of Act 6 of <year>1971</year>, 
hear appeals from decisions given in the said district before the 
passing of this Act" rep. by Act 12 of <year>1891</year>. 
7." jaunsari Bawar" was one of the Scheduled Districts of the State 
of Uttar Pradesh, see the Scheduled Districts Act, <year>1874</year> (14 of <year>1874</year>), 
First Schedule, Pt. IV, but has ceased to be so under the Constitution 
of India. 
8. The words" and referred to in s. 11 of Act 24 of <year>1864</year>" rep. by 
Act 12 of <year>1891</year>.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>