<act><tid>1562126</tid>
<title>PROCEDURE OF THE HIGH COURT FOR UTTAR PRADESH 
ACT NO. 13 OF <year>1869</year> 
[ 19th March, <year>1869</year>]</title>

An Act further to amend the Procedure of the High Court of 
Judicature 
for <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Uttar Pradesh].
Preamble.- WHEREAS it is expedient to amend the procedure of 
the 
High Court of Judicature for <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Uttar Pradesh]; It is hereby enacted 
as 
follows:-





<article><tid>1980609</tid>
<number>1</number>[ Trial of Natives and European British subjects conjointly.] 
Rep. by the Advocate- General' s (Power;) Act, <year>1875</year> (10 of <year>1875</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>1825734</tid>
<number>2</number>[ Record of evidence.] Rep., ibid.


</article>



<article><tid>1037217</tid>
<number>3</number>Power to award costs on petitions, etc.- Whenever any 
petition, application or motion is made in any matter coming before 
the said Court in the exercise of its civil <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> or other 
jurisdiction, the Court shall have power to award and apportion costs 
in any manner it may think fit.


</article>



<article><tid>1995837</tid>
<number>4</number>Penalty for making false statements in support of petitions, 
etc.- Whenever the Court shall require the statements in support of any 
such petition, application or motion to be verified by a declaration 
in writing, the person making such verification shall, if any such 
statement is false, and if he either knows or believes it to be false, 
or does not believe it to be true, be deemed to have intentionally 
given false evidence in a stage of a judicial proceeding.
---------------


<pagefootnote><pagenum>999999</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs by the A. O. <year>1950</year> for the North Western Provinces.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs., ibid., for the North Western Provinces of Fort William".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>The word Criminal" is omitted as so much of s. 3 as relates to 
criminal jurisdiction was rep, by the High Court' s Criminal Procedure 
Act, <year>1875</year> (10 of <year>1875</year>), s. 2.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>So much of s. 4 relates to criminal jurisdiction was rep., ibid.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>