<act><title>PUBLIC GAMBLING ACT,1867</title> 

  
  
 <article><number>1</number> Interpretation 
clause.—In this Act— 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[***]  
 "Common 
gaming-house” means any house, walled enclosure, room or place in which cards, 
dice, tables or other instruments of gaming are kept or used for the profit or 
gain of the person owning, occupying, using or keeping such house, enclosure, 
room or place, whether by way of charge for the use of the instruments of 
gaming, or of the house, enclosure, room or place or otherwise howsoever. 
 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[***] 
 STATE AMENDMENTS 
 Assam:  
 Assam Game and Betting Act, 1970 (18 
of 1970) extends this Act to the whole of Assam, excluding the autonomous State 
of Meghalaya but including the City of Shillong. section 2 gives definition of “bet”, 
“acceptance of bet”, “Betting House”, “instruments of betting”, “records of 
betting”, “District Magistrate”, “District Superintendent of Police”, ‘person’ 
‘valuable security’, ‘the Act’ and ‘invitation for betting’ for the purpose of 
this Act in its application to Assam.  
 [Vide Assam Act 18 of 1970, sec. 2.] 

 Himachal Pradesh: 

 In section 
1, the following definitions shall be deemed to be substituted:— 

 “Gaming” 
includes wagering or betting on any figures or numbers or dates to be 
subsequently ascertained or disclosed, or on the occurrence or non-occurrence of 
any natural event, or in any other manner whatsoever except wagering or betting 
upon a horse race, when such wagering or betting upon a horse race takes 
place:—  
 <section>
<number>a</number> on the day on which such race is to 
be run, and  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> in an enclosure which the stewards 
controlling such race have, with the sanction of the State Government, set apart 
for the purpose, but does not include a lottery;  
 “Instrument 
of gaming” includes any article used as a means or an appurtenance of, or for 
the purpose, of carrying on or facilitating gaming and any document used as a 
register or record or evidence of any gaming and, in particular, satta papers 
that is to say, any document wherein may be recorded any words and/or figures 
evidencing bets and used or intended to be used for in connection with 
gaming;  
 Explanation.—If any document is recovered from the 
possession of any person containing words and, or figures, which prima facie 
appear to evidence bets, it shall be presumed that the words and figures 
evidence bets and the document was used or intended to be used for gaming unless 
the person aforesaid proves to the contrary;  
 ‘Common 
gaming house’ means any house or room or tent or enclosure or vehicle or vessel 
or any place whatsoever in which any instruments of gaming are kept or used for 
gaming purposes:—  
 </section><section>
<number>a</number> with a view to the profit or gain 
of any person owning, occupying, or keeping such house, room, tent, enclosure, 
vehicle, vessel or place whether by way of charge for the use of such house, 
room, tent, enclosure, vehicle, vessel, place or instrument or otherwise 
howsoever,  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> with or without a view to such 
profit or gain if the gaming for the purpose of which such instruments are so 
kept or used in gaming on any figures or numbers or dates to be subsequently 
ascertained or disclosed, or on the occurrence or non-occurrence of any natural 
event.” Him. Pra. Act 30 of 1976, S. 2.  
 Madhya Pradesh: 

 In section 1(1) before the definition 
of “common gaming-house” the following definitions shall be inserted:— 

 “‘Gaming’ includes wagering or betting 
but does not include a lottery.”  
 Any transaction by which person in any 
capacity whatever employs another in any capacity whatever or engages for 
another in any capacity whatever to wager or bet with another person shall be 
deemed to be ‘gaming’  
 The collection or soliciting of bets 
receipt or distribution of winnings or prizes in money or otherwise in respect 
of wagering or betting or any act which is intended tointended to aid or 
facilitate wagering or betting or such collection, soliciting, receipt or 
distribution shall also be deemed to be ‘gaming’ and  
 “Instruments of gaming”.—The 
expression ‘instruments of gaming’ includes any article used or intended to be 
used as a subject or means of gaming, any document used or intended to be used 
as a register or record or evidence of any gaming the proceeds of any gaming and 
any winnings or prizes in money or otherwise distributed or intended to be 
distributed in respect of any gaming.  
 <subsection><number>2</number> for the definition of ‘common 
gaming-house’, the following shall be substituted, namely:— 

 “Common gaming-house means— 

 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number> in the case of gaming— 

 <subsubsubsection>
<number>a</number> on the market price of cotton, 
opium or other commodity or on the digits of the number used in stating such 
price; or  
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
<number>b</number> on the amount of variation in the 
market price of any such commodity or on the digits of the number used in 
stating the amount of such variation, or  
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
<number>c</number> on the market price of any stock or 
share or on the digits of the number used in stating such price, or 
 
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
<number>d</number> on the occurrence or non-occurrence 
of rain or other natural event, or  
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
<number>e</number> on the quantity of rainfall or on 
the digits of the number used in stating such quantity, any house, room, tent, 
enclosure, space, vehicle, vessel or any place whatsoever in which such gaming 
takes place or in which instruments of gaming are kept or used for such 
gaming;  
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number> in the case of any other form of 
gaming, any house, room, tent, enclosure, space, vehicle, vessel or any place 
whatsoever in which any instruments of gaming are kept or used for the profit or 
gain of the person owning, occupying, using or keeping such house, room, tent, 
enclosure, space, vehicle, vessel, place or instrument or otherwise 
howsoever.”—  
 <subsubsubsection>[<number>C</number>P. Act 3 of 1927, sec. 2. and M.P. 
Acts 12 of 1954, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 26-3-1954); 23 of 1958, sec. 3 and Sch.] 

 In the definition of “Common Gaming 
House” in clause (i),—  
 
(a) in item (e), insert the word ‘or’ 
at the end, and  
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number> after item (e), insert the 
following item, namely:—  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number> on the digits or figures or signs 
or symbols or pictures used in stating the opening, middle or closing digits or 
figures or signs or symbols or picture declared for or in connection with worli 
matka gaming or any other form of gaming.—[Vide M.P. Act 47 of 1976, sec. 
2 (6-10-1976)].  
 Manipur:  
 In section 1—  
 <subsection>
<number>I</number> after the word ‘enclosure’, insert 
the words “Tent, Space, Vehicle” and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>II</number> add the following definitions after 
the definition of “common gaming house”, namely:—  
 
“instrument of gaming” includes any 
article used as a means or appurtenance to or for the purpose of carrying on or 
facilitating gaming  
 
“gaming” includes wagering or betting 
but not include a lottery.”  
 Note.—Act as amended in Uttar 
Pradesh, Punjab and Madhya Pradesh, subject to certain modifications and 
restrictions, had been extended to the Union territory of Manipur is now a State 
and the said amendments would continue to be in force thereat by virtue of 
section 77 of Act 81 of 1971.  
 <subsubsection>[<number>S</number>R.O. 168, dated 30-1-1952, Gazette 
of India 1952. Pt. II, Sec. 3, p. 149; Act 81 of 1971, Sec.3.] 

 Punjab: Haryana: 
Chandigarh:  
 In its application to the State of 
Punjab, for the definition of common gaming-house in section 1, the following 
definitions shall be deemed to be substituted, namely:—  
 “‘Gaming’ includes wagering or betting 
on any figures or numbers or dates to be subsequently ascertained or disclosed, 
or on the occurrence or non-occurrence of any natural event, or in any other 
manner whatsoever except wagering or betting upon a horse-race when such 
wagering or betting upon a horse-race takes place—  
 <subsubsubsection>
<number>a</number> on the day on which such race is to 
be run, and  
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
<number>b</number> in any enclosure where such race is 
to be run, and sanction of the Provincial Government set apart from the purpose, 
but does not include a lottery.  
 ‘Instrument of gaming’ includes any 
article used as a means of appertenance of, or for the purpose of carrying on or 
facilitating gaming, and any document used as a register or evidence of any 
gaming.  
 ‘Common gaming-house’ means any house 
or room or tent or enclosure or vehicle or vessel or any place whatsoever in 
which any instruments of gaming are kept or used for gaming purposes— 

 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
<number>a</number> with a view to the profit or gain 
of any person owning, occupying or keeping such house, room, tent, enclosure, 
vehicle, vessel, place whether by way of charge for the use of such house, room, 
tent, enclosure, vehicle, vessel, place or instrument or otherwise 
howsoever;  
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
<number>b</number> with or without a view to such 
profit or gain if the gaming for the purpose of which such instruments are so 
kept or used in gaming on any figures or numbers or dates to be subsequently 
ascertained or disclosed, or on the occurrence or non-occurrence of any natural 
event.”  
 [Punjab Act 1 of 1929, sec. 3; 18 of 
1958, sec. 3 Sch. 9 of 1960, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 28-1-1960), 31 of 1966, sec. 
88].  
 Uttar Pradesh: 

 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>i</number> The definition of ‘gaming’ is same 
as that of Punjab. The definition of ‘instruments of gaming’ is same as that of 
Punjab, except the last words in that definition, namely, ‘and any 
document……….of any gaming’ which do not occur.  
 <subsubsection>[<number>U</number>P. Act 1 of 1917, sec. 2]. 

 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> In section 1, for the definition 
of ‘common gaming-house’ substitute the following, namely:— 

 “‘Common gaming-house ’means— 

 <subsubsection>
<number>1</number> in the case of gaming on the digits 
of the sale price of any commodity, for example, opium or cotton, or on the 
digits of papers or bales manipulated from within jars or other receptacles, or 
on the occurrence or non-occurrence of any natural event, for example, rainfall 
or the quantity of rainfall, any house, room, tent, walled enclosure, space, 
vehicle, vessel or any place whatsoever in which instruments of gaming are kept 
or used for such gaming;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>2</number> in the case of any other form of 
gaming, any house, room, tent, walled enclosure, space, vehicle, vessel or any 
place whatsoever in which any instruments of gaming are kept or used for the 
profit or gain of the person owing, occupying, using or keeping such house, 
room, tent, enclosure, space, vehicle, vessel or place whether by way of charge 
for the use of such house, room, tent, enclosure, space, vehicle, vessel, place 
or instrument, or otherwise howsoever.”  
 <subsubsubsection>[<number>U</number>P. Act 1 
of 1917, sec. 2 and later by U.P. Act 1 of 1925, sec. 2].  
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> in 
the definition of “instruments of gaming”, colon at the end shall be deleted and 
the following shall be added:—  
 “and, in 
particular, satta papers, that is to say, any document wherein may be recorded 
any words and/or figures evidencing bets and used or intended to be used for or 
in connection with gaming;”and  
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> after 
the definition of ‘instruments of gaming’ add the following as 
explanation, thereto,—  
 “Explanation.—If any document is recovered from the possession of 
any person containing words and/or figures, which prima facie appear to 
evidence bets, it shall be presumed that the words and figures evidence bets and 
the document was used or intended to be used for gaming, unless the person 
aforesaid proves to the contrary,”  
 <subsubsection>[<number>U</number>P. Act 21 of 1961, sec. 2 
(w.e.f. 7-9-1961)].
    
    




</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>2</number> Power to extend Act.—<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[Sections 13 and 17] of this Act shall extend to 
      the whole of the <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[said States] and it shall be competent to the 
      <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[State Government], whenever it may think fit, 
      to extend, by a notification to be published in three successive numbers 
      of the official Gazette, 
      all or any of the remaining sections of this Act to any city, town, 
      suburb, railway, station-house and place being not more than three miles 
      distant from any part of such station-house within the <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[States], and in such notification to define, 
      for the purposes of this Act, the limits of such city, town, suburb or 
      station-house, and from time to time, to alter the limits so defined. 
      
 From the date of any such extension, so much of any rule having the 
      force of law which shall be in operation in the territories to which such 
      extension shall have been made, as shall be inconsistent with or repugnant 
      to any section so extended, shall cease to have effect in such 
      territories.
  
 State Amendments
 Himachal 
      Pradesh.—For the 
      first paragraph of section 2, the following paragraph shall be deemed to 
      be substituted, namely:—
 “Sections 13 and 
      17 of this Act shall extend to the whole of the State of Himachal Pradesh, 
      and it shall be competent to the State Government, whenever it may think 
      fit, to extend by a notification to be published in the Official Gazette, 
      all or any of the remaining sections, of this Act to any area within the 
      territory of Himachal Pradesh.”
 <section>[<number>H</number>P. Act 30 of 
      1976, sec. 3].
 Madhya 
      Pradesh.—In section 
      2—
 <subsection><number>a</number> omit the words "three 
      successive numbers of”.
 </subsection></section><section>[<number>M</number>P. Act 25 of 
      1950, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 3-11-1950)].
 <subsection><number>b</number> for the words “and place 
      being not more than three miles distant from any part of such station 
      house” substitute the words “or local area”;
 </subsection></section><section>[<number>C</number>P. Act 3 of 
      1927, sec. 3].
 <subsection><number>c</number> for the words “within the 
      State" substitute the words "within the Mahakoshal region”;
 </subsection></section><section>[<number>M</number>P., 
      A.L.O.,1956].
 <subsection><number>d</number> for the words “within the 
      Mahakoshal region” substitute the words “within the State”;
 </subsection></section><section>[<number>M</number>P. Act 23 of 
      1958, sec. 3 Sch., Part A, item 3].
 <subsection><number>e</number> for the words “or 
      station-house” substitute a comma and the words “station-house or local 
      area”.
 </subsection></section><section>[<number>C</number>P. Act 3 of 
      1927, Sec. 3].
 </section><section><number>Manipur</number>—For Para 1, substitute the following,—
 “Sections 13 and 
      17, as amended by this notification, of this Act shall extend to the whole 
      of Manipur and it shall be competent to the Chief Commissioner whenever he 
      may think fit to extend, by notification to be published in three 
      successive numbers of the Official Gazette, all or any of the remaining 
      sections of this Act to any local area subject to his administration and 
      in such notification to define, for the purpose of this Act limits of such 
      area, and from time to time to alter the limits so defined.”
 </section><section>[<number>S</number>R.O. 168, Dated 
      30-1-1952, Published in the Gazette of India, 1952, Pt. II, Sec. 3, p. 
      149, dated 2nd February, 1952].
 Punjab: 
      Haryana: Chandigarh.—In its application to the State of Punjab, for the first 
      paragraph of section 2, the following paragraph shall be substituted, 
      namely:—
 “Sections 13 and 
      17 of this Act shall extend to the whole of the said territories, and it 
      shall be competent to the State Government whenever it may think fit, to 
      extend by notification, all or any of the remaining sections of this Act 
      to any area within the territories administered by the State 
      Government.”
 [Punjab Acts 1 of 
      1929, sec. 3; 18 of 1958, sec. 3 and Sch.: 31 of 1966, sec. 
88].
 Sections 3, 4, 4A, 
      5 to 11, 13A, 13B, 14, 15, 15A, 15B and 18 of the said Act have been 
      extended to the whole of Punjab.
 [See Punjab 
      Gazette, Pt. III (L.S.), p. 121, dated 27th January, 1964].
 Uttar 
      Pradesh.—For the 
      first paragraph of section 2, the following paragraph shall be 
      substituted, namely:—
 “Sections 13 and 
      17 of this Act shall extend to the whole of the said territories; and it 
      shall be competent to the State Government whenever it may think fit to 
      extend, by a notification to be published in the Official Gazette, all or 
      any of the remaining sections of this Act to any area within the Uttar 
      Pradesh.”
 </section><section>[<number>U</number>P. Act 5 of 
      1919, sec. 2].
   







 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>3. Penalty for owning or keeping or having 
      charge of a gaming-house.—Whoever, being the owner or occupier, or 
      having the use, of any house, walled enclosure, room or place situate 
      within the limits to which this Act applies, opens, keeps or uses the same 
      as a common gaming-house; and 
 whoever, being the owner or occupier of any such 
      house, walled enclosure, room or place as aforesaid, knowingly or wilfully 
      permits the same to be opened, occupied, used or kept by any other person 
      as a common gaming-house; and 
 whoever has the care or management of, or in any 
      manner assists in conducting the business of any house, walled enclosure, 
      room or place as aforesaid, opened, occupied, used or kept for the purpose 
      aforesaid; and 
 whoever advances or furnishes money for the 
      purpose of gaming with persons frequenting such house, walled enclosure, 
      room or place;
 shall be liable to a fine not exceeding two 
      hundred rupees, or to imprisonment of either description1, as defined in the Indian Penal Code (45 of 
      1860), for any term not exceeding three months2.
  
 State Amendments
 <section><number>Assam</number>—In section 3, for the words "two hundred rupees" substitute 
      the words "five hundred rupees".
 [Assam Act 18 of 1970, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 
      19-12-1970)].
 Himachal 
      Pradesh.—In section 3, for the words "house, 
      walled enclosure, room or place" wherever they occur the words "house, 
      room, tent, enclosure, vehicle, vessel or place". shall be deemed to be 
      substituted.—
 [Himachal Pradesh Act 30 of 1976, sec. 
      4].
 Madhya 
      Pradesh.—In section 3—
 <subsection><number>i</number> for the words "house, walled 
      enclosure, room or place" wherever they occur substitute the words "house, 
      room, tent, enclosure, space, vehicle, vessel or place";—
 </subsection></section><section>[<number>C</number>P. Act 3 of 
      1927, sec. 4].
 <subsection><number>ii</number> for the last paragraph the 
      following shall be substituted, namely:—
 "shall be 
      punished—
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> for a first offence with 
      imprisonment which may extend to six months or with fine which may extend 
      to one thousand rupees;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> for a second offence with 
      imprisonment which may extend to one year and, in the absence of special 
      reasons to the contrary to be mentioned in the judgment of the Court, 
      shall not be less than fourteen days, either with or without fine which 
      may exend to two thousand rupees; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>c</number> for a third or subsequent 
      offence with imprisonment which may extend to one year and, in the absence 
      of special reasons to the contrary to be mentioned in the judgment of the 
      Court, shall not be less than four months, together with fine which may 
      extend to two thousand rupees".
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>[<number>C</number>P. Act 3 of 
      1927, sec. 5, and M.P. Act 25 of 1950, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 
      3-11-1950)].
 </section><section><number>Manipur</number>—In section 3, after the words 'walled enclosure, insert the 
      words "tent, space, vehicle."
 </section><section>[<number>S</number>R.O. 168, dated 30th January, 1952, 
      published in the Gazette of India, Pt. II, Sec. 3, p. 149, dated 2nd 
      February, 1952; Act 81 of 1971, sec. 3].
 Punjab: Haryana: 
      Chandigarh.—Same as that of Madhya Pradesh 
      (i).—Punjab Acts 1 of 1929, sec. 4; 18 of 1958; 31 of 1966, sec. 
      88.
 Uttar 
      Pradesh.—In Section 3—
 <subsection><number>i</number> For the words "house, walled 
      enclosure, room or place" wherever they occur the words "house, room, 
      tent, walled enclosure, space, vehicle, vessel or place" shall be 
      substituted.
 </subsection></section><section>[<number>U</number>P. Act 1 of 
      1917, sec. 3].
 <subsection><number>ii</number> For the words "two hundred 
      rupees" substitute the words "five hundred rupees".
 </subsection></section><section>[<number>U</number>P. Act 34 of 
      1952, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 5-12-1952)].
 <subsection><number>iii</number> For the words "two hundred 
      rupees" substitute the words "five hundred rupees".
 </subsection></section><section>[<number>U</number>P. Act 34 of 
      1952, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 5-12-1952)].
 <subsection><number>iv</number> Delete the last 
      paragraph and substitute therefor the following paragraph, 
      namely:—
 "Shall be liable—
 in case of first offence to fine not 
      exceedng five hundred rupees nor less than two hundred rupees and to 
      rigorous imprisonment for a term not exceeding three months; and in the 
      case of any subsequent offence to fine not exceeding two thousand rupees 
      nor less than five hundred rupees and to rigorous imprisonment for a term 
      not exceeding twelve months nor less than three months."
 </subsection></section><section>[<number>U</number>P. Act 21 of 1961, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 
      7-9-1961)].
  









 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>4</number> Penalty for being found in gaming-house.—Whoever is found in 
      any such house, walled enclosure, room or place, playing or gaming with 
      cards, dice, counters, money or other instruments of gaming or is found 
      there present for the purpose of gaming, whether playing for any money, 
      wager, stake or otherwise, shall be liable to a fine not exceeding one 
      hundred rupees, or to imprisonment of either description, as defined in the Indian Penal Code (45 of 
      1860), for any term not exceeding one month;
 and any person found in any common gaming-house during any gaming 
      or playing therein shall be presumed, until the contrary be proved, to 
      have been there for the purposes of gaming. 
  
 STATE AMENDMENTS
 Himachal 
      Pradesh.—In section 4—
 Same as that of under section 
      3.
 [Himachal Pradesh Act 30 of 1976, Sec. 
      4].
 Madhya 
      Pradesh.—In section 4,—
 <section><number>i</number> for the words “house, walled 
      enclosure, room or place” wherever they occur, the words “house, room, 
      tent, enclosure, space, vehicle, vessel or place” shall be 
      substituted.
 <subsection>[<number>C</number> P. Act 3 of 
      1927, sec. 4].
 </subsection></section><section><number>ii</number> for the words “one hundred 
      rupees”, the words “five hundred rupees” and for the words “one month”, 
      the words “four months” shall be substituted.
 <subsection>[<number>M</number>P. Act 25 of 
      1950, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 3-11-1950)].
 </subsection><subsection><number>Manipur</number>—In section 4,—
 Same as in M.P. (ii).
 </subsection><subsection>[<number>S</number>R.O. 168, dated 30th January, 1952, 
      Gazette of India, 1952, Pt. II, Sec. 3, p.149].
 Punjab: Haryana: 
      Chandigarh.—Same as that of Madhya Pardesh 
      (i).
 [Punjab Act 1 of 1929, sec. 4; 18 of 
      1958, sec. 3 and Sch.; 31 of 1966, sec. 88].
 Uttar 
      Pradesh.—In section 4,—
 </subsection></section><section><number>i</number> for the words “house, walled 
      enclousure, room or place” wherever they occur, the words “house, room, 
      tent, walled enclosure, space, vehicle, vessel or place” shall be 
      substituted.
 <subsection>[<number>U</number>P. Act 1 of 
      1917, sec. 3].
 </subsection></section><section><number>ii</number> for the words “one hundred 
      rupees” substitute the words “three hundred rupees”.
 <subsection>[<number>U</number>P. Act 34 of 
      1952, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 5-12-1952)].
 </subsection></section><section><number>iii</number> in section 4 in the marginal 
      note, between the words ‘found in’and ‘gaming house’, add the words ‘or in 
      the immediate vicinity of’.
 </section><section><number>iv</number> (a) in para. 1 of section 4, 
      between the words “is found there present” and “for the purpose of”, add 
      the words “or in the immediate vicinity thereof”; and
 b) words beginning 
      with “shall be liable to a fine” and ending with “exceeding one month” 
      shall be deleted and the following shall be substituted 
      therefor:—
  “shall be liable—
 in the case of a 
      first offence to a fine not exceeding three hundred rupees nor less than 
      one hundred rupees or to rigorous imprisonment for any term not exceeding 
      one month, and in the case of any subsequent offence to a fine not 
      exceeding five hundred rupees nor less than two hundred rupees and to 
      rigorous imprisonment for a term not exceeding six months nor less than 
      one month.”
 </section><section><number>v</number> in para 2, between the words 
      “common gaming house” and “during any gaming”, add the words “and any 
      person found in the immediate vicinity thereof with any instument of 
      gaming”.
 <subsection> [<number>U</number>P. Act 21 of 1961, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 7-9-1961)].
 Himachal 
      Pradesh.—Insert section 
4A.
 Same as that of 
      Punjab, Haryana and Chandigarh.
 Madhya 
      Pradesh.—After section 4, insert the 
      following section 4A:—
  
 
  </subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><number>5</number> Powers to enter and authorise police to enter and 
search.—If the Magistrate of a district or other officer invested with the full powers of a 
Magistrate, or the District Superintendent of police, upon credible information, and 
after such enquiry as he may think necessary, has reason to believe at any 
house, walled enclosure, room or place, is used as a common gaming-house; 
 
 he may either himself enter, or by his 
warrant authorise any officer of police, not below such rank as the <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[State Government] shall appoint in this behalf to 
enter, with such assistance as may be found necessary, by night or by day, and 
by force, if necessary, any such house, walled enclosure, room or place;  
 and may seize or authorise such officer 
to seize all instruments of gaming and all moneys and securities for money, and 
articles of value, reasonably suspected to have been used or intended to be used 
for the purpose of gaming, which are found therein;  
 and may search or authorise such officer 
to search all parts of the house, walled enclosure, room or place, which he or 
such officer shall have so entered when he or such officer has reason to believe 
that any instruments of gaming are concealed therein, and also the persons of 
those whom he or such officer so takes into custody;  
 and may seize or authorise such officer to seize and 
take possession of all instruments of gaming found upon such search. 
 STATE AMENDMENTS 
 Himachal 
Pradesh:  
 In section 
5, same as that of under section 3—  
 [Himachal 
Pradesh Act, 30 of 1976, sec. 4].  
 Madhya 
Pradesh:  
 In section 5,—  
 <section>
<number>i</number> for the words “house, walled 
enclosure, room or place” wherever they occur, the words “house, room, tent, 
enclosure, space, vehicle, vessel or place” shall be substituted; 

 <subsection>
[<number>C</number>P. Act 3 of 1927, sec. 4]. 

 </subsection></section><section>
<number>ii</number> in the first paragraph, after the 
words “or the District Superintendent of Police; insert the words “or the Deputy 
or the Assistant Superintendent of Police”; and  
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number> in the fourth paragraph, add at the 
end the following words, namely:—  
 
 “and also all moneys 
and securities for money found on the person of such persons as are found 
playing or gaming or found there present for the purpose of gaming within the 
meaning of section 4”.  
 <subsection>[<number>M</number>P. Acts 
25 of 1950, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 3-11-1950); 23 of 1958].  
 Manipur:  
 In section 5, in paragraph 1,—  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>i</number> for the words “Magistate of a 
District”, substitute the words “District Magistrate”;  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> after the words “walled enclosure”, 
insert the words “tent, space, vehicle,”;  
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number> as in M.P. (iii). 

 <subsection>[<number>S</number>R.O. 
1168, dated 30th January, 1952, published in the Gazette of India, Pt. II, Sec. 
3, p.149, dated 2nd February, 1952].  
 Punjab: 
Haryana: Chandigarh:  
 Same as that 
of Madhya Paradeh (i).  
 [Punjab Act 
1 of 1929, sec. 4; 18 of 1958, sec. 3; 31 of 1968, sec. 88]. 

 Uttar 
Pradesh:  
 In section 5,—  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>i</number> for the words “house, walled 
enclosure, room or place” wherever they occur, the words “house, room, tent, 
walled enclosure, space, vehicle, vessel or place” shall be substituted; 

 <subsection>
[<number>U</number>P. Act 1 of 1917, sec. 3]. 

 </subsection></section><section>
<number>ii</number> in para 1, between the words “the 
District Superintendent of Police” and the words “upon credible information”, 
add the words “or any police officer of gazetted rank especially empowered in 
this behalf by the State Government”;  
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number> in para 3, delete the semi-colon 
and add the following words at the end: “and all persons found in the immediate 
vicinity thereof with any instruments of gaming”.  
 <subsection>
[<number>U</number>P. Act 21 of 1961, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 
7-9-1961)].  
 Madhya 
Pradesh:  
 After section 5, insert the following 
section 5A:—  
 </subsection></section></article><article><number>5A</number> Seizure of register, record or 
writing.—If the District Magistrate or the Additional District Magistrate or 
a Police Officer not below the rank of Assistant Superintendent of Police is of 
the opinion that any register, record or writing of any kind whatsoever which 
contains digits of figures or signs or symbols or pictures or combination of any 
two or more of such digits, figures, signs, symbols or pictures relates to worli 
matka gaming or some other form of gaming, he shall be entitled to seize the 
same and such register, record or writing shall be presumed to be an instrument 
of gaming unless it is shown by the person from whom it is seized that it is a 
register, record or writing of any transaction in connection with a lawful trade 
industry, business, profession or vocation of any lawful personal transaction of 
any person or it is otherwise not an instrument of gaming. 

 <section>[<number>M</number>P. Act 47 of 1976, sec. 4 
(w.e.f. 6-10-1976)].
    


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>6</number> Finding cards, etc., in suspected houses, to be evidence 
      that such houses are common gaming-houses.—When any cards, dice, 
      gaming-tables, cloths, boards or other instruments of gaming are found in 
      any house, walled enclosure, room or place entered or searched under the 
      provisions of the last preceding section, or about the person of any of 
      those who are found therein, it shall be evidence, until the contrary is 
      made to appear, that such house, walled enclosure, room or place, is used 
      as a common gaming-house, and that the persons found therein were there 
      present for the purpose of gaming, although no play was actually seen by 
      the Magistrate or police officer, or any of his 
      assistants.
  
 STATE AMENDMENTS
 Himachal Pradesh.—In section 6, 
      same as that of under section 3.
 [Himachal Pradesh Act 30 of 1976, sec. 
      4].
 Madhya Pradesh.—In section 6, 
      for the words “house, walled enclosure, room or place” wherever they 
      occur, the words “house, room, tent, enclosure, space, vehicle, vessel or 
      place” shall be substituted.
 <section>[<number>C</number>P. Act 3 of 1927, sec. 
      4].
 </section><section><number>Manipur</number>—Same as in Madhya 
      Pradesh, Uttar Pradesh and Punjab
 </section><section>[<number>S</number>R.O. 168, dated 30th January, 1952, 
      published in the Gazette of India, 1952, Pt.II, Sec. 3, p. 
149].
 Punjab: Haryana: 
      Chandigarh.—Same as that of Madhya Pradesh (i).
 [Punjab Act 1 of 1929, sec. 4; 18 of 
      1958, sec. 3; 31 of 1966, sec. 88].
 Uttar Pradesh.—(i) In section 
      6, for the words “house, walled enclosure, room or place” wherever they 
      occur, the words “house, room, tent, walled enclosure, space, vehicle, 
      vessel or place” shall be substituted.
 </section><section>[<number>U</number>P. Act 1 of 1917, sec. 
      3].
 <subsection><number>ii</number> between the words and comma “who 
      are found therein,”, and the words “it shall be evidence”, add the words 
      and comma “found in the immediate vicinity thereof".
 </subsection></section><section>[<number>U</number>P. Act 21 of 1961, sec 6 (w.e.f. 
      7-9-1961)].
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>7</number> Penalty on persons arrested for giving false names and 
      addresses.—If any person found in any common gaming-house 
      entered by any Magistrate or officer of police under the provisions of 
      this Act, upon being arrested, by any such officer or upon being brought 
      before any Magistrate, on being required by such officer or Magistrate to 
      give his name and address, shall refuse or neglect to give the same, or 
      shall give any false name and address, he may, upon conviction before the 
      same or any other Magistrate, be adjudged to pay any penalty not exceeding 
      five hundred rupees, together with such costs as to such Magistrate shall 
      appear reasonable, and on the non-payment of such penalty and costs, or in 
      the first instance, if to such Magistrate it shall seem fit, may be 
      imprisoned for any period not exceeding one month. 
  
 STATE AMENDMENTS
 <section><number>Assam</number>—In section 7, for the 
      words “five hunderd rupees” substitute the words “one thousand 
      rupees”.
 [Assam Act 18 of 1970, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 
      19-12-1970)].
 Madhya Pradesh.—In section 7, 
      for the words “five hundred rupees”, the words “one thousand rupees” and 
      for the words “one month”, the words “four months" shall be 
      substituted.
 </section><section>[<number>M</number>P. Act 25 of 1950, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 
      3-11-1950)].
 </section><section><number>Manipur</number>—Same as in Madhya 
      Pradesh.
 </section><section>[<number>S</number>R.O. 168, dated 30th January, 1952, 
      published in the Gazette of India, Pt. II, Sec. 3, p.149, dated 2nd 
      February, 1952].
 </section><section><number>Punjab</number>—In section 7, for the 
      words “before the some or any other Magistrate”, substitute the words 
      “before any Judicial Magistrate”.
 [Punjab Act 25 of 1964, sec. 2 and 
      Sch., Pt. II (w.e.f. 2-10-1964)].
 Uttar Pradesh.—In section 7, 
      between the words “person found in” and the words “any common gaming 
      house”, add the words and commas “or in the immediate vicinity 
      of”.
 </section><section>[<number>U</number>P. Act 21 of 1961, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 
      7-9-1961)].
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>8</number> On conviction for keeping a gaming-house, instruments of gaming 
      to be destroyed.—On conviction of any person for keeping or 
      using any such common gaming-house, or being present therein for the 
      purpose of gaming, the convicting Magistrate may order all the instruments 
      of gaming found therein to be destroyed, and may also order all or any of 
      the securities for money and other articles seized, not being instruments 
      of gaming, to be sold and converted into money, and the proceeds thereof 
      with all moneys seized therein to be forfeited or, in his discretion, may 
      order any part thereof to be returned to the persons appearing to have 
      severally thereunto entitled. 
  
 STATE AMENDEMENT
 Uttar 
      Pradesh.—In section 8,—
 <section>
<number>i</number> for the word ‘may’, occurring 
      between the word ‘and’ and the words ‘also order’, substitute the word 
      ‘shall’;
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> delete the words 
      ‘or, in his discretion, may order any part thereof to be returned to the 
      persons appearing to have been severally thereunto entitled’ and for semi 
      colon, after ‘forfeited’, substitute a full stop.
 <subsection>[<number>U</number>P. Act 21 of 1961, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 
      7-9-1961)].
 
  </subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>9</number> Proof of playing for stakes unnecessary.—It shall not be 
      necessary, in order to convict any person of keeping a common 
      gaming-house, or of being concerned in the management of any common 
      gaming-house, to prove that any person found playing at any game was 
      playing for any money, wager or stake. 
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>10</number> Magistrate may require any person apprehended to be sworn and 
      give evidence.—It shall be lawful for the Magistrate before 
      whom any persons shall be brought, who have been found in any house, 
      walled enclosure, room or place entered under the provisions of this Act, 
      to require any such persons to be examined on oath or solemn affirmation, 
      and give evidence touching any unlawful gaming in such house, walled 
      enclosure, room or place, or touching any act done for the purpose of 
      preventing, obstructing or delaying the entry into such house, walled 
      enclosure, room or place or any part thereof, of any Magistrate or officer 
      authorised as aforesaid.
 No 
      person so required to be examined as a witness shall be excused from being 
      so examined when brought before such Magistrate as aforesaid or from being 
      so examined at any subsequent time or by or before the same or any other 
      Magistrate, or by or before any Court on any proceeding or trial in any 
      ways relating to such unlawful gaming or any such acts as aforesaid, or 
      from answering any question put to him touching the matters aforesaid, on 
      the ground that his evidence will tend to criminate himself. 
      
 Any such person so required to be examined as a witness, who 
      refuses to make oath or take affirmation accordingly or to answer any such 
      question as aforesaid, shall be subject to be dealt with in all respects 
      as any person committing the offence described in section 178 or section 
      179 (as the case may be) of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860). 
      
  
 STATE AMENDMENTS
 Himachal Pradesh.—In section 
      10,—
 Same as that of under section 
      3.
 <section>[<number>H</number>P. Act 30 of 1976, sec. 
      4].
 Madhya Pardesh.—In section 10, 
      for the words “house, walled enclosure, room or place” wherever they 
      occur, the words “house, tent, enclosure, space, vehicle, vessel or place” 
      shall be substituted.
 </section><section>[<number>C</number>P. Act 3 of 1927, sec. 
      4].
 </section><section><number>Manipur</number>—In section 10, after 
      the words “walled enclosure”, insert the words “tent, space, 
      vehicle”.
 </section><section>[<number>S</number>R.O. 168, dated 30th January, 1952, 
      published in the Gazette of India, 1952, Pt. II, Sec. 3. p. 149; Act 81 of 
      1971, sec. 3]:
 Punjab: Haryana: 
      Chandigarh.—Same as that of Madhya Pradesh.
 [Punjab Act 1 of 1929, sec. 4; 18 of 
      1958, sec. 3; 31 of 1966, sec. 88].
 Uttar Pradesh.—In section 10, 
      for the words “house, walled enclosure, room or place” wherever they 
      occur, the words “house, room, tent, walled enclosure, space, vehicle, 
      vessel or place” shall be substituted.
 </section><section>[<number>U</number>P. Act 1 of 1917, sec. 3].
 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><number>11</number> Witnesses 
indemnified.—Any person who shall have been 
concerned in gaming contrary to this Act, and who shall be examined as witness 
before a Magistrate on the trial of any person for a breach of any of the 
provisions of this Act relating to gaming, and who, upon such examination, 
shall, in the opinion of the Magistrate, make true and faithful discovery, to 
the best of his knowledge, of all things as to which he shall be so examined, 
shall thereupon receive from the said Magistrate a certificate in writing to 
that effect and shall be freed from all prosecutions under this Act for anything 
done before that time in respect of such gaming. </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>12</number> Act not to apply to certain games.—Nothing in the 
      foregoing provisions of this Act contained shall be held to apply to any 
      game of mere skill wherever played. 
  
 STATE AMENDMENTS  
 Himachal Pradesh.—Section 12, shall be deemed to be 
      repealed.
 [Himachal Pradesh Act 30 of 1976, sec. 6].
 Punjab: Haryana: Chandigarh.—In its application to the State 
      of Punjab, section 12 is repealed by Punjab Act 1 of 1929, sec. 5; 13 of 
      1958, sec. 8; 31 of 1966, sec. 88.
 Uttar Pradesh.—Section 12 is repealed.
 <section>[<number>U</number>P. Act 1 of 1917, sec. 4].
 </section><section><number>Manipur</number>—Same as in Punjab and Uttar Pradesh
 </section><section>[<number>S</number>R.O. 168, dated 30th January 1952, Gazette of India, dated 2nd 
      February, 1952, Pt. II, sec. 3, p. 149; Act 81 of 1971, 
      sec. 3.]
 

  
  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>13</number> Gaming and setting birds and animals to fight in public 
      streets.—A police officer may apprehend without 
      warrant— 
 any person found playing for money or other valuable thing, with 
      cards, dice, counters or other instruments of gaming, used in playing any 
      game not being a game of mere skill, in any public street, place or 
      thoroughfare situated within the limits aforesaid, or
 any person setting any birds or animals to fight in any public 
      street, place or thoroughfare situated within the limits aforesaid, or 
      
 any person there present aiding and abetting such public fighting 
      of birds and animals. 
 Such person when apprehended shall be brought without delay before 
      a Magistrate, and shall be liable to a fine not exceeding fifty rupees, or 
      to imprisonment, either simple or rigorous, for any term not exceeding one 
      calendar month;
 Destruction of instruments of gaming found in public 
      streets.—Any such police officer may seize all 
      instruments of gaming found in such public place or on the person of those 
      whom he shall so arrest, and the Magistrate may, on conviction of the 
      offender, order such instruments to be forthwith destroyed. 
      
  
 STATE AMENDMENTS
 <section><number>Assam</number>—In section 13, for the words “fifty rupees”, substitute the 
      words “one hundred rupees”.
 [Assam Act 18 of 1970, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 
      19-12-1970)].
 Himachal 
      Pradesh.—In section 13, same as that of 
      Punjab.
 [Himachal Pradesh Act 30 of 1976, sec. 
      7 (w.e.f. 5-8-1976)].
 Madhya 
      Pradesh.—In section 13—
 <subsection> <number>i</number> for the first three 
      paragraphs, substitute the following, namely:—
 “A Ploice Officer may apprehend and 
      search without warrant—
 <subsubsection>      
      <number>a</number> any 
      person found gaming or reasonably suspected to be gaming in any public 
      street, or thoroughfare, or in any place to which the public have or are 
      permitted to have access;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>      
      <number>b</number> any 
      person setting any birds or animals to fight in any public street, 
      thoroughfare, or in any place to which the public have or are permitted to 
      have access:
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>      
      <number>c</number> any 
      person there present aiding and abetting such public fighting of birds and 
      animals.”
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>      [<number>M</number>P. 
      Act 12 of 1954, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 26-3-1954)].
 <subsection>      
      <number>ii</number> in the fourth 
      paragraph, for the words “fifty rupees”, the words “one hundred rupees” 
      and for the words “one calendar month”, the words “four claendar months” 
      shall be substituted; and
 </subsection><subsection>      
      <number>iii</number> in the fifth 
      paragraph, for the words “may seize”, the words “all moneys and” and after 
      the words “order such”, the words “moneys to be forfeited and such” shall 
      be inserted.
 </subsection></section><section>[<number>M</number>P. Act 25 of 1950, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 
      3-11-1950)].
 </section><section><number>Manipur</number>—In section 13, in para 5, after the words “such police 
      officer may seize”, insert the words “all birds and animals and” and at 
      the end of the same paragraph, after the word “destroyed”, add the words 
      “such birds and animals to be sold”.
 </section><section>[<number>S</number>R.O. 168, dated 30th January, 1952, 
      published in the Gazette of India, Pt. II, sec. 3, p. 149 dated 2nd 
      February, 1952; Act 81 of 1971, sec. 3].
 Punjab: Haryana: 
      Chandigarh.—In its application to the State 
      of Punjab, for section 13, substitute the following section, 
      namely:—
 </section></article><article><number>13</number> Penalty for gaming in 
      public street, etc.—Whoever is found gaming 
      in any public street, place or thoroughfare or setting any bird or any 
      animal to fight in any such street, place or thoroghfare shall be 
      punishable with fine not exeeding fifty rupees or with imprisonment of 
      either description for a term not exceeding one month.
 </article><article><number>13B</number> Power to arrest without 
      warrant.—Any police officer may arrest 
      without a warrant any person committing in his view any offence made 
      punishable be section 13 of section 13A.”
 [Punjab Act 9 of 1960, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 
      28-1-1960); Act 31 of 1966, sec. 88].
 Uttar 
      Pradesh.—In section 13,—
 <section>      
      <number>a</number> for the words 
      “playing for money or other valuable thing with cards, dice, counters or 
      other intruments of gaming, used in playing any game not being a game of 
      mere skill”, substitute the word “gaming”.
 <subsection>      [<number>U</number>P. 
      Act 1 of 1917, sec. 5].
 </subsection></section><section>      
      <number>b</number> between 
      paras 1 and 2, add the following new paragraph as follows:—
       “any 
      person found in any public street, place or thoroughfare within the limits 
      aforesaid with any instruments of gaming; or;
 </section><section>      
      <number>c</number> for the words, in 
      para 2, “or any person there present aiding and abetting such public 
      fighting of birds and animals”, substitute the words “or any person there 
      present making preparation for or aiding or abetting such gaming or public 
      fighting of birds or animals”; and
 </section><section>      
      <number>d</number> in the last para the 
      semi-colon after the words “shall be liable” shall be deleted and a dash 
      substituted therefor and clauses (a) and (b) after the said words “shall 
      be liable” shall be deleted and the following substituted 
      therefor:—
       “in the 
      case of a first offence to a fine not exceeding two hundred and fifty 
      rupees nor less than fifty rupees; or to rigorous imprisonment for a term 
      not exceeding one month; and
       in the 
      case of any subsequent offence to a fine not exceeding five hundred rupees 
      nor less than one hundred rupees and rigorous imprisonment for a term not 
      exceeding six months nor less than one month.”—
 <subsection>[<number>U</number>P. Act 21 of 1961. sec. 9 (w.e.f. 
      7-9-1961)].
 Himachal 
      Pradesh.—After section 13, insert the 
      following section 13A:—
 </subsection></section></article><article><number>13A</number> Enhanced punishment if 
      offence under section 13 relates to gaming with figures, 
      etc.—Where an offence committed by any 
      person under section 13 relates to gaming on any figures or numbers or 
      dates to be subsequently ascertained or disclosed, such persons shall, 
      notwithstanding anything contained in that section, be liable to fine not 
      exceeding five hundred rupees, or to imprisonment of either description 
      for a term not exceeding six months; or to both.
 Uttar 
      Pradesh.—After section 13, insert the 
      following new section, namely:—
 “13A. Exemption of games of 
      mere skill.—Nothing in this Act shall apply 
      to any game of mere skill, as distinguished from a game of chance or a 
      game of chance and skill combined, unless it is carried on in a common 
      gaming-house;”
 <section>[<number>U</number>P. Act 10 of 1938, sec. 
      2].
 Section 13B: 

 Himachal 
      Pradesh.—Insert the following section 
      13-B:—
 </section></article><article><number>13B</number> Power to arrest without 
      warrant.—Any police officer may arrest 
      without a warrant any person committing in his view any offence made 
      punishable by section 13 or section 13A.”
 [Himachal Pradesh Act. 30 of 1976, 
      sec. 7 (w.e.f. 5-8-1976)].
  
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>14</number> Offences by whom triable.—Offences punishable under this Act 
      shall be triable by any Magistrate having jurisdiction in the place where 
      the offence is committed. 
 But such Magistrate shall be restrained within the limits of his 
      jurisdiction under the Code of Criminal Procedure as to the amount of fine 
      or imprisonment he may inflict.
  
 STATE AMENDMENTS
 Uttar 
      Pradesh.—In section 14, insert the following 
      new paragraph between paras 1 and 2:—
 “Offences under section 3 of this Act 
      shall be non-bailable, anything contained to the contrary in any other law 
      notwithstanding.”— U.P. Act 21 of 1961, sec. 10 (7-9- 1961).
 After section 14, insert the following 
      section, namely:—
 </article><article><number>14A</number> 
      Compounding of offences.—An officer specially empowered in this behalf by the State 
      Government by notification may, subject to any general or special order of 
      the State Government in this behalf, compound any offence punishable under 
      this Act, either before or after the institution of the prosecution, on 
      realisation of such amount of composition fees as he thinks fit, not 
      exceeding the maximum amount of fine fixed for the offence; and where the 
      offence is so compounded—
 <section><number>i</number> before the 
      institution of the prosecution the offender shall not be liable to 
      prosecution for such offence and shall, if in custody, be set at 
      liberty:
 </section><section><number>ii</number> after the institution of the 
      prosecution, the composition shall amount to acquittal of the 
      offender:
 Provided that 
      nothing contained in this section shall authorise the composition of any 
      subsequent offence committed by an offender who has once been convicted 
      for any offence punishable under this Act.
 <subsection>[<number>U</number>P. Act 35 of 
      1979, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 21-12-1979)].
 
  </subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>15</number> Penalty for subsequent 
      offence.—Whoever, having been convicted of an offence 
      punishable under section 3 or section 4 of this Act shall again be guilty 
      of any offence punishable under either of such sections, shall be subject 
      for every such subsequent offence to double the amount of punishment to 
      which he would have been liable for the first commission of an offence of 
      the same description: 
 Provided that he shall not be liable in any case to a fine 
      exceeding six hundred rupees, or to imprisonment for a term exceeding one 
      year. 
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>16</number> Portion of fine may be paid to informer.—The Magistrate trying 
      the case may direct any portion of any fine which shall be levied under 
      sections 3 and 4 of this Act, or any part of the moneys or proceeds of 
      articles seized and ordered to be forfeited under this Act, to be paid to 
      an informer. 
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>17</number> Recovery and application of fines.—All fines imposed 
      under this Act may be recovered in the manner prescribed by section 61 of 
      the <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>Code of Criminal Procedure. <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[***]. 
 

  STATE 
AMENDMENTS
 <section><number>Manipur</number>—For section 17, substitute the 
      following:—
 “17. All fines 
      imposed under this Act may be recoverd in the manner prescribed under the 
      existing laws of the State for the realisation of fines.”
 </section><section>[<number>S</number>R.O. 168, dated 
      30th January, 1952, published in the Gazette of India., Pt. II, Sec. 3, p. 
      149, dated 2nd February, 1952; Act 81 of 1971, sec. 3].
  






 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>18</number> Offences under this Act to be "offences" within the meaning of 
      Penal Code.—[Repealed by the Repealing Act, 1874 (16 of 
      1874), sec. 1 and Sch., Part I].
  
 STATE AMENDMENTS
 Himachal Pradesh.—After section 
      17, the following new section shall be deemed to be inserted, 
      namely:—
 “18. Exemption of games of mere 
      skill.—Nothing in this Act shall apply to any game of mere skill 
      wherever played.”
 [Himachal Pradesh Act 30 of 1976, sec. 
      9].
 <section><number>Manipur</number>—Same as in 
      Punjab.
 </section><section>[<number>S</number>R.O. 168, dated 30th January, 1952, 
      published in the Gazette of India, Pt. II, Sec. 3, p. 149, dated 2nd 
      February, 1952, Act 81 of 1971, sec. 3].
 Punjab: Haryana: Chandigarh.—In 
      its application to the State of Punjab, after section 17, the following 
      new section shall be deemed to be inserted. namely:—
 “18. Exemption of games of mere 
      skill.—Nothing in this Act shall apply to any game of mere skill 
      wherever played.”
 [Punjab Act 1 of 1929, sec. 9; 18 of 
      1958, sec. 3; 31 of 1966, sec. 88].
    
 
  </section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>
Definitions of “Lieutenant-Governor” and “Chief Commissioner” rep. by the 
A.O. 1937.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>
The clauses relating to “Number” and “Gender” rep. by Act 17 of 1914, 
sec. 3 and Sch. II.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Subs. by Act 12 of 1891, for 
      “sections 13, 17 and 18”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Subs. by the Adaptation of 
      Laws Order, 1950, for “said 
      Provinces”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>  Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws 
      Order, 1950, for "Provincial Government".</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>  Subs. by Adaptation of Laws Order, 1950, for 
      “Provinces” which had been subs. by the Indian Independence (Adaptation of 
      Central Acts and Ordinances) Order, 1948, for “territories subject to its 
      government or 
      administration”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>  See section 53 of the 
      Code.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>  As to the enhanced punishment for a 
      second conviction of an offence under section 3 or section 4, see section 
      15 of this Act.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for “Provincial 
Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> See 
      now the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974). tc " 
1.	See now the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number> The 
      words “and such fines shall (subject to the provisions contained in the 
      last preceding section) be applied as the Lieutenant-Governor or Chief 
      Commissioner, as the case may be, shall from time to time direct” were 
      repealed by the Government of India (Adaptation of Indian Laws) Order, 
      1937. tc 
" 2. The words “and such fines shall (subject to the provisions contained in the 
last preceding section) be applied as the Lieutenant-Governor or Chief 
Commissioner, as the case may be, shall from time to time direct” were repealed 
by the Government of India (Adaptation of Indian Laws) Order, 1937."</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>