<act><tid>1959284</tid>
<title>Taxation on Income (Investigation Commission) Act, <year>1947</year></title>

Act No. XXX OF <year>1947</year>
[ 18th April, <year>1947</year>]

An Act to provide for an investigation into matters relating to 
taxation on income.

WHEREAS it is expedient, for the purpose of ascertaining whether the 
actual incidence of taxation on income is and has been in recent years 
in accordance with the provisions of law, and the extent to which the 
existing law and procedure for the assessment and recovery of such 
taxation is adequate to prevent the evasion thereof, to make provision 
for an investigation to be made into such matters;

It is hereby enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>532343</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.-
<section><tid>1366557</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called  
the Taxation on Income (Investigation Commission) Act, <year>1947</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>208342</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of British India.

</section>

<section><tid>837988</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1749998</tid>
<number>2</number>Interpretation.- In this Act," taxation on income" means any tax 
chargeable under the Indian Income- tax Act, <year>1922</year> (XI of <year>1922</year>) or the 
Excess Profits Tax Act, <year>1940</year> (XV of <year>1940</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>1514409</tid>
<number> 3</number> Constitution and functions of commission.- The Central Government 
may constitute a Commission to be called the Income- tax Investigation 
Commission (hereinafter referred to as the Commission) whose duties it 
shall be-
<section><tid>254402</tid>
<number>a</number>to investigate and report to the Central Government on all matters 
relating to taxation on income, with particular reference to the 
extent to which the existing law relating to, and procedure for, the 
assessment and collection of such taxation is adequate to prevent the 
evasion thereof;

</section>

<section><tid>436200</tid>
<number>b</number>to investigate in accordance with the provisions of this Act any 
case referred to it under section 5 and report thereon to the Central 
Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>951343</tid>
<number> 4</number> Composition of Commission.-
<section><tid>582244</tid>
<number>1</number>The Commission shall consist of a  
Chairman (being a person who is or has been a Judge of a High court) 
and two other Commissioners, appointed by the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>235294</tid>
<number>2</number>On the occurrence from any cause of a vacancy among the 
Commissioners, the Central Government may, if it thinks fit, 
appoint a person to fill the vacancy.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>574258</tid>
<number> 5</number> Power of Central Government to refer cases for investigation.-
<section><tid>449774</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, at any time before the 31st day of 
December, <year>1947</year>, refer to the Commission for investigation and report 
any case in which the Central Government has prima facie reasons for 
believing that a person has to a substantial extent evaded payment of 
taxation on income, together with such material as may be available in 
support of such belief.

</section>

<section><tid>1104510</tid>
<number>2</number>If in the course of investigation into a case referred to it under 
sub- section (1), the Commission has reason to believe that some person 
other than the person whose case is being investigated has himself 
evaded payment of taxation on income, it may make a report to the 
Central Government stating its reasons for such belief, and on receipt 
of such report the Central Government may at any time refer the case 
of such other person to the Commission for investigation and report.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1934111</tid>
<number> 6</number> Powers of Commission.-
<section><tid>1270312</tid>
<number>1</number>The Commission shall have power to  
administer oaths, and shall have all the powers of a Civil Court under 
the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (V of <year>1908</year>), for the purposes of 
taking evidence on oath, enforcing the attendance of witnesses and of 
persons whose cases are being investigated, compelling the production 
of documents and issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses, 
and shall be deemed to be a Civil Court for all the purposes of 
section 195 and Chapter XXXV of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1898</year> 
 (V of <year>1898</year>); and any reference in the said Chapter to the presiding 
officer of a Court shall be deemed to include a reference to the 
Chairman of the Commission.

</section>

<section><tid>38871</tid>
<number>2</number>If in the course of any investigation under this Act it appears to 
the Commission to be necessary to examine any accounts or documents 
which it cannot itself conveniently examine, the Commission may 
authorise any person qualified in its opinion to make such examination 
to examine the accounts or documents and interrogate for that purpose 
any person having charge or custody thereof and make a report thereon 
to the Commission; and any person having charge or custody of such 
accounts or documents shall be bound to produce them to the person so 
authorised and to give to such person any information in respect 
thereof which the person so authorised may require.

</section>

<section><tid>1030831</tid>
<number>3</number>The Commissioners and all persons authorised by the commission 
under this section shall be deemed to be public servants within the 
meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (XLV of <year>1860</year>).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1267418</tid>
<number> 7</number> Procedure of Commission.-
<section><tid>680462</tid>
<number>1</number>The Commission shall, subject to the  
provisions of this Act, have power to regulate its own procedure 
 (including the fixing of places and times of its sittings and deciding  
  whether to sit in public or in private) and may act notwithstanding a 
vacancy in the number of the Commissioners.

</section>

<section><tid>937936</tid>
<number>2</number>In making an investigation under clause (b) of section 3, the 
Commission shall act in accordance with the principles of natural 
justice, shall follow as far as practicable the principles of the 
Indian Evidence Act, <year>1872</year> (1 of <year>1872</year>), and shall give the person whose 
case is being investigated a reasonable opportunity of rebutting any 
evidence adduced against him.

</section>

<section><tid>274697</tid>
<number>3</number>Any person whose case is being investigated the Commission may be 
represented by a pleader duly authorised to act on his behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>1217285</tid>
<number>4</number>Except with the previous sanction of the Central Government,-

<subsection><tid>285463</tid>
<number>a</number>no suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall be instituted 
against any person in any civil or criminal court for any evidence 
given by him in any proceedings before the Commission, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1135050</tid>
<number>b</number>no evidence so given shall be admissible in evidence against such 
person in any suit, prosecution or other proceeding before such Court.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>486744</tid>
<number>5</number>No document shall be inadmissible in evidence in any proceedings 
before the Commission on the ground that it is not duly stamped or 
registered.

</section>

<section><tid>1944989</tid>
<number>6</number>Nothing in section 54 of the Indian Income- tax Act, <year>1922</year> (XI of  
  <year>1922</year>) or in that section as applied to excess profits tax by section 
 21 of the Excess Profits Tax Act, <year>1940</year> (XV of <year>1940</year>) shall apply to the 
disclosure of any of the particulars referred to therein in any 
proceeding before the Commission or in any report made by the 
Commission to the Central Government or in any report made to the 
Commission by a person authorised under sub- section (2) of section 6.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1702463</tid>
<number> 8</number> Power to direct reopening of assessment proceedings.-
<section><tid>70213</tid>
<number>1</number>After  
considering any report made to it under clause (b) of section 3, the 
Central Government may, by order in writing, direct that proceedings 
to assess in respect of the income of any period commencing after the 
 31st day of December, <year>1938</year> the person to whose case the report relates 
to income- tax, super- tax or excess profits tax shall be taken or 
reopened; and upon such a direction being made, such assessment 
proceedings may be taken and completed under the appropriate law, 
notwithstanding anything contained in section 34 of the Indian 
Income- tax Act, <year>1922</year> (XI of <year>1922</year>), or section 15 of the Excess Profits 
Tax Act, <year>1940</year> (XV of <year>1940</year>), or any other law, and notwithstanding any 
lapse of time.

</section>

<section><tid>129630</tid>
<number>2</number>On a direction being made under sub- section (1), a copy of the 
report of the Commission so far as it relates to the case of the 
person concerned, shall be furnished to him.

</section>

<section><tid>1593229</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any other 
law, in any proceedings directed to be taken under sub- section (1), 
any evidence in the case adduced before the Commission or a person 
authorised by it under sub- section (2) of section 6 shall be 
admissible in evidence.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1289802</tid>
<number>9</number>Bar of jurisdiction.- No act or proceeding of the Commission or 
any person authorised by it under sub- section (2) of section 6 shall 
be called in question in any manner by any Court, and no suit, 
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Crown or 
any Commissioner or any other person for anything in good faith done 
or intended to be done under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1074725</tid>
<number>10</number>Power to make rules.- The Central Government may, by notification 
in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the purposes of 
this Act.

</article>



 </act>