<act><title>THE AIRPORTS ECONOMIC REGULATORY AUTHORITY OF INDIA 
ACT, 2008 </title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title, commencement and application. </title>
<section><number>1</number> This Act 
may be called the Airports Economic Regulatory Authority of India Act, 2008. 

 </section><section><number>2</number> It shall come into force on such date 1 as the Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, appoint. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> It applies to 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> all airports whereat air transport services are operated or are 
  intended to be operated, other than airports and airfields belonging to or 
  subject to the control of the Armed Forces or paramilitary Forces of the 
  Union; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> all private airports and leased airports; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> all civil enclaves; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> all major airports. </subsection>


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires, 
 
 <section><number>a</number> aeronautical service means any service provided 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> for navigation, surveillance and supportive communication thereto for 
    air traffic management; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> for the landing, housing or parking of an aircraft or any other 
    ground facility offered in connection with aircraft operations at an 
    airport; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> for ground safety services at an airport; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> for ground handling services relating to aircraft, passengers and 
    cargo at an airport; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> for the cargo facility at an airport; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vi</number> for supplying fuel to the aircraft at an airport; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vii</number> for a stake-holder at an airport, for which the charges, in the 
    opinion of the Central Government for the reasons to be recorded in writing, 
    may be determined by the Authority; 
 </subsection></section><section><number>b</number> airport means a landing and taking off area for aircrafts, usually 
    with runways and aircraft maintenance and passenger facilities and includes 
    an aerodrome as defined in clause (2) of section 2 of the Aircraft Act, 1934 
    (22 of 1934); 
 </section><section><number>c</number> airport user means any person availing of passenger or cargo 
    facilities at an airport; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> Appellate Tribunal means the Airports Economic Regulatory Authority 
    Appellate Tribunal established under section 17; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> Authority means the Airports Economic Regulatory Authority 
    established under sub-section (1) of section 3; 
 </section><section><number>f</number> civil enclave means an area, if any, allotted at an airport 
    belonging to any armed force of the Union, for use by persons availing of 
    any air transport services from such airport or for the handling of baggage 
    or cargo by such service, and includes land comprising of any building and 
    structure on such area; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> Chairperson means the Chairperson of the Authority appointed under 
    sub-section (2) of section 4; 
 </section><section><number>h</number> leased airport means an airport in respect of which a lease has 
    been made under section 12A of the Airports Authority of India Act, 1994 (55 
    of 1994); 
 </section><section><number>i</number> major airport means any airport which has, or is designated to 
    have, annual passenger throughout in excess of one and a half million or any 
    other airport as the Central Government may, by notification, specify as 
    such; 
 </section><section><number>j</number> Member means a Member of the Authority and includes the 
    Chairperson; 
 </section><section><number>k</number> prescribed means prescribed by rules made under this Act; 
 </section><section><number>l</number> private airport has the same meaning as assigned to it in clause 
    (nn) of section 2 of the Airports Authority of India Act, 1994 (55 of 1994); 
    
 </section><section><number>m</number> regulations means regulations made by the Authority under this Act; 
    
 </section><section><number>n</number> service provider means any person who provides aeronautical 
    services and is eligible to levy and charge user development fees from the 
    embarking passengers at any airport and includes the authority which manages 
    the airport; 
 </section><section><number>o</number> stake-holder includes a licensee of an airport, airlines operating 
    thereat, a person who provides aeronautical services, and any association of 
    individuals, which in the opinion of the Authority, represents the passenger 
    or cargo facility users; 
 </section><section><number>p</number> words and expressions used but not defined in this Act and defined in 
    the Airports Authority of India Act, 1994 (55 of 1994) shall have 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number>Establishment of Authority. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government 
shall, within three months from the date of commencement of this Act, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, establish an Authority, to be known as the 
Airports Economic Regulatory Authority, to exercise the powers conferred on, and 
the functions assigned to it, by or under this Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Authority shall be a body corporate by the name aforesaid, having 
perpetual succession and a common seal, with power to acquire, hold and dispose 
of property, both movable and immovable, and to contract and shall, by the said 
name, sue or be sued. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The head office of the Authority shall be at such place as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify. 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> </title><title>Composition of Authority. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The 
Authority shall consist of a Chairperson and two other Members to be appointed 
by the Central Government: 
 Provided that whenever the Authority is deciding a matter involving a civil 
enclave in a defence airfield, there shall be an additional Member, not below 
the rank of Additional Secretary to the Government of India, to be nominated by 
the Ministry of Defence. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Chairperson and Members of the Authority shall be appointed by the 
Central Government from amongst persons of ability and integrity having adequate 
knowledge of, and professional experience in, aviation, economics, law, commerce 
or consumer affairs: 
 Provided that a person who is or has been in the service of Government shall 
not be appointed as a Member unless such person has held the post of Secretary 
or Additional Secretary to the Government of India or any equivalent post in the 
Central or State Government for a total period of not less than three years. 

 </section><section><number>3</number> The Chairperson and other Members shall be whole-time Members. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Chairperson or other Members shall not hold any other office. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Chairperson shall be the Chief Executive of the Authority. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Chairperson and other Members of the Authority shall be appointed by 
the Central Government on the recommendation of Selection Committee referred to 
in section 5. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Constitution of Selection Committee to recommend Members. 
</title>
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government shall, for the purpose of sub-section (6) 
of section 4 constitute a Selection Committee consisting of the following, 
namely: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> Cabinet Secretary Chairman; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> Secretary, in the Ministry of Civil Aviation Member; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> Secretary, Department of Legal Affairs in the  Ministry of Law and 
  Justice Member; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> Secretary, in the Ministry of Defence Member; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> One expert to be nominated by the Ministry of  Civil Aviation  
  Member. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Central Government shall within one month from the date of occurrence 
of any vacancy by reason of death, resignation or removal of the Chairperson or 
a Member and six months before the superannuation or end of tenure of any 
Chairperson or any Member, make a reference to the Selection Committee for 
filling up of the vacancy. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Selection Committee shall finalise the selection of the Chairperson 
and Members within one month from the date on which the reference is made to it. 

 </section><section><number>4</number> The Selection Committee shall recommend a panel of two names for every 
vacancy referred to it. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Before recommending any person for appointment as a Chairperson or other 
Member of the Authority, the Selection Committee shall satisfy itself that such 
person does not have any financial or other interest which is likely to affect 
prejudicially his functions as a Member. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> No appointment of the Chairperson or other Member shall be invalid merely 
by reason of any vacancy in the Selection Committee. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Terms of office and other conditions of service, etc., of 
Chairperson and Members. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Chairperson and other Members, shall 
hold office, as such, for a term of five years from the date on which he enters 
upon his office, but shall not be eligible for re-appointment: 
 Provided that no Chairperson or other Member shall hold office, as such, 
after he attains 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> in the case of the Chairperson, the age of sixty-five years; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> in the case of any other Member, the age of sixty-two years. 
</subsection>
 Explanation. For the purposes of this sub-section, a Member may be 
appointed as Chairperson of the Authority, but a person who has been the 
Chairperson shall not be eligible for appointment as a Member. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The salary and allowances payable to, and the other terms and conditions 
of service of, the Chairperson and other Members shall be such as may be 
prescribed. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The salary, allowances and other conditions of service of the Chairperson 
and other Members shall not be varied to their disadvantage after their 
appointment. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), the Chairperson or 
any Member may, 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> relinquish his office by giving, in writing to the Central Government, 
  a notice of not less than three months; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> be removed from his office in accordance with the provisions of section 
  8. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Chairperson or any Member ceasing to hold office, as such, shall 

 
 <subsection><number>a</number> be ineligible for further employment under the Central Government or 
  any State Government for a period of two years from the date he ceases to hold 
  such office; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> not accept any commercial employment including private for a period of 
  two years from the date he ceases to hold such office; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> not represent any person before the Authority in any other manner. 
</subsection>
 Explanation. For the purposes of this sub-section, 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> employment under the Central Government or State Government includes 
  employment under any local or other authority within the territory of India or 
  under the control of the Central Government or State Government or under any 
  corporation or society owned or controlled by the Government. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> commercial employment means employment in any capacity under, or 
  agency of, a person engaged in trading, commercial, industrial or financial 
  business in any field and includes also a director of a company or partner of 
  a firm and it also includes setting up practice either independently or as 
  partner of a firm or as an adviser or a consultant. 
</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Power of Chairperson. </title>The Chairperson shall have powers 
of general superintendence and directions in the conduct of the affairs of the 
Authority and he shall, in addition to presiding over the meetings of the 
Authority, exercise and discharge such powers and functions of the Authority and 
shall discharge such other powers and functions as may be prescribed. 
  </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number> Removal and suspension of Members. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
Government may, by order, remove from office the Chairperson or other Member, if 
the Chairperson or such other Member, as the case may be, 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> has been adjudged an insolvent; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> has been convicted of an offence which, in the opinion of the Central 
  Government, involves moral turpitude; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> has become physically or mentally incapable of acting as a Member; or 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> has acquired such financial or other interest, as is likely to affect 
  prejudicially his functions as a Member; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> has so abused his position, as to render his continuance in office 
  prejudicial to the public interest; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> has engaged at any time during his term of office in any other 
  employment. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Chairperson or any other Member shall not be removed from his office 
except by an order of the Central Government on the ground of his proved 
misbehaviour or incapacity after the Central Government, has, on an inquiry, 
held in accordance with the procedure prescribed in this behalf by the Central 
Government, come to the conclusion that the Member ought on any such ground to 
be removed. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Central Government may suspend any Member in respect of whom an 
inquiry under sub-section (2) is being initiated or pending until the Central 
Government has passed an order on receipt of the report of the inquiry. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>9</number> </title><title>Appointment of Secretary, experts, professionals 
and officers and other employees of Authority. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
Government may appoint a Secretary to discharge his functions under this Act. 

 </section><section><number>2</number> The Authority may appoint such officers and other employees as it 
considers necessary for the efficient discharge of its functions under this Act. 

 </section><section><number>3</number> The salaries and allowances payable to and other terms and conditions of 
service of the Secretary and officers and other employees of the Authority and 
the number of such officers and other employees shall be such as may be 
prescribed. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Authority may engage, in accordance with the procedure specified by 
regulations such number of experts and professionals of integrity and 
outstanding ability, who have special knowledge of, and experience in, 
economics, law, business or such other disciplines related to aviation as it 
deems necessary to assist the Authority in the discharge of its functions under 
this Act. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>10</number> Meetings. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Authority shall meet at such places 
and times and shall observe such rules of procedure in regard to the transaction 
of business at its meetings (including the quorum at its meetings), as may be 
determined by regulations. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Chairperson shall preside at the meeting of the Authority and if for 
any reason the Chairperson is unable to attend a meeting of the Authority, any 
other Member chosen by the members present from amongst themselves at the 
meeting shall preside at the meeting. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> All questions which come up before any meeting of the Authority shall be 
decided by a majority of votes of the Members present and voting and, in the 
event of an equality of votes, the Chairperson or the Member presiding shall 
have the right to exercise a second or casting vote. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Save as otherwise provided in sub-section (1), every Member shall have 
one vote. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>11</number> Authentication.</title>All orders and decisions of the 
Authority shall be authenticated by signatures of the Secretary or any other 
officer of the Authority, duly authorised by the Authority in this 
behalf.</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>12</number> Vacancies, etc., not to invalidate proceedings of Authority. 
</title>No act or proceedings of the Authority shall be invalid merely by 
reason of 
 
 <section><number>a</number> any vacancy in, or any defect in, the constitution of the Authority; or 
  
 </section><section><number>b</number> any defect in the appointment of a person acting as a Member of the 
  Authority; or 
 </section><section><number>c</number> any irregularity in the procedure of the Authority not affecting the 
  merits of the case. </section>

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>13</number> </title><title>Functions of Authority. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The 
Authority shall perform the following functions in respect of major airports, 
namely: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> to determine the tariff for the aeronautical services taking into 
  consideration 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> the capital expenditure incurred and timely investment in improvement 
    of airport facilities; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> the service provided, its quality and other relevant factors; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number> the cost for improving efficiency; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iv</number> economic and viable operation of major airports; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>v</number> revenue received from services other than the aeronautical services; 
    
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>vi</number> the concession offered by the Central Government in any agreement or 
    memorandum of understanding or otherwise; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>vii</number> any other factor which may be relevant for the purposes of this 
    Act: </subsubsection>
 Provided that different tariff structures may be determined for different 
  airports having regard to all or any of the above considerations specified at 
  sub-clauses (i) to (vii); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> to determine the amount of the development fees in respect of major 
  airports; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> to determine the amount of the passengers service fee levied under rule 
  88 of the Aircraft Rules, 1937 made under the Aircraft Act, 1934 (22 of 1934); 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> to monitor the set performance standards relating to quality, 
  continuity and reliability of service as may be specified by the Central 
  Government or any authority authorised by it in this behalf; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> to call for such information as may be necessary to determine the 
  tariff under clause (a); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> to perform such other functions relating to tariff, as may be entrusted 
  to it by the Central Government or as may be necessary to carry out the 
  provisions of this Act. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Authority shall determine the tariff once in five years and may if so 
considered appropriate and in public interest, amend, from time to time during 
the said period of five years, the tariff so determined. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> While discharging its functions under sub-section (1) the Authority shall 
not act against the interest of the sovereignty and integrity of India, the 
security of the State, friendly relations with foreign States, public order, 
decency or morality. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Authority shall ensure transparency while exercising its powers and 
discharging its functions, inter alia, 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> by holding due consultations with all stake-holders with the airport; 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> by allowing all stake-holders to make their submissions to the 
  authority; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> by making all decisions of the authority fully documented and 
  explained. </subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>14</number> Powers of Authority to call for information, conduct 
investigations, etc. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Where the Authority considers it expedient so 
to do, it may by order in writing 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> call upon any service provider at any time to furnish in writing such 
  information or explanation relating to its functions as the Authority may 
  require to access the performance of the service provider; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> appoint one or more persons to make an inquiry in relation to the 
  affairs of any service provider; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> direct any of its officers or employees to inspect the books of account 
  or other documents of any service provider. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where any inquiry in relation to the affairs of a service provider has 
been undertaken under sub-section (1) 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> every office of the Government department, if such service provider is 
  a department of the Government; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> every director, manager, secretary or other officer, if such service 
  provider is a company; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> every partner, manager, secretary or other officer, if such service 
  provider is a firm; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> every other person or body of persons who has had dealings in the 
  course of business with any of the persons mentioned in clause (b) or (c), 
</subsection>
 shall be bound to produce before the Authority making the inquiry, all such 
books of account or other documents in his custody or power relating to, or 
having a bearing on the subject-matter of such inquiry and also to furnish to 
the Authority with any such statement or information relating thereto, as the 
case may be, required of him, within such time as may be specified. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every service provider shall maintain such books of account or other 
documents as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Authority shall have the power to issue such directions to monitor 
the performance of the service providers as it may consider necessary for proper 
functioning by service providers. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>15</number> Power of Authority to issue certain directions. </title>The 
Authority may, for the purpose of discharge of its functions under this Act, 
issue, from time to time to the service providers, such directions, as it may 
consider necessary. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>16</number> Power of seizure. </title>The Authority or any other officer 
specially authorised by it in this behalf may enter any building or place where 
the Authority has reason to believe that any document relating to the 
subject-matter of the inquiry may be found, and may seize any such document or 
take extracts or copies therefrom subject to the provisions of section 100 of 
the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) in so far as they may be 
applicable. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>17</number> </title><title>Establishment of Appellate Tribunal. 
</title>The Central Government shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
establish an Appellate Tribunal to be known as the Airports Economic Regulatory 
Authority Appellate Tribunal to 
 
 <section><number>a</number> adjudicate any dispute 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> between two or more service providers; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> between a service provider and a group of consumer: </subsection>
 Provided that the Appellate Tribunal may, if considers appropriate, obtain 
  the opinion of the Authority on any matter relating to such dispute: 
 Provided further that nothing in this clause shall apply in respect of 
  matters 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> relating to the monopolistic trade practice, restrictive trade 
    practice and unfair trade practice which are subject to the jurisdiction of 
    the Monopolies and Restrictive Trade Practices Commission established under 
    sub-section (1) of section 5 of the Monopolies and Restrictive Trade 
    Practices Act, 1969 (54 of 1969); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> relating to the complaint of an individual consumer maintainable 
    before a Consumer Disputes Redressal Forum or a Consumer Disputes Redressal 
    Commission or the National Consumer Redressal Commission established under 
    section 9 of the Consumer Protection Act, 1986 (68 of 1986); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> which are within the purview of the Competition Act, 2002 (12 of 
    2003); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> relating to an order of eviction which is appealable under section 
    28K of the Airports Authority of India Act, 1994 (55 of 1994). 
  </subsection>
 </section><section><number>b</number> hear and dispose of appeal against any direction, decision or order of 
  the Authority under this Act. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>18</number> Application for settlement of disputes and appeals to Appellate 
Tribunal. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government or a State Government or a local 
authority or any person may make an application to the Appellate Tribunal for 
adjudication of any dispute as referred to in clause 
<subsection><number>a</number> of section 17. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The Central Government or a State Government or a local authority or any 
person aggrieved by any direction, decision or order made by the Authority may 
prefer an appeal to the Appellate Tribunal. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every appeal under sub-section (2) shall be preferred within a period of 
thirty days from the date on which a copy of the direction or order or decision 
made by the Authority is received by the Central Government or the State 
Government or the local authority or the aggrieved person and it shall be in 
such form, verified in such manner and be accompanied by such fee as may be 
prescribed: 
 Provided that the Appellate Tribunal may entertain any appeal after the 
expiry of the said period of thirty days if it is satisfied that there was 
sufficient cause for not filing it within that period. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> On receipt of an application under sub-section (1) or an appeal under 
sub-section (2), the Appellate Tribunal may, after giving the parties to the 
dispute or the appeal an opportunity of being heard, pass such orders thereon as 
it thinks fit. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Appellate Tribunal shall send a copy of every order made by it to the 
parties to the dispute or the appeal and to the Authority, as the case may be. 

 </section><section><number>6</number> The application made under sub-section (1) or the appeal preferred under 
sub-section (2) shall be dealt with by it as expeditiously as possible and 
endeavour shall be made by it to dispose of the application or appeal finally 
within ninety days from the date of receipt of application or appeal, as the 
case may be: 
 Provided that where any such application or appeal could not be disposed of 
within the said period of ninety days, the Appellate Tribunal shall record its 
reasons in writing for not disposing of the application or appeal within that 
period. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> The Appellate Tribunal may, for the purpose of examining the legality or 
propriety or correctness, of any dispute made in any application under 
sub-section (1), or of any direction or order or decision of the Authority 
referred to in the appeal preferred under sub-section (2), on its own motion or 
otherwise, call for the records relevant to deposing of such application or 
appeal and make such orders as it thinks fit. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title>19 </title>. <title>Composition of Appellate Tribunal. 
</title>
<section><number>1</number> The Appellate Tribunal shall consist of a Chairperson and not more 
than two Members to be appointed, by notification in the Official Gazette, by 
the Central Government: 
 Provided that the Chairperson or a Member holding a post as such in any other 
Tribunal, established under any law for the time being in force, in addition to 
his being the Chairperson or a Member of that Tribunal, may be appointed as the 
Chairperson or a Member, as the case may be, of the Appellate Tribunal under 
this Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The selection of Chairperson and Members of the Appellate Tribunal shall 
be made by the Central Government in consultation with the Chief Justice of 
India or his nominee. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title>20 </title>. <title>Qualifications for appointment of Chairperson 
and Members. </title>A person shall not be qualified for appointment as the 
Chairperson or a Member of the Appellate Tribunal unless he 
 
 <section><number>a</number> in the case of Chairperson, is, or has been, a Judge of the Supreme 
  Court or the Chief Justice of a High Court; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> in the case of a Member, has held the post of Secretary to the 
  Government of India or any equivalent post in the Central Government or the 
  State Government for a total period of not less than two years in the 
  Ministries or Departments dealing with aviation or economics or law or a 
  person who is well-versed in the field of aviation or economics or law. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>21</number> </title><title>Term of office. </title>The Chairperson and 
every other Member of the Appellate Tribunal shall hold office as such for a 
term not exceeding three years from the date on which he enters upon his office: 

 Provided that no Chairperson or other Member shall hold office as such after 
he has attained, 
 
 <section><number>a</number> in the case of Chairperson, the age of seventy years; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> in the case of any other Member, the age of sixty-five years. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>22</number> Terms and conditions of service. </title>The salary and 
allowances payable to and the other terms and conditions of service of the 
Chairperson and other Members of the Appellate Tribunal shall be such as may be 
prescribed: 
 Provided that neither the salary and allowances nor the other terms and 
conditions of service of the Chairperson or a Member of the Appellate Tribunal 
shall be varied to his disadvantage after appointment. 
  </article> 

  
 <article><title>23 </title>. <title>Vacancies. </title>If, for reason other than 
temporary absence, any vacancy occurs in the office of the Chairperson or a 
Member of the Appellate Tribunal, the Central Government shall appoint another 
person in accordance with the provisions of this Act to fill the vacancy and the 
proceedings may be continued before the Appellate Tribunal from the stage at 
which the vacancy is filled. </article> 

  
 <article><title>24 </title>. <title>Removal and resignation. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The 
Central Government may remove from office, the Chairperson or any Member of the 
Appellate Tribunal, who 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> has been adjudged an insolvent; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> has been convicted of an offence which, in the opinion of the Central 
  Government, involves moral turpitude; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> has become physically or mentally incapable of acting as the 
  Chairperson or a Member; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> has acquired such financial or other interest as is likely to affect 
  prejudicially his functions as the Chairperson or a Member; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> has so abused his position as to render his continuance in office 
  prejudicial to the public interest. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), the Chairperson or 
a Member of the Appellate Tribunal shall not be removed from his office on the 
ground specified in clause (d) or clause (e) of that sub-section unless the 
Supreme Court on a reference being made to it in this behalf by the Central 
Government, has, on an enquiry, held by it in accordance with such procedure as 
it may specify in this behalf, reported that the Chairperson or a Member ought, 
on such grounds, to be removed. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Central Government may suspend from office, the Chairperson or a 
Member of the Appellate Tribunal in respect of whom a reference has been made to 
the Supreme Court under sub-section (2), until the Central Government has passed 
an order on receipt of the report of the Supreme Court on such reference. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title>25 </title>. <title>Staff of Appellate Tribunal. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The 
Central Government shall provide the Appellate Tribunal with such officers and 
employees as it may deem fit. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The officers and employees of the Appellate Tribunal shall discharge 
their functions under the general superintendence of its Chairperson. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The salaries and allowances and other conditions of service of such 
officers and employees of the Appellate Tribunal shall be such as may be 
prescribed. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>26</number> Decision to be by majority. </title>If the Chairperson and 
other Members differ in opinion on any matter, such matter shall be decided 
according to the opinion of the majority. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>27</number> </title><title>Members, etc., to be public servants. 
</title>The Chairperson, Members and other officers and employees of the 
Appellate Tribunal shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of 
section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860). </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>28</number> Civil court not to have jurisdiction. </title>No civil court 
shall have jurisdiction to entertain any suit or proceeding in respect of any 
matter which the Appellate Tribunal is empowered by or under this Act to 
determine and no injunction shall be granted by any court or other authority in 
respect of any action taken or to be taken in pursuance of any power conferred 
by or under this Act. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title>29 </title>. <title>Procedure and powers of Appellate Tribunal. 
</title>
<section><number>1</number> The Appellate Tribunal shall not be bound by the procedure laid 
down by the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), but shall be guided by 
the principles of natural justice and, subject to the other provisions of this 
Act, the Appellate Tribunal shall have powers to regulate its own procedure. 

 </section><section><number>2</number> The Appellate Tribunal shall have, for the purposes of discharging its 
functions under this Act, the same powers as are vested in a civil court under 
the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), while trying a suit, in respect 
of the following matters, namely: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person and examining him 
  on oath; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> requiring the discovery and production of documents; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> receiving evidence on affidavits; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> subject to the provisions of sections 123 and 124 of the Indian 
  Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872), requisitioning any public record or document 
  or a copy of such record or document, from any office; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses or documents; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> reviewing its decisions; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> dismissing an application for default or deciding it, ex parte 
  ; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> setting aside any order of dismissal of any application for default or 
  any order passed by it, ex parte ; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> any other matter which may be prescribed. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every proceeding before the Appellate Tribunal shall be deemed to be a 
judicial proceeding within the meaning of sections 193 and 228, and for the 
purposes of section 196 of the Indian Penal Code, 1860 (45 of 1860) and the 
Appellate Tribunal shall be deemed to be a civil court for the purposes of 
section 195 and Chapter XXVI of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 
1974). </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>30</number> Right to legal representation. </title>The applicant or 
appellant may either appear in person or authorises one or more chartered 
accountants or company secretaries or cost accountants or legal practitioners or 
any of its officers to present his or its case before the Appellate Tribunal. 

 Explanation .For the purposes of this section, 
 
 <section><number>a</number> chartered accountant means a chartered accountant as defined in 
  clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Chartered Accountants Act, 
  1949 (38 of 1949) and who has obtained a certificate of practice under 
  sub-section (1) of section 6 of that Act; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> company secretary means a company secretary as defined in clause (c) 
  of sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Company Secretaries Act, 1980 (56 of 
  1980) and who has obtained a certificate of practice under sub-section (1) of 
  section 6 of that Act; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> cost accountant means a cost accountant as defined in clause (b) of 
  sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Cost and Works Accountants Act, 1959 (23 
  of 1959), and who has obtained a certificate of practice under sub-section (1) 
  of section 6 of that Act; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> legal practitioner means an advocate, vakil or an attorney of any 
  High Court, and includes a pleader in practice. </section>

</article> 

  
 <article><title>31 </title>. <title>Appeal to Supreme Court. </title>
<section><number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 
1908) or in any other law, an appeal shall lie against any order, not being an 
interlocutory order, of the Appellate Tribunal to the Supreme Court on one or 
more of the grounds specified in section 100 of that Code. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> No appeal shall lie against any decision or order made by the Appellate 
Tribunal with the consent of the parties. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every appeal under this section shall be preferred within a period of 
ninety days from the date of the decision or order appealed against: 
 Provided that the Supreme Court may entertain the appeal after the expiry of 
the said period of ninety days, if it is satisfied that the appellant was 
prevented by sufficient cause from preferring the appeal in time. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>32</number> Orders passed by Appellate Tribunal to be executable as a decree. 
</title> 
<section><number>1</number> An order passed by the Appellate Tribunal under this Act shall be 
executable by the Appellate Tribunal as a decree of civil court, and for this 
purpose, the Appellate Tribunal shall have all the powers of a civil court. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), the Appellate 
Tribunal may transmit any order made by it to a civil court having local 
jurisdiction and such civil court shall execute the order as if it were a decree 
made by that court. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>33</number> Budget. </title>The Authority shall prepare, in such form and 
at such time in each financial year as may be prescribed, its budget for the 
next financial year, showing the estimated receipts and expenditure of the 
Authority and forward the same to the Central Government, for information. 
</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>34</number> Grants by Central Government. </title>The Central Government 
may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in this behalf, make to 
the Authority grants of such sums of money as are required to be paid for the 
salaries and allowances payable to the Chairperson and other Members and the 
administrative expenses, including the salaries and allowances and pension 
payable to or in respect of officers and other employees of the Authority. 
</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>35</number> Annual statement of accounts. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Authority shall 
maintain proper accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual 
statement of accounts in such form as may be prescribed by the Central 
Government in consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India. 

 </section><section><number>2</number> The accounts of the Authority shall be audited by the Comptroller and 
Auditor-General of India at such intervals as may be specified by him. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Comptroller and Auditor-General of India or any person appointed by 
him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the Authority under this Act 
shall have the same rights, privileges and authority in connection with such 
audit, as the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India generally has, in 
connection with the audit of the Government accounts and, in particular, shall 
have the right to demand the production of books, accounts, connected vouchers 
and other documents and papers and to inspect any of the offices of the 
Authority. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The accounts of the Authority, as certified by Comptroller and 
Auditor-General of India or any other person appointed by him in this behalf, 
together with the audit report thereon, shall be forwarded annually to the 
Central Government and the Central Government shall cause the same to be laid 
before each House of Parliament. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>36</number> Furnishing of returns, etc., to Central Government. </title>
<section><number>1</number> 
The Authority shall furnish to the Central Government, at such time and in such 
form and manner as may be prescribed or as the Central Government may direct, 
such returns and statements and such particulars in regard to any matter under 
the jurisdiction of the Authority, as the Central Government may, from time to 
time, require. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Authority shall prepare, once every year, in such form and at such 
time as may be prescribed, an annual report, giving a summary of its activities 
during the previous year and copies of the report shall be forwarded to the 
Central Government. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> A copy of the report received under sub-section (2) shall be laid by the 
Central Government, as soon as may be after it is received, before each House of 
Parliament. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>37</number> Penalty for wilful failure to comply with orders of Appellate 
Tribunal. </title>If any person wilfully fails to comply with the order of the 
Appellate Tribunal, he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to one 
lakh rupees and in case of a second or subsequent offence with fine which may 
extend to two lakh rupees and in the case of continuing contravention with 
additional fine which may extend to two lakh rupees for every day during which 
such default continues. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>38</number> Punishment for non-compliance of orders and directions under this 
Act. </title>Whoever fails to comply with any order or direction given under 
this Act, or contravenes, or attempts to contravene or abets the contravention 
of the provisions of this Act or of any rules or regulations made thereunder 
shall be punishable with fine which may extend to one lakh rupees and in the 
case of a second or subsequent offence with fine which may extend to two lakh 
rupees and in the case of a continuing contravention with an additional fine 
which may extend to four thousand rupees for every day during which the default 
continues. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>39</number> Punishment for non-compliance with order of the Authority or 
Appellate Tribunal. </title>If any person wilfully fails to comply with an 
order of the Authority or of the Appellate Tribunal, passed under Chapter IV, he 
shall be punishable with fine which may extend to one lakh rupees and, in the 
case of a second or subsequent offence, with fine which may extend to two lakh 
rupees and in the case of a continuing failure, with an additional fine which 
may extend to four thousand rupees for every day during which such failure 
continues. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>40</number> Offences by companies. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Where an offence under this 
Act has been committed by a company, every person who, at the time the offence 
was committed, was in charge of, and was responsible to the company for the 
conduct of, the business of the company, as well as the company, shall be deemed 
to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and 
punished accordingly: 
 Provided that nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such 
person liable to any punishment provided in this Act, if he proves that the 
offence was committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised all due 
diligence to prevent the commission of such offence. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence 
under this Act has been committed by a company, and it is proved that the 
offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is attributable 
to any neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary or other officer 
of the company, such director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be 
deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against 
and punished accordingly. 
 Explanation. For the purposes of this section 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> company means any body corporate and includes a firm or other 
  association of individuals; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> director means a whole-time director in the company and in relation 
  to a firm, means a partner in the firm. </subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>41</number> Offences by Government Departments. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Where an 
offence under this Act has been committed by any Department of Government or any 
of its undertakings, the Head of the Department or its undertakings shall be 
deemed to be guilty of an offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against 
and punished accordingly unless he proves that the offence was committed without 
his knowledge or that he had exercised all due diligence to prevent the 
commission of such offence. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence 
under this Act has been committed by any Department of Government or its 
undertakings and it is proved that the offence has been committed with the 
consent or connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of any 
officer, other than the Head of the Department, or its undertakings, such 
officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to 
be proceeded against and punished accordingly. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>42</number> Directions by Central Government. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
Government may, from to time to time, issue to the Authority such directions as 
it may think necessary in the interest of the sovereignty and integrity of 
India, the security of the State, friendly relations with foreign States, public 
order, decency or morality. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Without prejudice to the foregoing provisions, the Authority shall, in 
exercise of its powers or the performance of its functions, be bound by such 
directions on questions of policy as the Central Government may give in writing 
to it from time to time: 
 Provided that the Authority shall, as far as practicable, be given an 
opportunity to express its views before any direction is given under this 
sub-section. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The decision of the Central Government whether a question is one of 
policy or not shall be final. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>43</number> Members, officers and employees of Authority to be public 
servants. </title>The Chairperson, Members, officers and other employees of 
the Authority shall be deemed, when acting or purporting to act in pursuance of 
any of the provisions of this Act, to be public servants within the meaning of 
section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860). </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>44</number> Bar of jurisdiction. </title>No civil court shall have 
jurisdiction in respect of any matter which the Authority is empowered by or 
under this Act to determine. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>45</number> Protection of action taken in good faith. </title>No suit, 
prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against the Central Government 
or the Authority or any Member, officer or other employees thereof for anything 
which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or the rules 
and regulations made thereunder. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>46</number> Exemption from tax on wealth and income. 
</title>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Wealth-tax Act, 1957 (27 of 
1957), the Income-tax, Act, 1961  (43 of 1961), or any other enactment for 
the time being in force relating to tax on wealth, income, profits or gains, the 
Authority shall not be liable to pay wealth-tax, income-tax or any other tax in 
respect of their wealth, income, profits or gains derived. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>47</number> Cognizance of offences. </title>No court shall take cognizance 
of an offence punishable under this Act, except upon a complaint in writing made 
by the Authority or by any officer of the Authority duly authorised by the 
Authority for this purpose. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>48</number> Delegation of powers. </title>The Authority may, by general or 
special order in writing, delegate to the Chairperson or any Member or officer 
of the Authority, subject to such conditions and limitations, if any, as may be 
specified in the order, such of its powers and functions under this Act (except 
the power to settle disputes and the power to make regulations), as it may deem 
necessary. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>49</number> Power of Central Government to supersede Authority. </title>
<section><number>1</number> 
If, at any time, the Central Government is of opinion 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> that on account of a grave emergency, the Authority is unable to 
  discharge the functions and duties imposed on it by or under the provisions of 
  this Act; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> that the Authority has persistently made default in complying with any 
  direction issued by the Central Government under this Act or in the discharge 
  of the functions and duties imposed on it by or under the provisions of this 
  Act and as a result of which default, the financial position of the Authority 
  or the administration of any airport, heliport, airstrip, civil enclave or 
  aeronautical communication station has deteriorated; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> that circumstances exist which render it necessary in the public 
  interest so to do, the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
  Gazette, supersede the Authority for such period, not exceeding six months, as 
  may be specified in the notification: 
 Provided that before issuing a notification under this sub-section for the 
  reasons mentioned in clause (b), the Central Government shall give a 
  reasonable opportunity to the Authority to show cause as to why it should not 
  be superseded and shall consider the explanations and objections, if any, of 
  the Authority. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Upon the publication of a notification under sub-section (1) superseding 
the Authority, 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> all the Members shall, as from the date of supersession, vacate their 
  offices as such; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> all the powers, functions and duties which may, by or under the 
  provisions of this Act, be exercised or discharged by or on behalf of the 
  Authority, shall until the Authority is re-constituted under sub- section (3), 
  be exercised and discharged by such person or persons as the Central 
  Government may direct; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> all property owned or controlled by the Authority shall, until the 
  Authority is re-constituted under sub-section (3), vest in the Central 
  Government. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> On the expiration of the period of supersession specified the 
  notification issued under sub-section (1), the Central Government may, 
 <subsection><number>a</number> extend the period of supersession for such further term not exceeding 
  six months, as it may consider necessary; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> re-constitute the Authority by fresh appointment and in such case the 
  Members who vacated their offices under clause (a) of sub-section (2) shall 
  not be deemed disqualified for appointment: 
 Provided that the Central Government may, at any time before the expiration 
  of the period of supersession, whether as originally specified under 
  sub-section (1) or as extended under this sub-section, take action under 
  clause (b) of this sub-section. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number> The Central Government shall cause a notification issued under 
  sub-section (1) and a full report of any action taken under this section and 
  the circumstances leading to such action to be laid before both Houses of 
  Parliament at the earliest opportunity. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>50</number> Application of other laws not barred. </title>The provisions of 
this Act shall be in addition to, and not in derogation of, the provisions of 
any other law for the time being in force. 
  </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>51</number> Power to make rules. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government may, by 
notification in Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the provisions of 
this Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely: 

 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the salary and allowances payable to, and the other conditions of 
  service of, the Chairperson and other Members under sub-section (2) of section 
  6; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the form and manner in which and the Authority before whom the oath of 
  office and secrecy shall be made and subscribed under sub-section (4) of 
  section 6; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the powers and functions to be exercised or discharged by the 
  Chairperson under section 7; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> the procedure for conducting any inquiry made under sub-section (2) of 
  section 8; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> the salaries and allowances payable to, and the other terms and 
  conditions of service of the Secretary, officers and other employees of the 
  Authority under sub-section (3) of section 9; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> the performance standards relating to the quality, continuity and 
  reliability of service to be monitored under clause (d) of sub-section (1) of 
  section 13; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> the books of account or other documents which are required to be 
  maintained by the service provider under sub-section (3) of section 14; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> the form and manner in which the form shall be verified and fee to be 
  accompanied by the form under sub-section (3) of section 18; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> the salary and allowances payable to, and the other terms and 
  conditions of service of, the Chairperson and other Members of the Appellate 
  Tribunal under section 22; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> the salaries and allowances and other conditions of service of such 
  officers and employees of the Appellate Tribunal under sub-section (3) of 
  section 25; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number> the matters in respect of which the Authority will have the powers of a 
  civil court under clause (a) of sub-section (2) of section 29; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number> the form in which the Authority shall prepare, and at such time in each 
  financial year, its budget and the time at which such budget shall be prepared 
  under section 33; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>m</number> the form in which proper accounts and other relevant records shall be 
  maintained and the annual statement of accounts shall be prepared by the 
  Authority under sub-section (1) of section 35; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>n</number> the form, manner and the time in which the returns and statements shall 
  be furnished by the Authority under sub-section (1) of section 36; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>o</number> the form and time at which the annual report, shall be prepared by the 
  Authority under sub-section (2) of section 36; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>p</number> any other matter which is to be, or may be, prescribed, or in respect 
  of which provision is to be made by rules. </subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>52</number> Power to make regulations. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Authority may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, and with the previous approval of the 
Central Government, make regulations, not inconsistent with this Act, and the 
rules made thereunder, to carry out the purposes of this Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
power, such regulations may provide for all or any of the following matters, 
namely: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the procedure in accordance with which the experts and professionals 
  may be engaged under sub-section (4) of section 9; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the places and time of meetings of the Authority and the procedure to 
  be followed at such meetings, (including the quorum at its meetings) under 
  sub-section (1) of section 10; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> any other matter which is required to be, or may be, specified by 
  regulations. </subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>53</number> Rules and regulations to be laid before Parliament. 
</title>Every rule made by the Central Government, and every regulation made 
by the Authority, under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is 
made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total 
period of thirty days, which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in 
making any modification in the rule or regulation or both Houses agree that the 
rule or regulation should not be made, the rule or regulation shall thereafter 
have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; 
so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice 
to the validity of anything previously done under that rule or regulation. 
  </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>54</number> Amendment of certain enactments. </title>The enactments 
specified in the Schedule to this Act shall be amended in the manner specified 
therein and such amendments shall take effect on the date of establishment of 
the Authority. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>55</number> Power to remove difficulties. </title>
<section><number>1</number> If any difficulty 
arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions, not 
inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as may appear to it to be 
necessary for removing the difficulty: 
 Provided that no order shall be made under this section after the expiry of 
two years from the date of commencement of this Act. (2) Every order made 
under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before 
each House of Parliament. </section></article><form>
 

THE AIRPORTS ECONOMIC REGULATORY 
AUTHORITY OF INDIA ACT, 2008 

 

 
 

THE SCHEDULE 
 

( See section 54) 
 

AMENDMENT TO THE AIRCRAFT ACT, 1934 
 

(22 of 1934) 
 

Section 5, sub-section ( 2 ), clause (ab), for or revision on 
tariff of operators of air transport services, substitute or revision on 
tariff of operators of air transport services [other than the tariff referred to 
in clause (a) of sub-section (1) of section 13 of the Airports Economic 
Regulatory Authority of India Act, 2008]. 
 

AMENDMENT TO THE AIRPORTS AUTHORITY OF INDIA ACT, 1994 

 

(55 of 1994) 
 

1. Section 22A, for the portion beginning with the words 
The Authority may and ending with the words for the purposes of, substitute 
the following: 
 

The Authority may, 
 

(i) after the previous approval of the Central Government in this behalf, 
levy on, and collect from, the embarking passengers at an airport other than the 
major airports referred to in clause (h) of section 2 of the Airports Economic 
Regulatory Authority of India Act, 2008 the development fees at the rate as may 
be prescribed; 
 

(ii) levy on, and collect from, the embarking passengers at major airport 
referred to in clause (h) of section 2 of the Airports Economic Regulatory 
Authority of India Act, 2008 the development fees at the rate as may be 
determined under clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 13 of the Airports 
Economic Regulatory Authority of India Act, 2008, 
 

and such fees shall be credited to the Authority and shall be regulated and 
utilised in the prescribed manner, for the purposes of 
 

2. Section 41, in sub-section (2), clause (ee), for the 
rate of development fees and, substitute 
 

the rate of development fees in respect of airports other than major 
airports and. </form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>