<act><title>The National Tiger 
Conservation Authority (Salaries, Allowances and Other Conditions of 
Appointment) Rules, 20061
</title> 

   

   

 <article><number>1</number> Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These rules may 
be called the National Tiger Conservation Authority (Salaries, Allowances and 
other Conditions of Appointment) Rules, 2006.
 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They 
shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official 
Gazette.

</section></article> 

   

   

 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In these rules, unless the context 
otherwise requires,—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>
“Act” means the Wild Life (Protection) Act, 1972 (53 of 1972);   
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> “Chairperson” means the Chairperson 
of the Tiger Conservation Authority;   
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>
“Fund” means the Tiger Conservation Authority Fund constituted under 
sub-section (2) of section 38Q;  
 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>
“member” means a member of the Tiger Conservation Authority;   
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>
“Member-Secretary” means the Member-Secretary of the Tiger Conservation 
Authority;   
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>
“section” means section of the Act;  
 
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>
“Tiger Conservation Authority” means the National Tiger Conservation 
Authority constituted under section 38L;  
 
 </section><section>       <number>h</number>
“Vice-Chairperson” means the Vice-Chairperson of the Tiger Conservation 
Authority.   </section></article> 

   

   

 <article><number>3</number> Travelling and other allowances to the Chairperson, 
Vice-Chairperson and members.—
<section><number>1</number> The Chairperson, Vice-Chairperson and members 
shall be entitled to travelling allowances and daily allowances in respect of 
journeys performed by them in connection with the work of the Tiger Conservation 
Authority at the rates as are admissible to a Union Minister, Union Ministers of 
State and a Secretary to the Government of India respectively.
 
 </section><section><number>2</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rule (1), the Chairperson or any other 
member, who is a Member of Parliament, shall not be entitled to any remuneration 
other than the allowances, defined in clause (a) of section 2 of the Parliament 
(Prevention of Disqualification) Act, 1959 (10 of 1959) or as the case may be, 
other than the allowances, if any, receive without incurring such 
disqualification.
 
   

   </section></article> 

   

   

 <article><number>4</number> Appointment of Member-Secretary on re-constitution of the 
Tiger Conservation Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government shall, by notification in 
the Official Gazette, appoint a Member-Secretary of the Tiger Conservation 
Authority on its re-constitution, who shall exercise such powers and perform 
such duties as are assigned to him under the Act and those assigned by the 
Authority.
 
 </section><section><number>2</number> A 
person to be appointed as Member-Secretary shall be an Inspector-General of 
Forests or an Officer of equivalent rank in the Indian Forest Service, having at 
least ten years experience in a tiger reserve or wildlife 
management.
 
   

   </section></article> 

   

 <article><number>5</number> Terms and other conditions of service of 
Member-Secretary.—The Member-Secretary of the Tiger Conservation 
Authority, subject to the provisions contained in the proviso to sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> 
of section 38N of the Act, shall be entitled to the salary in the pay scale of 
rupees 18400-500-22400/- and shall also be entitled to such allowances, leave, 
provident fund, pension and other retirement benefits, official accommodation 
and medical facilities as are for the time being admissible to the officers of 
the Central Government belonging to Group ‘A’ of the corresponding scale of 
pay.
 
   
</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>