<act><tid>1421454</tid>
<title>THE <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> BANARAS] HINDU UNIVERSITY ACT, <year>1915</year></title>

ACT NO. 16 OF <year>1915</year>
[ 1st October, <year>1915</year>.]

An Act to establish and incorporate a teaching and residential Hindu 
University at <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Banaras].

WHEREAS it is expedient to establish and incorporate a teaching 
and residential Hindu University at <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Banaras], and to dissolve the 
Hindu University Society, a Society registered under the Societies 
Registration Act, <year>1860</year> (21 of <year>1860</year>), and to transfer to, and vest in, 
the said University all property and rights now vested in the said 
Society; It is hereby enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>1366277</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1965024</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Banaras] Hindu University Act, <year>1915</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>438291</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> date as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>519767</tid>
<number> 2</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1510966</tid>
<number>a</number>" Academic Council" means the Academic Council of the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>410062</tid>
<number>b</number>" College" means a college or teaching institution 
 (other than a secondary, primary or infant school or  
  pathasala) maintained, by, or admitted to the 
privileges of, the University;

</section>

<section><tid>398899</tid>
<number>c</number>" Court" means the University Court;

</section>

<section><tid>1368202</tid>
<number>d</number>" Executive Council" means the University Executive 
Council;

</section>

<section><tid>63300</tid>
<number>e</number>" Faculty" means a Faculty of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1270838</tid>
<number>f</number>" Ordinances" means the Ordinances of the University for 
the time being in force;

</section>

<section><tid>1501974</tid>
<number>g</number>" Regulations" means the Regulations of the University 
for the time being in force;

</section>

<section><tid>1238597</tid>
<number>h</number>" Statutes" means the Statutes of the University for the 
time being in force;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>24</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 55 of <year>1951</year>, s. 2, for" Benares". 
2.  1st April, <year>1916</year>, see Gazette of India, <year>1916</year>, Pt. I, p. 352. 
3. Subs. by Act 52 of <year>1966</year>, s. 2, for the former section (w. e. f. 31-  
  12- <year>1966</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>742226</tid>
<number>i</number>" Teacher" means a salaried professor, reader, lecturer 
or tutor who imparts instruction in a Faculty of, or in 
a college maintained by, the University and includes 
any other person who is declared to be a teacher by the 
Academic Council;

</section>

<section><tid>1943656</tid>
<number>j</number>" University" means the Banaras Hindu University.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>515029</tid>
<number> 3</number> Incorporation. <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<section><tid>160397</tid>
<number>1</number>The Chancellor and the Vice- Chancellor  
and the members of the Court, the Executive Council and the Academic 
Council, for the time being, shall be a body corporate by the name of 
the Banaras Hindu University.]

</section>

<section><tid>1764487</tid>
<number>2</number>The University shall have perpetual succession and a common 
seal, and shall sue, and be sued, by the name first aforesaid.
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>918255</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> University open to all classes, castes and creeds. The 
University shall be open to persons of either sex and of whatever 
race, creed, caste or class, and it shall not be lawful for the 
University to adopt or impose on any person any test whatsoever of 
religious belief or profession in order to entitle him to be admitted 
therein, as a teacher or student, or to hold any office therein, or to 
graduate thereat, or to enjoy or exercise any privilege thereof, 
except in respect of any particular benefaction accepted by the 
University, where such test is made a condition thereof by any 
testamentary or other instrument creating such benefaction:
Provided that nothing in this section shall be deemed to prevent 
religious instruction being given in the manner prescribed by the 
Ordinances <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> to those who, or, in the case of minors, whose parents 
or guardians, have given their consent thereto in writing.].



</article>



<article><tid>864675</tid>
<number> 4A</number> Powers of the University. The University shall have the 
following powers, namely:-
<section><tid>1036768</tid>
<number>1</number>to provide for instruction in such branches of learning 
as the University may think fit, and to make provision 
for research and for the advancement and dissemination 
of knowledge;

</section>

<section><tid>1581057</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> to promote the study of religion, literature, 
history, science and art of Vedic, Hindu, Buddhist, 
Jain, Islamic. Sikh, Christian, Zoroastrian and other 
civilisations and cultures;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>25</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 52 of <year>1966</year>, s. 3, for sub- section (1)  (w. e. f. 31- 12-  
  <year>1966</year>). 
2. Sub- section (3) omitted by s. 3, ibid. (w. e. f. 31- 12- <year>1966</year>). 
3. Subs. by Act 55 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3, for ss. 4, 5 and 6. 
4. Subs. by Act 52 of <year>1966</year>, s. 4, for" to those who have consented 
to receive it" (w. e. f. 31- 12- <year>1966</year>). 
5. Subs. by s. 5, ibid., for clauses (2) and (3)  (w. e. f. 31- 12-  
  <year>1966</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1095241</tid>
<number>3</number>to hold examinations and to grant diplomas and 
certificates, and confer degrees and other academic 
distinctions to and on persons--

<subsection><tid>1140328</tid>
<number>a</number>who shall have pursued a course of study in 
the University or in a college and passed the 
examination or who shall have carried on research work 
in the manner prescribed by the Ordinances, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1967357</tid>
<number>b</number>who are teachers of the University or any 
college under conditions laid down in the Statutes or 
the Ordinances and shall have passed the examinations 
of the University under like conditions, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1903270</tid>
<number>c</number>who, being women, shall have pursued a course 
of private study in subjects provided for by the 
Ordinances and shall have passed the examinations of 
the University in their subjects under conditions laid 
down in the Ordinances;]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1912219</tid>
<number>4</number>to confer honorary degrees or other distinctions in the 
manner laid down in the Statutes;

</section>

<section><tid>1040205</tid>
<number>5</number>to grant such diplomas <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or certificates] to, and to 
provide such lectures and instruction for, persons not 
being members of the University as the University may 
determine;

</section>

<section><tid>1585456</tid>
<number>5A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> to withdraw degrees, diplomas, certificates and 
other academic distinctions;]

</section>

<section><tid>107413</tid>
<number>6</number>to co- operate with other Universities and authorities 
in such manner and for such purposes as the University 
may determine;

</section>

<section><tid>1270285</tid>
<number>7</number>to institute professorships, readerships, lecturerships 
and other teaching posts required by the University and 
to appoint persons to such professorships, readerships, 
lecturerships and other posts;

</section>

<section><tid>228959</tid>
<number>8</number>to institute and award fellowships (including  
  travelling fellowships) scholarships, studentships, 
exhibitions and prizes in accordance with the Statutes 
and the Ordinances;

</section>

<section><tid>37027</tid>
<number>9</number>to institute and maintain halls and hostels and to 
recognise places of residence for students of the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>468405</tid>
<number>9A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> to institute, establish, maintain, reconstitute, 
amalgamate, divide or abolish departments, faculties or 
colleges
<pagefootnote><pagenum>26</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 52 of <year>1966</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 31- 12- <year>1966</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


and carry out inspection thereof and inquiry in 
relation thereto;]


</section>

<section><tid>425023</tid>
<number>10</number>to demand and receive such fees and other charges as 
may be prescribed by the Ordinances;

</section>

<section><tid>528504</tid>
<number>11</number>to supervise and control the residence and to regulate 
the discipline of students of the University, and to 
make arrangements for promoting their health <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> and 
welfare];

</section>

<section><tid>741134</tid>
<number>12</number>to make special arrangements in respect of the 
residence, discipline, and teaching of women students;

</section>

<section><tid>630664</tid>
<number>12A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> to regulate and enforce discipline among salaried 
officers, teachers and other employees of the 
University in accordance with the Statutes and 
Ordinances;]

</section>

<section><tid>1359190</tid>
<number>13</number>to create administrative, ministerial and other 
necessary posts and to make appointments thereto; <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>

</section>

<section><tid>174308</tid>
<number>13A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> to acquire, hold, manage and dispose of property, 
movable or immovable, including trust or endowed 
property, for the purposes of the University;]

</section>

<section><tid>1686445</tid>
<number>13B</number>with the approval of the Central Government, to borrow 
on the security of the property of the University, 
money for the purpose of the University;]

</section>

<section><tid>1793815</tid>
<number>14</number>to do all such other acts and things, whether 
incidental to the powers aforesaid or not, as may be 
requisite in order to further the objects of the 
University.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>294059</tid>
<number> 5</number> Visitor.
<section><tid>934020</tid>
<number>1</number>The President of India shall be the Visitor of  
the University.

</section>

<section><tid>568008</tid>
<number>2</number>The Visitor shall have the right to cause an inspection to be 
made, by such person or persons as he may direct, of the University, 
its buildings, laboratories and equipment <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> of any college] and of 
any institution maintained by the University, and also of the 
examinations, teaching and other work conducted or done by the 
University and to cause an inquiry to be made in like manner in 
respect of any matter connected with the University.

</section>

<section><tid>1574855</tid>
<number>3</number>The Visitor shall in every case give notice to the University 
of his intention to cause an inspection or inquiry to be made, and the 
University shall be entitled to appoint a representative who shall 
have the right to be present and be heard at such inspection or 
inquiry.

</section>

<section><tid>135867</tid>
<number>4</number>The Visitor may address the Vice- Chancellor with reference to 
the result of such inspection and inquiry, and the Vice- Chancellor
<pagefootnote><pagenum>27</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 52 of <year>1966</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 31- 12- <year>1966</year>). 
2. The word" and" omitted by s. 5, ibid. (w. e. f. 31- 12- <year>1966</year>). 
3. Ins. by s. 6, ibid. (w. e. f. 31- 12- <year>1966</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


shall communicate to the Executive Council the views of the Visitor 
with such advice as the Visitor may offer upon the action to be taken 
thereon.


</section>

<section><tid>658594</tid>
<number>5</number>The Executive Council shall communicate through the Vice 
Chancellor to the Visitor such action, if any, as it is proposed to 
take or has been taken upon the result of such inspection or inquiry.

</section>

<section><tid>800747</tid>
<number>6</number>Where the Executive Council does not, within a reasonable 
time, take action to the satisfaction of the Visitor, the Visitor may, 
after considering any explanation furnished or representation made by 
the Executive Council, issue such directions as he may think fit and 
the Executive Council shall be bound to comply with such directions.

</section>

<section><tid>445942</tid>
<number>7</number>Without prejudice to the foregoing provisions of this section 
the Visitor may, by order in writing, annul any proceeding of the 
University which is not in conformity with this Act, the Statutes or 
the Ordinances:
Provided that before making any such order, he shall call upon 
the University to show cause why such an order should not be made and 
if any cause is shown within a reasonable time, shall consider the 
same.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1436392</tid>
<number> 6</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Officers of the University. The following shall be the 
officers of the University, namely:-
<section><tid>1672036</tid>
<number>a</number>the Chancellor,

</section>

<section><tid>1774061</tid>
<number>b</number>the Vice- Chancellor,

</section>

<section><tid>309865</tid>
<number>c</number>the Rector,

</section>

<section><tid>366966</tid>
<number>d</number>the Registrar,

</section>

<section><tid>1576658</tid>
<number>e</number>the Finance Officer,

</section>

<section><tid>30729</tid>
<number>f</number>the Deans of Faculties,

</section>

<section><tid>391304</tid>
<number>g</number>the Dean of Students,

</section>

<section><tid>821960</tid>
<number>h</number>the Librarian,

</section>

<section><tid>1876068</tid>
<number>i</number>the Chief Proctor,

</section>

<section><tid>1878154</tid>
<number>j</number>such other persons in the service of the University as 
may be declared by the Statutes to be the officers of 
the University.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1037251</tid>
<number> 7</number> Chancellor.
<section><tid>344785</tid>
<number>1</number>The Chancellor shall be elected by the Court  
and shall hold office for a term of three years:
<pagefootnote><pagenum>28</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 52 of <year>1966</year>, s. 7, for sections 6 and 7 (w. e. f 31- 12-  
  <year>1966</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Provided that the Chancellor shall, notwithstanding the 
expiration of his term, continue to hold his office until the election 
of his successor.


</section>

<section><tid>301010</tid>
<number>2</number>If the office of the Chancellor becomes vacant, the functions 
of his office shall, until some person is elected under sub- section 
 (1) to the vacant office, be performed by the Vice- Chancellor.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1631059</tid>
<number> 7A</number> Powers of Chancellor.
<section><tid>972191</tid>
<number>1</number>The Chancellor shall, by virtue of  
his office, be the Head of the University.

</section>

<section><tid>1222396</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chancellor shall, if present, preside at convocation of 
the University for conferring degrees and at all meetings of the 
Court.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>710150</tid>
<number> 7B</number> Vice- Chancellor. <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<section><tid>9270</tid>
<number>1</number>The Vice- Chancellor shall be  
appointed by the Visitor on the recommendation of a Selection 
Committee constituted by the Visitor for the purpose:
Provided that, if the Visitor does not approve of such 
recommendation, he may call for one or more fresh recommendations.]


</section>

<section><tid>1803530</tid>
<number>3</number>The Vice- Chancellor shall be a whole- time salaried officer of 
the University.

</section>

<section><tid>385969</tid>
<number>4</number>The Vice- Chancellor shall hold office for a term of <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> three 
years] from the date on which he enters upon his office and shall, on 
the expiration of his term of office, be <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> eligible for re- 
appointment to that office for a second term]:
Provided that the Vice- Chancellor shall, notwithstanding the 
expiration of his term, continue to hold his office until his 
successor is appointed and enters upon his office.


</section>

<section><tid>466069</tid>
<number>5</number>The emoluments and other terms and conditions of service of 
the Vice- Chancellor shall be prescribed by the Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>922247</tid>
<number>6</number>If the office of the Vice- Chancellor becomes vacant, the 
functions of his office shall, until some person is appointed under 
sub- section (1) to the vacant office, be performed by the Rector:
Provided that if there is no Rector, the Registrar shall carry on 
the current duties of the Vice- Chancellor and call a meeting of the 
Executive Council forthwith and take its directions for the carrying 
on of the work of the University.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>29</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 34 of <year>1969</year>, s. 2, for sub- sections (1) and (2) 
 (w. e. f. 5- 9- <year>1969</year>). 
2. Subs. by s. 2, ibid., for" five years" (w. e. f 5- 9- <year>1969</year>). 
3. Subs. by s. 2, ibid., for" ineligible for reappointment to that 
office" (w. e. f. 5- 9- <year>1969</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1147111</tid>
<number> 7C</number> Powers and duties of Vice- Chancellor.
<section><tid>978196</tid>
<number>1</number>The Vice- Chancellor  
who shall be the principal executive and academic officer of the 
University, shall take rank next to the Chancellor and shall exercise 
general supervision and control over the affairs of the University and 
give effect to the decisions of its authorities.

</section>

<section><tid>1775116</tid>
<number>2</number>The Vice- Chancellor shall be the ex officio Chairman of the 
Executive Council, the Academic Council <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> and the Finance 
Committee and shall, in the absence of the Chancellor, preside at any 
convocation of the University for conferring degrees and also at any 
meeting of the Court; he shall be entitled to be present at and to 
address any meeting of any authority or board or committee of the 
University but shall not be entitled to vote thereat unless he is a 
member of such authority or board or committee.

</section>

<section><tid>1565330</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall be the duty of the Vice- Chancellor to see that the 
provisions of this Act, the Statutes, the Ordinances and the 
Regulations are duly observed.

</section>

<section><tid>1860723</tid>
<number>4</number>The Vice- Chancellor shall have power to convene meetings of 
the Court, the Executive Council <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> and the Academic Council] and 
shall perform all such acts as may be necessary to carry out the 
provisions of this Act, the Statutes and the Ordinances.

</section>

<section><tid>1918624</tid>
<number>5</number>If, in the opinion of the Vice- Chancellor, any emergency has 
arisen which requires immediate action to be taken, the Vice- 
Chancellor shall take such action as he deems necessary and shall 
report the same for approval at the next meeting to the authority 
which, in the ordinary course, would have dealt with the matter:
Provided that, if the action taken by the Vice- Chancellor is not 
approved by the authority concerned, he may refer the matter to the 
Visitor, whose decision thereon shall be final:

Provided further that, where any such action taken by the Vice- 
Chancellor affects any person in the service of the University, such 
person shall be entitled to prefer, within thirty days from the date 
on which he receives notice of such action, an appeal to the Executive 
Council.


</section>

<section><tid>26202</tid>
<number>6</number>The Vice- Chancellor shall exercise such other powers as may 
be prescribed by the Statutes, the Ordinances or the Regulations.]]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1465530</tid>
<number>8</number>Powers and duties of officers, terms of office and filling of 
casual vacancies. Subject to the provisions of this Act, the powers 
and duties of <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the other officers of the University], the term for 
which they shall
<pagefootnote><pagenum>30</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words", the Standing Committee of the Academic Council" 
omitted by Act 34 of <year>1969</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 5- 9- <year>1969</year>). 
2. Subs. by s. 3, ibid., for", the Academic Council and the 
Standing Committee of the Academic Council" (w. e. f. 5- 9- <year>1969</year>). 
3. Subs. by Act 52 of <year>1966</year>, s. 8, for" the officers of the 
University" (w. e. f. 31- 12- <year>1966</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


hold office, and the filling up of casual vacancies in such offices, 
shall be provided for by the Statutes.



</article>



<article><tid>668067</tid>
<number> 8A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Authorities of the University. The following shall be the 
authorities of the University, namely:-
<section><tid>268224</tid>
<number>a</number>the Court,

</section>

<section><tid>1464680</tid>
<number>b</number>the Executive Council,

</section>

<section><tid>1871711</tid>
<number>c</number>the Academic Council,

</section>

<section><tid>1450816</tid>
<number>d</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>

</section>

<section><tid>782641</tid>
<number>e</number>the Finance Committee,

</section>

<section><tid>450743</tid>
<number>f</number>the Faculties,

</section>

<section><tid>884731</tid>
<number>g</number>such other authorities as may be declared by the 
Statutes to be the authorities of the University.]









</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1397459</tid>
<number> 10</number> Executive Council.
<section><tid>1919238</tid>
<number>1</number>The Executive Council shall, subject  
to the control of the <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> visitor], be the executive body of the 
University and shall have charge of the management and administration 
of the revenue and property of the University and the conduct of all 
administrative affairs of the University not otherwise provided for.

</section>

<section><tid>373230</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Executive Council 
shall exercise such other powers and perform such other duties as may 
be conferred or imposed on it by the Statutes or the Ordinances.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1261890</tid>
<number> 11</number> Academic Council.
<section><tid>745710</tid>
<number>1</number>The <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Academic Council] shall be the  
academic body of the University and, subject to the Act, the Statutes 
and <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> Ordinances.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>31</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 52 of <year>1966</year>, s. 9 (w. e. f. 31- 12- <year>1966</year>). 
2. Cl. (d) omitted by Act 34 of <year>1969</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 5- 9- <year>1969</year>). 
3. Subs. by Act 52 of <year>1966</year>, s. 10, for ss. 9 and 10 (w. e. f. 31- 12-  
  <year>1966</year>). 
4. Subs. by Act 34 of <year>1969</year>, s. 5, for ss. 9 and 9A (w. e. f. 5- 9-  
  <year>1969</year>). 
5. Subs. by s. 6, ibid., for" Court" (w. e. f. 5- 9- <year>1969</year>). 
6. Subs. by Act 55 of <year>1951</year>, s. 2, for" Senate". 
7. Subs. by s. 2, ibid., for" Regulations".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


shall have <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> charge of the organization of <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> study and research] 
in the University and the Colleges, the courses of study and the 
examination <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> of students and the conferment of ordinary and 
honorary degrees <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> and shall exercise such other powers and perform 
such other duties as may be conferred or imposed on it by the Statutes 
and Ordinances, and shall have the right to advise the Executive 
Council on all academic matters.]

<footcitenum>5</footcitenum>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1278912</tid>
<number>12</number>[ The Standing Committee of the Academic Council.] Rep. by the 
Banaras Hindu University (Amendment) Act, <year>1969</year> (34 of <year>1969</year>), s. 7 
 (w. e. f. 5- 9- <year>1969</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>1236388</tid>
<number>12A</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Other authorities. Subject to the provisions of this Act, 
the functions, powers and duties of the other authorities of the 
University shall be provided for by the Statutes.


</article>



<article><tid>657322</tid>
<number> 12B</number> Disqualifications.
<section><tid>234606</tid>
<number>1</number>A person shall be disqualified for  
being chosen as, and for being, a member of any of the authorities of 
the University--

<subsection><tid>510582</tid>
<number>a</number>if he is of unsound mind or is a deaf- mute or suffers 
from contagious leprosy;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>282668</tid>
<number>b</number>if he is an undischarged insolvent;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>568545</tid>
<number>c</number>if he has been convicted by a court of law of an 
offence involving moral turpitude and sentenced in 
respect thereof to imprisonment for not less than six 
months.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>158973</tid>
<number>2</number>If any question arises as to whether a person is or had been 
subjected to any of the disqualifications mentioned in sub- section (1) 
the question shall be referred for the decision of the Visitor and his 
decision shall be final, and no suit or other proceeding shall lie in 
any court of law against such decision.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>385743</tid>
<number> 13</number> Audit of accounts. <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>
<section><tid>810199</tid>
<number>1</number>The accounts of the University  
shall, once at least in every year and at intervals of not more than 
fifteen months, be audited by the Comptroller and Auditor- General of 
India.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>32</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The word" entire" omitted by Act 55 of <year>1951</year>, s. 7. 
2. Subs. by Act 52 of <year>1966</year>, s. 11, for" instruction" (w. e. f. 31- 12-  
  <year>1966</year>). 
3. The words" and discipline" omitted by s. 11, ibid. (w. e. f. 31- 12-  
  <year>1966</year>). 
4. Ins. by s. 11, ibid. (w. e. f. 31- 12- <year>1966</year>). 
5. Sub- section (2) omitted by Act 55 of <year>1951</year>, s. 7. 
6. Subs. by Act. 52 of <year>1966</year>, s. 12, for section 12A (w. e. f 31- 12-  
  <year>1966</year>). 
7. Subs. by Act 55 of <year>1951</year>, s. 9, for former sub- section (1).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1862955</tid>
<number>2</number>The accounts, when audited, shall be published in the 
Official Gazette and a copy of the accounts, together with the 
auditor' s reports, shall be <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> submitted] <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> to the Visitor].



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1696722</tid>
<number> 14</number> Permanent reserve to cover recurring charges. The University 
shall invest, and keep invested, in securities in which trust funds 
may be invested, in accordance with the provisions of the law relating 
to trusts in <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> India], a sum of <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> forty- five lakhs of rupees] as a 
permanent endowment to meet the recurring charges of the University 
other than charges in respect of scholarships, prizes and rewards:
Provided that--

<section><tid>801646</tid>
<number>1</number>any Government securities, as defined by the Indian 
Securities Act, <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> <year>1920</year> (10 of <year>1920</year>),] which may be 
held by the University shall, for the purpose of this 
section, be reckoned at their face- value; and

</section>

<section><tid>332485</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum> the aforesaid sum of forty- five lakhs of rupees 
shall be reduced by such sum as, at the commencement of 
the Banaras Hindu University (Amendment) Act, <year>1966</year> 
 (52 of <year>1966</year>),] the Central Government shall, by order 
in writing, declare to be the total capitalised value, 
for the purposes of this section--

<subsection><tid>375030</tid>
<number>a</number>of all permanent recurring grants of money 
which have been made to the University <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> by any ruler 
of any Indian State]; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>167314</tid>
<number>b</number>of the total income accruing from immovable 
property which has been transferred to the University.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>180099</tid>
<number> 15</number> Maintenance and admission to privileges of Colleges.
<section><tid>1677970</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Central Hindu College, <footcitenum>8</footcitenum> Banaras], shall, from such <footcitenum>9</footcitenum> date as the 
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
appoint in this behalf, be deemed to be a College maintained by the 
University, and the University may found and maintain
<pagefootnote><pagenum>33</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 52 of <year>1966</year>, s. 13, for" submitted to the Visitor" 
 (w. e. f. 31- 12- <year>1966</year>). 
2. The words" to the Court and" omitted by Act 34 of <year>1969</year>, s. 8 
 (w. e. f. 5- 9- <year>1969</year>). 
3. Subs. by Act 55 of <year>1951</year>, s. 10, for" the States". 
4. Subs. by Act 52 of <year>1966</year>, s. 14, for" fifty lakhs of rupees" 
 (w. e. f. 31- 12- <year>1966</year>). 
5. Subs. by s. 14, ibid., for" <year>1886</year>" (w. e. f. 31- 12- <year>1966</year>.  
6. Subs. by s. 14, ibid., for" the aforesaid sum of fifty lakhs 
shall be reduced by such sum as, at the commencement of this act" 
 (w. e. f. 31- 12- <year>1966</year>). 
7. Subs. by s. 14, ibid., for" by any Indian Prince or Chief" (w. e. f  
  31- 12- <year>1966</year>). 
8. Subs. by Act 55 of <year>1951</year>, s. 2, for" Benares". 
9.  1st October <year>1917</year>, see Gazette of India, <year>1917</year>, Pt. I, p. 1641.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


other colleges and <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> institutions including High Schools, within a 
radius of fifteen miles from the main temple of the University] for 
the purposes of carrying out instruction and research.


</section>

<section><tid>474061</tid>
<number>1A</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> The University may also found and maintain (within or  
  beyond the aforementioned limits) special centres and laboratories for 
research in Humanities, Science and Technology, Education, Medicine 
and other professional subjects and in other spheres of learning and 
knowledge.]

</section>

<section><tid>1251182</tid>
<number>2</number>With the approval of the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Academic Council] and the 
sanction of the Visitor, and subject to the Statutes and 
 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Ordinances] the University may admit colleges and <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> institutions 
including High Schools, within the aforementioned limits] to such 
privileges of the University, subject to such conditions, as it thinks 
fit:
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Provided that no new college or institution started after the 
commencement of the Banaras Hindu University (Amendment) Act, <year>1966</year> 
 (52 of <year>1966</year>), shall be admitted to any such privilege of the 
University.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1910255</tid>
<number>16</number>Recognition of degrees. The degrees, diplomas, certificates 
and other academic distinctions granted by the University shall be 
recognised by <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> the Central and State Governments] to the same extent 
and in the same manner as the corresponding degrees, diplomas, 
certificates and other academic distinctions granted by any other 
University incorporated by <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> a Central Act.].


</article>



<article><tid>1775574</tid>
<number>16A</number><footcitenum>8</footcitenum> Pension Provident Fund or insurance scheme. The 
University shall constitute for the benefit of its officers, teachers 
and other <footcitenum>9</footcitenum> employees] such pension or provident fund <footcitenum>10</footcitenum> or provide 
such insurance scheme] as it may deem fit in such manner and subject 
to such conditions as may be prescribed by the Statutes.]


</article>



<article><tid>1236972</tid>
<number> 16B</number> <footcitenum>11</footcitenum> Conditions of service of officers and teachers.
<section><tid>563218</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Every salaried officer and teacher of the University shall be 
appointed under a written contract, which shall be lodged with the 
University and a copy of which shall be furnished to the officer or 
teacher concerned.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>34</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 55 of <year>1951</year>, s. 11, for" institutions in Benares". 
2. Ins. by Act 52 of <year>1966</year>, s. 15 (w. e. f. 31- 12- <year>1966</year>). 
3. Subs. by Act 55 of <year>1951</year>, s. 2, for" senate". 
4. Subs. by s. 2, ibid., for" Regulations". 
5. Ins. by Act 52 of <year>1966</year>, s. 15 (w. e. f. 31- 12- <year>1966</year>). 
6. Subs. by A. O. <year>1948</year>, for" any Government in British India". 
7. Subs. by A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" an act of the Central Legislature". 
8. Ins. by Act 29 of <year>1930</year>, s. 4. 
9. Subs. by Act 52 of <year>1966</year>, s. 16, for" servants" (w. e. f. 31- 12-  
  <year>1966</year>). 
10. Ins. by Act 55 of <year>1951</year>, s. 12. 
11. Ins. by Act 52 of <year>1966</year>, s. 17 (w. e. f 31- 12- <year>1966</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>230118</tid>
<number>2</number>Any dispute arising out of a contract between the University 
and any of its officers or teachers shall, at the request of the 
officer or teacher concerned or at the instance of the University, be 
referred to a Tribunal of Arbitration consisting of one member 
appointed by the Executive Council, one member nominated by the 
officer or the teacher concerned and an umpire appointed by the 
Visitor.

</section>

<section><tid>1108894</tid>
<number>3</number>The decision of the Tribunal of Arbitration shall be final 
and shall not be questioned in any court of law.

</section>

<section><tid>1475014</tid>
<number>4</number>No suit or proceeding shall lie in any court of law in 
respect of any matter which is required by sub- section (2) to be 
referred to the Tribunal of Arbitration.

</section>

<section><tid>442272</tid>
<number>5</number>The Tribunal of Arbitration shall have power to regulate its 
own procedure.

</section>

<section><tid>1362401</tid>
<number>6</number>Nothing contained in any law for the time being in force 
relating to arbitration shall apply to arbitrations under this 
section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>196677</tid>
<number> 16C</number> Proceedings not to be invalidated by vacancies etc. No act 
or proceedings of any authority or board or committee of the 
University shall be invalid merely by reason of--
<section><tid>994364</tid>
<number>a</number>any vacancy in, or defect in the constitution thereof, 
or

</section>

<section><tid>865538</tid>
<number>b</number>any defect in the election, nomination or appointment 
of a person acting as a member thereof, or

</section>

<section><tid>573867</tid>
<number>c</number>any irregularity in its procedure not affecting the 
merits of the case.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>121945</tid>
<number>16D</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit, 
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any officer, 
teacher or other employee of the University for anything which is in 
good faith done or intended to be done by him under this Act or the 
Statutes or the Ordinances or the Regulations.]


</article>



<article><tid>77046</tid>
<number> 17</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Statutes.
<section><tid>1836949</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the  
Statutes may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:- 
-

<subsection><tid>110739</tid>
<number>a</number>the constitution of the Court and the constitution, 
powers and duties of the other authorities of the 
University other than the powers and duties provided 
for in this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1474756</tid>
<number>b</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the appointment by election, nomination or 
otherwise] of members of the authorities of the 
University, their continuance in office, the filling of 
vacancies of members thereof and all other matters 
relating to the authorities;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>35</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 52 of <year>1966</year>, s. 18, for section 17 (w. e. f 31- 12-  
  <year>1966</year>). 
2. Subs. by Act 34 of <year>1969</year>, s. 9, for" the election and appointment" 
 (w. e. f. 5- 9- <year>1969</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>17814</tid>
<number>c</number>the appointment, powers and duties of the officers of 
the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1400911</tid>
<number>d</number>the institution of degrees, diplomas, certificates and 
other academic distinctions;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1164998</tid>
<number>e</number>the conferment of honorary degrees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1535650</tid>
<number>f</number>the holding of convocations to confer degrees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1028627</tid>
<number>g</number>the establishment, reconstitution, amalgamation, 
division or abolition of faculties, departments, 
hostels, colleges and institutions;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>42591</tid>
<number>h</number>the withdrawal of degrees, diplomas, certificates and 
other academic distinctions;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1930881</tid>
<number>i</number>conditions under which colleges and institutions 
including High Schools may be admitted to the 
privileges of the University and the withdrawal of such 
privileges;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>336449</tid>
<number>j</number>the institution of fellowships, scholarships, 
studentships, medals and prizes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>737896</tid>
<number>k</number>the registration of graduates and the maintenance of a 
register of registered graduates;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1715035</tid>
<number>l</number>the classification and the manner of appointment of 
teachers in the University and the colleges;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>44066</tid>
<number>m</number>the constitution of a pension or provident fund and the 
establishment of an insurance scheme for the benefit of 
the officers, teachers and other employees of the 
University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>262804</tid>
<number>n</number>the meetings of the Court, the Executive Council, the 
Academic Council, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Finance Committee or the 
Faculties, the quorum at such meetings and the 
procedure to be followed in the conduct of their 
business;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>146448</tid>
<number>o</number>the discipline of students;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1302752</tid>
<number>p</number>all other matters which are to be or may be provided 
for by the Statutes.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>117691</tid>
<number>2</number>The Statutes in force at the commencement of the Banaras 
Hindu University (Amendment) Act, <year>1966</year> (52 of <year>1966</year>), shall be those set 
out in the Schedule to this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>410564</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the Executive Council may, from time to time, make new or 
additional Statutes or may amend or repeal the Statutes.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>36</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" the Standing Committee of the Academic Council", 
omitted by Act 34 of <year>1969</year>, s. 9 (w. e. f. 5- 9- <year>1969</year>). 
2. Subs. by s. 9, ibid., for sub- sections (3), (4), (5) and (6) 
 (w. e. f. 5- 9- <year>1969</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>589045</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Every new Statute or addition to a Statute or any 
amendment or repeal of a Statute shall require the previous approval 
of the Visitor who may sanction or disallow it or remit it for further 
consideration.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>524332</tid>
<number> 18</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Ordinances
<section><tid>294041</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act and  
the Statutes, the Ordinances may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1879239</tid>
<number>a</number>the admission of students to the University and their 
enrolment as such;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>165221</tid>
<number>b</number>the courses of study to be laid down for all degrees, 
diplomas and certificates of the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1434498</tid>
<number>c</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the qualifications for admission to courses of study 
for degrees, diplomas, certificates and other academic 
distinctions and to examinations of the University and 
the award of degrees, diplomas, certificates and other 
academic distinctions;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>645301</tid>
<number>d</number>the fees to be charged for courses of study in the 
University and for admission to the examinations, 
degrees and diplomas of the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>843026</tid>
<number>e</number>the conditions of the award of fellowships, 
scholarships, studentships, exhibitions, medals and 
prizes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1418344</tid>
<number>f</number>the conduct of examinations, including the terms of 
office and manner of appointment and the duties of 
examining bodies, examiners and moderators;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1337542</tid>
<number>ff</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> the remuneration and allowances to examiners, 
moderators and other persons engaged in the business of 
the University;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>313315</tid>
<number>g</number>the maintenance of discipline among the students of the 
University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1587962</tid>
<number>h</number>the conditions of residence of students at the 
University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>898028</tid>
<number>i</number>the special arrangements, if any, which may be made for 
the residence, discipline and teaching of women 
students, and the prescribing for them of special 
courses to study:

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1186350</tid>
<number>j</number>the giving of religious instruction;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1865744</tid>
<number>k</number>the emoluments and the terms and conditions of service 
of <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> employees] of the University;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>36A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Re- numbered by Act 34 of <year>1969</year>, s. 9 (w. e. f. 5- 9- <year>1969</year>). 
2. Subs. by act 55 of <year>1951</year>, s. 14, for ss. 18 and 19. 
3. Subs. by act 52 of <year>1966</year>, s. 19, for clause (c)  (w. e. f. 31- 12-  
  <year>1966</year>). 
4. Ins. by s. 19, ibid. (w. e. f. 31- 12- <year>1966</year>). 
5. Subs. by s. 19, ibid., for" teachers" (w. e. f. 31- 12- <year>1966</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>799875</tid>
<number>l</number>the management of colleges and other institutions 
founded or maintained under sub- section (1) of section 
15;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1108396</tid>
<number>ll</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the meetings of any board or committee that may be 
set up under this Act or the Statutes, the quorum at 
such meetings and the procedure to be followed in the 
conduct of their business;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>105593</tid>
<number>m</number>the supervision and inspection of colleges and other 
institutions admitted to privileges of the University 
under sub- section (2) of section 15; <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>443762</tid>
<number>mm</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the powers and duties of teachers and salaried 
officers and the powers which may be delegated to them;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>944209</tid>
<number>mmm</number>the conditions and qualifications for the registration 
of graduates;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>292059</tid>
<number>n</number>all other matters which by this Act or the Statutes are 
to be or may be provided for by the Ordinances.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>918723</tid>
<number>2</number>The Regulations of the University as in force immediately 
before the commencement of the Banaras Hindu University (Amendment) 
Act, <year>1951</year> (55 of <year>1951</year>), shall be deemed to be the first Ordinances made 
under this section.

</section>

<section><tid>1653987</tid>
<number>3</number>The said Ordinances may be amended, repealed or added to at 
any time by the Executive Council:
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Provided that no Ordinance shall be made--


<subsection><tid>860850</tid>
<number>a</number>regarding the recognition of examinations of other 
Universities and institutions as equivalent to the 
University examinations, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>443152</tid>
<number>b</number>affecting the conditions, mode of appointment or duties 
of examiners or the conduct or standard of examinations 
or of any course of study,
unless a draft of such ordinance has been proposed by the Academic 
Council.]


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>850272</tid>
<number>4</number>The Executive Council shall not have power to amend any draft 
proposed by the Academic Council under the provisions of sub- section 
 (3) but may reject the proposal or return the draft to the Academic 
Council for reconsideration, either in whole or in part, together with 
any amendments which the Executive Council may suggest.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>36B</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 52 of <year>1966</year>, s. 19 (w. e. f. 31- 12- <year>1966</year>). 
2. The word" and" omitted by s. 19, ibid. (w. e. f. 31- 12- <year>1966</year>). 
3. Subs. by s. 19, ibid., for former proviso (w. e. f. 31- 12- <year>1966</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>516208</tid>
<number>5</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Where the Executive Council has rejected the draft of an 
Ordinance proposed by the Academic Council, the Academic Council may 
appeal to the Visitor who may pass such order thereon as he thinks 
fit.

</section>

<section><tid>299915</tid>
<number>6</number>All Ordinances made by the Executive Council shall be 
submitted, as soon may be, to the Visitor who may disallow any such 
Ordinance or remit it to the Executive Council for further 
consideration.

</section>

<section><tid>1273268</tid>
<number>7</number>The Visitor may, by order, direct that the operation of any 
Ordinance shall be suspended until he has had an opportunity of 
exercising his power of disallowance, and any order of suspension 
under this sub- section shall cease to have effect on the expiration of 
one month from the date of such order.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>722725</tid>
<number> 19</number> Power to make regulations.
<section><tid>472734</tid>
<number>1</number>The authorities of the  
University may make Regulations consistent with this Act, the Statutes 
and the Ordinances--

<subsection><tid>37806</tid>
<number>a</number>laying down the procedure to be observed at their 
meetings and the number of members required to form a 
quorum;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>218452</tid>
<number>b</number>providing for all matters which by this Act, the 
Statutes or the Ordinances are to be prescribed by 
Regulations; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1021024</tid>
<number>c</number>providing for all matters solely concerning such 
authorities or committees appointed by them and not 
provided for by this Act, the Statutes or the 
Ordinances.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1187709</tid>
<number>2</number>Every authority of the University shall make Regulations 
providing for the giving of notice to the members of such authority of 
the dates of meetings and of the business to be considered at meetings 
and for the keeping of a record of the proceedings of meetings.

</section>

<section><tid>1782756</tid>
<number>3</number>The Executive Council may direct the amendment, in such 
manner as it may specify, of any Regulation made under this section or 
the annulment of any such Regulation:
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Provided that any authority of the University which is 
dissatisfied with any such direction may, within two months of the 
date of such direction, appeal to the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Visitor], whose decision 
thereon shall be final.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>36C</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 34 of <year>1969</year>, s. 10, for sub- sections (5), (6), (7) and 
 (8)  (w. e. f 5- 9- <year>1969</year>). 
2. Proviso added by Act 52 of <year>1966</year>, s. 20 (w. e. f. 31- 12- <year>1966</year>). The 
former proviso was omitted by Act 34 of <year>1958</year>, s. 6. 
3. Subs. by Act 34 of <year>1969</year>, s. 11, for" Court" (w. e. f. 5- 9- <year>1969</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>527648</tid>
<number>19A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Constitution of boards and committees. Where any 
authority of the University is given power by this Act or by the 
Statutes to appoint boards or committees, such board or committee 
shall, unless there is some special provision to the contrary, consist 
of members of the authority concerned and of such other persons (if  
  any) as the authority in each case may think fit.]]


</article>



<article><tid>435452</tid>
<number> 20</number> Dissolution and transfer of property of the Hindu University 
Society.
<section><tid>1787948</tid>
<number>1</number>From the commencement of this Act, the Hindu University  
Society shall be dissolved, and all property, movable and immovable, 
and all rights, powers and privileges of the Hindu University society 
which, immediately before the commencement of this Act, belong to, or 
were vested in, the said Society, shall vest in the University, and 
shall be applied to the objects and purposes for which the University 
is incorporated.

</section>

<section><tid>930407</tid>
<number>2</number>From the commencement of this Act, all debts and liabilities 
of the said Society shall be transferred and attached to the 
University, and shall thereafter be discharged and satisfied by the 
University.

</section>

<section><tid>3130</tid>
<number>3</number>Any will, deed or other document, whether made or executed 
before or after the commencement of this Act, which contains any 
bequest, gift or trust in favour of the Central Hindu College or the 
said Society shall, on the commencement of this Act, be construed as 
if the University were therein named, instead of the said College or 
Society.

</section>

</article>



 </act>