<act><tid>975999</tid>
<title>THE PUNJAB LAWS ACT, <year>1872</year></title>

ACT NO. 4 OF <year>1872</year>
[ 28th March, <year>1872</year>.]

An Act for declaring which of certain rules, laws and regulations 
have the force of law in the Punjab and for other purposes.

Preamble.

WHEREAS certain rules, laws and regulations, made heretofore for 
the Punjab, acquired the force of law under the provisions of section 
 25 of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Indian Councils Act, <year>1861</year>; (24 and 25 Vict., c. 67.) and 
whereas it is expedient to declare which of the said rules, laws and 
regulations shall henceforth be in force in the Punjab, and to amend, 
consolidate or repeal others of the said rules, orders and 
regulations; It is hereby enacted as follows:--





<article><tid>779748</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Punjab Laws Act, <year>1872</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1339981</tid>
<number>2</number>Local extent. It extends to the territories <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> which, 
immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in the 
States of Punjab and Delhi], but not so as to alter the effect of any 
regulations made for any parts of the said territories under the 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Statute 33 Vict, ch. 3, section 1;
Commencment.

and it shall come into force on the first day of June, <year>1872</year>.



</article>



<article><tid>53792</tid>
<number>3</number>Enactments in force. The Regulations, Acts and Orders 
specified in the First Schedule hereto annexed are in force in the 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> territories to which this Act extends] to the extent specified in 
the third column of the said Schedule.


</article>



<article><tid>1676878</tid>
<number>4</number>[ Enactments repealed.] Rep. by the Second Repealing and 
Amending Act, <year>1914</year> (17 of <year>1914</year>), s. 3 and Sch. II.
Civil Judicature



</article>



<article><tid>134995</tid>
<number> 5</number> <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Decisions in certain cases to be according to Native law. 
In questions regarding succession, special property of females, 
betrothal, marriage, divorce, dower, adoption, guardianship, minority, 
bastardy, family relations, wills, legacies, gifts, partitions, or any 
religious usage or institution, the rule of decision shall be--
<section><tid>887152</tid>
<number>a</number>any custom applicable to the parties concerned, which is 
not contrary to justice, equity or good conscience, and
<pagefootnote><pagenum>16</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Rep. by the Government of India Act, <year>1915</year>. 
2. Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for 
" constituting the States of Punjab and Delhi". 
3. Subs., ibid., for" States of Punjab and Delhi". 
4. Subs. by Act 12 of <year>1878</year>, s. 1, for the original s. 5. The 
provisions of this section have been rep. in so far as they are 
inconsistent with those of the Muslim Personal Law (Shariat) 
Application Act, <year>1937</year> (26 of <year>1937</year>): see s. 6, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


has not been, by this or any other enactment, altered 
or abolished, and has not been declared to be void by 
any competent authority;


</section>

<section><tid>758468</tid>
<number>b</number>the Muhammadan law, in cases where the parties are 
Muhammadans, and the Hindu law, in cases where the 
parties are Hindus, except in so far as such law has 
been altered or abolished by legislative enactment, or 
is opposed to the provisions of this Act, or has been 
modified by any such custom as is above referred to.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1756227</tid>
<number>6</number>Decisions in cases not specially provided for. In cases not 
otherwise specially provided for, the Judges shall decide according to 
justice, equity and good conscience.


</article>



<article><tid>193682</tid>
<number>7</number>Local customs and mercantile usages when valid. All local 
customs and mercantile usages shall be regarded as valid, unless they 
are contrary to justice, equity or good conscience, or have, before 
the passing of this Act, been declared to be void by any competent 
authority.
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>

</article>



<article><tid>1836556</tid>
<number>8</number> 8, 8A to 8C[ Repealed.] <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
Pre- emption

</article>



<article><tid>941347</tid>
<number>9</number> (Rep. by the Punjab Pre- emption Act, <year>1905</year>)  (Punjab Act 2  
  of <year>1905</year>), s. 2 1.
Decrees concerning land



</article>



<article><tid>513854</tid>
<number>21</number>[ Copy of decrees affecting land to be forwarded to Deputy 
Commissioner.] Rep. by the Punjab Land Revenue Act, <year>1887</year> (17 of <year>1887</year>).
Insolvency

 22 t

Insolvency Rep. by the Provincial Insolvency Act.

 22 to 32. Insolvency Rep. by the Provincial Insolvency Act, <year>1907</year> 
 (3 of <year>1907</year>).



</article>



<article><tid>1892482</tid>
<number>33</number>[ Saving of previous insolvency proceedings.] Rep. by the 
Amending Act, <year>1891</year> (12 of <year>1891</year>).
Minors and the Court of Wards

 34 t

Rep. by the Punjab Court of Wards Act, <year>1903</year>

 34 to 38. Rep. by the Punjab Court of Wards Act, <year>1903</year> (Punjab Act  
  2 of <year>1903</year>), s. 2 (1).

<pagefootnote><pagenum>17</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ss. 8, 8A, 8B and 8C, which had been subs. for s. 8 by the Punjab 
Descent of Jaghirs Act, <year>1900</year> (Pun. 4 of <year>1900</year>), s. 2, and the heading 
" Descent of Jaghirs", rep. by the Punjab Jaghirs Act, <year>1941</year> (Pun. 5 of  
  <year>1941</year>), s. 13.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>309512</tid>
<number>39</number>Indian Penal Code to apply to offences committed previous to 
 1st January, <year>1862</year>. The provisions of the Indian Penal Code, with the 
exception of Chapter VI, shall be applicable to all offences committed 
before first January, <year>1862</year> (45 of <year>1860</year>), in territory which was, at 
the time of the commission of such offence, subject to the State 
Government of the Punjab:
Saving of privileges conferred on certain Chiefs.

Provided that nothing contained in this section shall affect any 
privilege conferred on certain Chiefs in the Punjab by the Central 
Government, or by the Board of Administration for the affairs of the 
Punjab, nor any indemnity or pardon granted by competent authority.



</article>



<article><tid>1470711</tid>
<number> 39A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Power to establish system of village- watchmen and 
municipal- watchmen, and to make rules. The State Government may 
establish a system of village- watchmen or municipal watchmen in any 
part of the territories under its administration, and in furtherance 
of this object may, from time to time, make rules to provide for the 
following matters:--
<section><tid>514569</tid>
<number>a</number>the definition of the limits of watchmen' s beats;

</section>

<section><tid>1013398</tid>
<number>b</number>the determination of the several grades of watchmen, and 
the number of each grade to be appointed to each beat;

</section>

<section><tid>1003568</tid>
<number>c</number>the appointment, suspension, dismissal and resignation 
of watchmen of each grade;

</section>

<section><tid>1636952</tid>
<number>d</number>the equipment and discipline of, and the control and 
supervision over, such watchmen;

</section>

<section><tid>213304</tid>
<number>e</number>the conferring upon them, and the exercise by them, of 
any powers and the enjoyment by them of any protection 
or privilege, which may be exercised and enjoyed by a 
police- officer under any law for the time being in 
force;

</section>

<section><tid>1359778</tid>
<number>f</number>the performance by them of such duties relating to 
police, sanitation or statistics, or for the benefit of 
the village communities or municipalities within their 
respective beats, as the State Government thinks fit;

</section>

<section><tid>70852</tid>
<number>g</number>the exercise of authority over, and the rendering of aid 
to, such watchmen by headmen of the villages or members 
of the Municipal Committees of the towns comprised in 
their respective beats;

</section>

<section><tid>437515</tid>
<number>h</number>the performance, by the headmen of villages comprised in 
the beat of any watchmen, of any of the duties of a 
village- watchman in aid of, or substitution for, such 
watchman;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>18</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ss. 39A and 39B were subs. by Act 24 of <year>1881</year>, s. 2, for ss. 39A 
and 39B.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>706070</tid>
<number>i</number>the exercise, by such village- headmen for the purposes 
referred to in clauses (g) and (h), or by members of 
Municipal Committees for the purposes referred to in 
clause (g) of this section, of any of the powers, and 
the enjoyment by such headmen or members of any 
privilege or protection, of a village- watchman, or a 
municipal- watchman, as the case may be;

</section>

<section><tid>1704938</tid>
<number>j</number>the determination of the rate at which, and the mode in 
which, watchmen shall be paid, and, in the case of 
village- watchmen, of the mode in which their pay, the 
expenses of their equipment, and other charges 
connected with the village- watchmen- system shall be 
provided for, whether out of cesses or funds already 
leviable or available in the villages comprised in the 
beat, or by a special tax in money or kind to be 
imposed on any class of persons residing or owning 
property in, or resorting to, such villages, or partly 
in one of these ways and partly in the other;

</section>

<section><tid>1460520</tid>
<number>k</number>the collection with or without the aid of the village- 
headmen, and by any process available for the 
realisation of the land- revenue, of any tax imposed 
under clause (j) of this section, and the application 
of, and the mode of accounting for, the same; and 
generally for

</section>

<section><tid>1745169</tid>
<number>l</number>the efficient working of the system of village- watchmen 
or municipal watchmen:
Provided--

first, that the rules to be made regarding the appointment 
of village- watchmen shall allow to the headmen of the 
villages comprised in the beat to which such a watchman 
is to be appointed a power of nomination to be 
exercised in such manner and subject to such reasonable 
conditions as may be prescribed by such rules;

secondly, that the rules to be made under clause (j) of this 
section with regard to village- watchmen shall include 
provisions for recording and securing due consideration 
of the views and opinions on the matters therein 
referred to of the headmen of the villages comprised in 
each beat.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>126762</tid>
<number>39B</number>Obligation to assist watchmen and headmen. Every person is 
bound to render to a village- watchman, or municipal watchman, or 
village- headman discharging the duties of a police- officer under the 
rules made hereunder, all the assistance which he is bound to render 
to a police- officer.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>19</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Person obstructing watchman or headman may be arrested without 
warrant.

Any person who obstructs such watchman or headman in the 
discharge of such duties may be arrested without warrant by a police- 
officer or by any watchman or village- headman empowered in this behalf 
by the State Government.]



</article>



<article><tid>1802612</tid>
<number>39C</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Power to direct local taxation for payment of police 
enrolled under Act 5 of <year>1861</year>. Whenever it seems to the State 
Government expedient that the duties of watch- and- ward and other 
internal police- service of any town or village not comprised within 
the limits of a municipality or within the limits of a village- 
watchman' s beat as defined under the power conferred by section 39A 
should be performed by police- officers enrolled under <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Act V of <year>1861</year>, 
the State Government may direct that the said service shall be so 
performed, and may also <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> direct that the charges for the time being 
fixed by such Government on account of such service shall be defrayed 
by taxes to be levied in such town or village.


</article>



<article><tid>1452698</tid>
<number>39D</number>Notice of taxes proposed to be levied. When the State 
Government has, under section 39C, directed that taxes shall be levied 
in any town or village, the Deputy Commissioner may from time to time 
issue a public notice in such town or village explaining the nature of 
the taxes he proposes to levy.
Objections to taxation.

Any inhabitant of such town or village objecting to the taxation 
thus proposed may, within fifteen days from the publication of such 
notice, send his objection in writing to the Deputy Commissioner.

Procedure thereon.

After the expiry of fifteen days from the publication of the 
notice, the Deputy Commissioner may submit for the information of the 
State Government a report of the proposal made by him. Such report 
shall contain specific mention of the objections (if any) urged to his 
proposal and his opinion on such objections.

No such tax shall be levied until it has, upon such report, been 
approved by the State Government.



</article>



<article><tid>830087</tid>
<number>39E</number>Power to fix rates of tax. When any such tax has been so 
approved by the State Government, the Deputy Commissioner may from 
time to time, subject to such rules consistent with this Act as the 
State Government may from time to time prescribe, determine the rates 
at which it is to be levied.


</article>



<article><tid>3096</tid>
<number>39F</number>Power to make rules for collection of taxes. The State 
Government may from time to time make rules to provide for the 
collection of such taxes by any process available
<pagefootnote><pagenum>20</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ss. 39C to 39G were ins. by Act 15 of <year>1875</year>, s. 2. 
2. The Police Act. 
3. The words" subject to the control of the G. G. in C." rep. by the 
A. O. <year>1937</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


for the realisation of the land- revenue and to regulate the 
application and mode of accounting for the same.



</article>



<article><tid>527171</tid>
<number>39G</number>[ Validation clause.] Rep. by the Amending Act, <year>1891</year> (12 of  
  <year>1891</year>).]
Honorary police- officers



</article>



<article><tid>1422492</tid>
<number>40</number>State Government may confer powers of police- officer. The 
State Government may, if it thinks fit, confer on any person any of 
the powers which may be exercised by a police- officer under any Act 
for the time being in force, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> and may withdraw any powers so 
conferred].
Track law



</article>



<article><tid>1328349</tid>
<number>41</number>Trackers may call for assistance in carrying on tracks. When 
an offence is, has been, or may reasonably be supposed to have been 
committed, and the tracks of the persons who may reasonably be 
supposed to have committed such offence, or of any animal or other 
property reasonably supposed to be connected with such offence, are 
followed to a spot within the immediate vicinity of a village, the 
person following such tracks may call upon any headman or village- 
watchman in such village to assist in carrying on the tracks.


</article>



<article><tid>1958788</tid>
<number>42</number>Penalty for withholding assistance or conniving at offence or 
escape. If such headman or watchman do not forthwith give such 
assistance, or if the inhabitants of such village do not afford full 
opportunity for search in their houses for the offenders, or, if from 
the circumstances of the case, there shall appear good reason to 
believe that the inhabitants of such village, or any of them were 
conniving at the offence or at the escape of the offenders, and such 
offenders cannot be traced beyond the village, the Magistrate of the 
district may, with the previous sanction of the Commissioner of the 
Division inflict a fine upon such village not exceeding five hundred 
rupees, except in the case of stolen property over five hundred rupees 
in value, in which case the fine shall not exceed the value of such 
property.
Appeal to High Court.

An appeal against all convictions under this section shall lie to 
the High Court of Punjab.

Fine may be awarded to injured parties, and fee to tracker.

The Magistrate may direct that the fine imposed under this 
section or any part thereof shall be awarded to any persons injured by 
such offence in compensation for such injury; and, in the case of 
stolen property recovered through the agency of a tracker, may direct 
that such property be not restored to its owner until he has paid to 
such

<pagefootnote><pagenum>21</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 12 of <year>1878</year>, s. 5.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


tracker such fee, not exceeding one- fourth part of the value of the 
stolen property, as to the said Magistrate seems fit.

Slaughter of kine



</article>



<article><tid>1607629</tid>
<number>43</number>Control of slaughter of kine and sale of beef. The slaughter 
of kine and the sale of beef shall not take place, except <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> subject 
to rules to be from time to time, either generally or in any 
particular instance, prescribed by the State Government.
Armed men and foreign vagrants



</article>



<article><tid>272303</tid>
<number>44</number>Control of entry into towns of bands of armed men. No band of 
armed men shall enter into any city or town, except <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> subject to 
rules to be from time to time, either generally or in any particular 
instance, prescribed by the State Government.


</article>



<article><tid>773946</tid>
<number>45</number>Powers of Magistrate of district as to foreign vagrants. The 
Magistrate of the district may, if he considers that any band of 
foreign vagrants is likely to occasion a breach of the peace or to 
commit any offence under the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>), prohibit 
such band from entering his district; or, if they are already in his 
district, may require them within a given time to leave it.


</article>



<article><tid>1800376</tid>
<number>46</number>Surveillance, etc., of band failing to comply with 
Magistrate' s order. If any such band fail to comply with the orders of 
the said Magistrate within the prescribed period, he shall report the 
matter to the State Government, and the State Government may give such 
directions for the surveillance, control or deportation of such band, 
as to it seems fit.
Miscellaneous



</article>



<article><tid>1153562</tid>
<number>47</number>Crossing of streams on buoys or skins. No person shall cross 
any river or stream on a buoy or inflated skin, nor shall have in his 
possession or custody any buoy or skin for the purpose of being used 
in crossing any river or stream, except <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> subject to rules to be 
from time to time, either generally or in any particular instance, 
prescribed by the State Government.


</article>



<article><tid>313975</tid>
<number>48</number>Use of pasturage or natural product of Government land. No 
person shall make use of the pasturage or other natural product of any 
land being the property of the Government, except with the consent and 
subject to rules to be from time to time, either generally or in any 
particular instance, prescribed by <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the Government concerned].
<pagefootnote><pagenum>22</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" with the consent and" omitted by Act 12 of <year>1878</year>, s. 6. 
2. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" the Govt. for whose purposes the 
land is vested in His Majesty".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>1969819</tid>
<number>49</number>[ Growing, selling or keeping opium.] Rep. by the Opium Act, 
 <year>1878</year> (1 of <year>1878</year>), s. 2 and Sch.


</article>



<article><tid>15763</tid>
<number>50</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Power to make rules as to matters mentioned in sections 43 
to 48. The State Government may from time to time make rules as to the 
matters mentioned in <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> section 43 to 48] inclusive.
Existing rules.

All existing rules upon such matters, which might have been made 
under this section had it been in force, shall be deemed to have been 
made hereunder.



</article>



<article><tid>682432</tid>
<number> 50A</number> Conditions of validity of rules hereafter made under this 
Act. <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Rules made under this Act shall not be valid unless]:--
<section><tid>1721012</tid>
<number>a</number>they are consistent with the laws for the time being in 
force in the <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> territories to which this Act extends];

</section>

<section><tid>659216</tid>
<number>b</number>they are published in the Official Gazette;
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>591298</tid>
<number>50B</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Penalty for contravention of rules. If any person 
contravenes the provisions of any rule made by the State Government 
under this Act, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term 
which may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to fifty 
rupees, or with both.]]


</article>



<article><tid>535876</tid>
<number>51</number><footcitenum>7</footcitenum> Republication of rules and orders. All rules which the 
State Government is empowered to issue under this Act, and all 
circulars issued by the High Court of Punjab, shall be republished 
from time to time by the State Government, and upon such 
republication, shall be arranged in the order of their subject- matter, 
and all such alterations or amendments as may have been made since the 
last preceding publication thereof, or may have become necessary or 
advisable, shall be embodied therewith, and upon such republication 
all such rules and circulars previously issued shall be repealed.]


</article>



<article><tid>1393004</tid>
<number>52</number>[ Recovery of advances made by Government.] Rep. by the 
Northern India Takkavi Act, <year>1879</year> (10 of <year>1879</year>).
<pagefootnote><pagenum>23</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ss. 50, 50A and 50B subs. by Act 15 of <year>1875</year>, s. 3, for the 
original s. 50, 
2. Subs. by Act 12 of <year>1891</year>, s. 2 and Sch. II, for" sections forty- 
three to forty- nine". 
3. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" All rules hereafter made by the L. 
G. under any power conferred by this Act shall be subject to the 
control of the G. G. in C. and no such rules shall be valid unless". 
4. Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" States 
of Punjab and Delhi". 
5. Cl. (c) rep. by Act 4 of <year>1914</year>. 
6. Subs. by Pun. Act 15 of <year>1961</year>, s. 2, for s. 50B. 
7. Subs. by Pun. Act 1 of <year>1910</year>, for the original s. 51.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



 </act>