<act><title>


The sales promotion employees (conditions of 
    service) 
    rules, 19761</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title.—These rules may be called 
    the Sales Promotion Employees (Conditions of Service) Rules, 1976.
  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In these rules 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>   “Act” means the Sales Promotion 
    Employees (Conditions of Service) Act, 1976 (11 of 1976);  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   “authorised medical attendant” means the 
    medical practitioner authorised by the employer for the purposes of any of 
    the provisions of the Act or the rules made thereunder;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   “casual leave” means leave to cover 
    casual absence of the sales promotion employees from duty for personal 
    reasons;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   “earned leave” means leave admissible 
    under clause (a) of section 4;  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   “extraordinary leave” means leave 
    granted to the sales promotion employee in special circumstances and when—  
 </section><section>
<number>a</number>   no other leave is admissible; or  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   other leave is admissible but the 
    employee applies in writing for the grant of extraordinary leave;  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   “Form” means a Form appended to these 
    rules;  
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>   “leave” means earned leave, leave on 
    medical certificate, extraordinary leave, leave not due, casual leave, study 
    leave or quarantine leave;   
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>   “leave not due” means leave which is not 
    due to the sales promotion employee but which may be granted to him in 
    anticipation of its being earned subsequently;  
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>   “leave on medical certificate” means 
    leave admissible under clause (b) of section 4;  
 </section><section>
<number>j</number>   “quarantine leave” means leave of 
    absence from duty by reason of the presence of an infectious disease in 
    household of the sales promotion employee;   
 </section><section>
<number>k</number>   “section” means a section of the Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>l</number>   “study leave” means leave granted to a 
    sales promotion employee to enable him to undertake a course of study.  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Applicability of this Chapter.—The 
    provisions of this Chapter shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
    inconsistent therewith contained in any agreement or Contract of service or 
    award applicable to a sales promotion employee:  
 
Provided that 
    where under any such agreement or contract of service or award a sales 
    promotion employees is entitled to benefits in respect of any matter 
    provided in this Chapter which are more favourable to him than those to 
    which he would be entitled to under this Chapter, the sales promotion 
    employee shall continue to be entitled to the more favourable benefits in 
    respect of that matter notwithstanding that he received benefits in respect 
    of other matters under these rules.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> Number 
    of holidays in a year.—A sales 
    promotion employee shall be entitled to ten holidays in a calendar year.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Compensatory holidays.—If a sales 
    promotion employee is required to attend to his duties on a holiday, a 
    compensatory holiday shall be given to him, within thirty days immediately 
    following the holiday, on a day mutually agreed upon by him and his 
    employer. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> Wages 
    for holidays.—A sales promotion 
    employee shall be entitled to wages of all holidays, as if he was on duty.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number> Wages 
    for weekly day of rest.—A sales 
    promotion employee shall be entitled to wages for the weekly day of rest as 
    if he was on duty.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Competent officers.—Every 
    establishment may designate one or more officers in the establishment as 
    competent officers for the purpose of this Chapter.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Application for leave.—
<section><number>1</number> A 
    sales promotion employee who desires to obtain leave of absence shall apply 
    in writing to the competent officer.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Application for leave, other than for casual leave, leave on medical 
    certificate and quarantine leave, shall be made not less then one month 
    before the date of commencement of leave, except in urgent or unforeseen 
    circumstances.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Recording of reason for refusal or postponement of leave.—If 
    leave is refused or postponed, the competent officer shall record the 
    reasons for such refusal or postponement as the case may be, and send a copy 
    of the order to the sales promotion employee concerned.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Affixing of holidays to leave.—Holidays, 
    other than weekly days of rest, shall not be prefixed or suffixed to any 
    leave without the prior sanction of the competent officer.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Holidays intervening during the period of leave.—A 
    holiday, including a weekly rest day, intervening during any leave, except 
    casual leave, granted under these rules shall form part of the period of 
    leave.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>13</number> Recall 
    before expiry of leave.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    establishment may recall a sales promotion employee on leave if the employer 
    considers it necessary to do so and in the event of such recall the employee 
    shall be entitled to travelling allowance for the journey undertaken by him 
    to join duty if at the time of recall the employee is spending his leave at 
    a place other than his headquarters.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    travelling allowance which shall be paid to a sales promotion employee under 
    sub-rule (1) shall be determined in accordance with the rules of the 
    establishment governing travelling allowance for journeys undertaken by the 
    employees in the course of their duties.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>14</number> Earned 
    leave and cash compensation for earned leave not availed of.— 
    
<section><number>1</number> The maximum limit up to which earned leave can be accumulated shall be 
    180 days out of which a sales promotion employee can avail himself of 90 
    days at a time:  
 
Provided that 
    where a sales promotion employee is suffering from any lingering illness 
    such as, tuberculosis, cancer, leprosy, heart disease or mental illness, or 
    any disability which prevents him from attending to his duties, the 
    competent authority may allow the sales promotion employee to avail himself 
    of earned leave for any period exceeding 90 days at a time.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When a 
    sales promotion employee voluntarily relinquishes his post, or retires from 
    service on reaching the age of superannuation, he shall be entitled to cash 
    compensation for earned leave earned by him and not availed of:  
 
Provided that 
    a sales promotion employee shall not be entitled to cash compensation for 
    earned leave not availed of for a period exceeding 120 days.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rule (2) where a sales promotion 
    employee had applied for earned leave due to him so as to enable him to 
    avail of such leave immediately before he voluntarily relinquishes his post 
    or retires on reaching the age of superannuation and such leave was refused, 
    the sales promotion employee shall be entitled to cash compensation for the 
    entire period of earned leave so refused as well as cash compensation for 
    the period of earned leave due to him, in respect of which no application to 
    avail of the same was made; so, however, that the total period of earned 
    leave for which cash compensation shall be payable under this sub-rule shall 
    not exceed 180 days.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where a 
    sales promotion employee dies while in service his heirs shall be entitled 
    to cash compensation for the entire earned leave due to such employee and 
    not availed of.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where a 
    sales promotion employee’s services are terminated for any reason whatsoever 
    (not being termination as punishment), he shall be entitled to cash 
    compensation for the entire earned leave due to him and not availed of.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The cash 
    compensation payable under this rule in respect of earned leave shall be 
    equal to the amount of wages due to the sales promotion employee for the 
    period of leave not availed of or refused.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>15</number> Medical 
    leave.—
<section><number>1</number> For the purposes of 
    availing leave on medical certificate under clause (b) of section 4, the 
    sales promotion employee shall produce a medical certificate from on 
    authorised medical attendant:  
 
Provided that 
    where a sales promotion employee has proceeded to a place other than his 
    headquarters with the permission of his employer or in the course of the 
    discharge of his duties and there falls ill, he may produce a medical 
    certificate from any registered medical practitioner practising at the place 
    where he falls ill:  
 
Provided 
    further that the employer may, when the registered medical practitioner 
    whose certificate is produced is not in the service of the Government, 
    arrange at his own expense for the medical examination of the employee 
    concerned by any Government Medical Officer not below the rank of a Civil 
    Assistant Surgeon or by any other Medical Officer in charge of a hospital 
    run by a local authority or a public organisation at that place.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Leave on 
    medical certificate may be taken in continuation of earned leave.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A sales 
    promotion employee shall be entitled at his option to convert leave on 
    medical certificate on one-half of the wages to half the amount of leave on 
    full wages (hereinafter referred to as converted leave).  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Leave on 
    medical certificate or converted leave may be granted to an employee at his 
    request notwithstanding that earned leave is due to him.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Every 
    establishment may authorise one or more medical practitioners registered 
    under the Indian Medical Council Act, 1956 (102 of 1956) as authorised 
    medical attendants for the purposes of the Act or the rules made thereunder.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Quarantine leave.—
<section><number>1</number> Where, in 
    consequence of the presence of an infectious disease, in the house-hold of a 
    sales promotion employee, his attendance is considered hazardous to the 
    health of other people, the employee concerned may be granted quarantine 
    leave.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    quarantine leave may be granted for a period upto 30 days on the 
    recommendation of the authorised medical attendant or Public Health Officer.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A sales 
    promotion employee on quarantine leave shall be treated as on duty for all 
    purposes.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Extraordinary leave.—A sales 
    promotion employee may be granted extraordinary leave in special 
    circumstances without wages at the discretion of the employer.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>18</number> Leave 
    not due.—A sales promotion 
    employee who has no leave to his credit, may be granted leave not due, at 
    the discretion of the employer.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>19</number> Study 
    leave.—A sales promotion employee 
    may be granted study leave with or without wages at the discretion of the 
    employer.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>20</number> Casual 
    leave.—
<section><number>1</number> A sales promotion 
    employee shall be eligible for casual leave for fifteen days in a calendar 
    year.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Casual 
    leave not availed of during a calendar year shall not be carried forward to 
    the following year.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The sales 
    promotion employee may take any amount of casual leave at a time and casual 
    leave may be combined with any other kind of leave.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>21</number> 
    An employee on casual leave shall be entitled to wages as if he was on duty.  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    
<section><number>1</number> The letter of appointment to be furnished to a sales promotion employee 
    under section 5 shall be in Form A.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    change in the particulars mentioned in the letter of appointment given to an 
    employee shall be communicated to the employee concerned forthwith either by 
    personal service with proper receipt or by registered post acknowledgement 
    due.  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>23</number> 
    Maintenance of Registers and other documents.—Every 
    establishment shall prepare and maintain the following registers and 
    records, namely:—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>   a Register of Sales Promotion Employees 
    in Form B;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   Service Books for every employee in Form 
    C;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   a Register of Service Books in Form D;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   Leave Account of each employee in Form 
    E.  
 

  

 
  


</section></article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




The sales promotion employees (conditions of 
    service)  

    rules, 1976
 

 
 

 
 

 
 


FORM A
 


[See rule 22(1)]
 



    Letter of Appointment
 

 
 


1. Name of the establishment...............................................................................................
 


2.Address.................................................................................................................................
 


3. Name of the employer.......................................................................................................
 


4. Name and address of the sales promotion 
    employee*
 


5. Shri/Smt.....................................................is 
    appointed as...........................................in 
 


this establishment with effect form................................................................................
 


6. His/Her appointment is on probation 
    for................................/temporary basis/permanent basis. 

                                                            
    (insert here the period)
 


7. His/Her scale of wages/rate of increment in 
    wages per........................shall be........................  

                                                                               
    (insert here the period) (insert here the amount)
 


8. He/She will draw a total wages 
    of.......................per ...................... composed of the 
    following, namely:—
 


         
    (i)   Basic Pay......................................Dearness 
    Allowance.......................................
 


                              (insert here the 
    amount)                                 (insert here the amount)
 


        
    (ii)   Other allowances.............................................................................................................
 


                                                        
    (insert here the particulars)
 


9. Other conditions of service................................................................................................
 

 
 


Date...............................        
    
 


Signature of the employer.
 


 
 


-----------------------
 


      
    *.   Any Change of address of the employee shall be communicated 
    to the employer.
 


-----------------------
 


 
 

 
 

 
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>