<act><title>


The Geographical Indications of Goods 
    (Registration and Protection) Rules, 20021</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Geographical Indications of Goods 
    (Registration and Protection) Rules, 2002.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They 
    shall come into force on the date on which the Act comes into force.<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “Act” means The Geographical 
    Indications of Goods (Registration and Protection) Act, 1999 (48 of 1999); 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    “agent” means a person authorised under 
    section 76; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    “application for registration of a 
    geographical indication” includes the geographical indication for goods 
    contained in it; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    “appropriate office of the Geographical 
    Indications Registry” means the relevant office of the Geographical 
    Indications Registry as specified in rule 4; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    “business” includes the trading, 
    dealing, production exploitation, making or manufacturing, as the case may 
    be, of the goods to which geographical indication relates; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    “class fee” means the fee prescribed 
    under entry no. 1 of the First Schedule; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    “Convention Country” means a country 
    notified as such under sub-section (1) of section 84; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    “Convention Application” means an 
    application for the registration of a geographical indication made by virtue 
    of section 84; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    “divisional application” means a 
    divided application made by the division of a single initial application for 
    registration of a geographical indication for different classes of goods; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>    “divisional fee” means the fee so 
    prescribed under the First Schedule; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>    “Form” means a form set forth in either 
    the Second or the Third Schedule; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>    “graphical representation” means the 
    representation of a geographical indication for goods in paper form; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number>    “journal” means the Geographical 
    Indications Journal; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>n</number>    “notified date” means the date on which 
    the rules come into force; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>o</number>    “opposition” includes an opposition to 
    the registration of a geographical indication or authorised user as the case 
    may be; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>p</number>    “principal place of business in India” 
    means the relevant place in India as specified in rule 3; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>q</number>    “publish” means publish in the 
    Geographical Indications Journal; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>r</number>    “registered geographical indications 
    agent” means a geographical indications agent whose name is actually on the 
    Register of Geographical Indications Agent maintained under rule 102; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>s</number>    “renewal” means and includes renewal of 
    a geographical indication by the registered proprietor of geographical 
    indication or of the authorised user of a geographical indication as the 
    case may be; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>t</number>    “Schedule” means a Schedule to the 
    rules; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>u</number>    “section” means a section of the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>    “Specification” means the designation 
    of goods in respect of which a geographical indication is registered or 
    proposed to be registered; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>w</number>    all other words and expressions used 
    but not defined in these rules and defined in the Act shall have the meaning 
    assigned to them in the Act. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    these rules, except as otherwise indicated, a reference to a section is a 
    reference to that section in the Act, a reference to a rule is a reference 
    to that rule in these rules, a reference to a Schedule is a reference to 
    that Schedule to these rules and a reference to a Form is a reference to 
    that form mentioned in the Second or Third schedule, as the case may be. 
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Principal place of business in India.—Principal 
    place of business in India” means— 
 <section>
<number>i</number>    where a person carries on business in 
    the goods concerned bearing a geographical indication— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    if the business is carried on in India 
    at only one place, that place; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    if the business is carried on in India 
    at more places than one, the place mentioned by him as the principal place 
    of business in India; 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>ii</number>    where a person is not carrying on a 
    business of the goods concerned bearing a geographical indication—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    if he is carrying on any other business 
    in India at only one place, that place; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    if he is carrying on any other business 
    in India at more places than one, the place mentioned by him as the 
    principal place of business in India; and 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>iii</number>    where a person does not carry on any 
    business in India but has a place of residence in India, then such place of 
    residence in India. 
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Appropriate office of the Geographical Indications Registry.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The “appropriate office of the Geographical Indications Registry” for the 
    purposes of making an application for registration of a geographical 
    indication under section 11(1) or registration as an authorised user under 
    sub-section (1) of section 17 or for giving notice of opposition under 
    sub-section (1) of section 14 or sub-section (3)(e) of section 17, as the 
    case may be, or for filing an application for rectification under section 27 
    or for any other proceedings under the Act and the rules shall be, in 
    relation to a geographical indication for which an
application for registration is made on or after the notified date, 
    the office of the Geographical Indications Registry within whose territorial 
    limits— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    the principal place of business in 
    India of the applicant as disclosed in his application or, in the case of an 
    association of persons or producers the principal place of business in India 
    of the applicant whose name is first mentioned in the application, as having 
    such place of business is situate; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    where neither the applicant nor any of 
    the association of persons or producers, as the case may be, has a principal 
    place of business in India, the place mentioned in the address for service 
    in India as specified in the application is situate. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rule (1) all applications, 
    communications, documents or fee authorised or required by the Act or the 
    rules to be sent, served, left or paid shall be sent or paid at or to the 
    Head Office of the Registry notified by the Central Government initially and 
    subsequently at the appropriate office as and when notified. 
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Jurisdiction of appropriate office not altered by change in the principal 
    place of business or address for service.—No 
    change in the principal place of business in India or in the address for 
    service in India, as the case may be, of an applicant or of any of the 
    association of persons or producers for registration in relation to any 
    geographical indication for which an application for registration is made on 
    or after the notified date, made or effected subsequent to that date shall 
    affect the jurisdiction of the appropriate office of the Geographical 
    Indications Registry. 
  
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Entry of the appropriate office in the Register.—Subject 
    to sub-rule (2) of rule 4, in respect of every geographical indication 
    registered after the notified date, the Registrar shall cause to be entered 
    in the register the appropriate office of the Geographical Indications 
    Registry and the Registrar may, at any time, correct any error in the entry 
    so made. 
  
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Leaving of documents, etc.—Save 
    as otherwise provided in sub-rule (2) of rule 4 all applications, notices, 
    statements or other documents or any fee authorised or required by the Act 
    or the rules to be made, served, left or sent or paid at or to the 
    Geographical Indications Registry in relation to a geographical indication 
    shall be made, served, left or sent or paid to the appropriate office of 
    Geographical Indications Registry. 
  
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Documents, etc., filed or left not at the appropriate office.—Subject 
    to the provisions of rule 7, in an exceptional case where any application, 
    statement or other document or any fee authorised or required by the Act or 
    the rules is made, served, left or sent or paid, at or to an office 
    inadvertently which is not the appropriate office of the Geographical 
    Indications Registry as and when such an office is notified under this Act 
    by the Central Government under sub-rule (2) of rule 4, the Registrar may on 
    a written request return such application, statement or document to the 
    appropriate office if he is satisfied that it was bona fide error on 
    the part of the applicant in such cases: 
 
Provided 
    the period for which such application, or statement or document is retained 
    by the office, which is not the appropriate office shall be excluded for the 
    purposes of computing the period of limitation where any of such 
    application, statement or document is required to be presented within the 
    prescribed period: 
 
Provided 
    before declining any such request the Registrar shall provide an opportunity 
    of being heard. 
  
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Issue of notices, etc.—Subject 
    to sub-rule (2) of rule 4 any notice or communication relating to any 
    application, matter or proceeding under the Act or the rules shall 
    ordinarily be issued from the appropriate office of the Geographical 
    Indications Registry but may, nevertheless, be issued by the Head of Office 
    of any office of the Geographical Indications Registry. 
  
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Fees.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The fees to be paid in respect of applications, oppositions, registration, 
    renewal or any other matters under the Act or the rules shall be those 
    specified in the First Schedule, hereinafter referred to as the prescribed 
    fees.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where in respect of any matter a fee is required to be paid under the rules, 
    the form or the application or the request of the petition, therefor, shall 
    be accompanied by the prescribed fee.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Fees 
    may be paid in cash or sent by money order addressed to the Registrar of 
    Geographical Indications or by a bank draft issued by, or by a cheque drawn 
    on by a scheduled bank at the place where the appropriate office of the 
    Geographical Indications Registry is situated and if sent through posts 
    shall be deemed to have been paid at the time when the money order or the 
    properly addressed bank draft or cheque would be delivered in the ordinary 
    course of post.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Bank 
    drafts and cheques shall be crossed and made payable to the Registrar at the 
    appropriate office of the Geographical Indications Registry and they shall 
    be drawn on a scheduled bank at the place where the appropriate office of 
    the Geographical Indications Registry is situate.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> 
    Where a fee is payable in respect of filing of document and either the 
    document is filed without fee or with insufficient fee, such document shall 
    be deemed to have not been filed for the purposes any proceedings under the 
    rules.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> 
    Where any fee paid by a party is ordered to be returned by the Registrar 
    under any of the provisions of the Act or the rules the amount may be 
    refunded by money order in which event money order commission shall be 
    deductible from such amount.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The 
    Registrar may after notification in the Geographical Indications Journal 
    make available electronic fee transfer facilities subject to such conditions 
    as may be specified on that behalf.
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Forms.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The forms set forth in the Second and the Third Schedules shall be used in 
    all cases to which they are applicable and may be modified as directed by 
    the Registrar to meet other cases. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any 
    form, when filed at the Geographical Indications Registry shall be 
    accompanied by the prescribed fee. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A 
    requirement under this rule to use a form as set forth in the schedules is 
    satisfied by the use either of a replica of that form or of a form which is 
    acceptable to the Registrar and contains the information required by the 
    form as set forth in the schedule and complies with any direction as to the 
    use of such a form. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Registrar may after notification in the Geographical Indications Journal 
    specify such forms as are required to be submitted in machine readable 
    forms. Thereafter, such forms shall be completed in such a manner as may be 
    specified as to permit an automated input of the content into a computer 
    such as by character recognition or scanning. 
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Size, etc., of documents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to any other directions that may be given by the Registrar, all 
    applications, notices, statements, or other documents except the 
    geographical indication required by the Act or the rules to be made, served, 
    left or sent, at or to the Geographical Indications Registry shall be 
    typewritten, lithographed or printed in Hindi or in English in large and 
    legible characters with deep permanent ink upon strong paper, and except in 
    the case of affidavits, on one side only and of size of approximately 33 cms 
    by 20 cms and shall have on the left hand part thereof a margin of not less 
    than 4 centimetres. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Duplicate documents including copies of geographical indications shall be 
    filed at the Geographical Indications Registry if at any time so required by 
    the Registrar. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Registrar may after notification in the Geographical Indications Journal 
    alter the size of all applications, notices, statements or other documents 
    and forms required under the rules to make it compatible in machine readable 
    form. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Registrar may after notification in the Geographical Indications Journal 
    permit the filing of applications, statements, notices or other documents by 
    electronic means subject to such conditions as he may specify either 
    generally by published notice in the Journal or in any particular case by 
    written notice to the persons desiring to file any such documents by such 
    means. 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Signing of documents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    An application for the registration of a geographical indication purporting 
    to be filed by an association of persons or producers shall be signed by the 
    authorised signatory thereof to sign such documents and a document 
    purporting to be signed by a body corporate or any organisation or any 
    authority established by or under any law for the time being in force shall 
    be signed by the Chief Executive or the Managing Director or the Secretary 
    or other principal officer of such organisation. A document purporting to be 
    signed by a partnership shall be signed by at least one of the partners. The 
    capacity in which an individual signs a document on behalf of an association 
    of persons or a body corporate shall be stated below his signature. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Signatures to an application and any other documents shall be accompanied by 
    the name of the signatory in English or in Hindi and in capital letters. 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Service of documents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    All applications, notices, statements, papers having representations affixed 
    thereto, or other documents authorised or required by the Act or the rules 
    to be made, served, left or sent, at or to the Geographical Indications 
    Registry or with or to the Registrar or any other person may be sent through 
    the post by a prepaid letter. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any 
    application or any document so sent shall be deemed to have been made, 
    served, left or sent at the time when the letter containing the same would 
    be delivered in the ordinary course of post. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In 
    proving such sending it shall be sufficient to prove that the letter was 
    properly addressed and put into the post. 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Particulars of address, etc., of applicants and other persons.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Names and addresses of the association of persons, producers, authorised 
    users and other persons shall be given in full, together with their 
    nationality, calling and such other particulars as are necessary for 
    identification. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    the case of a body corporate the full name and nationality of the Board of 
    Directors thereof shall be stated. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In 
    the case of foreign applicants and persons having no principal place of 
    business in India, their addresses in their home country shall be given in 
    addition to their address for service in India. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> In 
    the case of a body corporate or any organisation or authority established by 
    or under any law for the time being in force, the country of incorporation 
    or the nature of registration, if any, as the case may be, shall be given. 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Statement of principal place of business in India in an application.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every application for registration of a geographical indication or as an 
    authorised user shall state the principal place of business in India, if 
    any, of the applicant or the authorised user or in the case of association 
    of persons or producers of goods such of them, as have a principal place of 
    business in India. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of rules 17, 18, and 20, any written communication 
    addressed to an applicant or his agent, or an authorised user or his agent 
    or in the case of association of persons, the person authorised to act in
the matter in connection with the registration of a geographical 
    indication or their agent, at the address of his principal place of business 
    in India given by him in the application shall be deemed to be properly 
    addressed. 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Address for service.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    An address for service in India shall be given— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    by every applicant for registration of 
    a geographical indication or by an authorised user of a geographical 
    indication who has no principal place of business in India; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    in the case of an association of 
    persons or producers for registration of a geographical indication if none 
    of them has a principal place of business in India; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    by the applicant for a geographical 
    indication who had his principal place of business in India at the date of 
    making the application for registration but has subsequently ceased to have 
    such place; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    by every applicant or authorised user 
    in any proceeding under the Act or the rules and every person filing a 
    notice of opposition, who do not have a principal place of business is 
    India; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    by every person granted leave to 
    intervene under rule 67 (the intervener); 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    every proprietor of a registered 
    geographical indication which is the subject of an application to the 
    Registrar for the invalidation or rectification of the registered 
    geographical indication; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    by every applicant for cancelling, 
    expunging and varying any entry on the register relating to a geographical 
    indication or of an authorised user under sub-sections (1) and (2) of 
    section 27. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Any 
    written communication addressed to a person as aforesaid at an address for 
    service in India given by him shall be deemed to be properly addressed. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Unless an address for service in India as required in sub-rule (1) is given, 
    the Registrar shall be under no obligation to send any notice that may be 
    required by the Act or the rules and no subsequent order or decision in the 
    proceedings shall be called in question on the ground of any lack or 
    non-service of notice. 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Address for service in application and opposition proceedings.—An 
    applicant for registration of a geographical indication or as an authorised 
    user or an opponent filing a notice of opposition may notwithstanding that 
    he has a principal place of business in India, if he so desires, may furnish 
    to the Registrar with an address in India to which communications in 
    relation to the application or opposition proceedings only may be sent. Such 
    address of the applicant or the authorised user or the opponent shall be 
    deemed, unless subsequently cancelled, to be the actual address of the 
    applicant or the authorised user or the opponent, as the case may be, and 
    all communications and documents in relation to the application, or notice 
    of opposition may be served by leaving them at, or sending them by post to 
    such address of the applicant or the authorised user or the opponent, as the 
    case may be. 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Non-availability of an address for service.—The 
    Registrar may, at any time when a doubt arises as to the continued 
    availability of an address for service in India entered in the register, 
    request the person for whom it is entered by letter directed to any other 
    address entered in the register or if no such address is entered in the 
    register to the address at which the Registrar considers that the letter 
    would reach him to confirm the address for service in India and if within 
    two months of making such a request the Registrar receives no such 
    confirmation, he may strike the entry in the register of the address for 
    service in India and require such person to furnish a fresh address for 
    service in India or his address at the principal place of business in India, 
    if he has any at that time. 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> 
    Agency.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The authorisation of an agent for the purpose of section 76 shall be 
    executed on Form GI-10 or in such other written form as the Registrar may 
    deem sufficient and proper. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    the case of such authorisation, service upon the agent of any document 
    relating to the proceeding or matter shall be deemed to be service upon the 
    person so authorising him; all communications directed to be made to such 
    person in respect of the proceeding or matter may be addressed to such 
    agent, and all appearances before Registrar relating thereto may be made by 
    or through such agent. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In 
    any particular case the Registrar may require the personal signature or 
    presence of an applicant, opponent, proprietor, authorised user or other 
    person. 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>21</number> 
    Classification of goods.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    For the purposes of the registration of a geographical indication or as an 
    authorised user, goods shall be classified in the manner specified in the 
    Fourth Schedule. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    goods mentioned in the Fourth Schedule only provide a means by which the 
    general content of numbered international classes can be quickly identified. 
    They correspond to the major content of each class and are not intended to 
    be exhaustive in accordance with the International Classification of Goods. 
    For determining the classification of particular goods and for full 
    disclosure of the content of international classification, reference may be 
    made to the alphabetical index of goods if any, published by the Registrar 
    under sub-section (3) of section 8 or the current edition of International 
    Classification of Goods for the purpose of registration of trade marks 
    published by the World Intellectual Property Organisation or any subsequent 
    edition as may be available. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Where goods of more than one class are set out in an application for which 
    only one application fee has been paid, the Registrar shall require the 
    applicant to amend the application in order to restrict the goods to a 
    single class. 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Request to Registrar for search.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person may request the Registrar on Form GI-5 to cause a search to be 
    made in respect of specified goods classified in any one class in the Fourth 
    Schedule in order to ascertain whether any geographical indication is on 
    record which resembles a trade mark or geographical indication of which two 
    representations accompany the form. The Registrar shall cause a search to be 
    made and inform the applicant of the result of such search. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    within three months from date of communication of the result of the search 
    aforesaid an application is made for the registration of the trade mark or 
    geographical indication in question and the Registrar takes objection on the 
    ground that the mark or the geographical indication resembles a geographical 
    indication, which was not disclosed in the search, but was on record on the 
    last of the date on which the search was made the applicant shall be 
    entitled, after withdrawal of the application for the registration of the 
    said trade mark or the geographical indication, to have repaid to him the 
    fee paid for search in Form GI-5.
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> 
    Form and signing of application.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every application for the registration of a geographical indication shall be 
    made in the prescribed form and shall be signed by the applicant or his 
    agent and must be made in triplicate alongwith three copies of a Statement 
    of Case. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An 
    application to register a geographical indication for a specification of 
    goods included in any one class shall be made in Form GI-1. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An 
    application to register a geographical indication under section 84(1) for a 
    specification of goods included in any one class from a convention country 
    shall be made in Form GI-1. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A 
    single application for the registration of a geographical indication for 
    different classes of goods from a convention country under section 84(1) 
    shall be made in Form GI-1. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> A 
    single application for the registration of a geographical indications for 
    different classes of goods shall be made in Form GI-1. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> 
    Every application for the registration of a geographical indication for 
    goods must satisfy the following conditions:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the geographical indication must be 
    defined with sufficient precision so that the right to obtain relief in 
    respect of infringement of geographical indication can be determined; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the graphical representation must be 
    able to stand in place of the geographical indication without the need for 
    supporting samples; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    it must be reasonably practicable for 
    persons inspecting the Register or reading the Geographical Indications 
    Journals to understand from the graphical representation what the 
    geographical indication is; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    an application for the registration of 
    a three dimensional geographical indication shall not be acted upon as such 
    unless the application for registration contains a statement to that effect; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    where a colour combination is claimed 
    as an element of a geographical indication in an application for the 
    registration, it shall not be acted upon as such unless the application 
    contains a statement to that effect and specifies the colours.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>7</number> An 
    amendment to divide an application under proviso to section 15 shall be made 
    in Form GI-5. 
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> 
    Every application shall be in respect of one geographical indications only 
    for as many class or classes of goods as may be made. 
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> The 
    Registrar may require a more concise description of a geographical 
    indications if relates to colour combination, a three-dimensional 
    geographical indication, design which are symbols of definite concepts, a 
    configuration of goods or packaging to evaluate the substantive rights in 
    the geographical indications. 
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> 
    Where an applicant files a single application for one or more classes and 
    the Registrar determines that the goods applied for fall in class or classes 
    in addition to those applied for, the applicant may restrict the 
    specification of goods to the class applied for or amend the application to 
    add additional class or classes on payment of the appropriate class fee and 
    the divisional fee. The new class created through a division retains the 
    benefit of original filing date or in the case of an application from a 
    convention country, the convention application date under sub-section (1) of 
    section 84 provided the claim, was otherwise properly asserted in the 
    original application. 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Application under convention arrangement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where an application for registration of a geographical indications is filed 
    by an applicant from a convention country under section 84, a certificate by 
    the Registry or competent authority of the Geographical Indications Office 
    of the convention country shall be included in the application for 
    registration under sub-rule (3) or (4) of rule 23, as the case may be, and 
    it shall include the particulars of the geographical indication, the country 
    and the date or dates of filing of the first application in the convention 
    country and such other particulars as may be required by the Registrar. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Unless such certificate has been filed at the time of the filing of the 
    application for registration, there shall be filed, within two months of the 
    filing of the application under sub-rule (3) or (4) of rule 23, as the case 
    may be, certifying or verifying to the satisfaction of the Registrar the 
    date of the filing of the application, the country, the representation of 
    geographical indication, the class and goods covered by the application. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    application relied under sub-rule (1) must be the applicants’ first 
    application in a convention country for the same geographical indications 
    and for all or some of the goods under that application. The application 
    must include a statement indicating the filing date of the foreign 
    application relied upon, the convention country where it was filed, the 
    serial number, if available and a statement indicating the convention 
    application date as claimed. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Where a single application under sub section (3) of section 11 from a 
    convention country is received in respect of a geographical indications for 
    one or more classes of goods, the applicant must establish a continuous 
    valid basis for the convention application date in all classes. 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Statement of user in applications.—An 
    application to register a geographical indication or as an authorised user 
    shall, contain a statement of the period during which, and the person by 
    whom it has been used in respect of the goods mentioned in the application. 
    The applicant shall file an affidavit testifying to such user with exhibits 
    showing the geographical indication as used, the volume of sales under that 
    geographical indication, the definite territory of the country, region or 
    locality in the country to which geographical indication relates and such 
    other particulars as the Registrar on perusal of the application may call 
    for from the applicants. 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>26</number> 
    Representation of geographical indication.—Every 
    application for the registration of a geographical indication and where 
    additional copies of the application are required every such copy, shall 
    contain a representation of the geographical indication in the space 
    provided on the application form for that purpose provided the size of such 
    representation shall not exceed 33 centimetres by 20 centimetres with a 
    margin of 4 centimetres on the left hand side. 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>27</number> 
    Additional representations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every application for the registration of a geographical indication shall, 
    except as hereinafter provided, be made in triplicate and shall be 
    accompanied by five additional representations of the geographical 
    indication. The representations of the geographical indication on the 
    application and each of its copies and the additional representations shall 
    correspond exactly with one another. The additional representations shall in 
    all cases be noted with the specification and class of goods for which 
    registration is sought, the name and address of the applicant, together with 
    the name and address of his agent, if any, the period of use, and such other 
    particulars as required under sub-rule (1) to rule 32 by the Registrar and 
    shall be signed by the applicant or his agent. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where an application contains a statement to the effect that the applicant 
    wishes to claim combination of colours as a distinctive feature of the 
    geographical indication, the application shall be accompanied with three 
    reproduction of the geographical indication in black and white and five 
    reproduction of the geographical indication in colour. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> (i) 
    Where an application for the registration of a geographical indication 
    consist of shape of goods or its packaging, the reproduction furnished shall 
    consist of at least three different view of the geographical indication and 
    a description by word of the geographical indication. 
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> If 
    the Registrar considers the different views and description of the 
    geographical indication in sub-para (i) still does not sufficiently show the 
    particulars of the shape of goods or its packaging he may call upon the 
    applicant to furnish a specimen of the goods or packaging, as the case may 
    be, as sold in respect of the geographical indication. 
  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>28</number> 
    Representations to be durable and satisfactory.—(l) 
    All representations in respect of a geographical indication shall be of a 
    durable nature, and each additional representation required to be filed with 
    an application for registration shall be mounted on a sheet of strong paper 
    of the size of approximately 33 centimetres by 20 centimetres leaving a 
    margin of not less than 4 centimetres on the left hand part of the sheet. 
 <section>
<number>2</number> If 
    the Registrar is not satisfied with any representation of a geographical 
    indication he may at any time require another representation satisfactory to 
    him to be substituted before proceedings with the application. 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>29</number> 
    Transliteration and translation.—(l) 
    Where a geographical indication contains a word or words in characters other 
    than Devanagari or Roman, there shall be endorsed on the application form 
    and the additional representation thereof, a sufficient transliteration and 
    translation to the satisfaction of the Registrar of each of such words, and 
    every such endorsement shall state the language to which the word belongs 
    and shall be signed by the applicant or his agent failing which the 
    Registrar shall be under no obligation to take any action on the 
    application. 
 <section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where an application for a geographical indication or authorised user 
    contains a word or words in a language other than Hindi or English, the 
    Registrar may ask for an exact translation thereof together with the name of 
    the language, and such translation and name, if he so requires, shall be 
    endorsed and signed as aforesaid. 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>30</number> 
    Name or description of goods on a Geographical Indication.—Where 
    the name or description of any goods appears on a geographical indication, 
    the Registrar may refuse to register such geographical indication. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>31</number> 
    Deficiencies.—Subject 
    to sub-rule (2) of rule 10, where an application for registration of a 
    geographical indication does not satisfy requirements under section 11 or 
    rule 23, the Registrar shall send notice thereof to the Applicants to remedy 
    the deficiencies and if within one month from the date of receipt of the 
    notice, the applicants fails to remedy any deficiency so notified by him the 
    application may be treated as abandoned. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>32</number> 
    
<section><number>1</number> Content of application.—Every 
    application for the registration of a geographical indication shall be made 
    in the prescribed forms and shall contain the following:— 
 </section><section>
<number>1</number>    a statement as to how the geographical 
    indication serves to designate the goods as originating from the concerned 
    territory of the country or region or locality in the country, as the case 
    may be, in respect of specific quality, reputation or other characteristics 
    which are due exclusively or essentially to the geographical environment, 
    with its inherent natural and human factors, and the production, processing 
    or preparation of which takes place in such territory, region or locality as 
    the case may be; 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>    the class of goods to which the 
    geographical indication relates shall apply; 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>    the geographical map of the territory 
    of the country or region or locality in the country in which the goods are 
    produced or originate or are being manufactured; 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number>    the particulars regarding the 
    appearance of the geographical indication as to whether it is comprised of 
    the words or figurative elements or both; 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number>    A statement containing such particulars 
    of the producers of the concerned goods proposed to be initially registered. 
    The statement may contain such other particulars of the producers mentioned 
    in section 1l (2) (f) including a collective reference to all the producers 
    of the goods in respect of which the application is made. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number>    the statement contained in the 
    application shall also include the following:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    an affidavit as to how the applicant 
    claim to represent the interest of the association of persons or producers 
    or any organization or authority established by or under any law; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the standards benchmark for the use of 
    the geographical indication or the industry standard as regards the 
    production, exploitation, making or manufacture of the goods having specific 
    quality, reputation, or other characteristic of such goods that is 
    essentially attributable to its geographical origin with the detailed 
    description of the human creativity involved, if any or other characteristic 
    from the definite territory of the country, region or locality in the 
    country, as the case may be; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the particulars of the mechanism to 
    ensure that the standards, quality, integrity and consistency or other 
    special characteristic in respect of the goods to which the geographical 
    indication relates which are maintained by the producers, maker or 
    manufacturers of the goods, as the case may be; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    three certified copies of the map of 
    the territory, region or locality showing the title, name of publisher and 
    date of issue along with the application; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the particulars of special human skill 
    involved or the uniqueness of the geographical environment or other inherent 
    characteristics associated with the geographical indication to which the 
    application relates; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    the full name and address of the 
    association of persons or organisation or authority representing the 
    interest of the producers of the concerned goods; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    particulars of the inspection 
    structure, if any, to regulate the use of the definite territory region or 
    locality mentioned in the application; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    where the geographical indication is a 
    homonymous indication to an already registered geographical indication, the 
    material factors differentiating the application from the registered 
    geographical indications and particulars of protective measures adopted by 
    the applicant to ensure consumers of such goods are not confused or mislead 
    or confused in consequence of such registration. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Acknowledgement of receipt of application.—Every application for the 
    registration of a geographical indication in respect of any goods shall, on 
    receipt, be acknowledged by the Registrar. The acknowledgement shall be by 
    way of return of one of the additional representations of the geographical 
    indication filed by the applicant along with his application with the 
    official number of the application duly entered thereon. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>33</number> 
    Examination of application.—Upon 
    receipt of an application, the Registrar shall examine the application and 
    the accompanying Statement of Case as required under rule 32 
<section><number>1</number> as to 
    whether it meets the requirements of the Act and the Rules and for this 
    purpose, he shall ordinarily constitute a Consultative Group of not more 
    than seven representatives chaired by him from organization or authority or 
    persons well versed in the varied intricacies of this law or field to 
    ascertain the correctness of the particulars furnished in the Statement of 
    Case referred to in rule 32 (1) which shall ordinarily be finalised within 
    three months from the date of constitution of the Consultative Group. 
    Thereupon, the Registrar shall issue a Examination Report on the application 
    to the applicant. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>34</number>
Objection to acceptance-hearing.—
<section><number>1</number> If, on consideration of the 
    applica-tion on merits and of any evidence of use or of a given quality, 
    reputation or other characteristic of such goods that are essentially 
    attributable to its geographical origin or of any other matter relevant 
    which the applicant may be required to furnish, the Registrar has any 
    objection to the acceptance of the application or proposes to accept it 
    subject to such conditions, amendments, modifications or limitations as he 
    may think right to impose, the Registrar shall communicate such objection or 
    proposal in writing to the applicant. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    within two months from the date of communication mentioned in sub-rule (1), 
    the applicant does not amend his application according to the proposal 
    aforesaid, or submit his observations to the Registrar or apply for a 
    hearing or fails to attend the hearing, as the case may be, the application 
    shall be dismissed. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>35</number> 
    Decision of Registrar.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The decision of the Registrar under rule 34 or rule 37 after a hearing or 
    without a hearing if the applicant has duly communicated his observations in 
    writing and has stated that he does not desire to be heard, shall be 
    communicated to the applicant in writing and if the applicant intends to 
    appeal from such decision he may within one month from the date of receipt 
    of such communication request the Registrar to state in writing the grounds 
    of, and the materials used by him in arriving at, his decision. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In a 
    case where the Registrar makes any requirements to which the applicant does 
    not object the applicant shall comply therewith before the Registrar issues 
    a statement in writing under sub-rule (1). 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    date when the statement in writing under sub-rule (1) is sent shall be 
    deemed to be the date of the Registrar’s decision for the purpose of appeal. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>36</number> 
    Correction and amendment of application.—An 
    applicant for registration of a geographical indication may, whether before 
    or after acceptance of his application but before the registration of the 
    geographical indication, apply on Form GI-5 accompanied by the prescribed 
    fee for the correction of any error in or in connection with his application 
    or any amendment of his application provided such proposed amendment does 
    not relate to amendment of the geographical indication or amendment in the 
    description of goods or to the definite territory, region or locality, as 
    the case may be, that would have the effect of substantially altering or 
    substituting the original application. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>37</number> 
    Withdrawal of acceptance by the Registrar.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If, after the acceptance of an application but before the registration of 
    the geographical indication, the Registrar has any objection to the 
    acceptance of the application on the ground that it was accepted in error, 
    or that the geographical indication ought not to have been accepted in the 
    circumstances of the case, or proposes that the geographical indication 
    should be registered only subject to conditions or limitations, or to 
    conditions additional to or different from the conditions or limitations 
    subject to which the application has been accepted, the Registrar shall 
    communicate such objection in writing to the applicant. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Unless within thirty days from the date of the communication mentioned in 
    sub-rule (1) the applicant amends his application to comply with the 
    requirements of the Registrar or applies for a hearing, the acceptance of 
    the application shall be deemed to be withdrawn by the Registrar, and the 
    application shall proceed as if it had not been accepted. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Where the applicant intimates the Registrar within the period mentioned in 
    sub-rule (2) that he desires to be heard, the Registrar shall give notice to 
    the applicant of a date when he will hear him. Such appointment shall be for 
    a date at least 15 days after the date of the notice, unless the applicant 
    consents to a shorter notice. The applicant may state that he does not 
    desire to be heard and submit such submissions as he may consider desirable. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Registrar may, after hearing the applicant and on considering the 
    submissions, if any, of the applicant pass such orders as he may deem fit. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>38</number> 
    Manner of Advertisement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    An application for the registration of a geographical indication required or 
    permitted to be advertised by sub-section (1) of section 13 or to be 
    re-advertised by sub-clause (2) of that section shall be ordinarily 
    advertised in the Journal within three months of the acceptance of an 
    application for advertisement. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Registrar may after notification in the Journal put the published 
    Geographical Indications Journal on the internet, website or any other 
    electronic media. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Registrar may after notification in the Journal make available the 
    Geographical Indications Journal in CD-ROM on payment of the cost thereof. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>39</number> 
    Notification of correction or amendment of application.—In 
    the case of an application to which para (b) of sub-section (2) of section 
    13 applies, the Registrar may if he so decides, instead of causing the 
    application to be advertised again, insert in the Journal a notification 
    setting out the number of the application, the class in which it was made, 
    the name and address of the principal place of business in India, if any, of 
    the applicant or where the applicant has no principal place of business in 
    India his address for service in India, the number of the Journal in which 
    it was advertised and the correction or amendment made in the application. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>40</number> 
    Request to Registrar for particulars of advertisement of a Geographical 
    Indication.—Any 
    person may request the Registrar on Form GI-7 to be informed of the number, 
    date and page of the Journal in which a geographical indication specified in 
    the form was advertised and the Registrar shall furnish such particulars to 
    the person making the request. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>41</number> 
    Notice of Opposition.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notice of opposition to the registration of a geographical indication under 
    sub-section (1) of section 14 or an authorised user under section 17(3)(e) 
    shall be given in triplicate on Form GI-2 within three months or within such 
    further period not exceeding one month in the aggregate from the date when 
    such Journal was made available to the public (which date shall be certified 
    as such by the Registrar) as the case may be, of the application for 
    registration in the Journal. The notice shall include a statement of the 
    grounds upon which the opponents objects to the registration of the 
    geographical indication or of the authorised user, as the case may be. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where a Notice of Opposition is filed in respect of single application for 
    the registration of a geographical indication it shall bear the fee in 
    respect of each class in relation to which the opposition is filed. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Where an opposition is filed only for a particular class or classes in 
    respect of a single application made under sub-section (3) of section 11, 
    the application shall not proceed to registration until a request in Form 
    GI-5 for division of the application together with the divisional fee is 
    made by the applicant. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Where in respect of a single application for the registration of a 
    geographical indication no notice of opposition is filed in any class or 
    classes, the application in respect of such class or classes shall proceed 
    to registration after the division of the application in the class or 
    classes in respect of which an opposition is pending. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> An 
    application for an extension of the period within which a notice of 
    opposition to the registration of a geographical indication or an authorised 
    user may be given under sub-section (l) of section 14, shall be made on Form 
    GI-2 accompanied by the prescribed fee before the expiry of the period of 
    three months under sub-section (1) of section 14. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> A 
    copy of notice of opposition shall be ordinarily served by the Registrar to 
    the applicants within two months of the receipt of the same by the 
    appropriate office. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>42</number> 
    Verification of Notice of Opposition.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The notice of opposition shall be verified by the opponent. 

 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    verification shall specifically state by reference to the numbered 
    paragraphs of the notice of opposition, what is verified of his own 
    knowledge and what is verified upon information received and believed to be 
    true. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    verification shall be signed by the person making it and shall state the 
    date and the place at which it was signed. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>43</number> 
    Counter-statement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The counter-statement required by sub-section (2) of section 14 shall be 
    sent in triplicate on Form GI-2 within two months from the receipt by the 
    applicant of the copy of the notice of opposition from the Registrar and 
    shall set out what facts, if any, alleged in the notice of opposition, are 
    admitted by the applicant. A copy of the counter-statement shall be served 
    by the Registrar on the person giving notice of opposition ordinarily within 
    two months from the date of receipt of the same. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    counter-statement shall be verified in the same manner as the notice of 
    opposition as stated in rule 42. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>44</number> 
    Evidence in support of opposition by the opponents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Within two months from services on him of a copy of the counter-statement or 
    within such further period not exceeding one month in the aggregate 
    thereafter as the Registrar may on request allow, the opponent shall either 
    leave with the Registrar such evidence by way of affidavit as he may desire 
    to adduce in support of his opposition or shall intimate to the Registrar 
    and to the applicant in writing that he does not desire to adduce evidence 
    in support of his opposition but intends to rely on the facts stated in the 
    notice of opposition. He shall deliver to the applicant copies of any 
    evidence that he leaves with the Registrar under this sub-rule and intimate 
    the Registrar forthwith in writing of such delivery. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    an opponent takes no action under sub-rule (1) within the time mentioned 
    therein, he shall, be deemed to have abandoned his opposition. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An 
    application for the extension of the period of one month mentioned in 
    sub-rule (1) shall be made in Form GI-9 accompanied by prescribed fees 
    before the expiry of the period of two months mentioned therein. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>45</number> 
    Evidence in support of application by the applicant.—(l) 
    Within two months or within such further period not exceeding one month 
    thereafter in the aggregate as the Registrar may on request allow, on the 
    receipt by the applicant of the copies of affidavits in support of 
    opposition or of the intimation that the opponent does not desire to adduce 
    any evidence in support of his opposition, the applicant shall leave with 
    the Registrar such evidence by way of affidavit as he desires to adduce in 
    support of his application and shall deliver to the opponent copies thereof 
    or shall intimate to the Registrar and the opponent that he does not desire 
    to adduce any evidence but intends to rely on the facts stated in the 
    counter-statement and or on the evidence already left by him in connection 
    with the application in question. In case the applicant relies on any 
    evidence already left by him in connection with the application, he shall 
    deliver to the opponent copies thereof. 
 <section>
<number>2</number> An 
    application for the extension of the period of one month mentioned in 
    sub-rule (1) shall be made in Form GI-9 accompanied by prescribed fees 
    before the expiry of the period of two months mentioned therein. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>46</number> 
    Evidence in reply by opponent.—Within 
    one month from the receipt by the opponent of the copies of the applicant’s 
    affidavit or within such further period not exceeding one month in the 
    aggregate thereafter as the Registrar may on request on Form GI-9 
    accompanied by the prescribed fee allow, the opponent may leave with the 
    Registrar evidence by affidavit in reply and shall deliver to the applicant 
    copies thereof. This evidence shall be confined to matters strictly in reply.
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>47</number> 
    Further evidence.—No 
    further evidence shall be left on either side, but in any proceedings before 
    the Registrar, he may at any time, if he thinks fit, give leave to either 
    the applicant or the opponent to leave any evidence upon such terms as to 
    costs or otherwise as he may think fit. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>48</number> 
    Exhibits.—Where 
    there are exhibits to affidavits filed in an opposition, a copy of the 
    exhibit or impression of each exhibit shall be sent to the other party on 
    his request and at his expense, or, if such copies or impression cannot 
    conveniently be furnished, the original shall be left at the Registry in 
    order that they may be open to inspection. The original exhibits shall be 
    produced at the hearing unless the Registrar otherwise directs. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>49</number> 
    Translation of documents.—Where 
    a document in a language other than Hindi or English is referred to in the 
    notice of opposition or any other proceedings before the Registrar, 
    counter-statement or an affidavit filed in an opposition, an attested 
    translation thereof in English or Hindi shall be furnished in duplicate. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>50</number> 
    Hearing and decision.—(l) 
    Upon completion of the evidence if any, the Registrar shall give notice to 
    the parties of a date when he will hear the arguments in the case. Such 
    notice shall be ordinarily given within three months of completion of the 
    evidence. The date of hearing shall be for a date at least one month after 
    the date of the first notice, unless the parties consent to a shorter 
    notice. Within fourteen days from the receipt of the first notice, any party 
    who intends to appear shall so notify the Registrar. Any party who does not 
    so notify the Registrar within the time last aforesaid shall be treated as 
    not desiring to be heard and the Registrar shall proceed ex parte in 
    the matter. 
 <section>
<number>2</number> If 
    sufficient cause is shown, not more than two request for adjournment for one 
    month each by either the opponent or the applicant to the proceeding may be 
    considered by the Registrar on a request in Form GI-9 accompanied with the 
    grounds for such request. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If 
    the applicant is not present at the adjourned date of hearing and has not 
    notified his intention to appear at the hearing, the Registrar may treat the 
    application as dismissed. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If 
    the opponent is not present at the adjourned date of hearing and has not 
    notified his intention to appear at the hearing, the Registrar may treat the 
    opposition as dismissed for want of prosecution and the application may 
    proceed to registration. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> In 
    every case of adjournment the Registrar shall fix a day for further hearing 
    of the case and shall make such order as to cost occasioned by the 
    adjournment or such higher costs as the Registrar deems fit. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    fact that the agent or advocate on record of a party is engaged in another 
    court, shall not be a ground for adjournment. 
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> 
    Where illness of an advocate on record or agent or his inability to conduct 
    the case for any reason is put forward as a ground for adjournment, the 
    Tribunal shall not grant the adjournment unless it is satisfied that the 
    advocate on record or agent, as the case may be, could not have engaged 
    another agent or advocate in time. 
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> The 
    Registrar shall take on record written arguments if submitted by a party to 
    the proceeding. 
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> The 
    Registrar shall have powers to limit time for oral arguments. 
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> The 
    decision of the Registrar shall be notified to the parties in writing. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>51</number> 
    Security for costs.—The 
    security for costs which the Registrar may require under sub-section (6) of 
    section 14 may be fixed at any amount which he may consider proper, and such 
    amount may be further enhanced by him at any stage in the opposition or 
    other proceedings. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>52</number> 
    Procedure for giving notice.—The 
    notice which the Registrar is required by sub-section (3) of section 16 to 
    give to an applicant, shall be sent on Form O-1 to the applicant at the 
    address of his principal place of business in India or if he has no 
    principal place of business in India at the address for service in India as 
    stated in the application but if the applicant has authorised an agent for 
    the purpose of the application, the notice shall be sent to the agent and a 
    duplicate thereof to the applicant. The notice shall specify twenty one days 
    time from the date thereof or such further time as the Registrar may allow 
    on a request made in the prescribed Form GI-9 for completion of the 
    registration.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>53</number> 
    Entry in the Register.—(l) 
    Where no Notice of Opposition is filed to an application for the 
    registration of a geographical indication advertised or re-advertised in the 
    Journal within the period specified in sub­-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 14 or 
    where an opposition is filed and it is dismissed and the appeal period is 
    over, the Registrar shall, subject to the provisions of sub-section (1) of 
    section 16 enter the geographical indication in Part A of the register on 
    receipt of a request. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    entry of a geographical indication in the register shall specify the date of 
    filing of application, the actual date of the registration, the goods and 
    the class in respect of which it is registered, and all particulars required 
    by sub-section (1) of section 6 including— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the name and description of the 
    applicant, the address of the principal place of business in India, if any, 
    of the proprietor of the geographical indication or in the case of an 
    association of persons of such of the association of persons as have a 
    principal place of business in India; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    where the proprietor of the 
    geographical indication has no place of business in India his address for 
    service in India as entered in the application for registration together 
    with his address in his home country; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    in the case of an association of 
    persons or producers, where none of the association of persons or producers 
    has a principal place of business in India, the address for service in India 
    as given in the application together with the address of each of the 
    association of persons or producers in his home country; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    particulars of the trade, business, 
    profession, occupation or other description of the proprietor or of the 
    association of persons or producers of the geographical indication as 
    entered in the application for registration; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    particulars affecting the scope of the 
    registration or the rights conferred by the registration; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    the priority date, if any, to be 
    accorded pursuant to claim to a right of a convention application made under 
    section 84; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    a summary of the particulars furnished 
    under rule 32 as finally accepted by the Registrar; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    the appropriate office of the 
    Geographical Indications Registry in relation to the Geographical 
    Indication. 

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>54</number> 
    Death of applicant before registration.—In 
    case of death of any applicant for the registration of a geographical 
    indication after the date of his application and before the geographical 
    indication has been entered in the register, the Registrar may, on proof of 
    the applicant’s death and on proof of the transmission of the interest of 
    the deceased person, substitute in the application his successor in interest 
    in place of the name of such deceased applicant and the application may 
    proceed thereafter as so amended.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>55</number> 
    Certificate of registration.—(l) 
    The certificate of registration of a geographical indication or an 
    authorised user to be issued by the Registrar under sub-section (2) of 
    section 16 shall be on Form O-2, with such modification as the circumstances 
    of a case may require, and the Registrar shall annex a copy of the 
    geographical indication or authorised user to the certificate. 
 <section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Registrar may issue a duplicate or further copies of the certificate of 
    registration of a geographical indication on request by the registered 
    proprietor on Form GI-7 accompanied by the prescribed fee. An unmounted 
    representation of the geographical indication exactly as shown in the form 
    of application for registration thereof at the time of registration shall 
    accompany such request. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    certificate of registration referred to in sub-rule (1) shall not be used in 
    legal proceedings or for obtaining registration abroad. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>56</number> 
    Authorised User.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    An application to the Registrar for the registration under section 17 by a 
    producer as an authorised user of the registered geographical indication 
    shall be made jointly by the registered proprietor and the proposed 
    authorised user in Form GI-3 and shall be accompanied by a Statement of Case 
    of how he claims to be the producer of the registered geographical 
    indication along with an affidavit. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    copy of the letter of consent from the registered proprietor of the 
    geographical indication may accompany the application and where such consent 
    letter is not furnished, a copy of the application shall be endorsed to the 
    registered proprietor for information and the Registrar shall be intimated 
    of due service by the proposed authorised user. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>57</number>
    Upon 
    receipt of an application for the registration as an authorised user in 
    respect of a registered geographical indication, the Registrar shall cause 
    it to be examined and shall issue a report. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>58</number>
    Thereupon, 
    the provisions of rules 34 to 52, 54 and 55 shall apply mutatis mutandis
    to further proceedings in respect of an application for the registration 
    of an authorised user of a registered geographical indication. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>59</number> 
    Registration of an authorised user entry in the Register.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where no notice of opposition is filed to an application advertised or 
    re-advertised in the Journal within the period specified under sub-clause 
    (e) of sub-section (3) of section 17 or where an opposition is filed and it 
    is dismissed and the appeal period is over, the Registrar shall enter the 
    authorised user in Part B of the register on receipt of a request for 
    issuance of the registration certificate in Form GI-3 together with the 
    prescribed fee. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    entry of an authorised user in the register shall specify the date of filing 
    of application for registration as an authorised user, the actual date of 
    the registration, the goods and class or classes in respect of which it is 
    registered, and all particulars required by sub-section (1) of section 6 
    including— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    The address of the principal place of 
    business in India, if any, of the registered proprietor of the geographical 
    indication; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    Particulars of the geographical 
    indication registered including the specification of goods and the class in 
    which it is registered; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    The address of the principal place of 
    business in India, if any, of the authorised user; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    Where the authorised user of a 
    registered geographical indication has no place of business in India his 
    address for service in India as entered in the application for registration 
    together with his address in his home country; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    Particulars of the trade, business, 
    profession, occupation, dealership or other description of the authorised 
    user of the geographical indication as entered in the application for 
    registration; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    The priority date, if any, to be 
    accorded pursuant to a convention application made under section 84; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    The appropriate office of Geographical 
    Indications Registry in relation to the geographical indication. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Registrar may issue a duplicate or further copies of the certificate of 
    registration as an authorised user on a request in Form GI-7 accompanied by 
    prescribed fee. An unmounted representation of the geographical indication 
    exactly as shown in the form of application for registration thereof at the 
    time of registration shall accompany such request. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>60</number> 
    Renewal of registration.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    An application for the renewal of the registration of a geographical 
    Indication or an authorised user of a registered geographical indication 
    shall be made on Form GI-4 or Form GI-3, as the case may be, and may be made 
    at any time not more than six months before the expiration of the last 
    registration of the geographical indication or the authorised user. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Such 
    application for renewal must be filed by the person who is the proprietor of 
    the registered geographical indication failing which by any of the 
    authorised users on record, as the case may be. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If 
    the proprietor, as set forth in the application for renewal, is not the same 
    person or the same legal entity as the registrant shown in the registration, 
    continuity of title from the registrant to the present owner must be shown 
    in the first instance. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Registrar may accept an application for renewal from the managing trustee, 
    executors, administrators and the like, when supported by court order or 
    other evidence of such persons authority to act on behalf of the present 
    proprietor. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> For 
    the removal of doubt, it is clarified that where the registered proprietor 
    of the geographical indication has ceased to exist, the renewal of the 
    registered geographical indication shall be effected by any of the 
    authorised users of the registered geographical indication acting 
    collectively whose name has been entered in Part B of the register on the 
    due date of renewal. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> 
    Before issuing a renewal certificate, the Registrar may call upon the 
    registered proprietor to file an affidavit concerning the use of the 
    registered geographical indication in India where he has reasons to believe 
    that the registered geographical indication may not be in use in the market. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>61</number> 
    Notice before removal of geographical indication or authorised user from 
    register.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    At a date not less than one month and not more than three months before the 
    expiration of the last registration of a geographical indication or 
    authorised user, as the case may be, if no application on Form GI-4 or Form 
    GI-3, as the case may be, for renewal of the registration of a geographical 
    indication or of an authorised user together with the prescribed fee has 
    been received, the Registrar shall notify the registered proprietor or the 
    authorised user, as the case may be, or in the case of an association of 
    persons or producers of a registered geographical indication each of the 
    association of persons, producers registered as registered proprietors or 
    the person authorised to act on their behalf, if any, in writing on Form O-3 
    or O-5, as the case may be, of the approaching expiration at the address of 
    their respective principal places of business in India as entered in the 
    register or where such registered proprietor or authorised user has no 
    principal place of business in India at his address for service in India 
    entered in the register. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where, in the case of a geographical indication or authorised user the 
    registration of which (by reference to the date of application for 
    registration) becomes due for renewal, the geographical indication or 
    authorised user is registered at any time within six months before the date 
    on which renewal is due, the registration may be renewed by the payment of 
    the renewal fee within six months after the actual date of registration and 
    where the renewal fee is not paid within that period the Registrar shall 
    subject to rule 63, remove the geographical indication or authorised user 
    from the register. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Where, in the case of a geographical indication or authorised user the 
    registration of which (by reference to the date of application for 
    registration) becomes due for renewal, the geographical indication or 
    authorised user is registered after the date of renewal, the registration 
    may be renewed by the payment of the renewal fee within six months of the 
    actual date of registration and where the renewal fee is not paid within 
    that period the Registrar shall, subject to rule 63, remove the geographical 
    indication or authorised user from the register. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>62</number> 
    Advertisement of removal of geographical indication or the authorised user 
    from the register.—If 
    at the expiration of last registration of a geographical indication or an 
    authorised user, the renewal fees has not been paid, the Registrar may 
    remove the geographical indication or the authorised user, as the case may 
    be, from the register and advertise the fact forthwith in the Journal: 
 
Provided 
    the Registrar shall not remove the geographical indication or the authorised 
    user from the register if an application is made in Form GI-4 within six 
    months from the expiration of the last registration of the geographical 
    indication or the authorised user accompanied by prescribed fees and 
    appropriate surcharge. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>63</number> 
    Restoration and renewal of registration.—An 
    application for the restoration of a geographical indication or authorised 
    user to the register and renewal of its registration under sub-section (5) 
    of section 18, shall be made in Form GI-4 after six months and within one 
    year from the expiration of the last registration of the geographical 
    indication or the authorised user, as the case may be, accompanied by the 
    prescribed fee. The Registrar shall, while considering the request for 
    registration, have regard to the interest of the persons who have either 
    applied or registered identical or deceptively similar geographical 
    indication or other affected persons in the intervening period. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>64</number> 
    Notice and advertisement of renewal and restoration.—Upon 
    the renewal or restoration and renewal of registration, a notice to that 
    effect shall be sent to the registered proprietor or the concerned 
    authorised user and the said renewal or restoration and renewal shall be 
    advertised in the Journal. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>65</number> 
    Application to rectify or remove a geographical indication from the 
    register.—An 
    application to the Registrar under section 27 for the cancelling, expunging 
    or varying of any entry relating to a geographical indication or of the 
    Statement of Case referred to under rule 32 
<section><number>1</number> recorded in the Register of 
    Geographical Indication or an authorised user in the register shall be made 
    in triplicate on Form GI-6 or Form GI-5, as the case may be, shall be 
    accompanied by a statement in triplicate setting out fully the nature of the 
    applicant’s interest, the facts upon which he bases his case and the relief 
    which he seeks. Where the application is made by a person who is not the 
    registered proprietor of the geographical indication in question, the 
    application and the statement aforesaid shall be left at the Geographical 
    Indications Registry in triplicate. In case there are authorised users, such 
    application and statements shall be accompanied by as many copies thereof as 
    there are authorised users on the register or alternatively furnish proof of 
    publication in leading national newspapers circulated widely in the definite 
    territory, region or locality to which the geographical indication relates 
    notifying to the general public of proposed application for rectification or 
    removal with full particulars thereof. A copy each of the application and 
    statement shall be transmitted within two months by the Registrar to the 
    registered proprietor and to any other person who appears from the register 
    to have an interest in the geographical indication or makes a request for 
    the same. The application shall be verified in the manner prescribed under 
    rule 42 for verification of notice of opposition 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>66</number> 
    Further procedure.—Within 
    two months or within such further period not exceeding two months in the 
    aggregate from the receipt by a registered proprietor of the copy of the 
    application mentioned in rule 65 from the Registrar, he shall send to the 
    Registrar and to the person making the application on Form GI-2 a counter 
    statement in triplicate of the grounds on which the application is 
    contested. The Registrar shall serve a copy of the counter-statement on the 
    person making the application within one month of the receipt of the same. 
    The provisions of rules 44 to 51 shall thereafter apply mutatis mutandis
    to the further proceedings on the application. The Registrar shall not, 
    however, rectify the register or remove the geographical indication or any 
    authorised user from the register merely because the registered proprietor 
    or the authorised user has not filed a counter-statement unless he is 
    satisfied that the delay in filing the counter-statement is wilful and is 
    not justified by the circumstance of the case. In any case of doubt any 
    party may apply to the Registrar for directions. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>67</number> 
    Intervention by third parties.—Any 
    person alleging interest in a registered geographical indication in respect 
    of which an application is made under rule 65 may apply on Form GI-6 for 
    leave to intervene, stating the nature of his interest, and the Registrar 
    may refuse or grant such leave after hearing if so required the parties 
    concerned, upon such terms and conditions including undertakings or 
    conditions as to security for cost as he may deem fit to impose.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>68</number> 
    Rectification of the register by the Registrar of his own motion.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The notice, which the Registrar is required be give under sub-section (4) of 
    section 27 shall be sent in writing to the registered proprietor and to any 
    other person who appears from the register to have any interest in the 
    registered geographical indication, and shall state the grounds on which the 
    Registrar proposes to rectify the register and shall also specify the time, 
    not being less, than one month from the date of such notice, within which an 
    application for a hearing shall be made. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Unless within the time specified in the notice aforesaid, any person so 
    notified sends to the Registrar a statement in writing setting out fully the 
    facts upon which he relies to meet the grounds stated in the notice or 
    applies for a hearing, he may be treated as not desiring to take part in the 
    proceedings and the Registrar may act accordingly. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If 
    the Registrar decides to rectify the register he shall communicate his 
    decision in writing. 
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>69</number> 
    Alteration of address in register.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A registered proprietor or an authorised user of a geographical indication 
    the address of whose principal place of business in India or whose address 
    in his home country, as the case may be, is changed so that the entry in the 
    register is rendered incorrect shall forthwith request the Registrar on Form 
    GI-5 to make the appropriate alteration of the address in the register, and 
    the Registrar shall alter the register accordingly if he is satisfied in the 
    matter. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    registered proprietor or an authorised user of a geographical indication, 
    whose address for service in India entered in the register is changed, 
    whether by discontinuance of the entered address or otherwise, so that the 
    entry in the register is rendered incorrect, shall forthwith request the 
    Registrar on Form GI-5 to make the appropriate alteration of the address in 
    the Register, and the Registrar shall alter the register accordingly if he 
    is satisfied in the matter. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A 
    registered proprietor or an authorised user of a geographical indication the 
    address of whose principal place of business in India or whose address for 
    service in India is altered by a public authority, so that the changed 
    address designates the same premises as entered in the register, may make 
    the aforesaid request to the Registrar on Form GI-5 and if he does so he 
    shall leave therewith a certificate of the alteration given by the said 
    authority. If the Registrar is satisfied as to the facts of the case, he 
    shall alter the register accordingly but shall not require any fees to be 
    paid on the forms, notwithstanding the provisions of sub-rule (2) of rule 10 
    or sub-rule (2) of rule 11. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> (i) 
    Where a registered proprietor makes a request under sub-rule (1), (2) or 
    (3), he shall serve a copy of the request on the authorised user or users, 
    if any, and inform the Registrar accordingly. 
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> 
    Where the request aforesaid is made by an authorised user, he shall serve a 
    copy thereof on the registered proprietor and other authorised users, if any 
    or alternatively issue a public notice in at least two leading local 
    newspapers circulated widely in the definite territory, region or locality 
    to which geographical indication relates or issue a public notice in at 
    least two leading local newspapers and inform the Registrar that he had done 
    so. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> In 
    case of the alteration of the address of a person entered in the register as 
    the address for service in India of more than one registered proprietor or 
    authorised users of geographical indications, the Registrar may, on proof 
    that the said address is the address of the applicant and if satisfied that 
    it is just to do so, accept an application from that person on Form GI-5 
    amended so as to suit the case, for the appropriate alteration of the 
    entries of his address as the address for service in the several 
    registrations, particulars of which shall be given in the form and may alter 
    the entries accordingly. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> All 
    applications under this rule shall be signed by the registered proprietor or 
    the authorised user, as the case may be, or by an agent expressly authorised 
    by him for the purpose of such an application, unless in exceptional 
    circumstances the Registrar otherwise allows. 
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>70</number> 
    Application under section 28.—Where 
    an application has been made under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 28 for the 
    alteration of the register by correction, change, cancellation or striking 
    out of goods or for the entry of a memorandum in the register, the Registrar 
    may require the applicant to furnish such evidence by affidavit or otherwise 
    as the Registrar may think fit, as to the circumstances in which the 
    application is made. Such application shall be made on Form GI-5 as may be 
    appropriate and a copy thereof shall be served by the applicant on the 
    authorised user or users, if any, or issue a public notice in at least two 
    leading local newspapers under the registration of the geographical 
    indication in question and to any other person who appears from the register 
    to have an interest in the geographical indication and inform the Registrar 
    he has done so. 
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>71</number> 
    Alteration of registered geographical indication.—Where 
    the registered proprietor of a geographical indication applies under section 
    29 for leave to add to or alter the registered geographical indication, he 
    shall make the application in writing on Form GI-9 and shall furnish five 
    copies of the geographical indication as it will appear when so added to or 
    altered. A copy of the application and of the geographical indication so 
    amended or altered shall be served by the applicant on every authorised 
    users on the record or issue a public notice in at least two leading local 
    newspapers and inform the Registrar he has done so. 
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>72</number> 
    Advertisement before decision and opposition, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Registrar shall consider the application and shall, advertise the 
    application in the Journal before deciding it. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Within three months from the date of advertisement under sub-rule (1), or 
    within such period not exceeding one month in the aggregate any person may 
    give notice of opposition to the application on Form GI-2 and may also send 
    therewith a statement of his objections. The notice and the statement, if 
    any, shall be sent in triplicate. In case there are any authorised users 
    under the registration of the geographical indication in question, such 
    notice and statement may also be accompanied by as many copies thereof as 
    there are authorised users. A copy each of the notice and statement shall be 
    transmitted by the person giving notice to registered proprietor and 
    authorised user if any or alternatively issue a public notice in at least 
    two leading local newspapers circulated widely in the definite territory, 
    region or locality to which the geographical indication relates. The 
    Registrar shall forward within two months a copy of the notice and statement 
    to the registered proprietor and within two months from the receipt by the 
    registered proprietor of such copies from the Registrar, he shall send to 
    the Registrar on Form GI-2 a counter-statement in triplicate of the grounds 
    on which the opposition is contested. If the registered proprietor sends 
    such a counter-statement the Registrar shall serve a copy thereof on the 
    person giving notice of opposition within one month and the provisions of 
    rules 44 to 51 shall thereafter apply mutatis mutandis to the further 
    proceedings on the opposition. The Registrar shall not refuse the 
    application merely because the registered proprietor has not filed a 
    counter-statement unless he is satisfied that the delay in filing the 
    counter-statement is wilful and is not justified by the circumstance of the 
    case. In any case of doubt any party may apply to the Registrar for 
    directions. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If 
    there is no opposition, within the time specified in sub-rule (2), the 
    Registrar shall, after hearing the applicant if he so desires allow or 
    refuse the application and shall communicate his decision in writing to the 
    applicant. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>73</number> 
    Decision—Advertisement—Notification.—If 
    the Registrar decides to allow the application he shall alter the 
    geographical indication in the register accordingly and insert in the 
    Journal a notification that the geographical indication has been altered. If 
    the application has not been advertised under rule 71, he shall also 
    advertise in the Journal the geographical indications as altered. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>74</number> 
    Refusal or Invalidation of Registration of Trade Marks.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the Registrar of Trade Marks on his own motion decides to refuse the 
    registration of a trade mark or invalidate a registered trade mark pursuant 
    to sub-section 
<subsection><number>a</number> of section 25 of the Geographical Indications of Goods 
    (Registration and Protection) Act, 1999, he shall in writing notify the 
    applicants or the registered proprietor of the trade mark, as the case may 
    be, stating the reason for the same. Thereafter, the Registrar shall decide 
    the matter after giving the applicant or the registered proprietor of the 
    trade mark, as the case may be, an opportunity of being heard. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    request under sub-section (a) of section 25 to refuse a trade mark or 
    invalidate a registered trade mark which contains or consists of a 
    geographical indication not originating in the territory of a country, or a 
    region, or locality in that territory which such geographical indication 
    indicates , which is likely to cause confusion or mislead persons as to the 
    true place of origin of such goods or class or classes of goods shall be 
    made in the prescribed form under the Trade Marks Rules, 2002. Thereafter, 
    in case of a request for refusal the Registrar of Trade Marks shall forward 
    the same to the applicant and provide an opportunity of being heard to the 
    applicant. In case of a request for invalidation, the Registrar of Trade 
    Marks shall forward the request to the registered proprietor and the 
    procedure set out in rule 93 of the Trade Marks Rules, 2002 shall apply 
    mutatis mutandis to further proceedings on the matter. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>75</number> 
    Refusal or invalidation of registered Trade Mark conflicting with a 
    geographical indication notified under section 22 (2).—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the Registrar of Trade Marks on his own motion decides to refuse an 
    application or invalidate the registration of a trade mark pursuant to 
    sub-section (b) of section 25 of the Geographical Indications of Goods 
    (Registration and Protection) Act, 1999, he shall notify in writing to the 
    applicant or the registered proprietor of the trade mark, as the case may 
    be, stating the reasons for the same. Thereafter, the Registrar shall decide 
    the matter after giving the applicant or the registered proprietor of the 
    trade mark, as the case may be, an opportunity of being heard. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Refusal or invalidation under section 25 (b) of notified geographical 
    indications.—A request under sub-section (b) of section 25 to refuse an 
    application for the registration of a trade mark or invalidate a registered 
    trademark which conflict with or which contains or consists of a 
    geographical indication identifying goods or class or classes of goods 
    notified under sub-section (2) of section 22 shall be made in the prescribed 
    form under the Trade Marks Rules, 2002. Thereafter, in case of request for 
    refusal, the Registrar of Trade Marks shall forward the same to the 
    applicant and provide an opportunity of being heard to the applicant. In 
    case of request for invalidation, the Registrar of Trade Mark shall forward 
    the request to the registered proprietor and the procedure set out in rule 
    93 of the Trade Marks Rules, 2002 shall apply mutatis mutandis to 
    further proceedings on the matter. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>76</number> 
    Publication of refusal or invalidation of geographical indications.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Registrar of Trade Marks shall record and publish a reference to the 
    refusal or the invalidation of the registration of a trade mark pursuant to 
    section 25 of the Geographical Indications of Goods (Registration and 
    Protection) Act, 1999 and forwarded a copy of the publication to the 
    Registrar of Geographical Indications. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    publication of the reference to the refusal or the invalidation of the 
    registration of a trade mark pursuant to section 25 of the Geographical 
    Indication of Goods (Registration and Protection) Act, 1999 shall include— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the representation of the mark; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the application or registration number 
    of the trade mark, as the case may be; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the name and address of the applicant 
    or the registered proprietor, as the case may be; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the date of application or the date of 
    registration in the case of a registered trade mark, as the case may be; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the list of goods or class of goods in 
    respect of which the trade mark was applied for or was registered; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    a summary of the ground on which the 
    application for registration of a trade mark had been refused or the 
    registration of the registered trade mark was invalidated. 

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>77</number> 
    Additional protection to certain goods.—An 
    application may be made to the Registrar in respect of goods notified by the 
    Central Government under sub-section (2) of section 22 for additional 
    protection for a registered geographical indications in Form GI-9 
    accompanied by prescribed fee in triplicate along with a Statement of Case. 
    Such case shall be furnished in triplicate and shall be accompanied with the 
    copy of the notification issued. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>78</number> 
    The application shall be made jointly by the registered proprietor of the 
    geographical indication in India and by all the producers of the 
    geographical indication whose name has been entered in the register as 
    authorised user in Part B.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>79</number> 
    Consideration by the Registrar.—The 
    Registrar on receipt of the application for additional protection for such 
    goods in respect of a registered geographical indication in India shall 
    examine whether there are measurable attributes to the particular 
    geographical indication in relation to the goods or classes of goods in 
    question with special regard to the reputation of the goods or classes of 
    goods on a global scale, which requires the additional protection envisaged 
    under sub-section (2) of section 22 be conferred against usurpation or 
    imitation of the geographical indication even where the true origin of the 
    goods or classes of goods is indicated or if the registered geographical 
    indication is used in translated form or is accompanied by terms such as 
    “kind”, “type”, “style”, “imitation” or other like expressions. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>80</number> 
    Hearing before refusing an application.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If on consideration of the application or any other matter which the 
    applicant may or may be required to furnish, the Registrar has any 
    objections to the acceptance of the application or proposes to accept it 
    subject to such conditions, as he may think right to impose, the Registrar 
    shall communicate such objections or proposals in writing to the applicant. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    decision of the Registrar under sub-rule (l) after a hearing or without a 
    hearing if the applicant has duly communicated his observations in writing 
    and has stated that he does not desire to be heard shall be communicated to 
    the applicant in writing and if the applicant intends to appeal from such 
    decisions, he may within two months from the date of such communication 
    request the Registrar requiring him to state in writing the grounds and the 
    material used by him in arriving at his decision. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>81</number> 
    Entry in the register.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the Registrar decides to allow the geographical indication in respect 
    of which additional protection is to be provided as envisaged under 
    sub-section (2) of section 22, he shall enter in the register a summary of 
    the grounds and the material used by him in arriving at his decision to 
    accord additional protection to the notified goods in respect of the 
    relevant geographical indication application. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    entry in Part A of the Register shall state the date on which the 
    application for additional protection was made, the name, description and 
    principal place of business in India of the registered proprietor and if 
    they do not carry on business in India their address for service in India. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>82</number> 
    (A) Single application.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where an application for the registration of a geographical indication for 
    goods is made under sub-section (3) of section 11, the specification of 
    goods contained in it shall set out the classes in consecutive numerical 
    order beginning with the lowest number and list under each class the goods 
    appropriate to that class. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    the specification of goods contained in the original application for the 
    registration of a geographical indication lists by reference to a class or 
    classes in the Fourth Schedule in which they do not fall, the Registrar 
    shall require the applicant to divide the application on payment of a 
    divisional fee in Form GI-5 to the class or classes to which the application 
    relates together with such class fee as may be appropriate. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Applications filed under sub-section (3) of section 11 when ordered to be 
    advertised shall be published in a separate section of the Geographical 
    Indications Journal. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Registrar shall issue a single certificate of registration in respect of an 
    application made under sub-section (3) of section 11 which has proceeded to 
    registration. 
 <subsection>
<number>B</number> 
    Divisional Application.—(1) 
    Where an application is made in Form GI-5 under proviso to section 15 for 
    the division of a single application, such an application shall be divided 
    into two or more separate applications upon the payment of a division fee 
    and such class fees as are appropriate.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> At 
    any time before registration an applicant may request the Registrar for a 
    division of his application for registration (the original applications) 
    into two or more separate applications (divisional applications), indicating 
    for each division the specification of goods. The Registrar shall treat each 
    divisional application as a separate application for registration with the 
    same filing date as the original application. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In 
    the case of a request to divide some, but not all, of the goods in a class, 
    a divisional fee for separate application to be created by division shall be 
    submitted. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If 
    the request to divide does not include necessary fee or is otherwise 
    deficient, the Registrar will notify the applicant of deficiency. The 
    applicant must correct any such deficiency within thirty days. If the 
    applicant fails to correct the deficiency within the time provided, the 
    request will be considered as abandoned and the application will be 
    proceeded further without regard to the request. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> 
    Where a request to divide an application is received, the Registrar shall 
    assign an additional separate new serial number or numbers, as the case may 
    be, and it will be cross referenced with the original application. Such 
    additional separate application or applications shall be assigned same 
    filing date as the original application. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> For 
    the removal doubt, it is clarified that no new registration is effected when 
    a single application is divided. On the contrary, applications already filed 
    are merely separated or divided into individual files. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>83</number> 
    Extension of time.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    An application for extension of time under section 64 (not being a time 
    expressly provided in the Act or a time for the extension of which provision 
    is made in the rules) shall be made on Form GI-9. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Upon 
    an application made under sub-rule (1) the Registrar, if satisfied that the 
    circumstances are such as to justify the extension of the time applied for, 
    may subject to the provisions of the rules where a maximum time limit is 
    prescribed and subject to such conditions as he may think fit to impose, 
    extend the time and notify the parties accordingly and the extension may be 
    granted though the time for doing the act or taking the proceeding for which 
    it is applied for has already expired. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>84</number> 
    Exercise of discretionary power of Registrar.—The 
    time within which a person entitled under section 61 to an opportunity of 
    being heard shall exercise his option of requiring to be heard shall, save 
    as otherwise expressly provided in the Act or the rules, be one month from 
    the date of a notice which the Registrar shall give to such person before 
    determining the matter with reference to which such person is entitled to be 
    heard. If within that month such person is required to be heard, the 
    Registrar shall appoint a date for the hearing and shall give 10 day’s 
    notice thereof. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>85</number> 
    Notification of decision.—The 
    decision of the Registrar in the exercise of any discretionary power given 
    to him by the Act or the rules shall be notified to the person affected. s

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>86</number> 
    Amendments and correction of irregularity in procedure.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any document, communication or other representation respecting a 
    geographical indication or an authorised user may be amended and any 
    irregularity in procedure which in the opinion of the Registrar, may be 
    obviated without detriment to the interests of any person, may be corrected, 
    if the Registrar thinks fit and proper on such terms as he may direct. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Registrar may require the amendment of any application or representation of 
    a geographical indication or any other document or the addition of any 
    matter thereto in order to bring it in accordance with the formal 
    requirements of the Act. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>87</number> 
    Directions not otherwise prescribed.—Where 
    in the opinion of the Registrar, it is necessary for the proper prosecution 
    or completion of any proceedings under the Act or rules for a person to 
    perform an act, file a document or produce evidence, which is not provided 
    for by the Act or the rules, the Registrar may by notice in writing require 
    the person to perform the act, file the document or produce the evidence, 
    specified in the notice. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>88</number> 
    Hearings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to sub-rule (2) of rule 4 in relation to a geographical indication 
    for which an application for registration is made on or after the notified 
    date, the application as well as any proceeding under the Act and the rules 
    shall, in the event of a hearing becoming necessary, be heard at the 
    appropriate office of the Geographical Indications Registry at which such 
    application was made under sub-section (4) of section 11, or at such place 
    within the territorial jurisdiction of that office as the Registrar may deem 
    proper. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where an officer exercising the powers of the Registrar who has heard any 
    matter under the Act or the rules, has reserved orders therein, is 
    transferred from one office of the Registry to another or reverts to another 
    appointment before passing an order or rendering decision therein, he may, 
    if the Registrar so directs, pass the order or render the decision as if he 
    had continued to be the officer in the office of the Registry where the 
    matter was heard. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>89</number> 
    Costs in uncontested cases.—Where 
    any opposition duly instituted under the rules is not contested by the 
    applicant, the Registrar in deciding whether costs should be awarded to the 
    opponent shall consider whether the proceedings might have been avoided if 
    reasonable notice had been given by the opponent to the applicant before the 
    notice of opposition was filed. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>90</number> 
    Exception to rule 89.—Notwithstandings 
    anything in rule 89, costs in respect of fees specified under entries, 7, 8 
    and 9 of the First Schedule and of all stamps used on and affixed to 
    affidavits used in the proceedings shall follow the event. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>91</number> 
    Scale of costs.—Subject 
    to the provisions of rules 89 and 90, in all proceedings before the 
    Registrar the Registrar may, save as otherwise expressly provided by the 
    Act, award such costs, not exceeding the amount admissible therefor, as he 
    considers reasonable having regard to all the circumstances of the case. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>92</number> 
    Application for review of Registrar’s decision.—An 
    application to the Registrar for the review of his decision under clause (c) 
    of section 60 shall be made on Form GI-7 within one month from the date of 
    such decision or within such further period not exceeding one month 
    thereafter as the Registrar may on request allow, and shall be accompanied 
    by a statement setting forth the grounds on which the review is sought. 
    Where the decision in question concerns any other person in addition to the 
    applicant, such application and statement shall be left in triplicate and 
    the Registrar shall forthwith transmit a copy each of the application and 
    statement to the other person concerned. The Registrar may, after giving the 
    parties an opportunity of being heard, reject or grant the application, 
    either unconditionally or subject to any conditions or limitations, as he 
    thinks fit. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>93</number> 
    Form, etc., of Affidavits.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Affidavits required by the Act and the rules to be filed at the 
    Geographical Indications Registry or furnished to the Registrar, unless 
    otherwise provided in the Second Schedule, shall be headed in the matter or 
    matters to which they relate, shall be drawn up in the first person, and 
    shall be divided into paragraphs consecutively numbered, and each paragraph 
    shall, as far as practicable, be confined to one subject. Every affidavit 
    shall state the description and the true place of abode of the person making 
    the same, shall bear the name and address of the person filing it and shall 
    state on whose behalf it is filed. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where two or more persons join in an affidavit, each of them shall depose 
    separately to such facts which are within his personal knowledge and those 
    facts shall be stated in separate paragraphs. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Affidavits shall be taken— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    In India before any court or person 
    having by law authority to receive evidence, or before any officer empowered 
    by such court as aforesaid to administer oaths or to take affidavits, 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    in any country or place outside 
    India—before a diplomatic or consular officer, within the meaning of the 
    Diplomatic and Consular Officers (Oaths and Fee) Act, 1948, of such country 
    or place, or before a notary public, or before a judge or magistrate, of the 
    country or place. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    person before whom an affidavit is taken shall state the date on which and 
    the place where the same is taken and shall affix his seal, if any, or the 
    seal of the court to which he is attached, thereto and sign his name and 
    description at the end thereof. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Any 
    affidavit purporting to have affixed, impressed or subscribed thereto or 
    therein the seal or signature of any person authorised by sub-rule (3) to 
    take an affidavit, in testimony of the affidavit having been taken before 
    him, may be admitted by the Registrar without proof of the genuineness of 
    the seal or signature or of the official character of that person. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> 
    Alterations and interlineations shall, before an affidavit is sworn or 
    affirmed, be authenticated by the initials of the person before whom the 
    affidavit is taken. 
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> 
    Where the deponent is illiterate, blind or unacquainted with the language in 
    which the affidavit is written, a certificate by the person taking the 
    affidavit that the affidavit was read, translated or explained in his 
    presence to the deponent, that the deponent seemed perfectly to understand 
    it and that the deponent made his signature or mark in his presence, shall 
    appear in the jurat. 
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> 
    Every affidavit filed before the Registrar in connection with any of the 
    proceedings under the Act or the rules shall be duly stamped under the law 
    for the time being in force. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>94</number> 
    Inspection of documents.—The 
    documents mentioned in sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 78 shall be available for 
    inspection at the Head Office of the Geographical Indications Registry. A 
    copy of the register and such of the other documents mentioned in section 
    78, as the Central Government may by notification in the Official Gazette 
    direct, shall be available for inspection at each branch office of the 
    Geographical Indications Registry as and when established. The inspection 
    shall be on payment of the prescribed fee and at such times on all the days 
    on which the offices of the Geographical Indications Registry are not closed 
    to the public, as may be fixed by the Registrar. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>95</number> 
    Distribution of copies of Journal and other documents.—The 
    Central Government may direct the Registrar to distribute the journal and 
    any other document which it may consider necessary, to such places as may be 
    fixed by the Central Government in consultation with the State Governments 
    and notified from time to time in the Official Gazette. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>96</number> 
    Certified copies of documents.—The 
    Registrar may furnish certified copies of any entry in the register or 
    certified copies of any documents referred to in sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 
    79 or of any decision or order of the Registrar, or give a certificate other 
    than a certificate under sub-section (2) of section 16 as to any entry, 
    matter or thing which he is authorised or required by the Act or the rules 
    to make or do, upon receipt from any person of an application therefor on 
    Form GI-7 accompanied by the prescribed fee. The Registrar shall not be 
    obliged to include in any certificate or certified copy a copy of any 
    geographical indication unless he is furnished by the applicant with a copy 
    thereof suitable for the purpose. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>97</number> 
    Certificate for use in obtaining registration abroad.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where a certificate relating to the registration of a geographical 
    indication is desired for use in obtaining registration in any territory 
    outside India, the Registrar shall include in the certificate a copy of the 
    geographical indication and may require the applicant for the certificate to 
    furnish him with a copy of the geographical indication suitable for that 
    purpose, and if the applicant fails to do so, the Registrar may refuse to 
    issue the certificate. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where a geographical indication is registered, without limitation of colour, 
    the copy of the geographical indication to be included in the certificate, 
    may be either in the colour in which it appears upon the register or in any 
    other colour or colours and it shall be stated in the certificate that the 
    geographical indication is registered without limitation of colour. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Registrar may state in the certificate such particulars concerning the 
    application for registration or the registration of the geographical 
    indication as may deem fit to him, and may specify the terms/and conditions 
    and other limitation appearing on the Register. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>98</number> 
    Time for appeal.—(l) 
    An appeal to the Intellectual Property Appellate Board from any decision of 
    the Registrar under the Act or the rules shall be made within three months 
    from the date of receipt of such decision or within such further time as the 
    said Appellate Board may allow.
 <section>
<number>2</number> A 
    copy of every application to the said Intellectual Property Appellate Board 
    under the Act or the rules shall be served on the Registrar. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>99</number> 
    Certificate of validity to be noted.—Where 
    the Intellectual Property Appellate Board has certified as provided in 
    section 72 with regard to the validity of a registered geographical 
    indication, the proprietor thereof may request the Registrar on Form GI-7 to 
    add to the entry in the register a note that the certificate of validity has 
    been granted in the course of the proceedings, particulars of which shall be 
    given in the request. An officially certified copy of the certificate shall 
    be sent with the request, and the Registrar shall record a note to that 
    effect in the register and publish the note in the Journal. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>100</number> 
    Return of exhibits.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the exhibits produced in any matter or proceeding under the Act or the 
    rules are no longer required in the Geographical Indications Registry, the 
    Registrar may notify the party concerned to take back the exhibits within a 
    time specified by him and if the party fails to do so, such exhibits shall 
    be dealt with in the manner mentioned under sub-rule (2) below. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where any exhibits have been produced in any proceeding, the Registrar may, 
    if satisfied that it is no longer necessary to retain them, cause them to be 
    destroyed, after the expiration of six months from the notified date. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>101</number> 
    Destruction of records.—Where 
    an application for the registration of a geographical indication or an 
    authorised user has been withdrawn abandoned or refused or the geographical 
    indication or the authorised user has been removed from the register, the 
    Registrar may, at the expiration of three years after the application is so 
    withdrawn or is abandoned or is refused or after the geographical indication 
    is removed from the register, as the case may be, destroy all or any of the 
    records relating to the application for the geographical indication or the 
    authorised user concerned. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>102</number> 
    Register of Geographical Indications Agents.—The 
    Registrar of Geographical Indications shall maintain a Register of 
    Geographical Indications Agents wherein shall be entered the name, address 
    of the place of residence, address of the principal place of business, the 
    nationality, qualifications and date of registration of every registered 
    Geographical Indications Agent. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>103</number> 
    Registration of existing registered trade marks agent.—(l) 
    Subject to rule 104 every person whose name is on the notified date on the 
    Register of Trade Marks Agents maintained under the Trade Marks Rules, 2002 
    shall be deemed to be registered as a Geographical Indications Agent under 
    the Act and the rules.
 <section>
<number>2</number> The 
    continuance fee of Geographical Indications Agents deemed to be registered 
    under sub-rule (l) shall be payable as and from the notified date. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Registrar may publish the Dress Code for Registered Geographical Indications 
    Agent in the Geographical Indications Journal. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Registrar may publish in the Journal a code of conduct for registered 
    Geographical Indications Agents. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>104</number> 
    Qualifications for registration.—Subject 
    to the provisions of rule 105, a person shall be qualified to be registered 
    as a Geographical Indications Agent if he— 
 <section>
<number>i</number>    is a citizen of India; 
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    is not less than 21 years of age; 
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>    has passed the examination prescribed 
    in rule 108 or is an Advocate within the meaning of the Advocates Act, 1961; 
 </section><section>
<number>iv</number>    is a graduate of any university in 
    India or possess an equivalent qualification; and 
 </section><section>
<number>v</number>    is, considered by the Registrar as a 
    fit and proper person to be registered as a Geographical Indications Agent. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>105</number> 
    Persons debarred from registration.—A 
    person shall not be eligible for registration as a Geographical Indications 
    Agent if he— 
 <section>
<number>i</number>    has been adjudged by a competent court 
    to be of unsound mind; 
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    is an undischarged insolvent; 
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>    being a discharged insolvent has not 
    obtained from the court a certificate to the effect that his insolvency was 
    caused by misfortunate without any misconduct on his part; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>iv</number>    has been convicted by a competent 
    court, whether within or without India of an offence punishable with 
    transportation or imprisonment, unless the offence of which he has been 
    convicted has been pardoned or unless on an application made by him, the 
    Central Government by order in this behalf, has removed the disability;
     
 </section><section>
<number>v</number>    being a legal practitioner has been 
    held guilty of professional misconduct by any High Court in India or by any 
    court beyond the limits of India;  
 </section><section>
<number>vi</number>    being a chartered accountant, or a 
    company secretary has been held guilty of negligence or misconduct by a High 
    Court; or  
 </section><section>
<number>vii</number>    being a registered Geographical 
    Indication Agent has been held guilty of professional misconduct by the 
    Registrar. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>106</number> 
    Manner of making application.—Subject 
    to sub-rule (2) of rule 4 all applications under the provisions of this Part 
    shall be made in triplicate, and shall be sent to or left at that office of 
    the Geographical Indications Registry within whose territorial limits the 
    principal place of business of the applicant is situate. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>107</number> 
    Application for registration as a Geographical Indications Agent.—(l) 
    Every person desiring to be registered as a Geographical Indications Agent 
    shall make an application on Form GI-8.
 <section>
<number>2</number> The 
    applicant shall furnish such further information bearing on his application 
    as may be required of him at any time by the Registrar. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>108</number> 
    Procedure on application and qualifying requirements.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    On receipt of an application for the registration of a person as a 
    Geographical Indications Agent, the Registrar, if satisfied that the 
    applicant fulfils the prescribed qualifications, shall appoint a date in the 
    due course on which the candidate will appear before him for a written 
    examination in Geographical Indications Law and the Practice and Procedure 
    in relation thereto and followed by an interview. The candidate will be 
    expected to possess a detailed knowledge of the provisions of the Act and 
    the rules and a knowledge of the elements on law of geographical indication. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    qualifying mark for the written examination and for interview shall be 40 
    per cent and 50 per cent respectively and a candidate shall be declared to 
    have passed the examination only if he obtained an aggregate of 50 per cent 
    of the total marks. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>109</number> 
    Certificate of registration.—After 
    a candidate has been interviewed and any further information bearing on his 
    application, which the Registrar may consider necessary, has been obtained 
    and if the Registrar considers the applicant eligible and qualified for 
    registration as a Geographical Indications Agent, he shall send an 
    intimation to that effect to the applicant and any person so intimated may 
    pay the prescribed fee in Form GI-8 for his registration as a Geographical 
    Indications Agent. Upon receipt of the prescribed fee, the Registrar shall 
    cause the applicant’s name to be entered in the register of Geographical 
    Indications Agents and shall issue to him a certificate on Form O-4 of his 
    registration as a Geographical Indications Agents. s

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>110</number> 
    Continuance of a name in the Register of Geographical Indications Agents.—The 
    continuance of a person’s name in the Register of Geographical Indications 
    Agents shall be subject to his payment of the fees prescribed in Form GI-8. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>111</number> 
    Removal of agent’s name from the Register of Geographical Indications 
    Agents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Registrar shall remove from the Register of Geographical Indications 
    Agents the name of any registered Geographical Indications Agent— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    from whom a request has been received 
    to that effect; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    from whom the annual fee has not been 
    received on the expiry of three months from the date on which it became due. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Registrar shall remove from the Register of Geographical Indications Agents 
    the name of any Registered Geographical Indications agent— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    who is found to have been subject at 
    the time of his registration, or thereafter has become subject to any of the 
    disabilities stated in clauses (i) to (vi) of rule 105; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    whom the Registrar has declared not to 
    be a fit and proper person to remain in the Register by reason of any act of 
    negligence, misconduct or dishonesty committed in his professional capacity; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    whose name has been entered in the 
    register by an error or on account of misrepresentation or suppression of 
    material fact: 
 
Provided 
    that before making such declaration under clauses (b) and (c) the Registrar 
    shall call upon the person concerned to show cause why his registration 
    should not be cancelled and shall make such further enquiry, if any, as it 
    may consider necessary. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Registrar shall remove from the Register of Geographical Indications Agents 
    the name of any registered Geographical Indications Agent who is dead. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    removal of the name of any person from the Register of Geographical 
    Indications Agents shall be notified in the Official Gazette and in the 
    Journal and shall, wherever possible, be communicated to the person 
    concerned. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>112</number> 
    Power of Registrar to refuse to deal with certain agents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Registrar may refuse to recognise— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    any individual whose name has been 
    removed from, and not restored to the Register; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    any person, not being registered as a 
    Geographical Indications Agent, who in the opinion of the Registrar is 
    engaged wholly or mainly in acting as agent in applying for Geographical 
    Indications in India or elsewhere in the name or for the benefit of the 
    person by whom he is employed; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    any company or firm, if any person whom 
    the Registrar could refuse to recognise as agent in respect of any business 
    under these rules, is acting as a director or manager of the company or is a 
    partner in the firm. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Registrar shall also refuse to recognise as agent in respect of any business 
    under this rule any person who neither resides nor has a place of business 
    in India. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>113</number> 
    Restoration of removed names.—The 
    Registrar may, on an application made on Form GI-8 within six months from 
    the date of removal of his name from the Register of Geographical 
    Indications Agent accompanied by the fee specified in the First Schedule 
    from a person whose name has been removed under clause (b) of sub-rule (l) 
    of rule 111, restore his name to the Register of Geographical Indications 
    Agent and continue his name therein for a period of one year from the date 
    on which his last annual fee became due. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>114</number> 
    Alteration in the Register of Geographical Indications Agents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A registered Geographical Indications Agent may apply for alteration of his 
    name, address of the place of residence, address of the principal place of 
    business or qualifications entered in the Register of Geographical 
    Indications Agent. On receipt of such application the Registrar shall cause 
    the necessary alteration to be made in the Register of Geographical 
    Indications Agents. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every alteration made in the Register of Geographical Indications Agents 
    shall be notified in the Journal. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>115</number> 
    Publication of the Register of Geographical Indications Agents.—The 
    Register of Geographical Indications Agents shall be published from time to 
    time and a complete list thereof at least once in two years in the 
    Geographical Indications Journal as the Registrar may deem fit, the entries 
    being arranged in the alphabetical order of the surnames of the registered 
    Geographical Indications Agents and copies thereof shall be placed on sale. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>

    <number>116</number> Appeal.—An 
    appeal shall lie to Intellectual Property Appellate Board from any order or 
    decision of the Registrar in regard to the registration of Geographical 
    Indications Agents under Part II of these rules, and the decision of the 
    Appellate Board shall be final and binding. 

 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   15th September, 2003
    vide S.O. 1051(E), dated 15-9-2003, published in the Gazette of 
    India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(ii), dated 15th September, 2003.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>