<act><tid>1173811</tid>
<title>THE TRANSFER OF PROPERTY (AMENDMENT) 
SUPPLEMENTARY ACT, <year>1929</year></title>

ACT NO. 21 OF <year>1929</year>
An Act to supplement the Transfer of Property (Amendment) 
Act, <year>1929</year>.

[ 4th October, <year>1929</year>.]

WHEREAS by reason of the passing of the Transfer of Property 
 (Amendment) Act, <year>1929</year>, it is expedient that certain amendments 
whould be made in certain other enactments; It is hereby enacted 
as follows:-



<article><tid>143288</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>398028</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Transfer of Property (Amendment) 
Supplementary Act, <year>1929</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>421981</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on the first day of April, <year>1930</year>.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1480930</tid>
<number> 15</number> 
<section><tid>1967123</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as provided in sub- section (2), nothing in this Act  
shall be deemed to affect-

<subsection><tid>23149</tid>
<number>a</number>the terms or incidents of any transfer or disposition of 
property made or effected before the first day of April, <year>1930</year>;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>418567</tid>
<number>b</number>the validity, invalidity, effect or consequences of anything 
already done or suffered before the aforesaid date;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1444862</tid>
<number>c</number>any right, title, obligation or liability already acquired; 
accrued or incurred before such date;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1919132</tid>
<number>d</number>any remedy or proceeding in respect of such right, title, 
obligation or liability; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>909069</tid>
<number>e</number>anything done in the course of any proceeding pending in any 
Court on the aforesaid date;
and any such remedy or proceeding may be enforced, instituted or 
continued, as the case may be, as if this ACt had not been passed.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>358897</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in section 9 of this Act, 
in the Presidency of Bombay and such other territories as the 
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
specify in this behalf, f a suit by a mortgagee for foreclosure or 
sale on a mortgage by deposit of title- deeds may be instituted 
within two years from the date of the commencement of this ACt, or 
within sixty years from the date when the money secured by the 
mortgage became due, whichever period expires first; and no such 
suit instituted within the said period of sixty years and pending 
at the date of the commencement of this ACt, either in a Court of 
first instance or of appeal, shall be dismissed on the ground that 
the twelve years' rule of limitation is applicable.

</section>

</article>



 </act>