<act><title>

The
National Council for Teacher Education 
Act, 1993</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>1</number>
Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
This Act may be called the National Council for Teacher Education Act, 1993.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
It extends to the whole of India, except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
It shall come into force on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint. 


   






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In
this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 <section><number>a</number>
“appointed day” means the date of establishment of the National
Council for Teacher Education under sub-section (1) of section 3;
 </section><section><number>b</number>
“Chairperson” means the Chairperson of the Council appointed under
clause (a) of sub­section (4) of section 3;
 </section><section><number>c</number>
“Council” means the National Council for Teacher Education
established under sub­section (1) of section 3;
 </section><section><number>d</number>
“examining body” means a University, agency or authority to which an
institution is affiliated for conducting examinations in teacher education
qualifications;
 </section><section><number>e</number>
“institution” means an institution which offers courses or training
in teacher education;
 </section><section><number>f</number>
“Member” means a Member of the Council and includes the Chairperson
and Vice-Chairperson;
 </section><section><number>g</number>
“Member-Secretary” means the Member-Secretary of the Council
appointed under clause (c) of sub-section (4) of section 3;
 </section><section><number>h</number>
“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under section 31;
 </section><section><number>i</number>
“recognised institution” means an institution recognised by the
Council under section 14;
 </section><section><number>j</number>
“Regional Committee” means a committee established under
section 20;
 </section><section><number>k</number>
“regulations” means regulations made under section 32;
 </section><section><number>l</number>
“teacher education” means programmes of education, research or
training of persons for equipping them to teach at pre-primary, primary,
secondary and senior secondary stages in schools, and includes non-formal
education, part-lime education, adult education and correspondence education;
 </section><section><number>m</number>
“teacher education qualification” means a degree, diploma or
certificate in teacher education awarded by a University or examining body in
accordance with the provisions of this Act;
 </section><section><number>n</number>
“University” means a University defined under clause (f) of section 2
of the University Grants Commission Act, 1956 (3 of 1956), and includes an
institution deemed to be a University under section 3 of that Act;
 </section><section><number>o</number>
“Vice-Chairperson” means the Vice-Chairperson of the Council
appointed under clause (b) of sub-section (4) of section 3.
  
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>3</number>
Establishment of the Council.—
<section><number>1</number>
With effect from such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the
Official Gazette, appoint there shall be established a Council to be called the
National Council for Teacher Education. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Council shall be a body corporate by the name aforesaid, having perpetual
succession and a common seal with power to contract and shall, by the said name,
sue and be sued.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
The head office of the Council shall be at Delhi and the Council may, with the
previous approval of the Central Government, establish regional offices at other
places in India.
 </section><section><number>4</number>
The Council shall consist of the following Members, namely:—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
a Chairperson to be appointed by the Central Government;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
a Vice-Chairperson to be appointed by the Central Government;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
a Member-Secretary to be appointed by the Central Government;
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
the Secretary to the Government of India in the Department dealing with
Education ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>
the Chairman, University Grants Commission established under section 4 of
the University Grants Commission Act, 1956 (3 of 1956) or a member thereof
nominated by him, ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>
the Director, National Council of Educational Research and Training, ex
officio;
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number>
the Director, National Institute of Educational Planning and
Administration, ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number>
the Adviser (Education), Planning Commission, ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number>
the Chairman, Central Boards of Secondary Education, ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number>
the Financial Adviser to the Government of India in the Department
dealing with Education, ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number>
the Member-Secretary, All-India Council for Technical Education, ex
officio;
 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number>
the Chairpersons of all Regional Committees, ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection><number>m</number>
thirteen persons possessing experience and knowledge in the field of
education or teaching to be appointed by the Central Government as under, from
amongst the—
 <subsubsection><number>i</number>
Deans of Faculties of Education and Professor
of Education in Universities —Fourt;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> experts in secondary teacher education — One;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number> experts in pre-primary and primary teacher
education — Three;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iv</number> experts in non-formal education and adult
education — Two;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>v</number> experts in the field of natural sciences, social
sciences, linguistics, vocational education, work
experience, educational technology and special
education, by rotation, in the manner prescribed — Three;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>n</number>
nine Members to be appointed by the Central Government to represent the
States and the Union territory Administrations in the manner prescribed;
 </subsection><subsection><number>o</number>
three Members of Parliament of whom one shall be nominated by the
Chairman of the Council of States and two by the Speaker of the House of the
People;
 </subsection><subsection><number>p</number>
three Members to be appointed by the Central Government from amongst
teachers of primary and secondary education and teachers of recognised
institutions.
 </subsection></section><section><number>5</number>
It is hereby declared that the office of the Member of the Council shall not
disqualify its holder for being chosen as or for being a member of either House
of Parliament.
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>4</number>
Term of office and conditions of service of Members.—
<section><number>1</number>
The Chairperson, Vice-Chairperson and the Member-Secretary shall hold office on
a full-time basis.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The term of office of the Chairperson, the Vice-Chairperson and the
Member-Secretary shall be four years, or till they complete the age of sixty
years, whichever is earlier.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
The conditions of service of the Chairperson, the Vice-Chairperson and the
Member-Secretary shall be such as may be prescribed.
 </section><section><number>4</number>
The term of office of Members [other than the Members specified in clauses (a)
to (l) and clauses (n) and (o) of sub-section (4) of section 3] shall be two
years or till fresh appointments are made, whichever is later, and other
conditions of service of such Members shall be such as may be prescribed.
 </section><section><number>5</number>
If a casual vacancy occurs in the office of Chairperson, whether by reason of
death, resignation or inability to discharge the functions of a Chairperson
owing to illness or other incapacity, the Vice-Chairperson holding office as
such 
 </section><section><number>6</number>
If a casual vacancy occurs in the office of the Vice-Chairperson or any other
Member, whether by reason of death, resignation or inability to discharge his
functions owing to illness or other incapacity, such vacancy shall be filled up
by making fresh appointment and the person so appointed shall hold office for
the remainder of the term of the office of the person in whose place such person
is so appointed.
 </section><section><number>7</number>
The Chairperson shall, in addition to presiding over the meetings of the
Council, exercise and discharge such powers and duties of the Council as may be
delegated to him by the Council and such other powers and duties as may be
prescribed.
 </section><section><number>8</number>
The Vice-Chairperson shall perform such functions as may be assigned to him by
the Chairperson from time to time.
  
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>5</number>
Disqualification for office of Member.—A
person shall be disqualified for being appointed as a Member if he—
 <section><number>a</number>
has been convicted and sentenced to imprisonment for an offence, which,
in the opinion of the Central Government, involves moral turpitude; or
 </section><section><number>b</number>
is an undischarged insolvent; or
 </section><section><number>c</number>
is of unsound mind and stands so declared by a competent court; or
 </section><section><number>d</number>
has been removed or dismissed from the service of the Government or a
body corporate owned or controlled by the Government; or
 </section><section><number>e</number>
has in the opinion of the Central Government such financial or other
interest in the Council as is likely to affect prejudicially the discharge by
him of his functions as Member.
  
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>6</number>
Vacation of office of Member.—The
Central Government shall remove a Member if he—
 <section><number>a</number>
becomes subject to any of the disqualifications mentioned in
section 5:
 Provided that no Member shall be
removed on the ground that he has become subject to the disqualification
mentioned in clause (e) of that section, unless he has been given a reasonable
opportunity of being heard in the matter; or
 </section><section><number>b</number>
refuses to act or becomes incapable of acting; or
 </section><section><number>c</number>
is, without obtaining leave of absence from the Council, absent from
three consecutive meetings of the Council; or
 </section><section><number>d</number>
in the opinion of the Central Government, has so abused his position as
to render his continuance in office detrimental to the public interest:
 
Provided that no Member shall be
removed under this clause unless he has been given a reasonable opportunity of
being heard in the matter.
  
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>7</number>
Meetings of the Council.—
<section><number>1</number> The
Council shall meet at such time and places, and shall observe such rules of
procedure in regard to the transaction of business at its meetings (including
the quorum at such meetings) as may be provided by regulations:
 Provided
that the Council shall meet at least once every year.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Chairperson, and in the absence of the Chairperson, the Vice-Chairperson
shall preside at the meetings of the Council.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
If for any reason the Chairperson and the Vice-Chairperson, both are unable to
attend any meeting of the Council, any other Member chosen by the Members
present at the meeting shall preside at that meeting.
 </section><section><number>4</number>
All questions which come up before any meeting of the Council shall be decided
by a majority of votes of the Members present and voting and in the event of any
equality of votes, the Chairperson, or in the absence of the Chairperson the
person presiding, shall have and exercise a second or casting vote.
  
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>8</number>
Vacancies, etc., not to invalidate proceedings of the Council.—No
act or proceeding of the Council shall be invalid merely by reason of—
 <section><number>a</number>
any vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution of, the Council; or
 </section><section><number>b</number>
any defect in the appointment of a person acting as a Member of the
Council; or
 </section><section><number>c</number>
any irregularity in the procedure of the Council not affecting the merits
of the case.
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>9</number>
Power to co-opt.—
<section><number>1</number> The Council may
co-opt, in such manner and for such purposes as may be determined by
regulations, not more than three persons, whose assistance or advice it may
desire in carrying out any of the provisions of this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The person co-opted by the Council under sub-section (1) for any purpose shall
have a right to take part in the discussions relevant to that purpose, but shall
not have a right to vote at a meeting of the Council, and shall not be a Member
for any other purpose.
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>10</number>
Appointment of officers and other employees of the Council.—
<section><number>1</number>
For the purpose of enabling the Council to discharge its functions efficiently
under this Act, the Council shall, subject to such regulations as may be made in
this behalf, appoint (whether on deputation or otherwise) such number of
officers and other employees as it may consider necessary:
 Provided
that the category of posts equivalent to Group ‘A’ posts in the Central
Government shall be subject to the approval of the Central Government.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Every officer or other employee appointed by the Council shall be subject to
such conditions of service as may be determined by regulations.
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>11</number>
Authentication of the orders and other instruments of the Council.—All
orders and decisions of the Council shall be authenticated by the signature of
the Chairperson or any other Member authorised by the Council in this behalf,
and all other instruments issued by the Council shall be authenticated by the
signature of the Member-Secretary or any other officer of the Council authorised
in like manner in this behalf by the Chairperson.
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>12</number>
Functions of the Council.—It shall be the duty of the Council to take all such
steps as it may think fit for ensuring planned and co-ordinated development of
teacher education and for the determination and maintenance of standards for
teacher education and for the purposes of performing its functions under this
Act, the Council may—
 <section><number>a</number>
undertake surveys and studies relating to various aspects of teacher
education and publish the result thereof;
 </section><section><number>b</number>
make recommendations to the Central and State Governments, Universities,
University Grants Commission and recognised institutions in the matter of
preparation of suitable plans and programmes in the field of teacher education;
 </section><section><number>c</number>
co-ordinate and monitor teacher education and its development in the
country;
 </section><section><number>d</number>
lay down guidelines in respect of minimum qualifications for a person to
be employed as a teacher in schools or in recognised institutions;
 </section><section><number>e</number>
lay down norms for any specified category of courses or training in
teacher education, including the minimum eligibility criteria for admission
thereof, and the method of selection of candidates, duration of the course,
course contents and mode of curriculum;
 </section><section><number>f</number>
lay down guidelines for compliance by recognised institutions, for
starting new courses or training and for providing physical and instructional
facilities, staffing pattern and staff qualifications;
 </section><section><number>g</number>
lay down standards in respect of examinations leading to teacher
education qualifications, criteria for admission to such examinations and
schemes of courses of training;
 </section><section><number>h</number>
lay down guidelines regarding tuition fees and other fees chargeable by
recognised institutions;
 </section><section><number>i</number>
promote and conduct innovation and research in various areas of teacher
education and disseminate the results thereof;
 </section><section><number>j</number>
examine and review periodically the implementation of the norms,
guidelines and standards laid down by the Council, and to suitably advise the
recognised institutions;
 </section><section><number>k</number>
evolve suitable performance appraisal systems, norms and mechanisms for
enforcing accountability on recognised institutions;
 </section><section><number>l</number>
formulate schemes for various levels of teacher education and identify
recognised institutions and set up new institutions for teacher development
programmes;
 </section><section><number>m</number>
take all necessary steps to prevent commercialisation of teacher
education; and
 </section><section><number>n</number>
perform such other functions as may be entrusted to it by the Central
Government. 
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article> <number>13</number> Inspection.—
<section><number>1</number>
For the purposes of ascertaining whether the recognised institutions are
functioning in accordance with the provisions of this Act, the Council may cause
inspection of any such institution, to be made by such persons as it may direct,
and in such manner as may be prescribed.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Council shall communicate to the institution the date on which inspection
under sub­-section (1) is to be made and the institution shall be entitled to
be associated with the inspection in such manner as may be prescribed.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
The Council shall communicate to the said institution, its views in regard to
the results of any such inspection and may, after ascertaining the opinion of
that institution, recommend to that institution the action to be taken as a
result of such inspection.
 </section><section><number>4</number>
All communications to the institution under this section shall be made to the
executive authority thereof, and the executive authority of the institution
shall report to the Council the action, if any, which is proposed to be taken
for the purposes of implementing any such recommendation as is referred to in
sub-section (3).
  
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>14</number>
Recognition of institutions offering course or training in teacher education.—
<section><number>1</number>
Every institution offering or intending to offer a course or training in teacher
education on or after the appointed day, may, for grant of recognition under
this Act, make an application to the Regional Committee concerned in such form
and in such manner as may be determined by regulations: 
 Provided
that an institution offering a course or training in teacher education
immediately before the appointed day, shall be entitled to continue such course
or training for a period of six months, if it has made an application for
recognition within the said period and until the disposal of the application by
the Regional Committee.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The fee to be paid along with the application under sub-section (1) shall be
such as may be prescribed.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
On receipt of an application by the Regional Committee from any institution
under sub-section (1), and after obtaining from the institution concerned such
other particulars as it may consifer necessary, it shall,—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
if it is satisfied that such institution has adequate financial
resources, accommodation, library, qualified staff, laboratory and that it
fulfils such other conditions required for proper functioning of the institution
for a course or training in teacher education, as may be determined by
regulations, pass an order granting recognition to such institution, subject to
such conditions as may be determined by regulations; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
if it is of the opinion that such institution does not fulfil the
requirements laid down in sub-clause (a), pass an order refusing recognition to
such institution for reasons to be recorded in writing:
 Provided
that before passing an order under sub-clause (b), the Regional Committee shall
provide a reasonable opportunity to the concerned institution for making a
written representation.
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number>
Every order granting or refusing recognition to an institution for a course or
training in teacher education under sub-section (3) shall be published in the
Official Gazette and communicated in writing for appropriate action to such
institution and to the concerned examining body, the local authority or the
State Government and the Central Government.
 </section><section><number>5</number>
Every institution, in respect of which recognition has been refused shall
discontinue the course or training in teacher education from the end of the
academic session next following the date of receipt of the order refusing
recognition passed under clause (b) of sub-section (3).
 </section><section><number>6</number>
Every examining body shall, on receipt of the order under sub-section (4),—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
grant affiliation to the institution, where recognition has been granted;
or
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
cancel the affiliation of the institution, where recognition has been
refused.
  





 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>15</number>
Permission for a new course or training by recognised institution.—
<section><number>1</number>
Where any recognised institution intends to start any new course or training in
teacher education, it may make an application to seek permission therefor to the
Regional Committee concerned in such form and in such manner as may be
determined by regulations.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The fees to be paid along with the application under sub-section (1) shall be
such as may be prescribed.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
On receipt of an application from an institution under sub-section (1), and
after obtaining from the recognised institution such other particulars as may be
considered necessary, the Regional Committee shall,—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
if it is satisfied that such recognised institution has adequate
financial resources, accommodation, library, qualified staff, laboratory and
that 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
if it is of the opinion that such institution does not fulfil the
requirements laid down in sub-clause (a), pass an order refusing permission to
such institution, for reasons to be recorded in writing:
 Provided
that before passing an order refusing permission under sub-clause (b), the
Regional Committee shall provide a reasonable opportunity to the institution
concerned for making a written representation.
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number>
Every order granting or refusing permission to a recognised institution for a
new course or training in teacher education under sub-section (3), shall be
published in the Official Gazette and communicated in writing for appropriate
action to such recognised institution and to the concerned examining body, the
local authority, the State Government and the Central Government.
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>16</number>
Affiliating body to grant affiliation after recognition or permission by the
Council.—Notwithstanding anything
contained in any other law for the time being in force, no examining body shall,
on or after the appointed day,—
 <section><number>a</number>
grant affiliation, whether provisional or otherwise, to any institution;
or
 </section><section><number>b</number>
hold examination, whether provisional or otherwise, for a course or
training conducted by a recognised institution,
 unless
the institution concerned has obtained recognition from the Regional Committee
concerned, under section 14 or permission for a course or training under section
15.
  





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>17</number>
Contravention of provisions of the Act and consequences thereof.—
<section><number>1</number>
Where the Regional Committee is, on its own motion or on any representation
received from any person, satisfied that a recognised institution has
contravened any of the provisions of this Act, or the rules, regulations orders
made or issued thereunder, or any condition subject to which recognition under
sub-section (3) of section 14 or permission under sub-section (3) of section 15
was granted, it may withdraw recognition of such recognised institution, for
reasons to be recorded in writing:
 Provided
that no such order against the recognised institution shall be passed unless a
reasonable opportunity of making representation against the proposed order has
been given to such recognised institution:
 Provided
further that the order withdrawing or refusing recognition passed by the
Regional Committee shall come into force only with effect from the end of the
academic session next following the date of communication of such order.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
A copy of every order passed by the Regional Committee under sub-section (1),—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
shall be communicated to the recognised institution concerned and a copy
thereof shall also be forwarded simultaneously to the University or the
examining body to which such institution was affiliated for cancelling
affiliation; and
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
shall be published in the Official Gazette for general information.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number>
Once the recognition of a recognised institution is withdrawn under sub-section
(1), such institution shall discontinue the course or training in teacher
education, and the concerned University or the examining body shall cancel
affiliation of the institution in accordance with the order passed under
sub-section (1), with effect from the end of the academic session next following
the date of communication of the said order.
 </section><section><number>4</number>
If an institution offers any course or training in teacher education after the
coming into force of the order withdrawing recognition under sub-section (1), or
where an institution offering a course or training in teacher education
immediately before the appointed day fails or neglects to obtain recognition or
permission under this Act, the qualification in teacher education obtained
pursuant to such course or training or after undertaking a course or training in
such institution, shall not be treated as a valid qualification for purposes of
employment under the Central Government, any State Government or University, or
in any school, college or other educational body aided by the Central Government
or any State Government.
  
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 The National 
Council for Teacher Education  
Act, 1993
  
 <article>

1[<number>17A</number> No admission without 
recognition.—No institution shall 
admit any student to a course or training in teacher education, unless the 
institution concerned has obtained recognition under section 14 or permission 
under section 15, as the case may be.]
  



</article> 
 The National 
Council for Teacher Education  
Act, 1993
  
 <article><number>18</number> Appeals.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any person aggrieved by an order made under section 14 or section 15 or section 
17 of the Act may prefer an appeal to the Council within such period as may be 
prescribed.
 </section><section><number>2</number> No appeal shall be admitted 
if it is preferred after the expiry of the period prescribed therefor:
 Provided that an appeal may be 
admitted after the expiry of the period prescribed therefor, if the appellant 
satisfied the Council that he had sufficient cause for not preferring the appeal 
within the prescribed period.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every appeal made under this 
section shall be made in such form and shall be accompanied by a copy of the 
order appealed against and by such fees as may be prescribed.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The procedure for disposing 
of an appeal shall be such as may be prescribed:
 Provided that before disallowing 
an appeal, the appellant shall be given a reasonable opportunity to represent 
its case.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Council may confirm or 
reverse the order appealed against.
 


</section></article> 
 The National 
Council for Teacher Education  
Act, 1993
  
 <article>*<number>18A</number> Definition.—In 
this Chapter, “specified date” means the date of commencement of the National 
Council for Teacher Education (Amendment and Validation) Ordinance, 2006.
  



</article> 
 The National 
Council for Teacher Education  
Act, 1993
  
 <article>*<number>18B</number> Recognition of certain 
institutions.—
<section><number>1</number> Where an 
institution, offering a course or training in teacher education before the 
specified date, failed to make an application under sub-section (1) of section 
14, but an examining body granted affiliation to, and held examination for a 
course or training in teacher education conducted by, such institution, or such 
examination was due, before the specified date, the provisions of this Chapter 
shall apply in respect of such institution.
 </section><section><number>2</number> An institution falling under 
sub-section (1) may make an application to the Regional Committee concerned in 
such form and within such period and along with such fee, as may be prescribed.
 </section><section><number>3</number> An application under 
sub-section (2) shall be dealt with in such manner as may be prescribed.
 </section><section><number>4</number> An order granting 
recognition to an institution on its application under sub-section (2) shall be 
deemed to be effective from the date of grant of affiliation to it or holding of 
examination for a course or training conducted by it for the first time, 
whichever is earlier.
  



</section></article> 
 The National 
Council for Teacher Education  
Act, 1993
  
 <article>*<number>18C</number> Appeals of certain 
institutions.—
<section><number>1</number> Where an 
institution, offering a course or training in teacher education before the 
specified date, was refused recognition under clause (b) of sub-section (3) of 
section 14 and it failed to prefer an appeal under sub-section (1) of section 
18, but an examining body granted affiliation to, and held examination for a 
course or training conducted by, such institution, or such examination was due, 
before the specified date, such institution may prefer an appeal to the Council 
within a period of sixty days from the specified date.
 </section><section><number>2</number> An appeal under sub-section 
(1) shall be accompanied with such fee as is prescribed for an appeal under 
sub-section (3) of section 18.
 </section><section><number>3</number> An appeal under sub-section 
(1) shall be in the same form and dealt with in the same manner as an appeal 
preferred under sub-section (1) of section 18.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Where the Council reverses 
the order appealed under sub-section (1), an order granting recognition to an 
institution shall be deemed to be effective from the date of grant of 
affiliation to it or holding of examination for a course or training conducted 
by it for the first time, whichever is earlier.
  



</section></article> 
 The National 
Council for Teacher Education  
Act, 1993
  
 <article>*<number>18D</number> Validity of 
affiliations and examinations in respect of certain institutions.—Notwithstanding 
anything contained in section 16, where an institution offering a course or 
training in teacher education before the specified date, obtains recognition by 
virtue of sub-section (4) of section 18B or sub-section (4) of section 18C, the 
affiliation granted by an examining body to, and the examination held for a 
course or training conducted by, such institution, shall be deemed to have been 
validly granted and held, as the case may be.
  



</article> 
 The National 
Council for Teacher Education  
Act, 1993
  
 <article>*<number>18E</number> Validity of 
qualifications obtained from certain institutions.—Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-section (4) of section 17, where an institution 
offering a course or training in teacher education before the specified date, 
obtains recognition by virtue of sub-section (4) of section 18B or sub-section 
(4) of section 18C, the qualification in teacher education obtained pursuant to 
such course or training or after undertaking a course or training in such 
institution, shall be deemed to have been validly obtained.
  



</article> 
 The National 
Council for Teacher Education  
Act, 1993
  
 <article><number>18F</number> Validation.—Anything 
done or any action taken or any effect given in terms of sections 18B, 18C, 18D 
and 18E shall be valid, notwithstanding any judgment, decree or order of any 
court, tribunal or other authority to the contrary:
 Provided that where any 
unrecognised institution offering a course or training in teacher education 
before the specified date was directed by any court, tribunal or other authority 
to return the fees and pay compensation to students admitted by such 
institution, such institution shall comply with such direction:
 Provided further that in respect 
of students whose qualifications are deemed to have been validly obtained under 
section 18E, the amount of fees and compensation shall be credited to the Fund 
of the Council.
  



</article> 
 The National 
Council for Teacher Education  
Act, 1993
  
 <article><number>18G</number> Duration and savings.—This 
Chapter shall remain in force for a period of six months from the specified 
date, but its expiry under the operation of this section shall not affect—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  the previous operation of, or anything duly done 
or suffered under this Chapter, or
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  any right, privilege, obligation or liability 
acquired, accrued or incurred under this Chapter, or
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  any investigation, legal proceeding or remedy in 
respect of any such right, privilege, obligation or liability as aforesaid,
 and any such investigation, legal proceeding or remedy may be 
instituted, continued or enforced as if this Chapter had not expired.
  


</section></article> 
 The National 
Council for Teacher Education  
Act, 1993
  
 <article><number>19</number> Executive Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Council shall constitute a Committee, called the Executive Committee for 
discharging such functions as may be assigned to it by the Council or as may be 
determined by regulations.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Executive Committee 
shall consist of the following members, namely:—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  the Chairperson;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  the Vice-Chairperson;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  the Member-Secretary;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  the Secretary to the Government of India in the 
Department dealing with Education ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number>  the Secretary, University Grants Commission, 
ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>f</number>  the Director, National Council of Educational 
Research and Training, ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>g</number>  the Financial Adviser to the Government of India 
in the Department dealing with Education, ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>h</number>  four experts in teacher education to be 
nominated by the Central Government;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>i</number>  four State representatives to be nominated by 
the Central Government in such manner as may be prescribed;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>j</number>  the Chairpersons of the Regional Committees.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> The Chairperson and the 
Member-Secretary of the Council shall respectively, function as the Chairperson 
and the Member-Secretary of the Executive Committee.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Chairperson or in his 
absence, the Vice-Chairperson of the Council shall preside at the meetings of 
the Executive committee and in the absence of both the chairperson and the 
Vice-Chairperson, any other member chosen by the members present at the meeting 
shall preside as the meeting.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The quorum necessary for the 
transaction of business at the meetings of the Executive Committee shall be as 
laid down by regulations.
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Executive Committee may 
co-opt, in such manner and for such purposes, as may be determined by 
regulations, not more than two persons whose assistance and advice, it may 
desire in carrying out any of the functions assigned to the Executive Committee:
 Provided that the persons 
co-opted by the Executive Committee for any purpose shall have a right to take 
part in the discussions relevant to that purpose, but shall not have a right to 
vote at a meeting of the Executive Committee, and-shall not be a member for any 
other purpose.
 </section><section><number>7</number> The Council may, if it 
considers necessary, establish such other committees, for such specific purpose, 
as it may deem fit.
</section></article> 
 The National 
Council for Teacher Education  
Act, 1993
  
 <article><number>20</number> Regional Committees.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Council shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, establish the 
following Regional Committees, namely:—
 <subsection>        <number>i</number>  the Eastern Regional Committee;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>ii</number>  the Western Regional Committee;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number>  the Northern Regional Committee; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iv</number>  the Southern Regional Committee.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The Council may, if it 
considers necessary, establish with the approval of the Central Government, such 
other Regional Committees as it may deem fit.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Regional Committee shall 
consist of the following members, namely:—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  a Member to be nominated by the Council;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  one representative from each of the States and 
the Union territories of the region, to be nominated by the respective States 
and the Union territories;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  such number of persons, having special knowledge 
and experience in matters relating to teacher education, as may be determined by 
regulations.
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number> The Council shall nominate 
one of the members of the concerned Regional Committee to function as the 
chairperson of the said Committee.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The term of office of the 
members referred to in clause (c) and the allowances payable to such members 
shall be such as may be determined by regulations.
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Regional Committee shall 
in addition to its functions under sections 14, 15 and 17, perform such other 
functions, as may be assigned to it by the Council or as may be determined by 
regulations.
 </section><section><number>7</number> The functions of, the 
procedure to be followed by, the territorial jurisdiction of, and the manner of 
filling casual vacancies among members of, a Regional Committee shall be such as 
may be determined by regulations.
</section></article> 
 The National 
Council for Teacher Education  
Act, 1993
  
 <article><number>21</number> Power to terminate the 
Regional Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> If the 
Council is of the opinion that a Regional Committee is unable to perform, or has 
persistently made default in the performance of the duties imposed on it by or 
under this Act or has exceeded or abused its powers, or has wilfully or without 
sufficient cause, failed to comply with any direction issued by the Council for 
carrying out the provisions of this Act, the Council may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, terminate forthwith the Regional Committee.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Upon the publication of a 
notification under sub-section (1),—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  all members of the Regional Committee shall, 
notwithstanding that their term of office had not expired, as from the date of 
the termination, vacate their office as such members; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  all the powers and duties which may, by or under 
the provisions of this Act be exercised or performed by or on behalf of the 
Regional Committee shall, during the period when the term of office of its 
members stand terminated, be exercised and performed by such person or persons 
as the Council may direct.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> The Council may at any time 
after publication of a notification under sub-section (2), re-constitute the 
Regional Committee in the manner provided in sub-section (3) of section 20:
 Provided that it shall be 
competent for the Council to appoint any person, who was a member of a Regional 
Committee which was terminated, as a member of the re-constituted Regional 
Committee.
  
</section></article> 
 The National 
Council for Teacher Education  
Act, 1993
  
 <article><number>22</number> Payment to the Council.—The 
Central Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in 
this behalf, pay to the Council in each financial year such sums as may be 
considered necessary for the performance of the functions of the Council under 
this Act.
  
</article> 
 The National 
Council for Teacher Education  
Act, 1993
  
 <article><number>23</number> Fund of Council.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Council shall have its own fund; and all sums which may, from time to time, 
be paid to it by the Central Government or a State Government and all the 
receipts of the Council, including any sum which any other authority or person 
in India or abroad may pay to the Council, shall be credited to the fund and all 
payments by the Council shall be made therefrom.
 </section><section><number>2</number> All moneys belonging to the 
fund shall be deposited in such banks or invested in such manner as may be 
decided by the Council.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Council may spend such 
sums as it thinks fit for performing its functions under this Act; and such sums 
shall be treated as expenditure payable out of the fund of the Council.
  
</section></article> 
 The National 
Council for Teacher Education  
Act, 1993
  
 <article><number>24</number> Budget of the Council.—The 
Council shall prepare, in such form and at such time each year as may be 
prescribed, a budget in respect of the financial year next ensuing, showing the 
estimated receipts and expenditure, and copies thereof shall be forwarded to the 
Central Government.
  
</article> 
 The National 
Council for Teacher Education  
Act, 1993
  
 <article><number>25</number> Annual report.—The 
Council shall prepare once every year, in such form and at such time as may be 
prescribed, an annual report giving a true and full account of its activities 
during the previous year and copies thereof shall be forwarded to the Central 
Government and that Government shall cause the same to be laid before both 
Houses of Parliament.
  
</article> 
 The National 
Council for Teacher Education  
Act, 1993
  
 <article><number>26</number> Accounts and audit.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Council shall cause to be maintained such books of account in such form and 
in such manner as the Central Government may, in consultation with the 
Comptroller and Auditor-General of India, prescribe.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Council shall, as soon 
as may be, after closing its annual accounts, prepare a statement of accounts in 
such form and forward the same to the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India 
by such date as the Central Government may, in consultation with the Comptroller 
and Auditor-General, determine.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The accounts of the Council 
shall be audited by the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India at such times 
and in such manner as he thinks fit.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The accounts of the Council 
as certified by the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India or any other person 
appointed by him in this behalf, together with the audit report thereon shall be 
forwarded annually to the Central Government and that Government shall cause the 
same to be laid before both Houses of Parliament.
  
</section></article> 
 The National 
Council for Teacher Education  
Act, 1993
  
 <article><number>27</number> Delegation of powers and 
functions.—The Council may, by 
general or special order in writing, delegate to the chairperson or to any other 
member or to any officer of the Regional Committee, subject to such conditions 
and limitations, if any, as may be specified in the order, such of its powers 
and functions under this Act (except the power to make regulations under section 
32), as it may deem necessary.
  
</article> 
 The National 
Council for Teacher Education  
Act, 1993
  
 <article><number>28</number> Protection of action 
taken in good faith.—No prosecution 
or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central Government, the Council 
or any committees appointed by it, or any Member of the Council or member of 
such committees, or any officer or employee of the Central Government or the 
Council or any other person authorised by that Government or the Council, for 
anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or 
the rules or regulations made thereunder.
  
</article> 
 The National 
Council for Teacher Education  
Act, 1993
  
 <article><number>29</number> Directions by the Central 
Government.—
<section><number>1</number> The Council shall, in 
the discharge of its functions and duties under this Act be bound by such 
directions on questions of policy as the Central Government may give in writing 
to it from time to time.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The decision of the Central 
Government as to whether a question is one of policy or not shall be final.
  
</section></article> 
 The National 
Council for Teacher Education  
Act, 1993
  
 <article><number>30</number> Power to supersede the 
Council.—
<section><number>1</number> If the Central 
Government is of the opinion that the Council is unable to perform, or has 
persistently made default in the performance of the duties imposed on it by or 
under this Act or has exceeded or abused its powers, or has wilfully or without 
sufficient cause, failed to comply with any direction issued by the Central 
Government under section 29, the Central Government may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, supersede the Council for such period as may be specified in 
the notification:
 Provided that before issuing a 
notification under the sub-section, the Central Government shall give a 
reasonable opportunity to the Council to show cause why it should not be 
superseded and shall consider the explanation and objections, if any, of the 
Council.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Upon the publication of a 
notification under sub-section (1) superseding the Council—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  all the Members of the Council shall, 
notwithstanding that their term of office had not expired, as from the date of 
supersession, vacate their offices as such Members;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  all the powers and duties which may, by or under 
the provisions of this Act be exercised or performed by or on behalf of the 
Council shall, during the period of supersession, be exercised and performed by 
such person or persons as the Central Government may direct;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  all property vested in the Council shall, during 
the period of supersession, vest in the Central Government.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> On the expiry of the period 
of supersession specified in the notification issued under sub-section (1), the 
Central Government, may—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  extend the period of supersession for such 
further period as it may consider necessary; or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  re-constitute the Council in the manner provided 
in section 3.
 


</subsection></section></article> 
 The National 
Council for Teacher Education  
Act, 1993
  
 <article>

1[<number>30A</number> Penalty for contravention of 
section 17A.—An institution which 
contravenes section 17A shall be liable to pay to the Council a penalty of an 
amount equal to double the amount received from each student against his 
admission in such institution:
 Provided that before imposing 
any penalty, the Council shall give to the institution concerned a reasonable 
opportunity of being heard.]
  



</article> 
 The National 
Council for Teacher Education  
Act, 1993
  
 <article><number>31</number> Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules 
to carry out the provisions of this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> In particular, and without 
prejudice to the generality of the foregoing powers, such rules may provide for 
all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  the manner in which the Central Government is to 
appoint experts to the Council under sub-clause (v) of clause (m) of sub-section 
(4) of section 3;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  the manner in which the Central Government is to 
appoint Members to the Council from amongst the States and the Union territory 
Administrations under clause (n) of sub­section (4) of section 3;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  the conditions of service of the Chairperson, 
the Vice-Chairperson and the Member-Secretary under sub-section (3) and of 
Members under sub-section (4) of section 4;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  the powers and duties of the Chairperson under 
sub-section (7) of section 4;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number>  the manner in which and the persons by whom the 
inspection of an institution is to be made and the manner in which the 
institution is to be associated in such inspection under sub-sections (1) and 
(2) of section 13;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>f</number>  the fees payable on application for obtaining 
recognition under sub-section (2) of section 14 and for obtaining permission 
under sub-section (2) of section 15;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>g</number>  the period of limitation for an appeal under 
sub-section (1) of section 18, the form in which such appeal is to be made and 
the fees payable therefor under sub-section (3) of that section and the 
procedure for disposal of an appeal under sub-section (4) of that section;
 
1[(ga)  
the form in which and the period within which an application under sub-section 
(2) of section 18B is to be made, and the fee payable on such application;
 </subsection><subsection>      <number>gb</number>  the manner of dealing with an application under 
sub-section (3) of section 18B;]
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>h</number>  the manner in which the Central Government is to 
nominate the State representatives in the Executive Committee under clause (i) 
of sub-section (2) of section 19;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>i</number>  the form in which and the time within which the 
budget under section 24 and the annual report under section 25 of the Council is 
to be prepared;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>j</number>  the manner and the form in which the accounts 
of the Council are to be maintained under sub-section (1) of section 26;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>k</number>  any other matter which has to be, or may be, 
prescribed.
  



</subsection></section></article> 
 The National 
Council for Teacher Education  
Act, 1993
  
 <article><number>32</number> Power to make 
regulations.—
<section><number>1</number> The Council may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, make regulations not inconsistent with the 
provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder, generally to carry out the 
provisions of this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> In particular, and without 
prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such regulations may provide 
for all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  the time and the place of the meetings of the 
Council and the procedure for conducting business thereat under sub-section (1) 
of section 7;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  the manner in which and the purposes for which 
persons may be co-opted by the Council under sub-section (1) of section 9;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  the appointment and terms and conditions of 
service of officers and other employees of the Council under sub-sections (1) 
and (2) respectively of section 10;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  the norms, guidelines and standards in respect 
of—
 <subsubsection>             <number>i</number>  the minimum qualifications for a person to 
be employed as a teacher under clause (d) of section 12;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            <number>ii</number>  the specified category of courses or 
training in teacher education under clause (e) of section 12;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            <number>iii</number>  starting of new courses or training in 
recognised institutions under clause (f) of section 12;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>           <number>iv</number>  standards in respect of examinations 
leading to teacher education qualifications referred to in clause (g) of section 
12;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            <number>v</number>  the tuition fees and other fees chargeable 
by institutions under clause (h) of section 12;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>           <number>vi</number>  the schemes for various levels of teachers 
education, and identification of institutions for offering teacher development 
programmes under clause (l) of section 12;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number>  the form and the manner in which an application 
for recognition is to be submitted under sub-section (1) of section 14;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>f</number>  conditions required for the proper functioning 
of the institution and conditions for granting recognition under clause (a) of 
sub-section (3) of section 14;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>g</number>  the form and the manner in which an application 
for permission is to be made under sub­section (1) of section 15;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>h</number>  conditions required for the proper conduct of a 
new course or training and conditions for granting permission under clause (a) 
of sub-section (3) of section 15;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>i</number>  the functions which may be assigned by the 
Council to the Executive Committee under sub-section (1) of section 19;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>j</number>  the procedure and the quorum necessary for 
transaction of business at the meetings of the Executive Committee under 
sub-section (5) of section 19;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>k</number>  the manner in which and the purposes for which 
the Executive Committee may co-opt persons under sub-section (6) of section 19;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>l</number>  the number of persons under clause (c) of 
sub-section (3) of section 20;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>m</number>  the term of office and allowances payable to 
members under sub-section (5) of section 20;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>n</number>  additional functions to be performed by the 
Regional Committee under sub-section (6) of section 20;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>o</number>  the functions of, the procedure to be followed 
by the territorial jurisdiction of, and the manner of filling casual vacancies 
among members of, a Regional Committee under sub-section (7) of section 20;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>p</number>  any other matter in respect of which provision 
is to be, or may be, made by regulations.
</subsection></section></article> 
 The National 
Council for Teacher Education  
Act, 1993
  
 <article><number>33</number> Rules and regulations to 
be laid before Parliament.—Every rule 
and every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after 
it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total 
period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in 
making any modification in the rule or regulation, or both Houses agree that the 
rule or regulation should not be made, the rule or regulation shall thereafter 
have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; 
so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice 
to the validity of anything previously done under that rule of regulation.
  
</article> 
 The National 
Council for Teacher Education  
Act, 1993
  
 <article><number>34</number> Power to remove 
difficulties.—
<section><number>1</number> If any difficulty 
arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order, published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions not 
inconsistent with the provisions of this Act as may appear to be necessary for 
removing the difficulty:
 Provided that no order shall be 
made under this section after the expiry of two years from the commencement of 
this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every order made under this section shall be laid, as soon 
as may be after it is made before each House of Parliament.
</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>     Came
into force on 1-7-1995, vide S.O. 620(E), dated 1st July, 1995, published 
in the Gazette of India, Pt. II, Sec. 3(ii), dated
10th July, 1995.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>  Ins. by the National Council for Teacher Education 
(Amendment and Validation) Ordinance, 2006 (Ord. 2 of 2006), clause 2 (w.e.f. 
11-7-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>  Ins. by the National Council for Teacher Education 
(Amendment and Validation) Ordinance, 2006 (Ord. 2 of 2006), clause 4 (w.e.f. 
11-7-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>  Ins. by the National Council for Teacher Education 
(Amendment and Validation) Ordinance, 2006 (Ord. 2 of 2006), clause 5 (w.e.f. 
11-7-2006).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>