<act><title>

The ARMED FORCEs 
    (special powers) Act, 1958</title> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>

<number>1</number> Short title and 
    extent.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called [The 
    Armed Forces (Special Powers) Act, 1958].
 </section><section>

[<number>2</number> It extends to the whole of the State of [Arunachal 
    Pradesh, Assam, Manipur, Meghalaya, Mizoram, Nagaland and Tripura].

 
 
 

 

 







  







</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>

<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
    this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   
      “armed forces” mean the military forces and the air forces operating as 
      land forces, and includes other armed forces of the Union so operating;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   
      “disturbed area” means an area which is for the time being declared by 
      notification under section 3 to be a disturbed area;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   
      all other words and expressions used herein, but not defined and defined 
      in the Air Force Act, 1950 (45 of 1950), or the Army Act, 1950 (46 of 
      1950) shall have the meanings respectively to them in those Acts.
</section>
  

  





 
    .

</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>3</number> Power to declare areas to be disturbed 
      areas.—If, in relation to any State or Union territory to which this 
      Act extends, the Governor of that State or the Administrator of that Union 
      territory or the Central Government, in either case, if of the opinion 
      that the whole or any part of such State or Union territory, as the case 
      may be, is in such a disturbed or dangerous condition that the use of 
      armed forces in aid of the civil power is necessary, the Governor of that 
      State or the Administrator of that Union territory or the Central 
      Government, as the case may be, may, by notification in the Official 
      Gazette, declare the whole or such part of such State or Union territory 
      to be a disturbed area].
  








  
</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>

<number>4</number> Special Powers of 
    the armed forces.—Any 
    commissioned officer, warrant officer, non-commissioned officer or any other 
    person of equivalent rank in the armed forces may, in a disturbed area,—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   
      if he is of opinion that it is necessary so to do for the maintenance of 
      public order, after giving such due warning as he may consider necessary, 
      fire upon or otherwise use force, even to the causing of death, against 
      any person who is acting in contravention of any law or order for the time 
      being in force in the disturbed area prohibiting the assembly of five or 
      more persons or the carrying of weapons or of things capable of being used 
      as weapons or of fire-arms, ammunition or explosive substances;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   
      if he is of opinion that it is necessary so to do, destroy any arms dump, 
      prepared or fortified position or shelter from which armed attacks are 
      made or are likely to be made or are attempted to be made, or any 
      structure used as a training camp for armed volunteers or utilised as a 
      hide-out by armed gangs or absconders wanted for any offence;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   
      arrest, without warrant, any person who has committed a cognizable offence 
      or against whom a reasonable suspicion exists that he has committed or is 
      about to commit a cognizable offence and may use such force as may be 
      necessary to effect the arrest;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   
      enter and search without warrant any premises to make any such arrest as 
      aforesaid or to recover any person believed to be wrongfully restrained or 
      confined or any property reasonably suspected to be stolen property or any 
      arms, ammunition or explosive substances believed to be unlawfully kept in 
      such premises, and may for that purpose use such force as may be 
      necessary.
 

comments
 <subsection>
<number>i</number> 
      Conferment of power on non-commissioned officers like a Havaldar cannot be 
      said to be bad and unjustified; Inderjit Barua v. State of Assam, 
      AIR 1983 Del 514.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number> The 
      armed forces must act in cooperation with the district administration and 
      not as an independent body. Armed forces could work in harmony when they 
      deployed in disturbed area; Luithukla v. Rishang Keishing, 
      (1988) 2 Gau LR 159.
 

</subsection></section>
  
 


  





 
    .

</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>

<number>5</number> Arrested persons 
    to be made over to the police.—Any 
    person arrested and taken into custody under this Act shall be made over to 
    the officer in charge of the nearest police station with the least possible 
    delay, together with a report of the circumstances occasioning the arrest.


  







</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>6</number> Protection to persons 
      acting under Act.—No prosecution, suit or 
      other legal proceeding shall be instituted, except with the previous 
      sanction of the Central Government, against any person in respect of 
      anything done or purported to be done in exercise of the powers conferred 
      by this Act.
  
  
 .</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>

<number>7</number> Repeal and Saving.—[Repealed 
    by Amending and Repealing Act, 1960 (58 of 1960), First Schedule, sec. 2 (26-12-1960)].

  





  

</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 
 Subs. by Act 7 of 1972, 
      sec. 4 (w.e.f. 5-4-1972).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>