<act><tid>418325</tid>
<title>THE INDIAN BILLS OF LADING ACT, <year>1856</year></title>

ACT NO. 9 OF <year>1856</year> 
 11th April, <year>1856</year>
An Act to amend the Law relating to Bills of Lading.

Preamble.-- Whereas by the custom of merchants a bill of lading of 
goods being transferable by endorsement, the property in the goods may 
thereby pass to the endorsee, but nevertheless all rights in respect 
of the contract contained in the bill of lading continue in the 
original shipper or owner, and it is expedient that such rights should 
pass with the property; and whereas it frequently happens that the 
goods in respect of which bills of lading purport to be signed have 
has been laden on board, and it is proper that such bills of lading in 
the hands of a bona fide holder for value should not be questioned by 
the master or other person signing the same, on the ground of the 
goods not having been laden as aforesaid: It is enacted is follows:-





<article><tid>1649197</tid>
<number>1</number>Rights under bills of lading to vest in consignee of 
endorsee.-- Every consignee of goods named in a bill of lading, and 
every endorsee of a bill of lading to whom the property in the goods 
therein mentioned shall pass, upon or by reason of such consignment or 
endorsement shall have transferred to and vested in him all rights of 
suit, and be subject to the same liabilities in respect of such goods 
as if the contract contained in the bill of lading had been made with 
himself.


</article>



<article><tid>1000409</tid>
<number>2</number>Not to affect right of stoppage in transitu of claims for 
freight.-- Nothing herein contained shall prejudice or affect any right 
of stoppage in transitu, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or any right to claim freight against 
the original shipper or owner, or any liability of the consignee or 
endorsee by reason or in consequence of his being such consignee or 
endorsee, or of his receipt of the goods by reason or in consequence 
of such consignment or endorsement.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>47</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Short title given by the Indian Short Titles Act, <year>1897</year> (14 of  
  <year>1897</year>), s. 2 and Sch.

This Act is based on the Bills of Landing Act, <year>1855</year> (18 and  
  19 Vict., c. 111).

It has been declared to be in force in the whole of India 
except Part B States and the Scheduled Districts, by the Laws 
Local Extent Act, <year>1874</year> (15 of <year>1874</year>), s. 3

Extended to former Part B States by Act 18 of <year>1949</year>, s. 4.


Extended to Union territory of Pondicherry be Act 26 of 
<year>1968</year>, s. 3 and Sch.

It has been declared, by notification under s. 3 (a) of the 
Scheduled Districts Act, <year>1874</year> (14 of <year>1874</year>), to be in force in the 
following Scheduled Districts, namely:-

West Jalpaiguri, see Gazette of India, <year>1881</year>, Pt. I p. 
74.

The Districts of Hazaribagh, Lohardaga (now the Ranchi  
  district, see Calcutta Gazette, <year>1899</year>, Pt. I, p. 44), and Manbhum, 
and Pargana Dalbhum and the Kolhan in the District of Singhbhum, 
See Gazette of India, <year>1881</year>, Pt. I, p. 504.

Assam (except the North Lushai Hills), see Gazette of India, 
<year>1897</year>, Pt. I, p. 299.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>As to stoppage in transit, see the Indian Contract Act, <year>1872</year> (9  
  of <year>1872</year>), ss. 99- 106.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1354045</tid>
<number>3</number>Bill of lading in hands of consignee, ect., conclusive 
evidence of the shipment as against master, etc.-- Every bill of lading 
in the hands of a consignee or endorsee for valuable consideration, 
representing goods to have been shipped on board a vessel, shall be 
conclusive evidence of such shipment as against the master or other 
person signing the same, notwithstanding that such goods or some part 
thereof may not have been so shipped, unless such holder of the bill 
of lading shall have had actual notice at the time of receiving the 
same that the goods had not in fact been laden on board:
Provided that the master or other person so signing may exonerate 
himself in respect of such misrepresentation, by showing that it was 
caused without any default on his part, and wholly by the fraud of the 
shipper, or of the holder, or some person under whom the holder 
claims.


</article>



 </act>