<act><title>


The Presidential and Vice-Presidential Elections Rules, 19741 </title> 

  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These Rules may be called the Presidential and Vice-Presidential Elections 
Rules, 1974.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force at once.
 
 


</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>2</number> Interpretation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <subsection>
        
<number>a</number>  “Act” means  the Presidential and Vice-Presidential Elections 
Act, 1952 (31 of 1952);
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>b</number>  “article” means an article of the Constitution of India;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>c</number>  “Form” means a Form appended to these rules;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>d</number>  “section” means a section of the Act.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The General Clauses 
Act, 1897 (10 of 1897), shall apply for the interpretation of these rules as it 
applies for the interpretation of an Act of Parliament.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Public notice of 
intended election.—The 
public notice of an intended election referred to in section 5 shall be in Form 
1 and shall be published by the Returning Officer by such means, in such 
language or languages and in such places as the Election Commission may direct.
</article> 

  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Nomination paper.—Every 
nomination paper presented under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 5B shall be 
completed in Form 2 or Form 3, as may be appropriate.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Notice of withdrawal 
of candidature.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A notice of withdrawal of candidature under sub-section (1) of section 6 shall 
be in Form 4.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On receipt of such 
notice, the Returning Officer shall note thereon the date on which and the hour 
at which it was delivered, and cause a copy thereof, together with the note, to 
be affixed in some conspicuous place in his office.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Preparation and 
publication of the list of contesting candidates.—In 
every case in which a poll is to be taken under clause (b) of section 8, the 
Returning Officer shall, immediately after the expiry of the period within which 
candidature may be withdrawn under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 6—
 <subsection>
       
 <number>a</number> prepare in Form 5 a list of contesting candidates (that is to say, 
candidates who have been duly nominated but have not withdrawn their 
candidatures with in the time specified in that behalf), containing the names in 
alphabetical order as given in the nomination papers together with their 
addresses;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
 <number>b</number> cause the list to be published in the Gazette of India and in such other 
manner as the Election Commission may direct; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       
 <number>c</number> cause a copy of the list to be affixed in some conspicuous place in his 
office.
</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Fixing place and 
time of polling for Presidential election.—At 
every Presidential election where a poll is to be taken, the Election Commission 
shall—
 <section>
       
 <number>a</number> fix a place of polling in the Parliament House in New Delhi, and also in 
the premises in each State in which the Legislative Assembly, if any, of that 
State meets for the transaction of business;
 </section><section>
       
 <number>b</number> specify with reference to each such place of polling the group of electors 
who will be entitled to vote, and the hours during which the poll will be taken, 
at such place; and
 </section><section>
       
 <number>c</number> give due publicity to the places so fixed and the groups of electors and 
the hours so specified.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Fixing place and 
time of polling for Vice-Presidential election.—At 
every Vice-Presidential election where a poll is to be taken, the Election 
Commission shall—
 <section>
       
 <number>a</number> fix a place of polling in the Parliament House in New Delhi;
 </section><section>
       
 <number>b</number> specify the hours during which the poll will be taken; and
 </section><section>
       
 <number>c</number> give due publicity to the place so fixed and the hours so specified.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Presiding and 
polling officers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Returning Officer or such Assistant Returning Officer as may be specified in 
this behalf by the Election Commission shall conduct the poll at each place of 
polling. Every such officer is hereinafter referred to as the presiding officer.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The presiding officer 
may appoint such polling officer or officers as he thinks necessary to assist 
him in taking the poll, but he shall not so appoint any person who has been 
employed by, or on behalf of, or has been working for, a candidate in or about 
the election.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Design and form of 
ballot papers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every ballot paper shall have a counterfoil attached thereto and the said ballot 
paper and the counterfoil shall be in such form, and the particulars therein 
shall be in such language or languages, as the Election Commission may direct.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The names of the 
candidates shall be printed on the ballot paper in the same order as in the list 
of contesting candidates published under rule 6.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every presiding 
officer shall be supplied with a sufficient number of ballot papers by the 
Election Commission.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>11</number> Ballot boxes.—Every 
ballot box used at the poll shall be of a design previously approved by the 
Election Commission.
</article> 

  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Procedure before 
the commencement of poll.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The presiding officer shall, immediately before the commencement of the poll, 
allow inspection of the ballot box to be used at the poll to such candidates and 
authorised representatives of candidates as may be present at the place of 
polling.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The presiding officer 
shall then secure and seal the box in such manner that the slit for the 
insertion of ballot papers remains open, and shall also allow such candidates 
and authorised representatives of candidates as may be present to affix their 
own seals, if they so desire.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>13</number> Admission to the 
place of polling.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The presiding officer shall exclude from the place of polling all persons 
except—
 <subsection>
       
 <number>a</number> the polling officers and other public servants on duty; 
 </subsection><subsection>
       
 <number>b</number> the candidates, and one representative authorised in writing by each 
candidate;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
 <number>c</number> the electors;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
 <number>d</number> persons authorised by the Election Commission; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       
 <number>e</number> such other persons as the presiding officer may from time to time admit for 
the purpose of assisting him in taking the poll.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The presiding officer 
shall close the place of polling at the hour fixed under clause (b) of rule 7 
or, as the case may be, under clause (b) of rule 8 for the close of the poll and 
shall not admit therein any elector after that hour:
 
Provided that all electors 
present at the place before it is so closed shall be entitled to have their 
votes recorded.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>14</number> Procedure for 
giving ballot papers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The polling officer shall be furnished with an authentic list or part thereof of 
the electors entitled to vote at the place of polling.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Immediately before a 
ballot paper is delivered to an elector, a mark shall be placed against his name 
in the list, and the number of the elector as shown in that list shall be 
entered on the counterfoil of the ballot paper.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The elector shall sign 
his name in the list in token of receipt of the ballot paper, whereupon, but not 
earlier, the ballot paper shall be delivered to him.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>15</number> Supply of fresh 
ballot paper in certain circumstances.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An elector who has inadvertently dealt with his ballot paper in such a manner 
that it cannot be conveniently used as a ballot paper may, on delivering it to 
the presiding officer and on satisfying him of the inadvertence, obtain another 
ballot paper in place of the ballot paper so delivered, and the latter shall, 
together with its counterfoil, be marked as cancelled by the presiding officer.
 </section><section>
 <number>2</number> Any ballot papers so 
cancelled shall be kept in a separate envelope set apart for the purpose.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>16</number> Return of unused 
ballot papers by electors.—If 
an elector after obtaining any ballot paper for the purpose of recording his 
vote decides not to use the same, he shall return the ballot paper to the 
presiding officer, who shall mark it ‘Returned and cancelled’ and keep it in a 
separate envelope set apart for the purpose.
</article> 

  
 <article>
<number>17</number> Manner of recording 
votes.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every elector shall have as many preferences as there are candidates but no 
ballot paper shall be considered invalid solely on the ground that all such 
preferences are not marked.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An elector in giving 
his vote—
 <subsection>
       
 <number>a</number> shall place on his ballot paper the figure 1 in the space opposite the name 
of the candidate whom he chooses for his first preference; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>b</number> may, in addition, mark as many subsequent preferences as he wished by 
placing on his ballot paper the figures 2, 3, 4 and so on, in the spaces 
opposite the names of other candidates, in order of preference.
 
Explanation.—The 
figures referred to in clauses (a) and (b) of this sub-rule may be marked in the 
international form of Indian numerals or in the Roman form or in the form used 
in any Indian language but shall not be indicated in words. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The presiding officer 
shall, if requested by an elector, explain to him the instructions contained on 
the ballot paper for the recording of votes.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>18</number> Maintenance of 
secrecy of voting by electors within place of polling and voting procedure.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every elector to whom a ballot paper has been delivered under rule 14 shall 
maintain secrecy of voting within the place of polling and for that purpose 
observe the voting procedure hereinafter laid down.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An elector on 
receiving the ballot paper shall forthwith— 
 <subsection>
       
 <number>a</number> proceed to one of the voting compartments;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
 <number>b</number> record his vote in accordance with sub-rule (2) of rule 17;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
 <number>c</number> fold the ballot paper so as to conceal his vote;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
 <number>d</number> insert the folded ballot paper into the ballot box; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       
 <number>e</number> quit the place of polling.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Every elector shall 
vote without undue delay.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> No elector shall be 
allowed to enter a voting compartment when another elector is inside it.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>19</number> Recording of votes 
of illiterate or disabled elector.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If an elector is unable to read the ballot paper or to record his vote thereon 
in accordance with rule 17 by reason of illiteracy or blindness or, by not being 
conversant with the language in which the ballot papers are printed or, by 
reason of any physical or other disability, the presiding officer shall record 
the vote on the ballot paper in accordance with the wishes of the elector. 

 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The elector shall then 
himself or with the assistance of the presiding officer fold up the ballot paper 
so as to conceal his vote and insert it into the ballot box.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> While acting under 
this rule, the presiding officer shall observe as much secrecy as is feasible 
and shall keep a brief record of such instance but shall not indicate therein 
the manner in which any vote has been cast.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>20</number> Account of ballot 
papers.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
presiding officer shall at the close of the poll prepare a ballot paper account 
in Form 6 and enclose it in a separate cover with the words “Ballot Paper 
Account” superscribed thereon.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The presiding officer 
shall permit the authorised representative of a candidate, who so desires, to 
take a true copy of the entries in the ballot paper account and shall attest it 
as true copy.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>21</number> Sealing up of 
ballot boxes and papers after the close of poll.—
<section><number>1</number> 
As soon as practicable after the close of poll the presiding officer shall, in 
the presence of such candidates and authorised representatives of candidates as 
may be present, close and seal up the slit as well as the ballot box.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> He shall also make up 
into separate packets—
 <subsection>
       
 <number>a</number> the copy of the list of electors marked in accordance with rule 14;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
 <number>b</number> the counterfoils of ballot papers;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
 <number>c</number> the ballot papers cancelled under rules 15 and 16; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       
 <number>d</number> the unused ballot papers.
 
and seal each such packet 
with his own seal and the seals of those candidates and authorised 
representatives of candidates who may desire to affix their seal thereon.
</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>22</number> Transfer of ballot 
papers from ballot boxes in certain cases.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in rule 21, the Election Commission may, at a 
Presidential election, direct the presiding officer at any place of polling 
other than the Parliament House in New Delhi to follow after the close of the 
poll the procedure laid down in this rule instead of the procedure laid down in 
sub-rule (1) of rule 21.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where a direction has 
been issued under sub-rule (1), the presiding officer shall, as soon as 
practicable after the close of the poll, open the ballot box in the presence of 
such candidates and authorised representatives of candidates as may be present 
and transfer all the ballot papers contained in it without examining or counting 
them into a separate cover and record on such cover—
 <subsection>
       
 <number>a</number> the name of the place of polling; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       
 <number>b</number> the date of the poll.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> After such transfer he 
shall allow the candidates and their authorised representatives who may be 
present, to inspect the ballot box and demonstrate to them that it is empty.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> He shall then seal the 
cover with his own seal and the seals of those candidates and authorised 
representatives of candidates who may desire to affix their seals thereon.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The cover so sealed 
shall, for the purposes of rules 23, 25, 32 and 33, be deemed to be the ballot 
box used at that place of polling and the provisions of those rules shall apply 
accordingly.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>23</number> Despatch and 
custody of ballot boxes and paper.—
<section><number>1</number> 
At a Presidential election, the presiding officer at every place of polling 
other than the Parliament House in New Delhi shall forthwith cause the sealed 
ballot box and packets and all other papers used at the poll to be sent to the 
Returning Officer in accordance with such general or special instructions as may 
be issued in that behalf by the Election Commission.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Returning Officer 
shall make adequate arrangements for the safe custody of all sealed ballot boxes 
and packets and other papers used at the poll, until the commencement of the 
counting of votes.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>24</number> Adjournment of poll 
in emergencies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If the proceedings at any place of polling are interrupted or obstructed by riot 
or open violence, or if it is not possible to take the poll at any such place on 
account of a natural calamity or other sufficient cause, the presiding officer 
shall announce an adjournment of the poll to a date to be notified later, and 
immediately report the circumstances to the Election Commission and, unless he 
is the Returning Officer, also to the Returning Officer.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Whenever a poll is 
adjourned under sub-rule (1), the Election Commission shall, as soon as may be , 
fix the day on which, the place at which and the hours during which the 
adjourned poll shall be taken, and shall notify the said details to all 
concerned in such manner as it may think fit.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On the date on which 
such adjourned poll is taken, the electors who have already voted at the poll 
before its adjournment will not be entitled to vote, but only the remaining 
electors who were entitled to vote at the place of polling before its 
adjournment may vote.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>25</number> Fresh poll in case 
of destruction, etc., of ballot boxes.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If at an election, any ballot box is unlawfully taken away from the custody of 
the presiding officer or the Returning Officer or is in any way tampered with, 
destroyed or lost, the poll taken at the place of polling where that ballot box 
was used shall be deemed to have been vitiated; and the Returning Officer shall, 
as soon as practicable, report the matter to the Election Commission, which 
shall appoint a day for the taking of a fresh poll at that place and fix the 
hours during which it will be taken.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In every such case as 
aforesaid, the provisions of these rules shall apply to the fresh poll as they 
apply to the original poll. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>26</number> Voting by electors 
under preventive detention.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything in the foregoing provisions of this Chapter, an elector 
may, if he is subjected to preventive detention under any law for the time being 
in force, give his vote by postal ballot.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Election 
Commission shall send by registered post to the officer-in-charge of the jail or 
other place where the elector is detained the appropriate ballot paper, together 
with a form of declaration of identity and attestation of signature and 
necessary envelopes specially prepared for the purpose and a letter of 
instructions, so as to reach that officer in good time before the date fixed for 
polling.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On the date of polling 
the said officer shall deliver the ballot paper and other necessary papers to 
the elector, allow him all reasonable facilities and sufficient time, not 
exceeding two hours, for recording his vote in accordance with the instructions 
of the Election Commission, and if and when the elector has so recorded his 
vote, send the ballot paper and other connected papers in a sealed cover, either 
by registered post or through a special messenger, to the Returning Officer so 
as to reach him before the time fixed for the counting of votes under rule 27.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> It shall be the duty 
of every Government to intimate to the Election Commission at the appropriate 
time the names of electors, if any, who are subjected to preventive detention by 
or under the authority of that Government, together with the necessary 
particulars as to their places of detention. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>27</number> Place and time for 
counting of votes.—The 
counting of votes shall take place at the office of the Returning Officer in New 
Delhi on such day and at such time as the Election Commission may appoint in 
this behalf; and the Election Commission shall give notice to all the candidates 
of the date and time so appointed. 
</article> 

  
 <article>
<number>28</number> Admission to the 
place fixed for counting.—The 
Returning Officer shall exclude from the place fixed for counting of votes all 
persons except—
 <section>
       
 <number>a</number> such persons as he may appoint to assist him in the counting;
 </section><section>
       
 <number>b</number> the candidates and one representative at a time authorised in writing by 
each candidate;
 </section><section>
       
 <number>c</number> public servants on duty in connection with the election; and
 </section><section>
       
 <number>d</number>  persons authorised by the Election Commission.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>29</number> Maintenance of 
secrecy of voting.—Before 
the counting begins, the Returning Officer shall read out the provisions of 
section 22 to the persons present.
</article> 

  
 <article><number>30</number> Statement showing the number 
of votes of each elector at the Presidential election.—For the purposes of every 
Presidential election, the Election Commission shall furnish the Returning 
Officer with a statement showing the number of votes which every elector has 
under the provisions of clause (2) of article 55; and every ballot paper put in 
by an elector at that election shall be deemed to represent as many votes as 
that elector is shown as having in that statement.</article> 

  
 <article>
<number>31</number> Ballot papers when 
invalid.—
<section><number>1</number> A 
ballot paper shall be invalid on which—
 <subsection>
       
 <number>a</number> the figure 1 is not marked; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       
 <number>b</number> the figure 1 is marked opposite the name of more than one candidate or is 
so marked as to render it doubtful to which candidate it is intended to apply; 
or 
 </subsection><subsection>
       
 <number>c</number> the figure 1 and some other figures are marked opposite the name of the 
same candidate; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       
 <number>d</number> any mark is made by which the elector may afterwards be identified.
 
Explanation.—The 
figures referred to in clauses (a), (b) and (c) of this sub-rule may be marked 
in the international form of Indian numerals or in the Roman form or in the form 
used in any Indian language, but shall not be indicated in words.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A ballot paper shall 
also be invalid if, being a postal ballot paper, the signature of the elector is 
not duly attested.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>32</number> Procedure upon 
opening each ballot box.—After 
each ballot box and also each sealed cover (if any) received under sub-rule (3) 
of rule 26, has been opened, the Returning Officer shall—
 <section>
       
 <number>a</number> count the number of ballot papers taken out therefrom and complete Part II 
of the Ballot Paper Account in Form 6; 
 </section><section>
       
 <number>b</number>  scrutinise the ballot papers and separate those which in his opinion 
are valid from those which in his opinion are invalid, endorsing on the latter 
the word ‘rejected’ and the ground of rejection; and
 </section><section>
       
 <number>c</number> arrange all the valid ballot papers in parcels according to the first 
preferences recorded for each candidate:
 
Provided that if, at a 
Presidential election, the ballot box used at a place of polling contains ballot 
papers of electors who, at their request are specially permitted by the Election 
Commission in pursuance of rule 7 to cast their votes at the said place of 
polling, such ballot papers shall, after the counting and recording in Form 6 is 
completed, be separated and added to the other ballot papers of the same kind 
used by electors in the same category and shall thereafter be scrutinised.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>33</number> Determination of 
result.—After 
all the ballot boxes and sealed covers (if any) have been opened and the ballot 
papers have been scrutinised and arranged, the Returning Officer shall proceed 
to determine the result of the voting in accordance with the instructions 
contained in the Schedule to these rules.
</article> 

  
 <article>
<number>34</number> Recounting.—The 
Returning Officer may, either on his own initiative or at the instance of any 
candidate or of the authorised representative of a candidate in the absence of 
that candidate, recount votes, whether once or more than once, when the 
Returning Officer is not satisfied as to the accuracy of a previous count:
 
Provided that nothing 
herein contained shall make it obligatory on the Returning Officer to recount 
the same votes more than once.
</article> 

  
 <article>
<number>35</number> Declaration of 
result.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When the counting is complete and the result of the voting has been determined, 
the Returning Officer shall forthwith—
 <subsection>
       
 <number>a</number> announce the result to those present;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
 <number>b</number> report the result to the Central Government and the Election Commission 
under section 12;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
 <number>c</number> prepare and certify a return of the election in Form 7; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       
 <number>d</number> seal up in separate packets the valid ballot papers and the rejected ballot 
papers and record on each such packet a description of its contents.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Returning Officer 
shall, as soon as may be thereafter, forward the certified return to the 
Election Commission.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>36</number> Custody of ballot 
boxes and election papers.—All 
ballot boxes used at the election and the packets of ballot papers and all other 
papers relating to the election shall, after the election, be kept in such 
custody as the Election Commission may direct.
</article> 

  
 <article>
<number>37</number> Production and 
inspection of election papers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The packets of ballot papers, whether valid or rejected, and their counterfoils 
and the packets containing the lists of electors marked in accordance with rule 
14 shall not be opened, nor shall their contents be inspected by, or produced 
before, any person or authority, except under the order of the Supreme Court or 
other competent court.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> All other papers 
relating to the election shall be open to public inspection subject to such 
conditions and to the payment of such fee, if any, as the Election Commission 
may direct.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>38</number> Disposal of 
election papers.—The 
packets and other papers referred to in rule 37 shall be retained for a period 
of two years from the date of declaration of the result of the election, and 
shall thereafter be destroyed unless a direction to the contrary is given by the 
Supreme Court or other competent court or by the Election Commission.
</article> 

  
 <article>
<number>39</number> Copies of return of 
election.—Copies 
of the certified return of the election referred to in rule 35 shall be 
furnished by the Election Commission on payment of a fee of one rupee per copy.
</article> 

  
 <article>
<number>40</number> List of electors.—The 
Election Commission shall maintain a list of members of the electoral college 
referred to in article 54 and a list of members of the electoral college 
referred to in article 66, with their addresses corrected up to date for the 
purposes, respectively, of Presidential election and Vice-Presidential election.
</article> 

  
 <article>
<number>41</number> Repeal.—The 
Presidential and Vice-Presidential Election Rules, 1952, are hereby repealed.
 
 
</article> 

  
 
THE SCHEDULE
 
(See rule 33)
 
INSTRUCTIONS FOR THE 
DETERMINATION OF RESULT
 <article>
<number>1</number> In this Schedule—
 <section>
<number>1</number> the expression 
“continuing candidate” means any candidate not elected and not excluded from the 
poll at any given time.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> the expression “first 
preference” means the figure 1 set opposite the name of any candidate, the 
expression “second preference” similarly means the figure 2, the expression 
“third preference” the figure 3, and so on;
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> the expression “next 
available preference” means the second or subsequent preference recorded in 
consecutive numerical order for a continuing candidate, preferences for 
candidates already excluded being ignored;
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> the expression 
“unexhausted paper” means a ballot paper on which a further preference is 
recorded for a continuing candidate;
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> the expression 
“exhausted paper” means a ballot paper on which no further preference is 
recorded for a continuing candidate, provided that a paper shall be deemed to be 
exhausted in any case in which—-
 <subsection>
             
<number>a</number> the names of two or more candidates whether continuing or not are marked 
with the same figure, and are next in order of preference; or
 </subsection><subsection>
             
<number>b</number> the name of the candidate next in order of preference, whether continuing or 
not, is marked by a figure not following consecutively after some other figure 
on the ballot paper or by two or more figures.
 </subsection></section></article><article>
<number>2</number> Every ballot paper 
represents at each count—
 <section>
<number>a</number> in a Presidential 
election, the number of votes as determined under rule 30; and 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> in a Vice-Presidential 
election, one vote.
 </section></article><article>
<number>3</number> Ascertain the number of 
first preference votes secured by each candidate and credit him with that 
number.
 </article><article>
<number>4</number> Add up the numbers so 
credited to all the candidates, divide the total by two, and add one to the 
quotient disregarding any remainder. The resulting number is the quota 
sufficient to secure the return of a candidate at the election.
 </article><article>
<number>5</number> If at the end of the 
first or any subsequent count, the total number of votes credited to any 
candidate is equal to, or greater than, the quota, or there is only one 
continuing candidate, that candidate is declared elected.
 </article><article>
<number>6</number> If at the end of any 
count, no candidate can be declared elected,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>  exclude the candidate 
who up to that stage has been credited with the lowest number of votes.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> examine all the ballot 
papers in his parcel and sub-parcels, arrange the unexhausted papers in 
sub-parcels according to the next available preferences recorded thereon for the 
continuing candidates, count the number of votes in each such sub-parcel and 
credit it to the candidate for whom such preference is recorded, transfer the 
sub-parcel to that candidate, and make a separate sub-parcel of all the 
exhausted papers; and 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>  see whether any of the 
continuing candidates has, after such transfer and credit, secured the quota.
 
If, when a candidate has to 
be excluded under clause (a) above, two or more candidates have been credited 
with the same number of votes and stand lowest on the poll, exclude that  
candidate who had secured the lowest number of first preference votes, and if 
that number also was the same in the case of two or more candidates, decide by 
lot which of them shall be excluded.
 
All the sub-parcels of 
exhausted papers referred to in clause (b) above shall be  set apart as 
finally dealt with and the votes recorded thereon shall not thereafter be taken 
into account.
 
 
  
</section></article><form>
 




The Presidential and Vice-Presidential Elections Rules, 1974
 

 
 


FORM 1
 


(See rule 3)
 


PUBLIC NOTICE
 


OF
 


ELECTION TO THE OFFICE 
OF *PRESIDENT/*VICE-PRESIDENT OF INDIA
 


 
 


WHEREAS a notification 
under sub-section (1) of section 4 of the Presidential and Vice-Presidential 
Elections Act, 1952, for the holding of an election to fill the office of 
President/Vice-President of India has been issued by the Election Commission, I, 
……………………., the Returning Officer for such election, do hereby give notice that—
 


(i) nomination papers may 
be delivered by a candidate or any one of his proposers or seconders to the 
undersigned at his office in ………………New Delhi, or if he is unavoidably absent, to 
……………………..at the said office between 11 a.m. and 3 p.m. on any day (other than a 
public holiday) not later than the……………………………;
 


(ii) each nomination paper 
shall be accompanied by a certified copy of the entry relating to the candidate 
in the electoral roll for the Parliamentary constituency in which the candidate 
is registered as an elector;
 


(iii)  every candidate 
shall deposit or cause to be deposited a sum of rupees 

1[fifteen thousand] 
only. This amount may be deposited in cash with the Returning Officer at the 
time of presentation of the nomination paper or deposited earlier in the Reserve 
Bank of India or in a Government Treasury and in the latter case a receipt 
showing that the said deposit of the sum has been so made is required to be 
enclosed with the nomination paper;
 


(iv) forms of nomination 
papers may be obtained from the above said office at the times aforesaid;
 


(v) the nomination papers, 
other than those rejected under sub-section (4) of section 5B of the Act, will 
be taken up for scrutiny at .......…. (place) on…………………….(date) at 
…………….(hours);
 


(vi) the notice of 
withdrawal of candidates may be delivered by a candidate, or any one of his 
proposers or seconders who has been authorised in this behalf in writing by the 
candidate, to the undersigned at the place specified in paragraph (i) above 
before three o’clock in the afternoon of …….(date);
 


(vii) in the event of the 
election being contested, the poll will be taken on ………….(date) between hours of 
......………….. and ………….. at the places of polling fixed under the rules.
 


Place………………...                                                                                                                                       
(Signature)..………
 


Dated ……………….                                                                                                                                     
(Returning Officer)
 


(Designation)…………….
 


 
 


*Strike off if 
inapplicable.
 


 
 


 
</form><form>
 




The Presidential and Vice-Presidential Elections Rules, 1974
 

 
 


FORM 4
 


[See rule 5(1)]
 


NOTICE OF WITHDRAWAL
 


To
 


The Returning Officer for 
the election to the office of President/Vice-President of India.
 


I,………………………………..(name) 
………….(address) of a candidate at the above-mentioned election do hereby give 
notice that I withdraw my candidature.
 


Place………………                                                                                                                                         
………………………..
 


 


Date…………………                                                                                                                               
  Signature of candidate
 


Note.—The 
notice of withdrawal is required to be delivered under section 6(1) of the 
Presidential and Vice-Presidential Elections Act, 1952, by the candidate in 
person or by any one of his proposers or seconders who has been authorised in 
this behalf in writing by such candidate.
 


 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>