<act><title>

    The limestone and dolomite mines labour welfare fund Act, 1972</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Limestone and Dolomite Mines Labour Welfare Fund 
    Act, 1972.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends 
    to the whole of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It 
    shall come into force on such date1 as 
    the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint 
    and different dates may be appointed for different States. 
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In this Act, unless 
    the context otherwise requires,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   “agent” and “owner” have the meanings 
    respectively assigned to them in clauses (c) and (l) of sub-section (l) of 
    section 2 of the Mines Act, 1952 (35 of 1952); 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   “factory” and “occupier” have the 
    meanings respectively assigned to them in clauses (m) and (n) of section 2 
    of the Factories Act, 1948 (63 of 1948); 
 

1[(bb)   
    ”Limestone” includes minerals like lime-shell, calcareous sand and sea sand 
    essentially composed of lime-shell, marl, kankar or lime kankar;]2[(bb) 
    ”Limestone” includes minerals like lime-shell, calcareous sand and sea sand 
    essentially composed of lime-shell, marl, kankar or lime kankar;]" 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   “manager” means the manager referred to 
    in section 17 of the Mines Act, 1952 (35 of 1952); 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   a person is said to be employed in a 
    limestone or dolomite mine,— 
 <subsection>
<number>1</number>   If he is employed within the premises or 
    in the vicinity of such mine by the owner, agent or manager of such mine or 
    by a contractor or any other agency exclusively in any one or more of the 
    following, namely:— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   any limestone or dolomite mining 
    operation; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   the operation, servicing, maintenance 
    or repair of any machinery or any part thereof used in or about such mine; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>   the loading, unloading or despatch of 
    limestone or dolomite or any other material connected with the mining of 
    limestone or dolomite; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iv</number>   any work in any office, canteen or 
    creche situate within the precincts of such mine; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>v</number>   any welfare, health, sanitary or 
    conservancy services or any watch and ward duties at any place situate 
    within such premises or vicinity, not being a place occupied by any 
    residential building; or 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>2</number>   If, in any such area as may be notified 
    by the Central Government in the Official Gazette in this behalf, he is 
    employed by the owner, agent or manager of such mine or by a contractor or 
    any other agency exclusively in the loading, unloading or despatch of 
    limestone or dolomite or any other material connected with the mining of 
    limestone or dolomite; 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>e</number>   “prescribed” means prescribed by rules 
    made under this Act. 
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Levy and 
    collection of cess on limestone and dolomite.—With 
    effect from such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the 
    Official Gazette, appoint, there shall be levied and collected as a cess for 
    the purposes of this Act on so much of limestone and dolomite produced in 
    any mine— 
 <section>
<number>i</number>   as is sold or otherwise disposed of to 
    the occupier of any factory; or 
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>   as is used by the owner of such 
    mine for any purpose in connection with the manufacture of cement, 
1[iron, 
    steel, ferro-alloys, alloy steels, chemicals sugar, paper, fertilizers, 
    refractories, iron ore, pelletisation or such other article or goods or 
    class of articles, or goods, as the Central Government may, from time to 
    time, specify by notification, in the Official Gazette];
1[iron, 
    steel, ferro-alloys, alloy steels, chemicals sugar, paper, fertilizers, 
    refractories, iron ore, pelletisation or such other article or goods or 
    class of articles, or goods, as the Central Government may, from time to 
    time, specify by notification, in the Official Gazette];" 
 
a duty of excise, at such rate not exceeding 
    one rupee per metric tonne of limestone or dolomite, as the case may be, as 
    the Central Government may, from time to time, fix by notification in the 
    Official Gazette. 
 

    Explanation.—Where 
    the owner of any limestone or dolomite mine is also the occupier of any 
    factory, then, for the purposes of clause (ii), all limestone or dolomite, 
    as the case may be, produced in the mine and not sold or otherwise disposed 
    of to the occupier of any other factory shall be deemed, unless the contrary 
    is proved, to have been used by such owner for any purpose in connection 
    with the manufacture of 

    2[any article or goods 
    referred to in or specified under clause (ii)].
 

 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Payment 
    of duty of excise.—
<section><number>1</number> Every duty 
    of excise leviable under this Act on limestone or dolomite shall be 
    payable,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   to the occupier of the factory, by the 
    person by whom such limestone or dolomite is sold or otherwise disposed of 
    to such occupier; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   to the Central Government, by the 
    owner of the limestone or dolomite mine where the limestone or dolomite is 
    used by such owner for any purpose in connection with the manufacture of
    1[any 
    article or goods referred to in or specified under clause (ii) of section 
    3],
 
within such period as may be prescribed. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> All 
    amounts referred to in clause (a) of sub-section (1) shall be collected by 
    the occupier of the factory in such manner, and paid by him to the Central 
    Government within such period, as may be prescribed. 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Application of proceeds of duty of excise.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    An amount equivalent to the proceeds of the duty of excise levied under this 
    Act, reduced by the cost of collection as determined by the Central 
    Government, together with any income from investment of the said amount and 
    any other moneys received by the Central Government for the purposes of this 
    Act, shall, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law, be paid to 
    the credit of a fund to be called the Limestone and Dolomite Labour Welfare 
    Fund (hereinafter referred to as the Fund). 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Fund 
    shall be applied by the Central Government to meet the expenditure incurred 
    in connection with measures which, in the opinion of that Government, are 
    necessary or expedient to promote the welfare of persons employed in the 
    limestone or dolomite mines; and in particular—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   to defray the cost of measures for the 
    benefit of persons employed in the limestone or dolomite mines directed 
    towards—     
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   the improvement of public health and 
    sanitation, the prevention of disease and the provision and improvement of 
    medical facilities; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   the provision and improvement of water 
    supplies and facilities for washing; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>   the provision and improvement of 
    educational facilities; 
1[***]
2[***]" 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iv</number>   the improvement of standards of living 
    including housing and nutrition, the amelioration of social conditions and 
    the provision of recreational facilities; 
 

2[(v)   
    the provisions of family welfare, including family planning, education and 
    services;]
3[(v) 
    the provisions of family welfare, including family planning, education and 
    services;]" 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   to grant loan or subsidy to a State 
    Government, a local authority or the owner of a limestone or dolomite mine, 
    in aid of any scheme approved by the Central Government for any purpose 
    connected with the welfare of persons employed in limestone or dolomite 
    mines; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   to pay annually grants-in-aid to such of 
    the owners of limestone or dolomite mines who provide to the satisfaction of 
    the Central Government welfare facilities of the prescribed standard for the 
    benefit of persons employed in their mines, so, however, that the amount 
    payable as grants-in-aid to any such owner shall not exceed— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   the amount spent by him in the provision 
    of welfare facilities as determined by the Central Government or any person 
    specified by it in this behalf, or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   such amount as may be prescribed, 
 
whichever is less: 
 
Provided that no grant-in-aid shall be payable 
    in respect of any welfare facilities provided by the owner of a limestone or 
    dolomite mine where the amount spent thereon determined as aforesaid is less 
    than the amount prescribed in this behalf; 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   to meet the allowances, if any, of the 
    members of the Advisory Committees and the Central Advisory Committee 
    constituted under sections 6 and 7 respectively and the salaries and 
    allowances, if any, of persons appointed under section 8; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   any other expenditure which the Central 
    Government may direct to be defrayed from the Fund. 
 






 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Advisory 
    Committees.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
    Government may constitute as many Advisory Committees as it thinks fit, but 
    not exceeding one for each of the principal limestone or dolomite producing 
    States, to advise the Central Government on such matters arising out of the 
    administration of this Act as may be referred to it by that Government, 
    including matters relating to the application of the Fund.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Each 
    Advisory Committee shall consist of such number of persons as may be 
    appointed to it by the Central Government and the members shall be chosen in 
    such manner as may be prescribed: 
 
Provided that 
    each Advisory Committee shall include an equal number of members 
    representing the Government, the owners of limestone and dolomite mines and 
    the persons employed in the limestone and dolomite mines and that at least 
    one member of each such committee shall be a woman. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Chairman of each Advisory Committee shall be appointed by the Central 
    Government. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Central Government shall publish in the Official Gazette the names of all 
    members of every Advisory Committee. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Central 
    Advisory Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Central Government may constitute a Central Advisory Committee to 
    co-ordinate the work of the Advisory Committees constituted under section 6 
    and to advise the Central Government on any matter arising out of the 
    administration of this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Central Advisory Committee shall consist of such number of persons as may be 
    appointed to it by the Central Government and the members shall be chosen in 
    such manner as may be prescribed: 
 
Provided that 
    the Central Advisory Committee shall include an equal number of members 
    representing the Government, the owners of limestone and dolomite mines and 
    the persons employed in the limestone and dolomite mines. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Chairman of the Central Advisory Committee shall be appointed by the Central 
    Government. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Central Government shall publish in the Official Gazette the names of all 
    members of the Central Advisory Committee. 
 

 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>7A</number> Power to 
    co-opt, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> An Advisory Committee or the Central Advisory Committee 
    may, at any time and for such period as it thinks fit, co-opt any person or 
    persons to the Committee. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A person 
    co-opted under sub-section (1) to a Committee shall exercise and discharge 
    all the powers and functions of a member thereof, but shall not be entitled 
    to vote.] 
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Appointment of Inspectors, etc. and their powers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may appoint as many 

    1[Welfare 
    Commissioners, Welfare Administrators, Inspectors] and such other officers 
    and staff as it thinks necessary for the purposes of this Act.—(1) 
    The Central Government may appoint as many 

    2[Welfare 
    Commissioners, Welfare Administrators, Inspectors] and such other officers 
    and staff as it thinks necessary for the purposes of this Act." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    person so appointed shall be deemed to be a public servant within the 
    meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860). 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>
    

    2[Any Welfare 
    Commissioner, Welfare Administrator or Inspector] may,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   with such assistance, if any, as he may 
    think fit, enter at any reasonable time, any place which he considers it 
    necessary to enter for carrying out the purposes of this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   do within such place anything necessary 
    for the proper discharge of his duties; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   exercise such other powers as may be 
    prescribed. 
 
 






 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Power of 
    Central Government to exempt.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in this Act, if the Central Government is satisfied that 
    there is in force in any State or part thereof a law making adequate 
    provision for the financing of activities to promote the welfare of persons 
    employed in the limestone or dolomite mines, it may, by notification in the 
    Official Gazette, direct that all or any of the provisions of this Act shall 
    not apply or shall apply to such State or part thereof subject to such 
    exceptions and modifications as may be specified in the notification. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Annual 
    report of activities financed under the Act.—The 
    Central Government shall, as soon as may be, after the end of each financial 
    year cause to be published in the Official Gazette a report giving an 
    account of its activities financed under this Act during the previous 
    financial year, together with a statement of accounts. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>11</number> Interest payable by occupiers of factories 
      and owners of mines.—If any 
      occupier of a factory or any owner of a limestone or dolomite mine fails 
      to pay any amount payable by him to the Central Government under section 4 
      within the period prescribed therefor under that section, such occupier or 
      owner, as the case may be, shall be liable to pay simple interest at 
      twelve per cent. per annum on the amount to be paid, from the date on 
      which such payment is due till such amount is actually 
      paid.
  
 
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Penalty 
    for non-payment of duty of excise within the prescribed period.—If 
    any duty of excise payable by the occupier of the factory or the owner of 
    the limestone or dolomite mine to the Central Government under section 4 is 
    not paid to that Government within the period prescribed thereunder, it 
    shall be deemed to be in arrears and the authority prescribed in this behalf 
    may, after such inquiry as it deems fit, impose on the occupier of the 
    factory or, as the case may be, on the owner of the limestone or dolomite 
    mine a penalty not exceeding the amount of duty of excise in arrears: 
 
Provided that 
    before imposing any such penalty such occupier or such owner, as the case 
    may be, shall be given a reasonable opportunity of being heard and, if after 
    such hearing the said authority is satisfied that the default was for any 
    good and sufficient reason, no penalty shall be imposed under this section. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>13</number> Recovery of amounts due under the 
      Act.—Any amount due under this 
      Act (including the interest or penalty, if any, payable under section 11 
      or section 12, as the case may be) from any occupier of a factory or any 
      owner of a limestone or dolomite mine may be recovered by the Central 
      Government in the same manner as an arrears of land revenue. 
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> Penalty 
    for evasion of duty of excise.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whoever wilfully or intentionally evades or attempts to evade the payment of 
    duty of excise payable by him to the Central Government under this Act, 
    shall, on conviction, be punishable with imprisonment which may extend to 
    six months, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with 
    both. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No court 
    shall take cognizance of an offence punishable under this section, save on a 
    complaint made by or under the authority of the Central Government. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Offences by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> Where 
    an offence under this Act has been committed by a company, every person who 
    at the time the offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible 
    to, the company for the conduct of the business of the company as well as 
    the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable 
    to be proceeded against and punished accordingly: 
 
Provided that 
    nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to 
    any punishment, if he proves that the offence was committed without his 
    knowledge or that he had exercised all due diligence to prevent the 
    commission of such offence. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where any offence 
    under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the 
    offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is 
    attributable to any neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary 
    or other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary or other 
    officer shall be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to 
    be proceeded against and punished accordingly. 
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    this section,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   “company” means any body corporate and 
    includes a firm or other association of individuals; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   “director”, in relation to a firm, means 
    a partner in the firm. 
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> Power 
    to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
    Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette and subject to the 
    condition of previous publication, make rules for carrying out the purposes 
    of this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the assessment and collection of the 
    duty of excise levied under this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   the period within which the person 
    selling or otherwise disposing of the limestone or dolomite to the occupier 
    of the factory shall pay the duty of excise to such occupier; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   the period within which the owner of the 
    limestone or dolomite mine shall pay the duty of excise to the Central 
    Government; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   the manner in which the occupier of the 
    factory shall collect the duty of excise; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   the period within which the occupier of 
    the factory shall pay to the Central Government the duty of excise collected 
    by him; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   the determination of the cost of 
    collection of the duty of excise levied under this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>   the manner in which the Fund may be 
    applied for the measures specified in section 5; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>   the conditions governing the grant of 
    loan or subsidy under clause (b) of sub-section (2) of section 5; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>   the standard of welfare facilities to be 
    provided by owners of limestone or dolomite mines for the purposes of clause 
    (c) of sub-section (2) of section 5; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>   the determination of the amounts 
    referred to in sub-clause (ii) of clause (c) of sub-section (2) of section 5 
    and in the proviso to that clause; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>   the composition of the Advisory 
    Committees and the Central Advisory Committee constituted under sections 6 
    and 7 respectively, the manner in which the members thereof shall be chosen, 
    the term of office of such members, the allowances, if any, payable to them, 
    and the manner in which the said Advisory Committees and the Central 
    Advisory Committee shall conduct their business; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>   the recruitment, conditions of service 
    and the duties of all persons appointed under section 8; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number>   the powers that may be exercised 
    by 1[a 
    Welfare Commissioner or a Welfare Administrator or an Inspector] under 
    section 8;1[a 
    Welfare Commissioner or a Welfare Administrator or an Inspector] under 
    section 8;" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>n</number>   the furnishing to the Central 
    Government by the occupier of factories 
2[, 
    the purchasing agents or stockists of lime-stone or dolomite] and the 
    owners, agents or managers of limestone or dolomite mines, of such 
    statistical and other information as may be required to be furnished from 
    time to time by that Government;
2[, 
    the purchasing agents or stockists of lime-stone or dolomite] and the 
    owners, agents or managers of limestone or dolomite mines, of such 
    statistical and other information as may be required to be furnished from 
    time to time by that Government;" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>o</number>   the authority which may impose any 
    penalty under section 12. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> In making 
    any rule under clause (b) or clause (n) of sub-section (2), the Central 
    Government may direct that a breach thereof shall be punishable with fine 
    which may extend to five hundred rupees. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every rule 
    made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, 
    before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period 
    of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
    successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
    following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses 
    agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the 
    rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
    modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
    such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of 
    anything previously done under that rule. 
  








 



</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>