<act><tid>1330253</tid>
<title>THE INDIAN COMPANIES (FOREIGN INTERESTS) ACT, <year>1918</year></title>

ACT NO. 20 OF <year>1918</year>
[ 26th September, <year>1918</year>.]

An Act to take power to prohibit the alteration, except with the 
sanction of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Central Government], of articles of association 
which restrict foreign interests in certain Companies, and to provide 
for other purposes connected therewith.

WHEREAS it is expedient to take power to prohibit the alteration, 
except with the sanction of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Central Government], of articles of 
association which restrict foreign interests in certain companies, and 
to provide for other purposes connected therewith; It is hereby 
enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>335405</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Indian Companies 
 (Foreign Interests) Act, <year>1918</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1471633</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.
<section><tid>1492450</tid>
<number>1</number>In this Act- 

<subsection><tid>1092492</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the expression" Commonwealth citizen" has the same 
meaning as in section 1 of the British Nationality Act, <year>1948</year>, 
but shall include any association incorporated in any part of 
the Commonwealth, including India];

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1887758</tid>
<number>b</number>the expression" restrictive provision" means any 
provision in the articles of association of a company which, 
in the opinion of the Central Government, is designed to 
restrict or limit or has the effect of restricting or 
limiting the share or shares or interest which may be held, 
or the rights, powers or authority which may be conferred 
upon or exercised by or on behalf of persons other than 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Commonwealth citizens] in the company, or in respect of the 
control, management or direction of the affairs thereof.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1022316</tid>
<number>2</number>All words and expressions used in this Act and defined in 
the 4 Indian Companies Act, <year>1913</year>, (7 of <year>1913</year>) shall be deemed to have 
the meanings respectively attributed to them by that Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year> for" the G. G. in C.".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs., ibid., for cl. (a).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs., ibid., for" British subjects".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Now see the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>915219</tid>
<number>3</number>Application of Act. This Act shall apply to such companies as 
the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
declare to be companies with restrictive provisions, and any such 
notification shall specify the restrictive provisions.


</article>



<article><tid>557172</tid>
<number> 4</number> Alterations in restrictive provisions and winding up. So long 
as a notification issued under section 3 is in force in respect of any 
company, notwithstanding anything to the contrary in any other Act-
<section><tid>1713802</tid>
<number>1</number>no alteration of the articles of association of the 
company affecting either directly or indirectly any 
restrictive provision shall be of any effect until it has 
received the consent in writing of the Central Government;

</section>

<section><tid>297672</tid>
<number>2</number>a resolution for the voluntary winding up of the 
company shall be of no effect unless the Central Government 
authorizes or ratifies it by a written consent;

</section>

<section><tid>1394036</tid>
<number>3</number>any Court which has jurisdiction to wind up the company 
may in its discretion refuse to make a winding up order. In 
the exercise of its discretion, the Court shall be guided by 
the consideration whether the winding up is bona fide with a 
view to the discontinuance of the undertaking, or is with a 
view to continuing the undertaking freed either wholly or in 
part from any restrictive provision;

</section>

<section><tid>1623400</tid>
<number>4</number>the Central Government in giving consent, or the Court 
in making a winding up order, as the case may be, may impose 
such terms or conditions for giving effect to the purposes of 
this Act as <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> it] thinks fit.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for" he or it".

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>