<act><title>THE GOVERNMENT SECURITIES ACT, 2006 </title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title, application and commencement. </title>This Act may 
be called the Government Securities Act, 2006. 
 <section><number>2</number> This Act applies to Government securities created and issued whether 
before or after the commencement of this Act by the Central Government or a 
State Government. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> It applies in the first instance to whole of the States, except the State 
of Jammu and Kashmir, and to all the Union territories and it shall also apply 
to the State of Jammu and Kashmir which adopts this Act by resolution passed in 
that behalf under clause (1) of Article 252 of the Constitution. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> It shall come into force in all the States, except the State of Jammu and 
Kashmir, and in the Union territories on such date 1 as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint and in the State of Jammu 
and Kashmir which adopts this Act under clause (1) of Article 252 of the 
Constitution, on the date of such adoption; and any reference in this Act to the 
commencement of this Act shall, in relation to any State or Union territory, 
means the date on which this Act, comes into force in such State or Union 
territory. </section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.In 
this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  agent means 
a scheduled bank within the meaning of clause (e) of section 2 of the Reserve 
Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934), or any other person specified as such;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  Bank means 
the Reserve Bank of India constituted under section 3 of the Reserve Bank of 
India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934);
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  bond ledger 
account means an account with the Bank or an agent in which the Government 
securities are held in a dematerialised form at the credit of the holder;
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>  
constituents subsidiary general ledger account means a subsidiary general 
ledger account opened and maintained with the Bank by an agent on behalf of the 
constituents of such agent;
 </section><section>
        <number>e</number>  Government, 
in relation to any Government security, means the Central or State Government 
issuing the security;
 </section><section>
         <number>f</number>  Government 
security means a security created and issued by the Government for the purpose 
of raising a public loan or for any other purpose as may be notified by the 
Government in the Official Gazette and having one of the forms mentioned in 
section 3;
 </section><section>
        <number>g</number>  prescribed 
means prescribed by regulations made under this Act;
 </section><section>
        <number>h</number>  promissory 
note includes a treasury bill;
 </section><section>
         <number>i</number>  specified 
means specified by the Bank in the Official Gazette.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Forms of Government 
securities.A 
Government security may, subject to such terms and conditions as may be 
specified, be in such forms as may be prescribed or in one of the following 
forms, namely:
 <section>
         <number>i</number>  a Government 
promissory note payable to or to the order of a certain person; or
 </section><section>
        <number>ii</number>  a bearer 
bond payable to bearer; or
 </section><section>
        <number>iii</number>  a stock; or
 </section><section>
       <number>iv</number>  a bond held 
in a bond ledger account.
 
Explanation.For 
the purpose of this section, stock means a Government security,
 </section><section>
         <number>i</number>  registered 
in the books of the Bank for which a stock certificate is issued; or
 </section><section>
        <number>ii</number>  held at the 
credit of the holder in the subsidiary general ledger account including the 
constituents subsidiary general ledger account maintained in the books of the 
Bank,
 
and transferable by 
registration in the books of the Bank.


</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Subsidiary general 
ledger account.
<section><number>1</number> 
A subsidiary general ledger account including a constituents subsidiary general 
ledger account and a bond ledger account may be opened and maintained by the 
Bank subject to such conditions and restrictions as may be specified and in such 
form and on payment of such fee as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in the Benami Transactions (Prohibition) Act, 1988 (45 
of 1988), or any other law for the time being in force, the Government 
securities may be held on behalf of a constituent in a constituents subsidiary 
general ledger account under sub-section (1) and the holder of such account 
shall be deemed to be the holder of the securities held in that account:
 
Provided that the 
constituent as a beneficial owner of the Government security shall be entitled 
to claim from the holder all the benefits and be subjected to all the 
liabilities in respect of the Government securities held in the constituents 
subsidiary general ledger account.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The holder of a 
constituents subsidiary general ledger account shall maintain such records and 
adopt such procedure for safeguarding the interests of the constituents as may 
be specified.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Transfer of 
Government securities.
<section><number>1</number> 
No transfer of a Government security shall be valid if it does not purport to 
convey the full title to the security.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The transfer of the 
Government securities shall be made in such form and in such manner as may be 
prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any document relating 
to a Government security or any endorsement on a promissory note issued by the 
Government may, on the demand of a person who for any reason is unable to write, 
shall be executed on his behalf in such manner as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Nothing in this 
section shall affect any order made by the Bank under this Act, or any order 
made by a Court upon the Bank.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Holding of 
Government securities by holders of public offices.
<section><number>1</number> 
In the case of any public office to which the Government may, by notification in 
the Official Gazette, declare this sub-section to apply, a Government security 
may be held in the name of the office.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When a Government 
security is so held, it shall be deemed to be transferred without any or further 
endorsement or transfer deed from each holder of the office to the succeeding 
holder of the office on and from the date on which the latter takes charge of 
the office.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> When the holder of the 
office transfers to a party not being his successor in office where a Government 
security so held, the transfer shall be made by the signature of the holder of 
the office and the name of the office in the manner laid down in section 5.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where the holder of 
the office is temporarily absent for more than a fortnight from his office for 
any reason, he may authorise in writing such other person, who would be incharge 
of this office during the period of such absence, to effect transfer of the 
Government securities.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> This section applies 
as well to an office of which there are two or more joint holders as to an 
office of which there is a single holder.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Recognition of title 
to Government security of deceased sole holder or joint holders.
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to the provisions of sub-sections (2) and (3), if on the death of a sole 
holder or death of all the joint holders of a Government security there is no 
nomination in force, the executors or administrators of the deceased sole holder 
or all the deceased joint holders, as the case may be, or the holder of a 
succession certificate issued under Part X of the Indian Succession Act, 1925 
(39 of 1925) shall be the only person who may be recognised by the Bank as 
having any title to the Government security.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Nothing contained in 
this section shall bar the recognition by the Bank of any person as having a 
title to a Government security on the basis of a decree, order or direction 
passed by a competent court declaring the person as having title to the 
Government security or appointing a receiver to take possession of a security or 
on the basis of a certificate issued or order passed by any other authority who 
might have been empowered under any statute to confer on any such person a title 
to the Government security or on the basis of such other documents as may be 
prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in this section or in any other law for the time being in 
force, where the outstanding value of Government security held by a deceased 
sole holder or deceased joint holders, as the case may be, does not exceed an 
amount of rupees one lakh or such higher amount not exceeding rupees one crore 
as may be fixed by the Central Government by notification in the Official 
Gazette from time to time, the Bank may recognize a person as having title to 
such Government security of the deceased sole holder or deceased joint holders 
in such manner and subject to such conditions as may be prescribed.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Right of survivors 
of joint holders or several payees.Notwithstanding 
anything contained in section 45 of the Indian Contract Act, 1872 (9 of 1872) 
and subject to the provisions of sections 7 and 10,
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  when a 
Government security is held by two or more persons jointly, and either or any of 
them dies, the title to the Government security shall vest in the survivor or 
survivors of those persons; and
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  when a 
Government security is payable to two or more persons severally and either or 
any of them dies, the Government security shall be payable to the survivor or 
survivors of those persons or to the representative of the deceased or to any 
one of them:
 
Provided that nothing 
contained in this section shall affect any claim which any representative of a 
deceased joint holder or deceased holders of a Government security or a 
surviving joint holder or holders of a Government security, as the case may be, 
may have against the survivor or survivors or representatives under or in 
respect of any Government security to which this section applies.
 
Explanation.For 
the purposes of this section, a body incorporated or deemed to be incorporated 
under the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), or the Co-operative Societies Act, 
1912 (2 of 1912), or any other enactment for the time being in force relating to 
the incorporation of associations of individuals, shall be deemed to die when it 
is dissolved.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Nomination by 
holders of Government securities.
<section><number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in sections 7 and 8 or any other law for the 
time being in force, except the provisions of sub-section (2),
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  where a 
Government security other than in the form of promissory note or bearer bond is 
held by a person in his name or jointly with any other name or names, as the 
case may be, the sole holder or all the joint holders of the Government security 
together may nominate one or more persons in such form and in such manner as may 
be prescribed, who in the event of the death of the sole holder or the death of 
all the joint holders, as the case may be, would become entitled to the 
Government security and to payment thereon to the exclusion of all other 
persons, unless the nomination is varied or cancelled in the prescribed manner;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  where a 
nomination in respect of a Government security has been made in favour of two or 
more nominees and either or any of them is dead, the surviving nominee or 
nominees, as the case may be, shall be entitled to the Government security and 
payment thereon;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  where the 
nominee is a minor, it shall be lawful for the sole holder or all the joint 
holders of a Government security, as the case may be, to appoint in the 
prescribed manner any person in whom the Government security would be deemed to 
have vested in the event of death of such holder or joint holders of the 
Government security during the minority of the nominee;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  the 
recognition of right and claim of the nominee or nominees to the Government 
security held by a sole holder or joint holders, as the case may be, and any 
payment made by the Government or the Bank to the nominee or nominees shall 
constitute a full discharge and shall absolve the Government or the Bank of its 
liability in respect of the said Government security.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Any nomination or 
appointment made under sub-section (1) shall become void if the nominee 
predeceases, or where there are two or more nominees, if all the nominees 
predecease the holder or joint holders of the Government security making the 
nomination.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the amount due 
for the time being on a Government security is payable to two or more nominees 
and either or any of them dies, the title to the Government security shall vest 
in the survivor or survivors of those nominees and the amount for the time being 
due thereon shall be paid accordingly.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A transfer of a 
Government security made in accordance with sub-section (2) of section 5 shall 
automatically cancel the nomination previously made:
 
Provided that where a 
Government security is in the possession of a person either as a pledge or by 
way of security for any purpose, such possession shall not have the effect of 
cancelling the nomination, but the right of the nominee shall be subject to the 
right of the person so possessing it.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Government may, on 
the recommendation of the Bank, by notification in the Official Gazette, extend 
the facility of nomination to any Government security as may be specified 
therein.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Nothing contained in 
sub-section (1) shall affect the right or claim which any person may have 
against the person whose right and title to a Government security is recognised 
by the Government or the Bank or to whom the payment of the amount due on the 
Government security is made by the Government or the Bank under sub-section (1).
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> No notice of any claim 
of any person, other than the person or persons in whose name a Government 
security is held or the nominees thereof, shall be receivable by the Bank or the 
Government, nor shall the Bank or the Government be bound by any such notice 
even though expressly given to it:
 
Provided that where any 
decree, order, certificate or other authority from a court of competent 
jurisdiction relating to such Government security is produced before the Bank or 
the Government, the Bank or the Government shall take due note of such decree, 
order, certificate or other authority.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Government 
securities belonging to minor or insane person.
<section><number>1</number> 
Where any Government security is held on behalf of a minor, the payment of the 
same for the time being due on a Government security either by way of 
outstanding principal or interest thereon may be made to the father or mother of 
such minor and where neither parent is alive or where the living parents are or 
only living parent is incapable of action, to person entitled under the law for 
the time being in force to have care of the property of the minor.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When a Government 
security belongs to a minor or a person who is insane and incapable of managing 
his affairs and the outstanding principal value of the Government security does 
not in the aggregate exceed rupees one lakh or such higher amount not exceeding 
rupees one crore as the Central Government may, by a notification in the 
Official Gazette from time to time, fix, the Bank may make such order as it 
thinks fit for the vesting of such Government security in such person as it 
considers represents the minor or insane person.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Issue of duplicate 
securities and of new securities on conversion, consolidation, sub-division, 
renewal, stripping or reconstitution.
<section><number>1</number> 
If the person entitled to a Government security applies to the Bank alleging 
that the Government security has been lost, stolen or destroyed, or has been 
defaced or mutilated, the Bank may, on proof to its satisfaction of the loss, 
theft, destruction, defacement or mutilation of the Government security, and 
subject to such conditions and on payment of such fees as may be prescribed, 
order the issue of a duplicate Government security to the applicant.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the person entitled 
to a Government security applies to the Bank to have the Government security 
converted into a Government security of another form, or into a Government 
security issued in connection with another loan or to have it consolidated with 
other like Government securities, or to have it sub-divided, or to have it 
renewed, stripped or reconstituted, the Bank may, subject to such conditions and 
on payment of such fees as may be prescribed, cancel the Government security and 
order the issue of a new Government security or Government securities.
 
Explanation.A 
Government security may be stripped separately for interest and principal or 
reconstituted on the application of the holder subject to such terms and 
conditions as may be specified.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The person to whom a 
duplicate Government security or a new Government security is issued under this 
section shall be deemed for the purposes of section 18 to have been recognised 
by the Bank as the holder of the Government security; and a duplicate Government 
security or new Government security so issued to any person shall be deemed to 
constitute a new contract between the Government and such person and all persons 
deriving title thereafter through him:
 
Provided that the issue of 
new security under this section shall not affect the interest of third parties 
in whose favour a charge or other interest was lawfully created and was 
subsisting at the time of issue of the new security.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Summary 
determination by Bank of title to Government security in case of dispute.
<section><number>1</number> 
If the Bank is of opinion that a doubt exists as to the title to a Government 
security, it may proceed to determine, in accordance with such regulations as 
may be made, the person who shall for the purposes of the Bank be deemed to be 
the person entitled thereto.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> For the purpose of 
making any order which it is empowered to make under this Act, the Bank may 
request a District Magistrate to record or to have recorded the whole or any 
part of such evidence as any person whose evidence the Bank requires may produce 
and the District Magistrate so requested may either himself record, or may 
direct any Executive Magistrate empowered in this behalf by general or special 
order of the State Government to record the evidence, and shall forward a copy 
thereof to the Bank.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> For the purpose of 
making a vesting order under this Act, the Bank may direct one of its officers 
to record the evidence of any person whose evidence the Bank requires or may 
receive evidence upon affidavit.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A Magistrate or an 
officer of the Bank acting in pursuance of this section may administer an oath 
to any witness examined by him.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Law applicable in 
regard to Government securities.Notwithstanding 
that as a matter of convenience, the Government may have arranged for payments 
on a Government security to be made elsewhere than in India, the rights of all 
persons in relation to Government securities shall be determined in connection 
with all such questions as are dealt with by this Act by the law and in the 
Courts of India.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Postponement of 
payments and registration of transfers pending the making of vesting order.Where 
the Bank contemplates making an order under this Act to vest a Government 
security in any person, the Bank may suspend payment of interest on or the 
maturity value of the Government security or postpone the making of any order 
under section 7, section 10, section 11 or section 12 or the registration of any 
transfer of the Government security, as the case may be, until the vesting order 
has been made.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Power of Bank to 
require bonds.
<section><number>1</number> 
Before making any order which it is empowered to make under this Act, the Bank 
may require the person in whose favour the order is to be made to execute an 
indemnity bond with one or more sureties in such form as may be prescribed or to 
furnish security not exceeding twice the value of the subject-matter of the 
order, to be held at the disposal of the Bank, to pay to the Bank or any person 
to whom the Bank may assign the indemnity bond or security in furtherance of 
sub-section (2) the amount thereof.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A Court before which a 
claim in respect of the subject-matter of any such order is established may 
order the indemnity bond or security to be assigned to the successful claimant 
who shall thereupon be entitled to enforce the indemnity bond or realise the 
security to the extent of such claim.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Publication of 
notices in Official Gazette.Any 
notice required to be given by the Bank under this Act may be served by post, 
but every such notice shall also be published by the Bank in the Official 
Gazette or the Official Gazette of a State, according as the notice relates to a 
Government security, issued by the Central Government or a State Government, and 
on such publication shall be deemed to have been delivered to all persons for 
whom it is intended.


</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Procedure and scope 
of vesting order.
<section><number>1</number> 
The Bank shall, while making a vesting order under section 7, section 10, 
section 11 or section 12, follow such procedure as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An order made by the 
Bank under this Act may either confer full title to a Government security or a 
title only to the accrued and accruing interest on the Government security 
pending a further order vesting full title.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Legal effect of 
orders made by Bank.No 
recognition by the Bank of a person as the holder of a Government security, and 
no order made by the Bank under this Act shall be called in question by any 
Court so far as such recognition or order affects the relations of the 
Government or the Bank with the person recognised by the Bank as the holder of a 
Government security or with any person claiming an interest in such security; 
and any such recognition by the Bank of any person or any order by the Bank 
vesting a Government security in any person shall operate to confer on that 
person a title to the security subject only to his personal liability to the 
rightful owner of the security for money had and received on his account.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Stay of proceedings 
on order of Court.Where 
the Bank contemplates making with reference to any Government security any order 
which it is empowered to make under this Act, and before the order is made the 
Bank receives from a Court in India an order to stay the making of such order, 
the Bank shall either
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  hold the 
security together with any interest unpaid or accruing thereon until further 
orders of the Court are received; or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  apply to the 
Court to have the security transferred to the Official Trustees appointed for 
the State in which such Court is situated, pending the disposal of the 
proceedings before the Court.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Cancellation by 
Bank of vesting proceedings.Where 
the Bank contemplates making an order under this Act vesting a Government 
security in any person, the Bank may, at any time before the order is made, 
cancel any proceedings already taken for that purpose and may, on such 
cancellation, proceed anew to the making of such order.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Discharge in 
respect of interest on Government securities.Save 
as otherwise expressly provided in the terms of a Government security, no person 
shall be entitled to claim interest on such security in respect of any period 
which has elapsed after the earliest date on which demand could have been made 
for the payment of the amount due on such security.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Discharge in 
respect of bearer bonds.The 
Government shall be discharged from all liability on a bearer bond or on any 
interest coupon of such a bond on payment to the holder of such bond or coupon 
on presentation on or after the date when it becomes due of the amount expressed 
therein, unless before such payment, an order of a Court in India has been 
served on the Government restraining it from making payment.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Period of 
limitation of Governments liability in respect of interest.
<section><number>1</number> 
Where no shorter period of limitation is fixed by any law for the time being in 
force, the liability of the Government in respect of any interest payment due on 
a Government security shall terminate on the expiry of six years from the date 
on which the amount due by way of interest became payable:
 
Provided that the 
Government may allow a bona fide claim for payment of interest after the 
expiry of the period of six years in those cases where the holders of securities 
could not prefer their claims within the said period of six years.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-section (1), the Bank may specify the securities in 
respect of which, the circumstances under which, and the terms and conditions 
subject to which, interest may be paid even after the expiry of the period 
specified in the said sub-section.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>24</number> Inspection of 
documents.No 
person shall be entitled to inspect or to receive information derived from any 
Government security in the possession or custody of the Government or from any 
book, register or other document kept or maintained by or on behalf of the 
Government in relation to Government securities or any Government security, save 
in such circumstances and manner and subject to such conditions as may be 
prescribed.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Micro films, 
facsimile copies of documents, magnetic tapes and computer print outs as 
documents of evidence.
<section><number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being in 
force,
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  a micro film 
of a document or the reproduction of the image or images embodied in such micro 
film (whether enlarged or not); or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  a facsimile 
copy of a document; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  a statement 
contained in a document and included in a printed material produced by a 
computer, magnetic tape or any other form of mechanical or electronic data 
retrieval mechanism (hereinafter referred to a computer print out), if the 
conditions mentioned in sub-section (2) and the other provisions contained in 
this section are satisfied in relation to the statement and the computer in 
question,
 
shall be deemed to be also 
a document for the purposes of this Act and the regulations made thereunder and 
shall be admissible in any proceedings thereunder, without further proof or 
production of the original, as evidence of any contents of the original or of 
any fact stated therein of which direct evidence would be admissible.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The conditions 
referred to in sub-section (1) in respect of a computer print out shall be the 
following, namely:
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  the computer 
print out containing the statement was produced by the computer during the 
period over which the computer was used regularly to store or process 
information for the purposes of any activities regularly carried on over that 
period by the person having lawful control over the use of the computer;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  during the 
said period, there was regularly supplied to the computer in the ordinary course 
of the said activities, information of the kind contained in the statement or of 
the kind from which the information so contained is derived;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  throughout 
the material part of the said period, the computer was operating properly or, if 
not, then any respect in which it was not operating properly or was out of 
operation during that part of that period was not such as to affect the 
production of the document or the accuracy of the contents; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  the 
information contained in the statement reproduced or is derived from information 
supplied to the computer in the ordinary course of the said activities.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Where over any period, 
the function of storing or processing information for the purposes of any 
activities regularly carried on over that period as mentioned in clause (a) of 
sub-section (2) was regularly performed by computers, whether
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  by a 
combination of computers operating over that period; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  by different 
computers operating in succession over that period; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  by different 
combinations of computers operating in succession over that period; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  in any other 
manner involving the successive operation over that period, in whatever order, 
of one or more computers and one or more combinations of computers,
 
all the computers used for 
that purpose during that period shall be treated for the purposes of this 
section as constituting a single computer; and references in this section to a 
computer shall be construed accordingly.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> In any proceeding 
under this Act and the regulations made thereunder where it is desired to give a 
statement in evidence by virtue of this section, a certificate doing any of the 
following things, that is to say,
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  identifying 
the document containing the statement and describing the manner in which it was 
produced;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  giving such 
particulars of any device involved in the production of that document as may be 
appropriate for the purpose of showing that the document was produced by a 
computer;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  dealing with 
any of the matters to which the conditions mentioned in sub-section (2) relate, 
and purporting to be signed by a person occupying a responsible official 
position in the Bank in relation to the operation of the relevant device or the 
management of the relevant activities (whichever is appropriate),
 
shall be evidence of any 
matter stated in the certificate; and for the purposes of this sub-section it 
shall be sufficient for a matter to be stated to the best of the knowledge and 
belief of the person stating it.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> For the purposes of 
this section,
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  information 
shall be taken to be supplied to a computer if it is supplied thereto in any 
appropriate form and whether it is so supplied directly or (with or without 
human intervention) by means of any appropriate equipment;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  whether in 
the course of activities carried on by any official, information is supplied 
with a view to its being stored or processed for the purposes of those 
activities by a computer operated otherwise than in the course of those 
activities, that information, if duly supplied to that computer, shall be taken 
to be supplied to it in the course of those activities;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  a document 
shall be taken to have been produced by a computer whether it was produced by it 
directly or (with or without human intervention) by means of any appropriate 
equipment.
 
Explanation.For 
the purposes of this section,
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>a</number>  computer 
means any electronic, magnetic, optical or other high-speed data processing 
service device or system which performs logical, arithmetical and memory 
functions by manipulation of electronic, magnetic or optical impulses and 
includes all input, output, processing, storage, computer software or 
communication facilities which are connected or related to the computer in 
computer system or computer network;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  computer 
print out shall include ledgers, day-books, account books and other records, 
maintained in the ordinary course of business of the Bank or of the agent, 
printed on paper from the information stored in the computer or derived from 
such information; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  any reference 
to information being derived from other information;
 
shall be a reference its 
being derived therefrom by calculation, comparison or, any other process.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> The Bank and its 
officers to be deemed public officers.For 
the purposes of section 124 of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872), the 
provisions of Part IV of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) relating 
to suits by or against public officers in their official capacity, and the 
provisions of Rule 27 of Order V, and rule 52 of Order XXI of the said Code, the 
Bank and any officer of the Bank acting in his capacity as such shall be deemed 
to be a public officer.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Misuse of 
subsidiary general ledger account facility.Where 
a subsidiary general ledger account is opened by the Bank in favour of any 
holder of a Government security in terms of section 4 and,
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  it comes to 
the notice of the Bank that the said account is being operated contrary to the 
terms and conditions subject to which the account was opened; or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  the 
subsidiary general ledger account transfer form has bounced due to insufficiency 
of Government security or funds; or
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  the Bank is 
of opinion that the account is being operated contrary to the banking practice 
or in a manner prejudicial to the interests of the holders of Government 
securities in general; or
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>  the 
subsidiary general ledger account is being misused in any manner,
 
the Bank may, by order in 
writing, after giving an opportunity of being heard, debar the holder of such 
account from trading with the subsidiary general ledger account facility 
temporarily or permanently as it deems fit.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Pledge, 
hypothecation or lien.
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to such terms and conditions as may be prescribed, the holder of a 
Government security may create a pledge or hypothecation or lien in respect of 
such security.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On receipt of notice 
of pledge or hypothecation or lien from the holder of the Government security, 
the Bank or any agent maintaining the account in respect of such security shall 
make necessary entry in its record and such entry shall be evidence of the 
pledge, hypothecation or lien thereof, as the case may be.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>29</number> Power to call for 
information, cause inspection and issue directions.
<section><number>1</number> 
The Bank may at any time, for the purposes of this Act, call for such 
information as it deems necessary in relation to a Government security from any 
agent, or holder of subsidiary general ledger account including constituents 
subsidiary general ledger account and cause an inspection or scrutiny to be made 
by one or more of its officers or other persons, of any agent or holder of a 
subsidiary general ledger account including constituents subsidiary general 
ledger account.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Bank may, if it 
considers necessary so to do, issue such directions as it thinks fit, in 
relation to a Government security,
 <subsection>
         <number>i</number>  to the 
holders of the subsidiary general ledger accounts including constituents 
subsidiary general ledger account;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  to the 
agents maintaining bond ledger account; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>iii</number>  to any 
other person dealing with the Government securities, 
 
for carrying out the 
purposes of this Act.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>30</number> Contravention and 
penalties.
<section><number>1</number> 
If any person, for the purpose of obtaining for himself or for any other person 
any title to a Government security, makes to any authority in any application 
made under this Act or in the course of any inquiry undertaken in pursuance of 
this Act any statement which is false and which he either knows to be false or 
does not believe to be true, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term 
which may extend to six months, or with fine, or with both.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No Court shall take 
cognizance of any offence under sub-section (1) except on the complaint of the 
Bank.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Without prejudice to 
any other action which the Bank may deem fit to take, the Bank, after giving a 
reasonable opportunity of being heard, may impose on any person who contravenes 
any provision of this Act, or contravenes any regulation, notification or 
direction issued under this Act, or violates the terms and conditions for 
opening and maintenance of a subsidiary general ledger account, including 
Constituents subsidiary general ledger account, a penalty, not exceeding five 
lakh rupees and where such contravention is a continuing one, further penalty 
which may extend to five thousand rupees for every day after first day during 
which the contravention continues.


</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>31</number> Certain laws not to 
apply to Government securities.
<section><number>1</number> 
The Public Debt Act, 1944 (18 of 1944) shall cease to apply to the Government 
securities to which this Act applies and to all matters for which provisions 
have been made by this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding such 
cessation anything done or any action taken in the exercise of any power 
conferred by or under that Act shall be deemed to have been done or taken in the 
exercise of the powers conferred by or under this Act as if this Act was in 
force at all material times.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Nothing contained in 
the Depositories Act, 1996 (22 of 1996) or the regulations made thereunder shall 
apply to Government securities covered by this Act unless an agreement is 
executed to the contrary by any depository under the Depositories Act, 1996 with 
the Government or the Bank, as the case may be.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>32</number> Power to make 
regulations.
<section><number>1</number> 
The Bank may, with the previous approval of the Central Government, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, make regulations to carry out the purposes 
of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular and 
without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power such regulations may 
provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  the form in 
which and the terms and conditions subject to which the Government securities 
may be issued under section 3;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  the form in 
which and the fee to be charged for opening and maintenance of subsidiary 
general ledger account including constituents subsidiary general ledger account 
and bond ledger account by the Bank under sub-section (1) of section 4;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  the form and 
manner in which Government securities shall be transferred under sub-section (2) 
of section 5 and the manner in which any document relating to any Government 
security or any endorsement on a promissory note may be executed on behalf of a 
person who is unable to write under sub-section (3) of that section.
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  the documents 
to be produced for recognition of title to the Government security of a deceased 
sole holder or all deceased joint holders under sub-section (2) of section 7 and 
the manner in which and the conditions subject to which the Bank may recognise 
title to a Government security under sub-section (3) of that section;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>e</number>  the form and 
the manner in which a nomination may be made, varied or cancelled and the manner 
in which any person may be appointed in whom the Government security would be 
deemed to have vested in the event of death of holder or joint holders of 
Government security during the minority of a nominee under section 9;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>f</number>  the 
conditions governing the issue of duplicate Government securities and the fees 
to be paid therefor under section 11;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>g</number>  the manner in 
which the Bank may determine title to a Government security under section 12;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>h</number>  the form of 
bond under sub-section (1) of section 15;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>i</number>  the 
procedure for making vesting order referred to in sub-section (1) of section 17;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>j</number>  the 
circumstances and the manner in which and the conditions subject to which 
inspection of Government securities, books, registers and other documents may be 
allowed or information therefrom may be given under section 24;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>k</number>  the terms and 
conditions subject to which pledge or hypothecation or lien be created under 
sub-section (1) of section 28.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Every regulation made 
by the Bank under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, 
before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of 
thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive 
sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the 
session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the regulation or both Houses agree that the regulation should 
not be made, the regulation shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such 
modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that regulation.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>33</number> Construction of 
references to laws not in force in Jammu and Kashmir.Any 
reference in this Act to a law which is not in force in the State of Jammu and 
Kashmir shall, wherever, necessary, be constructed as including a reference to 
the corresponding law, if any, in force in that State.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>34</number> Power to remove 
difficulties.
<section><number>1</number> 
If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the 
Central Government may, by order, not inconsistent with the provisions of this 
Act, remove the difficulty:
 
Provided that no such 
order shall be made after the expiry of a period of two years from the 
commencement of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every order made under 
this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each 
House of Parliament.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>35</number> Repeal and saving.The 
Indian Securities Act, 1920 (10 of 1920) is hereby repealed.
 <section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding such 
repeal anything done or any action taken in the exercise of any power conferred 
by or under the Act shall be deemed to have been done or taken in the exercise 
of the powers conferred by or under this Act as if this Act was in force on the 
day on which such thing was done or action was taken.
 
  
</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>