<act><tid>503019</tid>
<title>THE PREVENTION OF TERRORISM (AMENDMENT) ACT <year>2003</year></title>

NO. 4 of <year>2004</year>
[ 2nd January, <year>2004</year>.]

An Act to amend the Prevention of Terrorism Act, <year>2002</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- fourth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>845957</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>753432</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Prevention of Terrorism (Amendment) Act, <year>2003</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1381552</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 27th day of 
October, <year>2003</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>211833</tid>
<number> 2</number> Amendment of section 60.- In section 60 of the Prevention of 
Terrorism Act, <year>2003</year> (15 of <year>2002</year>), after sub- section (3), the following 
sub- sections shall be inserted, namely:-
" (4) Without prejudice to the other provisions of this Act, any Review 
Committee constituted under sub- section (1) shall, on an application by 
any aggrieved person, review whether there is a prima facie for 
proceeding against the accused under this Act and issue directions 
accordingly.

<section><tid>1487681</tid>
<number>5</number>Any direction issued under sub- section (4),-

<subsection><tid>448102</tid>
<number>i</number>by the Review Committee constituted by the Central Government, 
shall be binding on the Central Government, the State Government and 
the police officer investigating the offence; and 
 (ii) by the Review Committee constituted by the State Government, shall 
be binding on the State Government and the police officer investigating 
the offence.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1868339</tid>
<number>6</number>Where the reviews under sub- section (4) relating to the same 
offence under this Act, have been made by a Review Committee 
constituted by the Central Government and a Review Committee 
constituted by the State Government, under sub- section (1), any 
direction issued by the Review Committee constituted by the Central 
Government shall prevail.

</section>

<section><tid>523328</tid>
<number>7</number>Where any Review Committee constituted under sub- section (1) is of 
opinion that there is no prima facie case for proceeding against the 
accused and issues directions under sub- section (4), then, the 
proceedings pending against the accused shall be deemed to have been 
withdrawn from the date of such direction.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1195006</tid>
<number> 3</number> Repeal and saving.-
<section><tid>1259564</tid>
<number>1</number>The Prevention of Terrorism (Amendment)  
Ordinance, <year>2003</year> (Ord. 4 of <year>2003</year>), is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1490179</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken 
under the Prevention of Terrorism Act, <year>2002</year> (15 of <year>2002</year>), as amended by 
the said Ordinance, shall be deemed to have been done or taken under 
the said Act, as amended by this Act.
T. K. VISWANATHAN,

Secy. to the Govt. of India.





</section>

</article>



 </act>