<act><tid>257409</tid>
<title>THE INDIAN COMPANIES (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>1930</year></title>

ACT NO. 19 OF <year>1930</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 4th April, <year>1930</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Indian Companies' Act, <year>1913</year>, for 
certain purposes.

WHEREAS it is expedient further to amend the Indian Companies 
Act, <year>1913</year>, (7 of <year>1913</year>). for the purposes hereinafter appearing; It is 
hereby enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>519170</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1689760</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Indian Companies (Amendment) Act, <year>1930</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>493585</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date 2 as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>622145</tid>
<number>2</number>[ Amendment of s. 144, Act 7 of <year>1913</year>.] Rep. by the Repealing 
Act, <year>1938</year> (1 of <year>1938</year>), s. 2 and Sch.


</article>



<article><tid>860740</tid>
<number> 3</number> Certificates granted before the commencement of this Act.
<section><tid>1753421</tid>
<number>1</number> 
All certificates granted by State Governments before the commencement 
of this Act entitling the holders, and all declarations made before 
the commencement of this Act by the Central Government entitling the 
members of any specified institution or association, to be appointed 
and to act as auditors of companies throughout <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the territories 
which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in 
Part A States and Part C States] shall be deemed to be cancelled on 
the expiry of one year from the commencement of this Act:
Provided that the Central Government may direct that any such 
certificate or declaration shall remain in force for a further period 
not exceeding one year:

Provided further that any person who-


<subsection><tid>1967870</tid>
<number>a</number>was entitled immediately before the commencement of 
this Act by reason of any such certificate or declaration to 
be appointed and to act as an auditor of companies throughout 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the said territories], and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been extended to Berar by the Berar Laws Act, 
<year>1941</year> (4 of <year>1941</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>This Act came into force on the 1st April, <year>1932</year>; see Gazette 
of India, <year>1932</year>, Pt. I, p. 299.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No, 3) Order, <year>1956</year> for" Part A 
States and Part C States".






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>736728</tid>
<number>b</number>has at any time, after he became so entitled and before 
the commencement of this Act, resided in India,
shall, if he possesses such qualifications as to good character and on 
payment of such fee as may be prescribed under clause (b) of sub- 
section (2A) of section 144 of the Indian Companies Act, <year>1913</year> (7 of  
  <year>1913</year>), be entitled to be enrolled on the Register of Accountants 
referred to in that sub- section.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1620719</tid>
<number>2</number>Persons holding restricted certificates granted by State 
Governments before the commencement of this Act entitling them to act 
as auditors within a State may continue so to act, on such conditions 
as may be prescribed by the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> appropriate Government] in rules made 
by notification in the Official Gazette and after previous 
publication.
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> In this section" the appropriate Government" means, in relation 
to companies falling within <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> entries 43 and 44] of List I in the 
Seventh Schedule to the <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Constitution], the Central Government, and 
in relation to other companies, the State Government.]


<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" G. G. in C.".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins., ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year> for" Item 33".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs., ibid. for" Govt. of India Act, <year>1935</year>".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>