<act><tid>157988</tid>
<title>THE COMPTROLLER AND AUDITOR- GENERAL' S (DUTIES, POWERS AND  
  CONDITIONSOF SERVICE) ACT, <year>1971</year></title>

ACT NO. 56 OF <year>1971</year>
[ 15th December, <year>1971</year>.]

An Act to determine the conditions of service of the Comptroller 
and Auditor- General of India and to prescribe his duties and powers 
and for matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- second Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>114538</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Comptroller and 
Auditor- General' s (Duties, Powers and Conditions of Service) Act, 
<year>1971</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>350390</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>772492</tid>
<number>a</number>accounts", in relation to, commercial undertakings 
of a Government, includes trading, manufacturing and 
profit and loss accounts and balance- sheets and other 
subsidiary accounts;

</section>

<section><tid>1584719</tid>
<number>b</number>" appropriation accounts" means accounts which relate 
the expenditure brought to account during a financial 
year, to the several items specified in the law made in 
accordance with the provisions of the Constitution or of 
the Government of Union Territories Act, <year>1963</year>, (20 of  
  <year>1963</year>.) for the appropriation of moneys out of the 
Consolidated Fund of India or of State, or of a Union 
territory having a Legislative Assembly, as the case may 
be;

</section>

<section><tid>746313</tid>
<number>c</number>" Comptroller and Auditor- General" means the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General of India appointed under 
article 148 of the Constitution;

</section>

<section><tid>1605568</tid>
<number>d</number>" State" means a State specified in the First 
Schedule to' the Constitution:

</section>

<section><tid>354685</tid>
<number>e</number>" Union" includes a Union territory, whether having 
a Legislative Assembly or not.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>72</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

CHAP

SALARY AND OTHER CONDITIONS OF SERVICE OF THE COMPTROLLER AND AUDITOR- GENERAL

CHAPTER II

SALARY AND OTHER CONDITIONS OF SERVICE OF THE COMPTROLLER AND 
AUDITOR- GENERAL




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>740177</tid>
<number> 3</number> Salary. There shall be paid to the Comptroller and Auditor- 
General a salary which is equal to the salary of the Judge of the 
Supreme Court:
Provided that if a person who immediately before the date of 
assuming office as the Comptroller and Auditor- General, was in receipt 
of, or, being eligible so to do, had elected to draw, a pension (other  
  than a disability or wound pension) in respect of any previous service 
under the Government of the Union or any of its predecessor 
Governments, or under the Government of a State or any of its 
predecessor Governments, his salary in respect of service as Comp- 
troller and Auditor- General shall be reduced-

<section><tid>94354</tid>
<number>a</number>by the amount of that pension; and

</section>

<section><tid>1700696</tid>
<number>b</number>if he had, before assuming office, received, in 
lieu of a portion of the pension due to him in respect 
of such previous service, the commuted value thereof, by 
the amount of that portion of the pension; <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>665147</tid>
<number>4</number>Term of office. The Comptroller and Auditor- General shall hold 
office for a term of six years from the date on which he assumes such 
office: Provided that where he attains the age of sixty- five years 
before the expiry of the said term of six years, he shall vacate such 
office on the date on which he attains the said age:
Provided further that he may, at any time, by writing under his 
hand addressed to the President, resign his office.

Explanation.- For the purpose of this section, the term of six 
years in respect of the Comptroller and Auditor- General holding office 
immediately before the commencement of this Act, shall be computed 
from the date on which he had assumed office.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>73</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Omitted by Act 51 of <year>1994</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 27. 3. <year>1990</year>)



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>1483708</tid>
<number> 5</number> Leave.
<section><tid>1064335</tid>
<number>1</number>A person who, immediately before the date of assuming  
office as the Comptroller and Auditor- General, was in the service of 
Government may be granted during his tenure of office but not 
thereafter, leave in accordance with the rules for the time being 
applicable to the Service to which he belonged before such date and he 
shall be entitled to carry forward the amount of leave standing at his 
credit on such date, notwithstanding anything contained in section 6.

</section>

<section><tid>1333932</tid>
<number>2</number>Any other person who is appointed as the Comptroller and 
Auditor- General may be granted leave in accordance with such rules as 
are for the time being applicable to a member of the Indian 
Administrative Service.

</section>

<section><tid>1943982</tid>
<number>3</number>The power to grant or refuse leave to the Comptroller and 
Auditor- General and to revoke or curtail leave granted to him, shall 
vest in the President.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>878422</tid>
<number> 6</number> Pension.
<section><tid>1197250</tid>
<number>1</number>A person who, immediately before the date of  
assuming office as the Comptroller and Auditor- General, was in the 
service of Government shall be deemed to have retired from service on 
the date on which he enters upon office as the Comptroller and Auditor 
General but his service as the Comptroller and Auditor- General shall 
be reckoned as continuing approved service counting for pension in the 
Service to which he belonged.

</section>

<section><tid>1099885</tid>
<number>2</number>Every person who enters upon office as the Comptroller and 
Auditor- General shall, on demitting the said office, be eligible to a 
pension of a sum of fifteen thousand rupees per annum which sum shall 
include the aggregate of all pensions payable to him and the commuted 
portion, if any, of his pension, and the pension equivalent of the 
retirement gratuity, if any, which may have been admissible to him 
under the rules for the time being applicable to the Service to which 
he belonged:
Provided that if such a person is or becomes eligible, at any 
time, under the rules for the time being governing the Service to 
which he belonged, to a pension higher than the said sum of fifteen 
thousand rupees, he shall be eligible to draw, as pension, the said 
higher amount.


</section>

<section><tid>1919760</tid>
<number>3</number>A person who, immediately before the date of assuming office 
as the Comptroller and Auditor- General, was in receipt of, or, had

<pagefootnote><pagenum>74</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

become eligible for receiving, a pension in respect of any previous 
service under Government, shall, on demitting office as the Comp- 
troller and Auditor- General, be eligible to, a pension of fifteen 
thousand rupees per annum which sum shall include the aggregate of all 
pensions payable to him and the commuted portion, if any, of his 
pension, and the pension equivalent of the retirement gratuity, if 
any, which may have been admissible to him under the rules for the 
time being applicable to the Service to which he belonged:

Provided that if such a person is or becomes eligible, at any 
time, under the rules for the time being governing the Service to 
which he belonged, to a pension higher than the said sum of fifteen 
thousand rupees, he shall be eligible to draw, as pension, the said 
higher amount.


</section>

<section><tid>91982</tid>
<number>4</number>Any other person who is appointed as the Comptroller, and 
Auditor- General shall, on demitting the said office, be eligible to a 
pension of fifteen thousand rupees per annum.

</section>

<section><tid>359684</tid>
<number>5</number>The person holding office immediately before the 
commencement of this Act as the Comptroller and Auditor- General shall 
be eligible to draw, at his option, pension at the rate at which it 
would be admissible to, him if this Act had not come into force or at 
the rate specified in this section.

</section>

<section><tid>295982</tid>
<number>6</number>A person who demits office as the Comptroller and Auditor- 
General by resignation shall, on such demission, be eligible to a pen- 
sion at the rate of two thousand rupees per annum for each completed 
year of his service as the Comptroller and Auditor- General:
Provided that in the case of a person referred to in sub- 
section (1) or sub- section (3), the aggregate amount of pension 
admissible under this sub- section together with the amount of pension 
including the commuted portion, if any, of his pension, and the 
pension equivalent of the retirement gratuity, if any, which may have 
been admissible to him under the rules for the time being applicable 
to the Service to which he belonged immediately before he assumed 
office as the Comptroller and Auditor- General, shall not exceed 
fifteen thousand rupees per annum or the higher pension referred to in 
proviso to sub- section (2) or sub- section (3), as the case may be.


</section>

<section><tid>1317492</tid>
<number>6A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing provisions 
of this section, a person referred to in subsection (1) who demits 
office[ whether in any manner specified in sub- section (8) or by 
resignation] as the Comptroller and Auditor- General after the 
commencement of the Comptroller and Auditor- General' s (Duties, Powers  
  and Conditions of Service) Amendment Act, <year>1984</year> shall, on such 
demission, be entitled to-

<subsection><tid>62673</tid>
<number>a</number>the pension to Which he would have been entitled under the 
rules of the Service to which he belonged by reckoning his 
service as the Comptroller and Auditor- General as continuing 
approved service counting for pension in such Service; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>773642</tid>
<number>b</number>a special pension of seven hundred rupees per. annum in 
respect of each completed year of service as the Comptroller 
and Auditor- General.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1522077</tid>
<number>6B</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing pro- 
visions of this section, a person referred to in sub- section (3) who 
demits office[ whether in any manner specified in sub- section (8) or 
by resignation] as the Comptroller and Auditor- General after the 
commencement of the Comptroller and Auditor- General' s (Duties, Powers  
  and Conditions of Service) Amendment Act, <year>1984</year>, shall, on such 
demission, be entitled to-

<subsection><tid>469379</tid>
<number>a</number>the pension payable to him in respect of any 
previous service under Government; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>979143</tid>
<number>b</number>a special pension of seven hundred rupees per annum 
in respect of each completed year of service as the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>74a</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 2 of <year>1984</year>, S. 2.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Omitted by Act 50 of <year>1987</year>, S. 2 (w. e. f. 1. 1. <year>1986</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by Act So of <year>1987</year>, S. 2.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>722734</tid>
<number>6C</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing 
provisions of this section, a person who demits office[ whether in any 
manner specified in sub- section (8) or by resignation] as the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General after the commencement of the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General' s (Duties, Powers and Conditions of  
  Service) Amendment Act, <year>1987</year>, shall, on such demission, be entitled 
to-

<subsection><tid>1057767</tid>
<number>a</number>a pension which is equal to the pension payable to a 
Judge of the Supreme Court,-

<subsubsection><tid>928753</tid>
<number>i</number>if such person is a person referred to in sub- 
section (1) or sub- section (3), in accordance with 
the provisions of Part III of the Schedule to the 
Supreme Court Judges (Conditions of Service) Act, <year>1958</year> 
 (hereafter in this Act referred to as the Supreme Court  
  Judges Act), as amended from time to time and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>105424</tid>
<number>ii</number>if such person is a person referred to in subsection 
 (4), in accordance, with the provisions of Part I of the 
Schedule to the Supreme Court Judges Act, as amended 
from time to time;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1353724</tid>
<number>b</number>such pension (including commutation of pension), family 
pension and gratuity as are admissible to a Judge of 
Supreme Court under the Supreme Court Judges Act and the 
rules made thereunder, as amended from time to time

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1631907</tid>
<number>6D</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Notwithstanding anything contend in the forgoing provisions 
of this section, a person who demitted office[ whether in any manner 
specified in sub- section 8 of by regisnation] as the comptroller and 
Audit- General, at any time before the 16th day, <year>1987</year>, shall be 
entitled to the pension specified in sub- section 6c on and from the 
date.]

</section>

<section><tid>1885990</tid>
<number>7</number>If a person who demits office as the Comptroller and 
Auditor- Genral is not eligible to any pension under this section but 
is eligible to a pesnion under the rules for the time being applicable 
to the service to which he belonged immediately before be assumed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>75</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Office as the Comptroller and Auditor- General, he shall, 
notwithstanding anything contained in this section, be eligible to 
draw such pension as is admissible to him under the said rules.


</section>

<section><tid>1996459</tid>
<number>8</number>Except where he demits office by resignation, a person 
holding office of the Comptroller and Auditor- General shall be deemed, 
for the purposes of this Act, to have demitted such office as such if, 
and only if,-

<subsection><tid>1556284</tid>
<number>a</number>he has completed the term of office specified in 
section 4, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>645805</tid>
<number>b</number>he has attained the age of sixty- five years, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>456586</tid>
<number>c</number>his demission of office is medically certified to be 
necessitated by ill health.
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>111594</tid>
<number>8</number>Right to subscribe to General Provident Fund. Every person 
holding office as the Comptroller and Auditor General shall be 
entitled to subscribe to the General Provident Fund (Central  
  Services).


</article>



<article><tid>505682</tid>
<number>9</number>Other conditions of service. <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Save as otherwise provided in 
this Act, the conditions of service relating to travelling allowance, 
provision of rent- free residence and exemption from payment of income- 
tax on the value of such rent- free residence, conveyance facilities, 
sumptuary allowance, medical facilities and such other conditions of 
service as are for the time being applicable to a Judge of the 
Supreme Court under Chapter IV of the Supreme Court Judges Act, and 
the rules made thereunder, shall, so far as may be, apply to serving 
or retired Comptroller and Auditor- General as the case may be.]
Provided that nothing in this section shall have effect so as to 
give a person, who immediately before the date of assuming office as 
the comptroller and Auditor- General, was in the service of Government, 
less favourable terms in respect of any of the matters aforesaid than 
those to which he would be entitled as a member of the Service to 
which he belonged, his service as Comptroller and Auditor- General 
being treated for the purpose of this proviso as continuing service in 
the Service to which he belonged.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>76</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Omitted by Act 50 of <year>1987</year>, S. 3.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by S. 4 ibid.





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

CHAP

DUTIES AND POWERS OF THE COMPTROLLER AND AUDITOR- GENERAL

CHAPTER III

DUTIES AND POWERS OF THE COMPTROLLER AND AUDITOR- GENERAL



</article>



<article><tid>1880612</tid>
<number> 10</number> Comptroller and Auditor- General to compile accounts of Union 
and States.
<section><tid>95592</tid>
<number>1</number>The Comptroller and Auditor- General shall be  
responsible-

<subsection><tid>1682162</tid>
<number>a</number>for compiling the accounts of the Union and of 
each State from the initial and subsidiary accounts 
rendered to the audit and accounts offices under his 
control by treasuries, offices or departments 
responsible for the keeping of such accounts; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>704158</tid>
<number>b</number>for keeping such accounts in relation to any of the 
matters specified in clause (a) as may be necessary:
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided that the President may, after consultation with the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General, by order, relieve him from the res- 
ponsibility for compiling-


<subsubsection><tid>925748</tid>
<number>i</number>the said accounts of the Union (either at once or  
  gradually by the issue of several orders); or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>772041</tid>
<number>ii</number>the accounts of any particular services or 
departments of the
Provided further that the Governor of a State may, with the 
previous approval of the President and after consultation with the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General, by order, relieve him from the 
responsibility for compiling-


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>925748</tid>
<number>i</number>the said accounts of the State (either at once or  
  gradually by the issue of several orders); or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>772041</tid>
<number>ii</number>the accounts of any particular services or 
departments of the State:]
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Provided also] that the President may, after consultation with 
the Comptroller and Auditor- General, by order, relieve him from the 
responsibility for keeping the accounts of any particular class or 
character.


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>435466</tid>
<number>2</number>Where, under any arrangement a person other than the Comp- 
troller and Auditor- General has, before the commencement of this Act, 
been responsible-

<subsection><tid>94198</tid>
<number>i</number>for compiling the accounts of any particular service or 
department of the Union or of a State, or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>77</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 58 of <year>1976</year>, s. 2, for the first proviso (w. e. f. 1- 3-  
  <year>1976</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by s. 2, ibid., for" Provided further" (w. e. f. 1- 3- <year>1976</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>848634</tid>
<number>ii</number>for keeping the accounts of any particular class or 
character, such arrangement shall, notwithstanding anything contained 
in subsection (1), continue to be in force unless, after consultation 
with the Comptroller and Auditor- General, it is revoked in the case 
referred to in clause (i), by an order of the President or the 
Governor of the State, as the case may be, and in the case referred 
to in clause (ii), by an order of the President.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1813364</tid>
<number>11</number>Comptroller and Auditor- General to prepare and submit accounts 
to the President, Governors of States and Administrators of Union 
territories having Legislative Assemblies. The Comptroller and 
Auditor- General shall, from the accounts complied by him or (by the  
  Government or any other person responsible In that behalf)], prepare in 
each year accounts (including, in the case of accounts compiled by  
  him, appropriation accounts) showing under the respective heads the 
annual receipts and disbursements for the purpose of the Union, of 
each State and of each Union territory having a Legislative Assembly, 
and shall submit those accounts to the President or the Governor of a 
State or Administrator of the Union territory having a Legislative 
Assembly, as the case may be, on or before such dates as he may, with 
the concurrence of the Government concerned, determine:
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Provided that the President may, after consultation with the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General, by order, relieve him from the 
responsibility for the preparation and submission of the accounts 
relating to annual receipts and disbursements for the purpose of the 
Union or of a Union territory having a Legislative Assembly:

Provided further that the Governor of a State may, with the 
previous approval of the President and after consultation with the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General, by order, relieve him from the 
responsibility for the preparation and submission of the accounts 
relating to annual receipts and disbursements for the purpose of the 
State.]



</article>



<article><tid>1604274</tid>
<number>12</number>Comptroller and Auditor General to give information and render 
assistance to the Union and States. The Comptroller and Auditor- 
General shall, in so far as the accounts, for the compilation or 
keeping of which he is responsible, enable him so to do, give to the 
Union Government, to the State Governments or to the Governments of 
Union territories having Legislative Assemblies, as the case may be, 
such information as they may, from time to time, require,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>78</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 58 of <year>1976</year>, s. 3, for certain words (w. e. f. 1- 3- <year>1976</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by s. 3, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 3- <year>1976</year>).






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

and render such assistance in the preparation of their annual 
financial statements as they may reasonably ask for.



</article>



<article><tid>1354764</tid>
<number> 13</number> General provisions relating to audit. It shall be the duty of 
the Comptroller and Auditor- General-
<section><tid>155533</tid>
<number>a</number>to audit all expenditure from the Consolidated Fund 
of India and of each State and of each Union territory 
having a Legislative Assembly and to ascertain whether 
the moneys shown in the accounts as having been 
disbursed were legally available for and applicable to 
the service or purpose to which they have been applied 
or charged and whether the expenditure conforms to the 
authority which governs it;

</section>

<section><tid>901306</tid>
<number>b</number>to audit all transactions of the Union and of the 
States relating to Contingency Funds and Public Accounts

</section>

<section><tid>1161605</tid>
<number>c</number>to audit all trading, manufacturing, profit and loss 
accounts and balance- sheets and other subsidiary 
accounts kept in any department of the Union or of a 
State;
and in each case to report on the expenditure, transactions or 
accounts so audited by him.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1614495</tid>
<number> 14</number> Audit of receipts and expenditure of bodies or authorities 
substantially financed from Union of State Revenues. <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1123989</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any  
body or authority is substantially financed by grants or loans from 
the Consolidated Fund of India or of any State or of Union territory 
having a Legislative Assembly, the Comptroller Auditor- General shall, 
subject to the provisions of any law for being in force applicable to 
the body or authority, as the case audit all receipts and 
expenditure of that body or authority and to him port on the receipts 
and expenditure audited by him.

</section>

<section><tid>347614</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General may, with the previous approval of the 
President or the Governor of a State or the Administrator of a Union 
territory having a Legislative Assembly, as the case may be, audit all 
receipts and expenditure of any body or authority where the grant or 
loan to such body or authority from the Consolidated Fund of India or 
of any State, or of any Union territory having a Legislative Assembly, 
as the case may be, in a financial year is not less than rupees one 
crore.

</section>

<section><tid>1958729</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the receipts and expenditure of any body or authority 
are, by virtue of the fulfillment of the conditions specified in sub- 
section (1) or sub- section (2), audited by the Comptroller and 
Auditor- General in a financial year, he shall continue to audit the 
receipts and expenditure of that body or authority for a further 
period of two years notwithstanding that the conditions specified in 
sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) are not fulfilled during any of the 
two subsequent years.
Explanation.- Where the grant or loan to a body or authority from the 
Consolidated Fund of India or of any State or of any Union territory 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> having a Legislative Assembly in a financial year is not less than 
[ rupees twenty five lakhs] and the amount of such grant or loan is not 
less than seventy five per cent of the total expenditure of that body 
or authority, such body or authority shall be deemed, for the purposes 
of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> this sub- section] to be substantially financed by such grants or 
loans as the case may be.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1490551</tid>
<number> 15</number> Functions of Comptroller and Auditor- General in the case of 
grants or loans given to other authorities or bodies.
<section><tid>946460</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any  
grant or loan is given for any specific purpose from the Consolidated 
Fund of India or of any State or of any Union territory having a 
Legislative Assembly to any authority or body, not being a foreign 
State or international Organisation, the Comptroller and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>78A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Remembered, subs. and ins. by Act 2 of <year>1984</year>, s. 3.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

Auditor- General shall scrutinise the procedures by which the 
sanctioning authority satisfies itself as to the fulfilment of the 
conditions subject to which such grants or loans were given and shall 
for this purpose have right of access, after giving reasonable 
previous notice, to the books and accounts of that authority or body:

Provided that the President, the Governor of a State or the 
Administrator of a Union territory having a Legislative Assembly, as 
the case may be, may, where he is of opinion that it is necessary so 
to do in the public interest, by order, relieve the Comptroller and 
Auditor- General, after consultation with him, from making any such 
scrutiny in respect of any body or authority receiving such grant or 
loan.


</section>

<section><tid>1801392</tid>
<number>2</number>Except where he is authorised so to do by the President, the 
Governor of a State or the Administrator of a Union territory having 
legislative Assembly, as the case may be, the Comptroller and Auditor 
General shall not have, while exercising the powers conferred on him 
by sub- section (1), right of access to the books and accounts of an 
corporation to which any such grant or loan as is referred to

<pagefootnote><pagenum>79</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

in sub- section (1) is given if the law by or under which such corpora- 
tion has been established provides for the audit of the accounts of 
such corporation by an agency other than the Comptroller and Auditor- 
General:

Provided that no such authorisation shall be made except after 
consultation with Comptroller and Auditor- General and except after 
giving the concerned corporation a reasonable opportunity of making 
representations with regard to the proposal to give to the Comptroller 
and Auditor- General right of access to its books and accounts.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1289483</tid>
<number>16</number>Audit of receipts of Union or of States. It shall be the duty 
of the Comptroller and Auditor- General to audit all receipts which are 
payable into the Consolidated Fund of India and of each State and of 
each Union territory having a Legislative Assembly and to satisfy 
himself that the rules and procedures in that behalf are designed to 
secure an effective check on the assessment, collection and proper 
allocation of revenue and are being duly observed and to make for this 
purpose such examination of the accounts as he thinks fit and report 
thereon.


</article>



<article><tid>1250105</tid>
<number>17</number>Audit of accounts of stores and stock. The Comptroller and 
Auditor- General shall have authority to audit and report on the 
accounts of stores and stock kept in any office or department of the 
Union or of a State.


</article>



<article><tid>763984</tid>
<number> 18</number> Powers of Comptroller and Auditor- General in connection with 
audit of accounts.
<section><tid>1565449</tid>
<number>1</number>The Comptroller and Auditor- General shall in  
connection with the performance of his duties under this Act, have 
authority-

<subsection><tid>1825368</tid>
<number>a</number>to inspect any office of accounts under the 
control of the Union or of a State, including treasuries 
and such offices responsible for the keeping of initial 
or subsidiary accounts, as submit accounts to him;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>273544</tid>
<number>b</number>to require that, any accounts, books, papers and 
other documents which deal with or from the basis of or 
are otherwise relevant to the transactions to which his 
duties in respect of audit extend, shall be sent to such 
place as he may appoint for his inspection;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1106167</tid>
<number>c</number>to put such questions or make such observations as 
he may consider necessary, to the person in charge of 
the office and to call for such information as he may 
require for

<pagefootnote><pagenum>80</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

the preparation of any account or report which it is his 
duty to prepare.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>367433</tid>
<number>2</number>The person in charge of any office or department, the 
accounts of which have to be inspected and audited by the Comptroller 
and Auditor- General, shall afford all facilities for such inspection 
and, comply with requests for information in as complete a form as 
possible and with all reasonable expedition.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>254457</tid>
<number> 19</number> Audit of Government companies and corporations.
<section><tid>1936294</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
duties and powers of the Comptroller and Auditor General in relation 
to the audit of the accounts of Government companies shall be 
performed and exercised by him in accordance with the provisions of 
the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>1332359</tid>
<number>2</number>The duties and powers of the Comptroller and Auditor- General 
in relation to the audit of the accounts of corporations (not being  
  companies) established by or under law made by Parliament shall be 
performed and exercised by him in accordance with the provisions of 
the respective legislations.

</section>

<section><tid>719285</tid>
<number>3</number>The Governor of a State or the Administrator of a Union 
territory having a Legislative Assembly may, where he is of opinion 
that it is necessary in the public interest so to do, request the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General to audit the accounts of a corporation 
established by law made by the Legislature of the State or of the 
Union territory, as the case may be, and where such request has been 
made, the Comptroller and Auditor- General shall audit the accounts of 
such corporation and shall have, for the purposes of such audit, right 
of access to the books and accounts of such corporation:
Provided that no such request shall be made except after 
consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor- General and except after 
giving reasonable opportunity to the corporation to make representa- 
tions with regard to the proposal for such audit.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1052771</tid>
<number> 19A</number> Laying of reports in relation to accounts of Government 
companies and corporations. <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<section><tid>179225</tid>
<number>1</number>The reports of the Comptroller and  
Auditor- General, in relation to the accounts of a Government company 
or a corporation referred to in section 19, shall be submitted to the 
Government or Governments concerned.

</section>

<section><tid>1024992</tid>
<number>2</number>The, Central Government shall cause every report received by 
it under sub- section (1) to be laid, as soon as may be after it is 
received, before each House of Parliament.

</section>

<section><tid>1115482</tid>
<number>3</number>The State Government shall cause every report received by it 
under, sub-, section (1) to be laid as soon as may be after it is 
received, before the Legislature of the State.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section," Government" or 
" State Government", in relation to a Union territory having a Legis- 
lative Assembly, means the Administrator of the Union territory.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1287061</tid>
<number> 20</number> Audit of accounts of certain authorities or bodies.
<section><tid>1204669</tid>
<number>1</number>Save  
as otherwise provided in section 19, where the audit of the accounts 
of any body or authority has not been entrusted to the Comptroller and 
Auditor- General by or under any law made by Parliament, he shall, if 
requested so to do by the President or the Governor of a State or the 
Administrator of a Union territory having a Legislative Assembly, as 
the case may be, undertake the audit of the accounts of such body or 
authority on such terms and conditions

<pagefootnote><pagenum>81</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 2 of <year>1984</year>, s. 4.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

as may be agreed upon between him and the concerned Government and 
shall have, for the purposes of such audit, right of access to the 
books and accounts of that body or authority:

Provided that no such request shall be made except after 
consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor- General.


</section>

<section><tid>1037323</tid>
<number>2</number>The Comptroller and Auditor- General may propose to the 
President or the Governor of a State or the Administrator of a Union 
territory having a Legislative Assembly, as the case may be, that he 
may be authorised to undertake the audit of the accounts of any body 
or authority, the audit of the accounts of which has not been 
entrusted to him by law, if he is of opinion that such audit is 
necessary because a substantial amount has been invested in, or 
advanced to, such body or authority by the Central or State Government 
or by the Government of a Union territory having a Legislative 
Assembly, and on such request being made, the President or the 
Governor or the Administrator, as the case may be, may empower the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General to undertake the audit of the accounts 
of such body or authority.

</section>

<section><tid>622581</tid>
<number>3</number>The audit referred to in sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) 
shall not be entrusted to the Comptroller and Auditor- General except 
where the President or the Governor of a State or the Administrator of 
a Union territory having a Legislative Assembly, as the case may be, 
is satisfied that it is expedient so to do in the public interest and 
except after giving a reasonable opportunity to the concerned body or 
authority to make representations with regard to the proposal for such 
audit.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER IV

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1317204</tid>
<number>21</number>Delegation of power of Comptroller and auditor- General. Any 
power exercisable by the Comptroller and Auditor- General under the 
provisions of this Act, or any other law may be exercised by such 
officer of his department as may be authorised by him in this behalf 
by general or special order:
Provided that except during the absence of the Comptroller and 
Auditor- General on leave or otherwise, no officer shall be authorised 
to submit on behalf of the Comptroller and Auditor- General any report 
which the Comptroller and Auditor- General is required by the Constitu- 
tion or the Government of Union Territories Act, <year>1963</year> (20 of <year>1963</year>) to 
Submit to the


<pagefootnote><pagenum>82</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

President or the Governor of a State or the Administrator of a Union 
territory having a Legislative Assembly, as the case may be.



</article>



<article><tid>224033</tid>
<number> 22</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>241167</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, after  
consultation with the, Comptroller and Auditor- General, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the 
provisions of this Act in so far as they relate to the maintenance of 
accounts.

</section>

<section><tid>647102</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1306266</tid>
<number>a</number>the manner in which initial and subsidiary 
accounts shall be kept by the treasuries, offices and 
departments rendering accounts to audit and accounts 
offices;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>237308</tid>
<number>b</number>the manner in which the accounts of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union or 
of a State or of] any particular service or department 
or of any particular class or character, in respect of 
which the Comptroller and Auditor- General has been 
relieved from the responsibility of compiling or keeping 
the accounts, shall be compiled or kept;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>671287</tid>
<number>c</number>the manner in which the accounts of stores and 
stock shall be kept in any office or department of the 
Union or of a State, as the case may be;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1075937</tid>
<number>d</number>any other matter which is required to be, or may 
be, prescribed by rules.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1696356</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as 
may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is 
in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised 
in one session or <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> in two or more successive sessions], and if, 
before the expiry of <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the session immediately following the session 
or the successive sessions aforesaid] both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rules shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>940191</tid>
<number>23</number>Power to make regulations. The Comptroller and Auditor- General is 
here by authorised to make rugulations for carrying into effect the 
provisions of this Act in
<pagefootnote><pagenum>83</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 58 of <year>1976</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 1- 3- <year>1976</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by s. 4, ibid., for certain words (w. e. f. 1- 3- <year>1976</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


so far as they relate to the scope and extent of audit, including 
laying down for the guidance of the Government Departments the general 
principles of Government accounting and the broad principles in 
regard to audit of receipts and expenditure.



</article>



<article><tid>464400</tid>
<number>24</number>Power to dispense with detailed audit. The Comptroller and 
Auditor- General is hereby authorised to dispense with, when 
circumstances so warrant, any part of detailed audit of any accounts 
or class of transactions and to apply such limited check in relation 
to such accounts or transactions as he may determine.


</article>



<article><tid>1205872</tid>
<number>25</number>Repeal. The Comptroller and Auditor- General (Conditions of  
  Service 21 of <year>1953</year>.) Act, <year>1953</year>, is hereby repealed.


</article>



<article><tid>26000</tid>
<number>26</number>Removal of doubts. For the removal of doubts, it is hereby 
declared that on the commencement of this Act the Government of India 
 (Audit and Accounts) Order, <year>1936</year>, as adapted by the India (Provisional  
  Constitution) Order, <year>1947</year>, shall cease to be in force except as 
respects anything done or any action taken thereunder.

</article>



 </act>