<act><tid>475914</tid>
<title>THE AUTHORITATIVE TEXTS (CENTRAL LAWS) ACT, <year>1973</year></title>

ACT NO. 50 OF <year>1973</year>
[ 5th December, <year>1973</year>.]

An Act to provide for <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> authoritative texts] of Central laws in 
certain languages.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- fourth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--





<article><tid>1093687</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>359246</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Authoritative Texts] (Central Laws) Act, <year>1973</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>496920</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1719788</tid>
<number> 2</number> Authoritative texts of Central laws in certain languages. A 
translation in any language (other than Hindi) specified in the Eighth 
Schedule to the Constitution, published under the authority of the 
President in the Official Gazette,--
<section><tid>285105</tid>
<number>a</number>of any Central Act or of any Ordinance promulgated by 
the President, or

</section>

<section><tid>505023</tid>
<number>b</number>of any order, rule, regulation or bye- law issued under 
the Constitution or under any Central Act,
shall be deemed to be the <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> authoritative text] thereof in such 
language.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>104063</tid>
<number> 3</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1479735</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the 
purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>957592</tid>
<number>2</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as 
may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is 
in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised 
in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>999999</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1988</year>, s. 2. 
2. Subs. by s. 3, ibid. 
3.  1st July <year>1981</year>, vide Notification No. S. O. 482 (E), dt. 15th 
June, <year>1981</year>. 
4 Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1988</year>, s. 4.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>