<act><title>


The Consumer Protection Rules, 19871</title> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Consumer Protection Rules, 1987.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “Act” means the Consumer Protection 
    Act, 1986 (68 of 1986);
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “agent” means a person duly authorised 
    by a party to present any complaint, appeal or reply on its behalf before 
    the National Commission;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “appellant” means a party which makes 
    an appeal against the order of the State Commission;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    “chairman” means a chairman of the 
    Central Consumer Protection Council established under sub-section (1) of the 
    section 4 of the Act;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    “memorandum” means any memorandum of 
    appeal filed by the appellant;
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    “opposite party” means a person who 
    answers complaint or claim;
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    “president” means the President of the 
    National Commission;
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>    “respondent” means the person who 
    answers any memorandum of appeal;
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>    “section” means section of the Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>j</number>    “state” includes Union territories 
    also;  
 </section><section>
<number>k</number>    words and expressions used in the rules 
    and not defined but defined in the Act shall have the meanings respectively 
    assigned to them in the Act.
 
 
 
 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>2A</number> State Governments 
    to recognise a laboratory as an appropriate laboratory.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    For the purpose of obtaining recognition as an appropriate laboratory, the 
    applicant shall send application, in triplicate, in the proforma prescribed 
    by the Bureau of Indian Standards with the relevant details to the 
    Department concerned with the consumer protection work in the State 
    Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The State 
    Government on receiving the application from the applicant, shall forward 
    its two copies to the Bureau of Indian Standards to assess the suitability 
    of the laboratory from the standards prescribed by them (Bureau of Indian 
    Standards). The fee charged by the Bureau of Indian Standards, for this 
    purpose, shall be paid by the applicant.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The State 
    Government on receiving the recommendations and approval of the Bureau of 
    Indian Standards, shall notify that laboratory as an “appropriate 
    laboratory” for the purpose of Consumer Protection Act, 1986 for a period of 
    three years.]  
 
 






 



</section></article> 

 <title> </title>
 <article><title><number>3</number> The Constitution of the Central Consumer Protection Council and the Working Groups. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government shall, by notification<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in the Official Gazette constitute the Central Consumer Protection Council (hereinafter referred to as the Central Council) which shall consist of <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[the following members, not exceeding <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[35], namely:—] 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[the Minister in-charge of Consumer Affairs in the Central Government] who shall be the Chairman of the Central Council; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the Minister of State (where he is not holding independent charge) or Deputy Minister <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[in charge of Consumer Affairs in the Central Government] who shall be the Vice-Chairman of the Central Council; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>c</number> the Minister in-charge of Consumer Affairs of two of the States from each region as mentioned in Schedule I to be changed by rotation on expiration of the term of the Council on each occasion; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ca</number> an administrator (whether designated as administrator or Lieutenant Governor), of a Union Territory, to represent a Union Territory, as mentioned in Schedule II, to be changed by rotation on expiration of the term of the Council on each occasion;] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> 3 [two] Members of Parliament— <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[one] from the Lok Sabha and <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[one] from the Rajya Sabha; 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[***] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> representatives of the Central Government Departments and autonomous organisations concerned with consumer interests—not exceeding <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[five]; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>fa</number> The Registrar, National Consumer Disputes Redressal Commission, New Delhi ;] 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>g</number> representatives of consumer organisations from amongst the Indian members of the International Organisation, namely, Consumer International—not exceeding six, to be nominated by the Central Government; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ga</number> representatives with proven expertise and experience who are capable of representing consumer interests, drawn from amongst consumer organisations, consumer activists, women, farmers, trade and industry—not exceeding five, one from each of the regions specified in Schedule annexed to these rules;] 
 <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[***] 
 <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[***] 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>j</number> the Secretaries in-charge of Consumer Affairs in the States to be nominated by the Central Government—not exceeding three;] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number> the <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[Secretary in-charge of Consumer Affairs in the Central Government] shall be the member-secretary of the Central Council. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The term of the Council shall be three years: 
 <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[Provided that the Council shall continue to function for a further period of three months or till it is reconstituted, whichever is earlier.] 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Any member may, by writing under his hand to the Chairman of the Central Council, resign from the Council. The vacancies, so caused or otherwise, shall be filled from the same category by the Central Government and such person shall hold office so long as the member whose place he fills would have been entitled to hold office, if the vacancy had not occurred. 
 <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[***] <title> </title>


 
 <subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 533(E), dated 14-8-1991. G.S.R. 64(E), dated 10-2-2005. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 800(E), dated 30-12-1993. G.S.R. 67(E), dated 11-2-2005. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 522(E), dated 22-6-1994. G.S.R. 273(E), dated 5-5-2006. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 605(E), dated 30-8-1995. G.S.R. 462(E), dated 4-8-2006. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 759(E), dated 21-11-1995. G.S.R. 637(E), dated 13-10-2006. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 95(E), dated 27-2-1997. G.S.R. 380(E), dated 2-6-2009. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 88(E), dated 24-2-1998. G.S.R. 462(E), dated 4-8-2009. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 175(E), dated 5-3-2004. G.S.R. 591(E), dated 20-8-2009. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 50(E), dated 1-2-2005. G.S.R. 579(E), dated 5-7-2010. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 385(E), dated 12-5-2011. 
</subsection>









</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Procedure of the Central Council. </title>—Under 
sub-section (2) of Section 5, the Central Council shall observe the following 
procedure in regard to the transaction of its business:— 
 <section><number>1</number> The meeting of the Central Council shall be presided over by the 
Chairman. In the absence of the Chairman, the Vice-Chairman shall preside over 
the meeting of the Central Council. In the absence of the Chairman and the 
Vice-Chairman, the Central Council shall elect a member to preside over that 
meeting of the Council. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Each meeting of the Central Council shall be called by giving, not less 
than ten days from the date of issue, notice in writing to every member. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every notice of a meeting of the Central Council shall specify the place 
and the day and hour of the meeting and shall contain statement of business to 
be transacted thereat. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> No proceedings of the Central Council shall be invalid merely by reasons 
of existence of any vacancy in or any defect in the constitution of the Council. 

 </section><section><number>5</number> For the purpose of performing its functions under the Act, the Central 
Council may constitute from amongst its members, such working groups as it may 
deem necessary and every working group so constituted shall perform such 
functions as are assigned to it by the Central Council. The findings of such 
working groups shall be placed before the Central Council for its consideration. 

 </section><section><footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[<number>6</number> In connection with the journey undertaken to and fro by the 
non-official members for attending the meeting of the Central Consumer 
Protection Council or its working group, they shall be entitled to 
<footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[economy class air fare]. The non-official members shall be entitled 
to a sum of <footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[ <footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[Rupees two thousand] per each day of the 
meeting] as incidental charges to cover the expenditure towards their daily 
allowance, lodging, local conveyance from residence to the station/airport and 
from station/airport to the venue of meeting and vice-versa. Every claim made 
under this sub-rule shall be subject to certifying that the member will not 
claim any benefit from any other Central Government Ministry, Department or 
Organization during his visit for attending the meeting of the Central Consumer 
Protection Council or any of its Working Group. Local non-official members 
residing at the place of the venue of the meeting, shall be paid 
<footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[consolidated conveyance and hire charges], to the tune of 
<footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[Rupees five hundred] per diem irrespective of the classification of 
the city. Members of Parliament attending meetings of the Council or its Working 
Group shall be entitled to travelling and daily allowances at such rates as are 
admissible to such members.] 
 </section><section><number>7</number> The resolution passed by the Central Council shall be recommendatory in 
nature. 
















</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Place of 
    the National Commission.—The 
    office of the National Commission shall be located in the Union Territory of 
    Delhi.  
 
 
 
 


</article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Working 
    days and office hours of the National Commission.—The 
    working days and office hours of the National Commission shall be the same 
    as that of the Central Government.  
 
 
 
 


</article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Seal and 
    emblem.—The official seal and 
    emblem of the National Commission shall be such as the Central Government 
    may specify.  
 
 
 
 


</article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Sitting 
    of the National Commission.—The 
    sitting of the National Commission as and when necessary, shall be convened 
    by the President.  
 
 
 
 


</article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Staff of 
    the National Commission.—The 
    Central Government shall appoint such staff as may be necessary to assist 
    the National Commission in its day to day work and to perform such other 
    functions as are provided under the Act and these rules or assigned to it by 
    the President. The salary payable to such staff shall be defrayed out of the 
    Consolidated Fund of India.  
  
  
 
 
 
 


</article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>9A</number> Fee for making 
    complaints before District Forum.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every complaint filed under sub-section (1) of section 12, sub-section (1) 
    of section 17 and clause 
<subsection><number>a</number> in sub-clause (i) of section 21 of the Act 
    shall be accompanied by a fee as specified in the table given below in the 
    form of crossed Demand Draft drawn on a nationalised bank or through a 
    crossed Indian Postal Order in favour of the President of the District 
    Forum, Registrar of the State Commission or the Registrar of the National 
    Commission as the case may be, and payable at the respective place where the 
    District Forum, State Commission or the National Commission is situated.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    concerned authority referred to in sub-rule (1) shall credit the amount of 
    fee received by it into the Consumer Welfare Fund of the respective State 
    and where such fund is not established into the Receipt Account of the State 
    Government and in the case of the National Commission, to the Consumer 
    Welfare Fund of the Central Government.  
 
TABLE
 
 
  

 
 Sl. No.
 Total 
        Value of good or services and the compensation claimed
 Amount 
        of Fee Payable

 
  

 
 (1)
 (2)
 (3)

 
  

 
  
 District Forum
  

 
 1.
 Upto one lakh rupees - For 
        complainants who are under the Below Poverty Line holding Antyodaya Anna 
        Yojna cards
 Nil

 
 2.
 Upto one lakh rupees- For 
        complainants other than Antyodaya Anna Yojana card holders
 Rs. 100

 
 3.
 Above one lakh upto five 
        lakh rupees
 Rs. 200

 
 4.
 Above five lakh upto Ten 
        lakh rupees
 Rs. 400

 
 5.
 Above Ten lakh upto twenty 
        lakh rupees
 Rs. 500

 
  
 State Commission
  

 
 6.
 Above twenty lakh upto 
        fifty lakh rupees
 Rs. 2000

 
 7.
 Above fifty lakh upto One 
        Crorerupees
 Rs. 4000

 
  
 National Commission
  

 
 8.
 Above one crore rupees
 Rs. 5000

 
  


 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    complainants who are under the Below Poverty Line shall be entitled for the 
    exemption of payment of fee only on production of an attested copy of the 
    Antyodaya Anna Yojana cards.]  
 
 
 
 



 
 
  

 
 
Sl. No.
 
Value of good or services 
        and the compensation claimed
 
Amount of Fee Payable

 
  

 
 
(1)
 
(2)
 
(3)

 
  

 
  
 District 
        Forum
  

 
 
1.
 Upto one 
        lakh rupees 
 Rs. 100

 
 
2.
 Upto one 
        lakh rupees and above but less than five lakh rupees
 Rs. 200

 
 
3.
 Five Lakh 
        rupees and above but less than Rs. 10 Lakh
 Rs. 400

 
 
4.
 Ten Lakh 
        rupees and above but not exceeding twenty lakh rupess (w.e.f. 10-2-2005)
 Rs. 500

 
  

 
  
  
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Additional powers of the National Commission, State Commission and District 
    Forum.—
<section><number>1</number> The National 
    Commission, the State Commission and the District Forum shall have power to 
    require any person,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    to produce before, and allow to be 
    examined and kept by an officer of the National Commission, the State 
    Commission or the District Forum, as the case may be, specified in this 
    behalf, such books, accounts, documents or commodities in the custody or 
    under the control of the person so required as may be specified or described 
    in the requisition, if the examination of such books, accounts, documents or 
    commodities are required for the purpose of this Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    to furnish to an officer so specified, 
    such information as may be required for the purpose of this Act.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> (a) Where 
    during any proceedings under this Act, the National Commission, the State 
    Commission or the District Forum, as the case may be, has any ground to 
    believe that any book, paper, commodity or document which may be required to 
    be produced in such proceedings, are being or may be, destroyed, mutilated, 
    altered, falsified or secreted, it may, by written order, authorise any 
    officer to exercise the power of entry and search of any premises. Such 
    authorised officer may also seize such books, papers, documents or 
    commodities as are required for the purpose of this Act:  
 
Provided that 
    such seizure shall be communicated to the National Commission, the State 
    Commission or the District Forum, as the case may be, as soon as it is made 
    or within a period not exceeding 72 hours of making such seizure after 
    specifying the reasons in writing for making such seizure.  
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The 
    National Commission, the State Commission or the District Forum, as the case 
    may be, on examination of such seized documents or commodities, as the case 
    may be, may order the retention thereof or may return it to the party 
    concerned.  
 
 
 
 


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>10A</number> Credit of the 
    fine into the Consumer Welfare Fund when consumers are not identified 
    conveniently.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where an order is passed by the National Commission in exercise of the 
    powers vested under clause (hb) of sub-section (1) of section 14 directing 
    the opposite party to pay such amount as determined by it on account of loss 
    or injury suffered due to defects in goods complained against or alleged 
    deficiency of service to a large number of consumers, who are not 
    identifiable conveniently such sum shall be credited by the National 
    Commission in the Consumer Welfare Fund established by the Central 
    Government under section 12(C) of the Central Excise Act, 1944 (1 of 1944).  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any amount 
    credited to the said Fund shall be utilized in accordance with the 
    provisions of the Consumer Welfare Fund Rules, 1992.]
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>10B</number> Number of 
    members in the National Commission.—The National Commission shall consist of not less 
    than four members and not more than 

    2[nine] members and at 
    least one of them shall be a woman.]  
 
 







 



</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>11</number> Salaries, honorarium and other allowances of the President and 
members of the National Commission. </title>— <footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number> The President of 
the National Commission shall be entitled to salary, allowances and other 
perquisites as are available to a sitting Judge of the Supreme Court 
 
 
 <footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[ Explanation .—For the purpose of this clause, if the 
members are not provided with chauffeur driven government vehicle or if the 
members do not opt for hired vehicle in lieu of conveyance allowance, the 
members shall be paid conveyance allowance per month at the rate of ten thousand 
rupees and the cost of one hundred fifty litres of petrol.] 
 
 <subsection><number>e</number> the members shall be entitled to one thousand free calls for the 
  telephone installed at their residence, with STD and ISD facilities; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> the members shall be entitled to fifteen days casual leave in a year.] 
  </subsection>
 </section><section><number>1A</number> The other members of the National Commission appointed on whole-time 
  basis shall be entitled to the following honorarium and other allowances with 
  effect from the 1st day of April, 2006, namely:— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the members shall be paid twenty-three thousand rupees per month by 
    way of honorarium: 
 Provided that the members, who are retired Judges of High Courts or 
    retired Secretaries to the Government of India shall have the option to 
    either receive consolidated honorarium of twenty-three thousand rupees per 
    month or receive remuneration of last pay drawn less pension; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> a woman who has not held an office of profit earlier, on appointment 
    as a member shall be entitled to a pay in the scale of Rs. 24050-26000 per 
    month along with other benefits; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the members shall be provided with Government accommodation or 
    receive house rent allowance of <footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[twenty five thousand rupees per 
    month with effect from 1st September, 2008 ] in lieu thereof; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> the members shall be paid conveyance allowance at the rate of ten 
    thousand rupees per month, if no chauffeur driven government vehicle is 
    provided in which event one hundred fifty litres of petrol shall be supplied 
    or the price thereof shall be paid; </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> <footcitenum>20</footcitenum>[The members] shall be entitled to travelling and 
daily allowances on official tours at the same rates as are admissible to g roup 
‘A' Officers of the Central Government. 
 
 <footcitenum>21</footcitenum>[***] 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The honorarium or the salary, as the case may be, and other allowances 
shall be defrayed out of the Consolidated Fund of India. 








</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Terms 
    and conditions of service of the President and members of the National 
    Commission.—
<section><number>1</number> Before 
    appointment, the President and a member of the National Commission shall 
    have to take an undertaking that he does not and will not have any such 
    financial or other interest as is likely to affect prejudicially his 
    functions as such member.  
 


    1[***]  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rule (2) the President or a member 
    may,—  
 

2[(a)    
    by writing under his hand and addressed to the Central Government resign his 
    office at any time but his office shall become vacant only when such 
    resignation is accepted by the Central Government;]  
 <subsection>
<number>b</number>    be removed from his office in 
    accordance with the provisions of rule 13.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The terms 
    and conditions of service of the President and the members shall not be 
    varied to their disadvantage during their tenure of office.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> A casual 
    vacancy caused by resignation or removal of the President or any other 
    member of the National Commission under sub-rule (3) or otherwise shall be 
    filled by fresh appointment.  
 


    3[(6) When the office 
    of the President of the National Commission is vacant or a person occupying 
    such office is by reason of absence or otherwise, unable to perform the 
    duties of his office, the same shall, save as otherwise provided in the 
    proviso to section 22D be performed by the senior most member of the 
    National Commission.]  
 


    4[(7) The President or 
    any member ceasing to hold office as such shall not hold any appointment in 
    or be connected with the management or administrations of an organisation 
    which have been the subject of any proceeding under the Act during his 
    tenure for a period of 5 years from the date on which he ceases to hold such 
    office].
 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>12A</number> Procedure for 
    selection of members.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Save as otherwise provided in sub‑rule (2), the process of appointment of a 
    member shall be initiated at least three months before the vacancy arises.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If a post 
    falls vacant due to resignation or death of a member or creation of a new 
    post, the process for filling the post shall be initiated immediately after 
    the post has fallen vacant or is created, as the case may be.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An 
    advertisement of a vacancy inviting applications from eligible candidates 
    may be published in leading newspapers in India or by vacancy circulars or 
    both, as may be decided by the Central Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> After 
    scrutiny of the applications received till the last date specified for 
    receipt of applications, a list of eligible candidates alongwith their 
    applications shall be placed before the Selection Committee constituted 
    under the third proviso to sub‑section (1) of section 20.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Selection Committee shall consider all the applications of eligible 
    applicants referred to it.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    Selection Committee may, if it considers necessary, depending on the number 
    of candidates, short list them on the basis of merit and call such short 
    listed candidates for personal interview to consider their suitability for 
    the post of Member.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The 
    Selection Committee may, on the basis of its assessment made by it, 
    recommend a panel of names of candidates for appointment as members from 
    amongst the applicants referred to in sub‑rule (5) in order of merit for the 
    consideration of the Central Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> The Central 
    Government shall, before seeking approval of the Appointments Committee of 
    the Cabinet, verify or cause to be verified the credentials and antecedents 
    of the candidates selected by the Central Government from the panel 
    recommended by the Selection Committee and satisfy the suitability of such 
    candidates for appointment as members.  
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> Every 
    appointment of a member shall be subject to his medical fitness.]  
 
 
  






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> Removal 
    of President or members from office in certain circumstances.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may remove from office, the President or any member, 
    who,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    has been adjudged as an insolvent; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    has been convicted of an offence which, 
    in the opinion of the Central Government, involves moral turpitude; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    has become physically or mentally 
    incapable of acting as the President or the member; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    has acquired such financial or other 
    interest as is likely to affect prejudicially his functions as the President 
    or a member; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    has so abused his position as to 
    render his continuance in office prejudicial to the public interest 
1[;or]  
 

2[(f)    
    remain absent in three consecutive sittings except for reasons beyond his 
    control.]  
 


    3[(2) Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in sub-rule (1), the President or any member of the 
    National Commission shall not be removed from his office except by an order 
    made by the Central Government on the grounds specified in clauses (d), (e) 
    and (f) of that sub-rule and after an inquiry held by a sitting Judge of the 
    Supreme Court nominated by the Chief Justice of India in which the President 
    or member of the National Commission, as the case may be, has been informed 
    of the charges against him and given a reasonable opportunity of being heard 
    in respect of those charges and found guilty.]  
 
 
  







 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Procedure to be followed by the National Commission.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A complaint containing the following particulars shall be presented by the 
    complainant in person or by his agent to the National Commission or be sent 
    by registered post, addressed to the National Commission:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the name, description and the address 
    of the complainant;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the name, description and address of 
    the opposite party or parties, as the case may be, so far as they can be 
    ascertained;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the facts relating to the complaint and 
    when and where it arose;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    documents in support of the allegations 
    contained in the complaint;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the relief which the complainant 
    claims.  
 


    1[(1A) Every complaint 
    under sub-rule (1) shall be accompanied by the relevant fee as is specified 
    in rule 9A.]  
 


    2[(1B) Every complaint 
    under sub‑rule (1) shall be filed in quadruplicate or with such number of 
    copies as may be required by the National Commission.]  
 


    3[(2) The National 
    Commission shall, in disposal of any complaint before it, as far as 
    possible, follow the procedure and conditions including the provisions 
    governing adjournments as laid down in sections 12 and 13 in relation to the 
    complaints received by the District Forum, with such modification as may be 
    considered necessary by the Commission.]  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> On the date 
    of hearing or any other date to which hearing could be adjourned, it shall 
    be obligatory on the parties or their agents to appear before the National 
    Commission. Where the complainant or his agent fails to appear before the 
    National Commission on such days, the National Commission may in its 
    discretion either dismiss the complaint for default or decide it on merits. 
    Where the opposite party or its agent fails to appear on the date of hearing 
    the National Commission may decide the complaint ex-parte.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    National Commission may, on such terms as it deems fit and at any stage of 
    the proceedings, adjourn the hearing of the complaint but the complaint 
    shall be decided, as far as possible, within a period of three months from 
    the date of notice received by opposite party where complaint does not 
    require analysis or testing of commodities and within five months if it 
    requires analysis or testing of commodities.  
 


    4[(4A) In the event of 
    a complaint being disposed of after the period specified in sub-rule (4), 
    the National Commission shall record in writing, the reasons for the delay 
    in such disposal.]  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If after 
    the proceedings conducted under sub-rule (3), the National Commission is 
    satisfied with the allegations contained in the complaint, it shall issue 
    orders to the opposite party or parties, as the case may be, directing him 
    or them to take one or more of the things as mentioned in sub-section (1) of 
    section 14. The National Commission shall also have the power to direct that 
    any order passed by it, where no appeal has been preferred under section 23 
    or where the order of the National Commission has been affirmed by the 
    Supreme Court under that section, be published in the Official Gazette or 
    through any other media and no legal proceedings shall lie against the 
    National Commission or any media for such publication.  
 












 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>14A</number> Appeals before 
    National Commission.—Every 
    appeal filed in terms of section 19 shall be accompanied by such amount as 
    specified in the second proviso to the said section and such amount may be 
    remitted in the form of a crossed Demand Draft drawn on a nationalized bank 
    in favour of the Registrar, National Commission, payable at Delhi. The 
    National Commission dealing with the appeals filed before them shall follow 
    the provisions of sections 19 and 19A as may be required to hear the appeals 
    filed before the Commission.  
 
Explanation.—In 
    this rule, “nationalized bank” means a corresponding new bank specified in 
    the First Schedule to the Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of 
    Undertakings) Act, 1970 (5 of 1970) or a corresponding new bank specified in 
    the First Schedule to the Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of 
    Undertakings) Act, 1980 (40 of 1980).]  
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Procedure for hearing the appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Memorandum shall be presented by the appellant or his agent to the National 
    Commission in person or be sent by registered post addressed to the 
    Commission.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    memorandum filed under sub-rule (1) shall be in legible handwriting 
    preferably typed and shall set forth concisely under distinct heads, the 
    grounds of appeal without any argument or narrative and such grounds shall 
    be numbered consecutively.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Each 
    memorandum shall be 

    1[accompanied by a 
    crossed demand draft as referred to in rule 14A and by a certified copy] of 
    the order of the State Commission appealed against and such of the documents 
    as may be required to support grounds of objection mentioned in the 
    memorandum.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> When the 
    appeal is presented after the expiry of the period of limitation as 
    specified in the Act, the memorandum shall be accompanied by an application 
    supported by an affidavit setting forth the facts on which the appellant 
    relies to satisfy the National Commission that he has sufficient cause for 
    not preferring the appeal within the period of limitation.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    appellant shall submit 

    2[four copies or such 
    number of copies] of the memorandum to the Commission for official purpose.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> On the date 
    of hearing or on any other day to which hearing may be adjourned, it shall 
    be obligatory for the parties or their agents to appear before the National 
    Commission. If appellant or his agent fails to appear on such date, the 
    National Commission may in its discretion either dismiss the appeal or 
    decide ex-parte on merits. If the respondent or his agent fails to 
    appear on such date, the National Commission shall proceed ex-parte 
    and shall decide the appeal on merits of the case.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The 
    appellant shall not, except by leave of the National Commission, urge or be 
    heard in support of any ground of objection not set forth in the memorandum 
    but the National Commission, in deciding the appeal, may not confine to the 
    grounds of objection set forth in the memorandum:  
 
Provided that 
    the Commission shall not rest its decision on any other ground other than 
    those specified in the memorandum unless the party who may be affected 
    thereby, has been given, an opportunity of being heard by the National 
    Commission.  
 


    3[(8) No adjournment 
    shall ordinarily be granted by the National Commission, unless sufficient 
    cause is shown and the reasons for grant of adjournment have been recorded 
    in writing by the Commission. The National Commission may also adjourn the 
    hearing of the appeal suo motu, on such terms as it may think fit and 
    at any stage of the proceedings for reasons to be recorded in writing. The 
    appeal shall be decided, as far as possible, within ninety days from the 
    date of its admission. In the event of an appeal being disposed of after the 
    period so specified, the National Commission shall record in writing the 
    reasons of the same at the time of disposal of the said appeal.]  
 


    4[(9) The order of the 
    National Commission shall be communicated to the parties concerned free of 
    cost.]
 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[15A. 
    Sitting of the National Commission and signing of orders.—
<section><number>1</number> Every 
    proceeding of the National Commission shall be conducted by the President
    

    2[or the senior-most 
    member 

    3[***]] and at least 
    two members thereof sitting together 

    4[except when a bench 
    is constituted by the President of the National Commission with one or more 
    members as he may deem fit:]  
 


    5[Provided that one 
    member or members for any reason are unable to conduct proceedings till it 
    is completed, the President or the senior-most member, as provided in 
    section 22D of the Act, shall conduct such proceedings from the stage at 
    which it was last heard by the previous member.]  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    order made by the National Commission shall be signed by the President
    

    2[or the senior-most 
    member 

    6[as provided under 
    section 22D]] and at least two members who conducted the proceeding and if 
    there is any difference of opinion among themselves, the opinion of majority 
    shall be the order of the National Commission:  
 
Provided 
    that where the proceeding is conducted by the President 

    1[or the senior-most 
    member 

    6[as provided under 
    section 22D]] and three members thereof and they differ on any point or 
    points, they shall state the point or points on which they differ and refer 
    the same to the other member for hearing on such point or points and such 
    point or points shall be decided accordingly to the opinion of the majority 
    of the National Commission.]
 
 
 
 











 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>16</number> Manner of deposit 
    of amount in appeals before Supreme Court.—Every 
    appeal filed before the Supreme Court in terms of section 23 shall be 
    accompanied by an amount as provided in the second proviso to that section 
    and such amount may be remitted in the form of a crossed Demand Draft drawn 
    on a nationalized bank in favour of Registrar, Supreme Court, payable at 
    Delhi.  
 
Explanation.—In 
    this rule, “nationalized bank” means a corresponding new bank specified in 
    the First Schedule to the Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of 
    Undertakings) Act, 1970 (5 of 1970) or a corresponding new bank specified in 
    the First Schedule to the Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of 
    Undertakings) Act, 1980 (40 of 1980).]
 
 





 



</article><form>
 
 
 
 
 

 
 
 

The Consumer Protection Rules, 
      1987
 

 
 

 
 

1[SCHEDULE I
 

[See rule 3(1)(c)]
 

1. Eastern Region—to consist of 
      the States of Bihar, Chattisgarh, Jharkhand, Orissa, and West 
      Bengal.
 

2. Western Region—to consist of 
      the States of Goa, Gujarat, Maharashtra, Madhya Pradesh and 
      Rajasthan.
 

3. Northern Region—to consist of 
      the States of Haryana, Himachal Pradesh,  Jammu &amp; Kashmir, 
      Punjab, Uttar Pradesh and Uttaranchal.
 

4. Southern Region—to consist of 
      the States of Andhra Pradesh, Karnataka, Kerala and Tamil Nadu.
 

5. North Eastern Region—to consist 
      of the States of Arunachal Pradesh, Assam, Manipur, Meghalaya, Mizoram, 
      Nagaland, Tripura and Sikkim.
 

 
 

 
 

-------------------------
 

1.
Ins. by G.S.R. 273 (E), dated 
      5th May, 2006 (w.e.f. 5-5-2006).
 

 -------------------------
 

 
 

 
 

 
 
 

 </form><form>
 
 
 
 
 

 
 
 

The Consumer Protection Rules, 
      1987
 

 
 

 
 

Schedule II
 

[See rule 3(1)(ca)]
 

 
 

The Union Territories of the 
      Andaman and Nicobar Islands, Chandigarh, Dadra and Nagar Haveli, Daman and 
      Diu, Lakshadweep, Pondicherry and the  National Capital Territory of 
      Delhi.]
 

 
 

 
 

 
 

 
 
 

 </form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> The Central Government has constituted the Central Consumer Protection Council for a period of three years with effect from 10th March, 2011,  vide  S.O. 496(E), dated 10th March, 2011, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(ii), dated 10th March, 2011.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 95(E), dated 27th February, 1997 (w.e.f. 27-2-1997).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 273(E), dated 5th May, 2006 (w.e.f. 5-5-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 800(E), dated 30th December, 1993 (w.e.f. 30-12-1993).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Omitted by G.S.R. 273(E), dated 5th May, 2006 (w.e.f. 5-5-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 175(E), dated 5th March, 2004 (w.e.f. 5-3-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 95(E), dated 27th February, 1997 (w.e.f. 27-2-1997).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 385(E), dated 12th May, 2011 (w.e.f. 12-5-2011).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> Omitted by G.S.R. 273(E), dated 5th May, 2006 (w.e.f. 5-5-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 175(E), dated 5th March, 2004 for sub-rule 
(6) (w.e.f. 5-3-2004). Earlier sub-rule (6) was substituted by G.S.R. 759(E), 
dated 21st November, 1995 (w.e.f. 21-11-1995).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 591(E), dated 20th August, 2009 for “avail 
first class or two-tier air-conditioned class of railway accommodation by all 
trains (including Rajdhani Express) and claim such fare or cost of actual mode 
of travel, whichever is less. The non-official members from Island territories 
shall be entitled to, to and fro air journey (economy class) in domestic 
airlines from the Islands to the nearest main-land airport and thereafter rail 
fare by entitled class. The non-official members who are senior citizens shall 
be entitled to, to and fro air-journey (economy class) in domestic airlines on 
availing senior citizen concessional air fare for their journeys provided the 
distance being travelled is 1000 kms or above”. (w.e.f. 20-8-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 64(E), dated 10th February, 2005, for “Rs. 
1000 per day” (w.e.f. 10-2-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 591(E), dated 20th August, 2009, for “Rs. 
1000” (w.e.f. 20-8-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 64(E), dated 10th February, 2005, for 
“consolidated conveyance, hire charges and incidental charges to cover the daily 
allowances” (w.e.f. 10-2-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 591(E), dated 20th August, 2009, for “Rs. 
200” (w.e.f. 20-8-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 64 (E), dated 10th February, 2005, for “six” (w.e.f. 
    5-3-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 462(E), dated 4th August, 2006 , for sub-rule 
(1) (w.e.f. 4-8-2006 ). Sub-rule (1), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 380(E), dated 2nd June, 2009 , for “eight 
thousand rupees per month” (w.e.f. 2-6-2009 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 380(E), dated 2nd June, 2009 (w.e.f. 2-6-2009 
).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 462(E), dated 4th August, 2006 , for “the 
President and the members” (w.e.f. 4-8-2006 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number> Sub-rule (2A) omitted by G.S.R. 462(E), dated 4th August, 
2006 (w.e.f. 4-8-2006 ). Sub-rule (2A), before omission, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 175 (E), dated 5th March, 2004 (w.e.f. 5-3-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 175 (E), dated 5th March, 2004 (w.e.f. 5-3-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number> 
      Sub-rules (7), (8) and (9) omitted and sub-rule (10) re-numbered as 
    sub-rule (7) by G.S.R. No. 533 (E), dated 14th August, 1991 (w.e.f. 
    14-8-1991).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number>   Ins. by G.S.R. 95 (E), dated 27th February, 1997 (w.e.f. 
    27-2-1997).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 175 (E), dated 5th March, 2004 (w.e.f. 5-3-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number>   Ins. by G.S.R. 64 (E), dated 10th February, 2005 (w.e.f. 10-2-2005). 
    Ed.— In the said G.S.R. 64 (E) it is stated that sub-rule (1A) is to be 
    inserted after sub-rule (1) whereas sub-rule (1A) has already been inserted 
    by G.S.R. 175 (E), dated 5th March, 2004 (w.e.f. 5-3-2004). Hence it is 
    renumbered as sub-rule (1B).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>28</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 175 (E), dated 5th March, 2004 (w.e.f. 5-3-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>29</number>   Ins. by G.S.R. 175 (E), dated 5th March, 2004 (w.e.f. 5-3-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>30</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 64 (E), dated 10th February, 2005, for “six 
    copies” (w.e.f. 10-2-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>31</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 175 (E), dated 5th March, 2004 (w.e.f. 5-3-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>32</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 533 (E), dated 14th August, 1991 (w.e.f. 
    14-8-1991).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>33</number>   Ins. by G.S.R. 95 (E), dated 27th February, 1997 (w.e.f. 27-2-1997).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>34</number>   The words “authorised under rule 12” omitted by G.S.R. 64 (E), dated 
    10th February, 2005 (w.e.f. 10-2-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>35</number>   Ins. by G.S.R. 175 (E), dated 5th March, 2004 (w.e.f. 5-3-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>36</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 64 (E), dated 10th February, 2005 for “Provided that 
    where the member or members for any reason are unable to conduct the 
    proceeding till it is completed, the President or the senior-most member 
    authorised under rule 12 shall conduct such proceeding de novo.” (w.e.f. 
    10-2-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>37</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 64 (E), dated 10th February, 2005 for “authorised under 
    rule 12” (w.e.f. 10-2-2005).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>