<act><title>


The Representation of the People Act, 1950</title> 

 



 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title.—This 
Act may be called the Representation of the People Act, 1950.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—1[***] 
In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  “article” 
means an article of the Constitution;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  “Assembly 
constituency” means a constituency provided 

2[by law] for the 
purpose of elections to the Legislative Assembly of a State;
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  “Council 
constituency” means a constituency provided 

3[by law] for the 
purpose of elections to the Legislative Council of a State;
 

 4[***] 
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>  “Election 
Commission” means the Election Commission appointed by the President under 
article 324;
 </section><section>
        <number>e</number>  “order” means 
an order published in the Official Gazette;
 </section><section>
         <number>f</number>  
“parliamentary constituency” means a constituency provided 

5[by law] for the 
purpose of elections to the House of the People;
 

 6[***]
 </section><section>
        <number>g</number>  “person” does 
not include a body of persons;
 </section><section>
        <number>h</number>  “prescribed” 
means prescribed by rules made under this Act;
 
 

7[(i)  “State” 
includes a Union territory;]
 </section><section>
         <number>j</number>  “State 
Government”, in relation to a Union territory, means the administrator thereof.
 

 8[***]
 












</section></article> 

 


 <article>

1[<number>3</number> Allocation 
of seats in the House of the People.—The allocation of seats to the States 
in the House of the People and the number of seats, if any, to be reserved for 
the Scheduled Castes and for the Scheduled Tribes of each State shall be shown 
in the First Schedule.]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>3A</number> 
Reservation of Seats in the House of People for Scheduled Castes and Scheduled 
Tribes in certain Part C States.—[Rep. by the Representation of the 
People Amendment) Act, 1958 (58 of 1958), sec. 3 (w.e.f. 
30-12-1958).]]
 
 



</article> 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[ <title><number>4</number> Filling of seats in the House of the People and parliamentary constituencies. </title>— <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[***] 
 <section><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> All the seats in the House of the People allotted to the States under section 3 shall be seats to be filled by persons chosen by direct election from parliamentary constituencies in the States.] 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every parliamentary constituency referred to in sub-section (2) shall be a single-member constituency. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Every State to which only one seat is allotted under section 3 shall form one parliamentary constituency. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>5</number> Save as provided in sub-section (4), the extent of all parliamentary constituencies except the parliamentary constituencies in the States of Arunachal Pradesh, Assam, Jharkhand, Manipur and Nagaland shall be as determined by the orders of the Delimitation Commission made under the provisions of the Delimitation Act, 2002 (33 of 2002) and the extent of the parliamentary constituencies in the States of Arunachal Pradesh, Assam, Jharkhand, Manipur and Nagaland shall be as provided for in the Delimitation of Parliamentary and Assembly Constituencies Order, 2008 having regard to the provisions of sections 10A and 10B of the Delimitation Act, 2002.] 






</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Parliamentary 
constituencies.—[Rep. 
by the Representation of the People (Amendment) Act, 1956 (2 of 1956), sec. 4 
(w.e.f. 
1-3-1956).]
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Delimitation of 
parliamentary constituencies.—[Rep. 
by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, 1956 (w.e.f. 
1-11-1956).]
 
 
</article> 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<title><number>7</number> Total number of seats in Legislative Assemblies and assembly constituencies. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[Subject to the provisions of <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[sub-sections (1A), (1B) and (1C)], the total number of seats] in the Legislative Assembly of each State specified in the Second Schedule, to be filled by persons chosen by direct election from assembly constituencies, and the number of seats, if any, to be reserved for the Scheduled Castes and for the Scheduled Tribes of the State, shall be as shown in that Schedule: 
 Provided that for the period referred to in clause (2) of article 371A, the total number of seats allotted to the Legislative Assembly of the State of Nagaland shall be <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[fifty-two], of which— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[twelve seats] shall be allocated to the Tuensang district and shall be filled by persons chosen by the members of the regional council, referred to in that article, from amongst themselves in such manner as the Governor, after consulting that Council may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify, and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the remaining forty seats shall be filled by persons chosen by direct election from assembly constituencies in the rest of the State. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[<number>1A</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), the total number of seats in the Legislative Assembly of the State of Sikkim, to be constituted at any time after the commencement of the Representation of the People (Amendment) Act, 1980 (8 of 1980), to be filled by persons chosen by direct election from assembly constituencies shall be thirty-two, of which— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> twelve seats shall be reserved for Sikkimese of Bhutia Lepcha origin; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> two seats shall be reserved for the Scheduled Castes of the State; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> one seat shall be reserved for the Sanghas referred to in section 25A. 
</subsection>
 Explanation .—In this sub-section “Bhutia” includes Chumbipa, Dopthapa, Dukpa, Kagatey, Sherpa, Tibetan, Tromopa and Yolmo.] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[<number>1B</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), in the Legislative Assemblies of the States of Arunachal Pradesh, Meghalaya, Mizoram and Nagaland, to be constituted at any time after the commencement of the Representation of the People (Third Amendment) Act, 1987 (40 of 1987),— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> <footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[fifty-nine seats] shall be reserved for the Scheduled Tribes in the Legislative Assembly of the State of Arunachal Pradesh ; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> fifty-five seats shall be reserved for the Scheduled Tribes in the Legislative Assembly of the State of Meghalaya ; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> thirty-nine seats shall be reserved for the Scheduled Tribes in the Legislative Assembly of the State of Mizoram ; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> fifty-nine seats shall be reserved for the Scheduled Tribes in the Legislative Assembly of the State of Nagaland .] 
</subsection>
 </section><section><footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[<number>1C</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), twenty seats shall be reserved for the Scheduled Tribes in the Legislative Assembly of the State of Tripura to be constituted at any time after the commencement of the Representation of the People (Amendment) Act, 1992 (38 of 1992)]. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every Assembly constituency referred to <footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[in sub-section (1) or sub-section (1A)] shall be a single-member constituency. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[<number>3</number> The extent of each assembly constituency in all the States and Union Territories except the assembly constituencies in the States of Arunachal Pradesh, Assam, Jharkhand, Manipur and Nagaland shall be as determined by the orders of the Delimitation Commission made under the provisions of the Delimitation Act, 2002 (33 of 2002) and the extent of each assembly constituency in the States of Arunachal Pradesh, Assam, Jharkhand, Manipur and Nagaland shall be as provided for in the Delimitation of Parliamentary and Assembly Constituencies Order, 2008 having regard to the provisions of sections 10A and 10B of the Delimitation Act, 2002.] 













</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>7A</number> Total 
number of seats in the Legislative Assembly of Sikkim and Assembly 
constituencies.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in section 7, in the 
Legislative Assembly of the State of Sikkim [deemed under the Constitution 
(Thirty-sixth Amendment) Act, 1975 to be the Legislative Assembly of that State 
duly constituted], the total number of seats to be filled by persons chosen by 
direct election from assembly constituencies shall be 32.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every Assembly 
constituency referred to in sub-section (1) shall be a single-member 
constituency.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In the Legislative 
Assembly so deemed to be duly constituted, the extent of each constituency and 
the reservation of seats shall be as provided for immediately before the 
commencement of the Constitution (Thirty-sixth Amendment) Act, 1975.]
 
 



</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>8</number> Consolidation of delimitation orders. </title>— <footcitenum>17</footcitenum><title></title>[
<section><number>1</number> Having regard to all the orders referred to in sub-section (5) of section 4 and sub-section (3) of section 7 relating to the delimitation of parliamentary and assembly constituencies in all States and Union Territories, except the States of Arunachal Pradesh, Assam, Jharkhand, Manipur and Nagaland, made by the Delimitation Commission and published in the Official Gazette, the Election Commission shall— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> after making such amendments as appear to it to be necessary for bringing up-to-date the description of the extent of the parliamentary and assembly constituencies as given in such orders, without, however, altering the extent of any such constituency; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> after taking into account the provisions of the Delimitation of Parliamentary and Assembly Constituencies Order, 1976, as made applicable pursuant to the orders made by the President under section 10A of the Delimitation Act, 2002 (33 of 2002) relating to delimitation of parliamentary and assembly constituencies in the States of Arunachal Pradesh, Assam, Manipur and Nagaland, and the provisions of section 10B of the said Act relating to delimitation of parliamentary and assembly constituencies in the State of Jharkhand, 
 consolidate all such orders into one single order to be known as the Delimitation of Parliamentary and Assembly Constituencies Order, 2008 and shall send authentic copies of that Order to the Central Government and to the Government of each State having a Legislative Assembly; and thereupon that Order shall supersede all the orders referred to in sub-section (5) of section 4 and sub-­section (3) of section 7 and shall have the force of law and shall not be called in question in any court.] 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> As soon as may be, after the said Order is received by the Central Government or by the Government of a State, that Government shall cause it to be laid before the House of the People or, as the case may be, the Legislative Assembly of the State. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[<number>3</number> The consolidation under sub-section (1) of the orders referred to in sub-section (5) of section 4, or as the case may be, sub-section (3) of section 7 shall not,<footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[as provided in sub-section (5) of section 10 of the Delimitation Act, 2002 (33 of 2002)], affect the representation in, and the territorial constituencies of, the House of the People or the Legislative Assembly of the State existing on the date of publication in the Gazette of India of any such order or orders as may be relevant. 





</section></article> 

  
 <article><footcitenum>20</footcitenum><title>[<number>8A</number> Delimitation of Parliamentary and Assembly Constituencies in the States of Arunachal Pradesh, Assam, Manipur or Nagaland. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> If the President is satisfied that the situation and the conditions prevailing in the States of Arunachal Pradesh, Assam, Manipur or Nagaland are conducive for the conduct of delimitation exercise, he may, by order, rescind the deferment order issued under the provisions of section 10A of the Delimitation Act, 2002 (33 of 2002) in relation to that State, and provide for the conduct of delimitation exercise in the State by the Election Commission. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> As soon as may be after the deferment order in respect of a State is rescinded under sub-section (1), the Election Commission may, by order, determine— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the parliamentary constituencies into which such State to which more than one seat is allotted in the First Schedule shall be divided; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the extent of each constituency; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the number of seats, if any, reserved for the Scheduled Castes or the Scheduled Tribes. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> As soon as may be after the deferment order in respect of a State is rescinded under sub-section (1), the Election Commission may, by order, determine— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the assembly constituencies into which such State shall be divided for the purpose of elections to the Legislative Assembly of that State; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the extent of each constituency; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the number of seats, if any, reserved for the Scheduled Castes or the Scheduled Tribes. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>4</number> Subject to the provisions of sub-section (1), the Election Commission shall, having regard to the provisions of the Constitution and the principles specified in clauses (c) and (d) of sub-section (1) of section 9 of the Delimitation Act, 2002 (33 of 2002) determine the parliamentary and assembly constituencies in the States of Arunachal Pradesh, Assam, Manipur and Nagaland in which seats shall be reserved, if any, for the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled Tribes. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Election Commission shall,— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> publish its proposals under sub-sections (2), (3) and (4) with respect to any State in the Official Gazette and also in such other manner as it thinks fit; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> specify a date on or after which the proposals will be further considered by it; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> consider all objections and suggestions which may have been received by it before the date so specified; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> hold, for the purpose of such consideration, if it thinks fit so to do, one or more public sittings at such place or places in such State as it thinks fit; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> after considering all objections and suggestions which may have been received by it before the date so specified, determine, by order, the delimitation of parliamentary and assembly constituencies in the State and also the constituency or constituencies in which seats shall be reserved, if any, for the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled Tribes and cause such order to be published in the Official Gazette; and, upon such publication, the order shall have the force of law and shall not be called in question in any court and the Delimitation of Parliamentary and Assembly Constituencies Order, 2008 shall be deemed to have been amended accordingly. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>6</number> Every order made under sub-sections (1) and (2) and clause (e) of sub-­section (5) shall be laid before each House of Parliament. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> Every order made under sub-sections (1) and (3) and clause (e) of sub-­section (5) shall, as soon as may be after it is published under that sub-section, be laid before the Legislative Assembly of the State concerned.] 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>9</number> Power of Election Commission to maintain Delimitation Order up-to-date. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The Election Commission may, from time to time, by notification published in the Gazette of India and in the Official Gazette of the State concerned,— 
 
 <subsection><footcitenum>21</footcitenum>[<number>a</number> correct any printing mistake in the Delimitation of Parliamentary and Assembly Constituencies Order, 2008 or any error arising therein from inadvertent slip or omission; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>aa</number> make such amendments in the Delimitation of Parliamentary and Assembly Constituencies Order, 2008 as appear to it to be necessary or expedient for consolidating with that Order any notification or order relating to delimitation of Parliamentary or assembly constituencies (including reservation of seats for the Scheduled Castes or the Scheduled Tribes in such constituencies) issued under section 8A of this Act or any other Central Act;] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> where the boundaries or name of any district or any territorial division mentioned in the Order are or is altered, make such amendments as appear to it to be necessary or expedient for bringing the Order up-to-date. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every notification under this section shall be laid as soon as may be after it is issued, before the House of the People and the Legislative Assembly to the State concerned.] 


 
 “(a) correct any printing mistake in the Delimitation of Parliamentary and Assembly Constituencies Order, 1966, or, as the case may be, the Delimitation of Parliamentary and Assembly Constituencies Order, 1976 or any error arising therein from inadvertent slip or omission; 
    (aa) make such amendments in the Delimitation of Parliamentary and Assembly Constituencies Order, 1976 as appear to it to be necessary or expedient for consolidating with that Order any notification or order relating to delimitation of Parliamentary or assembly constituencies (including reservation of seats for the Scheduled Castes or the Scheduled Tribes in such constituencies) issued under any Central Act;” 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>9A</number><footcitenum>22</footcitenum>[***] </title>




 
 <section><number>a</number> publish its proposals under sub-section (1) with respect to any State in the Official Gazette and also in such other manner as it thinks fit; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> specify a date on or after which the proposals will be further considered by it; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> consider all objections and suggestions which may have been received by it before the date so specified; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> hold, for the purpose of such consideration, if it thinks fit so to do, one or more public sittings at such place or places in such State as it thinks fit; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> after considering all objections and suggestions which may have been received by it before the date so specified, determine, by order, the assembly constituency or constituencies in the State in which seats shall be reserved for the Scheduled Tribes and cause such order to be published in the Official Gazette; and, upon such publication, the order shall have the full force of law and shall not be called in question in any court and the Delimitation of Parliamentary and Assembly Constituencies Order, 1976, or, as the case may be, the Mizoram (Delimitation of Assembly Constituencies) Order, 1986 shall be deemed to have been amended accordingly. 
</section>


 
 <section><number>a</number> in relation to the States of Meghalaya and Nagaland, the assembly constituencies in those States as specified in the Delimitation of Parliamentary and Assembly Constituencies Order, 1976; and 
 </section><section><number>b</number> in relation to the State of Mizoram , the assembly constituencies as specified in the Mizoram (Delimitation of Assembly Constituencies) Order, 1986.” 
</section>
</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>9B</number><footcitenum>23</footcitenum>[***] </title>




 
 <section><number>a</number> publish its proposals under sub-section (1) in the Official Gazette and also in such other manner as it thinks fit; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> specify a date on or after which the proposals will be further considered by it; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> consider all objections and suggestions which may have been received by it before the date so specified; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> hold, for the purpose of such consideration, if it thinks fit so to do, one or more public sittings at such place or places in the State as it thinks fit; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> after considering all objections and suggestions which may have been received by it before the date so specified, determine, by order, the three assembly constituencies in the State in which the said three additional seats shall be reserved for the Scheduled Tribes and cause such order to be published in the Official Gazette; and, upon such publication, the order shall have the full force of law and shall not be called in question in any court and the Delimitation of Parliamentary and Assembly Constituencies Order, 1976, shall be deemed to have been amended accordingly. 
</section>

</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Allocation of seats 
in the Legislative Councils.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The allocation of seats in the Legislative Councils of the States having such 
Councils shall be as shown in the Third Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In the Legislative 
Council of each State specified in the first column of the Third Schedule, there 
shall be the number of seats specified in the second column thereof opposite to 
that State, and of those seats,—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number> the numbers 
specified in the third, fourth and fifth columns shall be the numbers of seats 
to be filled by persons elected, respectively, by the electorates referred to in 
sub-clauses (a), (b) and (c) of clause (3) of article 171;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number> the number 
specified in the sixth column shall be the number of seats to be filled by 
persons elected by the members of the Legislative Assembly of the State from 
amongst persons who are not members of that Assembly; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number> the number 
specified in the seventh column shall be the number of seats to be filled by 
persons nominated by the Governor 

1[***] of the State 
in accordance with the provisions of clause (5) of article 171.
 

2[***]
 
 




</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Delimitation of 
Council constituencies.—As 
soon as may be after the commencement of this Act, the President shall, by 
order, determine—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  the 
constituencies into which each State having a Legislative Council shall be 
divided for the purpose of elections to that Council under each of the 
sub-clauses (a), (b) and (c) of clause (3) of article 171;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  the extent of 
each constituency; and
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  the number of 
seats allotted to each constituency.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Power to alter or 
amend orders.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
The President may, from time to time, after consulting the Election Commission, 
by order, alter or amend any order made by him under 

2[***] section 11.
 

3[(2) An order 
under sub-section (1) may contain provisions for the allocation of any member 
representing any Council constituency immediately before the making of the order 
to any constituency delimited a new or altered by the order and for such other 
incidental and consequential matters as the President may deem necessary.]
 
 





</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
 <number>13</number> Procedure as to 
orders delimiting constituencies.—1[***]
 

2[***]
 <section>
<number>3</number> Every order made under


3[***] section 11 
or section 12 shall be laid before Parliament as soon as may be after it is 
made, and shall be subject to such modifications as Parliament may make on a 
motion made within twenty days from the date on which the order is so laid.
 
 





</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<footcitenum>32</footcitenum>[<number>13A</number> Chief electoral 
officers.—
<section><number>1</number> There shall be for each State a chief electoral officer who 
shall be such officer of Government as the Election Commission may, in 
consultation with that Government, designate or nominate in this behalf.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to the 
superintendence, direction and control of the Election Commission, the chief 
electoral officer shall supervise the preparation, revision and correction of 
all electoral rolls in the State under this Act.]
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>[<footcitenum>33</footcitenum>[<number>13AA</number> 
District election officers.—
<section><number>1</number> For each district in a State, 
<footcitenum>34</footcitenum>[***] the Election 
Commission shall, in consultation with the Government of the State, designate or 
nominate a district election officer who shall be an officer of Government: 

 
Provided that the Election 
Commission may designate or nominate more than one such officer for a district 
if the Election Commission is satisfied that the functions of the office cannot 
be performed satisfactorily by one officer.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where more than one 
district election officer are designated or nominated for a district under the 
proviso to sub-section (1), the Election Commission shall in the order 
designating or nominating the district election officers also specify the area 
in respect of which each such officer shall exercise jurisdiction.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Subject to the 
superintendence, direction and control of the chief electoral officer, the 
district election officer shall co-ordinate and supervise all work in the 
district or in the area within his jurisdiction in connection with the 
preparation and revision of the electoral rolls for all parliamentary, assembly 
and council constituencies within the district.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The district election 
officer shall also perform such other functions as may be entrusted to him by 
the Election Commission and the chief electoral officer.]
 
 





</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
[<number>13B</number> Electoral 
registration officers.—
<section><number>1</number> The electoral roll 
<footcitenum>35</footcitenum>[for each 
parliamentary constituency in the State of Jammu and Kashmir or in a Union 
territory not having a Legislative Assembly] shall be prepared and revised by an 
electoral registration officer who shall be such officer of Government or of a 
local authority as the Election Commission may, in consultation with the 
Government of the State in which the constituency is situated, designate or 
nominate in this behalf.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An electoral 
registration officer may, subject to any prescribed restrictions, employ such 
persons as he thinks fit for the preparation and revision of the electoral roll 
for the constituency.]
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
[<number>13C</number> Assistant 
electoral registration officers.—
<section><number>1</number> The Election Commission may appoint one 
or more persons as assistant electoral registration officers to assist any 
electoral registration officer in the performance of his functions.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every assistant 
electoral registration officer shall, subject to the control of the electoral 
registration officer, be competent to perform all or any of the functions of the 
electoral registration officer.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
[<footcitenum>36</footcitenum>[<number>13CC</number> Chief 
Electoral Officers, District Election Officers, etc., deemed to be on deputation 
to Election Commission.—The officers referred to in this Part and any other 
officer or staff employed in connection with the preparation, revision and 
correction of the electoral rolls for, and the conduct of, all elections shall 
be deemed to be on deputation to the Election Commission for the period during 
which they are so employed and such officers and staff shall, during that 
period, be subject to the control, superintendence and discipline of the 
Election Commission.]]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
*[1[<number>13D</number> 
Electoral rolls for parliamentary constituencies.—
<section><number>1</number> The electoral roll for 
every parliamentary constituency, other than a parliamentary constituency in the 
State of Jammu and Kashmir or in a Union territory not having a Legislative 
Assembly, shall consist of the electoral rolls for all the assembly 
constituencies comprised within that parliamentary constituency; and it shall 
not be necessary to prepare or revise separately the electoral roll for any such 
parliamentary constituency:
 
Provided that for the 
period referred to in clause (2) of article 371A, it shall be necessary to 
prepare and revise separately the electoral roll for that part of the 
parliamentary constituency of Nagaland which comprises the Tuensang district and 
the provisions of Part III shall apply in relation to the preparation and 
revision of the electoral roll of the said part as they apply in relation to an 
assembly constituency.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The provisions of Part 
III shall apply in relation to every parliamentary constituency in the State of 
Jammu and Kashmir or in a Union territory not having a Legislative Assembly as 
they apply in relation to an assembly constituency.]]
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>14</number> 
Definitions.—In this Part, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  
“constituency” means an Assembly constituency 

2[***];
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  “qualifying 
date”, in relation to the preparation or revision of every electoral roll under 
this Part, means 

3[the 1st day of 
January] of the year in which it is so prepared or revised:]
 

4[Provided that 
“qualifying date”, in relation to the preparation or revision of every electoral 
roll under this Part in the year 1989, shall be the 1st day of April, 1989.]
 
 






</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Electoral roll for 
every constituency.—For 
every constituency there shall be an electoral roll which shall be prepared in 
accordance with the provisions of this Act under the superintendence, direction 
and control of the Election Commission.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Disqualifications 
for registration in an electoral roll.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A person shall be disqualified for registration in an electoral roll if he—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  is not a 
citizen of India; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  is of unsound 
mind and stands so declared by a competent court; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number> is for the 
time being disqualified from voting under the provisions of any law relating to 
corrupt 

1[***] practices 
and other offenses in connection with elections.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The name of any person 
who becomes so disqualified after registration shall forthwith be struck off the 
electoral roll in which it is included:
 

2[Provided that the 
name of any person struck off the electoral roll of a constituency by reason of 
a disqualification under clause (c) of sub-section (1) shall forthwith be 
reinstated in that roll if such disqualification is, during the period such roll 
is in force, removed under any law authorizing such removal.]
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> No person to be 
registered in more than one constituency.—No 
person shall be entitled to be registered in the electoral roll for more than 
one constituency 

1[***].
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> No person to be 
registered more than once in any constituency.—No 
person shall be entitled to be registered in the electoral roll for any 
constituency more than once.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>19</number> Conditions 
of registration.—Subject to the foregoing provisions of this Part, every 
person who—
 <section>
        <number>a</number> is not less 
than 

2[eighteen years] 
of age on the qualifying date, and
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number> is ordinarily 
resident in a constituency,
 
shall be entitled to be 
registered in the electoral roll for that constituency.]
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Meaning of 
“ordinarily resident”.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
A person shall not be deemed to be ordinarily resident in a constituency on the 
ground only that he owns, or is in possession of, a dwelling house therein.
 </section><section>
<number>1A</number> A person absenting 
himself temporarily from his place of ordinary residence shall not by reason 
thereof cease to be ordinarily resident therein.
 </section><section>
<number>1B</number> A member of 
Parliament or of the Legislature of a State shall not during the term of his 
office cease to be ordinarily resident in the constituency in the electoral roll 
of which he is registered as an elector at the time of his election as such 
member, by reason of his absence from that constituency in connection with his 
duties as such member.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A person who is a 
patient in any establishment maintained wholly or mainly for the reception and 
treatment of persons suffering from mental illness or mental defectiveness, or 
who is detained in prison or other legal custody at any place, shall not by 
reason thereof be deemed to be ordinarily resident therein.
 

2[(3) Any person 
having a service qualification shall be deemed to be ordinarily resident on any 
date in the constituency in which, but for his having such service 
qualification, he would have been ordinarily resident on that date.]
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Any person holding any 
office in India declared by the President3 in 
consultation with the Election Commission to be an office to which the 
provisions of this sub-section apply, 

4[***] shall be 
deemed to be ordinarily resident 

5[***] on any date 
in the constituency in which, but for the holding of any such office 

6[***], he would 
have been ordinarily resident 

7[***] on that 
date.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The statement of any 
such person as is referred to in sub-section (3) or sub-section (4) made in the 
prescribed form and verified in the prescribed manner, that 

8[but for his 
having the service qualification] or but for his holding any such office 

9[***] as is 
referred to in sub-section (4) he would have been ordinarily resident in a 
specified place 

10[***] on any 
date, shall, in the absence of evidence to the contrary, be 

8[accepted as 
correct].
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The wife of any such 
person as is referred to in sub-section (3) or sub-section (4) shall if she be 
ordinarily residing with such person 

10[***] be deemed 
to be ordinarily resident on 

11[***] in the 
constituency specified by such person under sub-section (5).
 

12[(7) If in any 
case a question arises as to where a person is ordinarily resident at any 
relevant time, the question shall be determined with reference to all the facts 
of the case and to such rules as may be made in this behalf by the Central 
Government in consultation with the Election Commission.]
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> In sub-sections (3) 
and (5) “service qualification” means—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number> being a member 
of the armed forces of the Union; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number> being a member 
of a force to which the provisions of the Army Act, 1950 (46 of 1950), have been 
made applicable whether with or without modifications; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number> being a member 
of an armed police force of a State, who is serving outside that State; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  being a 
person who is employed under the Government of India, in a post outside India.
 
 



























</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Meaning of 
“ordinarily resident”.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
A person shall not be deemed to be ordinarily resident in a constituency on the 
ground only that he owns, or is in possession of, a dwelling house therein.
 </section><section>
<number>1A</number> A person absenting 
himself temporarily from his place of ordinary residence shall not by reason 
thereof cease to be ordinarily resident therein.
 </section><section>
<number>1B</number> A member of 
Parliament or of the Legislature of a State shall not during the term of his 
office cease to be ordinarily resident in the constituency in the electoral roll 
of which he is registered as an elector at the time of his election as such 
member, by reason of his absence from that constituency in connection with his 
duties as such member.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A person who is a 
patient in any establishment maintained wholly or mainly for the reception and 
treatment of persons suffering from mental illness or mental defectiveness, or 
who is detained in prison or other legal custody at any place, shall not by 
reason thereof be deemed to be ordinarily resident therein.
 

2[(3) Any person 
having a service qualification shall be deemed to be ordinarily resident on any 
date in the constituency in which, but for his having such service 
qualification, he would have been ordinarily resident on that date.]
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Any person holding any 
office in India declared by the President3 in 
consultation with the Election Commission to be an office to which the 
provisions of this sub-section apply, 

4[***] shall be 
deemed to be ordinarily resident 

5[***] on any date 
in the constituency in which, but for the holding of any such office 

6[***], he would 
have been ordinarily resident 

7[***] on that 
date.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The statement of any 
such person as is referred to in sub-section (3) or sub-section (4) made in the 
prescribed form and verified in the prescribed manner, that 

8[but for his 
having the service qualification] or but for his holding any such office 

9[***] as is 
referred to in sub-section (4) he would have been ordinarily resident in a 
specified place 

10[***] on any 
date, shall, in the absence of evidence to the contrary, be 

8[accepted as 
correct].
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The wife of any such 
person as is referred to in sub-section (3) or sub-section (4) shall if she be 
ordinarily residing with such person 

10[***] be deemed 
to be ordinarily resident on 

11[***] in the 
constituency specified by such person under sub-section (5).
 

12[(7) If in any 
case a question arises as to where a person is ordinarily resident at any 
relevant time, the question shall be determined with reference to all the facts 
of the case and to such rules as may be made in this behalf by the Central 
Government in consultation with the Election Commission.]
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> In sub-sections (3) 
and (5) “service qualification” means—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number> being a member 
of the armed forces of the Union; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number> being a member 
of a force to which the provisions of the Army Act, 1950 (46 of 1950), have been 
made applicable whether with or without modifications; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number> being a member 
of an armed police force of a State, who is serving outside that State; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  being a 
person who is employed under the Government of India, in a post outside India.
 
 



























</subsection></section></article> 

 
 <article><title><footcitenum>69</footcitenum>[<number>20A</number> Special provisions for citizens of India residing outside India. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, every citizen of India,— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> whose name is not included in the electoral roll; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> who has not acquired the citizenship of any other country; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> who is absenting from his place of ordinary residence in India owing to his employment, education or otherwise outside India (whether temporarily or not), shall be entitled to have his name registered in the electoral roll in the constituency in which his place of residence in India as mentioned in his passport is located. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The time within which the name of persons referred to in sub-section (1) shall be registered in the electoral roll and the manner and procedure for registering of a person in the electoral roll under sub-section (1) shall be such as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every person registered under this section shall, if otherwise eligible to exercise his franchise, be allowed to vote at an election in the constituency.] 


</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>21</number> 
Preparation and revision of electoral rolls.—
<section><number>1</number> The electoral roll for each 
constituency shall be prepared in the prescribed manner by reference to the 
qualifying date and shall come into force immediately upon its final publication 
in accordance with the rules made under this Act.
 

2[(2) The said 
electoral roll—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number> shall, unless 
otherwise directed by the Election Commission for reasons to be recorded in 
writing, be revised in the prescribed manner by reference to the qualifying 
date—
 <subsubsection>
              <number>i</number> before 
each general election to the House of the People or to the Legislative Assembly 
of a State; and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>ii</number> before 
each bye-election to fill a casual vacancy in a seat allotted to the 
constituency; and
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number> shall be 
revised in any year in the prescribed manner by reference to the qualifying date 
if such revision has been directed by the Election Commission:
 
Provided that if the 
electoral roll is not revised as aforesaid, the validity or continued operation 
of the said electoral roll shall not thereby be affected.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-section (2), the Election Commission may at any time, 
for reasons to be recorded, direct a special revision of the electoral roll for 
any constituency or part of a constituency in such manner as it may think fit:
 
Provided that subject to 
the other provisions of this Act, the electoral roll for the constituency, as in 
force at the time of the issue of any such direction, shall continue to be in 
force until the completion of the special revision so directed.]
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 <article><footcitenum>72</footcitenum><title>[<number>22</number> Correction of entries in electoral rolls. </title>—If the electoral registration officer for a constituency, on application made to him or on his own motion, is satisfied after such inquiry as he thinks fit, that any entry in the electoral roll of the constituency— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> is erroneous or defective in any particular, 
 </section><section><number>b</number> should be transposed to another place in the roll on the ground that the person concerned has changed his place of ordinary residence within the constituency, or 
 </section><section><number>c</number> should be detected on the ground that the person concerned is dead or has ceased to be ordinarily resident in the constituency or is otherwise not entitled to be registered in that roll, the electoral registration officer shall, subject to such general or special direction, if any, as may be given by the Election Commission in this behalf, amend, transpose or delete the entry <footcitenum>73</footcitenum>[ after proper verification of facts in such manner as may be prescribed] : 
</section>
 Provided that before taking any action on any ground under clause 
<section><number>a</number> or clause (b) or any action under clause (c) on the ground that the person concerned has ceased to be ordinarily resident in the constituency or that he is otherwise not entitled to be registered in the electoral roll of that constituency, the electoral registration officer shall give the person concerned a reasonable opportunity of being heard in respect of the action proposed to be taken in relation to him. <footcitenum>74</footcitenum>[after proper verification of facts in such manner as may be prescribed]. 




</section></article> 

 
 <article><footcitenum>75</footcitenum><title>[<number>23</number> Inclusion of names in electoral rolls. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Any person whose name is not included in the electoral roll of a constituency may apply to the electoral registration officer for the inclusion of his name in that roll. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The electoral registration officer shall, if satisfied that the applicant is entitled to be registered in the electoral roll, direct his name to be included therein <footcitenum>76</footcitenum><title></title>[after proper verification of facts in such manner as may be prescribed]: 
 Provided that if the applicant is registered in the electoral roll of any other constituency, the electoral registration officer shall inform the electoral registration officer of that other constituency and that officer shall, on receipt of the information, strike off the applicant's name from that roll <footcitenum>77</footcitenum><title></title>[after proper verification of facts in such manner as may be prescribed]. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> No amendment, transposition or deletion of any entry shall be made under section 22 and no direction for the inclusion of a name in the electoral roll of a constituency shall be given under this section, after the last date for making nominations for an election in that constituency or in the parliamentary constituency within which that constituency is comprised and before the completion of that election.] 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>24</number> Appeals.—An 
appeal shall lie within such time and in such manner as may be prescribed—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  to the chief 
electoral officer, from any order of the electoral registration officer under 
section 22 or section 23, 

2[***]
 

3[***]]
 
 





</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>25</number> Fee for 
applications and appeals.—Every application under section 22 or section 23 
and every appeal under section 24 shall be accompanied by the prescribed fee 
which shall, in no case, be refunded.]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>25A</number> 
Conditions of registration as elector in Sangha constituency in Sikkim.—Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sections 15 and 19, for the Sangha constituency in the 
State of Sikkim, only the Sanghas belonging to monasteries, recognised for the 
purpose of the elections held in Sikkim in April, 1974, for forming the Assembly 
for Sikkim, shall be entitled to be registered in the electoral roll, and the 
said electoral roll shall, subject to the provisions of sections 21 to 25, be 
prepared or revised in such manner as may be directed by the Election 
Commission, in consultation with the Government of Sikkim.]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Preparation of 
electoral rolls for Assembly constituencies.—[Rep. 
by the Representation of the People (Amendment) Act, 1956 (2 of 1956), 
sec. 17 (w.e.f. 
1-3-1956).]
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Preparation of 
electoral roll for Council constituencies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In this section, “local authorities’ constituency”, “graduates’ constituency” 
and “teachers’ constituency” mean a constituency for the purpose of elections to 
a Legislative Council under sub-clause 
<subsection><number>a</number>, sub-clause (b) and sub-clause (c), 
respectively, of clause (3) of article 171.
 

1[(2) For the 
purpose of elections to the Legislative Council of a State in any local 
authorities’ constituency—
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>a</number> the electorate 
shall consist of members of such local authorities exercising jurisdiction in 
any place or area within the limits of that constituency as are specified in 
relation to that State in the Fourth Schedule;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number> every member 
of each such local authority within a local authorities’ constituency shall be 
entitled to be registered in the electoral roll for that constituency;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number> the electoral 
registration officer for every local authorities’ constituency shall maintain in 
his office in the prescribed manner and form the electoral roll for that 
constituency corrected up-to-date;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number> in order to 
enable the electoral registration officer to maintain the electoral roll 
corrected up-to-date, the chief executive officer of every local authority (by 
whatever designation such officer may be known) shall immediately inform the 
electoral registration officer about every change in the membership of that 
local authority; and the electoral registration officer shall, on receipt of the 
information, strike off from the electoral roll the names of persons who have 
ceased to be, and include therein the names of persons who have become, members 
of that local authority; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>e</number> the provisions 
of sections 15, 16, 18, 22 and 23 shall apply in relation to local authorities’ 
constituencies as they apply in relation to assembly constituencies.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> For the purpose of 
elections to the Legislative Council of a State in the graduates’ constituencies 
and the teachers’ constituencies, the State Government concerned may, with the 
concurrence of the Election Commission, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
specify—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number> the 
qualifications which shall be deemed to be equivalent to that of a graduate of a 
university in the territory of India, and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number> the 
educational institutions within the State not lower in standard than that of a 
secondary school.
 

2[(4) The 
provisions of sections 15, 16, 18, 21, 22 and 23 shall apply in relation to 
graduates’ constituencies and teachers’ constituencies as they apply in relation 
to assembly constituencies.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> Subject to the 
foregoing provisions of this section,—
 

3[***]
 

       4[(a)] every 
person who 

5[is] ordinarily 
resident in a graduates’ constituency and has, for at least three years 

6[before the 
qualifying date], been either a graduate of a university in the territory of 
India or in possession of any of the qualifications specified under clause (a) 
of sub-section (3) by the State Government concerned, shall be entitled to be 
registered in the electoral roll for that constituency; and 
 

       7[(b)] every 
person who 

8[is] ordinarily 
resident in a teachers’ constituency, and has, within the six years immediately


9[before the 
qualifying date] for a total period of at least three years, been engaged in 
teaching in any of the educational institutions specified under clause (b) of 
sub-section (3) by the State Government concerned, shall be entitled to be 
registered in the electoral roll for that constituency.
 

10[(6) For the 
purposes of sub-sections (4) and (5) the qualifying date shall be the Ist day of 
November of the year in which the preparation or revision of the electoral roll 
is commenced.]
 
 












</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
*[<number>27A</number> Constitution of 
electoral colleges for the filling of seats in the Council of States allotted to 
Union territories.—
<section><number>1</number> 

1[For the purpose 
of filling any seat] or seats in the Council of States allotted to any 

2[Union territory]


3[***] in the 
Fourth Schedule to the Constitution there shall be an electoral college for


4[each such 
territory] 

5[***]].
 

6[***]
 

7[***]
 

8[(3) The electoral 
college for the Union territory of Delhi shall consist of the elected members of 
the Legislative Assembly constituted for that territory under the Government of 
National Capital Territory of Delhi Act, 1991 (1 of 1992).]
 

9[(4) 

10[The electoral 
college for the Union territory of Pondicherry] shall consist of the elected 
members of the Legislative Assembly constituted for that territory under the 
Government of Union Territories Act, 1963 (20 of 1963).]
 

11[***]
 

12[***]
 
 















</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
*[<number>27B</number> Electoral 
college constituencies.—[Rep. by the Territorial Council Act,
1956 (103 of 1956), sec. 65. (w.e.f. 
1-1-1957).]]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
*[<number>27C</number> Delimitation of 
electoral college constituencies.—[Rep. by the Territorial Council 
Act, 1956 (103 of 1956), sec. 65 (w.e.f. 
1-1-1957).]]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
*[<number>27D</number> Power to alter 
or amend orders.—[Rep. by the Territorial Council Act, 1956 
(103 of 1956), sec. 65 (w.e.f. 
1-1-1957).]]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
*[<number>27E</number> Procedure as to 
orders delimiting constituencies.—[Rep. by the Representation of 
the People (Amendment) Act, 1956 (2 of 1956), sec. 21 
(w.e.f. 
1-3-1956).]]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
*[<number>27F</number> Electoral 
rolls for Council of States constituencies.—[Rep. by the 
Representation of the People (Amendment) Act, 1956 (2 of 1956) sec.
22 (w.e.f. 
1-3-1956).]]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
*[<number>27G</number> Termination of 
membership of electoral college for certain disqualifications.—If a person 
who is a member of an electoral college becomes subject to any disqualification 
for membership of Parliament under the provisions of any law relating to corrupt 
and illegal practices and other offences in connection with elections to 
Parliament, he shall thereupon cease to be such member of the electoral 
college.]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
*[<number>27H</number> Manner of 
filling of seats in the Council of States allotted to Union territories.—1[***] 
the seat or seats in the Council of States allotted to any 

2[Union territory]


3[***] in the 
Fourth Schedule to the Constitution shall be filled by a person or persons 
elected by the members of the electoral college for 

4[that territory]


5[***] in 
accordance with the system of proportional representation by means of the single 
transferable vote:
 

6[Provided that the 
person who immediately before the commencement of the Constitution (Seventh 
Amendment) Act, 1956, is filling the seat allotted to the Part C States of 
Manipur and Tripura shall, as from such commencement, be deemed to have been 
duly elected to fill the seat allotted to the Union territory of Tripura.]]
 
 









</article> 

 
 
 <article>
*[<number>27-I</number> Special 
provisions for the filling of the seats in the Council of States allotted to the 
States of Ajmer and Coorg and the States of Manipur and Tripura.—[Rep. 
by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, 1956 (w.e.f. 1-11-1956).]]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
*[<number>27J</number> Powers of 
electoral colleges to elect notwithstanding vacancies therein.—No election 
by the members of an electoral college 

1[***] under this 
Act shall be called in question on the ground merely of the existence of any 
vacancy in the membership of such college 

1[***].]
 
 




</article> 

 
 
 <article>
*[<number>27K</number> Electoral 
colleges for certain States for which Legislative Assemblies have been 
constituted.—[Rep. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, 
1956 (w.e.f. 
1-11-1956).]]
 
 



</article> 

 
 <article><title><number>28</number> Power to make rules. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government may, after consulting the Election Commission, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules<footcitenum>111</footcitenum>  for carrying out the purposes of this Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:— 
 
 <subsection><footcitenum>112</footcitenum>[<number>a</number> the determination of ordinary residence under sub-section (7) of section 20; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>aa</number> the particulars to be entered in the electoral rolls;] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the preliminary publication of electoral rolls <footcitenum>113</footcitenum>[***]; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the manner in which and the time within which claims and objections as to entries in electoral rolls may be preferred; 
 <footcitenum>114</footcitenum>[***] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> the manner in which notices of claims or objections shall be published; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> the place, date and time at which claims or objections shall be heard and the manner in which claims or objections shall be heard and disposed of; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> the final publication of electoral rolls; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>115</footcitenum>[<number>h</number> the revision and correction of electoral rolls and inclusion of names therein;] 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>116</footcitenum>[<number>hh</number> the procedure for proper verification of facts for amending, transposing or deleting any entry in the electoral rolls, under section 22; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>hhh</number> the procedure for proper verification of facts for inclusion of or striking off, names in the electoral rolls, under sub-section (2) of section 23;”. 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> any other matter required to be prescribed by this Act. 
</subsubsection></subsection>
 </section><section><footcitenum>117</footcitenum>[<number>3</number> Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.] 








</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>29</number> Staff of 
local authorities to be made available.—Every local authority in a State 
shall, when so requested by the chief electoral officer of the State, make 
available to any electoral registration officer such staff as may be necessary 
for the performance of any duties in connection with the preparation and 
revision of electoral rolls.]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>30</number> Jurisdiction of 
civil courts barred.—No 
civil court shall have jurisdiction—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  to entertain 
or adjudicate upon any question whether any person is or is not entitled to be 
registered in an electoral roll for a constituency; or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  to question 
the legality of any action taken by or under the authority of an electoral 
registration officer, or of any decision given by any authority appointed under 
this Act for the revision of any such roll.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>31</number> Making 
false declarations.—If any person makes in connection with—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  the 
preparation, revision or correction of an electoral roll, or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  the inclusion 
or exclusion of any entry in or from an electoral roll, 
 
a statement or declaration 
in writing which is false and which he either knows or believes to be false or 
does not believe to be true, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term 
which may extend to one year, or with fine, or with both.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>32</number> Breach of 
official duty in connection with the preparation, etc., of electoral rolls.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If any electoral registration officer, assistant electoral registration officer 
or other person required by or under this Act to perform any official duty in 
connection with preparation, revision or correction of an electoral roll or the 
inclusion or exclusion of any entry in or from that roll, is without reasonable 
cause, guilty of any act or omission in breach of such official duty, he shall 
be punishable 

2[with imprisonment 
for a term which shall not be less than three months but which may extend to two 
years and with fine].
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No suit or other legal 
proceeding shall lie against any such officer or other person for damages in 
respect of any such act or omission as aforesaid.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No court shall take 
cognizance of any offence punishable under sub-section (1) unless there is a 
complaint made by order of, or under authority from, the Election Commission or 
the chief electoral officer of the State concerned.]
 
 






</section></article><form>
 

THE 
REPRESENTATION OF THE PEOPLE ACT, 1950 
 





 




THE FOURTH SCHEDULE
 


[See section 27(2)]
 



Local Authorities for purposes of Elections to Legislative Councils
 



1[2[Andhra 
Pradesh
 


1. Municipal Corporations.
 


2. Municipalties.
 


3. Nagar Panchayats.
 


4. Cantonment Boards.
 


5. Zila Praja Parishads.
 


6. Mandal Praja Parishads.]
 



3[Bihar
 


1. Nagar Parishads.
 


2. Cantonment Boards.

 


3. Nagar Panchayats. 

 


4. Zila Parishads. 

 


5. Panchayat Samitis.
 


6. Nagar Nigams 
(Corporations).
 


7. Gram Panchayats.]
 



4[MADHYA 
PRADESH
 



5[1.Municipalities. 
                                                                4. Cantonment 
Boards.
 


2. Janapada Sabhas. 
                                                          5. Notified Area 
Committees.
 


3. Mandal Panchayats. 
                                                        6. Town Area 
Committees.]]
 



6[***]
 



7[MAHARASHTRA
 



8[1. Municipalities.
 


2. Cantonment Boards.
 



9[***]
 


4. Zila Parishad.]]
 



10[11[KARNATAKA]
 



12[1. City Municipal 
Corporations. 
 


2. City Municipal Councils.

 


3. Town Municipal Councils.
 


4. Town Panchayats.
 


5. Zilla Panchayats.
 


6. Taluk Panchayats.
 


7. Grama Panchayats.
 


8. Cantonment Boards.]]
 



UTTAR PRADESH
 



12[1. Municipal 
Corporations.
 


2. Municipal Councils.
 


3. Zila Panchayats.
 


4. Nagar Panchayats.
 


5. Kshettra Panchayats.
 


6. Cantonment Boards.]
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  The heading “Andhra 
Pradesh” and the entries relating thereto omitted by Act 34 of 1985, sec. 
5 (w.e.f. 1-6-1985).
 


   2.  Ins. by Act 1 of 2006, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 
11-1-2006).
 


   3.  Subs. by Act 6 of 2003, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 
6-1-2003) for— 
 



“BIHAR
 


        1. Municipalities. 
2. District Boards. 3. Cantonment Boards. 4. Notified Area Committees. 5. Zila 
Parishads. 6. Panchayat Samitis.”
 


   4.  Ins. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) 
Order, 1956.
 


   5.  Subs. by Act 37 of 1957, sec. 12, for 
the former entries.
 


   6.  The heading “Tamil 
Nadu” and the entries relating thereto omitted by the Tamil Nadu 
Legislative Council (Abolition) Act, 1986 (40 of 1986), sec. 5 
(w.e.f.1-11-1986).
 


   7.  Ins. by Act 40 of 1961, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 
20-9-1961).
 


   8.  Subs. by Act 2 of 1963, sec. 2, for 
the former entries.
 


   9.  Entry “3. Town Committees.” omitted by 
Act 21 of 1989, sec. 5.
 


  10.  Ins. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) 
Order, 1956.  
 


  11.  Subs. by the Mysore 
State 
(Alteration of Name) (Adaptation of Laws on Union Subjects) Order, 1974, sec. 3 
and Sch., for “Mysore” 
(w.e.f. 1-11-1973).
 


  12.  Subs. by Act 29 of 1996, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 
13-9-1996).
 


 
 


 
</form><form>
 

THE 
REPRESENTATION OF THE PEOPLE ACT, 1950 
 


 
 


THE FIFTH SCHEDULE.—[Rep. 
by the Government of Union Territories Act, 1963 (20 of 1963), sec. 57
and the Second Schedule (w.e.f. 
1-7-1963).]
 


 
</form><form>
 

THE 
REPRESENTATION OF THE PEOPLE ACT, 1950 
 


 
 


THE SIXTH SCHEDULE.—[Rep. 
by the Representation of the People (Amendment) Act, 1956 (2 of 1956), 
sec. 27 (w.e.f. 
1-3-1956).]
 


 
 

 
</form><form>
 

THE 
REPRESENTATION OF THE PEOPLE ACT, 1950 
 


 
 


THE SEVENTH SCHEDULE.—[Rep. 
by the Representation of the People (Amendment) Act, 1956 (2 of 1956), 
sec. 27 (w.e.f. 
1-3-1956).]
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by Act 47 of 1966, sec. 2, for section 4 (w.e.f. 14-12-1966).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Sub-section (1) omitted by Act 29 of 1975, sec. 11 (w.e.f. 15-8-1975).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Subs. by Act 29 of 1975, sec. 11, for sub-section (2) (w.e.f. 15-8-1975).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Subs. by Act 10 of 2008, sec. 2, for sub-section (5) (w.e.f. 16-4-2008). Earlier sub-section (5) was substituted by Act 88 of 1976, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 2-9-1976). Sub-section (5), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Sections 7, 8 and 9 subs. by Act 47 of 1966, sec. 4, for section 7 (w.e.f. 14-12-1966). Original sections 8 and 9 were rep. by Act 2 of 1956, sec. 5 and the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, 1956, respectively.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Subs. by Act 8 of 1980, sec. 2, for certain words (w.e.f. 1-9-1979).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Subs. by Act 38 of 1992, sec. 2, for “sub-sections (1A) and (1B)” (w.e.f. 5-12-1992).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Subs. by Act 61 of 1968, sec. 4, for “forty-six”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> Subs. by Act 61 of 1968, sec. 4, for “six seats”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> Ins. by Act 8 of 1980, sec. 2 (w.r.e.f. 1-9-1979).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number> Ins. by Act 40 of 1987, sec. 2 (w.r.e.f. 22-9-1987).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number> Subs. by Act 10 of 2008, sec. 3(i), for “thirty-nine seats” (w.e.f. 16-4-2008).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number> Ins. by Act 38 of 1992, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 5-12-1992).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number> Subs. by Act 8 of 1980, sec. 2, for “in sub-section (1)” (w.r.e.f. 1-9-1979).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number> Subs. by Act 10 of 2008, sec. 3(ii), for sub-section (3) (w.e.f. 16-4-2008). Sub-section (3), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>  Ins. by Act 10 of 
1976, sec. 2 and Sch. (w.r.e.f. 9-9-1975).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number> Subs. by Act 10 of 2008, sec. 4(i), for sub-section (1) (w.e.f. 16-4-2008). Sub-section (1), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number> Ins. by Act 88 of 1976, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 2-9-1976).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number> Subs. by Act 10 of 2008, sec. 4(ii), for “as provided in sub-section (5) of section 10 of the Delimitation Act, 1972 (76 of 1972)” (w.e.f. 16-4-2008).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number> Ins. by Act 10 of 2008, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 16-4-2008).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number> Subs. by Act 10 of 2008, sec. 6 for clause (a) and (aa) (w.e.f. 16-4-2008). Clauses (a) and (aa), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number> Section 9A omitted by Act 10 of 2008, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 16-4-2008). Section 9A, before omission, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number> Section 9B omitted by Act 10 of 2008, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 16-4-2008). Section 9B, before omission, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number>  The words “or 
Rajpramukh, as the case may be” omitted by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, 
1956 (w.e.f. 1-11-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number>  Sub-section (3) ins. 
by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, 1956 (w.e.f. 1-11-1956) and omitted by 
Act 37 of 1957, sec. 12 (w.e.f. 18-9-1957).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number>  Section 12 
re-numbered as sub-section (1) of that section by Act 20 of 1960, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 
8-5-1960).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number>  The words and 
figures “section 6, section 9, or” omitted by Act 2 of 1956, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 
1-3-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>28</number>  Ins. by Act 20 of 
1960, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 8-5-1960).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>29</number>  Sub-section (1) 
omitted by Act 2 of 1956, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-3-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>30</number>  Sub-section (2) 
omitted by Act 2 of 1956, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-3-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>31</number>  The words and 
figures “section 6, section 9,” omitted by Act 2 of 1956, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 
1-3-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>32</number> Section 13A ins. by 
Act 2 of 1956, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 1-3-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>33</number>  Ins. by Act 47 of 
1966, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 14-12-1966).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>34</number>  The words “other 
than a Union territory” omitted by Act 2 of 2004, sec. 2 (w.r.e.f. 29-10-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>35</number>  Subs. by Act 47 of 
1966, sec. 6, for certain words (w.e.f. 14-12-1966).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>36</number>  Ins. by Act 1 of 
1989, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 15-3-1989).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>37</number>  Subs. by Act 47 of 
1966, sec. 7, for section 13D (w.e.f. 14-12-1966).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>38</number>  Subs. by Act 2 of 
1956, sec. 11, for section 14 (w.e.f. 1-3-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>39</number>  The words “or an 
electoral college constituency” omitted by Act 103 of 1956, sec. 65 (w.e.f. 
1-1-1957).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>40</number>  Subs. by Act 58 of 
1958, sec. 5, for “the 1st day of March” (w.e.f. 1-1-1959).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>41</number>  Ins. by Act 21 of 
1989, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 22-5-1989).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>42</number>  The words “and 
illegal” ins. by Act 73 of 1950, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 23-12-1950) and omitted by Act 
58 of 1960, sec. 3 and Sch. II (w.e.f. 26-12-1960).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>43</number>  Ins. by Act 73 of 
1950, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 23-12-1950)</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>44</number>  The words “in the 
same State” ins. by Act 2 of 1956, sec. 12 (w.e.f. 1-3-1956) and omitted by Act 
58 of 1958, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 30-12-1958).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>45</number>  Subs. by Act 58 of 
1958, sec. 7, for section 19 (w.e.f. 30-12-1958).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>46</number>  Subs. by Act 21 of 
1989, sec. 4, for “twenty-one years” (w.r.e.f. 28-3-1989).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>47</number>  Subs. by Act 58 of 
1958, sec. 8, for sub-section (1) (w.e.f. 30-12-1958).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>48</number>  Sub-section (3) 
subs. by Act 2 of 1956, sec. 14 (w.e.f. 1-3-1956) and again subs. by Act 47 of 
1966, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 14-12-1966).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>49</number>  The following 
offices have been declared by the President by Notification No. S.O. 959, dated 
the 18th April, 1960:—</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>50</number>  Certain words 
omitted by Act 47 of 1966, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 14-12-1966).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>51</number>  The words “during 
any period or” omitted by Act 2 of 1956, sec. 14 (w.e.f. 1-3-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>52</number>  The words “or 
employment” omitted by Act 47 of 1966, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 14-12-1966).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>53</number>  The words “during 
that period or” omitted by Act 2 of 1956, sec. 14 (w.e.f. 1-3-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>54</number>  Subs. by Act 47 of 
1966, sec. 8, for certain words (w.e.f. 14-12-1966).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>55</number>  Certain words 
omitted by Act 47 of 1966, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 14-12-1966).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>56</number>  The words “during 
any period” omitted by Act 2 of 1956, sec. 14 (w.e.f. 1-3-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>57</number>  The words “during 
that period” omitted by Act 2 of 1956 sec. 14 (w.e.f. 1-3-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>58</number>  Subs. by Act 58 of 
1958, sec. 8, for sub-section (1) (w.e.f. 30-12-1958).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>59</number>  Sub-section (3) 
subs. by Act 2 of 1956, sec. 14 (w.e.f. 1-3-1956) and again subs. by Act 47 of 
1966, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 14-12-1966).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>60</number>  The following 
offices have been declared by the President by Notification No. S.O. 959, dated 
the 18th April, 1960:—</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>61</number>  Certain words 
omitted by Act 47 of 1966, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 14-12-1966).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>62</number>  The words “during 
any period or” omitted by Act 2 of 1956, sec. 14 (w.e.f. 1-3-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>63</number>  The words “or 
employment” omitted by Act 47 of 1966, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 14-12-1966).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>64</number>  The words “during 
that period or” omitted by Act 2 of 1956, sec. 14 (w.e.f. 1-3-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>65</number>  Subs. by Act 47 of 
1966, sec. 8, for certain words (w.e.f. 14-12-1966).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>66</number>  Certain words 
omitted by Act 47 of 1966, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 14-12-1966).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>67</number>  The words “during 
any period” omitted by Act 2 of 1956, sec. 14 (w.e.f. 1-3-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>68</number>  The words “during 
that period” omitted by Act 2 of 1956 sec. 14 (w.e.f. 1-3-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>69</number> Ins. by Act 36 of 2010, sec. 2.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>70</number>  Subs. by Act 2 of 
1956, sec. 15, for section 21 (w.e.f. 1-3-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>71</number>  Subs. by Act 47 of 
1966, sec. 9, for sub-section (2) (w.e.f. 14-12-1966).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>72</number> Subs. by Act 58 of 1958, sec. 9, for section 22 (w.e.f. 30-12-1958). Earlier section 22 was substituted by Act 2 of 1956, sec. 15 (w.e.f. 1-3-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>73</number> Ins. by Act 36 of 2010, sec. 3(a).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>74</number> Ins. by Act 36 of 2010, sec. 3(b).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>75</number> Subs. by Act 58 of 1958, sec. 9, for section 22 (w.e.f. 30-12-1958). Earlier section 22 was substituted by Act 2 of 1956, sec. 15 (w.e.f. 1-3-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>76</number> Ins. by Act 36 of 2010, sec. 3(a).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>77</number> Ins. by Act 36 of 2010, sec. 3(b).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>78</number>  Ins. by Act 40 of 
1961, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 20-9-1961). Earlier section 24 (along with sections 21, 22, 
23 and 25) were subs. by sections 21 to 23 by Act 2 of 1956, sec. 15 (w.e.f. 
1-3-1956) and again ins. by Act 60 of 1956, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 25-9-1956) and was 
omitted by Act 58 of 1958, sec. 10.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>79</number>  The word “and” 
omitted by Act 47 of 1966, sec. 11 (w.e.f. 14-12-1966).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>80</number>  Clause (b) omitted 
by Act 47 of 1966, sec. 11 (w.e.f. 14-12-1966).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>81</number>  Ins. by Act 40 of 
1961, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 20-9-1961). Earlier section 25 (along with sections 21, 22, 
23 and 24) were subs. by sections 21 to 23 by Act 2 of 1956) sec. 15 (w.e.f. 
1-3-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>82</number>  Ins. by Act 10 of 
1976, sec. 2 and Sch. (w.e.f. 9-9-1975).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>83</number>  Subs. by Act 2 of 
1956, sec. 18, for sub-section (2) (w.e.f. 1-3-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>84</number>  Subs. by Act 2 of 
1956, sec. 18, for sub-section (4) (w.e.f. 1-3-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>85</number>  Clause (a) omitted 
by Act 2 of 1956, sec. 18 (w.e.f. 1-3-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>86</number>  Clause (b) 
re-lettered as clause (a) by Act 2 of 1956, sec. 18 (w.e.f. 1-3-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>87</number>  Subs. by Act 40 of 
1961, sec. 4, for “on the qualifying date was” (w.e.f. 20-9-1961).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>88</number>  Subs. by Act 40 of 
1961, sec. 4, for “before that date” (w.e.f. 20-9-1961).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>89</number>  Clause (c) 
re-lettered as clause (b) by Act 2 of 1956, sec. 18 (w.e.f. 1-3-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>90</number>  Subs. by Act 40 of 
1961, sec. 4, for “on the qualifying date was” (w.e.f. 20-9-1961).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>91</number>  Subs. by Act 40 of 
1961, sec. 4, for “before that date” (w.e.f. 20-9-1961).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>92</number>  Sub-section (6) 
subs. by Act 2 of 1956 (w.e.f. 1-3-1956) and again subs. by Act 40 of 1961, sec. 
4 (w.e.f. 20-9-1961).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>93</number>  Subs. by Act 29 of 
1975, sec. 11, for certain words (w.e.f. 15-8-1975).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>94</number>  Subs. by the 
Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, 1956, for “Part C States” (w.e.f. 1-11-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>95</number>  The words “or group 
of such States” omitted by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, 1956 (w.e.f. 
1-11-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>96</number>  Subs. by the 
Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, 1956, for “each such State” (w.e.f. 
1-11-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>97</number>  The words “or group 
of States” omitted by Act 2 of 1956, sec. 19 (w.e.f. 1-3-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>98</number>  Proviso omitted by 
Act 2 of 1956, sec. 19 (w.e.f. 1-3-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>99</number>  Sub-section (2) 
omitted by Act 20 of 1963, sec. 57 and Sch. II.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>100</number>  Sub-section (3) 
subs. by Act 19 of 1966, sec. 35 (w.e.f. 7-9-1966) and again subs. by Act 1 of 
1992, sec. 55 (w.e.f. 2-10-1993).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>101</number>  Subs. by Act 20 of 
1963, sec. 57 and Sch. II, for sub-section (4).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>102</number>  Subs. by Act 69 of 
1986, sec. 7, for certain words (w.e.f. 20-2-1987).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>103</number>  Subs-section (5) 
omitted by Act 29 of 1975, sec. 11 (w.e.f. 15-8-1975).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>104</number>  This words “save as 
otherwise provided in section 27-I” omitted by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) 
Order, 1956 (w.e.f. 1-11-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>105</number>  Subs. by the 
Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, 1956, for “Part C States” (w.e.f. 1-11-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>106</number>  The words “or group 
of such States” omitted by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, 1956 (w.e.f. 
1-11-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>107</number>  Subs., by the 
Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, 1956, for “such State” (w.e.f. 1-11-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>108</number>  The words “or group 
of States” omitted by Act 2 of 1956. sec. 23 (w.e.f. 1-3-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>109</number>  Ins. by the 
Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, 1956 (w.e.f. 1-11-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>110</number>  The words “or the 
elected members of the Coorg Legislative Council” omitted by Act 49 of 1951, 
sec. 44 and Sch. V (w.e.f. 6-9-1951).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>111</number>  See   the Registration of Electors Rules, 1960.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>112</number> Subs. by Act 47 of 1966, sec. 12, for clause (a) (w.e.f. 14-12-1966).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>113</number> The words “in the constituencies to which they relate” omitted by Act 73 of 1950, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 23-12-1950).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>114</number> Clause (d) omitted by Act 20 of 1960, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 8-5-1960).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>115</number> Subs. by Act 2 of 1956, sec. 24, for clause (h) (w.e.f. 1-3-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>116</number> Ins. by Act 36 of 2010, sec. 5.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>117</number> Subs. by Act 88 of 1976, sec. 6, for sub-section (3) (w.e.f. 2-9-1976).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>118</number>  Subs. by Act 2 of 
1956, sec. 25, for section 29 (w.e.f. 1-3-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>119</number>  Section 31 ins. by 
Act 58 of 1958, sec. 11 (w.e.f. 30-12-1958) and subs. by Act 20 of 1960, sec. 4 
(w.e.f. 8-5-1960).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>120</number>  Ins. by Act 58 of 
1958, sec. 11 (w.e.f. 30-12-1958).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>121</number>  Subs. by Act 21 of 
1996, sec. 2, for “with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees” (w.e.f. 
1-8-1996).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>