<act><title>


the reserve bank of India act, 1934</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934. 
 


    1[(2) It extends to 
    the whole of India 

    2[3[***]].] 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> This 
    section shall come into force at once, and the remaining provisions of this 
    Act shall come into force on such date or dates4 as 
    the 

    5[Central Government] 
    may, by notification in the Gazette of India, appoint.  
 
 
 
 









 



</section></article> 
 The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,—
 
   1[***]
 
    2[(aii)]  
“the Bank” means the Reserve Bank of India constituted by this Act;
 
   3[(aiii)]  
“Bank for International Settlements” means by body corporate established with 
the said name under the law of Swit­zerland in pursuance of an agreement dated 
the 20th January, 1930, signed at the Hague;]
 <section>       <number>b</number>  “the Central Board” means the Central Board of 
Directors of the Bank;
 
   4[***]
 
5[6[(bvi)] 
   “Deposit Insurance Corporation” means the Deposit Insurance Corporation 
established under section 3 of the Deposit Insurance Corporation Act, 1961 (47 
of 1961);]
 
7[8[***]
 
   9[***]
 
10[(bviiia)] 
  “Exim Bank” means the Export-Import Bank of India established under the 
Export-Import Bank of India Act, 1981;]
 
  11[(bix)  
“foreign currency” and “foreign exchange’ have the meanings respectively 
assigned to them in the Foreign Exchange Regulation Act, 1973(46 of 1973);
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  “Industrial Finance Corporation” means the 
Industrial Finance Corporation of India established under the Industrial Finance 
Corporation Act, 1948 (15 of 1948);]
 
   12[(ca)  
“International Development Association” means the “Asso­ciation” referred to in 
the International Development Association (Status, Immunities and Privileges) 
Act, 1960 (32 of 1960);
 </section><section>      <number>cb</number>  “International Finance Corporation” means the 
“Corporation” referred to in the International Finance Corporation (Status, 
Immunities and Privileges) Act, 1958 (42 of 1958);
 </section><section>      <number>cc</number>  “International Monetary Fund” and “International 
Bank for Reconstruction and Development” means respectively the “International 
Fund” and the “International Bank”, referred to in the International Monetary 
Fund and Bank Act, 1945;]
 
  13[ccc)  
“National Bank” means the National Bank for Agriculture and Rural Development 
established under section 3 of the National Bank for Agriculture and Rural 
Development Act, 1981 (61 of 1981);]
 
14[cccc)  
“National Housing Bank” means the National Housing Bank established under 
section 3 of the National Housing Bank Act, 1987;]
 
15[***]
 
   16[(cv)  
“Reconstruction Bank” means the Industrial Reconstruction Bank of India 
established under section 3 of the Industrial Reconstruction Bank of India Act, 
1984;]
 </section><section>       <number>d</number> “rupee coin” means
17[***] 
rupees which are legal tender
18[in
19[India]] 
under the provisions of the Indian Coinage Act, 1906 (3 of 1906);
20[***]
 </section><section>       <number>e</number> “scheduled bank” means a bank included in the 
Second Schedule;
 
    21[(el) 
“Small Industries Bank” means the Small Industries Devel­opment Bank of India 
established under section 3 of the Small Industries Development Bank of India 
Act, 1989;
 
   22[(ea) 
“Sponsor Bank” means a Sponsor Bank as defined in the Regional Rural Banks Act, 
1976;]
 
23[24[(eb)] 
“State Bank” means the State Bank of India constitut­ed under the State Bank of 
India Act, 1955 (23 of 1955);]
 
25[***]
 
     26[(fi) 
“State Financial Corporation” means any State Financial Corporation established 
under the State Financial Corporations Act, 1951 (63 of 1951);]
 
     27[(g) 
“Unit Trust” means the Unit Trust of India established under section 3 of the 
Unit Trust of India Act, 1963 (52 of 1963);]
 
     28[(h)  
“agricultural operations”, “central co-operative bank”, “co-operative society”, 
“crops”, “marketing of corps”, “piscicul­ture”, “regional rural bank” and “State 
co-operative bank” shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the 
National Bank for Agriculture and Rural Development Act, 1981;
 <subsection>        <number>i</number>  “co-operative bank”, “co-operative credit 
society”, “direc­tor”, “primary agricultural credit society”, “primary 
co-operative bank” and “primary credit society” shall have the meanings 
respectively assigned to them in Part V of the Banking Regulation Act, 1949 (10 
of 1949).]
  






























</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Establishment and incorporation of Reserve Bank .—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A bank to be called the Reserve Bank of India shall be constituted for the 
    purposes of taking over the management of the currency from the 


    1[Central Government] 
    and of carrying on the business of banking in accordance with the provisions 
    of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Bank 
    shall be a body corporate by the name of the Reserve Bank of India, having 
    perpetual succession and a common seal, and shall by the said name sue and 
    be sued.
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>4</number> Capital of the 
    Bank.—The 
    capital of the Bank shall be five crores of rupees.]
  





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Increase and reduction of share capital.—[
    Rep. by Act 62 of 1948, sec. 7 and Sch. (w.e.f. 
    1-1-1949).]  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Offices, branches and agencies.—The 
    Bank shall, as soon as may be, establish offices in Bombay, Calcutta, 


    1[Delhi and Madras]
    

    2[***] and may 
    establish branches or agencies in any other place in India 

    3[***] or, with the 
    previous sanction of the 

    4[Central Government] 
    elsewhere,
 
 









 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>7</number> Management.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may from time to time give such directions to the 
    Bank as it may, after consultation with the Governor of the Bank, consider 
    necessary in the public inter­est.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Subject to any such directions, the general superintendence and direction of 
    the affairs and business of the Bank shall be entrusted to a Central Board 
    of Directors which may exercise all powers and do all acts and things which 
    may be exercised or done by the Bank.  
 


    2[(3) Save as 
    otherwise provided in regulations made by the Central Board, the Governor 
    and in his absence the Deputy Gover­nor nominated by him in his behalf, 
    shall also have powers of general superintendence and direction of the 
    affairs and the business of the Bank, and may exercise all powers and do all 
    acts and things which may be exercised or done by the Bank.]]  
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Composition of the Central Board, and term of office of Direc­tors.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Board shall consist of the following Directors, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    a Governor and
    2[not 
    more than four] Deputy Governors to be appointed by the Central Government;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    four Directors to 
    be nominated by the Central Government, one from each of the four Local 
    Boards as constituted by section 9;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> 
     
    3[ten] Directors to be nominated by the Central 
    Government; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    one Government 
    official to be nominated by the Central Gov­ernment.]  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Governor and Deputy Governors shall devote their whole time to the affairs 
    of the Bank, and shall receive such salaries and allowances as may be 
    determined by the Central Board, with the approval of the 

    4[Central Government]:  
 


    5[Provided that the 
    Central Board may, if in its opinion it is necessary in the public interest 
    so to do, permit the Governor or a Deputy Governor to undertake, at the 
    request of the Central Government or any State Government, such part-time 
    honorary work, whether related to the purposes of this Act or not, as is not 
    likely to interfere with his duties as Governor or Deputy Gover­nor, as the 
    case may be:]  
 


    6[Provided further 
    that the Central Government may, in consulta­tion with the Bank, appoint a 
    Deputy Governor as the Chairman of the National Bank, on such terms and 
    conditions as that Govern­ment may specify.]
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A 
    Deputy Governor and the Director nominated under clause (d) of sub-section 
    (1) may attend any meeting of the Central Board and take part in its 
    deliberations but shall not be entitled to vote:  
 


    7[Provided that when 
    the Governor is, for any reason, unable to attend any such meeting, a Deputy 
    Governor authorised by him in this behalf in writing may vote for him at 
    that meeting.]  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Governor and a Deputy Governor shall hold office for such term not exceeding 
    five years as the 

    8[Central Government] 
    may fix when appointing them, and shall be eligible for re-appointment.
 


    9[A Director nominated 
    under clause (c) of sub-section (1) shall 

    10[***] hold office 
    for a period of four years 

    11[and thereafter 
    until his successor shall have been nominated].]
 
A 
    Director nominated under clause (d) of sub-section (1) shall hold office 
    during the pleasure of the 

    9[Central Government.]
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> No 
    act or proceeding of the Board shall be questioned on the ground merely of 
    the existence of any vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution of, the 
    Board.
 


    12[13[***]
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> A retiring 
    Director shall be eligible for re-nomination.]
 
 
















 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>9</number> Local Boards, 
    their constitution and functions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A Local Board shall be constituted for each of the four areas specified in 
    the First Schedule and shall consist of five members to be appointed by the 
    Central Government to represent, as far as possible, territorial and 
    economic interests and the interests of co-operative and indigenous banks.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    members of the Local Board shall elect from amongst themselves one person to 
    be the chairman of the Board.  
 


    2[(3) Every member of 
    a Local Board shall hold office for a term of four years and thereafter 
    until his successor shall have been appointed and shall be eligible for re-appointment.]  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A 
    Local Board shall advise the Central Board on such matters as may be 
    generally or specifically referred to it and shall perform such duties as 
    the Central Board may delegate to it.]  
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Disqualifications of Directors and members of Local Boards.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No person may be a Director or a member of a Local Board who—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    is a salaried 
    Government official 
1[***]
    2[***], 
    or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    is, or at any time 
    has been, adjudicated an insolvent, or has suspended payment or has 
    compounded with his creditors, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    is fund lunatic or 
    becomes of unsound mind, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    is an officer or 
    employee of any bank, or  
 

3[(e)    
    is a Director of banking company within the meaning of clause (c) of section 
    5 of the 
4[Banking 
    Regulation Act, 1949 (10 of 1949)], or of a co-operative bank.]  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> No 
    two persons who are partners of the same mercantile firm, or are Directors 
    of the same private company, or one of whom is the general agent of or holds 
    a power of procuration from the other, or from a mercantile firm of which 
    the other is a partner, may be Directors or members of the same Local Board 
    at the same time.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Nothing in clause (a), clause (d) or clause (e) of sub-section (l) shall 
    apply to the Governor, or to a Deputy Governor or to the Director nominated 
    under clause (d) of sub-section (1) of section 8.  
 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Removal from and vacation of office.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The 

    1[Central Government] 
    may remove from office the Governor, or a Deputy Governor or 

    2[any other Director 
    or any member of Local Board]:  
 


    3[***]  
 


    4[(2) A Director 
    nominated under clause (b) or clause (c) of sub-section(l) of section 8 
    shall cease to hold office if without leave from the Central Board he 
    absents himself from three conse­cutive meetings of the Board convened under 
    sub-section (1) of section 13.]  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The
    

    1[Central Government] 
    shall remove from office any Direc­tor, and the Central Board shall remove 
    from office any member of a Local Board, if such Director or member becomes 
    subject to any of the disqualifications specified in sub-section (1) or 
    sub-section (2) of section 10.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A 
    Director or member of a Local Board removed or ceasing to hold office under 
    the foregoing sub-sections shall not be eligi­ble for re-appointment either 
    as Director or as member of a Local Board until the expiry of the term for 
    which his appointment was made.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The
    

    5[***] nomination
    

    6[***] as Director or 
    member of a Local Board of any person who is a member of 

    7[Parliament or the 
    Legis­lature 

    8[of any State]] shall 
    be void, unless within two months of the date of his 

    5[***] nomination
    

    6[***] he ceases to be 
    such member, and if any Director or member of a Local Board is elected or 
    nominated as a member of 

    9[Parliament or any 
    such Legislature], he shall cease to be a Director or member of the Local 
    Board as from the date of such election or nomination, as the case may be.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> A 
    Director may resign his office to the 

    10[Central 
    Government], and a member of a Local Board may resign his office to the 
    Central Board, and on the acceptance of the resignation the office shall 
    become vacant.  
 
 














 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Casual vacancies and absences.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If the Governor or a Deputy Governor by infirmity or otherwise is rendered 
    incapable of executing his duties or is absent on leave or otherwise in 
    circumstances not involving the vacation of his appointment, the 


    1[Central Government] 
    may, after consideration of the recommenda­tions made by the Central Board 
    in this behalf, appoint another person to officiate for him, and such person 
    may, notwithstanding anything contained in clause (d) or sub-section (1) of 
    section 10, be an officer of the Bank.  
 


    2[***]  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Where any casual vacancy in the office of any member of a Local Board occurs
    

    3[***], the Central 
    Board may nominate thereto any 

    4[***] person 
    recommended by the 

    5[other] members of 
    the Local Board.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Where any casual vacancy occurs in the office of a Director other than the 
    vacancies provided for in sub-section (1), the vacancy shall be filled
    

    6[by the Central 
    Government].  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> A 
    person nominated 

    7[***] under this 
    section to fill a casual vacancy shall 

    8[***] hold office for 
    the unexpired portion of the term of his predecessor.  
 
 












 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Meetings of the Central Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Meetings of the Central Board shall be conveyed by the Governor at least six 
    times in each year and at least once in each quarter.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any
    

    1[four Directors] may 
    require the Governor to convene a meeting of the Central Board at any time 
    and the Governor shall forthwith convene a meeting accordingly.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Governor, or 

    2[if for any reason, 
    he is unable to attend,] the Deputy Governor authorised by the Governor 
    under the proviso to sub-section (3) of section 8 to vote for him shall 
    preside at meetings of the Central Board, and, in the event of an equality 
    of votes, shall have a second or casting vote.  
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    General meetings.—[Rep. 
    by the Reserve Bank (Transfer of Public Ownership Act, 1948 (62 of 1948), 
    sec. 7 and Sch. (w.e.f. 
    1-1-1949).]  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    First constitution of the Central Board.—[Rep. 
    by the Reserve Bank (Transfer of Public Ownership) Act, 1948 (62 of 1948), 
    sec. 7 and Sch. (w.e.f. 
    1-1-1949).]  
 

 

 

 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    First constitution of local board.—[Rep. 
    by the Reserve Bank (Transfer of Public Ownership) Act, 1948 (62 of 1948), 
    sec. 7 and Sch. (w.e.f. 
    1-1-1949).]  
 

 

 


 
  


</article> 
 The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934
  
 <article><number>17</number> Business which the Bank 
may transact.—The Bank shall be 
authorised to carry on and transact the several kinds of business hereinafter 
specified, namely:—
 <section>       <number>1</number> the accepting of money on deposit without 
interest from, and the collection of money for,
1[***] 
the 2[Central 
Government]. 3[4[***] 
the 5[State] 
Government] 6[***]
7[***] 
local authori­ties, banks and any other persons:
 </section><section>       <number>2</number> (a)  the purchase, sale and rediscount of bills 
of exchange and promissory notes,
8[drawn 
on 9[and 
payable in India]] and arising out of bona fide commercial or trade 
transaction bearing two or more good signatures, one of which shall be that of a 
scheduled bank 
10[or a State co-operative bank]
11[or any 
finan­cial institution, which is predominantly engaged in the accept­ance or 
discounting of bills of exchange and promissory notes and which is approved by 
the Bank in this behalf]
12[***] 
and 13[maturing,—
 <subsection>                  <number>i</number> in the case of bills of exchange and 
promissory notes aris­ing out of any such transaction relating to the export of 
goods from India, within one hundred and eighty days, and
 </subsection><subsection>                 <number>ii</number> in any other case, within ninety days,

                   from the date of such purchase or 
rediscount exclusive of days of grace;]
 <subsubsection>            <number>b</number> the purchase, sale and rediscount of bills 
of exchange and promissory notes,
14[drawn
15[and 
payable in India]] and bearing two or more good signatures, one of which shall 
be that of a scheduled bank
15[or a
16[(State] 
co-operative bank]
17[or any 
financial institution, which is predominantly engaged in the acceptance or 
discounting of bills of exchange and promissory notes and which is approved by 
the Bank in this behalf] and drawn or issued for the purpose of
18[financing 
agricultural operations] or the marketing of crops, and maturing within
19[fifteen 
months] from the date of such purchase or rediscount, exclusive of days of 
grace;
 
         20[***]
 
           21[(bb) 
the purchase, sale and rediscount of bills of exchange and promissory notes 
drawn and payable in India and bearing two or more good signatures, one of which 
shall be that of a State co-operative bank or a State financial corporation
17[or any 
finan­cial institution, which is predominantly engaged in the accept­ance or 
discounting of bills of exchange and promissory notes and which is approved by 
the Bank in this behalf], and drawn or issued for the purpose of financing the 
production or marketing activities of cottage and small scale industries 
approved by the Bank and maturing within twelve months from the date of such 
purchase or rediscount, exclusive of days of grace, provided that the payment of 
the principal and interest of such bills of ex­change or promissory notes is 
fully guaranteed by the State Government;]
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            <number>c</number> the purchase, sale and rediscount of bills 
of exchange and promissory notes
22[drawn
23[and 
payable in India]] and bearing the signature of a scheduled bank,
24[***] 
and issued or drawn for the purpose of holding or trading in securities of
25[the 
Central Government
22[or a
26[State] 
Government]] 27[***] 
and maturing within ninety days from the date of such purchase or rediscount, 
exclusive of days of grace;
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>       <number>3</number> (a)  the purchase from and sale to scheduled 
banks 28[***] 
of 29[foreign 
exchange] 30[***];

 
             31[(b) 
the purchase sale and rediscount of bills of exchange (including treasury bills) 
drawn in or on any place in any coun­try outside India which is a member of the 
International Monetary Fund and maturing,—
 <subsection>                  <number>i</number> in the case of bills of exchange 
arising out of any bona fide transaction relating to the export of goods 
from India, within one hundred and eighty days, and
 </subsection><subsection>                 <number>ii</number> in any other case, within ninety days,
                   from the date of such purchase or 
rediscount:
                       Provided that no such purchase, sale 
or rediscount shall be made in India except with a scheduled bank or a State 
co-operative bank;]
 
32[***]
 
  33[(3A) 
the making to any scheduled bank or State co-operative bank, or loans and 
advances, against promissory notes or such bank, repayable on demand or on the 
expiry of fixed periods not exceeding one hundred and eighty days:
                  Provided that the borrowing bank furnishes 
a declaration in writing, to the effect that—
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>i</number> it holds bills of exchange arising out of 
any transaction relating to the export of goods from India of a value not less 
than the amount of such loans or advances,—
 <subsubsection>                 <number>a</number> drawn in India and no any place in any 
country outside India which is a member of the International Monetary Fund or in 
any other country notified in this behalf by the Bank in the Gazette of India, 
and
 

                     34[(b)  maturing not later than one hundred and 
eighty days from the date of the loan or advance, and it will, so long as any 
part of such loans and advances remains unpaid, continue to hold such bills of 
exchange of a value not less than the amount of such loans or advances 
outstanding for the time being; or]
 
              35[(ii)  
it has granted a pre-shipment loan or advance to an ex­porter or any other 
person in India in order to enable him to export goods from India, the amount of 
the loan or advance drawn and outstanding at any time being not less than the 
outstanding amount of the loan or advance obtained by the borrowing bank from 
the Bank.]]
 
   36[(3B) 
the making to any scheduled bank or State co-operative bank or loans and 
advances repayable on demand or on the expiry of fixed periods not exceeding one 
hundred and eighty days against promissory notes of such bank:
                  Provided that the borrowing bank furnished 
a declaration in writing to the effect that it has made loans and advances for
bona fide commercial or trade transactions or for financing agricultural 
operations or the marketing of crops or for other agricultural purposes as set 
out in the declaration and the said declaration includes such other particulars 
as may be required by the Bank;]
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>       <number>4</number> the making to
37[***] 
local authorities, scheduled banks,
38[39[***]
40[State] 
co-operative banks
41[and 
State Financial Corpo­rations
42[***]] 
or loans and advances, repayable on demand or on the expiry of fixed periods not 
exceeding ninety days, against the security of—
 <subsection>            <number>a</number>  stocks, funds and securities (other than 
immovable property) in which a trustee is authorized to invest trust money by 
any Act of Parliament
43[of the 
United Kingdom] or by any law for time being in force in
44[India]
45[***];
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>b</number>  gold or silver or documents of title to the 
same;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>c</number>  such bills of exchange and promissory notes 
as are eligible for purchase or rediscount by the Bank
46[or as 
are fully guar­anteed as to the repayment of the principal and payment of 
inter­est by a State Government];
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>d</number>  promissory notes of any scheduled bank
47[48[or
49[State]] 
co-operative bank], supported by documents of title to goods
50[such 
documents having been transferred], assigned, or pledged to any such bank as 
security for 51[a 
loan or advance made] for bona fide commercial or trade transactions, or for the 
purpose of 52[financing 
agricultural operations] or the marketing of crops:
 
53[Provided 
that loans and advances made against the security of bills of exchange and 
promissory notes arising out of any trans­action relating to the export of goods 
from India shall be repay­able on demand or on the expiry of fixed periods not 
exceeding one hundred and eighty days;]
 
54[(4A)  
the making to any State Financial Corporation
55[***] 
of loans and advances repayable on the expiry of fixed periods not exceeding 
eighteen months from the date of such loan or advance, against securities of the 
Central Government or of any State Government, of any maturity, or against bonds 
and debentures issued by that Corporation and guaranteed by the State Government 
concerned and maturing within a period not exceeding eighteen months from the 
date of such loan or advance:
 
56[Provided 
that the previous approval of the State Government shall be obtained for the 
borrowing by the State Financial Corpo­ration and the amount of loans and 
advances granted to that Corporation under this clause shall not, at any time, 
exceed in the aggregate
57[twice 
the paid-up share capital] thereof.]]
 
58[59[(4AA) 
the making of annual contributions to the National Rural Credit (Long Term 
Operations) Fund and the National Rural Credit (Stabilisation) Fund established 
under sections 42 and 43, respectively, of the National Bank for Agriculture and 
Rural Development Act, 1981.]
  
 
58[(4B)  
the making to the Industrial Finance Corporation of India
60[***] 
of loans and advances,—
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>a</number>  repayable on demand or on the expiry of 
fixed periods not exceeding ninety days from the date of such loan or advance, 
against securities of the Central Government or of any State Government; or
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>b</number>  repayable on the expiry of fixed periods 
not exceeding eighteen months from the date of such loan or advance, against 
securities of the Central Government of any maturity or against bonds and 
debentures issued by the Corporation and guaranteed by the Central Government 
and maturity within a period not exceeding eighteen months from the date of such 
loan or advance:
 
61[***]]
 
62[(4BB)  
the making to any financial institution notified by the Central Government in 
this behalf, of loans and advances,—
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>a</number>  repayable on demand or on the expiry of 
fixed periods not exceeding ninety days from the date of such loan or advance, 
against the securities of the Central Government or of any State Government, or
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>b</number>  repayable on the expiry of fixed periods 
not exceeding eighteen months from the date of such loan or advance, against 
securities of the Central Government or of any State Government, of any 
maturity, or against bonds and debentures issued by that financial institution 
and guaranteed by the Central Government or any State Government, and maturing 
within a period not exceeding eighteen months from the date of such loan or 
advance:
                  Provided that the amount of loans and 
advances granted to a financial institution under sub-clause (b) shall not, at 
any time, exceed in the aggregate sixty per cent of the paid-up share capital 
thereof;]
 
63[(4BBB) 
the making to the Unit Trust of loans and advances—
 <subsubsection>             <number>i</number>  repayable on demand or on the expiry of a 
fixed period not exceeding ninety days from the date of such loan or advance 
against the security of stocks, funds and securities (other than immovable 
property) in which a trustee is authorised to invest trust money by any law for 
the time being in force in India;
64[***]
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            <number>ii</number>  repayable on demand or within a period of 
eighteen months from the date of such loan or advance against the security of 
the bonds of the Unit Trust issued with the approval of and guar­anteed by the 
Central Government;]
 
65[(iii)  
for the purpose of any scheme other than the first unit scheme under the Unit 
Trust of India Act, 1963 (52 of 1963) on such terms and conditions and against 
the security of such other property of the Unit Trust as may be specified in 
this behalf by the Bank;]
 
66[(4C)  
the making to a Warehousing Corporation established under the Agricultural 
Produce (Development and Warehousing) Corpora­tions Act, 1956 (28 of 1956) of 
loans and advances,—
 <subsubsubsection>            <number>a</number>  repayable on demand or on the expiry of 
fixed periods not exceeding ninety days, from the date of such loan or advance, 
against securities of the Central Government or of any State Government, or
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>            <number>b</number>  repayable on the expiry of fixed periods 
not exceeding eighteen months from the date of such loan or advance, against 
securities of the Central Government or of any State Government, of any 
maturity, or against bonds and debentures issued by the corporation to which the 
loan or advance is made, and guaranteed by the Central or a State Government, 
and maturing within a period not exceeding eighteen months from the date of such 
loan or advance:
                  Provided that the amount of loans and 
advances granted under clause (b) shall not at any time exceed, in the 
aggregate, three crores of rupees in the case of the Central Warehousing 
Corpora­tion and fifty lakhs of rupees in the case of a State Warehousing 
Corporation;]
 
67[(4D)  
the making to the Deposit Insurance Corporation of loans and advances; and 
generally assisting the Corporation in such manner and on such terms as may be 
determined by the Central Board;]
 
68[(4DD)  
the making to the National Housing Bank of loans and advances and generally 
assisting the National Housing Bank in such manner and on such terms as may be 
determined by the Central Board;]
 
69[(4E)  
the making to the National Bank of loans and advances repayable on demand or on 
the expiry of fixed period not exceed­ing eighteen months from the date of 
making of the loan or ad­vance, either—
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection><subsubsection>             <number>i</number>  against the security of stocks, funds and 
securities (other than immovable property) in which a trustee is authorised to 
invest trust money by any law for the time being in force in India; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            <number>ii</number>  on such other terms and conditions as the 
Bank may specify;]
 
70[(4F)  
contributing to the initial Capital of the Unit Trust;]
 
71[(4G)  
the making of loans and advances to, and the purchasing of bonds and debentures 
of, 72[***]
73[the 
Exim Bank] 74[or 
the Reconstruction Bank]
75[or the 
Small Industries Bank] out of the National Industrial Credit (Long Term 
Operations) Fund established under section 46C;]
 
76[(4GG)  
the making of loans and advances to, and the purchasing of bonds and debentures 
of, the National Housing Bank out of the National Housing Credit (Long Term 
Operations) Fund established under section 46D;]
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>     <number>4H</number>  the making
72[***]
75[the 
Small Industries Bank] of loans and advances—
 <subsection>            <number>a</number>  repayable on demand or on the expiry of 
fixed periods not exceeding ninety days from the date of such Ioan or advance 
against the security of stocks, funds and securities (other than immovable 
property) in which a trustee is authorised to invest trust money by any law for 
the time being in force in India; or
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>b</number>  against the security of bills of exchange 
or promissory notes, arising out of bona fide commercial or trade transactions 
bearing two or more good signatures and maturing within five years from the date 
of such loan or advance;] 
 
77[(4-I)  
the making to scheduled banks,
78[***]
73[the 
Exim Bank] 79[the Reconstruction Bank or the Small Industries Bank] the 
Industrial Finance Corporation and any other financial institution as may, on 
the recommendation of the Bank, be ap­proved in this behalf by the Central 
Government of loans and advances repayable on demand or otherwise and against 
such secur­ity and on such other terms and conditions as may be approved in this 
behalf by the Central Board for the purpose of enabling such banks, or financial 
institution, as the case may be, to purchase foreign exchange from the Bank for 
the purpose of financing the import of capital goods or for such other purposes 
as may be approved by the Central Government;]
 
80[(4J)  
the making to the Exim Bank of loans and advances—
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>a</number>  repayable on demand or on the expiry of a 
fixed period not exceeding ninety days, from the date of such loan or advance 
against the security of stocks, funds and securities (other than immovable 
property) in which a trustee is authorised to invest trust money by any law for 
the time being in force in India; or
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>b</number>  against the security of bills of exchange 
or promissory notes, arising out of bona fide commercial or trade transactions 
bearing two or more good signatures and maturing within five years from the date 
of such loan or advance;]
 
81[(4K)  
the making to the Reconstruction Bank of loans and advances—
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>a</number>  repayable on demand or on the expiry of a 
fixed period not exceeding ninety days, from the date of such loan or advance 
against the security of stocks, funds and securities (other than immovable 
property) in which a trustee is authorised to invest trust money by any law for 
the time being in force in India; or
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>b</number>  against the security of bills of exchange 
or promissory notes, arising out of bona fide commercial or trade transactions 
bearing two or more goods signatures and maturing within five years from the 
date of such loan or advance;]
 </subsection></section><section>       <number>5</number>  the making to the
82[Central 
Government] 83[84[***]85[and
86[State] 
Governments]] of advances repayable in each case not later than three months 
from the date of the making of the advance;
 
     87[(6)  
the issue of demand drafts, telegraphic transfers and other kinds of remittances 
made payable at its own offices or agencies, the purchase of telegraphic 
transfers, and the making, issue and circulation of bank post bills;]
 
  88[(6A)  
dealing in derivatives, and, with the approval of the Central Board, in any 
other financial instrument.
  Explanation.—For the purposes of this clause, 
“derivative” means an instrument, to be settled at a future date, whose value is 
derived from change in one or a combination of more than one of the following 
underlyings, namely:—
 <subsection>            <number>a</number>  interest rate,
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>b</number>  price of securities of the Central 
Government or a State Government or of such securities of a local authority as 
may be specified in this behalf by the Central Government,
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>c</number>  price of foreign securities,
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>d</number>  foreign exchange rate,
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>e</number>  index of rates or prices,
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>f</number>  credit rating or credit index,
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>g</number>  price of gold or silver coins, or gold or 
silver bullion, or
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>h</number>  any other variable of similar nature;]
 
89[***]
 </subsection></section><section>       <number>8</number> the purchase and sale of securities
90[ of 
the Central 91[Government 
or a 92[State] 
Government]] of any maturity or of such securities of a local authority
93[***] 
as may be specified in this behalf by the
94[Central 
Government] on the recommendation of the Central Board:
                  Provided that securities fully guaranteed 
as to principal and interest by
95[any 
such Government 
96[or authority]] shall be deemed for the purposes of this clause to be 
securities of such Government
96[or 
authority];
 
97[***]
 
  98[(8A) 
the purchase and sale of shares in, or the capital of
99[the
100[101[National 
Bank]] 102[Deposit 
Insurance Corporation],
103[***], 
the State Bank 
104[or any other bank
105[or 
finan­cial institution] notified by the Central Government in this behalf];]
 
106[(8AA) 
the promoting, establishing, supporting or aiding in the promotion, 
establishment and support of any financial institu­tion, whether as its 
subsidiary or otherwise;]
 
107[(8B)  
the keeping of deposits with the State Bank for such specific purposes as may be 
approved by the Central Government in this behalf;]
 </section><section>       <number>9</number>  the custody of monies, securities and other 
articles of value, and the collection of the proceeds, whether principal, 
interest or dividends, of any such securities;
 </section><section>      <number>10</number>  the sale realisation of all property, whether 
movable or immovable, which may in any way come into the possession of the Bank 
in satisfaction, or part satisfaction, of any of its claims;
 </section><section>      <number>11</number> the acting as agent for
108[***] 
the 109[Central 
Government] 110[or 
any 111[State] 
Government 112[***] 
or any local authority
113[***]
114[or 
the Industrial Finance Corporation of India
115[***]
116[or 
any other body corporate which is established or constitut­ed by or under any 
other law] 117[or 
the Government of any such country outside India or
118[any 
such person or authority] is may be approved in this behalf by the Central 
Government] in the transaction of any of the following kinds of business, 
namely:—
 <subsection>            <number>a</number> the purchase and sale of gold or silver
119[or 
foreign ex­change];
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>b</number> the purchase, sale, transfer and custody of 
bills of exchange, securities or shares in any company;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>c</number> the collection of the proceeds, whether 
principal, interest or dividends, of any securities or shares;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>d</number> the remittance of such proceeds, at the risk 
of the princi­pal, by bills of exchange payable either in India or elsewhere;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>e</number> the management of public debt;
 
            120[(f) 
121[***] 
the issue and management of
122[***] 
bonds and deben­tures;]
 
123[(11A) 
the acting as agent for the Central Government,—
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>a</number> in guaranteeing the due performance by any 
small-scale indus­trial concern, approved by the Central Government, of its 
obliga­tions to any bank or other financial institution in respect of loans and 
advances made, or other credit facilities provided, to it by such bank or other 
financial institution and the making as such agent of payments in connection 
with such guarantee, and
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>b</number> in administering any scheme for subsidising 
the rate of interest or other charges in relation to any loans or advances made, 
or other credit facilities provided, by banks or other financial institutions 
for the purpose of financing or facilitat­ing any export from India and the 
making as such agent of pay­ments on behalf of the Central Government;]
 
124[(12)  
the purchase and sale of gold or silver coins and gold and silver bullion and 
foreign exchange and the opening of a gold account with the principal currency 
authority of any foreign country or the Bank for International Settlements or 
any interna­tional or regional bank or financial institution formed by such 
principal currency authority or authorities or by the Government of any foreign 
country;]
 
125[(12A) 
the purchase and sale of securities issued by the Govern­ment of any country 
outside India or by any institution or body corporate established outside India 
and expressed to be payable in a foreign currency or any international or 
composite currency unit, being in the case of purchase by the Bank securities 
matur­ing within a period of ten years from the date of purchase:
                  Provided that in the case of securities of 
an institution or body corporate, the repayment of principal and payment of 
interest in respect of such securities shall be guaranteed by the Government of 
the country concerned;]
 
126[(12AA)  
lending or borrowing of securities of the Central Government or a State 
Government or of such securities of a local authority as may be specified in 
this behalf by the Central Government or foreign securities;]
 
126[(12AB)  
dealing in repo or reverse repo:
                  Provided that lending or borrowing of funds 
by way of repo or reverse repo shall not be subject to any limitation contained 
in this section.
                  Explanation.—For the purposes of 
this clause,—
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>a</number>  “repo” means an instrument for borrowing 
funds by selling securities of the Central Government or a State Government or 
of such securities of a local authority as may be specified in this behalf by 
the Central Government or foreign securities, with an agreement to repurchase 
the said securities on a mutually agreed future date at an agreed price which 
includes interest for the funds borrowed;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>b</number>  “reverse repo” means an instrument for 
lending funds by purchasing securities of the Central Government or a State 
Government or of such securities of a local authority as may be specified in 
this behalf by the Central Government or foreign securities, with an agreement 
to resell the said securities on a mutually agreed future date at an agreed 
price which includes interest for the funds lent;]
 
127[(12B) 
the making of loans and advances in foreign currencies to scheduled banks,
128[***],
129[the 
Exim Bank], 130[or
131[the 
Reconstruction Bank or the Small Industries Bank]] the Industrial Finance 
Corporation, any State Financial Corporation and any other financial institution 
as may, on the recommendation of the Bank, be approved by the Central Government 
and on such terms and conditions as may be specified by the Central Board in 
this behalf, against promissory notes of such bank or financial institution, as 
the case may be:
                  Provided that the borrowing bank or 
financial institution, as the case may be, furnishes a declaration in writing to 
the effect that—
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>a</number> it has made loans and advances in foreign 
currencies for financing international trade or for the import of capital goods 
or for such other purposes as may be approved by the Central Government; and
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>b</number> that the amount of loans or advances so made 
and outstanding at any time will not be less than the outstanding amount of the 
loans or advances obtained by it from the Bank;]
 
132[(13) 
the opening of an account with an office outside India of any bank, including a 
bank incorporated in India or the making of an agency agreement with, and the 
acting as an agent or corre­spondent of, any bank incorporated outside India, or 
the princi­pal currency authority of any country under the law for the time 
being in force in that country or any international or regional bank or 
financial institution formed by such principal currency authorities or foreign 
governments, and the investing of the funds of the Bank in the shares and 
securities of any such inter­national or regional bank or financial institution 
or of any other foreign institution as may be approved by the Central Board in 
this behalf;]
 
133[(13A) 
   participation in any arrangement for the clearing and settlement of any 
amounts due from, or to, any person or authori­ty on account of the external 
trade of India with any other country or group of countries or of any 
remittances to, or from, that country or group of countries, including the 
advancing, or receiving, of any amount in any currency in connection therewith, 
and, for that purpose, becoming, with the approval of the Central Government, a 
member of any international or regional clearing union of central banks monetary 
or other authorities, or being associated with any such clearing arrangements, 
or becoming a member of any body or asso­ciation formed by central banks, 
monetary or other similar au­thorities, or being associated with the same in any 
manner;]
 </subsection></section><section>      <number>14</number> the borrowing of money for a period not exceeding 
one month for the purposes of the business of the Bank, and the giving of 
security for money so borrowed:
                  Provided that no money shall be borrowed 
under this clause from any person in India
134[***] 
other than a scheduled bank
135[***] 
or from any person outside India
136[***] 
other than a bank which is the principal currency authority of any country under 
the law for the time being in force in that country:
                  Provided further that the total amount of 
such borrowings from persons in India
136[***] 
shall not at any time exceed the amount of the
137[capital] 
of the Bank;
 

 138[***]
 </section><section>      <number>15</number>  the making and issue of bank notes subject to 
the provisions of this Act
139[***];
140[***]
 
141[(15A) 
the exercise of powers and functions and the performance of duties entrusted to 
the Bank under this Act or under any other law for the time being in force;]
 
142[15B)  
the providing of facilities for training in banking and for the promotion of 
research, where, in the opinion of the Bank, such provision may facilitate the 
exercise by the Bank of its powers and functions, or the discharge of its 
duties;]
 </section><section>      <number>16</number> generally, the doing of all such matters and 
things as may be incidental to or consequential upon the exercise of its powers 
or the discharge of its duties under this Act
143[***]
  

















































































































































</section></article> 
 The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934
  
 <article><number>18</number> Power of direct discount.—1[***] 
When, in the opinion of the 

2[Bank] 

3[***] a special occasion has arisen 
making it neces­sary or expedient that action should be taken 

4[under this section] for the purposes of 
regulating credit in the interests of Indian 

5[***] trade, commerce, industry and 
agricultural, the Bank may, notwithstanding any limitation contained in 

6[***] section 17,—
 
        7[
<section><number>1</number>  
purchase, sell or discount any bill of exchange or promis­sory note though such 
bill or promissory note is not eligible for purchase or discount by the Bank 
under that section; or]
 
   8[***]
 
        9[(3)  
make loans or advances to—
 <subsection>            <number>a</number> a State co-operative bank, or
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>b</number> on the recommendation of a State 
co-operative bank, to a co-operative society registered within the area in which 
the State co-operative bank operates, or
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>c</number>  any other person,
 repayable on demand or on the expiry of the fixed periods, not 
exceeding ninety days, on such terms and conditions as the Bank may consider to 
be sufficient.]
 

10[***]
 

11[***]
  













</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>18A</number> Validity of 
    loan or advance not to be questioned.— 
    Not­withstanding anything to the contrary contained in any other law for the 
    time being in force,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    the validity of 
    any loan or advance granted by the Bank in pursuance of the provisions of 
    this Act shall not be called in question merely on the ground of 
    non-compliance with the require­ments of such other law as aforesaid or of 
    any resolution, con­tract, memorandum, articles of association or other 
    instrument:  
 
      Provided that 
    nothing in this clause shall render valid any loan or advance obtained by 
    any company or co-operative society where such company or co-operative 
    society is not empowered by its memorandum to obtain loans or advances;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    where a loan or 
    advance has been granted under clause (3A) or under clause (3B) or section 
    17 or a loan or advance granted under clause (3) of section 18 by the Bank 
    to any person has been applied by such person, wholly or in part, in making 
    a loan or advance to any borrower, any sum received—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    by the borrowing 
    bank on account of bills of exchange in respect of which the declaration 
    under clause (i) of the proviso to clause (3A) of section 17 has been 
    furnished or in repayment or realisation of the outstanding loans and 
    advances referred to in clause (ii) of the said proviso or in the proviso to 
    clause (3B) of the said section or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    by the borrowing 
    bank or any other person in repayment or realisation of loans and advances 
    granted to a borrower out of funds obtained by it or by him from the Bank 
    under section 18,  
 
shall be utilised only for the repayment by 
    the borrowing bank or other person, as the case may be, of the amounts due 
    to be re­paid by it or by him to the Bank, and shall be held by it or by him 
    in trust for the Bank, until such time as the amounts are so repaid.]
 
 





 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Business which the Bank may not transact.—Save as otherwise provided in sections 17, 18, 

    1[42] and 45, the Bank 
    may not—
 <section>
<number>1</number>    engage in trade or 
    otherwise have a direct interest in any commercial, industrial or other 
    undertaking except such interest as it may in any way acquire in the course 
    of the satisfaction of any of its claims: provided that all such interests 
    shall be disposed of at the earliest possible moment; 
 

2[(2)    
    purchase the shares of any banking company or of any other company, or grant 
    loans upon the security of any such shares;] 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>    advance money on 
    mortgage of, or otherwise on the security of, immovable property or 
    documents of title relating thereto, or become the owner of immovable 
    property, except so far as is necessary for its own business premises and 
    residences for its officers and servants; 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number>    make loans or 
    advances; 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number>    draw or accept 
    bills payable otherwise than on demand; 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number>    allow interest on 
    deposits or current accounts.
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934
  
 <article><number>20</number> Obligation of the Bank to 
transact Government business.— The 
Bank shall undertake to accept monies for account of 

1[2[***]] 
the Central Government 

3[***] and to make payments up to the 
amount standing to the credit of 

4[its account], and to carry out 

5[its exchange], remittance and other 
banking operations, including the management of the public debt 

6[of the Union].
  








</article> 
 The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934
 


 

1[***]
  



 
 The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934
  
 <article><number>21</number> Bank to have the right to 
transact Government business in India.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The 

1[Central Government] 

2[***] shall entrust the Bank, on such 
conditions as may be agreed upon, with all 

3[its] money, remittance, exchange and 
banking transaction in India, and, in particular, shall deposit free of interest 
all 

3[its] cash balances with the Bank:
 Provided that nothing in this 
sub-section shall prevent the 

4[Central Government] 

5[***] from carrying on money 
transactions at places where the Bank has no branches or agencies, and the


4[Central Government] 

6[***] may hold at such places such 
bal­ances as 

7[it] may require.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The 

4[Central Government] 

8[***] shall entrust the Bank, on such 
conditions as may be agreed upon, with the management of the public debt and 
with the issue of any new loans.
 </section><section><number>3</number> In the event of any failure 
to reach agreement on the condi­tions referred to in this section the 

4[Central Government] shall decide what 
the conditions shall be.
 

9[(4) Any agreement made under this 
section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before Parliament.]
 

10[***]
  












</section></article> 
 The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934
  
 <article>

1[<number>21A</number> Bank to transact Government 
business of States on agree­ment.—
<section><number>1</number> The Bank may by agreement with the 
Government of any 

2[***] State 

3[***] undertake—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> all its money, remittance, exchange and banking 
transactions in India, including in particular, the deposit, free of interest, 
of all its cash balances with the Bank; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> the management of the public debt of, and the 
issue of any new loans by, that State.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Any Agreement made under 
this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before 
Parliament.]
  





</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>21B</number> Effect of 
    agreements made between the Bank and certain States before the 1st November, 
    1956.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any agreement made under section 21 or section 21A between the Bank and the 
    Govern­ment of a State specified in the Explanation below and in 
    force immediately before the 1st day of November, 1956, shall, as from that 
    day have effect as if it were an agreement made on that day under section 
    21A between the Bank and the Government of the corresponding State subject 
    to such modifications, if any, being of a character not affecting the 
    general operation of the agree­ment, as may be agreed upon between the Bank 
    and the Government of the corresponding State, or in default of such 
    agreement, as may be made therein by order of the Central Government.  
 

    Explanation.—In 
    this sub-section “corresponding State” means,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    in relation to the 
    agreement between the Bank and the State of Andhra, the State of Andhra 
    Pradesh;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    in relation to the 
    agreement between the Bank and any other Part A State as it existed before 
    the 1st day of November, 1956, the State with the same name; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    in relation to the 
    agreement between the Bank and the Part B State of Mysore or Travancore-Cochin 
    as it existed before the 1st day of November, 1956, the State of Mysore of 
    Kerala respective­ly.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Any 
    agreement made under section 21A between the Bank and the Government of the 
    Part B State of Hyderabad, Madhya Bharat or Saurashtra shall be deemed to 
    have terminated on the 31st day of October, 1956.]
 
 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Right to issue bank notes.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Bank shall have the sole right to issue bank notes in 

    1[India], and may, for 
    a period which shall be fixed by the 

    2[Central Government] 
    on the recom­mendation of the Central Board, issue currency notes of the 
    Government of India supplied to it by the 

    2[Central Government], 
    and the provisions of this Act applicable to bank notes shall, unless a 
    contrary intention appears, apply to all currency notes of the Government of 
    India issued either by the 

    2[Central Govern­ment] 
    or by the Bank in like manner as if such currency notes were bank notes, and 
    references in this Act to bank notes shall be construed accordingly.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On 
    and from the date on which this Chapter comes into force the 

    2[Central Government] 
    shall not issue any currency notes.  
 
 
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934
  
 <article><number>23</number> Issue Department.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The issue of bank notes shall be conducted by the Bank in an Issue Department 
which shall be separated and kept wholly distinct from the Banking Department, 
and the assets of the Issue Department shall not be subject to any liability 
other than the liabilities of the Issue Department as hereinafter defined in 
section 34.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Issue Department shall 
not issue bank notes to the Bank­ing Department or to any other person except in 
exchange for other bank notes or for such coin, bullion or securities as are 
permitted by this Act to form part of the Reserve.
 

1[***]
  



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>24</number> Denominations 
    of notes.—
<section><number>1</number> Subject to the provisions of sub-section (2) bank notes 
    shall be of the denominational value to two rupees, five rupees, ten rupees, 
    twenty rupees, fifty rupees, one hundred rupees, five hundred rupees, one 
    thousand rupees, five thousand rupees and ten thousand rupees or of such 
    other denominational values, not exceeding ten thousand rupees, as the 
    Central Govern­ment may, on the recommendation of the Central Board, specify 
    in this behalf.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Central 
    Government may, on the recommendation of the Central Board, direct the 
    non-issue or the discontinuance of issue of bank notes of such 
    denominational values as it may specify in this behalf.]
 
 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Form of bank notes.—The 
    design, form the material of bank notes shall be such as may be approved by 
    the 

    1[Central Govern­ment] 
    after consideration of the recommendations made by the Central Board.  
 
 



 



</article> 
 The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934
  
 <article><number>26</number> Legal tender character of 
notes.—
<section><number>1</number> Subject to the provi­sions 
of sub-section (2), every bank note shall be legal tender at any place in 

1[India] in payment, or on account for 
the amount expressed therein, and shall be guaranteed by the 

2[Central Government].
 </section><section><number>2</number> On recommendation of the 
Central Board the 

2[Central Govern­ment] may, by 
notification in the Gazette of India, declare that, with effect from such date 
as may be specified in the notifica­tion, any series of bank notes of any 
denomination shall cease to be legal tender 

3[save at such office or agency of the 
Bank and to such extent as may be specified in the notification].
 

4[***]
  






</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>26A</number> Certain bank 
    notes to cease to be legal tender.— Notwith­standing anything contained 
    in section 26, no bank note of the denominational value of five hundred 
    rupees, one thousand rupees or ten thousand rupees issued before the 13th 
    day of January, 1946, shall be legal tender in payment or on account for the 
    amount expressed therein.]  
 
 



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>27</number> 
    Re-issue notes.— 
    The Bank shall not re-issue bank notes which are torn, defaced or 
    excessively spoiled.  

 
  


</article> 
 The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934
  
 <article><number>28</number> Recovery of notes lost, 
stolen, mutilated or imperfect.—1[***] 
Notwithstanding anything contained in any enactment or rule of law to the 
contrary, no person shall of right be entitled to recover from the 

2[Central Government] or the Bank, the 
value of any lost, stolen, mutilated or imperfect currency note of the 
Government of India or bank note:
 Provided that the Bank may, with 
the previous sanction of the 

2[Central Government], prescribed the 
circumstances in and the conditions and limitations subject to which the value 
of such currency notes or bank notes may be refunded as of grace and the rules 
made under this proviso shall be laid on the table 

3[***] of 

4[Parliament].
 

5[***]
  







</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>28A</number> Issue of 
    special bank notes and special one rupee notes in certain cases.—
<section><number>1</number> For 
    the purpose of controlling the circula­tion of bank notes without India, the 
    Bank may, notwithstanding anything contained in any other provision of this 
    Act, issue bank notes of such design, form and material as may be approved 
    under sub-section (3) (hereinafter in this section referred to as special 
    bank notes) of the denominational values of five rupees, ten rupees and one 
    hundred rupees.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> For 
    the purpose of controlling the circulation of Government of India one rupee 
    notes without India, the Central Government may, notwithstanding anything 
    contained in any other provision of this Act or in the Currency Ordinance, 
    1940, (Ord. 4 of 1940) issue Government of India notes of the denominational 
    value of one rupee of such design, form and material as may be adopted under 
    sub-section (3) (hereinafter in this section referred to as special one 
    rupee notes).  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    design, form and material of the special bank notes shall be such as may be 
    approved by the Central Government after consideration of the 
    recommendations made by the Governor and of the special one rupee notes 
    shall be such as the Central Govern­ment may think fit to adopt.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Neither the special bank notes not the special one rupee notes shall be 
    legal tender in India.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    special one rupee note shall be deemed to be included in the expression 
    “rupee coin” for all the purposes of this Act except section 39, but shall 
    be deemed not to be a currency note for any of the purposes of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Where 
    a special bank note is on its face expressed to be payable at a specified 
    office or branch of the Bank, the obligation imposed by section 39 shall be 
    only on the specified office or branch and, further, shall be subject to 
    such regulations as may be made under this section. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The 
    Bank may, with the previous sanction of the Central Government, make 
    regulations to provide for all matters for which provision is necessary or 
    convenient for the purpose of giving effect to the provisions of this 
    section, and, in particular, the manner in which, and the conditions or 
    limitations subject to which—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    bank notes and one 
    rupee notes in circulation in any country outside India may be replaced by 
    special notes issued under this section;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    any such special 
    notes may be exchanged for any other bank notes or one rupee notes.]  
 
 
 
 



 



</subsection></section></article> 
 The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934
  
 <article><number>29</number> Bank exempt from stamp 
duty on bank notes.— The Bank shall 
not be liable to the payment of any stamp duty under the Indian Stamp Act, 1899 
(2 of 1899) in respect of bank notes 

1[***] issued by it.
  



</article> 
 The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934
  
 <article><number>30</number>
Powers of Central Government to supersede Central Board.—
<section><number>1</number> If in the 
opinion of the 

1[Central Government] the Bank fails to 
carry out any of the obligations imposed on it by or under this Act 

2[***] 

3[the Central Government] may, by 
no­tification in the Gazette of India, declare the Central Board to be 
superseded, and thereafter the general superintendence and direction of the 
affairs of the Bank shall be entrusted to such agency as the 

1[Central Government] may determine, and 
such agency may exercise the powers and do all acts and things which may be 
exercised or done by the Central Board under this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> When action is taken under 
this section the 

1[Central Govern­ment] shall cause a full 
report of the circumstances leading to such action and of the action taken to be 
laid before 

4[Parlia­ment] at the earliest possible 
opportunity and in any case within three months from the issue of the 
notification superseding the Board.
  






</section></article> 
 The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934
  
 <article><number>31</number> Issue of demand bills and 
notes.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
No person in 

2[India] other than the Bank, or, as 
expressly authorized by this Act the 

3[Central Government] shall draw, accept, 
make or issue any bill of exchange, hundi, promissory note or engagement for the 
payment of money payable to bearer on demand, or borrow, owe or take up any sum 
or sums of money on the bills, hundis or notes payable to bearer on demand of 
any such person:
 Provided that cheques or drafts, 
including hundis, payable to bearer on demand or otherwise may be drawn on a 
person’s account with a banker, shroff or agent.
 

4[(2) Notwithstanding anything contained 
in the Negotiable In­struments Act, 1881, (26 of 1881) no person in 

2[India] other than the Bank or, as 
expressly authorised by this Act, the Central Government shall make or issue any 
promissory note expressed to be payable to the bearer of the instrument.]
  






</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>32</number> 
    Penalty.—[Rep. 
    by the Reserve Bank of India 
    (Amendment) Act, 1974 (51 of 1974), sec. 9 
w.e.f. 13-12-1974).]  
 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>33</number> 
    Assets of the Issue Department.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The assets of the Issue Department shall consist of gold coin, gold bullion,
    

    1[foreign securities], 
    rupee coin and rupee securities to such aggregate amount as is not less than 
    the total of the liabilities of the Issue Department as hereinafter defined.  
 


    2[(2) The aggregate 
    value of the gold coin, gold bullion and foreign securities held as assets 
    and the aggregate value of the gold coin and gold bullion so held shall not 
    at any time be less than two hundred crores of rupees and one hundred and 
    fifteen crores of rupees, respectively.]  
 


    3[(3) The remainder of 
    the assets shall be held in rupee coin, Government of India rupee securities 
    of any maturity, promissory notes drawn by the National Bank for any loans 
    or advances under clause (4E) of section 17 and such bills of exchange and 
    promis­sory notes payable in India as are eligible for purchase by the Bank 
    under sub-clause (a) or sub-clause (b) or sub-clause (bb) of clause (2) of 
    section 17 or under clause (1) of section 18.]  
 


    4[***]  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> For 
    the purposes of this section, gold coin the gold bullion shall be valuated 
    at 

    5[6[a 
    price not exceeding the international market price for the lime being 
    obtaining]], rupee coin shall be valued at its face value, and securities 
    shall be valued 

    7[at rates not 
    exceeding the market rates] for the time being obtain­ing.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Of 
    the gold coin and gold bullion held as assets, not less than 
    seventeen-twentieths shall be held in 

    8[India], and all gold 
    coin and gold bullion held as assets shall be held in the custody of the 
    Bank or its agencies:  
 
Provided 
    that gold belonging to the Bank which is in any other bank or in any mint or 
    treasury or in transit may be reckoned as part of the assets.  
 


    9[(6) For the purposes 
    of this section, the foreign securities which may be held as part of the 
    assets shall be—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    securities of the 
    following kinds payable in the currency of any foreign country which is a 
    member of the International Mone­tary Fund, namely:—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>a</number>    balances with the 
    bank which is the principal currency au­thority of that foreign country and 
    any other balances or securi­ties in foreign currency maintained with or 
    issued by the Inter­national Monetary Fund, the International Bank for 
    Reconstruction and Development, the International Development Association or 
    the International Finance Corporation 
10[or 
    Asian Development Bank] or the Bank for International Settlements or 
11[any 
    banking or financial institution 
12[approved] 
    by the Central Government] in this behalf provided that they are repayable 
    within a 
13[period 
    of ten years]; 
10[or 
    Asian Development Bank] or the Bank for International Settlements or 
1[any 
    banking or financial institution 
2[approved] 
    by the Central Government] in this behalf provided that they are repayable 
    within a 
3[period 
    of ten years];" 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>b</number>    bills of exchange 
    bearing two or more good signatures and drawn on and payable at any place in 
    that foreign country and having a maturity not exceeding ninety days; and  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>c</number>    Government 
    securities of that foreign country maturing 
14[within 
    ten years]; 
4[within 
    ten years];" 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    any drawing 
    rights representing a liability of the Interna­tional Monetary Fund.  
 
 
















 



</subsection></section></article> 
 The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934
  
 <article><number>34</number> Liabilities of Issue 
Department.—
<section><number>1</number> The Liabilities of 
the Issue Department shall be an amount equal to the total of the amount of the 
currency notes of the Government of India and bank notes for the time being in 
circulation.
 

1[***]
 

2[***]
  




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>35</number> 
    Initial assets and liabilities.—[Rep. 
    by Act 62 of 1948, sec.7 and Sch. (w.e.f. 
1-1-1949).]  
 
 
 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>36</number> 
    Method of dealing with fluctuations in rupee coin assets.—[Rep. 
    by Act 55 of 1963, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 
1-2-1964).]  
 



 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>37</number> Suspension of 
    assets requirements as to foreign securities.— 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in the forego­ing provisions, the Bank 
    may, with the previous sanction of the Central Government, for periods not 
    exceeding six months in the first instance, which may, with the like 
    sanction, be extended from time to time by period not exceeding three months 
    at a time, hold as assets foreign securities of less amount in value than 
    that required by sub-section (2) of section 33:
 


    2[***]
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>38</number> 
    Obligations of Government and the Bank in respect of rupee coin.— 
    The 

    1[Central Government] 
    shall undertake not 

    2[***] to put into 
    circulation any rupees, except through the Bank, 

    3[***] and the Bank 
    shall undertake not to dispose of rupee coin other-wise than for the 
    purposes of circulation 

    4[***].  
 
 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>39</number> 
    Obligation to supply different forms of currency.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Bank shall issue rupee coin on demand in exchange for bank notes and 
    currency notes of the Government of India and shall issue currency notes or 
    bank notes on demand in exchange for coin which is legal tender under the 
    Indian Coinage Act, 1906 (3 of 1906).  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Bank shall, in exchange for currency notes or bank notes of 

    1[two] rupees or 
    upwards, supply currency notes or bank notes of lower value or other coins 
    which are legal tender under the Indian Coinage Act, 1906 (3 of 1906), in 
    such quantities as may, in the opinion of the Bank, be required for 
    circulation; and the 

    2[Central Government] 
    shall supply such coins to the Bank on demand. If the 

    2[Central Government] 
    at any time fails to supply such coins, the Bank shall be released from its 
    obligations to supply them to the public.
 
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>40</number> Transactions 
    in foreign exchange.— 
    The Bank shall sell to or buy from any authorized person who makes a demand 
    in that behalf at its office in Bombay, Calcutta, Delhi or Madras 


    2[or at such or its 
    branches as the Central Government may, by order determine]. foreign 
    exchange at such rates of exchange and on such conditions as the Central 
    Government may from time to time by general or special order determine, 
    having regard so far as rates of exchange are concerned to its obligations 
    to the Inter­national Monetary Fund:
 
Provided 
    that no person shall be entitled to demand to buy or sell foreign exchange 
    of a value less than two lakhs of rupees.
 

    Explanation.—In 
    the section “authorized person” means a person who is entitled by or under 
    the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[Foreign Exchange Regulation Act, 1973 (46 of 1973)] to buy, 
    or as the case may be, sell, the foreign exchange to which his demand 
    relates.]
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>41A</number> 
    Obligation to provide remittance between India and Burma.—[Rep. by 
    Act 11 of 1947, sec. 22 (w.e.f. 
1-4-1947).]]  
 
 



 



</article> 
 The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934
  
 <article><number>42</number> Cash reserves of 
scheduled banks to be kept with the Bank.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
Every bank included in the Second Schedule shall maintain with the Bank an 
average daily balance the amount of which shall not be less than 

2[such per cent. of the total of the 
demand and time liabilities in India of such bank as shown in the return 
referred to in sub-section (2), as the Bank may from time to time, having regard 
to the needs of securing the monetary stability in the country, notify in the 
Gazette of India].
 

3[***]
 Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this section,—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> “average daily balance” shall mean the average of 
the balances held at the close of business of each day
4[of a 
fortnight];
 
        5[(b) 
“fortnight” shall mean the period from Saturday to the second following Friday, 
both days inclusive;]
 
        6[(c) 
“liabilities” shall not include—
 <subsubsection>             <number>i</number> the paid-up capital or the reserves or any 
credit balance in the profit and loss account of the bank;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            <number>ii</number> the amount of any loan taken from the Bank
7[***]
8[or from 
the Exim Bank] 9[or 
from the Recon­struction Bank]
10[or 
from the National Housing Bank] or from the
11[National 
Bank] 12[or 
from the Small Industries Bank]
13[***];
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            <number>iii</number> in the case of a State co-operative bank, 
also any loan taken by such bank from a State Government
14[or 
from the National Co-operative Development Corporation established under the 
Na­tional Co-operative Development Corporation Act, 1962 (26 of 1962)] and any 
deposit of money with such bank representing the reserve fund or any part 
thereof 15[***] 
maintained with it by any co-operative society within its area of operation;
 
            16[(iv)  
in the case of a State co-operative bank, which has granted an advance against 
any balance maintained with it, such balance to the extent of the amount 
outstanding in respect of such advance;]
 
             14[(v) 
in the case a Regional Rural Bank, also any loan taken by such bank from its 
Sponsor Bank;]]
 
     16[(d)  
the aggregate of the liabilities” of a Scheduled bank which is not a State 
co-operative bank, to,—
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>             <number>i</number>  the State Bank;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            <number>ii</number> a subsidiary bank as defined in section 2 
of the State Bank of India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, 1959 (38 of 1959);
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            <number>iii</number> a corresponding new bank constituted by 
section 3 of the Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings) 
Act, 1970 (5 of 1970);
 
          17[(iiia)  
a corresponding new bank constituted by section 3 of the Banking Companies 
(Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings) Act, 1980 (40 of 1980)];
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>           <number>iv</number> a banking company as defined in clause (c) 
section 5 of the Banking Regulation Act, 1949 (10 of 1949);
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            <number>v</number> a co-operative bank; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>           <number>vi</number> any other financial institution notified by 
the Central Government in this behalf,
               shall be reduced by the aggregate of the 
liabilities of all such banks and institutions to the scheduled bank;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number> the aggregate of the “liabilities” of a scheduled 
bank which is a State co-operative bank, to,—
 <subsubsection>             <number>i</number> the State Bank;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            <number>ii</number> a subsidiary bank as defined in section 2 
of the State Bank of India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, 1959 (38 of 1959);
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            <number>iii</number> a corresponding new bank constituted by 
section 3 of the Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings) 
Act, 1970 (5 of 1970);
 
          17[(iiia)  
a corresponding new bank constituted by section 3 of the Banking Companies 
(Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings) Act, 1980 (40 of 1980);]
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>           <number>iv</number> a banking company as defined in clause (c) 
of section 5 of the Banking Regulation Act, 1949 (10 of 1949); or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            <number>v</number> any other financial institution notified by 
the Central Government in this behalf,
               shall be reduced by the aggregate of the 
liabilities of all such banks and institutions to the State co-operative bank.]
 

18[(1A) Notwithstanding anything 
contained in sub-section (1), the Bank may, by notification in the Gazette of 
India, direct that every scheduled bank shall, with effect from such date as may 
be specified in the notification, maintain with the Bank, in addi­tion to the 
balance prescribed by or under sub-section (1), an additional average daily 
balance the amount of which shall not be less than the 

19[rate specified in the notification, 
such addi­tional balance being calculated with reference to the excess of the 
total of the demand and time liabilities of the bank as shown in the return 
referred to in sub-section (2) over the total of its demand and time 
liabilities] at the close of business on the date specified in the notification 
as shown by such return so however, that the additional balance shall, in no 
case, be more than such excess:
 

20[Provided that the Bank may, by a 
separate notification in the Gazette of India, specify different dates in 
respect of a Bank subsequently included in the Second Schedule].
 

21[***]]
 

22[1C) The Bank may, for the purposes of 
this section, specify from time to time with reference to any transaction or 
class of trans­actions that such transaction or transactions shall be regarded 
as liability in India of a scheduled bank, and if any question arises as to 
whether any transaction or class of transactions shall be regarded, for the 
purposes of this section, as liability in India of a scheduled bank, the 
decision of the Bank thereon shall be final.]
 

23[(2) Every scheduled bank shall send to 
the Bank a return signed by two responsible officers of such bank showing—
 <subsubsubsection>       <number>a</number> the amount of its demand and time liabilities and 
the amount of its borrowings from banks in India,
24[classifying 
them into demand and time liabilities],
 

        25[***]
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>       <number>b</number> the total amount of legal tender notes and coins 
held by it in India,
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>       <number>c</number> the balance held by it at the Bank in India,
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>       <number>d</number> the balances held by it at other banks in current 
account and the money at call and short notice in India,
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>       <number>e</number>  the investments (at book value) in Central and 
State Govern­ment securities including treasury bills and treasury deposit 
receipts,
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>        <number>f</number> the amount of advances in India,
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>       <number>g</number> the inland bills purchased and discounted in 
India 26[and 
foreign bills purchased and discounted].
 27[at 
the close of business on each alternate Friday, and every such return shall be 
sent not later than seven days after the date to which it relates:]
 

28[Provided that the Bank may, by 
notification in the Gazette of India, delete or modify or add to any of the 
particulars speci­fied in the foregoing clauses:
 Provided further that] 

29[such alternate] Friday is a public 
holiday under the Negotiable Instruments Act, 1881 (26 of 1881), for one or more 
offices of a scheduled bank the return shall give the preceding working day’s 
figures in respect of such office or offices, but shall nevertheless be deemed 
to relate to that Friday:
 

30[Provided also that where the Bank is 
satisfied that the fur­nishing of a fortnightly return under this sub-section is 
imprac­ticable in the case of any scheduled bank by reason of the geo­graphical 
position of the bank and its branches, the Bank may allow such bank—
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection><subsubsection>        <number>i</number> to furnish a provisional return for the 
fortnight within the period aforesaid to be followed by a final return not later 
than twenty days after the date to which it relates, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>        <number>ii</number> to furnish in lieu of a fortnightly return a 
monthly return to be sent not later than twenty days after the end of the month 
to which it relates giving the details specified in this sub-section in respect 
of such bank at the close of business for the month.]]
 

31[(2A) Where the last Friday of a month 
is not an alternate Friday for the purpose of sub-section(2), every scheduled 
bank shall send to the Bank, a special return giving the details specified in 
sub-section (2) as at the close of business on such last Friday or where such 
last Friday is a public holiday under the Negotiable Instruments Act, 1881 (26 
of 1881), as at the close of business on the preceding working day and such 
return shall be sent not later than seven days after the date to which it 
re­lates.]
 

32[(3) If the average daily balance held 
at the Bank by a sched­uled bank during any 

33[fortnight] is below the minimum 
prescribed by or under sub-section (1) or sub-section (1A), such scheduled bank 
shall be liable to pay to the Bank in respect of that 

33[fortnight] penal interest at a rate of 
three per cent. above the bank rate on the amount by which such balance with the 
Bank falls short of the prescribed minimum, and if during the next succeeding


33[fortnight], such average daily balance 
is still below the prescribed minimum, the rates of penal interest shall be 
increased to a rate of five per cent. above the bank rate in respect of that


33[fortnight] and each subsequent 

33[fortnight] during which the default 
continues on the amount by which such balance at the Bank falls short of the 
prescribed minimum.]
 

34[(3A) When under the provisions of 
sub-section (3) penal inter­est at the increased rate of five per cent. above 
the bank rate has become payable by a scheduled bank, 

35[if thereafter the average daily 
balance held at the Bank during the next succeeding 

33[fortnight] is still below the 
prescribed minimum, —
 <subsubsubsection>       <number>a</number> every director, manager or secretary of the 
scheduled bank, who is knowingly and wilfully a party to the default, shall be 
punishable with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees and with a further 
fine which may extend to five hundred rupees for each subsequent
33[fortnight] 
during which the default continues, and
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>       <number>b</number> the Bank may prohibit the scheduled bank from 
receiving after the said
33[fortnight] 
any fresh deposit,]
 and, if default is made by the scheduled bank in complying with the 
prohibition referred to in clause (b), every director and officer of the 
scheduled bank who is knowingly and wilfully a party to such default or who 
through negligence or otherwise contributes to such default shall in respect of 
each such default be punishable with fine which may extend to five hundred 
rupees and with a further fine which may extend to five hundred rupees for each 
day after the first on which a deposit received in contravention of such 
prohibition is retained by the scheduled bank.
 Explanation.—In 
this sub-section “officer” includes a 

36[***] manager, secretary, branch 
manager, and branch secretary.]
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection></section><section><number>4</number> Any scheduled bank failing 
to comply with the provisions of sub-section (2) 

37[shall be liable to pay to the Bank] a 
penalty of one hundred rupees for each day during which the failure continues.
 

38[(5) (a) The penalties imposed by 
sub-sections (3) and (4) shall be payable within a period of fourteen days from 
the date on which a notice issued by the Bank demanding the payment of the same 
is served on the scheduled bank, and in the event of failure of the scheduled 
bank to pay the same within such period, may be levied by a direction of the 
principal civil court having juris­diction in the area where an office of the 
defaulting bank is situated, such direction to be mode only upon an application 
made in this behalf to the court by the Bank;
 <subsection><number>b</number> when the court makes a 
direction under clause (a), it shall issue a certificate specifying the sum 
payable by the scheduled bank and every such certificate shall be enforceable in 
the same manner as if it were a decree made by the court in a suit;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> notwithstanding anything 
contained in this section, if the Bank is satisfied that the defaulting bank and 
sufficient cause for its failure to comply with the provisions of sub-section 
(1), (1A) or (2), it may not demand the payment of the penal interest of the 
penalty, as the case may be.]
 

39[(6) The Bank shall, save as 
hereinafter provided, by notifica­tion in the Gazette of India,—
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>a</number>  direct the inclusion in the Second Schedule of 
any bank not already so included which carries on the business of banking
40[in 
India] and which—
 <subsubsection>             <number>i</number> has a paid-up capital and reserve of an 
aggregate value of not less than five lakhs or rupees, and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            <number>ii</number> satisfies and Bank that its affairs are not 
being conducted in a manner detrimental to the interests of its depositors, and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            <number>iii</number> 
41[is a 
State co-operative bank or a company] as defined
42[section 
3 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), or an insti­tution notified by the 
Central Government in this behalf] or a corporation or a company incorporated by 
or under any law in force in any place
43[outside 
India];
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> direct the exclusion from that Schedule of any 
scheduled bank,—
 <subsubsection>             <number>i</number> the aggregate value of whose paid-up 
capital and reserves becomes at any time less than five lakhs of rupees, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            <number>ii</number> which is, in the opinion of the Bank after 
making an inspec­tion under section 35 of the
44[Banking 
Regulation Act, 1949] (10 of 1949), conducting its affairs to the detriment of 
the interests of its depositors, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            <number>iii</number> which goes into liquidation or otherwise 
ceases to carry on banking business:
                  Provided that the Bank may, on application 
of the scheduled bank concerned and subject to such conditions, if any, as it 
may impose, defer the making of a direction under sub-clause (i) or sub-clause 
(ii) of clause(b) for such period as the Bank consider reasonable to give the 
scheduled bank an opportunity of increas­ing the aggregate value of its paid-up 
capital and reserves to not less than five lakhs of rupees or, as the case may 
be, of remov­ing the defects in the conduct of its affairs;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number> alter the description in that Schedule whenever 
any scheduled bank changes its name.
 Explanation.—In 
this sub-section the expression “value” means the real or exchangeable value and 
not the nominal value which may be shown in the boods of the bank concerned; and 
if any dispute arises in computing the aggregate value of the paid-up capital 
and reserves of a bank, a determination thereof by the Bank shall be final for 
the purposes of this sub-section.]
 

45[(6A) In considering whether a State 
co-operative bank or a regional rural bank should be included in or excluded 
from the Second Schedule, it shall be competent for the Bank to act on a 
certificate from the National Bank on the question whether or not a State 
co-operative bank or a regional rural bank, as the case may be, satisfies the 
requirements as to paid-up capital and reserves or whether its affairs are not 
being conducted in a manner detrimental to the interests of its depositors.]
 

46[(7) The Bank may, for such period and 
subject to such condi­tions as may be specified, grant to any scheduled bank 
such exemp­tions from the provisions of this section as it thinks fit with 
reference to all or any of its offices or with reference to the whole or any 
part of its assets and liabilities.]
  





















































</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>43</number> Publication of 
    consolidated statement by the Bank.— The Bank shall cause to be 
    published each 

    2[fortnight] a 
    consolidated state­ment showing the aggregate liabilities and assets of all 
    the scheduled banks together, based on the returns and information received 
    under this Act or any other law for the time being in force.]
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>43A</number> Protection of 
    action taken in good faith.—
<section><number>1</number> No suit or other legal proceeding shall 
    lie against the Bank or any of its officers for anything which is in good 
    faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of section 42 or section 43
    

    2[or in pursuance of 
    the provisions of Chapter IIIA].  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No 
    suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Bank or any of its 
    officers for any damage caused or likely to be caused by anything which is 
    in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of section 42 or 
    section 43 

    2[or in pursuance of 
    the provisions of Chapter IIIA].]  
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>44</number> 
    Power to require returns from co-operative banks.—
[Rep. by the Banking Laws (Application to Co-operative Societies) 
    Act, 1965 (23 of 1965), sec. 7 (w.e.f. 
1-3-1966).]  
 



 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>45</number> Appointment of 
    agents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Unless otherwise directed by the Central Government with reference to any 
    place, the Bank may, having regard to public interest, convenience of 
    banking, banking development and such other factors which in its opinion are 
    relevant in this regard, appoint the National Bank, or the State Bank, or a 
    corresponding new bank constituted under section 3 of the Banking Companies 
    (Acquisition and Transfer of undertakings) 
    Act, 1970 (5 of 1970), or a corresponding new bank consti­tuted under 
    section 3 of the Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of 
    Undertakings) Act, 1980 (40 of 1980), or any subsidi­ary bank as defined in 
    the State Bank of India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, 1959 (38 of 1959), as its 
    agent at all places, or at any place in India for such purposes as the Bank 
    may specify.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When any 
    bank is appointed by the Bank as its agent under sub-section (1) to receive 
    on behalf of the Bank any payment required to be made into the Bank, or any 
    bill, hundies or jother securities required to be delivered into the Bank, 
    under any law or rule, regulations or other instructions having the force of 
    law, the same may be paid or delivered into the bank so appointed as the 
    agent of the Bank.]
 
 



 



</section></article> 
 The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934
  
 <article>*<number>45A</number> Definitions.—In 
this Chapter, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  “banking company’ means a banking company as 
defined in section 5 of the
1[Banking 
Regulation Act, 1949] (10 of 1949) and includes the State Bank of India,
2[any 
subsidiary bank as defined in the State Bank of India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, 
1959 (38 of 1959), any corresponding new bank constituted by section 3 of the 
Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertak­ings) Act, 1970 (5 of 
1970), and any other financial institution notified by the Central Government in 
this behalf];
 </section><section>       <number>b</number> “borrower” means any person to whom any credit 
limit has been sanctioned by any banking company, whether availed of or not, and 
includes—
 <subsection>             <number>i</number> in the case of a company or corporation, 
its subsidiaries;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>ii</number> in the case of a Hindu undivided family, 
any member thereof or any firm in which such member is a partner;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>iii</number> in the case of a firm, any partner thereof 
or any other firm in which such partner is a partner; and
 </subsection><subsection>           <number>iv</number> in the case of an individual, any firm in 
which such indi­vidual is a partner;
 </subsection></section><section>       <number>c</number>  “credit information” means any information 
relating to—
 <subsection>             <number>i</number> the amounts and the nature of loans or 
advances and other credit facilities granted by a banking company to any 
borrower or class of borrowers;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>ii</number> the nature of security taken from any 
borrower 3[or 
class of borrowers] for credit facilities
4[granted 
to him or to such class];
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>iii</number> the guarantee furnished by a banking 
company for any of its customers
3[or any 
class of its customers];
 
               3[(iv)  
the means, antecedents, history of financial transactions and the 
creditworthiness of any borrower or class of borrowers;]
 
3[(v)  
any other information which the Bank may consider to be relevant for the more 
orderly regulation of credit or credit policy.]
  







</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
*<number>45B</number> 
    Power of Bank to collect credit information.—The 
    Bank may—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    collect, in such 
    manner as it may think fit, credit informa­tion from banking compaines; and  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    furnish such 
    information to any banking company in accordance with the provisions of 
    section 45D.  
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
*<number>45C</number> 
    Power to call for returns containing credit information.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    For the purpose of enabling the Bank to dis­charge its functions under this 
    Chapter, it may at any time direct any banking company to submit to it such 
    statements relat­ing to such credit information and in such form and within 
    such time as may be specified by the Bank from time to time.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    banking company shall, notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in 
    any law for the time being in force on in any instrument regulating the 
    constitution thereof or in any agreement executed by it, relating to the 
    secrecy of its deal­ings with its constituents, be bound to comply with any 
    direction issued under sub-section (1).  
 
 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
*<number>45D</number> 
    Procedure for furnishing credit information to banking companies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A banking company may, in connection with any financial arrangement entered 
    into or proposed to be entered into by it, with any person, make an 
    application to the Bank in such form as the Bank may specify requesting it 
    to furnish the applic­ant with such credit information as may be specified 
    in the application.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On 
    receipt of an application under sub-section (1), the Bank shall, as soon as 
    may be, furnish the applicant with such credit information relating to the 
    matters specified in the application, as may be in its possession:  
 
Provided 
    that the information so furnished shall not disclose the names of the 
    banking companies which have submitted such informa­tion to the Bank.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Bank may in respect of each application levy such fees, not exceeding 
    twenty-five rupees, as it may deem fit for furnish­ing credit information.
 
 



 



</section></article> 
 The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934
  
 <article>*<number>45E</number> Disclosure of 
information prohibited.—
<section><number>1</number> Any 
credit infor­mation contained in any statement submitted by a banking company 
under section 45C or furnished by the Bank to any banking company under section 
45D, shall be treated as confidential and shall not, except for the purposes of 
this Chapter, be published or other­wise disclosed.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Nothing in this section 
shall apply to—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> the disclosure by any banking company, with the 
previous permission of the Bank, of any information furnished to the Bank under 
section 45C;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> the publication by the Bank, if it considers 
necessary in the public interest so to do, of any information collected by it 
under section 45C, in such consolidated form as it may think fit without 
disclosing the name of any banking company or its borrow­ers;
 
        1[(c)  
the disclosure or publication by the banking company or by the Bank of any 
credit information to any other banking company or in accordance with the 
practice and usage customary among bankers or as permitted or required under any 
other law:
                  Provided that any credit information 
received by a banking compa­ny under this clause shall not be published except 
in accordance with the practice and usage customary among bankers or as 
permit­ted or required under any other law.]
 
2[(d) the 
disclosures of any credit information under the Credit Information Companies 
(Regulation) Act, 2005.]
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in any law for the time being in force, no court, tribunal or other 
authority shall compel the Bank or any banking company to produce or to give 
inspection of any statement submitted by that banking company under section 45C 
or to disclose any credit information furnished by the Bank to that banking 
company under section 45D.
  





</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
*<number>45F</number> 
    Certain claims for compensation barred.—No 
    person shall have any right, whether in contract or otherwise, to any 
    compen­sation for any loss incurred by reason of the operation of any of the 
    provisions of this Chapter.  
 
 




 



</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>45G</number> Penalties. </title>—[ Rep. by the Reserve Bank 
of India (Amendment) Act, 1974 (51 of 1974), sec. 15 (w.e.f. 13-12-1974 ) 
.]] 

</article> 
 The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934
  
 <article><number>45H</number> Chapter IIIB not to 
apply in certain cases.—The 
provi­sions of this Chapter shall not apply to the State Bank or a banking 
company as defined in section 5 of the 

1[Banking Regula­tion Act, 1949] (10 of 
1949) or 

2[a corresponding new bank as defined in 
clause (da) of section 5 of the Act or a subsidiary bank as defined in State 
Bank of India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, 1959 (38 of 1959)] or 

3[a Regional Rural Bank or a co-operative 
bank or a primary agricultural credit society or a primary credit society]:
 Provided that for the purposes 
of this Chapter, the 

4[Tamil Nadu Industrial Investment 
Corporation Limited] shall not be deemed to be a banking company.
  






</article> 
 The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934
  
 <article><number>45-I</number> 
Definitions.—In this Chapter, unless 
the context otherwise requires,—
         
1[
<section><number>a</number>  “business of a non-banking financial institution” means 
carrying on the business of a financial institution referred to in clause (c) 
and includes business of a non-banking financial company referred to in clause 
(f);]
    
2[(aa)]  “company” means a company as defined in section 3 of the 
Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), and includes a foreign company within the 
meaning of section 591 of that Act;
 </section><section>       <number>b</number> “corporation” means a 
corporation incorporated by an Act of any ligislature;
      
3[(bb)  “deposit” includes and shall be deemed always to have 
include any receipt of money by way of deposit or loan or in any other form, but 
does not include,—
 <subsection>             
<number>i</number> amounts raised by way of share capital;
 </subsection><subsection>            
<number>ii</number> amounts contributed as capital by partners of a firm;
 </subsection><subsection>            
<number>iii</number> amounts received from a scheduled bank or a co-operative bank or any other 
banking company as defined in clause (c) of section 5 of a Banking Regulation 
Act, 1949 (10 of 1949);
 </subsection><subsection>           
<number>iv</number>  any amount received from,—
 
4[***]  

 </subsection></section><section>                 
<number>b</number> a State Financial Corporation,
 </section><section>                 
<number>c</number> any financial institution specified in or under section 6A of the Industrial 
Development Bank of India Act, 1964 (18 of 1964), or
 </section><section>                 
<number>d</number> any other institution that may be specified by the Bank in this behalf;
 <subsection>            
<number>v</number> amounts received in the ordinary course of business, by way of—
 <subsubsection>                 
<number>a</number> security deposit,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>                 
<number>b</number> dealership deposit,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>                 
<number>c</number> earnest money, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>                 
<number>d</number> advance against orders for goods, properties or services;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>           
<number>vi</number> any amount received from an individual or a firm or an association of 
individuals not being a body corporate, registered under any enactment relating 
to money lending which is for the time being in force in any State; and
 </subsection><subsection>           
<number>vii</number> any amount received by way of subscriptions in respect of a chit.
                  
Explanation I.—“Chit” has the meaning assigned to it in clause (b) of 
section 2 of the Chit Funds Act, 1982 (40 of 1982).
                  
Explanation II.— Any credit given by a seller to a buyer on the sale of any 
property (whether movable or immovable) shall not be deemed to be deposit for 
the purposes of this clause;]
         
5[(c)  “financial institution” means any non-banking institution 
which carries on as its business or part of its business any of the following 
activities, namely:—
 </subsection><subsection>             
<number>i</number> the financing, whether by way of making loans or advances or othervise, of 
any activity other than its own;
 </subsection><subsection>            
<number>ii</number> the acquisition of shares, stock, bonds, debentures or securities issued by 
a Government or local authority or other marketable securities of a like 
nature;
 </subsection><subsection>            
<number>iii</number> letting or delivering of any goods to a hirer under a hire-purchase 
agreement as defined in clause (c) of section 2 of the Hire-Purchase Act, 1972 
(26 of 1972);
 </subsection><subsection>           
<number>iv</number> the carrying on of any class of insurance business;
 </subsection><subsection>            
<number>v</number> managing, conducting or supervising, as foreman, agent or in any other 
capacity, of chits or kuries as defined in any law which is for the time being 
in force in any State, or any business, which is similar thereto;
 </subsection><subsection>           
<number>vi</number> collecting, for any purpose or under any scheme or arrangement by whatever 
name called, monies in Iump sum or otherwise, by way of subscriptions or by sale 
of units, or other instruments or in any other manner and awarding prizes or 
gifts, whether in cash or king, or disbursing monies in any other way, to 
persons from whom monies are collected or to any other person,
                        
6[but does not include any institution, which carries on as its principal 
business,—
 <subsubsection>                 
<number>a</number> agricultural operations; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>               
<number>aa</number> industrial activity; or]
                             
7[Explanation.—For the purposes of this clause, “industrial 
activity” means any activity specified in sub-clauses (i) to (xviii) of clause 
(c) of section 2 of the Industrial Development Bank of India Act, 1964 (18 of 
1964);]
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            
<number>b</number> the purchase, or sale of any goods (other than securities) or the providing 
of any services; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            
<number>c</number> the purchase, construction or sale of immovable property, so, however, that 
no portion of the income of the institution is de­rived from the financing 
of purchases, constructions or sales of immovable property by other 
persons;]
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            
<number>d</number>  “firm” means a firm as defined in the Indian Partnership Act, 1932 (9 
of 1932) 8[***];
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            
<number>e</number> “non-banking institution” means a company, corporation, 9[or co-operative 
society];
               
10[(f)  “non-banking financial company” means—
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>                  
<number>i</number> a financial institution which is a company;
 </subsection><subsection>                 
<number>ii</number> a non-banking institution which is a company and which has as its principal 
business the receiving of deposits, under any scheme or arrangement or in any 
other manner, or lending in any manner;
 </subsection><subsection>                 
<number>iii</number> such other non-banking institution or class of such institu­tions, as 
the Bank may, with the previous approval of the Central Government and by 
notification in the Official Gazette, specify.]















</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>45-IA</number> Requirement 
    of registration and net owned fund.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwith-standing anything 
    contained in this Chapter or in any other law for the time being in force, 
    no non-banking financial company shall commence or carry on the business of 
    a non-banking financial institution without—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    obtaining a 
    certificate of registration issued under this Chapter; and 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    having the net 
    owned fund of twenty-five lakh rupees or such other amount, not exceeding 
    two hundred lakh rupees, as the Bank may, by notification in the Official 
    Gazette, specify.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    non-banking financial company shall make an application for registration to 
    the Bank in such form as the Bank may speci­fy:  
 
Provided 
    that a non-banking financial company in existence on the commencement of the 
    Reserve Bank of India (Amendment) Act, 1997 shall make an application for 
    registration to the Bank before the expiry of six months from such 
    commencement and notwith­standing anything contained in sub-section (1) may 
    continue to carry on the business of a non-banking financial institution 
    until a certificate of registration is issued to it or rejection of 
    application for registration is communicated to it.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), a non-banking 
    financial company in existence on the commencement of the Reserve Bank of 
    India (Amendment) Act, 1997 and having a net owned fund of less than 
    twenty-five lakh rupees may, for the purpose of enabling such company to 
    fulfil the requirement of the net owned fund, continue to carry on the 
    business of a non-banking financial institution—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    for a period of 
    there years from such commencement; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    for such further 
    period as the Bank may, after recording the reasons in writing for so doing, 
    extend,  
 
subject to the condition that such company 
    shall, within three months of fulfilling the requirement of the net owned 
    fund, inform the Bank about such fulfilment:
 
Provided 
    that the period allowed to continue business under this sub-section shall in 
    no case exceed six years in the aggregate.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Bank, for the purpose of considering the application for registration, may 
    require to be satisfied by an inspection of the books of the non-banking 
    financial company or otherwise that the following conditions are fulfilled:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    that the 
    non-banking financial company is or shall be in a position to pay its 
    present or future depositors in full as and when their claims accrue;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    that the affairs 
    of the non-banking financial company are not being or are not likely to be 
    conducted in a manner detrimental to the interest of its present or future 
    depositors;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    that the general 
    character of the management or the proposed management of the non-banking 
    financial company shall not be prejudicial to the public interest or the 
    interests of its de­positors;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    that the 
    non-banking financial company has adequate capital structure and earning 
    prospects;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    that the public 
    interest shall be served by the grant of certificate of registration to the 
    non-banking financial company to commence or to carry on the business of 
    India;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    that the grant of 
    certificate of registration shall not be prejudicial to the operation and 
    consolidation of the financial sector consistent with monetary stability and 
    economic growth considering such other relevant factors which the Bank may, 
    by notification in the Official Gazette, specify; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    any other 
    condition, fulfilment of which in the opinion of the Bank, shall be 
    necessary to ensure that the commencement of or carrying on of the business 
    in India by a non-banking financial company shall not be prejudicial to the 
    public interest or in the interests of the depositors.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Bank may, after being satisfied that the conditions specified in sub-section 
    (4) are fulfilled, grant a certificate of registration subject to such 
    conditions which it may consider fit to impose.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    Bank cancel a certificate of registration granted to a non-banking financial 
    company under this section if such company—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    ceases to carry on 
    the business of a non-banking financial institution in India; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    has failed to 
    comply with any condition subject to which the certificate of registration 
    had been issued to it; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    at any time 
    fails to fulfil any of the conditions referred to in clauses (d) to (g) of 
    sub-section (4); or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    fails—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>a</number>    to comply with any 
    direction issued by the Bank under the provisions of this Chapter; or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>b</number>    to maintain 
    accounts in accordance with the requirements of any law or any direction or 
    order issued by the Bank under the provisions of this Chapter; or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>c</number>    to submit or offer 
    for inspection its books of account and other relevant documents when so 
    demanded by an inspecting authority of the Bank; or  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>    has been 
    prohibited from accepting deposit by an order made by the Bank under the 
    provisions of this Chapter and such order has been in force for a period of 
    not less than three months:  
 
Provided 
    that before cancelling a certificate of registration on the ground that the 
    non-banking financial company has failed to company with the provisions of 
    clause (ii) or has failed to fulfil any of the conditions referred to in 
    clause (iii) the Bank, unless it is of the opinion that the delay in 
    cancelling the certificate of registration shall be prejudicial to public 
    interest or the interest of the depositors or the non-banking financial 
    company, shall give an opportunity to such company on such term as the Bank 
    may specify for taking necessary steps to comply with such provision or 
    fulfilment of such condition:  
 
Provided 
    further that before making any order of cancellation of certificate of 
    registration, such company shall be given a reasonable opportunity of being 
    heard.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>7</number> A 
    company aggrieved by the order of rejection of application for registration 
    or cancellation of certificate of registration may prefer an appeal, within 
    a period of thirty days from the date on which such order of rejection or 
    cancellation is communicated to it, to the Central Government and the 
    decision of the Central Government where an appeal has been preferred to it, 
    or of the Bank where no appeal has been preferred, shall be final:  
 
Provided 
    that before making any order of rejection of appeal, such company shall be 
    given a reasonable opportunity of being heard.  
 <subsection>

    <number>Explanations</number>—For 
    the purposes of this section,—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>I</number>    “net owned fund” 
    means—  
 <subsubsubsection>
<number>a</number>    the aggregate of 
    the paid-up equity capital and free reserves as disclosed in the latest 
    balance-sheet of the company after deducting there from—  
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    accumulated 
    balance of loss;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    deferred revenue 
    expenditure; and  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>    other intangible 
    assets; and  
 <subsubsubsection>
<number>b</number>  further reduced by the amounts 
    representing—  
 
(1)    investments of 
    such company in shares of—  
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    its subsidiaries;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    companies in the 
    same group;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>    all other 
    non-banking financial companies; and  
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number>    the book value of 
    debentures, bonds, outstanding loans and advances (including hire-purchase 
    and lease finance) made to, and deposits with,—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    subsidiaries of such 
    company; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   companies in the same group,
 
to the extent such book value exceeds ten per 
    cent, of (a) above.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>II</number>    “subsidiaries” and 
    “companies in the same group” shall have the same meanings assigned to them 
    in the Companies Act, 1956, (1 of 1956).]
 
 



 



</subsection></section></article> 
 The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934
  
 <article>

1[<number>45-IB</number> Maintenance of percentage of 
assets.—
<section><number>1</number> Every non-banking 
financial company shall invest and continue to invest in India in unencumbered 
approved securities, valued at a price not exceeding the current market price of 
such securities, an amount which, at the close of business on any day, shall not 
be less than five per cent. or such higher percentage not exceeding twenty-five 
per cent. as the Bank may, from time to time and by notification in the Official 
Gazette, specify, of the deposits outstanding at the close of business on the 
last working day of the second preceding quarter:
 Provided that the Bank may 
specify different percentages of investment in respect of different classes of 
non-banking finan­cial companies.
 </section><section><number>2</number> For the purpose of ensuring 
compliance with the provisions of this section, the Bank may require every 
non-banking financial company to furnish a return to it in such form, in such 
manner and for such period as may be specified by the Bank.
 </section><section><number>3</number> If the amount invested by a 
non-banking financial company at the close of business on any day falls below 
the rate specified under sub-section (1), such company shall be liable to pay to 
the Bank, in respect of such shortfall, a penal interest at a rate of three per 
cent. per annum above the bank rate on such amount by which the amount actually 
invested falls short of the specified percentage, and where the shortfall 
continues in the subsequent quarters, the rate of penal interest shall be five 
per cent. per annum above the bank rate on such shortfall for each subsequent 
quarter.
 </section><section><number>4</number> (a) The penal interest 
payable under sub-section (3) shall be payable within a period of fourteen days 
from the date on which a notice issued by the Bank demanding payment of the same 
is served on the non-banking financial company and, in the event of a failure of 
the non-banking financial company to pay the same within such period, penalty 
may be levied by a direction of the principal civil court having jurisdiction in 
the area where an office of the defaulting non-banking financial company is 
situated and such direction shall be made only upon an application made in this 
behalf to the court by the Bank; and
 <subsection><number>b</number> when the court makes a 
direction under clause (a), it shall issue a certificate specifying the sum 
payable by the non-banking financial company and every such certificate shall be 
enforceable in the same manner as if it were a decree made by the court in a 
suit.
 </subsection></section><section><number>5</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in this section, if the Bank is satisfied that the defaulting 
non-banking financial company had sufficient cause for its failure to comply 
with the provisions of sub-section (1), it may not demand the payment of the 
penal interest.
 Explanation.—For 
the purpose of this section,—
 <subsection>        <number>i</number> “approved securities” means securities of any 
State Govern­ment or of the Central Government and such bonds, both the 
prin­cipal whereof and the interest whereon shall have been fully and 
unconditionally guaranteed by any such Government;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>ii</number> “unencumbered approved securities” includes the 
approved securities lodged by the non-banking financial company with another 
institution for an advance or any other arrangement to the extent to which such 
securities have not been drawn against or availed of or encumbered in any 
manner;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number> “quarter” means the period of three months 
ending on the last day of March, June, September or December.]
  



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>45-IC</number> Reserve fund.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every non-banking financial company shall create a reserve fund the transfer 
    therein a sum not less than twenty per cent of its net profit every year as 
    disclosed in the profit and loss account and before any dividend is 
    declared.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No 
    appropriation of any sum from the reserve fund shall be made by the 
    non-banking financial company except for the purpose as may be specified by 
    the Bank from time to time and every such appropriation shall be reported to 
    the Bank within twenty-one days from the date of such withdrawal:  
 
Provided 
    that the Bank may, in any particular case and for suffi­cient cause being 
    shown, extend the period of twenty-one days by such further period as it 
    thinks fit or condone any delay in making such report.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), the Central 
    Government may, on the recommendation of the Bank and having regard to the 
    adequacy of the paid-up capital and reserves of a non-banking financial 
    company in relation to its deposit liabilities, declare by order in writing 
    that the provisions of sub-section (1) shall not be applicable to the 
    non-banking finan­cial company for such period as may be specified in the 
    order:  
 
Provided 
    that no such order shall be made unless the amount in the reserve fund under 
    sub-section (1) together with the amount in the share premium account is not 
    less than the paid-up capital of the non-banking financial company.]  
 
 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
*<number>45J</number> 
    Bank to regulate or prohibit issue of prospectus or adver­tisement 
    soliciting deposits of money.— 
    The Bank may, if it consider necessary in the public interest so to do, by 
    general or special order,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    regulate or 
    prohibit the issue by any non-banking institution of any prospectus or 
    advertisement soliciting deposits of money from the public, and  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    specify the conditions 
    subject to which any such prospectus or advertisement, if not prohibited, 
    may be issued.
 
 
 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>45JA</number> Power of Bank 
    to determine policy and issue directions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If the Bank is satisfied that, in the public interest or to regulate the 
    financial system of the country to its advantage or to prevent the affairs 
    of any non-banking finan­cial company being conducted in manner detrimental 
    to the inter­est of the depositors or in a manner prejudicial to the 
    interest of the non-banking financial company, it is necessary or expedi­ent 
    so to do, it may determine the policy and give directions to all or any of 
    the non-banking financial companies relating to income recognition, 
    accounting standards, making of proper provi­sion for bad and doubtful 
    debts, capital adequacy based on risk weights for assets and credit 
    conversion factors for off balance-sheet items and also relating to 
    deployment of funds by a non-banking financial company or a class of 
    non-banking financial companies or non-banking financial companies 
    generally, as the case may be, and such non-banking financial companies 
    shall be bound to follow the policy so determined and the direction so 
    issued.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Without prejudice to the generality of the powers vested under sub-section 
    (1), the Bank may give directions to non-banking financial companies 
    generally or to a class of non banking finan­cial companies or to any 
    non-banking financial company in partic­ular as to—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the purpose for which 
    advances or other fund based or non-fund based accommodation may not be 
    made; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the maximum amount of 
    advances of other financial accommoda­tion or investment in shares and other 
    securities which, having regard to the paid-up capital, reserves and 
    deposits of the non-banking financial company and other relevant 
    considerations, may be made by that non-banking financial company to any 
    person or a company or to a group of companies.]
 
 



 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
*<number>45K</number> 
    Power of Bank to collect information from non-banking insti­tutions as to 
    deposits and to give directions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Bank may at any time direct that every non-banking institution shall 
    furnish to the Bank, in such form, at such intervals and within such time, 
    such statements information or particulars relating to or connected with 
    deposits received by the non-banking institu­tion, as may be specified by 
    the Bank by general or special order.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Without prejudice to the generality of the power vested in the Bank under 
    sub-section (1), the statements, information or particulars to be furnished 
    under sub-section (1), may relate to all or any of the following matters, 
    namely, the amount of the deposits, the purposes and periods for which, and 
    the rates of interest and other terms and conditions on which, they are 
    re­ceived.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Bank may, if it considers necessary in the public inter­est so to do, give 
    directions to non-banking institutions either generally or to any 
    non-banking institution or group of non-banking institutions in particular, 
    in respect of any matters relating to or connected with the receipt of 
    deposits, including the rates of interest payable on such deposits, and the 
    periods for which deposits may be received.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If 
    any non-banking institution fails to comply with any direction given by the 
    Bank under sub-section (3), the Bank may prohibit the acceptance of deposits 
    by that non-banking institu­tion.  
 


    1[***]  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Every 
    non-banking institution receiving deposits shall, if so required by the Bank 
    and within such time as the Bank may speci­fy, cause to be sent at the cost 
    of the non-banking institution a copy of its annual balance-sheet and profit 
    and loss account or other annual accounts to every person from whom the 
    non-banking institution holds, as on the last day of the year to which the 
    accounts relate, deposits higher than such sum as may be speci­fied by the 
    Bank.  
 
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
*<number>45L</number> 
    Power of Bank to call for information from financial institutions and to 
    give directions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If the Bank is satisfied for the purpose of enabling it to regulate the 
    credit system of the country to its advantage it is necessary so to do, it 
    may—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    require financial 
    institutions either generally or any group of financial institutions or 
    financial institution in particular, to furnish to the Bank in such form, at 
    such intervals and within such time, such statements, information or 
    particulars relating to the business of such financial institutions or 
    institution, as may be specified by the Bank by general or special order;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    give to such 
    institutions either generally or to any such institution in particular, 
    directions relating to the conduct of business by them or by it as financial 
    institutions or institu­tion.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Without prejudice to the generality of the power vested in the Bank under 
    clause (a) of sub-section (1), the statements, informa­tion or particulars 
    to be furnished by a financial institution may relate to all or any of the 
    following matters, namely, the paid-up capital, reserves or other 
    liabilities, the investments whether in Government securities or otherwise, 
    the persons to whom, and the purposes and periods for which, finance is 
    provided and the terms and conditions, including the rates of interest, on 
    which it is provided.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In 
    issuing directions to any financial institution under clause (b) of 
    sub-section (1). the Bank shall have due regard to the conditions in which, 
    and the objects for which, the institu­tion has been established, its 
    statutory responsibilities, if any, and the effect the business of such 
    financial institution is likely to have on trends in the money and capital 
    markets.  







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
*<number>45M</number> 
    Duty of non-banking institutions to furnish statements, etc., required by 
    Bank.—It 
    shall be the duty or every non-banking institution to furnish the 
    statements, information or particulars called for, and to comply with any 
    direction given to it, under the provisions of this Chapter.
 




 



</article> 
 The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934
  
 <article>

1[<number>45MA</number> Powers and duties of auditors.—
<section><number>1</number> 
It shall be the duty of an auditor of a non-banking institution to inquire 
whether or not the non-banking institution has furnished to the Bank such 
statements, information or particulars relating to or connected with deposits 
received by it, as are required to be furnished under this Chapter, and the 
auditor shall, except where he is satisfied on such inquiry that the non-banking 
institution has furnished such statements, information or particulars, make a 
report to the Bank giving the aggregate amount of such deposits held by the 
non-banking institution.
 

2[(1A) The Bank may, on being satisfied 
that it is necessary so to do, in the public interest or in the interest of the 
deposi­tors or for the purpose of proper assessment of the books of accounts, 
issue directions to any non-banking financial company or any class of 
non-banking financial companies or non-banking financial companies generally or 
to the auditors of such non-banking financial company or companies relating to 
balance-sheet, profit and loss account, disclosure of liabilities in the books 
of accounts or any matter relating thereto.]
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where, in the case of 

3[a non-banking financial company], the 
auditor has made, or intends to make, a report to the Bank under sub-section 
(1), he shall include in his report under sub-section (2) of section 227 of the 
Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), the contents of the report which he has made or 
intends to make, to the Bank.]
 

4[(3) Where the bank is of the opinion 
that it is necessary so to do in the public interest or in the interest of the 
non-banking financial company or in the interest of depositors of such compa­ny 
it may at any time by order direct that a special audit of the accounts of the 
non-banking financial company in relation to any such transaction or class of 
transactions or for such period or periods, as may be specified in the order, 
shall be conducted and the Bank may appoint an auditor or auditors to conduct 
such special audit and direct the auditor or the auditors to submit the report 
to it.]
 

4[(4) The remuneration of the auditors as 
may be fixed by the Bank, having regard to the nature and volume of work 
involved in the audit and the expenses of or incidental to the audit, shall be 
borne by the non-banking financial company so audited.]
  






</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>45MB</number> Power of Bank 
    to prohibit acceptance of deposit and aliena­tion of assets.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If any non-banking financial company vio­lates the provisions of any section 
    or fails to comply with any direction or order given by the Bank under any 
    of the provisions of this Chapter, the Bank may prohibit the non-banking 
    financial company from accepting any deposit.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any agreement or 
    instruments or any law for the time being in force, the Bank, on being 
    satisfied that it is necessary so to do in the public interest or in the 
    interest of the depositors, may direct, the non-banking financial company 
    against which an order prohib­iting from accepting deposit has been issued, 
    not to sell, trans­fer, create charge or mortgage or deal in any manner with 
    its property and assets without prior written permission of the Bank for 
    such period not exceeding six months from the date of the order.]
 
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>45MC</number> Power of Bank 
    to file winding up petition.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Bank, on being satisfied that a non-banking financial company—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    is unable to pay 
    its debt; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    has by virtue of 
    the provisions of section 45IA become dis­qualified to carry on the business 
    of a non-banking financial institution; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    has been 
    prohibited by the Bank from receiving deposit by an order and such order has 
    been in force for a period of not less than three months; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the continuance of 
    the non-banking financial company is detrimental to the public interest or 
    to the interest of deposi­tors of the company,  
 
may file an application for winding up of such 
    non-banking finan­cial company under the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956).
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    non-banking financial company shall be deemed to be unable to pay its debt 
    if it has refused or has failed to meet within five working days any lawful 
    demand made at any to its offices or branches and the Bank certifies in 
    writing that such company is unable to pay its debt.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A 
    copy of every application made by the Bank under sub-section (1) shall be 
    sent to the Registrar of Companies.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> All 
    the provisions of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) relating to winding up 
    of a company shall apply to a winding up proceeding initiated on the 
    application made by the Bank under this provision.]  
 
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
*<number>45N</number> 
    Inspection.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Bank may, at any time, cause an in­spection to be made by one or more of 
    its officers or employees or other persons (hereafter in this section 
    referred to as the inspecting authority)—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    of any non-banking 
    institution, including a financial insti­tution, for the purposes of 
    verifying the correctness or comple­teness of any statement, information or 
    particulars furnished to the Bank or for the purpose of obtaining any 
    information or par­ticulars which the non-banking institution has failed to 
    furnish on being called upon to do so; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    of any 
    non-banking institution being a financial institu­tion, if the Bank 
    considers it necessary or expedient to inspect that institution.] 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    shall be the duty of every director or member of any committee or other body 
    for the time being vested with the man­agement of the affairs of the 
    non-banking institution or other officer or employee thereof to produce to 
    the inspecting authori­ty all such books, accounts and other documents in 
    his custody or power and to furnish that authority with any statements and 
    information relating to the business of the institution as that authority 
    may require of him, within such time as may be speci­fied by that authority.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    inspecting authority may examine on oath any director or member of any 
    committee or body for the time being vested with the management of the 
    affairs of the non-banking institution or other officer or employee thereof, 
    in relation to its business and may administer an oath accordingly.
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>45NA</number> Deposits not 
    to be solicited by unauthorised person.—No person shall solicit on 
    behalf of any non-banking institution either by publishing or causing to be 
    published any prospectus or advertisement or in any other manner deposits of 
    money from the public unless—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    he has been 
    authorised in writing by the said non-banking institution to do so and 
    specifies the name of the institution which has so authorised him, and  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    the prospectus or 
    advertisement complies with any order made by the Bank under section 45J and 
    with any other provision of law for the time being in force, applicable to 
    the publication of such prospectus or advertisement.]
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>45NB</number> Disclosure 
    of information.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any information relating to a non-banking financial company,—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    contained in any 
    statement or return submitted by such compa­ny under the provisions of this 
    chapter; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    obtained through 
    audit or inspection or otherwise by the Bank,  
 
shall be treated as confidential and shall 
    not, except otherwise provided in this section, be disclosed.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Nothing in this section shall apply to—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the disclosure by 
    any non-banking financial company, with the previous permission of the Bank, 
    of any information furnished to the Bank under sub-section (1);  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the publication by 
    the Bank, if it considers necessary in the public interest so to do, of any 
    information collected by it under sub-section (1) in such consolidated form 
    as it may think fit without disclosing the name of any non-banking financial 
    company or its borrowers;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the disclosure or 
    publication by the non-banking financial company or by the Bank of any such 
    information to any other non-banking financial company or in accordance with 
    the practice and usage customary amongst such companies or as permitted or 
    re­quired under any other law:  
 
Provided 
    that any such information received by a non-banking financial company under 
    this clause shall not be published except in accordance with the practice 
    and usage customary amongst companies or as permitted or required under any 
    other law.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act or in any other law for the 
    time being in force, the Bank, if it is satis­fied that, in the public 
    interest or in the interest of the depositors or the non-banking financial 
    company or to prevent the affairs of any non-banking financial company being 
    conducted in a manner detrimental to the interest of the depositors, it is 
    expedient so to do, may, either on its own motion or on being requested, 
    furnish or communicate any information relating to the conduct of business 
    by any non-banking financial company to any authority constituted under any 
    law.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time being in force, 
    no court or tribunal or other authority shall compel the Bank to produce or 
    to give inspection of any statement or other material obtained by the Bank 
    under any provisions of this chapter.]
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>45NC</number> Power of Bank 
    to exempt.—The 
    Bank, on being satisfied that it is necessary so to do, may declare by 
    notification in the Official Gazette that any or all of the provisions of 
    this Chapt­er shall not apply to a non-banking institution or a class of 
    non-banking institutions or a non-banking financial company or to any class 
    or non-banking financial companies either generally or for such period as 
    may be specified, subject to such conditions, limitations or restrictions as 
    it may think fit to impose.]  
 
 



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
*<number>45-O</number> 
    Penalties.—[Rep. 
    by the Reserve Bank of India 
    (Amendment )Act, 1974, (51 of 1974). sec. 22 (w.e.f. 13-12-1974).]
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
*<number>45P</number> 
    Cognizance of offencs.—[Rep. 
    by the Reserve Bank of India 
    (Amendment) Act,1974, sec.22 (w.e.f. 13-12-1974).]
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
*<number>45Q</number> 
    Chapter IIIB to override other laws.—The 
    provisions of this Chapter shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
    inconsistent therewith contained in any other law for the time being in 
    force or any instrument having effect by virtue of any such law.
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>45QA</number> Power of 
    Company Law Board to offer repayment of deposit.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every deposit accepted by a non-banking financial company, unless renewed, 
    shall be repaid in accordance with the terms and condition of such deposit.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where 
    a non-banking financial company has failed to repay and deposit or part 
    thereof in accordance with the terms and condi­tions of such deposit, the 
    Company Law Board constituted under section 10E of the Companies Act, 1956 
    (1 of 1956), may, if it is satisfied, either on its own motion or on an 
    application of the depositor, that it is necessary so to do to safeguard the 
    inter­ests of the company, the depositors or in the public interest, direct, 
    by order, the non-banking financial company to make repayment of such 
    deposit or part thereof forthwith or within such time and subject to such 
    conditions as may be specified in the order:  
 
Provided 
    that the Company Law Board may, before making any order under this 
    sub-section, give a reasonable opportunity of being heard to the non-banking 
    financial company and the other persons interested in the matter.]  
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>45QB</number> Nomination by 
    depositors.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where a deposit is held by a non-banking financial institution to the credit 
    of one or more persons, the depositor or, as the case may be, all the 
    depositors together may nominate, in the manner prescribed by rules made by 
    the Central Government under section 45ZA of the Banking Regula­tion Act, 
    1949 (10 of 1949), one person to whom in the event of the death of the sole 
    depositor or the death of all the deposi­tors. the amount of deposit may be 
    returned by the non-banking financial institution.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being in 
    force, or in any disposition, whether testamentary or otherwise, in respect 
    of such deposit, where a nomination made purports to confer on any person 
    the right to receive the amount of deposit from the non-banking financial 
    institution, the nomi­nee shall, on the death of the sole depositor or, as 
    the case may be, on the death of all the depositors, become entitled to all 
    the rights of the sole depositor or, as the case may be, of the depositors, 
    in relation to such deposit to the exclusion of all other persons, unless 
    the nomination is varied or cancelled in the manner prescribed by rules made 
    by the Central Government under section 45ZA of the Banking Regulation Act, 
    1949 (10 of 1949).  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where 
    the nominee is a minor, it shall be lawful for the depositor making the 
    nomination to appoint, in the manner pre­scribed by rules made by the 
    Central Government under section 45ZA of the Banking Regulation Act, 1949 
    (10 of 1949), any person to receive the amount of deposit in the event of 
    his death during the minority of the nominee.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Payment by a non-banking institution in accordance with the provisions of 
    this section shall constitute a full discharge to the non-banking 
    institution of its liabil­ity in respect of the deposit:  
 
Provided 
    that nothing contained in this sub-section shall effect the right or claim 
    which any person may have against the person to whom any payment is made 
    under this section.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> No 
    notice of the claim of any person, other than the person or persons in whose 
    name a deposit is held by a non-banking institution, shall be receivable by 
    the non-banking institution, nor shall the non-banking institution be bound 
    by any such notice even though expressly given to it:  
 
Provided that 
    where any decree order, certificate or other authority from a court of 
    competent jurisdiction relating to such deposit is procuced before a 
    non-banking institution, the non-banking institution shall take due note of 
    such decree, order, certificate or other authority.]
 
 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
*<number>45R</number> 
    Interpretation.—The 
    words and expressions used in this Chapt­er and defined in Chapter IIIB 
    shall have the meanings respec­tively assigned to them therein.
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    *1[<number>45S</number> Deposits not to 
    be accepted in certain cases.—
<section><number>1</number> No person, being an individual or a firm or an 
    unincorporated association of individuals shall, accept any deposit—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    if his or its business 
    wholly or partly includes any of the activities specified in clause (c) of 
    section 45-I; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    if his or its 
    principal business is that of receiving of deposits under any scheme or 
    arrangement or in any other manner or lending in any manner:
 
Provided 
    that nothing contained in this sub-section shall apply to the receipt of 
    money by an individual by way of loan from any of his relatives or to the 
    receipt of money by a firm by way of loan from the relative or relatives of 
    any of the partners.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where 
    any person referred to in sub-section (1) holds any deposit on the Ist day 
    of April, 1997 which is not in accordance with sub-section (1), such deposit 
    shall be repaid by that person immediately after such deposit becomes due 
    for repayment or within three years from the date of such commencement, 
    whichever is earlier:
 
Provided 
    that if the Bank is satisfied on an application made by any person to the 
    Bank that such person is unable to repay a part of the deposits for reasons 
    beyond his control or such repayment shall cause extreme hardship to him, it 
    may, by an order in writing, extend such period by a period not exceeding 
    one year subject to such conditions as may be specified in the order.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> on 
    and from the date of Ist day of April, 1997, no person referred to in 
    sub-section (1) shall issue or cause to be issued any advertisement in any 
    form for soliciting deposit.
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section, a person shall be deemed to be a relative of 
    another if, and only if,—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    they are members 
    of a Hindu undivided family; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    they are husband 
    and wife; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    the one is 
    related to the other in the manner indicated in the List of Relatives 
    below:—  
  
 

    List of Relatives
 <subsubsection>
<number>1</number> Father,                                            
    2. Mother (including step-mother), 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>3</number> Son (including step-son),                    
    4. Son’s wife, 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>5</number> Daughter (including step-daughter),      
    6. Father’s father,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
 <number>7</number> Father’s mother,                               
    8. Mother’s mother, 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>9</number> Mother’s father,                                
    10. Son’s son, 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>11</number> Son’s son’s wife,                              
    12. Son’s Daughter 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>13</number> Son’s Daughter’s husband,                 
    14. Daughter’s husband, 
 
15 Daughter’s son,                                
    16 Daughter’s son’s wife, 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>17</number> Daughter’s daugh­ter,                       
    18, Daughter’s daughter’s husband. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>19</number> Brother (including step-brother),         
    20. Brother’s wife, 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>21</number> Sister (including step-sister),             
    22. Sister’s husband].
 
  




 



</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
*<number>45T</number> 
    Power to issue search warrants.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any court having juris­diction to issue a search warrant under the Code of 
    Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), may, on an application by an officer 
    of the bank or of the State Government authorised in this behalf stating his 
    belief that certain documents relating to acceptance of deposits in 
    contravention of the provisions of section 45S are secreted in any place 
    within the local limits of the juris­diction of such court, issue a warrant 
    to search for such docu­ments.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    warrant issued under sub-section (1) shall be executed in the same manner 
    and shall have the same effect as a search war­rant issued under the Code of 
    Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).
  



 



</section></article> 
 The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934
  
 <article>*<number>45U</number> Definitions.—For 
the purposes of this Chapter,—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  “derivative” means an instrument, to be settled 
at a future date, whose value is derived from change in interest rate, foreign 
exchange rate, credit rating or credit index, price of securities (also called 
“underlying”), or a combination of more than one of them and includes interest 
rate swaps, forward rate agreements, foreign currency swaps, foreign 
currency-rupee swaps, foreign currency options, foreign currency-rupee options 
or such other instruments as may be specified by the Bank from time to time;
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  “money market instruments” include call or 
notice money, term money, repo, reverse repo, certificate of deposit, commercial 
usance bill, commercial paper and such other debt instrument of original or 
initial maturity up to one year as the Bank may specify from time to time;
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  “repo” means an instrument for borrowing funds 
by selling securities with an agreement to repurchase the securities on a 
mutually agreed future date at an agreed price which includes interest for the 
funds borrowed;
 </section><section>       <number>d</number>  “reverse repo” means an instrument for lending 
funds by purchasing securities with an agreement to resell the securities on a 
mutually agreed future date at an agreed price which includes interest for the 
funds lent;
 </section><section>       <number>e</number>  “securities” means securities of the Central 
Government or a State Government or such securities of a local authority as may 
be specified in this behalf by the Central Government and, for the purposes of 
“repo” or “reverse repo”, include corporate bonds and debentures.
  



</section></article> 
 The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934
  
 <article>*<number>45V</number> Transactions in 
derivatives.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in the Securities Contracts (Regulation) Act, 1956 (42 of 
1956) or any other law for the time being in force, transactions in such 
derivatives, as may be specified by the Bank from time to time, shall be valid, 
if at least one of the parties to the transaction is the Bank, a scheduled bank, 
or such other agency falling under the regulatory purview of the Bank under the 
Act, the Banking Regulation Act, 1949 (10 of 1949), the Foreign Exchange 
Management Act, 1999 (42 of 1999), or any other Act or instrument having the 
force of law, as may be specified by the Bank from time to time.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Transactions in such 
derivatives, as had been specified by the Bank from time to time, shall be 
deemed always to have been valid, as if the provisions of sub-section (1) were 
in force at all material times.
  



</section></article> 
 The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934
  
 <article>*<number>45W</number> Power to regulate 
transactions in derivatives, money market instruments, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Bank may, in public interest, or to regulate the financial system of the 
country to its advantage, determine the policy relating to interest rates or 
interest rate products and give directions in that behalf to all agencies or any 
of them, dealing in securities, money market instruments, foreign exchange, 
derivatives, or other instruments of like nature as the Bank may specify from 
time to time:
 Provided that the directions 
issued under this sub-section shall not relate to the procedure for execution or 
settlement of the trades in respect of the transactions mentioned therein, on 
the Stock Exchanges recognised under section 4 of the Securities Contracts 
(Regulation) Act, 1956 (42 of 1956).
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Bank may, for the 
purpose of enabling it to regulate agencies referred to in sub-section (1), call 
for any information, statement or other particulars from them, or cause an 
inspection of such agencies to be made.
  



</section></article> 
 The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934
  
 <article>*<number>45X</number> Duty to comply with 
directions and furnish information.—It 
shall be the duty of every director or member or other body for the time being 
vested with the management of the affairs of the agencies referred to in section 
45W to comply with the directions given by the Bank and to submit the 
information or statement or particulars called for under that section.]
  



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>46</number> 
    Contribution by Central Government to the Reserve Fund.—The
    

    1[Central Government] 
    shall transfer to the Bank rupee securities to the value of five crores of 
    rupees to be allocated by the Bank to the Reserve Fund.
 
 



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 


    1[46A Contribution 
    to National Rural Credit (Long Term Opera­tions) Fund and National Rural 
    Credit (Stabilisation) Fund.—The 
    Bank shall contribute every year such sums of money as it may consider 
    necessary and feasible to do so, to the National Rural Credit (Long Term 
    Operations) Fund and the National Rural Credit (Stabilisation) Fund 
    established and maintained by the National Bank under sections 42 and 43, 
    respectively, of the National Bank for Agriculture and Rural Development 
    Act, 1981.]
 
 



 



 
 The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934
  
 <article>

1[<number>46C</number> National Industrial Credit 
(Long Term Operations) Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
Bank shall establish and maintain a Fund to be known as the National Industrial 
Credit (Long Term Operations) Fund to which shall be credited—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  an initial sum of ten crores of rupees by the 
Bank;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  such further sums of money as the Bank may 
contribute every year:
 Provided that the annual 
contribution during each of the five years commencing with the year ending on 
the 30th day of June, 1965 shall not be less than five crores of rupees:
 Provided further that the 
Central Government may, if the circum­stances so require, authorise the Bank to 
reduce the said sum of five crores of rupees in any year.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The amount in the said fund 
shall be applied by the Bank only to the following objects, namely:—
 

2[***]
  
 
          3(c)  
the making to the Exim Bank
4[or the 
Reconstruction Bank
5[or the 
Small Industries Bank], as the case may be] of loans and advances for the 
purposes of any business of the Exim Bank
4[or the 
Reconstruction Bank
5[or the 
Small Industries Bank], as the case may be];
 <subsection>       <number>d</number> the purchasing of bonds and debentures issued by 
the Exim Bank 4[or 
the Reconstruction Bank,
5[or the 
Small Industries Bank], as the case may be.]
  









</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>46D</number> National 
    Housing Credit (Long Term Operations) Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Bank shall establish and maintain a Fund to be known as the National 
    Housing Credit (Long Term Operations) Fund to which shall be credited every 
    year such sums of money as it may consid­er necessary.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    amount in the said Fund shall be applied by the Bank only to the following 
    objects namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the making to the 
    National Housing Bank of loans and advances for the purpose of any business 
    of the National Housing Bank;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the purchasing of bonds 
    and debentures issued by the Nation­al Housing Bank.]
 
 



 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>47</number> Allocation of 
    surplus profits.—After 
    making provision for bad and doubtful debts, depreciation in assets, 
    contributions to staff and superannuation fund 

    2[and for all other 
    matters for which] provision is to be made by or under this Act or which are 
    usually provided for by bankers, the balance, of the profits shall be paid 
    to the Central Government.]  
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>48</number> 
    Exemption of Banks from income-tax and super-tax.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Not­withstanding anything contained in the 

    1[Income-tax Act, 1961 
    (43 of 1961)] or any other enactment for the time being in force relating to 
    income-tax or super-tax, the bank shall not be liable to pay income-tax or 
    super-tax on any of its income, profits or gains.
 


    2[***]
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>49</number> 
    Publication of Bank rate.—The 
    Bank shall make public from time to time the standard rate at which it is 
    prepared to buy or re-discount bills of exchange or other commercial paper 
    eligible for purchase under this Act.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>50</number> Auditors.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Not less than two auditors shall be appointed, and their remuneration fixed, 
    by the Central Govern­ment.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    auditors shall hold office for such term not exceeding one year as the 
    Central Government may fix while appointing them, and shall be eligible for 
    re-appointment.]  
 
 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>51</number> 
    Appointment of special auditors by Government.—Without 
    prejudice to anything contained in section 50, the 

    1[Central Government] 
    may at any time appoint the 

    2[Comptroller and 
    Audi­tor-General] 

    3[***] to examine and 
    report upon the accounts of the Bank.  
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>52</number> 
    Powers and duties of auditors.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every auditor shall be supplied with a copy of the annual balance-sheet, and 
    it shall be his duty to examine the same, together with the accounts and 
    vouchers relating thereto; and every auditor shall have a list delivered to 
    him of all books kept by the Bank, and shall at all reasonable time have 
    access to the books, accounts and other documents of the Bank, and may at 
    the expense of the Bank 

    1[***], employ 
    accountants or other person to assist him in investigating such accounts, 
    and may, in relation to such accounts, examine any Director or officer of 
    the Bank.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    auditors shall make a report 

    2[***] to the 


    3[Central Government]
    

    4[***] upon the annual 
    balance-sheet and accounts, and in every such report they shall state 
    whether, in their opinion, the balance-sheet is a full and fair 
    balance-sheet containing all necessary particulars and properly drawn up so 
    as to exhibit a true and correct view of the state of the Bank’s affairs, 
    and, in case they have called for any explanation or information from the 
    Central Board, whether it has been given and whether it is satisfactory
    

    5[***].  
 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>53</number> 
    Returns.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Bank shall prepare and transmit to the 

    1[Central Government] a 
    weekly account of the Issue Department and of the Banking Department in
    

    2[such] form as the
    

    1[Central Government] 
    may, by notification in the Gazette of India, pre­scribe. The 

    1[Central Government] 
    shall cause these accounts to be 

    3[published in the 
    Gazette of India at such intervals and in such modified form as it may deem 
    fit].  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Bank shall also, within two months from the date on which the annual 
    accounts of the Bank are closed, transmit to the 

    1[Central Government] a 
    copy of the annual accounts signed by the Governor, the Deputy Governors and 
    the Chief Accounting Officer of the Bank, and certified by the auditors, 
    together with a report by the Central Board on the working of the Bank 
    throughout the year, and the 

    1[Central Government] 
    shall cause such accounts and report to be published in the Gazette of 
    India.  
 


    4[***]
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>54</number> Rural Credit 
    and Development.—The 
    Bank may maintain expert staff to study various aspects of rural credit and 
    development and in particular it may:—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    tender expert 
    guidance and assistance to the National Bank;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    conduct special studies 
    in such areas as it may consider necessary to do so for promoting integrated 
    rural development.]
 
 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>54A</number> Delegation of 
    powers.—
<section><number>1</number> The Governor may, by general or special order, delegate to a 
    Deputy Governor, subjects to such conditions and limitations, if any, as may 
    be specified in the order, such of the powers and functions exercisable by 
    him 

    2[***] under this Act 
    or under any other law for the time being in force as he may deem necessary 
    for the efficient administration of the functions of the Bank.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    fact that a Deputy Governor exercises any power or does any act or thing in 
    pursuance of this Act shall be conclusive proof of his authority to do so.]  
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>54AA</number> Power of 
    Bank to depute its employees to other institu­tions.—2[
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Bank may, notwithstanding anything contained in any law, or in any 
    agreement, for the time being in force, depute any member of its staff for 
    such period as it may think fit,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    to any institution 
    which is wholly or substantially owned by the Bank;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    to the Development 
    Bank, so, however, that no such deputation shall continue after the 
    expiration of thirty months from the commencement of section 5 of the Public 
    Financial Institutions Laws (Amendment) Act, 1975;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    to the Unit Trust, 
    so, however, that no such deputation shall continue after the expiration of 
    thirty months from the date notified by the Central Government under 
    sub-section (1) of sec­tion 4A of the Unit Trust of India Act, 1963 (52 of 
    1963);  
 
and thereupon the person so deputed shall, 
    during the period of his deputation, render such service to the institution 
    to which he is so deputed as that institution may require.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where 
    a person has been deputed to an institution under sub-section (1), he shall 
    not be entitled to claim any salary, emolu­ments and other terms and 
    conditions of service which he would not have been entitled to claim if he 
    had not been so deputed.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Nothing contained in this section shall empower the Bank to depute any 
    member of its staff to any institution on any salary, emoluments or other 
    terms and conditions which is or are less favourable to him than that or 
    those to which he is entitled immediately before such deputation.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> For 
    the purposes of this section, an institution shall be deemed to be 
    substantially owned by the Bank if in the capital of the institution the 
    Bank has not less than forty per cent. share.  
 

    Explanation.—The 
    word “capital” means, in relation to the Unit Trust, the initial capital of 
    the Trust.]  
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>55</number> 
    Reports by the Bank.—[Rep. 
    by the Reserve Bank (Transfer to Public Ownership) Act, 1948 (62 of 1948), 
    sec. 7 and Sch. (w.e.f. 
    1-1-1949).]  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>56</number> 
    Power to require declaration as to ownership of registered shares.—[Rep. 
    by the Reserve Bank (Transfer to Public Ownership) Act, 1948 (62 of 1948), 
    sec. 7 and Sch. (w.e.f. 
    1-1-1949).]  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>57</number> 
    Liquidation of the Bank.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Nothing in the 

    1[Companies Act, 1956 
    (1 of 1956)] shall apply to the Bank and the Bank shall not be placed in 
    liquidation save by order of the 

    2[Central Govern­ment] 
    and in such manner as 

    3[it may direct].  
 


    4[***]  
 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>58</number> 
    Power of the Central Board to make regulations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Board may, with the previous sanction of the 

    1[Central Government],
    

    2[by notification in 
    the Official Gazette,] make regulations consistent with this Act to provide 
    for all matters for which provision is necessary or convenient for the 
    purpose of giving effect to the provisions of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing provision, 
    such regulations may provide for all or any of the following matters, 
    namely:—  
 


    3[***]  
 <subsection>
<number>f</number>    the manner in 
    which the business of the Central Board shall be transacted, and the 
    procedure to be followed at meetings thereof;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    the conduct of 
    business of Local Boards and the delegation to such Boards of powers and 
    functions;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    the delegation of 
    powers and functions of the Central Board 
4[***] 
    to Deputy Governors, Directors or officers of the Bank;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    the formation of 
    Committees of the Central Board, the delega­tion of powers and functions of 
    the Central Board to such Commit­tees, and the conduct of business in such 
    Committees;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>    the constitution 
    and management of staff and superannuation funds for the officers and 
    servants of the Bank;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>    the manner and 
    form in which contracts binding on the Bank may be executed;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>    the provision of 
    an official seal of the Bank and the manner and effect of its use;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number>    the manner and 
    form in which the balance-sheet of the Bank shall be drawn up and in which 
    the accounts shall be maintained;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>n</number>    the remuneration 
    of Directors of the Bank;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>o</number>    the relations of 
    the scheduled banks with the Bank and the returns to be submitted by the 
    scheduled banks to the Bank;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>p</number>    the regulation of 
    clearing-houses for the 
5[the 
    banks (in­cluding post office savings banks)];  
 

6[(pp)    
    the regulation of fund transfer through electronic means between the banks 
    or between the banks and other financial institutions referred to in clause 
    (c) of section 45-I, including the laying down of the conditions subject to 
    which banks and other financial institutions shall participate in such fund 
    transfers, the manner of such fund transfers and the rights and obligations 
    of the participants in such fund transfers;]  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>q</number>    the circumstances 
    in which, and the conditions and limita­tions subject to which, the value of 
    any lost, stolen, mutilated or imperfect currency note of the Government of 
    India or bank note may be refunded; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>r</number>    generally, for the 
    efficient conduct of the business of the Bank.  
 


    7[(3) Any regulation 
    made under this section shall have effect from such earlier or later date as 
    may be specified in the regu­lation.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> Every 
    regulation shall, as soon as may be after it is made by the Central Board, 
    be, forwarded to the Central Government and that Government shall cause a 
    copy of the same to be laid before each House of Parliament, while it is in 
    session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one 
    session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of 
    the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
    aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the regulation, 
    or both Houses agree that the regulation should not be made, the regulation 
    shall, thereafter, have effect only in such modified form or be of no 
    effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
    annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously 
    done under that regulation.]  
 


    8[(5)] Copies of all 
    regulations made under this section shall be available to the public on 
    payment.
 
 










 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>58A</number> Protection of 
    action taken in good faith.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central 
    Government or the Bank or any other person in respect of anything which is 
    in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or in pursuance of 
    any order, regulation or direction made or given thereunder.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No suit or 
    other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central Government or the Bank 
    for any damage caused or likely to be caused by anything which is in good 
    faith done or intended to be done under this Act or in pursuance of any 
    order, regulation or direction made or given thereunder.]
 
 



 



</section></article> 
 The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934
  
 <article>*<number>58B</number> Penalties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Whoever in any application, declaration, return, statement, information or 
particulars made, required or furnished by or under or for the purposes of any 
provisions of this Act, or any order, regulation or direction made or given 
thereunder or in any prospectus or advertisement issued for or in connection 
with the invitation by any person, of deposits of money from the public wilfully 
makes a statement which is false in any material particular knowing it to be 
false or wilfully omits to make a material statement shall be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years and shall also be liable 
to fine.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If any person fails to 
produce any book, account or other document or to furnish any statement, 
information or particulars which, under this Act or any order, regulation or 
direction made or given thereunder, it is his duty to produce or furnish or to 
answer any question put to him in pursuance of the provisions of this Act or of 
any order, regulation or direction made or given thereunder, he shall be 
punishable with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees in respect of each 
offence and if he persists in such failure or refusal, with further fine which 
may extend to one hundred rupees for every day, after the first during which the 
offence continues.
 </section><section><number>3</number> If any person contravenes 
the provisions of section 31, he shall be punishable with fine which may extend 
to the amount of the bill of exchange, hundi, promissory note or engagement for 
payment of money in respect whereof the offence is committed.
 </section><section><number>4</number> If any person discloses any 
credit information, the disclo­sure of which is prohibited under section 45E, he 
shall be pun­ishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six 
mounts, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both.
 

1[(4A) If any person contravenes the 
provisions of sub-section (1) of section 45-IA, he shall be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than one year but which may 
extend to five years and with fine which shall not be less than one lakh rupees 
but which may extend to five lakh rupees.
 </section><section><number>4AA</number> If any auditor fails to 
comply with any direction given or order made by the Bank under section 45MA, he 
shall be punishable with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees.
 </section><section><number>4AAA</number> Whoever fails to comply 
with any order made by the Company Law Board under sub-section (2) of section 
45QA, shall be punish­able with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
three years and shall also be liable to a fine of not less than rupees fifty for 
every day during which such non-compliance continues.]
 </section><section><number>5</number> If any person1[other 
than an auditor]—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> receives any deposit in contravention of any 
direction given or order made under Chapter IIIB; or
 
     1[(aa)  
fails to comply with any direction given or order made by the Bank under any of 
the provisions of Chapter IIIB; or]
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> issues any prospectus or advertisement otherwise 
than in accordance with section 45NA or any order made under section 45J, as the 
case may be,
 he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may 
extend to three years and shall also be liable to fine which may extend,—
 <subsubsection>        <number>i</number> in the case of a contravention falling under 
clause (a), to twice the amount of the deposit received; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>        <number>ii</number> in the case of a contravention falling under 
clause (b), to twice the amount of the deposit called for by the prospectus or 
advertisement.
 

2[(5A) If any person contravenes any 
provision of section 45S, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term 
which may extend to two years, or with fine which may extend to twice the amount 
of deposit received by such person in contravention of that section, or two 
thousand rupees, whichever is more, or with both:
 Provided that in the absence of 
special and adequate reasons to the contrary to be mentioned in the judgment of 
the court, the imprisonment shall not be less than one year and the fine shall 
not be less than one thousand rupees.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section><number>5B</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in section 29 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), it 
shall be lawful for Metropolitan Magistrate or a Judicial Magistrate of the 
first class to impose a sentence of the fine in excess of the limit specified in 
that section on any person convicted under sub-section (5A).]
 </section><section><number>6</number> If any other provision of 
this Act is contravened of if any default is made in complying with any other 
requirement of this Act or of any order, regulation or direction made or given 
or condition imposed thereunder, any person guilty of such contra­vention or 
default shall be punishable with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees 
and where a contravention or default is a continuing one, with further fine 
which may extend to one hundred rupees for every day, after the first, during 
which the contra­vention or default continues.
  





</section></article> 
 The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934
  
 <article>*<number>58C</number> Offences by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where a person committing a contravention or default referred to in section 58B 
is a company, every person who, at the time the contravention or default was 
committed. was in charge of, and was responsible to, the company for the conduct 
of the business of the company, as well as the company, shall be deemed to be 
guilty of the contravention or default and shall be liable to be proceeded 
against and punished accordingly:
 Provided that nothing contained 
in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to punishment if he 
proves that the con­travention or default was committed without his knowledge or 
that he had exercised all due diligence to prevent the contravention or default.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in sub-section (1), where an offence under this Act has been committed 
by a company and it is proved that the same was committed with the consent or 
con­nivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any director, 
manager, secretary, or other officer or employee of the company, such director, 
manager, secretary, other officer or employee shall also be deemed to be guilty 
of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished 
accordingly.
 Explanation 1.—Any 
offence punishable under this Act shall be deemed to have been committed at the 
place where the registered office or the principal place of business, as the 
case may be, in India, of the company is situated.
 Explanation 2.—For 
the purpose of this section,—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> “a company” means any body corporate and includes 
a corpora­tion, a non-banking institution, a firm, a co-operative society or 
other association of individuals;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> “director”, in relation to a firm, means a 
partner in the firm.
  



</subsection></section></article> 
 The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934
  
 <article>*<number>58D</number> Application of section 
58B barred.—Nothing contained in 
section 58B shall apply to, or in respect of, any matter dealt with in section 
42.
  



</article> 
 The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934
  
 <article>*<number>58E</number> Cognizance of offences.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No court shall take cognizance of any offence punishable under this Act except 
upon a complaint in writing made by an officer of the Bank, generally or 
specially authorised in writing in this behalf by the Bank, and no court other 
than that of a Metropolitan Magistrate or a Judicial Magistrate of the first 
class or a court superior thereto shall try any such offence:
 

1[Provided that in respect of any offence 
punishable under sub-section (5A) of section 58B, a complaint in writing may 
also be made by an officer of the State Government, generally or specially authorised in writing in this behalf by that Government.]
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) a Magistrate may, 
if he see reason so to do, dispense with the personal attendance of the officer 
of the Bank filing the complaint, but the Magistrate may in his discretion, at 
any stage of the proceedings, direct the personal attendance of the complainant.
  




</section></article> 
 The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934
  
 <article>*<number>58F</number> Application of fine.—A 
Court imposing any fine under this Act may direct that the whole or any part 
thereof shall be applied in, or towards payment of, the costs of the 
proceedings.]
  



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>58G</number> Power of Bank 
    to impose fine.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in section 58B, 
    if the contravention or default of the nature referred to in section 58B is 
    committed by a non-banking financial company, the Bank may impose on such 
    non-banking financial company—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    a penalty not 
    exceeding five thousand rupees; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    where the contravention 
    or default is under sub-section (4A) or clause (a) or clause (aa) of 
    sub-section (5) of section 58B, a penalty of five lakh rupees or twice the 
    amount involved in such contravention or default, where the amount is 
    quantifiable, whichever is more; and where such contravention or default is 
    a continuing one, further penalty which may extend to twenty-five thousand 
    rupees for every day, after the first, during which the contravention or 
    default continues.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> For 
    the purpose of imposing penalty under sub-section (1), the Bank shall serve 
    a notice on the non-banking financial compa­ny requiring it to show cause 
    why the amount specified in the notice should not be imposed as a penalty 
    and a reasonable oppor­tunity of being heard shall also be given to such 
    non-banking financial company.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any 
    penalty imposed by the Bank under this section shall be payable within a 
    period of thirty days from the date on which notice issued by the Bank 
    demanding payment of the sum is served on the non-banking financial company 
    and, in the event of failure of the non-banking financial company to pay the 
    sum within such period, may be levied on a direction made by the principal 
    civil court having jurisdiction in the area where the registered office or 
    the head office of the non-banking financial company is situ­ated:  
 
Provided 
    that no such direction shall be made, except on an application made by an 
    officer of the Bank authorised in this behalf, to by the principal civil 
    court.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    court which makes a direction under sub-section (4), shall issue a 
    certificate specifying the sum payable by the non-banking financial company 
    and every such certificate shall be enforceable in the same manner as if it 
    were a decree made by the court in a civil suit.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> No 
    complaint shall be filed against any non-banking financial company in any 
    court of law pertaining to any contravention or default in respect of which 
    any penalty has been imposed by the Bank under this section.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Where 
    any complaint has been filed against a non-banking financial company in a 
    court in respect of contravention or default of the nature referred to in 
    section 58B, no proceedings for imposition of penalty against that 
    non-banking financial company shall be taken under this section.]  
 
 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>59</number> 
    Amendment of Act 3 of 1906.—[Rep. 
    by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1937 (20 of 1937, sec. 3 and Sch. II.]  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>60</number> 
    Repeals.—[Rep. 
    by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1937 (20 of 1937, sec. 3 and Sch. II.]  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>61</number> 
    Amendment of sec­tion II, Act VII of 1913.—[Rep. 
    by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1937 (20 of 1937, sec. 7 and Sch. II.]  
  
 

 


 
  


</article><form>
 

THE RESERVE BANK OF INDIA ACT, 1934 
 

 
 

1[ THE FIRST SCHEDULE 
 


 

( See section 9) 
 

2[1. The Western Area shall consist of the States of Goa, Gujarat 
, Madhya Pradesh and Maharashtra and the Union Territories of Dadra and Nagar 
Haveli, and Daman and Diu . 
 

2. The Eastern Area shall consist of the States of Arunachal Pra­desh, 
Assam, Bihar, Manipur, Meghalaya, Mizoram, Nagaland, Orissa, Sikkim, Tripura and 
West Bengal and the Union territories of Andaman and Nicobar Islands.] 
 

3. The Northern Area shall consist of the States of Jammu and Kashmir , 
3[ Punjab , Haryana,] 4[Himachal Pradesh], Rajasthan and 
Uttar Pradesh and the Union territories of 5[ Chandigarh ] 
6[and Delhi ]. 
 

4. The Southern area shall consist of the States of Andhra Pra­desh, 
7[Karnataka.] 8[Tamil Nadu] and Kerala and the 
9[Union territories of Pondicherry and 10[ Lakshadweep 
]].] 
 

--------
 

1. Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, 1956, for the 
First Schedule. 
 

2. Subs. by Act 23 of 1997, sec. 12, for items 1 and 2 (w.e.f. 
9-1-1997 ). 
 

3. Subs. by the Punjab Reorganisation and Delhi High Court 
(Adaptation of Laws on Union Subjects) Order, 1968, for “Punjab” (w.r.e.f. 
1-11-1966). 
 

4. Ins. by the State of Himachal Pradesh (Adaptation of Laws on 
Union Subjects) Order, 1973 (w.r.e.f. 25-1-1971 ). 
 

5. Ins. by the Punjab Reorganisation and Delhi High Court 
(Adaptation of Laws on Union Subjects) Order, 1968 (w.r.e.f. 1-11-1966 ). 
 

6. Subs. by the State of Himachal Pradesh (Adaptation of Laws 
on Union Subjects) Order, 1973, for “Himachal Pradesh and Delhi ” (w.r.e.f. 
25-1-1971 ). 
 

7. Subs. by the Mysore State (Alteration of Name) (Adaptation 
of Laws on Union Subjects) Order, 1973, for ‘ Mysore ” (w.e.f. 1-11-1973 ). 
 

8. Subs. by the Madras State (Alteration of Name) (Adaptation 
of Laws on Union Subjects) Order, 1970, for “ Madras ” (w.r.e.f. 14-1-1969 ). 

 

9. Subs. by Reg. 7 of 1963, sec. 8, for “ Union Territory of 
Laccadive, Minicoy and Amindivi Islands ”. 
 

10. Subs. by the Laccadive, Minicoy and Amindivi Islands 
(Alternation of Name) (Adaptation of Laws) Order, 1974, for “Laccadive, Minicoy 
and Amindivi Islands ” (w.r.e.f. 1-11-1973 ). </form><form>
 

The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934
 

 
 

THE THIRD SCHDEULE.—[Rep. by Act 23 of 1955, sec. 52 
and Sch. III (w.e.f. 1-7-1955)].
 

 
</form><form>
 

The Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934
 

 
 

THE FOURTH SCHEDULE.—[Rep. by Act 62 of 1948, sec. 7 
and Sch. (w.e.f. 1-1-1949)]
 

 
</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




the reserve bank of India act, 1934
 

 
 

 
 




    THE FIFTH SCHEDULE.—[Rep. 
    by the 
India and 
    Burma

    (Burma Monetary Arrangements

    Order, 
    1937.]
 

 
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Subs. by Act 1 of 1984, sec. 5, for “Foreign Exchange 
    Regulation Act, 1947 (7 of 1947)” (w.e.f.  15-2-1984). tc 
    " 
    7. Subs. by Act 1 of 1984, sec. 5, for “Foreign Exchange Regulation Act, 
    1947 (7 of 1947)” (w.e.f.  15-2-1984)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> The proviso omitted by 
Act 26 of 2006, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-4-2007). The proviso before omission, stood as 
under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Ins. by Act 51 of 1974, 
sec. 13 (w.e.f. 13-12-1974).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Subs. by Act 21 of 1976, 
sec. 33, for  “a co-operative bank” (w.r.e.f. 26-9-1975).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>  Subs. by Act 
1 of 1984, sec. 9, for clause (bb) (w.e.f. 15-2-1984). Earlier clause (bb) was 
inserted by Act 51 of 1974, sec. 17 (w.e.f. 13-12-1974).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Subs. by Act 23 of 1997, 
sec. 5, for “a non-banking institution, being a company” (w.r.e.f. 9-1-1997).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>  Ins. by Act 28 of 1981, 
sec. 40 and Sch. II (w.e.f. 1-1-1982).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>   The words “or such auditors as it thinks fit” omitted by Act 
    62 of 1948, sec. 7 and Sch. (w.e.f. 1-1-1949). tc 
    " 
    8. The words “or such auditors as it thinks fit” omitted by Act 62 of 1948, 
    sec. 7 and Sch. (w.e.f. 1-1-1949)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>   Subs. by the India  and Burma (Burma Monetary 
    Arrangements) Order, 1937, for “Governor-General in Council”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>   Subs. by Act 24 of 1978, sec. 9, for certain words (w.e.f. 
    21-7-1978).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>   Subs. by  India  and Burma (Burma Monetary 
    Arrangements) Order, 1937, for “he may direct.” tc 
    " 
    3. Subs. by  India  and Burma (Burma Monetary Arrangements) Order, 
    1937, for “he may direct.”"</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>   Clauses  (a) to (e) omitted by Act 62 of 1948, sec. 7 
    and Sch. (w.e.f. 1-1-1949).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>