<act><tid>170080</tid>
<title>THE TRANSFER OF PROPERTY (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 3 OF <year>2003</year>
[ 31st December, <year>2002</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Transfer of Property Act, <year>1882</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>16944</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title.- This Act may be called the Transfer of Property 
 (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1614258</tid>
<number> 2</number> Substitution of new section for section 106.- For section 106 of 
the Transfer of Property Act, <year>1882</year> (4 of <year>1882</year>)  (hereinafter referred  
  to as the principal Act), the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 106. Duration of certain leases in absence of written contract or 
local usage.- (1) In the absence of a contract or local law or usage to 
the contrary, a lease of immovable property for agricultural or 
manufacturing purposes shall be deemed to be a lease from year to 
year, terminable, on the part of either lessor or lessee, by six 
months' notice; and a lease of immovable property for any other 
purpose shall be deemed to be a lease from month to month, terminable, 
on the part of either lessor or lessee, b fifteen days' notice.

<section><tid>1320808</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time 
being in force, the period mentioned in sub- section (1) shall commence 
from the date of receipt of notice.

</section>

<section><tid>290124</tid>
<number>3</number>A notice under sub- section (1) shall not be deemed to be invalid 
merely because the period mentioned therein falls short of the period 
specified under that sub- section, where a suit or proceeding is filed 
after the expiry of the period mentioned in t at sub- section.

</section>

<section><tid>1758151</tid>
<number>4</number>Every notice under sub- section (1) must be in writing, signed by 
or on behalf of the person giving it, and either be sent by post to 
the party who is intended to be bound by it or be tendered or 
servants at his residence, or (if such tender or delivery is not  
  practicable) affixed to a conspicuous part of the property.". 
delivered personally to such party, or to one of his fa ily or



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>698589</tid>
<number> 3</number> Transitory provisions.- The provisions of section 106 of the 
principal Act, as amended by section 2, shall apply to-
<section><tid>1006720</tid>
<number>a</number>all notices in pursuance of which any suit or proceeding is 
pending at the commencement of this Act; and

</section>

<section><tid>1704239</tid>
<number>b</number>all notices which have been issued before the commencement of this 
Act but where no suit or proceeding has been filed before such 
commencement.
SUBHASH C. JAIN,

Secy. to the Govt. of India.



</section>

</article>



 </act>