<act><tid>1900507</tid>
<title>THE UNION DUTIES OF EXCISE (ELECTRICITY) DISTRIBUTION ACT, <year>1980</year></title>

ACT NO. 14 OF <year>1980</year>
[ 25th March, <year>1980</year>.]

An Act to provide for the payment out of the Consolidated Fund of 
India of sums equivalent to the net proceeds of Union duties of excise 
on electricity to the States to which the law imposing the duty 
extends and for the distribution of those sums among those states in 
accordance with the recommendations of the Finance Commission, in its 
[ Interim report dated the 14th day of november <year>1983</year>]

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty- first Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--





<article><tid>376984</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1698420</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Union Duties of Excise (Electricity) Distribution Act, <year>1980</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1416760</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 1st day of 
April, <year>1979</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>818768</tid>
<number>2</number>Definition. In this Act, the expression" distributable Union 
duties of excise on electricity" means the net proceeds of Union 
duties of excise on electricity levied and collected, other than in 
Union territories, under the Central Excises and Salt Act, <year>1944</year> (1 of  
  <year>1944</year>.) and any other law for the levy and collection of such duty, 
unless the law earmarks the proceeds of the duty for any special 
purpose.
Explanation.-- The expression" net proceeds" has the same meaning 
as in clause (1) of article 279 of the Constitution.



</article>



<article><tid>704880</tid>
<number> 3</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> During the financial year commencing on the 1st day or 
April, <year>1984</year>, there shall be paid, out of the Consolidated Fund of 
india, to the States sums equivalent to the distributable Union duties 
of excise on electricity levied and coltected in that year and those 
sums shall be distributed, provisionally, to each of the States 
specified in column
<section><tid>1193499</tid>
<number>1</number>of the Table below in such percentage as is  
set out against it in column (2). 
TABLE 
 (1)  (2) 
State Percentage 
Andhra Pradesh............ 8. 51 
Assam.............. 1. 09 
Bihar.............. 5. 74 
Gujarat.............. 9. 66 
Haryana.............. 2. 49 
Himachal Pradesh........... 0. 55 
Jammu and Kashmi........... 1. 15 
Karnataka............. 7. 05 
Kerala.............. 4. 22 
Madhya Pradesh............ 7. 09 
Maharashtra............. 19. 38 
Manipur.............. 0. 04 
Meghalaya............. 0. 11 
Nagaland............. 0. 04 
Orissa.............. 3. 02 
Punjab.............. 3. 54 
Rajasthan............. 2. 92 
Sikkim............. 0. 01 
Tamil Nadu............. 7. 71 
Tripura............. 0. 08 
Uttar Pradesh............ 8. 17 
West Bengal............. 7. 43.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>10</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 28 of <year>1984</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1984</year>). 
2. Subs. by s. 3, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1746147</tid>
<number>4</number>Payment to be charged on the Consolidated Fund of India. The 
expenditure on the payments in pursuance of section 3 shall be charged 
on the Consolidated Fund of India.


</article>



<article><tid>108978</tid>
<number> 5</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>554313</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules providing for the 
time at which and the manner in which, any payments under this Act are 
to be made, for the making of adjustments between one financial year 
and another and for any other incidental or ancillary matters.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>54</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>546766</tid>
<number>2</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as 
may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is 
in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised 
in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.


</section>

</article>



 </act>