<act><title>


The Transplantation of Human Organs Act, 1994</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title, application and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Transplantation of Human Organs Act, 1994. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    applies, in the first instance, to the whole of the States of Goa, Himachal 
    Pradesh and Maharashtra and to all the Union territories and it shall also 
    apply to such other State which adopts this Act by resolution passed in that 
    behalf under clause (1) of Article 252 of the Constitution. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It 
    shall come into force in the States of Goa, Himachal Pradesh and Maharashtra 
    and in all the Union territories on such date1 as 
    the Central Government may, by notification, appoint and in any other State 
    which adopts this Act under clause (1) of article 252 of the Constitution, 
    on the date of such adoption; and any reference in this Act to the 
    commencement of this Act shall, in relation to any State or Union territory, 
    means the date on which this Act comes into force in such State or Union 
    territory.  
 
 
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “advertisement” includes any form 
    of advertising whether to the public generally or to any section of the 
    public or individually to selected persons;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “Appropriate Authority” means the 
    Appropriate Authority appointed under section 13;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “Authorisation Committee” means 
    the committee constituted under clause (a) or clause (b) of sub-section (4) 
    of section 9;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    “brain-stem death” means the 
    stage at which all functions of the brain-stem have permanently and 
    irreversibly ceased and is so certified under sub-section (6) of section 3;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    “deceased person” means a person 
    in whom permanent disappearance of all evidence of life occurs, by reason of 
    brain-stem death or in a cardio-pulmonary sense, at any time after live 
    birth has taken place;
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    “donor” means any person, not 
    less than eighteen years of age, who voluntarily authorises the removal of 
    any of his human organs for therapeutic purposes under sub-section (1) or 
    sub-section (2) of section 3;
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    “hospital” includes a nursing 
    home, clinic, medical centre, medical or teaching institution for 
    therapeutic purposes and other like institution;
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>    “human organ” means any part of a 
    human body consisting of a structured arrangement of tissues which, if 
    wholly removed, cannot be replicated by the body;
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>    “near relative” means spouse, 
    son, daughter, father, mother, brother or sister;  
 </section><section>
<number>j</number>    “notification” means a 
    notification published in the Official Gazette;  
 </section><section>
<number>k</number>    “payment” means payment in money 
    or money’s worth but does not include any payment for defraying or 
    reimbursing—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    the cost of removing, 
    transporting or preserving the human organ to be supplied; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    any expenses or loss of earnings 
    incurred by a person so far as reasonably and directly attributable to his 
    supplying any human organ from his body;
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>l</number>    “prescribed” means prescribed by rules 
    made under this Act;
 </section><section>
<number>m</number>    “recipient” means a person into 
    whom any human organ is, or is proposed to be, transplanted;  
 </section><section>
<number>n</number>    “registered medical practitioner” 
    means a medical practitioner who possesses any recognised medical 
    qualification as defined in clause (h) of section 2 of the Indian Medical 
    Council Act, 1956 (102 of 1956), and who is enrolled on a State Medical 
    Register as defined in clause (k) of that section;  
 </section><section>
<number>o</number>    “therapeutic purposes” means 
    systematic treatment of any disease or the measures to improve health 
    according to any particular method or modality; and  
 </section><section>
<number>p</number>    “transplantation” means the 
    grafting of any human organ from any living person or deceased person to 
    some other living person for therapeutic purposes.  
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Authority for removal of human organs.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any donor may, in such manner and subject to such conditions as may be 
    prescribed, authorise the removal, before his death, of any human organ of 
    his body for therapeutic purposes.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    any donor had, in writing and in the presence of two or more witnesses (at 
    least one of whom is a near relative of such person), unequivocally 
    authorised at any time before his death, the removal of any human organ of 
    his body, after his death, for therapeutic purposes, the person lawfully in 
    possession of the dead body of the donor shall, unless he has any reason to 
    believe that the donor had subsequently revoked the authority aforesaid, 
    grant to a registered medical practitioner all reasonable facilities for the 
    removal, for therapeutic purposes, of that human organ from the dead body of 
    the donor.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Where no such authority as is referred to in sub-section (2), was made by 
    any person before his death but no objection was also expressed by such 
    person to any of his human organs being used after his death for therapeutic 
    purposes, the person lawfully in possession of the dead body of such person 
    may, unless he has reason to believe that any near relative of the deceased 
    person has objection to any of the deceased person’s human organs being used 
    for therapeutic purposes, authorise the removal of any human organ of the 
    deceased person for its use for therapeutic purposes.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    authority given under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) or, as the case may 
    be, sub-section (3) shall be sufficient warrant for the removal, for 
    therapeutic purposes, of the human organ; but no such removal shall be made 
    by any person other than the registered medical practitioner.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> 
    Where any human organ is to be removed from the body of a deceased person, 
    the registered medical practitioner shall satisfy himself, before such 
    removal, by a personal examination of the body from which any human organ is 
    to be removed, that life is extinct in such body or, where it appears to be 
    a case of brain-stem death, that such death has been certified under 
    sub-section (6).  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> 
    Where any human organ is to be removed from the body of a person in the 
    event of his brain-stem death, no such removal shall be undertaken unless 
    such death is certified, in such form and in such manner and on satisfaction 
    of such conditions and requirements as may be prescribed, by a Board of 
    medical experts consisting of the following, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    the registered medical 
    practitioner, in charge of the hospital in which brain-stem death has 
    occurred;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    an independent registered 
    medical practitioner, being a specialist, to be nominated by the registered 
    medical practitioner specified in clause (i), from the panel of names 
    approved by the Appropriate Authority;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    a neurologist or a neurosurgeon 
    to be nominated by the registered medical practitioner specified in clause (i), 
    from the panel of names approved by the Appropriate Authority; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    the registered medical 
    practitioner treating the person whose brain-stem death has occurred.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>7</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (3), where brain-stem 
    death of any person, less than eighteen years of age, occurs and is 
    certified under sub-section (6), any of the parents of the deceased person 
    may give authority, in such form and in such manner as may be prescribed, 
    for the removal of any human organ from the body of the deceased person.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Removal of human organs not to be authorised in certain cases.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No facilities shall be granted under sub-section (2) of section 3 and no 
    authority shall be given under sub-section (3) of that section for the 
    removal of any human organ from the body of a deceased person, if the person 
    required to grant such facilities, or empowered to give such authority, has 
    reason to believe that an inquest may be required to be held in relation to 
    such body in pursuance of the provisions of any law for the time being in 
    force.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No 
    authority for the removal of any human organ from the body of a deceased 
    person shall be given by a person to whom such body has been entrusted 
    solely for the purpose of interment, cremation or other disposal.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Authority for removal of human organs in case of unclaimed bodies in 
    hospital or prison.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In the case of a dead body lying in a hospital or prison and not claimed by 
    any of the near relatives of the deceased person within forty-eight hours 
    from the time of the death of the concerned person, the authority for the 
    removal of any human organ from the dead body which so remains unclaimed may 
    be given, in the prescribed form, by the person in charge, for the time 
    being, of the management or control of the hospital or prison, or by an 
    employee of such hospital or prison authorised in this behalf by the person 
    in charge of the management or control thereof.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No 
    authority shall be given under sub-section (1) if the person empowered to 
    give such authority has reason to believe that any near relative of the 
    deceased person is likely to claim the dead body even though such near 
    relative has not come forward to claim the body of the deceased person 
    within the time specified in sub-section (1).  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Authority for removal of human organs from bodies sent for post-mortem 
    examination for medico-legal or pathological purposes.—Where 
    the body of a person has been sent for post-mortem examination—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    for medico-legal purposes by 
    reason of the death of such person having been caused by accident or any 
    other unnatural cause; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    for pathological purposes,
 
the person competent under this Act to give 
    authority for the removal of any human organ from such dead body may, if he 
    has reason to believe that such human organ will not be required for the 
    purpose for which such body has been sent for post-mortem examination, 
    authorise the removal, for therapeutic purposes, of that human organ of the 
    deceased person provided that he is satisfied that the deceased person had 
    not expressed, before his death, any objection to any of his human organs 
    being used, for therapeutic purposes after his death or, where he had 
    granted an authority for the use of any of his human organs for therapeutic 
    purposes after his death, such authority had not been revoked by him before 
    his death.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Preservation of human organs.—After 
    the removal of any human organ from the body of any person, the registered 
    medical practitioner shall take such steps for the preservation of the human 
    organ so removed as may be prescribed.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Savings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Nothing in the foregoing provisions of this Act shall be construed as 
    rendering unlawful any dealing with the body or with any part of the body of 
    a deceased person if such dealing would have been lawful if this Act had not 
    been passed.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Neither the grant of any facility or authority for the removal of any human 
    organ from the body of a deceased person in accordance with the provisions 
    of this Act nor the removal of any human organ from the body of a deceased 
    person in pursuance of such authority shall be deemed to be an offence 
    punishable under section 297 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Restrictions on removal and transplantation of human organs.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Save as otherwise provided in sub-section (3), no human organ removed from 
    the body of a donor before his death shall be transplanted into a recipient 
    unless the donor is a near relative of the recipient.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where any donor authorises the removal of any of his human organs after his 
    death under sub-section (2) of section 3 or any person competent or 
    empowered to give authority for the removal of any human organ from the body 
    of any deceased person authorises such removal, the human organ may be 
    removed and transplanted into the body of any recipient who may be in need 
    of such human organ.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If 
    any donor authorises the removal of any of his human organs before his death 
    under sub-section (1) of section 3 for transplantation into the body of such 
    recipient, not being a near relative, as is specified by the donor by reason 
    of affection or attachment towards the recipient or for any other special 
    reasons, such human organ shall not be removed and transplanted without the 
    prior approval of the Authorisation Committee.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number>(a) 
    The Central Government shall constitute, by notification, one or more 
    Authorisation Committees consisting of such members as may be nominated by 
    the Central Government on such terms and conditions as may be specified in 
    the notification for each of the Union territories for the purposes of this 
    section.  
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The 
    State Government shall constitute, by notification, one or more 
    Authorisation Committees consisting of such members as may be nominated by 
    the State Government on such terms and conditions as may be specified in the 
    notification for the purposes of this section.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> On 
    an application jointly made, in such form and in such manner as may be 
    prescribed, by the donor and the recipient, the Authorisation Committee 
    shall, after holding an inquiry and after satisfying itself that the 
    applicants have complied with all the requirements of this Act and the rules 
    made thereunder, grant to the applicants approval for the removal and 
    transplantation of the human organ.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> If, 
    after the inquiry and after giving an opportunity to the applicants of being 
    heard, the Authorisation Committee is satisfied that the applicants have not 
    complied with the requirements of this Act and the rules made thereunder, it 
    shall, for reasons to be recorded in writing, reject the application for 
    approval.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Regulation of hospitals conducting the removal, storage or transplantation 
    of human organs.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    On and from the commencement of this Act,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    no hospital, unless registered 
    under this Act, shall conduct, or associate with, or help in, the removal, 
    storage or transplantation of any human organ;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    no medical practitioner or any 
    other person shall conduct, or cause to be conducted, or aid in conducting 
    by himself or through any other person, any activity relating to the 
    removal, storage or transplantation of any human organ at a place other than 
    a place registered under this Act; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    no place including a hospital 
    registered under sub-section (1) of section 15 shall be used or cause to be 
    used by any person for the removal, storage or transplantation of any human 
    organ except for therapeutic purposes.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), the eyes or the ears 
    may be removed at any place from the dead body of any donor, for therapeutic 
    purposes, by a registered medical practitioner.  
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this sub-section, “ears” includes ear drums and ear bones.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Prohibition of removal or transplantation of human organs for any purpose 
    other than therapeutic purposes.—No 
    donor and no person empowered to give authority for the removal of any human 
    organ shall authorise the removal of any human organ for any purpose other 
    than therapeutic purposes.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Explaining effects, etc., to donor and recipient.—No 
    registered medical practitioner shall undertake the removal or 
    transplantation of any human organ unless he has explained, in such manner 
    as may be prescribed, all possible effects, complications and hazards 
    connected with the removal and transplantation to the donor and the 
    recipient respectively.  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Appropriate Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government shall appoint, by notification, one or more officers 
    as Appropriate Authorities for each of the Union territories for the 
    purposes of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    State Government shall appoint, by notification, one or more officers as 
    Appropriate Authorities for the purposes of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Appropriate Authority shall perform the following functions, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    to grant registration under 
    sub-section (1) of section 15 or renew registration under sub-section (3) of 
    that section;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    to suspend or cancel 
    registration under sub-section (2) of section 16;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    to enforce such standards, as 
    may be prescribed, for hospitals engaged in the removal, storage or 
    transplantation of any human organ;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    to investigate any complaint of 
    breach of any of the provisions of this Act or any of the rules made 
    thereunder and take appropriate action;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>    to inspect hospitals periodically 
    for examination of the quality of transplantation and the follow-up medical 
    care to persons who have undergone transplantation and persons from whom 
    organs are removed; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vi</number>    to undertake such other measures 
    as may be prescribed.  
  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Registration of hospitals engaged in removal, storage or transplantation of 
    human organs.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No hospital shall commence any activity relating to the removal, storage or 
    transplantation of any human organ for therapeutic purposes after the 
    commencement of this Act unless such hospital is duly registered under this 
    Act:  
 
Provided 
    that every hospital engaged, either partly or exclusively, in any activity 
    relating to the removal, storage or transplantation of any human organ for 
    therapeutic purposes immediately before the commencement of this Act, shall 
    apply for registration within sixty days from the date of such commencement:  
 
Provided 
    further that every hospital engaged in any activity relating to the removal, 
    storage or transplantation of any human organ shall cease to engage in any 
    such activity on the expiry of three months from the date of commencement of 
    this Act unless such hospital has applied for registration and is so 
    registered or till such application is disposed of, whichever is earlier.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every application for registration under sub-section (1) shall be made to 
    the Appropriate Authority in such form and in such manner and shall be 
    accompanied by such fees as may be prescribed.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No 
    hospital shall be registered under this Act unless the Appropriate Authority 
    is satisfied that such hospital is in a position to provide such specialised 
    services and facilities, possess such skilled manpower and equipments and 
    maintain such standards as may be prescribed.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Certificate of registration.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Appropriate Authority shall, after holding an inquiry and after 
    satisfying itself that the applicant has complied with all the requirements 
    of this Act and the rules made thereunder, grant to the hospital a 
    certificate of registration in such form, for such period and subject to 
    such conditions as may be prescribed.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If, 
    after the inquiry and after giving an opportunity to the applicant of being 
    heard, the Appropriate Authority is satisfied that the applicant has not 
    complied with the requirements of this Act and the rules made thereunder, it 
    shall, for reasons to be recorded in writing, reject the application for 
    registration.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Every certificate of registration shall be renewed in such manner and on 
    payment of such fees as may be prescribed.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Suspension or cancellation of registration.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Appropriate Authority may, suo moto or on complaint, issue a 
    notice to any hospital to show cause why its registration under this Act 
    should not be suspended or cancelled for the reasons mentioned in the 
    notice.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If, 
    after giving a reasonable opportunity of being heard to the hospital, the 
    Appropriate Authority is satisfied that there has been a breach of any of 
    the provisions of this Act or the rules made thereunder, it may, without 
    prejudice to any criminal action that it may take against such hospital, 
    suspend its registration for such period as it may think fit or cancel its 
    registration:  
 
Provided 
    that where the Appropriate Authority is of the opinion that it is necessary 
    or expedient so to do in the public interest, it may, for reasons to be 
    recorded in writing, suspend the registration of any hospital without 
    issuing any notice.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Appeals.—Any 
    person aggrieved by an order of the Authorisation Committee rejecting an 
    application for approval under sub-section (6) of section 9, or any hospital 
    aggrieved by an order of the Appropriate Authority rejecting an application 
    for registration under sub-section (2) of section 15 or an order of 
    suspension or cancellation of registration under sub-section (2) of section 
    16, may, within thirty days from the date of the receipt of the order, 
    prefer an appeal, in such manner as may be prescribed, against such order 
    to—  
 <section>
<number>i</number>    the Central Government where the 
    appeal is against the order of the Authorisation Committee constituted under 
    clause (a) of sub-section (4) of section 9 or against the order of the 
    Appropriate Authority appointed under sub-section (1) of section 13; or  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    the State Government, where the 
    appeal is against the order of the Authorisation Committee constituted under 
    clause (b) of sub-section (4) of section 9 or against the order of the 
    Appropriate Authority appointed under sub-section (2) of section 13.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Punishment for removal of human organ without authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person who renders his services to or at any hospital and who, for 
    purposes of transplantation, conducts, associates with, or helps in any 
    manner in, the removal of any human organ without authority, shall be 
    punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years and 
    with fine which may extend to ten thousand rupees.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where any person convicted under sub-section (1) is a registered medical 
    practitioner, his name shall be reported by the Appropriate Authority to the 
    respective State Medical Council for taking necessary action including the 
    removal of his name from the register of the Council for a period of two 
    years for the first offence and permanently for the subsequent offence.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Punishment for commercial dealings in human organs.—Whoever—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    makes or receives any payment for 
    the supply of, or for an offer to supply, any human organ;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    seeks to find a person willing to 
    supply for payment any human organ;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    offers to supply any human organ 
    for payment;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    initiates or negotiates any 
    arrangement involving the making of any payment for the supply of, or for an 
    offer to supply, any human organ;  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    takes part in the management or 
    control of a body of persons, whether a society, firm or company, whose 
    activities consist of or include the initiation or negotiation of any 
    arrangement referred to in clause (d); or  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    publishes or distributes or 
    causes to be published or distributed any advertisement,—  
 </section><section>
<number>a</number>    inviting persons to supply for 
    payment of any human organ;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    offering to supply any human 
    organ for payment; or  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    indicating that the advertiser is 
    willing to initiate or negotiate any arrangement referred to in clause (d),  
 
shall be punishable with imprisonment for a 
    term which shall not be less than two years but which may extend to seven 
    years and shall be liable to fine which shall not be less than ten thousand 
    rupees but may extend to twenty thousand rupees:
 
Provided 
    that the court may, for any adequate and special reason to be mentioned in 
    the judgment, impose a sentence of imprisonment for a term of less than two 
    years and a fine less than ten thousand rupees.  
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> 
    Punishment for contravention of any other provision of this Act.—Whoever 
    contravenes any provision of this Act or any rule made, or any condition of 
    the registration granted, thereunder for which no punishment is separately 
    provided in this Act, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which 
    may extend to three years or with fine which may extend to five thousand 
    rupees.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>21</number> 
    Offences by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where any offence punishable under this Act has been committed by a company, 
    every person who, at the time the offence was committed was in charge of, 
    and was responsible to, the company for the conduct of the business of the 
    company, as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence 
    and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:  
 
Provided 
    that nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person 
    liable to any punishment, if he proves that the offence was committed 
    without his knowledge or that he had exercised all due diligence to prevent 
    the commission of such offence.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where any offence 
    punishable under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved 
    that the offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is 
    attributable to any neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary 
    or other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary or other 
    officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be 
    liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.  
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “company” means any body 
    corporate and includes a firm or other association of individuals; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    “director”, in relation to a 
    firm, means a partner in the firm.  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Cognizance of offence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No court shall take cognizance of an offence under this Act except on a 
    complaint made by—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the Appropriate Authority 
    concerned, or any officer authorised in this behalf by the Central 
    Government or the State Government or, as the case may be, the Appropriate 
    Authority; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    a person who has given notice of 
    not less than sixty days, in such manner as may be prescribed, to the 
    Appropriate Authority concerned, of the alleged offence and of his intention 
    to make a complaint to the court.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> No 
    court other than that of a Metropolitan Magistrate or a Judicial Magistrate 
    of the first class shall try any offence punishable under this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Where a complaint has been made under clause (b) of sub-section (1), the 
    court may, on demand by such person, direct the Appropriate Authority to 
    make available copies of the relevant records in its possession to such 
    person.  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> 
    Protection of action taken in good faith.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any person 
    for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance 
    of the provisions of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No 
    suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central Government or 
    the State Government for any damage caused or likely to be caused for 
    anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of 
    the provisions of this Act.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by notification, make rules for carrying out the 
    purposes of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the manner in which and the 
    conditions subject to which any donor may authorise removal, before his 
    death, of any human organ of his body under sub-section (1) of section 3;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the form and the manner in which 
    a brain-stem death is to be certified and the conditions and requirements 
    which are to be satisfied for that purpose under sub-section (6) of section 
    3;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the form and the manner in which 
    any of the parents may give authority, in the case of brain-stem death of a 
    minor, for the removal of any human organ under sub-section (7) of section 
    3;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the form in which authority for 
    the removal of any human organ from an unclaimed dead body may be given by 
    the person in charge of the management or control of the hospital or prison 
    under sub-section (1) of section 5;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the steps to be taken for the 
    preservation of the human organ removed from the body of any person under 
    section 7;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    the form and the manner in which 
    an application may be jointly made by the donor and the recipient under 
    sub-section (5) of section 9;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    the manner in which all possible 
    effects, complications and hazards connected with the removal and 
    transplantation is to be explained by the registered medical practitioner to 
    the donor and the recipient under section 12;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    the standards as are to be 
    enforced by the Appropriate Authority for hospitals engaged in the removal, 
    storage or transplantation of any human organ under clause (iii) of 
    sub-section (3) of section 13;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    the other measures as the 
    Appropriate Authority shall undertake in performing its functions under 
    clause (vi) of sub-section (3) of section 13;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>    the form and the manner in which 
    an application for registration shall be made and the fee which shall be 
    accompanied, under sub-section (2) of section 14;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>    the specialised services and the 
    facilities to be provided, skilled manpower and the equipments to be 
    possessed and the standards to be maintained by a hospital for registration, 
    under sub-section (3) of section 14;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>    the form in which, the period for 
    which and the conditions subject to which certificate of registration is to 
    be granted to a hospital, under sub-section (1) of section 15;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number>    the manner in which and the fee 
    on payment of which certificate of registration is to be renewed under 
    sub-section (3) of section 15;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>n</number>    the manner in which an appeal may 
    be preferred under section 17;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>o</number>    the manner in which a person is 
    required to give notice to the Appropriate Authority of the alleged offence 
    and of his intention to make a complaint to the court, under clause (b) of 
    sub-section (1) of section 22; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>p</number>    any other matter which is 
    required to be, or may be, prescribed.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is 
    made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total 
    period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or 
    more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
    immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both 
    Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree 
    that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only 
    in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, 
    that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
    validity of anything previously done under that rule.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Repeal and saving.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Ear Drums and Ear Bones (Authority for Use for Therapeutic Purposes) 
    Act, 1982 (28 of 1982) and the Eyes (Authority for Use for Therapeutic 
    Purposes) Act, 1982 (29 of 1982) are hereby repealed.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    repeal shall, however, not affect the previous operation of the Acts so 
    repealed or anything duly done or suffered thereunder.    
 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>