<act><title>

The 
    prize chits and money circulation schemes (Banning) Act, 1978</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and extent.—
<section><number>1</number> This Act 
    may be called the Prize Chits and Money Circulation Schemes (Banning) Act, 
    1978.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends 
    to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In this Act, unless 
    the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “conventional chit” means a transaction 
    whether called chit, chit fund, kuri or by any other name by or under 
    which a person responsible for the conduct of the chit enters into an 
    agreement with a specified number of persons that every one of them shall 
    subscribe a certain sum of money (or certain quantity of grain instead) by 
    way of periodical instalments for a definite period and that each such 
    subscriber shall, in his turn, as determined by lot or by auction or by 
    tender or in such other manner as may be provided for in the chit agreement, 
    be entitled to a prize amount.
 
      
    Explanation.—In this clause 
    “prize amount” shall mean the amount, by whatever name called, arrived at by 
    deducting from out of the total amount paid or payable at each instalment by 
    all the subscribers, 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    the commission charged as service 
    charges as a promoter or a foreman or an agent; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    any sum which a subscriber agrees to 
    forego, from out of the total subscriptions of each instalment, in 
    consideration of the balance being paid to him; 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number>    “money” includes a cheque, postal 
    order, demand draft, telegraphic transfer or money order; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “money circulation scheme” means any 
    scheme, by whatever name called, for the making of quick or easy money, or 
    for the receipt of any money or valuable thing as the consideration for a 
    promise to pay money, on any event or contingency relative or applicable to 
    the enrolment of members into the scheme, whether or not such money or thing 
    is derived from the entrance money of the members of such scheme or 
    periodical subscriptions; 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    “prescribed” means prescribed by rules 
    made under this Act; 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    “prize chit” includes any transaction 
    or arrangement by whatever name called under which a person collects whether 
    as a promoter, foreman, agent or in any other capacity, monies in one lump 
    sum or in instalments by way of contributions or subscriptions or by sale of 
    units, certificates or other instruments or in any other manner or as 
    membership fees or admission fees or service charges to or in respect of any 
    savings, mutual benefit, thrift, or any other scheme or arrangement by 
    whatever name called, and utilises the monies so collected or any part 
    thereof or the income accruing from investment or other use of such monies 
    for all or any of the following purposes, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    giving or awarding periodically or 
    otherwise to a specified number of subscribers as determined by lot, draw or 
    in any other manner, prizes or gifts in cash or in kind, whether or not the 
    recipient of the prize or gift is under a liability to make any further 
    payment in respect of such scheme or arrangement; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    refunding to the subscribers or such 
    of them as have not won any prize or gift, the whole or part of the 
    subscriptions, contributions or other monies collected, with or without any 
    bonus, premium, interest or other advantage by whatever name called, on the 
    termination of the scheme or arrangement, or on or after the expiry of the 
    period stipulated therein, 
 
but does not 
    include a conventional chit;  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>f</number>  “Reserve Bank” means the Reserve Bank of 
    India constituted under the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934).
    
  
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Banning 
    of prize chits and money circulation schemes or enrolment as members or 
    participation therein.—No person 
    shall promote or conduct any prize chit or money circulation scheme, or 
    enrol as a member to any such chit or scheme, or participate in it 
    otherwise, or receive or remit any money in pursuance of such chit or 
    scheme. 
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Penalty 
    for contravening the provisions of section 3.—Whoever 
    contravenes the provisions of section 3  shall be punishable with 
    imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years, or with fine which 
    may extend to five thousand rupees, or with both: 
 
Provided that 
    in the absence of special and adequate reasons to the contrary to be 
    mentioned in the judgment of the court, the imprisonment shall not be less 
    than one year and the fine shall not be less than one thousand rupees. 
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Penalty 
    for other offences in connection with prize chits or money circulation 
    schemes.—Whoever, with a view to 
    the promotion or conduct of any prize chit or money circulation scheme in 
    contravention of the provisions of this Act or in connection with any chit 
    or scheme promoted or conducted as aforesaid,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    prints or publishes any ticket, coupon 
    or other document for use in the prize chit or money circulation scheme; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    sells or distributes or offers or 
    advertises for sale or distribution, or has in his possession for the 
    purpose of sale or distribution any ticket, coupon or other document for use 
    in the prize chit or money circulation scheme; or
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    prints, publishes or distributes, or 
    has in his possession for the purpose of publication or distribution—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    any advertisement of the prize chit or 
    money circulation scheme; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    any list, whether complete or not, of 
    members in the prize chit or money circulation scheme; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    any such matter descriptive of, or 
    otherwise relating to, the prize chit or money circulation scheme, as is 
    calculated to act as an inducement to persons to participate in that prize 
    chit or money circulation scheme or any other prize chit or money 
    circulation scheme; or 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>d</number>    brings, or invites any person to send, 
    for the purpose of sale or distribution, any ticket, coupon or other 
    document for use in a prize chit or money circulation scheme or any 
    advertisement of such prize chit or money circulation scheme; or
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    uses any premises, or causes or 
    knowingly permits any premises to be used, for purposes connected with the 
    promotion or conduct of the prize chit or money circulation scheme; or
    
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    causes or procures or attempts to 
    procure any person to do any of the above-mentioned acts,  
    
 
shall be 
    punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years, or 
    with fine which may extend to three thousand rupees, or with both: 
 
Provided that 
    in the absence of special and adequate reasons to the contrary to be 
    mentioned in the judgment of the court, the imprisonment shall not be less 
    than one year and the fine shall not be less than one thousand rupees.
     
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Offences 
    by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> Where an 
    offence under this Act has been committed by a company, every person who, at 
    the time the offence was committed, was in charge of, and was responsible 
    to, the company for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as 
    the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable 
    to be proceeded against and punished accordingly: 
 
Provided that 
    nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to 
    any punishment provided in this Act, if he proves that the offence was 
    committed without his knowledge or that he exercised all due diligence to 
    prevent the commission of such offence. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence 
    under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the 
    offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is 
    attributable to, any neglect on the part of, any director, manager, 
    secretary or other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary 
    or other officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall 
    be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly. 
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    this section— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “company” means any body corporate and 
    includes a firm or other association of individuals; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    “director”, in relation to a firm, 
    means a partner in the firm. 
 
 
  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Power to 
    enter, search and seize.—
<section><number>1</number> It 
    shall be lawful for any police officer not below the rank of an officer in 
    charge of a police station,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    to enter, if necessary by force, 
    whether by day or night with such assistance as he considers necessary, any 
    premises which he has reason to suspect, are being used for purposes 
    connected with the promotion or conduct of any prize chit or money 
    circulation scheme in contravention of the provisions of this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    to search the said premises and the 
    persons whom he may find therein; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    to take into custody and produce before 
    any Judicial Magistrate all such persons as are concerned or against whom a 
    complaint has been made or credible information has been received or a 
    reasonable suspicion exists of their having been concerned with the use of 
    the said premises for purposes connected with, or with the promotion or 
    conduct of, any such prize chit or money circulation scheme as aforesaid; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    to seize all things found in the said 
    premises which are intended to be used, or reasonably suspected to have been 
    used, in connection with any such prize chit or money circulation scheme as 
    aforesaid. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Any 
    officer authorised by the State Government in this behalf may— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    at all reasonable times, enter into and 
    search any premises which he has reason to suspect, are being used for the 
    purposes connected with, or conduct of, any prize chit or money circulation 
    scheme in contravention of the provisions of this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    examine any person having the control 
    of, or employed in connection with, any such prize chit or money circulation 
    scheme;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    order the production of any documents, 
    books or records in the possession or power of any person having the control 
    of, or employed in connection with, any such prize chit or money circulation 
    scheme; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    inspect and seize any register, books 
    of accounts, documents or any other literature found in the said premises.
    
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> All 
    searches under this section shall be made in accordance with the provisions 
    of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974). 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Forfeiture of newspaper and publication containing prize chit or money 
    circulation scheme.—Where any 
    newspaper or other publication contains any material connected with any 
    prize chit or money circulation scheme promoted or conducted in 
    contravention of the provisions of this Act or any advertisement in relation 
    thereto, the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    declare every copy of the newspaper and every copy of the publication 
    containing such material or the advertisement to be forfeited to the State 
    Government. 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Power to 
    try offences.—No court inferior 
    to that of a Chief Metropolitan Magistrate, or as the case may be, Chief 
    Judicial Magistrate, shall try any offence punishable under this Act.  
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>10</number> Offences under this Act to be 
      cognizable.—All offences 
      punishable under this Act shall be cognizable. 
  
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>11</number> Act not to apply to certain prize chits or 
      money circulation schemes.—Nothing contained in this Act shall apply to 
      any prize chit or money circulation scheme promoted by— 
 <section><number>a</number>    a State 
      Government or any officer or authority on its behalf; or 
 </section><section><number>b</number>    a company 
      wholly owned by a State Government which does not carry on any business 
      other than the conducting of a prize chit or money circulation scheme 
      whether it is in the nature of a conventional chit or otherwise; or 
 </section><section><number>c</number>    a banking 
      company as defined in clause (c) of section 5 of the Banking Regulation 
      Act, 1949 (10 of 1949), or a banking institution notified by the Central 
      Government under section 51 of that Act or the State Bank of India 
      constituted under section 3 of the State Bank of India Act, 1955 (23 of 
      1955), or a subsidiary bank constituted under section 3 of the State Bank 
      of India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, 1959 (38 of 1959), or a corresponding new 
      bank constituted under section 3 of the Banking Companies (Acquisition and 
      Transfer of Undertakings) Act, 1970 (5 of 1970), or a Regional Rural Bank 
      established under section 3 of Regional Rural Banks Act, 1976 (21 of 
      1976), or a co-operative bank as defined in clause (bii) of section 2 of 
      the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934); or 
 </section><section><number>d</number>    any 
      charitable or educational institution notified in this behalf by the State 
      Government, in consultation with the Reserve Bank. 
  



 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Transitional provisions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, a person conducting a prize 
    chit or money circulation scheme at the commencement of this Act may 
    continue to conduct such chit or scheme for such period as may be necessary 
    for the winding up of the business relating to such chit or scheme, so 
    however that such period shall not in any case extend beyond a period of two 
    years from such commencement: 
 
Provided that 
    the said person shall furnish to the State Government or to such officer as 
    may be authorised by it in this behalf and to such office of the Reserve 
    Bank as may be prescribed in such form and within such period as may be 
    prescribed, full information regarding the chit or scheme along with a 
    winding up plan prepared in accordance with the provisions of any rules that 
    may be made by the State Government in this behalf under this Act: 
 
Provided 
    further that if the State Government is satisfied, on an application made by 
    the person conducting the prize chit or money circulation scheme, that the 
    chit or scheme cannot be wound up within the period fixed in the winding up 
    plan furnished to the State Government under the foregoing proviso, it may, 
    in consultation with the Reserve Bank, permit such person to continue to 
    conduct the business relating to the said chit or scheme for such further 
    period as may be considered necessary having regard to the circumstances of 
    the case and the interests of the members of the said chit or scheme. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The State 
    Government may, in consultation with the Reserve Bank, approve the winding 
    up plan furnished under sub-section (1) with or without modifications or 
    reject the same and may grant or refuse to grant permission to continue to 
    conduct that chit or scheme: 
 
Provided that 
    no such winding up plan shall be modified or rejected without giving an 
    opportunity of being heard to the person who conducts such prize chit or 
    money circulation scheme. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If any 
    person fails to furnish full information regarding the said chit or scheme 
    along with its winding up plan in the form and within the period prescribed, 
    he shall forfeit his right to continue the business relating to the said 
    chit or scheme on the expiry of such period. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any agreement or 
    arrangement entered into between any person conducting any such chit or 
    scheme and the subscriber, the person conducting the chit or scheme shall, 
    within such period as may be prescribed, refund the monies or the 
    subscriptions collected till the date of default referred to in sub-section 
    (3). 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If any 
    person fails to comply with the provisions of sub-section (4), he shall be 
    punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years, or 
    with fine which may extend to three thousand rupees, or with both: 
 
Provided that 
    in the absence of special and adequate reasons to the contrary to be 
    mentioned in the judgment of the court, the imprisonment shall not be less 
    than one year and the fine shall not be less than one thousand rupees. 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> Power 
    to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The State 
    Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette and in consultation 
    with the Reserve Bank, make rules for the purpose of carrying out the 
    provisions of this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the office of the Reserve Bank to whom 
    full information regarding any prize chit or money circulation scheme may be 
    furnished under the first proviso to sub-section (1) of section 12, and the 
    form in which and the period within which such information may be furnished;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the particulars relating to the winding 
    up plan of the business relating to prize chits or money circulation 
    schemes.
 </subsection></section><section>
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>3</number> 
    Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it 
    is made, before the State Legislature.]
  
  





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> Repeals 
    and saving.—
<section><number>1</number> The Andhra 
    Pradesh Money Circulation Scheme (Prohibition) Act, 1965 (Andhra Pradesh Act 
    30 of 1965), as in force in the State of Andhra Pradesh, and in the Union
    territory of Chandigarh and 
    the Madhya Pradesh Dhan Parichalan Skeem (Pratishedh) Adhiniyam, 1975 
    (Madhya Pradesh Act 19 of 1975), are hereby repealed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding the repeal of any Act referred to in sub-section (1), 
    anything done or any action taken under the provisions of any such Act 
    shall, in so far as such thing or action is not inconsistent with the 
    provisions of this Act, be deemed to have been done or taken under the 
    provisions of this Act as if the said provisions were in force when such 
    thing was done or such action was taken and shall continue in force 
    accordingly until superseded by anything done or any action taken under this 
    Act. 
  
 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>  Ins. by Act 4 of 1986, sec. 4 and Sch. (w.e.f. 15-5-1986).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>