<act><tid>956538</tid>
<title>THE MANGROL AND MANAVADAR (ADMINISTRATION OF PROPERTY) ACT, <year>1949</year></title>

ACT NO. 2 OF <year>1949</year> 
[ 14th February, <year>1949</year>.]
An Act to provide for the vesting of certain properties belonging to 
the States of Mangrol and Manavadar in Kathiawar in the Managers 
of the said States.

WHEREAS the administration of the States of Mangrol and Manavadar 
has been taken over by the Central Government;

AND WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the vesting of certain 
properties belonging to the said States in the Managers thereof 
appointed by or on behalf of the Central Government and for certain 
matters incidental thereto;

It is hereby enacted an follows:--




<article><tid>1991776</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the mangrol and Manavadar 
 (Administration of Property) Act, <year>1949</year>.

</article>



<article><tid>1757763</tid>
<number>2</number>Definition. In this Act," Manager" means the Manager for the 
time being of the State of Mangrol or the State of Manavadar, as the 
case may be, appointed by, or on behalf of, the Central Government.

</article>



<article><tid>391991</tid>
<number> 3</number> Vesting of property in Manager. Notwithstanding anything 
contained in any other law for the time being in force or in any 
instrument or other document whatsoever, the properties described in 
the Schedule, which stand in the name of the Sheikh of Mangrol or in 
the name of the Khan of Manavadar, whether in his personal capacity or 
as the legal representative of any deceased person or in any other 
capacity, or the Begum Sahiban Fatma, or of any karbhari or other 
officer of Mangrol or Manavadar in his official capacity, or in the 
names of more than one of them, shall be deemed to have vested and 
always to have been vested on and from the 1st day of November, <year>1947</year>, 
as follows, namely:-
<section><tid>1509259</tid>
<number>a</number>if the properties are included in Part I of the 
Schedule, then in the manager of the State of Mangrol, 
and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>20</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1014299</tid>
<number>b</number>if the properties are included in Part II of the 
Schedule, then in the Manager of the State of 
Manavadar.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1575211</tid>
<number>4</number>Powers of Manager. The manager shall have and exercise, in 
relation to properties vested in him under section 3, all the rights, 
powers and authority which a full owner has or exercises in relation 
to his own property:
Provided that where any of the said properties was, immediately 
before the first day of November, <year>1947</year>, subject to nay trust lawfully 
created, the Manager shall, in the exercise of his powers in relation 
to such property be bound by the terms of that trust.


</article>



<article><tid>521784</tid>
<number>5</number>Payment to Manger to be a discharge of obligations. Any 
payment made to the Manager in the discharge of any of the obligations 
in relation to any of the properties described in the Schedule shall 
be a full discharge to the person or authority making the payment from 
all liability in respect of such payment.

</article>



<article><tid>793074</tid>
<number> 6</number> Issue of duplicate securities.
<section><tid>690206</tid>
<number>1</number>Where for any reason any of  
the Government securities described in the Schedule is not in the 
custody of the Manager in whom it has vested under the provisions of 
this Act, the Manager may make an application to the Reserve Bank of 
India for the issue of a duplicate security in lieu thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>913104</tid>
<number>2</number>When an application under sub- section (1) has been made, 
then, notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time 
being in force, the Reserve Bank of India shall issue a duplicate 
security to the Manager as if the original security had been lost.

</section>

<section><tid>59309</tid>
<number>3</number>Any duplicate security issued under the provisions of this 
section shall have the same effect as if it had been issued under 
section 11 of the Public Debt (Central Government) Act, <year>1944</year> (18 of  
  <year>1944</year>).


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>977062</tid>
<number>7</number>Transfers otherwise than by Manager void. Any transfer or 
other disposition of any property described in the Schedule made on or 
after the 1st day of November, <year>1947</year>, by any person other than the 
Manager or without his consent shall be, and shall always be deemed to 
have been, void and of no effect.

</article>



<article><tid>1835699</tid>
<number> 8</number> Power to call for information.
<section><tid>1002865</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the Central  
Government is of opinion that any person is in possession of any 
property which belongs to the State of Mangrol or the State of 
Manavadar, it may, by notice in writing, require such person to 
furnish such information as it may consider necessary for the purpose 
of determining whether the property is

<pagefootnote><pagenum>21</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

property belonging to the State of Mangrol or the State of Manavadar, 
as the case may be.


</section>

<section><tid>401046</tid>
<number>2</number>If any person to whom a notice is sent under sub- section (1) 
fails to comply therewith he shall be punishable with imprisonment 
which may extend to three months or with fine which may extend to one 
thousand rupees or with both.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1040435</tid>
<number> 9</number> Bar of jurisdiction of Court.
<section><tid>336322</tid>
<number>1</number>No Court shall have  
jurisdiction to entertain any civil or criminal proceeding in relation 
to any of the properties described in the Schedule or to enforce any 
liability in respect thereof save at the instance of the Manager.

</section>

<section><tid>1667023</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing in this section shall be deemed to prohibit the 
submission to the Central Government by any person other than the 
manager of any claim in relation to any such property and the decision 
of the Central Government on such claim shall be final and shall not 
be called in question in any Court.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1236254</tid>
<number> 10</number> Power of the Central Government to add to the Schedule.
<section><tid>1778805</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, from time to time, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, amend or alter the Schedule.

</section>

<section><tid>82925</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, the Central Government may, by notification as 
aforesaid, add to the items of property included in Parts I and II of 
the Schedule any other item which in its opinion represents property 
belonging to the State of Mangrol or the State of Manavadar, as the 
case may be, and on the issue of such notification any property 
specified in the notification shall be deemed to be and always to have 
been included in Part I or Part II of the Schedule, as the case may 
be.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1431272</tid>
<number>11</number>Bar of legal proceedings. No suit, prosecution or other legal 
proceeding shall lie against the Central Government, the Reserve Bank 
of India, any bank or company mentioned in the Schedule, or the 
Manager or any other person for anything which is in good faith done 
or intended to be done in pursuance of any of the provisions of this 
Act.

</article>



<article><tid>141250</tid>
<number> 12</number> Repeal.
<section><tid>1301053</tid>
<number>1</number>The Mangrol and Manavadar (Administration of   
  Property) Ordinance, <year>1948</year> (22 of <year>1948</year>), is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>568031</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action 
taken in exercise of any power conferred by or under the said 
Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or taken in exercise of 
the powers conferred by or under this Act, as if this Act had come 
into force on the 16th day of August, <year>1948</year>.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>22</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



 </act>