<act><title>


The National Human Rights Commission 
    (Annual Statement of Accounts) 
    Rules, 19961</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the National Human Rights Commission (Annual 
    Statement of Accounts) Rules, 1996.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date of 
    their publication in the Official Gazette.
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In these rules, unless 
    the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>   
    “Act” means the Protection Human of Rights Act, 1993 (10 of 1994);
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   
    “Audit Officer” means the Comptroller and Auditor General of India or any 
    person appointed by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the 
    Commission;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   
    “Commission” means the National Human Rights Commission constituted under 
    section 3 of the Act;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   
    “Form” means the form appended to these rules;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   
    “Secretary General” means the Officer appointed by Central Government under 
    section 11 of the Act.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Accounts of the Commission.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    annual statement of accounts of the Commission for every financial year 
    beginning with 1994-95 shall be prepared by the Secretary General or such 
    other officer of the Commission as may be authorised by the Secretary 
    General in this behalf.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The annual statement of accounts duly 
    approved by the Commission shall be submitted by the Secretary General to 
    the Central Government by such date as may be specified by the Central 
    Government.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Secretary General shall supervise the 
    maintenance of the accounts of the Commission, the compilation of financial 
    statement and return and shall also ensure that all accounts, books, 
    connected vouchers and other documents and papers of theCommission required 
    by the Audit Officer for the purpose of auditing the accounts of the 
    Commission are placed at the disposal of that officer.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The accounts of the Commission including 
    initial accounts shall be maintained in Form A.
 </section><section>


    <number>5</number> The annual statements of accounts shall be signed and authenticated by 
    the Secretary General.
 </section><section>


    <number>6</number> The annual statement of accounts shall be submitted to the Audit Officer 
    on or before the 30th of June following the year to which the accounts 
    relate and the Audit Officer shall audit the accounts of the Commission and 
    report thereon.
 </section><section>


    <number>7</number> The Commission shall, within thirty days of receipt of Audit Report, 
    remedy any defect or irregularity pointed out therein and report to the 
    Central Government and the Audit Officer about the action taken by it 
    thereon.
  
 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>