<act><title>

THE 
    DOCK WORKERS (regulation of Employment) 
    (incapability to major parts) act, 1997</title> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
    commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> This Act may be 
    called the Dock Workers (Regulation of Employment) (Inapplicability to Major 
    Ports) Act, 1997.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It shall come into force 
    on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as 
    the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.
  





  


</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  “appointed day”, in relation to a major port, 
means the date specified under section 3 for that major port;
 </section><section>       <number>b</number> “Board” has the same meaning as in the Major Port 
Trusts Act, 1963 (38 of 1963);
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  “Dock Labour Board” means a Dock Labour Board 
established under section 5-A of the Dock Workers (Regulation of Employment) 
Act, 1948 (9 of 1948);
 </section><section>       <number>d</number>  “major port” has the same meaning as in the 
Indian Ports Act, 1908 (15 of 1908).
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>3</number> Inapplicability of the 
provisions of the Dock Workers (Regulation of Employment) Act, 1948 to major 
ports.—The Central Government may, 
after settlement is arrived at between the Dock Labour Board of any major port, 
its workmen and the management of that major port in accordance with the 
provisions of the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 (14 of 1947), direct, by 
notification in the Official Gazette that the provisions of the Dock Workers 
(Regulation of Employment) Act, 1948 (9 of 1948), shall cease to have effect in 
relation to that major port with effect from the date specified in that 
notification.


</article> 

  
 <article><number>4</number> Transfer of assets and 
liabilities of the Dock Labour Board, etc., to the Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
On the appointed day in relation to a major port,—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  all property, assets and funds vested in the 
Dock Labour Board immediately before such day, shall vest in the Board.
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  all debts, obligations and liabilities incurred, 
all contracts entered into and all matters and things engaged to be done, by, 
with or for the Dock Labour Board immediately before such day, for or in 
connection with the purposes of the Dock Labour Board, shall be deemed to have 
been incurred, entered into and engaged to be done by, with or for the Board;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  all sums of money due to the Dock Labour Board 
immediately before such day shall be deemed to be due to the Board;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  all suits and other legal proceedings instituted 
by or against the Dock Labour Board immediately before such day for any matter 
in relation to the Dock Labour Board may be continued by or against the Board;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number>  every employee and worker serving under the Dock 
Labour Board shall hold office or service under the Board on the terms and 
conditions which are not in any way less favourable than those which  would have 
been admissible to him if there had not been transfer of his services to the 
board and shall continue to do so until his employment in the Board is duly 
terminated or until his tenure, remuneration or terms and conditions of service 
are duly altered by the Board.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 (14 of 1947), or in any other law 
for the time being in force, the transfer of the services of any employee under 
this section to the Board shall not entitle such employee to any compensation 
under that Act or any other law, and no such claim shall be entertained by any 
court, tribunal or authority.


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>  Came into force on 
    5-1-1998, vide S.O. 22(E), dated 5th January, 1998, published in the 
    Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(ii), dated 15th January, 1998.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>