<act><tid>815726</tid>
<title>THE ILLEGAL MIGRANTS (DETERMINATION BY TRIBUNALS) ACT, <year>1983</year></title>

ACT NO. 39 OF <year>1983</year>
[ 25th December, <year>1983</year>.]

An Act to provide for the establishment of Tribunals for the 
determination, in a fair manner, of the question whether a person is 
an illegal migrant to enable the Central Government to expel illegal 
migrants from India and for matters connected therewith or incidental 
thereto.

WHEREAS a good number of the foreigners who migrated into India 
across the borders of the eastern and north- eastern regions of the 
country on and after the 25th day of March, <year>1971</year>, have, by taking 
advantage of the circumstances of such migration and their ethnic 
similarities and other connections with the people of India and 
without having in their possession any lawful authority so to do, 
illegally remained in India;

AND WHEREAS the continuance of such foreigners in India is 
detrimental to the interests of the public of India;

AND WHEREAS on account of the number of such foreigners and the 
manner in which such foreigners have clandestinely been trying to pass 
off as citizens of India and all other relevant circumstances, it is 
necessary for the protection of the citizens of India to make special 
provisions for the detection of such foreigners in Assam and also in 
any other part of India in which such foreigners may be found to have 
remained illegally;

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty- fourth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1817033</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>591168</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Illegal Migrants (Determination by Tribunals) Act, <year>1983</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>137640</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.

</section>

<section><tid>534602</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force in the State of 
Assam on the 15th day of October, <year>1983</year> and in any other State on such 
date as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, appoint and different dates may be appointed for different 
States and references in this Act to the commencement of this Act 
shall be

<pagefootnote><pagenum>322</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

construed in relation to any State as references to the date of 
commencement of this Act in such State.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>810828</tid>
<number> 2</number> Application. Nothing in this Act shall apply to or in relation 
to--
<section><tid>7523</tid>
<number>a</number>any person who was in any State and who had been 
expelled from that State or India before the commencement of this 
Act in that State or in relation to whose expulsion from such 
State or India any order made before such commencement under any 
other law is in force;

</section>

<section><tid>996389</tid>
<number>b</number>any person detected as a foreigner at the time of his 
entry across any border of India;

</section>

<section><tid>1857642</tid>
<number>c</number>any foreigner who, having entered into India under a 
valid passport or travel document, continued to remain therein 
after the expiry of the period for which he was authorised to 
remain in India under such passport or travel document.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1082611</tid>
<number> 3</number> Definitions and construetion of references.
<section><tid>864890</tid>
<number>1</number>In this Act,  
unless the context otherwise requires,--

<subsection><tid>789101</tid>
<number>a</number>" Appellate Tribunal" means an Appellate Tribunal 
established by the Central Government under sub- section (1) of 
section 15;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1250718</tid>
<number>b</number>" foreigner" has the same meaning as in the Foreigners 
Act, <year>1946</year>; (31 of <year>1946</year>.)

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>434740</tid>
<number>c</number>" illegal migrant" means a person in respect of whom each 
of the following conditions is satisfied, namely:--

<subsubsection><tid>1365683</tid>
<number>i</number>he has entered into India on or after the 25th day 
of March, <year>1971</year>,

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>399412</tid>
<number>ii</number>he is a foreigner,

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>780596</tid>
<number>iii</number>he has entered into India without being in 
possession of a valid passport or other travel document or 
any other lawful authority in that behalf;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>317629</tid>
<number>d</number>" notification" means a notification published in the 
Official Gazette;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>897494</tid>
<number>e</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1350246</tid>
<number>f</number>" Tribunal" means a Tribunal established by the Central 
Government under sub- section (1) of section 5.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1491361</tid>
<number>2</number>Any reference in this Act to any law which is not in force in 
any area shall, in relation to that area, be construed as a reference 
to the corresponding law, if any, in force in that area.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1140173</tid>
<number> 4</number> Overriding effect of the Act.
<section><tid>393915</tid>
<number>1</number>The provisions of this Act  
or of any rule or order made thereunder shall have effect 
notwithstanding anything contained in the Passport (Entry into India) 
Act, <year>1920</year> (34 of <year>1920</year>.) or the Foreigners Act, <year>1946</year> (31 of <year>1946</year>.) or 
the Immigrants (Expulsion from Assam) Act, <year>1950</year> (10 of <year>1950</year>.) or the 
Passports Act, <year>1967</year> (15 of <year>1967</year>.) or any rule or order made under any 
of the said Acts and in force for the time being.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>323</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1059084</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
provisions of sub- section (1), nothing in the proviso to section 2 of 
the Immigrants (Expulsion from Assam) Act, <year>1950</year> (10 of <year>1950</year>.) shall 
apply to or in relation to an illegal migrant as defined in clause (c) 
of sub- section (1) of section 3.
CHAP

ESTABLISHMENT OF TRIBUNALS

CHAPTER II

ESTABLISHMENT OF TRIBUNALS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1628789</tid>
<number> 5</number> Establishment of Illegal Migrants (Determination) Tribunals.

<section><tid>1361745</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by notification, establish, for the  
purposes of this Act, as many Illegal Migrants (Determination) 
Tribunals as it may deem necessary and specify the principal place of 
sitting of, and the territorial limits within which, each such 
Tribunal shall exercise its jurisdiction.

</section>

<section><tid>242618</tid>
<number>2</number>No person shall be appointed as a member of any such Tribunal 
unless he is or has been a District Judge or an Additional District 
Judge in any State.

</section>

<section><tid>1786772</tid>
<number>3</number>Each Tribunal shall consist of two members.

</section>

<section><tid>1256947</tid>
<number>4</number>On the establishment of a Tribunal, the Central Government 
shall appoint one of the members thereof as the Chairman of such 
Tribunal.

</section>

<section><tid>1464940</tid>
<number>5</number>Each Tribunal shall sit in its principal place of sitting and 
in such other place or places as its Chairman may, from time to time, 
appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1282634</tid>
<number>6</number>Filling of vacancies. If, for any reason, any vacancy occurs 
in the office of the Chairman or the member of a Tribunal, the Central 
Government may fill the vacancy by appointing any person who fulfils 
the qualifications specified in sub- section (2) of section 5, as the 
Chairman, or, as the case may be, member of such Tribunal.


</article>



<article><tid>1081921</tid>
<number>7</number>Staff of the Tribunals. The Central Government shall make 
available to every Tribunal such staff as may be necessary for the 
discharge of its functions under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1060362</tid>
<number> 8</number> References or applications to Tribunals.
<section><tid>1187416</tid>
<number>1</number>If any question  
arises as to whether any person is or is not an illegal migrant, the 
Central Government may, whether such question has arisen on a 
representation made by such person against any order under the 
Foreigners Act, <year>1946</year> (31 of <year>1946</year>.) requiring him not to remain in 
India or to any other effect or has arisen in any other manner 
whatsoever, refer such question to a Tribunal for decision.

</section>

<section><tid>958710</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person may make an application to the Tribunal, for its 
decision, as to whether the person whose name and other particulars 
are given in the application, is or is not an illegal migrant:

</section>

<section><tid>331300</tid>
<number>3</number>" Proveded that no such application shall be entertained by the 
Tribunal unless the person in relation to whom the application is made 
is found, or resides, within the jurisdiction of the same police 
station wherein the applicant has his place of residence.";
 1 Subs. by Act 24 of <year>1988</year>, s. 2. 
 2 Subs. by s. 3, ibid. 
 3 Omitted and rules. by s. 4, ibid.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>324</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>331300</tid>
<number>3</number>Every application made under sub- section (2) shall be made in 
such form and in such manner as may be prescribed and shall be 
accompanied by affidavits sworn by not less than two persons residing 
within the jurisdiction of the same police station in which the person 
refferred to in the application is found, or residin, corroborating 
the averments made in the application, and shall also be accompanied 
by such fee, being not less than ten and not more than one hundred, 
rupees, as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>638878</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Every reference under sub- section (1) shall be made to 
the Tribunal within the territorial limits of whose jurisdiction the 
place of residence of the person named in such reference is, at the 
time of making such reference, situated:
Provided that where such person has no place of residence, the 
reference shall be made to the Tribunal within the territorial limit 
of whose jurisdiction such person is, at the time of making such 
reference, found.


</section>

<section><tid>996517</tid>
<number>5</number>Every application under sub- section (2) shall be made to the 
Tribunal within the territorial limis off whose jurisdiction the 
person named in such application is found or, as the case may be, has 
his place of residence, at the time of making such application."]

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1010057</tid>
<number> 8A</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Application to the Central Government for reference.
<section><tid>1890517</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Any person may make an application to the Cenral Government, for 
decision by a Tribunal, as to whether the person whose name and other 
particulars are given in the application, is or is not an illegal 
migrant, and where any such application is received by the Central 
Government, it may, on the basis of any information in its possesion 
or after making such inquiry as it deems fit, reject the application 
on the ground that the application is frivolous orr vexatious or it 
does not comply with the requirements of this section or refer such 
application to a Tribunal for decision.

</section>

<section><tid>1180050</tid>
<number>2</number>Every application made under sub- section (1) shall be made in 
such form and in such manner as may be prescribed and shall be 
accompanied by a declaration by another person residing within the 
jurisdiction of the same revenue sub- division in which the aspplicant 
resides in such form as may be prescribed to the effect that the 
particculars mentioned in the application are true to his knowledge, 
information and belief:
Provided that no person shall make more than ten such appli- 
cations or more than ten such declarations.


</section>

<section><tid>1081352</tid>
<number>3</number>Every reference under sub- section (1) shall be made to the 
Tribunal within the territorial limits of whose jurisdiction the place 
of residence of the person named in such reference is, at the time of 
making such reference, situated:
Provided that where such person has no cplace cof cresidence, the 
reference shall be made to the Tribunal within the territorial limits 
of whose jurisdiction such person is, at the time of making such 
reference, found."]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>121903</tid>
<number> 9</number> Powers of the Tribunal. Every Tribunal shall have the same 
powers as are vested in a civil court under the Code of Civil 
Procedure, <year>1908</year>, (5 of <year>1908</year>.) while trying a suit, in respect of the 
following matters, namely:--
<section><tid>478342</tid>
<number>a</number>summoning and enforcing the attendance of witnesses and 
examining them on oath;

</section>

<section><tid>1586110</tid>
<number>b</number>discovery and production of any document;

</section>

<section><tid>1022533</tid>
<number>c</number>reception of evidence on affidavits;

</section>

<section><tid>1834761</tid>
<number>d</number>requisitioning of public records from any court or 
office;

</section>

<section><tid>1087244</tid>
<number>e</number>issuing of any commission for the examination of 
witnesses.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>975386</tid>
<number> 10</number> Procedure with respect to references under sub- section
<section><tid>351141</tid>
<number>1</number>of  
section 8. On receipt of a reference under sub- section (1) of section 
 8 or sub- section (1) of section 8A the Tribunal shall serve on the 
person named in such reference, a notice, accompanied by a copy of 
such reference, calling upon him to make, within a period of thirty 
days from the date of receipt of such notice, such representation with 
regard to the averments made in the reference, and to produce such 
evidence as he may think fit in support of his defence:
Provided that if the Tribunal is satisfied that the person 
aforesaid was prevented by sufficient cause from making his 
representation and from producing evidence in support of his defence 
within the said period of thirty days, it may permit him to make his 
representation and to produce evidence in support of his defence, 
within such further period, not exceeding thirty days, as it may, by 
order, specify.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>459011</tid>
<number> 11</number> Procedure with respect to applications under sub- section (2) 
of section 8.
<section><tid>1240305</tid>
<number>1</number>On receipt of an application under sub- section (2)  
of section 8, the Tribunal shall issue a notice, accompanied by a copy 
of the application, to the prescribed authority calling upon it to 
furnish, after making such inquiry as that authority may deem fit, a 
report to the Tribunal with regard to the averments made in the 
application.
 1 Subs. by Act 24 of <year>1988</year>, s. 4. 
 2 Ins. by s. 5, ibid. 
 3 Subs. b s. 6, ibid.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>325</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1134641</tid>
<number>2</number>If, on a consideration of the report made by the prescribed 
authority, the Tribunal is satisfied that--

<subsection><tid>797367</tid>
<number>a</number>the person named in the application is not an illegal 
migrant or that the application is frivolous or vexatious, or has 
not been made in good faith, the Tribunal shall, after giving the 
applicant an opportunity to be heard, reject the application;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>425085</tid>
<number>b</number>there are reasonable grounds to believe that the person 
named in the application is an illegal migrant, the Tribunal 
shall issue a notice accompanied by a copy of the application, to 
the person named in the application, calling upon him to make, 
within thirty days from the date of receipt of the notice, such 
representation with regard to the averments made in the 
application and to produce such evidence as he may think fit in 
support of his defence:
Provided that if the Tribunal is satisfied that the person 
aforesaid was prevented by sufficient cause from making his 
representation and from producing evidence in support of his 
defence within the said period of thirty days, it may permit him 
to make his representation and to produce evidence in support of 
his defence, within such further period, not exceeding thirty 
days, as it may, by order, specify.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1283807</tid>
<number> 12</number> Determination of the question as to whether a person is an 
illegal migrant.
<section><tid>1963273</tid>
<number>1</number>The Tribunal to which a reference has been made  
under[" section 8, or section 8A, or to which an application has been 
made under section 8"] shall after taking such evidence as may be 
adduced before it may think fit and after hearing such persons as it 
may deem appropriate, by order, decide the question as to whether the 
person named in such reference or application, as the case may be, is 
or is not an illegal migrant:
Provided that where for the determination of such question in any 
case the decision on any issue renders any decision on any other issue 
or issues unnecessary, the Tribunal may not decide such other issue or 
issues.


</section>

<section><tid>848784</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Where the members of the Tribunal differ in their opinion 
on any point, the Chairman of the Tribunal shall state the point or 
points on which they differ and make a reference to the President of 
the Appellate Tribunal which exercises jurisdiction in relation to 
the Trubunal who shall refer the case for hearing on such point or 
points by a member of another Trubunal under its jurisdiction and 
such point or points shall be decided according to the opinion of 
that member and such decision shall be deemed to be the decision of 
the Tribunal.."]

</section>

<section><tid>1836524</tid>
<number>3</number>The Tribunal shall send a copy of every order passed by it to 
the prescribed authority or authorities and to the parties to the 
reference, or the appliction, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1623476</tid>
<number>4</number>Every order passed under sub- section (1) shall, subject to 
the decision of the Appellate Tribunal, be final and shall not be 
called in question in any court.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1341481</tid>
<number>13</number>Reference and application to be disposed of within six 
months. Every reference made to a Tribunal under[" section 8A or 
Application made to Tribunal under section 8"] shall be inquired 
into as expeditiously as possible and every endeavour shall be made to 
conclude such inquiry within a period of six months from the date of 
the service, on the person concerned, of a copy of such reference or 
application.
 1 Subs. and ins. by Act 24 of <year>1988</year>, s. 7. 
 2 Subs. by s. 8, ibid.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>326</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1344858</tid>
<number>14</number>Appeal. The Central Government, or any person, named in a 
reference or an application under section 8, or any applicant under 
sub- section (2) of that section[" or any person named in a reference 
under section 8"] may, if or he is not satisfied with any order made 
by a Tribunal under section 12, prefer an appeal to the Appellate 
Tribunal against such order.


</article>



<article><tid>1843624</tid>
<number> 15</number> Appellate Tribunal.
<section><tid>1922628</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification, establish for each State in which this Act is in force 
an Appellate Tribunal to be known as the Illegal Migrants 
 (Determination) Appellate Tribunal for deciding appeals preferred 
under section 14 against orders made by Tribunals in the State and 
specify the principal place of sitting of such Appellate Tribunal.

</section>

<section><tid>1373291</tid>
<number>2</number>No person shall be appointed as a member of an Appellate 
Tribunal unless he is or has been a Judge of a High Court.

</section>

<section><tid>907246</tid>
<number>3</number>An Appellate Tribunal shall consist of as many members, not 
being less than two and more than six, as the Central Government may 
think fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1326386</tid>
<number>4</number>The Central Government shall appoint one of the members of an 
Appellate Tribunal to be the President thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>1265486</tid>
<number>5</number>An Appellate Tribunal shall sit in its principal place of 
sitting or any such other place or places as the President thereof 
may, from time to time, appoint.

</section>

<section><tid>871624</tid>
<number>6</number>The powers and functions of an Appellate Tribunal may be 
exercised and discharged by benches constituted by the President 
thereof from amongst the members thereof[" which may either be single 
member benches or benches consisting of not less than tow members"].

</section>

<section><tid>879306</tid>
<number>7</number>The Central Government shall make available to every 
Appellate Tribunal such staff as may be necessary for the discharge of 
its functions under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1038310</tid>
<number>8</number>Every memorandum of appeal to an Appellate Tribunal shall be 
made in such form and in such manner as may be prescribed, and, in the 
case of an appeal preferred by an applicant under sub- section (2) of 
section 8, shall also be accompanied by such fee, not being less than 
twenty- five and more than one hundred rupees, as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1165779</tid>
<number>9</number>Every appeal shall be preferred within thirty days from the 
date on which the order sought to be appealed against was communicated 
to the appellant:
Provided that the Appellate Tribunal may, if it is satisfied that 
the appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from preferring the 
appeal within the said period, admit an appeal after the expiry of the 
aforesaid period of thirty days.


</section>

<section><tid>18335</tid>
<number>10</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Every Appellate Tribunal shall have the same powers as 
are vested in an appellate court under the Code of Civil Procedure, 
<year>1908</year>, while hearing an appeal."].
 1 Ins. by Act 24 of <year>1988</year>, s. 9. 
 2 Subs. by s. 10, ibid.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>327</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1329150</tid>
<number> 16</number> Order of the Appellate Tribunal.
<section><tid>182933</tid>
<number>1</number>The Appellate Tribunal  
may, after giving the parties to the appeal a reasonable opportunity 
of being heard, pass such orders thereon as it may think fit, 
confirming, modifying or annulling the order appealed against or may 
remand the case to the Tribunal which had passed such order with such 
directions to that Tribunal as the Appellate Tribunal may think fit, 
for fresh determination after taking additional evidence, if 
necessary.

</section>

<section><tid>1296578</tid>
<number>2</number>Where an appeal had been heard by the Appellate Tribunal and 
the members thereof differ in their opinion on any point, the decision 
on such point shall, where there is a majority, be according to the 
opinion of such majority, and where there is no majority and the 
members are equally divided in their opinion, they shall draw up a 
statement of the facts of the case and the point or points on which 
they differ in their opinion and make a reference of the point or 
points or of the appeal, as the case may be, to the President of such 
Tribunal, and on receipt of such reference, the President of the 
Tribunal shall arrange for the hearing of such point or points, or the 
appeal, by one or more of the members of the Appellate Tribunal, and 
such point or points, or the appeal, as the case may be, shall be 
decided according to the opinion of the majority of the members of the 
Appellate Tribunal, who have heard the appeal, including those who had 
first heard it.

</section>

<section><tid>1861399</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The Appellate Tribunal shall send a copy of every order 
passed by it under sub- section (1) to the parties to the appeal, 
to the Tribunal concerned and to the prescribed authority or 
authorities."].

</section>

<section><tid>1167043</tid>
<number>4</number>Every order passed under sub- section (1), other than an order 
remanding the case, shall be final and no order passed under that 
sub- section shall be called in question in any court.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1423539</tid>
<number> 17</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Power of superintendence by Appellate Tribunals.
<section><tid>236869</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Every Appellate Tribunal shall have superintendence overr all the 
Tribunals in the State.

</section>

<section><tid>607260</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing provi- 
sions, the Appellate Tribunal may--

<subsection><tid>637179</tid>
<number>a</number>call for returns from any Tribunal;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1965569</tid>
<number>b</number>make general rules and specify forms for regulating the 
practice and proceedings of Tribunals; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1258061</tid>
<number>c</number>specify the forms in which books, entries and accounts 
shall be kept by the officers of Tribunals."]
 1 Subs. and Omitted by Act 24 of <year>1988</year>, s. 11. 
 2 Subs. by s. 12, ibid.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>328</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

CHAP

PROVISIONS APPLICABLE TO ALL TRIBUNALS

CHAPTER III

PROVISIONS APPLICABLE TO ALL TRIBUNALS




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>714079</tid>
<number>18</number>Procedure. Subject to the provisions of this Act and the 
rules made thereunder, every Tribunal and every Appellate Tribunal 
shall have the power to regulate its own procedure in all matters 
arising out of the exercise of its powers or for the discharge of its 
functions.


</article>



<article><tid>1693724</tid>
<number>19</number>Proceeding before every Tribunal to be judicial proceeding 
for certain purposes. Every proceeding before a Tribunal or the 
Appellate Tribunal shall be deemed to be a judicial proceeding within 
the meaning of sections 193 and 228, and for the purposes of section 
 196 of the Indian Penal Code; (45 of <year>1860</year>.) and every such Tribunal or 
Appellate Tribunal, as the case may be, shall be deemed to be a civil 
court for the purposes of section 195 and Chapter XXVI of the Code of 
Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year>. (2 of <year>1974</year>.)
CHAP

ENFORCEMENT OF THE ORDERS MADE BY THE TRIBUNALS

CHAPTER IV

ENFORCEMENT OF THE ORDERS MADE BY THE TRIBUNALS



</article>



<article><tid>1838724</tid>
<number> 20</number> Expulsion of illegal migrant. <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1236016</tid>
<number>1</number>] Where a person has been  
determined by a Tribunal, or, as the case may be, by the Appellate 
Tribunal, to be an illegal migrant, the Central Government shall, by 
order served on such person, direct such person to remove himself from 
India within such time and by such route as may be specified in the 
order and may give such further directions in regard to his removal 
from India as it may consider necessary or expedient.

</section>

<section><tid>1662275</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Any police officer not below the rank of a Superintendent 
of Police shall have such powers as may be necessary, including the 
power to obtain a bond from any person for the due compliance of an 
order under sub- section (1) and to arrest such person in the event of 
his failure to furnish such bond to the satisfaction of such police 
officer."].
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER V

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1851577</tid>
<number> 21</number> Delegation of powers. The Central Government may, by 
notification, direct that the powers and duties conferred or imposed 
on it by this Act, other than the powers conferred by section 28, and 
the powers conferred by this section, may, subject to such conditions 
as may be specified in the notification, be exercised or discharged 
also by--
<section><tid>1790169</tid>
<number>a</number>any officer subordinate to the Central Government;

</section>

<section><tid>1710423</tid>
<number>b</number>any State Government or any officer subordinate to that 
Government.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1856415</tid>
<number>21A</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Power to bind certain persons against whom complaint is 
made under the Act. Notwithstanding anything contained in any other 
law for the time being in force, it shall be lawful for a police, if 
he is satisfied that the ccircumstances so require and for reasons to 
be recorded in writing, to direct any person against whom a reference 
or an application has been made under this Act to enter into a bond 
with or without sureties for making himself available for the inquiry 
and observance of such restrictions or conditions as may be specified 
by such police officer:
Provided that if such person person fails to enter into such bond 
he may be arrested and detained in such manner as may be prescribed."]



</article>



<article><tid>1346472</tid>
<number>22</number>Power to give effect to the orders, etc. Any authority 
empowered by or in pursuance of the provisions of this Act to exercise 
any power, may, in addition to any other action expressly provided for 
in this Act, take, or cause to be taken, such steps, and use, or cause 
to be used, such force, as may in its opinion be reasonably necessary 
for the effective exercise of such power.
 1 Renumbered and ins. by Act 24 of <year>1988</year>, s. 13. 
 2 Ins, by s. 14, ibid.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>329</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>127637</tid>
<number>23</number>Bar of jurisdiction of civil courts. Where a Tribunal or 
Appellate Tribunal has been established for any area for the purpose 
of determining whether a person is or is not an illegal migrant, no 
civil court shall have jurisdiction to entertain any question relating 
to that matter in that area and no injunction or any other order in 
respect of any action taken by, or before, the Tribunal or Appellate 
Tribunal in respect of that matter shall be granted or made by any 
civil court.


</article>



<article><tid>767374</tid>
<number>24</number>Transitory provision. Where in any suit or other legal 
proceeding pending, whether in a civil court or in any Tribunal 
established under any other law for the time being in force, 
immediately before the commencement of this Act, a question arises as 
to whether a person is or is not an illegal migrant, such court or 
Tribunal shall, without deciding such question, make an order 
transferring such suit or other legal proceeding to the Tribunal under 
this Act within the territorial limits of whose jurisdiction such 
court or other Tribunal is situate and on such transfer such question 
shall be dealt with by such Tribunal in accordance with the provisions 
of this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1497336</tid>
<number> 25</number> Penalties. Any person who,--
<section><tid>1327167</tid>
<number>a</number>contravenes or attempts to contravene, or abets the 
contravention of, any order made under section 20; or

</section>

<section><tid>1976417</tid>
<number>b</number>fails to comply with any direction given by any such 
order; or

</section>

<section><tid>6280</tid>
<number>c</number>harbours any person who has contravened any order made 
under section 20 or has failed to comply with any direction given 
by any such order, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> shall be punishable with imprisonment for 
a term which shall not be less than one year but which may extend 
to three years and with fine which shall not be less than two 
thousand rupees:
Provided that the court may, for adequate and special reasons to 
be mentioned in the judgment, impose a sentence of imprisonment for a 
term of less than one year or a fine of less than two thousand 
rupees."].




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>264728</tid>
<number>26</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit, 
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall he against any person for 
anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this 
Act.


</article>



<article><tid>342181</tid>
<number> 27</number> Power to remove difficulties.
<section><tid>1705953</tid>
<number>1</number>If any difficulty arises in  
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order to be published in the Official Gazette, make such 
provisions, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as 
appear to it to be necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty:
Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a 
period of two years from the commencement of this Act.


</section>

<section><tid>400145</tid>
<number>2</number>Every order made under this section shall, as soon as may be 
after it is made, be laid before each House of Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1616873</tid>
<number> 28</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1748162</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification, make rules to carry out the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>444386</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing powers, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:--
 1 Subs. by Act 24 of <year>1988</year>, s. 15.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>330</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


<subsection><tid>1079067</tid>
<number>a</number>the form and the manner in which an application may be 
made and the fee which shall accompany such application, as 
required by sub- section (3) of section 8;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>479240</tid>
<number>aa</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the form and the manner in which an application, 
and the form in which a declaration, may be made under sub- 
section (2) of section 8A;"]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1126184</tid>
<number>b</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the authority or authorities to be prescribed under 
section 11, 12 and 16;"].

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1337116</tid>
<number>c</number>the form and the manner in which an appeal to the 
Appellate Tribunal may be preferred and the fee which shall 
accompany such appeal, as required by sub- section (8) of section 
15;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1412513</tid>
<number>ca</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the manner of arrest and detention under the 
proviso to section 21A;"]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1653735</tid>
<number>d</number>any other matter which is required to be, or may be, 
prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>437818</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act 
shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House 
of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty 
days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>17029</tid>
<number> 29</number> Repeal and saving.
<section><tid>40647</tid>
<number>1</number>The Illegal Migrants (Determination by   
  Tribunals) Ordinance, <year>1983</year>, (8 of <year>1983</year>.) is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>50817</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action 
taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or 
taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.
 1 Ins. and Subs. by Act 24 of <year>1988</year>, s. 16.


</section>

</article>



 </act>