<act> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Railways) Rules, 19381
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Title and application.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Payment of Wages (2[***] 
Railways) Rules, 1938.
 

3[(1A) They extend 
to the whole of 
India 

4[***].
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> These rules apply in 
respect of the payment of wages to persons employed upon any 

3[Railway 
(including factories) by or under a Railway Administration 

5[or by a 
contractor 

4[***].]
 
 







</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Railways) Rules, 1938
 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  “the Act” means the Payment of 
Wages Act, 1936 (IV of 1936);
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  “the authority” means an 
authority appointed under sub-section (1) of section 15 of the Act;
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  “the Court” means the Court 
mentioned in sub-section (1) of section 17 of the Act;
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>  “deduction for breach of 
contract” means a deduction made in accordance with the provisions of the 
proviso to sub-section (2) of section 9;
 </section><section>
        <number>e</number>  “deduction for damage or loss” 
means a deduction made in accordance with the provisions of clause (c) of 
sub-section (2) of section 7;
 
 

1[***] 
 
 

2[(ff) (i)  ‘family’ means—
 </section><section>
                  <number>a</number>  spouse, and
 </section><section>
                  <number>b</number>  children whether 
married or unmarried of railway servant in that order of precedence.
 <subsection>
             <number>ii</number>  ‘dependent relative’ 
means—
 <subsubsection>
                  <number>a</number>  dependent parents;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                  <number>b</number>  his/her deceased sons’ 
widows and children;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                  <number>c</number>  unmarried or widowed 
sister brother/stepbrother provided residing with and wholly dependent on the 
railway servant.]
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        <number>g</number>  “Form” means a Form appended to 
these rules;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        <number>h</number>  “Inspector” means an Inspector 
authorised by or under section 14 of the Act;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
         <number>i</number>  “person employed” does not 
include any person to the payment of whose wages the Act does not apply;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
         <number>j</number>  “section” means a section of 
the Act;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        <number>k</number>  “paymaster” means the Railway 
Administration or other person or persons who may be nominated as such by the 
Railway Administration under clause (c) of section 3 and in the case of a person 
employed by a contractor, the contractor;
 
 

3[(l)  “Chief Labour Commissioner 
(Central)” means officer appointed as such by the Central Government;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        <number>ll</number>  “Regional Labour Commissioner 
(Central)” means an officer appointed as such by the Central Government;]
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>m</number>  “contractor” means a person 
fulfilling either directly or through a sub-contractor, a contract with a 
Railway Administration;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        <number>n</number>  “employer” means the Railway 
Administration and in the case of persons employed by a contractor, the 
contractor;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        <number>o</number>  words and expressions defined in 
the Act shall be deemed to have the same meaning as in the Act.
 
 





</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Railways) Rules, 1938
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>2A</number> 
Nominations.—
<section><number>1</number> The nomination from given by a railway servant in respect 
of payment of provident fund deposits shall be created as the nomination Form 
for the purpose of disbursement of unpaid wages.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Railways) Rules, 1938
 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Register of Fines.—
<section><number>1</number> 
On any railway where the employer has obtained approval under sub-section (1) of 
section 8 to a list of acts and omissions in respect of which fines may be 
imposed, the paymaster shall maintain a Register of Fines in Form I.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> At the beginning of a 
Register of Fines there shall be entered serially numbered the approved purpose 
or purposes on which the fines realised are to be expended.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> When any disbursements 
are made from the fines realised, a deduct-entry of the amount so expended shall 
be made in the Register of Fines, and a voucher or receipt in respect of the 
amount shall be affixed to the register. If more than one purpose has been 
approved, the entry of the disbursement shall also indicate the purpose for 
which it is made.
 

1[(4) Where no fine 
has been imposed on any employees in a wage period, a “nil” entry shall be made 
across the body of the register at the end of the wage period indicating also in 
precise terms the wage period to which the “nil” entry relates.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Railways) Rules, 1938
 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Register of deductions 
for damage or loss.—
<section><number>1</number> 
On every railway in which deductions for damage or loss are made, the paymaster 
shall maintain the Register required by sub-section (2) of section 10 in Form 
II.
 

1[(2) Where no 
deduction has been made from the wages of any employee in a wage period, a “nil” 
entry shall be made across the body of the register at the end of the wage 
period, indicating also in precise terms the wage period to which the “nil” 
entry relates.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Railways) Rules, 1938
 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Register of Wages.—A 
Register of Wages shall be maintained by every employer 

1[***] in such form 
as the paymaster finds convenient. The said Register shall include the following 
particulars:—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  the gross wages of each person 
employed for each wage-period;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  all deductions made from those 
wages, with an indication, in each case, of the clause of sub-section (2) of 
section 7 under which the deduction is made;
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  the wages actually paid to each 
person employed for each wage-period and the date of payment.
 
 



</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Railways) Rules, 1938
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>5A</number> Combined 
form of registers.—Notwithstanding anything contained in these rules, where 
a combined (alternative) form is sought to be used by the employer to avoid 
duplication of work for compliance with the provisions of any other Act or the 
rules framed thereunder, an alternative suitable form in lieu of any of the 
forms prescribed under these rules, may be used with the previous approval of 
the Chief Labour Commissioner 

2[Central].]
 
 




</article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Railways) Rules, 1938
 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Maintenance of 
Registers.—The 
registers required by rules 3, 4, 

1[, 5 and 18(3)],


2[including 
registers maintained in lieu thereof in accordance with the provisions of rule 
5A], shall be 

3[maintained upto 
date, kept and preserved for three years after the date of the last entry made 
in them, at the workspot and be produced before the Inspector on demand at the 
workspot]:
 

4[Provided that the 
pay master may with prior approval of the Regional Labour Commissioner (Central) 
preserve and keep the registers at a place other than the workspot:
 
Provided further that in 
the event of closure of any establishment of a Railway Administration or 
contractor, as the case may be, the pay master shall produce the registers 
before the Inspectors on demand in the office of the Inspector or any other 
place specified by him.]
 
The registers shall 
normally be maintained in English, but where they are maintained in any other 
language than English, a true translation thereof in English shall be available.
 
 






</article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Railways) Rules, 1938
 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Places for displaying 
notices.—The


1[Regional Labour 
Commissioner (Central)] shall specify such place or places on the railway, other 
than factories, as he thinks fit (hereinafter referred to as “specified place” 
or “specified places”) for the display of notices, lists and rules under rules 
8, 12 and 16.
 
 



</article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Railways) Rules, 1938
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>8</number> 

2[Notice of 
wage-period, dates of payment and the names and addresses of Inspectors].—
<section><number>1</number> 
The paymaster shall display in a conspicuous place at every station or 
establishment, within his jurisdiction, a notice in English and Hindi or in the 
language (if that be not Hindi) of the majority of the persons employed at such 
stations or establishments, as the case may be, showing,—
 <subsection>
         <number>i</number>  the wage period for which wages 
are payable; 

3[***]
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  the days or dates on which 
wages are to be paid;
 
 

4[(iii)  the days or dates on which 
unpaid wages are to paid; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iv</number>  names and addresses of 
Inspectors having jursdiction.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every such notice 
shall be maintained in a clean and legible condition.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A copy each of every 
such notice and of any alteration therein shall be sent to the Inspector not 
less than two weeks in advance of the day or date on which wages are to be 
paid.]
 
 






</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Railways) Rules, 1938
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>8A</number> 
Superivision of payment.—On direction of the Inspectors, the pay master or 
his representative at the workspot shall pay wages to the employed person under 
his supervision.]
 
 



</article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Railways) Rules, 1938
 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Prescribed authority.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
The 

2[Regional Labour 
Commissioner (Central)] shall be the authority competent to approve, under 
sub-section (1) of section 8, acts and omissions in respect of which fines may 
be imposed and, under sub-section (8) of section 8, the purposes to which the 
proceeds of fines shall be applied.
 

3[(2) The Chairman 
of the Staff Benefit Fund Committee functioning in each zonal railway, 
production units of the railways and other railway organisations, independent of 
a zonal railway, shall be the prescribed authority with whom the amount required 
to be deposited under clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 25A of the Act 
shall be deposited and who shall deal with the amount so deposited in the manner 
prescribed in rule 18B.]
 
 





</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Railways) Rules, 1938
 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Application in respect 
of fines.—Every 
employer requiring the power to impose fines in respect of any acts and omission 
on the part of employed persons shall send to the 

1[Regional Labour 
Commissioner (Central)],—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  a list, in English, in 
duplicate, clearly defining such acts and omissions;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  in cases where the Railway 
Administration itself does not intend to be the sole authority empowered to 
impose fines, a list, in duplicate, showing by virtue of office such of his 
officers as may pass orders imposing fines and the class of establishment on 
which any such officer may impose fine.
 
 



</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Railways) Rules, 1938
 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Approval of list of 
acts and omission.—The


1[Regional Labour 
Commissioner (Central)] may, on receipt of the list prescribed in sub-rule 
<section><number>a</number> 
of rule 10, and after such enquiry as he considers necessary, pass orders in 
respect of the list referred to in clause 
<subsection><number>a</number> of rule 10 either,—
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>a</number>  disapproving the list,
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  approving the list either in its 
original form or as amended by him, in which case such list shall be deemed to 
have been approved under sub-section (1) of section 8:
 
Provided that no order 
disapproproving or amending the list shall be passed unless the employer shall 
have been given an opportunity of showing cause orally or in writing against 
such order.
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Railways) Rules, 1938
 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Posting of list.—The 
employer shall display at or near the main entrance of every factory, and at the 
specified place or specified places, a copy in English, together with a literal 
translation thereof, in the language of the majority of the persons employed at 
such factory or place, of the list of acts and omissions approved by the 
Authority prescribed under rule 9.
 
 
</article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Railways) Rules, 1938
 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Persons authorised to 
impose fines.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No fine may be imposed upon a person employed by a Railway Administration by any 
person other than the Railway Administration, or by a person holding an 
appointment named in the list referred to in clause (b) of rule 10.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In the case of persons 
employed by a contractor, no fine may be imposed by any person other than the 
contractor:
 
Provided that a contractor 
who runs more than one establishment in two or more localities, and who employs 
not less than fifty persons in one locality, may with the approval of the 
Supervisor, delegate his power to fine to his representative in that locality.
 


</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Railways) Rules, 1938
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>14</number> Procedure 
for imposing fines and deductions for loss or damages.—
<section><number>1</number> No fine shall be 
imposed and no deductions for damage or loss under sub-section (1) of section 10 
of the Act shall be made from a person employed by a Railway Administration 
except in accordance with the procedure laid down in the rules in force on the 
Railway and until the employed person has been given an opportunity of showing 
cause against such imposition or deduction.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No fine shall be 
imposed on and no deduction for damage or loss shall be made from the wages of a 
person employed by a contractor until the person authorised to impose the fine 
or make the deduction has explained personally to the said person the act or 
omission, or damage or loss in respect of which the fine or deduction is 
proposed to be imposed, and the amount of the fine or deduction, which it is 
proposed to impose, and has heard his explanation in the presence of at least 
one other person.
 
 



</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Railways) Rules, 1938
 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Information to 
paymaster.—The 
person imposing a fine or directing the making of a deduction for damage or loss 
shall (unless such person is the paymaster) at once inform the paymaster of all 
particulars necessary for the completion of the register prescribed in rule 3 or 
rule 4, as the case may be.
 
 
</article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Railways) Rules, 1938
 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Deductions under the 
proviso to sub-section (2) of section 9.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No deduction under the proviso to sub-section (2) of section 9 shall be made 
from the wages of an employed person who is under the age of fifteen years or is 
a woman.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No such deduction 
shall be made from the wages of any employed person unless—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  there is provision in writing in 
the terms of the contract of employment requiring him to give notice of the 
termination of his employment; and
 <subsubsection>
              <number>i</number>  the period of this notice 
does not exceed fifteen days or the wage-period, whichever is less; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>ii</number>  the period of this notice 
does not exceed the period of notice which the employer is required to give of 
the termination of that employment;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  this rule has been displayed in 
English and in the language of the majority of the employed persons at or near 
the main entrance of the factory, and at the specified place or specified places 
concerned, and has been so displayed for not less than one month before the 
commencement of the absence in respect of which the deduction is made;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  notice has been displayed at or 
near the main entrance of the factory and at the specified place or specified 
places, concerned, giving the names of the persons from whom the deduction is 
proposed to be made, the number of days’ wages to be deducted and the conditions 
(if any), on which the deduction will be remitted:
 
Provided that where the 
deduction is proposed to be made from all the persons employed in any 
departments or sections or factories of the Railway, it shall be sufficient, in 
lieu of giving the names of the persons in such departments, sections or 
factories, to specify the departments, sections or factories affected.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> No such deduction 
shall exceed the wages of the person employed for the period by which the notice 
of termination of service given falls short of the period of such notice 
required by the contract of employment.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If any conditions have 
been specified in the notice displayed under clause (c) of sub-rule (2), no such 
deduction shall be made from any person who has complied with such conditions.
 


</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Railways) Rules, 1938
 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Annual Return.—Every 
employer shall send a return in Form III so as to reach the 

1[Regional Labour 
Commissioner (Central)] not later than the 15th of 

2[February] 
following the end of the year to which it relates.
 
 




</article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Railways) Rules, 1938
 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Advances to persons 
employed by a contractor.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An advance of wages not already earned shall not ordinarily exceed the amount 
equal to two calendar months’ wages of the employed person. In exceptional cases 
the amount of such advance may, with the previous sanction of the 

1[Regional Labour 
Commissioner (Central)], be made to the extent of four calendar months’ wages.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The advance may be 
recovered in instalments by deductions from wages spread over not more than 
twelve months in the case of ordinary advance and twenty months in the case of 
special advance. In no case shall the amount of instalment exceed one fourth of 
the wages earned in one month.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The amounts of all 
advances sanctioned and the repayments thereof shall be entered in a register in 
Form V.
 
 



</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Railways) Rules, 1938
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>18A</number> Deposit 
of amount of undisbursed wages.—In respect of the staff on Indian Railways 
including Production Units and their subordinate establishments, all amount of 
undisbursed wages remaining of his whereabouts not being known, shall be 
transferred to the Staff Benefit Fund by the Accounts Officer after the expiry 
of the three years.
 <section>
<number>2</number> The amount referred to 
in sub-rule (1) shall be deposited by the paymaster together with relevant 
details in Form VI to the Chairman, Staff Benefit Fund.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Railways) Rules, 1938
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>18B</number> Manner of 
dealing with amounts.—
<section><number>1</number> The amounts deposited with the Chairman, Staff 
Benefit Fund under rule 18A shall remain with the Chairman of the Fund for four 
years.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> As soon as possible 
the Railway Administration will publish in any two Newspapers circulated in the 
language commonly understood in the area in which the factory or the 
establishment in which the undisbursed wages were earned, is situated and will 
exhibit them on notice-board of the factory or establishment.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The prescribed 
authority shall release the money to the nominee or to that person who has claim 
to this money and which has been decided by the competent authority court.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Railways) Rules, 1938
  
 <article>1[<number>18C</number> The amount 
deposited under rule 18A shall be applied by the Chairman of the Staff Benefit 
Fund to met the expenditure for the purpose prescribed for Staff Benefit 
Fund.]
  


</article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Railways) Rules, 1938
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>18D</number> The 
family member/dependent relative of employed person to make claims.—The 
spouse or children and where the employed person does not have spouse or 
children, the dependent relative in the order of precedence given in clause (ff) 
(ii) of rule 2 can make claims of the amount at any time within seven years 
during which time the wages remain with the paymaster for a period of first 
three years, as specified in rule 18A 
<section><number>1</number> and then credited to the Staff Benefit 
Fund. In such cases, only the principal amount as remaining with the paymaster 
deposited by the paymaster with the Chairman, Staff Benefit Fund Committee shall 
be payable to the claimant.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Railways) Rules, 1938
 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Procedure, costs and 
court-fees.—The 
procedure to be followed by the authorities appointed under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of 
section 15 and the Courts mentioned in sub-section (1) of section 17 of the Act, 
the scales of costs which may be allowed in, and the amount of court-fees 
payable in respect of proceeding under the Act to which these rules apply shall 
be such procedure, scales and amounts as are from time to time, prescribed by 
the State Government in the exercise of its powers under the Act in that behalf 
for the authority or Court concerned.
 


</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Railways) Rules, 1938
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>19A</number> Payment 
of undisbursed wages.—
<section><number>1</number> If all amounts payable to an employed person as 
wages could not or cannot be paid on account of his death before payment or on 
account of his whereabouts not being known, shall be paid to the person 
nominated by him in this behalf.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where wages remain 
undisbursed because no nomination had been made by the employed person or for 
any reason such amounts could not be paid to the nominee of the employed person 
until the expiry of three years from the date the same had become payable all 
amounts of such undisbursed wages shall be transferred by the Accounts Officer 
to the Staff Benefit Fund before the expiry of the fifteenth day after the last 
day of the said period of three years.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Railways) Rules, 1938
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>19B</number> Manner of 
dealing with deposited amounts.—The amounts or undisbursed wages deposited 
with the Chairman Staff Benefit Fund shall be applied by him to meet the 
expenditure for the purpose prescribed for the Staff Benefit Fund.]
 
 



</article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Railways) Rules, 1938
 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Abstracts.—The 
abstracts of the Act and of the rules made thereunder to be displayed under 
section 25 shall be in Form IV.
 


</article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Railways) Rules, 1938
 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Penalties.—Any 
breach of rules 3, 4, 5, 

1[5A], 6, 8, 12, 
15, 

2[17 and 18(3)] of 
these rules shall be punishable with fine which may extend to two hundred 
rupees.
 
 




</article><form>
 

The Payment 
of Wages (Railways) Rules, 1938
 


 
 


Form III
 


(See rule 17)
 


Annual Return
 


Return for the year ending 31st 
December,.............
 


1. Name of the Railway/Contract Establishment 
and postal address.
 


2. Number of days worked during the year:
 


     3. (a)   *Number of man-days worked 
during the year:—
 



(b)   

†Average daily No. of persons employed 
during the year:
 


                
Adults...........................
 


                
Children...........................
 


         (c)   Gross amount paid as 
remuneration to persons getting less than 

1[Rs. 1600] per month including 
deductions under section 7(2) is..................of which the amount due to 
incentive bonus is..................and that due to money value of concessions$ is..................
 


4. Total wages paid including deductions 
under section 7 (2) on the following accounts:—
 


      (a)  Basic wages including overtime 
wages and non-profit sharing bonus.
 


      (b)  Dearness and other allowances in 
cash.
 


      (c)  Arrears of pay in respect of 
previous year paid during the year.
 


5. Number of cases and amount realised as:
 


 


Persons receiving less than
 


 



  1[Rs. 1600] per month
 



                                                                    No. of 
  cases         Amount
 


      (a)  Fines
 


      (b)  Deductions for damage or loss
 


      (c)  Deductions for breach of contract
 


6. Disbursement from the fines# fund:
 



                                                                        
Purpose           Amount
 


      (a)
 


      (b)
 


      (c)
 


      (d)
 


7. Balance of fines# fund 
in hand at the end of the year..................
 



2[8. Number of cases and amount of 
undisbursed wages on account of the death of the employed person or his 
whereabouts not being known deposited with the Chairman, Staff Benefit Fund.
 



                                                                                
Number    Amount
 



                                                                                
of cases
 


      (a)  Cases in which wages remained 
undisbursed for want of nomination.
 


      (b)  Cases in which wages could not be 
paid to person nominated by employed person for any reason.]
 


Signature......................
 


Designation..................
 


    *  This is the aggregate number of 
attendances during the year.
 


    †  The average daily number of persons 
employed during the year is obtained by dividing the aggregate number of 
attendance during the year by the number of working days.
 


    $  Money value of concessions should be 
obtained by taking the difference of the cost price paid by the employer and the 
actual price paid by the employees for supplies of essential commodities given 
free or at concessional rates.
 


    #  Fines fund referred to in columns 6 
and 7 will cover Staff Benefit Fund existing on Railways.
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Subs. by G.S.R. 1159 (E), dated 9th 
December, 1988 (w.e.f. 9-12-1988).
 


   2.  Ins. by G.S.R. 1159 (E), dated 9th 
December, 1988 (w.e.f. 9-12-1988).
 


 
</form><form>
 

The Payment of 
Wages (Railways) Rules, 1938
 


 
 


Form IV
 


Abstract of the payment of wages act, 1936, 
and the rules made thereunder
 


Whom the Act affects
 


1. The Act applies to the payment of wages to 
persons in this factory receiving less than 

1[Rs. 1600] a month.
 


2. No employed person can give up by contract 
or agreement his rights under the Act.
 


Definition of wages
 


3. ‘Wages’ means all remuneration (whether by 
way of salary, allowances or otherwise) expressed in terms of money or capable 
of being so expressed which would, of the terms of employment, express or 
implied, were fulfilled be payable to a person employed in respect of his 
employment or of work done in such employment, and includes—
 


      (a)  any remuneration payable under any 
award or settlement between the parties or order of a Court;
 


      (b)  any remuneration to which the 
person employed is entitled in respect of overtime work or holidays or any leave 
period;
 


      (c)  any additional remuneration payable 
under the terms of employment (whether called a bonus or by any other name);
 


      (d)  any sum which by reason of the 
termination of employment of the person employed is payable under any law, 
contract or instrument which provides for the payment of such sum, whether with 
or without deductions but does not provide for the time within which the payment 
is to be made;
 


      (e)  any sum to which the person 
employed is entitled under any scheme framed under any law for the time being in 
force,
 


but does not include,—
 


      (1)  any bonus (whether under a scheme 
of profit sharing or otherwise) which does not form part of the remuneration 
payable under the terms of employment or which is not payable under any award or 
settlement between the parties or order of a Court;
 


      (2)  the value of any 
house-accommodation, or the supply of light, water, medical attendance or other 
amenity or of any service excluded from the computation of wages by a general or 
special order of the State Government;
 


      (3)  any contribution paid by the 
employer to any pension or provident fund, and the interest which may have 
accrued thereon;
 


      (4)  any travelling allowance or the 
value of any travelling concessions;
 


      (5)  any sum paid to the employed person 
to defray special expenses entailed on him by the nature of his employment; or
 


      (6)  any gratuity payable on the 
termination of employment in cases other than those specified in sub-clause (d).
 


Responsibility for and method of payment
 


4. The railway administration or a person 
nominated by the railway administration for the concerned local area is 
responsible for the payment under the Act of wages to persons employed under 
him, and any contractor employing persons is responsible for payment to the 
persons he employs.
 


5. Wage-periods shall be fixed for the payment 
of wages at intervals not exceeding one month.
 


6. Wages shall be paid on a working day within 
7 days of the end of the wage-period (or within ten days if 1,000 or more 
persons are employed).
 


The wages of a person discharged shall be paid 
not later than the second working day after his discharge.
 


7. Payment in kind is prohibited.
 


Fines and Deductions
 


8. No deductions shall be made from wages 
except those authorised under the Act (See paragraphs 9-15 below).
 


9. (1) Fines can be imposed only for such acts 
and omissions as the employer may, with the previous approval of the Supervisor, 
specify by a notice displayed at or near the main entrance of the factory and 
after giving the employed person an opportunity for explanation.
 


(2) Fines—
 


      (a)  shall not exceed 

2[three per cent. of the wages payable 
to him in respect of that wage period in which fine is imposed];
 


      (b)  shall not be recovered by 
instalments, or later than sixty days of the date of imposition;
 


      (c)  shall be recorded in a register and 
applied to such purposes beneficial to the employed persons as are approved by 
the Supervisor;
 


      (d)  shall not be imposed on a child.
 


10. (a) Deductions for absence from duty can 
be made only of account of the absence of the employed person at times when he 
should be working and such deductions must not exceed an amount which is in the 
same proportion to his wages for the wage-period, as the time he was absent in 
that period is to the total time he should have been at work.
 


(b) If ten or more employed persons, acting in 
concert, absent themselves without reasonable cause and without due notice, the 
deduction for absence can include wages for eight days in lieu of notice, but—
 


      (1)  No deduction for breaking a 
contract can be made from a person under 15 or a woman;
 


      (2)  There must be a provision in 
writing which forms part of the contract of employment requiring that a specific 
period of notice of intention to cease work not exceeding 15 days or the period 
of notice which the employer has to give to discharge a worker, must be given to 
the employer and that wages may be deducted in lieu of such notice;
 


      (3)  The above provision must be 
displayed at or near the main entrance of the factory;
 


      (4)  No deduction of this nature can be 
made until a notice that this deduction is to be made has been posted at or near 
the main entrance of the factory;
 


      (5)  No deduction must exceed the wages 
of the employed person for the period by which the notice he gives of leading 
employment is less than the notice he should have give under his contract.
 


11. Deductions can be made for damage to or 
loss of goods expressly entrusted to an employed person or for loss of money for 
which he is required to account, where such damage or loss is due to his neglect 
or default.
 


Such deductions cannot exceed the amount of 
the damage or loss caused and can be made only after giving the employed persons 
an opportunity for explanation.
 


12. Deductions can be made, equivalent to the 
value thereof, for house accommodation supplied by the employer or by Government 
or any housing board set up under any law for the time being in force (whether 
the Government or the board is the employer or not) or any other authority 
engaged in the business of subsidizing house accommodation which may be 
specified in this behalf by the Central Government, amenities and services 
(other than tools and raw materials) supplied by the employer: provided these 
are accepted by the employed person as a part of the terms of his employment and 
have in the case of amenities and services been authorised by order of the 
Central Government.
 


13. (a) Deductions can be made for the 
recovery of advance or for adjustment of over-payment of wages.
 


(b) Advances made before the employment began 
can only be recovered from the first payment of wages for a complete wage period 
but no recovery can be made of advances given for travelling expenses before 
payment began.
 


(c) Advances of unearned wages can be made at 
the paymaster’s discretion during employment.
 


14. Deductions can be made for subscription to 
and for repayment of advances from any recognised provident fund.
 


15. Deductions can be made for payments to 
co-operative societies approved by the Central Government or to the postal 
insurance, subject to any conditions imposed by the Central Government.
 


Deductions can also be made with the written 
authorisation of the person employed for payment of any premium on his life 
insurance policy to the Life Insurance Corporation of India or for the purchase 
of securities of the Government of India or of any State Government or for being 
deposited in any Post Office Savings Bank in furtherance of any savings scheme 
of any such Government.
 


15A. Any loss of wages resulting from 
withholding of increment or promotion, reduction to a lower post or time scale 
or to a lower stage in a time scale or suspension does not constitute deduction 
from wages within the meaning of the Act. For this purpose the rules framed by 
an employer in relation to his employees in Railways for the purpose of any of 
the aforesaid penalties shall provide that:—
 


       (i)  any such penalty as aforesaid, 
except the penalty of suspension, shall not be imposed unless the person 
concerned—
 


           (a)  has been informed of the 
charges in respect of which it is proposed to impose the penalty;
 


           (b)  has been given a reasonable 
opportunity of showing cause why the proposed penalty should not be imposed.
 


      (ii)  the person concerned is given a 
right of appeal against any order imposing the penalty.
 


Inspections
 


16. An Inspector can enter on any premises and 
can exercise the powers of inspection (including examination of documents and 
taking of evidence) as he may deem necessary for carrying out the purposes of 
the Act.
 


Complaints of Deductions or Delays
 


17. (1) Where irregular deductions are made 
from wages, or delays in payment take place, an employed person can make an 
application in the prescribed form within 6 months to the Authority appointed by 
the State Government for the purpose. An application delayed beyond this period 
may be rejected unless sufficient cause for delay is shown.
 


(2) Any legal practitioner, official of a 
registered trade union, Inspector under the Act or other person acting with the 
permission of the authority can make the complaint on behalf of an employed 
person.
 


(3) A single application may be presented by, 
or on behalf of any number of persons belonging to the same factory, the payment 
of whose wages has been delayed.
 


Family member or dependant relations of 
employed person can make claims
 


17A. The spouse or children and where the 
employed person does not have spouse or children, the dependent relation can 
make claims at any time within seven years during which time the wages remain 
with the pay master for a period of 1st three years.
 


Action by the Authority
 


18. The Authority may award compensation to 
the employed person in addition to ordering the payment of delayed wages or the 
refund of illegal deductions.
 


If a malicious or vexatious complaint is made, 
the Authority may impose a penalty not exceeding Rs. 50 on the applicant and 
order that it be paid to the employer.
 


Appeal against the Authority
 


19. An appeal against an order dismissing 
either wholly or in part an application or against a direction may be preferred 
within thirty days in Madras, Bombay, Calcutta to the Court of Small Causes and 
elsewhere to the District Court—
 


      (a)  by the if the total amount directed 
to be paid exceeds Rs. 300;
 


      (b)  by an employed person or any 
official of a registered trade union authorised in writing to act on his behalf, 
if the total amount of wages withheld from him or his co-workers, exceeds rupees 
fifty;
 


      (c)  by a person directed to pay a 
penalty for a malicious or vexatious application.
 


Payment of undisbursed wages
 


19A. If all amounts payable to an employed 
person as wages could not be or cannot be paid on account of his death before 
payment or an account of his whereabouts not being known, shall be paid to the 
person nominated by him in this behalf.
 


Punishments for breaches of the Act
 


20. Any one delay in the payment of wages 
beyond the due date, or making any unauthorised deductions from wages is liable 
to a fine upto Rs. 500, only if prosecuted with the sanction of the Authority or 
the Appellate Court.
 


21. The paymaster who—
 


      (1)  does not fix a wage-period, or
 


      (2)  makes payment in kind, or
 


      (3)  fails to display at or near the 
main entrance of the factory this abstract in English and in the language of the 
majority of the employed persons, or
 


      (4)  breaks certain rules made under the 
Act, 
 


is liable to find not exceeding Rs. 200.
 


A complaint to this effect can be made only by 
the Inspector, or with his sanction.
 

 
 

—————
 

   1.  Subs. by G.S.R. 
1159 (E), dated 9th December, 1988 (w.e.f.
9-12-1988).
 

   2.  Subs. by G.S.R. 
1159 (E), dated 9th December, 1988 (w.e.f.
9-12-1988).
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>