<act><tid>1228287</tid>
<title>THE IMMIGRATION (CARRIERS' LIABILITY) ACT, <year>2000</year></title>

ACT NO. 52 OF <year>2000</year>
[ 11th December, <year>2000</year>.]

An Act to make the carriers liable in respect of passengers brought by 
them into India in contravention of the provisions of the Passport 
 (Entry into India) Act, <year>1920</year> and the rules made thereunder and matters 
connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- first Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>1847665</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.-
<section><tid>1632875</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Immigration  
 (Carriers' Liability) Act, <year>2000</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>236021</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>987177</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.-
<section><tid>644490</tid>
<number>1</number>In this Act, unless the context otherwise  
requires,-

<subsection><tid>478360</tid>
<number>a</number>" carrier" means a person who is engaged in the business of 
transporting passengers by water or air and includes any association 
of persons, whether incorporated or not, by whom the aircraft or the 
ship is owned or chartered;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>870044</tid>
<number>b</number>" Competent Authority" means the civil authority appointed under 
sub- paragraph (2) of paragraph 2 of the Foreigners Order, <year>1948</year> made 
under the Foreigners Act, <year>1946</year> (31 of <year>1946</year>) or any other officer 
notified by the Central Government in this behalf;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>922679</tid>
<number>c</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1363227</tid>
<number>2</number>Words and expressions not defined in this Act but defined in the 
Foreigners Act, <year>1946</year> (31 of <year>1946</year>) or the Passport (Entry into India) 
Act, <year>1920</year> (34 of <year>1920</year>) shall have the meanings respectively assigned 
to them in those Acts.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>558401</tid>
<number>3</number>Liability of carriers for passengers brought into India.- Where the 
competent authority is of the opinion that any carrier has brought a 
person in contravention of the provisions of the Passport (Entry into  
  India) Act, <year>1920</year> (34 of <year>1920</year>) and rules made thereunder into India, he 
may by order impose a penalty of rupees one lakh on such carrier:
Provided that no order shall be passed without giving the carrier an 
opportunity of being heard in the matter.



</article>



<article><tid>1222550</tid>
<number> 4</number> Appeals.-
<section><tid>836777</tid>
<number>1</number>An appeal shall lie against the order made under  
section 3 of this Act to the Joint Secretary to the Government of 
India in the Ministry of Home Affairs authorised in this behalf by 
that Government.

</section>

<section><tid>965784</tid>
<number>2</number>Every such appeal shall be preferred within thirty days from the 
date of the order appealed against:
Provided that the appellate authority may, if it is satisfied that the 
appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from preferring the appeal 
within the said period of thirty days, permit the appellant to prefer 
the appeal within a further period of thi ty days.


</section>

<section><tid>602859</tid>
<number>3</number>On receipt of any such appeal, the appellate authority shall, 
after giving the parties a reasonable opportunity of being heard and 
after making such inquiry as it deems proper, make such order, as it 
may think fit, confirming, modifying or reversin the order appealed 
against.

</section>

<section><tid>1735401</tid>
<number>4</number>Every appeal shall be preferred on payment of such fees as may be 
prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>948849</tid>
<number> 5</number> Recovery of penalty due to Government.- Where any penalty imposed 
under this Act is not paid, the competent authority may recover the 
penalty so payable by seizing, detaining or selling-
<section><tid>1822731</tid>
<number>a</number>the aircraft or the ship; or

</section>

<section><tid>790900</tid>
<number>b</number>any goods on the ship or aircraft, belonging to the carrier.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1956059</tid>
<number>6</number>Bar of legal proceedings.- No suit, prosecution or other legal 
proceeding shall lie against the Central Government or the competent 
authority or any officer of the Central Government or any other person 
exercising any powers or discharging any functi ns or performing any 
duty under this Act for anything in good faith done or intended to be 
done under this Act or any rule made thereunder.


</article>



<article><tid>1275016</tid>
<number>7</number>Application of Acts 16 of <year>1939</year>, 34 of <year>1920</year> and 31 of <year>1946</year> not 
barred.- The provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder shall 
be in addition to, and not in derogation of, the Registration of 
Foreigners Act, <year>1939</year>, the Passport (Entry into Indi) Act, <year>1920</year> and 
the Foreigners Act, <year>1946</year> or the rules or orders made thereunder.


</article>



<article><tid>1824961</tid>
<number> 8</number> Power to make rules.-
<section><tid>1584951</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the 
purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1045262</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for-

<subsection><tid>465839</tid>
<number>a</number>the fees which shall be paid for appeals under sub- section (4) of 
section 4;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>483226</tid>
<number>b</number>any other matter which is required to be, or may be, prescribed.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>306800</tid>
<number>9</number>Rules to be laid before Parliament.- Every rule made under this Act 
shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House 
of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty 
days which may be comprised in one session or i two or more successive 
sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both 
Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses 
agree that the rule should not be m de, the rule shall thereafter have 
effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may 
be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be 
without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under 
that rule.


</article>



<article><tid>1209378</tid>
<number> 10</number> Power to remove difficulties.-
<section><tid>1649978</tid>
<number>1</number>If any difficulty arises in  
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order, do anything not inconsistent with such provisions for 
the purpose of removing the difficulty:
Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of two 
years from the commencement of this Act.


</section>

<section><tid>1016959</tid>
<number>2</number>Every order under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be 
after it is made, before each House of Parliament.
SUBHASH C. JAIN, 
Secy. to the Govt. of India.



</section>

</article>



 </act>