<act><title>


The Protection of Women from Domestic Violence Rules, 20061</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Protection of Women from Domestic Violence Rules, 
2006.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the 26th day of October, 2006.
 
 



</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  “Act” means 
the Protection of Women from Domestic Violence Act, 2005 (43 of 2005);
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  “complaint” 
means any allegation made orally or in writing by any person to the Protection 
Officer;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  “Counsellor” 
means a member of a service provider competent to give counselling under 
sub-section (1) of section 14;
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  “Form” means a 
form appended to these rules;
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number>  “section” 
means a section of the Act;
 </section><section>
        <number>f</number>  words and 
expressions used and not defined in these rules but defined in the Act shall 
have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Qualifications and 
experience of Protection Officers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Protection Officers appointed by the State Government may be of the 
Government or members of non-governmental organizations:
 
Provided that preference 
shall be given to women.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every person appointed 
as Protection Officer under the Act shall have at least three years experience 
in social sector.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The tenure of a 
Protection Officer shall be a minimum period of three years.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The State Government 
shall provide necessary office assistance to the Protection Officer for the 
efficient discharge of his or her functions under the Act and these rules.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Information to 
Protection Officers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any person who has reason to believe that an act of domestic violence has been, 
or is being, or is likely to be committed may give information about it to the 
Protection Officer having jurisdiction in the area either orally or in writing.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In case the 
information is given to the Protection Officer under sub-rule (1) orally, he or 
she shall cause it to be reduced to in writing and shall ensure that the same is 
signed by the person giving such information and in case the informant is not in 
a position to furnish written information the Protection Officer shall satisfy 
and keep a record of the identity of the person giving such information.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Protection Officer 
shall give a copy of the information recorded by him immediately to the 
informant free of cost.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Domestic incident 
reports.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Upon receipt of a complaint of domestic violence, the Protection Officer shall 
prepare a domestic incident report in Form I and submit the same to the 
Magistrate and forward copies thereof to the police officer in charge of the 
police station within the local limits of jurisdiction of which the domestic 
violence alleged to have been committed has taken place and to the service 
providers in that area.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Upon a request of any 
aggrieved person, a service provider may record a domestic incident report in 
Form I and forward a copy thereof to the Magistrate and the Protection Officer 
having jurisdiction in the area where the domestic violence is alleged to have 
taken place.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Applications to the 
Magistrate.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every application of the aggrieved person under section 12 shall be in Form II 
or as nearly as possible thereto.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An aggrieved person 
may seek the assistance of the Protection Officer in preparing her application 
under sub-rule (1) and forwarding the same to the concerned Magistrate.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In case the aggrieved 
person is illiterate, the Protection Officer shall read over the application and 
explain to her the contents thereof.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The affidavit to be 
filed under sub-section (2) of section 23 shall be filed in Form III.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The applications under 
section 12 shall be dealt with and the orders enforced in the same manner laid 
down under section 125 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Affidavit for 
obtaining ex-parte orders of Magistrate.—Every 
affidavit for obtaining ex-parte order under sub-section (2) of section 
23 shall be filed in Form III.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Duties and functions 
of Protection Officers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
It shall be the duty of the Protection Officer—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  to assist the 
aggrieved person in making a complaint under the Act, if the aggrieved person so 
desires; 
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  to provide 
her information on the rights of aggrieved persons under the Act as given in 
Form IV which shall be in English or in a vernacular local language;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number>  to assist 
the person in making any application under section 12, or sub-section (2) of 
section 23 or any other provision of the Act or the rules made thereunder;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iv</number>  to prepare a 
“Safety Plan” including measures to prevent further domestic violence to the 
aggrieved person, in consultation with the aggrieved person in Form V, after 
making an assessment of the dangers involved in the situation and on an 
application being moved under section 12;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>v</number>  to provide 
legal aid to the aggrieved person, through the State Legal Aid Services 
Authority;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>vi</number>  to assist the 
aggrieved person and any child in obtaining medical aid at a medical facility 
including providing transportation to get the medical facility;
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>vii</number>  to assist in 
obtaining transportation for the aggrieved person and any child to the shelter;
 </subsection><subsection>
     <number>viii</number>  to inform the 
service providers registered under the Act that their services may be required 
in the proceedings under the Act and to invite applications from service 
providers seeking particulars of their members to be appointed as Counsellors in 
proceedings under the Act under sub-section (1) of section 14 or Welfare Experts 
under section 15;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>ix</number>  to scrutinise 
the applications for appointment as Counsellors and forward a list of available 
Counsellors to the Magistrate;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>x</number>  to revise once 
in three years the list of available Counsellors by inviting fresh applications 
and forward a revised list of Counsellors on the basis thereof to the concerned 
Magistrate;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>xi</number>  to maintain a 
record and copies of the report and documents forwarded under sections 9, 12, 
20, 21, 22, 23 or any other provisions of the Act or these rules;
 <subsubsection>
      <number>xii</number>  to provide 
all possible assistance to the aggrieved person and the children to ensure that 
the aggrieved person is not victimized or pressurized as a consequence of 
reporting the incidence of domestic violence;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
      <number>xiii</number>  to liaise 
between the aggrieved person or persons, police and service provider in the 
manner provided under the Act and these rules;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
     <number>xiv</number>  to maintain 
proper records of the service providers, medical facility and shelter homes in 
the area of his jurisdiction.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> In addition to the 
duties and functions assigned to a Protection Officer under clauses (a) to (h) 
of sub-section (1) of section 9, it shall be the duty of every Protection 
Officer—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  to protect the 
aggrieved persons from domestic violence, in accordance with the provisions of 
the Act and these rules;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  to take all 
reasonable measures to prevent recurrence of domestic violence against the 
aggrieved person, in accordance with the provisions of the Act and these rules.
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Action to be taken 
in cases of emergency.—If 
the Protection Officer or a service provider receives reliable information 
through e-mail or a telephone call or the like either from the aggrieved 
person or from any person who has reason to believe that an act of domestic 
violence is being or is likely to be committed and in a such an emergency 
situation, the Protection Officer or the service provider, as the case may be, 
shall seek immediate assistance of the police who shall accompany the Protection 
Officer or the service provider, as the case may be, to the place of occurrence 
and record the domestic incident report and present the same to the Magistrate 
without any delay for seeking appropriate orders under the Act.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Certain other 
duties of the Protection Officers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Protection Officer, if directed to do so in writing, by the Magistrate 
shall—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  conduct a home 
visit of the shared household premises and make preliminary enquiry if the court 
requires clarification, in regard to granting ex-parte interim relief to 
the aggrieved person under the Act and pass an order for such home visit;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  after making 
appropriate inquiry, file a report on the emoluments, assets, bank accounts or 
any other documents as may be directed by the court;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  restore the 
possession of the personal effects including gifts and jewellery of the 
aggrieved person and the shared household to the aggrieved person;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  assist the 
aggrieved person to regain custody of children and secure rights to visit them 
under his supervision as may be directed by the court;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number> assist 
the court in enforcement of orders in the proceedings under the Act in the 
manner directed by the Magistrate, including orders under section 12, section 
18, section 19, section 20, section 21 or section 23 in such manner as may be 
directed by the court;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  take the 
assistance of the police, if required, in confiscating any weapon involved in 
the alleged domestic violence.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Protection Officer 
shall also perform such other duties as may be assigned to him by the State 
Government or the Magistrate in giving effect to the provisions of the Act and 
these rules from time to time.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Magistrate may, in 
addition to the orders for effective relief in any case, also issue directions 
relating general practice for better handling of the cases, to the Protection 
Officers within his jurisdiction and the Protection Officers shall be bound to 
carry out the same.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Registration of 
service providers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any voluntary association registered under the Societies Registration Act, 1860 
(21 of 1860) or a company registered under the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) 
or any other law for time being in force with the objective of protecting the 
rights and interests of women by any lawful means including providing of legal 
aid, medical, financial or other assistance and desirous of providing service as 
a service provider under the Act shall make an application under sub-section (1) 
of section 10 for registration as service provider in Form VI to the State 
Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The State Government 
shall, after making such enquiry as it may consider necessary and after 
satisfying itself about the suitability of the applicant, register it as a 
service provider and issue a certificate of such registration:
 
Provided that no such 
application shall be rejected without giving the applicant an opportunity of 
being heard.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every association or 
company seeking registration under sub-section (1) of section 10 shall possess 
the following eligibility criteria, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  It should have 
been rendering the kind of services it is offering under the Act for at least 
three years before the date of application for registration under the Act and 
these rules as a service provider.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  In case an 
applicant for registration is running a medical facility, or a 
psychiatric counselling centre, or a vocational training institution, the State 
Government shall ensure that the applicant fulfils the requirements for running 
such a facility or institution laid down by the respective regulatory 
authorities regulating the respective professions or institutions.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  In case an 
applicant for registration is running a shelter home, the State Government 
shall, through an officer or any authority or agency authorised by it, inspect 
the shelter home, prepare a report and record its finding on the report, 
detailing that—
 <subsubsection>
             <number>i</number>  the 
maximum capacity of such shelter home for intake of persons seeking shelter;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>ii</number>  the 
place is secure for running a shelter home for women and that adequate security 
arrangements can be put in place for the shelter home;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>iii</number>  the 
shelter home has a record of maintaining a functional telephone connection or 
other communication media for the use of the inmates.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The State Government 
shall provide a list of service providers in the various localities to the 
concerned Protection Officers and also publish such list of newspapers or on its 
website.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Protection Officer 
shall maintain proper records by way of maintenance of registers duly indexed, 
containing the details of the service providers.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Means of service of 
notices.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The notices for appearance in respect of the proceedings under the Act shall 
contain the names of the person alleged to have committed domestic violence, the 
nature of domestic violence and such other details which may facilitate the 
identification of person concerned.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The service of notices 
shall be made in the following manner, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  The notices in 
respect of the proceedings under the Act shall be served by the Protection 
Officer or any other person directed by him to serve the notice, on behalf of 
the Protection Officer, at the address where the respondent is stated to be 
ordinarily residing in India by the complainant or aggrieved person or where the 
respondent is stated to be gainfully employed by the complainant or aggrieved 
person, as the case may be.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  The notice 
shall be delivered to any person in charge of such place at the moment and in 
case of such delivery not being possible it shall be pasted at a conspicuous 
place on the premises.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  For serving 
the notices under section 13 or any other provision of the Act, the provisions 
under Order V of the Civil Procedure Code, 1908 (5 of 1908) or the provisions 
under Chapter VI of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) as far as 
practicable may be adopted.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  Any order 
passed for such service of notices shall entail the same consequences, as an 
order passed under Order V of the Civil Procedure Code, 1908 (5 of 1908) or 
Chapter VI of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) respectively, 
depending upon the procedure found efficacious for making an order for such 
service under section 13 or any other provision of the Act and in addition to 
the procedure prescribed under the Order V or Chapter VI, the court may direct 
any other steps necessary with a view to expediting the proceedings to adhere to 
the time limit provided in the Act.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> On a statement on the 
date fixed for appearance of the respondent, or a report of the person 
authorised to serve the notices under the Act, that service has been effected 
appropriate orders shall be passed by the court on any pending application for 
interim relief, after hearing the complainant or the respondent, or both.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> When a protection 
order is passed restraining the respondent from entering the shared household or 
the respondent is ordered to stay away or not to contact the petitioner, no 
action of the aggrieved person including an invitation by the aggrieved person 
shall be considered as waiving the restraint imposed on the respondent, by the 
order of the court, unless such protection order is duly modified in accordance 
with the provisions of sub-section (2) of section 25.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Appointment of 
Counsellors.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A person from the list of available Counsellors forwarded by the Protection 
Officer, shall be appointed as a Counsellor, under intimation to aggrieved 
person.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The following persons 
shall not be eligible to be appointed as Counsellors in any proceedings, 
namely:—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  any person 
who is interested or connected with the subject matter of the dispute or is 
related to any one of the parties or to those who represent them unless such 
objection is waived by all the parties in writing.
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  any legal 
practitioner who has appeared for the respondent in the case or any other suit 
or proceedings connected therewith.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The Counsellors shall 
as far as possible be women.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Procedure to be 
followed by Counsellors.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Counsellor shall work under the general supervision of the court or the 
Protection Officer or both.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Counsellor shall 
convene a meeting at a place convenient to the aggrieved person or both the 
parties.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The factors warranting 
counselling shall include the factor that the respondent shall furnish an 
undertaking that he would refrain from causing such domestic violence as 
complained by the complainant and in appropriate cases an undertaking that he 
will not try to meet, or communicate in any manner through letter or telephone, 
electronic mail or through any medium except in the counselling proceedings 
before the counsellor or as permissibly by law or order of a court of competent 
jurisdiction.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Counsellor shall 
conduct the counselling proceedings bearing in mind that the counselling shall 
be in the nature of getting an assurance, that the incidence of domestic 
violence shall not get repeated.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The respondent shall 
not be allowed to plead any counter justification for the alleged act of 
domestic violence in counselling the fact that and any justification for the act 
of domestic violence by the respondent is not allowed to be a part of the 
Counselling proceeding should be made known to the respondent, before the 
proceedings begin.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The respondent shall 
furnish an undertaking to the Counsellor that he would refrain from causing such 
domestic violence as complained by the aggrieved person and in appropriate cases 
an undertaking that he will not try to meet, or communicate in any manner 
through letter or telephone, e-mail, or through any other medium except in the 
counselling proceedings before the Counsellor.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> If the aggrieved 
person so desires, the Counsellor shall make efforts of arriving at a settlement 
of the matter.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> The limited scope of 
the efforts of the Counsellor shall be to arrive at the understanding of the 
grievances of the aggrieved person and the best possible redressal of her 
grievances and the efforts shall be to focus on evolving remedies or measures 
for such redressal.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> The Counsellor shall 
strive to arrive at a settlement of the dispute by suggesting measures for 
redressal of grievances of the aggrieved person by taking into account the 
measures or remedies suggested by the parties for counselling and reformulating 
the terms for the settlement, wherever required.
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> The Counsellor shall 
not be bound by the provisions of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872) or 
the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), or the Code of Criminal 
Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), and his action shall be guided by the principles of 
fairness and justice and aimed at finding way to bring an end to domestic 
violence to the satisfaction of the aggrieved person and in making such an 
effort the Counsellor shall give due regard to the wishes and sensibilities of 
the aggrieved person.
 </section><section>
<number>11</number> The Counsellor shall 
submit his report to the Magistrate as expeditiously as possible for appropriate 
action.
 </section><section>
<number>12</number> In the event the 
Counsellor arrives at a resolution of the dispute, he shall record the terms of 
settlement and get the same endorsed by the parties.
 </section><section>
<number>13</number> The court may, on 
being satisfied about the efficacy of the solution and after making a 
preliminary enquiry from the parties and after, recording reasons for such 
satisfaction, which may include undertaking by the respondents to refrain from 
repeating acts of domestic violence, admitted to have been committed by the 
respondents, accept the terms with or without conditions.
 </section><section>
<number>14</number> The court shall, on 
being so satisfied with the report of counselling, pass an order, recording the 
terms of the settlement or an order modifying the terms of the settlement on 
being so requested by the aggrieved person, with the consent of the parties.
 </section><section>
<number>15</number> In cases, where a 
settlement cannot be arrived at in the counselling proceedings, the Counsellor 
shall report the failure of such proceedings to the Court and the court shall 
proceed with the case in accordance with the provisions of the Act.
 </section><section>
<number>16</number> The record of 
proceedings shall not be deemed to be material on record in the case on the 
basis of which any inference may be drawn or an order may be passed solely based 
on it.
 </section><section>
 <number>17</number> The Court shall pass 
an order under section 25, only after being satisfied that the 
application for such an order is not vitiated by force, fraud or coercion or any 
other factor and the reasons for such satisfaction shall be recorded in writing 
in the order, which may include any undertaking or surety given by the 
respondent.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Breach of 
Protection Orders.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An aggrieved person may report a breach of protection order or an interim 
protection order to the Protection Officer.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every report referred 
to in sub-rule (1) shall be in writing by the informant and duly signed by her.

 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Protection Officer 
shall forward a copy of such complaint with a copy of the protection order of 
which a breach is alleged to have taken place to the concerned Magistrate for 
appropriate orders.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The aggrieved person 
may, if she so desires, make a complaint of breach of protection order or 
interim protection order directly to the Magistrate or the Police, if she so 
chooses.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If, at any time after 
a protection order has been breached, the aggrieved person seeks his assistance, 
the protection officer shall immediately rescue her by seeking help from the 
local police station and assist the aggrieved person to lodge a report to the 
local police authorities in appropriate cases.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> When charges are 
framed under section 31 or in respect of offences under section 498A of the 
Indian Penal Code, 1860 (45 of 1860), or any other offence not summarily 
triable, the Court may separate the proceedings for such offences to be tried in 
the manner prescribed under Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) and 
proceed to summarily try the offence of the breach of Protection Order under 
section 31, in accordance with the provisions of Chapter XXI of the Code of 
Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Any resistance to the 
enforcement of the orders of the Court under the Act by the respondent or any 
other person purportedly acting on his behalf shall be deemed to be a breach of 
protection order or an interim protection order covered under the Act.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> A breach of a 
protection order or an interim protection order shall immediately be reported to 
the local police station having territorial jurisdiction and shall be dealt with 
as a cognizable offence as provided under sections 31 and 32.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> While enlarging the 
person on bail arrested under the Act, the Court may, by order, impose the 
following conditions to protect the aggrieved person and to ensure the presence 
of the accused before the court, which may include—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  an order 
restraining the accused from threatening to commit or committing an act of 
domestic violence;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  an order 
preventing the accused from harassing, telephoning or making any contact with 
the aggrieved person;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  an order 
directing the accused to vacate and stay away from the residence of the 
aggrieved person or any place she is likely to visit;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  an order 
prohibiting the possession or use of firearm or any other dangerous weapon;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  an order 
prohibiting the consumption of alcohol or other drugs;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  any other 
order required for protection, safety and adequate relief to the aggrieved 
person.
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Shelter to the 
aggrieved person.—
<section><number>1</number> 
On a request being made by the aggrieved person, the Protection Officer or a 
service provider may make a request under section 6 to the person in charge of a 
shelter home in writing, clearly stating that the application is being made 
under section 6.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When a Protection 
Officer makes a request referred to in sub-rule (1), it shall be accompanied by 
a copy of the domestic incident report registered, under section 9 or under 
section 10:
 
Provided that shelter home 
shall not refuse shelter to an aggrieved person under the Act, for her not 
having lodged a domestic incident report, prior to the making of request for 
shelter in the shelter home.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If the aggrieved 
person so desires, the shelter home shall not disclose the identity of the 
aggrieved person in the shelter home or communicate the same to the person 
complained against.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Medical facility to 
the aggrieved person.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The aggrieved person or the Protection Officer or the service provider may make 
a request under section 7 to a person in charge of a medical facility in 
writing, clearly stating that the application is being made under section 7.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When a Protection 
Officer makes such a request, it shall be accompanied by a copy of the domestic 
incident report:
 
Provided that the medical 
facility shall not refuse medical assistance to an aggrieved person under the 
Act, for her not having lodged a domestic incident report, prior to making a 
request for medical assistance or examination to
the medical facility.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If no domestic 
incident report has been made, the person-in-charge of the medical facility 
shall fill in Form I and forward the same to the local Protection Officer.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The medical facility 
shall supply a copy of the medical examination report to the aggrieved person 
free of cost.
 
 
  
</section></article><form>
 




The Protection of Women from Domestic Violence Rules, 2006
 





 




FORM VII 
 


[See rule 11(1)]
 




NOTICE FOR APPEARANCE UNDER SECTION 13(1) OF THE Protection of Women from 
Domestic Violence Act, 2005
 


IN THE COURT OF…………
 


P/S:……………
 


IN THE MATTER OF:
 



Ms…….                                                                                                               
COMPLAINANT
 


VERSUS
 


Mr……..
RESPONDENT
 


To,
 


Mr........................................
 



S/o.......................................
 



R/o......................................
 



.............................................
 



.............................................
 


WHEREAS the Petitioner has 
filed an application(s) under section…..of the Protection of Women from Domestic 
Violence Act, 2005 (43 of 2005);
 


You are hereby directed to 
appear before this Court on the…..day of……20……at…….. O’ clock in the…..noon 
personally or through a duly authorised counsel of this Court to show cause why 
the relief(s) claimed by the Applicant against you should not be granted, 
failing which the court shall proceed ex parte against you.
 


Given under my hand and the 
seal of the Court of……on the……. day of……20....
 


 
 


Seal of the 
Court                                                                                                
Signature
 

 
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>