<act><title>
THE
INDIAN PARTNERSHIP ACT, 1932</title> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>1</number>
Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
This Act may be called the Indian Partnership Act, 1932.
 </section><section><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>2</number>
It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[except
the State of Jammu and Kashmir].]
 </section><section><number>3</number>
It shall come into force on the 1st day of October, 1932, except section 69,
which shall come into force on the 1st day of October, 1933.
 


  
 
State
Amendments
 
Dadra
and Nagar Haveli.—In section 1, for
sub-section (3), substitute the following:—
 

“(3) It shall come into
force at once except section 69 which shall come into force on the 1st day of
July, 1966”.
 
[Vide
Reg. 6 of 1963, as amended by Reg. 2 of 1965.]
 
Goa,
Daman and Diu.—Same as in Dadra and
Nagar Haveli except for the date of enforcement of section 69 which is 1st day
of January, 1965.
 
[Vide
Reg. 11 of 1963].


 
Laccadive,
Minicoy and Amindivi Islands.—In its
application to Lakshadweep, in section 1, for sub-section (3), substitute the
following:—
 

“(3) It shall come into
force at once except section 69, which shall come into force on the expiry of a
period of one year from the date of commencement of the rest of this Act”.


 <subsection>
[<number>Reg</number>
8 of 1965, sec. 3 and Sch. 1].
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>Pondicherry</number>—Same
as in Dadra and Nagar Haveli, except for the date of enforcement of section 69
which is 1st day of July, 1964.
 </subsection><subsection>
[<number>Reg</number>
7 of 1963, sec. 3 and Sch. 1].


 
  









  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In
this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,—
 <section><number>a</number>
an “act of a firm” means any act or omission by all the partners, or
by any partner or agent of the firm which gives rise to a right enforceable by
or against the firm;
 </section><section><number>b</number>
“business” includes every trade, occupation and profession;
 </section><section><number>c</number>
“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act;
 </section><section><number>d</number>
“third party” used in relation to a firm or to a partner therein
means any person who is not a partner in the firm; and
 </section><section><number>e</number>
expressions used but not defined in this Act and defined in the Indian
Contract Act, 1872 (9 of 1872), shall have the meanings assigned to them in that
Act. 
 

  
 

State
Amendment
 <subsection>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—In
section 2, after clause (c), insert the following clause, namely:—
 

“(c-1) “Registrar”
means the Registrar of Firms appointed under sub-section (1) of section 57 and
includes the Deputy Registrar of Firms and Assistant Registrar of Firms
appointed under sub-section (2) of that section;”
 
[Vide
Maharashtra Act 29 of 1984, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 1-1-1985)].
  





  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
  
 <article><number>3</number> Application of 
      provisions of Act 9 of 1872.—The unrepealed provisions of the 
      Indian Contract Act, 1872, save in so far as they are inconsistent with 
      the express provisions of this Act, shall continue to apply to 
      firms.
  </article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>4</number>
Definition of “partnership”, “partner”, “firm” and “firm name”.—’’Partnership”
is the relation between persons who have agreed to share the profits of a
business carried on by all or any of them acting for all.
 


 Persons
who have entered into partnership with one another are called individually
“partners” and collectively a “firm”, and the name under which their
business is carried on is called the “firm name”.
  









  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>5</number>
Partnership not created by status.—The
relation of partnership arises from contract and not from status; 
 and,
in particular, the members of a Hindu undivided family carrying on a family
business as such, or a Burmese Buddhist husband and wife carrying business as
such, are not partners in such business. 
  
 
State
Amendment
 
Goa,
Daman and Diu.—In
section 5, for the words “Burmese Buddhist husband and wife carrying on
business as such”, substitute the words “a husband and wife under the regime
of communion of property carrying on business as such”.
 
[Vide
Goa, Daman and Diu Act 6 of 1966, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 22-8-1966)].
  









  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>6</number>
Mode of determining existence of partnership.—In
determining whether a group of persons is or is not a firm, or whether a person
is or is not a partner in a firm, regard shall be had to the real relation
between the parties, as shown by all relevant facts taken together.
 


 Explanation
1.—The
sharing of profits or of gross returns arising from property by persons holding
a joint or common interest in that property does not of itself make such persons
partners.
 


 Explanation
2.—The
receipt by a person of a share of the profits of a business, or of a payment
contingent upon the earning of profits or varying with the profits earned by a
business, does not of itself make him a partner with the persons carrying on the
business;
 


 and
in particular, the receipt of such share or payment—
 


 <section><number>a</number>
by a lender of money to persons engaged or about to engage in any
business, 
 

 </section><section><number>b</number>
by a servant or agent as remuneration, 
 

 </section><section><number>c</number>
by the widow or child of a deceased partner, as annuity, or  
 

 </section><section><number>d</number>
by a previous owner or part owner of the business, as consideration for
the sale of the goodwill or share thereof, 
 

 
does not of itself make the receiver a partner with the persons carrying on the 
business.
  










  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>7</number>
Partnership at will.—Where
no provision is made by contract between the partners for the duration of their
partnership, or for the determination of their partnership, the partnership is
‘partnership at will’.

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>8</number>
Particular partnership.—A
person may become a partner with another person in particular adventures or
undertakings.

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>9</number>
General duties of partners.—Partners
are bound to carry on the business of the firm to the greatest common advantage,
to be just and faithful to each other, and to render true accounts and full
information of all things affecting the firm to any partner or his legal
representative.
  
 

State
Amendment
 <section>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—In
section 9, for the words “or his legal representative”, substitute the words
“his heir or legal representative”.
 
[Vide
Maharashtra Act 29 of 1984, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-1-1985)].
  









  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>10</number>
Duty to indemnify for loss caused by fraud.—Every
partner shall indemnify the firm for any loss caused to it by his fraud in the
conduct of the business of the firm.

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>11</number>
Determination of rights and duties of partners by contract between the partners.—
<section><number>1</number>
Subject to the provisions of this Act, the mutual rights and duties of the
partners of a firm may be determined by contract between the partners, and such
contract may be expressed or may be implied by a course of dealing.
 Such
contract may be varied by consent of all the partners, and such consent may be
expressed or may be implied by a course of dealing.
 Agreements
in restraints of trade.—(2)
Notwithstanding anything contained in section 27 of the Indian Contract Act,
1872 (9 of 1872), such contracts may provide that a partner shall not carry on
any business other than that of the firm while he is a partner.
  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>12</number>
The conduct of the business.—Subject
to contract between the partners,—
 <section><number>a</number>
every partner has a right to take part in the conduct of the business;
 </section><section><number>b</number>
every partner is bound to attend diligently to his duties in the conduct
of the business;
 </section><section><number>c</number>
any difference arising as to ordinary matters connected with the business
may be decided by a majority of the partners, and every partner shall have the
right to express his opinion, before the matter is decided, but no change may be
made in the nature of the business without the consent of all the partners; and  
 

 </section><section>
<number>d</number>
every partner has a right to have access to and to inspect and copy any
of the books of the firm.
  
 
State
Amendment
 <subsection>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—In
section 12,—
 <subsubsection>

<number>a</number>
in clause (c), at the end, omit the word “and”;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

<number>b</number>
in clause (d), for the words “books of the firm”, substitute the
words “books of the firm; and”;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

<number>c</number>
after clause (d), insert the following clause, namely:—
 

“(e) in the event of the
death of a partner, his heirs or legal representatives or their duly authorised
agents shall have a right of accesses to and to inspect and copy any of the
books of the firm”.
 
[Vide
Maharashtra Act 29 of 1984, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 1-1-1985)].
  




  


</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>13</number> Mutual rights and liabilities.—Subject 
to contract between the partners,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>
a partner is not entitled to receive remuneration for taking part in the 
conduct of the business; 
 

 </section><section>
<number>b</number>
the partners are entitled to share equally in the profits earned, and 
shall contribute equally to the losses sustained by the firm; 
 

 </section><section>
<number>c</number>
where a partner is entitled to interest on the capital subscribed by him 
such interest shall be payable only out of profits; 
 

 </section><section>
<number>d</number>
a partner making, for the purposes of the business, any payment or 
advance beyond the amount of capital he has agreed to subscribe, is entitled to 
interest thereon at the rate of six per cent. per annum; 
 

 </section><section>
<number>e</number>
the firm shall indemnify a partner in respect of payments made and 
liabilities incurred by him— 
 

 <subsection>
<number>i</number>
in the ordinary and proper conduct of the business, and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>
in doing such act, in an emergency, for the purpose of protecting the 
firm from loss, as would be done by a person of ordinary prudence, in his own 
case, under similar circumstances; and 
 

 </subsection></section><section>
<number>f</number>
a partner shall indemnify the firm for any loss caused to it by his 
wilful neglect in the conduct of the business of the firm. 
 

  





  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>14</number> The property of the firm.—Subject 
to contract between the partners, the property of the firm includes all property 
and rights and interests in property originally brought into the stock of the 
firm, or acquired, by purchase or otherwise, by or for the firm, or for the 
purposes and in the course of business of the firm, and includes also the 
goodwill of the business.
 
Unless the contrary intention appears, property and rights and interests in 
property acquired with money belonging to the firm are deemed to have been 
acquired for the firm.
  










  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>15</number> Application of the property of the firm.—Subject 
to contract between the partners, the property of the firm shall be held and 
used by the partners exclusively for the purposes of the business. 
 



  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>16</number> Personal profits earned by partners.—Subject 
to contract between the partners,—
 


 <section>
<number>a</number>
if a partner derives any profit for himself from any transaction of the 
firm, or from the use of the property or business connection of the firm or the 
firm name, he shall account for that profit and pay it to the firm; 
 

 </section><section>
<number>b</number>
if a partner carries on any business of the same nature as and competing 
with that of the firm, he shall account for and pay to the firm all profits made 
by him in that business.
  








  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>17</number> Rights and duties of partners.—Subject 
to contract between the partners—
 


 <section>
<number>a</number>
after a change in the firm.—where a change occurs in the 
constitution of a firm, the mutual rights and duties of the partners in the 
reconstituted firm remain the same as they were immediately before the change, 
as far as may be; 
 

 </section><section>
<number>b</number>
after the expiry of the term of the firm, and.—where a firm 
constituted for a fixed term continues to carry on business after the expiry of 
that term, the mutual rights and duties of the partners remain the same as they 
were before the expiry, so far as they may be consistent with the incidents of 
partnership at will; and 
 

 </section><section>
<number>c</number>
where additional undertakings are carried out.—where a firm 
constituted to carry out one or more adventures or undertakings carries out 
other adventures or undertakings, the mutual rights and duties of the partners 
in respect of the other adventures or undertakings are the same as those in 
respect of the original adventures or undertakings.
  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>18</number> Partner to be agent of the firm.—Subject 
to the provisions of this Act, a partner is the agent of the firm for the 
purpose of the business of the firm.
 



  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>19</number> Implied authority of partner as agent of the firm.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to the provisions of section 22, the act of a partner which is done to 
carry on, in the usual way, business of the kind carried on by the firm, binds 
the firm.
 


 
The authority of a partner to bind the firm conferred by this section is called 
his “implied authority”.
 


 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In the absence of any usage or custom of trade to the contrary, the implied 
authority of a partner does not empower him to—
 


 <subsection>
<number>a</number>
submit a dispute relating to the business of the firm to arbitration, 
 

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
open a banking account on behalf of the firm in his own name, 
 

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>
compromise or relinquish any claim or portion of a claim by the firm, 
 

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>
withdraw a suit or proceeding filed on behalf of the firm, 
 

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>
admit any liability in a suit or proceeding against the firm, 
 

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>
acquire immovable property on behalf of the firm, 
 

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>
transfer immovable property belonging to the firm, or
(h)
enter into partnership on behalf of the firm. 
 

  








  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>20</number> Extension and restriction of partner’s implied authority.—The 
partners in a firm may, by contract between the partners, extend or restrict the 
implied authority of any partner.
 
Notwithstanding any such restriction, any act done by a partner on behalf of the 
firm which falls within his implied authority binds the firm, unless the person 
with whom he is dealing knows of the restriction or does not know or believe 
that partner to be a partner. 
  





  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>21</number> Partner’s authority in an emergency.—A 
partner has authority, in an emergency, to do all such acts for the purpose of 
protecting the firm from loss as would be done by a person of ordinary prudence, 
in his own case, acting under similar circumstances, and such acts bind the 
firm.

  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>22</number> Mode of doing act to bind firm.—In order to bind a 
      firm, an act or instrument done or executed by a partner or other person 
      on behalf of the firm shall be done or executed in the firm name, or in 
      any other manner expressing or implying an intention to bind the 
      firm.
  





  </article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>23</number>
Effect of admissions by a partner.—An
admission on representation made by a partner concerning the affairs of the firm
is evidence against the firm, if it is made in the ordinary course of business.
 



  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
  
 <article><number>24</number> Effect of notice to acting partner.—Notice to a partner, 
      who habitually acts in the business of the firm of any matter relating to 
      the affairs of the firm operates as notice to the firm, except in the case 
      of a fraud on the firm committed by or with the consent of that 
      partner.
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
  
 <article><number>25</number> Liability of a partner for acts of the 
      firm.—Every partner is liable, jointly with all the 
      other partners and also severally, for all acts of the firm done while he 
      is a partner.
  




  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
  
 <article><number>26</number> Liability of the firm for wrongful acts of a 
      partner.—Where, by the wrongful act or omission of a 
      partner acting in the ordinary course of the business of a firm, or with 
      the authority of his partners, loss or injury is caused to any third 
      party, or any penalty is incurred, the firm is liable therefor to the same 
      extent as the partner.
  




  </article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>27</number>
Liability of firm for misapplication by partners.—Where—
 


 <section><number>a</number>
a partner acting within his apparent authority receives money or property
from a third party and misapplies it, or 
 

 </section><section><number>b</number>
a firm in the course of its business receives money or property from a
third party, and the money or property is misapplied by any of the partners
while it is in the custody of the firm the firm is liable to make good the loss.
  




  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>28</number>
Holding out.—
<section><number>1</number>
Any one who by words spoken or written or by conduct represents himself or
knowingly permits himself to be represented, to be a partner in a firm, is
liable as a partner in that firm to any one who has on the faith of any such
representation given credit to the firm, whether the person representing himself
or represented to be a partner does or does not know that the representation has
reached the person so giving credit.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Where after a partner’s death the business is continued in the old firm name,
the continued use of that name or of the deceased partner’s name as a part
thereof shall not of itself make his legal representative or his estate liable
for any act of the firm done after his death.
 



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>29</number>
Rights of transferee or a partner’s interest.—
<section><number>1</number>
A transfer by a partner of his interest in the firm, either absolute or by
mortgage, or by the creation by him of a change on such interest, does not
entitle the transferee, during the continuance of the firm, to interfere in the
conduct of the business, or to require accounts, or to inspect the books of the
firm, but entitles the transferee only to receive the share of profits of the
transferring partner, and the transferee shall accept the account of profits
agreed to by the partners.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
If the firm is dissolved or if the transferring partner ceases to be a partner,
the transferee is entitled as against the remaining partners to receive the
share of the assets of the firm to which the transferring partner is entitled,
and, for the purpose of ascertaining that share, to an account as from the date
of the dissolution.
 


  




  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>30</number>
Minors admitted to the benefits of partnership.—
<section><number>1</number>
A person who is a minor according to the law to which he is subject may not be a
partner in a firm, but, with the consent of all the partners for the time being,
he may be admitted to the benefits of partnership.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Such minor has a right to such share of the property and of the profits of the
firm as may be agreed upon, and he may have access to and inspect and copy any
of the accounts of the firm.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
Such minor’s share is liable for the acts of the firm, but the minor is not
personally liable for any such act.
 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
Such minor may not sue the partners for an account or payment of his share of
the property or profits of the firm, save when severing his connection with the
firm, and in such case the amount of his share shall be determined by a
valuation made as far as possible in accordance with the rules contained in
section 48:
 


 Provided
that all the partners acting together or any partner entitled to dissolve the
firm upon notice to other partners may elect in such suit to dissolve the firm,
and thereupon the court shall proceed with the suit as one for dissolution and
for settling accounts between the partners, and the amount of the share of the
minor shall be determined along with the shares of the partners.
 


 </section><section><number>5</number>
At any time within six months of his attaining majority, or of his obtaining
knowledge that he had been admitted to the benefits of partnership, whichever
date is later, such person may give public notice that he has elected to become
or that he has elected not to become a partner in the firm, and such notice
shall determine his position as regards the firm:
 


 Provided
that, if he fails to give such notice, he shall become a partner in the firm on
the expiry of the said six months.
 


 </section><section><number>6</number>
Where any person has been admitted as a minor to the benefits of partnership in
a firm, the burden of proving the fact that such person had no knowledge of such
admission until a particular date after the expiry of six months of his
attaining majority shall lie on the persons asserting that fact.
 


 </section><section><number>7</number>
where such person becomes a partner,—
 


 <subsection><number>a</number>
his rights and liabilities as a minor continue up to the date on which he
becomes a partner, but he also becomes personally liable to third parties for
all acts of the firm done since he was admitted to the benefits of partnership,
and
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
his share in the property and profits of the firm shall be the share to
which he was entitled as a minor. 
 

 </subsection></section><section><number>8</number>
Where such person elects not to become a partner,—
 


 <subsection><number>a</number>
his rights and liabilities shall continue to be those of a minor under
this section up to the date on which he gives public notice, 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
his share shall not be liable for any acts of the firm done after the
date of the notice, and 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
he shall be entitled to sue the partners for his share of the property
and profits in accordance with sub-section (4). 
 

 </subsection></section><section><number>9</number>
Nothing in sub-sections (7) and (8) shall affect the provisions of section 28.
 


  










  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>31</number>
Introduction of a partner.—
<section><number>1</number>
Subject to contract between the partners and to the provisions of section 30, no
person shall be introduced as a partner into a firm without the consent of all
the existing partners.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Subject to the provisions of section 30, a person who is introduced as a partner
into a firm does not thereby become liable for any act of the firm done before
he became a partner.
 


  




  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>32</number>
Retirement of a partner.—
<section><number>1</number>
A partner may retire,—
 


 <subsection><number>a</number>
with the consent of all the other partners,
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
in accordance with an express agreement by the partners, or
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
where the partnership is at will, by giving notice in writing to all the
other partners of his intention to retire.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
A retiring partner may be discharged from any liability to any third party for
acts of the firm done before his retirement by an agreement made by him with
such third party and the partners of the reconstituted firm, and such agreement
may be implied by a course of dealing between such third party and the
reconstituted firm after he had knowledge of the retirement.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
Notwithstanding the retirement of a partner from a firm, he and the partners
continue to be liable as partners to third parties for any act done by any of
them which would have been an act of the firm if done before the retirement,
until public notice is given of the retirement:
 Provided
that a retired partner is not liable to any third party who deals with the firm
without knowing that he was a partner.
 </section><section><number>4</number>
Notices under sub-section (3) may be given by the retired partner or by any
partner of the reconstituted firm.
  










  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>33</number>
Expulsion of a partner.—
<section><number>1</number>
A partner may not be expelled from a firm by any majority of the partners, save
in the exercise in good faith of powers conferred by contract between the
partners.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The provisions of sub-sections (2), (3) and (4) of section 32 shall apply to an
expelled partner as if he were a retired partner.
 



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>34</number>
Insolvency of a partner.—
<section><number>1</number>
Where a partner in a firm is adjudicated an insolvent he ceases to be a partner
on the date on which the order of adjudication is made, whether or not the firm
is hereby dissolved.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Where under a contract between the partners the firm is not dissolved by the
adjudication of a partner as an insolvent, the estate of a partner so
adjudicated is not liable for any act of the firm and the firm is not liable for
any act of the insolvent, done after the date on which the order of adjudication
is made.
 



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>35</number>
Liability of estate of deceased partner.—Where
under a contract between the partners the firm is not dissolved by the death of
a partner, the estate of a deceased partner is not liable for any act of the
firm done after his death.
 


  





  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>36</number>
Right of outgoing partner to carry on competing business.—
<section><number>1</number>
An outgoing partner may carry on a business competing with that of the firm and
he may advertise such business, but, subject to contract to the contrary, he may
not,—
 


 <subsection><number>a</number>
use the firm name, 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
represent himself as carrying on the business of the firm, or 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
solicit the custom of persons who were dealing with the firm before he
ceased to be a partner. 
 

 Agreements
in restraint of trade.—(2)
A partner may make an agreement with his partners that on ceasing to be a
partner he will not carry on any business similar to that of the firm within a
specified period or within a specified local limits; and, notwithstanding
anything contained in section 27 of the Indian Contract Act, 1872 (9 of 1872),
such agreement shall be valid if the restrictions imposed are reasonable. 
  

  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>37</number>
Right of outgoing partner in certain cases to share subsequent profits.—Where any member of a firm has died or otherwise ceased to be a
partner, and the surviving or continuing partners carry on the business of the
firm with the property of the firm without any final settlement of accounts as
between them and the outgoing partner or his estate, then, in the absence of a
contract to the contrary, the outgoing partner or his estate is entitled at the
option of himself or his representatives to such share of the profits made since
he ceased to be a partner as may be attributable to the use of his share of the
property of the firm or to interest at the rate of six per cent. per annum on
the amount of his share in the property of the firm: 
 Provided
that whereby contract between the partners an option is given to surviving or
continuing partners to purchase the interest of a deceased or outgoing partner,
and that option is duly exercised, the estate of the deceased partner, or the
outgoing partner or his estate, as the case may be, is not entitled to any
further or other share of profits; but if any partner assuming to act in
exercise of the option does not in all material respects comply with the terms
thereof, he is liable to account under the foregoing provisions of this section.
 


  






  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>38</number>
Revocation of continuing guarantee by change in firm.—A
continuing guarantee given to a firm, or to a third party in respect of the
transactions of a firm, is, in the absence of agreement to the contrary, revoked
as to future transactions from the date of any change in the constitution of the
firm.
 




  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>39</number>
Dissolution of a firm.—The
dissolution of partnership between all the partners of a firm is called the
‘dissolution of the firm’.
 



  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>40</number>
Dissolution by agreement.—A
firm may be dissolved with the consent of all the partners or in accordance with
a contract between the partners.
 


  







  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>41</number>
Compulsory dissolution.—A
firm is dissolved,—
 


 <section><number>a</number>
by the adjudication of all the partners or of all the partners but one as
insolvent, or  
 

 </section><section><number>b</number>
by the happening of any event which makes it unlawful for the business of
the firm to be carried on or for the partners to carry it on in partnership: 
 

 Provided
that, where more than one separate adventure or undertaking is carried on by the
firm the illegality of one or more shall not of itself cause the dissolution of
the firm in respect of its lawful adventures and undertakings.
 


   



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>42</number>
Dissolution on the happening of certain contingencies.—Subject
to contract between the partners a firm is dissolved,—
 


 <section><number>a</number>
if constituted for a fixed term, by the expiry of that term; 
 

 </section><section><number>b</number>
if constituted to carry out one or more adventures or undertakings, by
the completion thereof; 
 

 </section><section><number>c</number>
by the death of a partner; and 
 

 </section><section><number>d</number>
by the adjudication of a partner as an insolvent. 
 

  








  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>43</number>
Dissolution by notice of partnership at will.—
<section><number>1</number>
Where the partnership is at will, the firm may be dissolved by any partner
giving notice in writing to all the other partners of his intention to dissolve
the firm.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The firm is dissolved as from the date mentioned in the notice as the date of
dissolution or, if no date is so mentioned, as from the date of the
communication of the notice.
 


  








  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>44</number>
Dissolution by the Court.—At
the suit of a partner, the Court may dissolve a firm on any of the following
grounds, namely:— 
 <section><number>a</number>
that a partner has become of unsound mind, in which case the suit may be
brought as well by the next friend of the partner who has become of unsound mind
as by any other partner; 
 

 </section><section><number>b</number>
that a partner, other than the partner suing, has become in any way
permanently incapable of performing his duties as partner; 
 

 </section><section><number>c</number>
that a partner, other than the partner suing, is guilty of conduct which
is likely to affect prejudicially the carrying on of the business, regard being
had to the nature of the business; 
 

 </section><section><number>d</number>
that a partner, other than the partner suing, wilfully or persistently
commits breach of agreements relating to the management of the affairs of the
firm or the conduct of its business, or otherwise so conducts himself in matters
relating to the business that it is not reasonably practicable for the other
partners to carry on the business in partnership with him; 
 

 </section><section><number>e</number>
that a partner, other than the partner suing, has in any way transferred
the whole of his interest in the firm to a third party, or has allowed his share
to be charged under the provisions of rule 49 of Order XXI of the First Schedule
to the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) or has allowed it to be sold in
the recovery of arrears of land revenue or of any dues recoverable as arrears of
land revenue due by the partner; 
 

 </section><section><number>f</number>
that the business of the firm cannot be carried on save at a loss; or 
 

 </section><section><number>g</number>
on any other ground which renders it just and equitable that the firm
should be dissolved. 
 

  











  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
  
 <article><number>45</number> Liability for acts of partners done after 
      dissolution.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding the dissolution of a firm, 
      the partners continue to be liable as such to third parties for any act 
      done by any of them which would have been an act of the firm if done 
      before the dissolution, until public notice is given of the 
      dissolution:
 Provided that the estate of a partner who dies, or who is 
      adjudicated an insolvent, or of a partner who, not having been known to 
      the person dealing with the firm to be a partner, retires from the firm, 
      is not liable under this section for acts done after the date on which he 
      ceases to be a partner.
 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notices under sub-section (1) may be given by any 
      partner.
  






  </section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>46</number>
Right of partners to have business wound up after dissolution.—On
the dissolution of a firm every partner or his representative is entitled, as
against all the other partners or their representatives, to have the property of
the firm applied in payment of the debts and liabilities of the firm, and to
have the surplus distributed among the partners or their representatives
according to their rights.
 


   



  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>47</number>
Continuing authority of partners for purposes of winding up.—After
the dissolution of a firm the authority of each partner to bind the firm, and
the other mutual rights and obligations of the partners continue notwithstanding
the dissolution, so far as may be necessary to wind up the affair of the firm
and to complete transactions begun but unfinished at the time of the
dissolution, but not otherwise:
 


 Provided
that the firm is in no case bound by the acts of a partner who has been
adjudicated insolvent; but this proviso does not affect the liability of any
person who has after the adjudication represented himself or knowingly permitted
himself to be represented as a partner of the insolvent.
 


   



  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>48</number>
Mode of settlement of accounts between partners.—In
settling the accounts of a firm after dissolution, the following rules shall,
subject to agreement by the partners, be observed:—
 


 <section><number>a</number>
losses, including deficiencies of capital, shall be paid first out of
profits, next out of capital, and, lastly, if necessary, by the partners
individually in the proportions in which they were entitled to share profits; 
 

 </section><section><number>b</number>
the assets of the firm, including any sums contributed by the partners to
make up deficiencies of capital, shall be applied in the following manner and
order:— 
 

 <subsection><number>i</number>
in paying the debts of the firm to third parties; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>
in paying to each partner rateably what is due to him from the firm for
advances as distinguished from capital;
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number>
in paying to each partner rateably what is due to him on account of
capital; and 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number>
the residue, if any, shall be divided among the partners in the
proportions in which they were entitled to share profits. 
 










  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>49</number>
Payment of firm debts and of separate debts.—Where
there are joint debts due from the firm, and also separate debts due from any
partner, the property of the firm shall be applied in the first instance in
payment of the debts of the firm, and, if there is any surplus, then the share
of each partner shall be applied in payment of his separate debts or paid to
him. The separate property of any partner shall be applied first in the payment
of his separate debts, and the surplus (if any) in the payment of the debts of
the firm.
 


   



  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>50</number>
Personal profits earned after dissolution.—Subject
to contract between the partners, the provisions of clause 
<section><number>a</number> of section 16
shall apply to transactions by any surviving partner or by the representatives
of a deceased partner, undertaken after the firm is dissolved on account of the
death of a partner and before its affairs have been completely wound up:
 


 Provided
that where any partner or his representative has brought the goodwill of the
firm, nothing in this section shall affect his right to use the firm name.
 


   



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>51</number>
Return of premium on premature dissolution.—Where
a partner has paid a premium on entering into partnership of a fixed term, and
the firm is dissolved before the expiration of that term otherwise than by the
death of a partner, he shall be entitled to repayment of the premium or of such
part thereof as may be reasonable, regard being had to the terms upon which he
became a partner and to the length of time during which he was partner,
unless,—
 


 <section><number>a</number>
the dissolution is mainly due to his own misconduct, or 
 

 </section><section><number>b</number>
the dissolution is in pursuance of an agreement containing no provision
for the return of the premium or any part of it.
  
   



  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
  
 <article><number>52</number> Rights where partnership contract is rescinded for fraud or 
      misrepresentation.—Where a contract creating partnership is 
      rescinded on the ground of the fraud or misrepresentation of any of the 
      parties thereto the party entitled to rescind is, without prejudice to any 
      other right, entitled,—
 
 <section><number>a</number> to a lien on, or a 
      right of retention of, the surplus or the assets of the firm remaining 
      after the debts of the firm have been paid, for any sum paid by him for 
      the purchase of a share in the firm and for any capital contributed by 
him;  
      
 </section><section><number>b</number> to rank as a creditor 
      of the firm in respect of any payment made by him towards the debts of the 
      firm; and  
 </section><section><number>c</number> to be indemnified by 
      the partner or partners guilty of the fraud or misrepresentation against 
      all the debts of the firm.  
      
   

  </section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>53</number>
Right to restrain from use of firm name or firm property.—After
a firm is dissolved, every partner or his representative may, in the absence of
a contract between the partners to the contrary, restrain any other partner or
his representative from carrying on a similar business in the firm name or from
using any of the property of the firm for his own benefit, until the affairs of
the firm have been completely wound up:
 Provided
that where any partner or his representative has bought the goodwill of the
firm, nothing in this section shall affect his right to use the firm name.
 


  





  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>54</number>
Agreements of restraint of trade.—Partners
may, upon or in anticipation of the dissolution of the firm, make an agreement
that some or all of them will not carry on a business similar to that of the
firm within a specified period or within specified local limits; and
notwithstanding anything contained in section 27 of the Indian Contract Act,
1872 (9 of 1872), such agreement shall be valid if the restrictions imposed are
reasonable.
 


   



  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>55</number>
Sale of goodwill after dissolution.—
<section><number>1</number>
In settling the accounts of a firm after dissolution, the goodwill shall,
subject to contract between the partners, be included in the assets, and it may
be sold either separately or along with other property of the firm.
 


 Rights
of buyer and seller of goodwill.—(2)
Where the goodwill of a firm is sold after dissolution, a partner may carry on a
business competing with that of the buyer and he may advertise such business,
but, subject to agreement between him and the buyer, he may not,—
 


 <subsection><number>a</number>
use the firm name, 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
represent himself as carrying on the business of the firm, or 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
solicit the custom of persons who were dealing with the firm before its
dissolution. 
 

 Agreements
in restraint of trade.—(3)
Any partner may, upon the sale of the goodwill of a firm, make an agreement with
the buyer that such partner will not carry on any business similar to that of
the firm within a specified period or within specified local limits and,
notwithstanding anything contained in section 27 of the Indian Contract Act,
1872 (9 of 1872), such agreement shall be valid if the restrictions imposed are
reasonable.
  






  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>56</number>
Power to exempt from application of this Chapter.—The
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[State
Government of any State] may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct
that the provisions of this Chapter shall not apply to <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[that
State] or to any part thereof specified in the notification. 


   








  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>57</number>
Appointment of Registrars.—
<section><number>1</number>
The State Government may appoint Registrars of Firms for the purposes of this
Act, and may define the areas within which they shall exercise their powers and
perform their duties.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Every Registrar shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of
section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).
  
 
State
Amendments
 <subsection>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—For
section 57, substitute the following section, namely,—
 
          “57. Appointment of
Registrar of Firms and Deputy Assistant Registrars of 
Firms.—(1) The State Government may, by notification in the Official
Gazette, appoint a Registrar of Firms who shall exercise, perform and discharge
the powers, functions and duties of the Registrar under this Act throughout the
State of Maharashtra.
 </subsection></section><section>
          <number>2</number> The State Government may
likewise appoint one or more Deputy Registrars of Firms and Assistant Registrars
of Firms who shall exercise, perform and discharge all or such of the powers,
functions and duties of the Registrar and in such areas as the State Government
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify.
 </section><section>
          <number>3</number> The officers appointed
under sub-section (1) and sub-section (2) shall be deemed to be public servants
within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code”.
 
[Vide
Maharashtra Act 29 of 1984, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-5-1985)].
 
Uttar
Pradesh.—For section 57, substitute the
following section, namely,—
 
          “57. Appointment of
Registrar, Deputy Registrars and Assistant Registrars.—(1) The
State Government may, by notification, appoint a Registrar of Firms who
shall exercise, perform and discharge the powers, functions and duties of the
Registrar under this Act throughout the State of Uttar Pradesh.
 </section><section>
          <number>2</number> The State Government may
likewise appoint one or more Deputy Registrars of Firms and Assistant Registrars
of Firms who shall exercise, perform and discharge all or such of the powers,
functions and duties of the Registrar and in such areas as are notified in the
notification.
 </section><section>
          <number>3</number> The officers appointed
under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) shall be deemed to be public servants
within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).”
 
[Vide
Uttar Pradesh Act 34 of 1979, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 22-10-1979)].

  


</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><number>58</number> Application for 
registration.—
<section><number>1</number> The registration of 
a firm may be effected at any time by sending by post or delivering to the 
Registrar of the area in which any place of business of the firm is situated or 
proposed to be situated, a statement in the prescribed form and accompanied by 
the prescribed fee, stating,—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  the firm name,
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  the place or principal place of business of the 
firm,
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  the names of any other places where the firm 
carries on business,
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  the date when each partner joined the firm,
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number>  the names in full and permanent addresses of the 
partners, and
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>f</number>  the duration of the firm.
 The statement shall be signed by 
all the partners, or by their agents specially authorised in this behalf.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Each person signing the 
statement shall also verify it in the manner prescribed.
 </section><section><number>3</number> A firm name shall not contain 
any of the following words, namely:—
               “Crown”, “Emperor”, “Empress”, “Empire”, 
“Imperial”, “King”, “Queen”, “Royal”, or words expressing or implying the 
sanction, approval or patronage of
1[Government], 
except 2[when 
the State Government] signifies 
3[its] consent to the use of such words as part of the firm name by order 
in writing 4[***].
  
 STATE AMENDMENTS
 
Goa, Daman and Diu.—In 
section 58,—
 <subsection>
         <number>i</number>  for sub-section (3), substitute the 
following sub-section, namely:—
 
            “(3) No firm shall be registered by a 
name which in the opinion of the Registrar is undesirable”.
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  after sub-section (3), insert the 
following sub-sections:—
 
            “(4) Any person aggrieved by an order 
of the Registrar under sub-section (3) may, within 30 days from the date of 
communication of such order, appeal to the State Government whose decision shall 
be final.
 </subsection></section><section>
             <number>5</number> A firm’s name shall not contain 
any of the following words, namely, Union, State, President, Republic, Governor 
or words expressing or implying sanction, approval or patronage of Government 
unless the Government of Goa, Daman and Diu signifies, by order in writing, its 
consent to the use of such words as part of the firm’s name:
 
                      Provided that nothing in 
this sub-section shall apply to any firm carrying on business under any such 
name, before the date of the commencement of the Indian Partnership (Goa, Daman 
and Diu Amendment) Act, 1966.
 </section><section>
             <number>6</number> Any person who contravenes the 
provisions of sub-section (5) shall be punishable with fine which may extend to 
five hundred rupees”.
 
[Vide Goa, Daman and Diu Act 6 of 1966, 
sec. 3 (w.e.f. 22-8-1966)].
 <subsection>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—In 
section 58,—
 <subsubsection>
        <number>a</number>  in sub-section (1),
 <subsubsubsection>
              <number>i</number> for the words “The registration 
of a firm”, substitute the words, brackets, figure and letter “Subject to the 
provisions of sub-section (1A), the registration of a firm”;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
             <number>ii</number> Omit the words “at any time”;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
            <number>iii</number> after the words “prescribed 
fee”, insert the words “and a true copy of the deed of partnership”;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
            <number>iv</number> after clause (a), insert the 
following clause, namely:—
 
                  “(aa) the nature of business of 
the firm;”;
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection><subsubsection>
        <number>b</number>  after sub-section (1), insert the 
following sub-section, namely:—
 
                    “(1A) The statement under 
sub-section (1) shall be sent or delivered to the Registrar within a period of 
one year from the date of constitution of the firm:
 
                    Provided that in the case of 
any firm carrying on business on or before the date of commencement of the 
Indian Partnership (Maharashtra Amendment) Act, 1984 (Maharashtra Act 29 of 
1984), such statement shall be sent or delivered to the Registrar within a 
period of one year from such date.”;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        <number>c</number>  for sub-section (3), substitute the 
following sub-sections, namely:—
 
                    “(3) A firm shall not have any 
of the names or emblems specified in the Schedule to the Emblems and Names 
(Prevention of Improper Use) Act, 1950 (12 of 1950), or any colourable imitation 
thereof, unless permitted so to do under that Act, or any name which is likely 
to be associated by the public with the name of any other firm on account of 
similarity, or any name which, in the opinion of the Registrar for reasons to be 
recorded in writing, is undesirable:
 
                    Provided that nothing in this 
sub-section shall apply to any firm registered under any such name before the 
date of the commencement of the Indian Partnership (Maharashtra Amendment) Act, 
1984 (Maharashtra Act 29 of 1984).
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
                    <number>4</number> Any person aggrieved by an 
order of the Registrar under sub-section (3) may, within 30 days from the date 
of communication of such order, appeal to the officer not below the rank of 
Deputy Secretary to Government authorised by the State Government in this 
behalf, in such manner, and on payment of such fee, as may be prescribed. On 
receipt of any such appeal, the authorised officer shall, after giving an 
opportunity of being heard to the appellant decide the appeal, and his decision 
shall be final”.­
 
[Vide Maharashtra Act 29 of 1984, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 
1-1-1985)].
 <subsection>
<number>Pondicherry</number>—In 
section 58, for sub-section (3), substitute the following sub-sections, namely:—
 
         “(3) The Registrar shall refuse to 
register—
 <subsubsection>
             <number>a</number> a firm under sub-section (1) or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>b</number> an alteration of the firm name,
 
         if the proposed name or alteration of the 
firm name is identical with the name of which any other existing firm has been 
registered or in the opinion of the Registrar so nearly resembles such other 
name as to be likely to deceive or mislead the public or the members of either 
firm.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
             <number>4</number> Any person who is aggrieved by an 
order of Registrar under sub-section (3) may file an appeal before such person 
or authority, in such manner, within such time and on payment of such fees as 
may be prescribed. The appeal shall be heard and decided in such manner as may 
be prescribed.”
 
[Vide Pondicherry Act 8 of 1969, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 
1-1-1970)].
 <subsection>
<number>Rajasthan</number>—In 
section 58, for sub-section (3), substitute the following sub-sections, namely:—
 
             “(3) No firm shall be registered by a 
name which, in the opinion of the State Government, is undesirable.
 </subsection></section><section>
             <number>4</number> Except with the previous 
sanction, in writing, of the State Government, no firm shall be registered by a 
name which contains any of the following words, namely:—
 <subsection>
             <number>a</number> ‘Union’, ‘State’, ‘President’, 
‘Republic’ or any word expressing or implying the sanction, approval or 
patronage of the Central or any State Government; and
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>b</number> ‘Municipal’, ‘Chartered’ or any 
word which suggests or is calculated to suggest connection with any municipality 
or local authority:
 
             Provided that nothing in this 
sub-section shall apply to any firm registered before the date of commencement 
of the Indian Partnership (Rajasthan Amendment) Act, 1971.”
 
[Vide Rajasthan Act 10 of 1971, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 
15-9-1971)].
 
Tamil Nadu.—Same 
as in Rajasthan, except that in the proviso to sub-section (4), for the words 
“Indian Partnership (Rajasthan Amendment) Act, 1971” substitute the words 
“Indian Partnership (Madras Amendment) Act, 1965”.
 
[Vide Tamil Nadu Act 35 of 1965, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 
1-4-1966)].
  










</subsection></section></article> 

  
  
 <article><number>59</number> Registration.—When 
the Registrar is satisfied that the provisions of section 58 have been duly 
complied with, he shall record an entry of the statement in a register called 
the Register of Firms, and shall file the statement1.
 STATE AMENDMENTS
 <section><number>Maharashtra</number>—Renumber 
section 59 as sub-section (1) of that section, and,—
 <subsection>        <number>a</number>  in sub-section 
(1) as so renumbered, after the words “file the statement”, insert the words “on 
the date such entry is recorded and such statement is filed, the firm shall be 
deemed to be registered,”;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>b</number>  after 
sub-section (1) as so renumbered, insert the following sub-section, namely:—
                     “(2) The 
firm, which is registered, shall use the brackets and word “(Registered)” 
immediately after its name”.
 [Vide Maharashtra Act 29 
of 1984, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 1-1-1985)].
 Section 59A
 Andhra Pradesh.—After 
section 59, insert the following section, namely:—
              “59A. Amendment 
of the Register of Firms.—(1) Notwithstanding anything in this Chapter, the 
Registrar of Firms, Andhra Pradesh, may, by order in writing, amend the register 
by deleting therefrom the entries relating to any firm, whose place of business 
has, by virtue of the provisions contained in the States Reorganisation Act, 
1956 and the Andhra Pradesh and Madras (Alteration of Boundaries) Act, 1959, 
ceased to be in the Andhra Pradesh; the Registrar may likewise amend the 
register by adding thereto the entries relating to any firm included in the 
register of another State but, whose place of business has, by reason of the 
said provisions, become included in the State of Andhra Pradesh:
                     Provided 
that the Registrar shall, before passing an order under this sub-section, give 
to the firm concerned an opportunity of making its representation, if any.
 <subsubsection>             <number>2</number> The Registrar 
shall cease to perform the functions of a Registrar under the Act in respect of 
any firm the entries relating to which are deleted as aforesaid and shall 
perform the functions of a Registrar under the Act in respect of any firm the 
entries relating to which are added as aforesaid.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>             <number>3</number> Any person 
aggrieved by an order under sub-section (1) may appeal to such authority and 
within such time as may be specified in this behalf by an order made by the 
Government of the Andhra Pradesh, and such Authority shall pass such order on 
the appeal as it thinks fit.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>             <number>4</number> An order of the 
Registrar under sub-section (1), or where an appeal has been preferred against 
it under sub-section (3), the order of the appellate authority, shall be final.”
 [Vide Andhra Pradesh Act 
7 of 1965, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 10-3-1965)].
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section><number>Kerala</number>—After 
section 59, insert the following section, namely:—
              “59A. Amendment 
of Register.—(1) Notwithstanding anything contained in this Chapter, the 
Registrar of Firms appointed by the State of Kerala may, by order in writing, 
amend the register by deleting therefrom the entries relating to any firm whose 
place of business has, by reason of the reorganisation of States, ceased to be 
situated in the State of Kerala.
              The Registrar may 
likewise amend the register by adding thereto the entries relating to any firm 
included in the register of the State of Madras but whose place of business has, 
by reason of the said reorganisation of States, become part of the State of 
Kerala:
              Provided that the 
Registrar shall, before passing an order, make such inquiry as he deems 
necessary.
 <subsection>             <number>2</number> After such 
amendment the Registrar shall cease to perform the functions of a Registrar in 
respect of any firm the entries relating to which have been deleted as aforesaid 
and shall perform all the functions of a Registrar in respect of all firms the 
entries relating to which are added as aforesaid.
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>3</number> Any person 
aggrieved by an order under sub-section (1) may appeal to such authority and 
within such time as may be specified in this behalf by the State Government of 
Kerala, and such authority shall pass such order on the appeal as it thinks fit.
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>4</number> An order of the 
Registrar under sub-section (1), or where an appeal has been preferred against 
it under sub-section (3), the order of the appellate authority, shall be final.
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>5</number> The provisions 
of this section shall cease to be in force from such date as the State 
Government of Kerala may, by notification in the Gazette, appoint.”
 [Vide Kerala Adaptation 
of Laws (No. 2) Order, 1957 (w.e.f. 30-10-1957)].
 Madhya Pradesh.—After 
section 59, insert the following section, namely:—
              “59A. (1) 
Notwithstanding anything contained in this Chapter, the Registrar of Firms 
appointed by the State of Madhya Pradesh may, by order in writing, amend the 
register by deleting therefrom the entries relating to any firm, whose place of 
business has, by reason of the reorganisation of States, ceased to be situated 
in the State of Madhya Pradesh.
              The Registrar may 
likewise amend the register by adding thereto the entries relating to any firm 
included in the register of another State but whose place of business has, by 
reason of the said reorganisation of States, become part of the State of Madhya 
Pradesh:
              Provided that the 
Registrar shall, before passing an order, make such inquiry as he deems 
necessary.
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>2</number> After such 
amendment the Registrar shall cease to perform the functions of a Registrar in 
respect of any firm the entries relating to which have been deleted as aforesaid 
and shall perform all the functions of a Registrar in respect of all firms the 
entries relating to which are added as aforesaid.
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>3</number> Any person 
aggrieved by an order under sub-section (1) may appeal to such authority and 
within such time as may be specified in this behalf by the State Government of 
Madhya Pradesh, and such authority shall pass such order on the appeal as it 
thinks fit.
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>4</number> An order of the 
Registrar under sub-section (1), or where an appeal has been preferred against 
it under sub-section (3), the order of the appellate authority shall be final.
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>5</number> The provisions 
of this section shall cease to be in force from such date as the State 
Government of Madhya Pradesh may, by notification in the State Gazette, 
appoint.”
 [Vide Madhya Pradesh 
Adaptation of Laws (State and Concurrent Subjects) (Third Amendment) Order, 1957 
(w.r.e.f. 1-11-1956)].
 </subsection></section><section><number>Maharashtra</number>—(i) 
After section 59, insert the following section, namely:—
              “59A. Deletion 
and addition of entries relating to certain firms, by reason of reorganisation 
of States.—(1) Notwithstanding anything contained in this Chapter, a 
Registrar of Firms appointed for any area by the Government of Bombay may, by 
order in writing, amend the Register of Firms maintained by him by deleting 
therefrom the entries relating to any firm, whose place of business has, by 
reason of the reorganisation of States under the States Reorganisation Act, 
1956, ceased to be situated in the State of Bombay. The Registrar may likewise 
and without any charge or fee therefor amend the Register by adding thereto the 
entries relating to any firm included in the Register of another State but whose 
place of business has, by reason for such reorganisation, become part of the 
area within his jurisdiction in the State of Bombay:
              Provided that the 
Registrar shall, before passing any order under this sub-section, make such 
inquiry as he deems necessary and give notice to the firm and the Registrar of 
the State concerned.
 <subsection>             <number>2</number> After such 
amendment, the Registrar shall cease to perform the functions of a Registrar in 
respect of any firm the entries relating to which have been deleted as aforesaid 
and shall perform the functions of a Registrar in respect of any firm the 
entries relating to which are added as aforesaid.
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>3</number> Any person 
aggrieved by an order under sub-section (1) may appeal to such authority, and 
within such time, as may be specified in this behalf by the Government of Bombay 
by notification in the Official Gazette; and such authority shall pass such 
order on the appeal as it thinks fit.
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>4</number> An order of a 
Registrar under sub-section (1), or when an appeal has been preferred against it 
under sub-section (3), the order of the appellate authority shall be final.
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>5</number> The provisions 
of this section shall cease to be in force from such date as the Government of 
Bombay may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.”
 [Vide Central Acts on 
State and Concurrent Subjects (Bombay Adaptation) (Amendment) Order, 1957 (w.e.f. 
17-10-1957)].
 Section 59A1.
 <subsubsection><number>ii</number> After section 59, insert 
the following section, namely:—
              “59A1. Late 
registration on payment of penalty.—If the statement in respect of any firm 
is not sent or delivered to the Registrar within the time specified in 
sub-section (1A) of section 58, then the firm may be registered on payment, to 
the Registrar, of a penalty of one hundred rupees per year of delay or a part 
thereof.”
 [Vide Maharashtra Act 29 
of 1984, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-1-1985)].
 Mysore (Karnataka).—In 
section 59A, in sub-section (1), for the words “by reason of the reorganisation 
of States”, the words, brackets, etc., “by reason of the addition of the Bellary 
district to the State of Mysore under the Andhra Pradesh State Act, 1953 
(Central Act 30 of 1953), or of the reorganisation of States under the States 
Reorganisation Act, 1956 (Central Act 37 of 1956)” shall be substituted.
 [Vide Mysore Act 19 of 
1961, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 14-9-1961)].
 Note.—This 
amendment relates to section 59A as introduced by Madras Adaptation of Laws 
(Central Acts) Order, 1957.
 Tamil Nadu.—After 
section 59, insert the following section, namely:—
              “59A. Special 
provision for amending the register.—(1) Notwithstanding anything contained 
in this Chapter, the Registrar of Firms appointed by the State Government of 
Madras may, by order in writing, amend the register by deleting therefrom the 
entries relating to any firm, the place of business of which has, by reason of 
the formation of the State of Andhra or of the addition of the Bellary district 
to the State of Mysore under the Andhra State Act, 1953 or of the reorganisation 
of States under the States Reorganisation Act, 1956, or of the alteration of 
boundaries under the Andhra Pradesh and Madras (Alteration of Boundaries) Act, 
1959, ceased to be located in the State of Madras.
              The Registrar may 
likewise amend the register by adding thereto the entries relating to any firm 
included in the register of another State but the place of business of which 
has, by reason of the said reorganisation of States or of the said alteration of 
boundaries, become part of the State of Madras:
              Provided that the 
Registrar may, before passing an order, make such inquiry as he deems necessary.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>             <number>2</number> After such 
amendment the Registrar shall cease to perform the functions of the Registrar in 
respect of any firm the entries relating to which have been deleted as aforesaid 
and shall perform all the functions of a Registrar in respect of all firms the 
entries relating to which are added as aforesaid.
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>3</number> Any person 
aggrieved by an order under sub-section (1) may appeal to such authority and 
within such time as may be specified in this behalf by the State Government of 
Madras, and such authority shall pass such order on the appeal as it thinks fit.
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>4</number> An order of the 
Registrar under sub-section (1), or where an appeal has been preferred against 
it under sub-section (3), the order of the appellate authority shall be final.
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>5</number> The provisions 
of this section shall cease to be in force from such date as the State 
Government of Madras may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.”
 [Vide Tamil Nadu (Added
Territories) Adaptation of Laws Order, 
1961 (w.r.e.f. 1-4-1960)].
 Section 59B
 </subsection></section><section><number>Gujarat</number>—After 
section 59A, insert the following section, namely:—
              “59B. Deletion 
of entries relating to certain firms by reason of reorganisation of Bombay 
State.—(1) Notwithstanding anything contained in this Chapter, a Registrar 
of Firms appointed for any area by the Government of Gujarat may, by order in 
writing, amend the Register of Firms maintained by him by deleting therefrom the 
entries relating to any firm whose place of business has, by reason of the 
reorganisation of the State of Bombay, by the Bombay Reorganisation Act, 1960, 
ceased to be situated in the State of Gujarat:
              Provided that the 
Registrar shall, before passing any order under this sub-section, make such 
inquiry as he deems necessary and give notice to the firm and the Registrar of 
the State of Maharashtra.
 <subsection>             <number>2</number> After such 
amendment the Registrar shall cease to perform the functions of a Registrar in 
respect of any firm the entries relating to which have been deleted as 
aforesaid.
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>3</number> Any person 
aggrieved by an order under sub-section (1) may appeal to such authority and 
within such time as may be specified in this behalf by the Government of 
Gujarat, by notification in the Official Gazette; and such authority shall pass 
such order on the appeal as it thinks fit.
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>4</number> An order of a 
Registrar under sub-section (1), or where an appeal has been preferred against 
it under sub-section (3), the order of the appellate authority shall be final.”
 [Vide Gujarat Adaptation 
of Laws (State and Concurrent Subjects) (Eighth Amendment) Order, 1961 (w.r.e.f. 
1-5-1960)].
 </subsection></section><section><number>Maharashtra</number>—After 
section 59A, insert the following section, namely:—
              “59B.—Same as in 
Gujarat, except that—
 <subsection>              <number>i</number> in the 
marginal note, for the words “re-organisation of Bombay
State”, substitute the words ‘formation of 
State of Gujarat’;
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>ii</number> in 
sub-sections (1) and (3), for the word “Gujarat”, substitue the word  “Maharashtra”, 
and in the proviso, for the word “Maharashtra”, 
substitute the word “Gujarat”;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>iii</number> in 
sub-section (1), for the words “by reason of re-organisation of the State of 
Bombay”, substitute the words “by reason of the formation of the State of 
Gujarat”.
 [Vide Central Acts on 
State and Concurrent Subjects (Maharashtra Adaptation) (Amendment) Order, 1961 (w.r.e.f. 
1-5-1960)].
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>60</number>
Recording of alterations in firm name and principal place of business.—
<section><number>1</number>
When an alteration is made in the firm name or in the location of the principal
place of business of a registered firm, a statement may be sent to the Registrar
accompanied by the prescribed fee, specifying the alteration and signed and
verified in the manner required under section 58.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
When the Registrar is satisfied that the provisions of sub-section (1) have been
duly complied with, he shall amend the entry relating to the firm in the
Register of Firms in accordance with the statement, and shall file it along with
the statement relating to the firm filed under section 59.
 


  
 
State
Amendment
 <subsection>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—In
section 60,—
 <subsubsection>

<number>a</number>
for sub-section (1), substitute the following sub-section, namely:—
 
      “(1) When an alteration is
made in the firm name or in the nature of business of a firm or in the location
of the principal place of business of a registered firm, a statement shall be
sent to the Registrar, within a period of 90 days from the date of making such
alteration, accompanied by the prescribed fee, specifying the alteration and
signed and verified in the manner required under section 58.”
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
      <number>b</number>
in the marginal note, for the words “firm name and”, substitute the
words “firm name, nature of business and”.
 
[Vide
Maharashtra Act 29 of 1984, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 1-1-1985)].
 
  



  


</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>61</number>
Noting of closing and opening of branches.—When
a registered firm discontinued business at any place or begins to carry on
business at any place, such place not being its principal place of business, any
partner or agent of the firm may send intimation thereof to the Registrar, who
shall make a note of such intimation in the entry relating to the firm in the
Register of Firms, and shall file the intimation along with the statement
relating to the firm filed under section 59.
 


  
 
State
Amendment
 <section>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—In
section 61, for the words “may send intimation thereof to the Registrar, who
shall”, substitute the following words, namely:—
 

“shall send intimation
thereof to the Registrar, within a period of 90 days from the date of such
discontinuance or, as the case may be, from the date on which the firm begins to
carry on business at such place. The Registrar shall then.”
 
[Vide
Maharashtra Act 29 of 1984, sec. 10 (w.e.f. 1-1-1985)].
  
 
  



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>62</number>
Noting of changes in names and addresses of partners.—When
any partner in a registered firm alters his name or permanent address, an
intimation of the alteration may be sent by any partner or agent of the firm to
the Registrar, who shall deal with it in the manner provided in section 61.
 


 
  



  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>63</number>
Recording of changes in and dissolution of a firm.—
<section><number>1</number>
When a change occurs in the constitution of a registered firm any incoming,
continuing or outgoing partner, and when a registered firm is dissolved any
person who was a partner immediately before the dissolution, or the agent of any
such partner or person specially authorised in this behalf, may give notice to
the Registrar of such change or dissolution, specifying the date thereof; and
the Registrar shall make a record of the notice in the entry relating to the
firm in the Register of Firms, and shall file the notice along with the
statement relating to the firm filed under section 59.
 


 Recording
of withdrawal of a minor.—(2)
When a minor who has been admitted to the benefits of partnership in a firm
attains majority and elects to become or not to become a partner, and the firm
is then a registered firm, he, or his agent specially authorised in this behalf,
may give notice to the Registrar that he has or has not become a partner, and
the Registrar shall deal with the notice in the manner provided in sub-section
(1).
 


  
 
State
Amendment
 <subsection>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—In
section 63,—
 <subsubsection>

<number>a</number>
in sub-section (1),—
 <subsubsubsection>

<number>i</number>
for the word “any”, wherever it occurs, substitute the word
“every”;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>

<number>ii</number>
for the words “may give notice to the Registrar of such change or
dissolution, specifying the date thereof”, substitute the following words,
namely:—
 

“shall, within a period of 90 days from the date of such change or
dissolution, give notice to the Registrar of such change or dissolution,
specifying the date thereof”;
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection><subsubsection>

<number>b</number>
after sub-section (1), insert the following sub-section, namely:—
 

“(1A) Where a change occurs in the constitution of a registered firm,
all persons, who after such change are partners of the firm, shall jointly send
an intimation of such change duly signed by them, to the Registrar, within a
period of 90 days from the date of occurrence of such change and the Registrar
shall deal with it in the manner provided by section 61”;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

<number>c</number>
in sub-section (2), for the words “may give notice to the Registrar”,
substitute the words “shall, within a period of 90 days from the date of his
election, give notice to the Registrar”.
 
[Vide
Maharashtra Act 29 of 1984, sec. 12 (w.e.f. 1-1-1985)].
  







  


</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>64</number>
Rectification of mistakes.—
<section><number>1</number>
The Registrar shall have power at all times to rectify any mistake in order to
bring the entry in the Register of Firms relating to any firm into conformity
with the documents relating to that firm filed under this Chapter.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
On application made by all the parties who have signed any document relating to
a firm filed under this Chapter, the Registrar may rectify any mistake in such
document or in the record or note thereof made in the Register of Firms.
 


 
  



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>65</number>
Amendment of Register by order of Court.—A
Court deciding any matter relating to a registered firm may direct that the
Registrar shall make any amendment in the entry in the Register of Firms
relating to such firm which is consequential upon its decision; and the
Registrar shall amend the entry accordingly.
 


 
  



  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>66</number>
Inspection of Register and filed documents.—
<section><number>1</number>
The Register of Firms shall be open to inspection by any person on payment of
such fee as may be prescribed.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
All statements, notices and intimations filed under this Chapter shall be open
to inspection, subject to such conditions and on payment of such fee as may be
prescribed.
 


 
  



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>67</number>
Grant of copies.—The
Registrar shall on application furnish to any person, on payment of such fee as
may be prescribed, a copy, certified under his hand, of any entry or portion
thereof in the Register of Firms.
 


 
  



  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>68</number>
Rules of evidence.—
<section><number>1</number>
Any statement, intimation or notice recorded or noted in the Register of Firms
shall, as against any person by whom or on whose behalf such statement,
intimation or notice was signed, be conclusive proof of any fact therein stated.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
A certified copy of an entry relating to a firm in the Register of Firms may be
produced in proof of the fact of the registration of such firm, and of the
contents of any statement, intimation or notice recorded or noted therein.
 


 
  



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 

 <article><number>69</number>
Effect of non-registration.—
<section><number>1</number>
No suit to enforce a right arising from a contract or conferred by this Act
shall be instituted in any court by or on behalf of any person suing as a
partner in a firm against the firm or any person alleged to be or to have been a
partner in the firm unless the firm is registered and the person suing is or has
been shown in the Register of Firms as a partner in the firm.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
No suit to enforce a right arising from a contract shall be instituted in any
Court by or on behalf of a firm against any third party unless the firm is
registered and the persons suing are or have been shown in the Register of Firms
as partners in the firm.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
The provisions of sub-sections (1) and (2) shall apply also to a claim of
set-off or other proceeding to enforce a right arising from a contract, but
shall not affect,— 
 <subsection><number>a</number>
the enforcement of any right to sue for the dissolution of a firm or for
accounts of a dissolved firm, or any right or power to realise the property of a
dissolved firm, or
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
the powers of an official assignee, receiver or Court under the
Presidency-towns Insolvency Act, 1909 (3 of 1909) or the Provincial Insolvency
Act, 1920 (5 of 1920) to realise the property of an insolvent partner.
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number>
This section shall not apply,—
 


 <subsection>
 <number>a</number>
to firms or to partners in firms which have no place of business in <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[the
territories to which this Act extends], or whose places of business in <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[the
said territories], are situated in areas to which, by notification under <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[section
56], this Chapter does not apply, or
 </subsection><subsection>
 <number>b</number>
to any suit or claim of set-off not exceeding one hundred rupees in value
which, in the Presidency-towns, is not of a kind specified in section 19 of the
Presidency Small Cause Courts Act, 1882 (5 of 1882), or, outside the
Presidency-towns, is not of a kind specified in the Second Schedule to the
Provincial Small Cause Courts Act, 1887 (9 of 1887), or to any proceeding in
execution or other proceeding incidental to or arising from any such suit or
claim. 
  
 

State
Amendments
 <subsubsection>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—(1)
In section 69,—
 <subsubsubsection>

<number>a</number>
in sub-section (1), insert the following proviso, namely:—
 

“Provided that the requirement of registration of firm under this
sub-section shall not apply to the suits or proceedings instituted by the heirs
or legal representatives of the deceased partner of a firm for accounts of the
firm or to realise the property of the firm.”;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>

<number>b</number>
after sub-section (2), insert the following sub-section, namely:—
 

“(2A) No suit to enforce any right for the dissolution of a firm or for
accounts of a dissolved firm or any right or power to realise the property of a
dissolved firm shall be instituted in any court by or on behalf of any person
suing as a partner in a firm against the firm or any person alleged to be or to
have been a partner in the firm, unless the firm is registered and the person
suing is or has been shown in the Register of Firms as a partner in the firm:
 

Provided that the requirement of
registration of firm under this sub-section shall not apply to the suits or
proceedings instituted by the heirs or legal representatives of the deceased
partner of a firm for accounts of a dissolved firm or to realise the property of
a dissolved firm.”;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>

<number>c</number>
in sub-section (3),—
 

(i) for the words, brackets and figures “sub-sections (1)
and (2)”, substitute the words, brackets, figures and letter “sub-sections
(1), (2) and (2A)”;
 

(ii) for clause (a), substitute the following clause,
namely:—
 

“(a) the firms constituted for a duration
up to six months or with a capital up to two thousand rupees; or.”
 
[Vide
Maharashtra Act 29 of 1984, sec. 13 (w.e.f. 1-1-1985)].
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number>
After section 69, insert the following section, namely:—
 

“69A. Penalty for
contravention of section 60, 61, 62 or 63.—If any statement, intimation or
notice under section 60, 61, 62 or 63 in respect of any registered firm is not
sent or given to the Registrar, within the period specified in that section, the
Registrar may, after giving notice to the partners of the firm and after giving
them a reasonable opportunity of being heard, refuse to make the suitable
amendments in the records relating to the firm, until the partners of the firm
pay such penalty, not exceeding ten rupees per day, as the Registrar may
determine in respect of the period between the date of expiry of the period
specified in sections 60, 61, 62 or as the case may be 63 and the date of making
the amendments in the entries relating to the firm.”
 
[Vide
Maharashtra Act 29 of 1984, sec. 14 (w.e.f. 1-1-1985)].
  


























  


</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>70</number>
Penalty for furnishing false particulars.—Any
person who signs any statement, amending statement, notice or intimation under
this Chapter containing any particular which he knows to be false or does not
believe to be true, or containing particulars which he knows to be incomplete or
does not believe to be complete, shall be punishable with imprisonment which may
extend to three months, or with fine, or with both.
 


 State
Amendment 


 <section><number>Maharashtra</number>—(1) In
section 70, for the words “shall be punishable with imprisonment which may
extend to three months, or with fine, or with both”, substitute
the following words, namely:— 


 
“shall, on conviction, be punished
with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or with fine, or with
both: 


 

Provided that in the absence of special and adequate reasons to the
contrary to be mentioned in the judgment of the Court, the fine shall not be
less than one thousand rupees.” 


 [Vide Maharashtra Act 29
of 1984, sec. 15 (w.e.f. 1-1-1985)]. 


 <subsection><number>2</number> After section 70, insert the
following section, namely:— 


 
“70A. Maximum fees and power to
amend Schedule I.—(1) The fees payable under this Act and the rules made
thereunder shall not exceed the maximum fees as specified in Schedule I. 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>2</number> Subject to the provisions of
this section, the State Government may, having regard to the expenditure
incurred or to be incurred for carrying out the purposes of this Act, from time
to time, by notification in the Official Gazette, vary any of the amounts of
maximum fees and other particulars specified in Schedule I, and, thereupon, the
said Schedule shall be deemed to be amended accordingly. 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>3</number> Every notification issued under
sub-section (2) shall take effect from the date of its publication in the
Official Gazette, unless some other date is specified therein for this purpose. 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>4</number> Every notification issued by the
State Government under sub-section (2) shall be laid, as soon as may be after it
is issued, before each House of the State Legislature, while it is in session,
for a total period of thirty days, which may be comprised in one session or in
two successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session in which it is
so laid or the session immediately following, both Houses agree in making any
modification in the notification or both Houses agree that the notification
should not be issued, and notify such decision in the Official Gazette, the
notification shall, from the date of publication of such decision, have effect
only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however,
that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the
validity of anything previously done or omitted to be done in pursuance of that
notification.” 


 
[Vide Maharashtra Act 29 of 1984,
sec. 16 (w.e.f. 1-1-1985)].
</subsection></section></article> 

  


   


 <article><number>71</number>
Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number>
The <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[State
Government] <footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[may
by notification in the Official Gazette make rules] describing the fees which
shall accompany documents sent to the Registrar of Firms, or which shall be
payable for the inspection of documents in the custody of the Registrar of
Firms, or for copies from the Register of Firms:
 


 Provided
that such fees shall not exceed the maximum fees specified in Schedule I.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The State Government may <footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[also]
make rules,—
 


 <subsection>
<number>a</number> prescribing
the form of statement submitted under section 58, and of the verification
thereof; 
 

 </subsection><subsection> 
<number>b</number> requiring statements, intimations and
notices under sections 60, 61, 62 and 63 to be in prescribed
        form, and prescribing the form
thereof; 
 

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> prescribing
the form of the Register of Firms, and the mode in which entries relating to
firms are to       be made therein, and the mode in
which such entries are to be amended or notes made therein; 
 

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>
regulating the procedure of the Registrar when disputes arise; 
 

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>
regulating the filing of documents received by the Registrar; 
 

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>
prescribing conditions for the inspection of original documents; 
 

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>
regulating the grant of copies; 
 

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>
regulating the elimination of registers and documents; 
 

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>
providing for the maintenance and form of an index to the Register of
Firms; and 
 

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>
generally, to carry out the purposes of this Chapter. 
 

 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number>
All rules made under this section shall be subject to the condition of previous
publication.
 


 </section><section>[<number>4</number>
Every rule made by the State Government under this section shall be laid, as
soon as it is made, before the State Legislature.]
 


 State
Amendments
 Andhra Pradesh.—In
section 71, in sub-section (1), after the proviso, insert the following proviso,
namely:—
 

“Provided further that the fees payable under this Act, shall be
collected in the form of Court-fee stamps which shall be affixed to the
documents sent to the Registrar of Firms.”
 [Vide Andhra Pradesh Act
27 of 1994, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 22-12-1994)].
 <subsection><number>Maharashtra</number>—In section
71,—
 <subsubsection>
<number>a</number>
for sub-section (1), substitute the following sub-section, namely:—
 
“(1) Subject to the provisions of
section 70A, the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette,
make rules prescribing the fees which shall accompany documents sent to the
Registrar or which shall be paid in respect of any intimation, notice or
application given to the Registrar or which shall be payable for the inspection
of documents in the custody of the Registrar or for copies from the Register of
Firms or which shall be paid for supply of any prescribed forms.”;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>b</number>
in sub-section (2),—
 <subsubsubsection>
<number>i</number>
in clause (a), for the words and figures “under section 58”,
substitute the words, brackets and figures “under sub-section (1) of section
58”;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
<number>ii</number>
after clause (a), insert the following clause, namely:—
 

“(aa) prescribing the manner of filing an appeal under sub-section (4)
of section 58;”
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>c</number>
for sub-section (4), substitute the following sub-section, namely:—
 
“(4) Every rule made under this
section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of
the State Legislature, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty
days, which may be comprised in one session or in two successive sessions, and
if, before the expiry of the session in which it is so laid or the session
immediately following, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule
or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, and notify such decision
in the Official Gazette, the rule shall, from the date of publication of such
decision, have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case
may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without
prejudice to the validity of anything previously done or omitted to be done in
pursuance of that rule.”
 [Vide Maharashtra Act 29
of 1984, sec. 17 (w.e.f. 1-1-1985)].
   






4.
Ins. by Act 20 of 1983, sec. 2 and Sch. (w.e.f. 15-3-1984).

</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 

   


   


   


 <article><number>72</number>
Mode of giving public notice.—A
public notice under this Act is given—
 


 <section>
<number>a</number>
where it relates to the retirement or expulsion of a partner from a
registered firm, or to the dissolution of a registered firm, or to the election
to become or not to become a partner in a registered firm by  
 
a person attaining majority who was admitted as a minor to the benefits of
partnership, by notice to Registrar of Firms under section 63, and by
publication in the Official Gazette and in at least one vernacular newspaper
circulating in the district where the firm to which it relate has its place or
principal place of business, and 
 

 </section><section><number>b</number>
in any other case, by publication in the Official Gazette and in at least
one vernacular newspaper circulating in the district where the firm to which it
relates has its place or principal place of business. 


 
 


</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>73</number>
Repeals.—[Rep.
by the Repealing Act, 1938 (1 of 1938), sec. 2 and Sch.].
 


</article> 

   


   


 <article><number>74</number>
Savings.—Nothing
in this Act or any repeal effected thereby shall affect or be deemed to
affect,—
 


 <section>
<number>a</number>
any right, title, interest, obligation or liability already acquired,
accrued or incurred before the commencement of this Act, or 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>b</number>
any legal proceeding or remedy in respect of any such right, title,
interest, obligation or liability, or anything done or suffered before the
commencement of this Act, or 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>c</number>
anything done or suffered before the commencement of this Act, or 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>d</number>
any enactment relating to partnership not expressly repealed by this Act,
or 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>e</number>
any rule of insolvency relating to partnership, or 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>f</number>
any rule of law not inconsistent with this Act. 
 
 


 State
Amendment 


 Goa,
Daman and Diu:.—Renumber section 74 as sub-section
(1) thereof and after sub-section (1) as so renumbered, insert the following
sub-section, namely:— 


 
“(2) Notwithstanding
anything contained in sub-section (1) and in any other law in force in the Union
territory of Goa, Daman and Diu, the provisions of sub-sections (1) and (2) of
section 69 shall apply to all suits instituted in the Union territory of Goa,
Daman and Diu after the 1st January, 1965, even if the cause of action with
respect to the said suits had arisen before that date.” 


 [Vide
Goa, Daman and Diu Act 6 of 1966, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 22-8-1966)]. 


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 
Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for sub-section (2).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> 
Subs. by Act 3 of 1951, sec. 3 and Sch., for “except Part B States”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> 
Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “Governor General in Council”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> 
Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “any Province”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> The words “the Crown or the Government of India or a 
Local Government”, have been successively adapted by the A.O. 1937, the A.O. 
1948 and the A.O. 1950 to read as above.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “when the Governor General 
in Council”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> In its application to the State of Madras, sec. 59A 
has been inserted by the Madras Added Territories (Adaptation of Laws) Order, 
1961.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> 
Subs. by Act 3 of 1951, sec. 3 and Sch., for “Part A States and Part C
States”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> 
Subs. by Act 3 of 1951, sec. 3 and Sch., for “such States”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> 
Subs. by Act 24 of 1934, sec. 2 and Sch. I, for section 55.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number> Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for
“Provincial Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number> Subs. by Act 20 of 1983,
sec. 2 and Sch., for “may make rules” (w.e.f. 15-3-1984).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>
Ins. by A.O. 1937.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>