<act><tid>838134</tid>
<title>THE COAL MINES (CONSERVATION AND DEVELOPMENT) 
ACT, <year>1974</year></title>

ACT NO. 28 OF <year>1974</year>
[ 26th August, <year>1974</year>.]

An Act to provide for the conservation of coal and development of coal 
mines and for matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- fifth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I 
PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1816005</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1425078</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Coal Mines (Conservation and Development) Act, <year>1974</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>273142</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India. 
 (3) It shall come into force on such day as the Central 
Government may, by notification, appoint in this behalf.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1916696</tid>
<number>2</number>Declaration as to expediency of control by Central 
Government. It is hereby declared that it is expedient in the public 
interest that the Central Government should take under its control the 
regulation and development of coal mines to the extent hereinafter 
provided.


</article>



<article><tid>1537429</tid>
<number> 3</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>536943</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means the day on which this Act comes 
into force;

</section>

<section><tid>1808359</tid>
<number>b</number>" blending" means the process of intimately mixing 
different varieties of coal so as to provide a mixture which 
on carbonisation results in coke;

</section>

<section><tid>1318551</tid>
<number>c</number>" coal" includes coke in all its forms but does not 
include lignite;

</section>

<section><tid>815432</tid>
<number>d</number>" Chief Inspector" and" Inspector" mean the persons 
respectively appointed as the Chief Inspector of Mines and 
Inspec-

<pagefootnote><pagenum>124</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>999999</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 1st April, <year>1975</year>, See Notification No. G. S. R 164 (E), dated the 26th 
March, <year>1975</year>, Gazette of India, Extraordinary, <year>1975</year>, Pt. II, Sec. 3 
 (i) p. 651.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

tor of Mines under the Mines Act, <year>1952</year>, and the provisions 
of that Act shall apply to the Chief Inspector and to all 
Inspectors while exercising their powers under the Act or the 
rules made thereunder;


</section>

<section><tid>1528217</tid>
<number>e</number>" notification" means a notification published in the 
official Gazette;

</section>

<section><tid>1258271</tid>
<number>f</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>493334</tid>
<number>g</number>" scheduled bank" means a bank for the time being 
included in the Second Schedule to the Reserve Bank of India 
Act, <year>1934</year> (2 of <year>1934</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>617275</tid>
<number>h</number>" railway" shall have the meaning assigned to it in the 
Indian Railways Act, <year>1890</year> (9 of <year>1890</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1511380</tid>
<number>i</number>" safety in coal mines" includes the safety of any 
railway situated on the surface above a coal mine;

</section>

<section><tid>147197</tid>
<number>j</number>" stowing" means the operation of filling, with sand or 
any other material, or with both, spaces left underground in 
a coal mine by the extraction of coal;

</section>

<section><tid>1435322</tid>
<number>k</number>" washing" means such process or combination of 
processes as may be approved in this behalf by the Central 
Government by which the whole or any part of the shaley and 
mineral matter found in the coal is removed therefrom;

</section>

<section><tid>484384</tid>
<number>l</number>" agent"," mine" and" owner" have the meanings 
respectively assigned to them in the Mines Act, <year>1952</year>. (35 of  
  <year>1952</year>)
CHAP

PROVISIONS RELATING TO CONSERVATION OF COAL AND DEVELOPMENT OF 
COAL MINES

CHAPTER II 
PROVISIONS RELATING TO CONSERVATION OF COAL AND DEVELOPMENT OF 
COAL MINES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>874610</tid>
<number> 4</number> Power of Central Government in respect of conservation of 
coal and development of coal mines.
<section><tid>14759</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may,  
for the purpose of conservation of coal and for the development of 
coal mines, exercise such powers and take or cause to be taken, such 
measures as it may deem necessary or proper or as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1353989</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
the Central Government may, by order in writing addressed to the 
owner, agent or manager of a coal mine, require him to take such 
measures as

<pagefootnote><pagenum>125</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

it may think necessary for the purpose of conservation of coal or for 
development of coal mines, including-


<subsection><tid>1018824</tid>
<number>a</number>in any coal mine, stowing for safety, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>705855</tid>
<number>b</number>the prevention of any factor which may adversely affect 
the conservation of coal or development of coal mine, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1934918</tid>
<number>c</number>washing of coal with a view to beneficiating and 
reducing the ash- contents of coal.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>726486</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The Central Government may, if it is satisfied after 
consideration of all the facts and circumstances that the recovery of 
the cost of measures, if any, undertaken by it under sub- section (1) 
or sub- section (2) in relation to a coal mine is justified, recover 
such cost from the owner, agent or manager of the coal mine, either 
wholly or partly, in the same manner as an arrear of land revenue.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>527523</tid>
<number> 5</number> Duty of owner to take steps for the conservation and 
devlopment of coal mine.
<section><tid>334152</tid>
<number>1</number>The owner of a coal mine shall take, in  
relation to each coal mine owned by him, such steps as may be 
necessary to ensure the conservation of coal and development of the 
coal mine.

</section>

<section><tid>6934</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the provisions of 
sub- section (1), the owner of a coal mine shall-

<subsection><tid>75246</tid>
<number>a</number>execute such stowing and other operations as may be 
necessary to be taken in furtherance of the objects of this 
Act in so far as such objects relate to the conservation of 
coal or development of the coal mine or the utilisation of 
coal obtained from the coal mine.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>722842</tid>
<number>b</number>acquire such stowing and other materials as may be 
necessary for ensuring the conservation of coal, and safety 
in, the coal mine;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>702058</tid>
<number>c</number>undertake research in relation to conservation of coal, 
development of coal mines and utilisation of coal;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1997842</tid>
<number>d</number>plan and undertake development of the coal mines in a 
scientific manner;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1787921</tid>
<number>e</number>undertake such other activity as the Central Government 
may, for the furtherance of the objects of this Act, direct.

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>71318</tid>
<number> 6</number> Imposition of esicxe duties.
<section><tid>69170</tid>
<number>1</number>With effect from the  
appointed day, there shall be levied and collected on all coal 
raised and despatched, and on all coke manufactured and despatched, 
from the collieries in India, such duty of excise, not exceeding 
rupees ten per tonne, as may be fixed from time to time by the Central 
Government by, notification, and different rates of duty may be levied 
on different grades or description of coal or coke:
Provided that the Central Government may, by general or special 
order, exempt any special grade or grades or description of coal or 
coke from the levy of such duty of excise.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>126</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 55 of <year>1985</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 1- <year>1986</year>).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1728820</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes of sub- section (1), coal shall be graded by 
the Central Government in accordance with such specifications as may 
be laid down by that Government from time to time.

</section>

<section><tid>891074</tid>
<number>3</number>All notifications issued under this section shall be laid, 
as soon as may be, before both Houses of Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>128083</tid>
<number>7</number>Imposition of customs duty. During the period in which any duty 
of excise is being levied under section 6, the Central Government may, 
by notification, impose on all coal (including soft and hard coke), 
imported or brought into India from any place outside India, a duty of 
customs (which shall be in addition to any duty of Customs for the  
  time being leviable under any other law), at the rates equivalent to 
the rates of duty of excise levied under section 6.


</article>



<article><tid>227744</tid>
<number> 8</number> Collection of excise duties. <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1989223</tid>
<number>1</number>] The duties of excise  
levied under section 6 shall be collected by such agencies and in 
which manner as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>940225</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Where any duty of excise referred to in sub- section (1) 
cannot be collected in the manner prescribed under that sub- section, 
it shall be recovered from the owner of the coal mine in the same 
manner as an arrear of land revenue".]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>113383</tid>
<number> 9</number> Utilisation of proceeds of duties levied and collected under 
sections 6 and 7. In each financial year, a sum not exceeding the net 
proceeds (determined in such manner as may be prescribed) of the 
duties of excise and customs levied and collected under sections 6 and 
7, respectively, during the preceding financial year or years shall be 
disbursed by the Central Government in accordance with such procedure 
as may be prescribed, to the owners, agents or managers of coal- mines 
or to any other person for one or more of the following purposes, 
namely:-
<section><tid>1786574</tid>
<number>a</number>conservation of coal and development of coal mines;

</section>

<section><tid>1561932</tid>
<number>b</number>grant of stowing materials and other assistance for 
stowing operations;

</section>

<section><tid>235150</tid>
<number>c</number>execution of stowing and other operations for the 
safety in coal mines or conservation of coal;

</section>

<section><tid>1416482</tid>
<number>d</number>prosecution of research work, connected with 
conservation and utilisation of coal; and

</section>

<section><tid>639916</tid>
<number>e</number>any other purpose connected with the conservation of 
coal or development of coal mines, or transportation, 
distribution or utilisation of coal:
Provided that the Central Government may disburse to the owners, 
agents or managers of coal mines or to any other person, a sum not


<pagefootnote><pagenum>127</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Remembered and Ins. by Act 55 of <year>1985</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 1- 1- <year>1986</year>).






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

exceeding the aggregate of the net proceeds of the duties of excise 
collected under section 8 of the Coal Mines (Conservation, Safety and  
  Development) Act, <year>1952</year>, (12 of <year>1952</year>) and remaining undisbursed before 
the commencement of this Act, for all or any of the purposes 
specified in this 
section.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1039263</tid>
<number> 10</number> Duty of owner to open Coal Mine Conservation and Development 
Account.
<section><tid>626618</tid>
<number>1</number>The owner of every coal mine, to whom any money is  
disbursed under section 9, shall open a separate account in a 
scheduled bank, to be known as the" Coal Mine Conservation and 
Development Account" and shall credit to the said Account all sums so 
disbursed to him:
Provided that where it is necessary so to do in relation to the 
different groups of coal mines owned by an owner, separate accounts 
may be opened in relation to each, such group of coal mines.


</section>

<section><tid>573028</tid>
<number>2</number>The money standing to the credit of the Coal Mine 
Conservation Development Account and accretions thereto shall be 
applied by the owner of the coal mine to-

<subsection><tid>85916</tid>
<number>a</number>the furtherance of the objects of this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1551427</tid>
<number>b</number>the acquisition of stowing or other materials needed 
for stowing operations in coal mines;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>692256</tid>
<number>c</number>the execution of stowing and other operations in 
furtherance of the objects of this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>603565</tid>
<number>d</number>the prosecution of research work connected with the 
conservation, development and utilisation of coal and safety 
in coal mines;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1796752</tid>
<number>e</number>the planning and development of coal mines in a 
scientific manner; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>75890</tid>
<number>f</number>any other expenditure which the Central Government may 
direct to be defrayed out of the money standing to the credit 
of the Account.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1223443</tid>
<number>3</number>The Account, referred to in sub- section (1), shall be kept 
in such manner and in such form as may be prescribed, and every such 
account shall be audited by the same person by whom the accounts of 
the owner of the coal mine are audited.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1471415</tid>
<number> 11</number> Power of Inspectors.
<section><tid>415283</tid>
<number>1</number>The Chief Inspector or any Inspector  
may make such examination and inquiries as he thinks fit in order to 
ascertain whether the
<pagefootnote><pagenum>128</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


provisions of this Act or of any rules and orders made thereunder are 
being complied with.


</section>

<section><tid>1211801</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chief Inspector or any Inspector may, with such 
assistance, if any, as he thinks fit enter, inspect and examine at any 
time by day or night any coal mine in order to ensure that stowing or 
any other operation has been, or is being, done effectively:
Provided that the power conferred by this sub- section shall not 
be exercised in such a manner as unreasonably to impede or obstruct 
the working of the mine.


</section>

<section><tid>180302</tid>
<number>3</number>Without prejudice to the provisions of the Mines Act, 
 <year>1952</year> (35 of <year>1952</year>) the Chief Inspector or any Inspector may, by order 
in writing, addressed to the owner, agent or manager of a coal mine, 
require him to take such protective measures, including stowing, in 
the mine as the Chief Inspector or the Inspector may think necessary, 
if in the opinion of the Chief Inspector or Inspector--

<subsection><tid>1538514</tid>
<number>a</number>the extraction or reduction of pillars in any part of 
the coal mine is likely to cause the crushing of pillars or 
the premature collapse of any part of the workings or 
otherwise endanger human life or the coal mine or a railway, 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1119976</tid>
<number>b</number>adequate provision against the outbreak of fire or 
flooding has not been made by providing for the sealing off 
and isolation of any part of the coal mine or for restricting 
the area that might be affected by fire or flooding, as the 
case may be.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>681859</tid>
<number>4</number>The powers conferred on the Inspector under sub- section (1), 
 (2) and (3) may also be exercised by such officer of the Central Gov- 
ernment as that Government may, by notification, specify in this 
behalf.
CHAP

DISSOLUTION OF THE COAL BOARD AND TRANSFER OF EMPLOYEES THEREOF

CHAPTER III 
DISSOLUTION OF THE COAL BOARD AND TRANSFER OF EMPLOYEES THEREOF


<pagefootnote><pagenum>12</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Dissolution of the Coal Board.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>485940</tid>
<number> 12</number> Dissolution of the Coal Board.
<section><tid>878125</tid>
<number>1</number>On the appointed day, the  
Coal Board, established under section 4 of the Coal Mines 
 (Conservation, Safety and Development) Act, <year>1952</year>, (12 of <year>1952</year>) shall 
stand dissolved.

</section>

<section><tid>1645461</tid>
<number>2</number>On the dissolution of the Coal Board,-

<pagefootnote><pagenum>129</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


<subsection><tid>468197</tid>
<number>a</number>all rights and privileges of the Coal Board shall 
become the rights and privileges, respectively, of the 
Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1339807</tid>
<number>b</number>the Central Government- shall be deemed to be the lessee 
of all properties held by the Coal Board, immediately before 
the appointed day, under any lease and that Government shall 
hold the lease under the same terms and conditions under 
which the lease was held by the Coal Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>132124</tid>
<number>c</number>all other properties, movable and immovable, including 
cash balances, reserve funds, investments and monies lying to 
the credit of the Coal Mines Safety and Conservation Fund and 
the Coal Development Fund, and all other rights and interests 
in, or arising out of, such properties as were. immediately 
before the appointed day, in the ownership, possession, power 
or control of the Coal Board, and all books of account, 
registers, records and all other documents of whatever nature 
relating thereto, shall vest in the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1372591</tid>
<number>d</number>all borrowings, liabilities and obligations of the Coal 
Board, of whatever kind and subsisting immediately before the 
appointed day, shall be deemed, on and from the appointed 
day, to be the borrowings, liabilities or obligations, as the 
case may be, of the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1262106</tid>
<number>e</number>all contracts entered into, and all matters and things 
engaged to be done by, with, or for, the Coal Board and 
subsisting immediately before the appointed day, shall be 
deemed, on and from the appointed day, to have been entered 
into or engaged to be done by, with or for, the Central 
Government; all licences and permits granted to the Coal 
Board and in force immediately before the appointed day shall 
be deemed, on and from the appointed day, to have been 
granted to the Central Government and shall have effect 
accordingly.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1155433</tid>
<number>13</number>Power of Central Government to direct vesting of rights in a 
Government company. Notwithstanding anything contained in section 12, 
the Central Government may, if it is satisfied that a Government 
company is willing to comply, or has complied, with such terms and 
conditions as that Government may think fit to impose, direct, by an 
order in writing, that the right, title and interest of the Coal Board 
in relation to any property
<pagefootnote><pagenum>130</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


shall, instead of continuing to vest in it, vest in the Government 
company either on the date of publication of the direction or on such 
earlier or later date (not being a date earlier than the appointed  
  day) as may be specified in the direction, and on such vesting, the 
liability or obligation, as the case may be, of the Coal Board in 
relation to such property shall, instead of continuing to be the 
liability or obligation of the Central Government, become the 
liability or obligation, as the case may be, of the Government 
company.



</article>



<article><tid>1900152</tid>
<number> 14</number> Continuation of suits, etc., against the Central Government.

<section><tid>1348203</tid>
<number>1</number>If, on the appointed day any suit appeal or other proceed-  
ing of whatever nature in relation to the Coal Board is pending by or 
against such Board, the same shall not abate, be discontinued or be in 
any way prejudicially affected by reason of the dissolution of the 
Coal Board; but the suit, appeal or other proceeding may be 
continued, prosecuted and enforced by or against the Central 
Government or the Government company in which the property of the Coal 
Board has become vested, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1003524</tid>
<number>2</number>Where, before the appointed day, any cause of action for any 
suit or proceeding or any right to appeal arose in favour of, or 
against, the Coal Board, and the institution of any suit or 
proceeding on such cause of action or the filing of such appeal was 
not barred before the appointed day, such suit or proceeding may be 
instituted or appeal may be filed by or against the Central Government 
or the Government company referred to in sub- section (1), as the case 
may be.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>20065</tid>
<number> 15</number> Transfer of service of existing employess of Coal Board.
<section><tid>500592</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being 
in force or in any contract to the contrary, every officer or other 
employee of the Coal Board shall, on and from the appointed day, 
become an officer or other employee, as the case may be, of such 
Government company or organisation as the Central Government may, in 
writing, specify and shall hold his office or service in such Govern- 
ment company or organisation, as the case may be, on the same terms 
and conditions and with the same rights to pension, gratuity and other 
matters as would have been admissible to him if the Coal Board had not 
been abolished, and shall continue to do so unless and until his 
employment in the Government company or organisation is terminated or 
until his remuneration or terms and conditions of service are duly 
altered by the Government company or organisation, as the case may be:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>131</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Provided that the tenure remuneration and other terms and 
conditions of service of any such officer or other employee shall not 
be altered to his disadvantage except with the previous approval of 
the Central Government or without such approval, except as a measure 
of punishment, under the rules of the Government company or the 
organisation concerned.


</section>

<section><tid>1473485</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any officer or other employee of the Coal Board 
becomes, under sub- section (1), an officer or other employee of any 
Government company or organisation, the period of service rendered, or 
deemed to have been rendered, by him under the Coal Board before the 
appointed day shall be deemed, for the purposes of fixation of pay 
and other emoluments, pension and other retirement benefits, to be the 
period of service rendered by him under the said Government company or 
organisation, as the case may be, as if the Government company or the 
organisation were in existence during the said period.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>480610</tid>
<number>16</number>No compensation to be paid for the transfer of service of any 
officer or other employee. Notwithstanding anything contained in any 
other law for the time being in force, the transfer of the service of 
any officer or other employee from the Coal Board to any Government 
company or organisation shall not entitle such officer or other 
employee to any compensation under this Act or under any other law for 
the time being in force and no such claim shall be entertained by any 
court, tribunal or other authority.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER IV 
MISCELLANEOUS



</article>



<article><tid>830083</tid>
<number>17</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit, prosecution 
or other legal proceedings shall lie against the Central Government or 
against the Chairman or any other member of the Coal Board or any 
officer thereof or any other person in respect of anything which is in 
good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or of 
any rules or orders made thereunder, or in pursuance of the Coal Mines 
 (Conservation, Safety and Development) Act, <year>1952</year> (12 of <year>1952</year>) or any 
rule made thereunder.


</article>



<article><tid>710176</tid>
<number> 18</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1371602</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification, and subject to the condition of previous publication, 
make rules to carry out the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1200361</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such 
rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>780911</tid>
<number>a</number>the measures to be taken for the purpose of 
conservation of coal and maintenance of safety in coal mines;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>132</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1780746</tid>
<number>b</number>the measures to be taken for the development of coal 
mines;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1614994</tid>
<number>c</number>the manner in which, and the conditions subject to 
which, sums at the credit of the Coal Mine Conservation and 
Development Account may be applied;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>199532</tid>
<number>d</number>the form in which the Coal Mine Conservation and 
Development Account shall be kept;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1787040</tid>
<number>e</number>any other matter which is required to be, or may be, 
prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1148041</tid>
<number>3</number>Any rule made under the provisions of this Act may provide 
that the contravention thereof shall be punishable with imprisonment 
for a term which may extend to three months, or with fine which may 
extend to two thousand rupees, or with both.

</section>

<section><tid>296864</tid>
<number>4</number>Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may 
be after it is made, before each House of Parliament while it is in 
session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the 
expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive session aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>19</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

[ Repeat.]


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1380959</tid>
<number>19</number>[ Repeat.] Rep. by the Repeating and Amending Act, <year>1978</year>, S. 2 
and Sch. I.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>20</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>