<act><tid>1641012</tid>
<title>THE CABLE TELEVISION NETWORKS (REGULATION) AMENDMENT ACT, <year>2000</year></title>

ACT NO. 36 OF <year>2000</year>
[ 1st September, <year>2000</year>]

An Act further to amend the Cable Television Networks (Regulation) 
Act, <year>1995</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- first Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>424986</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title.- This Act may be called the Cable Television Networks 
 (Regulation) Amendment Act, <year>2000</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1567963</tid>
<number> 2</number> Amendment of section 2.- In the Cable Television Networks 
 (Regulation) Act, <year>1995</year> (7 of <year>1995</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the  
  principal Act), in section 2, clause (a) shall be re- lettered as 
clause (aa) and before clause (aa) as so re- lettered, the fol owing 
clause shall be inserted, namely:-
' (a)" authorised officer" means, within his local limits of 
jurisdiction,-

<section><tid>1239595</tid>
<number>i</number>a District Magistrate, or

</section>

<section><tid>1744154</tid>
<number>ii</number>a Sub- divisional Magistrate, or

</section>

<section><tid>1217597</tid>
<number>iii</number>a Commissioner of Police,
and includes any other officer notified in the Official Gazette, by 
the Central Government or the State Government, to be an authorised 
officer for such local limits of jurisdiction as may be determined by 
that Government;'.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1319442</tid>
<number>3</number>Omission of section 5.- In section 5 of the principal Act, the 
proviso shall be omitted.


</article>



<article><tid>1754299</tid>
<number>4</number>Omission of section 6.- In section 6 of the principal Act, the 
proviso shall be omitted.


</article>



<article><tid>878719</tid>
<number> 5</number> Substitution of new section for section 8.- For section 8 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
" 8. Compulsory transmission of Doordarshan channels.- (1) Every cable 
operator shall, from the commencement of the Cable Television Networks 
 (Regulation) Amendment Act, <year>2000</year>, re- transmit at least two Doordarshan 
terrestrial channels and one regional langu ge channel of a State in 
the prime band, in satellite mode on frequencies other than those 
carrying terrestrial frequencies.

<section><tid>1997468</tid>
<number>2</number>The Doordarshan channels referred to in sub- section (1) shall be 
re- transmitted without any deletion or alteration of any programme 
transmitted on such channels.

</section>

<section><tid>78954</tid>
<number>3</number>The Prasar Bharati (Broadcasting Corporation of India) established 
under sub- section (1) of section 3 of the Prasar Bharati (Broadcasting  
  Corporation of India) Act, <year>1990</year> (25 of <year>1990</year>) may, by notification in 
the Official Gazette, specify the number a d name of every Doordarshan 
channel to be re- transmitted by cable operators in their cable service 
and the manner of reception and re- transmission of such channels.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>457674</tid>
<number>6</number>Amendment of section 11.- In section 11 of the principal Act, for 
sub- section 1, the following sub- section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (1) If any authorised officer has reason to believe that the 
provisions of sections 3, 5, 6 or 8 have been or are being contravened 
by any cable operator, he may seize the equipment being used by such 
cable operator for operating the cable television ne work.".



</article>



<article><tid>661840</tid>
<number>7</number>Amendment of section 18.- In section 18 of the principal Act, for 
the portion beginning with the words" by such officer" and ending with 
the words" specify in this behalf", the words" by any authorised 
officer" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1154817</tid>
<number> 8</number> Amendment of section 19.- In section 19 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1685156</tid>
<number>i</number>for the portion beginning with the words" an officer, not below 
the rank of" and ending with the words" by the State Government in 
this behalf", the words" any authorised officer" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>104087</tid>
<number>ii</number>for the words" any particular programme if it is", the words and 
figures" any programme or channel if, it is not in conformity with the 
prescribed programme code referred to in section 5 and advertisement 
code referred to in section 6 or if it is" s all be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1886541</tid>
<number> 9</number> Amendment of section 20.- Section 20 of the principal Act shall be 
re- numbered as sub- section
<section><tid>347814</tid>
<number>1</number>thereof and after sub- section (1) as so  
re- numbered, the following sub- sections shall be inserted, namely:-
" (2) Where the Central Government thinks it necessary or expedient so 
to do in the interest of the-


<subsection><tid>1606322</tid>
<number>i</number>sovereignty or integrity of India; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>781741</tid>
<number>ii</number>security of India; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>161319</tid>
<number>iii</number>friendly relations of India with any foreign State; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>566648</tid>
<number>iv</number>public order, decency or morality,
it may, by order, regulate or prohibit the transmission or 
re- transmission of any channel or programme.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1143826</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the Central Government considers that any programme of any 
channel is not in conformity with the prescribed programme code 
referred to in section 5 or the prescribed advertisement code referred 
to in section 6, it may by order, regulate or proh bit the 
transmission or re- transmission of such programme.".
SUBHASH C. JAIN. 
Secy. to the Govt. of India.



</section>

</article>



 </act>