<act><title>

The 
    Seeds Act, 1966</title> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Seeds Act, 1966.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends to the whole of India.
 </section><section>
 <number>3</number> It shall come into force on such 
    date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central Government may, by notification in the 
    Official Gazette, appoint, and different dates may be appointed for 
    different provisions of this Act, and for different States or for different 
    areas thereof.2 as 
    the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    appoint, and different dates may be appointed for different provisions of 
    this Act, and for different States or for different areas thereof." 
 
 






  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.­—In this Act, unless 
    the context otherwise requires,— 
 <section>
<number>1</number>   
    “agriculture” includes horticulture; 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>   “Central 
    Seed Laboratory” means the Central Seed Laboratory established or declared 
    as such under sub-section (1) of section 4; 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>   
    “certification agency” means the certification agency established under 
    section 8 or recognised under section 18; 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number>   
    “Committee” means the Central Seed Committee constituted under sub-section 
    (1) of section 3; 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number>   
    “container” means a box, bottle, casket, tin, barrel, case, receptacle, 
    sack, bag, wrapper or other thing in which any article or thing is placed or 
    packed; 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number>   “export” 
    means taking out of India to a place outside India; 
 </section><section>
<number>7</number>   “import” 
    means bringing into India from a place outside India; 
 </section><section>
<number>8</number>   “kind” 
    means one or more related species or sub-species of crop plants each 
    individually or collectively known by one common name such as cabbage, 
    maize, paddy and wheat; 
 </section><section>
<number>9</number>   “notified 
    kind or variety”, in relation to any seed, means any kind or variety thereof 
    notified under section 5; 
 </section><section>
<number>10</number>   
    “prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act; 
 </section><section>
<number>11</number>   “seed” 
    means any of the following classes of seeds used for sowing or planting— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   seeds of food crops including edible oil 
    seeds and seeds of fruits and vegetables; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   cotton seeds; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   seeds of cattle fodder; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>iv</number>   jute seeds,] 
 
and includes seedlings, and tubers, bulbs, 
    rhizomes, roots, cuttings, all types of grafts and other vegetatively 
    propagated material, of food crops or cattle fodder; 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>12</number>   “Seed 
    Analyst” means a Seed Analyst appointed under section 12; 
 </section><section>
<number>13</number>   “Seed 
    Inspector” means a Seed Inspector appointed under  
    section 13; 
 </section><section>
<number>14</number>   “State 
    Government”, in relation to a Union territory, means the administrator 
    thereof; 
 </section><section>
<number>15</number>   “State 
    Seed Laboratory”, in relation to any State, means the State Seed Laboratory 
    established or declared as such under sub-section (2) of section 4 for that 
    State; and
 </section><section>
<number>16</number>   
    “variety” means a sub-division of a kind identifiable by growth, yield, 
    plant, fruit, seed, or other characteristic.
 
 




  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Central Seed Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Central Government shall, as soon as may be after the commencement of this 
    Act, constitute a Committee called the Central Seed Committee to advise the 
    Central Government and the State Governments on matters arising out of the 
    administration of this Act and to carry out the other functions assigned to 
    it by or under this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Committee shall consist of the 
    following members, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   
    a Chairman to be nominated by the Central Government; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   
    eight persons to be nominated by the Central Government to represent such 
    interests as that Government thinks fit, of whom not less than two persons 
    shall be representatives of growers of seed; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   
    one person to be nominated by the Government of each of the States. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The members of the Committee shall, unless 
    their seats become vacant earlier by resignation, death or otherwise, be 
    entitled to hold office for two years and shall be eligible for re-nomination. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Committee may, subject to the previous 
    approval of the Central Government, make bye-laws fixing the quorum and 
    regulating its own procedure and the conduct of all business to be 
    transacted by it. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Committee may appoint one or more 
    sub-committees, consisting wholly of members of the Committee or wholly of 
    other persons or partly of members of the Committee and partly of other 
    persons, as it thinks fit, for the purpose of discharging such of its 
    functions as may be delegated to such sub-committee or sub-committees by the 
    Committee. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The functions of the Committee or any 
    sub-committee thereof may be exercised notwithstanding any vacancy therein. 
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The Central Government shall appoint a 
    person to be the secretary of the Committee and shall provide the Committee 
    with such clerical and other staff as the Central Government considers 
    necessary. 
  



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Central Seed Laboratory and State Seed 
    Laboratory.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government may, by notification in the 
    Official Gazette, establish a Central Seed Laboratory or declare any seed 
    laboratory as the Central Seed Laboratory to carry out the functions 
    entrusted to the Central Seed Laboratory by or under this Act. 
 </section><section>
 <number>2</number> The State Government may, by notification 
    in the Official Gazette, establish one or more State Seed Laboratories or 
    declare any seed laboratory as a State Seed Laboratory where analysis of 
    seeds of any notified kind or variety shall be carried out by Seed Analysts 
    under this Act in the prescribed manner. 
  























  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Power to notify kinds or varieties of 
    seeds.—If the Central Government, after consultation with the Committee, 
    is of opinion that it is necessary or expedient to regulate the quality of 
    seed of any kind or variety to be sold for purposes of agriculture, it may, 
    by notification in the Official Gazette, declare such kind or variety to be 
    a notified kind or variety for the purposes of this Act and different kinds 
    or varieties may be notified for different States or for different areas 
    thereof.
  



 
 
 
Sl. No.
 
Kind
 
Variety

 
 

<section><number>1</number>
 
(2)
 
(3)

 
  
  
  

 
 
1.
 
Paddy
 
HKR-126

 
 
2.
 
Paddy
 
SYE-2001

 
 
3.
 
Paddy
 
Palam Dhan-957(IET-13795)

 
 
4.
 
Paddy
 
Sharavathi (IR-57773)

 
 
5.
 
Paddy
 
JR-503(Richa)(IET-16789)

 
 
6.
 
Paddy
 
Pusa Sugandh - 5 (IET-17021)

 
 
7.
 
Paddy
 
Suruchi 5401 (MPH-5401)

 
 
8.
 
Paddy
 
Sugandhamati (IET-16775)

 
 
9.
 
Paddy
 
GR-9

 
 
10.
 
Paddy
 
PKV Makarand

 
 
11.
 
Paddy
 
PVK-SKL-3-11325-30-36

 
 
12.
 
Paddy
 
Indira Dhan -1 (IET-15376)(R 
        636-405_

 
 
13
 
Barley
 
NDB-1173

 
 
14.
 
Barley
 
VL Barley-56

 
 
15.
 
Wheat
 
Palam (HPW-147)

 
 
16.
 
Wheat
 
Chandrika (HPW-184)

 
 
17.
 
Wheat
 
VL Gehun - 802

 
 
18.
 
Wheat
 
Urja (HD-2864)

 
 
19.
 
Wheat
 
MACS-6145

 
 
20.
 
Sorghum
 
Parbhani Moti 
        (PVR-396/SPV-1411)

 
 
21.
 
Fodder Sorghum
 
Gujrat Fodder Sorghum - 5

 
 
22.
 
Maize
 
Pratap Makka - 3 (EC-3108)

 
 
23.
 
Maize
 
Super Kohinoor (BISCO-2418)

 
 
24.
 
Maize
 
Win Orange Sweet Corn

 
 
25.
 
Maize
 
BIO 9636 (BIO 92136)

 
 
26.
 
Maize
 
Vl Baby Corn-1 (VL-78)

 
 
27.
 
Maize
 
DK-984 (2784)

 
 
28.
 
Maize
 
IC-8209 (72A)

 
 
29.
 
Maize
 
Vivek Maize Hybrid - 15 
        (FH-3176)

 
 
30.
 
Maize
 
Vivek Maize Hybrid - 15 
        (FH-3186)

 
 
31.
 
Maize
 
Azad Kamal (R-9803)

 
 
32.
 
Pearl Millet
 
PROAGRO - 9444 (MSH-118)

 
 
33.
 
Pearl Millet
 
Parbhani Sampada (PPC-6)

 
 
34.
 
Groundnut
 
Kadiri - 5

 
 
35.
 
Groundnut
 
Kadiri - 6

 
 
36.
 
Groundnut
 
Prutha (Dh-86)

 
 
37.
 
Groundnut
 
RG-382

 
 
38.
 
Linseed
 
BINWA (KL-210)

 
 
39.
 
Soybean
 
Palam Soya (P-30-1-1)

 
 
40.
 
Soybean
 
TAMS-38

 
 
41.
 
Sunflower
 
PROSUN-09 (PRO-009)

 
 
42.
 
Sunflower
 
KBSH-41

 
 
43.
 
Sunflower
 
KBSH-42

 
 
44.
 
Sunflower
 
DRSF-108

 
 
45.
 
Red Clover
 
PRC-3

 
 
46.
 
Indian Mustard
 
CS-54 (CS614-4-1-4)

 
 
47.
 
Niger
 
NRS-96-1

 
 
48.
 
Niger
 
Birsa Niger - 2 (BNS-8)

 
 
49.
 
Safflower
 
Phule Kusyma (JLSF-414)

 
 
50.
 
Sunhemp
 
Narendra Sanai-1

 
 
51.
 
Sunhemp
 
Sailash (SH-14)

 
 
52.
 
Daincha
 
Pant Daincha-1

 
 
53.
 
Daincha
 
DH-2

 
 
54.
 
Mesta
 
Nirmal (MT-150)

 
 
55.
 
French Bean
 
Kailash (SRC-74)

 
 
56.
 
Chichpea
 
Haryana Kabuli Chana-2 (HK 
        94-1 34)

 
 
57.
 
Pigeon Pea
 
Malaviya Chamatkar (MAL-13)

 
 
58.
 
Horse Gram
 
Pratap Multhi - 1 (AK-42)

 
 
59.
 
Moth Bean
 
CAZRI Moth-3 (CZM-99)

 
 
60.
 
Rice Bean
 
Bidhan Rice Bean - 2 (KRB-4)

 
 
61.
 
Cluster Bean (Guar)
 
Surya (RGM-112)

 
 
62.
 
Cotton
 
RBDV - 7 (Pratap Kapi-1)

 
 
63.
 
Cotton
 
CICR -2(CISAA-2) (GSM Based 
        Hybrid)

 
 
64.
 
Cotton
 
Shresth (CSHH-198)

 
 
65.
 
Cotton
 
PH-348 (Yamuna)

 
 
66.
 
Cotton
 
PA-402

 
 
67.
 
Cotton
 
Phule LJA-794

 
 
68.
 
Cotton
 
Mahabeej - 106

 
 
69.
 
Cotton
 
Manabeej Dh-986

 
 
70.
 
Tossa Jute
 
Subala (S-19)

 
 
71.
 
White Jute
 
JRC 80 (Mitali White)

 
 
72.
 
Oat
 
Bundel Jai 992 (JHO 99-2)

 
 
73.
 
Setaria Grass
 
Setaria-92

 
 
74.
 
Tall Fescue Grass
 
Hima-4

 
 
75.
 
Guinea Grass
 
Bundel Guinea - 1 (JHGG 
        96-5)

 
 
76.
 
Sugarcase
 
Sweta (Cos 94270)



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Power to specify minimum limits of 
    germination and purity, etc.—The Central Government may, after 
    consultation with the Committee and by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    specify— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   the 
    minimum limits of germination and purity with respect to any seed of any 
    notified kind or variety; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   the mark 
    or label to indicate that such seed conforms to the minimum limits of 
    germination and purity specified under clause (a) and the particulars which 
    such mark or label may contain. 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Regulation or sale of seeds of notified 
    kinds or varieties.—No person shall, himself or by any other person on 
    his behalf, carry on the business of selling, keeping for sale, offering to 
    sell, bartering or otherwise supplying any seed of any notified kind or 
    variety, unless— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   such seed 
    is identifiable as to its kind or variety; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   such seed 
    conforms to the minimum limits of germination and purity specified under 
    clause (a) of section 6; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   the 
    container of such seed bears in the prescribed manner, the mark or label 
    containing the correct particulars thereof specified under clause (b) of 
    section 6; and 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   he 
    complies with such other requirements as may be prescribed. 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Certification agency.—The State 
    Government or the Central Government in consultation with the State 
    Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, establish a 
    certification agency for the State to carry out the functions entrusted to 
    the certification agency by or under this Act. 
  














  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>8A</number> The Central 
    Seed Certification Board.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government shall, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, establish a Central Seed Certification 
    Board (hereinafter referred to as the Board) to advise the Central 
    Government and the State Governments on all matters relating to 
    certification, and to co-ordinate the functioning of the agencies 
    established under section 8.1[8A. 
    The Central Seed Certification Board.—(1) The Central Government shall, 
    by notification in the Official Gazette, establish a Central Seed 
    Certification Board (hereinafter referred to as the Board) to advise the 
    Central Government and the State Governments on all matters relating to 
    certification, and to co-ordinate the functioning of the agencies 
    established under section 8." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Board shall consist of the following 
    members, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   
    a Chairman, to be nominated by the Central Government; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   
    four members, to be nominated by the Central Government from out of the 
    persons employed by the State Governments as Directors of Agriculture; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   
    three members, to be nominated by the Central Government from out of the 
    persons employed by the Agricultural Universities as Directors of Research; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   
    thirteen persons, to be nominated by the Central Government to represent 
    such interests as that Government thinks fit, of whom not less than four 
    persons shall be representatives of seed producers or tradesmen. 
 
 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> A member of the Board shall, unless his 
    seat becomes vacant earlier by resignation or otherwise, be entitled to hold 
    office for two years from the date of his nomination: 
 
Provided that a person nominated under clause 
    (ii) or clause (iii) of sub-section (2) shall hold office only for so long 
    as he holds the appointment by virtue of which his nomination was made.]
  


  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>8B</number> Other Committees.—The 
    Board may appoint as many Committees as it deems fit consisting wholly of 
    the members of the Board or wholly of other persons or partly of members of 
    the Board and partly of other persons as it thinks fit to exercise such 
    powers and perform such duties as may be delegated to them, subject to such 
    conditions as it may think fit, by the Board.]
 
 



  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>8C</number> Proceedings of 
    Board or Committee not to be invalid by reason of any vacancy therein.—No 
    proceeding of the Board or any Committee thereof shall become invalid merely 
    by reason of the existence of any vacancy therein or any defect in the 
    constitution thereof.]
 
 



  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<number>8D</number> Procedure for 
    Board.—The Board may, subject to the previous approval of the Central 
    Government, make bye-laws for the purpose of regulating its own 
    procedure and the procedure of any Committee thereof and the conduct of all 
    business to be transacted by it or such Committee.]
 
 



  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>8E</number> 
    Secretary and other officers.—The Central Government shall—1[8E. 
    Secretary and other officers.—The Central Government shall—" 
 <section>
<number>i</number>   
    appoint a person to be the Secretary of the Board, and  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>   
    provide the Board with such technical and other staff as the Central 
    Government considers necessary.]
 
 



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Grant of certificate by certification 
    agency.—
<section><number>1</number> Any person selling, keeping for sale, offering to sell, 
    bartering or otherwise supplying any seed of any notified kind or variety 
    may, if he desires to have such seed certified by the certification agency, 
    apply to the certification agency for the grant of a certificate for the 
    purpose. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every application under sub-section (1) 
    shall be made in such form, shall contain such particulars and shall be 
    accompanied by such fees as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On receipt of any such application for the 
    grant of a certificate, the certification agency may, after such enquiry as 
    it thinks fit and after satisfying itself that the seed to which the 
    application relates conforms to the <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[prescribed standards], 
    grant a certificate in such form and on such conditions as may be 
    prescribed:
 
<footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[Provided that such 
    standards shall not be lower that the minimum limits of germination and 
    purity specified for that seed under clause (a) of section 6.]3[Provided 
    that such standards shall not be lower that the minimum limits of 
    germination and purity specified for that seed under clause (a) of section 
    6.]" 
 
 




  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Revocation of certificate.—If the 
    certification agency is satisfied, either on a reference made to it in this 
    behalf or otherwise, that—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>   the 
    certificate granted by it under section 9 has been obtained by 
    misrepresentation as to an essential fact; or 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   the 
    holder of the certificate has, without reasonable cause, failed to comply 
    with the conditions subject to which the certificate has been granted or has 
    contravened any of the provisions of this Act or the rules made thereunder, 
 
then, without prejudice to any other penalty 
    to which the holder of the certificate may be liable under this Act, the 
    certification agency may, after giving the holder of the certificate an 
    opportunity of showing cause, revoke the certificate. 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> Appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> Any person aggrieved by 
    a decision of a certification agency under section 9 or section 10, may 
    within thirty days from the date on which the decision is communicated to 
    him and on payment of such fees as may be prescribed, prefer an appeal to 
    such authority as may be specified by the State Government in this behalf: 
 
Provided that the appellate authority may 
    entertain an appeal after the expiry of the said period of thirty days if it 
    is satisfied that the appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from 
    filing the appeal in time. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On receipt of an appeal under sub-section 
    (1), the appellate authority shall, after giving the appellant an 
    opportunity of being heard, dispose of the appeal as expeditiously as 
    possible. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every order of the appellate authority 
    under this section shall be final. 
  
 

    Comment
 
The following authorities, have 
    been declared as Appellate Authorities:— 
 </section><section>
  <number>1</number>   Director 
    of Agriculture, Assam, Shillong, for Assam State, vide Assam Gazette, 
    Pt. I, p. 3089, dated 24th April, 1969. 
 </section><section>
  <number>2</number>   Director 
    of Agriculture, Bihar, for Bihar State, vide Bihar Gazette Extra, 
    dated 6th February, 1970. 
 </section><section>
  <number>3</number>   A Board of 
    three members, for the Maharashtra State, vide Maharashtra Gazette, 
    Pt. IV A, p. 974, dated 24th September, 1970. 
 </section><section>
  <number>4</number>   A 
    Committee of five persons, one Chairman and four members, for Mysore State,
    vide Mysore Gazette, Pt. IV, Sec. 2C(ii) , p. 1902, dated 21st May, 
    1970. 
 </section><section>
  <number>5</number>   Director 
    of Agriculture, Himachal Pradesh, for Himachal Pradesh State, vide 
    Himachal Pradesh Gazette, Pt. I, p. 548, dated 3rd October, 1970. 
 
Note.—For Appellate 
    Authority for Delhi, see Delhi Gazette, Pt. IV, p. 529, dated 21st 
    May, 1970. 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Seed Analysts.—The State Government 
    may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint such persons as it 
    thinks fit, having the prescribed qualifications, to be Seed Analysts and 
    define the areas within which they shall exercise jurisdiction. 
  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> Seed Inspectors.—
<section><number>1</number> The State 
    Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint such 
    persons as it thinks fit, having the prescribed qualifications, to be Seed 
    Inspectors and define the areas within which they shall exercise 
    jurisdiction. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every Seed Inspector shall be deemed to be 
    a public servant within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code 
    (45 of 1860) and shall be officially subordinate to such authority as the 
    State Government may specify in this behalf. 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> Powers of Seed Inspector.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Seed Inspector may— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   
    take samples of any seed in any notified kind or variety from— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   any person selling such seed; 
    or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   any person who is in the 
    course of conveying, delivering or preparing to deliver such seed to a 
    purchaser or a consignee; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>   a purchaser or a consignee 
    after delivery of such seed to him;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   
    send such sample for analysis to the Seed Analyst for the area within which 
    such sample has been taken; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   
    enter and search at all reasonable times, with such assistance, if any, as 
    he considers necessary, any place in which he has reason to believe that an 
    offence under this Act has been or is being committed and order in writing 
    the person in possession of any seed in respect of which the offence has 
    been or is being committed, not to dispose of any stock of such seed for a 
    specific period not exceeding thirty days or, unless the alleged offence is 
    such that the defect may be removed by the possessor of the seed, seize the 
    stock of such seed; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   
    examine any record, register, document or any other material object found in 
    any place mentioned in clause (c) and seize the same if he has reason to 
    believe that if may furnish evidence of the commission of an offence 
    punishable under this Act; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   
    exercise such other powers as may be necessary for carrying out the purposes 
    of this Act or any rule made thereunder. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any sample of any seed of any 
    notified kind or variety is taken under clause (a) of sub-section (1), its 
    cost, calculated at the rate at which such seed is usually sold to the 
    public, shall be paid on demand to the person from whom it is taken. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The power conferred by this section 
    includes power to break-open any container in which any seed of any notified 
    kind or variety may be contained or to break-open the door of any premises 
    where any such seed may be kept for sale: 
 
 Provided that the power to break-open the 
    door shall be exercised only after the owner or any other person in 
    occupation of the premises, if he is present therein, refuses to open the 
    door on being called upon to do so. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where the Seed Inspector takes any action 
    under clause (a) of sub-section (1), he shall, as far as possible, call not 
    less than two persons to be present at the time when such action is taken 
    and take their signatures on a memorandum to be prepared in the prescribed 
    form and manner. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The provisions of the Code of 
    Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898)*, 
    shall, so far as may be, apply to any search or seizure under this section 
    as they apply to any search or seizure made under the authority of a warrant 
    issued under 
#section 
    98 of the said Code.*, 
    shall, so far as may be, apply to any search or seizure under this section 
    as they apply to any search or seizure made under the authority of a warrant 
    issued under 
#section 
    98 of the said Code." 
 
 




  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> Procedure to be followed by Seed 
    Inspectors.—
<section><number>1</number> Whenever a Seed Inspector intends to take sample of any 
    seed of any notified kind or variety for analysis, he shall— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   give 
    notice in writing, then and there, of such intention to the person from whom 
    he intends to take sample; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   except in 
    special cases provided by rules made under this Act, take three 
    representative samples in the prescribed manner and mark and seal or fasten 
    up each sample in such manner as its nature permits. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> When samples of any seed of any notified 
    kind or variety are taken under sub-section (1), the Seed Inspector 
    shall— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   deliver 
    one sample to the person from whom it has been taken; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   send in 
    the prescribed manner another sample for analysis to the Seed Analyst for 
    the area within which such sample has been taken; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   retain 
    the remaining sample in the prescribed manner for production in case any 
    legal proceedings are taken or for analysis by the Central Seed Laboratory 
    under sub-section (2) of section 16, as the case may be.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> If the person from whom the samples have 
    been taken refuses to accept one of the samples, the Seed Inspector shall 
    send intimation to the Seed Analyst of such refusal and thereupon the Seed 
    Analyst receiving the sample for analysis shall divide it into two parts and 
    shall seal or fasten up one of those parts and shall cause it, either upon 
    receipt of the sample or when he delivers his report, to be delivered to the 
    Seed Inspector who shall retain it for production in case legal proceedings 
    are taken. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where a Seed Inspector takes any action 
    under clause (c) of sub-section (1) of section 14,— on 
    (1) of section 14,—" 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   he shall 
    use all despatch in ascertaining whether or not the seed contravenes any of 
    the provisions of section 7 and if it is ascertained that the seed does not 
    so contravene, forthwith revoke the order passed under the said clause or, 
    as the case may be, take such action as may be necessary for the return of 
    the stock of the seed seized; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   if he 
    seizes the stock of the seed, he shall, as soon as may be, inform a 
    magistrate and take his orders as to the custody thereof; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   without 
    prejudice to the institution of any prosecution, if the alleged offence is 
    such that the defect may be removed by the possessor of the seed, he shall, 
    on being satisfied that the defect has been so removed, forthwith revoke the 
    order passed under the said clause. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> Where a Seed Inspector seizes any record, 
    register, document or any other material object under clause (d) of 
    sub-section (1) of section 14, he shall, as soon as may be, inform a 
    magistrate and take his orders as to the custody thereof. 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> Report of Seed Analyst.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Seed Analyst shall, as soon as may be after the receipt of the sample under 
    sub-section (2) of section 15, analyse the sample at the State Seed 
    Laboratory and deliver, in such form as may be prescribed, one copy of the 
    report of the result of the analysis to the Seed Inspector and another copy 
    thereof to the person from whom the sample has been taken. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> After the institution of a prosecution 
    under this Act, the accused vendor or the complainant may, on payment of the 
    prescribed fee, make an application to the court for sending any of the 
    samples mentioned in clause (a) or clause (c) of sub-section (2) of section 
    15 to the Central Seed Laboratory for its report and on receipt of the 
    application, the court shall first ascertain that the mark and the seal or 
    fastening as provided in clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 15 are in 
    tact and may then despatch the sample under its own seal to the Central Seed 
    Laboratory which shall thereupon send its report to the court in the 
    prescribed form within one month from the date of receipt of the sample, 
    specifying the result of the analysis. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The report sent by the Central Seed 
    Laboratory under sub-section (2) shall supersede the report given by the 
    Seed Analyst under sub-section (1). 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where the report sent by the Central Seed 
    Laboratory under sub-section (2) is produced in any proceedings under 
    section 19, it shall not be necessary in such proceedings to produce any 
    sample or part thereof taken for analysis. 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> Restriction on export and import of 
    seeds of notified kinds or varieties.—No person shall, for the purpose 
    of sowing or planting by any person (including himself), export or import or 
    cause to be exported or imported any seed of any notified kind or variety, 
    unless— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   
    it conforms to the minimum limits of germination and purity specified for 
    that seed under clause (a) of section 6; and  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   
    its container bears, in the prescribed manner, the mark or label with the 
    correct particulars thereof specified for that seed under clause (b) of 
    section 6. 
  


  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> Recognition of seed certification 
    agencies of foreign countries.—The Central Government may, on the 
    recommendation of the Committee and by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    recognise any seed certification agency established in any foreign country, 
    for the purposes of this Act. 
  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> Penalty.—If any person— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   
    contravenes any provision of this Act or any rule made thereunder; or 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   
    prevents a Seed Inspector from taking sample under this Act; or 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   
    prevents a Seed Inspector from exercising any other power conferred on him 
    by or under this Act, 
 
he shall, on conviction, be punishable— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   
    for the first offence with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   
    in the event of such person having been previously convicted of an offence 
    under this section, with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six 
    months, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both. 
  


  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> Forfeiture of property.—When any 
    person has been convicted under this Act for the contravention of any of the 
    provisions of this Act or the rules made thereunder, the seed in respect of 
    which the contravention has been committed may be forfeited to the 
    Government. 
  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>21</number> Offences by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> Where an 
    offence under this Act has been committed by a company, every person who at 
    the time the offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible to, 
    the company for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as the 
    company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to 
    be proceeded against and punished accordingly: 
 
 Provided that nothing contained in this sub-section 
    shall render any such person liable to any punishment under this Act if he 
    proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge and that he 
    exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence. 
 </section><section>
 <number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section 
    (1), where an offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it 
    is proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or connivance 
    of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any director, manager, 
    secretary or other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary 
    or other officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall 
    be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly. 
 
 Explanation.—For the purposes of this 
    section,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   “company” 
    means any body corporate and includes a firm or other association of 
    individuals; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   
    “director”, in relation to a firm, means a partner in the firm. 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> Protection of action taken in good 
    faith.—No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against 
    the Government or any officer of the Government for anything which is in 
    good faith done or intended to be done under this Act. 
  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> Power to give directions.—The 
    Central Government may give such directions to any State Government as may 
    appear to the Central Government to be necessary for carrying into execution 
    in the State any of the provisions of this Act or of any rule made 
    thereunder. 
  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> Exemption.—Nothing in this Act 
    shall apply to any seed of any notified kind or variety grown by a person 
    and sold or delivered by him on his own premises direct to another person 
    for being used by that person for the purpose of sowing or planting. 
  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>25</number> Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules 
    to carry out the purposes of this Act. 
 </section><section>
 <number>2</number> In particular and without prejudice to 
    the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   
    the functions of the Committee and the travelling and daily allowances 
    payable to members of the Committee and members of any sub-committee 
    appointed under sub-section (5) of section 3; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   
    the functions of the Central Seed Laboratory; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   
    the functions of a certification agency; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   
    the manner of marking or labelling the container of seed of any notified 
    kind or variety under clause (c) of section 7 and under clause (b) of 
    section 17; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   
    the requirements which may be complied with by a person carrying on the 
    business referred to in section 7;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   
    the form of application for the grant of a certificate under section 9, the 
    particulars it may contain, the fees which should accompany it, the form of 
    the certificate and the conditions subject to which the certificate may be 
    granted;
 </subsection><subsection>
<footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[<number>ff</number>   
    the standards to which seeds should conform;]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>   
    the form and manner in which and the fee on payment of which an appeal may 
    be preferred under section 11 and the procedure to be followed by the 
    appellate authority in disposing of the appeal; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>   
    the qualifications and duties of Seed Analysts and Seed Inspectors; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>   
    the manner in which samples may be taken by the Seed Inspector, the 
    procedure for sending such samples to the Seed Analyst or the Central Seed 
    Laboratory and the manner of analysing such samples;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>   
    the form of report of the result of the analysis under sub-section (1) or 
    sub-section (2) of section 16 and the fees payable in respect of such 
    report under the said sub-section (2); 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>   
    the records to be maintained by a person carrying on the business referred 
    to in section 7 and the particulars which such records shall contain; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>   
    any other matter which is to be or may be prescribed. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Every rule made under this Act shall be 
    laid as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament 
    while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be 
    comprised in one session or <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[in two or more successive sessions, 
    and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session 
    or the successive sessions aforesaid] both Houses agree in making any 
    modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be 
    made, that rule shall, thereafter have effect only in such modified form or 
    be of no effect, as the case may be; so however, that any such modification 
    or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
    previously done under that rule.
  





  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>  Sections 1 to 6, 8 to 11, 18, 22 to 25 came into force throughout India 
    on 2-9-1986, vide S.O. 3122, published in the Gazette of India, 
    Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3 (ii), dated 2nd September, 1968.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Ins. by Act 55 of 1972, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 16-1-1973).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   Ins. by Act 55 of 1972, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 16-1-1973).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   Ins. by Act 55 of 1972, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 16-1-1973).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>   Ins. by Act 55 of 1972, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 16-1-1973).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>   Ins. by Act 55 of 1972, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 16-1-1973).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>   Ins. by Act 55 of 1972, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 16-1-1973).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>   Subs. by Act 55 of 1972, sec. 4, for certain words (w.e.f. 
    16-1-1973).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>   Ins. by Act 55 of 1972, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 16-1-1973).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>   Ins. by Act 55 of 1972, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 16-1-1973).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>   Subs. by Act 55 of 1972, sec. 5, for certain words (w.e.f. 
    16-1-1973).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>