<act><title>

The 
    Suits Valuation Act, 1887</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Title and extent.—This 
    Act may be called the Suits Valuation Act, 1887 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[and 
    it extends to the whole of India except the territories which, immediately 
    before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised in Part B States].
  
 

State Amendments
 <section>
<number>Gujarat</number>—(i) Section 1, 
    shall be renumbered as sub-section (1) thereof;
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> after sub-section (1) so 
    renumbered, insert the following:—
 
            “(2) This Act as in 
    force in the Bombay area and Kutch area of the State of Gujarat immediately 
    before the commencement of the Suits Valuation (Gujarat Extension and 
    Amendment) Act, 1964 shall also extend to the Saurashtra Area of the State 
    of Gujarat.”
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number> For marginal note, 
    substitute “Title and extent to State of Gujarat.”
 
[Vide Gujarat Act 31 of 
    1964, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 1-5-1966).]
  
 
Madhya Pradesh.—In 
    section 1, after the words “Part B States” add the words “other than the 
    Madhya Bharat and Sironj regions of the State of Madhya Pradesh”. 

 
[Vide Madhya Pradesh Act 
    23 of 1958. sec. 3(1) and Sch., Part A.]
  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—In section 
    1, after the words “comprised in Part B States” insert the words 
    “other than the Hyderabad area of the State of Maharashtra.” 
 
[Vide Maharashtra Act 4 
    of 1960, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-11-1960)].
 
 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Extent and Commencement of Part I.—This 
    Part shall extend to such local areas, and come into force therein on such 
    dates, as the
    <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[State 
    Government], by notification in the Official Gazette directs.<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>
  
 

State Amendments
 <section>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—For section 
    2, substitute the following, namely:—
 
       “2. Commencement of 
    sections 3 to 5.—On the date of commencement of the Suits Valuation (Maharashtra 
    Extension and Amendment) Act, 1960, sections 3 to 5 (both inclusive) shall 
    cease to be in force throughout the State of Maharashtra but the State 
    Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, bring the said 
    sections into force in the whole of the State or any local area, from such 
    date as may be specified in such notification.” 
 
[Vide Maharashtra Act 4 
    of 1960, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 1-11-1960).]
  
 
Punjab: Haryana: Chandigarh (U.T.).—The 
    heading “suits relating to land” of Part I was omitted.
 
[Vide Punjab Act 13 of 
    1942, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 22-11-1942).]
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Power for State Government to make rules determining value of land for 
    jurisdictional purposes.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[State Government] may <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[***] make rules for 
    determining the value of land for purposes of jurisdiction in the suits 
    mentioned in the Court-fees Act, 1870 (7 of 1870), section 7, paragraphs
    v and
    vi and paragraph
    x, clause (d).
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The rules 
    may determine the value of any class of land, or of any interest in land, in 
    the whole or any part of a local area, and may prescribe different values 
    for different places within the same local area.  
  
 

state amendments
 <subsection>
<number>Gujarat</number>—In section 3(1), 
    for words, figures etc., “the Court-fees Act, 1870, section 7, paragraphs 
    (V) and (VI) and paragraph (X), clause (d) substitute the words “clause (d) 
    of paragraph (iv), paragraphs 
    (v), (vi) 
    and (vii) and clause (d) of 
    paragraph (xi), in section 6 
    of the Bombay Court-fee Act, 1959,”
 
[Vide Gujarat Act 31 of 
    1964, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-5-1966).]
  
 
Himachal Pradesh.—In 
    section 3(1) for the words and figures “the Court-fees
    act, 1870”, substitute the 
    words and figures “Himachal Pradesh Court-fees Act, 1968”. 
 
[Vide Himachal Pradesh 
    Act 30 of 1969, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 2-6-1970).]
  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—In section 3 
    for “the Court-fees Act, 1870, section 7, paragraphs (V) and (VI) and 
    paragraph (X), clause (d)” substitute “paragraphs (v) 
    and (vi) and clause (d) of 
    paragraph (xi) in section 6 of the Bombay Court-fees Act, 1959.”
 
[Vide Maharashtra Act 4 
    of 1960, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-11-1960).]
  
 
Uttar Pradesh.—(a) After 
    the figure “1870” the words “as in force for the time being in United 
    Provinces” were inserted.
 <subsubsection>
<number>b</number>   For the words and figures 
    “and VI and paragraph X, clause (d)” the figures and letters “VA and VB” 
    were substituted.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>c</number>    For the full stop at the 
    end a colon was substituted and the following was added as a fresh 
    paragraph, viz:—
 
                        
    “Provided that such rules shall provide that the value of land for the 
    purposes of jurisdiction shall in no case be less than the value as 
    determinable for the computation of Court-fees.”
 
[Vide Uttar Pradesh Act 7 
    of 1939, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 16-7-1939).]
  







 



</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Valuation of relief in certain suits relating to land not to exceed the 
    value of the land.—Where a suit 
    mentioned in the Court-fees Act, 1870 (7 of 1870), section 7, paragraph
    iv, or Schedule II,
    article 17, relates to land 
    or an interest in land of which the value has been determined by rules under 
    the last foregoing section, the amount at which for purposes of jurisdiction 
    the relief sought in the suit is valued shall not exceed the value of the 
    land or interest as determined by those rules.
  
 

state amendments
 <section>
<number>Gujarat</number>—In section 4 
    amendment is the same, except for omission of “(d)” and paragraph
    vii as in Maharashtra.
 
[Vide Gujarat Act 31 of 
    1964, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 1-5-1966).]
 
Himachal pradesh.—For the 
    expression, “the Court-fees Act, 1870, section 7, paragraph
    iv or Schedule II, Article 
    17,” substitute the words “the H.P. Court-fees Act, 1968, section 7, 
    paragraph iv, or Schedule II, 
    Article 13 or 18.”
 
[Vide Himachal Pradesh 
    Act 30 of 1969, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 6-2-1970).]
 </section><section>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—In section 4 
    for the words and figures “Court-fees Act, 1870, section 7, paragraphs
    iv or Schedule II, Article 
    17, “substitute the following, namely:—
 
          “Clause 
    (c),(d),(e),(g),(i), or (j) of paragraph
    iv or paragraph
    vii in section 6 or Article 
    3,5,6 or 7 in Schedule I or clause (f) of Article 23 in Schedule II to the 
    Bombay Court-fees Act, 1959.”
 
[Vide Maharashtra Act 4 
    of 1960, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 1-11-1960).]
 
Punjab: Haryana and 
    Chandigarh U.T.: Delhi.—After the word and figures “Article 17” the word 
    and figures “or 22” were inserted.—
 
[Vide Punjab Act 1 of 
    1938, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 30-4-1938).
 
Uttar Pradesh.—For 
    section 4, the following section was substituted, viz.—
 </section></article><article>
         <number>4</number> 
    Valuation of certain suits for the purposes of jurisdiction.—Suits 
    mentioned in paragraphs IV
<section><number>a</number>, IVA, IVB, V, VA, VB, VI, VIA; VIII and X(d) 
    of section 7 and Arts. 17, 18 and 19 of Sch. II of the Court-fees Act, 1870, 
    as in force for the time being in the Uttar Pradesh, shall be valued for the 
    purposes of jurisdiction at the market value of the property involved in or 
    affected by or the title to which is affected by the relief sought, or at 
    the amount involved in or affected by or the title to which is affected by 
    the relief sought, and such value shall, in the case of land, be deemed to 
    be the value as determinable in accordance with the rules framed under 
    section 3.”
 
[Vide U.P. Act 7 of 1939, 
    sec.3 (w.e.f. 16-7-1939).]
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>5</number> Making and enforcement of rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[State 
    Government] shall, before making rules under section 3, consult the High 
    Court with respect thereto.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> A rule under that section shall not take 
    effect till the expiration of one month after the rule has been published in 
    the <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[Official Gazette].
 






 



</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Repeal of section 14 of the 
Madras Civil Courts Act, 1873. </title>—On and from the date on which rules 
under section 3 take effect in any part of the territories under the 
administration of the Governor of Fort Saint George in Council to which the 
Madras Civil Courts Act, 1873 (3 of 1873) extends, section 14 of that Act shall 
be repealed as regards that part of those territories. 
 <title>STATE AMENDMENTS </title>
 <section><title><number>Gujarat</number> </title>—Delete section 6. 
 [ Vide Gujarat Act 31 of 1964, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 
1-5-1966).] 
 </section><section><title><number>Maharashtra</number> </title>—Omit section 6. 
 [ Vide Maharashtra Act 4 of 1960, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 
1-11-1960).] </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>7</number> Commencement of Part II.—This 
    Part 

    1[***] 
    shall come into force on the 1st day of July, 1887. 
  
 

    State Amendments
 <section>
<number>Gujarat</number>—In section 7, 
    add the following proviso:—
 
           “Provided that, in the Saurashtra Area of the State of Gujarat, it shall 
    come into force on the date of the coming into force of the Suits Valuation 
    (Gujarat Extension and Amendment) Act, 1964.”
 
[Vide Gujarat Act 31 of 
    1964, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 1-5-1966).]
  
 
Madhya Pradesh.—In 
    section 7, re-number section 7 as sub-section (1) thereof and after 
    sub-section (1) as so renumbered insert the following sub-section (2), 
    namely:— 
 
           “(2) 
    This Part shall be in force in the Madhya Bharat and Sironj regions of the 
    State of Madhya Pradesh from the commencement of the Madhya Pradesh 
    Extension of Laws Act, 1958 (23 of 1958).”
 
[Vide M.P. Act 23 of 
    1958, sec. 3(1) and Schedule, Part A.]
  
 </section><section>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—In section 7 
    add the following Proviso:—
 
           “Provided that, in the Hyderabad area of the State of Maharashtra it shall 
    come into force on the date of commencement of the Suits Valuation (Maharashtra 
    Extension and Amendment) Act, 1960.”
 
[Vide Maharastra Act 4 of 
    1960, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-11-1960).]
  
 
Punjab: Haryana:Chandigarh 
    U.T.—In Part II the heading “Other Suits” was omitted.—
 
[Vide Punjab Act 13 of 
    1942, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 22-11-1942).]
 
 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Court-fee value and jurisdictional value to be the same in certain suits.—Where 
    in suits other than those referred to in the Court-fees Act, 1870 (7 of 
    1870), section 7, paragraphs v, vi
    and ix, and paragraph
    x, clause (d),
    court-fees are payable ad 
    valorem under the Court-fees Act, 1870 (7 of 1870), the value as 
    determinable for the computation of 
    court-fees and the value for purposes of jurisdiction shall be the 
    same.  
  
 

state amendments
 <section>
<number>Gujarat</number>—In section 8, 
    for “the Court-fees Act, 1870, section 7, paragraphs 
    v, vi and ix and paragraph x, clause (d), Court-fees are payable 
    ad valorem, under Court-fees Act, 1870,” substitute the words “clause 
    (d) of paragraph iv, 
    paragraphs v, vi, vii and
    x and clause (d) of paragraph 
    (xi) in section 6 of Bombay Court-fees Act 1959, Court-fees are payable 
    under the Bombay Court-fees Act, 1959.”
 
[Vide Gujarat Act 31 of 
    1964, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 1-5-1966).]
  
 
Himachal Pradesh.—In 
    section 8, for the words “the Court-fees Act, 1870,” wherever they occur, 
    substitute the words “the Himachal Pradesh Court-fees Act, 1968.”—
 
[Vide Himachal Pradesh 
    Act 30 of 1969, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 6-2-1970).]
  
 </section><section>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—In section 
    8, for “the Court-fees Act, 1870, section 7, paragraphs
    v, vi and
    ix, and paragraph
    x, clause (d), Court-fees are 
    payable ad valorem under the Court-fees Act, 1870” substitute the 
    following, namely:—
 
                        
    “Paragraphs v,
vi and
    x and clause (d) of paragraph
    xi in section 6 of the Bombay 
    Court-fees Act, 1959, Court-fees are payable ad valorem under the 
    Bombay Court-fees Act, 1959.”
 
[Vide Maharashtra Act 4 
    of 1960, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 1-11-1960).]
  
 
Uttar Pradesh.—For the 
    words and figures “the Court-fees Act, 1870, section 7, paragraphs V, VI and 
    IX and paragraph X, clause (d),” the word and figure “section 4” were 
    substituted; and after the figures and comma “1870,” occurring for the 
    second time, the words “as in force for the time being in the Uttar Pradesh” 
    were added.
 
[Vide Uttar Pradesh Act 7 
    of 1939, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 16-7-1939).]
  







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Determination of value of certain suits by High Court.—When 
    the subject-matter of suits of any class, other than suits mentioned in the 
    Court-fees Act, 1870 (7 of 1870), section 7, paragraphs
    v and
    vi, and paragraph
    x, clause (d), is such that 
    in the opinion of the High Court it does not admit of being satisfactorily 
    valued, the High Court may with the previous sanction of the State 
    Government, direct that suits of that class shall, for the purposes of the 
    Court-fees Act, 1870 (7 of 1870), and of this Act and any other enactment 
    for the time being in force, be treated as if their subject-matter were of 
    such value as the High Court thinks fit to specify in this behalf.  
  
 

state amendment
 <section>
<number>Gujarat</number>—(i) In its 
    application to the Bombay area, Kutch area and Saurashtra area of the State 
    of Gujarat, in section 9 omit the words and figures “of the
    court-fees Act, 1870, and.”—
 
[Vide Bombay Act of 36 of 
    1959, sec. 50 and Schedule V (w.e.f. 1-8-1959).]
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> In section 9, for the words 
    and figures “the Court-fees Act, 1870, section 7, paragraphs
    v and
    vi, and paragraph
    x, clause (d),” substitute 
    “clause (d) of paragraph iv, 
    paragraphs v,
    vi and
    vii and clause (d) of 
    paragraph xi in section 6 of 
    the Bombay Court-fees Act,1959.”
 
[Vide Gujarat Act 31 of 
    1964, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-5-1966).]
 
Himachal Pradesh.—In 
    section 9, for the words and figures “the Court-fees Act, 1870” wherever 
    occurring, substitute the words and figures “the Himachal Pradesh Court-fees 
    Act, 1968.”—
 
[Vide Himachal Pradesh 
    Act 30 of 1969, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 6-2-1970).]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—For section 
    9 following section shall be substituted and deemed always to have been so:
 
              “9. 
    Value of certain suits to be three hundred rupees.—Where the 
    subject-matter of suits other than suits mentioned in the Court-fees Act, 
    1870, section 7, paragraphs v 
    and vi, paragraph
    x, clause (d), or in any 
    corresponding provision of the Court-fees Act, for the time being in force 
    in any area in the State, is such that it does not admit of being 
    satisfactorily valued, then such suits shall, for the purpose of this
    act, and if the High Court 
    with the previous sanction of the State Government, so directs also for the 
    purposes of any other enactment for the time being in force specified in 
    that behalf by the High Court, be treated as if their subject-matter is of 
    the value of three hundred rupees; and the provisions of the last preceding 
    section shall apply as if the Court-fees therein are payable ad valorem 
    under the relevant Court-fees Act.
 
[Vide Maharashtra Act 9 
    of 1970, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 16-3-1970).]
 
Uttar Pradesh.—For the 
    words and figures “the Court-fees Act, 1870, section 7, paragraphs V and VI 
    and paragraph X, clause (d)” the words and figures “section 4 or 8” were 
    substituted.—
 
[Vide Uttar Pradesh Act 7 
    of 1939, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 16-7-1939).]
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>10</number> Repeal of section 32, Punjab Courts Act, 
      1884 (18 of 1884).—[Repealed 
      by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1891 (12 of 1891), sec. 2 and Sch. 1, 
      Part I.]
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>10</number> Repeal of section 32, Punjab Courts Act, 
      1884 (18 of 1884).—[Repealed 
      by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1891 (12 of 1891), sec. 2 and Sch. 1, 
      Part I.]
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Procedure where objection is taken on appeal on revision that a suit or 
    appeal was not properly valued for jurisdictional purposes.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything in 

    1section 578 of the 
    Code of Civil Procedure (14 of 1882), an objection that by reason of the 
    over-valuation or under-valuation of a suit or appeal a Court of first 
    instance or lower Appellate Court which had no jurisdiction with respect to 
    the suit or appeal exercise jurisdiction with respect thereto shall not be 
    entertained by an Appellate Court unless—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the objection was taken in the Court of 
    first instance at or before the hearing at which issues were first framed 
    and recorded, or in the lower Appellate Court in the memorandum of appeal to 
    that Court, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the Appellate Court is satisfied, for 
    reasons to be recorded by it in writing, that the suit or appeal was 
    over-valued or under-valued, and that the over-valuation or under-valuation 
    thereof has prejudicially affected the disposal of the suit or appeal on its 
    merits.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If the 
    objection was taken in the manner mentioned in clause (a) of sub-section 
    (1), but the Appellate Court is not satisfied as to both the matters 
    mentioned in clause (b) of that sub-section and has before it the materials 
    necessary for the determination of the other grounds of appeal to itself, it 
    shall dispose of the appeals as if there had been no defect of jurisdiction 
    in the Court of first instance or lower Appellate Court.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If the 
    objection was taken in that manner and the Appellate Court is satisfied as 
    to both those matters and has not those materials before it, it shall 
    proceed to deal with the appeal under the rules applicable to the Court with 
    respect to the hearing of appeals; but if it remands the suit or appeal, or 
    frames and refers issues for trial, or requires additional evidence to be 
    taken, it shall direct its order to a Court competent to entertain the suit 
    or appeal.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    provisions of the section with respect to an Appellate Court shall, so far 
    as they can be made applicable, apply to a Court exercising revisional 
    jurisdiction under <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>section 622 of the Code of Civil Procedure 
    (14 of 1882) or other enactment for the time being in force.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> This 
    section <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[***] shall come into force on the first day of July, 
    1887.
  
 

state amendments
 <subsection>
<number>Gujarat</number>—In section 11.—
 <subsubsection>
           <number>i</number>  in sub-section 
    (1), for the words and figures “section 578 of the Code of Civil Procedure” 
    substitute “section 99 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908.”
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           <number>ii</number>  in 
    sub-section (4), for the words and figures “section 622 of the Code of Civil 
    Procedure” substitute the words “section 115 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 
    1908;”—and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           <number>iii</number>  to 
    sub-section (5) add the following proviso, namely:—
 
           “Provided that in the saurashtra 
    Area of the State of Gujarat, it shall come into force on the date of the 
    coming into force of the suits 
    Valuation (Gujarat Extension and Amendment) Act, 1964.”
 
[Vide Gujarat Act 31 of 
    1964, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 1-5-1966).]
  
 
Himachal Pradesh.—To 
    section 11 (1), add the following proviso:—
 
           “Provided that in a 
    suit for accounts, the value for the purposes of jurisdiction as determined 
    by the Court at any stage of the trial shall be final and conclusive and 
    shall not be liable to be contested in appeal or revision.”
 
[Vide H.P. Act 30 of 
    1969, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 6-2-1970).]
  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—In section 
    11—
 <subsubsection>
           <number>i</number>  in sub-section 
    (1) for the words and figures “section 578 of the Code of Civil Procedure” 
    substitute “section 99 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908;”
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           <number>ii</number>  in 
    sub-section (4) for the words and figures “section 622 of the Code of Civil 
    Procedure” substitute “section 115 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908;”
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           <number>iii</number>  to 
    sub-section (5), add the following proviso, namely:—
 
           “Provided 
    that, in the Hyderabad area of the State of Maharashtra it shall come into 
    force on the date of commencement of the Suits Valuation (Maharashtra 
    Extension and Amendment) Act, 1960.
 
[Vide Maharashtra Act 4 
    of 1960. sec. 11 (w.e.f. 1-11-1960).] 
  
 
Punjab: Haryana: Chandigarh.—The 
    heading of Part III “Supplemental Provisions” was omitted.
 
To sub-section (1) the following 
    Proviso was added:—
 
           “Provided that in a 
    suit for accounts the value for purposes of jurisdiction as determined by 
    the Court at any stage of the trial shall be final and conclusive and shall 
    not be liable to be contested in appeal or revision.”
 
[Vide Punjab Act 13 of 
    1942, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 22-11-1942).]
  











 



</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Proceedings pending at commencement of Part I or II.—Nothing 
    in Part I or Part II shall be construed to affect the jurisdiction of any 
    Court—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    with respect to any suit instituted 
    before rules under Part I applicable to the valuation of the suit take 
    effect, or Part II has come into force; as the case may be, or  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    with respect to any appeal arising out 
    of any such suit.  

 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Added by the adaptation 
    of Laws (No. 2) Order, 1956.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Subs. by Adaptation of Laws (No.2) Order, 1956, for “Government of a 
    Part A State or a Part C State”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   
    Part I of the Act has been declared to extend to the Punjab and to come into 
    force therein on the 1st day of March, 1889, see Gazette of India, 
    1889, Part I, page 107.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   
    Subs. by the Adaptation of Law Order, 1950, for “Provincial Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>   
    The words “subject to the control of the Governor General in Council” 
    omitted by Government of India (Adaptation of Indian Laws) Order, 1937.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>   Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws Order, 1950, for “Provincial 
    Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>   Subs. by the Government of India (Adaptation of Indian Laws) 
    Order, 1937.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>   The words “extends to the whole of India except
    part B States, and” omitted 
    by the Adaptation of laws 
    (No. 2) Order, 1956.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>   See now section 99 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (Act 5 
    of 1908).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>   See now section 115 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (Act 
    5 of 1908).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>   The words “extends to the whole of India except Part B States and” 
    omitted by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, 1956.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>