<act> 
 THE SUPREME COURT RULES, 1966
  
 
PART III
 Original Jurisdiction
 ORDER XXII
 PARTIES TO SUITS
 <article><number>1</number> Two or more plaintiffs may 
join in one suit in whom any right to relief in respect of or arising out of the 
same act or transaction or series of acts or transactions is alleged to exist.
 </article><article><number>2</number> Two or more defendants may be 
joined in one suit against whom any right to relief in respect of or arising out 
of the same act or transaction or series of acts or transactions is alleged to 
exist.
 </article><article><number>3</number> 
<section><number>1</number> The Court may at any such 
stage of the proceedings, either upon or without the application of either 
party, and on such terms as may appear to the Court to be just, order that the 
name of any plaintiff or defendant improperly joined be struck out, and that the 
name of any plaintiff or defendant who ought to have been joined, or whose 
presence before the Court may be necessary in order to enable the Court 
effectually and completely to adjudicate upon and settle all the questions 
involved in the suit, be added.
 </section><section><number>2</number> No person shall be added as 
a plaintiff without his consent.
 </section></article><article><number>4</number> Where it appears to the Court 
that any cause of action joined in one suit cannot conveniently be tried or 
disposed of together the Court may order separate trials or make such other 
order as may be expedient.
 </article><article><number>5</number> Where it appears to the Court 
that any joinder of plaintiffs or defendants may embarrass or delay the trial of 
the suit, the Court may order separate trials or make such order as may be 
expedient.
 ORDER XXIII
 PLAINTS
 <section><number>1</number> Every suit shall be 
instituted by the presentation of a plaint.
 </section><section><number>2</number> A plaint shall be presented 
to the Registrar, and all plaints shall be registered and numbered by him 
according to the order in which they are presented.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every plaint shall comply 
with the rules contained in Order XXVI of these rules so far as they are 
applicable.
 </section><section><number>4</number> A plaint shall contain the 
following particulars:—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  the names of the plaintiff and of the defendant;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  the facts constituting the cause of action and 
when it arose;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  the facts showing that the Court has 
jurisdiction;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  the declaration or relief which the plaintiff 
claims.
 </subsection></section></article><article><number>5</number> The plaintiff shall endorse 
on the plaint, or annex hereto a list of the documents (if any) which he has 
produced along with it and the Registrar shall sign the list if on examination 
he finds it to be correct.
 </article><article><number>6</number> The plaint shall be 
rejected:—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  where it does not disclose a cause of action.
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  where the suit appears from the statement in the 
plaint to be barred by any law.
 </section></article><article><number>7</number> Where a plaint is rejected 
the Court shall record an order to that effect with the reasons for the order.
 </article><article><number>8</number> The rejection of the plaint 
shall not of itself preclude the plaintiff from presenting a fresh plaint in 
respect of the same cause of action.
 </article><article><number>9</number> Where a plaintiff sues upon a 
document in his possession or power, he shall produce it to the Registrar when 
the plaint is presented and shall at the same time deliver the document or a 
copy thereof to be filed with the plaint.
 </article><article><number>10</number> Where the plaintiff relies 
on any other documents (whether in his possession or power or not) as evidence 
in support of his claim, he shall enter such documents in a list to be added or 
annexed to the plaint.
 </article><article><number>11</number> Where any such document is 
not in the possession or power of the plaintiff, he shall, if possible, state in 
whose possession or power it is.
 </article><article><number>12</number> A document which ought to be 
produced in Court by the plaintiff when the plaint is presented, or to be 
entered in the list to be added or annexed to the plaint, and which is not 
produced or entered accordingly, shall not without the leave to the Court, be 
received in evidence at the hearing of the suit.
 ORDER XXIV
 ISSUE AND SERVICE OF SUMMONS
 <section><number>1</number> When a suit has been duly 
instituted a summons shall be issued to the defendant to appear and answer the 
claim.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every summons shall be signed 
by the Registrar, and shall be sealed with the seal of the Court.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every summons shall be 
accompanied by a copy of the plaint.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The summons shall be served 
by being sent by registered post to the Attorney- General for India or the 
Advocate-General for the State, as the case may be, or to an advocate on record 
of the defendant empowered to accept service.
 </section><section><number>5</number> There shall be endorsed on 
every summons a notice requiring the defendant to enter an appearance within 
twenty-eight days after the summons has been served.
 </section><section><number>6</number> A defendant shall enter the 
appearance by filing in the Registry a memorandum in writing containing the name 
and place of business of his advocate on record if any, and in default of 
appearance being entered within the time mentioned in the summons, or as 
hereinafter provided, the suit may be heard ex parte.
 </section><section><number>7</number> The defendant shall forthwith 
give notice of his having entered an appearance to the plaintiff.
 </section><section><number>8</number> The plaintiff shall within 
fourteen days after the defendant has entered an appearance take out a summons 
for directions returnable before the Judge in Chambers, and the Judge shall on 
the hearing of the summons give such direction with respect to pleadings, 
interrogatories, the admission of documents and facts, the discovery, inspection 
and production of documents and such other interlocutory matters as he may think 
expedient.
 ORDER XXV
 WRITTEN STATEMENT, SET-OFF AND COUNTER-CLAIM
 </section><section><number>1</number> It shall not be sufficient 
for a defendant in his written statement to deny generally the facts alleged by 
the plaintiff but he shall deal specifically with each allegation of fact of 
which he does not admit the truth, except damage.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where a defendant denies an 
allegation of fact he shall not do so evasively but shall answer the point of 
substance.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Each allegation of fact in 
the plaint, if not denied specifically or by necessary implication, or not 
expressly stated to be not admitted in the pleading of the defendant, shall be 
taken to be admitted, but the Court may in its discretion require any fact so 
admitted to be proved otherwise than by such admission.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Where the defendant claims to 
set-off against a demand by the plaintiff any ascertained sum of money, he may 
in his written statement, but not afterwards without the leave of the Court, 
state the grounds of his claim and the particulars of the debt sought to be 
set-off.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The written statement 
containing the particulars mentioned in rule 4 of this order shall have the same 
effect as a plaint in a cross suit so as to enable the Court to pronounce a 
final judgment in respect both of the original claim and of set-off.
 </section><section><number>6</number> The rules relating to a 
written statement by a defendant shall apply to a written statement by a 
plaintiff in answer to a claim of set-off.
 </section><section><number>7</number> No pleading subsequent to the 
written statement of a defendant other than by way of defence to a set-off shall 
be presented except by the leave of the Court and upon such terms as the Court 
may think fit, but the Court may at any time require a written statement or 
additional written statement from any of the parties and may fix a time for 
presenting the same.
 </section><section><number>8</number> Where any party from whom a 
written statement is so required fails to present the same within the time fixed 
by the Court, the Court may pronounce judgment against him or make such orders 
in relation to the suit as it thinks fit.
 </section><section><number>9</number> The defendant, in addition to 
his right of pleading a set-off may set up by way of counter-claim against the 
claims of the plaintiff any right or claim in respect of a cause of action 
accruing to him either before or after the filing of the suit but before he has 
delivered his defence and before the time limited for delivering his defence has 
expired whether that counter-claim sounds in damages or not, and the 
counter-claim shall have the same effect as a cross-suit, so as to enable the 
Court to pronounce a final judgment in the same suit, both on the original claim 
and on the counter-claim.
 </section><section><number>10</number> The Court may if in its 
opinion the counter-claim cannot be disposed of in the pending suit or ought not 
to be allowed, refuse permission to the defendant to avail himself thereof, and 
require him to file a separate suit.
 ORDER XXVI
 PLEADINGS GENERALLY
 </section><section><number>1</number> In this Order ‘pleading’ 
means plaint or written statement.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every pleading shall contain, 
and contain only, a statement in a concise form of the material facts on which 
the party pleading relief, but not the evidence by which those facts are to be 
proved, nor any argumentative matter, and shall be divided into paragraphs 
numbered consecutively.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Dates, sums and numbers shall 
be expressed in figures.
 </section><section><number>4</number> A further and better 
statement of the nature of the claim or defence, or further and better 
particulars of any matter stated in any pleading may in all cases be ordered, 
upon such terms as to costs and otherwise, as may be just.
 </section><section><number>5</number> Wherever the contents of any 
document are material, it shall be sufficient to state the effect thereof as 
briefly as possible, without setting out the whole or any part thereof, unless 
the precise words of the document or any part thereof are material.
 </section><section><number>6</number> Every pleading shall be 
signed by an advocate on record on behalf of the Attorney-General for India or 
by an advocate on record on behalf of the Advocate-General for the State, as the 
case may be.
 </section><section><number>7</number> The Court may at any stage of 
the proceeding order to be struck out or amended any matter in any pleading 
which may be unnecessary or scandalous or which may tend to prejudice or 
embarrass or delay the trial of the suit, or which contravenes any of the 
provisions of this Order.
 </section><section><number>8</number> The Court may, at any stage 
of the proceedings, allow either party to amend his pleading in such manner and 
on such terms as may be just, but only such amendments shall be made as may be 
necessary for the purpose of determining the real question in controversy 
between the parties.
 </section><section><number>9</number> If a party who has obtained 
an order for leave to amend does not amend accordingly within the time limited 
for that purpose by the order, or if no time is thereby limited then within 
fourteen days from the date of the order, he shall not be permitted to amend 
after the expiration of such limited time or of such fourteen days, as the case 
may be unless the time is extended by the Court.
 </section><section><number>10</number> Amendments of pleadings made 
only for the purpose of rectifying a clerical error may be made on an order of 
the Registrar without notice, but unless otherwise ordered a copy of the order 
shall be served on all other parties.
 ORDER XXVII
 DISCOVERY AND INSPECTION
 </section><section><number>1</number> Order XI of the First 
Schedule to the Code except rules 5 and 23 of that order, shall apply with 
respect to discovery and inspection in suits instituted before the Court.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where the Court has made an 
order allowing one party to deliver interrogatories to the other, those 
interrogatories shall be answered by such persons as the Court may direct.
 </section><section><number>3</number> No application for leave to 
deliver interrogatories shall be made by the defendant until he has filed his 
written statement.
 </section><section><number>4</number> After an order has been made 
for the delivery of interrogatories one set of the interrogatories, as allowed 
shall be annexed and served with the order upon the person to be interrogated.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Court may, for sufficient 
reason, allow any affidavit to be sworn, on behalf of the party from whom 
discovery, production or inspection is sought, by any person competent to make 
the same.
 </section><section><number>6</number> Where any document is ordered 
to be deposited in Court a copy of the order and a schedule of the document 
shall be left in the Registry at the time when the deposit is made.
 </section><section><number>7</number> When the purpose for which 
any documents have been deposited in Court is satisfied, the party by whom they 
were deposited may, pending the suit, have them delivered out to him, if he has 
the consent in writing of the other party, or an order of the Court.
 ORDER XXVIII
 ADMISSIONS
 Order XII in the First Schedule 
to the Code with respect to admissions shall apply in suits instituted before 
the Court.
 ORDER XXIX
 SUMMONING AND ATTENDANCE OF WITNESSES
 </section><section><number>1</number> The provisions of sections 28 
and 32 of the Code shall apply to summons to give evidence or to produce 
documents under these rules.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Order XVI in the First 
Schedule to the Code with respect to the summoning and attendance of witnesses 
shall apply, with the exception of the proviso to sub-rule (3) of rule 10, and 
the words ‘(a) within the local limits of the Court’s ordinary original 
jurisdiction, or (b) without such limits but’ in rule 19.
 ORDER XXX
 ADJOURNMENTS
 In suits instituted before the 
Court, Order XVII in the First Schedule to the Code with respect to adjournments 
shall, apply, with the substitution in rule 2 of the words ‘in such manner as it 
thinks just’ for the words ‘in one of the modes directed in that behalf by Order 
IX or make such other order as it thinks fit’.
 ORDER XXXI
 HEARING OF THE SUIT
 </section><section><number>1</number> Rules 1, 2, 3, 16, 17 and 18 
of Order XVIII in the First Schedule to the Code with respect to the hearing of 
suits and examination of witnesses shall apply in suits instituted before the 
Court.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Witnesses in attendance shall 
be examined orally in open Court and their evidence taken down in shorthand in 
the form of question and answer by such officers of the Court as may be 
appointed for the purpose.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The transcript of the 
shorthand note shall be signed by the officer recording the note and shall be 
deemed the deposition of the witness and shall form part of the record.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The party to any suit or 
matter in which the evidence has been taken in shorthand, and the witness whose 
evidence has been taken, shall be entitled upon payment of the prescribed fee to 
be furnished with a certified copy of the handscript.
 ORDER XXXII
 WITHDRAWAL AND ADJUSTMENT OF SUITS
 </section><section><number>1</number> Rules 1, 2 and 3 of Order 
XXXIII in the First Schedule to the code with respect to the withdrawal and 
adjustment of suits shall apply in suits instituted before the Court.
 </section><section><number>2</number> No new suit shall be brought 
in respect of the same subject-matter until the terms or conditions, if any, 
imposed by the order permitting the withdrawal of a previous suit or giving 
leave to bring a new suit have been complied with.
 ORDER XXXIII
 PAYMENT INTO COURT
 Order XXXIV in the First 
Schedule to the Code with respect to payment into Court shall apply in suits 
instituted before the Court.
 ORDER XXXIV
 SPECIAL CASE
 Rules 1, 2 and 5 of Order XXXVI 
in the First Schedule to the Code with respect to procedure by way of special 
case shall apply in suits instituted before the Court, except the words—‘which 
would have jurisdiction to entertain a suit the amount or value of the 
subject-matter of which is the same as the amount or value of the subject-matter 
of the agreement’ in sub-rule (1) of rule 3, the words ‘claiming to be 
interested as plaintiff or plaintiffs’ to the end of sub-rule (2) of rule 3; and 
the words ‘and upon the judgment so pronounced a decree shall follow’ in 
sub-rule (2) of rule 5.
  
</section></article> 
 THE SUPREME COURT RULES, 1966
 

 
PART IV
 ORDER XXXV
 APPLICATIONS FOR ENFORCEMENT  
of FUNDAMENTAL RIGHTS
 (Article 32 of the 
Constitution)
 <article><number>1</number> 
<section><number>1</number> Every petition under 
article 32 of the Constitution shall be in writing and shall be heard by a 
Division Court of not less than five Judges provided that a petition which does 
not raise a substantial question of law as to the interpretation of the 
Constitution may be heard and decided by a Division Court of less than five 
Judges, and, during vacation, by the Vacation Judge sitting singly.
 </section><section><number>2</number> All interlocutory and 
miscellaneous applications connected with a petition under article 32 of the 
Constitution, may be heard and decided by a Division Court of less than five 
Judges, and, during vacation, by the Vacation Judge sitting singly, 
notwithstanding that in the petition a substantial question of law as to the 
interpretation of the Constitution is raised.
 </section></article><article><number>2</number> No Court-fees shall be 
payable on petitions for habeas corpus or other petitions under article 
32 of the Constitution arising out of criminal proceedings, or in proceedings 
connected with such petitions.
 Habeas Corpus
 </article><article><number>3</number> A petition for a writ of 
habeas corpus shall be accompanied by an affidavit by the person restrained 
stating that the petition is made at his instance and setting out the nature and 
circumstances of the restraint:
 Provided that where the person 
restrained is unable owing to the restraint to make the affidavit, the petition 
shall be accompanied by an affidavit to the like effect made by some other 
person acquainted with the facts, which shall state the reason why the person 
restrained is unable to make the affidavit.
 The petition shall state whether 
the petitioner has moved the High Court concerned for similar relief and if so, 
with what result.
 </article><article><number>4</number> The petition shall be posted 
before the Court for preliminary hearing, and if the Court is of the opinion 
that a prima facie case for granting the petition is made out, rule 
nisi shall issue calling upon the person or persons against whom the order 
is sought, to appear on a day to be named therein to show cause why such order 
should not be made and at the same time to produce in Court the body of the 
person or persons alleged to be illegally or improperly detained then and there 
to be dealt with according to law.
 </article><article><number>5</number> On the return day of such 
rule or any day to which the hearing thereof may be adjourned, if no cause is 
shown or if cause is shown and disallowed, the Court shall pass an order that 
the person or persons improperly detained shall be set at liberty. If cause is 
shown and allowed, the rule shall be discharged. The order for release made by 
the Court, shall be a sufficient warrant to any gaoler, public official, or 
other person for the release of the person under restraint.
 </article><article><number>6</number> In disposing of any rule, the 
Court may in its discretion make such order for costs as it may consider just.
 Mandamus, Prohibition, Certiorari, 
Quo-Warranto  
and other directions or Orders
 </article><article><number>7</number> A petition for a direction, 
or order, or writ including writs in the nature of mandamus, prohibition,
quo-warranto or certiorari shall set out the name and description 
of the petitioner, the nature of the fundamental right infringed the relief, 
sought and the grounds on which it is sought and shall be accompanied by an 
affidavit verifying the facts relied on and at least 

1[seven] copies of the petition and 
affidavit shall be lodged in the Registry. The petition shall also state whether 
the petitioner has moved the High Court concerned for similar relief and, if so, 
with what result.
 </article><article><number>8</number> The petition shall be posted 
before the Court for preliminary hearing and orders as to the issue of notice to 
the respondent. Upon the hearing, the Court, if satisfied that no fundamental 
right guaranteed by the Constitution has been infringed or that the petition is 
otherwise untenable, shall dismiss the petition and if not so satisfied, shall 
direct a rule nisi to issue to the respondent calling upon him to show 
cause why the order sought should not be made, and shall adjourn the hearing for 
the respondent to appear and be heard.
 </article><article>

2[<number>8A</number> If the Court, on preliminary 
hearing, orders issue of show cause notice to the Respondent, he shall be 
entitled to file his objections within 30 days from the date of receipt of such 
notice or not later than 2 weeks before the date appointed for hearing, 
whichever be earlier.]
 </article><article><number>9</number> Upon making the order for a 
rule nisi, the Court may, if it thinks fit, grant such ad interim 
relief to the petitioner as the justice of the case may require, upon such terms 
if any as it may consider just and proper.
 </article><article>

3[<number>10</number> 
<section><number>1</number> Unless the Court otherwise 
orders, the rule nisi together with a copy of the petition and of the 
affidavit in support thereof shall be served on the respondent not less than 
twenty-one days before the returnable date. The rule shall be served on all 
persons directly affected and on such other persons as the Court may direct.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Affidavits in opposition 
shall be filed in the Registry not later than four days before the returnable 
date and affidavits in reply shall be filed within two days of the service of 
the affidavit in opposition.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Within four weeks of the 
filing of the pleadings, the petitioner shall file written brief prepared in the 
following manner, namely:—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  At the outset, the brief shall contain a short 
summary of the pleading essential for the decision of the points in issue. This 
shall ordinarily not exceed two pages;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  Thereafter, the petitioner shall formulate 
propositions of fact and law that are proposed to be advanced at the hearing 
citing under each of those propositions, authorities including text books, 
statutory provisions, regulations, ordinances or bye-laws or orders that are 
desired to be relied upon. In the case of decisions, reference shall be given to 
official reports, if available. In the case of text books reference shall, if 
possible, be given to the latest edition. Where any statute, regulation, rule or 
ordinance or bye-law is cited or relied upon, so much thereof as may be 
necessary for the decision of the points in issue shall be set out.
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number> Within four weeks of the 
service of the petitioner’s written brief on him, the contesting respondent 
shall file his written brief setting out briefly the grounds on the basis of 
which he is opposing each of the propositions formulated by the petitioner. 
Under each of those grounds he shall cite such authorities as he may seek to 
rely in the same manner as the petitioner is required to do under sub-rule (3). 
In his written brief, the respondent may raise objections as to the 
maintainability or sustainability of either the petition as a whole or any 
relief claimed therein in the form of propositions, supported by authorities in 
the manner mentioned earlier.
 </section><section><number>5</number> Within one week of the 
receipt of the brief filed by the respondent, the petitioner may submit his 
reply brief which shall be concise and to the point in respect of the points 
raised in the respondent’s brief.
 </section><section><number>6</number> Copies of affidavits and 
briefs required to be filed under this rule shall be served on the opposite 
party or parties and the affidavits or brief shall not be accepted in the 
Registry, unless they contain an endorsement of service signed by such party or 
parties. Every party to the proceeding shall supply to any other party on demand 
and on payment of the proper charges, copies of any affidavit or brief filed by 
him. At least seven copies of affidavits and briefs shall be lodged in the 
Registry.
 </section><section><number>7</number> If the Court considers any 
of the propositions formulated or grounds taken by any of the parties in the 
written briefs filed as being irrelevant of frivolous the Court may award 
against such party or parties such costs as the Court may consider fit.
 </section><section><number>8</number> At the hearing of rule 
nisi, except with the special permission of the Court, no party shall be 
allowed to advance any proposition or urge any ground not taken in the written 
briefs, nor shall be allowed to rely on any authorities (including provisions of 
statute, rule, bye-law, regulation or order) other than those mentioned in the 
briefs, unless such authorities or provisions have been published or made after 
the written briefs were filed into Court. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> At the hearing of rule 
nisi, if the Court is of the opinion that an opportunity be given to the 
parties to establish their respective cases by leading further evidence, the 
Court may take such evidence or cause such evidence to be taken in such manner 
as it may deem fit and proper.
 </section><section><number>10</number> No party to a petition 
under this rule shall be entitled to be heard by the Court unless he has 
previously lodged his written brief in the petition.
 </section></article><article><number>11</number> The provisions contained in 
rules 

4[1 to 10] respectively of Order XVIII 
relating to petitions shall, so far as may be applicable, apply to petitions 
under this Court.
 ORDER XXXVI
 APPLICATIONS FOR TRANSFER OF CRIMINAL PROCEEDING UNDER
5[SECTION 
406 OF THE CRIMINAL PROCEDURE
CODE, 1973] 6[AND 
SECTION 11 OF THE TERRORIST  
AFFECTED AREAS (SPECIAL COURTS) ACT, 1984.]
 <section><number>1</number> Every petition for transfer 
under 

5[section 406 of the Code of Criminal 
Procedure, 1973] 

6[or under section 11 of the Terrorist 
Affected Areas (Special Courts) Act, 1984] shall be in writing. It shall set out 
concisely in separate paragraphs the facts and particulars of the case, the 
relief sought and the grounds therefor and shall be supported by an affidavit or 
affirmation.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The petition shall be posted 
before the Court for preliminary hearing and orders as to issue of notice. Upon 
the hearing the Court, if satisfied that no prima facie case for transfer 
has been made out or that the petition is otherwise not tenable, shall dismiss 
the petition; and if upon such hearing the Court is satisfied that a prima 
facie case for granting the petition is made out, it shall direct that 
notice be issued to the respondent to show cause why the order sought for should 
not be made; 

7[[such notice shall be given to the 
accused person where he is not the applicant, to the respondent State and to 
such other parties interested as the Court may think fit to direct.]
 </section><section><number>3</number> The notice shall be served 
not less than twenty-one days before the date fixed for the final hearing of the 
petition. Affidavits in opposition shall be filed in the Registry not later than 
four days before the date appointed for hearing and the affidavit in reply shall 
be filed not later than 2 p.m. 
preceding the day of the hearing of the petition. Copies of affidavits in 
opposition and in reply shall be served on the opposite party or parties and the 
affidavits shall not be accepted in the Registry unless they contain an 
endorsement of service signed by such party or parties.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Where the petition is 
dismissed, the Court, if it is of opinion that the application was frivolous or 
vexatious, may order the applicant to pay by way of compensation to any person 
who has opposed the application such sum not exceeding one thousand rupees as it 
may consider proper in the circumstances of the case.
  








</section></article> 
 THE SUPREME COURT RULES, 1966
 

 
PART IVA
 

1[ORDER XXXVIA
 APPLICATIONS FOR TRANSFER UNDER CLAUSE (1) OF  
ARTICLE 139A (1) OF THE CONSTITUTION
 <article><number>1</number> Every application under 
Article 139A 
<section><number>1</number> of the Constitution shall be in writing. It shall set out 
concisely in separate paragraphs, the facts and particulars of the cases, 
pending before the Supreme Court and one or more High Courts or as the case may 
be, before two or more High Courts, the names and addresses of the parties, the 
questions of law involved and a statement that the same or substantially the 
same questions of law are involved in all the cases and that such questions are 
substantial questions of general importance. 

2[In the case of an application made by 
the Attorney-General no affidavit shall be necessary in support thereof but it 
shall be accompanied by a certificate of the advocate on record to the effect 
that such questions are substantial questions of general importance in terms of 
clause (1) of article 139A of the Constitution, and in the case of an 
application made by a party to a case it shall be accompanied by an affidavit in 
support thereof and also by a certificate as aforesaid.] The petition shall be 
made on a Court-fee stamp of the value of rupees ten.
 </section></article><article><number>2</number> The application shall be 
posted before the Court for preliminary hearing and orders as to issue of 
notice. If upon such hearing, the Court is satisfied that a prima facie 
case for granting the application is made out, it shall direct that notice be 
issued to the parties in the case concerned to show cause why the cases be not 
withdrawn. A copy of the order shall be transmitted to the High Courts concerned 
which shall report within four weeks the stages at which the concerned cases 
stand in the High Courts.
 </article><article><number>3</number> The notice shall be served 
through the High Court not less than six weeks before the date fixed for the 
final hearing of the application. Affidavits by the parties shall be filed in 
the Registry not later than two weeks before the date appointed for hearing and 
the affidavit in reply by the Attorney-General shall be filed not later than two 
days preceding the day of the hearing of the application. Copies of affidavits 
shall be served on the parties and the Attorney-General and the affidavits shall 
not be accepted in the Registry unless they contain an endorsement of service.
 </article><article><number>4</number> After hearing the 
Attorney-General and the parties, if the Court is satisfied that a case for 
granting the application has been made out, it shall require the High Court to 
transfer the case to this Court for its decision after it is ripe for hearing. 
The order will be transmitted to the High Court with utmost expedition.
 </article><article>

3[<number>5</number> 
<section><number>1</number> On transfer, the case shall be 
registered in the Court as Transferred Case.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Registrar of the High 
Court shall have the record of the transferred case prepared and printed in 
accordance with the First Schedule to the Rules and transmit, within six months 
from the date of the order of the transfer, twenty copies of the said printed 
record, one copy of which shall be duly authenticated by him.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where the Court has ordered 
the transfer of the case at the instance of a party, the record abovesaid shall 
be prepared at the cost of such party.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Where the Court has directed 
the transfer of the case upon the application by the Union of India or the State 
Government, the record abovesaid shall be prepared at the cost of the Government 
of India or the State concerned, as the case may be.
 </section><section><number>5</number> Where the Court has directed 
the transfer of a case on its own motion, the record shall be prepared in 
accordance with the Rules of the High Court or subject to the directions of the 
Court, if any, regarding the cost thereof:
 Provided, however, that where 
the record has been printed for the purpose of the case before the High Court 
and sufficient number of copies of the said printed record are available, the 
same shall be sent to the Court and no fresh printing of the record shall be 
necessary, except, however, such additional papers as may be required.
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Registrar of the High 
Court shall give notice to the parties to the transferred case regarding the 
transmission of the printed record to the Court simultaneously with such 
transmission of the printed record.
 </section><section><number>7</number> Where in a case, the Court 
directs that the original record be sent for and the case record, prepared in 
the Court, the record shall be prepared under the supervision of the Registrar 
of the Court, and in accordance with the provisions of rules 15 to 18 of Order 
XV and the First Schedule to the Rules, the cost of the preparation of the 
record being borne as per the sub-rules (3), (4) and (5) of rule 5 of this 
Order, and as soon as the index of the record is settled, the Registrar of the 
Court shall cause an estimate of the cost of the preparation of the record to be 
prepared and served upon the party who is to bear the cost as per the sub-rule 
abovesaid and require the said party to deposit the said amount of cost within 
30 days of the service of the estimate. The said party may deposit the amount of 
estimate in lump sum or in such instalments as the Registrar may prescribe.]
 </section></article><article><number>6</number> The parties shall enter 
appearance in this Court in the Transferred Cases within 30 days of the service 
on them of such notice of transmission of the record unless they have already 
entered their appearance at an earlier stage.
 </article><article><number>7</number> Within sixty days of the 
receipt of the said notice regarding the despatch of the record to this Court, 
the petitioner/appellant/plaintiff shall file his written brief prepared in the 
following manner, namely:—
 <section>       <number>1</number> At the outset the brief shall contain a short 
summary of the facts essential for the decision of the questions in issue.
 </section><section>       <number>2</number> Thereafter, it shall contain propositions of law 
that are proposed to be advanced at the hearing, citing under each of those 
propositions, authorities including text books, statutory provisions, 
regulations, rules or Ordinances or bye-laws or orders that are desired to be 
relied upon. In the case of decisions, reference shall be given to official 
reports, if available. In the case of text books reference shall, if possible, 
be given to the latest edition. Where any Statute, Regulation, Rule or Ordinance 
or bye-law is cited or relied upon so much thereof as may be necessary for the 
decision of the questions in issue shall be set out. A list of the dates of the 
relevant events leading upto and concerning the litigation, in chronological 
order shall also be given at the end of the brief.
 </section><section>       <number>3</number> Within four weeks of the service of the written 
brief, the respondent/defendant shall file his written brief setting out briefly 
the grounds on the basis of which he is opposing each of the propositions of the 
Petitioner/Appellant/Plaintiff. Under each of those grounds, he shall cite such 
authorities as he may seek to rely on in the same manner as is required under 
sub-rule (2).
 </section><section>       <number>4</number> Copies of the briefs shall be served by such 
parties on the Attorney-General for India, and the Advocate-General for the 
State, where necessary, and he may file his written brief within four weeks of 
such service.
 </section><section>       <number>5</number> Within one week of the receipt of the brief filed 
by the respondent/defendant/Attorney-General/Advocate-General, the 
petitioner/appellant/plaintiff may submit his reply brief which shall be concise 
and to the point.
 </section><section>       <number>6</number> Copies of the briefs required to be filed shall 
be served on the opposite party or parties and briefs shall not be accepted in 
the Registry unless they contain an endorsement of service signed by such party 
or parties. Every party to the proceeding shall supply to any other party, on 
demand and on payment of the proper charges, copies of any briefs filed by him. 
At least fifteen copies of the written briefs shall be lodged in the Registry.
 </section><section>       <number>7</number> At the hearing of the reference, except with the 
special permission of the Court, no party shall be allowed to advance any 
proposition or urge any ground not taken in the written briefs nor shall he be 
allowed to rely on any authorities (including provisions of statute, Ordinance, 
rule, bye-law, regulation or order) other than those mentioned in the briefs 
unless such authorities or provisions have been published or made after the 
written briefs were filed in Court.
 </section><section>       <number>8</number> No party to the Transferred Case shall be 
entitled to be heard by the Court unless he has previously lodged his written 
brief.
 </section></article><article><number>8</number> The Transferred Cases shall 
thereafter be listed for final hearing before the Court.
 </article><article><number>9</number> The Court may pass such 
orders as to costs as it may deem proper.
 </article><article><number>10</number> Save as otherwise provided 
by the rules contained in this Order, the provisions of other Orders shall, so 
far as may be, apply to a Transferred Case under this Order.]
 

4[ORDER XXXVIB
 APPLICATIONS FOR TRANSFER UNDER ARTICLE 139A(2)  
of THE CONSTITUTION AND SECTION 25 OF  
the CODE OF CIVIL PROCEDURE, 1908
 <section><number>1</number> Every petition under article 
139A(2) of the Constitution or section 25 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908, 
shall be in writing. It shall state succinctly and clearly all relevant facts 
and particulars of the case, the name of the High Court or other Civil Court in 
which the case is pending and the grounds on which the transfer is sought. The 
petition shall be supported by an affidavit.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The petition shall be made on 
a Court-fee stamp of the value of rupees ten.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The petition shall be posted 
before the Court for preliminary hearing and orders as to issue of notice. Upon 
such hearing the Court, if satisfied that no prima facie case for 
transfer has been made out, shall dismiss the petition and if upon such hearing 
the Court is satisfied that a prima facie case for granting the petition 
is made out, it shall direct that notice be issued to the parties in the case 
concerned to show cause why the case be not transferred. A copy of the Order 
shall be transmitted to the High Court concerned.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The notice shall be served 
not less than four weeks before the date fixed for the final hearing of the 
petition. Affidavits in opposition shall be filed in the Registry not later than 
one week before the date appointed for hearing and the affidavit in reply shall 
be filed not later than two days preceding the day of the hearing of the 
petition. Copies of affidavits in opposition and in reply shall be served on the 
opposite party or parties and the affidavits shall not be accepted in the 
Registry unless they contain an endorsement of service signed by such party or 
parties.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The petition shall thereafter 
be listed for final hearing before the Court.
 </section><section><number>6</number> Save as otherwise provided by 
the rules contained in this Order the provisions of other orders (including 
Order XLIII) shall, so far as may be, apply to petition under this Order.]
  





</section></article> 
 THE SUPREME COURT RULES, 1966
 

 
PART V
 ORDER XXXVII
 SPECIAL REFERENCE UNDER ARTICLE 143 
of THE CONSTITUTION
 <article><number>1</number> On the receipt by the 
Registrar of the Order of the President referring a question of law or fact to 
the Court under article 143 of the Constitution the Registrar shall give notice 
to the Attorney-General for India to appear before the Court on a day specified 
in the notice to take the directions of the Court as to the parties who shall be 
served with notice of such reference, and the Court may, if it considers it 
desirable, order that notice of such reference, shall be served upon such 
parties as may be named in the order.
 </article><article><number>2</number> Subject to the directions of 
the Court the notice shall require all such parties served therewith as desired 
to be heard at the hearing of the reference to attend before the Court on the 
day fixed by the order to take the directions of the Court with respect to 
statements of facts and arguments and with respect to the date of the hearing.
 </article><article><number>3</number> Subject to the provisions of 
this Order, on a reference under article 143 of the Constitution, the Court 
shall follow as nearly as may be the same procedure as is followed in 
proceedings before the Court in the exercise of its original jurisdiction, but 
with such variations as may appear to the Court to be appropriate and as the 
Court may direct.
 </article><article><number>4</number> After the hearing of the 
reference under article 143 of the Constitution the Registrar shall transmit to 
the President the report of the Court thereon.
 </article><article><number>5</number> The Court may make such order 
as it thinks fit as to the costs of all parties served with notice under these 
rules and appearing at the hearing of the reference under article 143 of the 
Constitution.
</article> 
 THE SUPREME COURT RULES, 1966
 

 
PART VI
 ORDER XXXVIII
 REFERENCE UNDER ARTICLE 317(1) OF THE CONSTITUTION
 <article><number>1</number> On receipt by the Registrar 
of the order of the President referring to the Court a case for inquiry under 
article 317
<section><number>1</number> of the Constitution, the Registrar shall give notice to the 
Chairman or Member of the Public Service Commission concerned and to the 
Attorney-General for India or the Advocate-General of the particular State to 
appear before the Court on a day specified in the notice to take the directions 
of the Court in the matter of the inquiry. A copy of the charges preferred 
against him shall be furnished to the respondent along with the notice.
 </section></article><article><number>2</number> The Court may summon such 
witnesses as it consider necessary.
 </article><article><number>3</number> After hearing of the 
reference under article 317
<section><number>1</number> of the Constitution, the Registrar shall transmit 
to the President the Report of the Court.
 </section></article><article><number>4</number> No Court-fees or process fees 
shall be payable in connection with any reference dealt with by the Court under 
this Order.
</article> 
 THE SUPREME COURT RULES, 1966
 

 

1[PART VIA
 ORDER XXXVIIIA
 REFERENCE UNDER SECTION 257 OF THE  
INCOME-TAX ACT, 1961
 <article><number>1</number> A reference under section 257 
of the Income-tax Act, 1961, shall be forwarded to the Registrar of the Supreme 
Court.
 </article><article><number>2</number> On receipt of such reference, 
the reference shall be numbered as “Tax Reference Case No. ..........of 19 ”. No 
Court-fee shall be payable on such reference.
 </article><article><number>3</number> The reference shall be in the 
form of a statement of case containing numbered paragraphs setting out all 
relevant facts and proceedings, which have a bearing on the question or 
questions raised in chronological order with relevant dates. It shall contain an 
account of the conflict in the decisions of the High Courts which necessitate 
the Reference.
 </article><article><number>4</number> The Income Tax Appellate 
Tribunal shall, together with the reference through the President, submit the 
following documents:—
 <section>        <number>i</number>  A copy of the order of the Income Tax Officer;
 </section><section>        <number>ii</number>  Memorandum of appeal to the Appellate 
Assistant Commissioner;
 </section><section>       <number>iii</number>  A copy of the order of the Appellate Assistant 
Commissioner;
 </section><section>       <number>iv</number>  Memorandum of appeal to the Appellate Tribunal;
 </section><section>       <number>v</number>  A copy of the order of the Income Tax Appellate 
Tribunal under section 254 of the Income-tax Act, 1961;
 </section><section>       <number>vi</number>  A copy of the application for reference under 
section 256 of the Income-tax Act, 1961;
 </section><section>      <number>vii</number>  Such other documents, as in the opinion of the 
Income Tax Appellate Tribunal, may be required by the Supreme Court at the 
hearing of the reference.
 </section></article><article><number>5</number> The Income Tax Appellate 
Tribunal shall together with the reference prepare and transmit through its 
President at the expense of the party who moved the application under section 
256 of the Income-tax Act, 1961, along with the order of Reference, three copies 
of the transcript in English of the documents mentioned in rule 4, one of which 
shall be duly authenticated.
 </article><article><number>6</number> When the Income Tax Appellate 
Tribunal refers a case to the Supreme Court and transmits the transcript record 
of the said reference, it shall give notice of that fact to the parties, calling 
upon them to take such steps in the Supreme Court as may be necessary for 
bringing the reference to a final hearing and certify to the Registrar of the 
Court, the date or dates of service of notice.
 </article><article><number>7</number> The parties to the reference 
under section 256 of the Income Tax Act, 1961, shall, within 30 days of the 
service of the notice referred to in rule 6, enter appearance in this Court and 
take further steps for bringing the reference to a final hearing.
 </article><article><number>8</number> Upon receipt from the Income 
Tax Appellate Tribunal of the English transcript of the record as aforesaid, the 
Registrar of the Court shall require the party, who moved the application under 
section 256 of the Income Tax Act, 1961, to deposit the charges for printing the 
said record within such time as he may prescribe, but not exceeding 30 days and 
with all convenient speed arrange for preparation thereof.
 </article><article><number>9</number> The rules contained in Order 
XV, shall apply mutatis mutandis to such References with regard to the 
preparation of record and authentication thereof.
 </article><article><number>10</number> Upon the receipt of the 
reference along with the documents mentioned in rule 4, the Registrar shall lay 
the matter before the Chief Justice of India who shall appoint a bench of not 
less than three judges to hear the reference.
 </article><article><number>11</number> Unless otherwise ordered by 
the Court, costs shall be taxed by the Taxing Officer under the provisions of 
Second Schedule to these rules as may be applicable.
 </article><article><number>12</number> A copy of the order made by 
the Court hearing the reference, shall be sent forthwith to the Income Tax 
Appellate Tribunal under the Seal of the Court and the signature of the 
Registrar.
 </article><article><number>13</number> Save as otherwise provided 
by the rules contained this Order, the provisions of other rules (including the 
rules relating to appearance of Advocates, but excluding rules 7, 35, 36 and 37 
of Order XV) shall so far as may be, apply to references under section 257 of 
the Income-tax Act, 1961.]
  


</article> 
 THE SUPREME COURT RULES, 1966
 

 

1[PART VIB
 ORDER XXXVIIIB
 REFERENCE UNDER SECTION 7(2) OF THE MONOPOLIES AND  
RESTRICTIVE TRADE PRACTICES ACT, 1969 (54 OF 1969)
 <article><number>1</number> A reference under sub-section 
(2) of section 7 of the Monopolies and Restrictive Trade Practices Act, 1969 (54 
of 1969) shall be forwarded to the Registrar of the Supreme Court.
 </article><article><number>2</number> 
<section><number>1</number> The reference shall 
contain inter alia all the relevant facts of the case, definite charges 
against the member and the statement of grounds on which each such charge is 
based.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Central Government shall 
together with the reference transmit seven copies thereof and eight copies of 
transcript in English of the documents relating to the grounds on which the 
removal of the member is sought, one of which shall be duly authenticated.
 </section></article><article><number>3</number> On receipt of such reference, 
it shall be registered in the Register maintained for the purpose and numbered 
as “Reference No. ..........of 19 ........under Monopolies and Restrictive Trade 
Practices Act, 1969 (54 of 1969)”. No Court-fee shall be payable on such 
reference.
 </article><article><number>4</number> 
<section><number>1</number> As soon as the reference 
is registered and numbered the Registrar shall give notice to the member 
concerned calling upon him within four weeks from the date of service of notice 
on him to put in a written statement of his defence together with seven copies 
thereof and to state whether he desires to be heard in person. A copy of the 
documents mentioned in rule 2 shall be enclosed with the notice.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notice stating the date 
fixed for filing written statement by the member shall be given to the 
Attorney-General for India and the Central Government.
 </section></article><article><number>5</number> 
<section><number>1</number> After the written 
statement is received from the member or if no such written statement is 
received within the time allowed, the Court shall fix a date for the inquiry.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If the member does not 
appear on the date fixed for inquiry, the Court may proceed with the inquiry in 
the absence of the member.
 </section><section><number>3</number> At the inquiry, the oral and 
documentary evidence as the case may be, in support of the grounds on which the 
removal of the member is sought, shall be exhibited. The member shall be 
entitled to cross-examine the witnesses.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The evidence for the defence 
shall then be exhibited and the witnesses examined who shall be liable to cross 
examination by the prosecution.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The provisions of Order XXXI 
shall, as far as may be, apply to the recording of evidence.
 </section></article><article><number>6</number> The member shall have a right 
to be defended by a legal practitioner of his choice.
 </article><article><number>7</number> Every witness who is summoned 
to give evidence or to produce a document or thing before the Court shall be 
paid travelling and daily allowances at such rates as the Court may fix.
 </article><article><number>8</number> 
<section><number>1</number> After the close of the 
inquiry, the Court shall make an order at once or on such other day as may be 
fixed by it.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Court may pass such 
orders as to costs as it may deem proper.
 </section></article><article><number>9</number> After the order of the Court 
has been announced, the Registrar shall send a copy thereof to the Central 
Government.
 </article><article><number>10</number> Save as otherwise provided 
by the rules contained in this order, the provisions of other Orders shall, so 
far as may be, apply to references under sub-section (2) of section 7 of the 
Monopolies and Restrictive Trade Practices Act, 1969 (54 of 1969).]
 

2[ORDER XXXVIIIC
 REFERENCE UNDER SECTION 130A OF THE CUSTOMS ACT, 1962 (52 
OF 1962), SECTION 35H OF THE CENTRAL EXCISES AND
SALT ACT, 1944 (1 OF 1944), AND SECTION 82C OF THE  
GOLD (CONTROL) ACT, 1968 (45 OF 1968)
 <section><number>1</number> Rules 1 to 13 of Order 
XXXVIIIA of the rules relating to ‘Reference under section 257 of the Income Tax 
Act, 1961, shall, with necessary modifications and adaptations, apply to 
reference under this Order’.]
 
3[Order 
XXXVIIID
 Reference under sub-section (2) of Section 7 of the Sick 
Industrial Companies (special Provisions)
Act, 1985 (1 of 1986)
 Rule 1 to 10 of Order XXXVIIIB 
of the Rules relating to "Reference under section 7(2) of the Monopolies and 
Restrictive Trade Practices Act, 1969, shall, with necessary modifications and 
adaptations, apply to reference under this order”.]
  





</section></article> 
 THE SUPREME COURT RULES, 1966
  
 
PART VIII
 ORDER XL
 REVIEW
 <article><number>1</number> The court may review its 
judgment or order, but no application for review will be entertained in a civil 
proceeding except on the ground mentioned in Order XLVII, rule 1 of the Code, 
and in a criminal proceeding except on the ground of an error apparent on the 
face of the record.












</article> 
 THE SUPREME COURT RULES, 1966
  
 
PART IX
 ORDER XLI
 COSTS
 <article><number>1</number> Subject to the provisions of 
any statue or of these rules, the costs of and incidental to all proceedings, 
shall be in the discretion of the court. Unless the court otherwise orders an 
intervener shall not be entitled to costs.




























































</article> 
 THE SUPREME COURT RULES, 1966
  
 
PART X
 MISCELLANEOUS
 ORDER XLIII
 NOTICE OF PROCEEDINGS TO THE ATTORNEY-GENERAL  
for INDIA OR ADVOCATE-GENERAL OF STATES
 <article><number>1</number> The court may direct notice 
of any proceedings to be given to the Attorney-General for India or to the 
Advocate-General of any State, and the Attorney-General for India, or the 
Advocate-General to whom such notice is given may appear and take such part in 
the proceedings as he may be advised.
 </article><article><number>2</number> The Attorney-General for 
India or the Advocate-General of any State may apply to be heard in any 
proceedings before the Court, and the Court may, if in its opinion the justice 
of the case so requires, permit the Attorney-General for India or the 
Advocate-General so applying to appear and be heard, subject to such terms as to 
costs or otherwise as the Court may think fit.
 ORDER XLIV
 FORMS TO BE USED
 <section><number>1</number> Every writ, summons, orders, 
warrant or other mandatory process shall bear the attestation of the Chief 
Justice, and shall be signed by the Registrar with the day and the year of 
signing, and shall be sealed with the seal of the Court.
 </section></article><article><number>2</number> The forms set out in the 
Fifth Schedule to these rules, or forms substantially to the like effect with 
such variations as the circumstance of each case may require, shall be used in 
all cases where those forms are appropriate.
 ORDER XLV
 SERVICE OF DOCUMENTS
 <section><number>1</number> Except where otherwise 
provided by any Statute or prescribed by these rules, all notices, orders or 
other documents required to be given to or served on, any person shall be served 
by the Registry in the manner provided by the Code for the service of a summons.
 </section></article><article>

1[<number>2</number> Service of any notice, order or 
other document on the Advocate-on-record of any party shall be deemed sufficient 
service on the party whom he represents and may be effected by delivering it to 
the Advocate-on-record or by leaving it with a clerk in his employ at his 
office.]
 </article><article><number>3</number> Service of any notice, order 
or other document upon a person who resides at a place within the territory of 
India may ordinarily be effected by posting a copy of the document required to 
be served in a pre-paid envelope registered for acknowledgement addressed to the 
party or personally at the place where he ordinarily resides and through the 
District Judge concerned:
 Provided that the Registrar may 
direct in a particular case or class of cases, that the service shall be 
effected in the manner provided by the Code for the service of summons.
 </article><article><number>4</number> A document served by post 
shall be deemed to be served at the time at which it would be delivered in the 
ordinary course of post.
 </article><article><number>5</number> Except where the notice or 
process has been served through Registry, the party required to effect the 
service shall file an affidavit of service, along with such proof thereof as may 
be available stating the manner in which the service has been effected.
 </article><article><number>6</number> Where the notice, order or 
other document has been served through another Court, the service may be proved 
by the deposition or affidavit of the serving officer made before the Court 
through which the service was effected.
 </article><article><number>7</number> Service effected after Court 
hours shall for the purpose of computing any period of time subsequent to that 
service be deemed to have been effected on the following day.
 </article><article>

2[<number>8</number> If service of any notice, order or 
document has not been completed within six months from the date of issue of 
notice, the matter shall be reported to the Court for direction after notice to 
the Advocates-on-record for the parties. The Court may thereupon dismiss the 
matter for non-prosecution or give such direction in the matter as it deems 
fit.]
 ORDER XLVI
 COMMISSIONS
 <section><number>1</number> Order XXVI in the First 
Schedule to the Code with respect to commissions shall apply except rules 13, 
14, 19, 20, 21 and 22 thereof.
 </section><section><number>2</number> An application for the issue 
of a commission may be made by summons in Chambers after notice to all parties 
who have appeared or ex parte where there has been no appearance.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Commissioner shall, if 
the advocate or other person examining a witness so desires, record a question 
disallowed by the Commissioner and the answer thereto, but the same shall not be 
admitted as evidence until the Court before which the deposition is put in 
evidence shall so direct.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Court may, when the 
commission is not one for examination on interrogatories, order that the 
Commissioner shall have all the powers of a Court under Chapter X of the Indian 
Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872), to decide question as to the admissibility of 
evidence and to disallow any question put to a witness.
 </section><section><number>5</number> Unless otherwise ordered, the 
party at whose instance the commission is ordered to issue, shall lodge in the 
Court, copies of the pleadings in the case within twenty-four hours of the 
making of the order and those copies shall be annexed to the commission when 
issued.
 </section><section><number>6</number> Any party aggrieved by the 
decision of the Commissioner refusing to admit evidence or allow a question to 
be put may apply to the Court to set aside the decision and for direction to the 
Commissioner to admit the evidence or to allow the question but no such 
application shall be entertained if made later than seven days after the 
examination of the witness has been closed.
 </section><section><number>7</number> After the deposition of any 
witness has been taken down and before it is signed by him, it shall be read 
over and where necessary, translated to the witness, and shall be signed by him 
and left with the Commissioner who shall subscribe his name and the date of the 
examination.
 </section></article><article><number>8</number> Commissions shall be made 
returnable within such time as the Court may direct.
 ORDER XLVII
 POWER TO DISPENSE AND INHERENT POWERS
 <section><number>1</number> The Court may, for sufficient 
cause shown, excuse the parties from compliance with any of the requirements of 
these rules, and may give such direction in matters of practice and procedure as 
it may consider just and expedient.
 </section><section><number>2</number> An application to be excused 
from compliance with the requirements of any of the rules shall be addressed, in 
the first instance, to the Registrar, who shall take instructions of the Judge 
in Chambers thereon and communicate the same to the parties, but, if, in the 
opinion of the Registrar, it is desirable that the application should be dealt 
with in open Court, he may direct the applicant to serve the other party with a 
notice of motion returnable before the Court.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Court may enlarge or 
abridge any time appointed by these rules or fixed by any order enlarging time, 
for doing any act or taking any proceeding, upon such terms (if any) as the 
justice of the case may require, and any enlargement may be ordered, although 
the application therefor is not made until after the expiration of the time 
appointed or allowed.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Court may at any time, 
either of its own motion or on the application of any party, make such orders as 
may be necessary or reasonable in respect of any of the matters mentioned in 
rule 8 of Order XXIV of these rules, may issue summonses to persons whose 
attendance is required either to give evidence or to produce documents, or order 
any fact to be proved by affidavit.
 </section><section><number>5</number> Where there are two or more 
appeals arising out of the same matter, the Court may at any time either on its 
own motion or on the application of any party, order that the appeals be 
consolidated 

3[***].
 Unless otherwise ordered by this 
Court the liability of the parties to pay separate Court-fees shall not be 
affected by any order for consolidation.
 </section><section><number>6</number> Nothing in these rules shall 
be deemed to limit or otherwise affect the inherent powers of the Court to make 
such orders as may be necessary for the ends of justice or to prevent abuse of 
the process of the Court.
 

4[7. At any time before or as soon after 
the commencement of arguments at the final hearing of a case as may be feasible, 
the Court will ascertain from the counsel of each party to be heard the time 
which the counsel’s arguments on the matter are likely to take. The Court may 
then fix the time for the arguments of each party or each counsel. The counsel 
may be permitted to supplement the oral arguments by written submission, but 
will not be allowed to exceed the time so fixed unless the Court itself 
considers it necessary, or desires that he should do so on any matter requiring 
further elucidation by oral arguments.]
  





</section></article><form>
 

THE SUPREME COURT RULES, 1966
 

 
 

SCHEDULES
 

FIRST SCHEDULE
 

Rules as to 
Printing of Record
 

1. The record in appeals to the Court shall be printed in the 
form known as demy quarto on both sides of the paper with single spacing.
 

2. The size of the paper used shall be such that the sheet, 
when folded and trimmed, will be about 11 inches in height and 8½ inches in 
width 1[or 
29.7 cm. in height and 21 cm. in width].
 

3. The type to be used in the text shall be pica type but 
“Long Primer” shall be used in printing accounts, tabular matter and notes. 
Every tenth line shall be numbered in the margin.
 

4. Records shall be arranged in two parts in the same volume, 
where practicable, viz.—
 

     Part 
I—    The pleadings and proceedings, the transcript of the evidence of the 
witnesses, the judgments, decrees, etc., of the Courts below, down to the 
orders admitting the appeal.
 

     Part 
II—  The exhibits and documents.
 

5. The Index to Part I shall be in chronological order, and 
shall be placed at the beginning of the volume. 
 

The Index to Part II shall follow the order of the exhibit 
mark, and shall be placed immediately after the Index to Part I.
 

6. Part I shall be arranged strictly in chronological order,
i.e., in the same order as the index. 
 

Part II shall be arranged in the most convenient way for the 
use of the Court, as the circumstances of the case require. The documents shall 
be printed as far as suitable in chronological order, mixing plaintiff’s and 
defendant’s documents together when necessary. Each document shall show its 
exhibit mark, and whether it is a plaintiff’s or defendant’s document (unless 
this is clear from the exhibit mark) and in all cases documents relating to the 
same matter such as—
 

        (a)  a series of correspondence, or
 

        (b)  proceedings in a suit other than the one under 
appeal, shall be kept together. The order in the record of the documents in Part 
II will probably be different from the order of the Index, and the proper page 
number of each document shall be inserted in the printed Index.
 

The parties will be responsible for arranging the record in 
proper order for the Court, and in difficult cases counsel may be asked to 
settle it.
 

7. The documents in Part I shall be numbered consecutively.

 

The documents in Part II shall not be numbered, apart from the 
exhibit mark. 
 

8. Each document shall have a heading which shall consist of 
the number of exhibit mark and the description of the document in the Index, 
without the date.
 

9. Each document shall have a heading which shall be repeated 
at the top of each page over which the document extends viz.—
 

PART I
 

(a) Where the case has been before more than one Court the 
short name of the court shall first appear. Where the case has been before only 
one court, the name of the court need not appear.
 

(b) The heading of the document shall then appear consisting 
of the number and the description of the documents in the Index, with the date, 
except in the case of oral evidence.
 

(c) In the case of oral evidence, ‘plaintiff’s evidence’ or 
‘Defendant’s evidence’ shall appear next to the name of the court and then the 
number in the Index and the witness’s name, with ‘examination’, 
‘cross-examination’ or ‘re-examination’, as the case may be.
 

PART II
 

The word ‘Exhibit’ shall first appear and next to it the 
exhibit mark and the description of the document in the Index with the date.
 

Sufficient space shall be left after the heading to 
distinguish it from the rest of the matter printed on the page.
 

10. The parties shall agree to the omission of formal and 
irrelevant documents, but the description of the document may appear (both in 
the Index and the record), if desired, with the words ‘not printed’ against it.
 

A long series of documents, such as accounts, rent rolls, 
inventories, etc., shall not be printed in full, unless counsel advises, 
but the parties shall agree to short extracts being printed as specimens.
 

11. In case where maps are of an inconvenient size or 
unsuitable in character, the appellant shall, in agreement with the respondent, 
prepare maps, drawn properly, to scale and of reasonable size, showing as far as 
possible, the claims of the respective parties, in different colours.
 

 
 

—————
 

   1.  Ins. by G.S.R. 410, dated 26th February, 1968 (w.e.f. 
26-2-1968).
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>