<act><tid>1440429</tid>
<title>THE EMBLEMS AND NAMES (PREVENTATION OF IMPROPER USE) ACT, <year>1950</year></title>

ACT NO. 12 OF <year>1950</year>
[ 1st March, <year>1950</year>.]

An Act to prevent the improper use of certain emblems and names for 
professional and commercial purposes.

BE it enacted by Parliament as follows:--





<article><tid>312607</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extend, application and commencement.
<section><tid>922837</tid>
<number>1</number>This  
Act may be called the Emblems and Names (Prevention of Improper Use) 
Act, <year>1950</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1838873</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>, and also applies to 
citizens of India outside India.

</section>

<section><tid>752649</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>25541</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>9200</tid>
<number>a</number>" emblem" means any emblem, seal, flag, insignia, coat- 
of- arms or pictorial representation specified in the 
Schedule;

</section>

<section><tid>1665674</tid>
<number>b</number>" competent authority" means any authority competent 
under any lay for the time being in force to register 
any company, firm or other body of persons or any trade 
mark or design or to grant a patent:

</section>

<section><tid>1259657</tid>
<number>c</number>" name" includes any abbreviation of a name.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>236468</tid>
<number>3</number>Prohibition of improper use of certain emblems and names. 
Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time being in 
force, no person shall, except in such cases and under such conditions 
as may be prescribed by the Central Government, use or continue to 
use, for the purpose of any trade, business, calling or profession, or 
in the title of any patent, or in any trade mark or design, any name 
or emblem specified in the Schedule or any colourable imitation 
thereof without the previous permission of the Central Government or 
of such officer of Government as may be authorized in this behalf by 
the Central Government.


</article>



<article><tid>1521965</tid>
<number> 4</number> Prohibition of registration of certain companies etc.
<section><tid>1253682</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time being in 
force, no competent authority shall,--

<subsection><tid>1325145</tid>
<number>a</number>register any company, firm or other body or persons 
which bears any name, or
<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>999999</number> Extended to Sikkim Brought into force 
w. e. f. 16. 5. <year>1975</year> in Sikkim w. e. f. 1. 9. <year>1975</year> 
vide S. O. 208 (E), vide S. O. 4292 dt. 
16.  9. 75 
dated 16. 5. <year>1975</year>.

The Act comes into force in Pondicherry on 1. 10. <year>1963</year> vide Reg. 7 of 
<year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch. 1.

Extended to Goa, Daman and Diu with modifications by Reg. 12 of <year>1962</year>. 
s. 3 and shedule.

Extended to and brought into force in Dadra and Nacar Haveli (w. e. f.  
  1. 7. 65) by Reg. 6 of <year>1963</year>, s. 2 and sch. 1.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" except the State of Jammu and Kashmir" omitted by Act 
62  <year>1956</year>, s. 2 and Sch (w. e. f. 1- 11- 56). 
2.  1st September, <year>1950</year>, see gazette of India, <year>1950</year>, Pt. II, Sec, 3, 
p. 451.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1464872</tid>
<number>b</number>register a trade mark of design which bears any emblem 
or name, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1770938</tid>
<number>c</number>grant a patent in respect of an invention which bears a 
title containing any emblem or name,
if the use of such name or emblem is in contravention of section 3.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1814913</tid>
<number>2</number>If any question arises before a competent authority whether 
any emblem is an emblem specified in the Schedule or a colourable 
imitation thereof, the competent authority may refer the question to 
the Central Government, and the decision of the Central Government 
thereon shall be final.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>888872</tid>
<number>5</number>Penalty. Any person who contravenes the provisions of section 
 3 shall be punishable with fine which may extend to five hundred 
rupees.


</article>



<article><tid>1545127</tid>
<number>6</number>Previous sanction of prosecution. No prosecution for any 
offence punishable under this Act shall be instituted, except with the 
previous sanction of the Central Government or of any officer 
authorized in this behalf by general or special order of the Central 
Government.


</article>



<article><tid>711714</tid>
<number>7</number>Savings. Nothing in this Act shall exempt any person from any 
suit or other proceeding which might, apart from this Act, be brought 
against him.


</article>



<article><tid>273508</tid>
<number>8</number>Power of the Central Government to amend the Schedule. The 
Central Government may, be notification in the Gazette, add to or 
alter the Schedule, and any such addition or alternation shall have 
effect as if it had been made by this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>589610</tid>
<number> 9</number> Power to make rules. <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<section><tid>552284</tid>
<number>1</number>] The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the 
purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1259773</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as 
may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is 
in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised 
in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.]


</section>

</article>



 </act>