<act><tid>1499382</tid>
<title>THE NEGOTIABLE INSTRUMENTS (AMENDMENT AND MISCELLANEOUS  
  PROVISIONS) ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 55 OF <year>2002</year>
[ 17th December, <year>2002</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Negotiable Instruments Act, <year>1881</year>, the 
Bankers' Books Evidence Act, <year>1891</year> and the Information Technology Act, 
<year>2000</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>946991</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>1075172</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Negotiable Instruments (Amendment and Miscellaneous Provisions) Act, 
<year>2002</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>606133</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint and different 
dates may be appointed for different provisions of this Act.
CHAP

AMENDMENTS TO THE NEGOTIABLE INSTRUMENTS ACT, <year>1881</year>

CHAPTER II

AMENDMENTS TO THE NEGOTIABLE INSTRUMENTS ACT, <year>1881</year>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1072308</tid>
<number> 2</number> Substitution of new section for section 6.- For section 6 of the 
Negotiable Instruments Act, <year>1881</year> (26 of <year>1881</year>)  (hereinafter in this  
  Chapter referred to as the principal Act), the following section shall 
be substituted, namely:-
' 6." Cheque".- A" cheque" is a bill of exchange drawn on a specified 
banker and not expressed to be payable otherwise than on demand and it 
includes the electronic image of a truncated cheque and a cheque in 
the electronic form. Explanation I.- For the purposes of this section, 
the expressions-

<section><tid>1315130</tid>
<number>a</number>" a cheque in the electronic form" means a cheque which contains 
the exact mirror image of a paper cheque, and is generated, written 
and signed in a secure system ensuring the minimum safety standards 
with the use of digital signature (with or without biometrics  
  signature) and asymmetric crypto system;

</section>

<section><tid>225898</tid>
<number>b</number>" a truncated cheque" means a cheque which is truncated during the 
course of a clearing cycle, either by the clearing house or by the 
bank whether paying or receiving payment, immediately on generation of 
an electronic image for transmission, substitu ing the further 
physical movement of the cheque in writing.
Explanation II.- For the purposes of this section, the expression 
" clearing house" means the clearing house managed by the Reserve Bank 
of India or a clearing house recognised as such by the Reserve Bank of 
India.'.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>641810</tid>
<number> 3</number> Amendment of section 64.- Section 64 of the principal Act shall be 
re- numbered as sub- section
<section><tid>1772087</tid>
<number>1</number>thereof, and after sub- section (1) as  
so re- numbered, the following sub- section shall be inserted, namely:-
" (2) Notwithstanding anything contained in section 6, where an 
electronic image of a truncated cheque is presented for payment, the 
drawee bank is entitled to demand any further information regarding 
the truncated cheque from the bank holding the truncat d cheque in 
case of any reasonable suspicion about the genuineness of the apparent 
tenor of instrument, and if the suspicion is that of any fraud, 
forgery, tampering or destruction of the instrument, it is entitled to 
further demand the presentment of th truncated cheque itself for 
verification:

Provided that the truncated cheque so demanded by the drawee bank 
shall be retained by it, if the payment is made accordingly.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1966421</tid>
<number> 4</number> Amendment of section 81.- Section 81 of the principal Act shall be 
re- numbered as sub- section
<section><tid>1526858</tid>
<number>1</number>thereof, and after sub- section (1) as  
so re- numbered, the following sub- sections shall be inserted, namely:-
" (2) Where the cheque is an electronic image of a truncated cheque, 
even after the payment the banker who received the payment shall be 
entitled to retain the truncated cheque.


</section>

<section><tid>369296</tid>
<number>3</number>A certificate issued on the foot of the printout of the electronic 
image of a truncated cheque by the banker who paid the instrument, 
shall be prima facie proof of such payment.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1636980</tid>
<number> 5</number> Amendment of section 89.- Section 89 of the principal Act shall be 
re- numbered as sub- section
<section><tid>1883305</tid>
<number>1</number>thereof, and after sub- section (1) as  
so re- numbered, the following sub- sections shall be inserted, namely:-
" (2) Where the cheque is an electronic image of a truncated cheque, 
any difference in apparent tenor of such electronic image and the 
truncated cheque shall be a material alteration and it shall be the 
duty of the bank or the clearing house, as the case ay be, to ensure 
the exactness of the apparent tenor of electronic image of the 
truncated cheque while truncating and transmitting the image.


</section>

<section><tid>779747</tid>
<number>3</number>Any bank or a clearing house which receives a transmitted 
electronic image of a truncated cheque, shall verify from the party 
who transmitted the image to it, that the image so transmitted to it 
and received by it, is exactly the same.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1770822</tid>
<number>6</number>Amendment of section 131.- In section 131 of the principal Act, 
Explanation shall be re- numbered as Explanation I thereof, and after 
Explanation I as so re- numbered, the following Explanation shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" Explanation II.- It shall be the duty of the banker who receives 
payment based on an electronic image of a truncated cheque held with 
him, to verify the prima facie genuineness of the cheque to be 
the instrument that can be verified with due diligence and ordinary 
care.". truncated and any fraud, forgery or tampering apparent on the 
face of



</article>



<article><tid>306265</tid>
<number> 7</number> Amendment of section 138.- In section 138 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1681047</tid>
<number>a</number>for the words" a term which may be extended to one year", the 
words" a term which may be extended to two years" shall be 
substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1491653</tid>
<number>b</number>in the proviso, in clause (b), for the words" within fifteen 
days", the words" within thirty days" shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>932327</tid>
<number>8</number>Amendment of section 141.- In section 141 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, after the proviso, the following proviso shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" Provided further that where a person is nominated as a Director of a 
company by virtue of his holding any office or employment in the 
Central Government or State Government or a financial corporation 
owned or controlled by the Central Government or the tate Government, 
as the case may be, he shall not be liable for prosecution under this 
Chapter.".



</article>



<article><tid>4558</tid>
<number>9</number>Amendment of section 142.- In section 142 of the principal Act, 
after clause (b), the following proviso shall be inserted, namely:-
" Provided that the cognizance of a complaint may be taken by the Court 
after the prescribed period, if the complainant satisfies the Court 
that he had sufficient cause for not making a complaint within such 
period.".



</article>



<article><tid>1742462</tid>
<number> 10</number> Insertion of new sections after section 142.- After section 142 of 
the principal Act, the following sections shall be inserted, namely:-
" 143. Power of Court to try cases summarily.- (1) Notwithstanding 
anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of  
  <year>1974</year>), all offences under this Chapter shall be tried by a Judicial 
Magistrate of the first class or by a Metropolitan Magis rate and the 
provisions of sections 262 to 265 (both inclusive) of the said Code 
shall, as far as may be, apply to such trials: Provided that in the 
case of any conviction in a summary trial under this section, it shall 
be lawful for the Magistrate to pass a sentence of imprisonment for a 
term not exceeding one year and an amount of fine exceeding five 
thousand rupees:

Provided further that when at the commencement of, or in the course 
of, a summary trial under this section, it appears to the Magistrate 
that the nature of the case is such that a sentence of imprisonment 
for a term exceeding one year may have to be pass d or that it is, for 
any other reason, undesirable to try the case summarily, the 
Magistrate shall after hearing the parties, record an order to that 
effect and thereafter recall any witness who may have been examined 
and proceed to hear or rehear the ca e in the manner provided by the 
said Code.

<section><tid>495658</tid>
<number>2</number>The trial of a case under this section shall, so far as 
practicable, consistently with the interests of justice, be continued 
from day to day until its conclusion, unless the Court finds the 
adjournment of the trial beyond the following day to be ne essary for 
reasons to be recorded in writing.

</section>

<section><tid>1390141</tid>
<number>3</number>Every trial under this section shall be conducted as expeditiously 
as possible and an endeavour shall be made to conclude the trial 
within six months from the date of filing of the complaint.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1628845</tid>
<number> 144</number> Mode of service of summons.-
<section><tid>1038254</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything  
contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>), and for 
the purposes of this Chapter, a Magistrate issuing a summons to an 
accused or a witness may direct a copy of summons to b served at the 
place where such accused or witness ordinarily resides or carries on 
business or personally works for gain, by speed post or by such 
courier services as are approved by a Court of Session.

</section>

<section><tid>77866</tid>
<number>2</number>Where an acknowledgment purporting to be signed by the accused or 
the witness or an endorsement purported to be made by any person 
authorised by the postal department or the courier services that the 
accused or the witness refused to take delivery f summons has been 
received, the Court issuing the summons may declare that the summons 
has been duly served.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1845123</tid>
<number> 145</number> Evidence on affidavit.-
<section><tid>1869526</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in  
the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>), the evidence of the 
complainant may be given by him on affidavit and may, subject to all 
just exceptions be read in evidence in any e quiry, trial or other 
proceeding under the said Code.

</section>

<section><tid>772718</tid>
<number>2</number>The Court may, if it thinks fit, and shall, on the application of 
the prosecution or the accused, summon and examine any person giving 
evidence on affidavit as to the facts contained therein.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1721500</tid>
<number>146</number>Bank' s slip prima facie evidence of certain facts.- The Court 
shall, in respect of every proceeding under this Chapter, on 
production of bank' s slip or memo having thereon the official mark 
denoting that the cheque has been dishonoured, presume the f ct of 
dishonour of such cheque, unless and until such fact is disproved.
</article>



<article><tid>571408</tid>
<number>147</number>Offences to be compoundable.- Notwithstanding anything contained 
in the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>), every offence 
punishable under this Act shall be compoundable.".
CHAP

AMENDMENT TO THE BANKERS' BOOKS EVIDENCE ACT, <year>1891</year>

CHAPTER III

AMENDMENT TO THE BANKERS' BOOKS EVIDENCE ACT, <year>1891</year>



</article>



<article><tid>1045941</tid>
<number> 11</number> Amendment of section 2.- In section 2 of the Bankers' Books 
Evidence Act, <year>1891</year> (18 of <year>1891</year>),-
<section><tid>1132003</tid>
<number>a</number>for clause (3), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
' (3)" bankers' books" include ledgers, day- books, cash- books, 
account- books and all other records used in the ordinary business of 
the bank, whether these records are kept in written form or stored in 
a micro film, magnetic tape or in any other form of m chanical or 
electronic data retrieval mechanism, either onsite or at any offsite 
location including a back- up or disaster recovery site of both;';


</section>

<section><tid>1377133</tid>
<number>b</number>in clause (8), after sub- clause (b), the following sub- clause 
shall be inserted, namely:-
" (c) a printout of any entry in the books of a bank stored in a micro 
film, magnetic tape or in any other form of mechanical or electronic 
data retrieval mechanism obtained by a mechanical or other process 
which in itself ensures the accuracy of such pri tout as a copy of 
such entry and such printout contains the certificate in accordance 
with the provisions of section 2A.".

CHAP

AMENDMENTS TO THE INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY ACT, <year>2000</year>

CHAPTER IV

AMENDMENTS TO THE INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY ACT, <year>2000</year>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1107656</tid>
<number>12</number>Amendment of section 1.- In the Information Technology Act, <year>2000</year> 
 (21 of <year>2000</year>)  (hereinafter in this Chapter referred to as the principal  
  Act), in section 1, in sub- section (4), for clause (a), the following 
clause shall be substituted, namely:-
" (a) a negotiable instrument (other than a cheque) as defined in 
section 13 of the Negotiable Instruments Act, <year>1881</year> (26 of <year>1881</year>);".



</article>



<article><tid>623926</tid>
<number> 13</number> Insertion of new section 81A.- After section 81 of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
' 81A. Application of the Act to electronic cheque and truncated 
cheque.- (1) The provisions of this Act, for the time being in force, 
shall apply to, or in relation to, electronic cheques and the 
truncated cheques subject to such modifications and amendme ts as may 
be necessary for carrying out the purposes of the Negotiable 
Instruments Act, <year>1881</year> (26 of <year>1881</year>) by the Central Government, in 
consultation with the Reserve Bank of India, by notification in the 
Official Gazette.

<section><tid>1315922</tid>
<number>2</number>Every notification made by the Central Government under 
sub- section (1) shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, 
before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total 
period of thirty days which may be comprised in one sessi n or in two 
or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the 
notification or both Houses agree that the notif cation should not be 
made, the notification shall thereafter have effect only in such 
modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, 
that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to 
the validity of anything previo sly done under that notification.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this Act, the expressions" electronic 
cheque" and" truncated cheque" shall have the same meaning as assigned 
to them in section 6 of the Negotiable Instruments Act, <year>1881</year> (26 of  
  <year>1881</year>).'.

----

SUBHASH C. JAIN,

Secy. to the Govt. of India.



</section>

</article>



 </act>