<act><title>


    The Railway (Notices of and Inquiries into Accidents) Rules, 19981</title> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>1</number> Short title and 
    commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Railway (Notices of and Inquiries into 
    Accidents) Rules, 1998. 
 </section><section>

    <number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of 
    their publication in the Official Gazette. 
 

 
 

 





  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>2</number> Particulars to be 
    given in the notices.—The 
    notices mentioned in section 113 of the Railways Act, 1989 (24 of 1989) 
    (hereinafter referred to as the Act), shall contain the following 
    particulars, namely:—
 <section>

    <number>i</number>    Kilometerage, or station, or both, at which the accident occurred;  
 </section><section>

    <number>ii</number>    time and date of the accident;  
 </section><section>

    <number>iii</number>    number and description of the train, or trains;  
 </section><section>

    <number>iv</number>    nature of the accident;  
 </section><section>

    <number>v</number>    number of people killed or injured, as far as is known;  
 </section><section>

    <number>vi</number>    cause of the accident, as far as is known; and  
 </section><section>

    <number>vii</number>    probable detention to traffic.  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>3</number> Responsibility for 
    sending notices, to whom to be sent and mode thereof.—Whenever 
    any accident, as falls under section 113 of the Act (hereinafter referred to 
    as “Reportable train accident”) occurs in the course of working a railway, 
    the Station Master nearest to the place at which the accident has occurred 
    or, where there is no Station Master, the railway servant in charge of the 
    section of the railway on which the accident has occurred or any other 
    Station Master in charge of a section of a railway to whom the report of the 
    accident is made, shall give notice of the accident by telegraph to the 
    Commissioner of Railway Safety, the District Magistrate and the District 
    Superintendent of Police of the district in which the accident has occurred 
    or such other Magistrate or police officer as may be appointed in this 
    behalf by the State Government concerned and by telegraph, telephone or 
    through special messenger or such other quick means as may be available, to 
    the Superintendent of Railway Police and to the officer-in-charge of the 
    police station within the local limits of which the accident has occurred. 
 

Explanation.—For 
    the purpose of this rule, “Reportable Train accident” under section 113 of 
    the Act also includes those usually attended with loss of human life (such 
    as accidents to passenger trains involving collisions, derailments, 
    train-wrecking, or attempted train-wrecking, cases of running over 
    obstructions placed on the line, of passengers falling out of trains or of 
    fires in trains), or grievous hurt as defined in the Indian Penal Code 
    (hereinafter referred to as the grievous hurt), or serious damage to railway 
    property of the value exceeding twenty-five lakh rupees which have not 
    actually occurred but which by the nature of the accident might reasonably 
    have been expected to occur; and also cases of landslides or of breach by 
    rain or flood which cause the interruption of any important through-line of 
    communication for at least 24 hours. 
 


  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>4</number> Mode of sending 
    notices to the State Government.—The 
    notice of accidents, required under section 113 of the Act, to be sent 
    without delay by the Railway Administration, shall be sent to the State 
    Government— 
 <section>

    <number>a</number>    by telegram in the case of—  
 <subsection>

    <number>i</number>    accidents deemed, under the Explanation to Rule 3, to be 
    serious by reason of loss of human life;  
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>ii</number>    accidents by reason of which the permanent way is likely to be 
    blocked for more than twenty-four hours; and  
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>iii</number>    train-wrecking or attempted train-wrecking; and  
 </subsection></section><section>

    <number>b</number>    by letter in all other cases.  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>5</number> Railway servants 
    to report accidents.—Every 
    railway servant shall report, with as little delay as possible every 
    accident occurring in the course of working the railway which may come to 
    his notice and such report shall be made to the nearest Station Master, or, 
    where there is no Station Master, to the railway servant in charge of the 
    section of the railway on which the accident has occurred.
 


  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>6</number> Station Master or 
    railway servant in charge of the section to report accidents.—The 
    Station Master or the railway servant in charge of the section, shall report 
    all accidents in accordance with the rules laid down by the Railway 
    Administration concerned for the reporting of accidents.
 


  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>6A</number> 
    Responsibility of ensuring correct reporting of accidents.—The 
    responsibility of ensuring correct reporting of accidents shall be of the 
    Divisional Railway Manager (DRM) at Divisional Level and the General Manager 
    (GM) at Zonal Level.]
 

 

 





  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>7</number> Railway 
    Administration to report serious accidents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whenever a serious accident as defined in sub-rule (2) of Rule 2 of the 
    Statutory Investigation into Railway Accidents Rules, 1998 occurs, the 
    railway administration concerned shall, as soon after the accident as 
    possible, by telegraph, supply to the Press such particulars as are 
    mentioned in Rule 2 and as are till then available, and by supplementary 
    telegrams if necessary, immediately after further information is available. 
    A copy shall be sent simultaneously by express telegram to the Railway 
    Board, the Commissioner of Railway Safety of the circle concerned and the 
    Chief Commissioner of Railway Safety. In addition, the Commissioner of 
    Railway Safety shall be informed, telephonically, of any serious accident, 
    by the control of the division in which the accident has occurred. 
 </section><section>

    <number>2</number> For the purpose of sub-rule (1), an accident shall be a serious railway 
    accident where—  
 <subsection>

    <number>i</number>    accident to a train carrying passengers which is attended with loss 
    of life or with grievous hurt to a passenger or passengers in the train, or 
    with serious damage to railway property of the value exceeding Rs. 25,00,000 
    and any other accident which in the opinion of the Chief Commissioner of 
    railway Safety or Commissioner of Railway Safety requires the holding of an 
    inquiry by the Commissioner of Railway Safety, shall be deemed to be a 
    serious accident.  A workmen’s train or a ballast train carrying 
    workmen or cattle special train or a tower wagon or such other train 
    carrying workmen or cattle special, military special carrying authorised 
    escorts or similar such train shall be treated as a passenger train.
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>ii</number>    an accident involving a train carrying passengers leads to loss of 
    life or grievous injury to any railway servant irrespective of whether he 
    was travelling in that passenger train or not, it shall come under the 
    purview of inquiry by the Commission of
    railway Safety and shall be 
    treated as a serious railway accident’:  
 

    Provided that—  
 <subsubsection>

    <number>a</number>    cases of trespassers run over and injured or killed through their own 
    carelessness or of passengers injured or killed through their own 
    carelessness, and  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

    <number>b</number>    cases involving persons being railway servants or holding valid 
    passes/tickets or otherwise who are killed or grievously injured while 
    travelling outside the rolling-stock of a passenger train such as on 
    footboard or roof or buffer but excluding the inside of vestibules between 
    coaches, or run over at a level crossing or elsewhere on the Railway track 
    by a passenger train, and  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

    <number>c</number>    collusion, between a Road Vehicle and a passenger train at a Level 
    Crossing where no passenger or Railway Servant is killed or grievously hurt 
    shall not be treated as a Serious Railway Accident even if those travelling 
    in the road vehicle are killed or grievously hurt shall not be treated as 
    serious railway accident, unless the Chief Commissioner of Railway Safety or 
    Commissioner of Railway Safety is of the opinion that the accident requires 
    the holding of an inquiry by the Commissioner of Railway Safety. 
 


  


</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>8</number> Facility for 
    reaching the site of the accident.—Whenever 
    any accident has occurred in the course of working a railway, the Head of 
    the Railway Administration concerned shall give all reasonable aid to the 
    District Magistrate or the Magistrate appointed or deputed under Rule 17 or 
    to the Commission of Inquiry appointed under the Commissions of Inquiry Act, 
    1952 (60 of 1952), or any other authority to whom all or any of the 
    provisions of the said Act have been made applicable, and to the 
    Commissioner of Railway Safety, medical officers, the police and others 
    concerned to enable them to reach the scene of the accident promptly and 
    shall also assist those authorities in making inquires and in obtaining 
    evidence as to the cause of the accident. 
 


  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>9</number> Medical aid to the 
    persons grievously hurt in accidents.—Whenever 
    an accident, occurring in the course of working a railway, has been attended 
    with grievous hurt, it shall be the duty of the Head of the Railway 
    Administration concerned to afford medical aid to the sufferers and to see 
    that they are properly and carefully attended to till they are removed to 
    their homes or handed over to the care of their relatives or friends. In any 
    such case, or in any case in which any loss of human life or grievous hurt 
    has occurred, the nearest available local Medical Officer shall be sent for 
    if such Medical Officer is nearer at hand than the Railway Medical Officer.
 


  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>10</number> Arranging 
    attendance of railway servants at the place of judicial inquiries or 
    inquiries conducted by Commissioner of Railway Safety or a Magistrate.—When 
    an inquiry under Rule 2 of the Statutory Investigation into Railway 
    Accidents Rules, 1998, or under Rule 17 of these rules, or a judicial 
    inquiry is being made, the Head of the Railway Administration concerned 
    shall arrange for the attendance, as long as may be necessary, at the place 
    of inquiry, of all railway servants whose evidence is likely to be required 
    at such inquiry; and if the inquiry is to be held by the Commissioner of 
    Railway Safety under Rule 2 of the Statutory Investigation into Railway 
    Accidents Rules, 1998 the Head of the Railway Administration concerned 
    shall,— 
 <section>

    <number>a</number>    cause notice of the date, hour and place at which the inquiry will 
    begin to be given to the officers mentioned in clauses (a) and (c) of 
    sub-rule (1) of Rule 14, and
 </section><section>

    <number>b</number>    arrange for the attendance of the divisional officers, railway 
    servants required as witness at the inquiry. 
 


  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>11</number> Action to be 
    taken by Head of the railway Administration on receipt of the report of 
    Commissioner of Railway Safety.—Whenever 
    the Head of the Railway Administration concerned receives a copy of the 
    report of the Commissioner of Railway Safety under Rule 4 of the Statutory 
    Investigation into Railway Accidents Rules, 1998, he shall at once 
    acknowledge its receipt, and— 
 <section>

    <number>a</number>    submit his remarks, on the views expressed in the report, to the 
    Chief Commissioner of Railway Safety with copy to the Commissioner of 
    Railway Safety immediately on receipt of the report by the Railway 
    Administration and if he is not able to submit his remarks immediately he 
    shall in his acknowledgment of the report indicate his intention to submit 
    his remarks later a early as possible;  
 </section><section>

    <number>b</number>    if the Head of the Railway Administration concerned agree with the 
    views expressed in the report and considers the prosecution of any person or 
    persons desirable, he shall immediately forward a statement of such persons 
    to the District Magistrate of the district in which the accident occurred, 
    or to such other officer as the State Government may appoint in this behalf 
    and to the concerned police authorities;  
 </section><section>

    <number>c</number>    in case the District Magistrate or Police Authorities require copies 
    of the report, it may be sent to them, and the confidentiality of the report 
    should be made clear to the District Magistrate Police Authorities, and the 
    Police Authorities shall, as soon as possible, intimate the Head of the 
    Railway Administration concerned about their decision regarding launching 
    any prosecution.  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>12</number> Head of the 
    Railway Administration to offer remarks on the suggestions made in the 
    report of Commissioner of Railway Safety.—Whenever 
    the report of the Commissioner of Railway Safety points to the necessity for 
    or suggests a change in any of the rules or in the system of working of the 
    railway, the Head of the Railway Administration concerned shall, intimate 
    the action which has been taken, or which it proposes to take, to prevent a 
    recurrence of similar accidents, to the Chief Commissioner of Railway Safety 
    with copy to the Commissioner of Railway Safety.
 


  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>13</number> Joint inquiry 
    when dispensed with.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whenever a reportable train accident, such as is described in section 113 of 
    the Act has occurred in the course of working a railway, the Head of the 
    Railway Administration concerned shall cause an inquiry to be promptly made 
    by a committee of railway officers (to be called a “joint inquiry”) for a 
    thorough investigation of the causes which led to the accident:
 

    Provided that such an inquiry may be dispensed with—  
 <subsection>

    <number>a</number>    if any inquiry is to be held by the Commissioner of Railway Safety 
    under Rule 2 of the Statutory Investigation into Railway Accidents Rules, 
    1998, or a Commission appointed under the Commissions of Inquiry Act, 1952 
    (60 of 1952) or any other authority appointed by the Central Government to 
    which all or any of the provisions of the said Commission of Inquiry Act 
    have been made applicable under Rule 2 of the said ‘Statutory Investigation 
    into Railway Accidents Rules, or  
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>b</number>    if there is no reasonable doubt as to the cause of the accident; or  
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>c</number>    if any department of the railway administration concerned intimates 
    that it accepts all responsibility in the matter.  
 </subsection></section><section>

    <number>2</number> Where such inquiry is dispensed with under clause (b) or clause (c) of 
    the proviso to sub-rule (1), it shall be the duty of the Head of the 
    Department of the Railway Administration responsible for the accident to 
    make such inquiry (to be called a “departmental inquiry”) as he may consider 
    necessary and, if his staff or the system or working is at fault, to adopt 
    or suggest such measures as he may consider necessary for preventing a 
    recurrence of similar accidents.  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>14</number> Notice of joint 
    inquiry.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whenever a joint inquiry is to be made, the Head of the Railway 
    Administration concerned shall cause notice of the date and hour at which 
    the inquiry will commence, to be given to the following officers, namely:— 
 <subsection>

    <number>a</number>    the District Magistrate of the district in which the accident 
    occurred, or such other officer as the State Government may appoint in this 
    behalf, the Superintendent of the Railway Police and the District 
    Superintendent of Police;  
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>b</number>    the Commissioner of Railway Safety for the section of the railway on 
    which the accident occurred; and  
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>c</number>    the Head of the Railway Police having jurisdiction at the place where 
    the accident occurred or, if there are no Railway Police, the 
    officer-in-charge of the police station having jurisdiction at such place.  
 </subsection></section><section>

    <number>2</number> The date and hour at which the inquiry will commence shall be fixed so 
    as to give the officers mentioned in sub-rule (1) sufficient time to reach 
    the place where the inquiry is to be held.  
 </section><section>

    <number>3</number> When a joint inquiry is held into an accident after receipt of 
    information about the inability of the Commissioner of Railway Safety to 
    hold an inquiry, under sub-rule (5) of Rule 2 of the Statutory Investigation 
    into Railway Accidents Rules, 1998, the Head of the Railway Administration 
    concerned shall issue a Press Note in this behalf inviting the public to 
    tender evidence at the inquiry or send information relating to the accident 
    to the Joint Inquiry Committee at an address specified in the Press Note.  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>15</number> Report of joint 
    inquiry or departmental inquiry to be sent to the Head of the Railway 
    Administration and the action to be taken thereon.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    As soon as any joint inquiry or departmental inquiry has been completed, the 
    President of the Committee of railway officers or the Head of the 
    Department, as the case may be, shall send to the Head of the Railway 
    Administration concerned a report containing inter alia— 
 <subsection>

    <number>a</number>    brief description of the accident;  
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>b</number>    description of the locality of the accident;  
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>c</number>    detailed statement of the evidence taken;  
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>d</number>    the conclusions arrived at together with a note of dissent, if any;  
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>e</number>    reasons for conclusions arrived at;  
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>f</number>    the nature and extent of the damage done;  
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>g</number>    when necessary, a sketch illustrative of the accident;  
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>h</number>    the number of railway servants killed or injured;  
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>i</number>    the number of passengers skilled or injured;  
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>j</number>    an appendix containing extracts of the rules violated by the staff 
    responsible for the accidents.  
 </subsection></section><section>

    <number>2</number> The Head of the Railway Administration concerned shall forward, with his 
    remarks as to the action that is intended to be taken in regard to the staff 
    responsible for the accident or for the revision of the rules or the system 
    of working, a copy of the report referred to in sub-rule (1)—  
 <subsection>

    <number>a</number>    to the Commissioner of Railway Safety for the section of the railway 
    on which the accident occurred; 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>b</number>    if no inquiry or investigation has been made under Rule 17 or if a 
    joint or departmental inquiry has been held, first, to the District 
    Magistrate or the officer appointed under clause (a) of sub-rule (1) of Rule 
    14, and  
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>c</number>    if any judicial inquiry is being made, to the Magistrate making such 
    inquiry.  
 </subsection></section><section>

    <number>3</number> The copy of the report aforesaid shall be accompanied—  
 <subsection>

    <number>a</number>    in the case referred to in clause (b) of sub-rule (2), by a statement 
    of the persons involved in the accident whose prosecution the Head of the 
    Railway Administration concerned considers to be desirable;  
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>b</number>    in the case referred to in clause (c) of sub-rule (2), by a copy of 
    the evidence taken at the inquiry.  

  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>16</number> Reports of 
    inquiries into accidents not covered by section 113 to be forwarded to 
    Commissioner of Railway Safety.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whenever any accident, not of the nature specified in section 113 of the 
    Act, such as averted collisions, breaches of block rules or other technical 
    accidents, occurs in the course of working a railway, the Railway 
    Administration concerned may cause an inquiry, either a joint inquiry or a 
    departmental inquiry, to be held into the accident. 
 </section><section>

    <number>2</number> Where an inquiry is held as provided under sub-rule (1), the Head of the 
    Railway Administration concerned shall forward a copy of the report of the 
    inquiry to the Commissioner of Railway Safety for the section of the railway 
    on which the accident occurred.
 


  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>17</number> Magisterial 
    inquiry.—Whenever 
    an accident, such as is described in section 113 of the Act, has occurred in 
    the course of working a railway, the District Magistrate or any other 
    Magistrate who may be appointed in this behalf by the State Government, may 
    either—
 <section>

    <number>a</number>    himself make an inquiry into the causes which led to the accident; or  
 </section><section>

    <number>b</number>    depute a subordinate Magistrate, who if possible, should be a 
    Magistrate of the first class, to make such an inquiry; or  
 </section><section>

    <number>c</number>    direct investigation into the causes which led to the accident, to be 
    made by the police:  
 

    Provided that where, having regard to the nature of the accident, the 
    Central Government has appointed a Commission of Inquiry to inquire into it 
    under the Commission of Inquiry Act, 1952 (60 of 1952), or has appointed any 
    other authority to inquire into it and for that purpose has made all or any 
    of the provisions of the said Act applicable to that authority, a Magistrate 
    or a police officer shall not make his inquiry or investigation under this 
    rule and, where he has already commenced the inquiry or investigation, shall 
    not proceed further with it; and such Magistrate or police officer shall 
    hand over the evidence, records or other documents in his possession 
    relating to the inquiry or investigation to such authority as may be 
    specified by the Central Government in this behalf.
 


  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>18</number> Notice of 
    Magisterial inquiry.—Whenever 
    it is decided to make an inquiry under clause 
<section><number>a</number> or clause (b) of Rule 17, 
    the District Magistrate or other Magistrate appointed as aforesaid or the 
    Magistrate deputed under clause (b) of Rule 17, as the case may be, shall at 
    once inform the Head of the Railway Administration concerned and the 
    Divisional Railway Manager by telegraph, of the date and hour at which the 
    inquiry will commence so as to enable the Railway Administration to summon 
    the requisite expert evidence, and thereafter, he shall proceed to the scene 
    of the accident and conduct the inquiry. 
 


  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>19</number> Judicial Inquiry.—A 
    Magistrate, making an inquiry under Rule 17, may summon any railway servant, 
    and any other person whose presence he may think necessary, and after taking 
    the evidence and completing the inquiry shall, if he considers that there 
    are sufficient grounds for holding a judicial inquiry, take the requisite 
    steps for bringing to trial any person whom he may consider to be criminally 
    liable for the accident. 
 


  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>20</number> The result of 
    magisterial inquiry to be communicated to the Head of the Railway 
    Administration.—The 
    result of every inquiry or investigation made under Rule 17 shall be 
    communicated by the Magistrate who has held such inquiry or investigation, 
    to the Head of the Railway Administration concerned and to the Commissioner 
    of Railway Safety. 
 


  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>21</number> Procedure for 
    summoning railway servants to assist the Magistrate holding judicial 
    inquiry.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If in the course of any judicial inquiry into an accident occurring in the 
    course of working a railway, the Magistrate holding such inquiry desires the 
    assistance of the Commissioner of Railway Safety or Head of the Railway 
    Administration concerned, he shall issue a requisition to the Chief 
    Commissioner of Railway Safety or the Railway Board, for the presence of the 
    Commissioner of Railway Safety or the Head of the Railway Administration, 
    stating at the same time the nature of the assistance required, and if the 
    assistance of any Railway Officer is required the Magistrate shall issue a 
    requisition to the Head of the Railway Administration for his attendance in 
    the court. 
 </section><section>

    <number>2</number> The requisition referred to in sub-section (1) shall state the nature of 
    the assistance required. In summoning railway officials, the Magistrate 
    shall take care not to summon on the same day so large a number of the 
    employees, especially of one class, as to cause inconvenience to the working 
    of the railway. In the case of serious accidents the Magistrate may obtain 
    reports from the Commissioner of Railway Safety and the Head of the Railway 
    Administration concerned in regard to the accident, before finally 
    concluding the judicial inquiry.
 


  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>22</number> Communication of 
    the decision of judicial inquiry to the Railway Administration, Commissioner 
    of Railway Safety and the State Government.—On 
    the conclusion of the judicial inquiry the Magistrate shall send a copy of 
    his decision to the Head of the Railway Administration concerned and to the 
    Commissioner of Railway Safety, and shall, unless in any case he thinks it 
    unnecessary to do so, report the result of the inquiry to the State 
    Government.
 


  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>23</number> Police 
    investigation—when 
    to be dispensed with—report on loss of life, grievous hurt, or damage 
    to railway property.—
<section><number>1</number> The Railway Police may make an investigation 
    into the causes which led to any accident occurring in the course of working 
    a railway and shall do so whenever— 
 <subsection>

    <number>a</number>    any such accident is attended with loss of human life or with 
    grievous hurt, or with serious damage to railway property of the value 
    exceeding Rs. 25,00,000 or has prima facie been due to any criminal 
    act or omission; or 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>b</number>    the District Magistrate or the Magistrate appointed under Rule 17 has 
    given a direction under clause (c) of that rule:
 

    Provided that where, having regard to the nature of the accident, the 
    Central Government has appointed a Commission of Inquiry to inquire into it 
    under the Commissions of Inquiry Act, 1952 (60 of 1952), or has appointed 
    any other authority to inquire into it and for that purpose has made all or 
    any of the provisions of the said Act applicable to that authority, or where 
    a magisterial inquiry is being held under clause (a) or clause (b) of Rule 
    17, the Railway Police shall not make an investigation under this rule, and, 
    where they have already commenced their investigation shall not proceed 
    further with it; and shall hand over the records or other documents in their 
    possession relating to the investigation to such authority as may be 
    specified by the Central Government in this behalf. 
 </subsection></section><section>

    <number>2</number> The Railway Police shall report, with as little delay as possible to the 
    nearest Station Master, or where there is no Station Master, to the railway 
    servant in charge of the section of the railway, on which the accident has 
    occurred, every accident which may come to their notice occurring in the 
    course of working a railway attended with loss of human life, or with 
    grievous hurt or with serious damage to railway property of the value 
    exceeding twenty-five lakh rupees or which has prima facie been due 
    to any criminal act or omission. 
 


  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>24</number> Status of police 
    officer investigating the accident.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whenever an investigation is to be made by the Railway Police— 
 <subsection>

    <number>a</number>    in a case in which an accident is attended with loss of human life or 
    with grievous hurt, or with serious damage to railway property of the value 
    exceeding twenty five-lakh rupees; or 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>b</number>    in pursuance of a direction given under clause (c) of Rule 17,
 

    the investigation shall be conducted by the Head of the Railway Police of 
    the area in which the accident has occurred, or if that officer is unable to 
    conduct the investigation himself, by an officer to be deputed by him.
 </subsection></section><section>

    <number>2</number> The officer deputed under sub-rule (1) shall ordinarily be the senior 
    officer available, and shall whenever possible be a Gazetted Officer, and 
    shall in no case be of a rank lower than that of an Inspector: 
 

    Provided that the investigation may be carried out by an officer-in-charge 
    of a police station:—
 <subsection>

    <number>i</number>    in a case such as is referred to in clause (a) of sub-rule (1), if no 
    loss of life or grievous hurt has been caused to more persons than one or no 
    damage to railway property of value exceeding twenty-five lakh rupees has 
    been caused or there is no reason to suspect that any servant of the railway 
    has been guilty of neglect of any rule relating to the working of the 
    railway;
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>ii</number>    in the case referred to in clause (b) of sub-rule (1), if the 
    District Magistrate so directs.
 


  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>25</number> Notice of police 
    investigation.—The 
    officer who is to conduct an investigation in pursuance of Rule 24 shall at 
    once inform the Head of the Railway Administration concerned and the 
    Divisional Railway Manager by telegraph of the date and hour at which the 
    investigation will commence so that, if possible, the presence of a railway 
    official may be arranged for to watch the proceedings and to aid the officer 
    making the investigation, and thereafter, he shall proceed without delay to 
    the scene of the accident and conduct the investigation there; so, however, 
    that the absence of a railway official shall not be allowed to delay the 
    investigation which shall be conducted as soon as possible after the 
    accident has taken place. 
 


  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>26</number> Assistance by the 
    District Police.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In every case to which Rule 24 applies, immediate information shall be given 
    by the Railway Police of the area to the District Police. Who, if so, 
    required, shall afford all necessary assistance and shall, if occasion 
    arises, carry the investigation beyond the limits of the railway premises. 
    But the Railway Police of the area shall primarily be responsible for 
    carrying on the investigation within such limits.
 </section><section>

    <number>2</number> Subject to the provisions of these rules, the further prosecution of the 
    case, on the conclusion of the police investigation, shall rest with the 
    Railway Police. 
 


  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>27</number> Communication of 
    the result of police investigation.—The 
    result of every police investigation shall be reported at once to the 
    District Magistrate or other officer appointed in this behalf by the State 
    Government to the Head of the Railway Administration concerned or other 
    officer appointed by him, and to the Commissioner of Railway Safety.
 


  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>28</number> District Police 
    to discharge duties of Railway Police.—Where 
    there is no Railway Police in the area, the duties imposed by Rules 23, 24 
    and 25 sub-rule (2) of Rule 26, and Rule 27 on the Railway Police of the 
    area, or on the Head of such Railway Police, shall be discharged by the 
    District Police or by the District Superintendent of Police, as the case may 
    be. 
 


  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>29</number> Repeal and 
    saving.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Railway (Notices of and Inquiries into Accidents) Rules, 1973, are 
    hereby repealed. 
 </section><section>

    <number>2</number> Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken under the 
    rules hereby repealed shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the 
    corresponding provisions of these rules.
 


  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   2nd January, 1999.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>