<act><tid>652878</tid>
<title>THE PREVENTION OF INSULTS TO NATIONAL HONOUR (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2003</year></title>

ACT NO. 31 OF <year>2003</year>
[ 8th May, <year>2003</year>.]

An Act to amend the Prevention of Insults to National Honour Act, 
<year>1971</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- fourth Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>1882479</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title.- This Act may be called the Prevention of Insults to 
National Honour (Amendment) Act, <year>2003</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1671563</tid>
<number> 2</number> Amendment of section 2.- In section 2 of the Prevention of Insults 
to National Honour Act, <year>1971</year> (69 of <year>1971</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as  
  the principal Act),-
<section><tid>1150662</tid>
<number>a</number>for the words otherwise brings", the words" otherwise shows 
disrespect to or brings" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>801702</tid>
<number>b</number>after Explanation 3, the following Explanation shall be inserted, 
namely:-
' Explanation 4.- The disrespect to the Indian National Flag means and 
includes-


</section>

<section><tid>1150662</tid>
<number>a</number>a gross affront or indignity offered to the Indian National Flag; 
or

</section>

<section><tid>801702</tid>
<number>b</number>dipping the Indian National Flag in salute to any person or thing; 
or

</section>

<section><tid>447903</tid>
<number>c</number>flying the Indian National Flag at half- mast except on occasions 
on which the Indian National Flag is flown at half- mast on public 
buildings in accordance with the instructions issued by the 
Government; or

</section>

<section><tid>1514582</tid>
<number>d</number>using the Indian National Flag as a drapery in any form whatsoever 
except in State Funerals or armed forces or other para- military forces 
funerals; or

</section>

<section><tid>1848848</tid>
<number>e</number>using the Indian National Flag as a portion of costume or uniform 
of any description or embroidering or printing it on cushions, 
handkerchiefs, napkins or any dress material; or

</section>

<section><tid>709599</tid>
<number>f</number>putting any kind of inscription upon the Indian National Flag; or

</section>

<section><tid>350299</tid>
<number>g</number>using the Indian National Flag as a receptacle for receiving, 
delivering or carrying anything except flower petals before the Indian 
National Flag is unfurled as a part of celebrations on special 
occasions including the Republic Day or the Independen e Day; or

</section>

<section><tid>110574</tid>
<number>h</number>using the Indian National Flag as covering for a statute or a 
monument or a speaker' s desk or a speaker' s platform; or

</section>

<section><tid>1085408</tid>
<number>i</number>allowing the Indian National Flag to touch the ground or the floor 
or trail in water intentionally; or

</section>

<section><tid>1173981</tid>
<number>j</number>draping the Indian National Flag over the hood, top and sides or 
back or on a vehicle, train, boat or an aircraft or any other similar 
object; or

</section>

<section><tid>178489</tid>
<number>k</number>using the Indian National Flag as a covering for a building; or

<subsection><tid>420279</tid>
<number>i</number>intentionally displaying the Indian National Flag with the 
" saffron" down.'.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1856710</tid>
<number>3</number>Insertion of new section 3A.- After section 3 of the principal Act, 
the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 3A. Enhanced penalty on second and subsequent convictions.- Whoever, 
having already been convicted of an offence under section 2 or section 
3, is again convicted of any such offence shall be punishable for the 
second and for every subsequent offence, wit imprisonment for a term 
which shall not be less than one year.".

SUBJASH C. JAIN,

Secy. to the Govt. of India.


</article>



 </act>