<act><title>


The Appellate 
    Tribunal for Forfeited 
    Property (Procedure) Rules, 1989</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Appellate Tribunal for Forfeited Property 
    (Procedure) Rules, 1989.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force at once.
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “Act” means the Narcotic Drugs and 
    Psychotropic Substances Act, 1985 (61 of 1985);  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “appeal” means an appeal filed under 
    sub-section (1) of section 68-O;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “appellant” means a person who, being 
    aggrieved by an order made by the competent authority, prefers an appeal to 
    the Tribunal and includes the authorised representative of the appellant;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    “authorised representative” means—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    in relation to an appellant,—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>A</number>    any person being a relative of the 
    appellant and authorised in writing by the appellant to attend before the 
    Tribunal; or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>B</number>    a legal practitioner entitled to 
    practice in any civil court in India, who is authorised in writing by the 
    appellant to attend before the Tribunal; or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>C</number>    an accountant, being a member of the 
    Institute of Chartered Accountants of India constituted under section 3 of 
    the Chartered Accountants Act, 1949 (38 of 1949) or the Institute of Cost 
    and Works Accountants of India constituted under section 3 of the Cost and 
    Works Accountants Act, 1959 (23 of 1959), who is authorised in writing by 
    the appellant to attend before the Tribunal; or  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    in relation to a competent authority 
    who is a party to any proceedings before the Tribunal,—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>A</number>    a Law Officer of the Central 
    Government;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>B</number>    a Government Pleader or Standing 
    Counsel to the Central Government by whatever name called;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>C</number>    any officer of the Central Government 
    notified in this behalf by the Central Government by notification in the 
    Official Gazette;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>D</number>    any legal practitioner or officer of 
    the Central Government authorised in this behalf by the Central Government 
    or the competent authority;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>E</number>    any other legal practitioner or officer 
    of the Central Government acting on behalf of the person so notified or 
    authorised;  
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>e</number>    “Bench” means a Bench of the Tribunal 
    constituted under sub-section (3) or (4) of section 68-O;
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    “Chairman” means the Chairman of the 
    Tribunal;  
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    “competent authority” means a competent 
    authority as defined in sub-section (1) of section 68D;
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>    “legal representative” means a person 
    who in law represents the estate of a deceased person, and includes any 
    person treated by the Tribunal as representing the deceased person in the 
    proceedings pending before the Tribunal;
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>    “member” means member of the Tribunal 
    and includes the Chairman;
 </section><section>
<number>j</number>    “party” in relation to an appeal means 
    an appellant or the respondent, and the expression “parties” shall be 
    construed to mean the appellant and the respondent;
 </section><section>
<number>k</number>    “Registrar” means the
    registrar of the Tribunal and 
    includes such other officer who is authorised by the Chairman to perform the 
    functions of the registrar;
 </section><section>
<number>l</number>    “section” means a section of the Act;
 </section><section>
<number>m</number>    “Tribunal” means the Appellate Tribunal 
    for Forfeited Property, constituted by the Central Government under 
    sub-section (1) of section 68N.
 
 

 
  


  
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Language 
    of the Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    pleadings before the Tribunal may, at the option of the respective parties, 
    be in English or in Hindi.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> All orders 
    and other proceedings of the Tribunal may, at the option of the Tribunal, be 
    in English or in Hindi.  
 
 

 
  


  
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Headquarters of the Tribunal, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Headquarters of the Tribunal shall be at New Delhi.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Appeals 
    and petitions may be heard at the Headquarters or at the discretion of the 
    Chairman, at Bombay, Madras, Calcutta, Allahabad or any other place.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The office 
    of the Tribunal shall observe such public and other holidays as are observed 
    by the offices of the Central Government.  
 
 

 
  


  
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Procedure for filing appeals and petitions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person aggrieved by an order of the competent authority made under 
    section 68F, section 68-I, sub-section (1) of section 68K or section 68L may 
    prefer an appeal to the Tribunal; and every memorandum of appeal shall be in 
    the form annexed to these rules.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    memorandum of appeal shall be in English or in Hindi and shall set forth 
    concisely and under distinct heads the grounds of appeal without any 
    argument or narrative and such grounds shall be numbered consecutively.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every 
    memorandum of appeal or petition shall be in quadruplicate; and in the case 
    of a memorandum of appeal it shall be accompanied by four copies of the 
    order appealed against, one of which shall be either a certified copy of 
    such order or the order served on the appellant.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    address given at serial number 5 of the form appended to these rules as 
    referred to in sub-rule (1) shall be called the “registered address” of the 
    appellant and shall until duly changed by an application to the Tribunal be 
    deemed to be the address of the appellant for the purpose of the service of 
    all notices, processes and other communications in the appeal and other 
    connected proceedings till the final determination of the appeal and a 
    period of three months thereafter.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> In every 
    appeal, the competent authority which passed the order appealed against, 
    shall be impleaded as one of the respondents.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> A 
    memorandum of appeal shall be presented by the appellant in person, or when 
    there are more appellants than one by any of them, or by his authorised 
    representative, to the registrar or such other officer as may be authorised 
    in this behalf by the Chairman, or may be sent by registered post addressed 
    to the Registrar.  
 

    Explanation.—In this sub-rule, 
    the expression “authorised representative” shall include any person in the 
    employment or a legal practitioner or an accountant who is authorised to 
    appear on behalf of the appellant.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> When a 
    memorandum of appeal is sent by registered post, the date of receipt of the 
    said memorandum at the office of the Tribunal shall be the date of filing of 
    the appeal and the registrar 
    shall on every memorandum of appeal, endorse the date on which it is 
    presented or received at the office of the Tribunal and shall sign the 
    endorsement.  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> When an 
    appeal is presented after the expiry of forty-five days of the receipt of 
    the order served upon the appellant but not after sixty days, it shall be 
    accompanied by an application, supported by an affidavit, setting forth the 
    facts on which the appellant relies to satisfy the Tribunal that he had 
    sufficient cause for not preferring the appeal within forty-five days.  
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> Every 
    petition presented to the Tribunal, including a petition for stay, other 
    than petitions of a formal or routine character, shall be accompanied by an 
    affidavit as also four copies of such documents as are relied upon in 
    support of the petition.  
 
 

 
  


  
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Procedure for registration of appeals.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every memorandum of appeal filed within forty-five days of service of the 
    order of the competent authority, being in the form annexed to these rules 
    and otherwise in order, shall be registered in a book kept for the purpose 
    called the Register of Appeals and the
    registrar shall intimate the 
    appellant or his authorised representative accordingly.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If a 
    memorandum of appeal filed under sub-rule (1) is defective, but the defects 
    are minor or technical in character, the
    registrar may register the 
    appeal provisionally and call upon the appellant to remove the defects 
    within such time as may be specified and upon the defects being removed 
    within such specified time, the registration shall cease to be provisional 
    and the appeal shall be deemed to have been regularly registered under 
    sub-rule (1).  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> When a 
    memorandum of appeal is presented after the expiry of forty-five days but 
    within a period of sixty days after the date of service of the order of the 
    competent authority, and is otherwise in order, and is accompanied by a 
    petition for condition of delay, it shall be numbered and registered 
    provisionally subject to the delay being condoned by the Tribunal. Notice of 
    the application for condonation of delay may be given to the respondent, and 
    after hearing the parties, the Tribunal may condone the delay on being 
    satisfied that the appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from filing 
    the appeal in time. The registration of the appeal shall then cease to be 
    provisional and the appeal dealt with as though it has been registered under 
    sub-rule (1).  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> When the 
    memorandum of appeal is presented after the expiry of forty-five days but 
    within a period of sixty days after the date of service of the order of the 
    competent authority, and is not accompanied by a petition for condonation of 
    delay, the Registrar may register the appeal provisionally and call upon the 
    appellant to file a petition for condonation of delay within such time, as 
    may be specified, and in the event of such a petition being received, it 
    shall be treated as having been received along with the memorandum of appeal 
    and the appeal dealt within the manner prescribed in sub-rule (3).  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> When the 
    defects are not removed or a petition for condonation of delay is not filed 
    within the time specified in that behalf, the matter shall be placed before 
    the Tribunal for its orders.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Where a 
    memorandum of appeal is defective in material particulars, the
    registrar may return the 
    memorandum of appeal specifying the defects to the appellant, or may 
    intimate in writing those defects. On receipt of the memorandum of appeal 
    from the registrar the 
    appellant may within thirty days of its receipt re-submit the memorandum of 
    appeal with defects duly removed or in case of the memorandum of appeal 
    having not been returned to him and defects only having been intimated may 
    appear himself or through Counsel before the Registrar and remove those 
    defects within thirty days. The memorandum of appeal submitted thereafter if 
    found in order may be registered.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> When a 
    memorandum of appeal on the face of it appears to have been filed more than 
    sixty days after the date of service of the order of the competent authority 
    on the appellant, the appeal shall not be registered but the appellant shall 
    be called upon by the Registrar to show cause why the appeal should not be 
    dismissed as being out of time.  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> Every 
    petition for condonation of delay and every memorandum of appeal filed out 
    of time shall be placed before the Chairman who may direct the 
    petition/appeal to be posted before the Tribunal for its orders.  
 
 

 
  


  
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Procedure after registration of appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    After an appeal is registered one copy of the memorandum of appeal and 
    annexures thereto shall be served, as soon as possible, on the competent 
    authority either by registered post acknowledgement due, or through a 
    messenger and the parties shall be called upon to file their paper-books 
    within a period of thirty days from the date of receipt of the notice or 
    such further time as may be allowed. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Each party 
    shall file four copies of his paper-book which shall—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    be legibly typed or otherwise 
    reproduced by mechanical means;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    contain all documents upon which the 
    party proposes to rely during the course of hearing;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    contain only such documents and 
    material as have been referred, produced or relied upon, before the 
    competent authority;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    have pages number serially; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>    contain a full index or table of 
    contents.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> If the 
    paper-book referred to in sub-rule (2) contain any document in a language 
    other than English or Hindi a true translation thereof in English or Hindi 
    shall be added.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    parties shall be informed of the date and place of hearing of the appeal 
    either by registered post acknowledgement due or by notice served on them 
    through messenger:  
 
Provided that 
    where the parties or their authorised representatives are present before the 
    Tribunal, it may inform them orally of the date and place of hearing of the 
    appeal.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Any 
    petition for summoning witnesses or documents filed by a party may be heard, 
    if necessary, after giving notice to the other party.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Every 
    requisition, direction, letter, authorisation or written notice to be issued 
    by the Tribunal shall be signed by the Registrar and shall be sent by 
    registered post acknowledgement due or through a messenger.  
 
 

 
  


  
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Joint 
    hearing and disposal of appeals.—The 
    Tribunal may, whenever it considers necessary or expedient to do so, hear 
    one or more appeals together and dispose of them by a common order.  
 
 

 
  


  
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Grounds 
    which may be taken in appeal.—The 
    appellant shall not, except with the leave of the Tribunal, urge or be heard 
    in support of, any ground not set forth in the memorandum of appeal but the 
    Tribunal, in deciding the appeal shall not be confined to the grounds set 
    forth in the memorandum of appeal or taken with the leave of the Tribunal 
    under this rule:  
 
Provided that 
    the Tribunal shall not rest its decision on any ground other than the 
    grounds set forth in the memorandum of appeal unless the party which may be 
    affected thereby has had a reasonable opportunity of being heard on that 
    ground.  
 
 

 
  


  
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Adjournment.—The
    tribunal may adjourn the 
    hearing of any case to any other date and inform the parties or their 
    authorised representatives appearing on their behalf of the next date and 
    place of hearing of the case. 
 
 

 
  


  
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Dismissal of appeal for appellant’s default.—Where 
    on the day fixed for hearing or on any other day to which the hearing may be 
    adjourned, the appellant or his authorised representative does not appear 
    when the appeal is called on for hearing, the Tribunal may either dismiss 
    the appeal for default or proceed ex parte: 
 
Provided that 
    where the appeal has been dismissed for default or proceeded with ex 
    parte and the appellant appears thereafter and satisfies the Tribunal 
    that there was sufficient cause for his non-appearance when the appeal was 
    called on for hearing, the Tribunal shall, after giving notice to the 
    respondent, make an order setting aside the dismissal order or the ex 
    parte proceedings and restoring the appeal to its original number.  
 
 

 
  


  
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Effect 
    of death, insolvency, etc., on appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    An appeal shall not abate by reason only of the death of an appellant or on 
    his adjudication as an insolvent. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Tribunal may on an application made in this behalf by a legal representative 
    of a deceased appellant make him a party and proceed with the appeal.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> When no 
    application is made within ninety days of the death of an appellant or 
    within such further time as the Tribunal may allow for bringing his legal 
    representative on record, the appeal shall abate.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> On the 
    insolvency of an appellant, the appeal may be continued by the assignee or 
    the receiver for the benefit of creditors and if the assignee or the 
    receiver fails to continue the appeal, the Tribunal may on its own motion or 
    on an application by the respondent, dismiss the appeal.  
 
 

 
  


  
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> Remand 
    of case by the Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Tribunal may, whenever it considers it necessary, set aside an order of the 
    competent authority and remand the case to the competent authority for fresh 
    determination in the light of such directions as it may give.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Tribunal may if it considers necessary at any stage of the proceedings call 
    for a report or finding from the competent authority on such matters as it 
    may specify.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A copy of 
    any such report or finding referred to under sub-rule (2) shall be furnished 
    to the parties and they shall be heard thereon before the Tribunal 
    pronounces final orders.  
 
 

 
  


  
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Production of additional evidence before the Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The parties to an appeal shall not be entitled to produce additional 
    evidence, whether oral or documentary, before the Tribunal, where—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the competent authority from whose 
    order the appeal is preferred has refused to admit evidence which ought to 
    have been admitted, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the party seeking to produce additional 
    evidence, establishes that notwithstanding the exercise of due diligence, 
    such evidence was not within his knowledge or could not, after the exercise 
    of due diligence, be produced by him at the time when the order appealed 
    against was passed, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the Tribunal requires any document to 
    be produced or any witnesses to be examined to enable it to pronounce 
    orders, or for any other substantial cause, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the Tribunal is satisfied that the 
    competent authority has decided the case without giving a reasonable 
    opportunity to the appellant to adduce evidence on any point,  
 
it may allow such evidence or document to be 
    produced, or witness to be examined.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Wherever 
    additional evidence is allowed to be produced by the Tribunal, it shall 
    record the reason for its admission.  
 
 

 
  


  
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> Hearing 
    of appeals.—The place in which 
    the Tribunal sits for the purpose of hearing appeals shall be deemed to be 
    an open court, to which the public generally may have access so far as the 
    same can conveniently contain them:
 
Provided that 
    the Tribunal may, if it thinks fit, order at any stage of the hearing of an 
    appeal, that the public generally, or any particular person, shall not have 
    access to, or be or remain in, the room or building used by the Tribunal.  
 
 

 
  


  
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Pronouncement of order.—After the 
    hearing is over, the Tribunal may pronounce its order forthwith, or it may 
    reserve its order and if the orders are reserved, the Tribunal may at any 
    time before final orders are pronounced either on its own motion or on the 
    application of a party order that the appeal or petition be re-heard.
 
 

 
  


  
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> Order 
    to be communicated to parties.—Every 
    order of the Tribunal shall be in writing and a copy of every final order of 
    the Tribunal certified as a true copy by the
    registrar shall be supplied 
    free of cost to the parties as early as possible.
 
 

 
  


  
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> Signing 
    of orders.—
<section><number>1</number> Where the decision 
    of the Tribunal is unanimous, a common order shall be signed by all the 
    Members of the Tribunal. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A Member 
    who does not concur with the decision of the majority may deliver a 
    dissenting order.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where 
    there is a difference of opinion, the decision shall be in accordance with 
    the decision of the majority of Members of the Tribunal.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    decision of the majority shall be reduced to writing and signed by all the 
    members including the dissenting member.  
 
 

 
  


  
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Publication of orders.—Such of 
    the orders of the Tribunal as are deemed fit for publication in any 
    authoritative report or the press may be released for such publication on 
    such terms and conditions as the Tribunal may lay down. 
 
 

 
  


  
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> Orders 
    and directions in certain cases.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in these rules, the Tribunal may make such orders or 
    gives such directions as may be necessary or expedient to give effect to its 
    orders or to prevent abuse of its process or to secure the ends of justice.
 
 

 
  


  
</article><form>
 
 
 
 

s
 
 




The Appellate 
    Tribunal for Forfeited  

    Property (Procedure) Rules, 1989
 

 
 

 
 



    Form
 


(See 
    rules 5 and 6)
 


BEFORE 
    THE APPELLATE TRIBUNAL FOR FORFEITED PROPERTY, 

    NEW DELHI
 



    MEMORANDUM OF APPEAL
 

 
 


Section 68-O (1) of the Narcotic Drugs and 
    Psychotropic Substances Act, 1985
 


(61 of 1985)
 

 
 

 
 


F.P.A. No./M.P. 
    No..................................of......................20.........
 


To be filled up by the office of the Appellate 
    Tribunal.
 

 
 


In the 
    Matter of
 


Shri/Smt...............................................................................................................,Appellant;
 


Vs.
 


(i)    The Competent Authority, New 
    Delhi/*Bombay/Calcutta/Madras/Allahabad  Respondent
 


(ii)   Other respondents, if 
    any............................
 


1. Authority passing the order appealed 
    against:   
 


Comptent Authority, New 
    Delhi/Bombay/Calcutta/Madras/Allahabad*.
 


2. Date of the order.
 


3. Date of service of the order.
 


4. Specify whether a hearing in person or 
    through an authorised representative is desired.
 


5. Registered address of the appellant 
    (including telephone No., if any, for the service of all notices, processes 
    and communications).
 


6. Address of the Respondent:
 


(i)  The
    competent Authority, New 
    Delhi/Bombay/Calcutta/Madras/Allahabad.
 


(ii)  Other respondents, if any.  
 


7. Section or sub-section of the section of 
    Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances Act, 1985 under which the 
    Competent Authority passed the order and which is appealed against:
 


8. Relief claimed:
 


(i)  Specify whether the entire order is 
    disputed:
 


(ii)  If only certain items of properties are 
    disputed, enumerate them in an annexure:
 


9. Ground of appeal (Annex a separate sheet if 
    space is not sufficient).
 

 
 


.........................................
 


(Signature of Appellant)
 


........................................
 


Signature of Authorised 

    Representative, if any
 

 
 


Verification
 

 
 



    I,................................................................,the 
    appellant/authorised representative of the appellant, do hereby declare that 
    what is stated above is true to the best of my knowledge, information and 
    belief.
 


Verified today 
    the.............................day of.......................,20..........
 


Place..................................
 


Date..................................
 


.............................................
 


(Signature of the appellant or 

    his authorised representative)
 

 
 


*Strike out whatever is inapplicable. 
 


Notes.—(1) The memorandum of appeal 
    should be filed in quadruplicate accompanied by four copies of orders 
    appealed against (one of which shall be a certified copy of the order 
    appealed against or the original copy of it served on the appellant). Any 
    enclosure will also be in quadruplicate. 
 


(2) The memorandum of appeal should be written 
    in English or in Hindi and should set forth concisely and under distinct 
    heads the grounds of appeal and should be without any argument or narrative 
    and such grounds should be numbered consecutively. 
 


(3) It is enough if the memorandum of appeal 
    is signed either by the appellant or the authorised representative. Where it 
    is signed by the authorised representative, it should be accompanied by an 
    authorisation of the appellant in his favour. 
 


(4) For further details see the 
    Appellate Tribunal for Forfeited Property (Procedure) Rules, 1989 notified 
    under sub-section (5) of section 68-O of the
    narcotic Drugs and 
    Psychotropic Substances Act, 1985.  


 

 
 

 


 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>