<act><title>

THE DOWRY PROHIBITION (MAINTENANCE OF LISTS OF 
    PRESENTS TO THE BRIDE AND BRIDEGROOM) RULES, 19851</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Dowry Prohibition (Maintenance of Lists of 
    Presents to the Bride and Bridegroom) Rules, 1985.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They 
    shall come into force on the 2nd day of October, 1985 being the date 
    appointed for the coming into force of the Dowry Prohibition (Amendment) 
    Act, 1984 (63 of 1984).  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>2</number> Rules in accordance with which lists of presents are to be 
      maintained.—
<section><number>1</number> The list of presents which are given at the time of the 
      marriage to the bride shall be maintained by the 
      bride.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The list of presents which are given at the time of marriage to 
      the bridegroom shall be maintained by the bridegroom. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every list of presents referred to in sub-rule (1) or sub-rule 
      (2)— 
 <subsection><number>a</number>   shall be 
      prepared at the time of the marriage or as soon as possible after the 
      marriage, 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>   shall be in 
      writing,
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>   shall 
      contain,—
 <subsubsection><number>i</number>   a brief 
      description of each 
      present; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number>   the 
      approximate value of the present;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number>   the name 
      of the person who has given the present; and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iv</number>   where the person 
      giving the present is related to the bride or bridegroom, a description of 
      such relationship;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>d</number>   shall be 
      signed by both the bride and the bridegroom.
 Explanation 1.—Where the bride is unable to sign, 
      she may affix her thumb-impression in lieu of her signature after having 
      the list read out to her and obtaining the signature, on the list, of the 
      person who has so read out the particulars contained in the 
      list.
 Explanation 2.—Where the bridegroom is unable to 
      sign, he may affix his thumb-impression in lieu of his signature after 
      having the list read out to him and obtaining the signature, on the list 
      of the person who has so read out the particulars contained in the 
      list.
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number> The bride or the bridegroom may, if she or he so desires, 
      obtain on either or both of the lists referred to in sub-rule (1) or 
      sub-rule (2) the signature or signatures of any other person or persons 
      present at the time of the marriage.
  
 
  </section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>