<act><title>


    The CENTRAL RESERVE 
    POLICE FORCE ACT, 1949</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>


    <number>1</number> Short
title and extent.—
<section><number>1</number> This Act may be called the 
    Central Reserve Police Force Act, 1949.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    extends to the whole of India, and applies to members of the Force, wherever 
    they may be.

 
  



 
    .

</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>2</number>
Definitions.—In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the 
    subject or context,—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   “active duty” 
      means the duty to restore and preserve order in any local area in the 
      event of any disturbance therein;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   “close arrest” 
      means confinement within the Force or a detachment of the Force or a post 
      quarter-guard building or tent under charge of a guard;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   “the Force” means 
      the Central Reserve Police Force;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   “member of the 
      Force” means a person who has been appointed to the Force by the 
      Commandant, whether before or after the commencement of this Act, and in 
      sections 1, 3, 6, 7, 16, 17, 18 and 19, includes also a person appointed 
      to the Force by the Central Government whether before or after such 
      commencement;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   “open arrest” 
      means confinement within the precincts of any barracks, lines or camp for 
      the time being occupied by any part of the Force;
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   “prescribed” 
      means prescribed by rules made under this Act;
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>   “subordinate 
      officer” means a member of the Force of the rank of subedar-major, subedar, 
      jemadar or sub-inspector;
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>   the expressions 
      “assault”, “criminal force”, “fraudulently”, “reason to believe” and 
      “voluntarily causing hurt” have the meanings assigend to them respectively 
      in the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).
 

 

      COMMENTS
 </section><section>
<number>i</number> Member of Force 
      under suspension cannot be regarded as being on active duty; 
      Chaturbhuj v. State, 1982 Cr LJ 83 (Gau).
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> The words 
      “assault”, “criminal force”, “fraudulently”, “reason to believe” and 
      “voluntarily causing hurt” in section 2 (h) of the Act have been defined 
      in sections 351, 350, 25, 26 and 321 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 
      1860) respectively.
 
 
</subsection></section>

 
  



 
    .

</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>3</number>
Constitution of the Force.—
<section><number>1</number> There shall 
    continue to be an armed force maintained by the Central Government and 
    called the Central Reserve Police Force.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The Force shall be constituted in such manner, and the members of the Force 
    shall receive such pay, pension and other remuneration, as may be 
    prescribed.
 




 





</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>4</number>
Appointment and powers of superior 
    officers.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government may appoint to the Force a 
    Commandant and such other persons as it thinks fit to be assistant 
    commandants and company officers.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The Commandant and every other officer so appointed shall have, and may 
    exercise, such powers and authority as may be provided by or under this Act.

 
  



 
    .

</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>5</number>
Enrolment.—Before a person is appointed to be a member of the Force, 
    the statement contained in the recruiting roll set out in the Schedule shall 
    be read out and, if necessary, explained to him in the presence of an 
    officer appointed under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 4, and shall be signed by 
    such person in acknowledgement of its having been so read out to him:
 

    Provided that any person who has for a period of six months served with the 
    Force, shall, on appointment to the Force thereafter, be deemed to be a 
    member of the Force notwithstanding that the provisions of this section have 
    not been complied with in his case.

 
  



 
    .

</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>6</number>
Resignation and withdrawal from the 
    Force.—No member of the Force shall be at liberty to—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   resign his 
      appointment during the term of his engagement, except before the 
      expiration of the first three months of his service; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   withdraw himself 
      from all or any of the duties of his appointment, without the previous 
      permission in writing of the Commandant or Assistant Commandant or any 
      other officer authorised by the Commandant to grant such permission.
</section>
  

 
  



 
    .

</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>7</number>
General duties of members of the
Force.—
<section><number>1</number> It shall be 
    the duty of every member of the Force promptly to obey and to execute all 
    orders and warrants lawfully issued to him by any competent authority, to 
    detect and bring offenders to justice and to apprehend all persons whom he 
    is legally authorised to apprehend and for whose apprehension sufficient 
    grounds exist.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every member of the Force shall be liable to serve without and beyond, as 
    well as within the territory of India.
  

 
  



 
    .

</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>8</number> Superintendence,
control and administration of the
Force.—
<section><number>1</number> The superintendence of, and control over, the Force 
      shall vest in the Central Government; and the Force shall be administered 
      by the Central Government in accordance with the provisions of this Act 
      and of any rules made thereunder, through such officers as the Central 
      Government may from time to time appoint in this behalf.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The headquarters of the 
      Force shall be at Neemuch or at such other place as may from time to time 
      be specified by the Central Government.
 </section><section><number>3</number> While on active duty 
      outside its headquarters, the Force shall be subject to the general 
      control and direction of such authority or officer as may be prescribed or 
      as may be specially appointed by the Central Government in this 
      behalf.
  
 
  
 .</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>9</number>
More heinous offences.—Every member of the Force who—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   begins, excites, 
      causes or conspires to cause or joins in any mutiny, or, being present at 
      any mutiny, does not use his utmost endeavour to suppress it, or knowing, 
      or having reason to believe in, the existence of any mutiny, or of any 
      intention or conspiracy to mutiny or of any conspiracy against the State 
      does not, without delay, give information thereof to his superior officer; 
      or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   uses, or attempts 
      to use, criminal force to, or commits an assault on, his superior officer, 
      whether on or off duty, knowing or having reason to believe him to be 
      such; or
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   shamefully 
      abandons or delivers up any post or guard which is committed to his charge 
      or which it is his duty to defend; or
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   directly or 
      indirectly holds correspondence with, or assists or relieves any person in 
      arms against the State or omits to discover immediately to his superior 
      officer any such correspondence coming to his knowledge; or
 
who, while on active 
      duty,—
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   disobeys the 
      lawful command of his superior officer; or
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   deserts the 
      Force; or
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>   being a sentry, 
      sleeps upon his post or quits it without being regularly relieved or 
      without leave; or
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>   leaves his 
      commanding officer, or his post or party, to go in search of plunder; or
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>   quits his guard, 
      picquet, party or patrol without being regularly relieved or without 
      leave; or
 </section><section>
<number>j</number>   uses criminal 
      force to, or commits an assault on any person bringing provisions or other 
      necessaries to camp or quarters, or forces a safeguard or breaks into any 
      house or other place for plunder, or plunders, destroys or damages 
      property of any kind; or
 </section><section>
<number>k</number>   intentionally 
      causes or spreads a false alarm in action or in camp, garrison or 
      quarters; or
 </section><section>
<number>l</number>   displays 
      cowardice in the execution of his duty,
 
shall be punishable with transportation for 
      life for a term of not less than seven years or with imprisonment for a 
      term which may extend to fourteen years or with fine which may extend to 
      three months’ pay or with fine to that extent in addition to such sentence 
      of transportation or imprisonment.
  
 

      COMMENTS
 <subsection>
<number>i</number> If a member of the 
      Force, while not on active duty being under suspension, disobeys lawful 
      command of his superior officer, he commits an offence; Chaturbhuj 
      v. State, 1982 Cr LJ 83 (Gau).
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number> Section 9(e) to 
      (l) of the Act has to be regarded as part and parcel of section 10(p) and 
      if a member of the Force, while not on active duty, disobeys the lawful 
      command of his superior officer, he is punishable under the said clause;
      Chaturbhuj v. State, 1982 Cr LJ 83 (Gau).
 
 
</subsection></section>

 
  



 
    .

</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>10</number>
Less heinous offences.—Every member of the Force who—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   is in a state of 
      intoxication when on, or after having been warned for, any duty or on 
      parade or on the line of march; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   strikes or 
      attempts to force any sentry; or
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   being in command 
      of a guard, picquet or patrol, refuses to receive any prisoner or person 
      duly committed to his charge, or without proper authority releases any 
      person or prisoner placed under his charge, or negligently suffers any 
      such prisoner or person to escape; or
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   being under 
      arrest or in confinement, leaves his arrest or confinement, before he is 
      set at liberty by lawful authority; or
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   is grossly in 
      subordinate or insolent to his superior officer in the execution of his 
      office; or
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   refuses to 
      superintend or assist in the making of any field-work or other work of any 
      description ordered to be made either in quarters or in the field; or
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>   strikes or 
      otherwise ill-uses any member of the Force subordinate to him in rank or 
      position; or
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>   designedly or 
      through neglect injures or loses or fraudulently disposes of his arms, 
      clothes, tools, equipments, ammunition or accoutrements, or any such 
      articles entrusted to him or belonging to any other person; or
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>   malingers or 
      feigns or produces disease or infirmity in himself, or intentionally 
      delays his cure, or aggravates his disease or infirmity; or
 </section><section>
<number>j</number>   with intent to 
      render himself or any other person unfit for service, voluntarily causes 
      hurt to himself or any other person; or
 </section><section>
<number>k</number>   does not, when 
      called upon by his superior officer so to do or upon ceasing to be a 
      member of the Force forthwith deliver up, or duly account for, all or any 
      arms, ammunition, stores, accoutrements or other property issued or 
      supplied to him or in his custody or possession as such member; or
 </section><section>
<number>l</number>   knowingly 
      furnishes a false return or report of the number or state of any men under 
      his command or charge or of any money, arms, ammunition, clothing, 
      equipments, stores or other property in his charge, whether belonging to 
      such men or to the Government or to any member of, or any person attached 
      to the Force, or who, through design or culpable neglect, omits or refuses 
      to make or send any return or report of the matters aforesaid; or
 </section><section>
<number>m</number>   absents himself 
      without leave, or without sufficient cause overstays leave granted to him; 
      or
 </section><section>
<number>n</number>   is guilty of any 
      act or omission which, though not specified in this Act, is prejudicial to 
      good order and discipline; or
 </section><section>
<number>o</number>   contravenes any 
      provision of this Act for which no punishment is expressly provided; or
 
who, while not on 
      active duty,—
 </section><section>
<number>p</number>   commits any of 
      the offences specified in clauses (e) to (l) (both inclusive) of section 
      9,
 
shall be punishable with imprisonment for a 
      term which may extend to one year, or with fine which may extend to three 
      months’ pay, or with both.
  
 

      COMMENTS
 
Where the accused has 
      pleaded guilty of absence without leave and he has concurrently been 
      found to have disobeyed the lawful command of his superior officer, he 
      can rightly be convicted under section 10(m) and (p) of the Act; 
      Chaturbhuj v. State, (1982) Cr LJ 83 (Gau).
  
</section>

 
  




</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>11</number>
Minor punishments.—
<section><number>1</number> The Commandant or any other authority 
    or officer as may be prescribed, may, subject to any rules made under this 
    Act, award in lieu of, or in addition to, suspension or dismissal any one or 
    more of the following punishments to any member of the Force whom he 
    considers to be guilty of disobedience, neglect of duty, or remissness in 
    the discharge of any duty or of other misconduct in his capacity as a member 
    of the Force, that is to say,—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   reduction in 
      rank;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   fine of any 
      amount not exceeding one month’s pay and allowances;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   confinement to 
      quarters, lines or camp for a term not exceeding one month;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   confinement in 
      the quarter-guard for not more than twenty-eight days, with or without 
      punishment drill or extra guard, fatigue or other duty; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   removal from any 
      office of distinction or special emolument in the Force.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Any punishment specified in clause (c) or clause (d) of sub-section (1) may 
    be awarded by any gazetted officer when in command of any detachment of the 
    Force away from headquarters, provided he is specially authorised in this 
    behalf by the commandant.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    The assistant commandant, a company officer or a subordinate officer, not 
    being below the rank of subedar or inspector, commanding a separate 
    detachment or an outpost, or in temporary command at the headquarters of the 
    Force, may, without a formal trial, award to any member of the Force who is 
    for the time being subject to his authority any one or more of the following 
    punishment for the commission of any petty offence against discipline which 
    is not otherwise provided for in this Act, or which is not of a sufficiently 
    serious nature to require prosecution before a criminal court, that is to 
    say,—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   confinement for 
      not more than seven days in the quarter-guard or such other place as may 
      be considered suitable, with forfeiture of all pay and allowances during 
      its continuance;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   punishment drill, 
      or extra guard, fatigue or other duty, for not more than thirty days with 
      or without confinement to quarters, lines or camp;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   censure or severe 
      censure:
 

      Provided that this punishment may be awarded to a subordinate officer only 
      by the Commandant.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A 
    jemadar or sub-inspector who is temporarily in command of a detachment or an 
    outpost may, in like manner and for the commission of any like offence, 
    award to any member of the Force for the time being subject to his authority 
    any of the punishments specified in clause (b) of sub-section (3) for not 
    more than fifteen days.
 




 






</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>12</number>
Place of imprisonment and liability to
dismissal on imprisonment.—
<section><number>1</number> Every person sentenced 
    under this Act to imprisonment may be dismissed from the Force, and shall 
    further be liable to forfeiture of pay, allowance and any other moneys due 
    to him as well as of any medals and decorations received by him.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every such person shall, if he is so dismissed, be imprisoned in the 
    prescribed prison, but if he is not also dismissed from the Force, he may, 
    if the Court or the Commandant so directs, be confined in the quarter-guard 
    or such other place as the Court or the Commandant may consider suitable.
 





 





</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>13</number>
Deductions from pay and allowances.—The 
    following penal deductions may be made from the pay and allowances of a 
    member of the Force by his company officer, that is to say,—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   all pay and 
      allowances for every day of absence either on desertion or without leave 
      and for every day of imprisonment awarded by a Criminal Court or of 
      confinement awarded under section 11;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   all pay and 
      allowances for every day whilst he is in custody on a charge for an 
      offence of which he is afterwards convicted;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   all pay and 
      allowances for every day on which he is in hospital on account of sickness 
      certified by the medical officer attending on him at the hospital to have 
      been caused by an offence committed by him under this Act;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   all pay and 
      allowances ordered to be forfeited under section 11; and 

 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   such sum as may 
      be ordered by the Commandant or assistant commandant in order to make good 
      any expenses caused by the member of the Force, or any loss of, or damage 
      or destruction done by him to, any arms, ammunition, equipment, clothing, 
      instruments or decorations belonging to the Force or to any buildings or 
      property.
</section>

 
  



 
    .

</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>14</number>
Collective fines.—Whenever any weapon, part of a weapon or 
    ammunition, forming part of the equipment of a company or other similar unit 
    of the Force, is lost or stolen the Commandant may, after making such 
    inquiry as he thinks fit and subject to such rules as may be prescribed, 
    impose a collective fine upon the subordinate officers and men of such unit, 
    or upon so many of them as, in his judgment, should be held responsible for 
    such loss or theft.
  

 
  



 
    .

</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>15</number>
Arrest.—
<section><number>1</number> Any member of the Force who commits any offence specified 
    in section 9 or section 10 may be placed on open or close arrest by any 
    officer of the Force.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where any subordinate officer orders an arrest under sub-section (1), he 
    shall forthwith or at the earliest opportunity report the arrest to his 
    company or detachment Commander who shall after investigating the case order 
    the release or the continued arrest of the member of the Force arrested.
  

 
  



 
    .

</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>16</number>
Powers and duties conferrable and 
    imposable on members of the Force.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by general or special order, confer or impose 
    upon any member of the Force any of the powers or duties conferred or 
    imposed on a police officer of any class or grade by any law for the time 
    being in force.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 
    (5 of 1898) the Central Government may invest the Commandant or an assistant 
    commandant with the powers of a Magistrate of any class for the purpose of 
    inquiring into or trying any offence committed by member of the Force and 
    punishable under this Act, or any offence committed by a member of the Force 
    against the person or property of another member:
 

    Provided that—
 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   when the offender 
      is on leave or absent from duty, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   when the offence 
      is not connected with the offender's duties as a member of the Force, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   when it is a 
      petty offence, even if connected with the offender's duties as a member of 
      the Force,
</subsection>
 
the offence may, if the prescribed authority 
    within the limits of whose jurisdiction the offence has been committed, so 
    directs, be inquired into or tried by an ordinary Criminal Court having 
    jurisdiction in the matter.

 
  



 
    .

</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>17</number>
Protection for acts of members of
the Force.—
<section><number>1</number> In any suit or proceeding against any member of 
    the Force for any act done by him in pursuance of a warrant or order of a 
    competent authority it shall be lawful for him to plead that such act was 
    done by him under the authority of such warrant or order.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Any such plea may be proved by the production of the warrant or order 
    directing the act and if it is so proved the member of the Force shall 
    thereupon be discharged from liability in respect of the act so done by him, 
    notwithstanding any defect in the jurisdiction of the authority which issued 
    such warrant or order.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being in 
    force, any legal proceeding (whether civil or criminal) which may lawfully 
    be brought against any member of the Force for anything done or intended to 
    be done under the powers conferred by, or in pursuance of, any provision of 
    this Act or the rules thereunder, shall be commenced within three months 
    after the act complained of was committed, and not otherwise, and notice in 
    writing of such proceeding and of the cause thereof shall be given to the 
    defendant or his superior officer at least one month before the commencement 
    of such proceeding.

 
  



 
    .

</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>18</number>
Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government 
    may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out 
    the purposes of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   regulating the 
      classes and grades of, and the pay, pension and other remuneration of 
      members of the Force, and their conditions of service in the Force;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   regulating the 
      powers and duties of officers authorised to exercise any functions by or 
      under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   fixing the period 
      of service for members of the Force;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   regulating the 
      award of minor punishment under section 11, and providing for appeals 
      from, or the revision of, orders under that section, or the remission of 
      fines imposed under that section, and the remission of deductions made 
      under section 13;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   regulating the 
      several or collective liability of members of the Force in the case of the 
      loss or theft of weapons and ammunition;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   for the disposal 
      of criminal cases arising under this Act and for specifying the prison in 
      which a person convicted in any such case may be confined.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>3</number> 
    Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is 
    made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total 
    period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or 
    more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
    immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both 
    Houses agree in making any modification in the rule, or both Houses agree 
    that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only 
    in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, 
    that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
    validity of anything previously done under that rule.]
 








 






</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>19</number>
Validation of acts done before 
    commencement of Act.—Any order made, thing done, or action 
    taken by or in relation to a member of the Force, on or after the 15th day 
    of August, 1947, but before the commencement of this Act, shall for all 
    purposes be deemed to have been made, done or taken under this Act, as if 
    this Act were in force on the day on which such order was made, thing was 
    done or action was taken.
  

 
  



 
    .

</article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




    The CENTRAL RESERVE 
    POLICE FORCE ACT, 1949
 

 
 



 



    the schedule
 


recruiting roll 

(See section 5)
 

 
 


After you have served in the Force for such 
    period as the Central Government may prescribe, you may, at any time when 
    not on active duty, apply for discharge, through the officer to whom you may 
    be subordinate, to the Commandant, and you will be granted your discharge 
    after two months, from the date of your application, unless your discharge 
    would cause the vacancies in the Force to exceed one-tenth of the sanctioned 
    strength in which case you shall be bound to remain until this objection is 
    waived or removed. But when on active duty, you shall have no claim to a 
    discharge, and you shall be bound to remain to do your duty until the 
    necessity for retaining you in the Force ceases when you may make your 
    application in the above-mentioned manner:
 


Provided that, if you wish to withdraw from 
    the Force, you may submit your resignation at any time beofre the expiration 
    of the first three months of your service, but not afterwards until the 
    completion of the period prescribed as aforesaid; the Commandant may either 
    accept your resignation forthwith or at the end of three months from the 
    date of its receipt:
 


Provided, also, that the Commandant may, if 
    he thinks fit, allow you to resign at any time on your giving three months’ 
    notice of your wish to do so.
 


Signature of the member of the Force in 
    acknowledgement of the above having been read out to him.
 


Space for impression of the member's left 
    thumb to be taken in the presence of the enrolling officer.
 


Signed in my presence after I had 
    ascertained that the candidate understood the purport of what he signed.
 

 
 


    Place................................                                              
    Commandant, 

Date.................................                              
    or other authorised enrolling officer.
 
 

 



 


    .

</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>             Ins. by Act 4 of 1986, sec. 2 and Sch. (w.e.f. 15-5-1986).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>