<act><title>
THE 
    REPATRIATION OF PRISONERS 
    RULES, 20041</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    <number>1</number> Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called  the Repatriation of Prisoners Rules, 2004.
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the 
    Official Gazette. 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    <number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
    these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>


    <number>a</number>    “Act” means the Repatriation of Prisoners Act, 2003 (49 of 2003);  
 </section><section>


    <number>b</number>    “application” means an application made under section 4 of the Act;  
 </section><section>


    <number>c</number>    “diplomatic channel” means through the missions of the respective 
    countries;  
 </section><section>


    <number>d</number>    “section” means a section of the Act;  
 </section><section>


    <number>e</number>    all other words and expressions used in these rules and not defined 
    but defined in the Act shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them 
    in that Act.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    <number>3</number> Form of application.—An 
    application under section 4 of the Act shall be made by a prisoner for his 
    transfer on a plain paper and in Form I appended to these rules and in 
    accordance with the procedure and instructions set out in that form. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    <number>4</number> Means of forwarding the application.—The 
    application of the prisoner along with other information as required under 
    sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 6, shall be forwarded by the Central Government 
    to the Government of the contracting State either directly or through the 
    diplomatic channel.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    <number>5</number> Form of warrants.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A warrant under sub-section (1) of section 7 of the Act shall be issued in 
    Form 2 appended to these rules and in accordance with the procedure and 
    instruction set out in that form.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> A warrant under sub-section (2) of section 12 of the Act shall be issued 
    in Form 3 appended to these rules and in accordance with the procedure and 
    instructions set out in that form.  
 
  


</section></article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE 
    REPATRIATION OF PRISONERS  

     RULES, 2004
 

 
 

 
 




    FORM 1
 




    Application for transfer of sentenced person
 




    (Under rule 3)
 




    (Particulars are to be furnished in respect of the sentenced person)
 




    To
 




            Joint Secretary (CS),
 




            Government of India,
 




            Ministry of Home Affairs,
 




            North Block,
 




            New Delhi.
 




    Sir,
 




    I request that I may be transferred to serve remaining period of my sentence 
    in a prison situated in............... the country of my nationality (Name 
    of the contracting State). I hereby furnish the following information for 
    consideration of my application:—
 




                     1.    Name in block letters and nationality        :
 




                     2.    Name of father/husband                         :
 




                     3.    Full address in the contracting State        :
 




                     4.    Date of birth/age                                  :
 




                     5.    Offence(s) under which convicted            :
 




                     6.    Name of the Court which convicted          :
 




                     7.    Date of judgment                                  :
 




                     8.    The nature, duration and date of  

         commencement of the 
    sentence               :
 




                     9.    Name of the prison, where undergoing sentence.
 




    I, ............................................................ (Name in 
    full along with nationality and in block letters), son/daughter of Mr./Ms. 
    ................................... declare that the information furnished 
    by me as above is correct, complete and true to the best of my knowledge and 
    belief. I may be held liable for any action if any information furnished by 
    me is found incorrect.
 

 
 




    Address (In case signatory is other
 


than the prisoner:
 




    (Signature of the applicant or of the 
 




    person entitled to act on behalf of the
 




    prisoner in case of his ill health, mental
 




    condition, old age or being minor)
 




    (Please see instructions)
 

 
 




    Instructions
 




    1. The application in original should be sent to Joint Secretary (CS), 
    Government of India, Ministry of Home Affairs, North Block, New Delhi by 
    ordinary/registered post.
 




    2. A copy of the application may be delivered to the officer-in-charge of 
    the jail where the prisoner is undergoing the sentence.
 




    3. Following documents may be attached with the application:—
 




    (a)    A copy of the judgment passed against the prisoner.
 




    (b)    Document indicating that the prisoner is a citizen of the contracting 
    State.
 




    4. In case the application is being made by the person entitled to act on 
    behalf of the prisoner, he/she should write his/her full name along with 
    nationality and address below his/her signature.  
 

 
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE 
    REPATRIATION OF PRISONERS  

     RULES, 2004
 

 
 

 
 




    FORM 2
 




    Form of Warrant
 




    [See rule 5(1)]
 




    [Under sub-section (1) of section 7 of the Repatriation of Prisoners Act, 
    2003]
 

 
 




    Mr/Ms.............................................., the Jail 
    Superintendent/Jailor (or the officer’s designation who is incharge of the 
    prison where the prisoner is 
    imprisoned)...................................(Name of the Jail with full 
    address) is hereby directed to deliver the custody of Mr/Ms.............................................................(Name 
    and nationality of Prisoner), son/wife/daughter 
    of...................................... age ............. 
    address................ (as it appears in the prison record) who was 
    convicted of offences under section(s).................. of 
    ......................................................... (Name of the 
    legislation under which sentenced) to Mr/Ms............................................................ 
    [Name and designation of the authorised person (official) of the contracting 
    State],......................... at..............................(Place of 
    delivery of prisoner in India i.e. Embassy, Air Port etc.) 
    on.................................(Date of delivery) as requested by the 
    Government of............................... in terms of 
    Agreement/Arrangement between the Government of the Republic of India and 
    the Government of............................ on transfer of convicted 
    offenders entered into by India with............................(Name of the 
    contracting State) which came into force on........................ .
 




    2. Mr/Ms...................................... (Name of the prisoner) as 
    mentioned hereinabove, would undergo the remaining part of the sentence in 
    contracting State, which he/she would have undergone in India, had he/she 
    not been transferred out of India.
 




    3. In case the prisoner escapes from the custody within India, the prisoner 
    may be arrested without  warrant by any person  who shall without undue 
    delay deliver such prisoner to the nearest police station and the prisoner 
    so arrested  shall be liable for committing an offence under section 224 of 
    the Indian Penal Code and shall also be liable for such sentence of 
    imprisonment in India which he would have to undergo if the delivery of 
    custody of such prisoner had not been made under section 8.
 

 
 




    Authorised Officer of the State Government
 




    (Not below the rank of a Joint Secretary)
 




    To
 




            Shri/Smt..........................
 




            ......................................(Designation)
 




            Address ........................
 




            ....................................
 




    Copy to:
 




    (i)    Joint Secretary (CS), Ministry of Home Affairs, Government of India.
 




    (ii)    Joint Secretary (CPV), Ministry of External Affairs, Government of 
    India.
 




    (iii)    Secretary, Department of Prison
 




    Government of.........................................(State in which 
    imprisoned)
 




    (iv)    Charge-d’-Affairs, 
    Embassy..........................................................(Name of 
    the contracting State)
 




    Address (official)..........................  
 




    (v)    Mr/Ms.....................................[Name and address of the 
    Authorised person (official) of the contracting State]
 

 
 

 
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE 
    REPATRIATION OF PRISONERS  

     RULES, 2004
 

 
 

 
 




    FORM 3
 




    Form of Warrant
 




    [See rule 5(2)]
 




    [Under sub-section (2) of the section 12 of the Repatriation of Prisoners 
    Act, 2003]
 

 
 




    Mr/Ms.......................................... Designation 
    ...................................................................... 
    Address (official).................................................. , is 
    hereby directed to receive the custody of Mr/Ms............................................................(Name 
    and nationality of the prisoner) Address 
    ..................................................................... (as it 
    appears in the letter of the contracting State) at 
    .......................... (Place of receiving of the prisoner outside India 
    by authorised official) and to hold the prisoner for bringing him to India 
    from the place of receiving. The custody of the said prisoner shall be 
    handed over by the receiving officer to the officer-in-charge of 
    ........................................ (Name and address of the prison) 
    where the prisoner has to serve his/her remaining part of the sentence in 
    India as per the existing law for the offence committed by him/her in the 
    contracting State.
 




    2. In case the prisoner escapes from the custody, the said prisoner may be 
    arrested without warrant by any person who shall without undue delay deliver 
    such prisoner to the officer-in-charge of the nearest police station and the 
    prisoner so arrested shall be liable for committing an offence under section 
    224 of the Indian Penal Code or the applicable law depending upon the place 
    of escape and shall also be liable to be dealt with in accordance with this 
    warrant.
 

 
 




    Authorised Officer of the State Government
 




    (Not below the rank of a Joint Secretary)
 




    To
 




            Shri/Smt............................
 




            .........................................(Designation)
 




            Address ..........................
 




            ........................................
 




    Copy to:
 




    (i)    Joint Secretary (CS), Ministry of Home Affairs, Government of India.
 




    (ii)    Joint Secretary (CPV), Ministry of External Affairs, Government of 
    India.
 




    (iii)    Secretary, Department of Prison
 




    Government of.........................................(State in which 
    imprisoned)
 




    (iv)    Charge-d’-Affairs, 
    Embassy.............................................................(Name of 
    the contracting State)
 




    Address (official)..........................               

 


 
 

 
 

 
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>