<act><title>


THE BATTERIES (MANAGEMENT AND HANDLING) 
RULES, 20011</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Batteries (Management and Handling) Rules, 2001.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 


</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Application.—These 
rules shall apply to every manufacturer, importer, re-conditioner, assembler, 
dealer, recycler, auctioneer, consumer and bulk consumer involved in 
manufacture, processing, sale, purchase and use of batteries or components 
thereof.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  ‘Act’ means 
the Environment (Protection) Act, 1986 (29 of 1986);
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  ‘assembler’ 
means a person who manufactures lead acid batteries by assembling various 
components;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  ‘auction’  
means bulk sale of used lead acid batteries or component(s) thereof by 
invitation of tenders or auction, contract or negotiation by individual(s), 
companies or Government Departments;
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  ‘auctioneer’ 
means a person (s) who auctions used lead acid batteries or components, thereof;
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number>  ‘battery’ 
means lead acid battery which is a source of electrical energy and contains lead 
metal;
 </section><section>
        <number>f</number>  ‘bulk 
consumer’  means a consumer such as Central or State Government Departments of 
Railways, Defence, Telecom, Posts and Telegraph, State Road Transport 
Undertakings, State Electricity Boards and others who purchase batteries through 
Central ‘rate’ or running contract centrally placed on behalf of individual 
departments or user units under their jurisdiction;
 </section><section>
       <number>g</number>  ‘components’ 
means lead bearing components of a lead acid battery;
 </section><section>
       <number>h</number>  ‘consumer’ 
means a person using lead acid batteries excluding bulk consumers;
 </section><section>
        <number>i</number>  ‘dealer’ 
means a person who sells and receives lead acid batteries or components thereof 
to and from the consumers or other dealers or retailers on behalf of the 
manufacturers, importers, assemblers and reconditioners or otherwise;
 </section><section>
        <number>j</number>  ‘designated 
collection centre’ means a collection centre established, individually or 
jointly by one or more manufacturers or importers, assemblers and 
re-conditioners in pursuance of their responsibilities under rule 4 of these 
rules;
 </section><section>
       <number>k</number>  ‘importer’ 
means a person who imports new lead acid batteries or components containing lead 
thereof for the purpose of sale;
 </section><section>
        <number>l</number>  
‘manufacturer’ in relation to any factory manufacturing lead acid batteries or 
components thereof means a person or Chief Executive Officer (CEO) of the 
company who has control over the affairs of the factory or the premises for sale 
and collection of lead acid batteries or components thereof;
 </section><section>
       <number>m</number>  ‘original 
equipment manufacturer’  means manufacturer of equipment or product using lead 
acid batteries as a component;
 </section><section>
       <number>n</number>  
‘reconditioner’ means a person involved in repairing of lead acid batteries for 
selling the same in the market;
 </section><section>
       <number>o</number>  ‘recycler’ 
means an occupier who processes used lead acid batteries or components thereof 
for recovering lead;
 </section><section>
       <number>p</number>  ‘registered 
recycler’ means a recycler registered with the Ministry of Environment and 
Forests or an agency designated by it for reprocessing used lead acid batteries 
or components thereof;
 </section><section>
       <number>q</number>  ‘State Board’ 
means the concerned State Pollution Control Board or the Pollution Control 
Committee as the case may be;
 </section><section>
        <number>r</number>  ‘used 
batteries’ means used, damaged and old lead acid batteries or components 
thereof; and
 </section><section>
       <number>s</number>  the words not 
defined in these rules will have the same meaning as defined in the Environment 
(Protection) Act, 1986 and the rules framed thereunder.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>4</number> Responsibilities of 
manufacturer, importer, assembler and re-conditioner.—It shall be the 
responsibility of a manufacturer, importer, assembler and re-conditioner 
to—
 <section>        
<number>i</number>  ensure that the used batteries are collected back as per the Schedule 
against new batteries sold excluding those sold to original equipment 
manufacturer and bulk consumer(s);
 </section><section>        
<number>ii</number>  ensure that used batteries collected back are of similar type and 
specifications as that of the new batteries sold;
 </section><section>       
<number>iii</number>  file a half-yearly return of their sales and buy-back to the State 
Board in Form I latest by 30th June and 31st December of every year;
 </section><section>       
<number>iv</number>  set up collection centres either individually or jointly at various 
places for collection of used batteries from consumers or dealers;
 </section><section>       
<number>v</number>  ensure that used batteries collected are sent only to the registered 
recyclers;
 </section><section>       
<number>vi</number>  ensure that necessary arrangements are made with dealers for safe 
transportation from collection centres to the premises of registered 
recyclers;
 </section><section>      
<number>vii</number>  ensure that no damage to the environment occurs during 
transportation;
 </section><section>     
<number>viii</number>  create public awareness through advertisements, publications, 
posters or by other means with regard to the following:—
 <subsection>            
<number>a</number>  hazards of lead;
 </subsection><subsection>            
<number>b</number>  responsibility of consumers to return their used batteries only to the 
dealers or deliver at designated collection centres; and
 </subsection><subsection>            
<number>c</number>  addresses of dealers and designated collection centres;
 </subsection></section><section>       
<number>ix</number>  use the international recycling sign on the batteries;
 </section><section>       
<number>x</number>  buy recycled lead only from registered recyclers; and
 </section><section>       
<number>xi</number>  bring to the notice of the State Board or the Ministry of Environment 
and Forests any violation by the dealers.</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
5.
Registration of Importers.—The importer shall get himself registered with 
the Ministry of Environment and Forests or an agency designated by it by 
submitting details in Form II.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Customs clearance of 
imports of new lead acid batteries.—Customs 
clearance of imports shall be contingent upon—
 <section>
        <number>i</number>  valid 
registration with the Reserve Bank of India (with Importer’s Code Number);
 </section><section>
        <number>ii</number>  one time 
registration with the Ministry of Environment and Forests or an agency 
designated by it in Form II;
 </section><section>
       <number>iii</number>  undertaking 
in Form III; and
 </section><section>
       <number>iv</number>  a copy of the 
latest half-yearly return in Form IV.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number>
Responsibilities of dealer.—It shall be the responsibility of a dealer 
to—
 <section>
        <number>i</number>  ensure that 
the used batteries are collected back as per the Schedule against new batteries 
sold;
 </section><section>
        <number>ii</number>  give 
appropriate discount for every used battery returned by the consumer;
 </section><section>
       <number>iii</number>  ensure that
used batteries collected back are of similar type and specifications as that 
of the new batteries sold;
 </section><section>
       <number>iv</number>  file 
half-yearly returns of the sale of new batteries and buy-back of old batteries 
to the manufacturer in Form V by 31st May and 30th November of every year;
 </section><section>
       <number>v</number>  ensure safe 
transportation of collected batteries to the designated collection centres or to 
the registered recyclers; and
 </section><section>
       <number>vi</number>  ensure that 
no damage is caused to the environment during storage and transportation of used 
batteries.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Responsibilities of 
recycler.—Each 
recycler shall—
 <section>
        <number>i</number>  apply for 
registration to the Ministry of Environment and Forests or an agency designated 
by it if not applied already, by submitting information in Form VI;
 </section><section>
        <number>ii</number>  ensure 
strict compliance of the terms and conditions of registration; however, those 
already registered with the Ministry of Environment and Forests or agency 
designated by it for reprocessing used batteries would be bound by the terms and 
conditions of such registration;
 </section><section>
       <number>iii</number>  submit 
annual returns as per Form VII to the State Board;
 </section><section>
       <number>iv</number>  make 
available all records to the State Board for inspection;
 </section><section>
       <number>v</number>  mark 
‘Recycled’ on lead recovered by reprocessing; and
 </section><section>
       <number>vi</number>  create public 
awareness through advertisements, publications, posters or others with regard to 
the following:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  hazards of 
lead; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  obligation of 
consumers to return used batteries only to the registered dealers or deliver at 
the designated collection centres.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Procedure for 
registration/renewal of registration of recyclers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every recycler of used lead acid batteries shall make an application in Form VI 
along with the following documents to the Joint Secretary, Ministry of 
Environment and Forests or any officer designated by the Ministry or an agency 
designated by it for grant of registration or renewal—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  a copy of the 
valid consents under Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1974, as 
amended and Air (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1981, as amended;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  a copy of the 
valid authorisation under Hazardous Wastes (Management and Handling) Rules, 1989 
as amended;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  a copy of 
valid certificate of registration with District Industries Centre; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  a copy of the 
proof of installed capacity issued by either State Pollution Control 
Board/District Industries Centre.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Joint Secretary, 
Ministry of Environment and Forests or any officer designated by the 
Ministry or an agency designated by it shall ensure that the recyclers possess 
appropriate facilities, technical capabilities, and equipment to recycle used 
batteries and dispose of hazardous waste generated.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Joint Secretary, 
Ministry of Environment and Forests or any officer designated by the Ministry or 
an agency designated by it shall take decision on application for registration 
within 120 days of receipt of application form with complete details.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The registration 
granted under this rule shall be in force for a period of two years from the
date of issue or from the date of renewal unless suspended or cancelled 
earlier.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> An application for the 
renewal of registration shall be made in Form VI atleast six months before its 
expiry. The Joint Secretary, Ministry of Environment and Forests or any officer 
designated by the Ministry or an agency designated by it shall renew the 
registration of the recycler granted under sub-rule (4) of this rule, after 
examining each case on merit.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The Joint Secretary, 
Ministry of Environment and Forests or any officer designated by the Ministry or 
an agency designated by it may, after giving reasonable opportunity to the 
applicant of being heard, refuse to grant registration.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The Joint Secretary, 
Ministry of Environment and Forests or any officer designated by the Ministry or 
an agency designated by it may cancel or suspend a registration issued under 
these rules, if in his / her opinion, the registered recycler has failed to 
comply with any of the conditions of registration, or with any provisions of the 
Act or rules made thereunder after giving him an opportunity to explain and 
after recording the reasons therefor.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> It shall be the 
responsibility of the State Boards to monitor the compliance of conditions 
prescribed while according registration.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> An appeal shall lie 
against any order of suspension or cancellation or refusal of registration 
passed by the Joint Secretary to the Ministry of Environment and Forests or any 
officer designated by the Ministry or an agency designated by it. The appeal 
shall be in writing and shall be accompanied with a copy of the order appealed 
against and shall be presented within 30 days of passing of the order.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number>
Responsibilities of consumer or bulk consumer.—
<section><number>1</number> It shall be the 
responsibility of the consumer to ensure that used batteries are not disposed of 
in any manner other than depositing with the dealer, manufacturer, importer, 
assembler, registered recycler, reconditioner or at the designated collection 
centres.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It shall be the 
responsibility of the bulk consumer to—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  ensure that 
used batteries are not disposed of in any manner other than by depositing with 
the dealer/manufacturer/registered recycler/importer/ reconditioner or at the 
designated collection centres, and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  file 
half-yearly return in Form VIII to the State Board.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Bulk consumers or 
their user units may auction used batteries to registered recyclers only.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number>
Responsibilities of auctioneer.—The auctioneer shall—
 <section>
        <number>i</number>  ensure that 
used batteries are auctioned to the registered recyclers only;
 </section><section>
        <number>ii</number>  file 
half-yearly returns of their auctions to the State Boards in Form IX; and
 </section><section>
       <number>iii</number>  maintain a 
record of such auctions and make these records available to the State Board for 
inspection.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Prescribed 
Authority.—The 
prescribed authority for ensuring compliance of the provisions of these rules 
shall be the State Board. And, it shall file an annual compliance status report 
to the Central Pollution Control Board by 30th April of every year.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Duties of Central 
Pollution Control Board.—The 
Central Pollution Control Board shall compile and publish the data received 
every year from the State Boards. It shall review the compliance of the rules 
periodically to improve the collection and recycling of used lead batteries and 
apprise the Ministry of Environment and Forests, Government of India.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Computerisation of 
Records and Returns.—Ministry 
of Environment and Forests or an agency designated by it shall develop a system 
for computerised tracking of—
 <section>
        <number>i</number>  distribution 
and sale of batteries;
 </section><section>
        <number>ii</number>  collection, 
auction, transport and re-processing of used batteries;
 </section><section>
       <number>iii</number>  sale of 
re-processed lead by registered recyclers; and
 </section><section>
       <number>iv</number>  sale of lead 
from all domestic producers or importers.
 
 
</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>