<act><title>THE GAS CYLINDERS RULES, 2004 
1</title> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 20041
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004.
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force 
on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
  


</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>         <number>i</number>   “Act” means the Explosives Act, 1884 (4 of 
1884);
 </section><section>        <number>ii</number>   “Auto LPG” means liquefied petroleum gas 
meant for automotive fuel conforming to specification IS: 14861;
 </section><section>       <number>iii</number>   “Chief Controller” means the Chief Controller 
of Explosives, Government of India;
 </section><section>       <number>iv</number>   “composite cylinder” means a cylinder made of 
resin impregnated continuous filament wound over a metallic or a non-metallic 
liner. Composite cylinders using non-metallic liners are referred to as 
all-composite cylinders;
 </section><section>        <number>v</number>   “compressed gas” means any permanent gas, 
liquefiable gas or gas dissolved in liquid under pressure or gas mixture which 
in a closed gas cylinder exercises a pressure either exceeding 2.5 kgf/ cm2 abs. 
(1.5 Kgf/cm2gauge) 
at + 15oC 
or a pressure exceeding 3 Kgf/cm2 abs. 
(2 Kgf/cm2gauge) 
at +50oC 
or both.
  Explanation.—Hydrogen Fluoride 
falls within the scope of com­pressed gas although its vapour pressure at 50oC 
is 1.7 to 1.8 atmospheric gauge;
 </section><section>       <number>vi</number>   “Conservator” in relation to a port includes 
any person acting under the authority of the officer or body of person appointed 
to be Conservator of that port under section 7 of the Indian Ports Act, 1908 (15 
of 1908);
 </section><section>       <number>vii</number>   “Controller” includes the Joint Chief 
Controller of Explosives, the Deputy Chief Controller of Explosives, the 
Controller of Explosives and the Deputy Controller of Explosives;
 </section><section>      <number>viii</number>   “Compressed Natural Gas (CNG)” means mixtures 
of hydrocarbon gases and vapours, consisting mainly of Methane in gaseous form, 
which has been compressed for use as automotive fuel;
 </section><section>       <number>ix</number>   “CNG mother station” means CNG facilities 
connected with natural gas pipeline and having a compressor meant primarily to 
fill mobile cascades of daughter station. Such stations may also have stationery 
cascade for CNG dispensing to vehicles;
 </section><section>        <number>x</number>   “CNG online station” means CNG facilities 
connected with natural gas pipeline and having a compressor primarily to fill 
stationary cascades for dispensing CNG to vehicles;
 </section><section>       <number>xi</number>   “CNG daughter station” means CNG facilities 
not connected to natural gas pipeline. Such CNG dispensing station receives CNG 
through mobile cascade;
 <subsection>       <number>xii</number>   “critical temperature” means the temperature 
above which gas cannot be liquefied by the application of pressure alone;
 </subsection><subsection>      <number>xiii</number>   “dissolved acetylene cylinder” means a 
cylinder having a valve and with or without safety devices, containing a porous 
mass, a solvent for the storage of dissolved acetylene and at least suffi­cient 
acetylene to saturate the solvent at atmospheric pressure and at a temperature 
of +15oC.
  Explanation.—Acetone 
or any other solvent used shall not be capable of chemical reaction with the 
acetylene gas or with the porous mass or with the metal of the cylinder or 
valve;
 </subsection><subsection>      <number>xiv</number> “dissolved gas” means a gas which under 
pressure is dissolved in a fluid solvent appropriate to the particular gas as 
for example, acetylene in acetone or ammonia in water;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>xv</number>   “district authority” means—
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>a</number>   a Commissioner of Police or Deputy 
Commissioner of Police in any town having a Commissioner of Police; and
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>b</number>   in any other place, the District 
Magistrate;
 </subsection><subsection>      <number>xvi</number>   “District Magistrate” includes an 
Additional District Magistrate, and in the States of Punjab and Haryana and in 
the Karaikal, Mahe and Yanam areas of the Union Territory of Pondicherry, also 
includes a Sub‑Divisional Magistrate;
 </subsection><subsection>     <number>xvii</number>   “filling pressure” means the maximum 
permissible gauge pressure, converted to +15oC, 
at which a gas cylinder for permanent gas or gas dissolved under pressure can be 
filled;
 </subsection><subsection>    <number>xviii</number>   “filling ratio” means the ratio of the weight 
of a liquefiable gas introduced in the cylinder to the weight of the water the 
cylin­ders will hold at 15oC;
 </subsection><subsection>      <number>xix</number>   “flammable gas” means any gas which, if either 
a mixture of 13 per cent. or less (by volume) with air forms a flammable mixture 
or the flammability range with air is greater than 12 per cent. regardless of 
the lower limit and these limits shall be determined at atmospheric temperature 
and pressure;
  Explanation.—“flammability range” 
means the difference bet­ween the minimum and maximum percentages by volume of 
the gas in mixture with air that forms a flammable mixture;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>xx</number>   “Form” means a Form set forth in Schedule V;
 </subsection><subsection>      <number>xxi</number>   “Gas Cylinder” or “Cylinder” means any closed 
metal con­tainer having a volume exceeding 500 ml but not exceeding 1000 litres 
intended for the storage and transport of compressed gas, including any 
liquefied petroleum gas (LPG), container compressed natural gas (CNG) cylinder 
fitted to a motor vehicle as its fuel tank but not including any other such 
container fitted to a special transport or under-carriage and includes a 
composite cylinder, however, the water capacity of cylinders used for storage of 
CNG, nitrogen, compressed air, etc. may exceed 1000 liters up to 2500 liters 
provided the diameter of such cylinder does not exceed 60 cm;
 </subsection><subsection>     <number>xxii</number>   “high pressure liquefiable gas” means a 
liquefiable gas having a critical temperature between -10oC 
and +70oC;
 </subsection><subsection>    <number>xxiii</number>   “hydrostatic stretch test” means subjecting 
the cylinder to a hydrostatic pressure equal to the test pressure of the 
cylinder and recording the permanent stretch undergone by the cylinder;
 </subsection><subsection>    <number>xxiv</number>   “hydrostatic test” means the test to which a 
cylinder is subjected to a hydrostatic pressure equal to the test pressure of 
the cylinder;
 </subsection><subsection>     <number>xxv</number>   “import” means bringing into India by land, sea 
or air;
 </subsection><subsection>    <number>xxvi</number>   “inert gas” means a gas which is resistant to 
chemical action under normally encountered conditions;
 </subsection><subsection>   <number>xxvii</number>   “inspecting authority” means a person having 
qualifications and wide experience in the field of design, manufacture and 
testing of gas cylinders and recognised by the Chief Controller as authority for 
inspection and certification of gas cylinder;
 </subsection><subsection>  <number>xxviii</number>   “installation” means any premises wherein any 
place has been specially prepared for the manufacture (filling) or storage of 
compressed gas in cylinders;
 </subsection><subsection>    <number>xxix</number>   “liquefiable gas” means a gas that may be 
liquefied by pressure at -10oC 
but will be completely vaporised when in equilibrium with normal atmospheric 
pressure (760 mm. Hg) at 17.5°C which value shall be increased to 30°C for toxic 
gases;
 </subsection><subsection>     <number>xxx</number>   “liquified petroleum gas” means any material, 
which comprises predominantly of any of the following hydrocarbons or mixture of 
them with vapour pressure not exceeding 16.87 Kg/cm2 (gauge) at 65°C—
                Propane (C3H8), 
propylene (C3H6), 
butane (C4H10), 
(n-butane and iso-butane) and butylene (C4H8);
 </subsection><subsection>    <number>xxxi</number>   “low pressure liquefiable gas” means a 
liquefiable gas having critical temperature higher than +70oC;
 </subsection><subsection>   <number>xxxii</number>   “manufacture of gas” means filling of a 
cylinder with any com­pressed gas and also includes transfer of compressed gas 
from one cylinder to any other cylinder;
 </subsection><subsection>  <number>xxxiiii</number>   “oxidizing gas” means a gas which gives up 
Oxygen readily or removes hydrogen from a compound or attracts negative 
electrons;
 </subsection><subsection>  <number>xxxiv</number>   “permanent gas” means a gas whose critical 
temperature is below ‑10oC 
that is to say a gas which cannot be liquefied under any pressure at a 
temperature above ‑10oC;
 </subsection><subsection>   <number>xxxv</number>   “poisonous (toxic) gas” a gas which has a 
maximum allowable concentration in air for human respiration not exceeding 100 
mg/m3 at 
15°C and 1 kgf/cm2 absolute 
pressure;
 </subsection><subsection>  <number>xxxvi</number>   “Schedule” means the Schedule annexed to these 
rules;
 </subsection><subsection>  <number>xxxvii</number>   “tare weight” in relation to—
 <subsubsection>             <number>1</number>   acetylene cylinder means the weight of 
the cylinder to­gether with any fittings, permanently attached and includes the 
weight of valve and safety device, porous mass, requi­site quantity of solvent 
for dissolving acetylene, and the weight of acetylene gas saturating the solvent 
at atmos­pheric pressure and temperature of 15oC;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>             <number>2</number>   liquefiable gas cylinder means the weight 
of the cylinder together with any fittings permanently attached thereto and 
includes the weight of valve;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>             <number>3</number>   permanent gas cylinder means the weight 
of the cylinder together with any fittings permanently attached thereto and 
excludes the weight of valve;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>xxxviii</number>   “test pressure” means the internal pressure 
required for the hydrostatic test or hydrostatic stretch test of the cylinder, 
as follows:—
 <subsubsection>             <number>1</number>   For permanent and high pressure 
liquefiable gases, it should be calculated from the following:
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>                               <number>200</number> t. Re 
                     Ph =  
_______________
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>                               <number>1</number>25 (Do‑t) 
                     Where:
                     Ph = Test pressure in Kgf/cm2
                     Do = Outside diameter of the cylinder in 
mm.
                     t = Minimum calculated wall thickness of 
the cylinder shell in mm.
                     Re = Minimum specified yield strength of 
the material of cy­linder in Kgf/mm2, 
it is limited to 75 per cent. of the minimum value of the tensile strength in 
the case of normal­ised cylinder and 85 per cent. of the minimum value of the 
tensile strength for quenched and tempered cylinder, provided that the value of 
test pressure shall not exceed 80 per cent. of the yield strength.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>             <number>2</number>   For low pressure liquefiable gas – One 
and a half times the saturated vapour pressure of the gas at 65oC 
or as specified in IS: 8867, whichever is higher;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>  <number>xxxix</number>   “transport” means the moving of a cylinder 
filled with any compressed gas from one place to another;
 </subsection><subsection>   <number>xxxx</number>   “‘water capacity” means the volume of water in 
litres, a cylinder will hold at 15oC;
 </subsection><subsection>  <number>xxxxi</number>   “working pressure for low pressure liquefiable 
gas” means the saturated vapour pressure at 65oC.
  Explanation.—The values of 
saturated vapour pressure of different gases are specified in IS: 3710;
 </subsection><subsection>  <number>xxxxii</number>   “working pressure for permanent gas” means the 
internal pressure of the gas in the cylinder at a temperature of 15oC;
 </subsection><subsection><number>xxxxiii</number>   “yield strength” means the stress corresponding 
to a permanent strain of 0.2 per cent. of the original gauge length in a tensile 
test. For practical purposes it may be taken as a stress at which elon­gation 
first occurs in the test piece without the increase of load in a tensile test.
</subsection></section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>3</number> Filling, possession, 
import and transport of cylinders.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No per­son shall fill any cylinder with any compressed gas or import, possess or 
transport any cylinder so filled or intended to be filled with such gas unless—
 <subsection>        <number>a</number>   such cylinder and its valve have been 
constructed to a type and standard specified in Schedule I as amended from time 
to time by an order issued by the Chief Controller;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>b</number>   the test and inspection certificates issued by 
the inspecting authority in respect of cylinder and its valve are made available 
to the Chief Controller and prior approval of the said authority is obtained.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> For obtaining approval under 
clause (b) of sub-rule (1), the following particulars shall be submitted to the 
Chief Controller:—
 <subsection>         <number>i</number>   total number and serial number of the 
cylinders;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>ii</number>   name and address of the manufacturers of the 
cylinders;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number>   specification of the cylinders and the 
valves;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iv</number>   previous approval, if any;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>v</number>   the test and inspection certificates in 
respect of the cylinders;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>vi</number>   the test and inspection certificates 
pertaining to the valves fitted/to be fitted to the cylinders;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>vii</number>   scrutiny fee as specified in Schedule V.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> The test and inspection 
certificates required to be obtained from the inspecting authority in respect of 
cylinders and valves inspected and certified by it in accordance with the 
approved design and specification or code shall give the information included in 
Schedule II.
 </section><section><number>4</number> (a) Any person desiring to 
manufacture cylinders, valves, LPG regulators attached to self-closing valves, 
multi-function valves and other fittings shall obtain approval from the Chief 
Controller and in order to seek such approval, submit the particulars set forth 
in Schedule III and scrutiny fee as specified in Schedule V together with design 
drawings and calculations duly endorsed by Inspecting Authority.
 <subsection><number>b</number> For any subsequent changes 
in the design drawing, a fresh approval shall be obtained.
 </subsection></section><section><number>5</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in sub‑rule (1) cylinders of specifications not conforming to the 
specifications specified in Schedule I and imported into India for filling and 
shipment to the country of origin or supply to a foreign going vessel touching 
Indian port, could be filled with such gas, provided:
 <subsection>        <number>a</number>   the cylinder has passed the hydrostatic test 
or hydrostatic stretch test, as the case may be, within the period specified in 
these rules and the pressure applied during the test shall be the test pressure 
marked on the cylinder;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>b</number>   the cylinder is not filled with—
 <subsubsection>              <number>i</number>   any liquefiable gas in excess of the 
filling ratio specified in IS: 3710 for low pressure liquefiable gases and 
IS:8866 for high pressure liquefiable gases;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>             <number>ii</number>   any permanent gas at a pressure in 
excess of the pressure for which the cylinder is designed;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>        <number>c</number>   a separate record of the cylinder tested and 
filled is maintained at the filling station;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>d</number>   the filled cylinders are removed from the 
filling station and shipped off as expeditiously as possible.
</subsection></section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>4</number> Valves.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Valves fitted to gas cylinders shall comply in all respects with the following 
specifications, namely:—
 <subsection>        <number>a</number>   in respect of industrial gas cylinders, IS : 
3224;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>b</number>   in respect of medical gas cylinders, IS: 3745;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>c</number>   in respect of cylinders used with breathing 
apparatus, IS: 7302 as amended from time to time;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>d</number>   in respect of cylinders used for filling 
liquefied petroleum gas, IS: 8776 for cylinders of water capacity not exceeding 
5 litres and, IS: 8737 for cylinders of water capacity exceeding 5 litres;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>e</number>   in respect of auto LPG containers, IS: 15100;
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>f</number>   in respect of small Refrigerant cylinders, 
IS: 12300:
 Provided that the Chief 
Controller may, if he is of opinion that it is necessary so to do in the public 
interest, permit the use of valves not conform­ing to any of the above 
specifications.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Valves fitted to Carbon 
dioxide cylinders shall be provided in the body with a safety release consisting 
of softened copper disc so arranged as to burst at a pressure between 200Kg/cm2 and 
220 Kg/cm2.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Valves for cylinders 
containing flammable gases not listed in IS: 3224 shall have outlets provided 
with left handed screw threads for the pipes or other connections.
 </section><section><number>4</number> All other valves shall have 
outlets with right handed screw threads.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The valves shall be attached 
to the cylinder neck by screwing and not by making any permanent attachment or 
inserting adapter in between.
 </section><section><number>6</number> The design of 
spindle-operated valves shall be such that when fitted to the cylinders it shall 
not be possible to withdraw the spindle under normal operating conditions.
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>5</number> Safety relief devices.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Cylinders manufactured in India, if fitted with safety relief devices in their 
bodies, shall have such safety devices manufactured and maintained in accordance 
with IS: 5903.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Cylinders containing 
obnoxious or poisonous gases shall not be provided with any safety device.
 Explanation.—For 
the purpose of this sub‑rule, “obnoxious or poison­ous gases” include Carbon 
monoxide, Hydro‑cynic Acid, Hydrogen chlo­ride, Hydrogen bromide, Hydrogen 
fluoride, Sulphur dioxide, Chlorine, Methyl bromide, Nitrogen tetroxide, 
Nitrosyl chloride, Town gas, Hydrogen sulphide, Carbonyl Chloride (Phosgene), 
Cyanogen, Cyanogen Chloride, Fluorine and Carbon oxychloride.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Cylinders manufactured in 
foreign countries, approved for use in this country, if fitted with safety 
relief devices shall have these devices fully maintained in accordance with the 
requirements of the specifications to which they were originally made.
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>6</number> Marking on cylinders.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Markings generally:
 <subsection>        <number>a</number>   Every gas cylinder shall be clearly and 
permanently marked in accordance with the following conditions by stamping, 
engrav­ing or similar processes:—
 <subsubsection>              <number>i</number>   on the shoulder of the cylinder which 
shall be enforced by forging or other means, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>             <number>ii</number>   on such a part which is inseparably 
bound with the cylin­der and which is not or only negligibly effected by the 
stresses due to the gas pressure within it.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>        <number>b</number>   The name plate shall not be affixed to the 
cylinder by soldering if there is a risk of corrosion or embrittlement.
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>c</number>   In conjunction with the original marking, 
space shall be provided for stamping the test date obtained at the periodic 
inspection.
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>d</number>   Markings shall be so carried out and the 
letters and numerals used shall be of such shape and size that the marking is 
clear and easily readable and does not give place for misreading.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Marking on permanent and 
liquefiable gas cylinders:
 <subsection>        <number>a</number>   Every cylinder shall be marked with the 
following markings, namely:—
 <subsubsection>              <number>i</number>   Manufacturer’s, owner’s and inspector’s 
marking and rota­tion number (these markings shall be registered with the Chief 
Controller);
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>             <number>ii</number>   specification to which the cylinder has 
been made;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            <number>iii</number>   a symbol to indicate the nature of heat 
treatment given to the cylinder during manufacture or after repairs;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            <number>iv</number>   the date of the last hydrostatic test or 
hydrostatic stretch test, as the case may be, with the code mark of recognised 
testing station where the test was carried out and the code mark shall be 
registered with the Chief Controller. In the case of liquefied petroleum gas 
cylinders, the quarter and the year of test shall be given as an additional 
marking in a neck ring or on a shoulder plate;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>             <number>v</number>   working pressure and test pressure;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            <number>vi</number>   tare weight—
  Explanation.—In the case of 
liquefiable gas cylinders, tare weight shall include the weight of valve fitted 
to the cylinder. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            <number>vii</number>   water capacity.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>        <number>b</number>   All the markings, except the manufacturer’s 
markings, which may be on the base, shall be stamped on the neck end of the 
cylinder. However, seamless cylinders having no foot ring or skirt shall be 
stamped with the manufacturer’s marking on the neck and of the cylinder.
</subsection></section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>7</number> Markings on valve.—Valves 
fitted to the cylinder shall be clearly and durably marked in accordance with 
the following provisions by stamping, engraving or similar processes:—
 <section>         <number>i</number>   the specification of the valves;
 </section><section>        <number>ii</number>   year and month or quarter of manufacture;
 </section><section>       <number>iii</number>   manufacturer’s symbol;
 </section><section>       <number>iv</number>   working pressure;
 </section><section>        <number>v</number>   the name or chemical symbol of the gas for 
which the valve is to be used;
 </section><section>       <number>vi</number>   the type of screw threads on the outlet, in 
case of left handed as (L.H.);
 </section><section>       <number>vii</number>   Inspector’s stamp;
 </section><section>      <number>viii</number>   where dip tubes are provided, special 
indications shall be given by a clear and durable marking on the valve or on a 
badge fixed between the valve and the cylinder and the total length in 
millimeter of the tube shall also be indicated.
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>9</number> Labelling of cylinders.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every cylinder shall be labeled with the name of the gas and the name and 
address of the person by whom the cylinder was filled with gas.
 </section><section><number>2</number> A warning in the following 
terms shall be attached to every cylinder containing permanent or liquefiable 
gas, namely:—
 
“Warning”
 
GAS CYLINDERS RULES, 2004
 <subsection>         <number>i</number>   Do not change the colour of this cylinder.
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>ii</number>   This cylinder should not be filled with any 
gas other than the one it now contains.
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number>   No flammable material should be stored in the 
close vici­nity of this cylinder or in the same room in which it is kept.
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iv</number>   No oil or similar lubricant should be used on 
the valves or other fittings of this cylinder.
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>v</number>   Please look for the next date of test, which 
is marked on a metal ring inserted between the valve and the neck of the 
cylinder, and if this date is over, do not accept the cylinder for filling.
</subsection></section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>10</number> Restriction on delivery 
or despatch of cylinders.—
<section><number>1</number> No 
person shall deliver or despatch any cylinder filled with any compressed gas to 
any other person in India who is not the holder of a licence to possess such 
compressed gas cylinders or his authorised agent unless he is exempted under 
these rules to possess such compressed gas cylinders without a licence.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The gas cylinders delivered 
or despatched by a person under sub-rule (1) shall be of the type for which he 
is licensed and shall not exceed the quantity which the person to whom it is 
delivered or despatched is authorised to possess under these rules.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Nothing in sub‑rules (1) and 
(2) shall apply to the delivery or des­patch of gas cylinders to the Defence 
Forces of the Union, port authorities or Railway administration.
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>11</number> Repairing of seamless gas 
cylinders during use.—No person shall 
repair or cause to repair any leakage in the body of a seamless gas cylinder.
</article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>12</number> Repairing of welded or 
brazed cylinders.—
<section><number>1</number> Welded or 
brazed cylin­der showing leaks at any place other than the welded or brazed 
seams shall not be repaired and shall be rendered unserviceable.
 </section><section><number>2</number> In the case of cylinders 
having welded or brazed seam, repairing of minor defects, such as small weld 
cracks, pin holes, blow holes, undercuts in welding, leaks at the weld (shown in 
periodical hydrostatic test) may be allowed provided—
 <subsection>        <number>a</number>   the defects have been removed by grinding, 
chipping, gouging or other approved methods;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>b</number>   the repairing is carried out by a certified 
welder at the premises of a manufacturer of cylinders recognised by the Chief 
Control­ler under the supervision of a competent person by—
 <subsubsection>              <number>i</number>   welding if the original seams were 
welded;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>             <number>ii</number>   brazing, if the original seams were 
brazed;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>        <number>c</number>   the cylinder is properly heat‑treated after 
the repairs;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>d</number>   the welded or brazed seams of the cylinder are 
radiographed if the cylinder was originally required to be radiographed after 
its manufacture;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>e</number>   after repairs and heat‑treatment, the cylinder 
is subjected to the same pneumatic and hydrostatic test or hydrostatic stretch 
test as was done at the time of manufacture.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> Welded or brazed cylinder, 
before repairing, shall be thoroughly cleaned and gas‑freed or otherwise 
prepared for safely carrying out hot work and certified in writing, by a 
competent person, to have been so prepared. The certificate shall be preserved 
for a period of three months and produced to the Chief Controller on demand.
 </section><section><number>4</number> No person shall refill any 
cylinder which has been repaired under sub-rule (2) with any gas unless a full 
report on the repairs and test carried out on the cylinder, accompanied by the 
repairer’s certificate of testing are furnished to the Chief Controller and his 
permission is obtained for its refilling.
 </section><section><number>5</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in sub‑rule (2), no repairs shall be carried out to any dissolved 
acetylene gas cylinder showing leaks in its weld seam.
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>13</number> Prohibition of employment 
of children and intoxicated person­.—No 
child under the age of eighteen years and no person who is in a state of 
intoxication shall be employed incharge of loading or unloading or transport of 
any compressed gas cylinder or in any premises licensed under these rules.
</article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>14</number> Prohibition of smoking, 
fires, lights and dangerous substances­.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No person shall smoke and no fires, other than blow pipe flames for repairs, or 
no articles or such other substances of flammable nature or liable to 
spontane­ous ignition or to cause or communicate fire or explosion shall be 
allowed at any time in proximity to a place where any cylinder for flammable 
gases is being filled, stored or handled.
 </section><section><number>2</number> No person in or near any 
place where cylinders containing flam­mable gases are filled, stored or handled 
shall have in his possession any matches, fuses mobile phones or any other 
appliances for producing ignition or explosion.
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>15</number> General precautions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Cylinders together with their valves and other fittings and the identification 
colours under these rules shall always be maintained in good condition.
 </section><section><number>2</number> No oil or similar lubricant 
shall be used on any valves or other fittings of any cylinder.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Save as provided in rule 12 
and clause B 2 (1) (b) of Schedule IV, no cylinder shall be subjected to any 
heat treatment or exposed to a high temperature or to the Sun or stored with any 
other flammable or explosive material.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Every cylinder containing 
compressed gas shall have its valve se­curely closed so as to prevent leakage. 
Valves fitted to the cylinders contain­ing Liquefied Petroleum Gas and highly 
toxic gases like Boron trifluoride, Carbon monoxide, Fluorine, Hydrogen 
chloride, Cynogen chloride, Chlo­rine trifluoride, Hydrogen cynide, Hydrogen 
fluoride, Hydrogen sulphide, Methyl bromide, Nitrogen tetroxide, Chlorine, 
Ammonia or Sulphur dioxide shall be provided with security nut on the outlet to 
act as a secondary means of safeguard against leakage of gas.
 </section><section><number>5</number> If a leak in the valve 
cannot be rectified by tightening the gland nut or the spindle, the cylinder 
shall be removed to an open space where it is least dangerous to life and 
property and the filler shall be informed. In the case of LPG cylinder, the 
safety cap shall be fixed to arrest the leak and the cylinder shall be moved to 
an open space.
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>16</number> Special precautions 
against accidents.—
<section><number>1</number> No person 
shall commit or attempt to commit any act, which may tend to cause a fire or 
explosion in or about any place where gas under pressure in a cylinder is 
stored, handled or transported.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every person storing 
compressed gas cylinders and every person in charge of or engaged in the 
storage, handling and transport of such gas cylinders, shall at all times—
 <subsection>        <number>a</number>   comply with the provisions of these rules and 
the conditions of any licence relating thereto;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>b</number>   observe all precautions for the prevention of 
accident by fire or explosion; 
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>c</number>   prevent any person from committing any acts 
referred to in sub-rule (1).
</subsection></section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>17</number> Competent person to be 
incharge of operation.—Every person 
holding or acting under a licence granted under these rules, shall, whenever 
cylinders are filled, loaded, unloaded, examined or tested, depute a compe­tent 
and experienced person to be present and to conduct any of the said operations 
in accordance with provisions of these rules and the name, qualification and 
experience of such personnel deputed in each shift shall be furnished to the 
Chief Controller or Controller for considering filling permission round the 
clock.
</article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>18</number> Handling and use.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Cylinders shall be adequately supported during handling.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Conveyors, trolleys and 
cradles of adequate strength shall, as far as possible, be used when moving the 
cylinders.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The cylinders shall be 
handled carefully and not be allowed to fall upon one another or otherwise 
subjected to any undue shock.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Sliding, dropping or playing 
with cylinders is prohibited.
 </section><section><number>5</number> Liquefied petroleum gas 
cylinders and cylinders containing liquefi­able gases shall always be kept in an 
upright position and shall be so placed that they cannot be knocked over.
 </section><section><number>6</number> Cylinders used in horizontal 
position shall be so secured that they cannot roll.
 </section><section><number>7</number> Open flames, lights, mobile 
phones, lighting of fires, welding and smoking shall be prohibited in close 
proximity to any cylinder containing flammable gases except those while in use 
for welding, cutting or heating.
 </section><section><number>8</number> Working places shall not be 
classified as storage places for the purpose of licensing.
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>19</number> Restrictions on filling.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Welded cylinders shall not be used for filling any permanent or high pressure 
liquefiable gas or highly toxic gases like Boron trifluoride, Carbonyl chloride 
(Phosgene), Chlorine trifluoride, Cyanogen, Cyanogen chloride, Hydrogen cyanide, 
Hydrogen sulphide.
 </section><section><number>2</number> No cylinder, which has once 
been used for storage and transportation of coal gas, carbon monoxide or 
methane, shall be used for filling with any other gas except mixture of these 
gases with inert gases.
 </section><section><number>3</number> No cylinder shall be filled 
with any gas that is capable of combining chemically so as to endanger its 
serviceability.
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>20</number> Loading, unloading and 
transport of cylinders.—Cylinders 
filled with any compressed gas shall be transported duly complying with the 
provisions laid down in Schedule VI and also observing the relevant provisions 
of other statutes as applicable.
</article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>21</number> Storage of cylinders.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Cylinders shall be stored in a cool, dry, well ventilated place under cover, 
away from boilers, open flames, steam pipes or any potential sources of heat and 
such place of storage shall be easily accessible.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The storage room or shed 
shall be of fire resistant construction.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Thin wall cylinders such as 
liquefied petroleum gas cylinders and dissolved gas cylinders shall not be 
stacked in a horizontal position.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Cylinders containing 
flammable gases and toxic gases shall be kept separated from each other and from 
cylinders containing other types of gases by an adequate distance or by a 
suitable partition wall.
 </section><section><number>5</number> Cylinders shall not be 
stored under conditions, which will cause them to corrode.
 </section><section><number>6</number> Cylinders shall not be 
stored along with any combustible material.
 </section><section><number>7</number> Empty cylinders shall be 
segregated from the filled ones and care shall be taken that all the valves are 
tightly shut.
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>22</number> Electrical installations.—In 
premises for filling and storing flammable gases in cylinders all electric 
meters, distribution boards, switches, fuses, plugs and sockets, all electric 
fittings, fixed lamps, portable hand lamps and motors, shall be of flame proof 
construction conforming to IS: 2148 or such other specifications as approved by 
the Chief Controller and shall be effectively earthed.
</article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>23</number> Purity of gas.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Compressed gases shall be free from impurities, which are likely to corrode the 
metal of the cylinder or form an explosive substance with it or cause the gases 
to decompose or explode.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The gases shall be as dry as 
possible and in no instance shall the aqueous phase separate when a liquefied 
gas is cooled to 0°C.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Before filling any cylinder 
with gases like carbon monoxide, coal gas, hydrogen or methane, the gas shall be 
free from hydrogen sulphide and other sulphurous impurities as far as 
practicable. The moisture shall be less than 0.02 g/m3 of 
gas at normal temperature and pressure.
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>24</number> Cylinder subjected to the 
action of fire.—
<section><number>1</number> 
<subsection><number>a</number> A cylinder 
exposed to fire shall not be used unless it has undergone proper examination and 
hydrostatic test or hydrostatic stretch test.
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> If deleterious structural 
changes in the mate­rial due to the action of heat of the fire is 
apprehended to have taken place, the cylinder shall have to be subjected to 
proper heat treatment, followed by hydrostatic test or hydrostatic stretch test, 
as the case may be, before the cylinder is taken into use.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Dissolved acetylene cylinders, 
which have been damaged by fire shall be condemned and destroyed by an 
experienced and competent person.</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>25</number> Ownership of cylinder.—A 
cylinder shall not be filled with a compressed gas and transported unless it was 
charged by or with the written consent of the owner of the cylinder.
</article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>26</number> Re‑testing of cylinder.—A 
cylinder for which prescribed periodical re‑test has become due shall not be 
charged and transported until such re‑test has been properly made.
</article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>27</number> Owner’s record.—The 
owner of a cylinder shall keep for the life of each cylinder, a record 
containing the following information regarding each cylinder, namely:—
 <section>         <number>i</number>   Cylinder manufacturer’s name and the rotation 
number;
 </section><section>        <number>ii</number>   The specification number to which the 
cylinder is manufactured;
 </section><section>       <number>iii</number>   Date of original hydrostatic test or 
hydrostatic stretch test;
 </section><section>       <number>iv</number>   Cylinder manufacturer’s test and inspection 
certificates;
 </section><section>        <number>v</number>   Number and date of letter of approval granted 
by the Chief Controller.
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>28</number> Conversion of cylinders.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Gas cylinders designed and approved for filling with a particular gas shall not 
be used for filling with any other gas unless specific approval is obtained from 
the Chief Controller except that—
 <subsection>        <number>a</number>   inert gases, oxygen and compressed air 
cylinders made to the same specification and design may be converted from one 
gas to another after fitting with appropriate valve and painting with 
appropriate identification colour without prior permission from Chief 
Controller, with approval of the cylinder owner;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>b</number>   proper records of such conversions shall be 
maintained by the gas filler for examination of Chief Controller or Controller 
as and when needed.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Any person desiring for 
conversion approval shall submit to Chief Controller the following:—
 <subsection>         <number>i</number>   documentary evidence indicating that the 
cylinders have been purchased by him;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>ii</number>   an authenticated copy of letter permitting 
filling of the cylinders in the past;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number>   a statement in duplicate, showing 
manufacturer’s serial number of the cylinders in ascending order;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iv</number>   a certificate to the effect that the 
cylinder(s) had not been converted to any other gas service in the past;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>v</number>   scrutiny fee as specified in Schedule V.
</subsection></section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>29</number> Licence for import of gas 
cylinders.—No person shall import any 
cylinder filled or intended to be filled with any compressed gas except under 
and in accordance with the conditions of a licence granted under these rules and 
the relevant provisions of Foreign Trade (Development and Regulation) Act, 1992.
</article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>30</number> Declaration by the master 
of ship or ship’s agent.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
master of every ship carrying cylinders filled with compressed gas for 
importation into India, or the agent for such ship, shall give, the Conservator 
of the Port not less than 48 hours’ notice of its intended arrival at the port.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The master of every ship 
carrying such cylinders shall deliver to the pilot, before entering any port, a 
written declaration under his signature in Form A:
 Provided that if the agent for 
such ship delivers to the Conservator of the Port a written declaration referred 
to in sub‑rule (1) under his signature, no such declaration shall be made by the 
master of the ship.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every declaration delivered 
to a pilot under sub‑rule (2) shall be made over by him without delay to the 
Conservator of the Port and all declarations received by the Conservator of the 
Port shall be forwarded by him, with all convenient despatch, to the 
Commissioner of Customs of the Port.
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>31</number> Production of licence for 
import.—Every person desiring to 
import cylinders filled with any compressed gas or intended to be so filled 
shall produce personally or through his agent, before the Commissioner of 
Customs his licence for the import of such gas cylinders.
</article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>32</number> Permission of the 
Commissioner of Customs.—
<section><number>1</number> No 
imported cylinder shall be landed except with the permission of the Commissioner 
of Customs.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If the Commissioner of 
Customs is satisfied that the gas cylinders can lawfully be imported, he shall 
permit it to be landed.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Nothing in this rule shall 
affect the power of the Commissioner of Customs to detain the gas cylinders 
under any other law for the time being in force.
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>33</number> Importation by land.—No 
gas cylinder filled with any compressed gas, shall be imported by land save with 
the previous sanction in each case, of the Central Government and under such 
conditions and restrictions as it may impose.
</article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>34</number> Importation by air.—No 
cylinder filled with any compressed gas shall be imported by air save with the 
previous sanction in each case of the Director General Civil Aviation.
</article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>35</number> Periodicity of 
examination and testing of cylinders.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No person shall fill any cylinder with any compressed gas unless the cylinder 
has been examined and subjected to hydrostatic test or hydrostatic stretch test, 
as the case may be, and other tests set forth in Schedule IV within such period 
as is specified in IS: 8868 issued by Bureau of Indian Standards or as approved 
in writing by the Chief Controller.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any testing station desiring 
to obtain recognition for periodical test­ing and examination of cylinders shall 
provide the facilities set forth in Sched­ule IV and shall submit to Chief 
Controller the particulars of the facilities provided and scrutiny fee specified 
in Schedule V.
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>36</number> Condemning of cylinders.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any cylinder which fails to pass periodic examination or test or which loses in 
its tare weight by over 5 per cent or which for any other defect is found to be 
unsafe for use or after expiry of the service life of the cylinder, shall not be 
filled with any compressed gas and shall be destroyed by flattening it as a 
whole or after being cut into pieces in such a manner that the pieces cannot 
again be joined together by welding or otherwise to form a cylinder, under 
intimation to the owner of the cylinder, as specified in IS: 8198.
 Explanation.—Service 
life of On-board CNG cylinders to be twenty years and Auto LPG containers made 
of low carbon steel to be fifteen years unless otherwise specified in the 
respective codes.
 </section><section><number>2</number> All markings on the cylinder 
shall be defaced before it is destroyed.
 </section><section><number>3</number> History sheets or records of 
such cylinders shall be closed and kept on record for a period of one year. 
Reports of the details of such closed history cards or records shall be sent to 
the Chief Controller, in writing, on the 1st January, April, July and October 
every year.
 </section><section><number>4</number> A cylinder, which has been 
used for the generation of any gas or for any purpose other than storage, 
transportation and use of compressed gas shall be deemed to have been condemned 
and unsuitable for such as a cylinder within the meaning of these rules.
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>37</number> Additional requirements 
for dissolved acetylene cylinders.—Dis­solved 
Acetylene gas cylinder shall comply with the following additional provisions, 
namely:—
 <section>         <number>i</number>   The porous substance shall fill as completely 
as possible the cylinder into which the acetylene is compressed.
 </section><section>        <number>ii</number>   The porosity of the substance shall not 
exceed 92 per cent. and in no case shall be less than 75 per cent.
 </section><section>       <number>iii</number>   Any solvent used shall not be capable of 
chemical reaction with the acetylene gas or with the porous substance or with 
the metal of the cylinder.
 </section><section>       <number>iv</number>   If acetone is used as a solvent it shall 
comply with the requirements of IS: 170, the quantity of acetone including the 
gas in solution shall be such that the cylinder meets the requirements of 
additional tests specified in IS: 7312.
 </section><section>        <number>v</number>   The valves of the cylinders shall not contain 
more than 70 per cent. copper in their composition.
 </section><section>       <number>vi</number>   The pressure in the cylinder shall not exceeds 
16Kgf/Cm2 
at a temperature of 15°C.
 </section><section>       <number>vii</number>   Every cylinder shall before being filled with 
purpose mass be tested by hydrostatic pressure to a pressure of not less than 60 
Kgf/cm2. 
This pressure may be reduced to 53 Kgf/cm2
if the cylinder is fitted with fusible plug. No cylinder which shows a 
permanent stretch in excess of 7½ per cent. of the total stretch suffered during 
hydrostatic stretch test shall be allowed.
 </section><section>      <number>viii</number>   The safety relief devices if fitted, shall 
operated at a pressure of 53 Kgf/cm2
or at a temperature of 100°C+ 4°C/-2°C.
 </section><section>       <number>ix</number>   Every cylinder shall have permanently and 
conspicuously marked upon it or upon a brass plate soldered to it the name of 
the manufacturer and the words “Acetylene properly compressed into porous 
substance” and shall bear the following markings, namely:—
 <subsection>             <number>a</number>   Serial number and identification of 
manufacturer;
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>b</number>   Number of the standard;
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>c</number>   Test pressure;
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>d</number>   The date of hydrostatic stretch test with 
code mark of the place where the test was carried out;
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>e</number>   Date of filling of porous mass;
 </subsection><subsection>              <number>f</number>   Water capacity;
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>g</number>   A symbol of indicate the nature of heat 
treatment;
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>h</number>   Identification of porpous mass and 
porosity percentage;
 </subsection><subsection>              <number>i</number>   Tare weight (inclusive of valve);
 </subsection><subsection>              <number>j</number>   Inspector’s official mark;
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>k</number>   Maximum gas capacity.
</subsection></section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>38</number> Restriction on filling of 
dissolved acetylene in cylinders.—No 
person shall charge with acetylene any cylinder unless he is in possession of 
full particulars and the previous history of such cylinder and has otherwise 
assured himself that the cylinder complies with the requirements of these rules.
</article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>39</number> Examination of dissolved 
acetylene cylinders before filling.—When­ever 
a cylinder is charged with acetylene, it shall be subjected to a thorough visual 
examination in accordance with IS: 8433, if the history of the cylinder shows 
that it has not been subjected to such an examination within the previous two 
years and at the same time the valves shall be removed and the conditions of the 
porous substance at the neck of the cylinder ascertained:
 Provided that this period of 
periodical examination shall be one year in case the cylinders are filled with 
loose porous mass.
</article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>40</number> Licence for compression 
of acetylene.—The compression of the 
acetylene gas into a cylinder shall be carried out only in such premises as are 
licensed by the Chief Controller or Controller.
</article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>41</number> Record of dissolved 
acetylene cylinders.—Each firm 
charging acety­lene in cylinders shall keep a record of every cylinder charged 
by it this record shall give the following information, namely:—
 <section>        <number>a</number>   for each charge,
 <subsection>              <number>i</number>   the date of each charging of the 
cylinder,
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>ii</number>   the empty cylinder weight without gas,
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>iii</number>   the weight of solvent charged before gas 
charging,
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>iv</number>   full weight of thy cylinder;
 </subsection></section><section>        <number>b</number>   the dates upon which solvent has been added;
 </section><section>        <number>c</number>   the dates upon which the cylinder has been 
thoroughly exa­mined as provided in rule 39, the results of each such 
examina­tion and the name of the person carrying out such examination, and in 
the case of cylinders first issued by the firm, the tare weight of the cylinder 
including porous substance and acetone or other solvent, the nature of the 
solvent and the maximum pressure allowed in the cylinder.
 <subsection><number>2</number> This record shall be open 
for inspection of the Chief Controller or the Controller of Explosives.
</subsection></section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>42</number> Labelling of dissolved 
acetylene cylinders.—A warning label 
attached to every dissolved acetylene cylinder shall, in addition to the 
par­ticulars given in sub‑rule (2) of rule 9 bear the following additional 
particu­lars, namely:—
 <section>        <number>a</number>   date of last filling of gas in the cylinder;

 </section><section>        <number>b</number>   weight of gas filled;
 </section><section>        <number>c</number>   full cylinder weight;
 </section><section>        <number>d</number>   the name of the company filling the gas on the 
last date of the filling.
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>43</number> Licence for filling and 
possession.—
<section><number>1</number> No person shall fill 
any cylinder with compressed gas and no cylinder filled with compressed gas 
shall be possessed by any one except under and in accordance with the conditions 
of a licence granted under these rules.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The licensee shall be 
responsible, for all operations connected with the filling and possession of 
cylinders in the licensed premises.
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>44</number> No licence needed for 
filling and possession in certain cases.—­Notwithstanding 
anything contained in rule 43, no licence shall be necessary for—
 <section>        <number>a</number>   possession of any cylinder filled with a 
compressed gas by a carrier or other person for the purpose of transport in 
accordance with the provisions of these rules;
 </section><section>        <number>b</number>   possession of cylinder filled with—
 <subsection>              <number>i</number>   liquefied petroleum gas when the total 
quantity of gas does not exceed 100 kg at a time;
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>ii</number>   any other flammable but non‑toxic gas 
when the total num­ber of cylinders containing such gas does not exceed 25 or 
the total weight of gas does not exceed 200 kg, whichever is less, at a time;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>iii</number>   any non‑flammable non‑toxic gas when the 
total number of such cylinders does not exceed 200 at a time;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>iv</number>   any toxic gas when the total quantity of 
such cylinders does not exceed 5 at a time;
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>v</number>   acetylene gas contained in cylinders in 
dissolved state when the total quantity of such cylinder does not exceed 50 at a 
time.
</subsection></section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>45</number> Restriction on filling.—No 
person shall fill any cylinder with any compressed gas unless such a cylinder 
and its valve or other fittings—
 <section>        <number>a</number>   are of approved type and standard as per rule 
3 and has been specifically approved for filling by the Chief Controller,
 </section><section>        <number>b</number>   have passed the examination and test specified 
in rule 35,
 </section><section>        <number>c</number>   conform to the provisions of rules 4, 5, 6, 7 
and 8.
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>46</number> Working pressure and 
filling ratios.—
<section><number>1</number> The working or 
internal pressure in any cylinder charged with a permanent gas shall not exceed 
two-third of the test pressure.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Cylinders charged with 
liquefiable gases shall not be filled in excess of the filling ratios specified 
in IS: 3710 for low pressure liquefiable gases and IS: 8866 for high pressure 
liquefiable gases.
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>47</number> Prior approval of 
specifications and plans of premises proposed to be licensed.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every person desiring to obtain a licence to fill and store any compressed gas 
in any cylinder shall submit to the Chief Controller or Controller authorised by 
Chief Controller—
 <subsection>        <number>a</number>   specifications and plans drawn to scale in 
triplicate clearly indi­cating—
 <subsubsection>              <number>i</number>   the manner in which the provisions 
prescribed in these rules will be complied with,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>             <number>ii</number>   the premises proposed to be licensed, 
the area of which shall be distinctly coloured or otherwise marked,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            <number>iii</number>   the surrounding area lying within 100 
metres of the edge of all facilities which are proposed to be licensed;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>        <number>b</number>   scrutiny fee as specified in Schedule V.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> If the Chief Controller or 
Controller after scrutiny of the specifications and plans and after making such 
inquiries as considered necessary, satisfied that compressed gas will be filled 
and stored in the premises proposed to be licensed, accord­ing to the provisions 
of these rules, he shall return to the applicant one copy each of the 
specifications and plans signed by him conveying his sanction subject to such 
conditions as may be specified.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Prior approval specified in 
sub-rules (1) and (2) is not mandatory for installation of non-toxic 
non-flammable gases and an applicant for such installation is at liberty to 
install the facilities in accordance with provisions of these rules without 
obtaining prior approval from Chief Controller or Controller.
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>48</number> No Objection Certificate.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An applicant for a new licence in Form G, for a CNG dispensing station shall 
apply to the District Magistrate with two copies of site plan showing the 
location of the premises proposed to be licensed under these rules for a 
certificate to the effect that there is no objection to the applicant’s 
receiving a licence for a CNG dispensing station at the site proposed, and the 
District Magistrate, if satisfied, shall grant no objection certificate to the 
applicant who shall forward it to the Chief Controller or Controller with his 
application.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every certificate issued by 
the District Magistrate under sub-rule (1) above shall be accompanied by a copy 
of the plan of the proposed site duly endorsed by him under official seal.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Chief Controller or 
Controller may refer an application not accompanied by a certificate granted 
under sub-rule (1) to the District Magistrate for his observation.
 </section><section><number>4</number> If the District Magistrate, 
either on a reference being made to him or otherwise, intimates to the Chief 
Controller or Controller that any licence which has been applied for should not, 
in his opinion, granted, such licence shall not be issued without the sanction 
of the Central Government.
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>49</number> Application for licence.—A 
person wishing to obtain or renew a licence under these rules shall submit an 
application, in writing, to the Chief Controller or, Controller—
 <section>        <number>a</number>   in Form B for a licence prescribed in sub-rule 
(1) of rule 51, and
 </section><section>        <number>b</number>   in Form C for a licence prescribed in sub-rule 
(2) of rule 51.
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>50</number> Grant of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A licence under these rules may be granted by the Chief Controller or Controller 
on payment of the fees specified in Schedule V.
 </section><section><number>2</number> A licence under sub-rule (1) 
shall be granted if the provisions of these rules are complied with by the 
applicant.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every licence granted under 
these rules shall be subject to the conditions specified therein.
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>51</number> Period for which licences 
may be granted or renewed.—
<section><number>1</number> A 
licence in Form D for the import of cylinders filled or intended to be filled 
with compressed gas may be granted for such period as the Chief Controller may 
deem necessary subject to a maximum of one year.
 </section><section><number>2</number> A licence in Form E, F or G 
for filling and storage of compressed gases granted or renewed under these rules 
shall remain in force till the 30th day of September of the year upto which the 
licence is granted or renewed subject to a maximum of ten years.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in sub‑rule (2), the Chief Con­troller or Controller authorised by the 
Chief controller, where he is satisfied that a licence is required for a 
specific work which is not likely to last up to the 30th day of September of the 
year up to which the licence is granted or renewed may grant or renew a licence 
for such a period as is necessary.
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>52</number> Particulars of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every licence granted under these rules shall be subject to the condition 
specified therein and shall contain all the particulars, which are contained in 
the form specified under these rules.
 </section><section><number>2</number> One copy of the plan or 
plans for the licensed premises signed in token of approval by the Chief 
Controller or Controller shall be attached to the licence, which shall form part 
of such a licence, and an identical copy shall be filed for record in the Office 
of the Chief Controller or Controller.
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>53</number> Prior approval necessary 
for alteration in the licensed premises­.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No alteration shall be carried out in the licensed premises until the plan 
showing such alterations has been approved in writing by the Chief Controller or 
Controller authorised by Chief Controller.
 </section><section><number>2</number> A person wishing to carry 
out any alteration in the licensed premises shall submit to the Chief Controller 
or Controller—
 <subsection>        <number>a</number>   three copies of a properly drawn plan to 
scale, of the licensed premises showing in distinct colours the proposed 
alterations and the reasons therefor;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>b</number>   scrutiny fee as specified in Schedule V.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> If the Chief Controller or 
Controller, after scrutiny of the plan showing the pro­posed alteration and 
after making such enquiries as he deems fit, is satisfied that the proposed 
alteration may be carried out, he shall return to the licensee one copy of the 
plan signed by him and conveying his sanction subject to such condition or 
conditions as may be specified.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The holder of the licence 
shall apply to the Chief Controller or Controller for the amendment of the 
licence as soon as the sanctioned alteration has been carried out.
 </section><section><number>5</number> No additions or alterations 
carried out in the licensed premises sanctioned by the Chief Controller or 
Controller shall be brought into use unless the licence is received by the 
licensee duly amended.
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>54</number> Amendment of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any licence granted under these rules may be amended by the Chief Controller or 
Controller authorised by the Chief Controller.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The fee for amendment of a 
licence shall be amendment fee plus the amount, if any, by which the fee that 
would have been payable if the licence had originally been issued in the amended 
form exceeds the fee originally paid for the licence.
 </section><section><number>3</number> A licensee who desires to 
have his licence amended shall submit to the Chief Controller or Controller—
 <subsection>         <number>i</number>   an application duly filled in and signed in 
Form B if the licence has been granted in Form D and in Form C if the licence 
has been granted in Form E, F and G;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>ii</number>   the licence sought to be amended together 
with the approved plans attached to it;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number>   where any alterations in the licensed 
premises have been carried out, three copies of the properly drawn plans showing 
the altera­tions sanctioned under rule 53 by the Chief Controller or Controller;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iv</number>   fees for the amendment of the licence as 
specified in sub‑rule (2).
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number> The holder of a licence in 
Form E, F or G may, at any time before the expiry of the licence, apply to the 
licensing authority to transfer the licence to another person and every 
application for such transfer of a licence shall be accompanied with—
 <subsection>         <number>i</number>   a letter signed by the holder of the licence 
indicating the full name and postal address of the person to whom he wishes to 
transfer the licence and give complete possession of the licensed premises;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>ii</number>   the licence sought to be transferred together 
with the approved plan or plans attached to it;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number>   an application in Form C duly filled and 
signed by the person to whom the licence is sought to be transferred;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iv</number>   amendment fee as specified in Schedule V.
</subsection></section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>55</number> Renewal of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A licence may be renewed by the Chief Controller or Controller.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every licence granted in 
Forms E, F and G under these rules, may be renewed for a maximum period of ten 
years at a time where there has been no contra­vention of the provisions of the 
Act or any rules framed thereunder or of any condition of the licence so 
renewed.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where a licence, which has 
been renewed for more than one year, is surrendered before its expiry, the 
renewal fee paid for the un-expired portion of the licence shall be refunded to 
the licensee provided that no refund of renewal fee shall be made for the year 
during which the Chief Controller or Controller receives the renewed licence for 
surrender.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Every application for the 
renewal of a licence shall be accompanied by the licence, which is to be renewed 
together with or without approved plans attached to the licence, and the renewal 
fee.
 </section><section><number>5</number> Every application for the 
renewal of a licence shall be made so as to reach the licensing authority on or 
before the date on which it expires and if the application is so made, the 
licence shall be deemed to be in force until such date as the Chief Controller 
or Controller renews the licence or until an intimation that the renewal of the 
licence is refused, has been communicated to the applicant.
 </section><section><number>6</number> Where the renewal of a 
licence is refused, the fee paid shall be refunded to the licensee after 
deducting therefrom the proportionate fee for the period beginning from the date 
from which the licence was to be renewed up to the date on which renewal thereof 
is refused.
 </section><section><number>7</number> The same fee shall be 
charged for the renewal of a licence for every twelve months for the grant of 
such renewal:
 Provided that—
 <subsection>        <number>a</number>   if the application with accompaniments 
required under sub‑rule (4) is not received within the time specified in 
sub‑rule (5) but received not later than three months the licence shall be 
renewed only on payment of a fee amounting to twice the fee ordinarily payable;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>b</number>   if such an application with accompaniments is 
received by the Chief Controller or Controller after three months from the date 
of expiry but not later than one year from the date of expiry, the licence may, 
without prejudice to any other action that may be taken in this behalf, be 
renewed on payment of late fee at the rate of one year licence fee for every 
delay of three months or part thereof:
 Provided further that in the 
case of an application for the re­newal of a licence for a period of more than 
one year at a time, the fee prescribed under the first proviso, if payable shall 
be paid only for the first year of renewal.
 </subsection></section><section><number>8</number> No licence shall be renewed 
if the application for renewal is received by the Chief Controller or Controller 
after one year of the date of its expiry.
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>56</number> Refusal of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chief Controller or Controller refusing to grant, amend, renew or transfer a 
licence, shall communicate the reasons thereof to the applicant.
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>57</number> Suspension and 
cancellation of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> Every 
licence granted under these rules shall be liable to be suspended or cancelled 
by an order of the licensing authority for any contravention of the provisions 
of the Act or rules framed thereunder or of any condition contained in such 
licence, or by an order of the Central Government, if at any time the 
continuance of the licence in the hands of the licensee is deemed objectionable:
  Provided that—
 <subsection>        <number>a</number>   before suspending or cancelling a licence 
under this rule, the holder of the licence shall be given an opportunity of 
being heard;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>b</number>   the maximum period of suspension shall not 
exceed three months; and
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>c</number>   the suspension of a licence shall not debar 
the holder of the licence from applying for its renewal in accordance with the 
provisions of rule 55.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in sub‑rule (1) an opportunity of being heard may not be given to the 
holder of a licence before his licence is suspended or cancelled in cases—
 <subsection>        <number>a</number>   where the licence is suspended by the 
licensing authority as an interim measure for violation of any of the provisions 
of the Act or these rules, or of any condition contained in such licence or in 
his opinion such violation is likely to cause imminent danger to the public:
                     Provided that where a licence is so 
suspended, the licensing authority shall give the holder of the licence an 
opportunity of being heard before the order of suspension is confirmed;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>b</number>   where the licence is suspended or cancelled by 
the Central Government, if that Government considers that in the public interest 
or in the interest of the security of the State such oppor­tunity should not be 
given.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> The Chief Controller or 
Controller or the Central Government suspending or can­celling a licence under 
sub‑rule (1), shall communicate the reasons thereof to the applicant except when 
the licence is suspended under sub-rule (2).
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>58</number> Procedure on expiration, 
suspension or cancellation of licence.—A 
person licensed to fill or store compressed gas shall, on the expiration, 
sus­pension or cancellation of such licence, forthwith give notice to the Chief 
Controller or Controller of the nature and quantity of compressed gas in his 
possession and shall comply with the directions which the Chief Controller or 
Controller may give in regard to its disposal.
</article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>59</number> Appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An appeal shall lie with the Central Government against any order passed by the 
Chief Controller refusing to grant, amend or renew a licence or cancelling or 
suspending a licence and to the Chief Controller against any order passed by the 
Controller.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every appeal shall be in 
writing and shall be accompanied by a copy of the order appealed against and 
shall be presented within sixty days of the order passed.
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>60</number> Procedure on death or 
disability of licensee.—If a licensee 
dies or becomes insolvent or mentally incapable or is otherwise disabled, the 
person carrying on the business or legal heir of such licensee shall not be 
liable to any penalty of confiscation under the Act or these rules for 
exercising the powers granted to the licensee during such time as may reasonably 
be required to allow him to make an application for a new licence or transfer of 
the existing licence in his own name:
 Provided that nothing in this 
rule shall be deemed to authorise the exercise of any power under this rule by 
any person after the expiry of the period of the licence.
</article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>61</number> Loss of licence.—Where 
a licence granted under these rules is lost or accidentally destroyed, a 
duplicate copy of the licence may be granted on submission of a copy of the plan 
or plans identical with those attached to the licence and on payment of a fee as 
specified in Schedule V.
</article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>62</number> Production of licence on 
demand.—
<section><number>1</number> Every person holding or 
acting under a licence granted under these rules shall produce it, or an 
authenticated copy of it, at the place to which the licence applies, when called 
upon to do so by any of the officers specified in rule 71.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Copies of any licence may, 
for the purposes of this rule, be authenti­cated by the authority, which granted 
the licence—
 <subsection>        <number>a</number>   on payment of a fee as specified in Schedule V 
for each authenticated copy; and
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>b</number>   on the submission of a copy of the plan 
identical with the approved plan attached to the licence.
</subsection></section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>63</number> Procedure on reports of 
infringement.—The District Authority 
shall inform the Chief Controller or Controller of the action taken by him on 
any reports of infringement of the Act or of these rules, which the Chief 
Controller or Controller may make to him.
</article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>64</number> Executive control over 
authorities.—Every authority, other 
than the Central Government, acting under this Chapter shall perform its duties 
sub­ject to the control of the Central Government:
 Provided that nothing in these 
rules shall be deemed to affect the powers of executive control of the Chief 
Controller over the officers subordinate to him.
</article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>65</number> Licence fee and other 
than licence fee.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
Government may, by notification in the official Gazette, revise the fees as 
specified in Schedule V from time to time.
 </section><section><number>2</number> All fees payable under these 
rules shall be paid through crossed demand draft drawn on any Bank in favour of 
the Chief Controller of Explosives or Controller of Explosives or Department of 
Explosives payable at respective places as the case may be.
</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>66</number> Power to exempt. </title>—If 
the Chief Controller is satisfied that in respect of any cylinder or any mode of 
conveyance, any of the requirements of these rules may be safely suspended or 
modified, he may, by written order, authorise such suspension or modification 
for such period and under such condition as he may think fit and such order may 
be revoked at any time: 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[Provided that the reasons for such 
suspension or modification are recorded in writing.] 



</article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>67</number> Notice of accidents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The notice of an accident required to be given under sub‑section (1) of section 
8 of the Act shall be given forthwith—
 <subsection>        <number>a</number>   to the Chief Controller or Controller under 
whose jurisdiction the area falls by Fax, E-mail or telegram (Telegraphic 
Address— Explosives, Nagpur, E-mail  explosives@explosives.gov.in) 
followed by a letter giving particulars of the occurrence within 24 hours;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>b</number>   to the District Magistrate concerned; and
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>c</number>   to the officer-in‑charge of the nearest Police 
Station by the quick­est route.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Pending the visit of the 
Chief Controller or Controller or until instruction is received from the Chief 
Controller or Controller that he does not wish to make any further investigation 
or inquiry, all wreckage and debris shall be left untouched except in so far as 
its removal may be necessary for the rescue of the persons injured and recovery 
of the bodies of any persons killed by the accident or in the case of railway or 
road for the restoration of through communication or traffic.
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>68</number> Inquiry into accidents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Whenever a District Magistrate or a Com­missioner of Police or Magistrate 
subordinate to a District Magistrate (hereinafter in this rule referred to as 
the Magistrate) holds an inquiry under sub­-section (1) of section 9 of the Act, 
he shall adjourn such an inquiry unless the Chief Controller or Controller of an 
officer nominated by him is present to watch the proceedings or the Magistrate 
has received written information from the Chief Controller or Controller that he 
does not wish to send a representative.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Magistrate shall, at 
least fourteen days before holding an adjourned inquiry, send to the Chief 
Controller or Controller notice in writing of the time and place of holding the 
adjourned inquiry.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where an accident has been 
attended with loss of human life, the Magistrate, may before the inquiry is 
adjourned under sub‑rule (1) take evi­dence to identify the bodies and may order 
the internment thereof.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Chief Controller or 
Controller or his representative shall be at liberty at any such inquiry to 
examine any witness.
 </section><section><number>5</number> Where evidence is given at 
an inquiry of any neglect as having caused or contributed to the explosion or 
accident or of any defect in or about or in connection with any installation or 
any vehicle appearing to the Magis­trate to require a remedy and the Chief 
Controller or Controller or the officer nominated by him is not present at the 
enquiry, the Magistrate shall send to the Chief Controller notice in writing of 
the neglect or defect.
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>69</number> Inquiry into more serious 
accidents.—
<section><number>1</number> Whenever an inquiry is 
held under section 9A of the Act, the person holding such inquiry shall hold the 
same in open court in such manner and under such conditions as they may think 
most effectual for ascertaining the causes and circumstances of the accident, 
and enabling them to make the report under this rule:
 Provided that where the Central 
Government so directs, the inquiry may be held in camera.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Persons attending as 
witnesses before the enquiry court shall be allowed such expenses as would be 
allowed to witnesses for attending before a civil court subordinate to the High 
Court having jurisdiction in the place where the inquiry is held and in case of 
any dispute as to the amount to be allowed, the question shall be referred to 
the local Magistrate, who, on a request made by the enquiry officer, shall 
ascertain and certify the proper amount of such expenses.
 </section><section><number>3</number> All expenses incurred in or 
about an inquiry or investigation under sub-rule (2) of rule 69 shall be deemed 
to be part of the expenses of the Department of Explosives in executing the 
provisions of the Act.
</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>70</number> Dangerous 
practices.—
<section><number>1</number> If in any matter which 
is not provided for by any express provision of, or condition of a licence 
granted under these rules, the Controller finds any compressed gas filling 
station or a storage place, where a cylinder is being filled or possessed, or 
any part thereof or anything or practice therein or connected therewith or with 
the handling or transport of compressed gas cylinders, dangerous or defective, 
so as, in his opinion, to tend to endanger the public safety or the bodily 
safety of any person, such Controller may by an order in writing require the 
occupier of such filling station or storage place or the owner of the cylinder 
to remedy the same within such time as may be specified in the order, and the 
said occupier shall carry out the orders within the specified time.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where the occupier or owner 
objects to an order made under sub‑rule (1), he may appeal to the Chief 
Controller within the time specified in the order for compliance with 
it.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every appeal preferred under 
sub‑rule (2) shall be in writing and shall be accompanied by a copy of the order 
appealed against and shall be made within a period of thirty days from the date 
of the order appealed against.
 </section><section><number>4</number> If the occupier or owner fails 
to comply with an order made under sub‑rule (1) within the time specified in it 
or, where an appeal is preferred under sub‑rule (2), fails to comply with the 
order of the Chief Controller thereon within the time fixed in such order, he 
shall be deemed to have committed a breach of this 
rule.</section></article> 
 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>71</number> Powers of inspection,
search, seizure, detention and removal.—
<section><number>1</number>
Any of the officers, specified in the first column of the Table below may
exercise the powers specified in sub‑section (1) of section 7 of the Act
in the area specified in the corresponding entry in the second column of that
Table.
 TABLE
 
                       Officers                                                            Area

 </section><section><number>1</number>    The Chief Controller or Controller                                   The whole of   India
 </section><section><number>2</number>    All District Magistrates                                                Their
respective Districts
 </section><section><number>3</number>    All Magistrates subordinate to                                      Their
respective jurisdiction  
the District Magistrate
 </section><section><number>4</number>    The Commissioner of Police and                                    In Presidency
town or  
all Police Officer of rank not                                         their
suburbs  
below that of an Inspector
 </section><section><number>5</number>    All Police Officer of rank not                                         The
respective area over which below that of Sub-Inspector                                                           their
authority extends: 
 
   

 Provided that the powers of
removal and destruction under clause (d) of sub‑section (1) of section 7
of the Act shall not be exercised by any Magistrate or Police Officer except
under and in accordance with the instructions of the Chief Controller or
Controller.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every facility shall be
afforded to the officer specified in sub‑rule (1) to ascertain that these
rules are being duly observed.

</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>72</number> Protection of action taken 
in goods faith.—
<section><number>1</number> No suit, 
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central Government 
of Chief Controller or Controller for anything which is in good faith done or 
intended to be done in pursuance of these rules.
 </section><section><number>2</number> No suit or other legal 
proceeding shall lie against the Central Government or Chief Controller or 
Controller for any damage caused or likely to be caused by anything which is in 
good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of these 
rules.</section></article> 
 The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>73</number> Repeal and savings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Gas Cylinder Rules, 1981 are hereby repealed.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding such repeal—
 <subsection>        <number>a</number>  all licences granted or renewed under the said 
rules and all fees imposed or levied shall be deemed to have been granted, 
renewed or imposed or levied, as the case may be under the corresponding 
provisions of these rules, and
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>b</number> all approvals given and all powers conferred by 
or under any notification or rule shall, so far as they are consistent with the 
Act and these rules, be deemed to have been given or conferred by or under these 
rules.
</subsection></section></article><form>
 




The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
 

 
 

SCHEDULE I
 

[See rule 3 (1)]
 

TYPES AND STANDARDS OF CYLINDERS AND VALVES
 

A. CYLINDERS And 
Containers
 

1. Indian Origin
 

(a) Cylinders.—Welded 
low carbon steel cylinders for low pressure liquefiable gases manufactured to 
IS: 3196 Part 1, Part 2 &amp; Part 4, IS: 7142, auto LPG containers to IS: 14899, DA 
cylinders to IS: 7312 certified by Bureau of Indian Standards.
 

Seamless steel cylinders 
manufactured to IS: 7285 by M/s Bharat Pumps &amp; Compressors Limited, Naini, 
Allahabad, M/s. Everest Kanto Cylinders Limited, Mumbai/(manufacturing unit at 
Tarapur and Aurangabad, Maharashtra) and M/s. Maruti Koatsu Cylinders Limited, 
Halol, Gujarat certified by BIS or any other inspection authority approved by 
Chief Controller.
 

(b) Containers.—Tonne 
containers manufactured to BS: 1500, ASME Section VIII Division 1, IS: 2825 by 
M/s. Asco Industrial Corporation, New Delhi, M/s. Indian Sugar and General Engg. 
Corporation, Yamunagar, M/s. Anup Engineering Ltd., Ahmedabad, M/s. Kosan Metal 
Products Pvt. Ltd., Mumbai, M/s. Meenakshi Associated Pvt. Ltd., Surajpur Dist. 
Ghaziabad, M/s. Titanium Equipment and Anode Manufacturing Co. Ltd., Chennai, 
M/s. Expo Gas Containers Ltd., Mumbai and certified by an inspection authority 
approved by Chief Controller.
 

2. Austrian origin
 

(a) Cylinders conforming to 
BS: 5045: Part I: 1982 for Halon-1301 and FM 200 gas service as per approved 
drawings manufactured by M/s. Worthington Heiser Cylinders Gmbh, 
Austria—Inspected and certified by Bureau Veritas.
 

(b) Cylinders conforming to B 
S: 5045: Part I: 1982 for permanent and liquefiable gases as per approved 
drawings, manufactured by M/s. Worthington Heiser Cylinders Gmbh, 
Austria—inspected and certified by Bureau Veritas.
 

(c) Seamless steel cylinders 
for CNG gas on-board service to NZS: 5454-1989 specification, having working 
pressure 200 Bar and test pressure 335 Bar manufactured by M/s. Worthington 
Cylinders GmbH, Austria certified by M/s. Bureau Veritas as per approved 
drawings.
 

3. Argentina origin
 

Seamless steel cylinders for 
CNG gas on-board service to NZS: 5454-1989 having working pressure 200 Bar and 
test pressure 335 Bar manufactured by M/s. Argentoil S.A., Argentina certified 
by M/s. Bureau Veritas as per approved drawing.
 

4. Chinese origin
 

Seamless steel cylinders for 
high pressure gas cylinders conforming to IS: 7285 specification manufactured by 
M/s. Beijing Tianhai Industry Co. Ltd., Beijing, China—inspected and certified 
by Boiler &amp; Pressure Container Safety Supervisory Bureau of Labour Department 
R.C.C. as per approved drawings.
 

5. Italian origin
 

(a) Seamless steel cylinders 
for permanent gases (Air/Oxygen) conforming to BS: 5045: Part I:1982 
manufactured by M/s. Faber Industries S.P.A., Italy—inspected and certified by 
Lloyd’s as per approved drawings.
 

(b) Seamless steel cylinders 
for compressed and liquefiable gases conforming to DOT:3AA specification having 
water capacity 80.0 ltrs. &amp; 120 ltrs. working pressure 79 Bar and test pressure 
132 Bar, manufactured by M/s. Faber Industries S.p.a., Italy—inspected and 
certified by M/s. Lloyd’s as per approved drawings.
 

(c) Seamless steel cylinders 
for CNG gas on-board service to NZS:5454-1989 having working pressure 200 Bar 
and test pressure 335 Bar manufactured by M/s. Faber Industries, S.p.a., Italy, 
certified by M/s. Lloyd’s as per approved drawings.
 

6. Spain origin
 

Seamless steel cylinders for 
FM-200 gas service conforming to BS: 5045 Part 1 manufactured by M/s. Productos 
Tubulares, s.a., inspected and certified by M/s. Lloyd’s, as per approved 
drawings.
 

7. Japan origin
 

Steel cylinders manufactured 
by M/s. Showa Koatsu Kogyo Co. Ltd.,—inspected and certified by Company’s own 
Inspector or KHK or Lloyd’s or Bureau Veritas conforming to specifications DOT: 
3AA: 1800 and above, JIS; B : 8241 relating to Manganese Steel for permanent 
gases and DOT: 3A/DOT: 3AA for liquefiable gases as per approved drawings.
 

8. Polish origin
 

Auto LPG containers 
manufactured by M/s. Stako, Poland made to ECE-R-67-01 specification, inspected 
and certified by Institute of Transport Technical Supervision as per approved 
drawings.
 

9. U.K. origin
 

(a) Aluminium alloy cylinders 
conforming to BS:5045: Pt.3 or EN equivalent specification manufactured by M/s. 
Luxfur gas Cylinders, UK—inspected and certified by Lloyd’s or British 
Inspecting Engineers Ltd., as per approved drawings.
 

(b) Seamless steel cylinders 
for permanent and Liquefiable gases conforming to BS: 5045: Part I manufactured 
by M/s. UEF Chesterfield Cylinders, UK—inspected and certified by Lloyd’s or 
Bureau Veritas or British Inspecting Engineering Ltd., or any other appropriate 
authority as per approved drawings.
 

(c) Seamless steel cylinders 
for permanent and liquefiable gases conforming to DOT:3T specification 
manufactured by UEF Chesterfield Cylinders UD—inspected and certified by British 
Inspecting Engineers Ltd., as per approved drawings.
 

(d) Seamless steel cylinders 
for FM-200 gas service conforming to DOT: 4BA:500 specification manufactured by 
M/s. Fike Protection &amp; Systems, U.K., having water capacity 650 pounds, filling 
ratio 1.04 super pressurised with Nitrogen at 19.72 Bar as per approved 
drawings.
 

(e) Seamless steel cylinders 
for CNG gas on-board service to BS: 5045-1982 Part 1 having working pressure 200 
Bar and test pressure 344 Bar manufactured by M/s. UEF Chesterfield Cylinder, 
Derbyshire, UK certified by M/s. British Inspection Engineering Ltd., as per 
approved drawings.
 

10. USA origin
 

(a) Steel cylinders—inspected 
and certified by appropriate authority, conforming to specifications DOT: 3A/3AA 
for permanent and liquefiable gases manufactured by (1) M/s. Norris Cylinder 
Co., (2) M/s. Taylor Wharton Co., (3) M/s. Worthington Cylinder Co., (4) M/s. 
Norristi Industries, (5) M/s. Harris Burg Steel Co., and (6) M/s. Pressed Steel 
Tank Co., as per approved drawings.
 

(b) Aluminium alloy cylinders 
conforming to DOT:3AL specification manufactured by M/s. Luxfer Gas Cylinders, 
USA—inspected and certified by authorised Testing Inc. or Arrowhead Inc. as per 
approved drawings.
 

11. German origin
 

Seamless steel cylinders for 
permanent and liquefiable gas service conforming to BIS:5045/1/CM/S &amp; DOT:3AA 
manufactured by M/s. Mannesmann Cylinders Systems Gmbh, Germany—inspected and 
certified by Lloyd’s or TUV or any other authority as per approved drawings.
 


B. Valves
 

1. Indian origin
 

LPG valves and regulators 
manufactured to IS:8776, IS:8737, IS:9798, multi function valve to IS:15100, 
valves in respect of medical gas cylinder to IS: 3745 and valves in respect of 
cylinders used with breathing apparatus to IS:7302, certified by Bureau of 
Indian Standards and approved by the Chief Controller.
 

Valves in respect of 
industrial gas cylinder including CNG manufactured to IS:3224 and certified by 
BIS or an inspection agency approved by Chief Controller.
 

2. Italian origin
 

CNG valve Model 119, 198/1, 
120, VAL-B-305, VAL-B-323, VAL-B-315 manufactured by M/s. EMER S.r.l., Italy 
inspected and certified by Bureau Veritas.
 

Multi function valve Model 
MULTIVALVOLA BRC EUROPA manufactured by M/s. M.T.M. s.r.l., Italy, Model No. 
EMER s.r.l. tipo E-67-01, EMER LANDI RENZO manufactured by Emer, s.r.l., Italy, 
Model MV-305 manufactured by M/s. Lovato S.p.a., Italy. Model OMVL, Tomesetto 
Achile, Borel GPL Grenoble, G.M.S. manufactured by M/s. 
Tomasetto Achile, 
Italy to specification ECE-R-67-01 with set pressure 2.2 MPa as per approved 
drawings.
 

Note.—“approved” 
means approved by Chief Controller.
</form><form>
 




The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
 

 
 

SCHEDULE II
 

[See rule 3 (2)]
 

(A) The test and inspection 
certificates to be obtained from the Inspect­ing Authority in respect of 
cylinders manufactured in accordance with the approved design and specification 
or Code shall include the following particulars, namely:—
 

         1.  Place and date of inspection.
 

         2. Gas cylinders 
for................................................................................................gas.
 

         3. Manufactured 
by.....................................................................................................
 

         4. Location 
at................................................................................................................
 

         5. Manufactured 
for.....................................................................................................
 

         6. Location 
for...............................................................................................................
 

         7.  
Quantity.....................................................................................................................
 

         8. Serial Nos. from 
................................. 
to................................................inclusive.
 

         9. Specification to which the cylinders are 
manufactured.......................................
 

       10. Size ......................mm. Outside diameter 
mm............................................. long.
 

       11.  Minimum wall 
thickness.........................................................................................
 

       12. Neck and threading as 
per.............................................................. specification.
 

       13.  Process of manufacture (whether spun type, or 
billet pierced or welded).
 

       14.  Method of heat treatment.
 

       15.  Design working pressure in Kg/cm2 at 
15oC or 
65oC as 
the case may be.
 

       16.  Hydrostatic test/ hydrostatic stretch test 
pressure in Kg/cm2.
 

       17.  Record of Hydrostatic test/ Hydrostatic stretch 
test with the date of test, in respect of each 
cylinder..........................................................................................
 

       18.  Pneumatic test pressure in Kg/cm2......................................................................
 

       19.  Result of pneumatic 
test..........................................................................................
 

       20.  Tare weight and water capacity of each 
cylinder..............................................
 

       21.  Record of chemical analysis and physical 
properties of the steel used in the manufacture of 
cylinders......................................................................................
 

       22.  Manufacturer’s identification 
marks.....................................................................
 

       23.  Inspector’s 
mark......................................................................................................
 

       24.  Markings stamped on the shoulder of the 
cylinders........................................
 

       25.  Dated signature with stamp of the inspecting 
authority.................................
 

(B) The test and inspection 
certificates to be obtained from the Inspecting Authority in respect of valves 
manufactured in accordance with the approved design and specification or Code 
shall include the following particulars, namely:—
 

         1.  Manufactured 
by......................................................................................................
 

         2. Location 
at­.................................................................................................................
 

         3. Manufactured 
for­.....................................................................................................
 

         4. Location 
at­.................................................................................................................
 

         5. 
Quantity­.....................................................................................................................
 

         6. 
Specification..............................................................................................................
 

         7. Results of inspection
 

           ­(a) Valve inlet 
connection.......................................................................................
 

           (b) Valve outlet 
connection.....................................................................................
 

            (c) Valve outlet 
number............................................................................................
 

           (d) Hydraulic Pressure 
Test.....................................................................................
 

           (e) Pneumatic Proof 
Test..........................................................................................
 

            (f) Tensile 
strength...................................................................................................
 

           (g) Elongation per 
cent............................................................................................
 

           (h) Impact 
strength...................................................................................................
 

             (i) Quantity offered for 
inspection........................................................................
 

            (j) Quantity 
passed..................................................................................................
 

           (k) Quantity rejected and reasons for 
rejection...................................................
 

8. Date and signature with 
stamp of the inspecting authority.....................................
</form><form>
 




The Gas Cylinders Rules, 2004
 

 
 

SCHEDULE III
 

[See rule 3 (3)]
 

Particulars to be submitted by person desiring to fabricate 
cylinders, valves and other fittings
 

         1.  Applicant’s name and full address with 
telephone No(s). and E-mail address
 

         2.  Whether the applicant has manufactured any 
pressure vessel/cylinder/container/valve, if yes—
 

             (i)  Date from which such container/valves 
were manufactured.
 

            (ii)  For whom the container/valves were 
fabricated and their approximate numbers.
 

           (iii)  Details of the container/valves 
manufactured.
 

         3.  Specification/Codes proposed to be adopted for 
the manufac­ture of cylinder/containers/valves.
 

         4.  Organizational set up of the applicant with 
specific reference to qualifications and experience of the personnel engaged in 
the manufacture of cylinder/containers/valves.
 

         5.  Organizational set up of the inspecting 
personnel engaged by the applicant.
 

         6.  Process of manufacture of 
cylinders/containers/valves, beginning with raw material and ending with the 
finished cylinders/containers/valves.
 

         7.  Quality control checks/tests carried out at 
each stage of manu­facture of cylinders/containers/valves.
 

         8. (i)  Details of the equipment installed for 
chemical analysis and mechanical tests.
 

            (ii)  Details of templates/ gauges provided to 
check/test.
 

           (iii)  Steps taken to check the accuracy of 
testing and checking equipment and frequency of such checking.
 

         9.  Equipment available or carrying out 
non‑destructive examina­tion such as Gama Ray/X-ray equipment, viewer, etc. for 
radiographic examination, ultrasonic flaw detector, equipments for dye 
penetration and magnetic particle tests, etc.
 

       10.  List of machinery provided for manufacturing 
cylinders/containers/valves.
 

       11.  Name and address of the independent inspecting 
authority.
 

       12.  Records and certificates of tests :
 

             (i)  Proforma of records for various tests 
carried out by the inspecting and certifying organisation, and
 

            (ii)  Proforma of test and inspection 
certificate issued by the independent inspecting authority.
 

       13.  Whether the manufacturing unit has been 
certified under ISO or equivalent certification, (if so, documentary evidence 
thereof to be attached).
 

       14.  List of relevant codes, specifications and 
technical literature available.
 


Signature........................
 


Date................................                                                                          Name and designation
 


Place................................
</form><form>
 

THE GAS CYLINDERS RULES, 
20041
 

 
 

 
 

SCHEDULE IV 
 

(See rule 35) 
 

A. FACILITIES REQUIRED FOR CYLINDER TESTING STATIONS 

 

1. Management:-
 

1.1. General Requirements.—Personal, equipment, 
inspection procedures, recording and organisation shall be adequate and the test 
station will be operated with safe-operating conditions. The procedures and 
testing shall ensure that cylinders, which fail to meet the requirements and 
intent of these rules, are not returned into normal service. All personnel shall 
fully recognise their individual responsibilities and that the minimum 
inspectional requirement shall not be lowered for any reason whatsoever. 
 

Note.—The area of responsibility shall be divided into three 
separate function as indicated below. The numbers of personnel employed shall, 
however, be related to the quantum of work. 
 

1.2. Manager.—The manager responsible for the 
working of the test station shall be properly qualified; his qualifications 
shall include training on the dangers associated with gas cylinders, purpose of 
inspection, test methods, equipment, test requirements, and recording of test 
results, and he shall have appropriate technical qualification in Mechanical or 
Chemical Engineering. He shall also be conversant with the Codes, Specifications 
and/or Regulations applying to the cylinders for which the test station is 
approved. 
 

1.3. Supervisor .—The Supervisor shall 
possess the following qualifica­tions, namely:— 
 
 

(i) have at least two years' experience in the examination of 
  gas cylinder; 
 

(ii) be at least 21 years of age; 
 

(iii) be conversant with these rules, Codes, Specifications 
  and/or Regulations applying to the cylinders for which the test station is 
  approved. 
 

1.4. Operator .—Personnel conducting 
inspections and tests shall have qualifications and experience suitable for the 
work on which they are en­gaged. They shall be trained to understand the 
dangers associated with gas cylinders and the purpose and method of inspection. 

 

2. Equipment: 
 
 

2.1. Type of equipment .—The test 
  station shall have adequate equipment to carry out inspection and testing of 
  cylinders as required under these rules. It shall contain— 
 

(i) One set of these rules, Codes, Specifications and/or 
  Regulations applying to the cylinders which the test station is authorised to 
  test. All these rules, Codes, Specifications and/or Regulations shall be 
  maintained with all current amendments. 
 

(ii) Hydrostatic test apparatus comprising pressurising 
  equipment, pressure gauge and volumetric measuring equipment in 
  accor­dance with IS : 5844-Hydrostatic stretch testing of compressed gas 
  cylinders. The apparatus shall be equipped with at least two 15 cm diameter 
  (minimum) working pressure gauges. 
 

(iii) Non-destructive testing facilities like ultrasonic flaw 
  detection, acoustic emission techniques, etc. for detection of stress 
  corrosion cracks developed during the service. 
 

(iv) Dead-weight pressure gauge tester of appropriate pressure 
  range or a master pressure gauge of 15 cm. minimum diameter covering the 
  appropriate pressure range. 
 

(v) Boroscope, extra-low voltage lamps to permit adequate 
  internal viewing of cylinders and other lamps necessary for close examination 
  of external surfaces. 
 

(vi) Straightedges, templates, miscellaneous tool and gauges 
  for measurement. 
 

(vii) Weighing equipment, where applicable. 
 

(viii) One set of standard test weights for the weighing 
  machine, stamped by the relevant statutory authority. 
 

(ix) Adequate cylinder handling equipment. 
 

(x) Adequate cylinder draining equipment. 
 

(xi) Facilities for internal drying of cylinders. 
 

(xii) Marking and stamping equipment. 
 

2.2. Accuracy .—The accuracy of 
equipment shall be as follows:— 
 
 

(i) Hydrostatic test apparatus in accordance with IS:5844. 
  Volumetric equipment shall be capable of measuring a permanent change in 
  volume of the cylinder under test of the order of 1/20,000 of its total 
  capacity. 
 

(ii) Weighing equipment error not greater than ± 0.1 per cent. 
  
 

(iii) Working pressure gauge error not greater than 1 per 
  cent. of the pressure. 
 

(iv) Master pressure gauge error not greater than 0.25 per 
  cent. of the full scale deflection. 
 

2.3. Calibration .—Calibration of 
equipment shall be carried out at periods not exce (i) Working pressure gauge—1 
month. 
 
 

(ii) Master pressure gauge—6 months. 
 

(iii) Weighing equipment—checked by test weight daily when in 
  service. 
 

(iv) Test weights—2 years. 
 

3. Working Conditions. —Working conditions for 
the test stations shall be conducive to accurate and safe inspection and testing 
of gas cylinders. The test station shall comply with the following conditions:— 

 
 

(i) It shall have good lighting to permit ready external 
  examination of gas cylinders, preferably including natural lighting. 
 

(ii) It shall have adequate ventilation to remove residual 
  gases from cylinders. 
 

(iii) It shall provide sufficient space to permit safe 
  working. 
 

(iv) It shall be maintained in a clean dry condition. 

 

4. Quality management system. —The quality 
management system of a cylinder testing station for seamless steel/composite 
cylinder shall be got duly certified under ISO Standards from Bureau of Indian 
Standards or any other internationally reputed agency. 
 

B. TESTING OF CYLINDERS 
 

1. Condition of cylinders for test .—Cylinders 
forwarded to the test station for testing shall have first been emptied of their 
contents and then labelled as ‘empty'. Irrespective of this label all cylinders 
other than cylinders at the manufacturers works shall be presumed to contain gas 
under pressure and the following precautions shall accordingly be observed: 
 
 

(i) The cylinder contents shall be released in a safe manner 
  keeping in mind dangers associated with the nature of the gas in the cylinder. 
  Cylinders, which contain or may have been contami­nated by poisonous or 
  obnoxious substances shall be emptied only by test stations properly equipped 
  and experienced to handle the particular gas/substance. Such cylinders shall 
  be clearly labelled that they have been contaminated. 
 

(ii) The valve shall be opened and if no gas escapes and the 
  port is not visibly blocked, a charge of low-pressure nitrogen or other inert 
  gas shall be blown into the valve outlet. Discharge of gas after removal of 
  the nitrogen supply indicated that the cylinder is empty. When no gas 
  discharges the valves shall be treated as “obstructed”. Where a cylinder has 
  contained poisonous or obnoxious substances, and the valve is suspected of 
  being obstructed, the gas shall be released within an approved appli­ance 
  and the valves shall be removed in such a manner that the gas escapes without 
  danger to the operator. 
 

(iii) Should the valve be obstructed the contents of the 
  cylinder shall be released in a safe manner as stated in (i) above. Work on 
  cylinders containing combustible gases shall be carried out in the open air. 
  
 

Note. —A suitable method of dealing with a 
valve in which the spindle cannot be removed is to drill a 1/16th in (1.6 mm) 
diameter hole with a hand drill through the valve body to the gas passage below 
the spindle seating. Alternatively, a fine-tooth hacksaw may be used. Drilling 
or sawing must be stopped immediately upon the first sign of escaping gas. A 
continuous jet of water must be directed on to the cutting tools and the 
operator must wear protective clothing. 
 

2. Inspection of cylinders before carrying out 
hydrostatic/hydrostatic stretch test. —(1) Prior of carrying out 
hydrostatic/hydrostatic stretch test, every cylinder shall be thoroughly cleaned 
by steam cleaning or washing out with approved solvents. Where the interior of 
the cylinder is affected by rust or other foreign matter it shall be cleaned by 
one of the following methods, namely:— 
 
 

(a) Approved blasting, rotary wire brushing; 
 

(b) Burn out treatment carried out in a furnace at a 
  temperature not exceeding 300°C for a period of not exceeding one hour after 
  which all free rusts and any other foreign matter shall be removed by steam 
  cleaning or washing with approved solvents. 
 

(2) The cylinder after cleaning shall be visually examined 
externally and as far as practicable internally for surface defect in accordance 
with the IS:5845, IS:8451 or IS:13258 as the case may be, or any other Code 
approved in writing by the Chief Controller. 
 

3. Hydrostatic/hydorstatic stretch test/proof pressure 
test. —(1) For cylinders used for permanent gases, high pressure 
liquefiable gases and all toxic and corrosive gases:— 
 
 

(i) The cylinders shall be subjected to hydrostatic stretch 
  test in accordance with IS:5844. The test pressure applied to the cylinder 
  shall be retained for a period of not less than 30 seconds. 
 

(ii) The permanent stretch suffered by cylinder due to 
  application of test pressure shall not exceed the following limits, namely:— 
  
 
 

(a) In the case of cylinder below 10% of the total stretch 
    suffered 20 litres water capacity during the est. for non-corrosive gases. 
    
 

(b) In other cases. 10% of the total stretch suffered during 
    the test or 1/5000th of the original volume of the cylinder, whichever is 
    less. 
 

(iii) Any reduction in pressure noticed during the retention 
  of 30 seconds or any leakage, visible bulge or deformation should be treated 
  as case of failure in the test. 
 

(2) For cylinders for low pressure non-corrosive liquefiable 
gases: 
 
 

(i) The cylinder shall be subjected to hydrostatic test in 
  accordance with IS:5844 by non-jacket method except that the volumetric 
  changes during the test need not be measured. 
 

(ii) The test pressure shall be retained for a period of not 
  less than 30 seconds. Any reduction in pressure noticed during this retention 
  period or any leakage, visible bulge or deformation shall be treated as case 
  of failure in the test. 
 

(3) As soon as the test is completed, the cylinder shall 
thoroughly dried internally and shall be clearly stamped on the neck and with 
marks and figures indicating the person by whom the test has been carried out 
and the date of test. Code mark of the person by whom the test has been carried 
out shall be registered with the Chief Controller. 
 

4. Any cylinder which fails to pass periodic 
examination or test or which loses in its tare weight be over 5 per cent or 
which for any other defect is found to be unsafe for use and which cannot be 
repaired in accordance with rule 11 and 12 shall be reported to the owner of the 
cylinder and shall be destroyed by rendering the cylinder unusable as provided 
under rule 36. 
 

5. Records of test. —Full record of cylinders 
examined and tested at any testing station shall be maintained giving the 
following particulars, namely:— 
 
 

(a) Name of the manufacturer and the owner of cylinder. 
 

(b) Rotation Number. 
 

(c) The specification to which the cylinder conforms. 
 

(d) Date of original hydrostatic/hydrostatic stretch test. 

 

(e) Test reports and certificates furnished by the 
  manufacturer, if available. 
 

(f) Test pressure. 
 

(g) Maximum working pressure. 
 

(h) Water capacity. 
 

(i) Tare weight. 
 

(j) Variation, if any, in the tare weight marked on the 
  cylinder and actual tare weight. 
 

(k) Condition of cylinder shell. 
 

(l) Name of gas. 
 

(m) Type of valve fitted, and 
 

(n) Remarks, if any. 
 

Note. —(1) The above particulars shall form the 
history card or record for each cylinder and all changes from time to time shall 
be indicated therein. 
 

(2) The test station shall adopt procedures, which fully comply 
with the requirements of these rules and guidelines issued by Chief Controller 
from time to time. 
 

----------
 

1. Vide G.S.R. 627 (E), dated 21st September, 2004, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3 (i), dated 21st 
September, 2004.</form><form>
 

THE GAS CYLINDERS RULES, 
20041
 

 
 

 
 

Schedule VI 
 

( See rule 20) 
 

Transport of Cylinders 
 

1. Transport of cylinders by vehicles. —(a) 
Cylinders filled with any compressed gas shall not be transported by a bicycle 
or any other two wheeled mechanically propelled vehicle. 
 
 

(b) Cylinders shall be so transported as not to project in the 
  horizontal plane beyond the side or ends of the vehicle by which they are 
  transported. 
 

(c) There shall be no sharp projections on the insides of the 
  vehicle. 
 

(d) Cylinders shall be adequately secured to prevent their 
  falling off the vehicle and being subjected to rough handling, excessive 
  shocks or local stresses. 
 

(e) Cylinders transported in vehicles shall be blocked or 
  braced and be so secured to prevent movement, striking each other or falling 
  down. 
 

(f) Cylinders filled with any compressed gas shall not be 
  transported along with any other article of a highly flammable or corrosive 
  nature. 
 

2. Restriction on transport. —(a) Cylinders 
containing flammable gases shall not be transported along with the cylinders 
containing any other type of compressed gas: 
 
 

(b) Cylinders containing toxic or corrosive gas shall not be 
  transported along with food-stuffs. Nothwithstanding anything contained in 
  clause (a) above, DA cylinders not exceeding 25 in numbers may be transported 
  along with non-toxic non-flammable gases taking due precautions. 

 

3. Loading and unloading for transport. —(a) No 
lifting magnet shall be used in loading or unloading of cylinders filled with 
any compressed gas. 
 
 

(b) Where any such operation is carried on by means of a crane 
  or a fork-lift truck, a proper cradle with chains or wire rope slings shall be 
  used. 
 

4. Protection of valves during transport. —(a) 
Every cylinder containing compressed gas shall, when transported, have its valve 
protected against damage in the manner provided in sub-rules (b) and (c) unless 
it is securely packed in a box or crate. 
 
 

(b) Where the design of the cylinder does not provide for the 
  valve laying wholly below the level of the body of the cylinder, a stout metal 
  cap, metal cover or a protective metal ring or grill of a design approved by 
  the Chief Controller shall be provided, the design being such that the cap or 
  cover or ring or grill is nowhere in close proximity to any party of the valve 
  or valve body. 
 

(c) Where metal caps or metal covers are provided, to protect 
  valves fitted to cylinder other than those containing highly toxic gases like 
  Hydrogen cyanide, Phosgene, Cyanogen, Cyanogen chloride, it shall be provided 
  with a vent of such size so as to prevent any gas pressure inside the caps or 
  covers. 
 

(d) Cylinders containing highly toxic gases like Hydrogen 
  cyanide, Phosgene, Cyanogen, Cyanogen chloride gases, shall have their valves 
  protected with gas-tight metal caps or covers. 
 

(e) Nothing in sub-rules (a), (b) and (c) shall apply to 
  cylinders containing oxygen or nitrous oxide for medical purpose having water 
  capacity not exceeding 5 litres. 
 

5. Leaky cylinders. —(a) No person shall tender 
or transport and leaky cylinder. 
 
 

(b) Any cylinder containing a flammable or toxic gas, which 
  develops a leak during transport shall promptly be removed to an isolated open 
  place away from any source of ignition and the person responsible for 
  transportation shall immediately contact the filler or the consignor as the 
  case may be, for necessary advice. 
 

----------
 

1. Vide G.S.R. 627 (E), dated 21st September, 2004, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3 (i), dated 21st 
September, 2004.</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by G.S.R. 677(E), dated 24th October, 2007 (w.e.f. 
24-10-2007).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>