<act><tid>880333</tid>
<title>THE ADMINISTRATION OF EVACUEE PROPERTY ACT, <year>1950</year></title>

ACT NO. 31 OF <year>1950</year>
[ 17th April, <year>1950</year>.]

An Act to provide for the administration of evacuee property and for 
certain matters connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament as follows:--

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>552137</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>1493616</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Administration of Evacuee Property Act, <year>1950</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>261530</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India except <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the territories 
which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in 
the States] of Assam, West Bengal, Tripura, Manipur and Jammu and 
Kashmir.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>203985</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>197774</tid>
<number>a</number>" allotment" means the grant by a person duly authorized 
in this behalf of a right of use or occupation of any 
immovable evacuee property to any other person, but 
does not include a grant by way of lease;

</section>

<section><tid>1188197</tid>
<number>b</number>" Custodian- General" means the Custodian- General of 
Evacuee Property in India appointed by the Central 
Government under section 5;

</section>

<section><tid>1308915</tid>
<number>c</number>" Custodian" means the Custodian for the State, and 
includes any Additional, Deputy or Assistant Custodian 
of Evacuee Property appointed in that State;

</section>

<section><tid>637930</tid>
<number>d</number>" evacuee" means any person,--

<subsection><tid>860101</tid>
<number>i</number>who, on account of the setting up of the 
Dominions of India and Pakistan or on account of 
civil disturbances or the fear of such 
disturbances, leaves or has, on or after the 1st 
day of March, <year>1947</year>, left, any place in a State for 
any place outside the territories now forming part 
of India, or
<pagefootnote><pagenum>10</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" the 
States".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1806902</tid>
<number>ii</number>who is resident in any place now forming 
part of Pakistan and who for that reason is unable 
to occupy, supervise or manage in person his 
property in any part of the territories to which 
this Act extends, or whose property in any part of 
the said territories has ceased to be occupied, 
supervised or managed by any person or is being 
occupied, supervised or managed by an unauthorized 
person, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>390103</tid>
<number>iii</number>who has, after the 14th day of August, 
<year>1947</year>, obtained, otherwise than by way of purchase 
or exchange, any right to, interest in or benefit 
from any property which is treated as evacuee or 
abandoned property under any law for the time 
being in force in Pakistan, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>689595</tid>
<number>iv</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> who has, after the 18th day of 
October, <year>1949</year>, transferred to Pakistan, without 
the previous approval of the Custodian, his assets 
or any part of his assets situated in any part of 
the territories to which this Act extends, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>682733</tid>
<number>v</number>who has, after the 18th day of October, 
<year>1949</year>, acquired, if the acquisition has been made 
in person, by way of purchase or exchange, or, if 
the acquisition has been made by or through a 
member of his family, in any manner whatsoever, 
any right to, interest in, or benefit from, any 
property which is treated as evacuee or abandoned 
property under any law for the time being in force 
in Pakistan;]
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Explanation I].-- For the purposes of sub- 
clause (iii), the acquisition of any right to, 
interest in or benefit from any such property as 
is referred to in that sub- clause by a firm, 
private limited company or trust of which any 
person or any member of the family of such person 
wholly dependent on him for the ordinary 
necessaries of life is a partner, member or 
beneficiary, as the case may be shall be deemed to 
be an acquisition by that person within the 
meaning of that sub- clause.

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Explanation II.-- For the purposes of sub- 
clause (iv), the transfer to Pakistan by any 
person of any


<pagefootnote><pagenum>11</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 11 of <year>1953</year>, s. 2. 
2. Re- numbered by s. 2, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

reasonable sum of money in accordance with the 
rules made in this behalf by the Central 
Government for the purpose of financing any 
transaction in the ordinary course of his trade or 
for the maintenance of any member of the family of 
such person shall not be deemed to be a transfer 
of his assets within the meaning of that sub- 
clause.

Explanation III.-- For the purposes of sub- 
clause (v), the acquisition of any right to, 
interest in, or benefit from, any such property as 
is referred to in that sub- clause by a firm, 
private limited company or trust of which any 
person is a partner, member or beneficiary, as the 
case may be, shall be deemed to be an acquisition 
by that person of such right, interest or benefit 
within the meaning of that sub- clause;]

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>709372</tid>
<number>f</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> evacuee property" means any property of an evacuee 
 (whether held by him as owner or as a trustee or as a  
  beneficiary or as a tenant or in any other capacity), 
and includes any property which has been obtained by 
any person from an evacuee after the 14th day of 
August, <year>1947</year>, by any mode of transfer which is not 
effective by reason of the provisions contained in 
section 40,] but does not include--

<subsection><tid>420462</tid>
<number>i</number>any ornament and any wearing apparel, 
cooking vessels or other household effects in the 
immediate possession of an evacuee,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1935620</tid>
<number>ii</number>any property belonging to a joint stock 
company, the registered office of which was 
situated before the 15th day of August, <year>1947</year>, in 
any place now forming part of Pakistan and 
continues to be so situated after the said date;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1959166</tid>
<number>g</number>" member of the family" means any member of the family 
of any person who is wholly dependent upon the earnings 
of such person for the provision of the ordinary 
necessaries of life or who shares with such person in 
the ordinary expenses of the household to which they 
jointly belong or who owns property or carries on 
business jointly with such person;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>12</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Cl. (e) omitted by Act 11 of <year>1953</year>, s. 2. 
2. Subs. by s. 2, ibid., for certain words.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1432378</tid>
<number>h</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1800857</tid>
<number>i</number>" property" means property of any kind, and includes any 
right or interest in such property;

</section>

<section><tid>926516</tid>
<number>j</number>" unauthorized person" means any person (whether duly  
  empowered in this behalf by the evacuee or otherwise) 
who, after the 14th day of August, <year>1947</year>, has been 
occupying, supervising or managing the property of an 
evacuee without the approval of the Custodian.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1115795</tid>
<number>3</number>[ References to enactments not in force in Part B States.] Rep. 
by the Administration of Evacuee Property (Amendment) Act, <year>1953</year> (11 of  
  <year>1953</year>), s. 3.


</article>



<article><tid>25031</tid>
<number> 4</number> Act to override other laws. <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1832759</tid>
<number>1</number>] The provisions of this Act  
and of the rules and orders made thereunder shall have effect 
notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained in any other 
law for the time being in force or in any instrument having effect by 
virtue of any such law.

</section>

<section><tid>1854160</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that 
nothing in any other law controlling the rents of, or evictions from, 
any property shall apply, or be deemed ever to have applied, to 
evacuee property.]
CHAP

EVACUEE PROPERTY AND VESTING THEREOF IN THE CUSTODIAN

CHAPTER II

EVACUEE PROPERTY AND VESTING THEREOF IN THE CUSTODIAN




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1193056</tid>
<number>5</number>Appointment of Custodian- General, Deputy Custodian- General, 
etc. The Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, appoint a Custodian- General and as many Deputy and Assistant 
Custodians- General as may be necessary for the purpose of discharging 
the duties imposed upon the Custodian- General and the Deputy and 
Assistant Custodians- General by or under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1187120</tid>
<number> 6</number> Appointment of Custodians, etc. <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1277177</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government  
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint for any State a 
Custodian and as many Additional, Deputy or Assistant Custodians of 
Evacuee Property as may be necessary for the purpose of discharging 
the duties imposed
<pagefootnote><pagenum>13</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>S. 4 renumbered as sub- section (1) of that section by Act 42 of 
<year>1954</year>, s. 2. 
2. Ins. by s. 2, ibid. 
3. Subs. by Act 91 of <year>1956</year>, s. 2, for sub- section (1)  (w. e. f. 22- 10-  
  <year>1956</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


on the Custodian by or under this Act, and the same person may be 
appointed as the Custodian, or as the case may be, Additional, Deputy 
or Assistant Custodian of Evacuee Property for two or more States.]


</section>

<section><tid>1650676</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act, all Custodians, 
Additional, Deputy or Assistant Custodians of Evacuee Property shall 
discharge the duties imposed on them by or under this Act under the 
general superintendence and control of the Custodian- General.

</section>

<section><tid>1325218</tid>
<number>3</number>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (2), Additional, 
Deputy and Assistant Custodians shall discharge the duties imposed on 
them by or under this Act under the general superintendence and 
control of the Custodian for the State, but the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Central Government] 
may, by general or special order, provide for the distribution of work 
among them:
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Provided that nothing in this sub- section shall be deemed to 
empower the Custodian to question any order made by an Additional, 
Deputy or Assistant Custodian in respect of any matter which the 
Additional, Deputy or Assistant Custodian is empowered by or under 
this Act to determine.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1150879</tid>
<number> 7</number> Notification of evacuee property.
<section><tid>384107</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the Custodian is  
of opinion that any property is evacuee property within the meaning of 
this Act, he may, after causing notice thereof to be given in such 
manner as may be prescribed to the persons interested, and after 
holding such inquiry into the matter as the circumstances of the case 
permit, pass an order declaring any such property to be evacuee 
property.

</section>

<section><tid>1288009</tid>
<number>1A</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Where during the pendency of any proceeding under sub- 
section (1) for declaring any property to be evacuee property any 
person interested in the property dies, the proceeding shall, unless 
the Custodian otherwise directs, be continued and disposed of as if 
such person were alive.]

</section>

<section><tid>169146</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a notice has been issued under sub- section (1) in 
respect of any property, such property shall, pending the 
determination of the question whether it is evacuee property or 
otherwise, be incapable of being transferred or charged in any way, 
except with the leave of the Custodian, and no person shall be capable 
of taking any benefit from such transfer or charge except with such 
leave.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>14</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 91 of <year>1956</year>, s. 2, for" State Government" (w. e. f. 22-  
  10- <year>1956</year>). 
2. Ins. by s. 2, ibid., (w. e. f. 22- 10- <year>1956</year>). 
3. Ins. by Act 42 of <year>1954</year>, s. 3 (with restrospective effect).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>963858</tid>
<number>3</number>The Custodian shall, from time to time, notify, either by 
publication in the Official Gazette or in such other manner as may be 
prescribed, all properties declared by him to be evacuee properties 
under sub- section (1).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1010812</tid>
<number> 7A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Property not be declared evacuee property on or after 7th 
May, <year>1954</year>. Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, no property 
shall be declared to be evacuee property on or after the 7th day of 
May, <year>1954</year>:
Provided that nothing contained in this section shall apply to--

<section><tid>910836</tid>
<number>a</number>any property in respect of which proceedings are 
pending on the 7th day of May, <year>1954</year> for declaring such 
property to be evacuee property; and

</section>

<section><tid>114345</tid>
<number>b</number>the property of any person who, on account of the 
setting up of the Dominions of India and Pakistan or on 
account of civil disturbances or the fear of such 
disturbances had left on or after the 1st day of March, 
<year>1947</year>, any place now forming part of India, and who on 
the 7th day of May, <year>1954</year>, was resident in Pakistan:
Provided further that no notice under section 7 for declaring any 
property to be evacuee property with reference to clause (b) of the 
preceding proviso shall be issued after the expiry of six months from 
the commencement of the Administration of Evacuee Property (Amendment) 
Act, <year>1954</year> (42 of <year>1954</year>).

Explanation I.-- A person shall be deemed to have been resident in 
Pakistan on the 7th day of May, <year>1954</year>, within the meaning of clause (b) 
of the first proviso, if he was ordinarily residing in Pakistan before 
that date, notwithstanding that he was temporarily absent from 
Pakistan on that date.

Explanation II.-- A person who had left India for Pakistan before 
the 7th day of May, <year>1954</year>, on the authority of a passport or any other 
valid travel document issued by any competent authority in India, and 
who was temporarily residing in Pakistan on that date, shall not be 
deemed to have been resident in Pakistan on that date within the 
meaning of clause (b) of the first proviso.

Explanation III.-- A person who had left Pakistan for India on or 
after the 18th day of July, <year>1948</year>, and who was in India on the 7th day 
of May, <year>1954</year>, shall, unless he came to India under a valid permit for 
permanent return or for permanent resettlement, issued under

<pagefootnote><pagenum>15</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 42 of <year>1954</year>, s. 4. (w. e. f. 7th May, <year>1954</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


the Influx from Pakistan (Control) Act, <year>1949</year> (23 of <year>1949</year>), be deemed 
to have been resident in Pakistan on the 7th day of May, <year>1954</year>, within 
the meaning of clause (b) of the first proviso.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>115347</tid>
<number> 8</number> Vesting of evacuee property in the Custodian.
<section><tid>622142</tid>
<number>1</number>Any property  
declared to be evacuee property under section 7 shall be deemed to 
have vested in the Custodian for the State,--

<subsection><tid>1026445</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of the property of an evacuee as defined in 
sub- clause (i) of clause (d) of section 2, from the 
date on which he leaves or left any place in a State 
for any place outside the territories now forming part 
of India;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1416065</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of the property of an evacuee as defined in 
sub- clause (ii) of clause (d) of section 2, from the 
 15th day of August, <year>1947</year>; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>32854</tid>
<number>c</number>in the case of any other property, from the date of the 
notice given under sub- section (1) of section 7 in 
respect thereof.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1220978</tid>
<number>2</number>Where immediately before the commencement of this Act, any 
property in a State had vested as evacuee property in any person 
exercising the powers of Custodian under any law repealed hereby, the 
property shall, on the commencement of this Act, be deemed to be 
evacuee property declared as such within the meaning of this Act and 
shall be deemed to have vested in the Custodian appointed or deemed to 
have been appointed for the State under this Act, and shall continue 
to so vest:
Provided that where at the commencement of this Act there is 
pending before the High Court, the Custodian or any other authority 
for or in any State any proceeding under section 8 or section 30 of 
the Administration of Evacuee Property Ordinance, <year>1949</year> (12 of <year>1949</year>), 
or under any other corresponding law repealed by the Administration of 
Evacuee Property Ordinance, <year>1949</year> (27 of <year>1949</year>), then notwithstanding 
anything contained in this Act or in any other law for the time being 
in force, such proceeding shall be disposed of as if the definitions 
of' evacuee property' and' evacuee' contained in section 2 of this Act 
had become applicable thereto.


</section>

<section><tid>708836</tid>
<number>2A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Without prejudice to the generality of the provisions 
contained in sub- section (2), all property which under any law 
repealed hereby purports to have vested as evacuee property in any 
person exercising the powers of Custodian in any State shall,
<pagefootnote><pagenum>16</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 1 of <year>1960</year>, s. 2 (with retrospective effect).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


notwithstanding any defect in, or the invalidity of, such law or any 
judgment, decree or order of any court, be deemed for all purposes to 
have validly vested in that person, as if the provisions of such law 
had been enacted by Parliament and such property shall, on the 
commencement of this Act, be deemed to have been evacuee property 
declared as such within the meaning of this Act and accordingly, any 
order made or other action taken by the Custodian or any other 
authority in relation to such property shall be deemed to have been 
validly and lawfully made or taken.]


</section>

<section><tid>1106399</tid>
<number>3</number>Where any property in a State belonging to a joint stock 
company had vested in any person exercising the powers of a Custodian 
under any law previously in force, then nothing contained in clause 
 (f) of section 2 shall affect the operation of sub- section (2), but 
the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Central Government] may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, direct that the Custodian shall be divested of any such 
property in such manner and after such period as may be specified in 
the notification.

</section>

<section><tid>1922098</tid>
<number>4</number>Where after any evacuee property has vested in the Custodian 
any person is in possession thereof, he shall be deemed to be holding 
on behalf of the Custodian and shall on demand surrender possession of 
it to the Custodian or to any other person duly authorised by him in 
this behalf.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1694085</tid>
<number>9</number>Power of Custodian to take possession of evacuee property 
vested in him. If any person in possession of any evacuee property 
refuses or fails on demand to surrender possession thereof to the 
Custodian or to any person duly authorized by him in this behalf, the 
Custodian may use or cause to be used such force as may be necessary 
for taking possession of such property and may, for this purpose, 
after giving reasonable warning and facility to any woman not 
appearing in public to withdraw, remove or break open any lock, bolt 
or any door or do any other act necessary for the said purpose.


</article>



<article><tid>1741346</tid>
<number> 10</number> Powers and duties of the Custodian generally.
<section><tid>602357</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to  
the provisions of any rules that may be made in this behalf, the 
Custodian may take such measures as he considers necessary or 
expedient for the purposes of securing, administering, preserving and 
managing any evacuee property and generally for the purpose of 
enabling him satisfactorily to discharge any of the duties imposed on 
him by or under this Act and may, for any such purpose
<pagefootnote><pagenum>17</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 91 of <year>1956</year>, s. 3, for" State Government" (w. e. f. 22-  
  10- <year>1956</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


as aforesaid, do all acts and incur all expenses necessary or 
incidental thereto.


</section>

<section><tid>1738536</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the provisions 
contained in sub- section (1), the Custodian may, for any of the 
purposes aforesaid,--

<subsection><tid>1772201</tid>
<number>a</number>carry on the business of the evacuee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1512980</tid>
<number>b</number>appoint a manager for the property of the evacuee or 
for carrying on any business or undertaking of the 
evacuee and authorize the manager to exercise any of 
the powers of the Custodian under this section;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>859977</tid>
<number>c</number>enter, or authorize any other person to enter, any land 
or premises to inspect any evacuee property;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>320183</tid>
<number>d</number>take all such measures as may be necessary to keep any 
evacuee property in good repair;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1061755</tid>
<number>e</number>complete any building which has vested in him and which 
requires to be completed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1667258</tid>
<number>h</number>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>534437</tid>
<number>i</number>take such action as may be necessary for the recovery 
of any debt due to the evacuee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>941575</tid>
<number>j</number>institute, defend or continue any legal proceeding in 
any Civil or Revenue Court on behalf of the evacuee or 
refer any dispute between the evacuee and any other 
person to arbitration or compromise any claims, debts 
or liabilities on behalf of the evacuee;
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1725197</tid>
<number>l</number>in any case where the evacuee property which has vested 
in the Custodian consists of a share or shares in a 
company, exercise, notwithstanding anything to the 
contrary contained in the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Indian Companies Act, <year>1913</year> 
 (7 of <year>1913</year>), or in the articles of association of the 
company, the same rights in the matter of making a 
requisition for the convening of a meeting or of 
presenting a petition to the Court under the provisions 
of the Indian Companies Act, <year>1913</year>, or the articles of 
association of the company or in any other matter as 
the evacuee shareholder himself
<pagefootnote><pagenum>18</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Cls. (f), (g) and (h) omitted by Act 91 of <year>1956</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 22-  
  10- <year>1956</year>). 
2. Cl. (k) omitted by s. 4, ibid. (w. e. f. 22- 10- <year>1956</year>). 
3. See now the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


could have done had he been present, although the name 
of the Custodian does not appear in the register of 
members of the company;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>464288</tid>
<number>ll</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in any case where the evacuee property which has 
vested in the Custodian consists of fifty- one per cent. 
or more of the shares in a company, the Custodian may 
take charge of the management of the whole affairs of 
the company and exercise, in addition to any of the 
powers vested in him under this Act, all or any of the 
powers of the directors of the company, notwithstanding 
that the registered office of such company is situate 
in any part of the territories to which this Act 
extends, and notwithstanding anything to the contrary 
contained in this Act or the Indian Companies Act, <year>1913</year> 
 (7 of <year>1913</year>), or in the articles of association of the 
company:
Provided that the Custodian shall not take charge 
of such management of the company except with the 
previous approval of the Central Government;]


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1000145</tid>
<number>m</number>incur any expenditure, including the payment of taxes, 
duties, cesses and rates to Government or to any local 
authority <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1036526</tid>
<number>n</number>pay to the evacuee, or to any member of his family or 
to any other person as in the opinion of the Custodian 
is entitled thereto, any sums of money out of the funds 
in his possession;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1277603</tid>
<number>o</number>transfer in any manner whatsoever any evacuee property, 
notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in 
any law or agreement relating thereto:
Provided that the Custodian shall not sell any 
immovable property or any business or other undertaking 
of the evacuee, except with the previous approval of 
the Custodian- General;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>393042</tid>
<number>p</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> acquire any non- evacuee interest in evacuee property, 
whether by way of purchase or otherwise:
<pagefootnote><pagenum>18A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 11 of <year>1953</year>, s. 4. 
2. Certain words omitted by Act 91 of <year>1956</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 22- 10-  
  <year>1956</year>). 
3. Ins. by Act 1 of <year>1960</year>, s. 3. Original cl. (p) was omitted by Act 
91 of <year>1956</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 22- 10- <year>1956</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Provided that no such acquisition shall be made 
except with the previous approval of the Custodian- 
General;]


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>749326</tid>
<number>q</number>delegate, by general or special order, all or any of 
his functions under this Act to such officers or 
persons as he thinks fit.
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>122470</tid>
<number> 10A</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Power to recover rent or damages in respect of evacuee 
property vested in the Custodian.
<section><tid>1349489</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any person is in arrears  
of rent in respect of any evacuee property vested in the Custodian, 
the Custodian may, by order, require that person to pay the same 
within such time and in such instalments as may be specified in the 
order.

</section>

<section><tid>872180</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any person is deemed to be holding any evacuee property 
on behalf of the Custodian under sub- section (4) of section 8, the 
Custodian may, having regard to such principles of assessment of rent 
as may be prescribed, by order, assess the rent payable in respect of 
such property and that person shall be liable to pay the rent so 
assessed.

</section>

<section><tid>823674</tid>
<number>3</number>Where any person is, or has at any time been, in unauthorised 
possession of any evacuee property vested in the Custodian, the 
Custodian may, having regard to such principles of assessment of 
damages as may be prescribed, assess the damages on account of the use 
and occupation of such property and may, by order, require that person 
to pay the damages within such time and in such instalments as may be 
specified in the order.

</section>

<section><tid>97771</tid>
<number>4</number>Where any person being in possession of any evacuee property 
vested in the Custodian has caused damage to any such property, the 
Custodian may assess the compensation payable on account of the damage 
so caused and may, by order, require that person to pay the 
compensation within such time and in such instalments as may be 
specified in the order.

</section>

<section><tid>1136671</tid>
<number>5</number>No order shall be made under sub- section (2) or sub- section 
 (3) or sub- section (4), until after the issue of a notice in writing 
to the person concerned calling upon him to show cause within such 
time as may be specified in the notice why such order should not be 
made and until his objections, if any, and any evidence he may produce 
in support of the same have been considered by the Custodian.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>18B</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Proviso to cl. (q) omitted by Act 91 of <year>1956</year>. s. 4 (w. e. f. 22- 10-  
  <year>1956</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 1 of <year>1960</year>, s. 4.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1528168</tid>
<number> 11</number> Special provisions with respect to certain trust properties.

<section><tid>1883556</tid>
<number>1</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Where any evacuee property which has vested in the Custodian is  
property in trust for a public purpose of a religious or charitable 
nature, it shall be lawful for the Central Government, notwithstanding 
anything contained in the instrument of trust or any law for the time 
being in force, to appoint, by general or special order, new trustees 
in place of the evacuee trustees and the property shall remain vested 
in the Custodian only until such time as the new trustees are so 
appointed; and pending the appointment of such new trustees the trust 
property and the income thereof shall be applied by the Custodian for 
fulfilling, as far as possible, the purpose of the trust.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>19</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 91 of <year>1956</year>, s. 5, for sub- section (1)  (w. e. f. 22- 10-  
  <year>1956</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1140951</tid>
<number>2</number>In respect of any Wakf- alal- aulad,--

<subsection><tid>1738646</tid>
<number>a</number>where the mutawalli is an evacuee, the property forming 
the subject- matter of the wakf shall vest in the 
Custodian subject to the rights of the beneficiaries 
under the wakf, if any, who are not evacuees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1559526</tid>
<number>b</number>where not all the beneficiaries are evacuees, the 
rights and interests of such of the beneficiaries as 
are evacuees shall alone vest in the Custodian.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1409527</tid>
<number> 12</number> Power to vary or cancel leases or allotments of evacuee 
property.
<section><tid>405885</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for  
the time being in force, the Custodian may cancel any allotment or 
terminate any lease or amend the terms of any lease or agreement under 
which any evacuee property is held or occupied by a person, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> whether 
such allotment, lease or agreement was granted or entered into before 
or after the commencement of this Act]:
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Provided that in the case of any lease granted before the 14th 
day of August, <year>1947</year>, the Custodian shall not exercise any of the 
powers conferred upon him under this sub- section unless he is 
satisfied that the lessee--


<subsection><tid>96238</tid>
<number>a</number>has sublet, assigned or otherwise parted with the 
possession of the whole or any part of the property 
leased to him; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>372688</tid>
<number>b</number>has used or is using such property for a purpose other 
than that for which it was leased to him; <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> or]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>662093</tid>
<number>c</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> has failed to pay rent in accordance with the terms 
of the lease.]]
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Explanation.-- In this sub- section," lease" includes a lease 
granted by the Custodian and" agreement" includes an agreement entered 
into by the Custodian.]


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1248112</tid>
<number>2</number>Where by reason of any action taken under sub- section (1), 
any person has ceased to be entitled to possession of any evacuee 
property, he shall on demand by the Custodian surrender possession of 
such property to the Custodian or to any person duly authorized by him 
in this behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>1562458</tid>
<number>3</number>If any person fails to surrender possession of any property 
on demand under sub- section (2), the Custodian may, notwithstanding
<pagefootnote><pagenum>20</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 11 of <year>1953</year>, s. 5, for certain original words. 
2. Ins. by s. 5, ibid. 
3. Ins. by act 42 of <year>1954</year>, s. 5. 
4. Ins. by s. 5, ibid. (with retrospective effect).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


anything to the contrary contained in any other law for the time being 
in force, eject such person and take possession of such property in 
the manner provided in section 9.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1645656</tid>
<number> 12A</number> 
<section><tid>524499</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in  
this Act or in any other law for the time being in force, where 
tenancy rights have vested in the Custodian as evacuee property and 
the Custodian has granted a lease in respect of such property, the 
Custodian may, in any case where the lessor under whom the property 
was held immediately before it vested in the Custodian is not an 
evacuee, declare, by general or special order, that with effect from 
such date as may be specified in the order he shall stand absolved of 
all responsibilities with respect to the property or the lease granted 
by him.

</section>

<section><tid>1884617</tid>
<number>2</number>On the making of any such declaration as is referred to in 
sub- section (1),--

<subsection><tid>1398795</tid>
<number>a</number>the lease granted by the Custodian shall be deemed to 
have effect as if granted by the lessor under whom the 
property was held immediately before the Custodian 
assumed possession or control thereof and shall 
continue to have such effect until it is determined by 
lapse of time or by operation of law;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>806253</tid>
<number>b</number>all sums realised by the Custodian in respect of the 
said lease before the date of the declaration referred 
to in sub- section (1) shall, subject to the deduction 
of fees, if any, payable to the Custodian, become 
payable to the lessor against whom the lease has now 
effect.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>90362</tid>
<number>3</number>Nothing contained in this section shall--

<subsection><tid>1014599</tid>
<number>a</number>be deemed to empower the Custodian to grant, without 
the consent in writing of the original lessor or his 
successor in interest-

<subsubsection><tid>400251</tid>
<number>i</number>where the original lease is for a 
specified period, any lease for a period extending 
beyond the date on which the original lease would 
have expired; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1626174</tid>
<number>ii</number>Where the original lease is from year to 
year or month to month or on any other similar 
tenure, any lease on a tenure different from that 
of the original lease;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>21</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 11 of <year>1953</year>, s. 6.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>226542</tid>
<number>b</number>render the Custodian liable to any person for any sum 
in excess of the sum payable to the lessor under clause 
 (b) of sub- section (2); or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>764366</tid>
<number>c</number>prejudice any rights of the lessor or the lessee, to 
which he may be entitled under any other law for the 
time being in force, consistently with the terms and 
conditions if any, of the lease granted by the 
Custodian.]



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>533641</tid>
<number> 13</number> Payments to Custodian to be valid discharge.
<section><tid>674475</tid>
<number>1</number>Any amount  
due to any evacuee in respect of any property which has vested in the 
Custodian or in respect of any transaction entered into by the 
evacuee, shall be paid to the Custodian by the person liable to pay 
the same.

</section>

<section><tid>414691</tid>
<number>2</number>Any payment made otherwise than in accordance with sub- 
section (1) shall not discharge the person paying it from his 
obligation to pay the amount due, and shall not affect the right of 
the Custodian to enforce such obligation against any such person.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>256846</tid>
<number>14</number>Recouping of expenditure by Custodian. Any expenditure 
incurred by the Custodian in the exercise of any power conferred by or 
under this Act shall, in relation to any evacuee property in respect 
of which it has been incurred, be a charge on such property and shall, 
subject to the provisions of section 51, have priority over all other 
charges on the property, and such expenditure may be met or recouped 
by the Custodian out of the income accruing from such property or the 
sale proceeds thereof.


</article>



<article><tid>876178</tid>
<number> 15</number> Maintenance of accounts by Custodian.
<section><tid>1639547</tid>
<number>1</number>The Custodian shall  
maintain a separate account of the property of each evacuee possession 
whereof has been taken by him, and shall cause to be made therein 
entries of all receipts and expenditure in respect thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>1589678</tid>
<number>2</number>The accounts shall be maintained in such form and in such 
manner as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1208983</tid>
<number>3</number>The <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Central Government] shall cause the accounts 
maintained under this section to be inspected and audited at such 
intervals and by such persons as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>322080</tid>
<number> 16</number> Restoration of evacuee property.
<section><tid>685061</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to such rulesas may be made in this behalf, any evacuee or any 
person claiming tobe an heir of an evacuee may
CHAP

CERTAIN CONSEQUENCES OF PROPERTY VESTING IN CUSTODIAN

CHAPTER III

CERTAIN CONSEQUENCES OF PROPERTY VESTING IN CUSTODIAN




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1530326</tid>
<number> 17</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Exemption of evacuee property from processes of Court, 
etc.
<section><tid>590148</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as otherwise expressly provided in this Act, no evacuee  
property which has vested or is deemed to have vested in the Custodian 
under the provisions of this Act shall, so long as it remains so 
vested, be liable to be proceeded against in any manner whatsoever in 
execution of any decree or order of any Court or other authority, and 
any attachment or injunction or order for the appointment of a 
receiver in respect of any such property subsisting on the 
commencement of the Administration of Evacuee Property (Amendment) 
Act, <year>1951</year> (22 of <year>1951</year>). shall cease to have effect on such 
commencement and shall be deemed to be void.

</section>

<section><tid>1288750</tid>
<number>2</number>Where, after the 1st day of March, <year>1947</year>, any evacuee property 
which has vested in the Custodian or is deemed to have vested in the 
Custodian under the provisions of this Act has been sold in execution 
of any decree or order of any court or other authority, the sale shall 
be set aside if an application in that behalf has been made by the 
Custodian to such Court or authority on or before the 17th day of 
October, <year>1950</year>.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1940625</tid>
<number> 18</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Occupancy or tenancy rights not to be extinguished.
<section><tid>949126</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Where the rights of an evacuee in any land or in any house or other 
building consist or consisted of occupancy or tenancy rights, nothing 
contained in any law for the time being in force or in any contract or 
in any instrument having the force of law or in any decree or order of 
any Court, shall extinguish or be deemed to have extinguished any such 
rights either on the tenant becoming an evacuee within the meaning of 
this Act or at any time thereafter so as to prevent such rights from 
vesting in the Custodian under the provisions of this Act or to 
prevent the Custodian from exercising all or any of the powers 
conferred on him by this Act in respect of any such rights, and, 
notwithstanding anything contained in any such law, contract, 
instrument, decree or order, neither the evacuee nor the Custodian, 
whether as an occupancy tenant or as a tenant for a certain time, 
monthly or otherwise, of any land, or house or other building shall be 
liable to be ejected or be deemed to have become so liable on any 
ground whatsoever for any default of--

<subsection><tid>535591</tid>
<number>a</number>the evacuee committed after he became an evacuee or 
within a period of one year immediately preceding the 
date of his becoming an evacuee; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>27502</tid>
<number>b</number>the Custodian.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>25</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 22 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 (with retrospective effect). 
2. Subs. by Act 11 of <year>1953</year>, s. 8 (with retrospective effect).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>99940</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any person acquires or has acquired any rights under a 
Provincial Act or a State Act in respect of any property by reason of 
being in possession of that property, whether in pursuance of a grant, 
lease, or allotment made by the Custodian or otherwise, the 
acquisition of such rights shall not in any way affect or be deemed to 
have affected the rights and powers conferred on the Custodian under 
this Act in respect of that property.]
CHAP

Property of intending evacuees.

CHAPTER IV.--[ Property of intending evacuees.] <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Rep. by the 
Administration of Evacuee Property (Amendment) Act, <year>1953</year> (11 of <year>1953</year>), 
s. 9.

CHAP

APPEALS, REVIEW AND REVISION

CHAPTER V

APPEALS, REVIEW AND REVISION




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>549284</tid>
<number> 24</number> 
<section><tid>1538421</tid>
<number>1</number>Appeals from orders under sections 7, 16 and 40. Any  
person aggrieved by an order made under section 7, section 40 or 
section 48 may prefer an appeal--

<subsection><tid>952816</tid>
<number>a</number>to the Custodian, where the original order has been 
passed by a Deputy or Assistant Custodian and the 
amount or the value of the property which is the 
subject- matter of the order does not exceed two 
thousand rupees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>472582</tid>
<number>b</number>to the Custodian- General, in any other case.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>446950</tid>
<number>1A</number>An appeal shall lie to the Custodian- General from any order 
made on appeal by the Custodian under clause (a) of sub- section (1) on 
the ground that the order is contrary to law.

</section>

<section><tid>173091</tid>
<number>1B</number>An appeal under this section shall be made in such manner 
and within such time as may be prescribed.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>26</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Effect of repeal of Chapter IV.-- (1) The repeal of chapter IV 
shall not affect- 
 (a) any property which has vested in the Custodian under 
section 22 before the commencement of Act 11 of <year>1953</year>,

(b) any proceeding pending under that section on such 
commencement, and any such property shall continue to 
so vest and any such proceeding may be continued as if 
Act 11 of <year>1953</year> had not been passed. 
 (2) Save as aforesaid, on the repeal of Chapter IV every order 
passed under section 19 declaring any person to be intending evacuee 
and every attachment on property effected under that section shall 
cease to have effect and every proceeding pending under that section 
shall abate. 
 (3) Save to the extent to which it is otherwise provided in this 
note, the mention of particular matters in this note shall be without 
prejudice to the general application of section 6 of the General 
Clauses Act, <year>1897</year> (10 of <year>1897</year>), with respect to the effect of repeals 
 (see s. 17 of Act 11 of <year>1953</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 91 of <year>1956</year>, s. 7, for sub- section (1)  (w. e. f. 22- 10-  
  <year>1956</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1194781</tid>
<number>2</number>The Custodian to whom an appeal is preferred under clause (a) 
of sub- section (1) may dispose of it himself or may make it over for 
disposal to an Additional Custodian or to a Deputy Custodian 
authorized by the Custodian in writing in this behalf (in this Chapter  
  referred to as the authorized Deputy Custodian):
Provided that no appeal from an order of a Deputy Custodian shall 
be made over for disposal to the authorized Deputy Custodian.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1675256</tid>
<number>25</number>[ Appeals from other orders.] Rep. by the Administration of 
Evacuee property (Amendment) Act, <year>1956</year> (91 of <year>1956</year>), s. 8.


</article>



<article><tid>899608</tid>
<number>26</number>[ Powers of review or revision of Custodian, etc.] Rep. by s. 
8, ibid.


</article>



<article><tid>1169384</tid>
<number> 27</number> Powers of revision of Custodian- General.
<section><tid>1392575</tid>
<number>1</number>The Custodian-  
General may at any time, either on his own motion or on application 
made to him in this behalf, call for the record of any proceeding in 
which any <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Custodian has passed an order for the purpose of 
satisfying himself as to the legality or propriety of any such order 
and may pass such order in relation thereto as he thinks fit:
Provided that the Custodian- General shall not pass an order under 
this sub- section prejudicial to any person without giving him a 
reasonable opportunity of being heard.

<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>

<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Explanation.-- The power conferred on the Custodian- General 
under this section may be exercised by him in relation to any 
property, notwithstanding that such property has been acquired under 
section 12 of the Displaced Persons (Compensation and Rehabilitation) 
Act, <year>1954</year> (44 of <year>1954</year>).]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1783810</tid>
<number>28</number>Finality of orders under this Chapter. Save as otherwise 
expressly provided in this Chapter, every order made by the Custodian- 
General, <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Custodian, Additional Custodian, authorized Deputy 
Custodian, deputy Custodian or Assistant Custodian shall be final and 
shall not be called in question in any Court by way of appeal or 
revision or in any original suit, application or execution proceeding.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>27</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" District Judge or" omitted by Act 91 of <year>1956</year>, s. 9 
 (w. e. f. 22- 10- <year>1956</year>). 
2. Sub- sections (1A), (2) and (3) omitted by s. 9, ibid. 
3. Ins. by Act 1 of <year>1960</year>, s. 5. 
4. The words" District Judge" omitted by Act 91 of <year>1956</year>, s. 10.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


CHAP

PENALTIES AND PROCEDURE

CHAPTER VI

PENALTIES AND PROCEDURE



</article>



<article><tid>1545730</tid>
<number>29</number>[ Penalty for failure to surrender possession of evacuee 
property.] Rep. by the Administration of Evacuee property (Amendment) 
Act, <year>1956</year> (91 of <year>1956</year>), s. 8.


</article>



<article><tid>359173</tid>
<number>30</number>[ Penalty for wrongfully paying o receiving rents, etc.] Rep. 
by s. 8, ibid.


</article>



<article><tid>763200</tid>
<number>31</number>[ Penalty for concealing evacuee property.] Rep. by s. 8, 
ibid.


</article>



<article><tid>1188015</tid>
<number>32</number>Penalty for causing damage to evacuee property. Any person 
who wilfully destroys or causes damage to any evacuee property or 
unlawfully converts it to his own use shall be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years, or with fine, 
or with both.


</article>



<article><tid>1953503</tid>
<number>33</number>[ Penalty for false declaration in certain cases.] Rep. by the 
Administration of Evacuee Property (Amendment) Act, <year>1956</year> (91 of <year>1956</year>), 
s. 8.


</article>



<article><tid>509518</tid>
<number>34</number>Penalty for offences not expressly provided for. Any person 
who contravenes any provision of this Act or of any rule or order made 
thereunder, or obstructs the lawful exercise of any power conferred by 
or under this Act, or makes default in complying with any requirement 
of this Act or of any rule or order made thereunder, shall, if no 
express provision is made by this Act for punishment of such 
contravention, obstruction or default, be punishable with imprisonment 
for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine, or with both.


</article>



<article><tid>136739</tid>
<number>35</number>[ Penalty for offences committed by companies.] Rep. by the 
Administration of Evacuee Property (Amendment) Act, <year>1956</year> (91 of <year>1956</year>), 
s. 8.


</article>



<article><tid>1527452</tid>
<number>36</number>Penalty for abetment. Any person who abets any of the 
offences punishable under this Act shall be punishable with the 
punishment provided for the offence.


</article>



<article><tid>10046</tid>
<number>37</number>Offences to be cognizable. Notwithstanding anything contained 
in the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1898</year> (5 of <year>1898</year>), all offences 
under this Act shall be cognizable.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>28</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1236253</tid>
<number>38</number>Procedure for prosecution. No prosecution for any offence 
punishable under this Act shall be instituted except with the previous 
sanction of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Central Government] or of any officer authorized in 
this behalf, by general or special order, by the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Central 
Government].


</article>



<article><tid>1885885</tid>
<number> 39</number> Offences may be tried summarily. Any magistrate empowered to 
try in a summary way the offences specified in sub- section
<section><tid>1526022</tid>
<number>1</number>of  
section 260 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1898</year> (5 of <year>1898</year>), may, 
if an application is made in this behalf by the complainant and the 
Magistrate thinks fit, try any offence under this Act in accordance 
with the provisions contained in sections 262 to 265 of that Code, but 
nothing contained in sub- section (2) of section 262 of that Code shall 
apply to any such trial.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER VII

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>388629</tid>
<number> 40</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Validity of transfers respecting property subsequently 
declared to be evacuee property.
<section><tid>291182</tid>
<number>1</number>No transfer made after the 14th  
day of August, <year>1947</year> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> but before the 7th day of May, <year>1954</year>], by or on 
behalf of any person in any manner whatsoever of any property 
belonging to him shall be effective so as to confer any rights or 
remedies in respect of the transfer on the parties thereto or any 
person claiming under them or either of them, if, at any time after 
the transfer, the transferor becomes an evacuee within the meaning of 
section 2 or the property of the transferor is declared or notified to 
be evacuee property within the meaning of this Act, unless the 
transfer is confirmed by the Custodian in accordance with the 
provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>512185</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing contained in sub- section (1) shall apply to the 
transfer for valuable consideration of any such property as is 
referred to therein in any of the following cases, namely:-

<subsection><tid>462470</tid>
<number>a</number>where the transfer has been made with the previous 
approval of the Custodian before the commencement of 
the Administration of Evacuee Property (Amendment) Act, 
 <year>1953</year> (11 of <year>1953</year>);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>5006</tid>
<number>b</number>where the transferor has not left <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> India for Pakistan 
within a period of two years from the date of the 
transfer:
<pagefootnote><pagenum>29</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 91 of <year>1956</year>, s. 3, for" State Government" (w. e. f. 22-  
  10- <year>1956</year>). 
2. Subs. by Act 11 of <year>1953</year>, s. 13. 
3. Ins. by Act 42 of <year>1954</year>, s. 8 (w. e. f. 7- 5- <year>1954</year>). 
4. The words" or does not leave" omitted by Act 91 of <year>1956</year>, s. 11 
  w. e. f. 22- 10- <year>1956</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Provided that in the case of a transfer made 
before the commencement of the Administration of 
Evacuee Property (Amendment) Act, <year>1953</year> (11 of  
  <year>1953</year>), the transferor had not left India for 
Pakistan before such commencement, notwithstanding 
that a period of two years had already elapsed 
before such commencement;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1430439</tid>
<number>c</number>where the transfer is made after the commencement of 
the Administration of Evacuee Property (Amendment) Act, 
 <year>1953</year> (11 of <year>1953</year>). and--

<subsubsection><tid>1809699</tid>
<number>i</number>the value of the property or properties 
transferred in any one year is less than five 
thousand rupees, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1584415</tid>
<number>ii</number>the transfer is made with the previous 
approval of the Custodian or in the prescribed 
cases with the previous approval of the Custodian- 
General.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1734092</tid>
<number>3</number>An application under sub- section (1) for the confirmation of 
any transfer may be made by the transferor or the transferor or any 
person claiming under, or lawfully authorized by, either of them to 
the Custodian within two months from the date of the transfer or 
within two months from the date of the declaration or notification 
referred to in sub- section (1) whichever is later, and the provisions 
of section 5 of the Indian Limitation Act, <year>1908</year> (9 of <year>1908</year>). shall 
apply to any such application.

</section>

<section><tid>1112801</tid>
<number>4</number>Where an application under sub- section (1) has been made to 
the Custodian for confirmation, he shall hold an inquiry in respect 
thereof in the prescribed manner and may reject the application if he 
is of opinion that--

<subsection><tid>1275104</tid>
<number>a</number>the transaction has not been entered into in good faith 
or for valuable consideration; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>198916</tid>
<number>b</number>the transaction is prohibited under any law for the 
time being in force; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1921555</tid>
<number>c</number>the transaction ought not to be confirmed for any other 
reason.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1331526</tid>
<number>5</number>Where, in respect of any transfer made before the 
commencement of the Administration of Evacuee Property (Amendment) 
Act, <year>1953</year> (11 of <year>1953</year>). any application for confirmation thereof has 
been rejected solely on the ground--

<subsection><tid>1713595</tid>
<number>a</number>that although the transaction was entered into in good 
faith, the consideration paid was not adequate, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>404238</tid>
<number>b</number>that the application was barred by limitation,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>30</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

then, notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any law or 
contract or decree or order of a Civil Court or other authority, but 
subject to any rules that may be made by the Central Government in 
this behalf, the Custodian may and shall, where the application for 
confirmation was rejected by the Custodian- General, if the Custodian- 
General so directs, exercise any of the following powers in respect of 
the transfer, namely:--


<subsubsection><tid>1783242</tid>
<number>i</number>confirm the transfer if the consideration paid for the 
transfer is adequate;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1866658</tid>
<number>ii</number>confirm the transfer, if the transferee agrees to pay 
to the Custodian the difference in value between the 
value of the property as assessed by the Custodian and 
the amount actually paid by the transferee to the 
transferor;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1468985</tid>
<number>iii</number>if the transferee agrees, take possession of such part 
of the property as, after dividing it by metes and 
bounds, is equivalent in value to the difference 
between the value of the property as assessed by the 
Custodian and the amount actually paid by the 
transferee to the transferor;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>125962</tid>
<number>iv</number>if the transferee agrees, take possession of the entire 
property by paying off to the transferee the amount 
which the Custodian finds as having been actually paid 
by the transferee to the transferor as consideration 
for the transfer; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>190749</tid>
<number>v</number>if the transferee does not agree to any of the courses 
referred to in clauses (ii) to (iv) inclusive, auction 
the property and if the sale proceeds exceed the amount 
actually paid by the transferee, pay to the transferee 
the amount paid by him and take over the balance and if 
the sale proceeds are equivalent to, or fall short of, 
the amount actually paid by the transferee, pay the 
entire sale proceeds to the transferee:
Provided that where any application for 
confirmation of a transfer is rejected on the 
ground specified in clause (b) of this rejected on 
the ground specified in clause (b) of this sub- 
section the powers conferred on the Custodian by 
this section shall not be exercised unless the 
Custodian finds that the transaction has been 
entered into in good faith.


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>714731</tid>
<number>6</number>If the application is not rejected under sub- section (4), the 
Custodian may confirm the transfer either unconditionally or on such 
terms and conditions as he may think fit to impose.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>31</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1463519</tid>
<number>7</number>The Custodian may, in respect of any application for 
confirmation of transfer pending before him on the commencement of the 
Administration of Evacuee Property (Amendment) Act, <year>1953</year> (11 of  
  <year>1953</year>). which is liable to be rejected on either of the grounds 
specified in clauses (a) and (b) of sub- section (5), exercise any of 
the powers conferred on him under that sub- section.
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1018055</tid>
<number>41</number>Transactions relating to evacuee property void in certain 
circumstances. Subject to the other provisions contained in this Act, 
every transaction entered into by any person in respect of property 
declared or deemed to be declared to be evacuee property within the 
meaning of this Act, shall be void unless entered into by or with the 
previous approval of the Custodian.]


</article>



<article><tid>1910213</tid>
<number>42</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Power to call for information. The Custodian may, for the 
purpose of securing, administering, preserving and managing nay 
evacuee property and generally for the purpose of enabling him 
satisfactorily to discharge any of the duties imposed on him by or 
under this Act, require any person to submit to him such accounts, 
books or other documents or to furnish to him such information 
relating to any evacuee property as he may reasonably think 
necessary.]


</article>



<article><tid>1130528</tid>
<number>43</number>Vesting of property in Custodian not affected by death of 
evacuee, etc. Where in pursuance of the provisions of this Act any 
property has vested in the Custodian, neither the death of the evacuee 
at any time thereafter nor the fact that the evacuee who had a right 
or interest in that property had ceased to be an evacuee at any 
material time shall affect the vesting or render invalid anything done 
in consequence thereof.


</article>



<article><tid>124767</tid>
<number>44</number>Certain officers to be public servants. The Custodian- 
General, the Custodian and every other person duly appointed to 
discharge any duties imposed on them by this Act or the rules or 
orders made thereunder shall be deemed to be public servants within 
the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>763282</tid>
<number> 45</number> Powers of the Custodian while holding inquiry. For the 
purposes of holding any inquiry under this Act, custodian shall have 
the same powers as are vested in a Civil Court under the Code of Civil 
Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>). when trying a suit, in respect of the 
following matters, namely:-
<section><tid>722892</tid>
<number>a</number>enforcing the attendance of any person and examining 
him on oath;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>32</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Sub- section (8) omitted by Act 91 of <year>1956</year>, s. 11 (w. e. f. 22- 10-  
  <year>1956</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 1 of <year>1960</year>, s. 6. Original s. 42 was rep. by Act 91 of 
<year>1956</year>, s. 8.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>429317</tid>
<number>b</number>compelling the discovery and production of documents;

</section>

<section><tid>453259</tid>
<number>c</number>any prescribed matter;
and the inquiry by the Custodian shall be deemed to be a judicial 
proceeding within the meaning of sections 193 and 228 of the Indian 
Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>), and the Custodian shall be deemed to be a 
Court within (45 of <year>1860</year>) the meaning of sections 480 and 482 of the 
Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1898</year> (5 of <year>1898</year>).




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>375519</tid>
<number> 46</number> Jurisdiction of Civil Courts barred in certain matters. Save 
as otherwise expressly provided in this Act, no Civil or Revenue Court 
shall have jurisdiction--
<section><tid>1615285</tid>
<number>a</number>to entertain or adjudicate upon any question whether 
any property or any right to or interest in any 
property is or is not evacuee property; or
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>


</section>

<section><tid>226854</tid>
<number>c</number>to question the legality of any action taken by the 
Custodian- General or the Custodian under this Act; or

</section>

<section><tid>1315288</tid>
<number>d</number>in respect of any matter which the Custodian- General or 
the Custodian is empowered by or under this Act to 
determine.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1868316</tid>
<number> 47</number> Protection of action taken in good faith.
<section><tid>424150</tid>
<number>1</number>No suit,  
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Custodian- 
General or the Custodian or any person acting under the direction of 
the Custodian in respect of anything which is in good faith done or 
intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or of any rules or orders 
made thereunder.

</section>

<section><tid>1627031</tid>
<number>2</number>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the 
Central Government, the State Government, the Custodian- General or the 
Custodian or any other person in respect of any damage caused or 
likely to be caused by anything in good faith done or intended to be 
done in pursuance of this Act or of any rules or orders made 
thereunder.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>969039</tid>
<number> 48</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Recovery of certain sums as arrears of land revenue.
<section><tid>1408655</tid>
<number>1</number> 
any sum payable to the Government or to the Custodian in respect of 
any evacuee property, under any agreement, express or implied, lease 
or other document or otherwise howsoever, may be recovered in the same 
manner as an arrear of land revenue.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>33</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Cl. (b) omitted by Act 11 of <year>1953</year>, s. 14. 
2. Subs. by Act 91 of <year>1956</year>, s. 12, for the original section (w. e. f.  
  22- 10- <year>1956</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>671824</tid>
<number>2</number>If any question arises whether a sum is payable to the 
Government or to the Custodian within the meaning of sub- section (1), 
the Custodian shall, after making such inquiry as he may deem fit, and 
giving to the person by whom the sum is alleged to be payable an 
opportunity of being heard, decide the question; and the decision of 
the Custodian shall, subject to any appeal or revision under this Act, 
be final and shall not be called in question by any Court or other 
authority.

</section>

<section><tid>178555</tid>
<number>3</number>For the purposes of this section, a sum shall be deemed to be 
payable to the Custodian, notwithstanding that its recovery is barred 
by the Indian Limitation Act, <year>1908</year> (9 of <year>1908</year>), or any other law for 
the time being in force relating to limitation of actions.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>117236</tid>
<number>49</number>Record to be public documents. All records prepared or 
registers maintained under this Act shall be deemed to be public 
documents within the meaning of the Indian Evidence Act, <year>1872</year> (1 of  
  <year>1872</year>), and shall be presumed to be genuine until the contrary is 
proved.


</article>



<article><tid>557883</tid>
<number> 50</number> Notice of suits to the Custodian.
<section><tid>530665</tid>
<number>1</number>If in any suit it  
appears to the Civil or Revenue Court that a question relating to the 
property of an evacuee or an intending evacuee is involved, the Court 
shall not proceed to determine that question until after notice has 
been given to the Custodian.

</section>

<section><tid>864617</tid>
<number>2</number>A Court may, at any state of a suit or proceeding, either on 
its own motion or on application made in this behalf by the Custodian, 
make an order that the Custodian shall be added as a party to the suit 
or proceeding, if the Court is satisfied that such addition is 
necessary or proper for the satisfactory determination of the suit or 
proceeding.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1530671</tid>
<number> 51</number> Fees payable to the Custodian.
<section><tid>1513384</tid>
<number>1</number>The <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Central Government]  
may fix the fees payable to the Custodian for the management or 
disposal of any property vested in him.

</section>

<section><tid>865822</tid>
<number>2</number>Such fees shall be payable out of the income or sale proceeds 
of such property and shall be a first charge on the property.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>608903</tid>
<number>52</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Power to exempt. The Central Government may, by 
notification in the Officer Gazette, declare that all or any of the 
provisions of this Act or of the rules made thereunder shall not 
apply, or shall be deemed never to have applied, or shall cease to 
apply, or shall apply only with such
<pagefootnote><pagenum>34</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 91 of <year>1956</year>, s. 3, for" State Government" (w. e. f. 22-  
  10- <year>1956</year>). 
2. Subs. by act 11 of <year>1953</year>, s. 15, for the original section.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


modifications or subject to such conditions, restrictions or 
limitations as may be specified in the notification, to or in relation 
to any class of persons or class of property.]



</article>



<article><tid>518052</tid>
<number>53</number>Power to give directions. The Central Government may give 
directions to any State Government as to the carrying into execution 
in the State of any of the provisions contained in this Act or of any 
rules or orders made thereunder.


</article>



<article><tid>767116</tid>
<number>54</number>Power of Central Government to take action with regard to 
evacuee property. The central Government may, for the purpose of 
regulating the administration of any property which has vested in the 
Custodian under the provisions of this Act, pass such order or direct 
such action to be taken in relation thereto as, in its opinion, the 
circumstances of the case require and as is not inconsistent with any 
of the provisions contained in this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>42620</tid>
<number> 55</number> Delegation of powers.
<section><tid>625124</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may direct  
that any power exercisable by it under this Act shall be exercisable 
also by such officer or authority subordinate to the Central 
Government or by the State Government or by such officer or authority 
subordinate to the State Government as may be specified in the 
direction.

</section>

<section><tid>290325</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Any power exercisable by a State Government by virtue of a 
direction under sub- section (1) may, unless otherwise provided in such 
direction, be exercised also by such officer or authority as the State 
Government may specify in this behalf.]

</section>

<section><tid>253008</tid>
<number>3</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act and of the rules and 
orders made thereunder, the Custodian- General may delegate all or any 
of his powers under this Act to any Deputy or Assistant Custodian- 
General.

</section>

<section><tid>1667012</tid>
<number>4</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act and of the rules and 
orders made thereunder, the Custodian may delegate all or any of his 
powers under this Act to any Additional, Deputy or Assistant 
Custodian, subject to such conditions, if any, as may be specified by 
the Custodian.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1414807</tid>
<number> 56</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>77471</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> to carry out the 
purposes of this Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>35</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 1 of <year>1960</year>, s. 7. Original sub- section (2) was omitted 
by Act 91 of <year>1956</year>, s. 8 (w. e. f. 22- 10- <year>1956</year>). 
2. For the Administration of Evacuee Property (Central) Rules, 
<year>1950</year>, see Gazette of India, Pt. II, Sec. 3, p. 832.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1811365</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>851911</tid>
<number>a</number>the terms and conditions of service of the Custodian- 
General;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1971909</tid>
<number>b</number>The manner in which inquiries under this Act may be 
held;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1321507</tid>
<number>bb</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the transfer by the Custodian of any case pending 
before any officer subordinate to him or the withdrawal 
to himself for disposal of any case so pending or the 
exercise of any similar powers by the Custodian- General 
in respect of cases pending before any officer 
subordinate to him;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>793140</tid>
<number>c</number>the manner in which evacuee properties which have 
vested in the Custodian may be notified;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1390369</tid>
<number>d</number>the manner in which possession of any evacuee property 
may be taken by the Custodian;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1549639</tid>
<number>e</number>the manner in which any person claiming any right to, 
or interest in, any property which has been notified as 
evacuee property may have his claim registered and 
disposed of;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1227476</tid>
<number>f</number>the manner in which any attachment may be made by the 
Custodian;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>628143</tid>
<number>g</number>the manner in which trust properties which have vested 
in the Custodian may be administered or otherwise dealt 
with;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>709519</tid>
<number>h</number>the circumstances in which, and the conditions subject 
to which, the Custodian may sell any immovable property 
vested in him, and the procedure governing the grant of 
leases and the period for which leases may be granted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>100754</tid>
<number>i</number>the circumstances in which leases and allotments may be 
cancelled or terminated or the terms of any lease or 
agreement varied;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>720580</tid>
<number>j</number>the securities in which the Custodian may invest any 
moneys held by him;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>21816</tid>
<number>jj</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the manner in which rent of any property or damage 
for unauthorised possession of any property may be
<pagefootnote><pagenum>39</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 11 of <year>1953</year>, s. 16. 
2. Ins. by Act 1 of <year>1960</year>, s. 8.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>36</number>- 38

assessed, and the principles which may be taken into 
account in assessing such rent or damages;]

(k) the manner in which any moneys due to the Custodian may 
be recovered;

(l) the form and manner in which books of accounts and 
other records shall be maintained by the Custodian;

(m) the form in which any notice under this Act may be 
issued, the manner of its service and publication and 
the form in which any demand may be made by the 
Custodian;

(n) the nature of cases and the circumstances in which and 
the conditions subject to which certificated for 
restoration of property under section 16 may be issued;

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>

(p) the powers vested in a Civil Court which may be 
exercised by the Custodian while holding any inquiry 
under this Act;

(q) <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the manner in which applications for the previous 
approval of the Custodian may be made under section 40 
and the matters which he shall take into account in 
granting such approval, and the nature of cases and the 
circumstances in which the Custodian may confirm or 
refuse to confirm a transfer under that section;]

(r) the form and manner in which and the time within which 
appeals and applications for revision may be preferred 
under Chapter V and the fees payable in respect 
thereof;

(s) <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the terms and conditions of service of the Custodian 
and other officers appointed under this Act and for the 
furnishing of security by them;

(t) the work to be performed by the Custodian, and the 
Additional Deputy or Assistant Custodians;

(u) the delegation of powers of the Custodian to the 
Additional, Deputy or assistant Custodians;

(v) the fees payable to the Custodian for the management 
and disposal of any property vested in him and the 
manner in which such fees shall be paid; 
1. Cl. (o) omitted by Act 91 of <year>1956</year>, s. 13 (w. e. f. 22- 10- <year>1956</year>). 
2. Subs. by Act 11 of <year>1953</year>, s. 16. 
3. Subs. by Act 91 of <year>1956</year>, s. 13, for cl. (s)  (w. e. f. 22- 10- <year>1956</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1128292</tid>
<number>w</number>the persons by whom and the time at which books of 
accounts maintained under this Act may be inspected and 
audited;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>957748</tid>
<number>x</number>any other matter which has to be or may be prescribed 
under this Act.] 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>342297</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon 
as may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is 
in session for a period of thirty days which may be comprised in one 
session or in two successive sessions and if, before the expiry of the 
session in which it is so laid or the session immediately following, 
both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule, or both 
Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be, so however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1645770</tid>
<number>57</number>Temporary amendment of section 54 of the Indian Income- tax 
Act, <year>1922</year>. During the continuance of this Act, sub- section (3) of 
section 54 of the Indian Income- tax Act, <year>1922</year> (11 of <year>1922</year>), shall have 
effect as if after clause (o) thereof, the following clause had been 
inserted, namely:--
" (p) of any such particulars to the Custodian of evacuee 
property appointed under the Administration of Evacuee 
property Act, <year>1950</year> (31 of <year>1950</year>), for the purpose of 
enabling him to discharge the duties imposed upon 
him by or under the said Act".



</article>



<article><tid>1289701</tid>
<number> 58</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Repeals and savings.
<section><tid>1057524</tid>
<number>1</number>The Administration of Evacuee  
Property ordinance, <year>1949</year> (27 of <year>1949</year>), Hybd. Reg. 12 of 1359 F and 
the Hyderabad Administration of Evacuee Property Regulation, are 
hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>109041</tid>
<number>2</number>If, immediately before the commencement of this Act, there is 
in force in any State to which this Act extends any law which 
corresponds to this Act and which is not repealed by sub- section (1), 
that corresponding law shall stand repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>324600</tid>
<number>3</number>The repeal by this Act of the Administration of Evacuee 
Property Ordinance, <year>1949</year> (27 of <year>1949</year>), Hybd. Reg. 12 of 1359 F or 
the Hyderabad Administration of evacuee Property Regulation or of any 
corresponding law shall not affect the previous operation of that 
Ordinance, Regulation or corresponding
<pagefootnote><pagenum>39A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Sub- section (3) omitted by Act 91 of <year>1956</year>, s. 13 (w. e. f. 22- 10-  
  <year>1956</year>). 
2. Subs. by Act 1 of <year>1960</year>, s. 8, for sub- section (4) ins. by Act 11 
of <year>1953</year>, s. 16. 
3. Subs. by Act 66 of <year>1950</year>, (with retrospective effect).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


law, and subject thereto, anything done or any action taken in the 
exercise of any power conferred by or under that Ordinance, Regulation 
or corresponding law, shall be deemed to have been done or taken in 
the exercise of the powers conferred by or under this Act as if this 
Act were in force on the day on which such thing was done or action 
was taken.]



</section>

</article>



 </act>