<act><title>


The Company Secretaries Act, 1980</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title, extent 
and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
This Act may be called the Company Secretaries Act, 1980.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends to the 
whole of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall come into 
force on such date1 as 
the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.
 
 


</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions and 
interpretation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  “Associate” 
means an Associate Member of the Institute;
 

    1[(aa)  
“Authority” means the Appellate Authority referred to in section 22A;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>aaa</number>  “Board means 
the Quality Review Board constituted under section 29A;]
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  “Companies 
Act” means the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956);
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  “Company 
Secretary” means a person who is a member of the Institute;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  “Council” 
means the Council of the Institute constituted under section 9;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  “dissolved 
company” means the Institute of Company Secretaries of India registered under 
the Companies Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  “Fellow” 
means a Fellow Member of the Institute;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>g</number>  “Institute” 
means the Institute of Company Secretaries of India constituted under this Act;
 
 

1[(ga)  
“notification” means a notification published in the Official Gazette;]
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>h</number>  “prescribed” 
means prescribed by regulations made under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>i</number>  “President” 
means the President of the Council;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>j</number>  “Register” 
means the Register of members of the Institute maintained under this Act;
 

     1[(ja)  
“specified” means specified by rules made by the Central Government under this 
Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>jb</number>  “Tribunal” 
means a Tribunal established under sub-section (1) of section 10B;]
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>k</number>  
“Vice-President” means the Vice-President of the Council;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>l</number>  “year” means 
the period commencing on the 1st day of April of any year ending on the 31st day 
of March of the succeeding year;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>m</number>  words and 
expressions used herein and not defined but defined in the Companies Act shall 
have the meanings respectively assigned to them in that Act.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Save as otherwise 
provided in this Act, a member of the Institute shall be deemed “to be in 
practice” when, individually, or in partnership with one or more members of the 
Institute in practice or in partnership with members of such other recognised 
professions as may be prescribed, he, in consideration of remuneration received 
or to be received,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  engages 
himself in the practice of the profession of Company Secretaries to, or in 
relation to, any company; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  offers to 
perform or performs services in relation to the promotion, forming, 
incorporation, amalgamation, reconstruction, reorganisation or winding up of 
companies; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  offers to 
perform or performs such services as may be performed by—
 <subsubsection>
             <number>i</number>  an 
authorised representative of a company with respect to filing, registering, 
presenting, attesting or verifying any documents (including forms, applications 
and returns) by or on behalf of the company,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>ii</number>  a share 
transfer agent,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>iii</number>  an 
issue house,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           <number>iv</number>  a share 
and stock broker,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>v</number>  a 
secretarial auditor or consultant,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           <number>vi</number>  an 
adviser to a company on management, including any legal or procedural matter 
falling under the Capital Issues (Control) Act, 1947 (29 of 1947), the 
Industries (Development and Regulation) Act, 1951 (65 of 1951), the Companies 
Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), the Securities Contracts (Regulation) Act, 1956 (42 of 
1956), any of the rules or bye-laws made by a recognised stock exchange, the 
Monopolies and Restrictive Trade Practices Act, 1969 (54 of 1969), the Foreign 
Exchange Regulation Act, 1973 (46 of 1973), or under any other law for the time 
being in force,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           <number>vii</number>  issuing 
certificates on behalf of, or for the purposes of a company; or
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  holds himself 
out to the public as a Company Secretary in practice; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  renders 
professional services or assistance with respect to matters of principle or 
detail relating to the practice of the profession of Company Secretaries; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  renders such 
other services as, in the opinion of the Council, are or may be rendered by a 
Company Secretary in practice,
 
and the words “to be in 
practice”, with their grammatical variations and cognate expressions, shall be 
construed accordingly.
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Incorporation of the 
Institute.—
<section><number>1</number> 
All persons whose names are entered in the Register of the dissolved company 
immediately before the commencement of this Act and all persons who may 
hereafter have their names entered in the Register to be maintained under this 
Act, so long as they continue to have their names borne on the Register to be 
maintained under this Act, are hereby constituted a body corporate by the name 
of the Institute of Company Secretaries of India and all such persons shall be 
known as members of the Institute.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Institute shall 
have perpetual succession and a common seal and shall have power to acquire, 
hold and dispose of property, movable or immovable and shall by its name sue or 
be sued.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Entry of names in 
the Register.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any of the following persons shall be entitled to have his name entered in the 
Register, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  any person who 
immediately before the commencement of this Act was an Associate or a Fellow 
(including an Honorary Fellow) of the dissolved company;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  any person who 
is a holder of the Diploma in Company Secretaryship awarded by the Government of 
India;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  any person who 
has passed the examinations conducted by the dissolved company and has completed 
training either as specified by the dissolved company or as prescribed by the 
Council, except any such person who is not a permanent resident of India;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  any person who 
has passed such examination and completed such training, as may be prescribed 
for membership of the Institute;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  any person who 
has passed such other examination and completed such other training without 
India as is recognised by the Central Government or the Council as being 
equivalent to the examination and training prescribed under this Act for 
membership of the Institute:
 
Provided that in the case 
of any person belonging to any of the classes mentioned in this sub-section who 
is not permanently residing in India, the Central Government or the Council may 
impose such further conditions as it may deem to be necessary or expedient in 
the public interest.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every person belonging 
to the class mentioned in clause (a) or clause (b) of sub-section (1) shall have 
his name entered in the Register without the payment of any entrance fee.
 

1[(3) Every person 
belonging to any of the classes mentioned in clauses (c), (d) and (e) of 
sub-section (1) shall have his name entered in the Register on application being 
made and granted in the prescribed manner and on payment of such fees, as may be 
determined, by notification, by the Council, which shall not exceed rupees three 
thousand:
 
Provided that the Council 
may with the prior approval of the Central Government, determine the fee 
exceeding rupees three thousand, which shall not in any case exceed rupees six 
thousand.]
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Central Government 
may take such steps as may be necessary for the purpose of having the names of 
all persons belonging to the classes mentioned in clauses (a) and (b) of 
sub-section (1) entered in the Register at the commencement of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in this section, the Council may confer on any person 
Honorary Fellow Membership, if the Council is of the opinion that such person 
has made a significant contribution to the profession of Company Secretaries and 
thereupon the Council shall enter the name of such person in the Register but 
such person shall not have any voting rights in any election or meetings of the 
Institute and shall not also be required to pay any fee to the Institute.
 
 





</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Associates and 
Fellows.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The members of the Institute shall be divided into two classes designated 
respectively as Associates and Fellows.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person other than 
a person to whom the provisions of sub-section (4) apply, shall, on his name 
being entered in the Register, be deemed to have become an Associate and as long 
as his name remains so entered, shall be entitled to use the letters “A.C.S.” 
after his name to indicate that he is an Associate.
 

1[(3) A person, 
being an Associate who has been in continuous practice in India as a Company 
Secretary for at least five years and a person who has been an Associate for a 
continuous period of not less than five years and who possesses such 
qualifications or practical experience as the Council may prescribe with a view 
to ensuring that he has experience equivalent to the experience normally 
acquired as a result of continuous practice for a period of five years as a 
Company Secretary shall, on payment of such fees, as may be determined, by 
notification, by the Council, which shall not exceed rupees five thousand, and 
on application made and granted in the prescribed manner, be entered in the 
Register as a Fellow:
 
Provided that the Council 
may with the prior approval of the Central Government, determine the fee 
exceeding rupees five thousand, which shall not in any case exceed rupees ten 
thousand.
 
Explanation I.—For 
the purposes of this sub-section, a person shall be deemed to have practised in 
India for any period for which he has held a certificate of practice under 
section 6, notwithstanding that he did not actually practise during that period.
 
Explanation II.—In 
computing the continuous period during which a person has been an Associate of 
the Institute, there shall be included any continuous period during which the 
person has been an Associate of the dissolved company immediately before he 
became an Associate of the Institute.]
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Any person who was a 
Fellow of the dissolved company and who is entitled to have his name entered in 
the Register under clause (a) of sub-section (1) of section 4, shall be entered 
in the Register as a Fellow.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Any person whose name 
is entered in the Register as a Fellow shall, so long as his name remains so 
entered, be entitled to use the letters “F.C.S.” after his name to indicate that 
he is a Fellow.
 
 






</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>6</number> Certificate of 
practice.—
<section><number>1</number> No 
member of the Institute shall be entitled to practise, whether in India or 
elsewhere, unless he has obtained from the Council a certificate of 
practice.
 1[(2) A member who desires to be 
entitled to practise shall make an application in such form and pay such annual 
fee, for his certificate as may be determined, by notification, by the Council, 
which shall not exceed rupees three thousand, and such fee shall be payable on 
or before the 1st day of April in each year:
 Provided that the Council may with 
the prior approval of the Central Government, determine the fee exceeding rupees 
three thousand, which shall not in any case exceed rupees six 
thousand.]
 2[(3) The certificate of practice 
obtained under sub-section (1) may be cancelled by the Council under such 
circumstances as may be prescribed.]
  




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Members to be known 
as Company Secretaries.—Every 
member of the Institute in practice shall, and any other member may, use the 
designation of a Company Secretary and, no member using such designation shall 
use any other description, whether in addition thereto or in substitution 
therefor:
 
Provided that nothing in 
this section shall be deemed to prohibit any such member from adding any other 
description or letters to his name, if entitled thereto, to indicate membership 
of such other Institute whether in India or elsewhere as may be recognised in 
this behalf by the Council, or any other qualification that he may possess, or 
to prohibit a firm, all the partners of which are members of the Institute and 
in practice, from being known by its firm name as Company Secretaries.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Disabilities.—Notwithstanding 
anything contained in section 4, a person shall not be entitled to have his name 
entered in, or borne on the Register if he—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  has not 
attained the age of twenty-one years at the time of his application for the 
entry of his name in the Register; or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  is of unsound 
mind and stands so adjudged by a competent court; or
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  is an 
undischarged insolvent; or
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  being a 
discharged insolvent, has not obtained from the court a certificate stating that 
his insolvency was caused by misfortune without any misconduct on his part; or
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number>  has been 
convicted by a competent court, whether within or without India, of an offence 
involving moral turpitude and punishable with imprisonment or of an offence, not 
of a technical nature, committed by him in his professional capacity unless in 
respect of the offence committed he has either been granted a pardon or, on an 
application made by him in this behalf the Central Government has, by an order 
in writing, removed the disability; or
 </section><section>
        <number>f</number>  has been 
removed from membership of the Institute on being found on inquiry to have been 
guilty of professional or other misconduct:
 
                 Provided 
that a person who has been removed from membership for a specified period shall 
not be entitled to have his name entered in the Register until the expiry of 
such period.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Constitution of the 
Council of the Institute.—
<section><number>1</number> 
There shall be a Council of the Institute for the management of the affairs of 
the Institute and for discharging the functions assigned to it by or under this 
Act.
 

1[(2) The Council 
shall be composed of the following persons, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> not more than 
fifteen persons elected by the members of the Institute, from amongst the 
Fellows of the Institute chosen in such manner and from such regional 
constituencies as may be specified:
 
              Provided 
that a Fellow of the Institute, who has been found guilty of any professional or 
other misconduct and whose name is removed from the Register or has been awarded 
penalty of fine, shall not be eligible to contest the election,—
 <subsubsection>
             <number>i</number> in case 
of misconduct falling under the First Schedule of this Act, for a period of 
three years;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>ii</number> in case 
of misconduct falling under the Second Schedule of this Act, for a period of six 
years,
 
              from the 
completion of the period of removal of name from the Register or payment of 
fine, as the case may be;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> not more than 
five persons nominated in the specified manner by the Central Government.]
 

2[(3) No person 
holding a post under the Central Government or a State Government shall be 
eligible for election to the Council under clause (a) of sub-section (2).
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> No person who has been 
auditor of the Institute shall be eligible for election to the Council under 
clause (a) of sub-section (2) for a period of three years after he ceases to be 
an auditor.]










</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>10</number> 
Re-election or re-nomination to Council.—A 
member of the Council, elected or nominated under sub-section (2) of section 9, 
shall be eligible for re-election or, as the case may be, re-nomination:
 
Provided that no member 
shall hold the office for more than two consecutive terms:
 
Provided further that a 
member of the Council, who is or has been elected as President under sub-section 

<section><number>1</number> of section 12, shall not be eligible for election or nomination as a member 
of the Council.]















</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>10A</number> 
Settlement of disputes regarding election.—In 
case of any dispute regarding any election under clause 
<section><number>a</number> of sub-section (2) 
of section 9, the aggrieved person may make an application within thirty days 
from the date of declaration of the result of election to the Secretary of the 
Institute, who shall forward the same to the Central Government.]
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>10B</number> 
Establishment of Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
On receipt of any application under section 10A, the Central Government shall, 
by notification, establish a Tribunal consisting of a Presiding Officer and two 
other Members to decide such dispute and the decision of such Tribunal shall be 
final.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A person shall not be 
qualified for appointment,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> as a Presiding 
Officer of the Tribunal unless he has been a member of the Indian Legal Service 
and has held a post in Grade I of the service for at least three years;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> as a Member 
unless he has been a member of the Council for at least one full term and who is 
not a sitting member of the Council or who has not been a candidate in the 
election under dispute; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number> as a Member 
unless he holds the post of a Joint Secretary to the Government of India or any 
other post under the Central Government carrying a scale of pay which is not 
less than that of a Joint Secretary to the Government of India.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The terms and 
conditions of service of the Presiding Officer and Members of the Tribunal, 
their place of meetings and allowances shall be such as may be specified.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The expenses of the 
Tribunal shall be borne by the Council.]






</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Nomination in 
default of election.—If 
the members of the Institute fail to elect any member under clause 
<section><number>a</number> of 
sub-section (2) of section 9 from any of the regional constituency that may be 
notified under that clause, the Central Government may nominate any duly 
qualified person from such constituency to fill up the vacancy, and any person 
so nominated shall be deemed to be a duly elected member of the Council.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> President and 
Vice-President.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Council at its first meeting shall elect two of its members to be 
respectively the President and the Vice-President thereof, and so often as the 
office of the President or the Vice-President falls vacant, the Council shall 
choose a person to be the President or the Vice-President, as the case may be:
 
Provided that the 
President of the Council of the dissolved company shall continue to hold such 
office after the commencement of this Act, until such time as a President is 
elected under the provisions of this sub-section.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The President shall be 
the 

1[Head] of the 
Council.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The President or the 
Vice-President shall hold office for a period of one year from the date on which 
he is chosen but so as not to extend beyond his term of office as a member of 
the Council, and subject to his being a member of the Council at the relevant 
time, he shall be eligible for re-election 

2[under sub-section 
(1)].
 

3[(4) On the 
expiration of the duration of the Council, or of the term of office of the 
President and the Vice-President thereof, the President and the Vice-President 
shall continue to hold office until such time as a new President and the 
Vice-President is elected and takes over charge of their duties.]
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> In the event of the 
occurrence of any vacancy in the office of the President, the Vice-President 
shall act as President until the date on which a new President elected in 
accordance with the provisions of this section to fill such vacancy enters upon 
his office and when the President is unable to discharge his functions owing to 
absence, illness or any other cause, the Vice-President shall discharge his 
functions until the date on which the President resumes his duties.
 
 






</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Resignation of 
membership and casual vacancies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any member of the Council may at any time resign his membership by writing under 
his hand addressed to the President, and the seat of such member shall become 
vacant when such resignation is notified in the Official Gazette.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A member of the 
Council shall be deemed to have vacated his seat if he is declared by the 
Council to have been absent without sufficient excuse from three consecutive 
meetings of the Council 

1[or he has been 
found guilty of any professional or other misconduct and awarded penalty of 
fine] or of any of the Committees which has been constituted by the Council and 
of which he is a member or if his name is, for any cause, removed from the 
Register under the provisions of section 20.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A casual vacancy in 
the office of a member of the Council shall be filled by fresh election from the 
constituency concerned or by nomination by the Central Government, as the case 
may be, and the person elected or nominated to fill the vacancy shall hold 
office until the dissolution of the Council:
 
Provided that no election 
shall be held to fill a casual vacancy occurring within 

2[one year] prior 
to the date of the expiration of the terms of the Council, but such a vacancy 
may be filled by nomination by the Central Government after consultation with 
the President of the Council.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> No act done by the 
Council shall be called in question on the ground merely of the existence of any 
vacancy in, or defect in the constitution of the Council.
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Duration and 
dissolution of the Council.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The duration of any Council constituted under this Act shall be 

1[four years] from 
the date of its first meeting.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding the 
expiration of the duration of a Council (hereafter in this sub-section referred 
to as the former Council), the former Council shall continue to exercise its 
functions under this Act until a new Council is constituted in accordance with 
the provisions of this Act and on such constitution the former Council shall 
stand dissolved.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>15</number> Function 
of Council.—The 
Institute shall function under the overall control, guidance and supervision of 
the Council and the duty of carrying out the provisions of this Act shall be 
vested in the Council.
 <section>
<number>2</number> In particular, and 
without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing powers, the duties of the 
Council shall include—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  to approve 
academic courses and their contents;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the 
prescribing of fees for the examination of candidates for enrolment;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  the 
prescribing of qualifications for entry in the Register;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  the 
recognition of foreign qualifications and training for purposes of enrolment;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  the 
prescribing of guidelines for granting or refusal of certificates of practice 
under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  the levy of 
fees from members, examinees and other persons;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>g</number>  the regulation 
and maintenance of the status and standard of professional qualifications of 
members of the Institute;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>h</number>  the carrying 
out, by granting financial assistance to persons other than members of the 
Council or in any other manner, of research in such matters of interest to 
Company Secretaries as may be prescribed;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>i</number>  to enable 
functioning of the Director (Discipline), the Board of Discipline, the 
Disciplinary Committee and the Appellate Authority constituted under the 
provisions of this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>j</number>  to enable 
functioning of the Quality Review Board;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>k</number>  consideration 
to the recommendations of the Quality Review Board made under clause (a) of 
section 29B and details of action taken thereon in its annual report; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>l</number>  to ensure the 
functioning of the Institute in accordance with the provisions of this Act and 
in performance of other statutory duties as may be entrusted to the Institute 
from time to time.]
 
 


















</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>15A</number> Functions 
of Institute.—The 
functions of the Institute shall include—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  the 
examination of candidates for enrolment;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  the regulation 
of training of students;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  the 
maintenance and publication of a Register of persons qualified to practice as 
Company Secretaries;
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  collection of 
fees from members, examinees and other persons;
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number>  subject to the 
orders of the appropriate authorities under this Act, the removal of names from 
the Register and the restoration to the Register of names which have been 
removed;
 </section><section>
        <number>f</number>  the 
maintenance of a library and publication of books and periodicals relating to 
management of companies and allied subjects;
 </section><section>
       <number>g</number>  the conduct of 
elections to the Council of the Institute; and
 </section><section>
       <number>h</number>  the granting 
or refusal of certificates of practice as per guidelines issued by the Council.]
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>15B</number> Imparting 
education by Universities and other bodies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to the provisions of this Act, any Universities established by law or 
any body affiliated to the Institute, may impart education on the subjects 
covered by the academic courses of the Institute.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Universities or 
bodies referred to in sub-section (1) shall, while awarding degree, diploma or 
certificate or bestowing any designation, ensure that the award or designation 
do not resemble or is not identical to one awarded by the Institute.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Nothing contained in 
this section shall enable a University or a body to adopt a name or nomenclature 
which is in any way similar to that of the Institute.]
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>16</number> Officers 
and employees’ salary, allowances, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
For the efficient performance of its duties, the Council shall—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  appoint a 
Secretary of the Council to perform such duties as may be prescribed;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  appoint a 
Director (Discipline) to perform such functions as assigned to him under this 
Act and the rules and regulations framed thereunder;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  designate an 
officer of the Council or the Institute to carry out the administrative 
functions of the Institute as its chief executive.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Council may also—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  appoint such 
other officers and employees to the Council and the Institute as it considers 
necessary;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  require and 
take from the Secretary or from any other officer or employee of the Council and 
the Institute such security for the due performance of his duties, as the 
Council considers necessary;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  prescribe the 
salaries, fees, allowances of the officers and employees of the Council and the 
Institute and their terms and conditions of service;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  with the 
previous sanction of the Central Government, fix the allowances of the 
President, Vice-President and other members of the Council and members of its 
Committees;
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The Secretary of the 
Council shall be entitled to participate in the meetings of the Council but 
shall not be entitled to vote thereat.]
 
 








</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Committees of the 
Council.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Council shall constitute from amongst its members of the following Standing 
Committees, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  an Executive 
Committee;
 
 

1[(b)  a Finance 
Committee; and]
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  an Examination 
Committee.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Council may also 
constitute a Training and Educational Facilities Committee, Professional 
Research and Publications Committee and such other Committees from amongst its 
members as it deems necessary for the purpose of carrying out the provisions of 
this Act.
 

2[(3) Each of the 
Standing Committees shall consist of the President and the Vice-President ex 
officio, and minimum of three and maximum of five members to be elected by 
the Council from amongst its members.]
 

3[***]
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in this section, any Committee formed under sub-section (2) 
may, with the sanction of the Council, co-opt such other members of the 
Institute not exceeding 

4[one-thirds of the 
total membership of the Committee] as the Committee thinks fit, and any member 
so co-opted shall be entitled to exercise all the rights of a member of the 
Committee.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Every Committee 
constituted under this section shall elect its own Chairman:
 
Provided that—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  where the 
President is a member of such Committee, he shall be the Chairman of such 
Committee, and in his absence, the Vice-President, if he is a member of such 
Committee, shall be its Chairman; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  where the 
President is not a member of such Committee, but the Vice-President is a member, 
he shall be its Chairman.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>8</number> The Standing 
Committees and other Committees formed under this section shall exercise such 
functions and be subject to such conditions in the exercise thereof as may be 
prescribed.
 
 










</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Finances of the 
Council.—
<section><number>1</number> 
There shall be established a fund under the management and control of the 
Council into which shall be paid all moneys (including donations and grants) 
received by the Council and out of which shall be met all expenses including any 
donations made and liabilities properly incurred by the Council.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Council may invest 
any money for the time being standing to the credit of the fund in any 
Government security or in any other security approved by the Central Government.
 

1[(3) The Council 
shall keep proper accounts of the fund distinguishing capital from revenue in 
the manner prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Council shall 
prepare in the manner prescribed and approve, prior to the start of the 
financial year, an annual financial statement (the budget indicating all its 
anticipated revenues as well as all proposed expenditures for the forthcoming 
year.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The annual accounts of 
the Council shall be prepared in such manner as may be prescribed and be subject 
to audit by a Chartered Accountant in practice to be appointed annually by the 
Council:
 
Provided that no member of 
the Council or a person who has been a member of the Council during the last 
four years or a person who is in partnership with such member shall be eligible 
for appointment as an auditor under this sub-section:
 
Provided further that, in 
the event it is brought to the notice of the Council that the accounts of the 
Council do not represent a true and fair view of its finances, them the Council 
may itself cause a special audit to be conducted:
 
Provided also that if such 
information, that the accounts of the Council do not represent a true and fair 
view of its finances, is sent to the Council by the Central Government then, the 
Council may, wherever appropriate cause a special credit or take such other 
action as it considers necessary and shall furnish an action taken report on it 
to the Central Government.]
 

2[(5A) As soon as 
may be practicable at end of each year, the Council shall circulate the audited 
accounts to its members at least fifteen days in advance and consider and 
approve these accounts in a special meeting convened for the purpose.
 </section><section>
<number>5B</number> The Council shall 
cause to be published in the Gazette of India not later than the 30th day of 
September of the year next following, a copy of the audited accounts and the 
Report of the Council for that year duly approved by the Council and copies of 
the said accountants and Report shall be forwarded to the Central Government and 
to all members of the Institute.]
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Subject to such 
directions as the Central Government may, by order in writing, make in this 
behalf, the Council may borrow—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  any money 
required for meeting its liabilities on capital account on the security of the 
fund or on the security of any other assets for the time being belonging to it; 
or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  for the 
purpose of meeting current liabilities pending the receipt of income by way of 
temporary loan or overdraft.
 
 









</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Register.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Council shall maintain in the prescribed manner a Register of the members of 
the Institute.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Register shall 
include the following particulars about every member of the institute, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  his full name, 
date of birth, domicile, residential and professional addresses;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the date on 
which his name is entered in the Register;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  his 
qualifications;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  whether he 
holds a certificate of practice; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  any other 
particulars which may be prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The Council shall 
cause to be published in such manner as may be prescribed a list of members of 
the Institute as on the 1st day of April of each year, and shall, if requested 
to do so by any such member, send him a copy of such list 

1[on payment of 
such amount as may be prescribed].
 

2[(4) Every member 
of the Institute shall, on his name being entered in the Register, pay such 
annual membership fee as may be determined, by notification, by the Council, 
which shall not exceed rupees five thousand:
 
Provided that the Council 
may with the prior approval of the Central Government, determine the fee 
exceeding rupees five thousand which shall not in any case exceed rupees ten 
thousand.]
 
 





</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Removal from the 
Register.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Council may remove from the Register the name of any member of the 
Institute—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  who is dead; 
or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  from whom a 
request has been received to that effect; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  who has not 
paid any prescribed fee required to be paid by him; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  who is found 
to have been subject at the time when his name was entered in the Register, or 
who at any time thereafter has become subject to any of the disabilities 
mentioned in section 8, or who for any other reason has ceased to be entitled to 
have his name borne on the Register.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Council shall 
remove from the Register the name of any member in respect of whom an order has 
been passed under this Act removing him from membership of the Institute.
 

1[(3) If the name 
of any member has been removed from the Register under clause (c) of sub-section 
(1), on receipt of an application, his name may be entered again in the Register 
on payment of the arrears of annual fee and entrance fee along with such 
additional fee, as may be determined, by notification, by the Council, which 
shall not exceed rupees two thousand:
 
Provided that the Council 
may with the prior approval of the Central Government, determine the fee 
exceeding rupees two thousand, which shall not in any case exceed rupees four 
thousand.]






</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>21</number> 
Disciplinary Directorate.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Council shall, by notification, establish a Disciplinary Directorate headed 
by an officer of the Institute designated as Director (Discipline) and such 
other employees for making investigations in respect of any information or 
complaint received by it.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On receipt of any 
information or complaint alongwith the prescribed fee, the Director (Discipline) 
shall arrive at a prima facie opinion on the occurrence of the alleged 
misconduct.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the Director 
(Discipline) is of the opinion that a member is guilty of any professional or 
other misconduct mentioned in the First Schedule, he shall place the matter 
before the Board of Discipline and where the Director (Discipline) is of the 
opinion that a member is guilty of any professional or other misconduct 
mentioned in the Second Schedule or in both the Schedules, he shall place the 
matter before the Disciplinary Committee.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> In order to make 
investigations under the provisions of this Act, the Disciplinary Directorate 
shall follow such procedure as may be specified.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where a complainant 
withdraws the complaint, the Director (Discipline) shall place such withdrawal 
before the Board of Discipline or as the case may be, the Disciplinary 
Committee, and the said Board or Committee, if its is of the view that the 
circumstances so warrant, permit the withdrawal at any stage.]
 
 
























</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>21A</number> Board of 
Discipline.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Council shall constitute a Board of Discipline consisting of—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  a person with 
experience in law and having knowledge of the disciplinary matters and the 
profession, to be its presiding officer;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  two members 
one of whom shall be a member of the Council elected by the Council and the 
other member shall be the person designated under clause (c) of sub-section (1) 
of section (16);
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  the Director 
(Discipline) shall function as the Secretary of the Board.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Board of 
Discipline shall follow summary disposal procedure in dealing with all the cases 
before it.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the Board of 
Discipline is of the opinion that a member is guilty of a professional or other 
misconduct mentioned in the First Schedule, it shall afford to the member an 
opportunity of being heard before making any order against him and may 
thereafter take any one or more of the following actions, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  reprimand the 
member;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  remove the 
name of the member from the Register up to a period of three months;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  impose such 
fine as it may think fit which may extend to rupees one lakh.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The Director 
(Discipline) shall submit before the Board of Discipline all information and 
complaints where he is of the opinion that there is no prima facie case 
and the Board of Discipline may, if it agrees with the opinion of the Director 
(Discipline), close the matter or in case of disagreement, may advise the 
Director (Discipline) to further investigate the matter.]
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>21B</number> Disciplinary 
Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Council shall constitute a Disciplinary Committee consisting of the 
President or the Vice-President of the Council as the Presiding Officer and two 
members to be elected from amongst the members of the Council and two members to 
be nominated by the Central Government from amongst the persons of eminence 
having experience in the field of law, economics, business, finance or 
accountancy:
 
Provided that the Council 
may constitute more Disciplinary Committees as and when it considers necessary.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Disciplinary 
Committee, while considering the cases placed before it, shall follow such 
procedure as may be specified.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the Disciplinary 
Committee is of the opinion that a member is guilty of a professional or other 
misconduct mentioned in the Second Schedule or both the First Schedule and the 
Second Schedule, it shall afford to the member an opportunity of being heard 
before making any order against him and may thereafter take any one or more of 
the following actions, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  reprimand the 
member;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  remove the 
name of the member from the Register permanently or for such period, as it 
thinks fit;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  impose such 
fine as it may think fit, which may extend to rupees five lakhs.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The allowances payable 
to the members nominated by the Central Government shall be such as may be 
specified.]
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>21C</number> Authority, 
Disciplinary Committee, Board of Discipline and Director (Discipline) to have 
powers of civil court.—For 
the purposes of an inquiry under the provisions of this Act, the Authority, the 
Disciplinary Committee, Board of Discipline and the Director (Discipline) shall 
have the same powers as are vested in a civil court under the Code of Civil 
Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), in respect of the following matters, namely:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  summoning and 
enforcing the attendance of any person and examining him on oath;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  the discovery 
and production of any document; and
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  receiving 
evidence on affidavit.
 
Explanation.—For 
the purposes of sections 21, 21A, 21B, 21C and 22, “member of the Institute” 
includes a person who was a member of the Institute on the date of the alleged 
misconduct although he has ceased to be a member of the Institute at the time of 
the inquiry.]
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>21D</number> Transitional 
provisions.—All 
complaints pending before the Council or any inquiry initiated by the 
Disciplinary Committee or any reference or appeal made to a High Court prior to 
the commencement of the Company Secretaries (Amendment) Act, 2005 shall continue 
to be governed by the provisions of this Act, as if this Act had not been 
amended by the Company Secretaries (Amendment) Act, 2005.]
 
 




</article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>22</number> 
Professional or other misconduct defined.—For 
the purposes of this Act, the expression “professional or other misconduct” 
shall be deemed to include any act or omission provided in any of the Schedules, 
but nothing in this section shall be construed to limit or abridge in any way 
the power conferred or duty cast on the Director (Discipline) under sub-section 

<section><number>1</number> of section 21 to inquire into the conduct of any member of the Institute 
under any other circumstances.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>22A</number> 
Constitution of Appellate Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Appellate Authority constituted under sub-section (1) of section 22A of the 
Chartered Accountants Act, 1949 (38 of 1949), shall be deemed to be the 
Appellate Authority for the purposes of this Act subject to the modification 
that for clause (b) of said sub-section (1), the following clause had been 
substituted, namely:—
 
            “(b) the 
Central Government shall, by notification appoint two part-time members from 
amongst the persons who have been members of the Council of the Institute of 
Company Secretaries of India for at least one full term and who is not a sitting 
member of the Council.”]
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>22B</number> Term of 
office of members of Authority.—A 
person appointed as a member shall hold office for a term of three years from 
the date on which he enters upon his office or until he attains the age of 
sixty-two years, whichever is earlier.]
 
 




</article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>22C</number> Procedure, 
etc., of Authority.—The 
provisions of section 22C, section 22D and section 22F of the Chartered 
Accountants Act, 1949 (38 of 1949), shall apply to the Authority in relation to 
allowances and terms and conditions of service of its Chairperson and members, 
and in the discharge of its functions under this Act as they apply to it in the 
discharge of its functions under the Chartered Accountants Act, 1949.]
 
 




</article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>22D</number> Officers and 
other staff of Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Council shall make available to the Authority such officers and other staff 
members as may be necessary for the efficient performance of the functions of 
the Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The salaries and 
allowances and conditions of service of the officers and other staff members of 
the Authority shall be such as may be prescribed.]
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>22E</number> Appeal to 
Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any member of the Institute aggrieved by any order of the Board of Discipline or 
the Disciplinary Committee imposing on him any of the penalties referred to in 
sub-section (3) of section 21A and sub-section (3) of section 21B, may within 
ninety days from the date on which the order is communicated to him, prefer an 
appeal to the Authority:
 
Provided that the Director 
(Discipline) may also appeal against the decision of the Board of Discipline or 
the Disciplinary Committee to the Authority if so authorised by the Council, 
within ninety days:
 
Provided further that the 
Authority may entertain any such appeal after the expiry of the said period of 
ninety days, if it is satisfied that there was sufficient cause for not filing 
the appeal in time.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Authority may, 
after calling for the records of any case, revise any order made by the Board of 
Discipline or the Disciplinary Committee under sub-section (3) of section 21A 
and sub-section (3) of section 21B and may—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  confirm, 
modify or set aside the order;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  impose any 
penalty or set aside, reduce, or enhance the penalty imposed by the order;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  remit the case 
to the Board of Discipline or Disciplinary Committee for such further enquiry as 
the Authority considers proper in the circumstances of the case; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  pass such 
other order as the Authority thinks fit:
 
Provided that the 
Authority shall give an opportunity of being heard to the parties concerned 
before passing any order.]







</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Constitution and 
functions of Regional Councils.—
<section><number>1</number> 
For the purpose of advising and assisting it on matters concerning its 
functions, the Council may constitute such Regional Councils as and when it 
deems fit for one or more of the regional constituencies that may be notified by 
the Central Government under clause 
<subsection><number>a</number> of sub-section (2) of section 9.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Regional Councils 
shall be constituted in such manner and exercise such functions as may be 
prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in this section, each Regional Council of the dissolved 
company shall, on the commencement of this Act, become the Regional Council of 
the Institute for the area for which it was functioning as a Regional Council 
immediately before such commencement and shall function as such—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  for a period 
of two years from such commencement, or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  till a 
Regional Council is constituted for such area in accordance with the provisions 
of this section,
 
whichever is earlier.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>24</number> Penalty for falsely 
claiming to be a member, etc.—Subject 
to the provisions of section 7, any person who,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  not being a 
member of the Institute,—
 <subsection>
             <number>i</number>  
represents that he is a member of the Institute; or
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>ii</number>  uses the 
designation “Company Secretary”; or
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>iii</number>  uses 
the letters “A.C.S.” or “F.C.S.” after his name; or
 </subsection></section><section>
       <number>b</number>  being a member 
of the Institute, but not having a certificate of practice, represents that he 
is in practice or practises as a Company Secretary,
 
shall be punishable on 
first conviction with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, and on any 
subsequent conviction with imprisonment which may extend to six months, or with 
fine which may extend to five thousand rupees, or with both.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Penalty for using 
name of the Council, or awarding degree of Company Secretary.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Save as otherwise provided in this Act, no person shall—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  use a name or 
a common seal which is identical with the name or the common seal of the 
Institute or so nearly resembles it as to deceive or as is likely to deceive the 
public;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  award any 
degree, diploma or certificate or bestow any designation which indicates or 
purports to indicate the position or attainment of any qualification or 
competence in Company Secretaryship similar to that of a member of the 
Institute; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  seek to 
regulate in any manner whatsoever the profession of Company Secretaries.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person 
contravening the provisions of sub-section (1) shall, without prejudice to any 
other proceedings which may be taken against him, be punishable on first 
conviction with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, and on any 
subsequent conviction with imprisonment which may extend to six months, or with 
fine which may extend to five thousand rupees, or with both.
 

1[***]
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Companies not to 
engage in Company Secretaryship.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No company, whether incorporated in India or elsewhere, shall practise as 
Company Secretaries.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any company 
contravening the provisions of sub-section (1) shall be punishable on first 
conviction with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, and on any 
subsequent conviction with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees.


</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Unqualified persons 
not to sign documents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No person other than a member of the Institute shall sign any document on behalf 
of a Company Secretary in practice or a firm of such Company Secretaries in his 
or its professional capacity.
 

1[(2) Any person 
who contravenes the provisions of sub-section (1) shall, without prejudice to 
any other proceedings which may be taken against him, be punishable on first 
conviction with a fine not less than five thousand rupees but which may extend 
to one lakh rupees, and in the event of a second or subsequent conviction with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year or with a fine not less 
than ten thousand rupees but which may extend to two lakh rupees or with both.]
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Offences by 
companies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If the person committing an offence under this Act is a company, the company as 
well as every person in charge of, and responsible to, the company for the 
conduct of its business at the time of the commission of the offence shall be 
deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against 
and punished accordingly:
 
Provided that nothing 
contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to any 
punishment if he proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or 
that he had exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such 
offence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence under this Act has been 
committed by a company and it is proved that the offence has been committed with 
the consent or connivance of, or that the commission of the offence is 
attributable to any neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary or 
other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary or other officer 
shall also be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be 
proceeded against and punished accordingly.
 
Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this section,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  “company” 
means any body corporate and includes a firm or other association of 
individuals; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  “director”, in 
relation to a firm, means a partner in the firm.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>29</number> Sanction to 
prosecute.—No 
person shall be prosecuted under this Act except on a complaint made by or under 
the order of the Council or of the Central Government.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>29A</number> 
Establishment of Quality Review Board.—The 
Central Government shall, by notification, constitute a Quality Review Board 
consisting of a Chairperson and four other members.
 <section>
<number>2</number> The Chairperson and 
members of the Board shall be appointed from amongst the persons of eminence 
having experience in the field of law, economics, business, finance or 
accountancy.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Two members of the 
Board shall be nominated by the Council and other two members shall be nominated 
by the Central Government.]







</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>29B</number> 
Functions of Board.—The 
Board shall perform the following functions, namely:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  to make 
recommendations to the Council with regard to the quality of services provided 
by the members of the Institute;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  to review the 
quality of services provided by the members of the Institute including 
secretarial services; and
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  to guide the 
members of the Institute to improve the quality of services and adherence to the 
various statutory and other regulatory requirements.]







</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>29C</number> 
Procedure of Board.—The 
Board shall meet at such time and place and follow in its meetings such 
procedure as may be specified.]
 
 




</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>29D</number> 
Terms and conditions of service of Chairperson and members of Board and its 
expenditure.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The terms and conditions of service of the Chairperson and the members of the 
Board, and their allowances shall be such as may be specified.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The expenditure of the 
Board shall be borne by the Council.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>30</number> Appeal.—[Rep. 
by the Company Secretaries (Amendment) Act, 2006 (8 of 2006), sec. 26 (w.e.f. 
17-11-2006).]]
 
 












</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>31</number> Dissolution of the 
Institute of Company Secretaries of India registered under the Companies Act.—On 
the commencement of this Act—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  the company 
known as the Institute of Company Secretaries of India registered under the 
Companies Act shall stand dissolved and thereafter no person shall make, assert 
or take any claims or demands or proceedings against the dissolved company or 
against any officer thereof in his capacity as such officer except in so far as 
may be necessary, for enforcing the provisions of this Act;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  the right of 
every member to, or in respect of, the dissolved company shall be extinguished, 
and thereafter no member of that company shall make, assert or take any claims 
or demands or proceedings in respect of that company except as provided in this 
Act.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>32</number> Transfer of assets 
and liabilities of the dissolved company to the Institute.—
<section><number>1</number> 
On the commencement of this Act, there shall be transferred to and vested in the 
Institute all the assets and liabilities of the dissolved company.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The assets of the 
dissolved company shall be deemed to include all rights and powers, and all 
property, whether movable or immovable, of that company, including in 
particular, cash balances, reserve funds, investments, deposits and all other 
interests and rights in or arising out of such property as may be in the 
possession of the dissolved company and all books of accounts, papers or 
documents of the dissolved company; and the liabilities shall be deemed to 
include all debts, liabilities and obligations of whatever kind then existing of 
that company.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All contracts, debts, 
bonds, agreements and other instruments of whatever nature to which the 
dissolved company is a party, subsisting or having effect immediately before the 
commencement of this Act, shall be of as full force and effect against or in 
favour of the Institute, as the case may be, and may be enforced as fully and 
effectively as if instead of the dissolved company, the Institute had been a 
party thereto.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If, on the 
commencement of this Act, any suit, appeal or other legal proceeding of whatever 
nature by or against the dissolved company is pending, the same shall not abate, 
be discontinued or be in any way prejudicially affected by reason of the 
transfer to the Institute of the assets and liabilities of the dissolved company 
or of anything contained in this Act, but the suit, appeal or other proceeding 
may be continued, prosecuted and enforced by or against the Institute, in the 
same manner and to the same extent as it would or may be continued, prosecuted 
and enforced by or against the dissolved company if this Act had not been 
passed.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>33</number> Provisions 
respecting employees of the dissolved company.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every person employed in the dissolved company and continuing in its employment 
immediately before the commencement of this Act shall, as from such 
commencement, become an employee of the Institute, shall hold his office or 
service therein by the same tenure and upon the same terms and conditions and 
with the same rights and privileges as to pension and gratuity as he would have 
held the same under the dissolved company if this Act had not been passed, and 
shall continue to do so unless and until his employment in the Institute is 
terminated or until his remuneration, terms and conditions of employment are 
duly altered by the Institute.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 (14 of 1947), or in any 
other law for the time being in force, the transfer of the services of any 
employee of the dissolved company to the Institute shall not entitle any such 
employee to any compensation under that Act or other law, and no such claim 
shall be entertained by any court, tribunal or other authority.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>34</number> Alteration in the 
Register and cancellation of certificate.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where an order is made under this Act reprimanding a member, record of the 
punishment shall be entered against his name in the Register.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the name of any 
member is removed, the certificate of practice granted to him under this Act 
shall be recalled and cancelled.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>35</number> Directions of the 
Central Government.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, from time to time, issue such directions to the 
Council as in the opinion of the Central Government are conducive to the 
fulfillment of the objects of this Act and in the discharge of its functions, 
the Council shall be bound to carry out any such directions.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Directions issued 
under sub-section (1) may include directions to the Council to make any 
regulations or to amend or revoke any regulations already made.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If, in the opinion of 
the Central Government, the Council has persistently committed default in giving 
effect to the directions issued under this section, the Central Government may, 
after giving an opportunity to the Council to state its case, by order, dissolve 
the Council, whereafter a new council shall be constituted in accordance with 
the provisions of this Act with effect from such date as may be specified by the 
Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where the Central 
Government passes an order under sub-section (3) dissolving the Council, it may, 
pending the constitution of a new Council in accordance with the provisions of 
this Act, authorise any person or body of persons to take over the management of 
the affairs of the Institute and to exercise such functions as may be specified 
in this behalf by the Central Government.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>36</number> Protection 
of action taken in good faith.—No 
suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central 
Government or the Council or the Authority or the Disciplinary Committee or the 
Tribunal or the Board or the Board of Discipline or the Disciplinary Directorate 
or any officer of that Government, Council, Authority, Disciplinary Committee, 
Tribunal, Board, Board of Discipline, or the Disciplinary Directorate, for 
anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or 
any rule, regulation, notification, direction or order made thereunder.]
 
 




</article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>36A</number> Members, 
etc. to be public servants.—The 
Chairperson, Presiding Officer, members and other officers and employees of the 
Authority, Disciplinary Committee, Tribunal, Board, Board of Discipline or the 
Disciplinary Directorate shall be deemed to be public servants within the 
meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>37</number> Maintenance of 
branch offices.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where a Company Secretary in practice or a firm of such Company Secretaries has 
more than one office in  India, each one of such offices shall be in the 
separate charge of a member of the Institute:
 
Provided that the Council 
may in suitable cases exempt any Company Secretary in practice or firm of such 
Company Secretaries from the operation of this sub-section.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every Company 
Secretary in practice or firm of such Company Secretaries maintaining more than 
one office shall send to the Council a list of offices and the persons in charge 
thereof and shall keep the Council informed of any changes in relation thereto.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>38</number> Reciprocity.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where any country, notified by the Central Government in this behalf in the 
Official Gazette, prevents persons of Indian domicile from becoming members of 
any institution similar to the Institute established under this Act or from 
practising the profession of Company Secretaryship or subjects them to unfair 
discrimination in that country, no subject of any such country shall be entitled 
to become a member of the Institute or practise the profession of Company 
Secretaries in India.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to the 
provisions of sub-section (1), the Council may prescribe the conditions, if any, 
subject to which foreign qualifications relating to Company Secretaryship shall 
be recognised for the purposes of entry in the Register.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>38A</number> Power of 
Central Government to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, by notification, make rules to carry out the 
provisions of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular, and 
without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing powers, such rules may 
provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the manner of 
election and nomination in respect of members to the Council under sub-section 
(2) of section 9;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the terms and 
conditions of service of the Presiding Officer and Members of the Tribunal, 
place of meetings and allowances to be paid to them under sub-section (3) of 
section 10B;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  the procedure 
of investigation under sub-section (4) of section 21;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  the procedure 
while considering the cases by the Disciplinary Committee under sub-section (2) 
and fixation of allowances of the nominated members under sub-section (4) of 
section 21B;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  the procedure 
to be followed by the Board in its meetings under section 29C; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  the terms and 
conditions of service of the Chairperson and members of the Board under 
sub-section (1) of section 29D.]
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>39</number> Power to make 
regulations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Council may, by notification in the Gazette of India, make regulations for 
the purpose of carrying out the provisions of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular and 
without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such regulations may 
provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the 
professions that may be recognised under sub-section (2) of section 2 and 

1[items (2)] and 
(4) of Part I of the First Schedule;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the 
examinations and training for the purposes of clauses (c), (d) and (e) of 
sub-section (1) of section 4;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  the manner of 
making an application and granting thereof under sub-section (3) of section 4 or 
sub-section (3) of section 5;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  the fees 
payable under sub-section (3) of section 4, sub-section (3) of section 5, 
sub-section (2) of section 6, 

2[***] sub-section 
(3) of section 15, sub-section (4) of section 19 and clause (c) of sub-section 
(1) of section 20;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  the 
qualifications and practical experience for the purposes of sub-section (3) of 
section 5;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  the form in 
which an application may be made under sub-section (2) of section 6;
 
 

3[***]
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>h</number>  the 
transaction of business by the Council for the discharge of its functions under 
section 15 and other provisions of this Act, the place at which and the 
intervals at which the Council shall hold its meetings for the transaction of 
such business, the procedure to be followed at such meetings and all other 
matters connected therewith;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>i</number>  the 
regulation and maintenance of the status and standards of professional 
qualifications of members of the Institute, as required by 

4[clause (g)] of 
sub-section (2) of section 15;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>j</number>  the carrying 
out of research in matters of interest to Company Secretaries as required by


5[clause (h)] of 
sub-section (2) of section 15;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>k</number>  the 
maintenance of libraries and publication of books and periodicals relating to 
management of companies and allied subjects, as required by 

6[clause (f) of 
section 15A];
 
 

7[***]
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>m</number>  the 
transaction of business by the Standing Committees and other Committees referred 
to in section 17, the places at which and the intervals at which such Committees 
shall hold their meetings for the transaction of such business, the procedure to 
be followed at such meetings and all other matters connected therewith;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>n</number>  the manner in 
which the Register may be maintained under sub-section (1) of section 19;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>o</number>  the other 
particulars to be included in the Register, as required by clause (e) of 
sub-section (2) of section 19;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>p</number>  the manner in 
which the annual list of members of the Institute may be published under 
sub-section (3) of section 19;
 
 

8[***]
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>r</number>  the manner in 
which Regional Council may be constituted under sub-section (2) of section 23 
and the functions thereof;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>s</number>  the conditions 
subject to which foreign qualifications may be recognised under sub-section (2) 
of section 38;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>t</number>  any other 
matter which is required to be, or may be, prescribed under this Act.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> All regulations made 
by the Council under this Act shall be subject to the conditions of previous 
publication and to the approval of the Central Government.
 

9[***]
 
 
















</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>40</number> Rules, 
regulations and notifications to be laid before Parliament.—Every 
rule and every regulation made and every notification issued under this Act 
shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made or issued, before each House 
of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which 
may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, 
before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in 
the rule, regulation or notification, or both Houses agree that the rule, 
regulation or notification should not be made, or issued, the rule, regulation 
or notification shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of 
no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done 
under that rule, regulation or notification.]
 
 


</article><form>
 

The 
Company Secretaries Act, 1980
 

 
 

1[The 
First Schedule
 

[See 
sections 21(3), 21A(3) and 22]
 

Part 
I
 

Professional 
misconduct in relation to company  
secretaries in practice
 

A Company Secretary in practice 
shall be deemed to be guilty of professional misconduct, if he—
 

        
(1)  allows any person to practise in his name as a Company Secretary 
unless such person is also a Company Secretary in practice and is in partnership 
with or employed by him;
 

        
(2)  pays or allows or agrees to pay or allow, directly or indirectly, any 
share, commission or brokerage in the fees or profits of his professional 
business, to any person other than a member of the Institute or a partner or a 
retired partner or the legal representative of a deceased partner, or a member 
of any other professional body or with such other persons having such 
qualifications as may be prescribed, for the purpose of rendering such 
professional services from time to time in or outside India.
 

                  
Explanation.—In 
this item, “partner” includes a person residing outside India with whom a 
Company Secretary in practice has entered into partnership which is not in 
contravention of item (4) of this Part;
 

        
(3)  accepts or agrees to accept, any part of the profits of the 
professional work of a person who is not a member of the Institute:
 

                  
Provided that nothing herein contained shall be construed as prohibiting a 
member from entering into profit sharing or other similar arrangements, 
including receiving any share commission or brokerage in the fees, with a member 
of such professional body or other person having qualifications, as is referred 
to in item (2) of this 
Part;          
 

        
(4)  enters into partnership, in or outside India, with any person other 
than a Company Secretary in practice or such other person who is a member of any 
other profession body having such qualifications as may be prescribed, including 
a resident who but for his residence abroad would be entitled to be registered 
as a member under clause (e) of sub-section (1) of section 4 or whose 
qualifications are recognised by the Central Government or the Council for the 
purpose of permitting such partnerships; 
 

        
(5)  secures, either through the services of a person who is not an 
employee of such company secretary or who is not his partner or by means which 
are not open to a Company Secretary, any professional business:
 

                  
Provided that nothing herein contained shall be construed as prohibiting any 
arrangement permitted in terms of items (2), (3) and (4) of this 
Part;
 

        
(6)  solicits clients or professional work, either directly or indirectly, 
by circular, advertisement, personal communication or interview or by any other 
means:
 

                  
Provided that nothing herein contained shall be construed as preventing or 
prohibiting—
 

                   
(i)  any company secretary from applying or requesting for or inviting or 
securing professional work from another company secretary in practice; 
or
 

                  
(ii)  a member from responding to tenders or enquiries issued by various 
users of professional services or organisations from time to time and securing 
professional work as a consequence;
 

        
(7)  advertises his professional attainments or services, or uses any 
designation or expressions other than Company Secretary on professional 
documents, visiting cards, letterheads or sign boards, unless it be a degree of 
a University established by law in India or recognised by the Central Government 
or a title indicating membership of the Institute  of Company Secretaries 
of India or of any other institution that has been recognised by the Central 
Government or may be recognised by the Council:
 

                  
Provided that a member in practice may advertise through a write up setting out 
the services provided by him or his firm and particulars of his firm subject to 
such guidelines as may be issued by the Council;
 

        
(8)  accepts a position as a Company Secretary in practice previously held 
by another Company Secretary in practice without first communicating with him in 
writing;
 

        
(9)  charges or offers to charge, accepts or offers to accept, in respect 
of any professional employment fees which are based on a percentage of profits 
or which are contingent, upon the findings or results of such employment, except 
as permitted under any regulations made under this Act;
 

      
(10)  engages in any business or occupation other than the profession of 
Company Secretary unless permitted by the Council so to engage:
 

                  
 Provided that nothing contained herein shall disentitle a Company 
Secretary from being a director of a company except as provided in the Companies 
Act 1956 (1 of 1956);
 

      
(11)  allows a person not being a member of the Institute in   
practice, or a member not being his partner of sign on his behalf or on behalf 
of his firm, anything which he is required to certify as a Company Secretary, or 
any other statements relating thereto.
 

Part 
II
 

Professional 
misconduct in relation to members of  
the Institute in service
 

A member of the Institute (other 
than a member in practice) shall be deemed to be guilty of professional 
misconduct, if he, being an employee of any company, firm or person—
 

        
(1)  pays or allows or agrees to pay, directly or indirectly, to any person 
any share in the emoluments of the employment undertaken by him;
 

        
(2)  accepts or agrees to accept any part of fees, profits or gains from a 
lawyer, a Company Secretary or broker engaged by such company, firm or person or 
agent or customer of such company, firm or person by way of commission or 
gratification.
 

Part 
III
 

Professional 
misconduct in relation to members of  
the Institute generally
 

A member of the Institute, whether 
in practice or not, shall be deemed to be guilty of professional misconduct, if 
he—
 

        
(1)  not being a Fellow of the Institute, acts as a Fellow of the 
Institute;
 

        
(2)  does not supply the information called for, or does not comply with 
the requirements asked for, by the Institute, Council or any of its Committees, 
Director (Discipline), Board of Discipline, Disciplinary Committee, Quality 
Review Board or the Appellate Authority;
 

        
(3)  while inviting professional work from another Company Secretary or 
while responding to tenders or enquiries or while advertising through a write 
up, or anything as provided for in terms (6) and (7) of Part I of the Schedule, 
give information knowing it to be false;
 

Part 
IV
 

Other 
misconduct in relation to members of  
the Institute generally
 

A member of the Institute, whether 
in practice or not, shall be deemed to be guilty of other misconduct, 
if—
 

        
(1)  he is held guilty by any civil or criminal court for an offence which 
is punishable with imprisonment for a term not exceeding six months;
 

        
(2)  in the opinion of the Council, he brings disrepute to the professional 
or the institutes as a result of his action whether or not related to his 
professional work.]
 

 
 

—————
 

   1.  Subs. 
by Act 8 of 2006, sec. 32, for the First Schedule (w.e.f. 17-11-2006). The First 
Schedule, before substitution, stood as under: 
 

          
“The First 
Schedule
 

          
[See sections 21(4) and 22]
 

          
Part I
 

          
Professional misconduct in relation to members of the Institute in 
Practice
 

             
A Company Secretary in practice shall be deemed to be guilty of professional 
misconduct, if he—
 

            
(1)  allows any other person to practise in his name as a Company Secretary 
unless such other person is a Company Secretary or is a member of such other 
recognised profession as may be prescribed in this behalf, and is in partnership 
with or employed by him;
 

            
(2)  pays or allows or agrees to pay or allow, directly or indirectly, any 
share, commission or brokerage in the fees or profits of his professional work 
to any person, other than a member of the Institute or a partner or a retired 
partner or the legal representative of a deceased partner.
 

                  
Explanation.—In this item, 
“partner” includes a person residing outside India with whom a Company Secretary 
in practice has entered into partnership which is not in contravention of item 
(4) of this Part;
 

            
(3)  accepts or agrees to accept, except from a member of the institute or 
from any one belonging to any of the recognised professions prescribed for the 
purpose, any part of the profits, fees or other remuneration arising out of the 
work which is not of a professional nature;
 

            
(4)  enters into partnership with any person other than a Company Secretary 
in practice or a member of any other recognised profession as may be prescribed 
or a person resident without India who but for his residence abroad would have 
been entitled to be registered as a member of the Institute under clause (e) of 
sub-section (1) of section 4 or whose qualifications are recognised by the 
Central Government or the Council for the purpose of membership of the Institute 
provided that the Company Secretary shares in the fees or profits of the 
professional work of the partnership both within and without India;
 

            
(5)  secures, either through the services of a person not qualified to be 
his partner or by means which are not open to a Company Secretary, any 
professional work;
 

            
(6)  solicits clients or professional work, either directly or indirectly, 
by circular, advertisement, personal communication or interview or by any other 
means;
 

            
(7)  advertises his professional attainments or services, or uses any 
designation or expression other than Company Secretary on professional 
documents, visiting cards, letter-heads or sign boards, unless it be a degree of 
a University established by law in India or recognised by the Central Government 
or a title indicating membership of the Institute or of any other institution 
that has been recognised by the Central Government or may be recognised by the 
Council;
 

            
(8)  accepts the position of a Company Secretary in practice previously 
held by another Company Secretary in practice without first communicating with 
him in writing;
 

            
(9)  charges or offers to charge, accepts or offers to accept, in respect 
of any professional employment fees which are based on a percentage of profits 
or which are contingent upon the findings or results of such employment, except 
in cases which are permitted under any regulations made under this 
Act;
 

          
(10)  engages in any business or occupation other than the profession of 
Company Secretary unless permitted by the Council so to engage:
 

                      
 Provided that nothing contained herein shall disentitle a Company 
Secretary from being a director of a Company except as provided in the Companies 
Act;
 

          
(11)  accepts a position as Company Secretary in practice previously held 
by some other Company Secretary in practice in such conditions as to constitute 
under-cutting;
 

          
(12)  allows a person not being a member of the Institute in practice or a 
member not being his partner to sign on his behalf or on behalf of his firm 
anything which he is required to certify as a Company Secretary, or any other 
statements related thereto.
 

            
Part II
 

            
Professional misconduct in relation to members of the Institute in 
service
 

             
A member of the Institute (other than a member in practice) shall be deemed to 
be guilty of professional misconduct, if he, being an employee of any company, 
firm or person—
 

            
(1)  pays or allows or agrees to pay, directly or indirectly, to any person 
any share in the emoluments of the employment undertaken by the 
member;
 

            
(2)  accepts or agrees to accept any part of fees, profits or gains from a 
lawyer, a Company Secretary or broker engaged by such company, firm or person or 
agent or customer of such company, firm or person by way of commission or 
gratification;
 

            
(3)  discloses confidential information acquired in the course of his 
employment otherwise than as required by any law for the time being in force or 
as permitted by his employer.
 

            
Part III
 

            
Professional misconduct in relation to members of the Institute in 
generally
 

             
A member of the Institute whether in practice or not shall be deemed to be 
guilty of professional misconduct, if he—
 

            
(1)  includes in any statement, return or form to be submitted to the 
Council any particulars knowing them to be false;
 

            
(2)  not being a Fellow styles himself as a Fellow;
 

            
(3)  does not supply the information called for or does not comply with the 
requirements asked for by the Council or any of its Committees;
 

            
(4)  defalcates or embezzles moneys received in his professional 
capacity.” </form><form>
 

The 
Company Secretaries Act, 1980
 

 
 

1[The 
Second Schedule
 

[See 
sections 21(3), 21B(3) and 22]
 

Part 
I
 

Professional 
misconduct in relation to  
company secretaries in practice
 

A Company Secretary in practice 
shall be deemed to be guilty of professional misconduct, if he—
 

        
(1)  discloses information acquired in the course of his professional 
engagement to any person other than his client so engaging him, without the 
consent of his client, or otherwise than as required by any law for the time 
being in force;
 

        
(2)  certifies or submits in his name, or in the name of his firm, a report 
of an examination of the matters relating to company secretarial practice and 
related statements unless the examination of such statements has been made by 
him or by a partner or an employee in his firm or by another Company Secretary 
in practice;
 

        
(3)  permits his name or the name of his firm to be used in connection with 
any report or statement contingent upon future transactions in a manner which 
may lead to the belief that he vouches for the accuracy of the 
forecast;
 

        
(4)  expresses his opinion on any report or statement given to any business 
or enterprise in which he, his firm or a partner in his firm has a substantial 
interest;         
 

        
(5)  fails to disclose a material fact known to him in his report or 
statement but the disclosure of which is necessary in making such report or 
statement, where he is concerned with such report or statement in a professional 
capacity;
 

        
(6)  fails to report a material misstatement known to him and with which he 
is concerned in a professional capacity;
 

        
(7)  does not exercise due diligence, or is grossly negligent in the 
conduct of his professional duties;
 

        
(8)  fails to obtain sufficient information which is necessary for 
expression of an opinion or its exceptions are sufficiently material to negate 
the expression of an opinion;
 

        
(9)  fails to invite attention to any material departure from the generally 
accepted procedure relating to the secretarial practice;
 

      
(10)  fails to keep moneys of his client other than fees or remuneration or 
money meant to be expended in a separate banking account or to use such moneys 
for purposes for which they are intended within a reasonable time.
 

Part 
II
 

Professional 
misconduct in relation to members of  
the Institute generally 
 

A member of the Institute, whether 
in practice or not, shall be deemed to be guilty of professional misconduct, if 
he—
 

        
(1)  contravenes any of the provisions of this Act or the regulations made 
thereunder or any guidelines issued by the Council;
 

        
(2)  being an employee of any company, firm or person, discloses 
confidential information acquired in the course of his employment, except as and 
when required by any law for the time being in force or except as permitted by 
the employer;
 

        
(3)  includes in any information, statement, return or form to be submitted 
to the Institute, Council or any of its Committees, Director (Discipline), Board 
of Discipline, Disciplinary Committee, Quality Review Board or the Appellate 
Authority any particulars knowing them to be false;
 

        
(4)  defalcates or embezzles moneys received in his professional 
capacity.
 

Part 
III
 

Other 
misconduct in relation to members of  
the Institute generally
 

A member of the Institute, whether 
in practice or not, shall be deemed to be guilty of other misconduct, if he is 
held guilty by any civil or criminal court for an offence which is punishable 
with imprisonment for a term exceeding six months.]
 

 
 

—————
 


1.  Subs. by Act 8 of 2006, 
sec. 32, for the Second Schedule (w.e.f. 17-11-2006). The Second Schedule, 
before substitution, stood as under:
 

            
“The Second Schedule
 

            
[See sections 21(5) and 22]
 

Part 
I
 

            
Professional misconduct in relation to members of the Institute in 
 
            practice 
requiring action by a High Court
 

             
A Company Secretary in practice shall be deemed to be guilty of professional 
misconduct, if he—
 

            
(1)  discloses information acquired in the course of his professional 
engagement to any person other than the client so engaging him, without the 
consent of such client or otherwise than as required by any law for the time 
being in force;
 

            
(2)  certifies or submits in his name or in the name of his firm a report 
of an examination of the matters relating to Company Secretarial practice and 
related statements unless the examination of such statements has been made by 
him or by a partner or any employee in his firm or by another Company Secretary 
in practice;
 

            
(3)  permits his name or the name of his firm to be used in connection with 
any report or statement contingent upon future transactions in a manner which 
may lead to the belief that he vouches for the accuracy of the 
forecast;
 

            
(4)  expresses his opinion on any report or statement given to any business 
enterprise in which he, his firm or a partner in his firm has a substantial 
interest, unless he discloses the interest also in his report;
 

            
(5)  deliberately aids in or abets the concealment in his report or 
statement of a material fact known to him although the disclosure of which is 
necessary to make such statement not misleading;
 

            
(6)  fails to disclose in his report a material mis-statement known to him 
and with which he is concerned in a professional capacity;
 

            
(7)  is grossly negligent in the conduct of his professional 
duties;
 

            
(8)  fails to obtain sufficient information to warrant the expression of an 
opinion or makes exceptions which are sufficiently material to negate the 
expression of an opinion;
 

            
(9)  fails to invite attention to any material departure from the generally 
accepted procedure relating to the secretarial practice;
 

          
(10)  fails to keep moneys of his client in a separate banking account or 
to use such moneys for purposes for which they are intended.
 

            
Part II
 

            
Professional misconduct in relation to members of the Institute 
 
            generally 
requiring action by a High Court
 

             
A member of the Institute, whether in practice or not, shall be deemed to be 
guilty of professional misconduct, if he—
 

            
(1)  contravenes any of the provisions of this Act or the regulations made 
thereunder;
 

            
(2)  is guilty of such other act or omission as may be specified by the 
Council in this behalf, by notification in the Official Gazette.”
 

 
 

 </form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>  Section 29A ins. 
by Act 8 of 2006, sec. 25 (w.e.f. 17-11-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>  Section 29B ins. 
by Act 8 of 2006, sec. 25 (w.e.f. 17-11-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>  Section 29C ins. 
by Act 8 of 2006, sec. 25 (w.e.f. 17-11-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>  Section 29D ins. 
by Act 8 of 2006, sec. 25 (w.e.f. 17-11-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>  Section 30, before 
repeal, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>  Subs. by Act 8 of 
2006, sec. 27, for section 36 (w.e.f. 17-11-2006). Section 36, before 
substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>  Ins. by Act 8 of 
2006, sec. 28 (w.e.f. 17-11-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>  Ins. by Act 8 of 
2006, sec. 29 (w.e.f. 8-8-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>  Subs. by Act 8 of 
2006, sec. 30, for “items (1), (3)” (w.e.f. 8-8-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>  Ins. by Act 8 of 
2006, sec. 31 (w.e.f. 8-8-2006).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>