<act> 
 The Foreign exchange Management (Encashment of Draft, Cheque, 
Instrument and payment of  
interest) rules, 20001
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Foreign Exchange Management (Encashment of Draft, 
Cheque, Instrument and Payment of Interest) Rules, 2000.
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force 
on the 1st day of June, 2000.
  


</section></article> 
 The Foreign exchange Management (Encashment of Draft, Cheque, 
Instrument and payment of  
interest) rules, 2000
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>         <number>a</number>  “Act” means the Foreign Exchange Management 
Act, 1999 (42 of 1999);
 </section><section>         <number>b</number>  “Adjudicating Authority” means an officer 
appointed by the Central Government under sub-section (1) of section 16 of the 
Act;
 </section><section>         <number>c</number>  “authorised person” means a person as defined 
in clause (c) of section 2 of the Act;
 </section><section>         <number>d</number>  “cheque” includes a traveller’s cheque;
 </section><section>         <number>e</number>  “investigation” means an investigation as 
envisaged under section 37 of the Act;
 </section><section>          <number>f</number>  “Special Director (Appeals)” means Special 
Director (Appeals) appointed by the Central Government under sub-section (1) of 
section 17 of the Act;
 </section><section>         <number>g</number>  “Appellate Tribunal” means the Appellate 
Tribunal for Foreign Exchange established under section 18 of the Act.
</section></article> 
 The Foreign exchange Management (Encashment of Draft, Cheque, 
Instrument and payment of  
interest) rules, 2000
  
 <article><number>3</number> Delivery of draft, cheque 
and other instrument for encashment.—Where 
investigation referred to in section 37 is being taken up into any alleged 
contravention of any provision of the Act or of any rule, regulation, direction 
or order, or violation of any condition subject to which Reserve Bank of India 
gives authorisation, made thereunder, and any draft, cheque or other instrument 
relevant for such investigation such officer shall cause such draft, cheque or 
other instrument to be delivered for encashment to Reserve Bank of India or an 
authorised person as the officer may specify.
</article> 
 The Foreign exchange Management (Encashment of Draft, Cheque, 
Instrument and payment of  
interest) rules, 2000
  
 <article><number>4</number> Encashment of draft, 
cheque or other instrument.—The 
Reserve Bank of India or an authorised person shall take steps without delay for 
encashing the draft, cheque or other instrument and, on such encashment, shall 
credit the proceeds realised (less any commission and expenses incurred for such 
encashment) to a separate account in the name of the Directorate of Enforcement.
</article> 
 The Foreign exchange Management (Encashment of Draft, Cheque, 
Instrument and payment of  
interest) rules, 2000
  
 <article><number>5</number> Opening an account.—Where 
investigation referred to in section 37 of the Act is being taken up into any 
alleged contravention of any provision of the Act or any rule, regulation or 
direction or order, or violation of any condition subject to which Reserve Bank 
of India gives authorisation, the Indian currency relevant to such investigation 
is in the custody of an officer of Enforcement Directorate, then, such officer 
shall deposit the Indian currency in a nationalised bank to a separate account 
in the name of Directorate of Enforcement.
</article> 
 The Foreign exchange Management (Encashment of Draft, Cheque, 
Instrument and payment of  
interest) rules, 2000
  
 <article><number>6</number> Indemnity.—The 
Central Government shall indemnify the Reserve Bank of India or an authorised 
person against any liability which the Reserve Bank of India or an authorised 
person may incur by reason of, or in connection with, the encashment of the 
draft, cheque or other instrument delivered to it.
</article> 
 The Foreign exchange Management (Encashment of Draft, Cheque, 
Instrument and payment of  
interest) rules, 2000
  
 <article><number>7</number> Direction for payment of 
the proceeds.—
<section><number>i</number> Where it has been 
found during the course of investigation or adjudication that, any draft, cheque 
or other instrument is not relevant for such investigation, the Investigating 
Officer or the Adjudicating Authority, as the case may be, pass such order that 
the person to whom the proceeds of such draft, cheque or other instrument may be 
paid.
 </section><section><number>ii</number> Where it has been found 
during the course of appeal before the Special Director (Appeals) or the 
Appellate Tribunal or the High Court, as the case may be, that, any draft, 
cheque or other instrument is not considered relevant for such appeal, then, the 
Special Director (Appeals) or the Appellate Tribunal or High Court, as the case 
may be, pass such order specifying the person to whom the proceeds of the draft, 
cheque or other instruments may be paid.
</section></article> 
 The Foreign exchange Management (Encashment of Draft, Cheque, 
Instrument and payment of  
interest) rules, 2000
  
 <article><number>8</number> Payment of interest on the seized Indian currency.—
<section><number>i</number> 
Where it is found after completion of the investigation that the Indian currency 
seized under section 37 of the Act is not involved in the contravention and is 
to be returned, the same shall be returned to such persons together with 
interest at the rate of 6% per annum from the date of seizure till the date of 
payment.
 </section><section><number>ii</number> Where it has been found during the course of adjudication 
that the seized Indian currency is not relevant for such adjudication, the 
Adjudicating Authority may pass such order returning such Indian currency 
together with interest at the rate of 6% per annum to such person.
</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>