<act><title>

THE 
BIOLOGICAL DIVERSITY ACT, 
    2002</title> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Biological Diversity Act, 2002.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    extends to the whole of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It 
    shall come into force on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as 
    the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint 
    :
 

    Provided that different dates1 may 
    be appointed for different provisions of this Act and any reference in any 
    such provision to the commencement of this Act shall be construed as a 
    reference to the coming into force of that provision.




  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 
    BIOLOGICAL DIVERSITY ACT, 
    2002
 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>   “benefit 
    claimers” means the conservers of biological resources, their by-products, 
    creators and holders of knowledge and information relating to the use of 
    such biological resources, innovations and practices associated with such 
    use and application;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   
    “biological diversity” means the variability among living organisms from all 
    sources and the ecological complexes of which they are part and includes 
    diversity within species or between species and of eco-systems;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   
    “biological resources” means plants, animals and micro-organisms or parts 
    thereof, their genetic material and by-products (excluding value added 
    products) with actual or potential use or value but does not include human 
    genetic material;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   “bio-survey and bio-utilisation” means survey or collection of 
    species, sub-­species, genes, components and extracts of biological resource 
    for any purpose and includes characterisation, inventorisation and bioassay;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   
    “Chairperson” means the Chairperson of the National Biodiversity Authority 
    or, as the case may be, of the State Biodiversity Board;
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   “commercial utilization” means end user of biological resources for 
    commercial utilization such as drugs, industrial enzymes, food flavours, 
    fragrance, cosmetics, emulsifiers, oleoresins, colours, extracts and genes 
    used for improving crops and livestock through genetic intervention, but 
    does not include conventional breeding or traditional practices in use in 
    any agriculture,  horticulture, poultry, dairy farming, animal husbandry or 
    bee keeping;
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>   
    “fair and equitable benefit sharing” means sharing of benefits as determined 
    by the National Biodiversity Authority under section 21;
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>   “local bodies” means Panchayats and Municipalities, by whatever name 
    called, within the meaning of clause (1) of article 243B and clause (1) of 
    article 243Q of the Constitution and in the absence of any Panchayats or 
    Municipalities, institutions of self-government constituted under any other 
    provision of the Constitution or any Central Act or State Act;
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>   “member” means member of the National Biodiversity Authority or a 
    State Biodiversity Board and includes the Chairperson;
 </section><section>
<number>j</number>   
    “National Biodiversity Authority” means the National Biodiversity Authority 
    established under section 8;
 </section><section>
<number>k</number>   
    “prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act;  

 </section><section>
<number>l</number>   
    “regulations” means regulations made under this Act;
 </section><section>
<number>m</number>   
    “research” means study or systematic investigation of any biological 
    resource or technological application, that uses biological systems, living 
    organisms or derivatives thereof to make or modify products or processes for 
    any use;
 </section><section>
<number>n</number>   
    “State Biodiversity Board” means the State Biodiversity Board established 
    under section 22;
 </section><section>
<number>o</number>   
    “sustainable use” means the use of components of biological diversity in 
    such manner and at such rate that does not lead to the long-term decline of 
    the biological diversity thereby maintaining its potential to meet the needs 
    and aspirations of present and future generations.
 </section><section>
<number>p</number>   
    “value added products” means products which may contain portions or extracts 
    of plants and animals in unrecognizable and physically inseparable form.
 


 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Certain persons not to undertake Biodiversity related activities without 
    approval of National Biodiversity Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No person referred to in sub-section (2) shall without previous approval of 
    the National Biodiversity Authority, obtain any biological resource 
    occurring in India or knowledge associated thereto for research or for 
    commercial utilisation or for bio-survey and bio-utilisation.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The persons who shall be required to take the approval of the National 
    Biodiversity Authority under sub-section (1) are the following, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   a person 
    who is not a citizen of India;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   a citizen 
    of India, who is a non-resident as defined in clause (30) of section 2 of 
    the Income-tax Act, 1961 (43 of 1961);
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   a body 
    corporate, association or organisation—
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   not 
    incorporated or registered in India; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   
    incorporated or registered in India under any law for the time being in 
    force which has any non-Indian participation in its share capital or 
    management.
 





  

 
  
 

  


</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Results of research not to be transferred to certain persons without 
    approval of National Biodiversity Authority.—No 
    person shall, without the previous approval of the National Biodiversity 
    Authority, transfer the results of any research relating to any biological 
    resources occurring in, or obtained from India for monetary consideration or 
    otherwise to any person who is not a citizen of India or citizen of India 
    who is non-resident as defined in clause (30) of section 2 of the Income-tax 
    Act, 1961 (43 of 1961) or a body corporate or organisation which is not 
    registered or incorporated in India or which has any non-Indian 
    participation in its share capital or management.
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section, “transfer” does not include publication of 
    research papers or dissemination of knowledge in any seminar or workshop, if 
    such publication is as per the guidelines issued by the Central Government.
 





  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Sections 3 and 4 not to apply to certain collaborative research projects.—

<section><number>1</number> The provisions of sections 3 and 4 shall not apply to collaborative 
    research projects involving transfer or exchange of biological resources or 
    information relating thereto between institutions, including Government 
    sponsored institutions of India, and such institutions in other countries, 
    if such collaborative research projects satisfy the conditions specified in 
    sub-section (3).
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    All collaborative research projects, other than those referred to in 
    sub-section (1) which are based on agreements concluded before the 
    commencement of this Act and in force shall, to the extent the provisions of 
    agreement are inconsistent with the provisions of this Act or any guidelines 
    issued under clause (a) of sub-section (3), be void.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    For the purposes of sub-section (1), collaborative research projects shall,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   conform 
    to the policy guidelines issued by the Central Government in this behalf;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   be 
    approved by the Central Government.
 


 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Application for intellectual property rights not to be made without approval 
    of National Biodiversity Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No person shall apply for any intellectual property right, by whatever name 
    called, in or outside India for any invention based on any research or 
    information on a biological resource obtained from India without obtaining 
    the previous approval of the National Biodiversity Authority before making 
    such application:
 

    Provided that if a person applies for a patent, permission of the 
    National Biodiversity Authority may be obtained after the acceptance of the 
    patent but before the sealing of the patent by the patent authority 
    concerned:
 

    Provided further that the National Biodiversity Authority shall dispose of 
    the application for permission made to it within a period of ninety days 
    from the date of receipt thereof.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The National Biodiversity Authority may, while granting the approval under 
    this section, impose benefit sharing fee or royalty or both or impose 
    conditions including the sharing of financial benefits arising out of the 
    commercial utilisation of such rights.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    The provisions of this section shall not apply to any person making an 
    application for any right under any law relating to protection of plant 
    varieties enacted by Parliament.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Where any right is granted under law referred to in sub-section (3), the 
    concerned authority granting such right shall endorse a copy of such 
    document granting the right to the National Biodiversity Authority.
 





 


 
 

 

 



</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Prior intimation to State Biodiversity Board for obtaining biological 
    resource for certain purposes.—No 
    person, who is a citizen of India or a body corporate, association or 
    organisation which is registered in India, shall obtain any biological 
    resource for commercial utilisation, or bio-survey and bio-utilisation for 
    commercial utilisation except after giving prior intimation to the State 
    Biodiversity Board concerned:
 

    Provided that the provisions of this section shall not apply to the 
    local people and communities of the area, including growers and cultivators 
    of biodiversity, and vaids and hakims, who have been 
    practising indigenous medicine.
 


  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Establishment of National Biodiversity Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    With effect from such date<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> as 
    the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    appoint, there shall be established by the Central Government  for the 
    purposes of this Act, a body to be called the National Biodiversity 
    Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The National Biodiversity Authority shall be a body corporate by the name 
    aforesaid, having perpetual succession and a common seal, with power to 
    acquire, hold and dispose of property, both movable and immovable, and to 
    contract, and shall by the said name sue and be sued.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    The head office of the National Biodiversity Authority shall be at Chennai 
    and the National Biodiversity Authority may, with the previous approval of 
    the Central Government, establish offices at other places in India.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    The National Biodiversity Authority shall consist of the following Members, 
    namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   a 
    Chairperson, who shall be an eminent person having adequate knowledge and 
    experience in the conservation and sustainable use of biological diversity 
    and in matters relating to equitable sharing of benefits, to be appointed by 
    the Central Government;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   three ex 
    officio members to be appointed by the Central Government, one 
    representing the Ministry with Tribal Affairs and two representing the 
    Ministry dealing with Environment and Forests of whom one shall be the 
    Additional Director General of Forests or the Director General of Forests;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   seven ex 
    officio members to be appointed by the Central Government to represent 
    respectively the Ministries of the Central Government dealing with—
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   Agricultural 
    Research and Education;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   
    Biotechnology;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>   Ocean 
    Development;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iv</number>   
    Agriculture and Cooperation;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>v</number>   Indian 
    Systems of Medicine and Homeopathy;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>vi</number>   Science 
    and Technology;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>vii</number>   
    Scientific and Industrial Research;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   five 
    non-official members to be appointed from amongst specialists and scientists 
    having special knowledge of, or experience in, matters relating to 
    conservation of biological diversity, sustainable use of biological 
    resources and equitable sharing of benefits arising out of the use of 
    biological resources, representatives of industry, conservers, creators and 
    knowledge-holders of biological resources.
 






 


 
 

 

 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Conditions of service of Chairperson and Members.—The 
    term of office and conditions of service of the Chairperson and the other 
    members other than ex officio members of National Biodiversity 
    Authority shall be such as may be prescribed by the Central Government.
 


  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Chairperson to be Chief Executive of National Biodiversity Authority.—The 
    Chairperson shall be the Chief Executive of the National Biodiversity 
    Authority and shall exercise such powers and perform such duties, as may be 
    prescribed.
 


  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Removal of members.—The 
    Central Government may remove from the National Biodiversity Authority any 
    member who, in its opinion has—
 <section>
<number>a</number>   been 
    adjudged as an insolvent; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   been 
    convicted of an offence which involves moral turpitude; or
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   become 
    physically or mentally incapable of acting as a member; or
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   so abused 
    his position as to render his continuance in office detrimental to the 
    public interest; or
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   acquired 
    such financial or other interest as is likely to affect prejudicially his 
    functions as a member.
 

 


 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Meetings of National Biodiversity Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The National Biodiversity Authority shall meet at such time and place and 
    shall observe such rules of procedure in regard to the transaction of 
    business at its meetings (including the quorum at its meetings) as may be 
    prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The Chairperson of the National Biodiversity Authority shall preside at the 
    meetings of the National Biodiversity Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If 
    for any reason the Chairperson is unable to attend any meeting of the 
    National Biodiversity Authority, any member of the National Biodiversity 
    Authority chosen by the members present at the meeting shall preside at the 
    meeting.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    All questions which come before any meeting of the National Biodiversity 
    Authority shall be decided by a majority of the votes of the members present 
    and voting and in the event of equality of votes, the Chairperson or, in his 
    absence, the person presiding, shall have and exercise a second or casting 
    vote.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> 
    Every member who is in any way, whether directly, indirectly or personally, 
    concerned or interested in a matter to be decided at the meeting shall 
    disclose the nature of his concern or interest and after such disclosure, 
    the member concerned or interested shall not attend that meeting.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> No 
    act or proceeding of the National Biodiversity Authority shall be 
    invalidated merely by reason of—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   any 
    vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution of, the National Biodiversity 
    Authority; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   any 
    defect in the appointment of a person acting as a member; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   any 
    irregularity in the procedure of the National Biodiversity Authority not 
    affecting the merits of the case.
 

 


 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Committees of National Biodiversity Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The National Biodiversity Authority may constitute a committee to deal with 
    agro-biodiversity.
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this sub-section “agro-biodiversity” means biological 
    diversity of agriculture related species and their wild relatives.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Without prejudice to the provisions of sub-section (1), the National 
    Biodiversity Authority may constitute such number of committees as it deems 
    fit for the efficient discharge of its duties and performance of its 
    functions under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A 
    committee constituted under this section, shall co-opt such number of 
    persons, who are not members of the National Biodiversity Authority, as it 
    may think fit and the persons so co-opted shall have the right to attend the 
    meetings of the committee and take part in its proceedings but shall not 
    have the right to vote.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    The persons appointed as members of the committee under sub-section (2) 
    shall be entitled to receive such allowances or fees for attending the 
    meetings of the committee as may be fixed by the Central Government.
 

 


  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Officers and employees of National Biodiversity Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The National Biodiversity Authority may appoint such officers and other 
    employees as it considers necessary for the efficient discharge of its 
    functions under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The terms and conditions of service of such officers and other employees of 
    the National Biodiversity Authority shall be such as may be specified by 
    regulations.
 

 


  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Authentication of orders and decisions of National Biodiversity Authority.—
All orders and decisions of the National Biodiversity Authority shall be 
    authenticated by the signature of the Chairperson or any other member 
    authorised by the National Biodiversity Authority in this behalf and all 
    other instruments executed by the National Biodiversity Authority shall be 
    authenticated by the signature of an officer of the National Biodiversity 
    Authority authorised by it in this behalf.
 


  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Delegation of powers.—The 
    National Biodiversity Authority may, by general or special order in writing, 
    delegate to any member, officer of the National Biodiversity Authority or 
    any other person subject to such conditions, if any, as may be specified in 
    the order, such of the powers and functions under this Act (except the power 
    to prefer an appeal under section 50 and the power to make regulations under 
    section 64) as it may deem necessary.
 


  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Expenses of National Biodiversity Authority to be defrayed out of the 
    Consolidated Fund of India.—The 
    salaries and allowances payable to the members and the administrative 
    expenses of the National Biodiversity Authority including salaries, 
    allowances and pension payable to, or in respect of the officers and other 
    employees of the National Biodiversity Authority shall be defrayed out of 
    the Consolidated Fund of India.
 


  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>18</number>
Functions and powers of National Biodiversity Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> It shall 
    be the duty of the National Biodiversity Authority to regulate activities 
    referred to in sections 3, 4 and 6 and by regulations issue guidelines for 
    access  to biological resources and for fair and equitable benefit sharing.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The National Biodiversity Authority may grant approval for undertaking any 
    activity referred to in sections 3, 4 and 6.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    The National Biodiversity Authority may—
 <subsection>
     <number>a</number>   advise the 
    Central Government on matters relating to the conservation of biodiversity, 
    sustainable use of its components and equitable sharing of benefits arising 
    out of the utilisation of biological resources;
 </subsection><subsection>
     <number>b</number>   advise the 
    State Governments in the selection of areas of biodiversity, importance to 
    be notified under sub-section (1) of section 37  as heritage sites and 
    measures for the management of such heritage sites;
 </subsection><subsection>
     <number>c</number>   perform such 
    other functions as may be necessary to carry out the provisions of this Act.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    The National Biodiversity Authority may, on behalf of the Central 
    Government, take any measures necessary to oppose the grant of intellectual 
    property rights in any country outside India on any biological resource 
    obtained from India or knowledge associated with such biological resource 
    which is derived from India.
 

 


  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Approval by National Biodiversity Authority for undertaking certain 
    activities.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person referred to in sub-section (2) of section 3 who intends to obtain 
    any biological resource occurring in India or knowledge associated thereto 
    for research or for commercial utilisation or for bio-survey and bio-utilisation 
    or transfer the results of any research relating to biological resources 
    occurring in, or obtained from India, shall make application in such form 
    and payment of such fees as may be prescribed, to the National Biodiversity 
    Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Any person who intends to apply for a patent or any other form of 
    intellectual property protection whether in India or outside India referred 
    to in sub-section (1) of section 6, may make an application in such form and 
    in such manner as may be prescribed to the National Biodiversity Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On 
    receipt of an application under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2), the 
    National Biodiversity Authority may, after making such enquiries as it may 
    deem fit and if necessary after consulting an expert committee constituted 
    for this purpose, by order, grant approval subject to any regulations made 
    in this behalf and subject to such terms and conditions as it may deem fit, 
    including the imposition of charges by way of royalty or for reasons to be 
    recorded in writing, reject the application:
 

    Provided that no such order for rejection shall be made without 
    giving an opportunity of being heard to the person affected.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    The National Biodiversity Authority shall give public notice of every 
    approval granted by it under this section.
 





  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>20</number> 
    Transfer of biological resource or knowledge.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No person who has been granted approval under section 19 shall transfer any 
    biological resource or knowledge associated thereto which is the subject 
    matter of the said approval except with the permission of the National 
    Biodiversity Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Any person who intends to transfer any biological resource or knowledge 
    associated thereto referred to in sub-section (1) shall make an application 
    in such form and in such manner as may be prescribed to the National 
    Biodiversity Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On 
    receipt of an application under sub-section (2), the National Biodiversity 
    Authority may, after making such enquiries as it may deem fit and if 
    necessary after consulting an expert committee constituted for this purpose, 
    by order, grant approval subject to such terms and conditions as it may deem 
    fit, including the imposition of charges by way of royalty or for reasons to 
    be recorded in writing, reject the application:
 

    Provided that no such order for rejection shall be made without 
    giving an opportunity of being heard to the person affected.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    The National Biodiversity Authority shall give public notice of every 
    approval granted by it under this section.
 


  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>21</number> 
    Determination of equitable benefit sharing by National Biodiversity 
    Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The National Biodiversity Authority shall while granting approvals under 
    section 19 or section 20 ensure that the terms and conditions subject to 
    which approval is granted secures equitable sharing of benefits arising out 
    of the use of accessed biological resources, their by-products, innovations 
    and practices associated with their use and applications and knowledge 
    relating thereto in accordance with mutually agreed terms and conditions 
    between the person applying for such approval, local bodies concerned and 
    the benefit claimers.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The National Biodiversity Authority shall, subject to any regulations made 
    in this behalf, determine the benefit sharing which shall be given effect in 
    all or any of the following manner, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   grant of 
    joint ownership of intellectual property rights to the National Biodiversity 
    Authority, or where benefit claimers are identified, to such benefit 
    claimers;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   transfer 
    of technology;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   location 
    of production, research and development units in such areas which will 
    facilitate better living standards to the benefit claimers;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   association of 
    Indian scientists, benefit claimers and the local people with research and 
    development in biological resources and bio-survey and bio-utilisation;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   setting 
    up of venture capital fund for aiding the cause of benefit claimers;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   payment 
    of monetary compensation and other non-monetary benefits to the benefit 
    claimers as the National Biodiversity Authority may deem fit.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Where any amount of money is ordered by way of benefit sharing, the National 
    Biodiversity Authority may direct the amount to be deposited in the National 
    Biodiversity Fund:
 

    Provided that where biological resource or knowledge was a result of 
    access from specific individual or group of individuals or organisations, 
    the National Biodiversity Authority may direct that the amount shall be paid 
    directly to such individual or group of individuals or organizations in 
    accordance with the terms of any agreement and in such manner as it deems 
    fit.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    For the purposes of this section, the National Biodiversity Authority shall, 
    in consultation with the Central Government, by regulations, frame 
    guidelines.
 


 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Establishment of State Biodiversity Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    With effect from such date as the State Government may, by notification in 
    the Official Gazette, appoint in this behalf, there shall be established by 
    that Government for the purposes of this Act, a Board for the State to be 
    known as the ... (name of the State) Biodiversity Board.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, no State Biodiversity 
    Board shall be constituted for a Union territory and in relation to a Union 
    territory, the National Biodiversity Authority shall exercise the powers and 
    perform the functions of a State Biodiversity Board for that Union 
    territory:
 

    Provided that in relation to any Union territory, the National 
    Biodiversity Authority may delegate all or any of its powers or functions 
    under this sub-section to such person or group of persons as the Central 
    Government may specify.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    The Board shall be a body corporate by the name aforesaid, having perpetual 
    succession and a common seal, with power to acquire, hold and dispose of 
    property, both movable and immovable, and to contract, and shall by the said 
    name sue and be sued.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    The Board shall consist of the following members, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   a 
    Chairperson who shall be an eminent person having adequate knowledge and 
    experience in the conservation and sustainable use of biological diversity 
    and in matters relating to equitable sharing of benefits, to be appointed by 
    the State Government;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   not more than 
    five ex officio members to be appointed by the State Government to 
    represent the concerned Departments of the State Government;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   not more 
    than five members to be appointed from amongst experts in matters relating 
    to conservation of biological diversity, sustainable use of biological 
    resources and equitable sharing of benefits arising out of the use of 
    biological resources.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> 
    The head office of the State Biodiversity Board shall be at such place as 
    the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify.
 


 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>23</number> 
    Functions of State Biodiversity Board.—The 
    functions of the State Biodiversity Board shall be to—
 <section>
     <number>a</number>   advise the 
    State Government, subject to any guidelines issued by the Central 
    Government, on matters relating to the conservation of biodiversity, 
    sustainable use of its components and equitable sharing of the benefits 
    arising out of the utilisation of biological resources;
 </section><section>
     <number>b</number>   regulate by 
    granting of approvals or otherwise requests for commercial utilization or 
    bio-survey and bio-utilisation of any biological resource by Indians;
 </section><section>
     <number>c</number>   perform such 
    other functions as may be necessary to carry out the provisions of this Act 
    or as may be prescribed by the State Government.
 


  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Power of State Biodiversity Board to restrict certain activities violating 
    the objectives of conservation etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any citizen of India or a body corporate, organisation or association 
    registered in India intending to undertake any activity referred to in 
    section 7 shall give prior intimation in such form as may be prescribed by 
    the State Government to the State Biodiversity Board.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On 
    receipt of an intimation under sub-section (1), the State Biodiversity Board 
    may, in consultation with the local bodies concerned and after making such 
    enquiries as it may deem fit, by order, prohibit or restrict any such 
    activity if it is of opinion that such activity is detrimental or contrary 
    to the objectives of conservation and sustainable use of biodiversity or 
    equitable sharing of benefits arising out of such activity:
 

    Provided that no such order shall be made without giving an 
    opportunity of being heard to the person affected.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Any information given in the form referred to in sub-section (1) for prior 
    intimation shall be kept confidential and shall not be disclosed, either 
    intentionally or unintentionally, to any person not concerned thereto.
 


  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Provisions of sections 9 to 17 to apply with modifications to State 
    Biodiversity Board.—The 
    provisions of sections 9 to 17 shall apply to a State Biodiversity Board and 
    shall have effect subject to the following modifications, namely:—
 <section>
     <number>a</number>   references to 
    the Central Government shall be construed as references to the State 
    Government;
 </section><section>
     <number>b</number>   references to 
    the National Biodiversity Authority shall be construed as references to the 
    State Biodiversity Board;
 </section><section>
     <number>c</number>   reference to 
    the Consolidated Fund of India shall be construed as reference to the 
    Consolidated Fund of the State.
 


  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>26</number> 
    Grants or Loans by the Central Government.—The 
    Central Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in 
    this behalf, pay to the National Biodiversity Authority by way of grants or 
    loans such sums of money as the Central Government may think fit for being 
    utilised for the purposes of this Act.  
 


  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>27</number> 
    Constitution of National Biodiversity Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    There shall be constituted a Fund to be called the National Biodiversity 
    Fund and there shall be credited thereto—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   any 
    grants and loans made to the National Biodiversity Authority under section 
    26;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   all 
    charges and royalties received by the National Biodiversity Authority under 
    this Act; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   all sums 
    received by the National Biodiversity Authority from such other sources as 
    may be decided upon by the Central Government.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The Fund shall be applied for—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   channelling 
    benefits to the benefit claimers;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   
    conservation and promotion of biological resources and development of areas 
    from where such biological resources or knowledge associated thereto has 
    been accessed;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   
    socio-economic development of areas referred to in clause (b) in 
    consultation with the local bodies concerned.
 

 


 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>28</number> 
    Annual report of National Biodiversity Authority.—The 
    National Biodiversity Authority shall prepare, in such form and at such time 
    each financial year as may be prescribed, its annual report, giving a full 
    account of its activities during the previous financial year and furnish, to 
    the Central Government, before such date as may be prescribed, its audited 
    copy of accounts together with auditors’ report thereon.
 

 


  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>29</number> 
    Budget, accounts and audit.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The National Biodiversity Authority shall prepare a budget, maintain proper 
    accounts and other relevant records (including the accounts and other 
    relevant records of the National Biodiversity Fund) and prepare an annual 
    statement of account in such form as may be prescribed by the Central 
    Government in consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor-General of 
    India.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The accounts of the National Biodiversity Authority shall be audited by the 
    Comptroller and Auditor-General of India at such intervals as may be 
    specified by him and any expenditure incurred in connection with such audit 
    shall be payable by the National Biodiversity Authority to the Comptroller 
    and Auditor-General of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    The Comptroller and Auditor-General of India and any other person appointed 
    by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the National 
    Biodiversity Authority shall have the same rights and privileges and 
    authority in connection with such audit as the Comptroller and 
    Auditor-General generally has in connection with the audit of the Government 
    accounts and, in particular, shall have the right to demand the production 
    of books, accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and to 
    inspect any of the offices of the National Biodiversity Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    The accounts of the National Biodiversity Authority as certified by the 
    Comptroller and Auditor-General of India or any other person appointed by 
    him in this behalf together with the audit report thereon shall be forwarded 
    annually to the Central Government.
 

 

 


  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>30</number> 
    Annual report to be laid before Parliament.—The 
    Central Government shall cause the annual report and auditor’s report to be 
    laid, as soon as may be after they are received, before each House of 
    Parliament.
 

 


  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>31</number> 
    Grant of money by State Government to State Biodiversity Board.—
The State Government may, after due appropriation made by the State 
    Legislature by law in this behalf, pay to the State Biodiversity Board by 
    way of grants or loans such sums of money as the State Government may think 
    fit for being utilized for the purposes of this Act.
 

 


  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>32</number> 
    Constitution of State Biodiversity Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    There shall be constituted a Fund to be called the State Biodiversity Fund 
    and there shall be credited thereto—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   any grants and 
    loans made to the State Biodiversity Board under 
    section 31;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   any 
    grants or loans made by the National Biodiversity Authority;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   all sums 
    received by the State Biodiversity Board from such other sources as may be 
    decided upon by the State Government.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The State Biodiversity Fund shall be 
    applied for—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the 
    management and conservation of heritage sites;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   compensating 
    or rehabilitating any section of the people economically affected by 
    notification under sub-section (1) of  
    section 37;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   
    conservation and promotion of biological resources;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   
    socio-economic development of areas from where such biological resources or 
    knowledge associated thereto has been accessed subject to any order made 
    under section 24, in consultation with the local bodies concerned;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   meeting 
    the expenses incurred for purposes authorized by this Act.
 

 

 


 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>33</number> 
    Annual report of State Biodiversity Board.—The 
    State Biodiversity Board shall prepare, in such form and at such time in 
    each financial year as may be prescribed, its annual report, giving a full 
    account of its activities during the previous financial year, and submit a 
    copy thereof to the State Government.
 

 

 


  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>34</number> 
    Audit of accounts of State Biodiversity Board.—The 
    accounts of the State Biodiversity Board shall be maintained and audited in 
    such manner as may, in consultation with the Accountant-General of the 
    State, be prescribed and the State Biodiversity Board shall furnish, to the 
    State Government, before such date as may be prescribed, its audited copy of 
    accounts together with auditors’ report thereon.
 

 

 

 


  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>35</number> 
    Annual report of State Biodiversity Board to be laid before State 
    Legislature.—The 
    State Government shall cause the annual report and auditor’s report to be 
    laid, as soon as may be after they are received, before the House of State 
    Legislature.
 

 

 

 

 


  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>36</number> 
    Central Government to develop National strategies, plans, etc., for 
    conservation, etc., of biological diversity.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government shall develop national strategies, plans, programmes 
    for the conservation and promotion and sustainable use of biological 
    diversity including measures for identification and monitoring of areas rich 
    in biological resources, promotion of in situ and ex situ 
    conservation of biological resources, incentives for research, training and 
    public education to increase awareness with respect to biodiversity.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where the Central Government has reason to believe that any area rich in 
    biological diversity, biological resources and their habitats is being 
    threatened by overuse, abuse or neglect it shall issue directives to the 
    concerned State Government to take immediate ameliorative measures, offering 
    such State Government any technical and other assistance that is possible to 
    be provided or needed.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    The Central Government shall, as far as practicable wherever it deems 
    appropriate, integrate the conservation, promotion and sustainable use of 
    biological diversity into relevant sectoral or cross-sectoral plans, 
    programmes and policies.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    The Central Government shall undertake measures,—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   wherever 
    necessary, for assessment of environmental impact of that project which is 
    likely to have adverse effect on biological diversity, with a view to avoid 
    or minimise such effects and where appropriate provide for public 
    participation in such assessment;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   to 
    regulate, manage or control the risks associated with the use and release of 
    living modified organisms resulting from biotechnology likely to have 
    adverse impact on the conservation and sustainable use of biological 
    diversity and human health.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> 
    The Central Government shall endeavour to respect and protect the knowledge 
    of  local people relating to biological diversity, as recommended by the 
    National Biodiversity Authority through such measures, which may include 
    registration of such knowledge at the local, State or national levels, and 
    other measures for protection, including sui generis system.
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   “ex situ
    conservation” means the conservation of components of biological 
    diversity outside their natural habitats;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   “in situ 
    conservation” means the conservation of ecosystems and natural habitats and 
    the maintenance and recovery of viable populations of species in their 
    natural surroundings and, in the case of domesticated or cultivated species, 
    in the surroundings where they have developed their distinctive properties.

  

 
  
 

  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>37</number> 
    Biodiversity heritage sites.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Without prejudice to any other law for the time being in force, the State 
    Government may, from time to time in consultation with the local bodies, 
    notify in the Official Gazette, areas of biodiversity importance as 
    biodiversity heritage sites under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The State Government, in consultation with the Central Government, may frame 
    rules for the management and conservation of all the heritage sites.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    The State Government shall frame schemes for compensating or rehabilitating 
    any person or section of people economically affected by such notification.
 

 

 

 


  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>38</number> 
    Power of Central Government to notify threatened species.—
Without prejudice to the provisions of any other law for the time being 
    in force, the Central Government, in consultation with the concerned State 
    Government, may from time to time notify any species which is on the verge 
    of extinction or likely to become extinct in the near future as a threatened 
    species and prohibit or regulate collection thereof for any purpose and take 
    appropriate steps to rehabilitate and preserve those species.
 

 

 

 


  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>39</number> 
    Power of Central Government to designate repositories.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, in consultation with the National Biodiversity 
    Authority, designate institutions as repositories under this Act for 
    different categories of biological resources.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The repositories shall keep in safe custody the biological material 
    including voucher specimens deposited with them.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Any new taxon discovered by any person shall be notified to the repositories 
    or any institution designated for this purpose and he shall deposit the 
    voucher specimens with such repository or institution.
 

 

 

 


  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>40</number> 
    Power of Central Government to exempt certain biological resources.—
Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, the Central Government 
    may, in consultation with the National Biodiversity Authority, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, declare that the provisions of this 
    Act shall not apply to any items, including biological resources normally 
    traded as commodities.
 

 

 

 


  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>41</number> 
    Constitution of Biodiversity Management Committees.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every local body shall constitute a Biodiversity Management Committee within 
    its area for the purpose of promoting conservation, sustainable use and 
    documentation of biological diversity including preservation of habitats, 
    conservation of land races, folk varieties and cultivars, domesticated 
    stocks and breeds of animals and micro organisms and chronicling of 
    knowledge relating to biological diversity.
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this sub-section,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   
    “cultivar” means a variety of plant that has originated  and persisted 
    under cultivation or was specifically bred for the purpose of cultivation;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   “folk 
    variety” means a cultivated variety of plant that was developed, grown and 
    exchanged informally among farmers;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   
    “landrace” means primitive cultivar that was grown by ancient farmers and 
    their successors.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The National Biodiversity Authority and the State Biodiversity Boards shall 
    consult the Biodiversity Management Committees while taking any decision 
    relating to the use of biological resources and knowledge associated with 
    such resources occurring within the territorial jurisdiction of the 
    Biodiversity Management Committee.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    The Biodiversity Management Committees may levy charges by way of collection 
    fees from any person for accessing or collecting any biological resource for 
    commercial purposes from areas falling within its territorial jurisdiction.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>42</number> 
    Grants to Local Biodiversity Fund.—The 
    State Government may, after due appropriation made by State Legislature by 
    law in this behalf, pay to the Local Biodiversity Funds by way of grants or 
    loans such sums of money as the State Government may think fit for being 
    utilised for the purposes of this Act.
 

 

 

 

 


  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>43</number> 
    Constitution of Local Biodiversity Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    There shall be constituted a Fund to be called the Local Biodiversity Fund 
    at every area notified by the State Government where any institution of 
    self-government is functioning and there shall be credited thereto—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   any 
    grants and loans made under section 42;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   any 
    grants or loans made by the National Biodiversity Authority;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   any 
    grants or loans made by the State Biodiversity Boards;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   fees 
    referred to in sub-section (3) of section 41 received by the Biodiversity 
    Management Committee;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   all sums 
    received by the Local Biodiversity Fund from such other sources as may be 
    decided upon by the State Government.
 

 

 

 

 


 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>44</number> 
    Application of Local Biodiversity Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of sub-section (2), the management and the custody 
    of the Local Biodiversity Fund and the purposes for which such Fund shall be 
    applied in the manner as may be prescribed by the State Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The Fund shall be used for conservation and promotion of biodiversity in the 
    areas falling within the jurisdiction of the concerned local body and for 
    the benefit of the community in so far such use is consistent with 
    conservation of biodiversity.
 

 

 

 

 


  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>45</number> 
    Annual report of Biodiversity Management Committees.—The 
    person holding the custody of the Local Biodiversity Fund shall prepare, in 
    such form and during each financial year at such time as may be prescribed, 
    its annual report, giving a full account of its activities during the 
    previous financial year, and submit a copy thereof to the concerned local 
    body.
 

 

 

 


  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>46</number> 
    Audit of accounts of Biodiversity Management Committees.—The 
    accounts of the Local Biodiversity Fund shall be maintained and audited in 
    such manner as may, in consultation with the Accountant-General of the 
    State, be prescribed and the person holding the custody of the Local 
    Biodiversity Fund shall furnish, to the concerned local body, before such 
    date as may be prescribed, its audited copy of accounts together with 
    auditors’ report thereon.
 

 

 


  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>47</number> 
    Annual report etc., of the Biodiversity Management Committee to be submitted 
    to District Magistrate.—Every 
    local body constituting a Biodiversity Management Committee under 
    sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 41, shall cause, the annual report and audited 
    copy of accounts together with auditor’s report thereon referred to in 
    sections 45 and 46, respectively and relating to such Committee to be 
    submitted to the District Magistrate having jurisdiction over the area of 
    the local body.
 

 

 


  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>48</number> 
    National Biodiversity Authority to be bound by the directions given by 
    Central Government.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Without prejudice to the foregoing provisions of this Act, the National 
    Biodiversity Authority shall, in the discharge of its functions and duties 
    under this Act, be bound by such directions on questions of policy as the 
    Central Government may give in writing to it from time to time:
 

    Provided that the National Biodiversity Authority shall, as far as 
    practicable, be given opportunity to express its views before any direction 
    is given under this sub-section.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The decision of the Central Government whether a question is one of policy 
    or not shall be final.
 

 

 


  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>49</number> 
    Power of State Government to give directions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Without prejudice to the foregoing provisions of this Act, the State 
    Biodiversity Board shall, in the discharge of its functions and duties under 
    this Act, be bound by such directions on questions of policy as the State 
    Government, may give in writing to it from time to time:
 

    Provided that the State Biodiversity Board shall, as far as 
    practicable, be given an opportunity to express its views before any 
    direction is given under this sub-section.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The decision of the State Government whether a question is one of policy or 
    not shall be final.
 

 

 


  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>50</number> 
    Settlement of disputes between State Biodiversity Boards.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If a dispute arises between the National Biodiversity Authority and a State 
    Biodiversity Board, the said Authority or the Board, as the case may be, may 
    prefer an appeal to the Central Government within such time as may be 
    prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every appeal made under sub-section (1) shall be in such form as may be 
    prescribed by the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    The procedure for disposing of an appeal shall be such as may be prescribed 
    by the Central Government:
 

    Provided that before disposing of an appeal, the parties shall be 
    given a reasonable opportunity of being heard.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If 
    a dispute arises between the State Biodiversity Boards, the Central 
    Government shall refer the same to the National Biodiversity Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> 
    While adjudicating any dispute under sub-section (4), the National 
    Biodiversity Authority shall be guided by the principles of natural justice 
    and shall follow such procedure as may be prescribed by the Central 
    Government.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> 
    The National Biodiversity Authority shall have, for the purposes of 
    discharging its functions under this section, the same powers as are vested 
    in a civil court under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) in 
    respect of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   summoning 
    and enforcing the attendance of any person and examining him on oath;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   requiring 
    the discovery and production of documents;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   receiving 
    evidence on affidavits;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   issuing 
    commissions for the examination of witnesses or documents;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   reviewing 
    its decisions;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   dismissing an 
    application for default or deciding it ex parte;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>   setting aside 
    any order of dismissal of any application for default or any order passed by 
    it ex parte;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>   any other 
    matter which may be prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>7</number> 
    Every proceeding before the National Biodiversity Authority shall be deemed 
    to be a judicial proceeding within the meaning of sections 193 and 228 and 
    for the purpose of section 196 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860) and the 
    National Biodiversity Authority shall be deemed to be a civil court for all 
    the purposes of section 195 and Chapter XXVI of the Code of Criminal 
    Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).
 

 


 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>51</number> 
    Members, officers, etc., of National Biodiversity Authority and State 
    Biodiversity Board deemed to be public servants.—All 
    members, officers and other employees of the National Biodiversity Authority 
    or the State Biodiversity Board shall be deemed, when acting or purporting 
    to act in pursuance of any of the provisions of this Act, to be public 
    servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 
    1860).
 

 


  

 
  
 

  


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>52</number> Appeal. </title>—Any person, aggrieved by any determination of benefit sharing or order of the National Biodiversity Authority or a State Biodiversity Board under this Act, may file an appeal to the High Court within thirty days from the date of communication to him, of the determination or order of the National Biodiversity Authority or the State Biodiversity Board, as the case may be: 
 Provided that the High Court may, if it is satisfied that the appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from filing the appeal within the said period, allow it to be filed within a further period not exceeding sixty days: 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[Provided further that nothing contained in this section shall apply on and from the commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010: 
 Provided also that any appeal pending before the High Court, before the commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, shall continue to be heard and disposed of by the High Court as if the National Green Tribunal had not been established under section 3 of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010.] 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>52A</number> Appeal to National Green Tribunal. </title>—Any person aggrieved by any determination of benefit sharing or order of the National Biodiversity Authority or a State Biodiversity Board under this Act, on or after the commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, may file an appeal to the National Green Tribunal established under section 3 of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, in accordance with the provisions of that Act.] 


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>53</number> 
    Execution of determination or order.—Every 
    determination of benefit sharing or order made by the National Biodiversity 
    Authority or a State Biodiversity Board under this Act or the order made by 
    the High Court in any appeal against any determination or order of the 
    National Biodiversity Authority or a State Biodiversity Board shall, on a 
    certificate issued by any officer of the National Biodiversity Authority or 
    a State Biodiversity Board or the Registrar of the High Court, as the case 
    may be, deemed to be decree of the civil court and shall be executable in 
    the same manner as a decree of that court.
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section and section 52, the expression “State 
    Biodiversity Board” includes the person or group of persons to whom the 
    powers or functions under sub-section (2) of section 22 have been delegated 
    under the proviso to that sub-section and the certificate relating to such 
    person or group of persons under this section shall be issued by such person 
    or group of persons, as the case may be.
 

 


  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>54</number> 
    Protection of action taken in good faith.—No 
    suit, prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against the Central 
    Government or the State Government or any officer of the Central Government 
    or the State Government or any member, officer or employee of the National 
    Biodiversity Authority or the State Biodiversity Board for anything which is 
    in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or the rules or 
    regulations made thereunder.
 


  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>55</number> 
    Penalties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whoever contravenes or attempts to contravene or abets the contravention of 
    the provisions of section 3 or section 4 or section 6 shall be punishable 
    with imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years, or with fine 
    which may extend to ten lakh rupees and where the damage caused exceeds ten  
    lakh rupees such fine may commensurate with the damage caused, or with both.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Whoever contravenes or attempts to contravene or abets the contravention of 
    the provisions of section 7 or any order made under sub-section (2) of 
    section 24 shall be  punishable with imprisonment for a term which may 
    extend to three years, or with fine which may extend to five lakh rupees, or 
    with both.
 





  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>56</number> 
    Penalty for contravention of directions or orders of Central Government, 
    State Government, National Biodiversity Authority and State Biodiversity 
    Boards.—If  any 
    person contravenes any direction given or order made by the Central 
    Government, the State Government, the National Biodiversity Authority or the 
    State Biodiversity Board for which no punishment has been separately 
    provided under this Act, he shall be punished with a fine which may extend 
    to one lakh rupees and in case of a second or subsequent offence, with fine 
    which may extend to two lakh rupees and in the case of continuous 
    contravention with additional fine which may extend to two lakh rupees 
    everyday during which the default continues.
 

 


  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>57</number> 
    Offences by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where an offence or contravention under this Act has been committed by a 
    company, every person who at the time the offence or contravention was 
    committed was in charge of, and was responsible to, the company for the 
    conduct of the business of the company, as well as the company, shall be 
    deemed to be guilty of the offence or contravention and shall be liable to 
    be proceeded against and punished accordingly.
 

    Provided that nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such 
    person liable to any punishment provided in this Act, if he proves that the 
    offence or contravention was committed without his knowledge or that he had 
    exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence or 
    contravention.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence or 
    contravention under this Act has been committed by a company and it is 
    proved that the offence or contravention has been committed with the consent 
    or connivance of, or is attributable to, any neglect on the part of any 
    director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such director, 
    manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of the 
    offence or contravention and shall be liable to be proceeded against and 
    punished accordingly.
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section,—
 <subsection>
     <number>a</number>   “company” 
    means any body corporate and includes a firm or other association of 
    individuals; and
 </subsection><subsection>
     <number>b</number>   “director”, in 
    relation to a firm, means a partner in the firm.
 

 


  

 
  
 

  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>58</number> 
    Offences to be cognizable and non-bailable.—The 
    offences under this Act shall be cognizable and non-bailable.
 


  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>59</number> 
    Act to have effect in addition to other Acts.—The 
    provisions of this Act shall be in addition to, and not in derogation of, 
    the provisions in any other law, for the time being in force, relating to 
    forests or wildlife.
 


  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>60</number> 
    Power of Central Government to give directions to State Government.—The 
    Central Government may give directions to any State Government as to the 
    carrying into execution in the State of any of the provisions of this Act or 
    of any rule or regulation or order made thereunder.
 


  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>61</number> 
    Cognizance of offences.—No 
    Court shall take cognizance of any offence under this Act except on a 
    complaint made by,—
 <section>
     <number>a</number>   the Central 
    Government or any authority or officer authorised in this behalf by that 
    Government; or
 </section><section>
     <number>b</number>   any benefit 
    claimer who has given notice of not less than thirty days in the prescribed 
    manner, of such offence and of his intention to make a complaint, to the 
    Central Government or the authority or officer authorised as aforesaid.
 






  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>62</number> 
    Power of Central Government to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make 
    rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   terms and 
    conditions of service of the Chairperson and member under section 9;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   powers 
    and duties of the Chairperson under section 10;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   procedure 
    under sub-section (1) of section 12 in regard to transaction of business at 
    meetings;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   form of 
    application and payment of fees for undertaking certain activities under 
    sub-section (1) of section 19;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   the form 
    and manner of making an application under sub-section (2) of section 19;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   form of 
    application and the manner for transfer of biological resource or knowledge 
    under sub-section (2) of section 20;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>   form in 
    which, and the time of each financial year at which, the annual report of 
    the National Biodiversity Authority shall be prepared and the date before 
    which its audited copy of accounts together with auditor’s report thereon 
    shall be furnished under section 28;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>   form in 
    which the annual statement of account shall be prepared under sub-section 
    (1) of section 29;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>   the time 
    within which and the form in which, an appeal may be preferred, the 
    procedure for disposing of an appeal and the procedure for adjudication, 
    under section 50;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>   the 
    additional matter in which the National Biodiversity Authority may exercise 
    powers of the civil court under clause (h) of sub-section (6) of section 50;
    
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>   the 
    manner of giving notice under clause (b) of section 61;
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>l</number>   any other 
    matter which is to be, or may be, prescribed, or in respect of which 
    provision is to be made, by rules.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Every rule made under this section and every regulation made under this Act 
    shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of 
    Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which 
    may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and 
    if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or 
    the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
    modification in the rule or regulation or both Houses agree that the rule or 
    regulation should not be made, the rule or regulation shall thereafter have 
    effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; 
    so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without 
    prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule or 
    regulation.
 

 


 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>63</number> 
    Power of State Government to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make 
    rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the other 
    functions to be performed by the State Biodiversity Board under clause (c) 
    of section 23;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   the form 
    in which the prior intimation shall be given under sub-section (1) of 
    section 24;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   the form 
    in which, and the time of each financial year at which, the annual report 
    shall be prepared under section 33;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   the 
    manner of maintaining and auditing the accounts of the State Biodiversity 
    Board and the date before which its audited copy of the accounts together 
    with auditor’s report thereon shall be furnished under section 34;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   
    management and conservation of national heritage sites under section 37;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   the 
    manner of management and custody of the Local Biodiversity Fund and the 
    purposes for which such Fund shall be applied under sub-section (1) of 
    section 44;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>   the form 
    of annual report and the time at which such report shall be prepared during 
    each financial year under section 45;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>   the 
    manner of maintaining and auditing the accounts of the Local Biodiversity 
    Fund and the date before which its audited copy of the accounts together 
    with auditor’s report thereon shall be furnished under section 46;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>   any other 
    matter which is to be, or may be, specified.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Every rule made by the State Government under this section shall be laid, as 
    soon as may be after it is made, before each House of the State Legislature 
    where it consists of two Houses, or where such Legislature consists of one 
    House, before that House.
 


  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>64</number> 
    Power to make regulations.—The 
    National Biodiversity Authority shall, with the previous approval of the 
    Central Government by notification in the Official Gazette, are regulations 
    for carrying out the purposes of this Act.
 


  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>65</number> 
    Power to remove difficulties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the 
    Central Government may, by order, not inconsistent with the provisions of 
    this Act, remove the difficulty:
 

    Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a period of 
    two years from the commencement of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every order made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after 
    it is made, before each House of Parliament.  


  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 

<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Sections 1, 2, 8 
    to 17, 48, 54, 59, 62, 63, 64 and 65 came into force on 1-10-2003 vide
    S.O. 1146(E), dated Ist October, 2003, published in the Gazette of 
    India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(ii), dated Ist October, 2003.
    Sections 3 to 7, 18 to 47, 49 to 53, 55 to 58, 60 and 61 came into force on 
    1-7-2004 vide S.O. 753 (E), dated Ist July, 2004, published in the 
    Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(ii)., dated 1st July, 2004.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> 
 The National 
    Biodiversity Authority has been established w.e.f. 1-10-2003, vide 
    S.O. 1147(E), dated 1st October, 2003.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Ins. by Act 19 of 2010, sec. 36 and Sch.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Ins. by Act 19 of 2010, sec. 36 and Sch.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>