<act><title>


the Central Advisory Committee on
 Equal Remuneration Rules, 19911</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Central Advisory Committee on Equal Remuneration 
    Rules, 1991.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette. 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   “Committee” means the Central Advisory 
    Committee constituted by the Central Government under sub-section (1) of 
    section 6 of the Equal Remuneration Act, 1976 (25 of 1976);  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   “Chairman” means the Chairman of the 
    Committee.  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Composition of the Committee.—The 
    Committee shall consist of not less than ten persons and not more than 
    twenty persons excluding the Chairman, to be nominated by the Central 
    Government, of which one-half shall be women. Nomination shall be made from 
    amongst the representatives of the Central Government, State 
    Governments/Union Territory Administrations, Members of Parliament 
    ‘Employers’ Organisations, Employees’ Organisations and Non-Governmental 
    Organisations engaged in the study and welfare activities of women labour. 
    The composition of the Committee shall not be invalid for the reason that 
    representative belonging to any of the aforesaid categories has not been 
    included in the Committee.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Term of 
    office of members of the Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Save as otherwise expressly provided in these rules, the term of office of a 
    non-official member of the Committee shall be two years from the date of his 
    nomination:  
 
Provided that 
    such member shall notwithstanding the expiry of the said period of two 
    years, continue to hold office until his successor is nominated.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    non-official member of the Committee nominated to fill a casual vacancy 
    shall hold office for the remainder period of the term of office of the 
    number in whose place he is nominated.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    official members of the Committee shall hold office during the pleasure of 
    the Central Government.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Allowances of members.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    travelling allowances of an official member shall be governed by the rules 
    applicable to him for journey performed by him on official duties and shall 
    be paid by the authority paying his salary.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    non-official members of the Committee shall be paid travelling allowance for 
    attending the meeting of the Committee, at such rates as are admissible to 
    Group ‘A’ officers of the Central Government and daily allowances shall be 
    calculated at the maximum rate admissible to Group ‘A’ officers of the 
    Central Government in their respective places.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Cessation 
    of membership.—If any member of 
    the Committee not being an ex-officio member of the Committee, fails 
    to attend three consecutive meetings of the Committee, without obtaining the 
    leave of the Chairman for such absence, he shall cease to be a member of the 
    Committee:  
 
Provided that 
    the Chairman may, if he is satisfied that such member was prevented by 
    sufficient cause from attending three consecutive meetings of the Committee 
    without obtaining such leave, direct that such cessation shall not take 
    place and on such direction being made, such member shall continue to be 
    member of the Committee.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Disqualification of membership.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A person shall be disqualified on being nominated as, and for being, a 
    member of the Committee if he,—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   is of unsound mind and stands so 
    declared by a competent court; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   is an undischarged insolvent; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   has been or is convicted of an offence 
    which, in the opinion of the Central Government involves moral turpitude.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If a 
    question arises as to whether a disqualification has been incurred under 
    sub-rule (1), the Central Government shall decide the same.  
  
  
 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>