<act><tid>1762328</tid>
<title>THE SALARIES AND ALLOWANCES OF MINISTERS (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2001</year></title>

ACT NO. 44 OF <year>2001</year>
[ 11th September, <year>2001</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Salaries and Allowances of Ministers Act, 
<year>1952</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- second Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>527585</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>1606564</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Salaries and Allowances of Ministers (Amendment) Act, <year>2001</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>311392</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>631479</tid>
<number> 2</number> Substitution of new section for section 5.- For section 5 of the 
Salaries and Allowances of Ministers Act, <year>1952</year> (58 of <year>1952</year>) 
 (hereinafter referred to as the principal Act), the following section 
shall be substituted, namely:-
" 5. Sumptuary allowance to Ministers.- There shall be paid a sumptuary 
allowance to each Minister at the following rates, namely:-

<section><tid>771895</tid>
<number>a</number>the Prime Minister Rupees three thousand per mensem;

</section>

<section><tid>1276051</tid>
<number>b</number>every other Minister who is Rupees two thousand 
a member of the Cabinet per mensem;

</section>

<section><tid>1249653</tid>
<number>c</number>a Minister of State Rupees one thousand per mensem;

</section>

<section><tid>757001</tid>
<number>d</number>a Deputy Minister Rupees six hundred per mensem.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>536267</tid>
<number>3</number>Amendment of section 6.- In section 6 of the principal Act, for 
sub- section (1A), the following sub- section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (1A) A Minister shall be entitled to travelling allowance in respect 
of not more than twelve return journeys performed, during each year, 
within India, for himself and his family, whether travelling together 
or separately at the same rates at which trav lling allowance is 
payable to such Minister under clause (b) of sub- section (1) in 
respect of tours referred to in that clause, subject to the overall 
entitlement of forty- eight single journeys in each year.".

SUBHASH C. JAIN, 
Secy. to the Govt. of India.


</article>



 </act>