<act><title>THE BUREAU OF ENERGY EFFICIENCY (PARTICULARS AND MANNER OF THEIR DISPLAY ON LABELS OF DISTRIBUTION TRANSFORMERS) REGULATIONS, 20091</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> </title><title>Short title and commencement. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> These regulations may be called the Bureau of Energy Efficiency (Particulars and Manner of their Display on Labels of Distribution Transformers) Regulations, 2009. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of their publication in the Official Gazette. 



</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>2</number> </title><title>Definition. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> In these regulations, unless the context otherwise requires,- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> "Act" means the Energy Conservation Act, 2001; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>aa</number> "Form" means a Form appended to these regulations;] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> "distribution transformer" means the transformer which is oil immersed, naturally air cooled, three phased, double wound, non-sealed, out door distribution transformer of standard ratings of 16, 25, 63, 100, 160 and 200 kVA of 11 kV which is manufactured or commercially purchased or sold in India; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> "label" means any written, printed, marked, stamped or graphic matter affixed to, or appearing upon, the distribution transformer; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>ca</number> "permittee" means a person to whom permission has been granted under regulation 7;] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> "section" means the section of the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> "star rating or star level" means the level of energy efficiency displayed on the label of distribution transformer on the basis of relative energy efficiencies or loss standards which is the total losses at fifty per cent loading and hundred per cent loading of the distribution transformer. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Words and expressions used herein and not defined, but defined in the Act, shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act. 



</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>3</number> </title><title>Particulars to be displayed on the labels. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> On every distribution transformer the following particulars shall be displayed on its label, namely:- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the logo of the Bureau of Energy Efficiency; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> that the equipment is a distribution transformer; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> that it is a oil filled, naturally cooled type; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> name of the manufacturer and brand; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> capacity in kVA as tested; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> voltage is up to 11 kV; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> total losses at 50% loading in watts; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> total losses at 100% loading in watts; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> star level; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> model and year of manufacturing; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number> Bureau's authorisation number. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The design, colour, size and content of label shall be as specified in the Schedule annexed to these regulations. 


</section></article> 

  
  
 <article> <title><number>4</number> </title><title>Time limit for display of labels. </title>-A label containing particulars specified in regulation 3 shall be displayed on every distribution transformer within a period of six months from the date of coming into force of these regulations. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Manner of display of label. </title>-The label shall be affixed on the front base of the distribution transformer near the name plate, so as to be prominently visible. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>6</number> Permission for display of label. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> No label shall be affixed on a distribution transformer without obtaining the permission of the Bureau. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> For the purpose of obtaining permission under sub-regulation (1), an application shall be made in Form-l or in electronic form: 
 Provided that separate application shall be made for each model of distribution transformer. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every application under sub-regulation (2) shall be accompanied by- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> an application fee of rupees one thousand payable by demand draft drawn in favour of the Bureau of Energy Efficiency, New Delhi or by any electronic mode of payment; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> a label Security Fee of rupees one lakh payable by demand draft drawn in favour of the Bureau of Energy Efficiency, New Delhi or by any electronic mode of payment; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> documents specified therein.] 
</subsection>



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>7</number> Grant of permission. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> On receipt of an application under regulation 6 and after being satisfied that all requirements are therein complied with, the Bureau may, within a period of one month from the date of such receipt, grant, subject to such terms and conditions as are specified in regulation 8, permission for affixing label on distribution transformer in Form-II or in electronic form. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Bureau shall maintain a register in Form-III and enter the name of permittee therein. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The permission so granted under sub-regulation (1) shall be valid for a period of three years and may be renewed for a further period of three years by the Bureau. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> An application for renewal of permission shall be made at least three months before its expiry and shall be accompanied by a fee of rupees five hundred payable by demand draft drawn in favour of the Bureau of Energy Efficiency, New Delhi or by any electronic mode of payment. 
(5) On receipt of application for renewal under sub-regulation (4) and after being satisfied that all requirements are complied with, the Bureau may, within a period of one month from the date of such receipt, renew permission in Form II.]



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>8</number> Terms and conditions for display of particulars on label. </title>-Every permittee shall comply with the following terms and conditions, namely:- 
 
 <section><number>a</number> The star level displayed on the label of the distribution transformer shall conform to energy consumption standards for distribution transformer notified under clause (a) of section 14 of the Act; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> the label shall be affixed only on such model of distribution transformer for which permission has been granted; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> the label shall be printed and affixed on the distribution transformer at the cost of the permittee; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> the permittee shall ensure that the star level displayed on the label of distribution transformer shall be maintained at all time; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> the permittee shall pay the label fee as specified in regulation 9; 
 </section><section><number>f</number> the permittee shall furnish to the Bureau a statement containing details of production of labelled equipment and the accrued labelling fee due for each quarter within the following month of the close of each quarter of the financial year; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> the permittee shall comply with such other terms and conditions which the Bureau may specify.]
  
</section>



</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<number>9</number> Label Fee. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> Every permittee shall pay to the Bureau a label fee of rupees one hundred on each label affixed on the distribution transformer. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The label fee specified under sub-regulation (1) shall be paid annually within one month from the date of closure of each financial year: 
 Provided that on failure to pay the label fee within the period so specified, the Bureau may recover the amount due with interest thereon at ten per cent. from the Label Security Fee paid under clause (b) of sub-regulation (3) of regulation 6.] 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[

 
<title><number>10</number> Refund of Label Security Fee. </title>-</title>Subject to the proviso to sub-regulation (2) of regulation 9, a permittee shall be entitled to a refund of the Label Security Fee on ceasing to manufacture distribution transformer.] 



</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>11</number> Verification by the Bureau. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> The Bureau may, either suo motu, or on the complaint received by it, carry out verification to ensure that the distribution transformer conforms to the star level and other particulars displayed on its label and that it complies with the other terms and conditions of permission. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where upon a complaint received under sub-regulation (1), the Bureau is required to carry out verification by testing the distribution transformer in a laboratory, a notice shall be issued to the permittee for carrying out such testing and the complainant shall be called upon to deposit such expenses relating to testing, transportation and other incidental expenses with the Bureau, within such time, as may be determined by the Bureau. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where samples of distribution transformer used for testing fails the test, the permittee shall be afforded another opportunity and the Bureau shall conduct a second test with twice the quantity of distribution transformer used in the first test, at the cost of the permittee. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Where the second test also fails, the Bureau shall direct that the permittee shall, within a period of two months,- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> correct the star level displayed on the label of the distribution transformer or remove the defects and deficiencies found during testing; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> withdraw all the stocks from the market to comply with the directions of the Bureau; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> change the particulars displayed on advertising material. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>5</number> Where the permittee fails to comply with the directions issued by the Bureau under sub-regulation (4), the Bureau shall- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> withdraw the permission; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> notify the consumers in such manner as it deems fit; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> initiate adjudication proceedings against such permittee under section 27 of the Act.]
  
</subsection>



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>12</number> Cancellation of Permission. </title>-The Bureau may cancel the permission granted under regulation 7 if the permittee- 
 
 <section><number>a</number> fails to comply with any of the terms and conditions specified under regulation 8; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> fails to pay label fee within the period specified under regulation 9.] 
</section>



</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Came into force on 7-7-2009.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>	Ins. by Notification No. 2/11(5)/03-BEE-3, dated 5th January, 2010.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>	Ins. by Notification No. 2/11(5)/03-BEE-3, dated 5th January, 2010.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>	Ins. by Notification No. 2/11(5)/03-BEE-3, dated 5th January, 2010.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>	Ins. by Notification No. 2/11(5)/03-BEE-3, dated 5th January, 2010.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>	Ins. by Notification No. 2/11(5)/03-BEE-3, dated 5th January, 2010.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>	Ins. by Notification No. 2/11(5)/03-BEE-3, dated 5th January, 2010.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>	Ins. by Notification No. 2/11(5)/03-BEE-3, dated 5th January, 2010.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>	Ins. by Notification No. 2/11(5)/03-BEE-3, dated 5th January, 2010.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>