<act><title>

The
Punjab Disturbed Areas Act, 1983 </title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>1</number>
Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
This Act may be called the Punjab Disturbed Areas Act, 1983.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
It extends to the whole of the State of Punjab.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 7th day of October
1983.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>2</number>
Definition.—In this Act,
“disturbed area” means an area which is for the time being declared by
notification under section 3 to be a disturbed area.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>3</number>
Powers to declare areas to be disturbed areas.—The
State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare that the
whole or any part of any district of Punjab as may be specified in the
notification, is a disturbed area.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>4</number>
Power to fire upon persons contravening certain orders.—Any
Magistrate or Police Officer not below the rank of Sub-Inspector or Havildar in
case of the Armed Branch of the Police may, if he is of opinion that it is
necessary so to do for the maintenance of public order, after giving such due
warning, as he may consider necessary, fire upon, or otherwise use force, even
to the causing of death against any person who is acting in contravention of any
law or order for the time being in force in the disturbed area, prohibiting the
assembly of five or more persons or the carrying of weapons or of things capable
of being used as weapons or of fire-arms, ammunition or explosive substances.
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>5</number>
Powers to destroy arms dump, fortified positions, etc.—Any
Magistrate or Police Officer not below the rank of a Sub-Inspector may, if he is
of opinion that it is necessary so to do, destroy any arms dump, prepared or
fortified position or shelter from which armed attacks are made or are likely to
be made or are attempted to be made or any structure used as training camp for
armed volunteers or utilized as a hide-out by armed gangs or absconders wanted
for any offence.
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>6</number>
Protection of persons acting under sections 4 and 5.—No
suit, prosecution or other legal proceedings shall be instituted except with the
previous sanction of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[Central
Government] against any person in respect of anything done or purporting to be
done in exercise of the powers conferred by sections 4 and 5. 


   






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>7</number>
Repeal and saving.—
<section><number>1</number> The Punjab
Disturbed Areas Ordinance, 1983
(5 of 1983), is hereby repealed.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken under the said
Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the corresponding
provisions of this Act.

 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by President Act 2 of 1989, sec. 2, for “State Government” (w.e.f.
3-4-1989).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>