<act><tid>792853</tid>
<title>THE CORONERS ACT, <year>1871</year></title>

ACT NO. 4 OF <year>1871</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 27th January, <year>1871</year>.]

An Act to consolidate and amend the laws relating to Coroners.

Preamble.-- WHEREAS it is expedient to consolidate and amend the 
laws 
relating to Coroners in the Presidency- towns; It is hereby enacted 
as 
follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I 
PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>896210</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title.- This Act may be called the Coroners Act, <year>1871</year>.
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>



</article>



<article><tid>1129443</tid>
<number>2</number>[ Repeal of enactments] Rep. by the Repealing Act, <year>1873</year> (12 of  
  <year>1873</year>).
CHAP

APPOINTMENT OF CORONERS

CHAPTER II 
APPOINTMENT OF CORONERS



</article>



<article><tid>275894</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Coroners of Calcutta and Bombay.- Within the local limits of 
the ordinary original civil jurisdiction of each of the High Courts of 
Judicature at Fort William and Bombay there shall be a Coroner. Such 
Coroners shall be called respectively the Coroner of Calcutta and the 
Coroner of Bombay.]


</article>



<article><tid>705707</tid>
<number>4</number>Their appointment, suspension and removal.- Every such' officer 
shall be appointed and may be suspended or removed by the State 
Government <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>.


</article>



<article><tid>719464</tid>
<number>5</number>Coroners to be public servants.- Every Coroner shall be deemed a 
public servant within the meaning of the Indian Penal Code (45 of  
  <year>1860</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>1074444</tid>
<number>6</number>Power to hold other offices.- Any Coroner may hold 
simultaneously any other office under Government.


</article>



<article><tid>1009657</tid>
<number>7</number>[ Oath to be taken by Coroner.] Rep. by the Indian Oaths Act, 
 <year>1873</year> (10 of <year>1873</year>).
CHAP

DUTIES AND POWERS OF CORONERS

CHAPTER III 
DUTIES AND POWERS OF CORONERS



</article>



<article><tid>217742</tid>
<number>8</number>Jurisdiction to inquire into deaths.- When a Coroner"[ has 
reason to believe] that the death of any person has been caused by 
accident, homicide, suicide, or suddenly by means unknown, or that any 
person being a prisoner has died in prison,
and that the body is lying within the place for which the Coroner 
is so appointed, the Coroner shall inquire into the cause of death.

Every such inquiry shall be deemed a judicial proceeding within 
the meaning of section 193 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>).



</article>



<article><tid>214755</tid>
<number>9</number>Coroner to be sent for when prisoner dies.- Whenever a prisoner 
dies in a prison situate within the place for which a Coroner is so 
appointed, the Superintendent of the prison shall send for the Coroner 
before the body is[ disposed of]. Any Superintendent failing herein 
shall on conviction before a Magistrate be punished with fine not 
exceeding five hundred rupees.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>122</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been amended in the Presidency- town of Bombay by Bombay 
Act 13 of <year>1930</year>, in the Bombay States by Bombay Act 25 of <year>1942</year>, and in 
West Bengal by Bengal Act 7 of <year>1944</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The local extent and commencement clauses of this section rep., 
respectively, by Act 10 of <year>1881</year>, s. 2. and Act 16 of <year>1874</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 5 of <year>1889</year>, s. 2, for the original section.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>The words" Every person now holding such office shall be deemed to 
have been appointed under this Act" rep. by Act 12 of <year>1891</year>.

  5. Subs. by Act 1) of <year>1881</year>, s. 5, for" is informed".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Subs. by Act 4 of <year>1908</year>, s. 2, for" buried".



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

 (Chapter III.- Duties and Powers of Coroners.)

Nothing in the former part of this section applies to cases in 
which the death has been caused by cholera or other epidemic disease.



</article>



<article><tid>1208106</tid>
<number>10</number>Power to hold inquests on bodies within local limits wherever 
cause of death occurred.- Whenever an inquest ought to be golden on any 
body lying dead within the local limits of the jurisdiction of any 
Coroner, he shall hold such inquest, whether or not the cause of death 
arose within his jurisdiction.


</article>



<article><tid>1715695</tid>
<number>11</number>Power to order body to be disinterred.- A Coroner may order a 
body to be disinterred within a reasonable time after the death of the 
deceased person either for the purpose of taking an original 
inquisition where none has been taken, or a further inquisition[ where 
the Coroner considers it necessary or desirable in the interests of 
justice to take a further inquisition].


</article>



<article><tid>1094710</tid>
<number>12</number>Summoning jury.- On receiving notice of any death mentioned 
in section 8, the Coroner shall summon five, seven, nine, eleven, 
thirteen or fifteen respectable persons to appear before him at a time 
and place to be specified in the summons, for the purpose of inquiring 
when, how and by what means the deceased came by his death.
Inquest may be on Sunday.- Any inquest under this Act may be held 
on a Sunday.



</article>



<article><tid>359665</tid>
<number>13</number>Opening Court.- When the time arrives, the Coroner shall 
proceed to the place so specified, open the Court by proclamation, and 
call over the names of the jurors.


</article>



<article><tid>880372</tid>
<number>14</number>Jurors to be sworn.- When a sufficient jury is in attendance, 
he shall administer an oath to each juror to give a true verdict 
according to the evidence, and shall then proceed with the jury to 
view the body.


</article>



<article><tid>1153907</tid>
<number>15</number>View of body.- The Coroner and the jury shall view and 
examine the body at the first sitting of the inquest, and the Coroner 
shall make such observations to the jury Is the appearance of the body 
requires:
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Provided that the Coroner may, with the concurrence of a 
majority of the jury, dispense with a view of the body, if he is 
satisfied, from medical evidence or medical certificates, that no 
advantage would result from such viewing.]



</article>



<article><tid>938510</tid>
<number>16</number>Proclamation for- witnesses.- The Coroner shall then make 
proclamation for the attendance of witnesses, or, where the inquiry is 
conducted in secret, shall call in separately such as know anything 
concerning the death.


</article>



<article><tid>1269143</tid>
<number>17</number>Summoning witnesses.- <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> It shall be the duty of all persons 
acquainted with the circumstances attending the death to appear before 
the inquest as witnesses; the Coroner shall inquire of such 
circumstances and the cause of death, and, if before or during the 
inquiry he is informed that any person, whether within or without the 
local limits of his jurisdiction, can give evidence or produce any 
document material thereto, may issue a summon requiring him to attend 
and give evidence or produce such document on the inquest.
Any person disobeying such summons shall be deemed to have 
committed an offence under section 174, section 175 or section 176 of 
the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>), as the case may be.]

For the purpose of causing prisoners to be brought up to give 
evidence, the Coroner shall be deemed a Criminal Court within the 
meaning of <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Part IX 5 of the Prisoners Act, <year>1900</year> (3 of <year>1900</year>)].



</article>



<article><tid>986516</tid>
<number>18</number>Post- mortem examination fees to medical witnesses.-- The 
Coroner may direct the performance of a postmortem examination with or 
without an analysis of the contents of the stomach or intestines by 
any medical witness summoned to attend the inquest: and every medical 
witness, other than the Chemical Examiner to Government, shall be 
entitled to such reasonable renumeration as the Coroner thins fit.
</article>



<article><tid>1707922</tid>
<number>18A</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Report of Chemical Examiner.- Any document purporting to 
be a report under the hand of any Chemical Examiner or Assistant 
Chemical Examiner to Government upon any matter or thing duly 
submitted to him for examination or analysis and report in the course 
of any
<pagefootnote><pagenum>123</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by s. 3, ibid., for" where the first was insufficient".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>ins. by Act 4 of <year>1908</year>, s. 4.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs, by Act 10 of <year>1881</year>, s. 6, for the original paragraphs.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by Act 4 of <year>1908</year>, for" Act No. XV of <year>1869</year> (to provide  
failures for obtaining the evidence and appearance of prisoners and 
  for service of process upon them)".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Now see the Prisoners (Attendance in Courts) Act, <year>1955</year> (32 of  
  <year>1955</year>),

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Ins. by Act 4 of <year>1908</year>, s. 6.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


 (Chapter III.- Duties and Powers of Coroners.)

proceeding under this Act, may be used as evidence in any inquest 
under this Act and inany subsequent inquiry, trial or other 
proceeding under the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1898</year> (5 of <year>1898</year>).]



</article>



<article><tid>497506</tid>
<number>19</number>Evidence to be on oath. Evidence on behalf of accused.- All 
evidence given under this Act shall be on oath, and the Coroner shall 
be bound to receive evidence on behalf of the party (if any) accused 
of causing the death of the deceased person.
Interpreter.- Witnesses unacquainted with the English language 
shall be examined through the medium of an interpreter, who shall be 
sworn to interpret truly as well the oath as the questions put to, and 
the answers given by, the witnesses.

Questions suggested by jury.- After each witness has been 
examined, the Coroner shall inquire whether the jury wish any further 
questions to be put to the witness, and, if the jury wish that any 
such questions should be put, the Coroners shall put them accordingly.



</article>



<article><tid>1559542</tid>
<number>20</number>Coroner to take down evidence in writing.- The Coroner shall 
commit to writing the material parts of the evidence given to the 
jury, and shall read or cause to be read over such parts to the 
witness and then procure his signature thereto.
Witnesses to sign depositions.- Any witnesses refusing so to sign 
shall be deemed to have committed an offence under section 180 of the 
Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>).

Coroner to subscribe depositions.- Every such deposition shall be 
subscribed by the Coroner.

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Coroner a Magistrate.- For the purposes of section 26 of the 
Indian Evidence Act, <year>1872</year> (1 of <year>1872</year>), a Coroner shall be deemed to be 
a Magistrate.]



</article>



<article><tid>962516</tid>
<number>21</number>Adjournment of inquest.- The Coroner may adjourn the inquest 
from time to time, and from place to place.
Jurors' recognizances.- Whenever the inquest is adjourned, the 
Coroner shall take the recognizances of the jurors to attend at the 
time and place appointed, and notify to the witnesses when and where 
the inquest will be proceeded with.

The amount of such recognizances shall in each case be fixed by 
the Coroner <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> and the whole, or such part thereof as to the Coroner 
seems fit, shall, in default of attendance by the jurors, be 
recoverable in the same manner as a fine imposed under section 31].



</article>



<article><tid>1148803</tid>
<number>22</number>Coroner to sum up to jury.- When all the witnesses have been 
examined, the Coroner shall sum up the evidence to the jury, and the 
jury shall then consider of their verdict.


</article>



<article><tid>596699</tid>
<number>23</number>Coroner to draw up inquisition.- When the verdict is 
delivered the Coroner shall draw up the inquisition according to the 
finding of the jury, or, when the jury is not unanimous, according to 
the opinion of the majority.


</article>



<article><tid>1887774</tid>
<number> 24</number> Contents of inquisition.- Every inquisition under this Act 
shall be signed by the Coroner with his name and style of office and 
by the jurors, and shall set forth-
<section><tid>1891613</tid>
<number>1</number>where, when and before whom the inquisition is holden, 
 (2) who the deceased is, 
 (3) where his body ties, 
 (4) the names of the jurors, and that they present the 
inquisition upon oath, 
 (5) where, when and by what means the deceased came by his 
death, and 
 (6) if his death was occasioned by the criminal act of another, 
who is guilty thereof.
If the name of the deceased be unknown, he may be described as a 
certain person to the jurors unknown.

Every such inquisition shall be in the form set forth in the 
Second Schedule hereto annexed, with such variation as the 
circumstances of each case require.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>144762</tid>
<number>25</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Procedure where death is found due to an act amounting to 
an offence.- When the jury or a majority of the jury find that the 
death of the deceased person was occasioned by an act which amounts to 
an offence under any law in force in <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> India], the Coroner shall 
immediately after the inquest forward a copy of the inquisition, 
together with the names and addresses of the witnesses, to the 
Commissioner of Police.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>124</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 10 of <year>1881</year>, s. 7. 
2. Ins. by Act 4 of <year>1908</year>, s. 7. 
3. Subs. by s. 8, ibid., for the original section. 
4. Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" a Part A 
State or a Part C State"..



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


 (Chapter III.- Duties and Powers of Coroners. Chapter IV.- Coroners,  
  Juries. Chapter V.- Rights and Liabilities of Coroners.)



</article>



<article><tid>1916138</tid>
<number>26</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Power to arrest and commit for trial- The Coroner may also, 
where the verdict justifies him in so doing, issue his warrant for the 
apprehension of the person who is found to have caused the death of 
the deceased person, and send him forthwith to a Magistrate empowered 
to commit him for trial.]


</article>



<article><tid>1925851</tid>
<number>27</number>[ Power to accept bail.] Rep. by, the Coroners (Amendment) 
Act, <year>1908</year> (4 of <year>1908</year>), s. 10.


</article>



<article><tid>1559093</tid>
<number>28</number>Warrant for disposal.- When the proceedings are closed, or 
before, if it be necessary to adjourn the inquest, the Coroner shall 
give his warrant for the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> disposal] of the body on which the inquest 
has been taken.


</article>



<article><tid>1580280</tid>
<number>29</number>Inquisitions not to be quashed for want of form.- No 
inquisition found upon or by any inquest shall be quashed for any 
technical defect.
Amendment of inquisition.- In any case of technical defect, a 
Judge of the High Court may, if he thinks fit, order the inquisition 
to be amended, and the same shall forthwith be amended accordingly.



</article>



<article><tid>666991</tid>
<number>30</number>Cessation of jurisdiction as to treasure trove, wrecks, etc.- 
It shall no longer be the duty of the Coroner to inquire whether any 
person dying by his own act was or was not felo de se, to inquire of 
treasure trove or wrecks, to seize any fugitive' s goods, to execute 
process or to exercise as Coroner any jurisdiction not expressly 
conferred by this Act.
Felo de se.- A felo de se shall not forfeit his goods.

Deodands.- Deodands are hereby abolished.

CHAP

CORONERS' JURIES

CHAPTER IV 
CORONERS' JURIES



</article>



<article><tid>1135275</tid>
<number>31</number>Fine on juror neglecting to attend.- Whenever any person has 
been duty summoned to appear as a juror by a Coroner, and fails or 
neglects to attend at the time and place specified in the summons; the 
Coroner may cause him to be openly called in his Court three times to 
appear and serve as a juror; and upon the non- appearance of such 
person, and proof that such summons has been served upon him or left 
at his usual place of abode, may impose such fine upon the defaulter, 
not exceeding fifty rupees, as the Coroner seems fit.


</article>



<article><tid>1456363</tid>
<number>32</number>Certificate as to defaulting juror.- The Coroner shall make 
out and sign a certificate, containing the name and surname, the 
residence and trade or calling of every person so making default, 
together with the amount of the fine so imposed, and the cause of such 
fine, and shall send such certificate to one of the Magistrates of the 
place of which he is the Coroner.
Service of copy of certificate.- and shall cause a copy of such 
certificate to be served upon the person so fined, by having it left 
at his usual place of residence, or by sending the same through the 
Post Office, addressed as aforesaid and registered.



</article>



<article><tid>1611187</tid>
<number>33</number>Levy of fine.- Thereupon such Magistrate shall cause the fine 
to be levied in the same manner as if it had been imposed by himself.


</article>



<article><tid>1636950</tid>
<number>34</number>Jurors not to be summoned twice within the year.- Unless in 
case of necessity, no person who has appeared, or has been summoned to 
appear, as a juror on an inquest, and has not made default shall, 
within one year after such appearance or summons, be summoned to 
appear as a juror under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>596334</tid>
<number>35</number>Jurors on inquest on prisoner.- When an inquest is held on 
the body of a prisoner dying within aprison, no officer of the 
prison and no prisoner confined therein shall be a juror on such 
inquest.
CHAP

RIGHTS AND LIABILITIES OF CORONERS

CHAPTER V 
RIGHTS AND LIABILITIES OF CORONERS



</article>



<article><tid>540439</tid>
<number>36</number>Coroner' s salary.- Every Coroner shall be entitled to such 
salary for the performance of the duty of his office as is prescribed 
in that behalf by the State Government.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>125</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 4 of <year>1908</year>, s. 9, for the original section.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by s. 11, ibid, for" burial".



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


 (Chapter V.- Rights and liabilities of Coroners. First Schedule.  
  Second Schedule.)



</article>



<article><tid>353649</tid>
<number>37</number>Disbursements to be repaid.- All disbursements duly made by a 
Coroner for fees to medical witnesses, hire of rooms for the jury, and 
the like, shall be repaid to him by the State Government.


</article>



<article><tid>284606</tid>
<number>38</number>Power to appoint deputy.- Every Coroner may from time to time, 
with the previous sanction of the State Government, appoint, by 
writing under his hand, a proper person to act for him as his deputy 
in the holding of inquests <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 0.
All inquests taken and other acts done by any such deputy, under 
or by virtue of any such appointment, shall be deemed to be the acts 
of the Coroner appointing him:

Provided that no such deputy shall act for any such Coroner 
except during the illness of the said Coroner, or during his absence 
for any lawful and reasonable cause.

Revocation of appointment.- Every such appointment may at any time 
be cancelled and revoked by the Coroner by whom it was made.



</article>



<article><tid>1897153</tid>
<number>39</number>Exemption from serving on juries.- No Coroner or Deputy 
Coroner shall be liable to serve as a juror.


</article>



<article><tid>1295637</tid>
<number>40</number>Privilege from arrest.- Coroners and Deputy Coroners shall be 
privileged from arrest while engaged in the discharge of their 
official duty.


</article>



<article><tid>20957</tid>
<number>41</number>Penalty for failure to comply with Act.- Any Coroner or Deputy 
Coroner failing to comply with the provisions of this Act, or 
otherwise misconducting himself in the execution of his office, shall 
be liable to such fine as the Chief Justice of the High Court, upon 
summary examination and proof of the failure or misconduct, thinks fit 
to impose.


</article>



<article><tid>1192269</tid>
<number>42</number>Limitation of suits.- No proceeding for anything done under 
this Act, or for any failure to comply with its provisions, shall be 
commenced or prosecuted after tender of sufficient amends.

</article>



 </act>