<act><tid>1154689</tid>
<title>THE GOVERNMENT OF UNION TERRITORIES ACT, <year>1963</year></title>

ACT NO. 20 OF <year>1963</year>
[ 10th May, <year>1963</year>.]

An Act to provide for Legislative Assemblies and Councils of Ministers 
for certain Union territories and for certain other matters.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fourteenth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--

PART

PRELIMINARY

PART I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1486168</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1307339</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Government of Union Territories Act, <year>1963</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>402674</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint:
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Provided that it shall come into force in the Union territory 
of Mizoram on such date, being a date not earlier than the date of 
commencement of the Government of Union Territories (Amendment) Act, 
 <year>1971</year> (83 of <year>1971</year>), as the Central Government may, by notification in 
the Official Gazette, appoint:]


<pagefootnote><pagenum>702</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Part I, sections 3, 4 and 14 of Part II, Part III, sections 53, 
56 and 57 of Part V and First and Second Schedules, so far as they are 
applicable, came into force in the Union territory of Goa, Daman and 
Diu, on the 13th May, <year>1963</year>, by Notifn. No. G. S. R. 814, dated 13- 5- 
<year>1963</year>, see Gazette of India Extraordinary, Pt. II, Sec. 3 (i), p. 423 
and the remaining provisions of the Act came into force in the Union 
territory of Goa, Daman and Diu, on 20- 12- <year>1963</year>: vide Notifn. No. G. S. R 
<year>1922</year> dt. 16- 12- <year>1963</year>, Gaz. of India, Exty., Pt. II, Sec. 3 (i), p. 867. 
Part I, sections 53, 56 and 57 of Part V and the Second Schedule, so 
far as they are applicable, came into force in the Union territory 
of Pondicherry of the 13th May, <year>1963</year>, by Notifn. No. G. S. R. 815, dated 
13- 5- <year>1963</year>, see ibid., and the remaining provisions came into force on 
the 1st July, <year>1963</year>, by Notifn. No. G. S. R. 1025, dated 15- 6- <year>1963</year>, 
see Gazette of India, Extraordinary, Pt. II, Sec. 3 (i), p. 471. 
All the provisions came into force in the Union territories of 
Himachal Pradesh, Manipur and Tripura, and so much of the provisions 
as apply to the Union territory of Delhi, came into force in that 
Union territory, on the 1st July, <year>1963</year>, by Notifn. No. S. O. 1660, 
dated 14- 6- <year>1963</year>, see Gazette of India, Extraordinary, Pt. II. Sec. 
3 (ii), p. 301. 
So much of the provisions as apply to the Union territory of 
Dadra and Nagar Haveli came into force in that Union territory, on the 
1st July, <year>1963</year>, by Notifn. No. G. S. R. 1025, dated 15- 6- <year>1963</year>, see 
Gazette of India, Extraordinary, Pt. II, Sec. 3 (i), p. 471.

Sections 1, 2, 3, 4, 14, 38, 43A and 56 of the Act shall come into 
force in the Union Territory of Mizoram on 17- 2- <year>1972</year>: vide Notifn. 
No. G. S. R. 81 (E) dated 16- 2- <year>1972</year>, Gaz. of India, Exty., Pt. II, Sec. 
3 (i), p. 241.

All the provisions of the Act, other than those which have 
already come into force in the Union territory of Mizoram, shall, so 
far as they are applicable, come into force in that Union territory on 
3- 51972; vide Notifn. No. G. S. R. 269 (E) dated 30- 4- <year>1972</year>, Gaz. of 
India, Exty., Pt. II, Sec. 3 (i), p-....

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by Act 83 of <year>1971</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 16- 2- <year>1972</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided further that it shall come into force in the Union 
territory of Arunachal Pradesh on such date, being a date not earlier 
than the date of commencement of the Government of Union Territories 
 (Amendment) Act, <year>1975</year> (29 of <year>1975</year>), as the Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, appoint:]

<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Provided also that, subject to the preceding provisos,] 
different dates may be appointed for different provisions of this Act 
and for different Union territories and any reference in any such 
provision to the commencement of this Act shall be construed as a 
reference to the coming into force of that provision.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1331127</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions and interpretation.
<section><tid>805739</tid>
<number>1</number>In this Act, unless the  
context otherwise requires,--

<subsection><tid>45293</tid>
<number>a</number>" Administrator" means the administrator of <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Union 
territory] appointed by the President under artcle 239;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>419120</tid>
<number>b</number>" article" means an article of the Constitution;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>426237</tid>
<number>c</number>" assembly constituency" means a constituency provided 
under this Act for the purpose of elections to the 
Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Union territory];

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>867707</tid>
<number>d</number>" Election Commission" means the Election Commission 
appointed by the President under article 324;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>685078</tid>
<number>e</number>" Judicial Commissioner" includes an Additional Judicial 
Commissioner;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>911444</tid>
<number>f</number>" scheduled castes" in relation to <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Union 
territory] mean such castes, races or tribes or parts 
of or groups within such castes, races or tribes as are 
deemed under article 341 to be scheduled castes in 
relation to that Union territory;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1086279</tid>
<number>g</number>" scheduled tribes" in relation to <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Union 
territory] mean such tribes or tribal communities or 
parts of or groups within such tribes or tribal 
communities as are deemed under article 342 to be 
scheduled tribes in relation to that Union territory;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>703</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 29 of <year>1975</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 15- 8- <year>1975</year>). 
2 Subs. by s. 2, ibid., for" Provided further that" (w. e. f. 15- 8-  
  <year>1975</year>). 
For dates see page 701. 
3 Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1987</year>, s. 65 (w. e. f. 30- 5- <year>1987</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1563284</tid>
<number>h</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>" Union territory" means the Union territory of 
Pondicherry.]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>190069</tid>
<number>2</number>Any reference in this Act to laws made by Parliament shall be 
construed as including a reference to Ordinances promulgated by the 
President under article 123 and a reference to Regulations made by the 
President under article 240.
PART

LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLIES

PART II

LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLIES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1985445</tid>
<number> 3</number> Legislative Assemblies for Union territories and their 
composition.
<section><tid>1659023</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be a Legislative Assembly for each Union  
territory.

</section>

<section><tid>273644</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> The total number of seats in the Legislative Assembly of 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory] to be filled by persons chosen by direct 
election shall be thirty.]

</section>

<section><tid>1698823</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government may nominate not more than three 
persons, not being persons in the service of Government, to be members 
of the Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory].

</section>

<section><tid>1801968</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Seats shall be reserved for the Scheduled Castes in the 
Legislative Assembly of the Union territory.]

</section>

<section><tid>1589487</tid>
<number>5</number>The number of seats reserved for the scheduled castes or the 
scheduled tribes in the Legislative Assembly <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union 
territory]] under sub- section (4) shall bear, as nearly as may be, the 
same proportion to the total number of seats in the Assembly as the 
popu-
<pagefootnote><pagenum>704</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1987</year>, s. 65 (w. e. f. 30- 5- <year>1987</year>). 
2. Subs. by the State of Himachal Pradesh (Adaptation of Laws on  
  Union Subjects) Order, <year>1973</year>, for sub- section (2)  (w. e. f. 25- 1- <year>1971</year>). 
3. Subs. by s. 2, ibid., for" of the Union territory of Pondicherry" 
 (w. e. f. 30- 9- <year>1976</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


lation of the scheduled castes in the Union territory or of the 
scheduled tribes in the Union territory, as the case may be, in 
respect of which seats are so reserved, bears to the total population 
of the Union territory.

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>' Explanation.-- In this sub- section, the expression 
" population" means the population as ascertained at the last preceding 
census of which the relevant figures have been published.

Provided that the reference in this Explanation to the last 
preceding census of which the relevant figures have been published 
shall, until the relevant figures for the first census taken after the 
year <year>2000</year> have been published, be construed as a reference to the <year>1971</year> 
census.']


</section>

<section><tid>1020276</tid>
<number>6</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Notwithstanding anything in sub- section (4), the 
reservation of seats for the Scheduled Castes in the Legislative 
Assembly of the Union territory shall cease to have effect on the same 
date on which the reservation of seats for the Scheduled Castes in the 
House of the People shall cease to have effect under article 334:
Provided that nothing in this sub- section shall affect any 
representation in the Legislative Assembly of the Union territory 
until the dissolution of the then existing Assembly.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1794096</tid>
<number> 4</number> Qualification for membership of Legislative Assembly. A person 
shall not be qualified to be chosen to fill a seat in the Legislative 
Assembly of <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the Union territory] unless he--
<section><tid>337627</tid>
<number>a</number>is a citizen of India and makes and subscribes before 
some person authorised in that behalf by the Election 
Commission an oath or affirmation according to the form 
set out for the purpose in the First Schedule;

</section>

<section><tid>731327</tid>
<number>b</number>is not less than twenty- five years of age; and

</section>

<section><tid>1368352</tid>
<number>c</number>possesses such other qualifications as may be prescribed 
in that behalf by or under any law.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1724047</tid>
<number>5</number>Duration of Legislative Assemblies. The Legislative Assembly 
of <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the Union territory], unless sooner dissolved, shall continue 
for five years from the date appointed for its first meeting and no 
longer, and the expiration of the said period of five years shall 
operate as a dissolution of the Assembly:
Provided that the said period may, while a Proclamation of 
Emergency issued under clause (1) of article 352 is in operation, be 
extended by the President by order for a period not exceeding one year 
at a time and not extending in any case beyond a period of six months 
after the Proclamation has ceased to operate.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>704A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins by Act 19 of <year>1984</year>, s. 2. 
2. Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1987</year>, s. 65 (w. e. f. 30- 5- <year>1987</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>1722034</tid>
<number> 6</number> Sessions of Legislative Assembly, prorogation and dissolution.

<section><tid>854164</tid>
<number>1</number>The Administrator shall, from time to time, summon the Legislative  
Assembly to meet at such time and place as he thinks fit, but six 
months shall not intervene between its last sitting in one session and 
the date appointed for its first sitting in the next session.

</section>

<section><tid>1145575</tid>
<number>2</number>The Administrator may, from time to time,--

<subsection><tid>463654</tid>
<number>a</number>prorogue the Assembly;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1415503</tid>
<number>b</number>dissolve the Assembly.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>900301</tid>
<number> 7</number> Speaker and Deputy Speaker of Legislative Assembly.
<section><tid>1202822</tid>
<number>1</number>Every  
Legislative Assembly shall, as soon as may be, choose two members of 
the Assembly to be respectively Speaker and Deputy Speaker thereof 
and, so often as the office of Speaker or Deputy Speaker becomes 
vacant, the Assembly shall choose another member to be Speaker or 
Deputy Speaker, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1292337</tid>
<number>2</number>A member holding office as Speaker or Deputy Speaker of an 
Assembly--

<subsection><tid>1729958</tid>
<number>a</number>shall vacate his office if he ceases to be a member of 
the Assembly;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1839867</tid>
<number>b</number>may at any time by writing under his hand addressed, if 
such member is the Speaker, to the Deputy Speaker, and 
if such member is the Deputy Speaker, to the Speaker, 
resign his office;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>677066</tid>
<number>c</number>may be removed from his office by a resolution of the 
Assembly passed by a majority of all the then members 
of the Assembly:
Provided that no resolution for the purpose of clause (c) shall 
be moved unless at least fourteen days' notice has been given of the 
intention to move the resolution:

Provided further that whenever the Assembly is dissolved, the 
Speaker shall not vacate his office until immediately before the first 
meeting of the Assembly after the dissolution.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>501675</tid>
<number>3</number>While the office of Speaker is vacant, the duties of the 
office shall be performed by the Deputy Speaker or, if the office of 
Deputy Speaker is also vacant, by such member of the Assembly as may 
be determined by the rules of procedure of the Assembly.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>704B</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>433376</tid>
<number>4</number>During the absence of the Speaker from any sitting of the 
Assembly, the Deputy Speaker, or, if he is also absent, such person as 
may be determined by the rules of procedure of the Assembly, or, if no 
such person is present, such other person as may be determined by the 
Assembly, shall act as Speaker.

</section>

<section><tid>1535365</tid>
<number>5</number>There shall be paid to the Speaker and the Deputy Speaker of 
the Legislative Assembly such salaries and allowances as may be 
respectively fixed by the Legislative Assembly of the Union territory 
by law and, until provision in that behalf is so made, such salaries

<pagefootnote><pagenum>705</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

and allowances as the Administrator may, with the approval of the 
President, by order determine.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>268227</tid>
<number> 8</number> Speaker or Deputy Speaker not to preside while a resolution 
for his removal from office is under consideration.
<section><tid>729772</tid>
<number>1</number>At any sitting  
of the Legislative Assembly, while any resolution for the removal of 
the Speaker from his office is under consideration, the Speaker, or 
while any resolution for the removal of the Deputy Speaker from his 
office is under consideration, the Deputy Speaker, shall not, though 
he is present, preside and the provisions of sub- section (4) of 
section 7 shall apply in relation to every such sitting as they apply 
in relation to a sitting from which the Speaker or, as the case may 
be, the Deputy Speaker is absent.

</section>

<section><tid>1125208</tid>
<number>2</number>The Speaker shall have the right to speak in, and otherwise 
to take part in the proceedings of, the Legislative Assembly while any 
resolution for his removal from office is under consideration in the 
Assembly and shall, notwithstanding anything in section 12, be 
entitled to vote only in the first instance on such resolution or on 
any other matter during such proceedings but not in the case of an 
equality of votes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1970158</tid>
<number> 9</number> Right of Administrator to address and send messages to 
Legislative Assembly.
<section><tid>484566</tid>
<number>1</number>The Administrator may address the  
Legislative Assembly and may for that purpose require the attendance 
of members.

</section>

<section><tid>1873286</tid>
<number>2</number>The Administrator may also send messages to the Assembly 
whether with respect to a Bill then pending in the Assembly or 
otherwise, and when a message is so sent, the Assembly shall with all 
convenient dispatch consider any matter required by the message to be 
taken into consideration.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>369058</tid>
<number>10</number>Rights of Ministers as respects Legislative Assembly. Every 
Minister shall have the right to speak in, and otherwise to take part 
in the proceedings of, the Legislative Assembly of the Union 
territory, and to speak in, and otherwise to take part in the 
proceedings of, any committee of the Legislative Assembly of which he 
may be named a member, but shall not by virtue of this section be 
entitled to vote.


</article>



<article><tid>730042</tid>
<number>11</number>Oath or affirmation by members. Every member of the 
Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory] shall, before taking 
his seat, make and subscribe before the Administrator, or some person 
appointed in that behalf by him, an oath or affirmation according to 
the form set out for the purpose in the First Schedule.


</article>



<article><tid>1261715</tid>
<number> 12</number> Voting in Assembly, power of Assembly to act notwithstanding 
vacancies and quorum.
<section><tid>655960</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as otherwise provided in this Act, all  
questions at any sitting of the Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union 
territory] shall
<pagefootnote><pagenum>706</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1987</year>, s. 65 (w. e. f. 30- 5- <year>1987</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


be determined by a majority of votes of the members present and voting 
other than the Speaker or person acting as such.


</section>

<section><tid>1285987</tid>
<number>2</number>The Speaker or person acting as such shall not vote in the 
first instance but shall have and exercise a casting vote in the case 
of an equality of votes.

</section>

<section><tid>466060</tid>
<number>3</number>The Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory] shall 
have power to act notwithstanding any vacancy in the membership 
thereof, and any proceedings in the Legislative Assembly of a <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the 
Union territory] shall be valid notwithstanding that it is discovered 
subsequently that some person who was not entitled so to do, sat or 
voted or otherwise took part in the proceedings.

</section>

<section><tid>888383</tid>
<number>4</number>The quorum to constitute a meeting of the Legislative 
Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory] shall be one- third of the total 
number of members of the Assembly.

</section>

<section><tid>1201448</tid>
<number>5</number>If at any time during a meeting of the Legislative Assembly 
of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory] there is no quorum, it shall be the duty of 
the Speaker, or person acting as such, either to adjourn the Assembly 
or to suspend the meeting until there is a quorum.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>359436</tid>
<number> 13</number> Vacation of seats.
<section><tid>850286</tid>
<number>1</number>No person shall be a member both of  
Parliament and of the Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory] 
and if a person is chosen a member both of Parliament and of such 
Assembly, then, at the expiration of such period as may be specified 
in the rules made by the President, that person' s seat in Parliament 
shall become vacant, unless he has previously resigned his seat in the 
Legislative Assembly of the Union territory.

</section>

<section><tid>1586551</tid>
<number>2</number>If a member of the Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union 
territory]--

<subsection><tid>850440</tid>
<number>a</number>becomes subject to any disqualification mentioned in 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> section 14 or section 14A] for membership of the 
Assembly, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1354388</tid>
<number>b</number>resigns his seat by writing under his hand addressed to 
the Speaker,
his seat shall thereupon become vacant.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>18099</tid>
<number>3</number>If for a period of sixty days a member of the Legislative 
Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the union territory] is without permission of the 
Assembly absent from all meetings thereof, the Assembly may declare 
his seat vacant:
Provided that in computing the said period of sixty days, no 
account shall be taken of any period during which the Assembly is 
prorogued or is adjourned for more than four consecutive days.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>707</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1987</year>, s. 65 (w. e. f. 30- 5- <year>1987</year>). 
2. Subs. by Act 24 of <year>1985</year>, s. 2.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>272869</tid>
<number> 14</number> Disqualifications for membership.
<section><tid>1087922</tid>
<number>1</number>A person shall be  
disqualified for being chosen as, and for being, a member of the 
Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory]--

<subsection><tid>1419149</tid>
<number>a</number>if he holds any office of profit under the Government of 
India or the Government of any State or the Government 
of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory] other than an office 
declared by law made by Parliament or by the 
Legislative Assembly of the Union territory not to 
disqualify its holder; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>684918</tid>
<number>b</number>if he is for the time being disqualified for being 
chosen as, and for being, a member of either House of 
Parliament under the provisions of sub- clause (b), sub- 
clause (c) or sub- clause (d) of clause (1) of article 
 102 or of any law made in pursuance of that article.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1840771</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes of this section, a person shall not be 
deemed to hold an office of profit under the Government of India or 
the Government of any State or the Government of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union 
territory] by reason only that he is a Minister either for the Union 
or for such State or Union territory.

</section>

<section><tid>898912</tid>
<number>3</number>If any question arises as to whether a member of the 
Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory] has become 
disqualified for being such a member under the provisions of sub- 
section (1), the question shall be referred for the decision of the 
President and his decision shall be final.

</section>

<section><tid>1350514</tid>
<number>4</number>Before giving any decision on any such question, the 
President shall obtain the opinion of the Election Commission and 
shall act according to such opinion.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1871623</tid>
<number> 14A</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Disqualification on ground of defection for being a 
member. The provisions of the Tenth Schedule to the Constitution 
shall, subject to the necessary modifications (including modifications  
for construing references therein to the Legislative Assembly of a 
State, article 188, article 194 and article 212 as references, 
respectively, to the Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory], 
  section 11, section 16 and section 37 of this Act), apply to and in 
relation to the members of the Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union 
territory] as they apply to and in relation to the members of the 
Legislative Assembly of a State, and accordingly,--
<section><tid>217776</tid>
<number>a</number>the said Tenth Schedule as so modified shall be deemed 
to form part of this Act; and

</section>

<section><tid>1922962</tid>
<number>b</number>a person shall be disqualified for being a member of the 
Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory] if he is so 
disqualified under the said Tenth Schedule as so modified.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1313040</tid>
<number>15</number>Penalty for sitting and voting before making oath or 
affirmation or when not qualified or when disqualified. If a person 
sits or votes as a member of the Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union 
territory] before he has complied with the requirements of section 11 
or when he knows that he is not qualified or that he is disqualified 
for membership thereof, he shall be liable in respect of each day on 
which he so sits or votes to a penalty of five hundred rupees to be 
recovered as a debt due to the Union.


</article>



<article><tid>575222</tid>
<number> 16</number> Powers, privileges, etc., of members.
<section><tid>1863567</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the  
provisions of this Act and to the rules and standing orders regulating 
the procedure of the Legislative Assembly, there shall be freedom of 
speech in the Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory].

</section>

<section><tid>1455853</tid>
<number>2</number>No member of the Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union 
territory] shall be liable to any proceedings in any court in respect 
of anything said or any vote given by him in the Assembly or any 
committee thereof, and no person shall be so liable in respect of the 
publication
<pagefootnote><pagenum>708</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1987</year>, s. 65 (w. e. f. 30- 5- <year>1987</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 24 of <year>1985</year>, s. 3.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


by or under the authority of such Assembly of any report, paper, votes 
or proceedings.


</section>

<section><tid>158168</tid>
<number>3</number>In other respects, the powers, privileges and immunities of 
the Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory] and of the members 
and the committees thereof shall be such as are for the time being 
enjoyed by the House of the People and its members and committees.

</section>

<section><tid>953632</tid>
<number>4</number>The provisions of sub- sections (1), (2) and (3) shall apply 
in relation to persons who by virtue of this Act have the right to 
speak in, and otherwise to take part in the proceedings of, the 
Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory] or any committee 
thereof as they apply in relation to members of that Assembly.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>321094</tid>
<number>17</number>Salaries and allowances of members. Members of the 
Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory] shall be entitled to 
receive such salaries and allowances as may from time to time be 
determined by the Legislative Assembly of the Union territory by law 
and, until provision in that behalf is so made, such salaries and 
allowances as the Administrator may, with the approval of the 
President, by order determine.


</article>



<article><tid>1920832</tid>
<number> 18</number> Extent of legislative power.
<section><tid>543540</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of  
this Act, the Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory] may make 
laws for the whole or any part of the Union territory with respect to 
any of the matters enumerated in the State List or the Concurrent List 
in the Seventh Schedule to the Constitution in so far as any such 
matter is applicable in relation to Union territories.

</section>

<section><tid>958273</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing in sub- section (1) shall derogate from the powers 
conferred on Parliament by the Constitution to make laws with respect 
to any matter for <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory] or any part thereof.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1118085</tid>
<number>19</number>Exemption of property of the Union from taxation. The 
property of the Union shall, save in so far as Parliament may by law 
otherwise provide, be exempted from all taxes imposed by or under any 
law made by the Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory] or by 
or under any other law in force in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory]:
Provided that nothing in this section shall, until Parliament by 
law otherwise provides, prevent any authority within <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union 
territory] from levying any tax on any property of the Union to which 
such property was immediately before the commencement of the 
Constitution liable or treated as liable, so long as that tax 
continues to be levied in that Union territory.



</article>



<article><tid>1018425</tid>
<number> 20</number> Restrictions on laws passed by Legislative Assembly with 
respect to certain matters. <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> 1] The provisions of article 286, 
article 287 and article 288 shall apply in relation to any law passed 
by the Legislative Assembly of
<pagefootnote><pagenum>709</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1987</year>, s. 65 (w. e. f. 30- 5- <year>1987</year>). 
2. S. 20 renumbered as sub- section (1) thereof by Act 83 of <year>1971</year>, s. 
5 (w. e. f. 16- 2- <year>1972</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory] with respect to any of the matters referred to 
in those articles as they apply in relation to any law passed by the 
Legislature of a State with respect to those matters.

<section><tid>1301195</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> The provisions of article 304 shall, with the necessary 
modifications, apply in relation to any law passed by the Legislative 
Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory] with respect to any of the matters 
referred to in that article as they apply in relation to any law 
passed by the Legislature of a State with respect to those matters.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1363944</tid>
<number>21</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Inconsistency between laws made by Parliament and laws 
made by Legislative Assembly. If any provision of a law made by the 
Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory] with respect to any 
matter enumerated in the State List in the Seventh Schedule to the 
Constitution is repugnant to any provision of a law made by Parliament 
with respect to that matter, whether passed before or after the law 
made by the Legislative Assembly of the Union territory, or, if any 
provision of a law made by the Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union 
territory] with respect to any matter enumerated in the Concurrent 
List in the Seventh Schedule to the Constitution is repugnant to any 
provision of any earlier law, other than a law made by the Legislative 
Assembly of the Union territory, with respect to that matter, then, in 
either case, the law made by Parliament, or, as the case may be, such 
earlier law shall prevail and the law made by the Legislative Assembly 
of the Union territory shall, to the extent of the repugnancy, be 
void:
Provided that if such law made by the Legislative Assembly of the 
Union territory has been reserved for the consideration of the 
President and has received his assent, such law shall prevail in that 
Union territory:

Provided further that nothing in this section shall prevent 
Parliament from enacting at any time any law with respect to the same 
matter including a law adding to, amending, varying or repealing the 
law so made by the Legislative Assembly of the Union territory.]



</article>



<article><tid>750214</tid>
<number> 22</number> Sanction of the administrator required for certain 
legislative proposals. No Bill or amendment shall be introduced into, 
or moved in, the Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory] 
without the previous sanction of the Administrator, if such Bill or 
amendment makes provision with respect to any of the following 
matters, namely:--
<section><tid>849795</tid>
<number>a</number>constitution and organisation of the court of the 
Judicial Commissioner;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>710</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1987</year>, s. 65, for" Union territory" (w. e. f.  
  30- 5- <year>1987</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 83 of <year>1971</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 16- 2- <year>1972</year>). 
3. Subs. by Act 29 of <year>1975</year>, s. 4, for s. 21 (w. e. f. 15- 8- <year>1975</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>855676</tid>
<number>b</number>jurisdiction and powers of the court of the Judicial 
Commissioner with respect to any of the matters in the 
State List or the Concurrent list in the Seventh 
Schedule to the Constitution.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>986663</tid>
<number> 23</number> Special provisions as to financial Bills.
<section><tid>712967</tid>
<number>1</number>A Bill or  
amendment shall not be introduced into, or moved in, the Legislative 
Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory] except on the recommendation of 
the Administrator, if such Bill or amendment makes provision for any 
of the following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>103777</tid>
<number>a</number>the imposition, abolition, remission, alteration or 
regulation of any tax;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1330657</tid>
<number>b</number>the amendment of the law with respect to any financial 
obligations undertaken or to be undertaken by the 
Government of the Union territory;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>693465</tid>
<number>c</number>the appropriation of moneys out of the Consolidated Fund 
of the Union territory;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1803516</tid>
<number>d</number>the declaring of any expenditure to be expenditure 
charged on the Consolidated Fund of the Union territory 
or the increasing of the amount of any such 
expenditure;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>912104</tid>
<number>e</number>the receipt of money on account of the Consolidated Fund 
of the Union territory or the custody or issue of such 
money:
Provided that no recommendation shall be required under this sub- 
section for the moving of an amendment making provision for the 
reduction or abolition of any tax.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>407497</tid>
<number>2</number>A Bill or amendment shall not be deemed to make provision for 
any of the matters aforesaid by reason only that it provides for the 
imposition of fines or other pecuniary penalties, or for the demand or 
payment of fees for licences or fees for services rendered, or by 
reason that it provides for the imposition, abolition, remission, 
alteration or regulation of any tax by any local authority or body for 
local purposes.

</section>

<section><tid>955508</tid>
<number>3</number>A Bill which, if enacted and brought into operation, would 
involve expenditure from the Consolidated Fund of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union 
territory] shall not be passed by the Legislative Assembly of the 
Union territory unless the Administrator has recommended to that 
Assembly the consideration of the Bill.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>711</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1987</year>, s. 65," for Union territory" (w. e. f.  
  30- 5- <year>1987</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1031918</tid>
<number> 24</number> Procedure as to lapsing of Bills.
<section><tid>763884</tid>
<number>1</number>A Bill pending in the  
Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory] shall not lapse by 
reason of the prorogation of the Assembly.

</section>

<section><tid>694742</tid>
<number>2</number>A Bill which is pending in the Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the 
Union territory] shall lapse on a dissolution of the Assembly.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1617130</tid>
<number> 25</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Assent to Bills.-- When a Bill has been passed by the 
Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory], it shall be presented 
to the Administrator and the Administrator shall declare either that 
he assents to the Bill or that he withholds assent therefrom or that 
he reserves the Bill for the consideration of the President:
Provided that the Administrator may, as soon as possible after 
the presentation of the Bill to him for assent, return the Bill if it 
is not a Money Bill together with a message requesting that the 
Assembly will reconsider the Bill or any specified provisions thereof, 
and, in particular, will consider the desirability of introducing any 
such amendments as he may recommend in his message and, when a Bill is 
so returned, the Assembly will reconsider the Bill accordingly, and if 
the Bill is passed again with or without amendment and presented to 
the Administrator for assent, the Administrator shall declare either 
that he assents to the Bill or that he reserves the Bill for the 
consideration of the President:

Provided further that the Administrator shall not assent to, but 
shall reserve for the consideration of the President, any Bill which,-

<section><tid>189537</tid>
<number>a</number>in the opinion of the Administrator would, if it became 
law, so derogate from the powers of the High Court as 
to endanger the position which that Court is, by the 
Constitution, designed to fill; or

</section>

<section><tid>684487</tid>
<number>b</number>relates to any of the matters specified in clause (1) of 
article 31A; or

</section>

<section><tid>1499169</tid>
<number>c</number>the President may, by order, direct to be reserved for 
his consideration; or

</section>

<section><tid>1831485</tid>
<number>d</number>relates to matters referred to in sub- section (5) or 
section 7 or section 17 or section 34 or sub- section 
 (6) of section 45 or in entry 1 or entry 2 of the State 
List in the Seventh Schedule to the Constitution:
<pagefootnote><pagenum>712</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1987</year>, s. 65, for" a Union territory" (w. e. f.  
  30- 5- <year>1987</year>). 
2. Subs. by Act 83 of <year>1971</year>, s. 7, for s. 25 (w. e. f. 16- 2- <year>1972</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Provided also that without prejudice to the provisions of the 
second proviso, the Administrator shall not assent to, but shall 
reserve for the consideration of the President, any Bill which has 
been passed by the Legislative Assembly of the Union territory of 
Mizoram and which relates to any area comprised in any autonomous 
district in that Union territory under the Sixth Schedule to the 
Constitution.

Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section and section 25A, a 
Bill shall be deemed to be a Money Bill if it contains only provisions 
dealing with all or any of the matters specified in sub- section (1) of 
section 23 or any matter incidental to any of those matters and, in 
either case, there is endorsed thereon the certificate of the Speaker 
of the Legislative Assembly signed by him that it is a Money Bill.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>148866</tid>
<number>25A</number>Bills reserved for consideration.-- When a Bill is reserved 
by an Administrator for the consideration of the President, the 
President shall declare either that he assents to the Bill or that he 
withholds assent therefrom:
Provided that where the Bill is not a Money Bill, the President 
may direct the Administrator to return the Bill to the Legislative 
Assembly together with such a message as is mentioned in the first 
proviso to section 25 and, when a Bill is so returned, the Assembly 
shall reconsider it accordingly within a period of six months from the 
date of receipt of such message and, if it is again passed by the 
Assembly with or without amendment, it shall be presented again to the 
President for his consideration.]



</article>



<article><tid>1769853</tid>
<number>26</number>Requirements as to sanction and recommendations to be 
regarded as matters of procedure only.-- No Act of the Legislative 
Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory] no provision in any such Act, 
shall be invalid by reason only that some previous sanction or 
recommendation required by this Act was not given, if assent to that 
Act was given <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> by the Administrator, or, on being reserved by the 
Administrator for the consideration of the President, by the 
President].


</article>



<article><tid>1147134</tid>
<number> 27</number> Annual financial statement.--
<section><tid>1436628</tid>
<number>1</number>The Administrator of each  
Union territory shall in respect of every financial year cause to be 
laid before the Legislative Assembly of the Union territory, with the 
previous approval of the President, a statement of the estimated 
receipts and expenditure of the Union territory for that year, in this 
Part referred to as the" annual financial statement".
<pagefootnote><pagenum>712A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1987</year>, s. 65, for" a Union territory" (w. e. f.  
  30- 5- <year>1987</year>). 
2. Subs. by Act 29 of <year>1975</year>, s. 5, for" by the President" (w. e. f. 15-  
  8- <year>1975</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1167252</tid>
<number>2</number>The estimates of expenditure embodied in the annual financial 
statement shall show separately--

<subsection><tid>1834990</tid>
<number>a</number>the sums required to meet expenditure described by this 
Act as expenditure charged upon the Consolidated Fund 
of the Union territory, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>798825</tid>
<number>b</number>the sums required to meet other expenditure proposed to 
be made from the Consolidated Fund of the Union 
territory;
and shall distinguish expenditure on revenue account from other 
expenditure.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>713</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>740726</tid>
<number>3</number>The following expenditure shall be expenditure charged on the 
Consolidated Fund of each Union territory:--

<subsection><tid>1783017</tid>
<number>a</number>the emoluments and allowances of the Administrator and 
other expenditure relating to his office as determined 
by the President by general or special order;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>76427</tid>
<number>b</number>the charges payable in respect of loans advanced to the 
Union territory from the Consolidated Fund of India 
including interest, sinking fund charges and redemption 
charges, and other expenditure connected therewith;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>10230</tid>
<number>c</number>the salaries and allowances of the Speaker and the 
Deputy Speaker of the Legislative Assembly;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>13823</tid>
<number>d</number>expenditure in respect of the salaries and allowances of 
a Judicial Commissioner;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1531454</tid>
<number>e</number>any sums required to satisfy any judgment, decree or 
award of any court or arbitral tribunal;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1652500</tid>
<number>f</number>expenditure incurred by the Administrator in the 
discharge of his special responsibility;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1859896</tid>
<number>g</number>any other expenditure declared by the Constitution or by 
law made by Parliament or by the Legislative Assembly 
of the Union territory to be so charged.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>442499</tid>
<number> 28</number> Procedure in Legislative Assembly with respect to 
estimates.--
<section><tid>401399</tid>
<number>1</number>So much of the estimates as relates to expenditure  
charged upon the Consolidated Fund of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory] shall 
not be submitted to the vote of the Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the 
Union territory], but nothing in this sub- section shall be construed 
as preventing the discussion in the Legislative Assembly of any of 
those estimates.

</section>

<section><tid>1427451</tid>
<number>2</number>So much of the said estimates as relates to other expenditure 
shall be submitted in the form of demands for grants to the 
Legislative Assembly, and the Legislative Assembly shall have power to 
assent, or to refuse to assent, to any demand, or to assent to any 
demand subject to a reduction of the amount specified therein.

</section>

<section><tid>1536167</tid>
<number>3</number>No demand for a grant shall be made except on the 
recommendation of the Administrator.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>958090</tid>
<number> 29</number> Appropriation Bills.--
<section><tid>1203734</tid>
<number>1</number>As soon as may be after the grants  
under section 28 have been made by the Assembly, there shall be 
introduced a Bill to provide for the appropriation out of the 
Consolidated Fund of the Union territory of all moneys required to 
meet--

<subsection><tid>1495948</tid>
<number>a</number>the grants so made by the Assembly, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1309189</tid>
<number>b</number>the expenditure charged on the Consolidated Fund of the 
Union territory but not exceeding in any case the 
amount shown in the statement previously laid before 
the Assembly.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>714</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1987</year>, s. 65, for" a Union territoryy" (w. e. f.  
  30- 5- <year>1987</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>342742</tid>
<number>2</number>No amendment shall be proposed to any such Bill in the 
Legislative Assembly which will have the effect of varying the amount 
or altering the destination of any grant so made or of varying the 
amount of any expenditure charged on the Consolidated Fund of the 
Union territory and the decision of the person presiding as to whether 
an amendment is inadmissible under this sub- section shall be final.

</section>

<section><tid>1148986</tid>
<number>3</number>Subject to the other provisions of this Act, no money shall 
be withdrawn from the Consolidated Fund of the Union territory except 
under appropriation made by law passed in accordance with the 
provisions of this section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1344226</tid>
<number> 30</number> Supplementary, additional or excess grants.--
<section><tid>370371</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Administrator shall--

<subsection><tid>699575</tid>
<number>a</number>if the amount authorised by any law made in accordance 
with the provisions of section 29 to be expended for a 
particular service for the current financial year is 
found to be insufficient for the purposes of that year 
or when a need has arisen during the current financial 
year for supplementary or additional expenditure upon 
some new service not contemplated in the annual 
financial statement for that year, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>592956</tid>
<number>b</number>if any money has been spent on any service during a 
financial year in excess of the amount granted for that 
service and for that year,
cause to be laid before the Legislative Assembly of the Union 
territory, with the previous approval of the President, another 
statement showing the estimated amount of that expenditure or cause to 
be presented to the Legislative Assembly of the Union territory with 
such previous approval a demand for such excess, as the case may be.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1834098</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of sections 27, 28 and 29 shall have effect in 
relation to any such statement and expenditure or demand and also to 
any law to be made authorising the appropriation of moneys out of the 
Consolidated Fund of the Union territory to meet such expenditure or 
the grant in respect of such demand as they have effect in relation to 
the annual financial statement and the expenditure mentioned therein 
or to a demand for a grant and the law to be made for the 
authorisation of appropriation of moneys out of the Consolidated Fund 
of the Union territory to meet such expenditure or grant.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>643754</tid>
<number> 31</number> Votes on account.--
<section><tid>373461</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything in the  
foregoing provisions of this Part, the Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the 
Union territory] shall have power to make any grant in advance in 
respect of the estimated expenditure
<pagefootnote><pagenum>715</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1987</year>, s. 65, for" a Union territory" (w. e. f.  
  30- 5- <year>1987</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


for a part of any financial year pending the completion of the 
procedure prescribed in section 28 for the voting of such grant and 
the passing of the law in accordance with the provisions of section 29 
in relation to that expenditure and the Legislative Assembly shall 
have power to authorise by law the withdrawal of moneys from the 
Consolidated Fund of the Union territory for the purposes for which 
the said grant is made.


</section>

<section><tid>1324</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of sections 28 and 29 shall have effect in 
relation to the making of any grant under sub- section (1) or to any 
law to be made under that sub- section as they have effect in relation 
to the making of a grant with regard to any expenditure mentioned in 
the annual financial statement and the law to be made for the 
authorisation of appropriation of moneys out of the Consolidated Fund 
of the Union territory to meet such expenditure.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1483763</tid>
<number>32</number>Authorisation of expenditure pending its sanction by 
Legislative Assembly.-- Notwithstanding anything in the foregoing 
provisions of this Part, the Administrator may authorise such 
expenditure from the Consolidated Fund of the Union territory as he 
deems necessary for a period of not more than six months beginning 
with the date of the constitution of the Consolidated Fund of the 
Union territory, pending the sanction of such expenditure by the 
Legislative Assembly of the Union territory.


</article>



<article><tid>790445</tid>
<number> 33</number> Rules of procedure.--
<section><tid>228530</tid>
<number>1</number>The Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the  
union territory] may make rules for regulating, subject to the 
provisions of this Act, its procedure and the conduct of its business:
Provided that the Administrator shall, after consultation with 
the Speaker of the Legislative Assembly and with the approval of the 
President, make rules--


<subsection><tid>1462697</tid>
<number>a</number>for securing the timely completion of financial 
business;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1505111</tid>
<number>b</number>for regulating the procedure of, and the conduct of 
business in, the Legislative Assembly in relation to 
any financial matter or to any Bill for the 
appropriation of moneys out of the Consolidated Fund of 
the Union territory;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1916106</tid>
<number>c</number>for prohibiting the discussion of, or the asking of 
questions on, any matter which affects the discharge of 
the functions of the Administrator in so far as he is 
required by this Act to act in his discretion.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1342708</tid>
<number>2</number>Until rules are made under sub- section (1), the rules of 
procedure and standing orders with respect to the Legislative Assembly
<pagefootnote><pagenum>716</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1987</year>, s. 65, for" a Union territory" (w. e. f.  
  30- 5- <year>1987</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


of the State of Uttar Pradesh in force immediately before the 
commencement of this Act in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory] shall have effect 
in relation to the Legislative Assembly of that Union territory 
subject to such modifications and adaptations as may be made therein 
by the Administrator.

<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>717040</tid>
<number> 34</number> Official language or languages of Union territory and 
language or languages to be used in Legislative Assembly thereof.--
<section><tid>1779692</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Union territory] may by law adopt 
any one or more of the languages in use in the Union territory or 
Hindi as the official language or languages to be used for all or any 
of the official purposes of the Union territory:
Provided that so long as the Legislative Assembly of the Union 
territory of Pondicherry does not decide otherwise, the French 
language shall continue to be used as an official language of that 
Union territory for the same official purposes for which it was being 
used in that territory immediately before the commencement of this 
Act:

Provided further that the President may be order direct--


<subsection><tid>330239</tid>
<number>i</number>that the official language of the Union shall be adopted 
for such of the official purposes of the Union 
territory as may be specified in the order;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>959143</tid>
<number>ii</number>that any other language shall also be adopted 
throughout the Union territory or such part thereof for 
such of the official purposes of the Union territory as 
may be specified in the order, if the President is 
satisfied that a substantial proportion of the 
population of the Union territory desires the use of 
that other language for all or any of such purposes.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1202048</tid>
<number>2</number>The business in the Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Union 
territory] shall be transacted in the official language or languages 
of the Union territory or in Hindi or in English:
Provided that the Speaker of the Legislative Assembly or person 
acting as such, as the case may be, may permit any member who


<pagefootnote><pagenum>717</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1987</year>, s. 65, for" any Union territory" (w. e. f.  
  30- 5- <year>1987</year>). 
2. The Proviso omitted by Act 69 of <year>1986</year>, s. 44 (w. e. f. 20- 2- <year>1987</year>). 
3. Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1987</year>, s. 65, for" a Union territory".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

cannot adequately express himself in any of the languages aforesaid to 
address the Assembly in his mother- tongue.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1477580</tid>
<number> 35</number> Language to be used for Acts, Bills, etc.-- Notwithstanding 
anything contained in section 34, until Parliament by law otherwise 
provides, the authoritative texts--
<section><tid>1855636</tid>
<number>a</number>of all Bills to be introduced or amendments thereto to 
be moved in the Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union 
territory],

</section>

<section><tid>150581</tid>
<number>b</number>of all Acts passed by the Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the 
Union territory], and

</section>

<section><tid>1299791</tid>
<number>c</number>of all orders, rules, regulations and bye- laws issued 
under any law made by the Legislative Assembly of 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory],
shall be in the English language:

Provided that where the Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union 
territory] has prescribed any language other than the English language 
for use in Bills introduced in, or Acts passed by, the Legislative 
Assembly of the Union territory or in any order, rule, regulation or 
bye- law issued under any law made by the Legislative Assembly of the 
Union territory, a translation of the same in the English language 
published under the authority of the Administrator in the Official 
Gazette shall be deemed to be the authoritative text thereof in the 
English language.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>979105</tid>
<number>36</number>Restriction on discussion in the Legislative Assembly.-- No 
discussion shall take place in the Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the 
Union territory] with respect to the conduct of any Judicial 
Commissioner or of any judge of the Supreme Court or of a High Court 
in the discharge of his duties.


</article>



<article><tid>1923988</tid>
<number> 37</number> Courts not to inquire into proceedings of Legislative 
Assembly.--
<section><tid>942611</tid>
<number>1</number>The validity of any proceedings in the Legislative  
Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory] shall not be called in question on 
the ground of any alleged irregularity of procedure.

</section>

<section><tid>1660843</tid>
<number>2</number>No officer or member of the Legislative <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union 
territory] in whom powers are vested by or under this Act for 
regulating procedure or the conduct of business, or for maintaining 
order in the Legislative Assembly shall be subject to the jurisdiction 
of any court in respect of the exercise by him of those powers.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>718</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1987</year>, s. 65, for" a Union territory" (w. e. f.  
  30- 5- <year>1987</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


PART

DELIMITATION OF CONSTITUENCIES

PART III

DELIMITATION OF CONSTITUENCIES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>431529</tid>
<number> 38</number> Definitions.-- In this Part, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1590163</tid>
<number>a</number>" associate member" means a member associated with the 
Delimitation Commission under section 42 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or with the 
Election Commission <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> under section 43A or section 
43C]];

</section>

<section><tid>786072</tid>
<number>b</number>" Delimitation Commission" means the Delimitation 
Commission constituted under section 3 of the 
Delimitation Commission Act, <year>1962</year> (61 of <year>1962</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>731818</tid>
<number>bb</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>" Election Commission" means the Election Commission 
appointed by the President under article 324;]

</section>

<section><tid>1801428</tid>
<number>c</number>" latest census figures" mean the census figures in 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Union territory] ascertained at the latest 
census of which the finally published figures are 
available;

</section>

<section><tid>1208140</tid>
<number>d</number>" parliamentary constituency" means a constituency 
provided by law for the purpose of elections to the 
House of the People from <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Union territory] 
including the Union territory of Delhi.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>274713</tid>
<number>39</number>Assembly constituencies.-- For the purpose of elections to 
the Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Union territory], the Union 
territory shall be divided into single- member assembly constituencies 
in accordance with the provisions of this Part in such manner that the 
population of each of the constituencies shall, so far as practicable, 
be the same throughout the Union territory.


</article>



<article><tid>1925264</tid>
<number>40</number>Representation of Pondicherry in the House of the People.-- 
There shall be allotted one seat to the Union territory of Pondicherry 
in the House of the People and that Union territory shall form one 
parliamentary constituency.


</article>



<article><tid>1917239</tid>
<number> 41</number> Duties of Delimitation Commission.--
<section><tid>1595444</tid>
<number>1</number>It shall be the duty  
of the Delimitation Commission--

<subsection><tid>843628</tid>
<number>a</number>to delimit the assembly constituencies in each Union 
territory, and
<pagefootnote><pagenum>718A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 83 of <year>1971</year>, s. 9 (w. e. f. 16- 2- <year>1972</year>). 
2. Subs. by Act 29 of <year>1975</year>, s. 7, for" under section 43A" (w. e. f.  
  15- 8- <year>1975</year>). 
3. Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1987</year>, s. 65, for" a Union territory" (w. e. f.  
  30- 5- <year>1987</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1526731</tid>
<number>b</number>to determine, on the basis of the latest census figures, 
the number of seats to be reserved for the scheduled 
castes and for the scheduled tribes in the Legislative 
Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory] other than the 
Union territory of Goa, Daman and Diu, and the 
constituencies in which these seats shall be so 
reserved.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>496937</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall also be the duty of the Delimitation Commission--

<subsection><tid>1059778</tid>
<number>a</number>to readjust, on the basis of the latest census figures, 
the division of each of the Union territories of Delhi, 
Himachal Pradesh, Manipur and Tripura into 
parliamentary constituencies, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the number being 7, 4, 
 2 and 2];
<pagefootnote><pagenum>719</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1987</year>, s. 65, for" a Union territory" (w. e. f.  
  30- 5- <year>1987</year>). 
2. Subs. by Act 19 of <year>1966</year>, s. 37, for certain words (w. e. f. 13- 6-  
  <year>1966</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1230424</tid>
<number>b</number>to determine the constituency in which the seat shall be 
reserved for the scheduled castes or for the scheduled 
tribes, as the case may be; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>425566</tid>
<number>c</number>to divide the Union territory of Goa, Daman and Diu into 
two single- member parliamentary constituencies.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1619958</tid>
<number> 42</number> Associate members.
<section><tid>1331744</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purpose of assisting the  
Delimitation Commission in its duties, the Delimitation Commission 
shall associate with itself,--

<subsection><tid>1868612</tid>
<number>a</number>in respect of the Union territory of Delhi, all the 
members of the House of the People representing that 
Union territory;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1383343</tid>
<number>b</number>in respect of each of the Union territories of Himachal 
Pradesh, Manipur and Tripura, all the members of the 
House of the People representing that Union territory 
and three members of the Legislative Assembly of that 
Union territory to be nominated by the Speaker of the 
Assembly from among the members thereof;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>572492</tid>
<number>c</number>in respect of the Union territory of Goa, Daman and Diu, 
the two members of the House of the People representing 
that Union territory;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>332740</tid>
<number>d</number>in respect of the Union territory of Pondicherry, three 
members of the Legislative Assembly of that Union 
territory to be nominated by the Speaker of the 
Assembly from among the members thereof.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>217638</tid>
<number>2</number>The nomination of members of the several Legislative 
Assemblies under sub- section (1) shall be made by the respective 
Speakers thereof as soon as practicable and shall be communicated to 
the Delimitation Commission.

</section>

<section><tid>1557805</tid>
<number>3</number>If owing to death or resignation the office of an associate 
member falls vacant, it shall be filled as soon as practicable under 
and in accordance with the foregoing provisions of this section.

</section>

<section><tid>355429</tid>
<number>4</number>None of the associate members shall have the right to vote or 
to sign any decision of the Delimitation Commission.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>495692</tid>
<number>43</number>Procedure as to delimitation.-- The provisions of sections 7, 
9, 10 and 11 of the Delimitation Commission Act, <year>1962</year> (61 of <year>1962</year>), 
shall apply, as far as may be, in relation to the delimitation of 
parliamentary and assembly constituencies under this Part as they 
apply in relation to the delimitation of parliamentary and assembly 
constituencies under that Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>720</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1540826</tid>
<number> 43A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Special provision for delimitation of constituencies of 
Mizoram Legislative Assembly.--
<section><tid>250902</tid>
<number>1</number>The provisions of sections 39 to  
 43 (both inclusive) shall not apply to the delimitation of 
constituencies for the purpose of elections to the Legislative 
Assembly of the Union territory of Mizoram.

</section>

<section><tid>1900494</tid>
<number>2</number>The Election Commission shall, in the manner herein provided, 
distribute the seats assigned to the Legislative Assembly of the Union 
territory of Mizoram under sub- section (2) of section 3 to single 
member assembly constituencies and delimit them on the basis of the 
latest census figures having regard to the provisions of the 
Constitution and to the following provisions:--

<subsection><tid>978063</tid>
<number>a</number>all constituencies shall, as far as practicable, be 
geographically compact areas;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1960430</tid>
<number>b</number>in delimiting the constituencies, regard shall be had to 
physical features, existing boundaries of 
administrative units, facilities of communication and 
public convenience.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1669269</tid>
<number>3</number>For the purpose of assisting in the performance of its 
functions under sub- section (2), the Election Commission shall 
associate with itself as associate members--

<subsection><tid>1246095</tid>
<number>a</number>all the persons who, having been elected to the 
Legislative Assembly of the State of Assam from the 
Lungleh, Aijal East and Aijal West territorial 
constituencies, are members of that Assembly 
immediately before the day appointed under clause (b) 
of section 2 of the North- Eastern Areas 
 (Reorganisation) Act, <year>1971</year> (81 of <year>1971</year>); and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1851969</tid>
<number>b</number>such three elected members of the District Council of 
the Mizo District as the Chairman thereof may nominate:
Provided that none of the associate members shall have a right to 
vote or sign any decision of the Election Commission.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>617600</tid>
<number>4</number>If, owing to death or resignation, the office of an associate 
member falls vacant, it shall be filled, if practicable, in accordance 
with the provisions of sub- section (3).

</section>

<section><tid>1674345</tid>
<number>5</number>The Election Commission shall--

<subsection><tid>1018264</tid>
<number>a</number>publish its proposals for the delimitation of 
constituencies, together with the dissenting proposals, 
if any, of any associate member who desires publication 
thereof in the Official Gazette and in such other 
manner as the Commission
<pagefootnote><pagenum>721</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 83 of <year>1971</year>, s. 10 (w. e. f. 16- 2- <year>1972</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


may consider fit, together with a notice inviting 
objections and suggestions in relation to the proposals 
and specifying a date on or after which the proposals 
will be further considered by it;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>193272</tid>
<number>b</number>consider all objections and suggestions which may have 
been received by it before the date so specified;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1532045</tid>
<number>c</number>after consideration of objections and suggestions which 
may have been received by it before the date so 
specified, determine by one or more orders the 
delimitation of constituencies and cause such order or 
orders to be published in the Official Gazette; and 
upon such publication, the order or orders shall have 
the full force of law and shall not be called in 
question in any court.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>92759</tid>
<number>6</number>The Election Commission may, from time to time, by 
notification in the Official Gazette,--

<subsection><tid>691856</tid>
<number>a</number>correct any printing mistake in any order made under 
sub- section (5) or any error arising therein from 
inadvertent slip or omission;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1997770</tid>
<number>b</number>where the boundaries or name of any territorial division 
mentioned in any such order or orders are or is 
altered, make such amendments as appear to it to be 
necessary or expedient for bringing such order up- to- 
date.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>364141</tid>
<number>7</number>Every order made under sub- section (5) and every notification 
issued under sub- section (6) shall be laid as soon as may be after it 
is made or issued before the Legislative Assembly of the Union 
territory of Mizoram.

</section>

<section><tid>387099</tid>
<number>8</number>All things done, and all steps taken, before the commencement 
of this Act in the Union territory of Mizoram with a view to 
delimiting the territorial constituencies of that Union territory for 
purposes of elections to the Legislative Assembly of that Union 
territory shall, in so far as they are in conformity with the 
foregoing provisions of this section, be deemed to have been done or 
taken under those provisions as if those provisions were in force at 
the time such things were done or such steps were taken.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>722</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


<pagefootnote><pagenum>43B</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Representation of Arunachal Pradesh in the House of the people.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1849660</tid>
<number>43B</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Representation of Arunachal Pradesh in the House of the 
people. In the House of the People to be constituted after the general 
election to that House to be held after the commencement of the 
Government of Union Territories (Amendment) Act, <year>1975</year> (29 of <year>1975</year>) 
and thereafter, there shall be allotted two seats to the Union 
territory of Arunachal Pradesh and the First Schedule to the 
Representation of the People Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of <year>1950</year>) shall be deemed 
to have been amended accordingly.


</article>



<article><tid>1331885</tid>
<number> 43C</number> Special provisions for delimitation of parliamentary 
constituencies in Arunachal Pradesh and constituencies of Arunachal 
Pradesh Legislative Assembly.
<section><tid>1844410</tid>
<number>1</number>The provisions of sections 39 to 43  
 (both inclusive) shall not apply to the delimitation of parliamentary 
constituencies in the Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh or to the 
delimitation of constituencies for the purpose of elections to the 
Legislative Assembly of that Union territory.

</section>

<section><tid>1219696</tid>
<number>2</number>The Election Commission shall divide the Union territory of 
Arunachal Pradesh into two single- member parliamentary constituencies 
on the basis of the latest census figures.

</section>

<section><tid>668840</tid>
<number>3</number>The Election Commission shall also, in the manner herein 
provided, distribute the seats assigned to the Legislative Assembly of 
the Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh under sub- section (2) of 
section 3 to single- member assembly constituencies and delimit them on 
the basis of the latest census figures having regard to the following 
provisions:--

<subsection><tid>105156</tid>
<number>a</number>all constituencies shall, as far as practicable, be 
geographically compact areas;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1640323</tid>
<number>b</number>every assembly constituency shall be so delimited as to 
fall only within one parliamentary constituency;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1375391</tid>
<number>c</number>in delimiting the constituencies, regard shall be had to 
physical features, existing boundaries of 
administrative units facilities of communication and 
public convenience.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>309203</tid>
<number>4</number>For the purpose of assisting in the performance of its 
functions under sub- sections (2) and (3), the Election Commission 
shall associate with itself as associate members--

<subsection><tid>1279232</tid>
<number>a</number>the member of the House of the People representing the 
Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1836606</tid>
<number>b</number>such five members of the Legislative Assembly of the 
Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh as the Speaker of
<pagefootnote><pagenum>722A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 29 of <year>1975</year>, s. 8 (w. e. f. 15- 8- <year>1975</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


that Assembly shall, having regard to the composition 
of the Legislative Assembly, nominate:

Provided that none of the associate members shall have a right to 
vote or sign any decision of the Election Commission.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>226992</tid>
<number>5</number>If owing to death or resignation, the office of an associate 
member falls vacant, it shall be filled, if practicable, in accordance 
with the provisions of sub- section (4).

</section>

<section><tid>1665512</tid>
<number>6</number>The Election Commission shall--

<subsection><tid>387384</tid>
<number>a</number>publish its proposals for the delimitation of 
constituencies together with the dissenting proposals, 
if any, of any associate member who desires publication 
thereof in the Official Gazette and in such other 
manner as the Commission may consider fit, together 
with a notice inviting objections and suggestions in 
relation to the proposals and specifying a date on or 
after which the proposals will be further considered by 
it;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>709993</tid>
<number>b</number>consider all objections and suggestions which may have 
been received by it before the date so specified;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>326234</tid>
<number>c</number>after consideration of objections and suggestions which 
may have been received by it before the date so 
specified, determine by one or more orders the 
delimitation of constituencies and cause such order or 
orders to be published in the Official Gazette; and 
upon such publication, the order or orders shall have 
the full force of law and shall not be called in 
question in any court.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>763492</tid>
<number>7</number>The Election Commission may, from time to time, by 
notification in the Official Gazette,--

<subsection><tid>843955</tid>
<number>a</number>correct any printing mistake in any order made under 
sub- section (6) or any error arising therein from 
inadvertent slip or omission;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>552275</tid>
<number>b</number>where the boundaries or name of any territorial division 
mentioned in any such order or orders are or is 
altered, make such amendments as appear to it to be 
necessary or expedient for bringing such order up- to- 
date.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>722517</tid>
<number>8</number>Every order made under sub- section (6) and every notification 
issued under sub- section (7) shall be laid as soon as may be after

<pagefootnote><pagenum>722B</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

it is made or issued before the House of the People and the 
Legislative Assembly of the Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh.


</section>

<section><tid>1457280</tid>
<number>9</number>All things done, and all steps taken, before the commencement 
of this Act in the Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh with a view to 
delimiting the territorial constituencies of that Union territory for 
purposes of elections to the Legislative Assembly of that Union 
territory shall, in so far as they are in conformity with the 
foregoing provisions of this section, be deemed to have been done or 
taken under those provisions as if these provisions were in force at 
the time such things were done or such steps were taken.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1113710</tid>
<number> 43D</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Special provision for determination of constituencies in 
the Legislative Assembly of Goa, Daman and Diu for Scheduled Castes 
and Scheduled Tribes.
<section><tid>424683</tid>
<number>1</number>The Election Commission shall determine on  
the basis of the latest census figures--

<subsection><tid>943242</tid>
<number>i</number>the number of seats to be reserved for the Scheduled 
Castes and for the Scheduled Tribes in the Legislative 
Assembly of the Union territory of Goa, Daman and 
Diu (hereafter in this section referred to as the  
  Legislative Assembly) having regard to the provisions 
of sub- section (5) of section 3; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1432901</tid>
<number>ii</number>the constituencies in which those seats shall be so 
reserved having regard to the provisions of clause (c), 
or, as the case may be, clause (d), of sub- section (1) 
of section 9 of the Delimitation Act and without 
altering the extent of any constituency as delimited by 
the Delimitation Commission.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1187799</tid>
<number>2</number>The Election Commission shall--

<subsection><tid>464311</tid>
<number>a</number>publish its proposals for the determination of the 
constituencies in which seats shall be reserved for the 
Scheduled Castes or for the Scheduled Tribes, as the 
case may be, in the Gazette of India and in the 
Official Gazette of the Union territory of Goa, Daman 
and Diu and also in such other manner as the Election 
Commission may consider fit, together with a notice 
inviting objections and suggestions in relation to the 
proposals and specifying a date on or after which the 
proposals will be further considered by it;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1227004</tid>
<number>b</number>consider all objections and suggestions which may have 
been received by it before the date so specified;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>722C</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 86 of <year>1976</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 30- 9- <year>1976</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1910901</tid>
<number>c</number>after consideration of objections and suggestions which 
may have been received by it before the date so 
specified, determine by one or more orders the number 
of seats to be reserved for the Scheduled Castes or for 
the Scheduled Tribes, as the case may be, in the 
Legislative Assembly and the constituencies in which 
those seats shall be so reserved and cause such order 
or orders to be published in the Gazette of India and 
in the Official Gazette of the Union territory of Goa, 
Daman and Diu; and upon such publication in the Gazette 
of India, the order or orders shall have the full force 
of law and shall not be called in question in any court 
and the Second Schedule to the Representation of the 
People Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of <year>1950</year>) and the order made by 
the Delimitation Commission under section 9 of the 
Delimitation Act in relation to the Legislative 
Assembly shall be deemed to have been amended 
accordingly.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>138298</tid>
<number>3</number>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (4), the re- 
adjustment of representation of any territorial constituencies in the 
Legislative Assembly necessitated by any order made by the Election 
Commission under this section, shall apply in relation to every 
election to the Legislative Assembly held after the publication in the 
Gazette of India, under sub- section (2), of such order.

</section>

<section><tid>189364</tid>
<number>4</number>Nothing contained in the foregoing sub- sections shall affect 
the representation in the Legislative Assembly existing on the date of 
publication in the Gazette of India, under sub- section (2), of any 
order made by the Election Commission.

</section>

<section><tid>1782885</tid>
<number>5</number>The Election Commission may, from time to time, by 
notification in the Gazette of India and in the Official Gazette of 
the Union territory of Goa, Daman and Diu--

<subsection><tid>1590051</tid>
<number>a</number>correct any printing mistake in any order made under 
sub- section (2) or any error arising therein from 
inadvertent slip or omission;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>722D</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>528357</tid>
<number>b</number>where the boundaries or name of any territorial division 
mentioned in any such order are, or is, altered, make 
such amendments as appear to it to be necessary or 
expedient for bringing such order up- to- date.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>279449</tid>
<number>6</number>Every order made under sub- section (2) and every notification 
issued under sub- section (5) shall be laid, as soon as may be, after 
it is made or issued before the Legislative Assembly.
Explanation.-- In this section,--


<subsection><tid>198059</tid>
<number>a</number>" Delimitation Act" means the Delimitation Act, <year>1972</year> (76  
  of <year>1972</year>);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>281855</tid>
<number>b</number>" Delimitation Commission" means the Delimitation 
Commission constituted under section 3 of the 
Delimitation Act.]



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>262783</tid>
<number>43E</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Special provisions as to readjustment of territorial 
constituencies. Notwithstanding anything contained in sections 38 to 
 43D (both inclusive), until the relevant figures for the first census 
taken after the year <year>2000</year> have been published, it shall not be 
necessary to readjust the division of each Union territory into 
territorial constituencies and any reference to the" latest census 
figures" in this Part shall be construed as a reference to the <year>1971</year> 
census figures.]
PART

COUNCIL OF MINISTERS

PART IV

COUNCIL OF MINISTERS



</article>



<article><tid>1861368</tid>
<number> 44</number> Council of Ministers.
<section><tid>1014746</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be a Council of  
Ministers in each Union territory with the Chief Minister at the head 
to aid and advise the Administrator in the exercise of his functions 
in relation to matters with respect to which the Legislative Assembly 
of the Union territory has power to make laws except in so far as he 
is required by or under this Act to act in his discretion or by or 
under any law to exercise any judicial or quasi- judicial functions:
Provided that, in case of difference of opinion between the 
Administrator and his Ministers on any matter, the Administrator shall 
refer it to the President for decision and act according to the 
decision given thereon by the President, and pending such decision it 
shall be competent for the Administrator in any case where the matter 
is in his opinion so urgent that it is necessary for him to take 
immediate action, to take such action or to give such direction in the 
matter as he deems necessary:

<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>

<pagefootnote><pagenum>722E</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 19 of <year>1984</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 1- 3- <year>1984</year>). 
2. Omitted by Act 34 of <year>1986</year>, s. 41 (w. e. f. 20- 2- <year>1987</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>


</section>

<section><tid>1234072</tid>
<number>3</number>If and in so far as any special responsibility of the 
Administrator is involved under this Act, he shall, in the exercise of 
his functions, act in his discretion.

</section>

<section><tid>1739159</tid>
<number>4</number>If any question arises as to whether any matter is or is not 
a matter as respects which the Administrator is by or under this Act 
required to act in his discretion, the decision of the Administrator 
thereon shall be final.

</section>

<section><tid>1528740</tid>
<number>5</number>If any question arises as to whether any matter is or is not 
a matter as respects which the Administrator is required by any law to 
exercise any judicial or quasi- judicial functions, the decision of the 
Administrator thereon shall be final.

</section>

<section><tid>1313608</tid>
<number>6</number>The question whether any, and if so what, advice was tendered 
by Ministers to the Administrator shall not be inquired into in any 
court.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>723</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Omitted by Act 69 of <year>1986</year>, s. 44 (w. e. f. 20- 2- <year>1987</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1002680</tid>
<number> 45</number> Other provisions as to Ministers.
<section><tid>1677904</tid>
<number>1</number>The Chief Minister  
shall be appointed by the President and the other Ministers shall be 
appointed by the President on the advice of the Chief Ministers.

</section>

<section><tid>131846</tid>
<number>2</number>The Ministers shall hold office during the pleasure of the 
President.

</section>

<section><tid>1231330</tid>
<number>3</number>The Council of Ministers shall be collectively responsible to 
the Legislative Assembly of the Union territory.

</section>

<section><tid>493712</tid>
<number>4</number>Before a Minister enters upon his office, the Administrator 
shall administer to him the oaths of office and of secrecy according 
to the forms set out for the purpose in the First Schedule.

</section>

<section><tid>885131</tid>
<number>5</number>A Minister who for any period of six consecutive months is 
not a member of the Legislative Assembly of the Union territory shall 
at the expiration of that period cease to be a Minister.

</section>

<section><tid>1804326</tid>
<number>6</number>The salaries and allowances of Ministers shall be such as the 
Legislative Assembly of the Union territory may from time to time by 
law determine, and until the Legislative Assembly so determines, shall 
be determined by the Administrator with the approval of the President.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>334242</tid>
<number> 46</number> Conduct of business.
<section><tid>1941993</tid>
<number>1</number>The President shall make rules-- 

<subsection><tid>1702517</tid>
<number>a</number>for the allocation of business to the Ministers; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1987125</tid>
<number>b</number>for the more convenient transaction of business with the 
Ministers including the procedure to be adopted in the 
case of a difference of opinion between the 
Administrator and the Council of Ministers or a 
Minister.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>448119</tid>
<number>2</number>Save as otherwise provided in this Act, all executive action 
of the Administrator, whether taken on the advice of his Ministers or 
otherwise, shall be expressed to be taken in the name of the 
Administrator.

</section>

<section><tid>1984609</tid>
<number>3</number>Orders and other instruments made and executed in the name of 
the Administrator, shall be authenticated in such manner as may be 
specified in rules to be made by the Administrator, and the validity 
of an order or instrument which is so authenticated shall not be 
called in question on the ground that it is not an order or instrument 
made or executed by the Administrator.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>724</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

PART

MISCELLANEOUS AND TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS

PART V

MISCELLANEOUS AND TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>593114</tid>
<number> 47</number> Consolidated Fund of the Union territory.
<section><tid>1318165</tid>
<number>1</number>As from such  
date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, appoint in this behalf, all revenues received in <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the Union 
territory] by the Government of India or the Administrator of the 
Union territory in relation to any matter with respect to which the 
Legislative Assembly of the Union territory has power to make laws, 
and all grants made and all loans advanced to the Union territory 
from the Consolidated Fund of India and all moneys received by the 
Union territory in repayment of loans shall form one Consolidated Fund 
to be entitled" the Consolidated Fund of the Union territory".

</section>

<section><tid>1817134</tid>
<number>2</number>No moneys out of the Consolidated Fund of <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the Union 
territory] shall be appropriated except in accordance with, and for 
the purposes and in the manner provided in, this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>779193</tid>
<number>3</number>The custody of the Consolidated Fund of <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the Union 
territory], the payment of moneys into such Fund, the withdrawal of 
moneys therefrom and all other matters connected with or ancillary to 
those matters shall be regulated by rules made by the Administrator 
with the approval of the President.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1856935</tid>
<number> 48</number> Contingency Fund of the Union territory.
<section><tid>1094061</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be  
established a Contingency Fund in the nature of an imprest to be 
entitled" the Contingency Fund of the Union territory" into which 
shall be paid from and out of the Consolidated Fund of the Union 
territory such sums as may, from time to time, be determined by law 
made by the Legislative Assembly of the Union territory; and the said 
Fund shall be held by the Administrator to enable advances to be made 
by him out of such Fund.

</section>

<section><tid>188602</tid>
<number>2</number>No advances shall be made out of the Contingency Fund of the 
Union territory except for the purposes of meeting unforeseen 
expenditure pending authorisation of such expenditure by the 
Legislative Assembly of the Union territory under appropriations made 
by law.

</section>

<section><tid>1228734</tid>
<number>3</number>The Administrator may make rules regulating all matters 
connected with or ancillary to the custody of, the payment of moneys 
into, and the withdrawal of moneys from, the Contingency Fund of the 
Union territory.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>358864</tid>
<number> 49</number> Audit reports. The reports of the Comptroller and Auditor- 
General of India relating to the accounts of <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the Union territory] 
for any period subsequent to the date referred to in sub- section
<section><tid>1768662</tid>
<number>1</number> 
of section 47 shall be submitted to the Administrator who shall cause 
them to be laid before the Legislative Assembly of the Union 
territory.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>410233</tid>
<number>50</number>Relation of Administrator and his Ministers to President. 
Notwithstanding anything in this Act, the Administrator and his 
Council of Ministers shall be under the general control of, and comply 
with such particular directions, if any, as may from time to time be 
given by, the President.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>725</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The Consolidated Fund of the Union Territory of Mizoram shall 
come into existence w. e. f. 3- 5- <year>1972</year>: vide Notification No. S. O. 
330 (E), dated 1- 4- <year>1972</year>, Gazette of India, Extraordinary, Pt. II, 
Sec. 3 (ii), p. 897. 
2. Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1987</year>, s. 65, for" a Union territory" (w. e. f.  
  30- 5- <year>1987</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>517872</tid>
<number> 51</number> Provision in case of failure of constitutional machinery. If 
the President, on receipt of a report from the Administrator of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the 
Union territory] or otherwise, is satisfied,--
<section><tid>1564787</tid>
<number>a</number>that a situation has arisen in which the administration 
of the Union territory cannot be carried on in 
accordance with the provisions of this Act, or

</section>

<section><tid>739600</tid>
<number>b</number>that for the proper administration of the Union 
territory it is necessary or expedient so to do,
the President may, by order, suspend the operation of all or any of 
the provisions of this Act for such period as he thinks fit and make 
such incidental and consequential provisions as may appear to him to 
be necessary or expedient for administering the Union territory in 
accordance with the provisions of article 239.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1377303</tid>
<number>52</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Authorisation of expenditure by President. Where the 
Legislative Assembly of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory] is dissolved, or its 
functioning as such Assembly remains suspended, on account of an order 
under section 51, it shall be competent for the President to authorise 
when the House of the People is not in session expenditure from the 
Consolidated Fund of that Union territory pending the sanction of such 
expenditure by Parliament.]


</article>



<article><tid>1488925</tid>
<number> 53</number> Provisions for election to Parliament from Goa, Daman and 
Diu, and Pondicherry.
<section><tid>638774</tid>
<number>1</number>As soon as practicable after the  
commencement of this Act, elections shall be held in accordance with 
law--

<subsection><tid>62170</tid>
<number>a</number>to fill the seats in the House of the People allotted to 
the Union territory of Goa, Daman and Diu; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1898134</tid>
<number>b</number>to fill the seat in the House of the People and the seat 
in the Council of States allotted to the Union 
territory of Pondicherry.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>127635</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the 
time being in force, the members nominated to represent the Union 
territory of Goa, Daman and Diu in the House of the People shall 
continue to be such until the election of the members to fill the two 
seats in that House allotted to that Union territory:
Provided that where the dates of election of the members are 
different, the members so nominated shall cease to be members of that 
House on the earlier of those two dates.

Explanation.-- In this sub- section, the expression" date of 
election" has the same meaning as in section 67A of the Representation 
of the People Act, <year>1951</year> (43 of <year>1951</year>).

<pagefootnote><pagenum>726</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1987</year>, s. 65, for" a Union territory" (w. e. f.  
  30- 5- <year>1987</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 1 of <year>1980</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 25- 9- <year>1979</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>737434</tid>
<number> 54</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Transitional provisions for administration of justice in 
certain areas in the Union territory of Mizoram. On and from the 
commencement of this Act in the Union territory of Mizoram and until 
other provisions in this behalf are made by a competent Legislature or 
other competent authority, the administration of justice in those 
areas of that Union territory which are not comprised in any 
autonomous district under the Sixth Schedule to the Constitution shall 
be carried on, so far as may be, in accordance with the provisions of 
paragraphs 4 and 5 of that Schedule, as if those areas were comprised 
in an autonomous district under that Schedule and the provisions of 
the said paragraphs were in force in those areas and for this 
purpose,--
<section><tid>762607</tid>
<number>i</number>all powers and functions of a District Council under the 
provisions of the said paragraph 4 shall be exercised 
and discharged by the Administrator or any officer 
appointed by him in this behalf;

</section>

<section><tid>1355821</tid>
<number>ii</number>the said paragraph 5 shall have effect as if references 
to the District Council, the Regional Council and the 
courts constituted by the District Council, by whatever 
form of words, had been omitted therefrom; and

</section>

<section><tid>1817432</tid>
<number>iii</number>references to Governor in the said paragraphs 4 and 5 
shall be construed as references to the Administrator.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1364137</tid>
<number> 54A</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Provision as to provisional Legislative Assembly of 
Arunachal Pradesh.
<section><tid>35668</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act  
 (including provisions relating to the strength of the Legislative  
  Assembly of the Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh), until the 
Legislative Assembly of the Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh has 
been duly constituted and summoned to meet for the first session under 
and in accordance with the provisions of this Act, there shall be a 
provisional Legislative Assembly which shall consist of members, being 
those persons referred to in clauses (b), (c) and (d) of section 3 of 
the North- East Frontier Agency (Administration) Supplementary 
Regulation, <year>1971</year> (4 of <year>1971</year>) and who are functioning, immediately 
before the commencement of this Act in the Union territory of 
Arunachal Pradesh, as members of the Pradesh Council constituted under 
the said section 3.

</section>

<section><tid>291030</tid>
<number>2</number>The term of office of the members of the provisional 
Legislative Assembly shall expire immediately before the first meeting 
of the Legislative Assembly duly constituted after the first general 
election to that Assembly.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>726A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 83 of <year>1971</year>, s. 12, for s. 54 (w. e. f. 16- 2- <year>1972</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 29 of <year>1975</year>, s. 10.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>180605</tid>
<number>3</number>The provisional Legislative Assembly constituted under this 
section shall, for so long as it is in existence, be deemed to be the 
Legislative Assembly duly constituted under this Act and accordingly 
the other provisions of this Act, so far as may be, apply in relation 
to the provisional Legislative Assembly as they apply in relation to 
the Legislative Assembly.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1265452</tid>
<number> 55</number> Contracts and suits. For the removal of doubts it is hereby 
declared that--
<section><tid>1799488</tid>
<number>a</number>all contracts in connection with the administration of 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory] are contracts made in the 
exercise of the executive power of the Union;

</section>

<section><tid>1156056</tid>
<number>b</number>all suits and proceedings in connection with the 
administration of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory] shall be 
instituted by or against the Government of India.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1476297</tid>
<number>56</number>Power of President to remove difficulties. If any difficulty 
arises in relation to the transition from the provisions of any of the 
laws repealed by this Act or in giving effect to the provisions of 
this Act and, in particular, in relation to the constitution of the 
Legislative Assembly for <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the Union territory], the President may by 
order do anything not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act 
which appear to him to be necessary or expedient for the purpose of 
removing the difficulty.


</article>



<article><tid>656416</tid>
<number> 57</number> Amendment to certain- enactments.
<section><tid>1953989</tid>
<number>1</number>The enactments specified  
in the Second Schedule--

<subsection><tid>1265316</tid>
<number>a</number>shall, together with all rules, notifications and orders 
made or issued thereunder, extend to and come into 
force in the Union territories of Goa, Daman and Diu, 
and Pondicherry; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>140787</tid>
<number>b</number>shall be subject to the amendments mentioned in the 
fourth column of the said Schedule.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>382256</tid>
<number>2</number>All things done, and all steps taken, before the commencement 
of this Act in connection with the preparation or revision of 
electoral rolls for the purpose of elections to the House of the 
People from the Union territories of Goa, Daman and Diu, and 
Pondicherry, and to the Legislative Assemblies of those Union 
territories shall, in so far as they are in conformity with the 
provisions of the Represen-
<pagefootnote><pagenum>727</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1987</year>, s. 65, for" a Union territory" (w. e. f.  
  30- 5- <year>1987</year>). 
2. Subs. by s. 65, ibid., for" any Union territory" (w. e. f.  
  30- 5- <year>1987</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


tation of the People Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of <year>1950</year>), as amended by this Act, 
be deemed to have been done in accordance with law.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1058258</tid>
<number> 58</number> Repeal and savings.
<section><tid>1129103</tid>
<number>1</number>The following laws are hereby  
repealed:--

<subsection><tid>732836</tid>
<number>a</number>the Territorial Councils Act, <year>1956</year> (103 of <year>1956</year>);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>889128</tid>
<number>b</number>the Decree No. 46- 2381, dated the 25th October, <year>1946</year>, as 
subsequently amended, relating to the Representative 
Assembly of the State of Pondicherry;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1520745</tid>
<number>c</number>the Decree No. 47- 1490, dated the 12th August, <year>1947</year>, as 
subsequently amended, relating to the setting up of a 
Council of Government in the State of Pondicherry;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>538524</tid>
<number>d</number>the State of Pondicherry (Representation of the People) 
Order, <year>1955</year>, in so far as it relates to the 
Representative Assembly of Pondicherry.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1872247</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding the repeal of the Territorial Councils Act, 
 <year>1956</year> (103 of <year>1956</year>),--

<subsection><tid>1714775</tid>
<number>a</number>every officer and other employee of the Territorial 
Council of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Union territory] serving under the 
Council immediately before such repeal shall become an 
officer or other employee of Government and shall be 
employed in connection with the administration of the 
Union territory with such designation as the 
Administrator may determine and shall hold office by 
the same tenure and at the same remuneration and on the 
same terms and conditions of service as he would have 
but for such repeal held the same and shall continue to 
do so unless and until such tenure, remuneration and 
terms and conditions are duly altered by the 
Administrator:
Provided that--


<subsubsection><tid>825842</tid>
<number>i</number>the tenure, remuneration and terms and 
conditions of service of any such officer or other 
employee shall not be altered to his disadvantage 
without the previous sanction of the Central 
Government;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>725197</tid>
<number>ii</number>any service rendered by any such officer 
or other employee before such repeal shall be 
deemed to be service rendered in connection with 
the administration of the Union territory;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1857315</tid>
<number>iii</number>the Administrator may employ any such 
officer or other employee in the discharge of such 
functions as the Administrator may think proper 
and every such officer or other employee shall 
discharge those functions accordingly;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>728</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1987</year>, s. 65, for" a Union territory" (w. e. f.  
  30- 5- <year>1987</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>740597</tid>
<number>b</number>anything done or any action taken (including any  
notification, order, scheme, rule, form, notice or bye- 
  law made or issued, any licence or permission granted) 
under the repealed Act shall in so far as it is not 
inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, continue 
in force unless and until it is superseded by anything 
done or any action taken in accordance with law;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1803310</tid>
<number>c</number>all debts, obligations and liabilities incurred, all 
contracts entered into and all matters and things 
engaged to be done by, with or for the Territorial 
Council before such repeal shall be deemed to have been 
incurred, entered into or engaged to be done in 
exercise of the executive power of the Union for the 
purposes of the administration of the Union territory;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1507016</tid>
<number>d</number>all assessments, valuations, measurements or divisions 
made by the Territorial Council shall, in so far as 
they are not inconsistent with the provisions of this 
Act, continue in force unless and until they are 
superseded by any assessment, valuation, measurement or 
division made by the Administrator in accordance with 
law;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>500877</tid>
<number>e</number>all properties, movable and immovable, and all interests 
of whatsoever nature and kind, vested in the 
Territorial Council immediately before such repeal 
shall, with all rights of whatsoever description, used, 
enjoyed or possessed by that Council, vest in the Union 
for the purposes of the administration of the Union 
territory;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1910983</tid>
<number>f</number>all rates, taxes, cesses, fees, rents, fares and other 
charges which immediately before such repeal were being 
lawfully levied by the Territorial Council shall 
continue to be levied at the same rate at which they 
were being levied by the Council immediately before 
such repeal until provision to the contrary is made by 
law;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>201255</tid>
<number>g</number>all rates, taxes, cesses, fees, rents, fares and other 
charges due to the Territorial Council immediately 
before such repeal shall be deemed to be due to the 
Union in connection with the administration of the 
Union territory;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1275504</tid>
<number>h</number>all suits, prosecutions and other legal proceedings 
instituted or which might have been instituted by or 
against the Territorial Council may be continued or 
instituted by or against the Government of India.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>729</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



 </act>