<act><title>THE FOREIGN EXCHANGE MANAGEMENT (REMITTANCE OF ASSETS) REGULATIONS, 20001</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>i</number> These regulations may be called the Foreign Exchange Management (Remittance of Assets) Regulations, 2000. 
 
 


</section><section><number>ii</number> They shall come into effect on 1st day of June, 2000. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>In these regulations, unless the context requires otherwise, 
 
 <section><number>i</number> Act' means the Foreign Exchange Management Act, 1999 (42 of 1999); 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> authorised dealer' means a person authorised as an authorised dealer under sub-section (1) of section 10 of the Act; 
 </section><section><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>iii</number> Non-resident Indian (NRI)' means a person resident outside India who is a citizen of India ;] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>iv</number>] Person of Indian Origin (PIO)' means a citizen of any country other than Bangladesh or Pakistan , if 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> he at any time held Indian passport; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> he or either of his parents or any of his grand-parents was a citizen of India by virtue of the Constitution of India or the Citizenship Act, 1955 (57 of 1955); or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the person is a spouse of an Indian citizen or a person referred to in sub-clause (a) or (b); 
</subsection>
 </section><section><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>v</number>] remittance of asset' means remittance outside India of funds representing a deposit with a bank or a firm or a company, provident fund balance or superannuation benefits, amount of claim or maturity proceeds of Insurance policy, sale proceeds of shares, securities, immovable property or any other asset held in India in accordance with the provisions of the Act or rules or regulations made thereunder; 
 </section><section><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> [<number>vi</number>] the words and expressions used but not defined in these regulations shall have the same meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act. 
</section>




</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Prohibition on remittance outside India of assets held in India. </title>Save as otherwise provided in the Act or rules or regulations made or issued thereunder, no person whether resident in India or not, shall make remittance of any asset held in India by him or by any other person: 
 Provided that the Reserve Bank may, for sufficient reasons, permit any person to make remittance of any asset held in India by him or by any other person. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Permission for remittance of assets in certain cases. </title> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number> A person specified in sub-regulations (2) and (3) may make remittance of assets through an authorised dealer, to the extent specified in those sub-regulations.] 
 </section><section><number>2</number> A citizen of foreign state, not being a citizen of Nepal or Bhutan or a Person of Indian Origin (PIO), who 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> has retired from an employment in India ; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> has inherited the assets from a person referred to in sub-section (5) of section 6 of the Act; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> is a widow resident outside India and has inherited assets of her deceased husband who was an Indian citizen resident in India , may remit an amount, not exceeding <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[ <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[US $ 1,000,000 (US Dollar one million only)] per <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[financial] year], on production of, 
 
 <subsubsection><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>a</number> documentary evidence in support of acquisition, inheritance or legacy of assets by the remitter; and] 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[an undertaking by the remitter and certificate from a Chartered Accountant in the format prescribed by the Central Board of Direct Taxes, Ministry of Finance, Government of India in their Circular No. 10/2002, dated October 9, 2002:] 
</subsubsection>
</subsection>
 Provided that for purpose of arriving at annual ceiling of remittance under the sub-regulation (2), the funds representing sale proceeds of shares and immovable property owned or held by the citizen of foreign state on repatriation basis in accordance with the Foreign Exchange Management (Acquisition and Transfer of Immovable Property in India) Regulations, 2000 and Foreign Exchange Management (Transfer of Indian Security by a Person Resident Outside India) Regulations, 2000 made under the Act, shall not be included: 
 Provided further that where the remittance is made in more than one instalment, the remittance of all instalments shall be made through the same authorised dealer. 
 
 <subsection><number>iv</number> had come to India for studies/training and has completed his studies/training, may remit the balance available in his account, provided such balance represents funds derived out of remittances received from abroad through normal banking channels or rupees proceeds of foreign exchange brought by such person and sold to an authorised dealer or out of stipend/scholarship received from the Government or any Organisation in India. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>3</number> A Non-Resident Indian (NRI)/Person of Indian Origin (PIO), may remit an amount, not exceeding US $ 1,000,000 (US dollar one million only) per <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[financial] year, 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> Out of the balances held in NRO accounts/sale proceeds of assets/the assets in India acquired by him by way of inheritance/legacy on production of 
 
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> documentary evidence in support of acquisition, inheritance or legacy of assets by the remitter, and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[an undertaking by the remitter and certificate from a Chartered Accountant in the format prescribed by the Central Board of Direct Taxes, Ministry of Finance, Government of India in their Circular No. 10/2002 dated October 9, 2002.] 
</subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> Under a deed of settlement made by either of his parents or a close relative (as defined in section 6 of the Companies Act, 1956) and the settlement taking effect on the death of the settler, on production of 
 
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> the original deed of settlement; and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[an undertaking by the remitter and certificate from a Chartered Accountant in the format prescribed by the Central Board of Direct Taxes, Ministry of Finance, Government of India in their Circular No. 10/2002 dated October 9, 2002.] 
</subsubsection>
</subsection>
 <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[***] 
 Provided <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[***] that where the remittance under clauses (i) and (ii) is made in more than one instalment, the remittance of all instalments shall be made through the same authorised dealer.] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[<number>4</number> An Authorised dealer in India may, without approval from Reserve Bank, effect remittance of assets made by a person eligible under sub-  
  regulation (2) or sub-regulation (3) as the case may be and also allow remittance out of the assets of Indian companies under liquidation under the provisions of the Companies Act, 1956, subject to the following conditions: 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> Authorised Dealer shall ensure that the remittance is in compliance with the order issued by a court in India/order issued by the official liquidator or the liquidator in the case of voluntary winding up; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> no remittance shall be allowed unless the applicant submits 
 
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> No objection or Tax clearance certificate from Income Tax authority for the remittance. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> Auditor's certificate confirming that all liabilities in India have been either fully paid or adequately provided for. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>c</number> Auditor's certificate to the effect that the winding up is in accordance with the provisions of the Companies Act, 1956. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>d</number> In case of winding up otherwise than by a court, an auditor's certificate to the effect that there is no legal proceedings pending in any court in India against the applicant or the company under liquidation and there is no legal impediment in permitting the remittance.] 
</subsubsection>
</subsection>












</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Permission to an Indian entity to remit funds in certain cases. </title>An entry in India may remit the amount being its contribution towards the provident fund/superannuation/pension fund in respect of the expatriate staff in its employment who are resident in India but not permanently resident therein. 
 Explanation .For the purpose of this regulation, 
 
 <section><number>a</number> expatriate staff means a person whose provident/superannuating/pension fund is maintained outside India by his principal employer outside India ; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> not permanently resident' means a person resident in India for employment of a specified duration (irrespective of length thereof) or for a specific job or assignment, the duration of which does not exceed three years. 
</section>


</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Reserve Bank's prior permission in certain cases. </title>
<section><number>1</number> A person who desires to make a remittance of assets in the following cases, may apply to the Reserve Bank, namely: 
 
 <subsection><footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[<number>i</number> Remittance exceeding US $ 1,000,000 (US Dollar one million only) per calendar year 
 
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> on account of legacy, bequest or inheritance to a citizen of foreign State, permanently resident outside India ; and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> by a Non-Resident Indian (NRI)/Person of Indian Origin (PIO), out of the balances held in NRO accounts/sale proceeds of assets/the assets in India acquired by way of inheritance/legacy.] 
</subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> remittance to a person resident outside India on the ground that hardship will be caused to such a person if remittance from India is not made; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[<number>iii</number> Authorised Dealer shall act as per regulation (7) as regards closure of Branch/Liaison Office.] 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> On consideration of the application made under sub-regulation (1), the Reserve Bank may permit the remittance, subject to such terms and conditions as it deem necessary. 


 
 <subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 576(E), dated 19-8-2002. G.S.R. 400(E), dated 15-5-2007. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 630(E), dated 4-8-2003. G.S.R. 90(E), dated 15-2-2008. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 699(E), dated 1-9-2003. G.S.R. 837(E), dated 24-9-2009. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 493(E), dated 4-8-2004. G.S.R. 199(E), dated 19-1-2011. 
</subsection>


 
 (iii) remittance of winding up proceeds of a branch/office other than project office in India of a person resident outside India : 
 <subsection><number>B</number> Auditor's certificate, 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> indicating the manner in which the remittable amount has been arrived and supported by a statement of assets and liabilities of the applicant, and indicating the manner of disposal of assets; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> confirming that all liabilities in India including arrears of gratuity and other benefits to employees, etc., of the branch/office have been either fully met or adequately provided for; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number> confirming that no income accruing from sources outside India (including proceeds of exports) has remained unrepatriated to India ; 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>C</number> no-objection or tax clearance certificate from income-tax authority for the remittance; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>D</number> confirmation from the applicant that no legal proceedings in any court in India are pending and there is no legal impediment to the remittance; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>E</number> a report from the Registrar of Companies regarding compliance with the provisions of the Companies Act, 1956, in case of winding-up of the office in India.. 
</subsection>
</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[ <title><number>7</number> Permission to remit winding up proceeds of branch/office (Other than Project Office). </title>
<section><number>1</number> A branch or office established in India by a person resident outside India may, for making remittance of its winding up proceeds, apply to the Authorised Dealer concerned supported by the following documents, namely: 
 
 <subsection><number>A</number> copy of the Reserve Bank's permission for establishing the branch/office in India ; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>B</number> Auditors certificate: 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> indicating the manner in which the remittable amount has been arrived and supported by a statement of assets and liabilities of the applicant, and indicating the manner of disposal of assets; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> confirming that all liabilities in India including arrears of gratuity and other benefits to employees etc., of the branch/office have been either fully met or adequately provided for; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number> confirming that no income accruing from sources outside India (including proceeds of exports) has remained unrepatriated to India; and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iv</number> confirming that the branch/office has complied with all regulatory requirements stipulated by the Reserve Bank of India from time-to-time regarding functioning of such offices in India . 
</subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>C</number> no-objection or Tax clearance certificate from the Income Tax authority for the remittance; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>D</number> confirmation from the applicant that no legal proceedings in any Court in India are pending and there is no legal impediment to the remittance; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>E</number> a report from the Registrar of Companies regarding compliance with the provisions of the Companies Act, 1956, in case of winding up of the office in India. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> On consideration of the application made under sub-regulation (1), the authorised dealer concerned may permit the remittance subject to the directions issued by the Reserve Bank in this regard, from time-to-time.] 


 
 <subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 576(E), dated 19-8-2002. G.S.R. 400(E), dated 15-5-2007. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 630(E), dated 4-8-2003. G.S.R. 90(E), dated 15-2-2008. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 699(E), dated 1-9-2003. G.S.R. 837(E), dated 24-9-2009. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 493(E), dated 4-8-2004. G.S.R. 199(E), dated 19-1-2011. 
</subsection>

</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 576(E), dated 13th May, 2002 (w.e.f. 19-8-2002).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Clauses (iii), (iv) and (v) re-numbered as clauses (iv), (v) and (vi) respectively by G.S.R. 576(E), dated 13th May, 2002 (w.e.f. 19-8-2002).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 576(E), dated 13th May, 2002 (w.e.f. 19-8-2002).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 630(E), dated 8th July, 2003 (w.e.f. 4-8-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 400(E), dated 15th May, 2007, for calendar (w.r.e.f. 16-11-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 400(E), dated 15th May, 2007, for a tax clearance/no objection certificate from the Income-tax authority for the remittance (w.r.e.f. 16-11-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 493(E), dated 29th June, 2004, for sub-regulation (3) (w.e.f. 4-8-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 400(E), dated 15th May, 2007, for calendar (w.r.e.f. 16-11-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 400(E), dated 15th May, 2007, for tax clearance/no objection certificate from the income-tax authority for the remittance (w.r.e.f. 16-11-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> Proviso omitted by G.S.R. 400(E), dated 15th May, 2007 (w.r.e.f. 16-11-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number> The word further omitted by G.S.R. 400(E), dated 15th May, 2007 (w.r.e.f. 16-11-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 90(E), dated 18th September, 2007, for Sub-regulation (4) (w.r.e.f. 31-5-2007).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 630(E), dated 8th July, 2003 (w.e.f. 4-8-2003) and G.S.R. 576(E), dated 13th May, 2002 (w.e.f. 19-8-2002).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 199(E), dated 19th January, 2011, for clause (iii) (w.r.e.f. 1-2-2010). Earlier 
  clause (iii) was amended by G.S.R. 837(E), dated 24th September, 2009 (w.e.f. 23-11-2009) 
  and G.S.R. 699(E), dated 2nd July, 2003 (w.e.f. 1-9-2003). Clause (iii), before substitution by G.S.R. 199(E), stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 199(E), dated 19th January, 2011 (w.r.e.f. 1-2-2010).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>