<act><title>THE COMPETITION COMMISSION OF INDIA (FORM OF ANNUAL STATEMENT OF ACCOUNTS) RULES, 20091</title> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be called the Competition Commission of India (Form of Annual Statement of Accounts) Rules, 2009. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of their publication in the Official Gazette. 



</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires, 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> Act' means the Competition Act, 2002 (12 of 2003); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> Commission' means the Competition Commission of India established under sub-section (1) of section 7 of the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>  Fund' means the Competition Fund constituted under sub-section (1) of section 51 of the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> Form' means Form annexed to these rules; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> Schedule' means the Schedule to the form annexed to these Rules; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> Year' means the financial year beginning on 1st April and ending on 31st March of the year immediately following. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The words and expressions used in these rules but not defined shall have the same meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act. 


</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Forms of Financial Statements. </title>The Commission shall maintain its accounts in the Form of financial statements annexed to these rules. In maintaining the financial statements, the Commission shall follow the instructions and accounting principles as are indicated by the Central Government from time to time. 


</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Incurring of Expenditure by the Commission. </title>Every officer of the Commission incurring or authorizing expenditure from the Competition Fund should be guided by the Standards of financial propriety and other rules of General Financial Rules, 2005. 


</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Annual Statement of Accounts. </title>
<section><number>1</number> At the end of a period of twelve months ending with 31st March of every year, the Commission shall prepare the following financial statements along with necessary schedules, notes on accounts and significant accounting policies in accordance with the notes and instructions for compilation of financial statements prescribed by Government of India, Ministry of Finance, Controller-General of Accounts as modified and annexed to these rules: 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> balance sheet, 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> income and expenditure account, 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> receipt and payment account. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The balance sheet, income and expenditure account and receipt and payment account and the schedules referred to in sub-rule (1), shall be approved and adopted by the Commission or a Committee authorised by the Commission in this behalf and, for purposes of authentication, be signed by the Chairman and one Member of the Commission. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The approved accounts of the Commission shall be forwarded by the Commission to the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India or any other person appointed by him on his behalf within three months after the expiry of the year for the purposes of audit. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The annual accounts of the Commission, as certified by the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India or any other person appointed by him in his behalf, together with the audit report thereon after adoption by the Commission shall be forwarded to the Central Government for laying before both the Houses of Parliament. 


</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Maintenance of Accounts etc. </title>The Commission shall preserve the balance sheet, income and expenditure account, schedules to above statements, and the receipt and payment account, referred to in sub-rule 
<section><number>1</number> of rule 4 for a minimum period of ten years, following the year to which they relate. 


</section></article><form>
 

THE COMPETITION COMMISSION OF INDIA (FORM OF ANNUAL STATEMENT OF ACCOUNTS) RULES, 20091
 

 
 

SCHEDULE XXII 
 

SIGNIFICANT ACCOUNTING POLICIES (illustrative) 
 

1. ACCOUNTING CONVENTION 
 

The financial statements are prepared on the basis of historical cost convention, unless otherwise stated and on the accrual method of accounting. 
 

2. INVESTMENTS 
 

2.1 Investments classified as long-term investments are carried at cost. Provision for decline, other than temporary, is made in carrying cost of such investments. 
 

2.2 Investments classified as Current are carried at lower of cost and fair value. Provision for shortfall on the value of such investments is made for each investment considered individually and not on a global basis. 
 

2.3 Cost includes acquisition expenses like brokerage, transfer stamps. 
 

3. FIXED ASSETS 
 

3.1 Fixed Assets are stated at cost of acquisition inclusive of inward freight, duties and taxes and incidental and direct expenses related to acquisition. In respect of projects involving construction, related pre-operational expenses (including interest on loans for specific project prior to its completion), form part of the value of the assets capitalized. 
 

3.2 Fixed Assets received by way of non-monetary grants (other than towards the Corpus Fund), are capitalized at values stated, by corresponding credit to Capital Reserve. 
 

4. DEPRECIATION 
 

4.1 Depreciation is provided on straight-line method as per rates specified in the Income-tax Act, 1961 except depreciation on cost adjustments arising on account of conversion of foreign currency liabilities for acquisition of fixed assets, which is amortized over the residual life of the respective assets. 
 

-------
 

1. Vide  G.S.R. 204(E), dated 27th March, 2009, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 27th March, 2009. 
</form><form>
 

THE COMPETITION COMMISSION OF INDIA (FORM OF ANNUAL STATEMENT OF ACCOUNTS) RULES, 20091
 

 
 

SCHEDULE XXIII 
 

CONTINGENT LIABILITIES AND NOTES ON ACCOUNTS (Illustrative) 
 

1. CONTINGENT LIABILITIES 
 

1.1 Claims against the Entity not acknowledged as debts  Rs. ............................. (Previous year Rs. .............................) 
 

1.2 In respect of: 
 

 Bank guarantees given by/on behalf of the Entity  Rs. ............................. (Previous year Rs. .............................) 
 

 Letters of Credit opened by Bank on behalf of the Entity  Rs. ............................. (Previous year Rs. .............................). 
 

 Bills discounted with banks Rs. ......................... (Previous year Rs. .......................). 
 

1.3 Disputed demands in respect of: 
 

1.4 In respect claims from parties for non-execution of orders, but contested by the Entity  Rs. ............................. (Previous year Rs. .............................). 
 

2. CAPITAL COMMITMENTS 
 

Estimated value of contracts remaining to be executed on capital account and not provided for (net of advances) Rs. ............................. (Previous year Rs. .............................). 
 

3. LEASE OBLIGATIONS 
 

Future obligations for rentals under finance lease arrangements for plant and machinery amount to Rs. (Previous year Rs. .............................). 
 

4. CURRENT ASSETS, LOANS AND ADVANCES 
 

In the opinion of the Management, the current assets, loans and advances have a value on realization in the ordinary course of business, equal at least to the aggregate amount shown in the Balance Sheet. 
 

5. TAXATION 
 

In view of there being no taxable income under Income-tax Act, 1961, no provision for Income-tax has been considered necessary. 
 

Current Year Previous Year 
 

6. FOREIGN CURRENCY TRANSACTIONS 
 

6.1 Value of Imports calculated on C.I.F Basis: 
 

 Purchase of Finished Goods 
 

 Raw Materials &amp; Components (Including in transit) 
 

 Capital Goods 
 

 Stores, Spares and Consumables 
 

Expenditure in foreign currency: 
 

(a) Travel 
 

(b) Remittances and Interest payment to Financial Institutions/Banks in Foreign Currency 
 

(c) Other expenditure: 
 

 Commission on Sales 
 

 Legal and Professional Expenses 
 

 Miscellaneous Expenses 
 

Earnings: 
 

Value of Exports on FOB basis 
 

Remuneration to auditors: 
 

As Auditors 
 

 Taxation matters 
 

 For Management services 
 

 For certification 
 

Others 
 

7. Corresponding figures for the previous year have been regrouped/rearranged, wherever necessary. 
 

8. Schedules 1 to 23 are annexed to and form an integral part of the Balance Sheet as at ................... and the Income and Expenditure Account for the year ended on that date. 
 

-------
 

1. Vide  G.S.R. 204(E), dated 27th March, 2009, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 27th March, 2009. 
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Came into force on 27-3-2009.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>