<act><title>THE NATIONAL COUNCIL FOR TEACHER 
EDUCATION (PROCEDURE FOR RECOGNITION OF CERTAIN CATEGORIES OF INSTITUTIONS) 
RULES, 20061</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement:-</title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be called the National Council for 
Teacher Education (Procedure for Recognition of Certain Categories of 
Institutions) Rules, 2006. 
 
 


</section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date of their 
  publication in the Official Gazette. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions.</title>—In these rules unless the context otherwise requires,—

 
 <section><number>a</number> “Act” means the National Council of Teacher Education Act, 1993 (73 of 1993);
 </section><section><number>b</number> “application form” means the application form appended to these rules;
 </section><section><number>c</number> “Certificate” means a certificate specified in Appendix to these rules;
 </section><section><number>d</number> “section” means section of the Act; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> all other words and expressions used and not defined in these rules but defined in the Act shall have the same meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act.
  
</section>


</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Applicability</title>.—These rules shall be applicable to all matters relating to validation of qualifications in teacher education obtained through certain institutions offering a course or training in teacher education referred to in section 18B and for holding examination for a course or training in teacher education which may be conducted by the applicant institution and who apply to the Regional Committee of the National Council for Teacher Education under sub-section (2) of section 18B;
 
  



</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Submission of application and fee.—</title>
<section><number>1</number> Every application for recognition under section 18B shall be made in Form A.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The form may be down loaded from the Council’s Website www.ncte-in.org.  
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every institution desirous of getting recognition under section 18B shall submit its application in duplicate along with the documents mentioned in the application form and accompanied by a non-refundable fee of thirty thousand rupees.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The fee shall be submitted by way of demand draft drawn on a Nationalised Bank or State Bank of India or a subsidiary thereto payable to the Member-Secretary of the National Council for Teacher Education, payable at a place where the office of Regional Committee is located.
 
  



</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Time limit.—</title>
<section><number>1</number> Every application referred to in rule 4 shall be submitted within 10 days from the date of commencement of these rules for each course or training in teacher education along with a demand draft in respect of the application fee and another demand draft in respect of the fee and compensation, if any, payable under section 18F. 
(2) The demand drafts referred to in sub-rule (1) shall be in the name of Member-Secretary of the National Council for Teacher Education, drawn on a Nationalised Bank or State Bank of India or a subsidiary thereto, payable at the place where the Office of the Regional Committee is located.
 
  



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Processing of applications.—</title>The Regional Office of the National Council for Teacher Education shall process the applications received by it under these rules in the following manner, namely.—

 <section><number>1</number> It shall be the responsibility of the institution, which has applied for recognition to submit the application complete in all respects to the Regional Committee concerned along with the documents and the fee.  
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Regional Committee shall scrutinize every application received by it under these rules and the deficiencies, if any, shall be pointed out to the applicants within ten days from the date of receipt of application and the applicant shall rectify the defects within a period of ten days from the date of receipt of the communication under these rules.  
 </section><section><number>3</number> The National Council for Teacher Education shall constitute one or more Visiting Teams and depute them for inspection of the institutions under intimation to the applicant institutes.  
 </section><section><number>4</number> After the inspection, the Visiting Teams shall finalize their reports on the suitability of the institution for recognition clearly bringing out the facilities and infrastructure available with the applicant and forward the same to the Regional Committee immediately. 

 </section><section><number>5</number> On receipt of the report of the Visiting Team, the Regional Committee shall consider the same and inform the applicant its decision for the purpose of validation of qualification and conduct of examination.
  


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Validation of qualifications.—</title>
<section><number>1</number> The applicant institution whose qualifications in offering a course or training in teacher education have been validated by the Regional Committee shall issue a certificate to this effect to each student who has undergone the teacher training course from the date from which the validation of qualification has been so granted, on its own cost and shall also issue a public notice to this effect for the information of all concerned in two local newspapers and one national daily prominently.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The grant of recognition under these rules does not mean grant of recognition in any manner under section 14 or section 15 for running the teachertraining institutions for future and the institution would have to apply afresh under the relevant provisions of the Act for that purpose independently which would be considered under the normal procedure and the rules and regulations made under the Act.


</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>8</number> Certification of amount of fee and compensation, under section 18F to be credited to the fund of the Council.—</title>The applicant institution whose qualifications in teacher educations have been validated or given permission to hold the examinations as per section 18F, shall be entitled to get the amount of fee deposited and compensation granted by the court, if any, certified from the concerned University or Affiliating body or Examining Body.


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>