<act><tid>1362077</tid>
<title>THE SALARY AND ALLOWANCES OF LEADERS OFOPPOSITION IN PARLIAMENT ACT, <year>1977</year></title>

ACT NO. 33 OF <year>1977</year>
[ 18th August, <year>1977</year>.]

An Act to provide for the Salary and Allowances of Leaders of 
Opposition in Parliament.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- eighth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-


<pagefootnote><pagenum>1</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Short title and commencement.



<article><tid>146761</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1114856</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Salary and Allowences of Leaders of Opposition in Parliament Act, 
<year>1977</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>680041</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date 1 as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Definition.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>904359</tid>
<number>2</number>Definition. In this Act," Leader of the Opposition", in 
relation to either House of Parliament, means that member of the 
Council of States or the House of the People, as the case may be, who 
is, for the time being, the Leader in that House of the party in 
opposition to the Government having the greatest numerical strength 
and recognised as such by the Chairman of the Council of States or the 
Speaker of the House of the People, as the case may be.
Explanation.- Where there are two or more parties in opposition to 
the Government, in the Council of States or in the House of the People 
having the same numerical strength, the Chairman of the Council of 
States or the Speaker of the House of the People, as the case may be, 
shall, having regard to the status of the parties, recognise any one 
of the Leaders of such parties as the Leader of the Opposition for the 
purposes of this section and such recognition shall be final and 
conclusive.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Salary, and daily, constituency and sumptuary allowances.

</article>



<article><tid>982871</tid>
<number> 3</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Salary, and daily, constituency and sumptuary allowances.

<section><tid>1616415</tid>
<number>1</number>Each Leader of the Opposition shall, so long as he continues as  
such leader, be entitled to receive a salary per mensem and allowance 
for each day at the same rates as are specified in section 3 of 
the Salary, Allowances and Pension of Members of Parliament Act, <year>1954</year> 
with respect to members of Parliament.

</section>

<section><tid>1332076</tid>
<number>2</number>Each Leader of the Opposition shall also be entitled to 
receive a constituency allowance at the same rate as is for the time 
being specified under section 8 of the said Act with respect to 
members of Parliament.

</section>

<section><tid>1365786</tid>
<number>3</number>There shall be paid to each Leader of the Opposition a sum- 
ptuary allowance of one thousand rupees per mensem.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Residence for Leaders of Opposition.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1823282</tid>
<number> 4</number> Residence for Leaders of Opposition.
<section><tid>1813955</tid>
<number>1</number>Each Leader of the  
Opposition shall, so long as he continues as such Leader and for a 
period of one month immediately thereafter, be entitled without 
payment of rent to the use of a furnished residence

<pagefootnote><pagenum>194</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1st November, <year>1977</year>, see Notification No. G. S. R. 664 AEQ, dated 1st 
November, <year>1977</year> Gazette of India, Extraordinary, <year>1977</year>. Pt. II, Sec. 
3 (i) p. 2075.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 78 of <year>1985</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 26- 12- <year>1985</year>)


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

and no charge shall fall on the Leader of the Opposition personally in 
respect of the maintenance of such residence.


</section>

<section><tid>1445834</tid>
<number>2</number>In the event of death of a Leader of the Opposition, his 
family shall be entitled to the use of the furnished residence 
occupied by him-

<subsection><tid>1033615</tid>
<number>a</number>for a period of one month immediately after his death, 
without payment of rent and no charge shall fall on his 
family in respect of the maintenance of such residence; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>12372</tid>
<number>b</number>for a further period of one month, on payment of rent 
at such rates as may be prescribed by rules made in this 
behalf by the Central Government and also charges in respect 
of electricity and water consumed in that residence during 
such further period.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section," residence" 
includes the staff quarters and other buildings appurtenant thereto, 
and the garden thereof, and" maintenance" in relation to a residence 
includes the payment of local rates and taxes and the provision of 
electricity and water.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Travelling and daily allowances to Leaders of Opposition.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1800246</tid>
<number> 5</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1260919</tid>
<number>1</number>] Travelling and daily allowances to Leaders of  
Opposition. Subject to any rules made in this behalf by the Central 
Government, a Leader of the Opposition shall be entitled to-

<subsection><tid>1719115</tid>
<number>a</number>travelling allowances for himself and the members of 
his family and for transport of his and his family' s effects-

<subsubsection><tid>214218</tid>
<number>i</number>in respect of the journey to Delhi from his usual 
place of residence outside Delhi for assuming office; 
and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>777047</tid>
<number>ii</number>in respect of the journey from Delhi to his usual 
place of residence outside Delhi on relinquishing 
office; and

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>995431</tid>
<number>b</number>travelling and daily allowances in respect of tours 
undertaken by him in the discharge of his duties as Leader of 
the Opposition, whether by sea, land or air.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1397480</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> A Leader of the Opposition and any One member of his family 
accompanying him shall be entitled to travelling allowances in respect 
of not more than six return journeys performed, during each year, 
within India at the same rates at which travelling allowances are 
payable to such Leader under clause (b) of sub- section (1) in respect 
of tours referred to in that clause.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this sub- section," return 
journey" means a journey from one place to another place and the 
return journey from such other place to the first mentioned place.]


<pagefootnote><pagenum>6</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Medical treatment, etc., to Leaders of Opposition.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1494793</tid>
<number>6</number>Medical treatment, etc., to Leaders of Opposition. Subject to 
any rules made in this behalf by the Central Government, a Leader of 
the Opposition and the members of his family shall be entitled free 
of charge to accommodation in hospitals maintained by the Government 
and also to medical treatment.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>7</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Leaders of Opposition not to draw salary or allowances as Members 
ofParliament.

</article>



<article><tid>509014</tid>
<number>7</number>Leaders of Opposition not to draw salary or allowances as 
Members of Parliament. No Leader of the Opposition in receipt of a 
salary or allowance under this Act shall be entitled to receive any 
sum out of funds provided
</article>



<article><tid>146761</tid>
<number>1</number>Renumbered and Ins. by Act 98 of <year>1985</year>, S. 3 (w. e. f. 26- 12- <year>1985</year>)

<pagefootnote><pagenum>195</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

by Parliament by way of salary or allowance in respect of his member- 
ship of either House of Parliament.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>8</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Amenities to Leaders of Opposition.

</article>



<article><tid>1713698</tid>
<number> 8</number> Amenities to Leaders of Opposition.
<section><tid>142673</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to any rules  
made in this behalf by the Central government, each Leader of the 
Opposition shall be entitled to telephone and secretarial facilities.

</section>

<section><tid>1929094</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to any rules made in this behalf by the Central 
Government, each Leader of the Opposition shall be entitled to a 
conveyance allowance of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> three thousand rupees] per month:
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Provided that where a Leader of the Opposition is provided with 
conveyance facility with a driver for the purposes of security or 
otherwise for any period, he shall not be entitled to the conveyance 
allowance for that period.]


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1529388</tid>
<number>8A</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Advance to Leader of Opposition for purchase of motor car. 
There may be paid to a Leader of the Opposition, by way of a repayable 
advance, such sum of money as may be prescribed by rules made in this 
behalf by the Central Government for the purchase of a motor car in 
order that he may be able to discharge conveniently and efficiently 
the duties of his office.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>9</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Notification respecting the date on which persons became or ceased tobe 
Leaders of Opposition to be conclusive evidence thereof.

</article>



<article><tid>1504957</tid>
<number>9</number>Notification respecting the date on which persons became or 
ceased to be Leaders of Opposition to be conclusive evidence thereof. 
The date on which any person became or ceased to be a Leader the 
Opposition shall be published in the Official Gazette, and any such 
notification shall be conclusive evidence of the fact that he became, 
or ceased to be, a Leader of the Opposition on that date for all the 
purposes of this Act.
</article>



<article><tid>137801</tid>
<number> 9A</number> <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Exemption from liability to pay income- tax on certain 
perquisites received by a Leader of the Opposition. Notwithstanding 
anything contained in the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year>, the value of rent free 
furnished residence (including maintenance thereof) provided to a 
Leader of the Opposition under sub- section
<section><tid>1717965</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 4 shall not  
be included in the computation of his income chargeable under the 
heading" Salaries" under section 15 of the Income- tax Act. <year>1961</year>.]

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1028704</tid>
<number> 10</number> Power to make rule
<section><tid>1680549</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out 
the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1406297</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of 
the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>320906</tid>
<number>a</number>the rates at which rent shall be payable by the family 
of a deceased Leader of the Opposition to the use of the 
furnished residence occupied by him under clause (b) of sub- 
section (2) of section 4;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>172534</tid>
<number>b</number>the travelling and daily allowances admissible to a 
Leader of the Opposition under section 5;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1952272</tid>
<number>c</number>the medical treatment admissible to a Leader of the 
Opposition and the members of his family under section 6;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>82929</tid>
<number>d</number>the telephone and secretarial facilities admissible to 
a Leader of the Opposition and the conditions subject to 
which he shall be entitled to conveyance allowance under 
section 8.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>414656</tid>
<number>e</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> the advance payable to a Leader of the Opposition 
under section 8A.]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1792284</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as 
may after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in 
session,
<pagefootnote><pagenum>196</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 7 of <year>1991</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1991</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by S. 2 ibid (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1991</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by s. 3, ibid (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1991</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Ins. by Act 78 of <year>1985</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 26- 12- <year>1985</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Ins. by Act 7 of <year>1991</year>, S. 4, (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1991</year>)





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one 
session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the 
expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.

Section 11 relates to amendment of the Salary, Allowances and 
Pension of Members of Parliament Act, <year>1954</year>. Not printed.

Section 12 relates to amendment of the Parliament (Prevention of  
  Disqualification) Act, <year>1959</year>. Not printed.



</section>

</article>



 </act>