<act><title>

The
Persons with Disabilities (Equal Opportunities, protection of Rights
and Full Participation) Act, 1995</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>1</number>
Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> This Act may be called the
Persons with Disabilities (Equal Opportunities, Protection of Rights and Full
Participation) Act, 1995.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
It shall come into force on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
as the Central Govern­ment may, by notification, appoint.
   






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In this Act, unless the context otherwise re­quires,— 
 <section><number>a</number>
“appropriate Government” means,— 


 <subsection><number>i</number>
in relation to the Central Government or any establishment wholly or
substantially financed by that Government, or a Cantonment Board constituted
under the Cantonment Act, 1924 (2 of 1924), the Central Government;
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>
in relation to a State Government or any establishment wholly or
substantially financed by that Government or any local authority, other than a
Cantonment Board, the State Government;
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number>
in respect of the Central Co-ordination Committee and the Central
Executive Committee, the Central Government;
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number>
in respect of the State Co-ordination Committee and the State Executive
Committee, the State Government;
 </subsection></section><section><number>b</number>
“blindness” refers to a condition where a person suffers from any of
the following conditions, namely:— 


 <subsection><number>i</number>
total absence of sight; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>
visual acuity not exceeding 6/60 or 20/200 (snellen) in the better eye
with correcting lenses; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number>
limitation of the field of vision subtending an angle of 20 degree or
worse;
 </subsection></section><section><number>c</number>
“Central Co-ordination Committee” means the Central Co-ordination
Committee constituted under sub-section (1) of section 3; 


 </section><section><number>d</number>
“Central Executive Committee” means the Central Executive Committee
constituted under sub-section (1) of section 9; 


 </section><section><number>e</number>
“cerebral palsy” means a group of non-progressive conditions of a
person characterised by abnormal motor control posture resulting from brain
insult or injuries occurring in the pre-natal, peri-natal or infant period of
development; 


 </section><section><number>f</number>
“Chief Commissioner” means the Chief Commissioner appointed under
sub-section (1) of section 57 


 </section><section><number>g</number>
“Commissioner” means the Commissioner appointed under sub-section (1)
of section 60; 


 </section><section><number>h</number>
“competent authority” means the authority appointed under
section 50; 


 </section><section><number>i</number>
“disability” means— 


 <subsection><number>i</number>
blindness;
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>
low vision;
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number>
leprosy-cured;
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number>
hearing impairment;
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number>
locomotor disability;
 </subsection><subsection><number>vi</number>
mental retardation;
 </subsection><subsection><number>viii</number>
mental illness;
 </subsection></section><section><number>j</number>
“employer” means,— 


 <subsection><number>i</number>
in relation to a Government, the authority notified by the Head of the
Department in this behalf or where no such authority is notified, the Head of
the Department; and
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>
in relation to an establishment, the Chief Executive Officer of that
establishment;
 </subsection></section><section><number>k</number>
“establishment” means a corporation established by or under a
Central, Provincial or State Act, or an authority or a body owned or controlled
or aided by the Government or a local authority or a Government company as
defined in section 617 of the Companies Act 1956 (1 of 1956) and includes
Departments of a Government; 


 </section><section><number>l</number>
“hearing impairment” means loss of sixty decibels or more in the
better ear in the conversational range of frequencies; 


 </section><section><number>m</number>
“institution for persons with disabilities” means an institution for
the reception, care, protection, education, training rehabilitation or any other
service of persons with disabilities; 


 </section><section><number>n</number>
“leprosy cured person” means any person who has been cured of leprosy
but is suffering from— 


 <subsection><number>i</number>
loss of sensation in hands or feet as well as loss of sensation and
paresis in the eye and eye-lid but with no manifest deformity;
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>
manifest deformity and paresis but having sufficient mobility in their
hands and feet to enable them to engage in normal economic activity;
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number>
extreme physical deformity as well as advanced age which prevents him
from undertaking any gainful occupation,
 and the expression “leprosy
cured” shall be construed according­ly; 


 </subsection></section><section><number>o</number>
“locomotor disability” means disability of the bones, joints or
muscles leading to substantial restriction of the movement of the limbs or any
form of cerebral palsy; 


 </section><section><number>p</number>
“medical authority” means any hospital or institution specified for
the purposes of this Act by notification by the appropriate Government; 


 </section><section><number>q</number>
“mental illness” means any mental disorder other than mental
retardation; 


 </section><section><number>r</number>
“mental retardation” means a condition of arrested or incomplete
development of mind of a person which is specially characterised by subnormality
of intelligence; 


 </section><section><number>s</number>
“notification” means a notification published in the Official
Gazette; 


 </section><section><number>t</number>
“person with disability” means a person suffering from not less than
forty per cent of any disability as certified by a medical authority; 


 </section><section><number>u</number>
“person with low vision” means a person with impairment of visual
functioning even after treatment or standard refractive correction but who uses
or is potentially capable of using vision for the planning or execution of a
task with appropriate assis­tive device; 


 </section><section><number>v</number>
“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act; 


 </section><section><number>w</number>
“rehabilitation” refers to a process aimed at enabling persons with
disabilities to reach and maintain their optimal physical, sensory,
intellectual, psychiatric or social functional levels; 


 </section><section><number>x</number>
“Special Employment Exchange” means any office or place established
and maintained by the Government for the collection and furnishing of
information, either by keeping of registers or otherwise, respecting— 


 <subsection><number>i</number>
persons who seek to engage employees from amongst the persons suffering
from disabilities;
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>
persons with disability who seek employment;
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number>
vacancies to which person with disability seeking employment may be
appointed;
 </subsection></section><section><number>y</number>
“State Co-ordination Committee” means the State Co-ordination
Committee constituted under sub-section (1) of section 13; 


 </section><section><number>z</number>
“State Executive Committee” means the State Executive Committee
constituted under sub-section (1) of section 19. 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>3</number>
Central Co-ordination Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government shall by
notification constitute a body to be known as the Central Co-ordination
Committee to exercise the powers conferred on, and to perform the functions
assigned to it, under this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Central Co-ordination Committee shall consist of—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
the Minister-in-charge of the Department of Welfare in the Central
Government, Chairperson, ex officio; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
the Minister of State-in-charge of the Department of Welfare in the
Central Government, Vice Chairperson, ex officio; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
Secretaries to the Government of India in charge of the Departments of
Welfare, Education, Woman and Child Development, Expenditure, Personnel Training
and Public Grievances, Health, Rural Development, Industrial Development, Urban
Affairs and Employment, Science and Technology, Legal Affairs, Public
Enterprises, Members, ex officio; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
Chief Commissioner, Member ex officio; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>
Chairman Railway Board, Member, ex officio; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>
Director General of Labour, Employment and Training, Member, ex
officio; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number>
Director, National Council for Educational Research and Training, Member,
ex officio; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number>
three Members of Parliament, of whom two shall be elected by the House of
the People and one by the Council of States, Members; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number>
three persons to be nominated by the Central Government to represent the
interests, which in the opinion of that Government ought to be represented,
Members; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number>
Directors of the— 


 <subsubsection><number>i</number>
National Institute for the Visually Handicapped, Dehradun;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number>
National Institute for the Mentally Handicapped, Secundrabad;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number>
National Institute for the Orthopaedically Handicapped, Calcutta;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iv</number>
Ali Yavar Jung National Institute for the Hearing Handicapped, Bombay
Members, ex officio;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>k</number>
four Members to be nominated by the Central Government by rotation to
represent the States and the Union territories in such manner as may be
prescribed by the Central Government: 


 
 Provided that no appointment under this
clause shall be made except on the recommendation of the State Government or, as
the case may be, the Union territory; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number> five persons as far as practicable, being persons with
disabilities, to represent non-governmental organisations or associations which
are concerned with disabilities, to be nominated by the Central Government, one
from each area of disability, Members: 


 
 Provided that while nominating persons under
this clause, the Central Government shall nominate at least one woman and one
person belonging to Scheduled Castes or Scheduled Tribes; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>m</number>
Joint Secretary to the Government of India in the Ministry of Welfare
dealing with the welfare of the handicapped, Member-secretary, ex officio. 


 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number>
The office of the Member of the Central Co-ordination Committee shall not
disqualify its holder for being chosen as or for being a Member of either House
of Parliament.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>4</number>
Term of office of Members.—
<section><number>1</number> Save as otherwise provide by or under this
Act a Member of Central Co-ordination Committee nomi­nated under clause (i) or
clause (1) of sub-section (2) of section 3 shall hold office for a term of three
years from the date of his nomination:
 Provided
that such a Member shall, notwithstanding the expiration of his term, continue
to hold office until his succes­sor enters upon his office.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The term of office of an ex officio Member shall come to an end as soon
as he ceases to hold the office by virtue of which he was so nominated.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
The Central Government may if it thinks fit remove any Member nominated under
clause (i) or clause (l) of sub-section (2) of the section 3, before the expiry
of his term of office after giving him a reasonable opportunity of showing cause
against the same.
 </section><section><number>4</number>
A Member nominated under clause (i) or clause (l) of sub-sec­tion (2) of
section 3 may at any time resign his office by writ­ing under his hand
addressed to the Central Government and the seat of the said Member shall
thereupon become vacant.
 </section><section><number>5</number>
A casual vacancy in the Central Co-ordination Committee shall be filled by a
fresh nomination and the person nominated to fill the vacancy shall hold office
only for the remainder of the term for which the Member in whose place he was so
nominated.
 </section><section><number>6</number>
A Member nominated under clause (i) or clause (l) of sub-section (2) of section
3 shall be eligible for renomination.
 </section><section><number>7</number>
Members nominated under clause (i) or clause (l) of sub-sec­tion (2) of section
3 shall receive such allowances as may be prescribed by the Central Government.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>5</number>
Disqualifications.—
<section><number>1</number> No person shall be a Member of the Cen­tral
Co-ordination Committee, who—
 <subsection><number>a</number> is, or at any time has been, adjudged insolvent or has
suspended payment of his debts or has compounded with his creditors, or 


 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
is of unsound mind and stands so declared by a competent court, or 


 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
is or has been convicted of an offense which, in the opinion of the
Central Government, involves moral turpitude, or 


 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
is or at any time has been convicted of an offence under this Act, or 


 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>
has so abused in the opinion of the Central Government his position as a
Member as to render his continuance in the Central Co-ordination Committee
detrimental to the interests of the general public. 


 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
No order of removal shall be made by the Central Government under this section
unless the Member concerned has been given a reasonable opportunity of showing
cause against the same.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1) or sub-section (6) of
section 4, a Member who has been removed under this section shall not be
eligible for renomination as a Member.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>6</number>
Vacation of seats by Members.—If a Member of the Central Co-ordination
Committee becomes subject to any of the disqualifi­cations specified in section
5, his seat shall become vacant.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>7</number>
Meetings of the Central Co-ordination Committee.—The Central Co-ordination
Committee shall meet at least once in every six months and shall observe such
rules of procedure in regard to the transaction of business at its meetings as
may be prescribed by the Central Government.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>8</number>
Functions of the Central Co-ordination Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> Subject to the
provisions of this Act, the function of the Central Co-ordination Committee
shall be to serve as the national focal point on disability matters and
facilitate the continuous evolution of a comprehensive policy towards solving
the problems faced by per­sons with disabilities.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing, the
Central Co-ordination Committee may perform all or any of the following
functions, namely:—
 <subsection><number>a</number> review and coordinate the activities of all
the Departments of Government and other Governmental and non-Governmental
Organizations which are dealing with matters relating to persons with
disabilities; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> develop a national policy to address issues
faced by person with disabilities; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> advise the Central Government on the
formulation of policies, programmes, legislation and projects with respect to
disability; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
take up the cause of persons with disabilities with the concerned
authorities and the international organizations with a view to provide for
schemes and projects for the disabled in the national plans and other
programmers and policies evolved by the international agencies; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> review in consultation with the donor
agencies their funding policies from the perspective of their impact on persons
with disabilities; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> take such other steps ensure barrier-free environment in
public places, work-places, public utilities, schools and other institutions; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number>
monitor and evaluate the impact of policies and programmes designed for
achieving equality and full participation of persons with disabilities; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number>
to perform such other functions as may be prescribed by the Central
Government. 



 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>9</number>
Central Executive Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government shall constitute a
Committee to be known as the Central Executive Committee to perform the
functions assigned to it under this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Central Executive Committee shall consist of—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
the Secretary to the Government of India in the Ministry of Welfare
Chairperson, ex officio; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
the Chief Commissioner, Member, ex officio; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
the Director-General for Health Services Member, ex officio; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
the Director-General, Employment and Training Member, ex officio; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>
six persons not below the rank of a Joint Secretary to the Government of
India, to represent the Ministries or Departments of Rural Development,
Education, Welfare, Personnel Public Grievances and Pension and Urban Affairs
and Employment, Science and Technology, Members, ex officio; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>
the Financial Advisor, Ministry of Welfare in the Central Government,
Member, ex officio; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number>
Advisor (Tariff) Railway Board, Member, ex officio; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number>
four members to be nominated by the Central Government, by rotation to
represent the State Governments and the Union territories in such manner as may
be prescribed by the Central Government. 


 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number>
one person to be nominated by the Central Government to represent the
interest, which in the opinion of that Central Government ought to be
represented, Member; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number>
five persons, as far as practicable, being persons with disabilities, to
represent non-Governmental Organizations or associations which are concerned
with disabilities, to be nomi­nated by the Central Government, one from each
area of disability, Members: 


 

Provided that while nominating persons under this clause, the Central
Government shall nominate at least one woman and one person belonging to
Scheduled Castes or Scheduled Tribes; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number>
Joint Secretary to the Government of India in the Ministry of Welfare
dealing with the welfare of the handicapped, Member-Secretary, ex officio. 


 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number>
Members nominated under clause (i) and clause (j) of sub-section (2) shall
receive such allowances as may be prescribed by the Central Government.
 </section><section><number>4</number>
A Member nominated under clause (i) and clause (j) of sub-section (2) may at any
time resign his office by writing under his hand addressed to the Central
Government and the seat of the said Member shall thereupon become vacant.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>10</number>
Functions of the Central Executive Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Executive
Committee shall be the executive body of the Central Co-ordination Committee and
shall be responsible for carrying out the decisions of the Central Co-ordination
Committee,
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Without prejudice to the provisions of sub-section (1), the Central Executive
Committee shall also perform such other func­tions as may be delegated to it by
the Central Co-ordination Committee.
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>11</number>
Meetings of the Central Executive Committee.—The Central Executive
Committee shall meet at least once in three months and shall observe such rules
of procedure in regard to the transaction of business at its meetings as may be
prescribed by the Central Government.
  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>12</number>
Temporary association of persons with Central Executive Com­mittee for
particular purposes.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Executive Com­mittee may associate
with itself in such manner and for such purposes as may be prescribed by the
Central Government any person whose assistance or advice it may desire to obtain
in performing any of its functions under this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
A person associated with the Central Executive Committee under sub-section (1)
for any purpose shall have the right to take part in the discussions of the
Central Executive Committee relevant to that purpose, but shall not have a right
to vote at a meeting of the said Committee, and shall not be a member for any
other purpose.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
A person associated with the said Committee under sub-section (1) for any
purpose shall be paid such fees and allowances, for attending its meetings and
for attending to any other work of the said Committee, as may be prescribed by
the Central Government.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>12</number>
Temporary association of persons with Central Executive Com­mittee for
particular purposes.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Executive Com­mittee may associate
with itself in such manner and for such purposes as may be prescribed by the
Central Government any person whose assistance or advice it may desire to obtain
in performing any of its functions under this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
A person associated with the Central Executive Committee under sub-section (1)
for any purpose shall have the right to take part in the discussions of the
Central Executive Committee relevant to that purpose, but shall not have a right
to vote at a meeting of the said Committee, and shall not be a member for any
other purpose.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
A person associated with the said Committee under sub-section (1) for any
purpose shall be paid such fees and allowances, for attending its meetings and
for attending to any other work of the said Committee, as may be prescribed by
the Central Government.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>13</number>
State Co-ordination Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> Every State Government shall, by
notification constitute a body to be known as the State Co-ordination Committee
to exercise the powers conferred on, and to perform the function assigned to it,
under this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The State Co-ordination Committee shall consist of—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
The Minister-in-Charge of the Department of Social Welfare in the State
Government, Chairperson, ex officio; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
the Minister of State in charge of the Department of Social Welfare, if
any, Vice-Chairperson, ex officio; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
Secretaries to the State Government in charge of the Departments of
Welfare, Education, Woman and Child Development, Expenditure, Personnel Training
and Public Grievances, Health, Rural Development, Industrial Development, Urban
Affairs and Employment, Science and Technology, Public Enterprises, by whatever
name called, Member, ex officio; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
Secretary of any other Department which the State Government considers
necessary, Member, ex officio; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>
Chairman Bureau of Public Enterprises (by whatever name called) Member, ex
officio; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>
five persons, as far as practicable, being persons with disabilities, to
represent non-Governmental Organisations or associations which are concerned
with disabilities, to be nominated by the State Government one from each area of
disability, Members:— 


  
Provided that while nominating persons under this clause the State
Government shall nominate at least one woman and one person belonging to
Scheduled Castes or Scheduled Tribes; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number>
three Members of State Legislature, of whom two shall be elected by the
Legislative Assembly and one by the Legislative Council, if any; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number>
three persons to be nominated by that State Government to represent
agriculture, industry or trade or any other interest, which in the opinion of
State Government ought to be represented, Members, ex officio; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number>
the Commissioner, Member, ex officio; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number>
Secretary to the State Government dealing with the welfare of the
handicapped, Member-Secretary, ex officio. 


 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number>
Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, no State Co-ordination
Committee shall be constituted for a Union territory and in relation to a Union
territory, the Central Co-ordination Committee shall exercise the functions and
perform the functions of a State Co-ordination Committee for the Union
territory:
 Provided
that in relation to a Union territory, the Central Co-ordination Committee may
delegate all or any of its powers and functions under this sub-section to such
person or body of persons as the Central Government may specify.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>14</number>
Terms and conditions of service of Members.—
<section><number>1</number> Save as otherwise provided
by or under this Act, a Member of a State Co-ordination Committee nominated
under clause (f) or clause (h) of sub-section (2) of section 13 shall hold
office for a term of three years from the date of his nomination:
 Provided
that such a Member shall, notwithstanding the expiration of his term, continue
to hold office until his succes­sor enters upon his office.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The term of office of an ex officio Member shall come to an end as soon
as he ceases to hold the office by virtue of which he was so nominated.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
The State Government may, if thinks fit, remove any Member nominated under
clause (f) or clause (h) of sub-section (2) of section 13, before the expiry of
his term of office after giving him a reasonable opportunity of showing cause
against the same.
 </section><section><number>4</number>
A Member nominated under clause (f) or clause (h) of sub-section (2) of section
13 may, at any time, resign his office by writing under his hand addressed to
the State Government and the seat of the said Member shall thereupon become
vacant.
 </section><section><number>5</number>
A casual vacancy in the State Co-ordination Committee shall be filled by a fresh
nomination and the person nominated to fill the vacancy shall hold office only
for the remainder of the term for which the Member in whose place he was so
nominated.
 </section><section><number>6</number>
A Member nominated under clause (f) and clause (h) of sub-section (2) of section
13 shall be eligible for renomination.
 </section><section><number>7</number>
Members nominated under clause (f) and clause (h) of sub-sec­tion (2) of
section 13 shall receive such allowances as may be prescribed by the State
Government.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>15</number>
Disqualifications.—
<section><number>1</number> No person shall be a Member of the State
Co-ordination Committee, who—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
is, or at any time, has been adjudged insolvent or has suspended payment
of his debtor has compounded with his creditors, or 


 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
is of unsound mind and stands so declared by a competent court, or 


 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
is or has been convicted of an offence which in the opinion of the State
Government involves moral turpitude, or 


 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
is or at any time has been convicted of an offence under this Act, or 


 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>
has so abused, in the opinion of the State Government, his position as a
member as to render his continuance in the State Co-ordination Committee
detrimental to the interests of the general public. 


 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
No order of removal shall be made by the State Government under this section
unless the Member concerned has been given a reaso­nable opportunity of showing
cause against the same.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1) or sub-section (6) of
section 14, a Member who has been removed under this section shall not be
eligible for renomination as a Member.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>16</number>
Vacation of seats.—If a Member of the State Co-ordination Committee
becomes subject to any of the disqualifications specified in section 15, his
seat shall become vacant.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>17</number>
Meetings of the State Co-ordination Committee.—The State Co-ordination
Committee shall meet at least once in every six months and shall observe such
rules of procedure in regard to the transaction of business at its meetings as
may be prescribed.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>18</number>
Functions of the State Co-ordination Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> Subject to the
provisions of this Act, the function of the State Co-ordination Committee shall
be to serve as the state focal point on disability matters facilitate the
continuous evolution of a comprehensive policy towards solving the problems
faced by persons with disabilities.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing function
the State Co-ordination Committee may, within the State perform all or any of
the following functions, namely:—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
review and coordinate the activities of all the Departments of Government
and other Governmental and non-Governmental Organisations which are dealing with
matters relating to persons with disabilities; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
develop a State policy to address issues faced by persons with
disabilities; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
advise the State Government on the formulation of policies, programmes,
legislation and projects with respect to disability; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
review in consultation with the donor agencies, their funding policies
from the perspective of their impact on persons with disabilities; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>
take such other steps to ensure barrier-free environment in public
places, work places, public utilities, schools and other institutions; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>
monitor and evaluate the impact of policies and programmes designed for
achieving equality and full participation of persons with disabilities; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number>
to perform such other functions as may be prescribed by the State
Government. 



 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>19</number>
State Executive Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> The State Government shall constitute a
committee to be known as the State Executive Com­mittee to perform the
functions assigned to it under this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The State Executive Committee shall consist of—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
the Secretary, Department of Social Welfare, Chairperson, ex officio; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
the Commissioner, Member, ex officio; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
nine persons not below the rank of a Joint Secretary to the State
Government, to represent the Departments of the Health, Finance, Rural
Development, Education, Welfare, Personnel Public Grievances, Urban Affairs,
Labour and Employment, Science and Technology, Members, ex officio; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
one person to be nominated by the State Government to represent the
interest, which in the opinion of the State Govern­ment ought to be
represented, Member; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>
five persons, as far as practicable being persons with disabilities, to
represent non-Governmental Organisations or associations which are concerned
with disabilities, to be nominated by the State Government, one from each area
of disability, Members: 


 

Provided that while nominating persons under this clause, the State
Government shall nominate at least one woman and one person belonging to
Scheduled Castes or Scheduled Tribes; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>
Joint Secretary dealing with the disability division in the Department of
Welfare, Member-Secretary, ex officio. 


 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number>
Members nominated under clause (d) and clause (e) of sub-section (2) shall
receive such allowances as may be prescribed by the State Government.
 </section><section><number>4</number>
A Member nominated under clause (d) or clause (e) may at any time resign his
office by writing under his hand addressed to the State Government and the seat
of the said Member shall thereupon become vacant.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>20</number>
Functions of the State Executive Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> The State Executive
Committee shall be the executive body of the State Co-ordination Committee and
shall be responsible for carrying out the decisions of the State Co-ordination
Committee.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Without prejudice to the provisions of sub-section (1), the State Executive
committee shall also perform such other functions as may be delegated to it by
the State Co-ordination Committee.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>21</number>
Meetings of the State Executive Committee.—The State Executive Committee
shall meet at least once in three months and shall observe such rules of
procedure in regard to the transaction of business at its meetings as may be
prescribed by the State Government.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>22</number>
Temporary association of persons with State Executive Committee for particular
purposes.—
<section><number>1</number> The State Executive Committee may association with itself in
such manner and for such purposes as may be prescribed by the State Government
any person whose assistance or advice it may desire to obtain in performing any
of its functions under this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
A person associated with the State Executive Committee under sub-section (1) for
any purpose shall have the right to take part in the discussions of the State
Executive Committee relevant to that purpose, but shall not have a right to vote
at a meeting of the said Committee, and shall not be a member for any other
purpose.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
A person associated with the said Committee under sub-section (1) for any
purpose shall be paid such fees and allowances, for attending its meetings and
for attending to any other work of the said Committee, as may be prescribed by
the State Government.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>22</number>
Temporary association of persons with State Executive Committee for particular
purposes.—
<section><number>1</number> The State Executive Committee may association with itself in
such manner and for such purposes as may be prescribed by the State Government
any person whose assistance or advice it may desire to obtain in performing any
of its functions under this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
A person associated with the State Executive Committee under sub-section (1) for
any purpose shall have the right to take part in the discussions of the State
Executive Committee relevant to that purpose, but shall not have a right to vote
at a meeting of the said Committee, and shall not be a member for any other
purpose.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
A person associated with the said Committee under sub-section (1) for any
purpose shall be paid such fees and allowances, for attending its meetings and
for attending to any other work of the said Committee, as may be prescribed by
the State Government.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>23</number>
Power to give directions.—In the performance of its func­tions under this
Act,— 
 <section><number>a</number>
the Central Co-ordination Committee shall be bound by such directions in
writing, as the Central Government may give to it; and 


 </section><section><number>b</number>
the State Co-ordination Committee shall be bound by such directions in
writing, as the Central Co-ordination Committee or the State Government may give
to it: 


 Provided that where a direction given by the State Government is
inconsistent with any direction given by the Central Co-ordination Committee,
the matter shall be referred to the Central Government for its decision. 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>24</number>
Vacancies not to invalidate proceedings.—No act or proceeding of the
Central Co-ordination Committee, the Central Executive Committee, a State
Co-ordination Committee or a State Executive Committee shall be called in
question on the ground merely on the existence of any vacancy in or any defect
in the constitution of such Committees.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>25</number>
Appropriate Governments and local authorities to take certain steps for the
prevention of occurrence of disabilities.—Within the limits of their
economic capacity and development, the appropriate Governments and the local
authorities, with a view to preventing the occurrence of disabilities, shall—
 <section><number>a</number>
undertake or cause to be undertaken surveys, investigations and research
concerning the cause of occurrence of disabilities; 


 </section><section><number>b</number>
promote various methods of preventing disabilities; 


 </section><section><number>c</number>
screen all the children at least once in a year for the purpose of
identifying “at-risk” cases; 


 </section><section><number>d</number>
provide facilities for training to the staff at the primary health
centres; 


 </section><section><number>e</number>
sponsor or cause to be sponsored awareness campaigns and disseminate or
cause to be disseminated information for general hygiene, health and sanitation; 


 </section><section><number>f</number>
take measures for pre-natal, per-natal and post-natal care of mother and
child; 


 </section><section><number>g</number>
educate the public through the pre-schools, schools, primary health
centres, village level workers and anganwadi workers; 


 </section><section>
<number>h</number>
create awareness amongst the masses through television, radio and other
mass media on the causes of disabilities and the preventive measures to be
adopted. 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>26</number>
Appropriate Governments and local authorities to provide children with
disabilities free education, etc.—The appropriate Governments and
the local authorities shall—
 <section><number>a</number>
ensure that every child with a disability has access to free education in
an appropriate environment till he attains the age of eighteen years; 


 </section><section><number>b</number>
endeavour to promote the integration of students with disabilities in the
normal schools; 


 </section><section><number>c</number>
promote setting up of special schools in Government and private sector
for those in need of special education, in such a manner that children with
disabilities living in any part of the country have access to such schools; 


 </section><section><number>d</number>
endeavour to equip the special schools for children with disabilities
with vocational training facilities. 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>26</number>
Appropriate Governments and local authorities to provide children with
disabilities free education, etc.—The appropriate Governments and
the local authorities shall—
 <section><number>a</number>
ensure that every child with a disability has access to free education in
an appropriate environment till he attains the age of eighteen years; 


 </section><section><number>b</number>
endeavour to promote the integration of students with disabilities in the
normal schools; 


 </section><section><number>c</number>
promote setting up of special schools in Government and private sector
for those in need of special education, in such a manner that children with
disabilities living in any part of the country have access to such schools; 


 </section><section><number>d</number>
endeavour to equip the special schools for children with disabilities
with vocational training facilities. 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>27</number>
Appropriate Governments and local authorities to make schemes and programmes for
non-formal education, etc.—The appropriate Governments and the local
authorities shall by notification make schemes for—
 <section><number>a</number>
conducting part-time classes in respect of children with disabilities who
having completed education up to class fifth and could not continue their
studies on a whole-time basis; 


 </section><section>
<number>b</number>
conducting special part-time classes for providing functional literacy
for children in the age group of sixteen and above; 


 </section><section><number>c</number>
imparting non-formal education by utilizing the available manpower in
rural areas after giving them appropriate orientation; 


 </section><section><number>d</number>
imparting education through open schools or open universities; 


 </section><section><number>e</number>
conducting class and discussions through interactive electronic or other
media; 


 </section><section><number>f</number>
providing every child with disability free of cost special books and
equipments needed for his education. 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>27</number>
Appropriate Governments and local authorities to make schemes and programmes for
non-formal education, etc.—The appropriate Governments and the local
authorities shall by notification make schemes for—
 <section><number>a</number>
conducting part-time classes in respect of children with disabilities who
having completed education up to class fifth and could not continue their
studies on a whole-time basis; 


 </section><section>
<number>b</number>
conducting special part-time classes for providing functional literacy
for children in the age group of sixteen and above; 


 </section><section><number>c</number>
imparting non-formal education by utilizing the available manpower in
rural areas after giving them appropriate orientation; 


 </section><section><number>d</number>
imparting education through open schools or open universities; 


 </section><section><number>e</number>
conducting class and discussions through interactive electronic or other
media; 


 </section><section><number>f</number>
providing every child with disability free of cost special books and
equipments needed for his education. 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>28</number>
Research for designing and developing new assistive devices, teaching aids, etc.—The
appropriate Governments shall initiate or cause to be initiated research by
official and non-Governmental agencies for the purpose of designing and
developing new assistive devices, teaching aids, special teaching materials or
such other items as are necessary to give a child with disability equal
opportunities in education.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>28</number>
Research for designing and developing new assistive devices, teaching aids, etc.—The
appropriate Governments shall initiate or cause to be initiated research by
official and non-Governmental agencies for the purpose of designing and
developing new assistive devices, teaching aids, special teaching materials or
such other items as are necessary to give a child with disability equal
opportunities in education.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>29</number>
Appropriate Governments to set up teachers’ training institutions to develop
trained manpower for schools for children with disabilities.—The
appropriate Governments shall set up adequate number of teachers’ training
institutions and assist the national institutes and other voluntary
organisations to develop teachers’ training programmes specialising in
disabilities so that requisite trained manpower is available for special schools
and integrated schools for children with disabilities.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>29</number>
Appropriate Governments to set up teachers’ training institutions to develop
trained manpower for schools for children with disabilities.—The
appropriate Governments shall set up adequate number of teachers’ training
institutions and assist the national institutes and other voluntary
organisations to develop teachers’ training programmes specialising in
disabilities so that requisite trained manpower is available for special schools
and integrated schools for children with disabilities.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>30</number>
Appropriate Governments to prepare a comprehensive education scheme providing
for transport facilities, supply of books, etc.—Without prejudice
to the foregoing provisions, the appropriate Governments shall by notification
prepare a comprehensive education scheme which shall make provision for—
 <section><number>a</number>
transport facilities to the children with disabilities or in the
alternative financial incentives to parents or guardians to enable their
children with disabilities to attend schools; 


 </section><section><number>b</number>
the removal of architectural barriers from schools, colleges or other
institutions imparting vocational and professional training; 


 </section><section><number>c</number>
the supply of books, uniforms and other materials to children with
disabilities attending school; 


 </section><section> <number>d</number>
the grant of scholarship to students with disabilities; 


 </section><section><number>e</number>
setting up of appropriate fora for the redressal of grievances of parents
regarding the placement of their children with disabilities; 


 </section><section><number>f</number>
suitable modification in the examination system to eliminate purely
mathematical questions for the benefit of blind students and students with low
vision;—  


 </section><section><number>g</number>
restructuring of curriculum for the benefit of children with
disabilities; 


 </section><section><number>h</number>
restructuring the curriculum for benefit of students with hearing
impairment to facilitate them to take only one language as part of their
curriculum. 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>31</number>
Educational institutions to provide amanuensis to students with visual handicap.—All
educational institutions shall provide or cause to be provided amanuensis to
blind students and students with or low vision.
  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>31</number>
Educational institutions to provide amanuensis to students with visual handicap.—All
educational institutions shall provide or cause to be provided amanuensis to
blind students and students with or low vision.
  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>32</number>
Identification of posts which can be reserved for persons with disabilities.—Appropriate
Governments shall—
 <section><number>a</number>
identify posts, in the establishments, which can be reserved for the
persons with disability; 


 </section><section><number>b</number>
at periodical intervals not exceeding three years, review the list of
posts identified and up-date the list taking into consideration the developments
in technology. 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>32</number>
Identification of posts which can be reserved for persons with disabilities.—Appropriate
Governments shall—
 <section><number>a</number>
identify posts, in the establishments, which can be reserved for the
persons with disability; 


 </section><section><number>b</number>
at periodical intervals not exceeding three years, review the list of
posts identified and up-date the list taking into consideration the developments
in technology. 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>33</number>
Reservation of posts.—Every appropriate Government shall appoint in every
establishment such percentage of vacancies not less than three per cent for
persons or class of persons with disability of which one per cent each shall be
reserved for persons suffering from—
 <section><number>i</number>
blindness or low vision; 


 </section><section><number>ii</number>
hearing impairment; 


 </section><section><number>iii</number>
locomotor disability or cerebral palsy, 


 in
the posts identified for each disability:
 Provided
that the appropriate Government may, having regard to the type of work carried
on in any department or establishment, by notification subject to such
conditions, if any, as may be specified in such notification, exempt any
establishment from the provisions of this section.
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>34</number> Special Employment Exchange.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
appropriate Government may, by notification, require that from such date as may 
be specified, by notification, the employer in every establishment shall furnish 
such information or return as may be prescribed in relation to vacancies 
appointed for persons with disability that have occurred or are about or occur 
in that establishment to such Special Employment Exchange as may be prescribed 
and the establishment shall thereupon comply with such requisition.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The form in which and the intervals of time 
for which information or returns shall be furnished and the particulars, they 
shall contain shall be such as may be prescribed. 
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>35</number>
Power to inspect record or document in possession of any establishment.—
Any person authorised by the Special Employment Exchange in writing, shall have
access to any relevant record or document in the possession of any establishment
and may enter at any reasonable time and premises where he believes such record
or document to be, and inspect or take copies of relevant records or documents
or ask any question necessary for obtaining any information.
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>35</number>
Power to inspect record or document in possession of any establishment.—
Any person authorised by the Special Employment Exchange in writing, shall have
access to any relevant record or document in the possession of any establishment
and may enter at any reasonable time and premises where he believes such record
or document to be, and inspect or take copies of relevant records or documents
or ask any question necessary for obtaining any information.
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>36</number>
Vacancies not filled up to be carried forward.—Where in any recruitment
year any vacancy under section 33 cannot be filled up due to non-availability of
a suitable person with disability or, for any other sufficient reason, such
vacancy shall be carried forward in the succeeding recruitment year and if in
the succeed­ing recruitment year also suitable person with disability is not
available, it may first be filled by interchange among the three categories and
only when there is no person with disability available for the post in that
year, the employer shall fill up the vacancy by appointment of a person, other
than a person with disability:
 Provided
that if the nature of vacancies in an establishment is such that a given
category of person cannot be employed, the vacancies may be interchanged among
the three categories with the prior approval of the appropriate Government.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>37</number>
Employers to maintain records.—
<section><number>1</number> Every employer shall maintain such
record in relation to the person with disability employed in his establishment
in such form and in such manner as may be prescribed by the appropriate
Government.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The records maintained under sub-section (1) shall be open to inspection at all
reasonable hours by such persons as may be authorised in this behalf by general
or special order by the appropriate Government.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>38</number>
Schemes for ensuring employment of persons with disabilities.—
<section><number>1</number> The
appropriate Governments and local authorities shall by notification formulate
schemes for ensuring employment of persons with disabilities, and such schemes
may provide for—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> the training and welfare of persons with disabilities; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the relaxation of upper age limit; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> regulating the employment; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
health and safety measures and creation of a non-handicapping environment
in places where persons with disabilities are employed; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> the manner in which and the persons by whom the cost of
operating the schemes is to be defrayed; and 


 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> constituting the authority responsible for
the administration of the scheme. 



 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>38</number>
Schemes for ensuring employment of persons with disabilities.—
<section><number>1</number> The
appropriate Governments and local authorities shall by notification formulate
schemes for ensuring employment of persons with disabilities, and such schemes
may provide for—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> the training and welfare of persons with disabilities; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the relaxation of upper age limit; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> regulating the employment; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
health and safety measures and creation of a non-handicapping environment
in places where persons with disabilities are employed; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> the manner in which and the persons by whom the cost of
operating the schemes is to be defrayed; and 


 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> constituting the authority responsible for
the administration of the scheme. 



 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>39</number>
All educational institutions to reserve seats for persons with disabilities.—All
Government educational institutions and other educational institutions receiving
aid from the Government, shall reserve not less that three per cent seats for
persons with disabilities.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>39</number>
All educational institutions to reserve seats for persons with disabilities.—All
Government educational institutions and other educational institutions receiving
aid from the Government, shall reserve not less that three per cent seats for
persons with disabilities.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>40</number>
Vacancies to be reserved in poverty alleviation schemes.—The appropriate
Governments and local authorities shall reserve not less than three per cent in
all poverty alleviation schemes for the benefit of persons with disabilities.
  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>40</number>
Vacancies to be reserved in poverty alleviation schemes.—The appropriate
Governments and local authorities shall reserve not less than three per cent in
all poverty alleviation schemes for the benefit of persons with disabilities.
  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>41</number>
Incentives to employers to ensure five per cent of the work force is composed of
persons with disabilities.—The appropriate Governments and the local
authorities shall, within the limits of their economic capacity and development,
provide incentives to employers both in public and private sectors to ensure
that at least five per cent of their work force is composed of persons with
disabilities.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>41</number>
Incentives to employers to ensure five per cent of the work force is composed of
persons with disabilities.—The appropriate Governments and the local
authorities shall, within the limits of their economic capacity and development,
provide incentives to employers both in public and private sectors to ensure
that at least five per cent of their work force is composed of persons with
disabilities.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>42</number>
Aids and appliances to persons with disabilities.—The appropriate
Governments shall by notification make schemes to provide aids and appliances to
persons with disabilities.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>43</number>
Schemes for preferential allotment of land for certain purposes.—The
appropriate Governments and local authorities shall by notification frame
schemes in favour of persons with disabilities, for the preferential allotment
of land at concessional rates of—
 <section><number>a</number>
house; 


 </section><section><number>b</number>
setting up business; 


 </section><section><number>c</number>
setting up of special recreation centres; 


 </section><section> <number>d</number>
establishment of special schools; 


 </section><section><number>e</number>
establishment of research centres; 


 </section><section><number>f</number>
establishment of factories by entrepreneurs with disabilities.
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>43</number>
Schemes for preferential allotment of land for certain purposes.—The
appropriate Governments and local authorities shall by notification frame
schemes in favour of persons with disabilities, for the preferential allotment
of land at concessional rates of—
 <section><number>a</number>
house; 


 </section><section><number>b</number>
setting up business; 


 </section><section><number>c</number>
setting up of special recreation centres; 


 </section><section> <number>d</number>
establishment of special schools; 


 </section><section><number>e</number>
establishment of research centres; 


 </section><section><number>f</number>
establishment of factories by entrepreneurs with disabilities.
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>44</number>
Non-discrimination in transport.—Establishments in the transport sector
shall, within the limits of their economic capacity and development for the
benefit of persons with disabilities, take special measures to—
 <section><number>a</number>
adapt rail compartments, buses, vessels and aircrafts in such a way as to
permit easy access to such persons; 


 </section><section><number>b</number>
adapt toilets in rail compartments, vessels, aircrafts and waiting rooms
in such a way as to permit the wheel chair users to use them conveniently. 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>45</number>
Non-discrimination on the road.—The appropriate Governments and the local
authorities shall, within the limits of their economic capacity and development,
provide for—
 <section><number>a</number>
installation of auditory signals at red lights in the public roads for
the benefit of persons with visually handicap; 


 </section><section><number>b</number>
causing curb cuts and slopes to be made in pavements for the easy access
of wheel chair users; 


 </section><section><number>c</number>
engraving on the surface of the zebra crossing for the blind or for
persons with low vision; 


 </section><section><number>d</number>
engraving on the edge of railway platforms for the blind or for persons
with low vision; 


 </section><section><number>e</number>
devising appropriate symbols of disability; 


 </section><section><number>f</number>
warning signals at appropriate places. 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>46</number>
Non-discrimination in the built environment.—The appropriate Governments
and the local authorities shall, within the limits of their economic capacity
and development, provide for—
 <section><number>a</number>
ramps in public buildings; 


 </section><section><number>b</number>
adaptation of toilets for wheel chair users; 


 </section><section><number>c</number>
braille symbols and auditory signals in elevators or lifts; 


 </section><section><number>d</number>
ramps in hospitals, primary health centres and other medical care and
rehabilitation institutions. 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>47</number>
Non-discrimination in Government employments.—
<section><number>1</number> No establishment shall
dispense with, or reduce in rank, an employee who acquires a disability during
his service:
 Provided
that, if an employee, after acquiring disability is not suitable for the post he
was holding, could be shifted to some other post with the same pay scale and
service benefits:
 Provided
further that if it is not possible to adjust the employee against any post, he
may be kept on a supernumerary post until a suitable post is available or he
attains the age of superannuation, whichever is earlier.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
No promotion shall be denied to a person merely on the ground of his disability:
 Provided
that the appropriate Government may, having regard to the type of work carried
on in any establishment, by notification and subject to such conditions, if any,
as may be specified in such notification, exempt any establishment from the
provisions of this section.
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>48</number>
Research.—The appropriate Governments and local authorities shall promote
and sponsor research, inter alia, in the following areas:—
 <section><number>a</number>
prevention of disability; 


 </section><section><number>b</number>
rehabilitation including community based rehabilitation; 


 </section><section><number>c</number>
development of assistive devices including their psycho-social aspects; 


 </section><section><number>d</number>
job identification; 


 </section><section><number>e</number>
on site modifications in offices and factories. 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>49</number>
Financial incentives to Universities to enable them to undertake research.—The
appropriate Governments shall provide financial assistance to universities,
other institutions of higher learning professional bodies and non-Governmental
research units or institutions, for undertaking research for special education,
rehabilitation and manpower development.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>49</number>
Financial incentives to Universities to enable them to undertake research.—The
appropriate Governments shall provide financial assistance to universities,
other institutions of higher learning professional bodies and non-Governmental
research units or institutions, for undertaking research for special education,
rehabilitation and manpower development.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>50</number>
Competent authority.—The State Government shall appoint any authority as
it deems fit to be a competent authority for the purposes of this Act.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>51</number>
No person to establish or maintain an institution for persons with disabilities
except in accordance with a certificate of registration.—Save as otherwise
provided under this Act, no person shall establish or maintain any institution
for persons with disabilities except under and in accordance with a certificate
of registration issued in this behalf by the competent authority:
 Provided
that a person maintaining an institution for persons with disabilities
immediately before the commencement of this Act may continue to maintain such
institution for a period of six months from such commencement and if he has made
an application for such certificate under this section within the said period of
six months, till the disposal of such application.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>51</number>
No person to establish or maintain an institution for persons with disabilities
except in accordance with a certificate of registration.—Save as otherwise
provided under this Act, no person shall establish or maintain any institution
for persons with disabilities except under and in accordance with a certificate
of registration issued in this behalf by the competent authority:
 Provided
that a person maintaining an institution for persons with disabilities
immediately before the commencement of this Act may continue to maintain such
institution for a period of six months from such commencement and if he has made
an application for such certificate under this section within the said period of
six months, till the disposal of such application.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>52</number>
Certificate of registration.—
<section><number>1</number> Every application for a certificate of
registration shall be made to be competent authority in such form and in such
manner as may be prescribed by the State Government.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
On receipt of an application under sub-section (1) the competent authority shall
make such enquiries as it may deem fit and where it is satisfied that the
applicant has complied with the requirements of this Act and the rules made
thereunder it shall grant a certificate of registration to the applicant and
where it is not so satisfied the competent authority shall, by order, refuse to
grant the certificate applied for:
 Provided
that before making any order refusing to grant a certificate the competent
authority shall give to the applicant a reasonable opportunity of being heard
and every order of refusal to grant a certificate shall be communicated to the
applicant in such manner as may be prescribed by the State Government.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
No certificate of registration shall be granted under sub-section (2) unless the
institution with respect to which an application has been made is in a position
to provide such facilities and maintain such standards as may be prescribed by
the State Government.
 </section><section><number>4</number>
A certificate of registration granted under this section,—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
shall, unless revoked under section 53, remain in force for such period
as may be prescribed by the State Government; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
may be renewed from time to time for a like period; and 


 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
shall be in such form and shall be subject to such conditions as may be
prescribed by the State Government. 


 </subsection></section><section><number>5</number>
An application for renewal of a certificate of registration shall be made not
less than sixty days before the period of validity.
 </section><section><number>6</number>
The certificate of registration shall be displayed by the institution in a
conspicuous place.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>53</number>
Revocation of certificate.—
<section><number>1</number> The competent authority may, if it has
reasonable cause to believe that the holder of the certificate of registration
granted under sub-section (2) of section 52 has—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
made a statement in relation to any application for the issue or renewal
of the certificate which is incorrect or false in material particulars; or 


 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
committed or has caused to be committed any breach of rules or any
conditions subject to which the certificate was granted, 


 it
may, after making such inquiry as it deems fit, by order, revoke the
certificate:
 Provided
that no such order shall be made until an opportunity is given to the holder of
the certificate to show cause as to why the certificate should not be revoked.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
Where a certificate in respect of an institution has been revoked under
sub-section (1), such institution shall cease to function from the date of such
revocation:
 Provided
that where an appeal lies under section 54 against the order of revocation, such
institution shall cease to function—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
where no appeal has been preferred immediately on the expiry of the
period prescribed for the filing of such appeal, or 


 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
where such appeal has been preferred, but the order of revocation has
been upheld, from the date of the order of appeal. 


 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number>
On the revocation of a certificate in respect of an institution the competent
authority may direct that any person with disability who is an inmate of such
institution on the date of such revocation, shall be—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
restored to the custody of her or his parent, spouse or lawful guardian,
as the case may be, or 


 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
transferred to any other institution specified by the competent
authority. 


 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number>
Every institution which holds a certificate of registration which is revoked
under this section shall, immediately after such revocation, surrender such
certificate to the competent authority.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>54</number>
Appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> Any person aggrieved by the order of the competent authority
refusing to grant a certificate or revoking a certifi­cate may, within such
period as may be prescribed by the State Government, prefer an appeal to that
Government against such refusal or revocation.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The order of the State Government on such appeal shall be final.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>55</number>
Act not to apply to institutions established or maintained by the Central or
State Government.—Nothing contained in this Chapter shall apply to an
institution for persons with disabili­ties established or maintained by the
Central Government or a State Government.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>55</number>
Act not to apply to institutions established or maintained by the Central or
State Government.—Nothing contained in this Chapter shall apply to an
institution for persons with disabili­ties established or maintained by the
Central Government or a State Government.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>56</number>
Institutions for persons with severe disabilities.—
<section><number>1</number> The appropriate
Government may establish and maintain institutions for persons with severe
disabilities at such places as it thinks fit. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Where, the appropriate Government is of opinion that any institution other than
an institution, established under sub-section (1), is fit for the rehabilitation
of the persons with severe disabilities, the Government may recognise such
institution as an institution for persons with severe disabilities for the
purposes of this Act:
 Provided
that no institution shall be recognised under this section unless such
institution has complied with the requirement of this Act and the rules made
thereunder.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
Every institution established under sub-section (1) shall be maintained in such
manner and satisfy such conditions as may be prescribed by the appropriate
Government.
 </section><section><number>4</number>
For the purposes of this section “person with severe disabili­ty” means a
person with eighty per cent or more of one or more disabilities.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>57</number>
Appointment of Chief Commissioner for persons with disabili­ties.—
<section><number>1</number> The
Central Government may, by notification, appoint a Chief Commissioner for
persons with disabilities for the purposes of this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
A person shall not be qualified for appointment as the Chief Commissioner unless
he has special knowledge or practical experi­ence in respect of matters
relating to rehabilitation.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
The salary and allowances payable to and other terms and conditions of service
(including pension, gratuity and other retirement benefits) of the Chief
Commissioner shall be such as may be prescribed by the Central Government.
 </section><section><number>4</number>
The Central Government shall determine the nature and catego­ries of officers
and other employees required to assist the Chief Commissioner in the discharge
of his functions and provide the Chief Commissioners with such officers and
other employees as it thinks fit.
 </section><section><number>5</number>
The officers and employees provided to the Chief Commissioner shall discharge
their functions under the general superintendence of the Chief Commissioner.
 </section><section><number>6</number>
The salaries and allowances and other conditions of service of officers and
employees provided to the Chief Commissioner shall be such as may be prescribed
by the Central Government.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>57</number>
Appointment of Chief Commissioner for persons with disabili­ties.—
<section><number>1</number> The
Central Government may, by notification, appoint a Chief Commissioner for
persons with disabilities for the purposes of this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
A person shall not be qualified for appointment as the Chief Commissioner unless
he has special knowledge or practical experi­ence in respect of matters
relating to rehabilitation.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
The salary and allowances payable to and other terms and conditions of service
(including pension, gratuity and other retirement benefits) of the Chief
Commissioner shall be such as may be prescribed by the Central Government.
 </section><section><number>4</number>
The Central Government shall determine the nature and catego­ries of officers
and other employees required to assist the Chief Commissioner in the discharge
of his functions and provide the Chief Commissioners with such officers and
other employees as it thinks fit.
 </section><section><number>5</number>
The officers and employees provided to the Chief Commissioner shall discharge
their functions under the general superintendence of the Chief Commissioner.
 </section><section><number>6</number>
The salaries and allowances and other conditions of service of officers and
employees provided to the Chief Commissioner shall be such as may be prescribed
by the Central Government.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>58</number> Functions of the 
Chief Commissioner.—The 
Chief Commissioner shall—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  coordinate the 
work of the Commissioners;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  monitor the 
utilisation of funds disbursed by the Central Government;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  take steps to 
safeguard the rights and facilities made available to persons with disabilities;
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  submit reports 
to the Central Government on the implementation of the Act at such intervals as 
the Government may prescribe.
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>59</number>
Chief Commissioner to look into complaints with respect to deprivation of rights
of persons with disabilities.—Without prejudice to the provisions of
section 58 the Chief Commissioner may of his own motion or on the application of
any aggrieved person or otherwise look into complaints with respect to matters
relating to—
 <section><number>a</number>
deprivation of rights of persons with disabilities; 


 </section><section><number>b</number>
non-implementation of laws, rules, bye-laws, regulations, executive
orders, guidelines or instructions made or issued by the appropriate Governments
and the local authorities for the welfare and protection of rights or persons
with disabilities, 


 and
take up the matter with the appropriate authorities. 
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>59</number>
Chief Commissioner to look into complaints with respect to deprivation of rights
of persons with disabilities.—Without prejudice to the provisions of
section 58 the Chief Commissioner may of his own motion or on the application of
any aggrieved person or otherwise look into complaints with respect to matters
relating to—
 <section><number>a</number>
deprivation of rights of persons with disabilities; 


 </section><section><number>b</number>
non-implementation of laws, rules, bye-laws, regulations, executive
orders, guidelines or instructions made or issued by the appropriate Governments
and the local authorities for the welfare and protection of rights or persons
with disabilities, 


 and
take up the matter with the appropriate authorities. 
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>60</number>
Appointment of Commissioners for persons with disabilities.—
<section><number>1</number> Every
State Government may, by notification appoint a Commis­sioner for persons with
disabilities for the purposes of this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
A person shall not be qualified for appointment as a Commissioner unless he has
special knowledge or practical experience in respect of matters relating to
rehabilitation.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
The salary and allowances payable to and other terms and conditions of service
(including pension, gratuity and other retirement benefits) of the Commissioner
shall be such as may be prescribed by the State Government.
 </section><section><number>4</number>
The State Government shall determine the nature and categories of officers and
other employees required to assist the Commissioner in the discharge of his
functions and provide the Commissioner with such officers and other employees as
it thinks fit.
 </section><section><number>5</number>
The officers and employees provided to the Commissioner shall discharge their
functions under the general superintendence of the Commissioner.
 </section><section><number>6</number>
The salaries and allowances and other conditions of service of officers and
employees provided to the Commissioner shall be such as may be prescribed by the
State Government.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>60</number>
Appointment of Commissioners for persons with disabilities.—
<section><number>1</number> Every
State Government may, by notification appoint a Commis­sioner for persons with
disabilities for the purposes of this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
A person shall not be qualified for appointment as a Commissioner unless he has
special knowledge or practical experience in respect of matters relating to
rehabilitation.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
The salary and allowances payable to and other terms and conditions of service
(including pension, gratuity and other retirement benefits) of the Commissioner
shall be such as may be prescribed by the State Government.
 </section><section><number>4</number>
The State Government shall determine the nature and categories of officers and
other employees required to assist the Commissioner in the discharge of his
functions and provide the Commissioner with such officers and other employees as
it thinks fit.
 </section><section><number>5</number>
The officers and employees provided to the Commissioner shall discharge their
functions under the general superintendence of the Commissioner.
 </section><section><number>6</number>
The salaries and allowances and other conditions of service of officers and
employees provided to the Commissioner shall be such as may be prescribed by the
State Government.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>61</number>
Powers of the Commissioner.—The Commissioner within the State shall—
 <section><number>a</number>
co-ordinate with the departments of the State Government for the
programmes and schemes for the benefit of persons with disabilities; 


 </section><section><number>b</number>
monitor the utilisation of funds disbursed by the State Government.; 


 </section><section><number>c</number>
take step to safeguard the rights and facilities made available to
persons with disabilities; 


 </section><section><number>d</number>
submit reports to the State Government on the implementation of the Act
at such intervals as that Government may prescribe and forward a copy thereof to
the Chief Commissioner. 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>62</number>
Commissioner to look into complaints with respect to matters relating to
deprivation of rights of persons with disabilities.—Without prejudice to
the provisions of section 61 the Commissioner may of his own motion or on the
application of any aggrieved person or otherwise look into complaints with
respect to matters relating to—
 <section><number>a</number>
deprivation of rights of persons with disabilities; 


 </section><section><number>b</number>
non-implementation of laws, rules, bye-laws, regulations, executive
orders, guidelines or instructions made or issued by the appropriate Governments
and the local authorities for the welfare the protection of rights of persons
with disabilities, 


 and
take up the matter with the appropriate authorities.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>62</number>
Commissioner to look into complaints with respect to matters relating to
deprivation of rights of persons with disabilities.—Without prejudice to
the provisions of section 61 the Commissioner may of his own motion or on the
application of any aggrieved person or otherwise look into complaints with
respect to matters relating to—
 <section><number>a</number>
deprivation of rights of persons with disabilities; 


 </section><section><number>b</number>
non-implementation of laws, rules, bye-laws, regulations, executive
orders, guidelines or instructions made or issued by the appropriate Governments
and the local authorities for the welfare the protection of rights of persons
with disabilities, 


 and
take up the matter with the appropriate authorities.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>63</number>
Authorities and officers to have certain powers of civil court.—
<section><number>1</number> The
Chief Commissioner and the Commissioners shall, for the purpose of discharging
their functions under this Act, have the same powers as are vested in a court
under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) while trying a suit, in
respect of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
summoning and enforcing the attendance of witnesses; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
requiring the discovery and production of any document; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
requisitioning any public record or copy thereof from any court or
office; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
receiving evidence on affidavits; and 


 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>
issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses or documents. 


 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
Every proceeding before the Chief Commissioner and Commissioners shall be a
judicial proceeding within the meaning of sections 193 and 228 of the Indian
Penal Code (45 of 1860) and the Chief Commissioner, the Commissioner, the
competent authority, shall be deemed to be a civil court for the purposes of
section 195 and Chapter XXVI of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of
1974).

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>63</number>
Authorities and officers to have certain powers of civil court.—
<section><number>1</number> The
Chief Commissioner and the Commissioners shall, for the purpose of discharging
their functions under this Act, have the same powers as are vested in a court
under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) while trying a suit, in
respect of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
summoning and enforcing the attendance of witnesses; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
requiring the discovery and production of any document; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
requisitioning any public record or copy thereof from any court or
office; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
receiving evidence on affidavits; and 


 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>
issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses or documents. 


 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
Every proceeding before the Chief Commissioner and Commissioners shall be a
judicial proceeding within the meaning of sections 193 and 228 of the Indian
Penal Code (45 of 1860) and the Chief Commissioner, the Commissioner, the
competent authority, shall be deemed to be a civil court for the purposes of
section 195 and Chapter XXVI of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of
1974).

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>64</number>
Annual report to be prepared by the Chief Commissioner.—
<section><number>1</number> The Chief
Commissioner shall prepare in such form and at such time for each financial year
as may be prescribed by the Central Government an annual report giving a full
account of his activities during the previous financial year and forward a copy
thereof to the Central Government.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Central Government shall cause the annual report to be laid before each
House of Parliament along with the recommendations explaining the action taken
or proposed to be taken on the recommendation made therein insofar as they
relate to the Central Government and the reasons for non-acceptance, if any, of
any such recommendation or part.
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>64</number>
Annual report to be prepared by the Chief Commissioner.—
<section><number>1</number> The Chief
Commissioner shall prepare in such form and at such time for each financial year
as may be prescribed by the Central Government an annual report giving a full
account of his activities during the previous financial year and forward a copy
thereof to the Central Government.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Central Government shall cause the annual report to be laid before each
House of Parliament along with the recommendations explaining the action taken
or proposed to be taken on the recommendation made therein insofar as they
relate to the Central Government and the reasons for non-acceptance, if any, of
any such recommendation or part.
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>65</number>
Annual reports to be prepared by the Commissioners.—
<section><number>1</number> The Commissioner
shall prepare in such form and at such time for each financial year as may be
prescribed by the State Government an annual report giving a full account of his
activities during the previous financial years and forward a copy thereof to the
State Government.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The State Government shall cause the annual report to be laid before each State
Legislature along with the recommendations explaining the action taken or
proposed to be taken on the recommendations made therein insofar as they relate
to the State Government and the reasons for non-acceptance, if any, of any such
recommendation or part

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>66</number>
Appropriate Governments and local authorities to undertake rehabilitation.—
<section><number>1</number>
The appropriate Governments and the local authorities shall within the limits of
their economic capacity and development undertake or cause to be undertaken
rehabilitation of all persons with disabilities.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
For purposes of sub-section (1), the appropriate Governments and local
authorities shall grant financial assistance to non-Govern­mental Organisations.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
The appropriate Governments and local authorities while formulating
rehabilitation policies shall consult the non-Governmental Organisations working
for the cause of persons with disabilities.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>66</number>
Appropriate Governments and local authorities to undertake rehabilitation.—
<section><number>1</number>
The appropriate Governments and the local authorities shall within the limits of
their economic capacity and development undertake or cause to be undertaken
rehabilitation of all persons with disabilities.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
For purposes of sub-section (1), the appropriate Governments and local
authorities shall grant financial assistance to non-Govern­mental Organisations.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
The appropriate Governments and local authorities while formulating
rehabilitation policies shall consult the non-Governmental Organisations working
for the cause of persons with disabilities.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>67</number>
Insurance scheme for employees with disabilities.—
<section><number>1</number> The appropriate
Government shall by notification frame an insurance scheme for the benefit of
its employees with disabilities.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, the appropriate Government
may instead of framing an insurance scheme frame an alternative security scheme
for its employees with disabilities.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>68</number>
Unemployment allowance.—The appropriate Governments shall within the
limits of their economic capacity and development shall by notification frame a
scheme for payment of an unemployment allowance to persons with disabilities
registered with the Special Employment Exchange for more than two years and who
could not be placed in any gainful occupation.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>69</number>
Punishment for fraudulently availing any benefit meant for persons with
disabilities.—Whoever, fraudulently avails or attempts to avail, any
benefit meant for persons with disabilities, shall be punishable with
imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years or with fine which may
extend to twenty thousand rupees or with both.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>69</number>
Punishment for fraudulently availing any benefit meant for persons with
disabilities.—Whoever, fraudulently avails or attempts to avail, any
benefit meant for persons with disabilities, shall be punishable with
imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years or with fine which may
extend to twenty thousand rupees or with both.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>70</number>
Chief Commissioners, Commissioners, officers and other staff to be public
servants.—The Chief Commissioner, the Commissioners and other officers and
staff provided to them shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning
of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>70</number>
Chief Commissioners, Commissioners, officers and other staff to be public
servants.—The Chief Commissioner, the Commissioners and other officers and
staff provided to them shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning
of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>71</number>
Protection of action taken in good faith.—No suit, prosecution or other
legal proceedings shall lie against the Central Government, the State
Governments or the local authority or any officer of the Government in respect
of anything which is done in good faith or intended to be done in pursuance of
this Act and any rules or orders made thereunder.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>72</number>
Act to be in addition to and not in derogation of any other law.—The
provisions of this Act, or the rules made thereunder shall be in addition to,
and not in derogation of any other law for the time being in force or any rules,
order or any instructions issued thereunder, enacted or issued for the benefits
of persons with disabilities.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>72</number>
Act to be in addition to and not in derogation of any other law.—The
provisions of this Act, or the rules made thereunder shall be in addition to,
and not in derogation of any other law for the time being in force or any rules,
order or any instructions issued thereunder, enacted or issued for the benefits
of persons with disabilities.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>73</number>
Power of appropriate Government to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The appropriate
Government may, by notification, make rules for carrying out the provisions of
this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing powers,
such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
the manner in which a State Government or a Union territory shall be
chosen under clause (k) of sub-section (2) of section 3; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
allowances which members shall receive under sub-section (7) of section
4; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
rules of procedure which the Central Co-ordination Committee shall
observe in regard to the transaction of business in its meeting under section 7; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
such other functions which the Central Co-ordination Committee may
perform under clause (h) of sub-section (2) of section 8; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>
the manner in which a State Government or a Union territory shall be
chosen under clause (h) of sub-section (2) of section 9; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>
the allowances which the Members shall receive under sub-section (3) of
section 9; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number>
rules of procedure which the Central Executive Committee shall observe in
regard to transaction of business at its meetings under section 11; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number>
the manner and purposes for which a person may be associated under
sub-section (1) of section 12; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number>
fees and allowances which a person associated with the Central Executive
Committee shall receive under sub-section (3) of section 12; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number>
allowances which members shall receive under sub-section (7) of 
section 14; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number>
rules of procedure which a State Co-ordination Committee shall observe in
regard to transaction of business in its meetings under section 17; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number>
such other functions which a State Co-ordination Committee may perform
under clause (g) of sub-section (2) of section 18; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>m</number>
the allowances which Members shall receive under sub-section (3) of
section 19; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>n</number>
rules of procedure which a State Executive Committee shall observe in
regard to transaction of business at its meetings under section 21; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>o</number>
the manner and purposes for which a person may be associated under sub-
section (1) of section 22; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>p</number>
fees and allowances which a person associated with the State Executive
Committee may receive under sub-section (3) of section 22; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>q</number>
information or return which the employer in every establishment should
furnish and the Special Employment Exchange to which such information or return
shall be furnished under sub-section (1) of section 34; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>r</number>
the form and the manner in which record shall be maintained by an
employer under sub-section (1) of section 37; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>s</number>
the form and manner in which an application shall be made under sub-
section (1) of section 52; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>t</number>
the manner in which an order of refusal shall be communicated under
sub-section (2) of section 52; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>u</number>
facilities or standards required to be provided or maintained under
sub-section (3) of section 52; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number>
the period for which a certificate of registration shall be valid under
clause (a) of sub-section (4) of section 52; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>w</number>
the form in which and conditions subject to which a certificate of
registration shall be granted under clause (c) of sub-section (4) of section 52; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>x</number>
period within which an appeal shall lie under sub-section (1) of 
section 54; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>y</number>
the manner in which an institution for persons with severe disabilities
shall be maintained and conditions which have to be satisfied under sub-section
(3) of section 60; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>z</number>
the salary, allowances and other terms and conditions of service of the
Chief Commissioner under sub-section (3) of section 57; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>za</number>
the salary allowances and other conditions of service of officers and
employees under sub-section (6) of section 57; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>zb</number>
intervals at which the Chief Commissioner shall report to the Central
Government under clause (d) of section 58; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>zc</number>
the salary, allowances, and other terms and conditions of service of the
Commissioner under sub-section (3) of section 60; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>zd</number>
the salary, allowances and other conditions of service of officers and
employees under sub-section (6) of section 60; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>ze</number>
intervals within which the Commissioner shall report to the State
Government under clause (d) of section 61; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>zf</number>
the form and time in which annual report shall be prepared under sub-
section (1) of section 64; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>zg</number>
the form and time in which annual report shall be prepared under
sub-section (1) of section 65; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>zh</number>
any other matter which is required to be or may be pre­scribed. 


 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number>
Every notification made by the Central Government under the proviso to section
33, proviso to sub-section (2) of section 47, every scheme framed by it under
section 27, section 30, sub-section (1) of section 38, section 42, section 43,
section 67, section 68 and every rule made by it under sub-section (1), shall be
laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while
it is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one
session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the
session immediately following the sessions or the successive sessions aforesaid,
both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule, notification or
scheme, both Houses agree that the rule, notification or scheme should not be
made, the rule, notification or scheme shall thereafter have effect only in such
modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be so, however, that any such
modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything
previously done under that rule, notification or scheme, as the case may be.
 </section><section><number>4</number>
Every notification made by the State Government under the proviso to 
section 33, proviso to sub-section (2) of section 47, every scheme made by it
under section 27, section 30, sub-section (1) of section 38, section 42, section
43, section 67, section 68, and every rule made by it under sub-section (1),
shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of State
Legis­lature, where it consist of two Houses or where such legislature consists
of one House before that House.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>74</number>
Amendment of Act 39 of 1987.—In section 12 of the Legal Services Act,
1987, for clause (d) the following clause shall be substituted,
namely:— 
 
 “(d) a person with disability as
defined in clause 
<section><number>i</number> of section 2 of the Persons With Disabilities (Equal
Opportunities, Protection of Rights and Full Participation) Act, 1995.”. 



 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>
Came into force on 7-2-1996, vide S.O. 107 (E), dated 7th
February, 1996.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>