<act><tid>364039</tid>
<title>THE <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> SALARY, ALLOWANCES AND PENSION] OF MEMBERSOF PARLIAMENT ACT, <year>1954</year></title>

ACT NO. 30 OF <year>1954</year>
[ 22nd May, <year>1954</year>.]

An Act to provide for the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> salary, allowances and pension] of 
Members of Parliament.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:





<article><tid>1843958</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>239253</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Salary, Allowances and Pension] of Members of Parliament Act, <year>1954</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>722543</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on the first day of June, <year>1954</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1873285</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act,-
<section><tid>1925539</tid>
<number>a</number>" committee" means a Committee of either House of 
Parliament, and includes a Joint Committee of both Houses;

</section>

<section><tid>521114</tid>
<number>b</number>" member" means a member of either House of Parliament, 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> but, save as otherwise expressly provided in this Act, does 
not include]-

<subsection><tid>1164470</tid>
<number>i</number>a Minister as defined in the Salaries and 
Allowances of Ministers Act, <year>1952</year> (58 of <year>1952</year>.); <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1434207</tid>
<number>ii</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> a Leader of the Opposition as defined in the 
Salary and Allowances of Leaders of Opposition in 
Parliament Act, <year>1977</year> (33 of <year>1977</year>.); and];

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>648329</tid>
<number>iii</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>] an officer of Parliament as defined in the 
Salaries and Allowances of Officers of Parliament Act, 
<year>1953</year>; (20 of <year>1953</year>).

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1875288</tid>
<number>c</number>" new member" means a member who takes his seat in 
either House of Parliament after the commencement of this Act 
and includes a member who is re- elected or re- nominated;

</section>

<section><tid>1244431</tid>
<number>d</number>" period of residence on duty" means the period during 
which a member resides at a place where a session of a House 
of Parliament or a sitting of a committee is held or where 
any other business connected with his duties as such member 
is transacted, for the purpose of attending such session or 
sitting

<pagefootnote><pagenum>136</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 105 of <year>1976</year>, s. 2, for" salaries and allowances" 
 (w. e. f. 9- 9- <year>1976</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 55 of <year>1958</year>, s. 2, for" but does not include".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Omitted by Act 33 of <year>1977</year>, s. 11 (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1977</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Ins. by s. 11, ibid., (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1977</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Sub- clause (ii) re- numbered as sub- clause (iii) thereof by s. 11, 
ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1977</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

or for the purpose of attending to such other business, and 
includes-


<subsection><tid>1394033</tid>
<number>i</number>in the case of a session of a House of Parliament, 
a period of such residence, not exceeding three days 
immediately preceding the commencement of the session 
and a period of such residence, not exceeding three 
days,, immediately succeeding the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> date on which the 
House of Parliament is adjourned sine die or for a 
period exceeding seven days], and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>355342</tid>
<number>ii</number>in the case of a sitting of a committee or any 
other business, a period of such residence, not 
exceeding two days, immediately preceding the 
commencement of the business of the committee or other 
business and a period of such residence, not exceeding 
two days, immediately succeeding the conclusion of the 
business of the committee or other business;
Explanation.- A member who ordinarily resides at a place 
where a session of a House of Parliament or a sitting of 
a committee is held or where any other business 
connected with his duties as such member is transacted 
shall, for the duration of the session or sitting or the 
time occupied for the transaction of other business 
 (including the three or two days immediately preceding  
  or succeeding), be deemed to reside at such place for 
the purpose of attending such session or sitting or, as 
the case may be, for the purpose of attending to such 
other business;


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1087457</tid>
<number>e</number>" term of office" means,- 
 (a) in relation to a person who is a member at the 
commencement of this Act, the period beginning with such 
commencement and ending with the date on, which his seat 
becomes vacant; 
 (b) <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> in relation to a new member,- 
 (i) where such new member is a member of the Council 
of" States elected in a biennial election, or nominated, 
to that House, the period beginning with the date of 
publication of the notification in the official Gazette 
notifying his name under section 71 of the 
Representation of the People Act, <year>1951</year> (43 of <year>1951</year>.); or 
 (ii) where such new member is a member of the House 
of the People elected in a general election held for 
the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>137</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 55 of <year>1958</year> s. 2, for" end of the session" 
 (retrospectively).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 105 of <year>1976</year>, s. 4, for sub- cl. (b), (w. e. f. 9- 9- <year>1970</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

purpose of constituting a new House of the People, the 
period beginning with the date of publication of the 
notification of the Election Commission under section 73 
of the said Act; or 
 (iii) where such new member is a member of 
either House of Parliament elected in a bye- election to 
that House or a member nominated to the House of the 
People, the period beginning with the date of his 
election referred to in section 67A of the said Act or 
as the case may be the date of his nomination,

and ending with, in each such case, the date on which his 
seat becomes vacant.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1145522</tid>
<number>3</number>Salarles and daily allowances. A member shall be entitled to 
receive a salary at the rate <footcitenum>10</footcitenum> One thousand and Five hundred rupees] 
per mensem during the whole of his term of office <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> and subject to 
any rules made under this Act] an allowance at the rate of <footcitenum>11</footcitenum> Two 
hundred rupees] for each day during any period of residence on duty.
<footcitenum>11</footcitenum> provided that no member shall be entitled to the aforesaid 
allowance unless he signs the register, maintained for this purpose by 
the Secretariat of the House of the People or, as the case may be, 
Council of States, on all the days (except intervening holidays for  
  which no such signing is required) of the session of the House for 
which the allowance is claimed.]



</article>



<article><tid>1625265</tid>
<number> 4</number> Travelling allowances.
<section><tid>1851446</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be paid to each member  
in respect of every journey performed by him <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> in India] for the 
purpose of attending a session of a House of Parliament or a meeting 
of a committee or for the purpose of attending to any other business 
connected with his duties as a member, from his usual place of 
residence to the place where the session or the meeting is to 
be held or the other business is to be transacted and for the return 
journey from such place to his usual place of residence-

<subsection><tid>1910780</tid>
<number>a</number>if the journey is performed by rail an amount equal to 
 <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> one first class fare] plus one <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> second class] fare for 
each such journey, irrespective of the class in which the 
member actually travels;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1073650</tid>
<number>b</number>if the journey is performed by air, an amount equal to 
one and one- fourth of the air fare for each such journey;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1223101</tid>
<number>c</number>if the journey or any part thereof cannot be performed 
by rail or air-

<subsubsection><tid>377556</tid>
<number>i</number><footcitenum>7</footcitenum> where the journey or any part thereof is per- 
formed by steamer, an amount equal to one and three- 
fifths of the fare (without diet) for the highest class 
in the steamer for each such journey or part thereof, 
or, if there is no regular steamer service. such amount 
for each

<pagefootnote><pagenum>138</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 26 of <year>1964</year>, s. 2 for" four hundred rupees" (w. e. f. 1- 6-  
  <year>1964</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 55 of <year>1958</year>, s. 3 for" plus" (retrospectively).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 25 of <year>1969</year>, s. 2. for" thirty- one rupees" (w. e. f. 16- 5-  
  <year>1969</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Ins. by Act 55 of <year>1958</year>, s. 4

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Subs. by Act 9 of <year>1955</year>, s. 2" one second class fare" (w. e. f. 1- 4-  
  <year>1955</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Subs. by Act 61 of <year>1982</year>, s. 2 for" third class"

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>7</number>Subs by Act 55 of <year>1958</year>, s. 4 for the original sub- clause (i) 
 (retrospectively)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>8</number>Subs. by Act 22 of <year>1983</year>, s. 2

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>9</number>Subs. by Act 74 of <year>1985</year>, s. 2

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>10</number>Subs. by Act 60 of <year>1988</year>, s. 2

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>11</number>Subs. and ins by Act 48 of <year>1993</year>, s. 2



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

such journey or part thereof as may be prescribed by 
rules made under section 9;]


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1758918</tid>
<number>ii</number>where the journey or any part thereof is performed 
by road, a road mileage at the rate of <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Five rupees per 
Kilometre]
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Provided that where the spouse, if any, of a member performs 
such journey or part thereof by road unaccompanied by such member, the 
road mileage prescribed under this sab- clause shall be allowed to him 
for such journey or part thereof:]

<footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Provided further that where a member performs journey by road in 
Delhi from and to an aerodrome, he shall be paid a minimum amount of 
one hundred and twenty rupees for each such journey.]

Explanation.- For the purposes of sub- clause (ii) of clause (c) 
this sub- section, the expression" journey" shall include the journey 
from and to the railway station, port or aerodrome to and from the 
usual place of residence of the member or as the case may be, the 
residence of the member at the place where the session of the House of 
Parliament or a meeting of the committee is to be held or where any 
other business is to be transacted.


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1157781</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), a 
member who performs a journey by road between places connected by 
rail or steamer, either wholly or in part, may draw the mileage 
allowance referred to in sub- clause (ii) of clause (c) of sub- section 
 (1) in place of, the travelling allowance which would have been 
admissible to him if he had travelled by rail or steamer, as the case 
may be
Provided that the total amount of travelling allowance drawn by 
such member for the entire journey shall not exceed the amount which 
would have been admissible to him had he performed such journey by 
rail or by steamer, as the case may be.


</section>

<section><tid>1551631</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> There shall be paid to a member in respect of a journey 
performed by him in the course of a tour outside India undertaken in 
the discharge of his duties as such member, such travelling and daily 
allowances as may be prescribed by rules made under section 9. 1



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>147385</tid>
<number> 5</number> Travelling allowances for intermediate journeys. <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>
<section><tid>301424</tid>
<number>1</number>I Where a  
member absents himself for less- than fifteen days during a session of 
a House of Parliament or a sitting of a committee for visiting any 
place in India, he shall be entitled to receive travelling allowances 
in respect of such journey to such place and for the' return journey-

<subsection><tid>1159917</tid>
<number>a</number>if the journey Is performed by rail, equal to 
 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> one first class fare] for each such journey irrespective of 
the class in which the member actually travels;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>138A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 61 of <year>1982</year>, s. 2, for certain words.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by Act 55 of <year>1958</year>, s. 4.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>section 5 re- numbered as sub- section (1) of that section by Act 
105 of <year>1976</year>. s. 5 (w. e. f. 9- 9- <year>1976</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by Act 9 of <year>1955</year>, s. 2 for" one second class fare" (w. e. f.  
  1- 4- <year>1955</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Ins by Act 60 of <year>1988</year> s. 3 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1988</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Subs. and ins by Act 48 of <year>1993</year>, s. 3


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>426568</tid>
<number>b</number>[ if the journey, being a journey during a sitting of the 
committee] 6 is performed by air, equal to one fare by air for each 
such journey:
Provided that such travelling allowances shall not exceed the 
total amount of daily allowances which would have been admissible to 
such member under section 3 for the days of absence if he had not so 
remained absent.

<footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Provided further that nothing in the first proviso shall apply, 
if the member performs the journey by air for visiting any place in 
India not more than once during a sitting of the Committee.]

[ (1A) Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), a 
member shall be entitled to receive travelling allowances in respect 
of every journey performed by air for visiting any place in India 
during the interval not exceeding seven days between two sitting of a 
Department related Standing Committee when a House of Parliament is 
adjourned for a fixed period during the Budget Session:

Provided that such travelling allowances, excluding the air fare, 
shall not exceed the total amount of daily allowances which would have 
been admissible to such member under siction 3 for the days of absence 
if he had not remained absent.]


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1273956</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Every member shall be entitled to an amount equal to the 
fare by air for each single journey by air (other than a journey  
referred to in section 4 or the second proviso to sub- section (1) of 
  this section or section 6C) performed by him from[ either alone or 
along with companion or spouse,] 8 any place in India to any other 
place in India during his term of office as such member:
Provided that no member shall be entitled to any payment under 
this sub- section in respect of any journeys in excess of[ twenty 
eight] 8 performed by him during any year.

Explanation I.- The provisions of clause (c) of sub- section (1) 
and of sub- section (2) of section 4 shall, so far as may be, apply to 
travelling allowances payable under this section as they apply to 
travelling allowances payable under that section.

Explanation II.- For the purposes of this section," year" means,-


<subsection><tid>694471</tid>
<number>i</number>in the case of a person who is, a member at the com- 
mencement of the Salary, Allowances and Pension of Members of 
Parliament (Amendment) Act, <year>1985</year>, the year beginning with 
such commencement and each of the subsequent years;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>636664</tid>
<number>ii</number>in the case of a person who becomes a member after such 
commencement, the year beginning with the date on which his, 
term of office as such member commences and each of the 
subsequent years:]
 8Explanation III.-- For the purposes of sub- section (2), any 
jurney performed by the companion or the spouse shall be added in 
computing the limit of twenty- eight journeys specified in the proviso 
to that sub- section.]




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1205107</tid>
<number> 6</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Free transit by railway.
<section><tid>1694545</tid>
<number>1</number>Every member shall be provided  
with one free non- transferable[ air conditioned two tier] 7 pass which 
shall entitle him to travel at any time by any railway in India.
Explanation.- <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> For the purposes of this sub- section and section 
 6A and 6B], a member shall include a Minister as defined in the 
Salaries and Allowances of Ministers Act, <year>1952</year> (58 of <year>1952</year>) <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> a Leaders 
of Opposition as defined in the Salary and Allowances of Leaders of 
Opposition in Parliament Act, <year>1977</year> 33 of <year>1977</year>. and an officer of 
Parliament as defined in the Salaries and Allowances of Officers of 
Parliament Act, <year>1953</year> 20 of <year>1953</year>. other than the Chairman of the 
Council of States.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>139</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs by Act 25 of <year>1969</year>, s. 3, for the previous proviso.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by Act 105 of <year>1976</year> s. 5 (w. e. f. 9- 9- <year>1976</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 55 of <year>1958</year>, s. 5 for the original section.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by Act 29 of <year>1972</year>, s. 3 for certain words.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Ins. by Act 33 of <year>1977</year>, s. 11. (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1977</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Subs. by Act 74 of <year>1985</year>, s. 3

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>7</number>Subs. by Act 60 of <year>1988</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1988</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>8</number>Ins. and subs. by Act 3 of <year>1993</year>, s. 2

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>9</number>Ins. by Act 15 of <year>1995</year>, S. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1995</year>)


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1073831</tid>
<number>2</number>A free railway pass issued to a member under sub- section (1) 
shall be valid for the term of his office and on the expiration of 
such term, the pass shall be surrendered to the Secretary of the House 
of the People or the Council of States, as the case may be:
Provided that where any such pass is issued to a new member 
before he takes his seat in either House of Parliament, he shall be 
entitled to use the pass for attending a session of that House for 
taking his seat therein.


</section>

<section><tid>204991</tid>
<number>3</number>Until a member is provided with a free railway pass under 
sub- section (1), he shall be, and shall be deemed always to have been 
entitled to an amount equal to one <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> air conditioned two tier] fare 
for any journey of the nature referred to in sub- section (1) of 
section 4 performed by him by rail.

</section>

<section><tid>1620301</tid>
<number>4</number>A member who on ceasing to be a member surrenders his pass 
shall, if he performs any return journey by rail of the nature 
referred to in sub- section (1) of section 4, be entitled and be deemed 
always to have been entitled in respect of that journey to an amount 
equal to one[ air conditioned two- tier] 3 fare.

</section>

<section><tid>703701</tid>
<number>5</number>Nothing in this section shall be construed as disentailing a 
member to any travelling allowances to which he is otherwise entitled 
under the provisions of this Act.]

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>96320</tid>
<number> 6A</number> Without prejudice to the provisions of section 6, every member 
representing the Union territory of the Andaman and Nicobar Islands 
or the Union territory of Lakshadweep shall-
<section><tid>1418231</tid>
<number>a</number>be provided with one free non- transferable pass which 
shall entitle him to travel at any time by the highest class 
by steamer to and from any part of his constituency and any 
other part of his constituency or the nearest part in the 
main land of India; and

</section>

<section><tid>775780</tid>
<number>b</number>be entitled to an amount equal to the fare by air from 
his usual place of residence to the nearest airport the main 
land of India <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> and back]
Provided that nothing in this sub- section shall be construed as 
absolving the member from payment of any diet charges payable by him 
during such travel.


<subsection><tid>1272671</tid>
<number>2</number>A free steamer pass issued to a member under sub- section (1) 
shall be valid for the term of his office and on the expiration of his 
term, the pass shall be surrendered to the Secretary of the House of 
the People:
Provided that where any such pass is issued to a new member 
before he takes his seat in the House of the People, he shall be 
entitled to use the pass for attending a session of that House for 
taking his seat therein.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>140</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 29 of <year>1972</year>. S. 4.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by the Laccadive Minicoy and Amindivi Islands (Alternation  
  of Name), Adaptation of Laws Order, <year>1974</year> (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1973</year>),

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 60 of <year>1988</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1988</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by s. 5, ibid (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1988</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Added by Act 30 of <year>1989</year>, s. 2.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>478531</tid>
<number>3</number>Until a member is provided with a free steamer pass under 
sub- section (1), he shall be entitled to an amount equal to one fare 
 (without diet) for the highest class for any journey of the nature 
referred to in sub- section (1) of section 4 performed by him by 
steamer.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1975832</tid>
<number>4</number>A member who on ceasing to be a member surrenders the 
steamer pass issued to him under sub- section (1) shall, if he performs 
any return journey by steamer of the nature referred to in sub- section 
 (1) of section 4, be entitled in respect of that journey to an amount 
equal to one fare (without diet) for the highest class.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1960233</tid>
<number>5</number>Nothing in this section shall be construed as disentitling a 
member to any travelling allowances to which he is otherwise entitled 
under the provisions of this Act.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1829873</tid>
<number>6</number>In addition to[ the facilities provided to a member] 4 under 
sub- section (1), he also be entitled-

<subsubsection><tid>1107283</tid>
<number>i</number>to one free pass for one person to accompany the member 
and travel by the[ highest class] 4 by steamer to and fro any 
part of the constituency of the member and any other part of 
his constituency or the nearest port in the mainland of 
India; <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> or]

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>812421</tid>
<number>ii</number>to one free- non- transferable pass for the spouse, if 
any of the member to travel by the highest class by steamer 
to and the usual place of residence of the member in his 
constituency and the nearest port in the mainland of India,

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>82719</tid>
<number>iii</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> To an amount equal to the fare by air either for the 
spouse, if any, of the member or for one person to accompany the 
member from the usual place of residence in the Island to the nearest 
airport of the main land of India[ and back.] 7
Provided that nothing in this sub- section shall be constructions 
absolving the person accompanying the member or the spouse of the 
member from payment of any diet charges payable by such person or 
spouse during such travel.]


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1919193</tid>
<number> 6AA</number> <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Special facility to members from Ladakh.
<section><tid>862838</tid>
<number>1</number>Without  
prejudice to the provisions of section 6, every member who has his 
ordinary place of residence in the Ladakh area of the State of Jammu 
and Kashmir shall be entitled to an amount equal to the fare by air 
for each single journey by air performed by him from any airport in 
Ladakh to the airport in Delhi and back at any time.

</section>

<section><tid>1220848</tid>
<number>2</number>In addition to the air travel provided to a member under 
sub- section (1), he shall also be entitled to an amount equal to the 
fare by air for each single journey by air- performed by the spouse, if 
any, of the member or one person to accompany such member, from any- 
airport in Ladakh area to the airport in Delhi and back at any time.]
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> 6B.] Travel facilities to members. Without prejudice to the 
other provisions of this Act the member shall be entitled-


<subsection><tid>1090016</tid>
<number>i</number>to travel by any railway in India at any time in first 
class air- conditioned on payment of the difference between 
the railway fares for first class air- conditioned[ and air 
conditioned two- tier.] 6

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1704500</tid>
<number>ii</number>to one free air[ conditioned two- tier] 6 railway pass for 
one person to accompany the member when he travels by rail; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1370860</tid>
<number>iii</number>to one free non- transferable[ air conditioned 
two- tier] 6 railway pass for the spouse, if any, of the member 
to travel from the usual place of residence of the member to 
Delhi and back once during every session.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>140A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 25 of <year>1969</year>, s. 5.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Re- numbered by Act 29 of <year>1972</year>, S. 4.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 61 of <year>1982</year>, s. 3, for" third class".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. and ins. by Act 60 of <year>1988</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1988</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Ins. by s. 6 ibid, (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1988</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Subs. by s. 7 ibid (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1988</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>7</number>Added by Act 30 of <year>1989</year>, s. 2


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

<footcitenum>8</footcitenum> and if such journey or any part thereof is performed by air from 
any place other than the usual place of residence of the member, to 
Delhi and back to an amount equal to the fare by air for such journey 
or part thereof.

Provided that where such journey or part thereof by such spouse 
is performed by air from any other place, the expenditure on such 
journey or part thereof shall not exceed the amount payable if the 
journey had been performed from the usual place of residence of the 
member to Delhi and back:]

<footcitenum>8</footcitenum> Provided further that where a member travels by rail in first 
class air- conditioned and no person accompanies that member in that 
journey in air- conditioned two- tier by virtue of the free air- 
conditioned two- tier railway pass referred to in clause (ii) then in 
determining the amount payable by the member under clause (i) the 
amount of air- conditioned two- tier fare for such journey shall be 
adjusted against the difference referred to in that clause; so 
however, that the member shall not be entitled to claim the balance 
of such air- conditioned two- tier fare left after such adjustment."]


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>798357</tid>
<number>6C</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Air travel facilities in certain circunstances. Without 
prejudice to the other provisions of this Act, where during any part 
of a year the usual place of residence of a member in his constituency 
is inaccessible to or from any place outside his constituency by road, 
rail or steamer due to climatic conditions, but there is air service 
between any place in his constituency, and the nearest place, having 
rail service, outside his constituency, such member shall be entitled 
to travel to and fro by air from the nearest place in his constituency 
where there is air service to such place having rail service:
Provided that where the nearest place having air service is 
outside his constituency, such member shall be entitled to travel to 
and fro by air only from such place to the nearest place having rail 
service.]

</article>



<article><tid>1670406</tid>
<number> 6D</number> <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Special facility to blind and physically incapacitated 
members. A member who is blind or who is, in the opinion of the 
Chairman of the Council of States or, as the case may be, the Speaker 
of the House of the People, so incapacitated physically as to require 
the facility of an attendant shall, with respect to each such journey 
by air as is referred to in clause (b) of sub- section
<section><tid>1434185</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 4  
or clause (b) of sub- section (1) or subsection (2) of section 5] or 
section 6C which he performs along with an attendant, be entitled (in  
addition to the allowances which he is entitled under section 4 or 
  section 5 or, as the case may be, section 6C) to an amount equal to 
one fare by air for such journey.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>332522</tid>
<number>7</number>Allowances during short intervals between the adjournment of 
a House of Parliament and the re- Assembly of that House, etc. <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Where 
the interval between the adjournment of a House of Parliament or, as 
the case may be, one sitting of a committee and the re- assembly of 
that House or the next sitting of the committee at the same place] 
does not exceed seven days and the member concerned

<pagefootnote><pagenum>140B</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 61 of <year>1982</year>, s. 3.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by s. 3 ibid., for" third class".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by s. 3 ibid., for certain words.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Ins. by Act 105 of <year>1976</year>, s. 6 (w. e. f. 9- 9- <year>1976</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Ins. by Act 27 of <year>1979</year>, s, 2.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Ins. by Act 55 of <year>1958</year> s. 6 for certain words (retrospectively)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>7</number>Subs. by Act 74 of <year>1985</year>, s. 4

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>8</number>Subs. by Act 60 of <year>1988</year>, s. 7 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1988</year>)




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

elects to remain at such place during the interval, he shall be 
entitled to draw for each day of residence at such place a daily 
allowances at the rate specified in section 3:

Provided that if the member leaves such place during the 
interval, his absence from the place shall be treated as absence 
during a session of a House of Parliament or a sitting of the 
committee, as the case may be, and the provisions of section 5 shall 
apply accordingly.



</article>



<article><tid>1475005</tid>
<number>8</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Constituency allowance and amenities. A member shall be 
entitled to such constituency allowance,[ office expense allowance] 8 
and to such medical facilities for himself and for members of his 
family and to such housing, telephone, water, electricity facilities 
or Such amount in cash in lieu of all or any of such facilities, as 
may be prescribed by rules under section 9.]
</article>



<article><tid>1089779</tid>
<number> 8A</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Pension] <footcitenum>9</footcitenum> With effect from the commencement of the 
Salary, Allowances and Pension of Members of Parliament (Amendment) 
Act, <year>1993</year>, there shall be paid a pension of one thousand and four 
hundred rupees per mensem to every person who has served for a period 
of four years, whether continuous or not."]
<section><tid>1539187</tid>
<number>i</number>as a member of the Council of States, or

</section>

<section><tid>405991</tid>
<number>ii</number>as a member of the House of the People; or

</section>

<section><tid>1874600</tid>
<number>iii</number>partly as a member of the Council of States and 
partly as member of the House of the People; or

</section>

<section><tid>98596</tid>
<number>iv</number>as a member of the Provisional Parliament; or

</section>

<section><tid>1988792</tid>
<number>v</number>party as a member of the Provisional Parliament and-

<subsection><tid>376177</tid>
<number>a</number>partly as a member of the Council of States and 
partly as a member of the House of the People, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>657651</tid>
<number>b</number>partly as a member of the Council of States or 
partly as a member of the House of the People;
<footcitenum>9</footcitenum> Provided that where any person has served as aforesaid for a 
period exceeding five years, there shall be paid to him an additional 
pension of two hundred and fifty rupees per mensem for every year in 
excess of five years:

Provided further that where any person has served as a Member of 
the House of the People twice for its duration as provided in clause 
 (2) of article 83 of the Constitution, whether consecutively or not, 
and who is not entitled to any pension under the foregoing provisions 
of this sub- section, he shall, with effect from the commencement of 
the Salary, Allowances and Pension of Members of Parliament 
 (Amendment) Act, <year>1993</year>, be entitled to a pension of one thousand and 
four hundred rupees per mensem:

Provided also that every person, who has served for any period as 
a member of the Provisional Parliament and who is not entitled to any 
pension under the foregoing provisions of this sub- section, shall, 
with effect from the cornmencement of the Salary, Allowances and 
Pension of Members of Parliament (Amendment) Act, <year>1993</year>, be entitled to 
a pension of one thousand and four hundred rupees per mensem.]


<pagefootnote><pagenum>140c</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 55 of <year>1958</year> s. 7, for" medical"

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1975</year>, s. 2 for" and postal facilities" (w. e. f.  
  16- 8- <year>1975</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by Act 105 of <year>1976</year>, s. 7.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Ins. by Act 21 of <year>1981</year>, s. 2

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Subs. by s. 2 ibid. for" Provided that".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Subs. by Act 74 of <year>1985</year>, s. 5

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>7</number>Subs. omitted and added by s. 6 ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>8</number>Ins. by Act 60 of <year>1988</year>, s. 8 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1988</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>9</number>Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1993</year>, s. 4


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

Explanation <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> (1)].- For the purpose of[ this sub- section] 1 
" Provisional Parliament" shall include the body which functioned as 
the Constituent Assembly of the Dominion of India immediately before 
the commencement of the Constitution.

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Explanation 2.- Where in any General Election held for the 
purpose of constituting a new House of the people, poll could not be 
taken in any parliamentary constituency or any part thereof on the 
date originally fixed under clause (d) of section 30 of the 
Representation of the people Act, <year>1951</year> on account of snow- falls or 
other weather conditions of an extreme nature in such constituency or 
part thereof or on account of such such constituency or part thereof 
being inaccessible for any reason, the member elected to such House 
from such constituency shall be deemed, for the purpose of this 
sub- section to have served as a member of such House from the date of 
publication, under section 73 of the said Act, of the notification 
relating to such House.]


<subsubsection><tid>804789</tid>
<number>1A</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> With effect from the commencement of the Salary, Allowance 
and Pension of Members of Parliament. (Amendment) Act, <year>1988</year>, there 
shall be paid a pension of five hundred rupees per mensem to the 
spouse, if any, or dependent of any member who dies during his term of 
office as such member, for a period of five years from the date of his 
death.]

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>658911</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any person entitled to pension under sub- section 
 (1),-

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1539187</tid>
<number>i</number>is elected to the- office of the President or 
Vice- President or is appointed to the office of the 
Governor of any State or the Administrator of any Union 
territory; or

</section>

<section><tid>405991</tid>
<number>ii</number>becomes a member of the Council of States or the 
House of the People or any Legislative Assembly of a 
State or Union territory or any Legislative Council of a 
State or the Metropolitan Council of Delhi constituted 
under section 3 of the Delhi Administration Act, <year>1966</year>, 
 (19 of <year>1966</year>); or

</section>

<section><tid>1874600</tid>
<number>iii</number>is employed on a salary under the Central 
Government or any State Government, or any corporation 
owned or controlled by the Central Government or any 
State Government, or any local authority or becomes 
otherwise entitled to any remuneration from such 
Government, corporation or local authority.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>140D</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Renumbered and ins. by Act 74 of <year>1985</year>, s. 6

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by Act 60 of <year>1988</year>, s. 9 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1988</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

such person shall not be entitled to any pension under sub- section (1) 
for the period during which he continues to hold such office or as 
such member, or is so employed, or continues to be entitled to such 
remuneration:

Provided that where the salary payable to such person for holding 
such office or being such member or so employed, or where the remu- 
neration referred to in clause (iii) payable to such person, is, in 
either case, less than the pension payable to him under sub- section 
 (1), such person shall be entitled only to receive the balance as 
pension under that sub- section.


<subsection><tid>1406548</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> where any person entitled to pension under sub- section (1) 
is also entitled to any other pension, such person shall be entitled 
to receive the pension under subsection (1) in addition to such other 
pension.]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1754618</tid>
<number>4</number>In computing the number of years, for the purposes of sub- 
section (1), the period during which a person has served as a Minister 
as defined in the Salaries and Allowances of Ministers Act, <year>1952</year> (58  
  of <year>1952</year>) or <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> as an Officer of Parliament] as defined in the Salaries 
and Allowances of Officers of Parliament Act, <year>1953</year>, (20 of <year>1953</year>) 
 (other than the Chairman of the Council of States <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> or as a Leader of  
the Opposition as defined in the Salary and Allowances of Leaders of 
Opposition in Parliament Act, <year>1977</year>, (33 of <year>1977</year>), or has served in

<pagefootnote><pagenum>140E</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 35 of <year>1982</year>, s. 2

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 33 of <year>1977</year>, s. 11, for" an Officer of Parliament" 
 (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1977</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by s. 11, ibid., for," or both" (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1977</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1993</year>, s. 4


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

all or any two of such, capacities] by virtue of his membership in the 
House of the People or in the Council of States shall also be taken 
  into account.)]


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1248539</tid>
<number>8B</number>Advances for purchase of conveyances. There may be paid. to 
a member by way of a repayable advance such sum of money not exceeding 
 <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Fifty thousand rupees] as may be determined by rules made in this 
behalf under section 9 for the purchase of a conveyance"]
</article>



<article><tid>1593840</tid>
<number> 9</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>184740</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purpose of making rules under  
this section, there shall be constituted a Joint Committee of both 
Houses of Parliament consisting of five members from the Council of 
States nominated by the Chairman and ten members from the House of the 
People nominated by the Speaker.

</section>

<section><tid>953800</tid>
<number>2</number>The Joint Committee constituted under sub- section (1) shall 
elect its Chairman and shall have power to regulate its procedure.

</section>

<section><tid>1923369</tid>
<number>2A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> A member of the Joint Committee shall hold office as such 
member for one year from the date of his nomination and any casual 
vacancy in the Joint Committee may be filled by nomination by the 
Chairman of the Council of States or the Speaker of the House of the 
People, as the case may be.
Explanation.- In the case of a. member of a Joint Committee hold- 
ing office as such immediately before the commencement of the Salaries 
and Allowances of Members of Parliament (Amendment) Act, <year>1958</year>, (55 of  
  <year>1958</year>). the period of one year shall be computed from the date of such 
commencement.]


</section>

<section><tid>534634</tid>
<number>3</number>The Joint Committee constituted under sub- section (1) may 1 
[ after consultation with the Central Government] make 2rules to 
provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1805568</tid>
<number>a</number>the routes for the performance of any journey;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1315975</tid>
<number>b</number>the manner in which fractions of a day shall be dealt 
with for the purpose of determining the daily allowance 
admissible for that day;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1309942</tid>
<number>c</number>the travelling allowance admissible where a member is 
provided with free transit for the whole or any part of a 
journey <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> and the reduction of the daily allowance where a 
member is provided with free board or lodging at the expense 
of the Government or a local authority];

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>100214</tid>
<number>cc</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the rate at which road mileage shall be paid under 
sub- clause (ii) of clause (c) of sub- section (1) of section 
 4;]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>140F</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 55 of <year>1958</year>. s. 8.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>For the Housing and Telephone Facilities (Members of Parliament) 
Rules <year>1956</year>, see Gazette of India, <year>1956</year>, Extraordinary, Part II, Sec. 
3, pp. 867- 870.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by Act 61 of <year>1982</year> s. 4

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Ins. by Act 74 for <year>1985</year>, s. 7

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Subs. by Act 60 of <year>1988</year>, s. 10 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1988</year>)


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1609878</tid>
<number>d</number>the travelling allowance admissible where the place 
from which a member commences his journey or to which he 
returns is not his usual place of residence;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>253514</tid>
<number>dd</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the travelling allowance admissible in respect of 
journeys performed by any vessel where there is no regular 
steamer service;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>386222</tid>
<number>ddd</number>the travelling and daily allowances admissible 
for. journeys performed by a member in the course of a tour 
outside India undertaken in connection with his duties as 
such member;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>447797</tid>
<number>e</number>the form in which certificates, if any, shall be 
furnished by a member for the purpose of claiming any 
allowance under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>363519</tid>
<number>ee</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the form in which certificates, if any, shall be 
furnished by any person for the purpose of claiming any 
pension under this Act;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>161723</tid>
<number>f</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum> the constituency allowance and medical and other 
facilities mentioned in section 8 and the amount to be paid 
in cash in lieu of such facilities;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>208318</tid>
<number>ff</number>the amount which may be paid by way of repayable 
advance for the Purchase of conveyance; the rate of interest 
thereon and the mode of recovery of such amount and interest 
thereon; and.]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>295714</tid>
<number>g</number>generally for regulating the payment of <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> daily and 
travel allowances and pension] under this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1913504</tid>
<number>4</number>Any rules made under sub- section (3) shall not take effect 
until they are approved and confirmed by the Chairman of the Council 
of States and the Speaker of the House of the People and are published 
in the Official Gazette, and such publication of the rules shall be 
conclusive proof that they have been duly made.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1676490</tid>
<number>10</number>[ Validation of payment of certain travelling allowances.] 
Rep by the Repealing and Amending Act, <year>1960</year> (58 of <year>1960</year>), s. 2 and 
Sch, I.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>999999</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 55 of <year>1958</year>, s. 8

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by Act 105 of <year>1976</year>, s. 8 (w. e. f. 9- 9- <year>1976</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1975</year>, s. 3 for cl. (f)  (w. e. f. 16- 8- <year>1975</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>For the Housing and Telephone Facilities (Members of Parliament) 
Rules, <year>1956</year>, see Gazette of India. <year>1956</year> Extraordinary, Part II, Sec. 3 
pp. 867- 870.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Subs. by Act 105 of <year>1976</year>, s. 8, for" daily and travilling 
allowances" (w. e. f. 9- 9- <year>1976</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Subs. by Act 74 of <year>1985</year>, s. 8.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>