<act><title>

The
Industrial Disputes (Banking and Insurance Companies) Act, 1949</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>1</number>
Short title and extent.—
<section><number>1</number>
This Act may be called the Industrial Disputes (Banking and Insurance Companies)
Act, 1949.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[except
the State of Jammu and Kashmir].
   







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In
this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context, the
expressions “award”, “banking company”, “industrial dispute” and
“insurance company” have the meanings respectively assigned to them in
section 2 of the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 (14 of 1947) as amended by this
Act. 
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>3</number> Amendment of section 2, Act 14 of 1947.—[Rep. by the 
      Repealing and Amending Act, 1952 (48 of 1952), sec. 2 and Sch 1 (w.e.f. 
      2-8-1952).] 
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>4</number>
Prohibition of references by State Governments of certain industrial disputes
for adjudication, inquiry or settlement.—Notwithstanding
anything contained in any other law, it shall not be competent for a State
Government or any officer or authority subordinate to such Government to refer
an industrial dispute concerning any banking or insurance company or any matter
relating to such dispute, to any tribunal or other authority for adjudication,
inquiry or settlement.
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>5</number>
Abatement of proceedings relating to disputes pending before State tribunals and
reference of such disputes to tribunals constituted by the Central Government.—
<section><number>1</number>
Where under any law any industrial dispute concerning any banking or insurance
company or any matter relating to such dispute has, before the 30th day of
April, 1949, been referred by a State Government or any officer or authority
subordinate to such Government to any tribunal or other authority for
adjudication or settlement and any proceedings in respect of or arising out of
such reference were immediately before that date pending before any tribunal or
other authority, then on the aforesaid date such reference shall be deemed to
have been withdrawn and all such proceedings shall have abated. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Central Government shall, as soon as may be after the commencement of this
Act, by order in writing refer under section 10 of the said Act every industrial
dispute to which the provisions of sub-section (1) apply to an Industrial
Tribunal constituted under the said Act for adjudication. 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>6</number>
Powers of Central Government to refer disputes in respect of which awards or
decisions have been made for re-adjudication.—
<section><number>1</number>
Where any award or decision has been made in respect of any industrial dispute
concerning any banking or insurance company by any tribunal or other authority
constituted or appointed by a State Government, or any officer or authority
subordinate to such Government, then the Central Government may, notwithstanding
that the said award or decision is in force, by order in writing refer under
section 10 of the said Act the dispute or any of the matters in dispute to an
Industrial Tribunal constituted under the said Act for re-adjudication and stay
the implementation of the award or decision so made or of any part of such award
or decision until the Industrial Tribunal to which the dispute or any of the
matters in dispute is referred for re-adjudication has submitted its award or
for such further period as the Central Government may consider necessary. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
After the Industrial Tribunal to which the dispute or any of the matters in
dispute has been so referred for re-adjudication has submitted its award under
sub-section (1) of section 15 of the said Act, the Central Government may, by
order in writing, declare that the award or decision previously made in respect
of such dispute by the tribunal or other authority constituted or appointed by
the State Government or any officer or authority subordinate to such Government
or such part of that award or decision as may be specified in the order shall
cease to be in operation. 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>7</number>
Repeal of Ordinance 28 of 1949.—
<section><number>1</number>
The Industrial Disputes (Banking and Insurance Companies) Second Ordinance, 1949
(28 of 1949) is hereby repealed. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Notwithstanding such repeal, any thing done or any action taken in the exercise
of any power conferred by or under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have
been done or taken in the exercise of the powers conferred by or under this Act,
as if this Act were in force on the day on which such thing was done or action
taken. 
  
 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>
Subs. by Act 3 of 1951, sec. 3 and Sch., for “Except Part B States” (w.e.f.
1-4-1951).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>