<act><tid>402812</tid>
<title>THE COMPANIES (SECOND AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 11 OF <year>2003</year>
[ 13th January, <year>2003</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Companies Act, <year>1956</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>597200</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>412116</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Companies (Second Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1558854</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint:
Provided that different dates may be appointed for different 
provisions of this Act and any reference in any such provision to the 
commencement of this Act shall be construed as a reference to the 
commencement of that provision.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>920975</tid>
<number> 2</number> Amendment of section 2.- In section 2 of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1  
  of <year>1956</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the principal Act),-
<section><tid>1317866</tid>
<number>a</number>after clause (1A), the following clause shall be inserted, 
namely:-
' (1B)" Appellate Tribunal" means the National Company Law Appellate 
Tribunal constituted under sub- section (1) of section 10FR;';


</section>

<section><tid>1193040</tid>
<number>b</number>after clause (19A), the following clauses shall be inserted, 
namely:-
' (19AA)" industrial company" means a company which owns one or more 
industrial undertakings;


<subsection><tid>1999822</tid>
<number>19AB</number>" industrial undertaking" means any undertaking, pertaining to 
any industry carried on in one or more factories or units by any 
company, as defined in clause (aa) of section 3 of the Industries 
include a small- scale industrial undertaking as defined in clause (j) 
of that section;'; (Development and Regulation) Act, <year>1951</year> (65 of  
  <year>1951</year>) bu does not

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>595577</tid>
<number>c</number>after clause (29), the following clause shall be inserted, 
namely:-
' (29A)" net worth" means the sum total of the paid- up capital and free 
reserves after deducting the provisions or expenses as may be 
prescribed.

Explanation.- For the purposes of this clause," free reserves" means 
all reserves created out of the profits and share premium account but 
does not include reserves created out of revaluation of assets, write 
back of depreciation provisions and amalgamati n;';


</section>

<section><tid>777656</tid>
<number>d</number>after clause (31A), the following clause shall be inserted, 
namely:-
' (31AA)" operating agency" means any group of experts consisting of 
persons having special knowledge of business or industry in which the 
sick industrial company is engaged and includes public financial 
institution, State level institution, scheduled ban or any other 
person as may be specified as the operating agency by the Tribunal;';


</section>

<section><tid>1448966</tid>
<number>e</number>in clause (33), for the words" High Courts", the words" the 
Tribunal" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>313355</tid>
<number>f</number>after clause (46A), the following clauses shall be inserted, 
namely:-
' (46AA)" sick industrial company" means an industrial company which 
has-


<subsection><tid>1272768</tid>
<number>i</number>the accumulated losses in any financial year equal to fifty per 
cent. or more of its average net worth during four years immediately 
preceding such financial year; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>565399</tid>
<number>ii</number>failed to repay its debts within any three consecutive quarters 
on demand made in writing for its repayment by a creditor or creditors 
of such company;

<subsubsection><tid>1191986</tid>
<number>46AB</number>" State level institution" means any of the following 
institutions, namely:-
' (a) the State Financial Corporations established under section 3 or 
section 3A and institutions notified under section 46 of the State 
Financial Corporations Act, <year>1951</year> (63 of <year>1951</year>);


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1193040</tid>
<number>b</number>the State Industrial Development Corporations registered under 
this Act;';

</section>

<section><tid>1937761</tid>
<number>g</number>after clause (49), the following clause shall be inserted, 
namely:-
' (49A)" Tribunal" means the National Company Law Tribunal constituted 
under sub- section (1) of section 10FB;'.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1657486</tid>
<number>3</number>Amendment of section 10E.- In section 10E of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (1A), for the words" conferred on it", at both the places 
where they occur, the words, brackets and figures" conferred on it 
before the commencement of the Companies (Second Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>" 
shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1098686</tid>
<number>4</number>Amendment of section 10F.- In section 10F of the principal Act, after 
the words" any decision or order of the Company Law Board", the words, 
brackets and figures" made before the commencement of the Companies 
 (Second Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>" shall be inser ted.


</article>



<article><tid>1905325</tid>
<number> 5</number> Insertion of new section 10FA.- After section 10F of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 10FA. Dissolution of Company Law Board.- (1) On and from the 
commencement of the Companies (Second Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>, the Board 
of Company Law Administration constituted under sub- section (1) of 
section 10E shall stand dissolved.

<section><tid>966324</tid>
<number>2</number>On the dissolution of the Company Law Board, the persons appointed 
as Chairman, Vice- Chairman and members and officers and other 
employees of that Board and holding office as such immediately before 
such commencement shall vacate their respective off ces and no such 
Chairman, Vice- Chairman and member and officer and other employee 
shall be entitled to claim any compensation for the premature 
termination of the term of his office or of any contract of service:
Provided that every officer or other employee, who has been, 
immediately before the dissolution of the Company Law Board, appointed 
on deputation basis to that Board, shall, on such dissolution, stand 
reverted to his parent cadre, Ministry or Department, as the case may 
be:

Provided further that every officer and other employee of the Company 
Law Board employed on regular basis by that Board, shall become, on 
and from the dissolution of the Board, the officer and employee, 
respectively, of the Central Government with the sa e rights and 
privileges as to pension, gratuity and other like benefits as would 
have been admissible to him if the rights in relation to that Board 
had not been transferred to, and vested in, the Central Government and 
shall continue to do so unless and until his employment in the Central 
Government is duly terminated or until his remuneration, terms and 
conditions of employment are duly altered by that Government:

Provided also that notwithstanding anything contained in the 
Industrial Disputes Act, <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>), or in any other law for 
the time being in force, the transfer of the services of any officer 
or other employee employed in the Company Law Board, to he Central 
Government shall not entitle such officer or other employee to any 
compensation under this Act or under any other law for the time being 
in force and no such claim shall be entertained by any court, tribunal 
 (including the Tribunal under this ct) or other authority:

Provided also that where the Company Law Board has established a 
provident fund, superannuation fund, welfare fund or other fund for 
the benefit of the officers and other employees employed in that 
Board, the monies relatable to the officers and other em loyees whose 
services have been transferred by or under this Act to the Central 
Government shall, out of the monies standing, on the dissolution of 
the Company Law Board to the credit of such provident fund, 
superannuation fund, welfare fund or other fun, stand transferred to, 
and vest in, the Central Government and such monies which stand so 
transferred shall be dealt with by that Government in such manner as 
may be prescribed.


</section>

<section><tid>1200373</tid>
<number>3</number>All matters or proceedings or cases pending before the Company Law 
Board on or before the constitution of the Tribunal under section 
10FB, shall, on such constitution, stand transferred to the National 
Company Law Tribunal and the said Tribunal shall dispose of such cases 
in accordance with the provisions of this Act.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1405511</tid>
<number>6</number>Insertion of new Parts IB and IC.- After Part IA of the principal 
Act, the following Parts shall be inserted, namely:-
' PART IB

NATIONAL COMPANY LAW TRIBUNAL

</article>



<article><tid>1484851</tid>
<number>10FB</number>Constitution of National Company Law Tribunal.- The Central 
Government shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute 
a Tribunal to be known as the National Company Law Tribunal to 
exercise and discharge such powers and functions as are, or may be, 
conferred on it by or under this Act or any other law for the time 
being in force.
</article>



<article><tid>199510</tid>
<number>10FC</number>Composition of Tribunal.- The Tribunal shall consist of a 
President and such number of Judicial and Technical Members not 
exceeding sixty- two, as the Central Government deems fit, to be 
appointed by that Government, by notification in the Official G zette.
</article>



<article><tid>1407746</tid>
<number> 10FD</number> Qualifications for appointment of President and Members.-
<section><tid>1081181</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The Central Government shall appoint a person who has been, or is 
qualified to be, a Judge of a High Court as the President of the 
Tribunal.

</section>

<section><tid>244776</tid>
<number>2</number>A person shall not be qualified for appointment as Judicial Member 
unless he-

<subsection><tid>8458</tid>
<number>a</number>has, for at least fifteen years, held a judicial office in the 
territory of India; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>733131</tid>
<number>b</number>has, for at least ten years been an advocate of a High Court, or 
has partly held judicial office and has been partly in practice as an 
advocate for a total period of fifteen years; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1392035</tid>
<number>c</number>has held for at least fifteen years a Group' A' post or an 
equivalent post under the Central Government or a State Government 
[ including at least three years of service as a Member of the Indian 
Company Law Service (Legal Branch) in Senior Administra ive Grade in 
that service]; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>637520</tid>
<number>d</number>has held for at least fifteen years a Group' A' post or an 
equivalent post under the Central Government (including at least three  
years of service as a Member of the Indian Legal Service in Grade I of 
  that service).

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1559703</tid>
<number>3</number>A person shall not be qualified for appointment as Technical 
Member unless he-

<subsection><tid>1770314</tid>
<number>a</number>has held for at least fifteen years a Group' A' post or an 
equivalent post under the Central Government or a State Government 
[ including at least three years of service as a Member of the Indian 
Company Law Service (Accounts Branch) in Senior Adminis rative Grade 
in that service]; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>282821</tid>
<number>b</number>is, or has been, a Joint Secretary to the Government of India 
under the Central Staffing Scheme, or held any other post under the 
Central Government or a State Government carrying a scale of pay which 
is not less than that of a Joint Secretary to th Government of India, 
for at least five years and has adequate knowledge of, and experience 
in, dealing with problems relating to company law; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>846226</tid>
<number>c</number>is, or has been, for at least fifteen years in practice as a 
chartered accountant under the Chartered Accountants Act, <year>1949</year> (38 of  
  <year>1949</year>); or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>468690</tid>
<number>d</number>is, or has been, for at least fifteen years in practice as a cost 
accountant under the Costs and Works Accountants Act, <year>1959</year> (23 of  
  <year>1959</year>); or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>248596</tid>
<number>e</number>is, or has been, for at least fifteen years working experience as 
a Secretary in whole- time practice as defined in clause (45A) of 
section 2 of this Act and is a member of the Institute of the 
Companies Secretaries of India constituted under the Comp ny 
Secretaries Act, <year>1980</year> (56 of <year>1980</year>); or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>461621</tid>
<number>f</number>is a person of ability, integrity and standing having special 
knowledge of, and professional experience of not less than twenty 
years in, science, technology, economics, banking, industry, law, 
matters relating to industrial finance, industrial mana ement, 
industrial reconstruction, administration, investment, accountancy, 
marketing or any other matter, the special knowledge of, or 
professional experience in, which would be in the opinion of the 
Central Government useful to the Tribunal; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1794683</tid>
<number>g</number>is, or has been, a Presiding Officer of a Labour Court, Tribunal 
or National Tribunal constituted under the Industrial Disputes Act, 
 <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>); or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>383161</tid>
<number>h</number>is a person having special knowledge of, and experience of not 
less than fifteen years in, the matters relating to labour.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this Part,-


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>710283</tid>
<number>i</number>" Judicial Member" means a Member of the Tribunal appointed as such 
under sub- section (2) of section 10FD and includes the President of 
the Tribunal;

<subsubsection><tid>1151091</tid>
<number>ii</number>" Technical Member" means a Member of the Tribunal appointed as 
such under sub- section (3) of section 10FD.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1028747</tid>
<number> 10FE</number> Term of office of President and Members.- The President and 
every other Member of the Tribunal shall hold office as such for a 
term of three years from the date on which he enters upon his office, 
but shall be eligible for re- appointment:
Provided that no President or other Member shall hold office as such 
after he has attained,-

<section><tid>1124152</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of the President, the age of sixty- seven years;

</section>

<section><tid>1472956</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of any other Member, the age of sixty- five years:
Provided further that the President or other Member may retain his 
lien with his parent cadre or Ministry or Department, as the case may 
be, while holding office as such.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1978676</tid>
<number>10FF</number>Financial and administrative powers of Member 
Administration.- The Central Government shall designate any Judicial 
Member or Technical Member as Member Administration who shall exercise 
such financial and administrative powers as may be vested in h m under 
the rules which may be made by the Central Government:
Provided that the Member Administration shall have authority to 
delegate such of his financial and administrative powers as he may 
think fit to any other officer of the Tribunal subject to the 
condition that such officer shall, while exercising such dele ated 
powers continue to act under the direction, superintendence and 
control of the Member Administration.

</article>



<article><tid>1990474</tid>
<number>10FG</number>Salary, allowances and other terms and conditions of service of 
President and other Members.- The salary and allowances and other terms 
and conditions of service of the President and other Members of the 
Tribunal shall be such as may be prescribed:
Provided that neither the salary and allowances nor the other terms 
and conditions of service of the President and other Members shall be 
varied to their disadvantage after their appointment.

</article>



<article><tid>630200</tid>
<number> 10FH</number> Vacancy in Tribunal.-
<section><tid>1171064</tid>
<number>1</number>In the event of the occurrence of any  
vacancy in the office of the President of the Tribunal by reason of 
his death, resignation or otherwise, the senior- most Member shall act 
as the President of the Tribunal until the dat on which a new 
President, appointed in accordance with the provisions of this Act to 
fill such vacancy, enters upon his office.

</section>

<section><tid>446825</tid>
<number>2</number>When the President is unable to discharge his functions owing to 
absence, illness or any other cause, the senior- most Member or, as the 
case may be, such one of the Members of the Tribunal, as the Central 
Government, may, by notification, authorise i this behalf, shall 
discharge the functions of the President until the date on which the 
President resumes his duties.

</section>

<section><tid>1987071</tid>
<number>3</number>If, for reason other than temporary absence, any vacancy occurs in 
the office of the President or a Member, the Central Government shall 
appoint another person in accordance with the provisions of this Act 
to fill the vacancy and the proceedings may e continued before the 
Tribunal from the stage at which the vacancy is filled.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1859996</tid>
<number>10FI</number>Resignation of President and Member.- The President or a Member 
of the Tribunal may, by notice in writing under his hand addressed to 
the Central Government, resign his office:
Provided that the President or a Member shall, unless he is permitted 
by the Central Government to relinquish his office sooner, continue to 
hold office until the expiry of three months from the date of receipt 
of such notice or until a person duly appoi ted as his successor 
enters upon his office or until the expiry of the term of office, 
whichever is the earliest.

</article>



<article><tid>175330</tid>
<number> 10FJ</number> Removal and suspension of President or Member.-
<section><tid>752003</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may, in consultation with the Chief Justice of India, 
remove from office the President or any Member of the Tribunal, who-

<subsection><tid>416764</tid>
<number>a</number>has been adjudged an insolvent; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>97609</tid>
<number>b</number>has been convicted of an offence which, in the opinion of the 
Central Government, involves moral turpitude; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>49302</tid>
<number>c</number>has become physically or mentally incapable of acting as such 
President or Member of the Tribunal; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1039731</tid>
<number>d</number>has acquired such financial or other interest as is likely to 
affect prejudicially his functions as such President or Member of the 
Tribunal; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>851568</tid>
<number>e</number>has so abused his position as to render his continuance in office 
prejudicial to the public interest:
Provided that no such President or a Member shall be removed on any of 
the grounds specified in clauses (b) to (e) without giving him 
reasonable opportunity of being heard in respect of those charges.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1681943</tid>
<number>2</number>The President or a Member of the Tribunal shall not be removed 
from his office except by an order made by the Central Government on 
the ground of proved misbehaviour or incapacity after an inquiry made 
by a Judge of the Supreme Court in which such Pr sident or a Member 
had been informed of the charges against him and given a reasonable 
opportunity of being heard in respect of those charges.

</section>

<section><tid>594330</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government may suspend from office the President or 
Member of the Tribunal in respect of whom a reference has been made to 
the Judge of the Supreme Court under sub- section (2) until the Central 
Government has passed orders on receipt of he report of the Judge of 
the Supreme Court on such reference.

</section>

<section><tid>1844524</tid>
<number>4</number>The Central Government may, by rules, regulate the procedure for 
the investigation of misbehaviour or incapacity of the President or a 
Member referred to in sub- section (2).

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1288335</tid>
<number> 10FK</number> Officers and employees of Tribunal.-
<section><tid>1717311</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government  
shall provide the Tribunal with such officers and other employees as 
it may deem fit.

</section>

<section><tid>587265</tid>
<number>2</number>The officers and other employees of the Tribunal shall discharge 
their functions under the general superintendence of the Member 
Administration.

</section>

<section><tid>135405</tid>
<number>3</number>The salaries and allowances and other terms and conditions of 
service of the officers and other employees of the Tribunal shall be 
such as may be prescribed.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>273699</tid>
<number> 10FL</number> Benches of Tribunal.-
<section><tid>1729137</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of this  
section, the powers of the Tribunal may be exercised by Benches, 
constituted by the President of the Tribunal, out of which one shall 
be a Judicial Member and another shall be a Technical M mber referred 
to in clauses (a) to (f) of sub- section (3) of section 10FD:
Provided that it shall be competent for the Members authorised in this 
behalf to function as a Bench consisting of a single Member and 
exercise the jurisdiction, powers and authority of the Tribunal in 
respect of such class of cases or such matters perta ning to such 
class of cases, as the President of the Tribunal may, by general or 
special order, specify:

Provided further that if at any stage of the hearing of any such case 
or matter, it appears to the Member of the Tribunal that the case or 
matter is of such a nature that it ought to be heard by a Bench 
consisting of two Members, the case or matter may b transferred by the 
President of the Tribunal or, as the case may be, referred to him for 
transfer to such Bench as the President may deem fit.


</section>

<section><tid>104951</tid>
<number>2</number>The President of the Tribunal shall, for the disposal of any case 
relating to rehabilitation, restructuring or winding up of the 
companies, constitute one or more Special Benches consisting of three 
or more Members, each of whom shall necessarily be Judicial Member, a 
Technical Member appointed under any of the clauses (a) to (f) of 
sub- section (3) of section 10FD, and a Member appointed under clause 
 (g) or clause (h) of sub- section (3) of section 10FD:
Provided that in case a Special Bench passes an order in respect of a 
company to be wound up, the winding up proceedings of such company may 
be conducted by a Bench consisting of a single Member.


</section>

<section><tid>766585</tid>
<number>3</number>If the Members of a Bench differ in opinion on any point or 
points, it shall be decided according to the majority, if there is a 
majority, but if the Members are equally divided, they shall state the 
point or points on which they differ, and the case shall be referred 
by the President of the Tribunal for hearing on such point or points 
by one or more of the other Members of the Tribunal and such point or 
points shall be decided according to the opinion of the majority of 
Members of the Tribunal who h ve heard the case, including those who 
first heard it.

</section>

<section><tid>1989938</tid>
<number>4</number>There shall be constituted such number of Benches as may be 
notified by the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>684196</tid>
<number>5</number>In addition to the other Benches, there shall be a Principal Bench 
at New Delhi presided over by the President of the Tribunal.

</section>

<section><tid>1784359</tid>
<number>6</number>The Principal Bench of the Tribunal shall have powers of transfer 
of proceedings from any Bench to another Bench of the Tribunal in the 
event of inability of any Bench from hearing any such proceedings for 
any reason:
Provided that no transfer of any proceedings shall be made under this 
sub- section except after recording the reasons for so doing in 
writing.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>821246</tid>
<number> 10FM</number> Order of Tribunal.-
<section><tid>1075119</tid>
<number>1</number>The Tribunal may, after giving the  
parties to any proceeding before it, an opportunity of being heard, 
pass such orders thereon as it thinks fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1275015</tid>
<number>2</number>The Tribunal may, at any time within two years from the date of 
the order, with a view to rectifying any mistake apparent from the 
record, amend any order passed by it under sub- section (1), and shall 
make such amendment if the mistake is brought to ts notice by the 
parties.

</section>

<section><tid>1288004</tid>
<number>3</number>The Tribunal shall send a copy of every order passed under this 
section to all the parties concerned.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1842538</tid>
<number>10FN</number>Power to review.- The Tribunal shall have power to review its 
own orders.
</article>



<article><tid>1081295</tid>
<number>10FO</number>Delegation of powers.- The Tribunal may, by general or special 
order, delegate, subject to such conditions and limitations, if any, 
as may be specified in the order, to any Member or officer or other 
employee of the Tribunal or other person authoris d by the Tribunal to 
manage any industrial company or industrial undertaking or any 
operating agency, such powers and duties under this Act as it may deem 
necessary.
</article>



<article><tid>1759538</tid>
<number> 10FP</number> Power to seek assistance of Chief Metropolitan Magistrate and 
District Magistrate.-
<section><tid>1980447</tid>
<number>1</number>The Tribunal or any operating agency, on  
being directed by the Tribunal may, in order to take into custody or 
under its control all property, effects and actiona le claims to which 
a sick industrial company is or appears to be entitled, request, in 
writing, the Chief Metropolitan Magistrate or the District Magistrate 
within whose jurisdiction any property, books of account or any other 
document of such sick indus rial company, be situate or be found, to 
take possession thereof, and the Chief Metropolitan Magistrate or the 
District Magistrate, as the case may be, shall, on such request being 
made to him,-

<subsection><tid>956247</tid>
<number>a</number>take possession of such property, books of account or other 
documents; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1562606</tid>
<number>b</number>cause the same to be entrusted to the Tribunal or the operating 
agency.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1442678</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purpose of securing compliance with the provisions of 
sub- section (1), the Chief Metropolitan Magistrate or the District 
Magistrate may take or cause to be taken such steps and use or cause 
to be used such force as may, in his opinion, be nec ssary.

</section>

<section><tid>52744</tid>
<number>3</number>No act of the Chief Metropolitan Magistrate or the District 
Magistrate done in pursuance of this section shall be called in 
question in any court or before any authority on any ground 
whatsoever.
PART IC

APPELLATE TRIBUNAL


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1252446</tid>
<number> 10FQ</number> Appeal from order of Tribunal.-
<section><tid>48944</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person aggrieved by an  
order or decision of the Tribunal may prefer an appeal to the 
Appellate Tribunal.

</section>

<section><tid>533231</tid>
<number>2</number>No appeal shall lie to the Appellate Tribunal from an order or 
decision made by the Tribunal with the consent of parties.

</section>

<section><tid>247668</tid>
<number>3</number>Every appeal under sub- section (1) shall be filed within a period 
of forty- five days from the date on which a copy of the order or 
decision made by the Tribunal is received by the appellant and it 
shall be in such form and accompanied by such fee as ay be prescribed:
Provided that the Appellate Tribunal may entertain an appeal after the 
expiry of the said period of forty- five days from the date aforesaid 
if it is satisfied that the appellant was prevented by sufficient 
cause from not filing the appeal in time.


</section>

<section><tid>1613912</tid>
<number>4</number>On receipt of an appeal preferred under sub- section (1), the 
Appellate Tribunal shall, after giving parties to the appeal, an 
opportunity of being heard, pass such orders thereon as it thinks fit, 
confirming, modifying or setting aside the order appe led against.

</section>

<section><tid>1775557</tid>
<number>5</number>The Appellate Tribunal shall send a copy of every order made by it 
to the Tribunal and parties to the appeal.

</section>

<section><tid>1831426</tid>
<number>6</number>The appeal filed before the Appellate Tribunal under sub- section 
 (1) shall be dealt with by it as expeditiously as possible and 
endeavour shall be made by it to dispose of the appeal finally within 
six months from the date of the receipt of the appea.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>28374</tid>
<number> 10FR</number> Constitution of Appellate Tribunal.-
<section><tid>1375306</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government  
shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute with effect 
from such date as may be specified therein, an Appellate Tribunal to 
be called the" National Company Law Appellate Tribunal" consisting of 
a Chairperson and not more than two Members, to be appointed by that 
Government, for hearing appeals against the orders of the Tribunal 
under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>682517</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chairperson of the Appellate Tribunal shall be a person who 
has been a Judge of the Supreme Court or the Chief Justice of a High 
Court.

</section>

<section><tid>49059</tid>
<number>3</number>A Member of the Appellate Tribunal shall be a person of ability, 
integrity and standing having special knowledge of, and professional 
experience of not less than twenty- five years in, science, technology, 
economics, banking, industry, law, matters re ating to labour, 
industrial finance, industrial management, industrial reconstruction, 
administration, investment, accountancy, marketing or any other 
matter, the special knowledge of, or professional experience in which, 
would be in the opinion of the C ntral Government useful to the 
Appellate Tribunal.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1096150</tid>
<number> 10FS</number> Vacancy in Appellate Tribunal, etc.-
<section><tid>1269356</tid>
<number>1</number>In the event of the  
occurrence of any vacancy in the office of the Chairperson of the 
Appellate Tribunal by reason of his death, resignation or otherwise, 
the senior- most Member of the Appellate Tribunal shal act as the 
Chairperson of the Appellate Tribunal until the date on which a new 
Chairperson appointed in accordance with the provisions of this Act to 
fill such vacancy enters upon his office.

</section>

<section><tid>496087</tid>
<number>2</number>When the Chairperson of the Appellate Tribunal is unable to 
discharge his functions owing to absence, illness or any other cause, 
the senior- most Member or, as the case may be, such one of the Member 
of the Appellate Tribunal, as the Central Governme t may, by 
notification, authorise in this behalf, shall discharge the functions 
of the Chairperson until the date on which the Chairperson resumes his 
duties.

</section>

<section><tid>79366</tid>
<number>3</number>If, for reason other than temporary absence, any vacancy occurs in 
the office of the Chairperson or a Member, the Central Government 
shall appoint another person in accordance with the provisions of this 
Act to fill the vacancy and the proceedings ma be continued before the 
Appellate Tribunal from the stage at which the vacancy is filled.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>348768</tid>
<number> 10FT</number> Term of office of Chairperson and Members.- The Chairperson or a 
Member of the Appellate Tribunal shall hold office as such for a term 
of three years from the date on which he enters upon his office, but 
shall be eligible for re- appointment for anot er term of three years:
Provided that no Chairperson or other Member shall hold office as such 
after he has attained,-

<section><tid>1011412</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of the Chairperson, the age of seventy years;

</section>

<section><tid>361192</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of any other Member, the age of sixty- seven years.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>29870</tid>
<number>10FU</number>Resignation of Chairperson and Members.- The Chairperson or a 
Member of the Appellate Tribunal may, by notice in writing under his 
hand addressed to the Central Government, resign his office:
Provided that the Chairperson or a Member of the Appellate Tribunal 
shall, unless he is permitted by the Central Government to relinquish 
his office sooner, continue to hold office until the expiry of three 
months from the date of receipt of such notice r until a person duly 
appointed as his successor enters upon his office or until the expiry 
of his term of office, whichever is the earliest.

</article>



<article><tid>176770</tid>
<number> 10FV</number> Removal and suspension of Chairperson and Members of Appellate 
Tribunal.-
<section><tid>845540</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, in consultation with the  
Chief Justice of India, remove from office the Chairperson or any 
Member of the Appellate Tribunal, who-

<subsection><tid>350007</tid>
<number>a</number>has been adjudged an insolvent; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>208249</tid>
<number>b</number>has been convicted of an offence which, in the opinion of the 
Central Government, involves moral turpitude; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>767426</tid>
<number>c</number>has become physically or mentally incapable of acting as such 
Chairperson or Member of the Appellate Tribunal; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1647903</tid>
<number>d</number>has acquired such financial or other interest as is likely to 
affect prejudicially his functions as such Chairperson or Member of 
the Appellate Tribunal; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>186600</tid>
<number>e</number>has so abused his position as to render his continuance in office 
prejudicial to the public interest.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1886983</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chairperson or a Member of the Appellate Tribunal shall not be 
removed from his office except by an order made by the Central 
Government on the ground of proved misbehaviour or incapacity after an 
inquiry made by a Judge of the Supreme Court in w ich such Chairperson 
or Member had been informed of the charges against him and given a 
reasonable opportunity of being heard in respect of those charges.

</section>

<section><tid>906052</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government may suspend from office the Chairperson or 
a Member of the Appellate Tribunal in respect of whom a reference has 
been made to the Judge of the Supreme Court under sub- section (2) 
until the Central Government has passed orders n receipt of the report 
of the Judge of the Supreme Court on such reference.

</section>

<section><tid>417910</tid>
<number>4</number>The Central Government may, by rules, regulate the procedure for 
the investigation of misbehaviour or incapacity of the Chairperson or 
a Member referred to in sub- section (2).

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>722857</tid>
<number> 10FW</number> Salary, allow- ances and other terms and conditions of service 
of Chairperson and Members.-
<section><tid>200990</tid>
<number>1</number>The salary and allowances and other  
terms and conditions of service of the Chairperson and other Members 
of the Appellate Tribunal shall be such as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>907597</tid>
<number>2</number>The salary, allowances and other terms and conditions of service 
of the Chairperson and other Members of the Appellate Tribunal shall 
not be varied to their disadvantage after appointment.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1382660</tid>
<number> 10FX</number> Selection Committee.-
<section><tid>1539608</tid>
<number>1</number>The Chairperson and Members of the  
Appellate Tribunal and President and Members of the Tribunal shall be 
appointed by the Central Government on the recommendations of a 
Selection Committee consisting of-

<subsection><tid>595285</tid>
<number>a</number>Chief Justice of India or his nominee Chairperson;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>573308</tid>
<number>b</number>Secretary in the Ministry of Finance and Company Affairs Member;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1198643</tid>
<number>c</number>Secretary in the Ministry of Labour Member;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>555345</tid>
<number>d</number>Secretary in the Ministry of Law and Justice (Department of Legal  
  Affairs or Legislative Department) Member;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>758488</tid>
<number>e</number>Secretary in the Ministry of Finance and Company Affairs 
 (Department of Company Affairs) Member.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>33063</tid>
<number>2</number>The Joint Secretary in the Ministry or Department of the Central 
Government dealing with this Act shall be the Convenor of the 
Selection Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>418548</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government shall, within one month from the date of 
occurrence of any vacancy by reason of death, resignation or removal 
of the Chairperson and Members of the Appellate Tribunal and President 
and Members of the Tribunal and six months bef re the superannuation 
or end of tenure of the Chairperson and Members of the Appellate 
Tribunal and President and Members of the Tribunal, make a reference 
to the Selection Committee for filling up of the vacancy.

</section>

<section><tid>24659</tid>
<number>4</number>The Selection Committee shall recommend within one month a panel 
of three names for every vacancy referred to it.

</section>

<section><tid>1583712</tid>
<number>5</number>Before recommending any person for appointment as the Chairperson 
and Members of the Appellate Tribunal and President and Members of the 
Tribunal, the Selection Committee shall satisfy itself that such 
person does not have financial or other interest which is likely to 
affect prejudicially his functions as such Chairperson or Member of 
the Appellate Tribunal or President or Member of the Tribunal, as the 
case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1833882</tid>
<number>6</number>No appointment of the Chairperson and Members of the Appellate 
Tribunal and President and Members of the Tribunal shall be 
invalidated merely by reason of any vacancy or any defect in the 
constitution of the Selection Committee.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>883065</tid>
<number>10FY</number>Chairperson, etc., to be public servants.- The Chairperson, 
Members, officers and other employees of the Appellate Tribunal and 
the President, Members, officers and other employees of the Tribunal 
shall be deemed to be public servants within the mea ing of section 21 
of the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>).
</article>



<article><tid>1458818</tid>
<number>10FZ</number>Protection of action taken in good faith.- No suit, prosecution 
or other legal proceedings shall lie against the Appellate Tribunal or 
its Chairperson, Member, officer or other employee or against the 
Tribunal, its President, Member, officer or oth r employee or 
operating agency or liquidator or any other person authorised by the 
Appellate Tribunal or the Tribunal in the discharge of any function 
under this Act for any loss or damage caused or likely to be caused by 
any act which is in good faith d ne or intended to be done in 
pursuance of this Act.
</article>



<article><tid>594343</tid>
<number> 10FZA</number> Procedure and powers of Tribunal and Appellate Tribunal.-
<section><tid>1960534</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The Tribunal and the Appellate Tribunal shall not be bound by the 
procedure laid down in the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>), 
but shall be guided by the principles of natural j stice and, subject 
to the other provisions of this Act and of any rules made by the 
Central Government, the Tribunal and the Appellate Tribunal shall have 
power to regulate their own procedure.

</section>

<section><tid>719964</tid>
<number>2</number>The Tribunal and the Appellate Tribunal shall have, for the 
purposes of discharging its functions under this Act, the same powers 
as are vested in a civil court under the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> 
 (5 of <year>1908</year>) while trying a suit in respect of the following matters, 
namely:-

<subsection><tid>1532172</tid>
<number>a</number>summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person and examining 
him on oath;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>728879</tid>
<number>b</number>requiring the discovery and production of documents;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1673327</tid>
<number>c</number>receiving evidence on affidavits;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1884701</tid>
<number>d</number>subject to the provisions of sections 123 and 124 of the Indian 
Evidence Act, <year>1872</year> (1 of <year>1872</year>), requisitioning any public record or 
document or copy of such record or document from any office;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>314313</tid>
<number>e</number>issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses or documents;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>87978</tid>
<number>f</number>reviewing its decisions;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>174532</tid>
<number>g</number>dismissing a representation for default or deciding it ex parte;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1268831</tid>
<number>h</number>setting aside any order of dismissal of any representation for 
default or any order passed by it ex parte; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1446809</tid>
<number>i</number>any other matter which may be prescribed by the Central 
Government.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1469861</tid>
<number>3</number>Any order made by the Tribunal or the Appellate Tribunal may be 
enforced by that Tribunal in the same manner as if it were a decree 
made by a court in a suit pending therein, and it shall be lawful for 
the Tribunal or the Appellate Tribunal to send i case of its inability 
to execute such order, to the court within the local limits of whose 
jurisdiction,-

<subsection><tid>1349018</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of an order against a company, the registered office 
of the company is situate; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1152025</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of an order against any other person, the person 
concerned voluntarily resides or carries on business or personally 
works for gain.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>383812</tid>
<number>4</number>All proceedings before the Tribunal or the Appellate Tribunal 
shall be deemed to be judicial proceedings within the meaning of 
sections 193 and 228, and for the purposes of section 196, of the 
Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>) and the Tribunal and the A pellate 
Tribunal shall be deemed to be a civil court for the purposes of 
section 195 and Chapter XXVI of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> 
 (2 of <year>1974</year>).

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1884013</tid>
<number> 10G</number> Power to punish for contempt.- The Appellate Tribunal shall have 
the same jurisdiction, powers and authority in respect of contempt of 
itself as the High Court has and may exercise, for this purpose under 
the provisions of the Contempt of Courts Act, <year>1971</year> (70 of <year>1971</year>), which 
shall have the effect subject to modifications that-
<section><tid>562993</tid>
<number>a</number>the reference therein to a High Court shall be construed as 
including a reference to the Appellate Tribunal;

</section>

<section><tid>338259</tid>
<number>b</number>the reference to the Advocate- General in section 15 of the said 
Act shall be construed as a reference to such law officers as the 
Central Government may specify in this behalf.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>540815</tid>
<number> 10GA</number> Staff of Appellate Tribunal.-
<section><tid>1239876</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government shall  
provide the Appellate Tribunal with such officers and other employees 
as it may think fit.

</section>

<section><tid>175227</tid>
<number>2</number>The officers and other employees of the Appellate Tribunal shall 
discharge their functions under the general superintendence of the 
Chairperson of the Appellate Tribunal.

</section>

<section><tid>1522469</tid>
<number>3</number>The salaries and allowances and other conditions of service of the 
officers and other employees of the Appellate Tribunal shall be such 
as may be prescribed.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1418365</tid>
<number>10GB</number>not to have jurisdiction.- No civil court shall have 
jurisdiction to entertain any suit or proceeding in respect of any 
matter which the Tribunal or the Appellate Tribunal is empowered to 
determine by or under this Act or any other law for the time eing in 
force and no injunction shall be granted by any court or other 
authority in respect of any action taken or to be taken in pursuance 
of any power conferred by or under this Act or any other law for the 
time being in force.
</article>



<article><tid>840613</tid>
<number>10GC</number>Vacancy in Tribunal or Appellate Tribunal not to invalidate 
acts or proceedings.- No act or proceeding of the Tribunal or the 
Appellate Tribunal shall be questioned or shall be invalid merely on 
the ground of existence of any vacancy or defect in th establishment 
of the Tribunal or the Appellate Tribunal, as the case may be.
</article>



<article><tid>112914</tid>
<number> 10GD</number> Right to legal representation.- The applicant or the appellant 
may either appear in person or authorise one or more chartered 
accountants or company secretaries or cost accountants or legal 
practitioners or any officer to present his or its case bef re the 
Tribunal or the Appellate Tribunal, as the case may be.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,-

<section><tid>765118</tid>
<number>a</number>" chartered accountant" means a chartered accountant as defined in 
clause (b) of sub- section (1) of section 2 of the Chartered 
Accountants Act, <year>1949</year> (38 of <year>1949</year>) and who has obtained a certificate 
of practice under sub- section (1) of section 6 of that Act;

</section>

<section><tid>960774</tid>
<number>b</number>" company secretary" means a company secretary as defined in clause 
 (c) of sub- section (1) of section 2 of the Companies Secretaries Act, 
 <year>1980</year> (56 of <year>1980</year>) and who has obtained a certificate of practice under 
sub- section (1) of section 6 of that Act;

</section>

<section><tid>364284</tid>
<number>c</number>" cost accountant" means a cost accountant as defined in clause (b) 
of sub- section (1) of section 2 of the Cost and Works Accountants Act, 
 <year>1959</year> (23 of <year>1959</year>) and who has obtained a certificate of practice under 
sub- section (1) of section 6 of that Act;

</section>

<section><tid>757338</tid>
<number>d</number>" legal practitioner" means an advocate, a vakil or any attorney of 
any High Court, and includes a pleader in practice.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1916557</tid>
<number>10GE</number>Limitation.- The provisions of the Limitation Act, <year>1963</year> (36 of  
  <year>1963</year>) shall, as far as may be, apply to an appeal made to the 
Appellate Tribunal.
</article>



<article><tid>1033454</tid>
<number>10GF</number>Appeal to Supreme Court.- Any person aggrieved by any decision 
or order of the Appellate Tribunal may file an appeal to the Supreme 
Court within sixty days from the date of communication of the decision 
or order of the Appellate Tribunal to him on a y question of law 
arising out of such decision or order: Provided that the Supreme 
Court may, if it is satisfied that the appellant was prevented by 
sufficient cause from filing the appeal within the said period, allow 
it to be filed within a further period not exceeding sixty days.'.


</article>



<article><tid>990048</tid>
<number> 7</number> Substitution of new section for section 17.- For section 17 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
" 17. Special resolution and confirmation by Central Government 
required for alteration of memorandum.- (1) A company may, by special 
resolution, alter the provisions of its memorandum so as to change the 
place of its registered office from one State to a other, or with 
respect to the objects of the company so far as may be required to 
enable it-

<section><tid>29365</tid>
<number>a</number>to carry on its business more economically or more efficiently; 
or

</section>

<section><tid>197269</tid>
<number>b</number>to attain its main purpose by new or improved means; or

</section>

<section><tid>1642403</tid>
<number>c</number>to enlarge or change the local area of its operations; or

</section>

<section><tid>1755913</tid>
<number>d</number>to carry on some business which under the existing circumstances 
may conveniently or advantageously be combined with the business of 
the company; or

</section>

<section><tid>1700002</tid>
<number>e</number>to restrict or abandon any of the objects specified in the 
memorandum; or

</section>

<section><tid>517338</tid>
<number>f</number>to sell or dispose of the whole or any part of the undertaking, or 
of any of the undertakings, of the company; or

</section>

<section><tid>910334</tid>
<number>g</number>to amalgamate with any other company or body of persons.

<subsection><tid>198990</tid>
<number>2</number>The alteration of the provisions of memorandum relating to the 
change of the place of its registered office from one State to another 
shall not take effect unless it is confirmed by the Central Government 
on petition.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>444679</tid>
<number>3</number>Before confirming the alteration, the Central Government must be 
satisfied-

<subsubsection><tid>1316526</tid>
<number>a</number>that sufficient notice has been given to every holder of the 
debentures of the company, and to every other person or class of 
persons whose interests will, in the opinion of the Central 
Government, be affected by the alteration; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>15866</tid>
<number>b</number>that, with respect to every creditor who, in the opinion of the 
Central Government, is entitled to object to the alteration, and who 
signifies his objection in the manner directed by the Central 
Government, either his consent to the alteration has be n obtained or 
his debt or claim has been discharged or has been determined, or has 
been secured: Provided that the Central Government may, in the case 
of any person or class of persons, for special reasons, dispense with 
the notice required by clause (a).

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1840428</tid>
<number>4</number>The Central Government shall cause notice of the petition for 
confirmation of the alteration to be served on the Registrar who shall 
also be given a reasonable opportunity of appearing before the Central 
Government and state his objections and sugges ions, if any, with 
respect to the confirmation of the alteration.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1550530</tid>
<number>5</number>The Central Government may make an order confirming the alteration 
on such terms and conditions, if any, as it thinks fit, and may make 
such order as to costs as it thinks proper.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>614149</tid>
<number>6</number>The Central Government shall, in exercising its powers under this 
section, have regard to the rights and interests of the members of the 
company and of every class of them, as well as to the rights and 
interests of the creditors of the company and of every class of them.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1009327</tid>
<number>7</number>The Central Government may, if it thinks fit, adjourn the 
proceedings in order that an arrangement may be made to the 
satisfaction of the Central Government for the purchase of the 
e such orders as it thinks fit for facilitating, or carrying into 
effect, any such arrangement: interests of dissentient members; and 
may give such directions and ma Provided that no part of the capital 
of the company may be expended for any such purchase.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>583970</tid>
<number>8</number>Amendment of sections 18, 19, 43 and 49.- In sections 18, 19, 43 
and 49 of the principal Act, for the words" Company Law Board", 
wherever they occur, the words" Central Government" shall be 
substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1180522</tid>
<number>9</number>Amendment of sections 55A and 58A.- In sections 55A and 58A of the 
principal Act, for the words" Company Law Board", wherever they occur, 
the word" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>306420</tid>
<number> 10</number> Amendment of section 58AA.- In section 58AA of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>722654</tid>
<number>a</number>for the words" Company Law Board", wherever they occur, the word 
" Tribunal" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>551915</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (3), in the first proviso, for the words" the 
Board", the words" the Tribunal" shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>783240</tid>
<number>11</number>Amendment of section 75.- In section 75 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, in clause (c), in sub- clause (ii), for the word 
" Court", the word" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1956230</tid>
<number> 12</number> Amendment of section 79.- In section 79 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1954654</tid>
<number>a</number>for the words" Company Law Board", wherever they occur, the words 
" Central Government" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1163868</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (2), in clause (ii), in the proviso, for the words 
" unless that Board is of opinion", the words" unless the Central 
Government is of opinion" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>525772</tid>
<number>c</number>after sub- section (3), the following proviso shall be inserted, 
namely:-
' Provided that in the case of revival and rehabilitation of sick 
industrial companies under Chapter VIA, the provisions of this section 
shall have effect as if for the words" Central Government", the word 
" Tribunal" had been substituted.'.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1758752</tid>
<number> 13</number> Amendment of section 80A.- In section 80A of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>734511</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1), in the proviso, for the words" Company Law 
Board", the word" Tribunal" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1419487</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (2), for the words" any court", the words" any 
court or the Tribunal" shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>926895</tid>
<number>14</number>Amendment of sections 100 to 104 and 107.- In sections 100 to 104 
and 107 of the principal Act, for the word" Court", wherever it 
occurs, the word" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1688659</tid>
<number>15</number>Amendment of sections 111 and 111A.- In sections 111 and 111A of 
the principal Act, for the words" Company Law Board", wherever they 
occur, the word" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1910325</tid>
<number>16</number>Amendment of section 113.- In section 113 of the principal Act, 
for the words" Company Law Board", wherever they occur, the words 
" Central Government" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>521525</tid>
<number> 17</number> Amendment of section 117B.- In section 117B of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1318016</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (4), for the words" Company Law Board", wherever 
they occur, the words" Central Government" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1407807</tid>
<number>b</number>after sub- section (4), the following proviso shall be inserted, 
namely:-
' Provided that in the case of revival and rehabilitation of a sick 
industrial company under Part VIA, the provisions of this section 
shall have effect as if for the words" Central Government", the word 
" Tribunal" had been substituted.'.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>517127</tid>
<number>18</number>Amendment of section 117C.- In section 117C of the principal Act, 
for the words" Company Law Board", at both the places where they 
occur, the word" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1777837</tid>
<number>19</number>Amendment of section 118.- In section 118 of the principal Act, 
for the words" Company Law Board", the words" Central Government" 
shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1509037</tid>
<number> 20</number> Substitution of new section for section 141.- For section 141 of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 141. Rectification by Central Government of register of charges.- (1) 
The Central Government, on being satisfied-

<section><tid>1335685</tid>
<number>a</number>that the omission to file with the Registrar the particulars of 
any charge created by a company or of any charge subject to which any 
property has been acquired by the company or of any modification of 
any such charge or of any issue of debentures of a series, or that the 
omission to register any charge within the time required by this Part 
or that the omission to give intimation to the Registrar of the 
payment or satisfaction of a charge, within the time required by this 
Part, or that the omission o mis- statement of any particular with 
respect to any such charge, modification or issue of debentures of a 
series or with respect to any memorandum of satisfaction or other 
entry made in pursuance of section 138 or section 139, was accidental 
or due to i advertence or some other sufficient cause or is not of a 
nature to prejudice the position of creditors or shareholders of the 
company; or

</section>

<section><tid>353557</tid>
<number>b</number>that on other grounds, it is just and equitable to grant relief,
may on the application of the company or any person interested and on 
such terms and conditions as it may seem to the Central Government 
just and expedient, direct that the time for the filing of the 
particulars or for the registration of the charge or f r the giving of 
intimation of payment or satisfaction shall be extended or, as the 
case may require, that the omission or mis- statement shall be 
rectified.


<subsection><tid>210541</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may make such order as to the costs of an 
application under sub- section (1) as it thinks fit.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>665186</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the Central Government extends the time for the registration 
of a charge, the order shall not prejudice any rights acquired in 
respect of the property concerned before the charge is actually 
registered.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>22513</tid>
<number>21</number>Amendment of sections 144 and 163.- In sections 144 and 163 of the 
principal Act, for the words" Company Law Board", the words'' Central 
Government'' shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>283170</tid>
<number> 22</number> Substitution of new section for section 167.- For section 167 of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
' 167. Power of Central Government to call annual general meeting.- (1) 
If default is made in holding an annual general meeting in accordance 
with section 166, the Central Government may, notwithstanding anything 
contained in this Act or in the articles of the company, on the 
application of any member of the company, call, or direct the calling 
of, a general meeting of the company and give such ancillary or 
consequential directions as the Central Government thinks expedient in 
relation to the calling, hold ng and conducting of the meeting. 
Explanation.- The directions that may be given under this sub- section 
may include a direction that one member of the company present in 
person or by proxy shall be deemed to constitute a meeting.

<section><tid>1287995</tid>
<number>2</number>A general meeting held in pursuance of sub- section (1) shall, 
subject to any directions of the Central Government, be deemed to be 
an annual general meeting of the company:
Provided that in the case of revival and rehabilitation of sick 
industrial companies under Chapter VIA, the provisions of this section 
shall have effect as if for the words" Central Government", the word 
" Tribunal" had been substituted.'.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1144418</tid>
<number>23</number>Amendment of section 168.- In section 168 of the principal Act, 
for the words" Central Government", the words" Tribunal or the Central 
Government, as the case may be" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>172356</tid>
<number> 24</number> Substitution of new section for section 186.- For section 186 of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 186. Power of Tribunal to order meeting to be called.- (1) If for any 
reason it is impracticable to call a meeting of a company, other than 
an annual general meeting, in any manner in which meetings of the 
company may be called, or to hold or conduct the meeting of the 
company in the manner prescribed by this Act or the articles, the 
Tribunal may, either of its own motion or on the application of any 
director of the company, or of any member of the company who would be 
entitled to vote at the meeting,-

<section><tid>1696718</tid>
<number>a</number>order a meeting of the company to be called, held and conducted in 
such manner as the Tribunal thinks fit; and

</section>

<section><tid>23098</tid>
<number>b</number>give such ancillary or consequential directions as the Tribunal 
thinks expedient, including directions modifying or supplementing in 
relation to the calling, holding and conducting of the meeting, the 
operation of the provisions of this Act and of th company' s articles.
Explanation.- The directions that may be given under this sub- section 
may include a direction that one member of the company present in 
person or by proxy shall be deemed to constitute a meeting.


<subsection><tid>556178</tid>
<number>2</number>Any meeting called, held and conducted in accordance with any such 
order shall, for all purposes, be deemed to be a meeting of the 
company duly called, held and conducted.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>494120</tid>
<number>25</number>Amendment of section 188 and 196.- In sections 188 and 196 of the 
principal Act, for the words" Company Law Board", wherever they occur, 
the words" Central Government" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1483768</tid>
<number> 26</number> Amendment of section 203.- In section 203 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1283803</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1), for the word" Court", at both the places where 
it occurs, the words" Court or the Tribunal, as the case may be" shall 
be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>631769</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (2),-

<subsection><tid>1784536</tid>
<number>i</number>in clause (a), for the words" includes the Court by which he is 
convicted as well as any Court having jurisdiction to wind up", the 
words" includes the Court or the Tribunal by which he is convicted, as 
well as any Court or the Tribunal having jurisd ction to wind up" 
shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1849767</tid>
<number>ii</number>in clause (b), for the word" Court", the words" Court or the 
Tribunal" shall be substituted;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1275040</tid>
<number>c</number>in sub- sections (3) and (4), for the words" Court having 
jurisdiction to wind up a company", the words" Court or the Tribunal 
having jurisdiction to wind up a company" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1498501</tid>
<number>d</number>in sub- section (5), for the words" attention of the Court", the 
words" attention of the Court or the Tribunal, as the case may be," 
shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1580215</tid>
<number>27</number>Amendment of sections 219 and 225.- In sections 219 and 225 of the 
principal Act, for the words" Company Law Board", wherever they occur, 
the words" Central Government" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>597316</tid>
<number>28</number>Amendment of section 227.- In section 227 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (3), after clause (f), the following clause shall be 
inserted, namely:-
'' (g) whether the cess payable under section 441A has been paid and if 
not, the details of amount of cess not so paid.''.



</article>



<article><tid>1522576</tid>
<number>29</number>Amendment of sections 235 and 236.- In sections 235 and 236 of the 
principal Act, for the words'' Company Law Board'', wherever they 
occur, the word'' Tribunal'' shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>671641</tid>
<number>30</number>Amendment of section 237.- In section 237 of the principal Act, in 
clause (b), in the opening portion, for the words'' if in the opinion 
of the Company Law Board'', the words'' in its opinion or in the 
opinion of the Tribunal'' shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>964917</tid>
<number>31</number>Amendment of section 241.- In section 241 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (2), in clause (dd), for the words'' Company Law Board'', 
the word'' Tribunal'' shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>965716</tid>
<number>32</number>Amendment of section 243.- In section 243 of the principal Act, 
for the word" Court", at both the places where it occurs, the word 
" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>159355</tid>
<number>33</number>Amendment of sections 247, 250, 251 and 269.- In sections 247, 
250, 251and 269 of the principal Act, for the words" Company Law 
Board", wherever they occur, the word" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1983049</tid>
<number>34</number>Amendment of section 284.- In section 284 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (4), in the proviso, for the words'' Company Law Board'', 
the words'' Central Government'' shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>186539</tid>
<number>35</number>Amendment of sections 304 and 307.- In sections 304 and 307 of the 
principal Act, for the words'' Company Law Board'', the words 
'' Central Government or Tribunal, as the case may be'' shall be 
substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>95273</tid>
<number>36</number>Amendment of section 318.- In section 318 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (3), in clause (d), for the words" or subject to the 
supervision of the Court", the words" order of the Tribunal" shall be 
substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1981028</tid>
<number>37</number>Amendment of section 349.- In section 349 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (4), after clause (o), the following clause shall be 
inserted, namely:-'' (p) amount paid as cess under section 441A.''.


</article>



<article><tid>289614</tid>
<number>38</number>Amendment of Chapter IVA of Part VI.- In Part VI of the principal 
Act, in Chapter IVA, for the words" Company Law Board", wherever they 
occur, the word" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1823707</tid>
<number> 39</number> Amendment of section 391.- In section 391 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>50282</tid>
<number>a</number>for the word" Court", wherever it occurs, the word" Tribunal" 
shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>734541</tid>
<number>b</number>sub- section (7) shall be omitted;

</section>

<section><tid>204772</tid>
<number>c</number>below sub- section (7), the portion beginning with the words" The 
provisions of" and ending with the words" the application" shall be 
omitted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>996100</tid>
<number> 40</number> Substitution of new section for section 392.- For section 392 of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 392. Power of Tribunal to enforce compromise and arrangement.- (1) 
Where the Tribunal makes an order under section 391 sanctioning a 
compromise or an arrangement in respect of a company, it-

<section><tid>1682652</tid>
<number>a</number>shall have power to supervise the carrying out of the compromise 
or an arrangement; and

</section>

<section><tid>57339</tid>
<number>b</number>may, at the time of making such order or at any time thereafter, 
give such directions in regard to any matter or make such 
modifications in the compromise or arrangement as it may consider 
necessary for the proper working of the compromise or arrange ent.

<subsection><tid>1951046</tid>
<number>2</number>If the Tribunal aforesaid is satisfied that a compromise or an 
arrangement sanctioned under section 391 cannot be worked 
satisfactorily with or without modifications, it may, either on its 
own motion or on the application of any person interested in he 
affairs of the company, make an order winding up the company, and such 
an order shall be deemed to be an order made under section 433 of this 
Act.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1145278</tid>
<number>3</number>The provisions of this section shall, so far as may be, also apply 
to a company in respect of which an order has been made before the 
commencement of the Companies (Second Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year> sanctioning 
a compromise or an arrangement.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>849537</tid>
<number> 41</number> Amendment of section 394.- In section 394 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>656411</tid>
<number>a</number>for the word" Court", wherever it occurs, the word" Tribunal" 
shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1887939</tid>
<number>b</number>in the first proviso to sub- section (1), the words" the Company 
Law Board or" shall be omitted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1285915</tid>
<number>42</number>Amendment of sections 394A and 395.- In sections 394A and 395 of 
the principal Act, for the word" Court", wherever it occurs, the word 
" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1708218</tid>
<number>43</number>Amendment of section 396.- In section 396 of the principal Act, 
for the words" Company Law Board", at both the places where they 
occur, the word" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>496335</tid>
<number>44</number>Amendment of Chapter VI of Part VI.- In Part VI of the principal 
Act, in Chapter VI, for the words" Company Law Board", wherever they 
occur, the word" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1620993</tid>
<number> 45</number> Amendment of section 410.- In section 410 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>435150</tid>
<number>a</number>for the words" Company Law Board", the word" Tribunal" shall be 
substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>569231</tid>
<number>b</number>for the words" or Board", the words" or the Tribunal" shall be 
substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>778124</tid>
<number>46</number>Substitution of new section for section 424.- For section 424 of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
'' 424. Application of sections 421 to 423 to, receivers and managers 
appointed by Tribunal, and, managers appointed in pursuance of an 
instrument.- The provisions of sections 421 to 423 shall apply to the 
receiver of, or any person appointed to manage, th property of a 
company, appointed by the Tribunal or to any person appointed to 
manage, the property of a company under any powers contained in an 
instrument, in like manner as they apply to a receiver appointed under 
any powers contained in an instrumen.".



</article>



<article><tid>357427</tid>
<number>47</number>Insertion of new Part VIA.- After Part VI of the principal Act, 
the following Part shall be inserted, namely:-
' PART VIA

REVIVAL AND REHABILITATION OF SICK INDUSTRIAL COMPANIES

</article>



<article><tid>771348</tid>
<number> 424A</number> Reference to Tribunal.-
<section><tid>660843</tid>
<number>1</number>Where an industrial company, has  
become a sick industrial company, the Board of directors of such 
company shall make a reference to the Tribunal, and prepare a scheme 
of its revival and rehabilitation and submit the same o the Tribunal 
along with an application containing such particulars as may be 
prescribed, for determination of the measures which may be adopted 
with respect to such company: Provided that nothing contained in this 
sub- section shall apply to a Government company:
Provided further that a Government company may, with the prior 
approval of the Central Government or a State Government, as the case 
may be, make a reference to the Tribunal in accordance with the 
provisions of this sub- section and thereafter all the pro isions of 
this Act shall apply to such Government company.


</section>

<section><tid>1581317</tid>
<number>2</number>The application under sub- section (1) shall be accompanied by a 
certificate from an auditor from a panel of auditors prepared by the 
Tribunal indicating-

<subsection><tid>1873410</tid>
<number>a</number>the reasons of the net worth of such company being fifty per cent. 
or less than fifty per cent.; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1022376</tid>
<number>b</number>the default in repayment of its debt making such company a sick 
industrial company,
as the case may be.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>998879</tid>
<number>3</number>Without prejudice to the provisions of sub- section (1), the 
Central Government or the Reserve Bank of India or a State Government 
or a public financial institution or a State level institution or a 
scheduled bank may, if it has sufficient reasons to elieve that any 
industrial company has become, for the purposes of this Act, a sick 
industrial company, make a reference in respect of such company to the 
Tribunal for determination of the measures which may be adopted with 
respect to such company:
Provided that a reference shall not be made under this sub- section in 
respect of any industrial company by-


<subsection><tid>1673055</tid>
<number>a</number>the Government of any State unless all or any of the industrial 
undertakings belonging to such company are situated in such State;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>568140</tid>
<number>b</number>a public financial institution or a State level institution or a 
scheduled bank unless it has, by reason of any financial assistance or 
obligation rendered by it, or undertaken by it, with respect to such 
company, an interest in such company.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1952155</tid>
<number>4</number>A reference under sub- section (1) or sub- section (3) shall be made 
to the Tribunal within a period of one hundred and eighty days from 
the date on which the Board of directors of the company or the Central 
Government or the Reserve Bank of India or a State Government or a 
public financial institution or a State level institution or a 
scheduled bank, as the case may be, come to know, of the relevant 
facts giving rise to causes of such reference or within sixty days of 
final adoption of accounts, which ver is earlier.

</section>

<section><tid>186270</tid>
<number>5</number>The Tribunal may, on receipt of a reference under sub- section (1), 
pass an order as to whether a company in respect of which a reference 
has been made has become a sick industrial company and such order 
shall be final.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>617247</tid>
<number> 424B</number> Inquiry into working of sick industrial companies.-
<section><tid>28403</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Tribunal may make such inquiry as it may deem fit for determining 
whether any industrial company has become a sick industrial company-

<subsection><tid>846711</tid>
<number>a</number>upon receipt of a reference with respect to such company under 
section 424A; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>204402</tid>
<number>b</number>upon information received with respect to such company or upon its 
own knowledge as to the financial condition of the company.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1871110</tid>
<number>2</number>The Tribunal may, if it deems necessary or expedient so to do for 
the expeditious disposal of an inquiry under sub- section (1), require 
by order any operating agency to enquire into the scheme for revival 
and make a report with respect to such matter as may be specified in 
the order.

</section>

<section><tid>1487131</tid>
<number>3</number>The operating agency shall complete its inquiry as expeditiously 
as possible and submit its report to the Tribunal within twenty- one 
days from the date of such order:
Provided that the Tribunal may extend the said period to forty days 
for reasons to be recorded in writing for such extension.


</section>

<section><tid>1194925</tid>
<number>4</number>The Tribunal shall conclude its inquiry as expeditiously as 
possible and pass final orders in the proceedings within sixty days 
from the commencement of the inquiry:
Provided that the Tribunal may extend the said period to ninety days 
for reasons to be recorded in writing for such extension.

Explanation.- For the purposes of this sub- section, an inquiry shall be 
deemed to have commenced upon the receipt by the Tribunal of any 
reference or information or upon its own knowledge reduced to writing 
by the Tribunal.


</section>

<section><tid>38472</tid>
<number>5</number>Where the Tribunal deems it fit to make an inquiry or to cause an 
inquiry to be made into any industrial company under sub- section (1) 
or, as the case may be, under sub- section (2), it may appoint one or 
management and control of the affairs of any other company to be a 
special director or special directors on the board of such industrial 
company on such terms and conditions as may be prescribed for 
safeguarding its financial and other i more persons who possess 
knowledge, experience and expertise in terests or in the public 
interest.

</section>

<section><tid>1163079</tid>
<number>6</number>The special director or special directors appointed under 
sub- section (5) shall submit a report to the Tribunal within sixty 
days from the date of appointment of such director or directors, about 
the state of affairs of the company in respect of whic reference has 
been made under sub- section (1) and such special director or directors 
shall have all the powers of a director of a company under this Act, 
necessary for discharge of his or their duties.

</section>

<section><tid>1430244</tid>
<number>7</number>The Tribunal may issue such directions to a special director 
appointed under sub- section (5) as it may deem necessary or expedient 
for proper discharge of his duties.

</section>

<section><tid>919297</tid>
<number>8</number>The appointment of a special director referred to in sub- section 
 (5) shall be valid and effective notwithstanding anything to the 
contrary contained in any other provisions of this Act or in any other 
law for the time being in force or in the memoran um and articles of 
association or any other instrument relating to the industrial 
company, and any provision regarding share qualification, age limit, 
number of directorships, removal from office of directors and such 
like conditions contained in any suc law or instrument aforesaid, 
shall not apply to any special director or directors appointed by the 
Tribunal.

</section>

<section><tid>920019</tid>
<number>9</number>Any special director appointed under sub- section (5), shall-

<subsection><tid>162243</tid>
<number>a</number>hold office during the pleasure of the Tribunal and may be removed 
or substituted by any person by order of the Tribunal;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1136215</tid>
<number>b</number>not incur any obligation or liability by reason only of his being 
a director or for anything done or omitted to be done in good faith in 
the discharge of his duties as a director or anything in relation 
thereto;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>82803</tid>
<number>c</number>not be liable to retirement by rotation and shall not be taken 
into account for computing the number of directors liable to such 
retirement;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>218846</tid>
<number>d</number>not be liable to be prosecuted under any law for anything done or 
omitted to be done in good faith in the discharge of his duties in 
relation to the sick industrial company.

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1496822</tid>
<number> 424C</number> Powers of Tribunal to make suitable order on completion of 
inquiry.-
<section><tid>596122</tid>
<number>1</number>If after making an inquiry under section 424B, the  
Tribunal is satisfied that a company has become a sick industrial 
company, the Tribunal shall, after considering all the rele ant facts 
and circumstances of the case, decide, as soon as may be, by an order 
in writing, whether it is practicable for the company to make its net 
worth exceed the accumulated losses or make the repayment of its debts 
referred to in clause (b) of sub- ection (2) of section 424A within a 
reasonable time.

</section>

<section><tid>1459410</tid>
<number>2</number>If the Tribunal decides under sub- section (1) that it is 
practicable for a sick industrial company to make its net worth exceed 
the accumulated losses or pay its debt referred to in that sub- section 
within a reasonable time, the Tribunal shall, by or er in writing and 
subject to such restrictions or conditions as may be specified in the 
order, give such time to the company as it may deem fit to make its 
net worth exceed the accumulated losses or make repayment of the 
debts.

</section>

<section><tid>1812398</tid>
<number>3</number>If the Tribunal decides under sub- section (1) that it is not 
practicable for a sick industrial company to make its net worth exceed 
the accumulated losses or make the repayment of its debts referred to 
in clause (b) of sub- section (2) of section 424A within a reasonable 
time and that it is necessary or expedient in the public interest to 
adopt all or any of the measures specified in section 424D in relation 
to the said company it may, as soon as may be, by order in writing, 
direct any operating agen y specified in the order to prepare, having 
regard to such guidelines as may be specified in the order, a scheme 
providing for such measures in relation to such company.

</section>

<section><tid>331749</tid>
<number>4</number>The Tribunal may,-

<subsection><tid>461951</tid>
<number>a</number>if any of the restrictions or conditions specified in an order 
made under sub- section (2) are not complied with by the company 
concerned, or if the company fails to revive in pursuance of the said 
order, review such order on a reference in that behal from any agency 
referred to in sub- section (3) of section 424A or on its own motion 
and pass a fresh order in respect of such company under sub- section 
 (3);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1148009</tid>
<number>b</number>if the operating agency specified in an order made under 
sub- section (3) makes a submission in that behalf, review such order 
and modify the order in such manner as it may deem appropriate.

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1721535</tid>
<number> 424D</number> Preparation and sanction of schemes.-
<section><tid>160478</tid>
<number>1</number>Where an order is made  
under sub- section (3) of section 424C in relation to any sick 
industrial company, the operating agency specified in the order shall 
prepare as expeditiously as possible and ordinarily ithin a period of 
sixty days from the date of such order, having regard to the 
guidelines framed by the Reserve Bank of India in this behalf, a 
scheme with respect to such company providing for any one or more of 
the following measures, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1288748</tid>
<number>a</number>the financial reconstruction of such industrial company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1806863</tid>
<number>b</number>the proper management of such industrial company by change in, or 
take over of, the management of such industrial company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1182349</tid>
<number>c</number>the amalgamation of-

<subsubsection><tid>1474317</tid>
<number>i</number>such industrial company with any other company; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1489221</tid>
<number>ii</number>any other company with such industrial company (hereafter in this  
section, in the case of sub- clause (i), the other company, and in the 
case of sub- clause (ii), such industrial company, referred to as 
 " transferee- company");

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1056824</tid>
<number>d</number>the sale or lease of a part or whole of any industrial undertaking 
of such industrial company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>766743</tid>
<number>e</number>the rationalisation of managerial personnel, supervisory staff and 
workmen in accordance with law;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1342245</tid>
<number>f</number>such other preventive ameliorative and remedial measures as may be 
appropriate;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1563928</tid>
<number>g</number>repayment of debt;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>434659</tid>
<number>h</number>such incidental, consequential or supplemental measures as may be 
necessary or expedient in connection with or for the purposes of the 
measures specified in clauses (a) to (g):
Provided that the Tribunal may extend the said period of sixty days to 
ninety days for reasons to be recorded in writing for such extension.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1054818</tid>
<number>2</number>The scheme referred to in sub- section (1) may provide for any one 
or more of the following, namely:-

<subsection><tid>691384</tid>
<number>a</number>the constitution, name and registered office, the capital, assets, 
powers, rights, interests, authorities and privileges, duties and 
obligations of the sick industrial company or, as the case may be, of 
the transferee company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1683330</tid>
<number>b</number>the transfer to the transferee company of the business, 
properties, assets and liabilities of the sick industrial company on 
such terms and conditions as may be specified in the scheme;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1694081</tid>
<number>c</number>any change in the Board of directors, or the appointment of a new 
Board of directors, of the sick industrial company and the authority 
by whom, the manner in which and the other terms and conditions on 
which, such change or appointment shall be made nd in the case of 
appointment of a new Board of directors or of any director, the period 
for which such appointment shall be made;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1615725</tid>
<number>d</number>the alteration of the memorandum or articles of association of the 
sick industrial company or, as the case may be, of the transferee 
company for the purpose of altering the capital structure thereof, or 
for such other purposes as may be necessary to ive effect to the 
reconstruction or amalgamation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1029328</tid>
<number>e</number>the continuation by or against the sick industrial company or, as 
the case may be, the transferee company of any action or other legal 
proceeding pending against the sick industrial company immediately 
before the date of the order made under sub- sect on (3) of section 
424C;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>437185</tid>
<number>f</number>the reduction of the interest or rights which the shareholders 
have in the sick industrial company to such extent as the Tribunal 
considers necessary in the interests of the reconstruction, revival or 
rehabilitation or repayment of debts of such sick industrial company 
or for the maintenance of the business of such industrial company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>851355</tid>
<number>g</number>the allotment to the shareholders of the sick industrial company, 
of shares in such company or, as the case may be, in the transferee 
company and where any shareholder claims payment in cash and not 
allotment of shares, or where it is not possible to allot shares to 
any shareholder, the payment of cash to those shareholders in full 
satisfaction of their claims-

<subsubsection><tid>1729475</tid>
<number>i</number>in respect of their interest in shares in the sick industrial 
company before its reconstruction or amalgamation; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>948218</tid>
<number>ii</number>where such interest has been reduced under clause (f) in respect 
of their interest in shares as so reduced;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>541800</tid>
<number>h</number>any other terms and conditions for the reconstruction or 
amalgamation of the sick industrial company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1559713</tid>
<number>i</number>sale of the industrial undertaking of the sick industrial company 
free from all encumbrances and all liabilities of the company or other 
such encumbrances and liabilities as may be specified, to any person, 
including a co- operative society formed by he employees of such 
undertaking and fixing of reserve price for such sale;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>247475</tid>
<number>j</number>lease of the industrial undertaking of the sick industrial company 
to any person, including a co- operative society formed by the 
employees of such undertaking;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1375629</tid>
<number>k</number>method of sale of assets of the industrial undertaking of the sick 
industrial company such as by public auction or by inviting tenders or 
in any other manner as may be specified and for the manner of 
publicity therefor;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>506670</tid>
<number>l</number>issue of the shares in the sick industrial company at the face 
value or at the intrinsic value which may be at discount value or such 
other value as may be specified to any industrial company or any 
person including the executives and employees of su h sick industrial 
company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>11034</tid>
<number>m</number>such incidental, consequential and supplemental matters as may be 
necessary to secure that the reconstruction or amalgamation or other 
measures mentioned in the scheme are fully and effectively carried 
out.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1220813</tid>
<number>3</number> (a) The scheme prepared by the operating agency shall be examined 
by the Tribunal and a copy of the scheme with modification, if any, 
made by the Tribunal shall be sent, in draft, to the sick industrial 
company and the operating agency and in the case of amalgamation, also 
to any other company concerned, and the Tribunal may publish or cause 
to be published the draft scheme in brief in such daily newspapers as 
the Tribunal may consider necessary, for suggestions and objections, 
if any, within such per od as the Tribunal may specify.

<subsection><tid>712388</tid>
<number>b</number>The complete draft scheme shall be kept at the place where 
registered office of the company is situated or at such places as 
mentioned in the advertisement.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1337737</tid>
<number>c</number>The Tribunal may make such modifications, if any, in the draft 
scheme as it may consider necessary in the light of the suggestions 
and objections received from the sick industrial company and the 
operating agency and also from the transferee company nd any other 
company concerned in the amalgamation and from any shareholder or any 
creditors or employees of such companies:
Provided that where the scheme relates to amalgamation, the said 
scheme shall be laid before the company other than the sick industrial 
company in the general meeting for the approval of the scheme by its 
shareholders and no such scheme shall be proceede with unless it has 
been approved, with or without modification, by a special resolution 
passed by the shareholders of the transferee company.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>639143</tid>
<number>4</number>The scheme may thereafter be sanctioned, within sixty days by the 
Tribunal (hereinafter referred to as the sanctioned scheme) and shall 
come into force on such date as the Tribunal may specify in this 
behalf:
Provided that the Tribunal may extend the said period of sixty days to 
ninety days for reasons to be recorded in writing for such extension:

Provided further that different dates may be specified for different 
provisions of the scheme.


</section>

<section><tid>808875</tid>
<number>5</number>The Tribunal may, on the recommendations of the operating agency 
or otherwise, review any sanctioned scheme and make such modifications 
as it may deem fit or may by order in writing direct any operating 
agency specified in the order, having regard to such guidelines 
including the guidelines framed by the Reserve Bank of India in this 
behalf in order to prepare a fresh scheme providing for such measures 
as the operating agency may consider necessary.

</section>

<section><tid>595633</tid>
<number>6</number>When a fresh scheme is prepared under sub- section (5), the 
provisions of sub- sections (3) and (4) shall apply in relation thereto 
as they apply to in relation to a scheme prepared under sub- section 
 (1).

</section>

<section><tid>220326</tid>
<number>7</number>Where a sanctioned scheme provides for the transfer of any 
property or liability of the sick industrial company in favour of any 
other company or person or where such scheme provides for the transfer 
of any property or liability of any other company r person in favour 
of the sick industrial company, then, by virtue of, and to the extent 
provided in, the scheme, on and from the date of coming into operation 
of the sanctioned scheme or any provision thereof, the property shall 
be transferred to, and v st in, and the liability shall become the 
liability of, such other company or person or, as the case may be, the 
sick industrial company.

</section>

<section><tid>327572</tid>
<number>8</number>The sanction accorded by the Tribunal under sub- section (4) shall 
be conclusive evidence that all the requirements of this scheme 
relating to the reconstruction or amalgamation, or any other measure 
specified therein have been complied with and a cop of the sanctioned 
scheme certified in writing by an officer of the Tribunal to be a true 
copy thereof, shall, in all legal proceedings (whether in appeal or  
  otherwise), be admitted as evidence.

</section>

<section><tid>652727</tid>
<number>9</number>A copy of the sanctioned scheme referred to in sub- section (8) 
shall be filed with the Registrar within the prescribed time by the 
company in respect of which such scheme relates.

</section>

<section><tid>942430</tid>
<number>10</number>On and from the date of the coming into operation of the 
sanctioned scheme or any provision thereof, the scheme or such 
provision shall be binding on the sick industrial company and the 
transferee company or, as the case may be, the other company an also 
on the shareholders, creditors and guarantors and employees of the 
said companies.

</section>

<section><tid>1166040</tid>
<number>11</number>The creditors of a sick industrial company may also prepare a 
scheme for revival or rehabilitation of such sick industrial company 
and submit the same to the Tribunal for its sanction:
Provided that no scheme shall be submitted by the creditors to the 
Tribunal unless such scheme has been approved by at least three- fourth 
in value of creditors of the sick industrial company.


</section>

<section><tid>1705204</tid>
<number>12</number>All the provisions relating to the preparation of scheme by the 
operating agency and sanction of such scheme by the Tribunal shall, as 
far as may be, apply to the scheme referred to in sub- section (11).

</section>

<section><tid>371747</tid>
<number>13</number>The scheme referred to in sub- section (11) if sanctioned by the 
Tribunal shall be binding on all the creditors and on other concerned.

</section>

<section><tid>777602</tid>
<number>14</number>If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of 
the sanctioned scheme, the Tribunal may, on the recommendation of the 
operating agency or otherwise, by order, do anything, not inconsistent 
with such provisions, which appears to it to e necessary or expedient 
for the purpose of removing the difficulty.

</section>

<section><tid>1674894</tid>
<number>15</number>The Tribunal may, if it deems necessary or expedient so to do, by 
order in writing, direct any operating agency specified in the order 
to implement a sanctioned scheme with such terms and conditions and in 
relation to the sick industrial company as ay be specified in the 
order.

</section>

<section><tid>1541791</tid>
<number>16</number>Where the whole of the undertaking of the sick industrial company 
is sold under a sanctioned scheme, the Tribunal may distribute the 
sale proceeds to the parties entitled thereto in accordance with the 
provisions of section 529A and other provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>616665</tid>
<number>17</number>The Tribunal may monitor periodically the implementation of the 
sanctioned scheme.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1567866</tid>
<number> 424E</number> Rehabilitation by giving financial assistance.-
<section><tid>1845376</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the  
scheme relates to preventive, ameliorative, remedial and other 
measures with respect to the sick industrial company, the scheme may 
guarantees or reliefs or concessions or sacrifices from the Central 
Government, a State Government, any scheduled bank or other bank, a 
public financial institution or State level institution or any 
institution or other authority (any Government, b provide for  
financial assistance by way of loans, advan es or nk, institution or 
other authority required by a scheme to provide for such financial 
assistance being hereafter in this section referred to as the person 
  required by the scheme to provide financial assistance) to the sick 
industrial company.

</section>

<section><tid>1131239</tid>
<number>2</number>Every scheme referred to in sub- section (1) shall be circulated to 
every person required by the scheme to provide financial assistance 
for his consent within a period of sixty days from the date of such 
circulation or within such further period, not xceeding sixty days, as 
may be allowed by the Tribunal, and if no consent is received within 
such period or further period, it shall be deemed that consent has 
been given.

</section>

<section><tid>1891787</tid>
<number>3</number>Where in respect of any scheme the consent referred to in 
sub- section (2) is given by every person required by the scheme to 
provide financial assistance, the Tribunal may, as soon as may be, 
sanction the scheme and on and from the date of such sanct on the 
scheme shall be binding on all concerned.

</section>

<section><tid>1717761</tid>
<number>4</number>On the sanction of the scheme under sub- section (3), the financial 
institutions and the banks required to provide financial assistance, 
shall designate by mutual agreement a financial institution and a bank 
from amongst themselves which shall be resp nsible to disburse 
financial assistance by way of loans or advances or guarantees or 
reliefs or concessions or sacrifices agreed to be provided or granted 
under the scheme on behalf of all financial institutions and banks 
concerned.

</section>

<section><tid>1150287</tid>
<number>5</number>The financial institution and the bank designated under 
sub- section (4) shall forthwith proceed to release the financial 
assistance to the sick industrial company in fulfilment of the 
requirement in this regard.

</section>

<section><tid>1657342</tid>
<number>6</number>Where in respect of any scheme consent under sub- section (2) is 
not given by any person required by the scheme to provide financial 
assistance, the Tribunal may adopt such other measures, including the 
winding up of the sick industrial company, as it may deem fit.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>799535</tid>
<number> 424F</number> Arrangement for continuing operations, etc., during 
inquiry.-
<section><tid>1464758</tid>
<number>1</number>At any time before completion of the inquiry under  
section 424B, the sick industrial company or the Central Government or 
the Reserve Bank of India or a State Government or a public f nancial 
institution or a State level institution or a scheduled bank or any 
other institution, bank or authority providing or intending to provide 
any financial assistance by way of loans or advances or guarantees or 
reliefs, or concessions to such indus rial company may make an 
application to the Tribunal-

<subsection><tid>1906326</tid>
<number>a</number>agreeing to an arrangement for continuing the operations of the 
sick industrial company; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>318479</tid>
<number>b</number>suggesting a scheme for the financial reconstruction of the sick 
industrial company.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1016904</tid>
<number>2</number>The Tribunal may, within sixty days of the receipt of the 
application under sub- section (1), pass such orders thereon as it may 
deem fit.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1865962</tid>
<number> 424G</number> Winding up of sick industrial company.-
<section><tid>671231</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the Tribunal,  
after making inquiry under section 424B and after consideration of all 
the relevant facts and circumstances and after giving an opportunity 
sick industrial company is not likely to make its net worth exceed the 
accumulated losses within a reasonable time while meeting all its 
financial obligations and that the company as a result thereof is not 
likely to become viable i of being heard to all concerned parties, is 
o the opinion that the future and that it is just and equitable that 
the company should be wound up, it may record its findings and order 
winding up of the company.

</section>

<section><tid>667204</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purpose of winding up of the sick industrial company, the 
Tribunal may appoint any officer of the operating agency, if the 
operating agency gives its consent, as the liquidator of such 
industrial company and the officer so appointed shall for the purpose 
of the winding up of such sick industrial company, be deemed to be, 
and have all the powers of, the official liquidator under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>240862</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (2), the 
Tribunal may cause to be sold the assets of the sick industrial 
company in such manner as it may deem fit and pass orders for 
distribution in accordance with the provisions of section 529A, a d 
other provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>545345</tid>
<number>4</number>Without prejudice to the other provisions contained in this Act, 
the winding up of a company shall, as far as may be, concluded within 
one year from the date of the order made under sub- section (1).

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>77842</tid>
<number> 424H</number> Operating agency to prepare complete inventory, etc.- Where for 
the proper discharge of the functions of the Tribunal under this Part, 
the circumstances so require, the Tribunal may, through any operating 
agency, cause to be prepared-
<section><tid>1789822</tid>
<number>a</number>with respect to a company a complete inventory of-

<subsection><tid>804421</tid>
<number>i</number>all assets and liabilities of whatever nature;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1823771</tid>
<number>ii</number>all books of account, registers, maps, plans, records, documents 
of title or ownership of property and all other documents of whatever 
nature relating thereto;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1209855</tid>
<number>b</number>a list of shareholders and a list of creditors showing separately 
in the list of creditors, the secured creditors and unsecured 
creditors;

</section>

<section><tid>1499031</tid>
<number>c</number>a valuation report in respect of the shares and assets in order to 
arrive at the reserve price for the sale of a part or whole of the 
industrial undertaking of the company or for fixation of the lease 
rent or share exchange ratio;

</section>

<section><tid>1614952</tid>
<number>d</number>an estimate of reserve price, lease rent or share exchange ratio;

</section>

<section><tid>1643563</tid>
<number>e</number>proforma accounts, where no up- to- date audited accounts are 
available.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>458507</tid>
<number>424I</number>Direction not to dispose of assets.- The Tribunal may, if it is 
of the opinion, that any direction is necessary in the interest of the 
sick industrial company or creditors or shareholders or in the public 
interest, by order, direct such company not o dispose of, except with 
the prior approval of the Tribunal, any of its assets during the 
period of inquiry under section 424B or during the period of 
preparation or consideration of the scheme under section 424C.
</article>



<article><tid>398918</tid>
<number>424J</number>Power of Tribunal to call for periodic information.- On receipt 
of reference under section 424A, the Tribunal may call for any 
periodic information from the company as to the steps taken by the 
company to make its net worth exceed the accumulated lo ses or to make 
repayment of its debts referred to in that section, as the case may 
be, and the company shall furnish such information.
</article>



<article><tid>1068398</tid>
<number> 424K</number> Misfeasance proceedings.-
<section><tid>768038</tid>
<number>1</number>If, in the course of scrutiny or  
implementation of any scheme or proposal, it appears to the Tribunal 
that any person who has taken part in the promotion, formation or 
management of the sick industrial company or its un ertaking, 
including any past or present director, manager or officer or employee 
of the sick industrial company-

<subsection><tid>1829812</tid>
<number>a</number>has misapplied or retained, or become liable or accountable for, 
any money or property of the sick industrial company; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>577943</tid>
<number>b</number>has been guilty of any misfeasance, malfeasance or non- feasance of 
breach of trust in relation to the sick industrial company, the 
Tribunal may, by order, direct him to repay or restore the money or 
property or any part thereof, with or without interest, as it thinks 
just, or to contribute such sum to the assets of the sick industrial 
company or the other person, entitled theret by way of compensation in 
respect of the misapplication, retainer, misfeasance or breach of 
trust as the Tribunal thinks just, and also report the matter to the 
Central Government for any other action which that Government may deem 
fit.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>711670</tid>
<number>2</number>If the Tribunal is satisfied on the basis of the information and 
evidence in its possession with respect to any person who is or was a 
director or an officer or other employee of the sick industrial 
company, that such person by himself or along with thers had diverted 
the funds or other property of such company for any purpose other than 
a bona fide purpose of the company or had managed the affairs of the 
company in a manner highly detrimental to the interests of the 
company, the Tribunal shall by o der, direct the public financial 
institutions, scheduled banks and State level institutions not to 
provide, during a period of ten years from the date of the order, any 
financial assistance to such person or any firm of which such person 
is a partner or ny company or other body corporate of which such 
person is a director (by whatever name called).

</section>

<section><tid>333469</tid>
<number>3</number>No order shall be made by the Tribunal under this section against 
any person unless such person has been given an opportunity for making 
his submissions.

</section>

<section><tid>1428495</tid>
<number>4</number>This section shall apply notwithstanding that the matter is one 
for which the person may be criminally liable.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>916926</tid>
<number> 424L</number> Penalty for certain offences.-
<section><tid>1978821</tid>
<number>1</number>Whoever violates the  
provisions of this Part or any scheme, or any order, of the Tribunal 
or the Appellate Tribunal or makes a false statement or gives false 
evidence to the Tribunal or the Appellate Tribunal, and ttempts to 
tamper the records of reference or appeal filed under this Act, he 
shall be punishable with simple imprisonment for a term which may 
extend to three years or shall be liable to fine not exceeding ten 
lakh rupees.

</section>

<section><tid>1262975</tid>
<number>2</number>No court shall take cognizance of any offence under sub- section 
 (1) except on a complaint in writing of an officer of the Tribunal or 
the Appellate Tribunal or any officer of the Central Government 
authorised by it or any officer of an operating agen y as may be 
authorised in this behalf by the Tribunal or the Appellate Tribunal, 
as the case may be.'.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>407021</tid>
<number> 48</number> Amendment of section 425.- In section 425 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1,-
<section><tid>168402</tid>
<number>i</number>in clause (a), for the word" Court", the word" Tribunal" shall be 
substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>395612</tid>
<number>ii</number>in clause (b), the word" or" occurring at the end shall be 
omitted;

</section>

<section><tid>486907</tid>
<number>iii</number>clause (c) shall be omitted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1494913</tid>
<number>49</number>Amendment of sections 426 and 427.- In sections 426 and 427 of the 
principal Act, for the word" Court", the word" Tribunal" shall be 
substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1424760</tid>
<number>50</number>Amendment of heading and sub- heading before section 433.- In the 
heading and sub- heading before section 433 of the principal Act, for 
the word" Court", the word" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1217453</tid>
<number> 51</number> Substitution of new section for section 433.- For section 433 of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 433. Circumstances in which company may be wound up by Tribunal.- A 
company may be wound up by the Tribunal,-

<section><tid>1133947</tid>
<number>a</number>if the company has, by special resolution, resolved that the 
company be wound up by the Tribunal;

</section>

<section><tid>638258</tid>
<number>b</number>if default is made in delivering the statutory report to the 
Registrar or in holding the statutory meeting;

</section>

<section><tid>901529</tid>
<number>c</number>if the company does not commence its business within a year from 
its incorporation, or suspends its business for a whole year;

</section>

<section><tid>1857527</tid>
<number>d</number>if the number of members is reduced, in the case of a public 
company, below seven, and in the case of a private company, below two;

</section>

<section><tid>1145123</tid>
<number>e</number>if the company is unable to pay its debts;

</section>

<section><tid>1876824</tid>
<number>f</number>if the Tribunal is of the opinion that it is just and equitable 
that the company should be wound up;

</section>

<section><tid>1676973</tid>
<number>g</number>if the company has made a default in filing with the Registrar its 
balance sheet and profit and loss account or annual return for any 
five consecutive financial years;

</section>

<section><tid>131793</tid>
<number>h</number>if the company has acted against the interests of the sovereignty 
and integrity of India, the security of the State, friendly relations 
with foreign States, public order, decency or morality;

</section>

<section><tid>1578827</tid>
<number>i</number>if the Tribunal is of the opinion that the company should be wound 
up under the circumstances specified in section 424G:
Provided that the Tribunal shall make an order for winding up of a 
company under clause (h) on application made by the Central Government 
or a State Government.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1747014</tid>
<number> 52</number> Amendment of section 434.- In section 434 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1,-
<section><tid>638605</tid>
<number>i</number>in clause (a), for the words" five hundred rupees", the words" one 
lakh rupees" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1713859</tid>
<number>ii</number>in clause (b), for the words" any Court", the words" any Court or 
Tribunal" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1749260</tid>
<number>iii</number>in clause (c), for the word" Court", at both the places where it 
occurs, the word" Tribunal" shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>718439</tid>
<number>53</number>Omission of heading before section 435 and sections 435 to 
438.- Heading occurring before section 435 and sections 435 to 438 of 
the principal Act shall be omitted.


</article>



<article><tid>1137986</tid>
<number> 54</number> Amendment of section 439.- In section 439 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1944339</tid>
<number>i</number>for the word" Court", wherever it occurs, the word" Tribunal" 
shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>432829</tid>
<number>ii</number>in sub- section (1), after clause (f), the following clause shall 
be inserted, namely:-
" (g) in a case falling under clause (h) of section 433, by the Central 
Government or a State Government;";


</section>

<section><tid>1100048</tid>
<number>iii</number>in sub- section (5), for the word, brackets and letter" and (f)", 
the brackets, letters and word" (f) and (g)" shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1303232</tid>
<number> 55</number> Insertion of new section 439A.- After section 439 of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 439A. Statement of affairs to be filed on winding up of a 
company.- (1) Every company shall file with the Tribunal a statement of 
its affairs along with the petition for winding up.

<section><tid>415312</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a company opposes a petition for its winding up, it shall 
file with the Tribunal a statement of its affairs.

</section>

<section><tid>979318</tid>
<number>3</number>The statement of affairs referred to in sub- section (1) or 
sub- section (2) shall be accompanied by-

<subsection><tid>929586</tid>
<number>a</number>the last known addresses of all directors and company secretary of 
such company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1772298</tid>
<number>b</number>the details of location of assets of the company and their value;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1013210</tid>
<number>c</number>the details of all debtors and creditors with their complete 
addresses;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>151651</tid>
<number>d</number>the details of workmen and other employees and any amount 
outstanding to them;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1142054</tid>
<number>e</number>such other details as the Tribunal may direct.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>991647</tid>
<number> 56</number> Substitution of new sections for sections 440 and 441.- For 
sections 440 and 441 of the principal Act, the following sections 
shall be substituted, namely:-
" 440. Right to present winding up petition where company is being 
wound up voluntarily.- (1) Where a company is being wound up 
voluntarily, a petition for its winding up by the Tribunal may be 
presented by-

<section><tid>1477174</tid>
<number>a</number>any person authorised to do so under section 439; or

</section>

<section><tid>522123</tid>
<number>b</number>the Official Liquidator.

<subsection><tid>1766879</tid>
<number>2</number>The Tribunal shall not make a winding up order on a petition 
presented to it under sub- section (1), unless it is satisfied that the 
voluntary winding up cannot be continued with due regard to the 
interests of the creditors or contributories or both.

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>406251</tid>
<number> 441</number> Commencement of winding up by Tribunal.-
<section><tid>1916741</tid>
<number>1</number>Where, before the  
presentation of a petition for the winding up of a company by the 
Tribunal, a resolution has been passed by the company for voluntary 
winding up, the winding up of the company shall be de med to have 
commenced at the time of the passing of the resolution, and unless the 
Tribunal, on proof of fraud or mistake, thinks fit to direct 
otherwise, all proceedings taken in the voluntary winding up shall be 
deemed to have been validly taken.

</section>

<section><tid>89997</tid>
<number>2</number>In any other case, the winding up of a company by the Tribunal 
shall be deemed to commence at the time of the presentation of the 
petition for the winding up.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>216735</tid>
<number>57</number>Insertion of new sections 441A, 441B, 441C, 441D, 441E, 441F and 
441G.- After section 441 of the principal Act, the following shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" Levy by way of cess and formation of Rehabilitation and Revival Fund

</article>



<article><tid>113672</tid>
<number> 441A</number> Levy and collection of cess on turnover or gross receipts of 
companies.-
<section><tid>904537</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be levied and collected, for the purposes  
of rehabilitation or revival or protection of assets of the sick 
industrial company, a levy by way of cess at such rat not less than 
0. 005 per cent. and not more than 0. 1 per cent. on the value of 
annual turnover of every company or its annual gross receipt, 
whichever is more as the Central Government may, from time to time, 
specify by notification in the Official Gazet e.

</section>

<section><tid>1751440</tid>
<number>2</number>Every company shall pay to the Central Government the cess 
referred to in sub- section (1) within three months from the close of 
every financial year.

</section>

<section><tid>1723442</tid>
<number>3</number>Every company shall furnish, in such form as may be prescribed, to 
the Central Government and the Tribunal the details of its turnover 
and gross receipts with payment of cess under sub- section (1).

</section>

<section><tid>773022</tid>
<number>4</number>The Central Government may, by rules made in this behalf, specify 
the manner in which the cess shall be paid under sub- section (2).

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1663690</tid>
<number>441B</number>Crediting proceeds of cess to Consolidated Fund of India.- The 
proceeds of the cess levied and collected under section 441A shall 
first be credited to the Consolidated Fund of India and the Central 
Government may, if Parliament by appropriation made by law in this 
behalf so provides, pay to the Tribunal, from time to time, out of 
such proceeds (after deducting the cost of collection), such sums of 
money as it may think fit for being utilised for the purposes of the 
Fund.
</article>



<article><tid>7228</tid>
<number> 441C</number> Rehabilitation and revival Fund.-
<section><tid>1161800</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be formed for  
the purposes of rehabilitation or revival or protection of assets of a 
sick industrial company, a Fund to be called the Rehabilitation and 
Revival Fund.

</section>

<section><tid>408873</tid>
<number>2</number>There shall be credited to the Fund-

<subsection><tid>720784</tid>
<number>a</number>all amounts paid under section 441B;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1627651</tid>
<number>b</number>any amount given as grants by the Central Government for the 
purposes of this Fund;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1291749</tid>
<number>c</number>any amount given to the Fund from any other source;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1256453</tid>
<number>d</number>any income from investment of the amount in the Fund;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>786755</tid>
<number>e</number>amount refunded by the company under section 441G.

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>47910</tid>
<number> 441D</number> Application of Fund.- The Fund shall be applied by the Tribunal 
for the purpose of-
<section><tid>784288</tid>
<number>a</number>making interim payment of workmen' s dues pending the revival or 
rehabilitation of the sick industrial company; or

</section>

<section><tid>1271920</tid>
<number>b</number>payment of workmen' s dues due to the workmen, referred to in 
sub- section (3) of section 529, of the sick industrial company; or

</section>

<section><tid>1256938</tid>
<number>c</number>protection of assets of sick industrial company; or

</section>

<section><tid>800030</tid>
<number>d</number>revival or rehabilitation of sick industrial company;
which in the opinion of the Tribunal are necessary or expedient for 
the said purposes.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>269301</tid>
<number>441E</number>Power to call for information.- The Central Government or 
Tribunal may require any company to furnish for the purposes of 
rehabilitation or revival or protection of assets of sick industrial 
companies, such statistical and other information in such orm and 
within such period as may be prescribed.
</article>



<article><tid>1342683</tid>
<number> 441F</number> Penalty for non- payment of cess.-
<section><tid>1461458</tid>
<number>1</number>If any cess payable by a  
company under section 441A is not paid in accordance with the 
provisions of that section, it shall be deemed to be in arrears and 
the same shall be recovered by the Tribunal in such mann r as may be 
prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1829945</tid>
<number>2</number>The Tribunal may, after such inquiry as it deems fit, impose on 
the company, which is in arrears under sub- section (1), a penalty not 
exceeding ten times the amount in arrears:
Provided that before imposing such penalty, such company shall be 
given a reasonable opportunity of being heard, and if, after such 
hearing, the Tribunal is satisfied that the default was for any good 
and sufficient reason, no penalty shall be imposed un er this 
sub- section.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1281316</tid>
<number> 441G</number> Refund of fund in certain cases.-
<section><tid>1320784</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the fund has been  
applied by the Tribunal for any of the purposes specified in clauses 
 (a) to (d) of section 441D, such amount of fund shall be recovered 
from the company after its revival or rehabilitatio or out of sale 
proceeds of its assets after discharging the statutory liabilities and 
payment of dues to creditors.

</section>

<section><tid>756412</tid>
<number>2</number>The amount referred to in sub- section (1) shall be recovered in 
the manner as the Tribunal may direct.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1469599</tid>
<number>58</number>Amendment of heading before section 442.- In the heading before 
section 442 of the principal Act, for the word" Court", the word 
" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1049173</tid>
<number>59</number>Omission of section 442.- Section 442 of the principal Act shall 
be omitted.


</article>



<article><tid>1385803</tid>
<number> 60</number> Substitution of new sections for sections 443 and 444.- For 
sections 443 and 444 of the principal Act, the following sections 
shall be substituted, namely:-
" 443. Power of Tribunal on hearing petition.- (1) On hearing a winding 
up petition, the Tribunal may-

<section><tid>719773</tid>
<number>a</number>dismiss it, with or without costs; or

</section>

<section><tid>1944748</tid>
<number>b</number>adjourn the hearing conditionally or unconditionally; or

</section>

<section><tid>1317775</tid>
<number>c</number>make any interim order that it thinks fit; or

</section>

<section><tid>1432303</tid>
<number>d</number>make an order for winding up the company with or without costs, or 
any other order that it thinks fit:
Provided that the Tribunal shall not refuse to make a winding up order 
on the ground only that the assets of the company have been mortgaged 
to an amount equal to or in excess of those assets, or that the 
company has no assets.


<subsection><tid>1990287</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the petition is presented on the ground that it is just and 
equitable that the company should be wound up, the Tribunal may refuse 
to make an order of winding up, if it is of the opinion that some 
other remedy is available to the petitioners an that they are acting 
unreasonably in seeking to have the company wound up instead of 
pursuing that other remedy.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1751474</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the petition is presented on the ground of default in 
delivering the statutory report to the Registrar, or in holding the 
statutory meeting, the Tribunal may-

<subsubsection><tid>1405114</tid>
<number>a</number>instead of making a winding up order, direct that the statutory 
report shall be delivered or that a meeting shall be held; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>153538</tid>
<number>b</number>order the costs to be paid by any persons who, in the opinion of 
the Tribunal, are responsible for the default.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1804111</tid>
<number>444</number>Order for winding up to be communicated to Official Liquidator 
and Registrar.- Where the Tribunal makes an order for the winding up of 
the company, the Tribunal, shall within a period not exceeding two 
weeks from the date of passing of the order, cau e intimation thereof 
to be sent to the Official Liquidator and the Registrar.".


</article>



<article><tid>486676</tid>
<number> 61</number> Amendment of section 446.- In section 446 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1235884</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1), for the word" Court" at both the places where 
it occurs, the word" Tribunal" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1471716</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (2), for the words" The court which is winding up 
the company", the words" The Tribunal" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>471440</tid>
<number>c</number>sub- section (3) shall be omitted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1049637</tid>
<number>62</number>Insertion of new section 446.- After section 446 of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 446A. Responsibility of directors and officers to submit to Tribunal 
audited books of account.- The directors and other officers of every 
company shall ensure that books of account of the company are 
completed and audited up to date of winding up order m de by the 
Tribunal and submitted to it at the cost of the company, failing which 
such directors and officers shall be liable for punishment for a term 
not exceeding one year and a fine for an amount not exceeding one lakh 
rupees.".



</article>



<article><tid>1716265</tid>
<number> 63</number> Substitution of new section for section 448.- For section 448 of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
' 448. Appointment of Official Liquidator.- (1) For the purposes of 
this Act, so far as it relates to the winding up of a company by the 
Tribunal, there shall be an Official Liquidator who-

<section><tid>1743179</tid>
<number>a</number>may be appointed from a panel of professional firms of chartered 
accountants, advocates, company secretaries, costs and works 
accountants or firms having a combination of these professions, which 
the Central Government shall constitute for the Tribun l; or

</section>

<section><tid>672709</tid>
<number>b</number>may be a body corporate consisting of such professionals as may be 
approved by the Central Government from time to time; or

</section>

<section><tid>221329</tid>
<number>c</number>may be a whole- time or a part- time officer appointed by the 
Central Government:
Provided that, before appointing the Official Liquidator, the Tribunal 
may give due regard to the views or opinion of the secured creditors 
and workmen.


<subsection><tid>1095600</tid>
<number>2</number>The terms and conditions for the appointment of the Official 
Liquidator and the remuneration payable to him shall be-

<subsubsection><tid>1454696</tid>
<number>a</number>approved by the Tribunal for those appointed under clauses (a) and 
 (b) of sub- section (1), subject to a maximum remuneration of five per 
cent. of the value of debt recovered and realisation of sale of 
assets;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>631281</tid>
<number>b</number>approved by the Central Government for those appointed under 
clause (c) of sub- section (1) in accordance with the rules made by it 
in this behalf.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>6266</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the Official Liquidator is an officer appointed by the 
Central Government under clause (c) of sub- section (1), the Central 
Government may also appoint, if considered necessary, one or more 
Deputy Official Liquidators or Assistant Official Liqui ators to 
assist the Official Liquidator in the discharge of his functions, and 
the terms and conditions for the appointment of such Official 
Liquidators and the remuneration payable to them shall also be in 
accordance with the rules made by the Central overnment.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1489792</tid>
<number>4</number>All references to the" Official Liquidator" in this Act shall be 
construed as reference to the Official Liquidator specified in 
sub- section (1), or to the Deputy Official Liquidator or Assistant 
Official Liquidator referred to in sub- section (3), as he case may be.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1013915</tid>
<number>5</number>The amount of the remuneration payable shall-

<subsubsection><tid>1954036</tid>
<number>a</number>form part of the winding up order made by the Tribunal;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1383041</tid>
<number>b</number>be treated as first charge on the realisation of the assets and be 
paid to the Official Liquidator or to the Central Government, as the 
case may be.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1300954</tid>
<number>6</number>The Official Liquidator shall conduct proceedings in the winding 
up of a company and perform such duties in reference thereto as the 
Tribunal may specify in this behalf:
Provided that the Tribunal may-


<subsubsection><tid>1190737</tid>
<number>a</number>transfer the work assigned from one Official Liquidator to another 
Official Liquidator for the reasons to be recorded in writing;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1670062</tid>
<number>b</number>remove the Official Liquidator on sufficient cause being shown;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>959335</tid>
<number>c</number>proceed against the Official Liquidator for professional 
misconduct.'.



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>961364</tid>
<number>64</number>Amendment of section 450.- In section 450 of the principal Act, 
for the word" Court" wherever it occurs, the word" Tribunal" shall be 
substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1448917</tid>
<number> 65</number> Amendment of section 451.- In section 451 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1136803</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1), for the word" Court", the word" Tribunal" 
shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1177204</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (2), for the words" Official Liquidator", the 
words, brackets, letter and figures" the Official Liquidator referred 
to in clause (c) of sub- section (1) of section 448" shall be 
substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1512628</tid>
<number>66</number>Amendment of sections 453 to 456.- In sections 453 to 456 of the 
principal Act, for the word" Court", wherever it occurs, the word 
" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1037700</tid>
<number> 67</number> Amendment of section 457.- In section 457 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>650236</tid>
<number>a</number>for the word" Court", wherever it occurs, the word" Tribunal" 
shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>753232</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (1), after clause (c), the following clause shall 
be inserted, namely:-
" (ca) to sell whole of the undertaking of the company as a going 
concern;";


</section>

<section><tid>1317603</tid>
<number>c</number>after sub- section (2), the following sub- sections shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (2A) The liquidator shall-


</section>

<section><tid>650236</tid>
<number>a</number>appoint security guards to protect the property of the company 
taken into his custody and to make out an inventory of the assets in 
consultation with secured creditors after giving them notice;

</section>

<section><tid>753232</tid>
<number>b</number>appoint, as the case may be, valuer, chartered surveyors or 
chartered accountant to assess the value of the company' s assets 
within fifteen days after taking into custody of property, assets 
referred to in sub- clause (a) and effects or actionable cla ms subject 
to such terms and conditions as may be specified by the Tribunal;

</section>

<section><tid>1317603</tid>
<number>c</number>give an advertisement, inviting bids for sale of the assets of the 
company, within fifteen days from the date of receiving valuation 
report from the valuer, chartered surveyors or chartered accountants 
referred to in clause (b), as the case may be.

<subsection><tid>522419</tid>
<number>2B</number>The liquidator shall, immediately after the order for winding up 
or appointing the liquidator as provisional liquidator is made, issue 
a notice requiring any of the persons mentioned in sub- section (2) of 
section 454, to submit and verify a statemen of the affairs of the 
company and such notice shall be served by the liquidator.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>969149</tid>
<number>2C</number>The liquidator may apply to the Tribunal for an order directing 
any person who, in his opinion, is competent to furnish a statement of 
the affairs under sections 439A and 454 and such person shall for the 
said purpose be served a notice by the liqui ator in the manner as may 
be prescribed.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>95956</tid>
<number>2D</number>The liquidator may, from time to time, call any person for 
recording any statement for the purpose of investigating the affairs 
of the company which is being wound up and it shall be the duty of 
every such person to attend to the liquidator at such ime and place as 
the liquidator may appoint and give the liquidator all information 
which he may require and answer all such questions relating to winding 
up of company as may be put to him by the liquidator.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1052637</tid>
<number>2E</number>Every bidder shall, in response to the advertisement referred to 
in clause (c) of sub- section (2A), deposit, his offer in the manner as 
may be prescribed, with liquidator or provisional liquidator, as the 
case may be, within forty- five days from the date of the advertisement 
and the liquidator or provisional liquidator shall permit inspection 
of property and assets in respect of which bids were invited:
Provided that such bid may be withdrawn within three days before the 
last day of closing of the bid:

Provided further that the inspection of property shall be open for not 
more than five days before closing of the bid.


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1397214</tid>
<number>2F</number>The advertisement inviting bids shall contain the following 
details, namely:-

<subsubsection><tid>1035818</tid>
<number>a</number>name, address of registered office of the company and its branch 
offices, factories and plants and the place where assets of the 
company are kept and available for sale;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>441443</tid>
<number>b</number>last date for submitting bids which shall not exceed ninety days 
from the date of advertisement;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>702507</tid>
<number>c</number>time during which the premises of the company shall remain open 
for inspection;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1454680</tid>
<number>d</number>the last date for withdrawing the bid;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>399328</tid>
<number>e</number>financial guarantee which shall not be less than one- half of the 
value of the bid;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1008571</tid>
<number>f</number>validity period of the bids;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1729527</tid>
<number>g</number>place and date of opening of the bids in public;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1571099</tid>
<number>h</number>reserve price and earnest money to be deposited along with the 
bid;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1400013</tid>
<number>i</number>any other terms and conditions of sale which may be prescribed.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1754142</tid>
<number>2G</number>The liquidator appointed shall-

<subsubsection><tid>1249892</tid>
<number>a</number>maintain a separate bank account for each company under his charge 
for depositing the sale proceeds of the assets and recovery of debts 
of each company;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1529371</tid>
<number>b</number>maintain proper books of account in respect of all receipts and 
payments made by him in respect of each company and submit half yearly 
return of receipts and payments to the Tribunal.".



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1712375</tid>
<number>68</number>Amendment of sections 458 and 458A.- In sections 458 and 458A of 
the principal Act, for the word" Court", wherever it occurs, the word 
" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1001675</tid>
<number>69</number>Substitution of new section for section 459.- For section 459 of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 459. Provision for legal assistance to liquidator.- The liquidator 
may, with the sanction of the Tribunal, appoint one or more chartered 
accountants or company secretaries or cost accountants or legal 
practitioners entitled to appear before the Tribunal nder section 10GD 
to assist him in the performance of his duties.".



</article>



<article><tid>562139</tid>
<number>70</number>Amendment of sections 460 to 465.- In sections 460 to 465 of the 
principal Act, for the word" Court", wherever it occurs, the word 
" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>147921</tid>
<number>71</number>Amendment of heading before section 466.- In the heading before 
section 466 of the principal Act, for the word" Court", the word 
" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1814158</tid>
<number> 72</number> Substitution of new section for section 466.- For section 466 of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 466. Power of Tribunal to stay winding up.- (1) The Tribunal may at 
any time after making a winding up order, on the application either of 
the Official Liquidator or of any creditor or contributory, and on 
proof to the satisfaction of the Tribunal that a l proceedings in 
relation to the winding up ought to be stayed, make an order staying 
the proceedings, either altogether or for a limited time, on such 
terms and conditions as the Tribunal thinks fit.

<section><tid>3730</tid>
<number>2</number>On any application under this section, the Tribunal may, before 
making an order, require the Official Liquidator to furnish to the 
Tribunal a report with respect to any facts or matters which are in 
his opinion relevant to the application.

</section>

<section><tid>1849295</tid>
<number>3</number>A copy of every order made under this section shall forthwith be 
forwarded by the company, or otherwise as may be prescribed, to the 
Registrar, who shall make a minute of the order in his books relating 
to the company.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>194723</tid>
<number>73</number>Amendment of sections 467 to 469.- In sections 467 to 469 of the 
principal Act, for the word" Court", wherever it occurs, the word 
" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1184503</tid>
<number> 74</number> Substitution of new section for section 470.- For section 470 of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 470. Power of Tribunal to make calls.- (1) The Tribunal may, at any 
time after making winding up order, and either before or after it has 
ascertained the sufficiency of the assets of the company,-

<section><tid>1045889</tid>
<number>a</number>make calls on all or any of the contributories for the time being 
on the list of the contributories, to the extent of their liability, 
for payment of any money which the Tribunal considers necessary to 
satisfy the debts and liabilities of the company and the costs, 
charges and expenses of winding up, and for the adjustment of the 
rights of the contributories among themselves; and

</section>

<section><tid>238606</tid>
<number>b</number>make an order for payment of any calls so made.

<subsection><tid>1612683</tid>
<number>2</number>In making a call, the Tribunal may take into consideration the 
probability that some of the contributories may, partly or wholly, 
fail to pay the call.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>533342</tid>
<number>75</number>Amendment of section 471.- In section 471 of the principal Act, 
for the word" Court", at both the places where it occurs, the word 
" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>723197</tid>
<number>76</number>Substitution of new section for section 472.- For section 472 of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 472. Moneys and securities paid into bank to be subject to order of 
Tribunal.- All moneys, bills, hundis, notes and other securities paid 
or delivered into the Reserve Bank of India in the course of the 
winding up of a company by the Tribunal, shall be s bject in all 
respects to the orders of the Tribunal.".



</article>



<article><tid>1150461</tid>
<number>77</number>Amendment of sections 473 to 477.- In sections 473 to 477 of the 
principal Act, for the word" Court", wherever it occurs, the word 
" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1289106</tid>
<number> 78</number> Amendment of section 478.- In section 478 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>570121</tid>
<number>a</number>for the word" Court", wherever it occurs, the word" Tribunal" 
shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>885283</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (3) and clause (b) of sub- section (6), for the 
words" advocate, attorney or pleader entitled to appear before the 
Court", the words, figures and letters" chartered accountants or 
company secretaries or cost accountants or legal practit oners 
entitled to appear before the Tribunal under section 10GD" shall be 
substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1415074</tid>
<number>c</number>for sub- section (10), the following sub- section shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (10) An examination under this section may, if the Tribunal so 
directs, be held before any person or authority authorised by the 
Tribunal.";


</section>

<section><tid>1380164</tid>
<number>d</number>in sub- section (11), for the words" exercised by the Judge or 
officer", the words" exercised by the person or authority" shall be 
substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1890448</tid>
<number>79</number>Amendment of section 479.- In section 479 of the principal Act, 
for the word" Court", wherever it occurs, the word" Tribunal" shall be 
substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1573377</tid>
<number>80</number>Substitution of new section for section 480.- For section 480 of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 480. Saving of existing powers of Tribunal.- Any powers conferred on 
the Tribunal by this Act shall be in addition to, and not in 
derogation of, any existing powers of instituting proceedings against 
any contributory or debtor of the company, or the esta e of any 
contributory or debtor, for the recovery of any call or other sums.".



</article>



<article><tid>681497</tid>
<number>81</number>Amendment of section 481.- In section 481 of the principal Act, 
for the word" Court" at both the places where it occurs, the word 
" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>695034</tid>
<number>82</number>Amendment of section 483.- In section 483 of the principal Act, 
for the words" any order made, or decision given", the words, brackets 
and figures" any order made or decision given before the commencement 
of the Companies (Second Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1387529</tid>
<number>83</number>Amendment of sections 490 to 492.- In sections 490 and 492 of the 
principal Act, for the word" Court", wherever it occurs, the word 
" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>976508</tid>
<number> 84</number> Amendment of section 494.- In section 494 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (5),-
<section><tid>1125197</tid>
<number>a</number>for the words" or subject to the supervision of the Court", the 
words" the Tribunal" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>875915</tid>
<number>b</number>for the words" sanctioned by the Court", the words" sanctioned by 
the Tribunal" shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1657810</tid>
<number> 85</number> Amendment of section 497.- In section 497 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1388528</tid>
<number>a</number>for the word" Court", wherever it occurs, the word" Tribunal" 
shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1643369</tid>
<number>b</number>for the words" Official Liquidator", wherever they occur, the 
words, brackets, letter and figures" Official Liquidator referred to 
in clause (c) of sub- section (1) of section 448" shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1535138</tid>
<number>86</number>Amendment of sections 502 to 504, 506 and 507.- In sections 502 to 
504, 506 and 507 of the principal Act, for the word" Court", wherever 
it occurs, the word" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1391006</tid>
<number> 87</number> Amendment of section 509.- In section 509 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>737071</tid>
<number>a</number>for the words" Official Liquidator", wherever it occurs, the 
words, brackets, letter and figures" Official Liquidator referred to 
in clause (c) of sub- section (1) of section 448" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1993736</tid>
<number>b</number>for the word" Court", wherever it occurs, the word" Tribunal" 
shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1589589</tid>
<number>88</number>Amendment of sections 511A and 512.- In sections 511A and 512 of 
the principal Act, for the word" Court", wherever it occurs, the word 
" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>783432</tid>
<number>89</number>Amendment of section 513.- In section 513 of the principal Act, 
after sub- section (3), the following proviso shall be inserted, 
nemely:-
" Provided that, notwithstanding anything contained in any other law 
for the time being in force, a body corporate consisting of such 
professionals as may be approved by the Central Government from time 
to time, shall be qualified for appointment as Offic al Liquidator 
under section 448.".



</article>



<article><tid>1266101</tid>
<number> 90</number> Substitution of new section for section 515.- For section 515 of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 515. Power of Tribunal to appoint and remove liquidator in voluntary 
winding up.- (1) If from any cause whatever, there is no liquidator 
acting, the Tribunal may appoint the Official Liquidator or any other 
person as a liquidator.

<section><tid>531179</tid>
<number>2</number>The Tribunal may, on cause shown, remove a liquidator and appoint 
the Official Liquidator or any other person as a liquidator in place 
of the removed liquidator.

</section>

<section><tid>1567577</tid>
<number>3</number>The Tribunal may also appoint or remove a liquidator on the 
application made by the Registrar in this behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>1687795</tid>
<number>4</number>If the Official Liquidator is appointed as liquidator under the 
proviso to sub- section (2) of section 502 or under this section, the 
remuneration to be paid to him shall be fixed by the Tribunal and 
shall be credited to the Central Government.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1201950</tid>
<number>91</number>Amendment of section 517.- In section 517 of the principal Act, 
for the word" Court", at both the places where it occurs, the word 
" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>181520</tid>
<number> 92</number> Substitution of new sections for sections 518 and 519.- For 
sections 518 and 519 of the principal Act, the following sections 
shall be substituted, namely:-
" 518. Power to apply to Tribunal to have questions determined or 
powers exercised.- (1) The liquidator or any contributory or creditor 
may apply to the Tribunal,-

<section><tid>566478</tid>
<number>a</number>to determine any question arising in the winding up of a company; 
or

</section>

<section><tid>1176834</tid>
<number>b</number>to exercise, as respects the enforcing of calls, the staying of 
proceedings or any other matter, all or any of the powers which the 
Tribunal might exercise if the company were being wound up by the 
Tribunal.

<subsection><tid>1792844</tid>
<number>2</number>The liquidator or any creditor or contributory may apply to the 
Tribunal for an order setting aside any attachment, distress or 
execution put into force against the estate or effects of the company 
after the commencement of the winding up.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>234940</tid>
<number>3</number>The Tribunal, if satisfied on an application under sub- section (1) 
or sub- section (2) that the determination of the question or the 
required exercise of power or the order applied for will be just and 
beneficial, may accede wholly or partially to the application on such 
terms and conditions as it thinks fit, or may make such other order on 
the application as it thinks just.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>728985</tid>
<number>4</number>A copy of an order staying the proceedings in the winding up, made 
by virtue of this section, shall forthwith be forwarded by the 
company, or otherwise as may be prescribed, to the Registrar, who 
shall make a minute of the order in his books relating to the company.

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1632190</tid>
<number> 519</number> Application of liquidator to Tribunal for public examination of 
promoters, directors, etc.-
<section><tid>982945</tid>
<number>1</number>The liquidator may make a report to the  
Tribunal stating that in his opinion a fraud has been committed by any 
person in the promotion or formation of the company or by any officer 
of the company in relation to the company since its formation; and 
the Tribunal may, after considering the report, direct that that 
person or officer shall attend before the Tribunal on a day appointed 
by it for that purpose, an be publicly examined as to the promotion or 
formation or the conduct of the business of the company, or as to his 
conduct and dealings as officer thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>669551</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of sub- sections (2) to (11) of section 478 shall 
apply in relation to any examination directed under sub- section (1) as 
they apply in relation to an examination directed under sub- section 
 (1) of section 478 with references to the liqui ator being substituted 
for references to the Official Liquidator in those provisions.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1575534</tid>
<number>93</number>Omission of sections 522 to 527.- Sections 522 to 527 of the 
principal Act shall be omitted.


</article>



<article><tid>1316892</tid>
<number>94</number>Amendment of sections 531 and 531A.- In sections 531 and 531A of 
the principal Act, for the words" or subject to the supervision of the 
Court", the words" the Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1184711</tid>
<number>95</number>Amendment of sections 533 and 535.- In sections 533 and 535 of the 
principal Act, for the word" Court", wherever it occurs, the word 
" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1548247</tid>
<number> 96</number> Amendment of section 536.- In section 536 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (2),-
<section><tid>1842010</tid>
<number>a</number>for the words" or subject to the supervision of the Court", the 
words" the Tribunal" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1060312</tid>
<number>b</number>for the words" unless the Court", the words" unless the Tribunal" 
shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1795337</tid>
<number> 97</number> Substitution of new section for section 537.- For section 537 of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 537. Avoidance of certain attachments, executions, etc., in winding 
up by Tribunal.- (1) Where any company is being wound up by the 
Tribunal-

<section><tid>370385</tid>
<number>a</number>any attachment, distress or execution put in force, without leave 
of the Tribunal against the estate or effects of the company, after 
the commencement of the winding up; or

</section>

<section><tid>452310</tid>
<number>b</number>any sale held, without leave of the Tribunal, of any of the 
properties or effects of the company after such commencement, shall be 
void.

<subsection><tid>1901384</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing in this section applies to any proceedings for the 
recovery of any tax or impost or any dues payable to the Government.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1813596</tid>
<number> 98</number> Amendment of section 538.- In section 538 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1,-
<section><tid>145388</tid>
<number>a</number>for the words" or subject to the supervision of the Court", the 
words" the Tribunal" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1200560</tid>
<number>b</number>for the words" by the Court", the words" by the Tribunal" shall be 
substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1615136</tid>
<number>99</number>Amendment of sections 540 and 542.- In sections 540 and 542 of the 
principal Act, for the word" Court", wherever it occurs, the word 
" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1155108</tid>
<number> 100</number> Substitution of new section for section 543.- For section 543 of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 543. Power of Tribunal to assess damages against delinquent 
directors, etc.- (1) If in the course of winding up of a company, it 
appears that any person who has taken part in the promotion or 
formation of the company, or any past or present director, man ger, 
liquidator or officer of the company-

<section><tid>640642</tid>
<number>a</number>has misapplied, or retained, or become liable or accountable for, 
any money or property of the company; or

</section>

<section><tid>100615</tid>
<number>b</number>has been guilty of any misfeasance or breach of trust in relation 
to the company,
the Tribunal may, on the application of the Official Liquidator, or 
the liquidator, or of any creditor or contributory, made within the 
time specified in that behalf in sub- section (2), examine into the 
conduct of the person, director, manager, liquidato or officer 
aforesaid, and compel him to repay or restore the money or property or 
any part thereof respectively, with interest at such rate as the 
Tribunal thinks just, or to contribute such sum to the assets of the 
company by way of compensation in res ect of the misapplication, 
retainer, misfeasance or breach of trust, as the Tribunal thinks just.


<subsection><tid>1139000</tid>
<number>2</number>An application under sub- section (1) shall be made within five 
years from the date of the order for winding up, or of the first 
appointment of the liquidator in the winding up, or of the 
misapplication, retainer, misfeasance or breach of trust as the case 
may be, whichever is longer.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1604238</tid>
<number>3</number>This section shall apply notwithstanding that the matter is one 
for which the person concerned may be criminally liable.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>855561</tid>
<number>101</number>Amendment of section 544.- In section 544 of the principal Act, 
for the word" Court", the word" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1424415</tid>
<number> 102</number> Amendment of section 545.- In section 545 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1372889</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1), for the words" or subject to the supervision 
of Court", the words" the Tribunal" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1878258</tid>
<number>b</number>for the word" Court", wherever it occurs, the word" Tribunal" 
shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>253102</tid>
<number> 103</number> Amendment of section 546.- In section 546 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>522137</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1),-

<subsection><tid>1369523</tid>
<number>i</number>for the words" sanction of the Court", the words" sanction of the 
Tribunal" shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>695975</tid>
<number>ii</number>for the words" or subject to the supervision of the Court", the 
words" the Tribunal" shall be substituted;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>820348</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (1A),-

<subsection><tid>1171757</tid>
<number>i</number>for the words" winding up by the Court", the words" winding up by 
the Tribunal" shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1366508</tid>
<number>ii</number>for the words" sanction of the Court", the words" sanction of the 
Tribunal" shall be substituted;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>839238</tid>
<number>c</number>in sub- sections (2) and (3), for the word" Court", wherever it 
occurs, the word" Tribunal" shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>164296</tid>
<number>104</number>Amendment of section 547.- In section 547 of the principal Act, 
in sub- section 1, for the words" or under the supervision of the 
Court", the words" the Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1536100</tid>
<number>105</number>Amendment of section 549.- In section 549 of the principal Act, 
for the words" or subject to the supervision of Court", the words" the 
Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1348853</tid>
<number> 106</number> Amendment of section 550.- In section 550 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1206849</tid>
<number>i</number>in sub- section (1), for clause (a), the following clause shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (a) in the case of winding up by the Tribunal, in such manner as the 
Tribunal directs;";


</section>

<section><tid>541948</tid>
<number>ii</number>in sub- section (3), in clause (b), for the words" appeal to the 
Court", the words" appeal to the Tribunal" shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1739675</tid>
<number> 107</number> Amendment of section 551.- In section 551 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1717855</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1), for clause (a), the following clause shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (a) in the case of a winding up by the Tribunal, in Tribunal; and";


</section>

<section><tid>1799819</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (2), for the word" Court", the word" Tribunal" 
shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>849417</tid>
<number>108</number>Amendment of section 553.- In section 553 of the principal Act, 
for the word" Court", wherever it occurs, the word" Tribunal" shall be 
substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>337847</tid>
<number> 109</number> Amendment of section 555.- In section 555 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1152810</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- sections (6) and (9), for the words" or under the 
supervision of the Court", the words" the Tribunal" shall be 
substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1027441</tid>
<number>b</number>for the word" Court", wherever it occurs, the word" Tribunal" 
shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>165306</tid>
<number>110</number>Amendment of section 556.- In section 556 of the principal Act, 
for the word" Court", at both the places where it occurs, the word 
" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1476629</tid>
<number>111</number>Amendment of heading before section 557.- In the heading before 
section 557 of the principal Act, for the word" Court", the word 
" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1854214</tid>
<number>112</number>Amendment of section 557.- In section 557 of the principal Act, 
for the word" Court", wherever it occurs, the word" Tribunal" shall be 
substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1400566</tid>
<number> 113</number> Amendment of section 558.- In section 558 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>722156</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1), in clause (a), for the word" Court", the words 
" Court or the Tribunal" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1616486</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (2),-

<subsection><tid>1772923</tid>
<number>i</number>for the words" All Courts", the words" All Courts, Tribunals" 
shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1136927</tid>
<number>ii</number>for the words" such Court", the words" such Court, Tribunal" 
shall be substituted.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>137220</tid>
<number>114</number>Amendment of sections 559, 560, 581 and 582.- In sections 559, 
560, 581 and 582 of the principal Act, for the word" Court", wherever 
it occurs, the word" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>372821</tid>
<number> 115</number> Amendment of section 583.- In section 583 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1672289</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1), for the words, brackets and figure 
" sub- sections (2)", the words, brackets and figure" sub- sections (3)" 
shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>562203</tid>
<number>b</number>sub- section (2) shall be omitted;

</section>

<section><tid>1815974</tid>
<number>c</number>in sub- section (3), for the words" or subject to the supervision 
of Court", the words" by the Tribunal" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>750361</tid>
<number>d</number>in sub- section (4), for the word" Court", the word" Tribunal" 
shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1267409</tid>
<number>e</number>in sub- section (5),-

<subsection><tid>718917</tid>
<number>i</number>in clauses (a) and (b), for the word" Court", the word" Tribunal" 
shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1970931</tid>
<number>ii</number>in clause (c), for the words" order of any Court", the words 
" order of any Court or Tribunal" shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>128130</tid>
<number>iii</number>in clause (d), for the words" satisfaction of the Court", the 
words" satisfaction of the Tribunal" shall be substituted.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1437535</tid>
<number>116</number>Amendment of sections 587 to 589.- In sections 587 to 589 of the 
principal Act, for the word" Court", wherever it occurs, the word 
" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1541300</tid>
<number>117</number>Amendment of section 610.- In section 610 of the principal Act, 
in sub- section (2), for the words" Company Law Board", wherever they 
occur, the word" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>383852</tid>
<number>118</number>Amendment of section 614.- In section 614 of the principal Act, 
in sub- section 1, for the words" Company Law Board", the word 
" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>616187</tid>
<number>119</number>Amendment of section 621.- In section 621 of the principal Act, 
in sub- section 1, the brackets, words and figures" (other than an  
offence with respect to which proceedings are instituted under section 
  545)" shall be omitted.


</article>



<article><tid>725341</tid>
<number>120</number>Substitution of new section for section 621A.- For section 621A 
of the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
</article>



<article><tid>596781</tid>
<number> 621A</number> Composition of certain offences.-
<section><tid>1447005</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything  
contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>), any 
offence punishable under this Act (whether committed by a company or  
  any officer thereof), not being an offence punisha le with 
imprisonment only, or with imprisonment and also with fine, may, 
either before or after the institution of any prosecution, be 
compounded by the Central Government on payment or credit, by the 
company or the officer, as the case may be, to the Ce tral Government 
of such sum as that Government may prescribe:
Provided that the sum prescribed shall not, in any case, exceed the 
maximum amount of the fine which may be imposed for the offence so 
compounded: Provided further that in prescribing the sum required to 
be paid or credited for the compounding of an offence under this 
sub- section, the sum, if any, paid by way of additional fee under 
sub- section (2) of section 611 shall be taken into account.


</section>

<section><tid>718191</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing in sub- section (1) shall apply to an offence committed by 
a company or its officer within a period of three years from the date 
on which a similar offence committed by it or him was compounded under 
this section. Explanation.- For the purposes of this section, any 
second or subsequent offence committed after the expiry of a period of 
three years from the date on which the offence was previously 
compounded, shall be deemed to be a first offence.

</section>

<section><tid>661487</tid>
<number>3</number> (a) Every application for the compounding of an offence shall be 
made to the Registrar who shall forward the same, together with his 
comments thereon to the Central Government.

<subsection><tid>1508727</tid>
<number>b</number>Where any offence is compounded under this section, whether before 
or after the institution of any prosecution, an intimation thereof 
shall be given by the company to the Registrar within seven days from 
the date on which the offence is so compounded

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1589029</tid>
<number>c</number>Where any offence is compounded before the institution of any 
prosecution, no prosecution shall be instituted in relation to such 
offence, either by the Registrar or by any shareholder of the company 
or by any person authorised by the Central Governm nt against the 
offender in relation to whom the offence is so compounded.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1496432</tid>
<number>d</number>Where the composition of any offence is made after the institution 
of any prosecution, such composition shall be brought by the Registrar 
in writing, to the notice of the Court in which the prosecution is 
pending and on such notice of the composition of the offence being 
given, the company or its officer in relation to whom the offence is 
so compounded shall be discharged.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1233730</tid>
<number>4</number>The Central Government while dealing with a proposal for the 
compounding of an offence for a default in compliance with any 
provision of this Act which requires a company or its officer to file 
or register with, or deliver or send to, the Registrar a y return, 
account or other document, may, direct, by order, if it or he thinks 
fit to do so, any officer or other employee of the company to file or 
register with, or on payment of the fee, and the additional fee, 
required to be paid under section 611, s ch return, account or other 
document within such time as may be specified in the order.

</section>

<section><tid>768167</tid>
<number>5</number>Any officer or other employee of the company who fails to comply 
with any order made by the Central Government under sub- section (4) 
shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
six months, or with fine not exceeding fifty tho sand rupees or with 
both.

</section>

<section><tid>943474</tid>
<number>6</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal 
Procedure, <year>1973</year>-

<subsection><tid>1311255</tid>
<number>a</number>any offence which is punishable under this Act with imprisonment 
or with fine, or with both, shall be compoundable with the permission 
of the Court, in accordance with the procedure laid down in that Act 
for compounding of offences;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1484976</tid>
<number>b</number>any offence which is punishable under this Act with imprisonment 
only or with imprisonment and also with fine shall not be 
compoundable.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1445076</tid>
<number>7</number>No offence specified in this section shall be compounded except 
under and in accordance with the provisions of this section.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1331329</tid>
<number>121</number>Amendment of section 626.- In section 626 of the principal Act, 
for the word" Court", the words" Court or Tribunal" shall be 
substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>826998</tid>
<number> 122</number> Amendment of section 627.- In section 627 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1505258</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1), after the words" a Judge of a High Court in 
Chambers", the words" or Tribunal, as the case may be" shall be 
inserted;

</section>

<section><tid>423591</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (3), after the words" Judge of the High Court", the 
words" or Tribunal, as the case may be" shall be inserted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>348229</tid>
<number>123</number>Amendment of section 632.- In section 632 of the principal Act, 
for the word" Court", the words" Court or Tribunal" shall be 
substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1384113</tid>
<number>124</number>Amendment of section 634A.- In section 634A of the principal Act, 
the following proviso shall be inserted, namely:-
" Provided that the provisions of this section shall not apply on and 
after the commencement of the Companies (Second Amendment) Act, 
<year>2002</year>.".



</article>



<article><tid>1660804</tid>
<number>125</number>Amendment of section 635.- In section 635 of the principal Act, 
in sub- section (4), for the words" Company Law Board", the words 
" Company Law Board or Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>535362</tid>
<number> 126</number> Amendment of section 635B.- In section 635B of the principal 
Act,-
<section><tid>150629</tid>
<number>a</number>for the words" Company Law Board" wherever they occur, the word 
" Tribunal" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1340687</tid>
<number>b</number>for the word" Court" at both the places where it occurs, the words 
" Appellate Tribunal" shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>200075</tid>
<number> 127</number> Substitution of new section for section 637A.- For section 637A 
of the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 637A. Power of Central Government or Tribunal to accord approval, 
etc., subject to conditions and to prescribe fees on applications.- (1) 
Where the Central Government or Tribunal is required or authorised by 
any provision of this Act,-

<section><tid>701379</tid>
<number>a</number>to accord approval, sanction, consent, confirmation or recognition 
to or in relation to, any matter; or

</section>

<section><tid>496806</tid>
<number>b</number>to give any direction in relation to any matter; or

</section>

<section><tid>28902</tid>
<number>c</number>to grant any exemption in relation to any matter,
then, in the absence of anything to the contrary contained in such or 
any other provision of this Act, the Central Government or Tribunal 
may accord, give or grant such approval, sanction, consent, 
confirmation, recognition, direction or exemption, subje t to such 
conditions, limitations or restrictions as it may think fit to impose 
and may, in the case of contravention of any such condition, 
limitation or restriction, rescind or withdraw such approval, 
sanction, consent, confirmation, recognition, direc ion or exemption.


<subsection><tid>1625324</tid>
<number>2</number>Save as otherwise expressly provided in this Act, every 
application which may be, or is required to be, made to the Central 
Government or Tribunal under any provision of this Act-

<subsubsection><tid>1688203</tid>
<number>a</number>in respect of any approval, sanction, consent, confirmation or 
recognition to be accorded by that Government or Tribunal to, or in 
relation to, any matter; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1869745</tid>
<number>b</number>in respect of any direction or exemption to be given or granted by 
that Government or Tribunal in relation to any matter; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1087312</tid>
<number>c</number>in respect of any other matter,
shall be accompanied by such fee as may be prescribed:

Provided that different fees may be prescribed for applications in 
respect of different matters or in case of applications by companies, 
for applications by different classes of companies.".




</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>89670</tid>
<number>128</number>Amendment of heading before section 640A.- In the heading before 
section 640A of the principal Act, for the words" Court or the Company 
Law Board", the words" Court or the Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1562816</tid>
<number>129</number>Substitution of new section for section 640A.- For section 640A 
of the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 640A. Exclusion of time required in obtaining copies of order of 
Court or Tribunal.- Except as expressly provided in this behalf 
elsewhere in this Act, where by any provision of this Act, any order 
of the Court or Tribunal is required to be filed with th Registrar, or 
a company or any other person within a period specified therein, then, 
in computing that period, the time taken in drawing up the order and 
in obtaining a copy thereof shall be excluded.".



</article>



<article><tid>654689</tid>
<number> 130</number> Substitution of new section for section 643.- For seciton 643 of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 643. Power of Central Government to make rules relating to winding 
up.- (1) The Central Government shall, make rules consistent with the 
Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year>, providing for all matters relating to 
the winding up of companies, which by this Act, are to be prescribed, 
and may make rules providing for all such matters as may be 
prescribed.

<section><tid>1389300</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
forgoing power, such rule may provide for all or any of the following 
matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>517353</tid>
<number>i</number>as to the mode of proceedings to be held for winding up of a 
company by the Tribunal;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1596824</tid>
<number>ii</number>for the voluntary winding up of companies, whether by members or 
by creditors;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>85030</tid>
<number>iii</number>for the holding of meetings of creditors and members in 
connection with proceedings under section 391;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>413210</tid>
<number>iv</number>for giving effect to the provisions of this Act as to the 
reduction of the capital;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>769394</tid>
<number>v</number>generally for all applications to be made to the Tribunal under 
the provisions of this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1127239</tid>
<number>vi</number>the holding and conducting of meetings to ascertain the wishes of 
creditors and contributories;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>298557</tid>
<number>vii</number>the settling of lists of contributories and the rectifying of 
the register of members where required and collecting and applying the 
assets;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1722532</tid>
<number>viii</number>the payment, delivery, conveyance, surrender or transfer of 
money, property, books or papers to the liquidator;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>596908</tid>
<number>ix</number>the making of calls; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1163020</tid>
<number>x</number>the fixing of a time within which debts and claims shall be 
proved.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>16748</tid>
<number>3</number>All rules made by the Supreme Court on the matters referred to in 
this section as it stood immediately before the commencement of the 
Companies (Second Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>, and in force at such 
commencement, shall continue to be in force, in so far s they are not 
inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, till such time the rules 
are made by the Central Government and any reference to the High Court 
in relation to winding up of a company in such rules shall be 
construed as a reference to the Tri unal.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>561475</tid>
<number>131</number>Insertion of new section 647A.- After section 647 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 647A. Transfer of winding up proceedings to Tribunal.- All 
proceedings (including proceedings relating to arbitration,  
compromises, arrangements and reconstruction and winding up of a 
  company) pending before the commencement of the Companies (Second Amen  
  ment) Act, <year>2002</year> before any District Court or High Court, under this 
Act, or the Insurance Act, <year>1938</year> or any other law for the time being in 
force other than under the Banking Regulation Act, <year>1949</year>, shall be 
transferred to the Tribunal from the date to be n tified by the 
Central Government, in the Official Gazette, and the Tribunal may 
proceed with the matter either de novo or from the stage it was so 
transferred:

Provided that where the winding up of a company has commenced, subject 
to the supervision of the District Court or a High Court, before the 
commencement of the Companies (Second Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>, such 
winding up shall continue to be under the supervi ion of the District 
Court or the High Court, as the case may be, and the company shall be 
wound up in the same manner and in the same incidents as if the 
Companies (Second Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year> had not been passed.".



</article>



<article><tid>1363701</tid>
<number>132</number>Amendment of Schedule XI to Companies Act, <year>1956</year>.- In Schedule XI 
to the principal Act, for the words" Company Law Board" wherever they 
occur, the word" Tribunal" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1402856</tid>
<number>133</number>Amendment of other enactment.- The enactment specified in the 
Schedule to this Act shall be amended in the manner specified therein.


</article>



<article><tid>726978</tid>
<number> 134</number> Insertion of new section 651A.- After section 651 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 651A. Reference of winding up of companies in any law.- Unless the 
context otherwise requires,-

<section><tid>1163440</tid>
<number>a</number>any reference to the winding up of a company by a Court or High 
Court or winding up of a company subject to supervision of a Court or 
High Court in any law (except the Banking Regulation Act, <year>1949</year>) shall, 
in so far as it relates to winding up of a co pany, be construed as 
winding up of a company by the Tribunal in accordance with the 
provisions of this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>543107</tid>
<number>b</number>any reference to the Company Law Board in any law, so far as it 
relates to the Company Law Board, shall be construed as the Tribunal 
under this Act.


</section>

</article>



 </act>