<act> 
 The Fiscal Responsibility and Budget Management Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the fiscal Responsibility and Budget Management Rules, 
2004.
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force 
on the 5th day of July, 2004.
</section></article> 
 The Fiscal Responsibility and Budget Management Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>       <number>a</number>   “Act” means the 
Fiscal Responsibility and Budget Management Act, 2003 (39 of 2003);
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>   “Form” means a 
form appended to these rules;
 </section><section>        <number>c</number>   “GDP” means 
gross domestic product at current prices;
 </section><section>       <number>d</number>   “section” means 
a section of the Act;
 </section><section>       <number>e</number>   words and 
expressions used herein but not defined and defined in the Act shall have the 
meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act.
</section></article> 
 The Fiscal Responsibility and Budget Management Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>3</number> Annual targets.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In order to achieve the target of revenue deficit as set out in sub-section (1) 
of section 4, by the 31st day of March, 2008, the Central Government shall 
reduce such deficit by an amount equivalent to 0.5 per cent or more of the GDP 
at the end of each financial year, beginning with the financial year 2004-2005.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Central Government shall 
reduce the fiscal deficit by an amount equivalent to 0.3 per cent or more of the 
GDP at the end of each financial year beginning with the financial year 
2004-2005, so that fiscal deficit is brought down to not more than 3 per cent of 
GDP at the end of 31st day of March, 2008.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Central Government shall 
not give guarantees aggregating to an amount exceeding 0.5 per cent of the GDP 
in any financial year beginning with the financial year 2004-2005.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Central Government shall 
not assume additional liabilities (including external debt at current exchange 
rate) in excess of 9 per cent of GDP for the financial year 2004-2005 and in 
each subsequent financial year, the limit of 9 per cent of GDP shall be 
progressively reduced by at least one percentage point of GDP.
</section></article> 
 The Fiscal Responsibility and Budget Management Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>4</number> Medium Term Fiscal Policy 
Statement, Fiscal Policy Strategy Statement and Macro Economic Framework 
Statement.—The Medium Term Fiscal 
Policy Statement, Fiscal Policy Strategy Statement and Macro-Economic Framework 
Statement required to be laid before both Houses of Parliament by the Central 
Government along with the annual financial statement and demands for grants 
shall be in Forms F-1, F-2 and F-3 respectively.
</article> 
 The Fiscal Responsibility and Budget Management Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>5</number> Fiscal Indicators.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In the Medium Term Fiscal Policy Statement, three year rolling targets in 
respect of the following fiscal indicators shall be as given in Form F-1, 
namely:—
 <subsection>        <number>i</number>   revenue 
deficit as a percentage of GDP;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>ii</number>   fiscal deficit 
as a percentage of GDP;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number>   tax revenue 
as a percentage of GDP; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iv</number>   total 
outstanding liabilities of the Central Government as a percentage of GDP.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The Fiscal Policy Strategy 
Statement in Form F-2 shall also contain the intra-year benchmarks for assessing 
the trends in receipts and expenditure relating to annual targets and Budget 
Estimates.
</section></article> 
 The Fiscal Responsibility and Budget Management Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>6</number> Disclosures.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In order to ensure greater transparency in its fiscal operation in the public 
interest, the Central Government shall, at the time to presenting the annual 
financial statement and demands for grants, make disclosures of the following:—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>   any significant 
change in accounting standards, policies and practices affecting or likely to 
affect the computation of prescribed fiscal indicators.
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>   statements of 
receivables and guarantees in Forms D-1 to D-3.
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>c</number>   a statement of 
assets in Form D-4.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The provisions of sub-rule 
(1) shall be complied with not later than with the presentation of the annual 
financial statement and demands for grants for the financial year 2006-2007.
</section></article> 
 The Fiscal Responsibility and Budget Management Rules, 2004
  
 <article><number>7</number> Measures to enforce 
compliance.—In case the outcome of 
the quarterly review of trends in receipts and expenditure, made under 
sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 7, at the end of second quarter of any financial year 
beginning with the financial year 2004-2005 shows that—
 <subsection>        <number>i</number>   the total 
non-debt receipts are less than 40 per cent of Budget Estimates for that year; 
or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>ii</number>   the fiscal 
deficit is higher than 45 per cent of the Budget Estimates for that year; or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number>   the revenue 
deficit is higher than 45 per cent of the Budget Estimates for that year,
               then,—
 <subsubsection>            <number>a</number>   as required under sub-section (2) of that 
section, the Central Government shall take appropriate corrective measures; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            <number>b</number>   as required under sub-section (3) of that 
section, the Minister-in-charge of the Ministry of Finance shall make a 
statement in both Houses of Parliament during the session immediately following 
the end of the second quarter detailing the corrective measures taken, the 
manner in which any supplementary demands for grants are proposed to be financed 
and the prospects for the fiscal deficit of that financial year.
</subsubsection></subsection></section></article><form>
 




The Fiscal Responsibility and Budget Management Rules, 2004
 


 
 

Form F-2
 

(See rule 4)
 

Fiscal Policy Strategy Statement
 

A. Fiscal Policy Overview
 

[This paragraph will present 
an overview of the fiscal policy currently in vogue.]
 

B. Fiscal policy for the ensuing financial year
 

[This paragraph shall have 
five sub-paragraphs dealing with—
 

        (1)  Tax Policy.—In the sub-paragraph on tax 
policy, major changes proposed to be introduced in direct and indirect taxes in 
the ensuing financial year will be presented. It shall contain an assessment of 
income tax exemption limits and how far it relates to per capita income, 
principles regarding tax exemptions and target group for exemptions.
 

        (2)  Expenditure Policy.—Under expenditure 
policy, major changes proposed in the allocation of expenditure shall be 
indicated. It shall also contain an assessment of principles regarding the 
benefits and target group of beneficiaries.
 

        (3)  Government Borrowings. Lending and 
Investments.—In this sub-paragraph on Government borrowings, the policy 
relating to internal debt, external debt, Government lending, investments and 
other activities; including principles regarding average maturity structure, 
bunching of repayments, etc., shall be indicated.
 

        (4)  Contingent and other Liabilities.—Any 
change in the policy on contingent and other liabilities and in particular 
guarantees which have potential budgetary implications shall be indicated.
 

        (5)  Pricing of Administered Goods.—Any-change 
proposed in the pricing of administered products, including the progress towards 
market-based principles shall be spelt out.]
 

C. Strategic priorities for the ensuing year.
 

[(1) Resource mobilization for 
the ensuing financial year through tax, non-tax and other receipts shall be 
spelt out.
 

(2) The broad principles 
underlying the expenditure management during the ensuing year shall be spelt 
out.
 

(3) Priorities relating to 
management of public debt proposed during the ensuing year shall be indicated.]
 

D. Rationale for Policy changes
 

[(1) The rationale for policy 
changes consistent with the Medium Term Fiscal Policy Statement, in respect of 
direct and indirect taxes proposed in the ensuing Budget shall be spelt out.
 

(2) The rationale for major 
policy changes in respect of budgeted expenditure including expenditure on 
subsidies shall be indicated.
 

(3) Rationale for changes, if 
any, proposed in the management of the public debt shall be indicated.
 

(4) The need for changes, if 
any, proposed in respect of pricing of administered goods shall be spelt out.]
 

E. Targets for the ensuing year
 

[At the end of the second 
quarter, a mid-year assessment shall be made of the trends in receipts and 
expenditures and achievement of targets of deficit reduction in relation to 
Budget Estimates. In case the total non-debt receipts are less than 40 per cent 
of Budget Estimates for that year; or the fiscal deficit is higher than 45 per 
cent of the Budget Estimates for that year; or the revenue deficit is higher 
than 45 per cent of the Budget Estimates for that year, the Central Government 
shall take action as required under sub-sections (2) and (3) of section 7.]
 

F. Policy Evaluation
 

[This paragraph shall contain an evaluation of the changes 
proposed in the fiscal policy for the ensuing year with reference to fiscal 
deficit reduction and objectives set out in the medium term fiscal policy 
statement.]
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>