<act> 
 
The PREVENTION OF MONEY-LAUNDERING 
(MANNER OF RECEIVING THE RECORDS AUTHENTICATED OUTSIDE 
INDIA) RULES, 20051
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Prevention of Money-laundering (Manner of 
Receiving the Records Authenticated Outside India) Rules, 2005.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The PREVENTION OF MONEY-LAUNDERING 
(MANNER OF RECEIVING THE RECORDS AUTHENTICATED OUTSIDE 
INDIA) RULES, 2005
 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  “Act” means the Prevention of 
Money-laundering Act, 2002 (15 of 2003);
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  “record” means the record in any 
form received from any place outside India and authenticated in the manner as 
specified in these rules;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  “section” means a section of the 
Act.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> All other words and 
expressions used and not defined in these rules but defined in the Act, shall 
have the meaning respectively assigned to them in the Act.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The PREVENTION OF MONEY-LAUNDERING 
(MANNER OF RECEIVING THE RECORDS AUTHENTICATED OUTSIDE 
INDIA) RULES, 2005
 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Manner of 
authentication of records received from outside India.— 

<section><number>1</number> For the purposes of sub-section (2) of section 22 of the Act, any record 
received from the place outside India shall be deemed to be authenticated if 
such record is received,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  from an authority designated 
under an agreement or treaty entered into by the Central Government with the 
Government of any country for exchange of information or investigations of cases 
relating to any offence under the Act, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  which is purporting to have 
affixed, impressed or submitted thereon or thereto the seal and signature of any 
person who is authorised by section 3 of the Diplomatic and Consular Officers 
(Oaths and Fees) Act, 1948 (41 of 1948) to do any notorial acts shall be deemed 
to be duty authenticated for the purposes of sub-section (2) of section 22 of 
the Act.
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The PREVENTION OF MONEY-LAUNDERING 
(MANNER OF RECEIVING THE RECORDS AUTHENTICATED OUTSIDE 
INDIA) RULES, 2005
 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Interpretation.—If 
any question arises relating to the interpretation of these rules, the matter 
shall be referred to the Central Government and the decision of the Central 
Government shall be final.
  
  
</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>