<act><tid>1443989</tid>
<title>THE INDIAN TREASURE- TROVE ACT, <year>1878</year></title>

ACT NO. 6 OF <year>1878</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 13th February, <year>1878</year>.]

An Act to amend the law relating to Treasure- trove.

Preamble.

WHEREAS it is expedient to amend the law relating to 
treasuretrove; It is hereby enacted as follows:--

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>132481</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Indian Treasure- trove 
Act, <year>1878</year>.
Extent.

It extends to the whole of India except <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the territories which, 
immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in Part B 
States].

<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>



</article>



<article><tid>1941589</tid>
<number>2</number>[ Repeal of enactments.] Rep. by the Repealing and Amending 
Act, <year>1891</year> (12 of <year>1891</year>), s. 2 and Sch. I.


</article>



<article><tid>25764</tid>
<number>3</number>Interpretation- clause." Treasure." In this Act--
" treasure" means anything of any value hidden in the soil, 
or in anything affixed thereto:


<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been declared to be in force in--

Sonthal Parganas by the Sonthal Parganas Settlement 
Regulation (Reg. 3 of <year>1872</year>), s. 3;

Khondmals District by the Khondmals Laws Regulation, <year>1936</year> 
 (Reg. 4 of <year>1936</year>), s. 3 and Sch; and

Angul District by the Angul Laws Regulation, <year>1936</year> (Reg. 5 of  
  <year>1936</year>), s. 3 and Sch.

It has also been declared, by notification under s. 3 (a) of the 
Scheduled Districts Act, <year>1874</year> (14 of <year>1874</year>), to be in force in the 
Scheduled Districts of Hazaribagh, Lohardaga and Manbhum, and Pargana 
Dhalbhum and the Kolhan in the District of Singbhum- see Gazette of 
India, <year>1881</year>, Pt. I, p. 504. (The District of Lohardaga included at  
that time the present District of Palamau, which was separated in 
<year>1894</year>; Lohardaga is now called the Ranchi District; see Calcutta 
  Gazette, <year>1899</year>, Pt. I, p. 44)

Amended in--

Bihar by Bihar Act 22 of <year>1947</year>.

Madras by Madras Act 36 of <year>1949</year>.

Extended to Laccadive, Minicoy and Amindivi Islands (w. e. f.  
  1. 10. <year>1967</year>): vide Reg. 8 of <year>1965</year>, s. 3 and Sch. (with modifn)

Extended to and brought into forco in Dadra and Nagar Havoli (w. e. f.  
  1. 7. 65) by Reg. 6 of <year>1963</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I.


</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" Part B 
States". 
3 The words" And it shall come into force at once." rep. by Act 10 
of <year>1914</year>, s. 3 and Sch. II.

Rep. in its application to Billary district by Mysore Act 14 of <year>1955</year>.

Am in Punjab by Pun. Act 24 of <year>1960</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

" Collector."

" Collector." means (1) any Revenue- officer in independent 
charge of a district, and (2) any officer appointed by 
the State Government to perform the functions of a 
Collector under this Act

" Owner."

When any person is entitled, under any reservation in an 
instrument of transfer of any land or thing affixed thereto, to 
treasure in such land or thing, he shall, for the purposes of this 
Act, be deemed to be the owner of such land or thing.

PROCEDURE ON FINDING TREASURE



</article>



<article><tid>850356</tid>
<number> 4</number> Notice by finder of treasure. Whenever any treasure exceeding 
in amount or value ten rupees is found, the finder shall, as soon as 
practicable, give to the Collector notice in writing--
<section><tid>528509</tid>
<number>a</number>of the nature and amount or approximate value of such 
treasure;

</section>

<section><tid>721162</tid>
<number>b</number>of the place in which it was found;

</section>

<section><tid>467416</tid>
<number>c</number>of the date of the finding;
and either deposit the treasure in the nearest Government 
treasury, or give the Collector such security as the Collector thinks 
fit, to produce the treasure at such time and place as he may from 
time to time require.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>236526</tid>
<number> 5</number> Notification requiring claimants to appear. On receiving a 
notice under section 4, the Collector shall, after making such enquiry 
 (if any) as he thinks fit, take the following steps (namely):--
<section><tid>1047348</tid>
<number>a</number>he shall publish a notification in such manner as the 
State Government from time to time prescribes in this 
behalf, to the effect that, on a certain date 
 (mentioning it) certain treasure (mentioning its  
  nature, amount and approximate value) was found in a 
certain place (mentioning it); and requiring all 
persons claiming the treasure, or any part thereof, to 
appear personally or by agent before the Collector on a 
day and at a place therein mentioned, such day not 
being earlier than four months, or later than six 
months, after the date of the publication of such 
notification;

</section>

<section><tid>196467</tid>
<number>b</number>when the place in which the treasure appears to the 
Collector to have been found was at the date of the 
finding in the possession of some person other than the 
finder,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

the Collector shall also serve on such person a special 
notice in writing to the same effect.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1437787</tid>
<number>6</number>Forfeiture of right on failure to appear. Any person having 
any right to such treasure or any part thereof, as owner of the place 
in which it was found or otherwise, and not appearing as required by 
the notification issued under section 5, shall forfeit such right.


</article>



<article><tid>1600227</tid>
<number> 7</number> Matters to be enquired into and determined by the Collector. 
On the day notified under section 5, the Collector shall cause the 
treasure to be produced before him, and shall enquire as to and 
determine--
<section><tid>293246</tid>
<number>a</number>the person by whom, the place in which, and the 
circumstances under which, such treasure was found; and

</section>

<section><tid>72589</tid>
<number>b</number>as far as is possible, the person by whom, and the 
circumstances under which, such treasure was hidden.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>341565</tid>
<number>8</number>Time to be allowed for suit by person claiming the treasure. 
If, upon an enquiry made under section 7, the Collector sees reason to 
believe that the treasure was hidden within one hundred years before 
the date of the finding, by a person appearing as required by the said 
notification and claiming such treasure, or by some other person under 
whom such person claims, the Collector shall make an order adjourning 
the hearing of the case for such period as he deems sufficient, to 
allow of a suit being instituted in the Civil Court by the claimant, 
to establish his right.


</article>



<article><tid>1797766</tid>
<number>9</number>When treasure may be declared ownerless. If upon such enquiry 
the Collector sees no reason to believe that the treasure was so 
hidden; or
if, where a period is fixed under section 8, no suit is 
instituted as aforesaid within such period to the knowledge of the 
Collector; or

if such suit is instituted within such period, and the 
plaintiff' s claim is finally rejected;

the Collector may declare the treasure to be ownerless. 
Appeal against such declaration. Any person aggrieved by a declaration made under this section may 
appeal against the same within two months from the date thereof to the 
Chief Controlling Revenue- authority <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>.

Subject to such appeal, every such declaration shall be final and 
conclusive.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>6</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>For definition of Chief Controlling Revenue- authority, see the 
General Clauses Act, <year>1897</year> (10 of <year>1897</year>), s. 3 (10).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>1499680</tid>
<number>10</number>Proceedings subsequent to declaration. When a declaration has 
been made in respect of any treasure under section 9, such treasure 
shall, in accordance with the provisions hereinafter contained, either 
be delivered to the finder thereof, or be divided between him and the 
owner of the place in which it has been found in manner hereinafter 
provided.


</article>



<article><tid>501299</tid>
<number>11</number>When no other person claims as owner of place, treasure to be 
given to finder. When a declaration has been made in respect of any 
treasure as aforesaid, and no person other than the finder of such 
treasure has appeared as required by the notification published under 
section 5 and claimed a share of the treasure as owner of the place in 
which it has been found, the Collector shall deliver such treasure to 
the finder thereof.


</article>



<article><tid>601831</tid>
<number> 12</number> When only one such person claims and his claim is not 
disputed, treasure to be divided, and shares to be delivered to 
parties. When a declaration has been made as aforesaid in respect of 
any treasure, and only one person other than the finder of such 
treasure has so appeared and claimed, and the claim of such person is 
not disputed by the finder, the Collector shall proceed to divide the 
treasure between the finder and the person so claiming according to 
the following rule (namely):--
If the finder and the person so claiming have not entered into 
any agreement then in force as to the disposal of the treasure, 
threefourths of the treasure shall be allotted to such finder and the 
residue to such person. If such finder and such person have entered 
into any such agreement, the treasure shall be disposed of in 
accordance therwith:

Provided that the Collector may in any case, if he thinks fit, 
instead of dividing any treasure as directed by this section,--

<section><tid>159781</tid>
<number>a</number>allot to either party the whole or more than his share 
of such treasure, on such party paying to the Collector 
for the other party such sum of money as the Collector 
may fix as the equivalent of the share of such other 
party, or of the excess so allotted, as the case may 
be; or

</section>

<section><tid>1616819</tid>
<number>b</number>sell such treasure or any portion thereof by public 
auction and divide the sale- proceeds between the 
parties according to the rule hereinbefore prescribed:
Provided also, that when the Collector has by his declaration 
under section 9 rejected any claim made under this Act by any person 
other than the said finder or person claiming as owner of the place in 
which the treasure was found, such division shall not be made until 
after the expiration of two months without an appeal having been 
presented


<pagefootnote><pagenum>7</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

under section 9 by the person whose claim has been so rejected, or, 
when an appeal has been so presented, after such appeal has been 
dismissed.

When the Collector has made a division under this section, he 
shall deliver to the parties the portions of such treasure, or the 
money in lieu thereof, to which they are respectively entitled under 
such division.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>565359</tid>
<number>13</number>In case of dispute as to ownership of place, proceedings to 
be stayed. When a declaration has been made as aforesaid in respect of 
any treasure, and two or more persons have appeared as aforesaid and 
each of them claimed as owner of the place where such treasure was 
found, or the right of any person who has so appeared and claimed is 
disputed by the finder of such treasure, the Collector shall retain 
such treasure and shall make an order staying his proceedings with a 
view to the matter being enquired into and determined by a Civil 
Court.


</article>



<article><tid>576519</tid>
<number>14</number>Settlement of such dispute, Any person who has so appeared 
and claimed may, within one month from the date of such order, 
institute a suit in the Civil Court to obtain a decree declaring his 
right; and in every such suit the finder of the treasure and all 
persons disputing such claim before the Collector shall be made 
defendants.


</article>



<article><tid>1380219</tid>
<number>15</number>and division thereupon. If any such suit is instituted and 
the plaintiff' s claim is finally established therein, the Collector 
shall, subject to the provisions of section 12, divide the treasure 
between him and the finder.
If no such suit is instituted as aforesaid, or if the claims of 
the plaintiffs in all such suits are finally rejected, the Collector 
shall deliver the treasure to the finder.



</article>



<article><tid>854636</tid>
<number>16</number>Power to acquire the treasure on behalf of Government. The 
Collector may, at any time after making a declaration under section 9, 
and before delivering or dividing the treasure as hereinbefore 
provided, declare by writing under his hand his intention to acquire 
on behalf of the Government the treasure, or any specified portion 
thereof, by payment to the persons entitled thereto of a sum equal to 
the value of the materials of such treasure or portion, together with 
one- fifth of such value, and may place such sum in deposit in his 
treasury to the credit of such persons; and thereupon such treasure or 
portions shall be deemed to be the property of Government, and the 
money so deposited shall be dealt with, as far as may be, as if it 
were such treasure or portion.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>8</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1028312</tid>
<number>17</number>Decision of Collector final, and no suit to lie against him 
for acts done bona fide. No decision passed or act done by the 
Collector under this Act shall be called in question by any Civil 
Court, and no suit or other proceeding shall lie against him for 
anything done in good faith in exercise of the powers hereby 
conferred.


</article>



<article><tid>1216585</tid>
<number>18</number>Collector to exercise powers of Civil Court. A Collector 
making any enquiry under this Act may exercise any power conferred by 
the Code of Civil Procedure <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> on a Civil Court for the trial of 
suits (14 of <year>1882</year>)].


</article>



<article><tid>833721</tid>
<number>19</number>Power to make rules. The State Government may, from time to 
time, make rules consistent with this Act, to regulate proceedings 
hereunder.
Such rules shall, on being published in the Official Gazette, 
have the force of law.

PENALTIES



</article>



<article><tid>1574527</tid>
<number>20</number>Penalty on finder failing to give notice, etc. If the finder 
of any treasure fails to give the notice, or does not either make the 
deposit or give the security, required by section 4, or alters or 
attempts to alter such treasure so as to conceal its identity, the 
share of such treasure, or the money in lieu thereof to which he would 
otherwise be entitled, shall vest in Government,
and he shall, on conviction before a Magistrate, be punished with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or with fine, or 
with both.



</article>



<article><tid>622896</tid>
<number>21</number>Penalty on owner abetting offence under section 20. If the 
owner of the place in which any treasure is found abets, within the 
meaning of the Indian Penal Code (15 of <year>1860</year>), any offence under 
section 20, the share of such treasure, or the money in lieu thereof 
to which he would otherwise be entitled, shall vest in Government,
and he shall, on conviction before a Magistrate, be punished with 
imprisonment which may extend to six months, or with fine, or with 
both.


</article>



 </act>