<act><tid>1282978</tid>
<title>THE COUNTESS OF DUFFERIN' S FUND ACT, <year>1957</year></title>

ACT NO. 63 OF <year>1957</year> AN ACT TO PROVIDE FOR THE TRANSFER OF THE FUND KNOWN 
AS THECOUNTESS OF
[ 27th December <year>1957</year>.]





<article><tid>1596031</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Countess of Dufferin' s 
Fund Act, <year>1957</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1691398</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>1932190</tid>
<number>a</number>" Association" means the National Association for 
Supplying Medical Aid by Women to the Women of India, being a 
society registered under the Societies Registration Act, <year>1860</year> 
; (21 of <year>1860</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>213532</tid>
<number>b</number>" Fund" means all property, movable or immovable, of 
or belonging to the Association.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>984695</tid>
<number> 3</number> Dissolution of Association and transfer of Fund. On the 
commencement of this Act-
<section><tid>1378785</tid>
<number>a</number>the Association shall stand dissolved;

</section>

<section><tid>385615</tid>
<number>b</number>the Fund shall vest in the Central Government; and

</section>

<section><tid>685127</tid>
<number>c</number>all the debts and liabilities of the Association shall 
be transferred to the Central Government and shall thereafter 
be discharged and satisfied by it out of the Fund.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1059936</tid>
<number>4</number>Validation of certain acts done before the commencement of 
this Act. Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time 
being in force, all acts and things done, before the commencement of 
this Act, by any person acting or purporting to act in pursuance of 
the Resolutions passed at the extraordinary general meeting of the 
Association held on the 19th day of April, <year>1948</year>, shall be valid and 
shall be deemed always to have been valid and no suit or other pro- 
ceeding shall be instituted, maintained or continued against any 
person whatever on the ground that any such act or thing was not done 
in accordance with law.

</article>



 </act>