<act><tid>1057200</tid>
<title>THE HINDU MINORITY AND GUARDIANSHIPACT, <year>1956</year></title>

ACT NO. 32 OF <year>1956</year>
[ 25th August, <year>1956</year>.]

An Act to amend and codify certain parts of the law relating to 
minority and guardianship among Hindus.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Seventh Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:--





<article><tid>829514</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>570093</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Hindu  
Minority and Guardianship Act, <year>1956</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1177028</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu 
and Kashmir and applies also to Hindus domiciled in the territories to 
which this Act extends who are outside the said territories.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1754302</tid>
<number>2</number>Act to be supplemental to Act 8 of <year>1890</year>. The provisions of this 
Act shall be in addition to, and not, save as hereinafter expressly 
provided, in derogation of, the Guardians and Wards Act, <year>1890</year>. (8 of  
  <year>1890</year>.)
</article>



<article><tid>219718</tid>
<number> 3</number> 
<section><tid>1544220</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act applies- 

<subsection><tid>1049940</tid>
<number>a</number>Application of Act. to any person who is a Hindu by 
religion in any of it forms or developments, including a 
Virashaiva a Lingayat or a follower of the Brahmo, Prarthana 
or Arya Samaj,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1858499</tid>
<number>b</number>to any person who is a Buddhist, Jaina or Sikh by 
religion, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>48352</tid>
<number>c</number>to any other person domiciled in the territories to 
which this Act extends who is not a Muslim, Christian, Parsi 
or Jew by religion, unless it is proved that any such person 
would not have been governed by the Hindu law or by any 
custom or usage as part of that law in respect of any of the 
matters dealt with herein if this Act had not been passed.
Explanation.- The following persons are Hindus, Buddhists, Jainas 
or Sikhs by religion, as the case may be:-


<subsubsection><tid>1266709</tid>
<number>i</number>any child, legitimate or illegitimate, both of whose 
parents are Hindus, Buddhists, Jainas or Sikhs by religion;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1171302</tid>
<number>ii</number>any child, legitimate or illegitimate, one of whose 
parents is a Hindu, Buddhist, Jaina or Sikh by religion and 
who is brought up as a member of the tribe, community, group 
or family to which such parent belongs or belonged; and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>184</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The Act has been extended to Dadra and Nagar Haveli by Reg. 6 of 
<year>1963</year>, s. 2 and Sch. 1.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>26008</tid>
<number>iii</number>any person who is a convert or re- convert to the 
Hindu, Buddhist, Jaina or Sikh religion.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1107227</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1). 
nothing contained in this Act shall apply to the members of any 
Scheduled Tribe within the meaning of clause (25) of article 366 of 
the Constitution unless the Central Government, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, otherwise directs. 1

</section>

<section><tid>65709</tid>
<number>3</number>The expression" Hindu" in any portion of this Act shall be 
construed as if it included a person who, though not a Hindu by 
religion, is, nevertheless, a person to whom this Act applies by 
virtue of the provisions contained in this section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>207413</tid>
<number> 4</number> Definitions. In this Act,-
<section><tid>1525931</tid>
<number>a</number>" minor" means a person who has not completed the age of 
eighteen years

</section>

<section><tid>1230109</tid>
<number>b</number>" guardian" means a person having the care of the 
person of a minor or of his property or of both his person 
and property, and includes-

<subsection><tid>74761</tid>
<number>i</number>a natural guardian,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>375553</tid>
<number>ii</number>a guardian appointed by the will of the minor' s 
father or mother,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>578346</tid>
<number>iii</number>a guardian appointed or declared by a court, 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1899442</tid>
<number>iv</number>a person empowered to act as such by or under any 
enactment relating to any court of wards; (c)" natural 
guardian" means any of the guardians mentioned in 
section 6.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1284833</tid>
<number> 5</number> Over- riding effect of Act. Save as otherwise expressly provided 
in this Act,-
<section><tid>1981625</tid>
<number>a</number>any text, rule or interpretation of Hindu law or any 
custom or usage as part of that law in force immediately 
before the commencement of this Act shall cease to have 
effect with respect to any matter for which provision is made 
in this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>556160</tid>
<number>b</number>any other law in force immediately before the 
commencement of this Act shall cease to, have effect in so 
far as it is inconsistent with any of the provisions 
contained in this Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>185</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>In its application to Pondicherry, in section 3, after sub- section 
 (2), the following shall be inserted-

" (2A) Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), 
nothing contained in this Act shall apply to the Renoncants 
of the Union territory of Pondicherry."- (Vide Act 26 of  
  <year>1968</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1755046</tid>
<number> 6</number> Natural guardians of a Hindu Minor. The natural guardians of a 
Hindu minor, in respect of the minor' s person as well as in respect of 
the minor' s property (excluding his or her undivided interest in joint  
  family property), are-
<section><tid>905442</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of a boy or an unmarried girl- the father. 
and after him, the mother: provided that the custody of a 
minor who has not completed the age of five years shall 
ordinarily be with the mother;

</section>

<section><tid>1946451</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of an illegitimate boy or an illegitimate 
unmarried girl- the mother, and after her, the father; (c) in 
the case of a married girl- the husband:
Provided that no person shall be entitled to act as the natural 
guardian of a minor under the provisions of this section-


</section>

<section><tid>905442</tid>
<number>a</number>if he has ceased to be a Hindu, or

</section>

<section><tid>1946451</tid>
<number>b</number>if he has completely and finally renounced the world by 
becoming a hermit (vanaprastha) or an ascetic (yati or  
  sanyasi).
Explanation.- In this section, the expressions" father" and 
" mother" do not include a step- father and a step- mother.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>630916</tid>
<number>7</number>Natural guardianship of adopted son. The natural guardianship 
of an adopted son who is a minor passes, on adoption, to the adoptive 
father and after him to the adoptive mother.


</article>



<article><tid>1331750</tid>
<number> 8</number> Powers of natural guardian.
<section><tid>1128375</tid>
<number>1</number>The natural guardian of a Hindu  
minor has power, subject to the provisions of this section, to do all 
acts which are necessary or reasonable and proper for the benefit of 
the minor or for the realization, protection or benefit of the minor' s 
estate; but the guardian can in no case bind the minor by a personal 
covenant.

</section>

<section><tid>1284096</tid>
<number>2</number>The natural guardian shall not, without the previous permis- 
sion of the court,-

<subsection><tid>1443016</tid>
<number>a</number>mortgage or charge, or transfer by sale, gift, exchange 
or otherwise, any part of the immovable property of the 
minor, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>968323</tid>
<number>b</number>lease any part of such property for a term exceeding 
five years or for a term extending more than one year beyond 
the date on which the minor will attain majority.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1761633</tid>
<number>3</number>Any disposal of immovable property by a natural guardian, in 
contravention of sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) is voidable at the 
instance of the minor or any person claiming under him.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>186</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>287173</tid>
<number>4</number>No court shall grant permission to the natural guardian to 
do any of the acts mentioned in sub- section (2) except in case of 
necessity or for an evident advantage to the minor.

</section>

<section><tid>587656</tid>
<number>5</number>The Guardians and Wards Act, <year>1890</year>, (8 of <year>1890</year>) shall apply, to 
and in respect of an application for obtaining the permission of the 
court under sub- section (2) in all respects as if it were an 
application for obtaining the permission of the court under section 29 
of that Act, and in particular-

<subsection><tid>1642886</tid>
<number>a</number>proceedings in connection with the application shall be 
deemed to be proceedings under that Act within the meaning of 
section 4A thereof;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>828433</tid>
<number>b</number>the court shall observe the procedure and have the 
powers specified in sub- sections (2), (3) and (4) of section 
 31 of that Act; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>303071</tid>
<number>c</number>an appeal shall lie from an order of the court refusing 
permission to the natural guardian to do any of the acts 
mentioned in sub- section (2) of this section to the court to 
which appeals ordinarily lie from the decisions of that 
court.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>352331</tid>
<number>6</number>In this section," court" means the city civil court or a 
district court or a court empowered under section 4A of the Guardians 
and Wards Act, <year>1890</year>, within the local limits of whose jurisdiction the 
 (8 of <year>1890</year>) immovable property in respect of which the application is 
made is situate, and where the immovable property is situate within 
the jurisdiction of more than one such court, means the court within 
the local limits of whose jurisdiction any portion of the property is 
situate.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>961362</tid>
<number> 9</number> Testamentary guardians and their powers.
<section><tid>1180584</tid>
<number>1</number>A Hindu father  
entitled to act as the natural guardian of his minor legitimate 
children may, by will, appoint a guardian for any of them in respect 
of the minor' s person or in respect of the minor' s property (other  
  than the undivided interest referred to in section 12) or in respect 
of both.

</section>

<section><tid>148023</tid>
<number>2</number>An appointment made under sub- section (1) shall have no 
effect if the father predeceases the mother, but shall revive if the 
mother dies without appointing, by will, any person as guardian.

</section>

<section><tid>833178</tid>
<number>3</number>A Hindu widow entitled to act as the natural guardian of her 
minor legitimate children, and a Hindu mother entitled to act as the 
natural guardian of her minor legitimate children by reason of the 
fact that the father has become disentitled to act as such, may, by 
will, appoint a guardian for any of them in respect of the minor' s

<pagefootnote><pagenum>187</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

person or in respect of the minor' s property (other than the undivided  
  interest referred to in section 12) or in respect of both.


</section>

<section><tid>982907</tid>
<number>4</number>A Hindu mother entitled to act as the natural guardian of 
her minor illegitimate children may, by will, appoint a guardian for 
any of them in respect of the minor' s person or in respect of the 
minor' s property or in respect of both.

</section>

<section><tid>1219948</tid>
<number>5</number>The guardian so appointed by will has the right to act as 
the minor' s guardian after the death of the minor' s father or mother, 
as the case may be, and to exercise all the rights of a natural 
guardian under this Act to such extent and subject to such 
restrictions, if any, as are specified in this Act and in the will.

</section>

<section><tid>1734925</tid>
<number>6</number>The right of the guardian so appointed by will shall, where 
the minor is a girl, cease on her marriage.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>10</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Incapacity of minor to act as guardian of property.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1807002</tid>
<number>10</number>Incapacity of minor to act as guardian of property. A minor 
shall be incompetent to act as guardian of the property of any minor.


</article>



<article><tid>127967</tid>
<number>11</number>De facto guardian not to deal with minor' s property. After the 
commencement of this Act, no person shall be entitled to dispose of, 
or deal with, the property of a Hindu minor merely on the ground of 
his or her being the de facto guardian of the minor.


</article>



<article><tid>1434877</tid>
<number>12</number>Guardian not to be appointed for minor' s undivided interest in 
joint family property. Where a minor has an undivided interest in 
joint family property and the property is under the management of an 
adult member of the family, no guardian shall be appointed for the 
minor in respect of such undivided interest:
Provided that nothing in this section shall be deemed to a affect 
the jurisdiction of a High Court to appoint a guardian in respect of 
such interest.



</article>



<article><tid>94208</tid>
<number> 13</number> Welfare of minor to be paramount consideration.
<section><tid>1255190</tid>
<number>1</number>In the  
appointment or declaration of any person as guardian of a Hindu minor 
by a court, the welfare of the minor shall be the paramount 
consideration.

</section>

<section><tid>1710735</tid>
<number>2</number>No, person shall be entitled to the guardianship by virtue 
of the provisions of this Act or of any law relating to guardianship 
in marriage among Hindus, if the court is of opinion that his or her 
guardianship will not be for the welfare of the minor.


</section>

</article>



 </act>