<act><tid>266568</tid>
<title>THE INCHEK TYRES LIMITED AND NATIONAL RUBBERMANUFACTURERS LIMITED 
 (NATIONALISATION) ACT, <year>1984</year></title>

ACT NO. 17 OF <year>1984</year>
[ 31st March, <year>1984</year>.]

An Act to provide for the acquisition and transfer of the 
undertakings of the Inchek Tyres Limited and the National Rubber Manu- 
facturers Limited, with a view to securing the proper management of 
such undertakings so as to subserve the interests of the general 
public by ensuring the continued manufacture, production and 
distribution of tyres, tubes and other rubber goods which are 
essential to the needs of the economy of the country and for matters 
connected therewith or incidental thereto.

WHEREAS the Inchek Tyres Limited and the National Rubber Manufacturers 
Limited had been engaged in the manufacture, production and 
distribution of articles mentioned in the First Schedule to the 
Industries (Development and Regulation) Act, <year>1951</year> (65 of <year>1951</year>), 
namely, tyres, tubes and other rubber goods;

AND WHEREAS the management of the undertakings of the Inchek Tyres 
Limited and the management of the undertakings of the National Rubber 
Manufacturers Limited were taken over by the Central Government under 
the provisions of the Industries (Development and Regulation) Act, 
 <year>1951</year> (65 of <year>1951</year>);

AND WHEREAS for the purpose of securing the optimum utilisation of the 
available facilities for the manufacture, production and distribution 
of tyres, tubes and other rubber goods by the undertakings of the two 
companies, investment of a large amount is necessary;

AND WHEREAS it is necessary to acquire the undertakings of the Inchek 
Tyres Limited and the National Rubber Manufacturers Limited to enable 
the Central Government to have such investments made and to ensure 
that the interests of the general public are served by the 
continuance, by the undertakings of the companies, of the manufacture, 
production and distribution of the aforesaid articles which are 
essential to the needs of the economy of the country;


<pagefootnote><pagenum>117</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty- fifth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>708038</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>590135</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Inchek Tyres Limited and National Rubber Manufacturers Limited 
 (Nationalisation) Act, <year>1984</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1604907</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 14th day of 
February, <year>1984</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>482553</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>703368</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day"' means the 14th day of February <year>1984</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>1599245</tid>
<number>b</number>" Commissioner" means the Commissioner of Payments appointed under 
section 15;

</section>

<section><tid>1295632</tid>
<number>c</number>" existing Government company" means a Government company which 
is carrying on business on the appointed day;

</section>

<section><tid>1177284</tid>
<number>d</number>" new Government company" means a Government company formed and 
registered on or after the appointed day;

</section>

<section><tid>293488</tid>
<number>e</number>" notification" means a notification published in the Official 
Gazette;

</section>

<section><tid>930112</tid>
<number>f</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>934327</tid>
<number>g</number>" specified date", in relation to any provision of this Act, means 
such date as the Central Government may, by notification, specify for 
the purposes of that provision, and different dates may be specified 
for different provisions of this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1093926</tid>
<number>h</number>" two companies" means the Inchek Tyres Limited and the National 
Rubber Manufacturers Limited, being companies as defined in the 
Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), and having their registered offices 
at" Leslie House", 19 Jawaharlal Nehru Road, Calcutta- 700013;

</section>

<section><tid>1605959</tid>
<number>i</number>words and expressions used herein and not defined but defined in 
the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), shall have the meanings 
respectively assigned to them in that Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>118</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>125775</tid>
<number>3</number>Transfer to, and vesting in, the Central Government of the 
undertakings of the two companies. On the appointed day, the 
undertakings of each of the two companies, and the right, title and 
interest of each of the two companies in relation to its undertakings, 
shall, by virtue of the Act, stand transferred to, and shall vest in, 
the Central Government.


</article>



<article><tid>381645</tid>
<number> 5</number> Companies to be liable for certain prior liabilities.
<section><tid>348202</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Every liability, other than the liability specified in sub- section 
 (2), of each of the two companies in respect of any period prior to 
the appointed day, shall be the liability of the concerned company and 
shall be enforceable against it and not against the Central 
Government, or where the undertakings of the two companies vest in an 
existing, or a new, Government Company, against such Government 
company.

</section>

<section><tid>751154</tid>
<number>2</number>Any liability arising in respect of materials supplied to 
either of the two companies after the management of its undertakings 
had been taken over by the Central Government, shall, on and from the 
appointed day, be the liability of the Central Government or of the 
existing, or new, Government company aforesaid, and shall be 
discharged by that Government or, as the case may be, the existing, or 
new, Government company, as and when repayment for such supplies 
becomes due and payable.

</section>

<section><tid>602615</tid>
<number>3</number>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that-

<subsection><tid>1126190</tid>
<number>a</number>save as otherwise expressly provided in this section or in 
any other provision of this Act, no liability, other than the 
liability specified in sub- section (2), of either of the two companies 
in relation to its undertakings in respect of any period prior to the 
appointed day shall be enforceable against the Central Government, or, 
where the undertakings of the two companies vest in an existing, or a 
new, Government company, against such Government company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>802408</tid>
<number>b</number>no award, decree or order of any court, tribunal or other 
authority in relation to the undertakings of either of the two 
companies, passed on or after the appointed day, in respect of any 
matter, claim or dispute, not being a matter, claim or dispute in 
relation to any matter referred to in sub- section (2), which arose 
before that day, shall be enforceable against the Central Government, 
or where the undertakings of the two

<pagefootnote><pagenum>120</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

companies vest in an existing, or a new, Government company, 
against such Government company;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1240035</tid>
<number>c</number>no liability incurred by either of the two companies before 
the appointed day, for the contravention of any provision of law for 
the time being in force, shall be enforceable against the, Central 
Government, or, where the undertakings of the two companies vest in 
an existing, or a new, Government company, against such Government 
company.
CHAP

PAYMENT OF AMOUNTS

CHAPTER III

PAYMENT OF AMOUNTS




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>325001</tid>
<number>8</number>Payment of amount. For the transfer to, and vesting in, the 
Central Government, under section 3, of the undertakings of each of 
the two companies, and the right, title and interest of each of the 
two companies in relation to its undertakings, there shall be paid by 
the Central Government to each of the two companies, in cash and in 
the manner specified in Chapter VI, amount equal to the amount 
specified against the name of such company in the First Schedule.


</article>



<article><tid>781231</tid>
<number> 10</number> Management, etc., of the undertakings of the two companies. 
The general superintendence, direction, control and management of the 
affairs and business of the undertakings of each of the two companies, 
the Tight, title and interest in relation to which have vested in the 
Central Government under section 3, shall,-
<section><tid>853338</tid>
<number>a</number>where a direction has been given by the Central Government under 
sub- section (1) of section 6, vest on and from the date specified in 
such direction, in the existing Government company specified therein; 
or

</section>

<section><tid>1898326</tid>
<number>b</number>where a declaration has been made under sub- section (1) of section 
7, vest, on and from the date of such declaration, in the new 
Government company specified therein;
and thereupon the existing, or new, Government company so specified, 
shall be entitled to exercise, to the exclusion of all other persons 
all such powers and do all such things as either, or both, of the two 
companies, is or are, authorised to exercise and do in relation to its 
or their undertakings.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>122</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>133297</tid>
<number> 11</number> Duty of persons in charge of management of undertakings of 
the two companies to deliver all assets, etc.
<section><tid>1822227</tid>
<number>1</number>On the vesting of  
the management of the undertakings of the two companies in an 
existing, or a new, Government company, all persons in charge of the 
management of the undertakings of either of the two companies 
immediately before such vesting shall be bound to deliver to such 
Government company, all assets, books of account, registers and other 
documents in their custody relating to the undertakings.

</section>

<section><tid>611543</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may issue such directions as it may 
deem desirable in the circumstances of the case to the existing, or 
new, Government company and such Government company may also, if it is 
considered necessary so to do, apply to the Central Government at any 
time for instructions as to the manner in which the management of the 
undertakings of the two companies shall be conducted or in relation to 
any other matter arising in the course of such management.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>206187</tid>
<number> 12</number> Duty of persons account for assets, etc., in their 
possession.
<section><tid>1150412</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person who has, on the appointed day, in his  
possession or under his control any assets, books, documents or other 
papers relating to the undertakings owned by either of the two 
companies, which have vested in the Central Government or in an 
existing, or a new, Government company under this Act, shall be liable 
to account for the said assets, books, documents and other papers to 
the Central Government or the existing, or new, Government company, as 
the case may be, and shall deliver them to the Central Government or 
the existing, or new, Government company or to such person or persons 
as the Central Government or the existing, or new, Government company 
may specify in this behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>944305</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government or the Government company aforesaid 
may take, or cause to be taken, all necessary steps for securing 
possession of the undertakings of the two companies which have vested 
in the Central Government or the Government company under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1144743</tid>
<number>3</number>The two companies shall, within such period as the Central 
Government may allow in this behalf, furnish to that Government a 
complete inventory of all their properties and assets, as on the 
appointed day, pertaining to the undertakings which have vested in the 
Central Government under section 3, and, for this purpose, the Central 
Government or the Government company aforesaid shall afford to the two 
companies all reasonable facilities.
CHAP

PROVISIONS RELATING TO EMPLOYEES OF THE TWO COMPANIES

CHAPTER V

PROVISIONS RELATING TO EMPLOYEES OF THE TWO COMPANIES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1790715</tid>
<number> 13</number> Continuance of employees.
<section><tid>1851902</tid>
<number>1</number>Every person who has been,  
immediately before the appointed day, employed in any undertaking of 
either of the two companies shall become,-

<subsection><tid>1324411</tid>
<number>a</number>on and from the appointed day, an employee of the Central 
Government, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1391466</tid>
<number>b</number>where the undertakings of the two companies are directed, under 
section 6 or under section 7, to vest, in an existing, or a new, 
Government company, an employee of such Government company on and from 
the date of such vesting,
and shall hold office or service under the Central Government or the 
existing, or new, Government company, as the case may be, with the 
rights and privileges as to pension, gratuity and other matters, 
admissible to him immediately


<pagefootnote><pagenum>123</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

before the appointed day, as modified by the Memorandum of Settlement 
signed by the representatives of the management and the employees of 
each of the two companies on the 10th day of February, <year>1984</year>, and shall 
continue to do so unless and until his employment under the Central 
Government or the existing or new, Government company, as the case may 
be, is duly terminated or until his remuneration and other conditions 
of service are duly altered by the Central Government, or the 
existing, or new, Government company, as the case may be.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>947462</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial Disputes 
Act, <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>), or in any other law for the time being in 
force, the transfer of the services of any officer or other person 
employed in any undertaking of either of the two companies, to the, 
Central Government or the existing, or new, Government company, shall 
not entitle such officer or other employee to any compensation under 
this Act or any other law for the time being in force and no such 
claim shall be entertained by any court, tribunal or other authority.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1803909</tid>
<number> 14</number> Provident fund and other funds.
<section><tid>1146000</tid>
<number>1</number>Where either of the two  
companies has established a provident fund, superannuation, welfare or 
other fund for the benefit of the persons employed in any of its 
undertakings, the moneys relatable to the officers or other employees 
whose services have become transferred by or under this Act to the 
Central Government or an existing, or a new, Government company shall, 
out of the moneys standing, on the appointed day, to the credit of 
such provident fund, super- annuation, welfare or other fund, stand 
transferred to, and shall vest in, the Central Government or the 
existing, or new, Government company, as the care may be.

</section>

<section><tid>368444</tid>
<number>2</number>The moneys which stand transferred under sub- section (1) to 
the Central Government or the existing, or new, Government company, as 
the case may be, shall be dealt with by that Government or the 
existing, or new, Government company in such manner as may be 
prescribed.
CHAP

COMMISSIONER OF PAYMENTS

CHAPTER VI

COMMISSIONER OF PAYMENTS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>330234</tid>
<number> 15</number> Appointment of Commissioner of Payments.
<section><tid>62817</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government shall, for the purpose of disbursing the amounts payable 
under sections 8 and 9 to each of the two companies, by notification, 
appoint a Commissioner of Payments.

</section>

<section><tid>1699082</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may appoint such other persons as it 
may think fit to assist the Commissioner and thereupon the 
Commissioner may authorise one or more of such persons also to 
exercise all or any of the powers exercisable by him under this Act 
and different persons may be authorised to exercise different powers.

</section>

<section><tid>1386180</tid>
<number>3</number>Any person authorised by the Commissioner to exercise any of 
the powers exercisable by the Commissioner may exercise those powers 
in the same manner and with the same effect as if they have been 
conferred on that person directly by this Act and not by way of 
authorisation.

</section>

<section><tid>1998993</tid>
<number>4</number>The salaries and allowances of the Commissioner and other 
persons appointed under this section shall be defraved out of the 
Consolidated Fund of India.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>124</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>509299</tid>
<number> 16</number> Payment by Central Government to the Commissioner.
<section><tid>1894143</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Central Government shall, within thirty days from the specified 1 date, 
pay in cash to the Commissioner, for payment to each of the two 
companies,-

<subsection><tid>1355366</tid>
<number>a</number>an amount equal to the amount specified against the name of such 
company in the First Schedule; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>63620</tid>
<number>b</number>an amount equal to the amounts payable to each of the two company 
in the First schedule; and

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1125061</tid>
<number>2</number>A deposit account shall be opened by the Central Government 
in favour of the Commissioner in the Public Account of India and every 
amount paid under this Act to the Commissioner shall be deposited by 
him to the credit of the said deposit account and the said deposit 
account shall be operated by the Commissioner.

</section>

<section><tid>223140</tid>
<number>3</number>Separate records shall be maintained by the Commissioner in 
respect of the undertakings of each of the two companies in relation 
to which payments have been made to him under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>503684</tid>
<number>4</number>Interest accruing on the amount standing to the credit of the 
deposit account referred to in sub- section (2) shall enure to the 
benefit of the two companies.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>186029</tid>
<number> 17</number> Certain powers of Central Government or existing, or new, 
Government company.
<section><tid>590514</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government or the existing, or  
new, Government company, as the case may be, shall be entitled to 
receive up to the specified date, to the exclusion of all other 
persons, any money due to either of the two companies in relation to 
its undertakings which have vested in the Central Government or the 
existing, or now, Government company, as the case may be, and realised 
after the appointed day notwithstanding that the realisation pertains 
to a period prior to the appointed day.

</section>

<section><tid>205233</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government, or the existing, or new, Government 
company, as the case may be, may make a claim to the Commissioner with 
regard to every payment made by it after the appointed day, for 
discharging any liability of either of the two companies, not being 
any liability specified in sub- section (2) of section 5, in relation 
to any period prior to the appointed day, and every such claim shall 
have priority, in accordance with the priorities attaching, under this 
Act, to the matter in relation to which such liability has been 
discharged by the Central Government or the existing, or new, 
Government company.

</section>

<section><tid>1381332</tid>
<number>3</number>Save as otherwise provided in this Act, the liabilities of 
either of the two companies in respect of any transaction prior to the 
appointed day which have not been discharged on or before the 
specified date shall be the liabilities of the respective company.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>932439</tid>
<number> 19</number> Priority of claims. The claims arising out of the matters 
specified in the Second Schedule shall have priorities in accordance 
with the following principles, namely:-
<section><tid>1646836</tid>
<number>a</number>Category I shall have precedence over all other categories and 
Category II shall have precedence over Category III, and so on;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>125</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1. 12. <year>1984</year>: Vide Notification. No. S. O. 895 (E), dt. 30. 12. <year>1984</year>

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number> 1. 4. <year>1985</year>: Vide Notification. No. S. O. 24 (E), dt. 17. 1. <year>1985</year>.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1819486</tid>
<number>b</number>the claims specified in each of the categories shall rank equally 
and be paid in full, but, if the amount is insufficient to meet such 
claims in full, they shall abate in equal proportions and be paid 
accordingly; and

</section>

<section><tid>272229</tid>
<number>c</number>the question of discharging any liability with regard to a matter 
specified in a lower category shall arise only if a surplus is left 
after meeting all the liabilities specified in the immediately higher 
category.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>400513</tid>
<number> 20</number> Examination of claims.
<section><tid>784581</tid>
<number>1</number>On receipt of the claims made  
under section 18, the Commissioner shall arrange the claims in the 
order of priorities specified in the Second Schedule and examine the 
same in accordance with such order.

</section>

<section><tid>1778313</tid>
<number>2</number>If, on examination of the claims, the Commissioner is of 
opinion that the amount paid to him under this Act is not sufficient to 
meet the liabilities specified in any lower category, he shall not be 
required to examine the claims in respect of such lower category.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1490934</tid>
<number> 21</number> Admission or rejection of claims.
<section><tid>1464439</tid>
<number>1</number>After examining the  
claims with reference to the priorities specified in the Second 
Schedule, the Commissioner shall fix a date on or before which every 
claimant shall file the proof of his claim.

</section>

<section><tid>311422</tid>
<number>2</number>Not less than fourteen days' notice of the date so fixed 
shall be given by advertisement in one issue of any daily newspaper in 
the English language having circulation in the major part of the 
country and in one issue of any daily newspaper in such regional 
language as the Commissioner may consider suitable, and every such 
notice shall call upon the claimant to file the proof of his claim 
with the Commissioner within the period specified in the adver- 
tisement.

</section>

<section><tid>321391</tid>
<number>3</number>Every claimant who fails to file the proof of his claim 
within the period specified by the Commissioner shall be excluded 
from the disbursement made by the Commissioner.

</section>

<section><tid>427961</tid>
<number>4</number>The Commissioner shall, after such investigation as may, in 
his opinion, be necessary and after giving the concerned company an 
opportunity of refuting the claim and after giving the claimant a 
reasonable opportunity of being heard, admit or reject by order in 
writing the claim in whole or in part.

</section>

<section><tid>733150</tid>
<number>5</number>The Commissioner shall have the power to regulate his own 
procedure in all matters arising out of the discharge of his functions, 
including the place or places at which he may hold his sittings and 
shall, for the purpose of making any investigation under this Act, have 
the same powers as are vested in a civil court under the Code of Civil 
Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>), while trying a suit, in respect of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>593628</tid>
<number>a</number>the summoning and enforcing the attendance of any witness and 
examining him on oath;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1475796</tid>
<number>b</number>the discovery and production of any document or other material 
object producible as evidence;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>520504</tid>
<number>c</number>the reception of evidence on affidavits;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1792064</tid>
<number>d</number>the issuing of any commission for the examination of witnesses.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1103973</tid>
<number>6</number>Any investigation before the Commissioner shall be deemed to 
be a judicial proceeding within the meaning of sections 193 and 228 of 
the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>) and the Commissioner shall be 
deemed to be a civil court for the purposes of section 195 and Chapter 
XXVI of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>).

<pagefootnote><pagenum>126</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>189118</tid>
<number>7</number>A claimant who is dissatisfied with the decision of the 
commissioner may prefer an appeal against such decision to the 
principal civil court of original jurisdiction within the local limits 
of whose jurisdiction the registered office of the concerned company 
is situated:
Provided that where a person who is a Judge of a High Court is 
appointed, to be the Commissioner such appeal shall lie to the High 
Court exercising jurisdiction over the place in which the registered 
office of the concerned company is situated and such appeal shall be 
heard and disposed of by not less than two Judges of that High Court.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1919869</tid>
<number>22</number>Disbursement of money by Commissioner. After admitting a 
claim under this Act, the amount due in respect of such claim shall be 
paid by the Commissioner to the person or persons to whom such amount 
is due, and on such payment, the liability of each of the two 
companies in respect of such claim shall stand discharged.


</article>



<article><tid>939047</tid>
<number> 23</number> Disbursement of amounts to the companies.
<section><tid>757665</tid>
<number>1</number>If, out of the  
moneys paid to him in relation to the undertakings of either of the 
two companies, there is a balance left after meeting the liabilities 
as specified in the Second Schedule, the Commissioner shall disburse 
such balance to the concerned company.

</section>

<section><tid>216921</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the possession of any machinery, equipment or other 
property has vested in the Central Government or the existing, or new, 
Government company under this Act, but such machinery, equipment or 
other property does not belong to either of the two companies, it 
shall be lawful for the Central Government or the existing, or new, 
Government company, as the case may be, to continue to possess such 
machinery or equipment or other property on the same terms and 
conditions under which they were possessed by either of the two 
companies immediately before the appointed day.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>517037</tid>
<number>24</number>Undisbursed or unclaimed amount to be deposited with the 
general revenue account. Any money paid to the Commissioner which 
remains undisbursed or unclaimed on the date immediately preceding 
the date on which the office of the Commissioner is finally wound up, 
shall be, transferred by the Commissioner, before his office is 
finally wound up, to the general revenue account of the Central 
Government; but a claim to any money so transferred may he preferred 
to the Central Government by the person entitled to such payment and 
shall be dealt with as if such transfer had not been made, and the 
order, if any, for the payment of the claim being treated as an order 
for the refund of revenue.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER VII

MISCELLANEOUS



</article>



<article><tid>1104190</tid>
<number>25</number>Act to have over- riding effect. The provisions of this Act 
shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith 
contained in any other law for the time being in force or in any 
instrument having effect by virtue of any law, other than this Act, or 
in any decree or order of any court, tribunal or other authority.


</article>



<article><tid>944527</tid>
<number> 26</number> Contracts to cease to have effect unless ratified by the 
Central Government or existing, or New, Government company. Every 
contract entered into by either of the two companies in relation to 
any of its undertakings which has vested in the Central Government 
under section 3 for any service, sale or supply, and in force 
immediately before the appointed, day, shall, on and from the expiry 
of a period of one hundred and eighty days from such day, cease to 
have effect unless such contract is, before the expiry of that period, 
ratified, in writing, by the Central Government or the existing, or 
new, Government company and in ratifying such contract, the Central 
Government or the existing, or new, Government company may make such 
alteration or modification therein as it may think fit:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>127</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Provided that the Central Government or the existing, or new, 
Government company shall not omit to ratify a contract and shall not 
make any alteration or modification in a contract-

<section><tid>503671</tid>
<number>a</number>unless it is satisfied that such contract is unduly onerous, or 
has been entered into in bad faith, or is detrimental to the interests 
of the Central Government or such Government company; and

</section>

<section><tid>375552</tid>
<number>b</number>except after giving the parties to the contract a reasonable oppor- 
tunity of being beard and except after recording in writing its 
reasons for refusal to ratify the contract or for making any 
alteration or modification therein.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1348321</tid>
<number> 27</number> Penalties. Any person who,-
<section><tid>25670</tid>
<number>a</number>having in his possession, custody or control any property forming 
part of any undertaking of either of the two companies, wrongfully 
withholds such property from the Central Government or the existing, 
or new, Government company; or

</section>

<section><tid>1294877</tid>
<number>b</number>wrongfully obtains possession of, or retains, any property forming 
part of any undertaking of either of the two companies; or

</section>

<section><tid>315062</tid>
<number>c</number>wilfully withholds or fails to furnish to the Central Government or 
the existing, or new, Government company or any person or body of 
persons specified by that Government or Government company, any 
document relating to such undertaking, which may be in his posses- 
sion, custody or control; or

</section>

<section><tid>64099</tid>
<number>d</number>fails to deliver to the Central Government or the existing, or 
new, Government company, as the case may be, or any person or body of 
persons specified by that Government, or Government company, any 
assets, books of account, registers or other documents in his 
possession, custody or control, relating to the undertakings of either 
of the two companies; or

</section>

<section><tid>1322557</tid>
<number>e</number>wrongfully removes or destroys any property forming part of any 
undertaking of either of the two companies or prefers any claim which 
he knows or has reasonable cause to believe to be false or grossly 
inaccurate.
shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
two years, or with fine which may extend to ten thousand rupees, or 
with both.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>379644</tid>
<number> 28</number> Offences by companies.
<section><tid>1664302</tid>
<number>1</number>Where an offence under this Act  
has been committed by a company, every person who, at the time the 
offence was committed, was in charge of, and was responsible to, the 
company for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as the 
company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be 
liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly-:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the 
offence was committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised 
all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.


</section>

<section><tid>923943</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where 
any offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is 
proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or 
connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any 
director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such 
director, manager, secretary or other

<pagefootnote><pagenum>128</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

officer shall be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be 
liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.

Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,--


<subsection><tid>1513672</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm or other 
association of individuals; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>894519</tid>
<number>b</number>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner in the firm.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1152681</tid>
<number> 29</number> Protection of action taken in good faith.
<section><tid>1907944</tid>
<number>1</number>No suit,  
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central 
Government or the existing, or new, Government company or any officer 
or other employee of that Government or the Government company or any 
person authorised by that Government or Government company for 
anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this 
Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1693728</tid>
<number>2</number>No suit, or other legal proceeding, shall lie against the 
Central Government or the existing, or new, Government company, or any 
officer or other employee of that Government or Government company or 
any person authorised by that Government or Government company for any 
damage caused or likely to be caused by anything which is in good 
faith done or intended to be done under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1602281</tid>
<number> 30</number> Delegation of powers.
<section><tid>1139857</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification, direct that all or any of the powers exercisable by it 
under this Act, other than the powers conferred by this section, 
section 31 or section 32, may also be exercised by such person or 
persons as may be specified in the notification.

</section>

<section><tid>1306590</tid>
<number>2</number>Whenever any delegation of power is made under sub- section 
 (1), the person to whom such power has been delegated shall act under 
the direction, control and supervision of the Central Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1312323</tid>
<number> 31</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>187850</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification, make rules for carrying out the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1255421</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>911862</tid>
<number>a</number>the time within which, and the manner in which, an intimation 
referred to in sub- section (3) of section 4 shall be given;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1373691</tid>
<number>b</number>the manner in which the moneys in any provident fund or other fund 
referred to in section 14 shall be dealt with;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1634273</tid>
<number>c</number>any other matter which is required to be, or may be, prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1711991</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act 
shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House 
of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty 
days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
both Houses agree that the rule should not he made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1066753</tid>
<number> 33</number> Repeal and saving.
<section><tid>1349954</tid>
<number>1</number>The Inchek Tyres Limited and National  
Rubber Manufacturers Limited (Nationalisation) Ordinance, <year>1984</year> (4 of  
  <year>1984</year>), is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>296069</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action 
taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or 
taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.


</section>

</article>



 </act>