<act><tid>65955</tid>
<title>THE MADHYA PRADESH STATE LEGISLATURE (DELEGATION OF POWERS) ACT, <year>1993</year></title>

NO. 9 OF <year>1993</year> 
[ 31st March, <year>1993</year>.]
An Act to confer on the President the power of the Legislature of the 
State of Madhya Pradesh to make laws.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- fourth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--




<article><tid>1274221</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Madhya Pradesh State 
Legislature (Delegation of Powers) Act, <year>1993</year>.

</article>



<article><tid>1972747</tid>
<number>2</number>Definition. In this Act," Proclamation" means the Proclamation 
issued on the 15th day of December, <year>1992</year>, under article 356 of the 
Constitution, by the President, and published with the notification of 
the Government of India in the Ministry of Home Affairs No. G. S. R. 
926 (E) of the said date.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</article>



<article><tid>431344</tid>
<number> 3</number> Conferment on the President of the power of the State 
Legislature to make laws.
<section><tid>994553</tid>
<number>1</number>The power of the Legislature of the  
State of Madhya Pradesh to make laws, which has been declared by the 
Proclamation to be exercisable by or under the authority of 
Parliament, is hereby conferred on the President.

</section>

<section><tid>1281543</tid>
<number>2</number>In exercise of the said power, the President may, from time 
to time, whether Parliament is or is not in session, enact, as 
President' s Act, a Bill containing such provisions as he considers 
necessary:
Provided that before enacting any such Act, the President shall, 
whenever he considers it practicable to do so, consult a Committee 
constituted for the purpose, consisting of twenty members of the House 
of the People nominated by the Speaker and ten members of the Council 
of States nominated by the Chairman.


</section>

<section><tid>498130</tid>
<number>3</number>Every Act enacted by the President under sub- section (2) 
shall as soon as may be after enactment, be laid before each House of 
Parliament.

</section>

<section><tid>1300756</tid>
<number>4</number>Either House of Parliament may, by resolution passed within 
thirty days from the date on which the Act has been laid before it 
under sub- section (3), which period may be comprised in one session or 
in two successive sessions, direct any modifications to be made in the 
Act and if the modifications are agreed to by the other House of 
Parliament during the session in which the Act has been so laid before 
it or the session succeeding, such modifications shall be given effect 
to by the President by enacting an amending Act under sub- section (2):
Provided that nothing in this sub- section shall affect the 
validity of the Act or of any action taken thereunder before it is so 
amended.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1274221</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Rajasthan State 
Legislature (Delegation of Powers) Act, <year>1993</year>.

</article>



<article><tid>1972747</tid>
<number>2</number>Definition. In this Act," Proclamation" means the Proclamation 
issued on the 15th day of December, <year>1992</year>, under article 356 of the 
Constitution, by the President, and published with the notification of 
the Government of India in the Ministry of Home Affairs No. G. S. R. 
930 (E) of the said date.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</article>



<article><tid>431344</tid>
<number> 3</number> Conferment on the President of the power of the State 
Legislature to make laws.
<section><tid>994553</tid>
<number>1</number>The power of the Legislature of the  
State of Rajasthan to make laws, which has been declared by the 
Proclamation to be exercisable by or under the authority of 
Parliament, is hereby conferred on the President.

</section>

<section><tid>1281543</tid>
<number>2</number>In exercise of the said power, the President may, from time 
to time, whether Parliament is or is not in session, enact, as 
President' s Act, a Bill containing such provisions as he considers 
necessary:
Provided that before enacting any such Act, the President shall, 
whenever he considers it practicable to do so, consult a Committee 
constituted for the purpose, consisting of twenty members of the House 
of the People nominated by the Speaker and ten members of the Council 
of States nominated by the Chairman.


</section>

<section><tid>498130</tid>
<number>3</number>Every Act enacted by the President under sub- section (2) 
shall, as soon as may be after enactment, be laid before each House of 
Parliament.

</section>

<section><tid>1300756</tid>
<number>4</number>Either House of Parliament may, by resolution passed within 
thirty days from the date on which the Act has been laid before it 
under sub- section (3), which period may be comprised in one session or 
in two successive sessions, direct any modifications to be made in the 
Act and if the modifications are agreed to by the other House of 
Parliament during the session in which the Act has been so laid before 
it or the session succeeding, such modifications shall be given effect 
to by the President by enacting and amending Act under sub- section 
 (2):
Provided that nothing in this sub- section shall affect the 
validity of the Act or of any action taken thereunder before it is so 
amended.



</section>

</article>



 </act>