<act><tid>644534</tid>
<title>THE PAYMENT OF TAXES (TRANSFER OF PROPERTY) ACT, <year>1949</year></title>

ACT NO. 22 OF <year>1949</year> 
[ 22nd April, <year>1949</year>.] W
An Act to make provision for the payment of taxes before transfers of 
property are registered in certain cases.




<article><tid>395939</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>300311</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Payment  
of Taxes (Transfer of Property) Act, <year>1949</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>642723</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>709546</tid>
<number> 2</number> Application of Act. This Act shall apply to any person--
<section><tid>16326</tid>
<number>i</number>who, on account of the setting up of the Dominions of 
India and Pakistan, or on account of civil disturbances 
or the fear of such disturbances, leaves or has, since 
the 14th day of August, <year>1947</year>, left any place in 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> India] for any place outside India, or who, since 
the said date, has been residing in any place outside 
India; or

</section>

<section><tid>163780</tid>
<number>ii</number>who, in the opinion of any of the Income- tax 
authorities specified in sub- section (1) of section 5 
of the Indian Income- tax Act, <year>1922</year> (11 of <year>1922</year>), or a 
Custodian of Evacuee Property or a Collector, is likely 
to leave <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> India] with the intention of settling in 
any place outside <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> India], and in respect of whom a 
declaration that he is a person to whom this Act 
applies has been received from any such Income- tax 
authority, Custodian of Evacuee Property or Collector 
by the registering officer of the area in which any 
property belonging to such person is situate.
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>523159</tid>
<number> 3</number> Payment of taxes before registration of documents.
<section><tid>1728871</tid>
<number>1</number>Where  
any document required to be registered under the provisions of clause 
 (a), clause (b), clause (c) or clause (e) of sub- section (1) of 
section 17 of the Indian Registration Act, <year>1908</year> (16 of <year>1908</year>), 
purports

<pagefootnote><pagenum>618</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" except the State of Jammu and Kashmir", omitted by Act 
41 of <year>1954</year>, s. 2 and Sch. 
2 Subs. by s. 2 and Sch., ibid., for" the States". 
3 The Explanation added by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, omitted by s. 2 and 
Sch., ibid.

Extended to Dadra and Nagar Haveli, Goa, Daman and Diu, and 
Pondicharry (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1963</year>)- by Reg. 3 of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 (1) and Sch.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

to transfer, assign, limit or extinguish any right, title or interest 
in any property, other than agricultural land, belonging to any person 
to whom this Act applies, no registering officer appointed under the 
said Act shall register any such document, unless it is certified by 
the Income- tax Officer of the area in which the property is situate in 
respect of the person whose right, title or interest in the property 
is to be so transferred, assigned, limited or extinguished under the 
terms of the document that--


<subsection><tid>13618</tid>
<number>a</number>such person is not liable to assessment or taxation 
under the Indian Income- tax Act, <year>1922</year> (11 of <year>1922</year>), 
the Excess Profits Tax Act, <year>1940</year> (15 of <year>1940</year>), or the 
Business Profits Tax Act, <year>1947</year> (21 of <year>1947</year>); or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1916425</tid>
<number>b</number>such person has either paid or made satisfactory 
provision for the payment of all existing or 
anticipated liabilities under any of the Acts specified 
in clause (a) of this sub- section; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>927437</tid>
<number>c</number>the Income- tax Officer is otherwise satisfied that the 
registration of the document will not prejudicially 
affect the recovery of all existing or anticipated 
liabilities referred to in clause (b) of this sub- 
section.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1018550</tid>
<number>2</number>Every Income- tax Officer refusing to issue a certificate 
under the provisions of sub- section (1) shall make an order of refusal 
and record his reasons therefor and, on application made by any person 
claiming to be affected by such order, shall, subject to the payment 
of such fee as may be prescribed, furnish him with a copy of the 
order.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1706788</tid>
<number> 4</number> Recovery of taxes where property has been transferred without 
a certificate.
<section><tid>1170546</tid>
<number>1</number>Where, in respect of the transfer made on or after  
the seventh day of February, <year>1948</year>, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in the territories which, 
immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in the 
States] of Bombay. West Bengal, Punjab, Bihar, Delhi and Ajmer, and in 
any <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> other territory] on or after the date on which the Transfer of 
Property (India) Ordinance, <year>1948</year> (3 of <year>1948</year>) was made applicable to 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> that territory], of any right, title or interest in any immovable 
property, other than agricultural land, belonging to any person to 
whom this Act applies, the Income- tax Officer of the area where the 
property is situate is satisfied, after giving such person notice in 
this behalf for a period of not less than one month, that no 
certificate in the terms mentioned in section 3 would have been issued 
to him if this Act had been in force on the date the transfer was 
made, he may
<pagefootnote><pagenum>619</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year> for" in the 
States". 
2 Subs., ibid., for" other State". 
3 Subs., ibid., for" that State".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


forward a statement to the Collector showing the existing and 
anticipated liabilities by way of taxes in respect of all or any of 
the parties to the transfer.


</section>

<section><tid>1471213</tid>
<number>2</number>On receipt of any statement under sub- section (1), the 
Collector shall proceed to recover the total amount shown in such 
statement as if it were an arrear of land revenue, and for the purpose 
of such recovery proceedings he may treat the property transferred as 
aforesaid as if it belonged to all or any of the persons named in the 
statement.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1510319</tid>
<number>5</number>Right of appeal. An appeal shall lie against the order of any 
Income- tax Officer refusing to issue a certificate under the 
provisions of sub- section (2) of section 3 to the Commissioner of 
Income- tax to whom the Income- tax Officer is subordinate, if presented 
to such Commissioner within thirty days from the date of the order, 
and the Commissioner may pass such orders thereon as he may think fit.

</article>



<article><tid>1100948</tid>
<number>6</number>Effect of Act over other laws. The provisions of this Act 
shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith 
contained in any other law for the time being in force.

</article>



<article><tid>305527</tid>
<number>7</number>Bar of suits. No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding 
shall lie against the Central Government or any person or authority in 
respect of anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done 
under this Act.

</article>



<article><tid>1841869</tid>
<number> 8</number> Power to make rules. <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<section><tid>467124</tid>
<number>1</number>] The Central Government may,  
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> by notification in the Official gazette,] make rules for the 
purpose of carrying into effect the objects of this Act, and, in 
particular, prescribe the fee payable under sub- section (2) of section 
3.

</section>

<section><tid>1824345</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as 
may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is 
in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised 
in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.]


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1218248</tid>
<number>9</number>Effect of expiry of Ordinance 21 of <year>1948</year>. On the expiry of the 
Payment of Taxes (Transfer of Property) Ordinance, <year>1948</year>, section 6 of 
the General Clauses Act, <year>1897</year> (10 of <year>1897</year>) shall apply as if the 
Ordinance had then been repealed by a Central Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>620</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Renumbered and ins. by Act 4 of <year>1986</year>, s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 15- 5-  
  <year>1986</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>