<act><title>

The 
    Iron Ore Mines, Manganese ore Mines and
    Chrome Ore Mines Labour Welfare Cess Act, 1976</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Iron Ore Mines <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[, Manganese Ore Mines 
    and Chrome Ore Mines Labour Welfare] Cess Act, 1976.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends 
    to the whole of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It 
    shall come into force on such date<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> as the Central Government 
    may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint, and different dates 
    may be appointed for different States:
 
Provided 
    that the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    apply in the first instance the provisions of this Act, only to iron ore 
    mines, or only to manganese ore mines, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[or only to chrome ore 
    mines,] in a State with effect from such date as may be specified in the 
    notification, and if that Government is satisfied that it is necessary, or 
    expedient so to do, it may extend this Act to all iron ore mines <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[, 
    manganese ore mines and chrome ore mines] in that State with effect from 
    such date as may be specified in the notification published in the Official 
    Gazette.
 
 
  






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> In this Act, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   “export” means taking out of India to a 
    place outside India;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   “Fund” means the Iron Ore Mines
    <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[, 
    Manganese Ore Mines and Chrome Ore Mines Labour Welfare] Fund formed under 
    section 3 of the Iron Ore Mines 
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[, Manganese Ore 
    Mines and Chrome Ore Mines Labour Welfare] Fund Act, 1976;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   “prescribed” means prescribed by rules 
    made under this Act.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Words and expressions used but not defined in this Act and defined in the 
    Iron Ore Mines <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[, Manganese Ore Mines and Chrome Ore Mines 
    Labour Welfare] Fund Act, 1976, shall have the meanings respectively 
    assigned to them in that Act.
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Levy and collection of cess on iron ore, manganese ore and chrome ore.—With 
    effect from such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the 
    Official Gazette, appoint, there shall be levied and collected as a cess for 
    the purposes of the Iron Ore Mines
<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[, 
    Manganese Ore Mines and Chrome Ore Mines Labour Welfare] Fund Act, 1976—
 <section>
<number>i</number>   on all iron ore produced in any mine,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   a duty of customs, where such iron ore 
    is exported; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   a duty of excise, where such iron ore is 
    sold or otherwise disposed of to the occupier of any metallurgical factory, 
    or to any person who in turn sells it to a metallurgical factory, or is used 
    by the owner of the mine in any metallurgical factory, 
 
at such rate not exceeding one rupee per 
    metric tonne of iron ore as the Central Government may, from time to time, 
    fix by notification in the Official Gazette;
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>ii</number>   on all manganese ore produced in any 
    mine,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   a duty of customs, where such manganese 
    ore is exported; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   a duty of excise, where such manganese 
    ore is sold or otherwise disposed of to the occupier of any metallurgical 
    factory, or to any person who in turn sells it to a metallurgical factory, 
    or is used by the owner of the mine in any metallurgical factory, 
 
at such rate not exceeding six rupees per 
    metric tonne of manganese ore as the Central Government may, from time to 
    time, fix by notification in the Official Gazette. 
 </subsection></section><section>

<footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>iii</number> 
      on all chrome ore produced in any mine,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   a duty of customs, where such chrome ore 
    is exported, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   a duty of excise, where such chrome ore 
    is sold or otherwise disposed of to the occupier of any metallurgical 
    factory, or to any person who in turn sells it to a metallurgical factory, 
    or is used by the owner of the mine in any metallurgical factory, 
 
at such rate not exceeding six rupees per 
    metric tonne of chrome ore or as the Central Government may, from time to 
    time fix, by notification in the Official Gazette.] 
 

    Explanation.—Where 
    the owner of any iron ore mine or manganese ore mine <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[or chrome 
    ore mine] is also the occupier of a metallurgical factory, then, for the 
    purposes of sub-clause (b) of clause (i) <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[or sub-clause (b) of 
    clause (ii) or sub-clause (b) of clause (iii), all the iron ore or manganese 
    ore or chrome ore,] as the case may be, produced in the mine and not sold or 
    otherwise disposed of to the occupier of any other metallurgical factory or 
    to any other person shall be deemed, unless the contrary is proved, to have 
    been used by such owner for his own metallurgical factory.
  








 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Payment of duty of customs and duty of excise.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every duty of customs leviable under this Act on any iron ore or manganese 
    ore <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[or chrome ore] shall be payable to the Central Government 
    by the person by whom the iron ore or, <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[manganese ore, or chrome 
    ore, as the case may be,] is exported.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every duty of excise leviable under this Act on any iron ore or manganese 
    ore <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[or chrome ore] shall be payable—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   to the occupier of the 
    metallurgical factory by the person by whom such iron ore or manganese ore
    <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[or 
    chrome ore] is sold or otherwise disposed of to such occupier;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   to the Central Government, by the 
    owner of the iron ore mine or manganese ore mine 
<footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[or 
    chrome ore mine] where the iron ore or manganese ore 
<footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[or 
    chrome ore] is used by such owner in any metallurgical factory,
 
within such period as may be prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> All 
    amounts referred to in clause (a) of sub-section (2) shall be collected by 
    the occupier of the metallurgical factory in such manner, and paid by him to 
    the Central Government within such period, as may be prescribed. 
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Crediting proceeds of duty to Consolidated Fund of India.—The 
    proceeds of duty of customs and duty of excise levied under section 3 shall 
    be credited to the Consolidated Fund of India. 
  


 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Power of Central Government to exempt.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in this Act, if the Central Government is of opinion that 
    in respect of any metallurgical factory or class of metallurgical factories 
    the levy of the duty of customs or duty of excise on iron ore or manganese 
    ore <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[or chrome ore] under this Act is disproportionate to the 
    cost of collection of such duty of customs or duty of excise from such 
    metallurgical factory or class of metallurgical factories, it may, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette and subject to such exceptions and 
    modifications as may be specified in the said notification, exempt such 
    metallurgical factory or class of metallurgical factories from all or any of 
    the provisions of this Act.
 
 



 



</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>7</number> Interest payable by occupiers of factories and owners of 
      mines.—If 
      any occupier of a factory or any owner of an iron ore mine or a manganese 
      ore mine <footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[or a chrome ore mine] fails to pay any amount 
      payable by him to the Central Government under section 4 within the period 
      prescribed thereunder, such occupier or owner, as the case may be; shall 
      be liable to pay simple interest at twelve per cent. per annum on the 
      amount to be paid from the date on which such payment is due till such 
      amount is actually paid.
  






 
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Penalty for non-payment of duty of excise within the prescribed period.—If 
    any duty of excise payable by the occupier of the metallurgical factory or 
    the owner of the iron ore mine or manganese ore mine <footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[or chrome 
    ore mine] to the Central Government under section 4 is not paid to that 
    Government within the period prescribed thereunder, it shall be deemed to be 
    in arrears and the authority prescribed in this behalf may, after such 
    inquiry as it deems fit, impose on the occupier of the metallurgical factory 
    or, as the case may be, on the owner of the iron ore mine or manganese ore 
    mine <footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[or chrome ore mine] a penalty not exceeding the amount of 
    duty of excise in arrears:
 
Provided that 
    before imposing any such penalty such occupier or such owner, as the case 
    may be, shall be given a reasonable opportunity of being heard and, if after 
    such hearing the said authority is satisfied that the default was for any 
    good and sufficient reason, no penalty shall be imposed under this section.
  






 



</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>9</number> Recovery of amounts due under the Act.—Any amount due under this Act 
      (including the interest or penalty, if any, payable under section 7 or 
      section 8, as the case may be) from any occupier of a metallurgical 
      factory or any owner of an iron ore mine or a manganese ore mine 
      <footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[or a chrome ore mine] may be recovered by the Central 
      Government in the same manner as an arrear of land 
      revenue.
  



 
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Penalty 
    for evasion of duty of excise.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whoever wilfully or intentionally evades or attempts to evade the payment of 
    duty of excise payable by him to the Central Government under this Act, 
    shall, on conviction, be punishable with imprisonment which may extend to 
    six months, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with 
    both.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No court 
    shall take cognizance of an offence punishable under this section, save on a 
    complaint made by, or under the authority of, the Central Government. 
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> Offence 
    by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> Where an 
    offence under this Act has been committed by a company, every person who at 
    the time the offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible to, 
    the company for the conduct of the business of the company as well as the 
    company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to 
    be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
 
Provided that 
    nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to 
    any punishment, if he proves that the offence was committed without his 
    knowledge or that he had exercised all due diligence to prevent the 
    commission of such offence. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where any offence 
    under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the 
    offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is 
    attributable to any neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary 
    or other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary or other 
    officer shall be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to 
    be proceeded against and punished accordingly. 
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    this section,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   “company” means any body corporate and 
    includes a firm or other association of individuals; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   “director”, in relation to a firm, means 
    a partner in the firm.  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Protection of action taken in good faith.—No 
    suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central 
    Government or any officer or other employee of the Central Government for 
    anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act 
    or the rules made thereunder. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> Repeal 
    and saving.—
<section><number>1</number> As from the 
    commencement of this Act, the Iron Ore Mines Labour Welfare Cess Act, 1961 
    (58 of 1961), shall stand repealed. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> (a) The 
    amount collected as cess, under the Act repealed by sub-section (1), shall 
    be credited to the Consolidated Fund of India. 
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The 
    Central Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in 
    this behalf, credit to the Fund an amount not exceeding the proceeds of cess 
    credited under clause (a), after deducting the cost of collection as 
    determined by that Government. 
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> Power 
    to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
    Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, and subject to the 
    condition of previous publication, make rules for carrying out the 
    provisions of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the assessment and collection of the 
    duty of customs or duty of excise levied under section 3;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   the making of refunds, remissions and 
    recoveries of the duty of customs or duty of excise levied under section 3; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   the period within which the person 
    selling or otherwise disposing of the iron ore or manganese ore 
<footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[or 
    chrome ore] to the occupier of the metallurgical factory shall pay the duty 
    of excise to such occupier under sub-section (2) of section 4;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   the period within which the owner 
    of the iron ore mine or manganese ore mine 
<footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[or 
    chrome ore mine] shall pay the duty of excise to the Central Government 
    under sub-section (2) of section 4;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   the manner in which the occupier of the 
    metallurgical factory shall collect the duty of excise under sub-section (3) 
    of section 4;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   the period within which the occupier of 
    the metallurgical factory shall pay to the Central Government the duty of 
    excise collected by him under sub-section (3) of section 4;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>   the authority which may impose any 
    penalty under section 8; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>   any other matter which has to be or may 
    be prescribed, or provided for, by rules under this Act. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> In making 
    any rule under clause (c) of sub-section (2), the Central Government may 
    direct that a breach thereof shall be punishable with fine which may extend 
    to five hundred rupees. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every rule 
    made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, 
    before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period 
    of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
    successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
    following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses 
    agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the 
    rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
    modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
    such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of 
    anything previously done under that rule. 
 

 






 



</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Subs. by Act 44 of 
    1982, sec. 3, for “and Manganese Ore Mines Labour Welfare” (w.e.f. 
    1-7-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Came into force on 
    1-9-1978, vide Gazette of India, Pt. II, Sec. 3(ii), dated 19th 
    August, 1978.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   Ins. by Act 44 of 
    1982, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-7-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   Subs. by Act 44 of 
    1982, sec. 4, for “and manganese ore mines” (w.e.f. 1-7-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>   Subs. by Act 44 of 1982, 
    sec. 4, for “and Manganese Ore Mines Labour Welfare” (w.e.f. 1-7-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>   Subs. by Act 44 of 
    1982, sec. 5, “and Manganese Ore Mines Labour Welfare” (w.e.f. 1-7-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>   Ins. by Act 44 of 
    1982, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-7-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>   Subs. by Act 44 of 
    1982, sec. 5, for certain words (w.e.f. 1-7-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>     Ins. by Act 44 of 
    1982, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 1-7-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>     Subs. by Act 44 of 
    1982, sec. 6, for “as the case may be, manganese ore” (w.e.f. 1-7-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>         Ins. by Act 44 
    of 1982, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 1-7-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>    Ins. by Act 44 
      of 1982, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-7-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>     Ins. by Act 44 
    of 1982, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 1-7-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>     Ins. by Act 44 
      of 1982, sec. 10 (w.e.f. 1-7-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>   Ins. by Act 44 of 
    1982, sec. 11 (w.e.f. 1-7-1983).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>