<act><tid>909838</tid>
<title>THE AUROVILLE (EMERGENCY PROVISIONS) ACT, <year>1980</year></title>

ACT NO. 59 OF <year>1980</year>
[ 17th December, <year>1980</year>.]

An Act to provide for the taking over, in the public interest, of the 
management of Auroville for a limited period and for matters connected 
therewith or incidental thereto.

WHEREAS Sri Aurobindo Society, a non- governmental organisation 
had been a channel of funds for the setting up of a cultural township 
known as Auroville, where people of different countries are expected 
to live together in harmony in one community and are expected to 
engage in cultural, educational, scientific and other pursuits aiming 
at human unity;

AND WHEREAS the United Nations Educational, Scientific and 
Cultural Organisation (hereinafter referred to as UNESCO'), being of 
the opinion that the project aforesaid would contribute to 
international understanding and promotion of peace, by a resolution 
passed in <year>1966</year>, commended Auroville to those interested in UNESCO' s 
ideals;

AND WHEREAS by a further resolution passed in <year>1968</year>, the UNESCO 
had invited its member- States and international non- governmental 
organisations to participate in the development of Auroville as an 
international cultural township designed to bring together the values 
of different cultures and civilisations in a harmonious environment 
with integrated living standards which correspond to man' s physical 
and spiritual needs;

AND WHEREAS by a further resolution passed at its sitting held 
from the 12th October to 14th November, <year>1970</year>, the UNESCO had directed 
its Director- General to take such steps as may be feasible, within the 
budgetary provisions, to promote the development of Auroville as an 
important international cultural programme;

AND WHEREAS Auroville was developed as a cultural township with 
the aid of funds received from different organisations in and outside 
India


<pagefootnote><pagenum>413</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

as also from the substantial grants received from the Central and 
State Governments;

AND WHEREAS pursuant to the complaints received with regard to 
the misuse of funds by Sri Aurobindo Society, a Committee was set up 
under the chairmanship of the Lieutenant- Governor of Pondicherry with 
representatives of the Government of Tamil Nadu and of the Ministry of 
Home Affairs in the Central Government, and the said Committee had, 
after a detailed scrutiny of the accounts of Sri Aurobindo Society, 
found instances of serious irregularities in the management of the 
said Society, misutilisation of its funds and their diversion to other 
purposes;

AND WHEREAS in view of the serious difficulties which have arisen 
with regard to the management of Auroville, it is necessary to take 
over, for a limited period, the management thereof and any delay in 
taking over the management of Auroville would be highly detrimental to 
the interests and objectives of Auroville;

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty- first Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>72709</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1127666</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Auroville (Emergency Provisions) Act, <year>1980</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>755916</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 10th day of 
November, <year>1980</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1525860</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1052511</tid>
<number>a</number>" Administrator" means the Administrator appointed under 
section 5;

</section>

<section><tid>1107165</tid>
<number>b</number>" appointed day" means the 10th day of November, <year>1980</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>1883779</tid>
<number>c</number>" Auroville" means so much of the undertakings as form 
part of, or are relatable to, the cultural township which is 
known as Auroville and the charter of which was proclaimed by the 
Mother' on the 28th day of February, <year>1968</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>1126643</tid>
<number>d</number>" Council" means the Auroville International Advisory 
Council' constituted under sub- section (1) of section 6;

</section>

<section><tid>1135140</tid>
<number>e</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>12740</tid>
<number>f</number>" Society" means Sri Aurobindo Society being a society as 
defined in the West Bengal Societies Registration Act, <year>1961</year> 
 (West Bengal Act XXVI of <year>1961</year>), and having its registered office 
at Calcutta;

</section>

<section><tid>1718026</tid>
<number>g</number>words and expressions used herein and not defined, but 
defined in the Societies Registration Act, <year>1860</year> (21 of <year>1860</year>), 
shall have the meanings, respectively, assigned to them in that 
Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>414</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

CHAP

TAKING OVER OF THE MANAGEMENT OF AUROVILLE

CHAPTER II

TAKING OVER OF THE MANAGEMENT OF AUROVILLE




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>625722</tid>
<number> 3</number> Management of Auroville to vest in the Central Government for 
a limited period.
<section><tid>1602902</tid>
<number>1</number>On and from the appointed day and for a period  
of two years thereafter, the management of Auroville shall vest in the 
Central Government:
Provided that where the Central Government is of opinion that in 
order to secure the proper management of Auroville, it is expedient 
that such management should continue to vest in that Government after 
the expiry of the said period of two years, it may, from time to time, 
issue directions for the continuance of such management for such 
period, not exceeding one year at a time, as it may think fit; so, 
however, that the total period for which such management shall 
continue to vest in the Central Government shall not, in any case, 
exceed <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> eight years.]


</section>

<section><tid>1034562</tid>
<number>2</number>Auroville shall be deemed to include all the assets, rights, 
leaseholds, powers, authorities and privileges, and all property 
 (movable and immovable), including lands, buildings, works, workshops, 
projects, stores, instruments, machinery, automobiles and other 
vehicles, cash balances, funds, including reserve funds, investments 
and book debts of the Society as form part of, or are relatable to, 
Auroville and all other rights and interests arising out of such 
properties as were immediately before the appointed day in the 
ownership, possession, power or control of the Society, whether within 
or without India, and all books of account, registers, maps, plans and 
all other documents of whatever nature relating thereto.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1586964</tid>
<number> 4</number> Application of West Bengal Act XXVI of <year>1961</year>.
<section><tid>526201</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being 
in force or in the memorandum or the rules and regulations of the 
Society,--

<subsection><tid>1999450</tid>
<number>a</number>on and from the appointed day, every member of the 
Governing Body of the Society, by whatever name called, shall 
cease to exercise any powers of management in relation to 
Auroville;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1048714</tid>
<number>b</number>it shall not be lawful for the members of the Society or 
any other person to nominate or appoint any person as Manager or 
Director of so much of the assets of the Society as form part of, 
or are relatable to, Auroville;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1210106</tid>
<number>c</number>no resolution in relation to Auroville passed at any 
meeting of the members of the Society or of the members of 
Auroville shall be given effect to unless it is approved by the 
Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>34815</tid>
<number>d</number>no proceeding for the dissolution of the Society or 
merger of the Society with any other society or for the 
appointment of a receiver in respect of any asset forming part 
of, or relatable to, Auroville, the management of which has 
vested in the Central Government under section 3, shall lie in 
any court except with the consent of the Central Government.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>569476</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions contained in sub- section (1) and to 
the other provisions contained in this Act and subject to such other 
exceptions, restrictions and limitations, if any, as the Central 
Government may,

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>72709</tid>
<number>1</number>Subs. by Act 44 of <year>1987</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 28- 10- <year>1987</year>).

<pagefootnote><pagenum>415</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

by notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf for 
the purposes of this Act, the provisions of the West Bengal Societies 
Registration Act, <year>1961</year> (West Bengal Act XXVI of <year>1961</year>), shall continue 
to apply to the Society in the same manner as they applied thereto 
before the appointed day.



</article>



<article><tid>1369361</tid>
<number> 5</number> Administrator of Auroville.
<section><tid>994241</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government shall,  
as from the appointed day, appoint a person or a body of persons as 
the Administrator for the purpose of taking over the management of 
Auroville and the Administrator shall carry on the management of 
Auroville for and on behalf of the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1629429</tid>
<number>2</number>The Administrator may authorise such person as he thinks fit 
also to exercise all or any of the powers exercisable by him under 
this Act and different persons may be authorised to exercise different 
powers, and subject to the general or special directions given or 
imposed by the Administrator, the person so authorised to exercise any 
powers of the Administrator may exercise those powers in the same 
manner and with the same effect as if they had been conferred on that 
person directly by this Act and not by way of authorisation.

</section>

<section><tid>1063201</tid>
<number>3</number>If, on the appointed day, any suit, appeal or other 
proceeding, of whatever nature, in relation to any property which has 
vested in the Central Government under section 3, instituted or 
preferred by or against the Society is pending, the same shall not 
abate, be discontinued or be, in any way, prejudicially affected by 
reason of the taking over of the management of Auroville or of 
anything contained in this Act but the suit, appeal or other 
proceeding may be pursued, prosecuted or enforced by or against the 
Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1725748</tid>
<number>4</number>The Central Government may issue such directions (including  
directions as to initiating, defending or continuing any legal 
  proceedings before any court, tribunal or other authority) to the 
Administrator, as to his powers and duties as that Government may deem 
desirable and the Administrator may apply to the Central Government at 
any time for instructions as to the manner in which he shall conduct 
the management of Auroville or in relation to any matter arising in 
the course of such management.

</section>

<section><tid>1542202</tid>
<number>5</number>Subject to the other provisions of this Act and to the 
control of the Central Government, the Administrator shall be 
entitled, notwithstanding anything contained in the West Bengal 
Societies Registration Act, <year>1961</year> (West Bengal Act XXVI of <year>1961</year>), or 
in any other law for the time being in force, to exercise, in relation 
to, Auroville, the powers of the Governing Body or Executive Committee 
or, as the case may be, of the Board of Trustees of the Society, 
including the powers to dispose of any property or assets of the 
Society, whether such powers are derived from the West Bengal 
Societies Registration Act, <year>1961</year>, or from the memorandum and rules and 
regulations of the Society or from any other source.

</section>

<section><tid>403477</tid>
<number>6</number>The Administrator and the other persons authorised by him 
under sub- section (2) shall receive from the funds of the Society 
relatable to Auroville such remuneration as the Central Government may 
fix.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>427188</tid>
<number> 6</number> Advisory Council.
<section><tid>26429</tid>
<number>1</number>As soon as may be after the commencement  
of this Act and in any case within one month from such commencement, 
the Central Government shall constitute, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, a Council to be called the Auroville International 
Advisory Council'.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>416</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1657467</tid>
<number>2</number>The Council may on its own motion or on a reference made to 
it by the Central Government advise the Central Government on any 
matter concerning the management of Auroville.

</section>

<section><tid>1975245</tid>
<number>3</number>In tendering any advice to the Central Government, the 
Council shall endeavour to secure that--

<subsection><tid>1603108</tid>
<number>a</number>the ideals for which Auroville has been established are 
encouraged, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1162897</tid>
<number>b</number>the members of Auroville are allowed freedom to grow and 
develop activities and institutions for the fulfilment of the 
aspirations and programmes envisaged in the Charter of Auroville.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>762349</tid>
<number>4</number>The Council shall consist of such number of members not 
exceeding five as may be appointed by the Central Government from 
amongst persons, who in its opinion are devoted to the ideals of human 
unity, peace and progress.

</section>

<section><tid>135948</tid>
<number>5</number>There shall be a Chairman of the Council who shall be elected 
by the members of the Council from among themselves.

</section>

<section><tid>621536</tid>
<number>6</number>The term of office of, the method of filling casual vacancies 
among, and the allowances and other remuneration, if any, payable to, 
the members of the Council shall be such as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>273126</tid>
<number>7</number>The Council shall, subject to any rules that may be made in 
this behalf under section 17, have power to regulate its own 
procedure.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1305613</tid>
<number> 7</number> Delivery of possession of properties of Auroville.
<section><tid>736510</tid>
<number>1</number>Every  
person having, on the appointed day, in his possession, custody or 
control any property forming part of, or relatable to, Auroville, 
shall deliver forthwith such property to the Administrator or to any 
officer or other employee of the Central Government as may be 
authorised by the Central Government in this behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>1621631</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person who has, on the appointed day, in his possession 
or under his control any books, papers or other documents relating to 
Auroville (including the minutes books containing resolutions in  
relation to Auroville adopted by persons in charge of the management 
  of the Society before the appointed day), the current cheque books 
relating to Auroville, any letters, memoranda, notes and other 
communications between him and the Society, shall, notwithstanding 
anything contained in any other law for the time being in force, be 
liable to account for the books, papers and other documents (including  
such minutes books, cheque books, letters, memoranda, notes and other 
  communications) to the Administrator or to such person (being an  
  officer or other employee of the Central Government) as may be 
authorised by the Central Government in this behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>1961229</tid>
<number>3</number>Every person in charge of the management of Auroville 
immediately before the appointed day shall, within ten days from that 
day or within such further period as the Central Government may allow 
in this behalf, furnish to the Administrator a complete inventory of 
all the properties and assets (including particulars of donations  
  received, book debts, investments and belongings) forming part of, or 
relatable to, Auroville immediately before the appointed day and all 
liabilities and obligations of the Society in relation to Auroville 
subsisting immediately

<pagefootnote><pagenum>417</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

before that day and also of all agreements entered into by the Society 
in relation to Auroville and in force immediately before the appointed 
day.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1754378</tid>
<number> 8</number> Relinquishment of management before the specified period.
<section><tid>934070</tid>
<number>1</number> 
If at any time it appears to the Central Government that the purposes 
for which the management of Auroville had been taken over have been 
fulfilled or that for any other reason it is not necessary that the 
management of Auroville should remain vested in that Government, it 
may, notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1) of section 
3, by order published in the Official Gazette, relinquish the 
management of Auroville with effect from such date as may be specified 
in the order.

</section>

<section><tid>1660233</tid>
<number>2</number>On and from the date specified in the order made under sub- 
section (1), the management of the property of the Society forming 
part of, or relatable to, Auroville, shall vest in the Governing Body 
 (by whatever name called) of the Society and such management shall be 
carried on in accordance with the provisions of the West Bengal 
Societies Registration Act, <year>1961</year> (West Bengal Act XXVI of <year>1961</year>), so, 
however, that the steps, if any, in relation to the management of the 
property of the Society forming part of, or relatable to, Auroville, 
may be taken after the publication of the order made under sub- section 
 (1).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>375775</tid>
<number> 9</number> Tribunal.
<section><tid>1278813</tid>
<number>1</number>If any dispute or doubt arises as to whether any  
asset, right, lease- hold, power, authority, privilege, property 
 (whether movable or immovable) including any land, building, works, 
workshop, project, stores, instruments, machinery, automobile or other 
vehicles, cash balances, funds (including reserve funds), investments 
and book debts forms or form part of, or is or are relatable to, 
Auroville for the purposes of section 3, such dispute or doubt shall, 
at the request of the Society or the Administrator or any other person 
interested or at the instance of the Central Government, be referred 
to a Tribunal consisting of one member (being a person who is or has  
  been a Judge of a High Court) to be appointed by the Central 
Government.

</section>

<section><tid>898470</tid>
<number>2</number>The Tribunal shall, for the purposes of any reference under 
sub- section (1), have all the powers of a civil court while trying a 
suit under the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>), in respect 
of the following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1535685</tid>
<number>a</number>summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person and 
examining him on oath;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1461244</tid>
<number>b</number>requiring the discovery and production of documents 
producible as evidence;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1965755</tid>
<number>c</number>recording evidence on oath;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>212032</tid>
<number>d</number>requisitioning any public record from any court or 
office;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>847235</tid>
<number>e</number>issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses or 
documents;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>562785</tid>
<number>f</number>such other matters as may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>457319</tid>
<number>3</number>The Tribunal shall have power to regulate its own procedure 
in all matters arising out of the discharge of its functions 
 (including the place or places at which it shall hold its sittings).

</section>

<section><tid>1535462</tid>
<number>4</number>All expenses incurred in connection with the Tribunal shall 
be defrayed out of the Consolidated Fund of India.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>418</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1511335</tid>
<number>10</number>Appeal. Any person aggrieved by the decision of the Tribunal 
under section 9 may, within thirty days from the date of such 
decision, prefer an appeal to the High Court at Madras and such appeal 
shall be heard and disposed of by not less than two Judges of that 
High Court:
Provided that the High Court may entertain the appeal after the 
expiry of the said period of thirty days if it is satisfied that the 
appellant had sufficient cause for not preferring the appeal within 
the period aforesaid.

CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER III

MISCELLANEOUS



</article>



<article><tid>1256801</tid>
<number>11</number>Act to have overriding effect. The provisions of this Act or 
any notification, order or rule made thereunder shall have effect 
notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained in any law 
other than this Act or in any instrument having effect by virtue of 
any law other than this Act or in any decree or order of any court.


</article>



<article><tid>1256360</tid>
<number> 12</number> Contracts, etc. cease to have effect unless ratified by the 
Central Government.
<section><tid>253094</tid>
<number>1</number>Every contract (including any contract of   
  employment or other arrangement) entered into by the Society in 
relation to Auroville, the management of which has vested in the 
Central Government under section 3, and in force immediately before 
the appointed day, shall, on and from the date of expiry of ninety 
days from the appointed day, cease to have effect unless such contract 
or other arrangement has been, before the expiry of that period, 
ratified, in writing, by the Central Government; and in ratifying such 
contract or other arrangement, the Central Government may make such 
alterations or modifications therein as it may think fit:
Provided that the Central Government shall not omit to ratify any 
contract or other arrangement and shall not make any alteration or 
modification therein--


<subsection><tid>728148</tid>
<number>a</number>unless it is satisfied that such contract or other 
arrangement is unduly onerous or has been entered into in bad 
faith or is detrimental to the interests of Auroville; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>822610</tid>
<number>b</number>except after giving the parties to the contract or other 
arrangement a reasonable opportunity of being heard and except 
after recording, in writing, its reasons for refusal to ratify 
the contract or other arrangement or for making any alteration or 
modification therein.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1747288</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time 
being in force, no person in respect of whom any contract or other 
arrangement is terminated, altered or modified under sub- section (1), 
or who ceases to exercise any powers or hold any office by reason of 
any provision contained in sub- section (1) of section 4, shall be 
entitled to claim any compensation for the premature termination of 
the contract or other arrangement or for any alteration or 
modification therein or for the loss of his powers or office.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>436086</tid>
<number>13</number>Exclusion of period of operation of Act. In computing the 
period of limitation prescribed by any law for the time being in force 
for any suit or application against any person by the Society in 
respect of any matter arising out of any transaction relating to 
Auroville, the time during which this Act is in force shall be 
excluded.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>419</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>711053</tid>
<number> 14</number> Protection of action taken in good faith.
<section><tid>552480</tid>
<number>1</number>No suit,  
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central 
Government or any officer or other employee of that Government or the 
Administrator or any person authorised under sub- section (2) of 
section 5 by the Administrator for anything which is in good faith 
done or intended to be done under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1312009</tid>
<number>2</number>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the 
Central Government or any officer or other employee of that Government 
or the Administrator or any person authorised under sub- section (2) of 
section 5 by the Administrator for any damage caused or likely to be 
caused by anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done 
under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>287902</tid>
<number> 15</number> Penalties. Any person who,--
<section><tid>1877254</tid>
<number>a</number>having in his possession or custody or control any asset 
or property forming part of, or relatable to, Auroville, 
wrongfully withholds such property from the Administrator or any 
person authorised under this Act, or

</section>

<section><tid>632163</tid>
<number>b</number>wrongfully obtains possession of any such asset or 
property forming part of, or relatable to, Auroville, or

</section>

<section><tid>1002192</tid>
<number>c</number>wilfully retains any asset or property forming part of, 
or relatable to, Auroville, or removes or destroys it, or

</section>

<section><tid>1932232</tid>
<number>d</number>wilfully withholds or fails to deliver any books, papers 
or other documents relatable to Auroville which may be in his 
possession or custody or under his control to the Administrator 
or any person authorised under this Act, or

</section>

<section><tid>1461246</tid>
<number>e</number>fails, without any reasonable cause, to furnish any 
inventory of properties and assets as provided in sub- section (3) 
of section 7, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term 
which may extend to two years, or with fine which may extend to 
ten thousand rupees, or with both.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1522407</tid>
<number> 16</number> Offences by companies.
<section><tid>1852668</tid>
<number>1</number>Where an offence under this Act  
has been committed by a company, every person who, at the time the 
offence was committed, was in charge of, and was responsible to, the 
company for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as the 
company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be 
liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the 
offence was committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised 
all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.


</section>

<section><tid>135693</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where 
any offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is 
proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or 
connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any 
director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such 
director, manager, secretary or other officer shall be deemed to be 
guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and 
punished accordingly.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>420</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section,--


<subsection><tid>820769</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm 
or other association of individuals; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>967412</tid>
<number>b</number>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner in 
the firm.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>364074</tid>
<number> 17</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1517603</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the 
provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>531646</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>825531</tid>
<number>a</number>the term of office of, the method of filling casual 
vacancies among, and the allowances and other remuneration, if 
any, payable to, the members of the Council under sub- section (6) 
of section 6;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1411812</tid>
<number>b</number>the additional matters in respect of which the Tribunal 
shall have the powers of a civil court under clause (f) of sub- 
section (2) of section 9; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1469332</tid>
<number>c</number>any other matter which is required to be, or may be, 
prescribed, or in respect of which rules may be made, under this 
Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1447526</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act 
shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House 
of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty 
days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1073619</tid>
<number> 18</number> Repeal and saving.
<section><tid>997081</tid>
<number>1</number>The Auroville (Emergency Provisions)  
Ordinance, <year>1980</year> (19 of <year>1980</year>) is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1261573</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action 
taken under the Ordinance so repealed shall be deemed to have been 
done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.


</section>

</article>



 </act>