<act><title>THE ARMED FORCES TRIBUNAL 
(SALARIES, ALLOWANCES AND CONDITIONS OF SERVICE OF CHAIRPERSON AND 
MEMBERS) RULES, 20091</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the Armed Forces Tribunal (Salaries, Allowances and Conditions of Service 
of Chairperson and Members) Rules, 2009. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of their publication 
in the Official Gazette. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>In these rules, unless the context 
otherwise requires, 
 
 <section><number>a</number> Act means the Armed Forces Tribunal Act, 2007 (55 of 2007); 
 </section><section><number>b</number> Tribunal means the Armed Forces Tribunal established under section 4 
  of the Act; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> Chairperson means the Chairperson of the Tribunal appointed under 
  section 7(1) of the Act; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> Member means a member (whether Judicial or Administrative) of the 
  Tribunal appointed under section 7(1) of the Act; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> words and expressions used herein and not defined but defined in the 
  Act shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act. 
</section>


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Pay and Allowances, Leave, Pension, Provident Fund, Travelling 
Allowance, Leave Travel Concession, Accommodation, etc., to the Chairperson and 
Members of the Armed Forces Tribunal. </title>1 <title></title>
<section><number>a</number> When a 
Retired Judge of the Supreme Court is appointed as Chairperson of the Tribunal, 
he shall be entitled to salary, allowances and other perquisites as are 
available to the sitting Judge of the Supreme Court, and as provided in the 
Supreme Court Judges (Salaries and Conditions of Services) Act, 1958 (51 of 
1958), and these shall apply mutatis mutandis alongwith rules made 
thereunder as amended from time to time. The Chairperson shall be entitled to 
take his spouse with him while travelling within the country while on official 
visit to Benches. 
 
 


</section><section><number>b</number> When a Retired Chief Justice of a High Court is appointed as 
  Chairperson of the Tribunal, he shall be entitled to salary, allowances and 
  other perquisites as are available to the sitting Chief Justice of a High 
  Court and as provided in the High Court Judges (Salaries and Conditions of 
  Services), Act 1954 (28 of 1954), and these shall apply mutatis mutandis 
  alongwith rules made thereunder as amended from time to time: 
 Provided that in case the Retired Judge of the Supreme Court or the Retired 
  Chief Justice of a High Court, is in receipt of, or has received or has become 
  entitled to receive any retirement benefits by way of pension, gratuity, 
  employer's contribution to the Contributory Provident Fund or other forms of 
  retirement benefits, the pay of such Chairperson shall be reduced by the gross 
  amount of pension or employer's contribution to the Contributory Provident 
  Fund or any other form of retirement benefits, if any (except pension 
  equivalent of retirement gratuity), drawn or to be drawn by him. 
 </section><section><number>c</number> When a serving or retired Judge of a High Court is appointed as 
  Judicial Member of the Tribunal or when any person from the three services is 
  appointed as Administrative Member of the Tribunal, he shall be entitled to 
  salary, allowances and other perquisites as are available to the sitting Judge 
  of a High Court and as provided in the High Court Judges (Salaries and 
  Conditions of Services) Act, 1954 (28 of 1954) and these shall apply 
  mutatis mutandis alongwith rules made thereunder as amended from time 
  to time: 
 Provided that in case the retired Judge of a High Court, or a person from 
  the three services, is in receipt of, or has received or has become entitled 
  to receive any retirement benefits by way of pension, gratuity, employer's 
  contribution to the Contributory Provident Fund or other forms of retirement 
  benefits, the pay of such Member shall be reduced by the gross amount of 
  pension or employer's contribution to the Contributory Provident Fund or any 
  other form of retirement benefits, if any (except pension equivalent of 
  retirement gratuity), drawn or to be drawn by him. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Residuary Provision. </title>Matters relating to the terms and 
conditions of service of the Chairperson or Members of the Tribunal with respect 
to which no express provision has been made in these rules, shall be determined 
by the rules and orders for the time being applicable to a Secretary to the 
Government of India. 
  


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Powers to relax rules. </title>The Central Government shall have 
power to relax any provision of these rules in respect of any class or category 
of persons. 


</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Came into force on 18-5-2009 .</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>