<act><tid>1662936</tid>
<title>THE INDIAN TRAMWAYS ACT, <year>1886</year></title>

ACT NO. 11 OF <year>1886</year>
[ 12th March, <year>1886</year>.] W

An Act to facilitate the construction and to regulate the working of 
tramways.





<article><tid>1001508</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1949446</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Indian Tramways Act, <year>1886</year>; and

</section>

<section><tid>1911584</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force at once.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>358953</tid>
<number> 2</number> Local extent.
<section><tid>1673557</tid>
<number>1</number>It extends in the first instance to <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the  
whole of India except <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the territories which, immediately before the 
 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in Part B States] and the 
territories which were on the 12th March, <year>1886</year>, respectively], 
administered by the Governor of Fort Saint George in Council, the 
Governor of Bombay in Council and the Lieutenant- Governor of Bengal.

</section>

<section><tid>1267519</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> This Act may by notification in the Official Gazette be 
extended to the whole or any part of the said territories by the State 
Government concerned.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>820652</tid>
<number> 3</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless there is something repugnant 
in the subject or context,--
<section><tid>1583940</tid>
<number>1</number>" local authority" means a municipal committee, district 
board, body of port commissioners or other authority 
legally entitled to, or entrusted by <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> the Central

<pagefootnote><pagenum>6</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" all the Provinces of India except 
the territories". 
2 Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" Part B 
States".


</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for the original sub- section. 
This Act has been extended to the whole of the Bombay Presidency 
except the city of Bombay, See Bombay Gazette, <year>1887</year>, Pt. I, P. 899; 
and to the city of Madras, See Fort St. George Gazette, <year>1886</year>, Pt. I, 
p. 750. It has also been partially extended to Berar by the Berar Laws 
Act, <year>1941</year> (4 of <year>1941</year>). 
For separate Acts on the subject of tramways in--

Bengal, see the Bengal Tramways Act, <year>1883</year> (Ben, 3 of <year>1883</year>); 
Calcutta, see the Calcutta Tramways (Electric Traction) Act, <year>1900</year> 
 (Ben. 4 of <year>1900</year>), and the Calcutta Tramways Act, <year>1880</year> (Ben. 1 of  
  <year>1880</year>); 
Bombay, see the Bombay Tramways Act, <year>1874</year> (Bom. 1 of <year>1874</year>).

The Act comes into force in Pondicherry on 1. 10. <year>1963</year> vide Reg. 7 of 
<year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch. I.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" the Govt.".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

Government or any State Government] with, the control 
or management of a municipal or local fund:


</section>

<section><tid>474075</tid>
<number>2</number>" road" means the way of a road, street, throughfare, 
passage or place along or across which a tramway 
authorized under this Act is, or is intended to be, 
laid, and includes the surface- soil and sub- soil of a 
road, and the footway, berms, drains and ditches of a 
road, and any bridge, culvert or causeway forming part 
of a road:

</section>

<section><tid>335152</tid>
<number>3</number>" road- authority", in relation to a road, means--

<subsection><tid>952713</tid>
<number>a</number>if a local authority maintains and repairs the 
road, then that authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>202403</tid>
<number>b</number>if a local authority does not maintain and 
repair the road, and the road is neither vested in 
Government nor maintained and repaired by <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> 
Government], then the person in whom the road is 
vested; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1622554</tid>
<number>c</number>if a local authority does not maintain and 
repair the road, and the road is vested in Government 
or maintained and repaired by <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Government], then 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Government for whose purposes a road is so 
vested or by which the road is maintained and repaired, 
as the case may be]:

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>298923</tid>
<number>4</number>" circle", in relation to a local authority or road- 
authority, means the area within the control of that 
authority:

</section>

<section><tid>288126</tid>
<number>5</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>" tramway" means a tramway having one, two or more 
rails, and includes--

<subsection><tid>1767079</tid>
<number>a</number>any part of a tramway, or any siding, turnout, 
connection, line or track belonging to a tramway;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1412301</tid>
<number>b</number>any electrical equipment of a tramway; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>69489</tid>
<number>c</number>any electric supply- line transmitting power 
from a generating station or sub- station to a tramway 
or from a generating station to a sub- station from 
which power is transmitted to a tramway:]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1799423</tid>
<number>6</number>" order" means an order authorizing the construction of a 
tramway under this Act, and includes a further order 
substituted for, or amending, extending or varying, 
that order:
<pagefootnote><pagenum>7</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" the Govt.". 
2 The words" the Central Government or any Provincial" omitted by 
the A. O. <year>1950</year>. 
3 Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" the L. G.". 
4 Subs. by Act 5 of <year>1911</year>, s. 2, for the original cl.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>453090</tid>
<number>7</number>" promoter" means a local authority or person in whose 
favour an order has been made, and includes a local 
authority or person on whom the rights and liabilities 
conferred and imposed on the promoter by this Act and 
by the order and any rules made under this Act as to 
the construction, maintenance and use of the tramway, 
have devolved:

</section>

<section><tid>69814</tid>
<number>8</number>" undertaking" includes all moveable and immoveable 
property of the promoter suitable to and used by him 
for the purposes of the tramway:

</section>

<section><tid>1644388</tid>
<number>9</number>" carriage", in the case of a tramway on which steam- 
power or any other mechanical power <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or electrical 
power] is used, includes and engine worked on the 
tramway for the purpose of producing <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or utilizing] 
that power:

</section>

<section><tid>1451871</tid>
<number>10</number>" toll" includes any charge leviable in respect of the 
use of a tramway:

</section>

<section><tid>847276</tid>
<number>11</number>" lessee" means a person to whom a lease has been 
granted of the right of user of a tramway and of 
demanding and taking the authorized tolls:

</section>

<section><tid>1872097</tid>
<number>12</number>" District Magistrate" includes an officer empowered by 
the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Government] by name or by virtue of his office 
to discharge within any local area all or any of the 
functions of a District Magistrate under this Act:

</section>

<section><tid>1334163</tid>
<number>13</number>" District Court" means a principal Civil Court of 
original jurisdiction, and includes a High Court having 
ordinary original civil jurisdiction:

</section>

<section><tid>1384747</tid>
<number>14</number>" Collector" means the chief officer in charge of the 
revenue- administration of a district, and includes an 
officer empowered by the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Government] by name or by 
virtue of his office to discharge within any local area 
the functions of a Collector under this Act: <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>

</section>

<section><tid>78385</tid>
<number>15</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made by the 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Government] under this Act: <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> and

</section>

<section><tid>1407781</tid>
<number>16</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>" Government" in relation to a tramway which is 
wholly within a municipal area or which is declared not 
to be 
a railway under clause (20) of article 366 of the 
Constitution, means the State Government and, in 
relation to any other tramway, means the Central 
Government.]]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>8</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 5 of <year>1911</year>, s. 3. 
2 Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G.". 
3 The word" and" omitted, ibid. 
4 Ins., ibid. 
5 Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for the original paragraph ins. by the 
A. O. <year>1937</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


ORDERS AUTHORIZING THE CONSTRUCTION OF TRAMWAYS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>419179</tid>
<number> 4</number> Application for and consent necessary to making of order.
<section><tid>890357</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] may make an order authorizing the construction of a 
tramway in a circle on application made--

<subsection><tid>228702</tid>
<number>a</number>by the local authority of the circle with the consent of 
the road- authority of any road or part of a road which 
is to be traversed by the tramway and of which the 
local authority is not itself the road- authority; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>393021</tid>
<number>b</number>by any person with the consent of the local authority of 
the circle, and of the road- authority of any road or 
part of a road which is to be traversed by the tramway 
and of which the local authority is not the road- 
authority:
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1599040</tid>
<number>2</number>A local authority shall not make an application for an order, 
or be deemed to consent to an application being made by any person for 
an order, unless the making of the application or the giving of the 
consent has been approved by the local authority in manner prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1408099</tid>
<number>5</number>Consent of local or road- authority not necessary in certain 
cases. When it is proposed to lay a tramway in two or more circles, 
and a local authority or road- authority having control in either or 
any of the circles does not consent thereto, or attaches conditions to 
its consent, the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] may, nevertheless, make an order 
authorizing the construction of the tramway in the circle, or by the 
order impose on the promoter any conditions which it deems fit, if, 
after considering the reasons of the authority for withholding its 
consent or attaching the conditions thereto, it is satisfied that the 
construction of the tramway in the circle is expedient, or, as the 
case may be, that the conditions attached by the authority to its 
consent ought not to be imposed.


</article>



<article><tid>1131895</tid>
<number> 6</number> Procedure for making order.
<section><tid>1183386</tid>
<number>1</number>The <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] on  
receiving an application shall consider it, and, if satisfied as to 
the propriety of proceeding thereon, publish in the Official Gazette, 
and in such other manner as it deems
<pagefootnote><pagenum>9</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G.". 
2 Proviso omitted by the A. O. <year>1937</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


sufficient for giving information to persons interested, a draft of a 
proposed order authorizing the construction of the tramway.


</section>

<section><tid>1699589</tid>
<number>2</number>A notice shall be published with the draft stating that any 
objection or suggestion which any person may desire to make with 
respect to the proposed order will, if submitted to the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] 
on or before a date to be specified in the notice, be received and 
considered.

</section>

<section><tid>1960370</tid>
<number>3</number>If, after considering any objections or suggestions which may 
have been made with respect to the draft on or before the date so 
specified, the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] is of opinion that the application 
should be granted, with or without addition or modification, or 
subject or not to any restriction or condition, it may make an order 
accordingly.

</section>

<section><tid>1497556</tid>
<number>4</number>Every order authorizing the construction of a tramway shall 
be published in the Official Gazette in English, and in the other 
prescribed language or languages, if any; and that publication shall 
be conclusive proof that the order has been made as required by this 
section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1362002</tid>
<number> 7</number> Contents of order.
<section><tid>1644542</tid>
<number>1</number>An order made under section 6 shall  
empower the promoter therein specified to construct and maintain the 
tramway therein described in the manner therein provided, and shall 
specify the time within which the tramway shall be commenced and the 
time within which it shall be completed and opened for public traffic.

</section>

<section><tid>901599</tid>
<number>2</number>The order may also provide, in manner consistent with this 
Act, for all or any of the following, among other matters, that is to 
say:--

<subsection><tid>1566653</tid>
<number>a</number>a period before the expiration of which the tramway 
shall not be commenced, and the conditions subject to 
which the local authority, when it is not itself the 
promoter, may, within that period elect to be 
substituted in the place of the promoter in respect of 
the undertaking or of so much thereof as is within its 
circle; and the limits of time within which, and the 
terms upon which, the local authority may, after the 
tramway has been constructed, require the promoter to 
sell to it the undertaking or so much thereof as is 
within its circle;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>940845</tid>
<number>b</number>the acquisition by the promoter of land for the purposes 
of the tramway, and the disposal by him of land which 
has been acquired but is no longer required for those 
purposes;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>10</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G.".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1602958</tid>
<number>c</number>the conditions subject to which roads may be opened and 
broken up for the purposes of the construction or 
maintenance of the tramway or any part thereof, and the 
method of, and materials to be used in, the reinstating 
of the roads, and the approval of the method and 
materials by the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] or the road- authority 
before the commencement of the work;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1466244</tid>
<number>d</number>the conditions on which the tramway may be constructed 
over a bridge or across a railway or tramway when the 
carriage- way over the bridge is to form part of the 
tramway or when the tramway is to cross a railway or 
another tramway on the level;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>656458</tid>
<number>e</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the space which shall ordinarily intervene between 
the outside of the carriage- way on either side of a 
road whereon the tramway is to be constructed, and--

<subsubsection><tid>709749</tid>
<number>i</number>in the case of a tramway having one rail, the 
rail of the tramway, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1336554</tid>
<number>ii</number>in the case of a tramway having two or more 
rails, the nearest rail of the tramway,
and the conditions on which a smaller space may be 
permitted;]


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>528353</tid>
<number>f</number>the gauge of the tramway, the rails to be used, and the 
mode in which, and the level at which, they shall be 
laid and maintained; and the adoption and application 
by the promoter of such improvements in the rails, and 
in their situation, and in the sub- structure upon which 
they rest, as the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] may from time to time 
require;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>726995</tid>
<number>g</number>the portion of the road or roads traversed by the 
tramway to be kept in repair by the promoter; the 
maintenance by the promoter to the satisfaction of the 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] or the road- authority, or both, of that 
portion of the road or roads; and the liability of the 
promoter, on the requisition of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government], 
from time to time to adopt and apply such improvements 
in the tramway as the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] may consider 
necessary or desirable for the safety or convenience of 
the public, and to alter the position or level of the 
tramway to suit future alterations in the road or 
roads;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>11</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G.". 
2 Subs. by Act 5 of <year>1911</year>, s. 4, for the original cl.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1230583</tid>
<number>h</number>the application of material excavated by the promoter in 
the construction or maintenance of the tramway;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>786932</tid>
<number>i</number>the provision of such crossing, passing- places, sidings, 
junctions and other works, in addition to those 
specified in or authorized by the order, as may from 
time to time be necessary or convenient to the 
efficient working of the tramway;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>813460</tid>
<number>j</number>the powers which may from time to time be exercised by 
the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government], the local authority, the road- 
authority or any person in respect of sewers, drains, 
telegraph- lines, gas- pipes, water- pipes or other things 
in or on land occupied by the tramway; the notice (if  
  any) to be given of the intended exercise of those 
powers; the manner in which the power shall be 
exercised; and the extent to which the tramway and the 
traffic thereon may be interfered with in the exercise 
thereof;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1571110</tid>
<number>k</number>the conditions subject to which the promoter may from 
time to time interfere with, or alter or require the 
alteration of the position of, drains (not being  
  sewers or main drains), telegraph- lines, gas- pipes, 
water- pipes or other things as aforesaid;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1986029</tid>
<number>l</number>the provision of a temporary tramway in place of a part 
of a tramway which has been removed, or of which the 
use has been discontinued by reason of the execution of 
any work affecting a road along which the part of the 
tramway was laid, or by reason of the use of the road 
being interrupted by floods or other cause;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>592204</tid>
<number>m</number>the motive power to be used on the tramway, and the 
conditions on which steam- power or any other mechanical 
power <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or electrical power] may be used;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1977767</tid>
<number>n</number>the nature, dimensions, fittings, appliances and 
apparatus of the carriages to be used on the tramway, 
and the inspection and examination thereof by officers 
of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] or the local authority, and the 
liabilty of the promoter or lessee, on the requisition 
of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government], from time to time, to adopt and 
apply such improvements in the carriages, and in the 
fittings, appliances and apparatus, as the 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] may consider necessary or desirable for 
the safety or convenience of the public;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>12</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O, <year>1937</year>, for" L. G.". 
2 Ins. by Act 5 of <year>1911</year>, s. 5.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>462392</tid>
<number>o</number>the traffic which may be carried on the tramway, the 
traffic which the promoter or lessee shall be bound to 
carry, and the traffic which he may refuse to carry; 
the tolls to be leviable by the promoter or lessee, and 
the periodical revision thereof by the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government]; 
and the regulation of the traffic and of the levy of 
the tolls;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1733365</tid>
<number>p</number>the use of the tramway free of toll by the local 
authority, with its own carriages, for specified 
purposes, during specified hours, with power to the 
local authority to make such sidings and other works as 
may be necessary for communication between its premises 
and the tramway;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1918721</tid>
<number>q</number>the conditions subject to which the promoter may 
transfer the undertaking, or any part thereof, by sale, 
mortgage, lease, exchange or otherwise; and the 
conditions subject to which the local authority may be 
the transferee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1881960</tid>
<number>r</number>the performance by the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] or by the local 
authority or road- authority of any work required by the 
Act or the order to be done by the promoter; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1423688</tid>
<number>s</number>the penalty to be incurred by the promoter or lessee for 
failure to observe any condition or direction contained 
in the order, and the application of the penalty when 
recovered.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>564705</tid>
<number>3</number>The <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] may, in providing in the order for the 
acquisition of land for the purposes of a tramway of which the 
promoter is not a company, direct that land may be acquired for the 
promoter under the provisions of the Land Acquisition Act, <year>1870</year>, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> 
 (10 of <year>1870</year>.) in the same manner and on the same conditions as it 
might be acquired for the purposes of the tramway if a company were 
the promoter.

</section>

<section><tid>1441316</tid>
<number>4</number>The order shall imply the condition--

<subsection><tid>540195</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of a tramway of which a local authority 
is the promoter, that a lease thereof shall be granted only 
in manner by this Act provided; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>203721</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of a tramway of which a local authority 
is not the promoter, that a lease thereof shall be only of 
the right of user and of demanding and taking the authorized 
tolls, and shall not confer or impose on the lessee any of 
the powers or duties of the promoter in respect of the 
construction or maintenance of the tramway.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>13</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G.". 
2 The relevant provisions of the Land Acquisition Act, <year>1894</year> (1 of  
  <year>1894</year>) to be referred to.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>103219</tid>
<number> 8</number> Further order.
<section><tid>1848181</tid>
<number>1</number>The <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] may, on the application  
of the promoter, revoke, amend, extend or vary the order by a further 
order.

</section>

<section><tid>99920</tid>
<number>2</number>An application for a further order shall be made in the same 
manner and subject to the same conditions as an application for an 
order.

</section>

<section><tid>68120</tid>
<number>3</number>The <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] may, in its discretion, either grant or 
reject the application.

</section>

<section><tid>878075</tid>
<number>4</number>If it grants the application, it shall make the further order 
in the same manner as an order, except that no addition to, or 
modification of, the rights, powers and authorities asked for in the 
application, or restriction or condition with respect thereto, shall 
be made or imposed by the further order without the consent in writing 
of the promoter.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1438743</tid>
<number> 9</number> Power to authorize joint work by local authorities.
<section><tid>171100</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Subject to, and in accordance with, the provisions of this Act, the 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] may, on a joint application, or on two or more 
separate applications, make an order empowering two or more local 
authorities, respectively, jointly to construst the whole, or 
separately to construct parts, of a tramway, and jointly or separately 
to own the whole or parts thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>1491355</tid>
<number>2</number>All the provisions of this Act which relate to the 
construction of tramways shall extend and apply to the construction of 
the whole and the separate parts of the tramway, and the form of the 
order may be adapted to the circumstances of the case.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>400614</tid>
<number> 10</number> Cessation of powers given by an order.
<section><tid>48614</tid>
<number>1</number>If a promoter  
authorized by an order to construct a tramway--

<subsection><tid>88455</tid>
<number>a</number>does not within the time specified in the order 
substantially commence the construction of the tramway, 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>891573</tid>
<number>b</number>having commenced the construction, suspends it without a 
reason sufficient in the opinion of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] 
to warrant the suspension, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>765871</tid>
<number>c</number>does not within the time specified in the order complete 
the tramway and open it for public traffic,
the following consequences shall ensue:--


<subsubsection><tid>327145</tid>
<number>i</number>the powers given by the order to the promoter for 
constructing the tramway and otherwise in relation thereto 
shall, unless the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government], by special direction in 
writing, prolongs the time or condones the suspension,
<pagefootnote><pagenum>14</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G.".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


cease to be exercised except as to so much of the tramway as 
is then completed;


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1298896</tid>
<number>ii</number>as to so much of the tramway as is then completed, 
the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] may either permit, or refuse to permit, 
the powers given by the order to continue;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1205356</tid>
<number>iii</number>if the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] refuses to permit the 
powers to continue, then so much of the tramway as is then 
completed may be dealt with, under the provisions of this 
Act relating to the discontinuance of tramways, as a tramway 
of the working whereof the discontinuance has been proved to 
the satisfaction of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government].

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>735447</tid>
<number>2</number>A notification published by the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] in the 
Official Gazette to the effect that on a date specified in the 
notification the construction of a tramway had not been substantially 
commenced or a tramway had not been completed and opened for public 
traffic, or that the construction of a tramway had been suspended 
without sufficient reason, shall, for the purposes of this section, be 
conclusive proof of the matter stated therein.
CONSTRUCTION AND MAINTENANCE OF TRAMWAYS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>50555</tid>
<number>11</number>Mode of formation of tramway. A tramway shall be constructed 
and maintained in the manner provided by the order.


</article>



<article><tid>364003</tid>
<number>12</number>Inspection of tramway before opening. A tramway, or portion 
or extension of, or addition to, a tramway, shall not be opened for 
public traffic <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> until it has been inspected and certified to be fit 
for such traffic <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> by an engineer appointed by Government]].


</article>



<article><tid>1569523</tid>
<number>13</number>Agreement between road- authority and promoter as to repair of 
roadway. Subject to the provisions of any order for the time being in 
force with respect to the matters mentioned in section 7, sub- section 
 (2), clause (g), the road- authority and the promoter may from time to 
time enter into agreements as to the keeping in repair of the whole or 
a part of a road traversed by a tramway, and as to the proportion to 
be paid by either of them of the expense of keeping the road or part 
in repair.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>15</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G.". 
2 Subs., ibid., for" until an engineer appointed in this behalf by 
the L. G. has inspected it and certified it to be fit for such 
traffic". 
3 Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for certain words.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

TRAFFIC ON TRAMWAYS.



</article>



<article><tid>1938694</tid>
<number> 14</number> Rights of promoters and the public over tramways.
<section><tid>1955257</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
promoter of a tramway shall, subject to the provisions of sub- section 
 (2) and to the other provisions of this Act and of the order, have the 
exclusive use of the tramway for carriages with flange- wheels or other 
wheels suitable to run on the rail described in the order as the rail 
to be used on the tramway:
Provided that nothing in this Act or in the order or any rule 
made under this Act shall affect the right of any person authorized to 
use a tramway or railway to pass across a tramway constructed under 
this Act with carriages having wheels suitable to run on the rail 
thereof.


</section>

<section><tid>558100</tid>
<number>2</number>The public shall have a right to pass along or across any 
part of a road along or across which a tramway is constructed, whether 
on or off the tramway, with carriages not having flange- wheels or 
other wheels suitable to run on the rail of the tramway:
Provided--


<subsection><tid>1041084</tid>
<number>a</number>that this sub- section shall not apply where the tramway 
is constructed on land the right to the exclusive 
possession of which has been acquired by the promoter; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1008604</tid>
<number>b</number>that the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] may by an order authorize the 
construction of a tramway on any part of a road with 
rails raised above the surface of the road, if it is 
satisfied that the convenience of the public will not 
be injuriously affected thereby.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1354666</tid>
<number> 15</number> Tolls leviable by promoter or lessee.
<section><tid>703857</tid>
<number>1</number>The promoter or  
lessee may demand and take, in respect of the tramway, tolls not 
exceeding the limits specified in or determinable under the order, or, 
if the order contains no provision in this behalf, then such sums as 
may from time to time be fixed by the promoter or lessee with the 
previous sanction of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government].

</section>

<section><tid>697406</tid>
<number>2</number>A list of all the tolls authorized to be levied shall be 
exhibited, in such languages as the District Magistrate may direct, in 
a conspicuous place inside and outside each of the carriages used upon 
the tramway.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1204044</tid>
<number> 16</number> Carriage of dangerous or offensive goods.
<section><tid>1638847</tid>
<number>1</number>A person shall  
not be entitled to carry or to require to be carried, on a tramway 
constructed under this Act, any goods of a dangerous or offensive 
nature.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>16</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G.".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1916415</tid>
<number>2</number>A person taking such goods with him on the tramway shall, 
before entering the carriage, give notice of their nature to the 
servant of the promoter or lessee in charge of the carriage.

</section>

<section><tid>679574</tid>
<number>3</number>A person sending such goods by the tramway shall distinctly 
mark their nature on the outside of the package containing them, or 
otherwise give notice thereof in writing to the servant of the 
promoter or lessee with whom he leaves them for the purpose of their 
being sent by the tramway.

</section>

<section><tid>187630</tid>
<number>4</number>Any servant of the promoter or lessee may refuse to carry 
upon the tramway a parcel which he suspects to contain goods of a 
dangerous or offensive nature, and, if any such parcel has been 
received for the purpose of being carried upon the tramway, may stop 
the transit thereof until he is satisfied as to the nature of its 
contents.

</section>

<section><tid>1538804</tid>
<number>5</number>Where a servant of the promoter or lessee refuses under sub- 
section (4) to carry a parcel which has been received for the purpose 
of being carried upon the tramway, he shall, as soon as may be, give 
notice of his refusal to the consignor or consignee if he refuses at a 
time when neither of them is present.
LICENSES TO USE TRAMWAYS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1964224</tid>
<number> 17</number> Grant to third parties of licenses to use tramway in certain 
events. If, at any time after a tramway or part of a tramway has been 
for three years opened for public traffic in a circle, the local 
authority of the circle represents in writing to the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] 
that the public is deprived of the full benefit of the tramway or of 
the part thereof, the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] may, if after considering any 
statement which the promoter or lessee or both may desire to make, and 
after such further enquiry as it deems necessary, it is satisfied as 
to the truth of the representation, grant a license to any person to 
use the tramway conformably to this Act and to the order and the rules 
made under this Act, subject to the following provisions, namely:--
<section><tid>105072</tid>
<number>a</number>the license shall be for a period not less than one year 
or more than three years from the date of the license, 
but the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] may in its discretion renew it;

</section>

<section><tid>488488</tid>
<number>b</number>the license shall be to use the whole of the tramway for 
the time being opened for public traffic, or such part 
or parts of the tramway as the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government], having 
regard to the cause for granting the license, thinks 
fit;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>17</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G.".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>642022</tid>
<number>c</number>the license shall specify the number of carriages which 
the licensee shall run upon the tramway, the mode in 
which, and times at which, the carriages shall be run, 
the tolls to be paid to the promoter or lessee by the 
licensee for the use of the tramway, and the tolls, 
being those for the time being leviable by the promoter 
or lessee, which the licensee may demand and take for 
the use of his carriages;

</section>

<section><tid>1348965</tid>
<number>d</number>the licensee and his officers and servants shall permit 
one person, duly authorized for that purpose by the 
promoter or lessee, to travel free of toll in or upon 
each carriage of the licensee run upon the tramway for 
the whole or any part of a journey;

</section>

<section><tid>718836</tid>
<number>e</number>any provision of this Act, or of the order or rules made 
under this Act, relating to the functions of a servant 
of a promoter or lessee shall be construed, so far as 
may be, as referring to a servant of the licensee; and

</section>

<section><tid>1701680</tid>
<number>f</number>the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] may revoke, alter or modify the 
license for any cause sufficient in its opinion to 
warrant the revocation, alteration or modification 
thereof.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>8333</tid>
<number>18</number>Licensee to give to promoter or lessee an account of traffic. 
A licensee shall, on demand, give to an officer or servant authorized 
in that behalf by the promoter or lessee an exact account in writing, 
signed by the licensee, of the number of passengers, or number or 
quantity of goods, conveyed by any and every carriage used by him on 
the tramway.
DISCONTINUANCE OF TRAMWAYS



</article>



<article><tid>1798472</tid>
<number>19</number>Cessation of powers of promoter and lessee on discontinuance 
of tramway. If it is proved to the satisfaction of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government], 
at any time after the opening of a tramway for public traffic, that 
the working of the tramway, or any part thereof, has been practically 
discontinued, for the space of three months, without a reason 
sufficient, in the opinion of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government], to warrant the 
discontinuance, the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government], if it thinks fit, may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, declare that the powers of the 
promoter and of the lessee, if any, in respect of the tramway or the 
part thereof of which the working has been so discontinued, shall, 
from the date of the notification, be at an end; and thereupon the said 
powers shall cease and determine, except in so far as they may be 
purchased by a local authority in manner by this Act provided.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>18</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G.".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>804604</tid>
<number> 20</number> Powers of road- authority on cessation of powers of promoter.
<section><tid>697685</tid>
<number>1</number>Where a notification has been published under section 19, the 
road- authority may, at any time after the expiration of two months 
from the date of the notification, remove the tramway or part of the 
tramway of which the working has been so discontinued, and use the 
materials thereof in reinstating the road.

</section>

<section><tid>1628320</tid>
<number>2</number>The promoter shall pay to the road- authority the cost 
incurred by that authority in removing the tramway or the part thereof 
and in reinstating the road.

</section>

<section><tid>633747</tid>
<number>3</number>The cost shall be certified by an officer of the road- 
authority, and his certificate, countersigned by the District 
Magistrate, shall be conclusive proof as to the cost incurred.

</section>

<section><tid>992683</tid>
<number>4</number>If the promoter does not pay the amount so certified within 
one month after the delivery to him of the certificate or of a copy 
thereof, the road- authority may, without any previous notice to the 
promoter and without prejudice to any other remedy which it may have 
for the recovery of the amount, sell and dispose of such materials of 
the tramway or part thereof removed as it has not used in reinstating 
the road, either by public auction or by private sale, and for such 
sum or sums, and to such person or persons, as it thinks fit, and may, 
out of the proceeds of the sale, pay and reimburse itself the amount 
of the cost aforesaid and of the expenses of the sale, and shall pay 
over the residue (if any) of the proceeds of the sale to the promoter.
INSOLVENCY OF PROMOTER




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>256368</tid>
<number> 21</number> Proceedings in case of insolvency of promoter.
<section><tid>1576439</tid>
<number>1</number>If, at any  
time after the opening of a tramway in a circle for public traffic, it 
appears to the road- authority or local authority of the circle that 
the promoter of the tramway is insolvent, so that he is unable to 
maintain the tramway, or to work it with advantage to the public, and 
either of those authorities makes a representation to that effect to 
the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government], the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government], may, if after considering any 
statement which the promoter may desire to make, and after such 
further enquiry as it deems necessary, it is satisfied as to the truth 
of the representation, declare, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, that the powers of the promoter shall, at the expiration of 
six months from the publication of the notification, be at an end; and 
the powers of the promoter shall cease and determine at the expiration 
of that period, except in so far as they may be purchased by a local 
authority in manner by this Act provided.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>19</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G.".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>56113</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a notification has been published under sub- section 
 (1), the road- authority may, at any time after the expiration of six 
months from the date thereof, remove the tramway in the same manner, 
and subject to the same provisions as to the payment of the cost of 
the removal and to the same remedy for recovery of the cost, in every 
respect as in cases of removal under section 20.
PURCHASE OF TRAMWAYS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>824157</tid>
<number> 22</number> Future purchase of undertaking by local authority.
<section><tid>412966</tid>
<number>1</number>Where  
the promoter of a tramway in a circle is not the local authority, with 
the previous sanction of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government], may--

<subsection><tid>1884250</tid>
<number>a</number>within such limits of time as may be specified in this 
behalf in the order, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1206279</tid>
<number>b</number>if a time was not specified in the order, then within 
six months after the expiration of a period of twenty- 
one years from the date of the order, and within six 
months after the expiration of every subsequent period 
of seven years, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>351127</tid>
<number>c</number>within two months after the publication of a 
notification under section 19 or within six months 
after the publication of a notification under section 
21,
by notice in writing, require the promoter to sell to the local 
authority his undertaking or the part thereof which is within the 
circle of the local authority; and thereupon the promoter shall sell 
the same upon the terms specified in the order, or, if the terms were 
not specified in the order, then upon the terms of paying the then 
value of the undertaking or of the part thereof, exclusive of any 
allowance for past or future profits of the undertaking or any 
compensation for compulsory sale or other consideration whatsoever.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1516384</tid>
<number>2</number>A requisition shall not be made under sub- section (1) unless 
the making thereof has been approved by the local authority in manner 
prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>344977</tid>
<number>3</number>When a sale has been made under this section, all the rights, 
powers and authorities of the promoter in respect of the undertaking 
or part thereof sold, or, where a notification has been published 
under section 19 or section 21, all the rights, powers and authorities 
of the promoter previous to the publication of the notification in 
respect of the undertaking or part thereof sold, shall be transferred 
to the authority to whom the undertaking or part has been sold, and 
shall vest in, and may be exercised by, that authority in the same 
manner
<pagefootnote><pagenum>20</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G.".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


as if the tramway had been constructed by it under an order made under 
this Act.


</section>

<section><tid>1605970</tid>
<number>4</number>Subject to, and in accordance with, the preceding provisions 
of this section, two or more local authorities may jointly purchase an 
undertaking or so much thereof as is within their circles.
WORKING OF TRAMWAYS OWNED BY LOCAL AUTHORITIES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>971964</tid>
<number> 23</number> Lease of, or working of, tramway by local authority.
<section><tid>796591</tid>
<number>1</number>When  
a local authority has under the authority of an order completed a 
tramway, or has under the provisions of this Act or of an order 
acquired possession of a tramway, it may, by a lease to be approved by 
the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government], let to any person the right of user of the tramway 
and of demanding and taking the authorized tolls.

</section>

<section><tid>1963248</tid>
<number>2</number>On the determination of a lease the local authority may from 
time to time let the right for such further term and on such 
conditions as the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] may approve.

</section>

<section><tid>77316</tid>
<number>3</number>Every lease made under this section shall imply a condition 
of re- entry if at any time after the making thereof it is proved to 
the satisfaction of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] that the lessee has practically 
discontinued the working of the tramway leased, or of any part 
thereof, for the space of one month without a reason sufficient, in 
the opinion of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government], to warrant the discontinuance.

</section>

<section><tid>1550021</tid>
<number>4</number>Notice of the intention of the local authority to make a 
lease shall be given in manner prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>134789</tid>
<number>5</number>If the local authority cannot by means of a lease obtain what 
it deems to be a fair rent for the tramway, it may itself, with the 
previous sanction of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] and for such term as the 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] directs, place and run carriages upon the tramway, and 
demand and take the authorized tolls in respect of the use of the 
carriages.
RULES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>639608</tid>
<number> 24</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1678877</tid>
<number>1</number>In addition to any other power to  
make rules expressly or by implication conferred by this Act, the 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] may make rules consistent with this Act--

<subsection><tid>433499</tid>
<number>a</number>as to the form in which an application for an order 
shall be made;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>21</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G.".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1122993</tid>
<number>b</number>as to the costs to be paid by an applicant in respect of 
an order, and the time when, and the place where, those 
costs shall be paid;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>877019</tid>
<number>c</number>as to the payment of money or lodgment of securities, by 
way of deposit, by the applicant for an order before 
the order is published under section 6, sub- section 
 (4), or a further order is made under section 8; the 
investment of money so paid; the disposal of interest 
or dividends from time to time accruing due on money or 
securities so paid, lodged or invested; the application 
of the money or securities or the produce thereof to 
the discharge of any liability incurred by the 
promoter; and the forfeiture, repayment or return of 
the money or securities;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1084456</tid>
<number>d</number>as to the plans and sections of any works to be 
deposited by applicants for orders or by promoters;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>214943</tid>
<number>e</number>for regulating the use of steam- power or any other 
mechanical power <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or electrical power] on a tramway;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1697189</tid>
<number>f</number>as to any matter specified in section 7, sub- section 
 (2), clauses (c), (d), (e), (j) and (k), as a matter 
which may be provided for in an order, when that matter 
has not been so provided for, or has not, in the 
opinion of the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Government], been effectually so 
provided for;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>5987</tid>
<number>g</number>as to the periodical submission, by promoters, lessees 
and licensees, of accounts of traffic and receipts to 
the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Government] or as that Government directs, and 
as to the forms in which those accounts are to be 
submitted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1866352</tid>
<number>h</number>as to the accidents of which report is to be made to the 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Government] or as that Government directs;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>278846</tid>
<number>i</number>as to any matter respecting which rules may be made 
under this section by a local authority or a promoter 
or lessee; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1984562</tid>
<number>j</number>generally, as to any other matter or thing in respect of 
which it may seem to the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Government] to be expedient 
to make rules for carrying out the purposes of this 
Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1715594</tid>
<number>2</number>A local authority may, from time to time, with the previous 
sanction of the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Government], make rules consistent with this Act
<pagefootnote><pagenum>22</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 5 of <year>1911</year>, s. 6. 
2 Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G.".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


and with the order and any rules made by the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] under this 
Act, for regulating--


<subsection><tid>1772154</tid>
<number>a</number>the rate of speed to be observed in travelling upon a 
tramway within the circle of the local authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>440473</tid>
<number>b</number>the use of animal power on the tramway;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1055473</tid>
<number>c</number>the distances at which carriages using the tramway are 
to be allowed to follow one after the other;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1730612</tid>
<number>d</number>the stopping of carriages using the tramway, and the 
notice to be given to the public of their approach;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>966659</tid>
<number>e</number>the manner in which carriages using the tramway after 
sunset and before sunrise are to be lighted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1195797</tid>
<number>f</number>the traffic on roads along or across which the tramway 
is laid;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1081118</tid>
<number>g</number>the number of passengers which may be carried in any 
carriage;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1279915</tid>
<number>h</number>the licensing and control of drivers, conductors and 
other persons having charge of the carriages of the 
promoter or lessee or a licensee; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>769645</tid>
<number>i</number>generally, the mode of use of the tramway.
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>289163</tid>
<number>3</number>The promoter or lessee of a tramway may, from time to time, 
with the previous sanction of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government], make rules <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> 
consistent with this Act and with the order and any rules made under 
this Act--

<subsection><tid>1852642</tid>
<number>a</number>for preventing the commission of any nuisance in or upon 
any carriage, or in or against any premises, belonging 
to him; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>563298</tid>
<number>b</number>for regulating the travelling in any carriage belonging 
to him.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1806461</tid>
<number>4</number>The <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] may cancel any rule made by a local 
authority or by a promoter or lessee under this section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>804187</tid>
<number> 25</number> Power to impose penalty by rule. The authority making any 
rule under section 24 may direct that a breach of it shall be 
punishable with fine which may extend--
<section><tid>371828</tid>
<number>a</number>if the authority making the rule is the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government], 
to two hundred rupees, and
<pagefootnote><pagenum>23</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G.". 
2 Proviso omitted by the A. O. <year>1950</year>. 
3 For an instance, see Mad. R. and O.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>714267</tid>
<number>b</number>if that authority is a local authority or a promoter or 
lessee, to twenty rupees;
and when the breach is a continuing breach, with a further fine which 
may extend--


</section>

<section><tid>520852</tid>
<number>c</number>if the authority making the rule is the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government], 
to fifty rupees, and

</section>

<section><tid>1179653</tid>
<number>d</number>if that authority is a local authority of a promoter or 
lessee, to five rupees,
for every day after the first during which the breach continues.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1006557</tid>
<number> 26</number> Procedure for making, and publication of, rules.
<section><tid>1849771</tid>
<number>1</number>Every  
authority having power to make rules under any section of this Act 
shall, before making the rules, publish a draft of the proposed rules 
for the information of persons likely to be affected thereby.

</section>

<section><tid>1763520</tid>
<number>2</number>The publication shall be made, in the case of rules made by 
the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government], in such manner as may in its opinion be sufficient 
for giving information to persons interested, and, in the case of 
rules made by a local authority or by a promoter or lessee, in manner 
prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>317042</tid>
<number>3</number>There shall be published with the draft a notice specifying a 
date, not earlier than the expiration of one month after the date of 
publication, at or after which the draft will be taken into 
consideration.

</section>

<section><tid>190092</tid>
<number>4</number>The authority shall receive and consider any objection or 
suggestion which may be made by any person with respect to the draft 
before the date so specified.

</section>

<section><tid>1620424</tid>
<number>5</number>The publication in the Official Gazette of a rule purporting 
to be made under this Act shall be conclusive proof that it has been 
duly made.
OFFENCES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>365758</tid>
<number> 27</number> Penalty for failure of promoter, lessee or licensee to comply 
with act or order. If a promoter--
<section><tid>11448</tid>
<number>a</number>constructs or maintains a tramway otherwise than in 
accordance with the order, or

</section>

<section><tid>611408</tid>
<number>b</number>opens the tramway for traffic or permits it to be so 
opened, before it has been inspected and certified in 
manner required by section 12, or
<pagefootnote><pagenum>24</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G.".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1135221</tid>
<number>c</number>fails to observe any requirement or condition of the 
order for neglect or breach whereof no penalty has been 
expressly provided in the order,
or if a promoter, lessee or licensee runs a carriage on a tramway 
otherwise than in accordance with the order,

he shall (without prejudice to the enforcement or specific  
performance of the requirements of this Act or of the order, or to any 
other remedy which may be obtained against him in a Court of Civil 
  Judicature), on complaint made by the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] or by the local 
authority or road- authority or by the District Magistrate or, with the 
previous sanction of the District Magistrate, by any person 
injuriously affected by the act or omission, be punished with fine 
which may extend to two hundred rupees, and in the case of a 
continuing offence to a further fine which may extend to fifty rupees 
for every day after the first during which the offence continues to be 
committed.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1573082</tid>
<number>28</number>Penalty for obstructing promoter in exercise of his powers. 
If any person without lawful excuse, the burden of proving which shall 
lie upon him, wilfully obstructs any person acting under the authority 
of the promoter in the lawful exercise of his powers in constructing 
or maintaining a tramway, or injures or destroys any mark made for the 
purpose of setting out the line of the tramway, he shall be punished 
with fine which may extend to fifty rupees.


</article>



<article><tid>1505495</tid>
<number> 29</number> Penalty for interfering with tramway. If any person without 
lawful excuse, the burden of proving which shall lie upon him, 
wilfully does any of the following things, namely:--
<section><tid>637815</tid>
<number>a</number>interferes with, removes or alters any part of a tramway 
constructed under this Act, or of the works connected 
therewith, or

</section>

<section><tid>186130</tid>
<number>b</number>places or throws upon or across any such tramway any 
wood, stone, refuse or other thing, or

</section>

<section><tid>207476</tid>
<number>c</number>does anything in such a manner as to obstruct any 
carriage using any such tramway, or

</section>

<section><tid>408478</tid>
<number>d</number>abets within the meaning of the Indian Penal Code (45 of  
  <year>1860</year>.) the doing of, or attempts to do, anything 
mentioned in clause (a), clause (b) or clause (c),
he shall (without prejudice to any other remedy which may be obtained  
  against him in a Court of Civil Judicature) be punished with fine 
which may extend to one hundred rupees.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>25</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G.".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1468702</tid>
<number>30</number>Penalty for using tramway with carriage having flange- wheels. 
If any person, except under a lease from, or by agreement with, the 
promoter, or under license from the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] granted under this 
Act, uses on a tramway, otherwise than as permitted by section 14, a 
carriage having flange- wheels or other wheels suitable to run on the 
rail of the tramway, he shall be punished with fine which may extend 
to two hundred rupees.


</article>



<article><tid>1377212</tid>
<number> 31</number> Penalty for evading payment of proper toll.
<section><tid>1095899</tid>
<number>1</number>If any person  
travelling or having travelled in a carriage of the promoter or lessee 
or of a licensee evades or attempts to evade payment of toll, or if 
any person having paid toll for a certain distance wilfully proceeds 
in any such carriage beyond that distance and does not pay the 
additional toll for the additional distance or attempts to evade 
payment thereof, or if any person wilfully refuses or neglects on 
arriving at the point to which he has paid toll to quit the carriage, 
he shall be punished with fine which may extend to ten rupees.

</section>

<section><tid>20904</tid>
<number>2</number>When a person commits an offence under this section and 
refuses on demand of a servant of the promoter, lessee or licensee to 
give his name and residence, or gives a name or residence which the 
servant has reason to believe to be false, he may be arrested and 
taken to the nearest police- station by the servant or any person whom 
the servant may call to his aid.

</section>

<section><tid>760887</tid>
<number>3</number>When the person is taken to the police- station he shall with 
the least possible delay be forwarded to the nearest Magistrate, 
unless his true name and residence are ascertained, in which case he 
shall be released on his executing a bond for his appearance before a 
Magistrate if so required.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>641992</tid>
<number>32</number>Penalty for taking or sending dangerous or offensive goods 
without giving notice. If any person takes or sends by a tramway any 
goods of a dangerous or offensive nature without giving the notice 
required by section 16, he shall be punished with fine which may 
extend to fifty rupees.


</article>



<article><tid>569876</tid>
<number> 33</number> Penalty for licensee not giving to promoter or lessee an 
account of traffic or giving false account.
<section><tid>1373968</tid>
<number>1</number>If a licensee fails on  
demand to give the account mentioned in section 18, or, with intent to 
evade the payment of tolls, gives a false account when he is called 
upon to give an account under that section, he shall be punished with 
fine which may extend to fifty rupees.

</section>

<section><tid>248629</tid>
<number>2</number>The fine shall be in addition to any tolls payable by the 
licensee to the promoter or lessee in respect of the passengers or 
goods conveyed by the carriage or carriages used by the licensee on 
the tramway.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>26</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G.".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>911967</tid>
<number>34</number>Saving of prosecutions under other laws. Nothing in this Act 
shall prevent a person from being prosecuted under any other law for 
an act or omission which constitutes an offence against this Act or 
the rules made under it, or from being liable under that other law to 
any other or higher punishment or penalty than that provided by this 
Act or the rules made under it:
Provided that a person shall not be punished twice for the same 
offence.

SETTLEMENT OF DIFFERENCES



</article>



<article><tid>1159581</tid>
<number> 35</number> Differences between promoters or lessees and authorities.
<section><tid>995959</tid>
<number>1</number> 
If any difference arises between the promoter or lessee on the one 
hand and the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government], or the local authority, or the road- 
authority, or a person having the charge of any sewers, drains, 
telegraph- lines, gas- pipes, water- pipes or other things in or on land 
occupied by the tramway, on the other hand, with respect to any 
interference or control exercised or claimed to be exercised by, or on 
behalf of, either party by virtue of this or any other Act, or of the 
order or the rules made under this Act, or with respect to the 
propriety of, or the mode of, the execution of any work, or with 
respect to any compensation to be made by or to the promoter or 
lessee, or on the question whether any work is such as ought 
reasonably to satisfy the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] or the road- authority or 
both, or with respect to any other subject or thing regulated by, or 
comprised in, this Act or the order or the rules made under this Act, 
and not otherwise expressly provided for therein, the matter in 
difference shall, except where the parties elect to proceed under 
section 523 of the Code of Civil Procedure, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> (14 of <year>1882</year>.) be 
settled, on the application of either party, by a referee.

</section>

<section><tid>1252660</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the difference is--

<subsection><tid>501563</tid>
<number>a</number>between the promoter or lessee on the one hand and the 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government], either as such or as the road- 
authority, on the other, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>870938</tid>
<number>b</number>between the promotor on the one hand and the local 
authority on the other, with respect to the sum to be 
paid by the local authority for an undertaking or part 
of an undertaking which that authority has required the 
promoter to sell under section 22,
the referee shall be the District Court within the jurisdiction of 
which the tramway is situate, or, where the tramway is within the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>27</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G.". 
2 The relevant provisions of the Arbitration Act, <year>1940</year> (10 of <year>1940</year>) 
to be referred to.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


jurisdiction of more than one District Court, the District Court with 
in the jurisdiction of which the greater part of the tramway is 
situate.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>716732</tid>
<number>3</number>In other cases the referee shall be appointed by the 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government].

</section>

<section><tid>45178</tid>
<number>4</number>Except where the referee is the District Court, the powers 
and procedure of the referee may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1955678</tid>
<number>5</number>In the case of a difference between a promoter on the one 
hand and a local authority on the other, with respect to the sum to be 
paid by the local authority for an undertaking or part of an 
undertaking which that authority has required the promoter to sell 
under section 22, an appeal shall lie to the High Court from the award 
of the referee as from an original decree of the District Court.

</section>

<section><tid>1653151</tid>
<number>6</number>In the case of every other difference the award of the 
referee shall be final.
RECOVERY OF TOLLS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>656960</tid>
<number>36</number>Recovery of moneys due from promoters and, in certain cases, 
from lessees. Any of the following moneys, namely, any rent due to a 
local authority from a lessee, any penalty recoverable from a promoter 
or lessee under an order, any sum payable by a promoter or lessee 
under an award of a referee, the cost of the performance under this 
Act by the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] or by a local authority or road- authority of 
any work required by this Act or by an order to be done by a promoter, 
and the cost incurred by a road- authority in removing a tramway and 
reinstating a road under this Act, may, without prejudice to any other 
remedy that the authority to which the money is due may have by suit 
or otherwise, be recovered by that authority, on application made in 
this behalf to the Collector, as if the sum due were an arrear of 
land- revenue due by the promoter or lessee or his surety (if any):
Provided that nothing in this section shall authorize the arrest 
of the promoter or lessee or his surety in execution of any process 
issued by the Collector.



</article>



<article><tid>114087</tid>
<number> 37</number> Recovery of tolls from licensees.
<section><tid>348926</tid>
<number>1</number>If a licensee fails to  
pay on demand the tolls due for the use of a tramway, the promoter or 
lessee to whom the tolls are due may, without prejudice to the remedy 
which he may have by suit, apply to a Magistrate to recover the amount 
of the tolls, and the Magistrate may, after giving notice to the 
licensee, if possible, and
<pagefootnote><pagenum>28</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G.".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


allowing him an opportunity of being heard, proceed to recover the 
amount by distress and the sale of any carriages or other moveable 
property of the licensee which may be found on the tramway or on 
premises connected therewith.


</section>

<section><tid>109307</tid>
<number>2</number>When a licensee has failed to pay on demand the tolls due 
from him, the promoter or lessee to whom the tolls are due may seize 
any carriage or other moveable property of the licensee on the tramway 
or on premises connected therewith, and detain the same for forty- 
eight hours unless the tolls are sooner paid.

</section>

<section><tid>327201</tid>
<number>3</number>When application is made to a Magistrate under sub- section 
 (1), he may make an interim order of distraint pending his final 
decision.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>182016</tid>
<number>38</number>Recovery of tolls from passengers. Any toll due to a 
promoter, lessee or licensee from a passenger may be recovered either 
by suit or, on application to a Magistrate having jurisdiction within 
any local area in which any part of the tramway is laid, by distress 
and sale of any moveable property belonging to the passenger within 
the local limits of the jurisdiction of the Magistrate.
SAVINGS



</article>



<article><tid>909851</tid>
<number> 39</number> Promoter to have right of user only.
<section><tid>1935328</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding  
anything contained in this Act, or in an order or any rule made under 
this Act, a promoter shall not acquire any right other than that of 
user only over a road along or across which he lays a tramway, nor 
shall anything contained in this Act, or in an order or any rule made 
under this Act, exempt the promoter of a tramway, or any other person 
using the tramway, from the payment of such charges as may lawfully be 
levied in respect of the use of a road or bridge along or across which 
the tramway is laid.

</section>

<section><tid>714015</tid>
<number>2</number>The State Government may, if it thinks fit, fix rates at 
which a promoter, lessee or licensee may compound for the charges 
payable in respect of the use of a road or bridge.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1253707</tid>
<number> 40</number> Saving of power over roads traversed by tramways.
<section><tid>352228</tid>
<number>1</number>Nothing  
in this Act, or in an order or any rule made under this Act, shall 
take away or abridge any power which a road- authority, local authority 
or other person has by law to break up, widen, alter, divert or improve 
a road, railroad or tramway along or across which a tramway is laid.

</section>

<section><tid>1271336</tid>
<number>2</number>The road- authority, local authority or other person executing 
any work referred to in sub- section (1) shall not be liable to pay

<pagefootnote><pagenum>29</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

to a promoter, lessee or licensee any compensation for injury done to 
a tramway by the execution of the work or for loss of traffic 
occasioned by the reasonable use of any power lawfully exercised for 
the execution thereof.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1910863</tid>
<number>41</number>Saving of power of local authority and police to regulate 
traffic on roads. Nothing in this Act, or in an order or any rule made 
under this Act, shall affect the powers of a local authority or of a 
Magistrate or police- officer to regulate the passage of traffic along 
or across a road along or across which a tramway is laid; and the 
authority, Magistrate or officer aforesaid may exercise its or his 
powers as well on as off the tramway and with respect as well to the 
traffic of a promoter, lessee or licensee as to the traffic of other 
persons.
SUPPLEMENTAL PROVISIONS



</article>



<article><tid>531606</tid>
<number>42</number>Promoters, lessees and licensees to be responsible for all 
injuries. A promoter, lessee or licensee shall be answerable for all 
injuries happening through his act or default, or through the act or 
default of any person in his employment, by reason or in consequence 
of any of his carriages or works, and shall save harmless all 
authorities and persons collectively and individually, and their 
officers and servants, from all damages and costs in respect of 
injuries so happening.


</article>



<article><tid>1304076</tid>
<number>43</number>Want of funds not a sufficient reason for default. For the 
purposes of this Act want of funds shall not be deemed to be a 
sufficient reason for the suspension of the construction, or the 
discontinuance of the working, of a tramway by a promoter or lessee.


</article>



<article><tid>1383596</tid>
<number>44</number>Power to exempt from municipal taxation. When a tramway is 
constructed under this Act within the limits of a municipality, the 
State Government may exempt the animals, plant, rolling- stocks, yards, 
workshops, engine- sheds, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> electrical generating stations or sub- 
stations] and depots of the promoter, lessee or licensee, for such 
period as it thinks fit, from all or any municipal taxes leviable 
within those limits.


</article>



<article><tid>1772890</tid>
<number> 45</number> Application by local authorities of local funds to tramways.

<section><tid>696026</tid>
<number>1</number>The fund to or with the control or management of which the local  
authority of a municipality, cantonment or district is entitled or 
entrusted shall, notwithstanding anything in any enactment respecting 
the purposes to which that fund may be applied, be applicable, subject 
to the control of the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> appropriate Government], to the payment of 
expenses incidental to the exercise of the
<pagefootnote><pagenum>30</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 5 of <year>1911</year>, s. 7. 
2 Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G.".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


powers and functions which may be vested in or exercised by a local 
authority under this Act.


</section>

<section><tid>1961560</tid>
<number>2</number>The fund shall also be applicable, with the previous sanction 
of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> appropriate Government], to a guarantee of the payment of 
interest on money to be applied, with the concurrence in writing of 
the local authority, within the limits of the local area under its 
control, to any of the purposes to which the fund might be applied by 
the local authority under sub- section (1).

</section>

<section><tid>533850</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> In this section" the appropriate Government" means the 
Government, Central or State, whose executive authority extends over 
the local authority in question.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>467352</tid>
<number>46</number>Extension of Act to existing tramways. The <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] 
may, with the consent of the local authority and road- authority and of 
the promoter and his lessee (if any), extend any part of this Act, or 
any rules made under this Act, either with or without modification, to 
the whole or any part of a tramway constructed, or authorized by the 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] to be constructed, before the passing of this Act, and 
may withdraw any part of the Act or any rules so extended.


</article>



<article><tid>597764</tid>
<number> 47</number> Prohibition of construction of tramways except under this 
Act.
<section><tid>749711</tid>
<number>1</number>A tramway of which the construction has not been authorized  
by the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] before the passing of this Act shall not, after 
the passing of this Act, be constructed for public traffic in any 
place to which this Act extends, except in pursuance of an order made 
under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>688360</tid>
<number>2</number>A person constructing a tramway in contravention of sub- 
section (1) of this section,
or after the passing of this Act maintaining or using for public 
traffic, otherwise than in pursuance of an order made under this Act, 
a tramway which was not constructed, or authorized by the 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] to be constructed, before the passing of this Act,

shall be liable, on the complaint of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] or local 
authority, to double the penalty to which a promoter acting otherwise 
than in accordance with an order is liable under section 27.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>57251</tid>
<number>48</number>Transfer of control on exclusion of local area from circle of 
local authority. If at any time a local area comprising a tramway to 
which this Act or any part thereof or any rule thereunder applies 
ceases to be
<pagefootnote><pagenum>31</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G.". 
2 Ins., ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


included in the circle of a local authority, the functions of that 
authority under this Act or the part thereof or the rule thereunder, 
and under the order (if any), shall, in respect of that local area, 
devolve on the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Government] or, if that Government so directs, on 
the local authority of the circle in which the tramway has been 
included.



</article>



<article><tid>163375</tid>
<number>49</number>[ Explanation and amendment of section 54 of Railway Act.] 
Rep. by the Indian Railways Act, <year>1890</year> (9 of <year>1890</year>), s. 2 and Sch. I.


</article>



<article><tid>428638</tid>
<number>50</number>Powers of Government exercisable from time to time. All 
powers conferred by this Act on <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> any Government] may be exercised 
from time to time as occasion requires.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>32</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" the L. G.". 
2 Subs., ibid., for" a L. G.".

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>