<act><title>THE MOTOR VEHICLES (ALL INDIA PERMIT FOR TOURIST TRANSPORT OPERA­TORS) RULES, 1993 </title> 
 THE MOTOR VEHICLES (ALL INDIA PERMIT 
FOR TOURIST  
TRANSPORT OPERATORS) RULES, 19931
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title, extent, 
commencement and exemption.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
rules may be called the Motor Vehicles (All India Permit for Tourist Transport 
Operators) Rules, 1993.
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall extend to the 
whole of India.
 </section><section><number>3</number> They shall come into force 
with effect from the date of publication.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The conditions prescribed in 
Rules 82 to 85A of the Central Motor Vehicles Rules, 1989 shall not apply to the 
permits granted under this scheme.
  



</section></article> 
 THE MOTOR VEHICLES (ALL INDIA PERMIT 
FOR TOURIST  
TRANSPORT OPERATORS) RULES, 1993
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these Rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  “Act” means the Motor Vehicles Act, 1988 (59 of 
1988);
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  “Authorisation certificate” means a certificate 
issued by an appropriate authority to a recognised Tourist Transport Operator 
authorising him to operate throughout the territory of India  or in such 
continuous States, not being less than three in number including the State in 
which the permit is issued, on recognised tourist circuits, as are specified in 
the All India Permit for a tourist vehicle granted to him;
 </section><section>       <number>c</number> “Appropriate Authority” means the authority which 
is author­ised under the Act to grant a permit in respect of a tourist vehicle;
 </section><section>       <number>d</number> “Rule” means the rule of the Central Motor 
Vehicles Rules, 1989;
 </section><section>       <number>e</number> “Section” means section of the Act;
 </section><section>        <number>f</number> “Schedule” means a Schedule appended to these 
Rules;
 
1[(g) 
“Tourist Transport Operator” means—
 </section><section>            <number>a</number>  A company or an individual engaged in a 
business of promotion of tourism by providing tourist transport vehicles on 
tourist circuits; or
 </section><section>            <number>b</number>  any travel agency (who possesses his own 
vehicle or have taken a vehicle on lease for this purpose for a period of at 
least one year) run by a company or an individual provides all tickets for 
travel by air, rail, ship, passport, visa and also arrange accommodation, tours, 
entertainment and other tourism related services; or
 </section><section>            <number>c</number>  the tour operator (Company or individual 
who provides for transport, accommodation, sight-seeing, entertainment and other 
tourist related, services for tourist, and who possesses his own vehicle or has 
taken a vehicle on lease for this purpose for a period of at least one year and 
is recognised by the Department of Tourist of the Government of India;]
 
        2[(h)  
“Tourist Circuit” means all places of tourist interest situated in a state for 
which package tours are prepared and sold by the recognised tourist transport 
operator.
 Explanation.—For 
the purpose of removal of doubts, it is clari­fied that the permit covering such 
tourist circuits shall be valid throughout the State.]
  




</section></article> 
 THE MOTOR VEHICLES (ALL INDIA PERMIT FOR 
TOURIST  TRANSPORT OPERATORS) RULES, 1993
  
 <article><number>3</number> Authorisation Certificate shall be issued only to a 
Tourist Transport Operator recognised by the Department of Tourism of the 
Central Government.</article> 
 THE MOTOR VEHICLES (ALL INDIA PERMIT 
FOR TOURIST  
TRANSPORT OPERATORS) RULES, 1993
  
 <article><number>4</number> Form, Contents and 
Duration etc., of the Authorisation Certifi­cate.— 

<section><number>1</number> Every application for the issue of an Authorisation Certifi­cate shall be 
made to the concerned State Transport Authority, in the Form as set forth in the 
First Schedule.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every Authorisation 
Certificate shall be in the Form as set forth in the Second Schedule.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The period of validity of an 
Authorisation Certificate shall not exceed one year at a time.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Authorisation 
Certificate may be renewed on an applica­tion made not less than fifteen days 
before the date of its expiry.
</section></article> 
 THE MOTOR VEHICLES (ALL INDIA PERMIT 
FOR TOURIST  
TRANSPORT OPERATORS) RULES, 1993
  
 <article><number>5</number> Procedure of applying for 
issue of Authorisation Certificate.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An application for an Authorisation Certificate may be made on any working day 
to the State Transport Authority concerned.
 </section><section><number>2</number> A State Transport Authority 
shall not ordinarily refuse to issue an Authorisation Certificate applied for 
under these rules.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Transport Authority may 
reject the application made under sub-rule (1) for good and sufficient reasons 
to be recorded in writing, or where the Authority is of the opinion that this 
would have the effect of increasing the number of Authorisation Certificates 
limited in terms of section 74(3):
 Provided that the Authorisation 
Certificate applied for shall be issued or refused within a period of thirty 
days from the date of receipt of application by the State Transport Authority.
</section></article> 
 THE MOTOR VEHICLES (ALL INDIA PERMIT 
FOR TOURIST  
TRANSPORT OPERATORS) RULES, 1993
  
 <article><number>6</number> Transfer of Permit.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Save as otherwise provided in sub-rule (2), an Authorisation Certificate shall 
not be transferable from one person to another except with the permission of the 
State Transport Authority which issued the Authorisation Certifi­cate and shall 
not, without such permission, confer on any person to whom a vehicle covered by 
the Authorisation Certificate is transferred, any right to use that vehicle in 
the manner author­ised by the Authorisation Certificate.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where the holder of an 
Authorisation Certificate dies, the person succeeding to the possession of the 
vehicles covered by the Authorisation Certificate may, for a period of three 
months use the Authorisation Certificate from the date of death of the holder 
and on his own intention to use the Authorisation Certifi­cate:
 Provided further that no 
Authorisation Certificate shall be so used, except after its renewal, after the 
date on which it would have ceased to be effective in the hands of the deceased 
holder.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The State Transport 
Authority may, on an application made to it within three months of the death of 
the holder of the Authori­sation Certificate, transfer that said certificate to 
the person succeeding to the possession of the vehicle covered by the 
Au­thorisation Certificate:
 Provided that the State 
Transport Authority may entertain an application made after the expiry of the 
said period of three months  if it is satisfied that the applicant was prevented 
from making an application within the specified time.
</section></article> 
 THE MOTOR VEHICLES (ALL INDIA PERMIT 
FOR TOURIST  
TRANSPORT OPERATORS) RULES, 1993
  
 <article><number>7</number> Replacement of vehicle.—The 
holder of an Authorisation Certifi­cate may, with the permission of the State 
Transport Authority by which the Authorisation Certificate was issued, replace 
any vehicle covered by the Authorisation Certificate by any other vehicle of the 
same nature.
 Explanation.—The 
vehicle of same nature would mean having the same seating capacity for which 
permit has been granted and composite fee paid  and such a replacement vehicle 
could be of any other make or model.
</article> 
 THE MOTOR VEHICLES (ALL INDIA PERMIT 
FOR TOURIST  
TRANSPORT OPERATORS) RULES, 1993
  
 <article><number>8</number> Appeals.—Any 
person aggrieved by:—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  the refusal of the State Transport Authority to 
issue an Authorisation Certificate or by condition attached to, an Authorisation 
Certificate issued by him; or
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  the order of revocation or suspension of the 
Authorisa­tion Certificate or by any variation of the condition thereof, or
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  the order of refusal to transfer the 
Authorisation Certificate under rule 6 of these rules or section 12; or
 </section><section>       <number>d</number>  the order of refusal to renew an Authorisation 
Certifi­cate: or
 </section><section>       <number>e</number>  any other order which may be made, 
 may within a period of thirty days from the date on which the said 
order is communicated to the applicant, appeal to the State Transport Appellate 
Tribunal constituted under sub-section (2) of section 89 of the Motor Vehicles 
Act, 1988, who shall after giving such person and the State Transport Authority 
an opportunity of being heard, give a decision thereon, which shall be final.
</section></article> 
 THE MOTOR VEHICLES (ALL INDIA PERMIT 
FOR TOURIST  
TRANSPORT OPERATORS) RULES, 1993
  
 <article><number>9</number> Authorisation Fee.—The 
fee for the issue of an Authorisa­tion Certificate shall be Rs. 500/- per annum 
and every applica­tion for the issue or renewal of the same shall be accompanied 
by a bank draft for the said amount in favour of the appropriate authority.
</article> 
 THE MOTOR VEHICLES (ALL INDIA PERMIT 
FOR TOURIST  
TRANSPORT OPERATORS) RULES, 1993
  
 <article><number>10</number> Seating capacity.—An 
All India Permit for Tourist Transport Operators shall be issued only in respect 
of vehicles with a seating capacity of not more than 

1[39] seats, excluding the driver and the 
conductor. Besides, provision of rule 128 of the Central Motor Vehicles Rules, 
1989, except for sub-rule (11) of the said rules, shall also apply to the 
tourist vehicles.
  


</article> 
 THE MOTOR VEHICLES (ALL INDIA PERMIT 
FOR TOURIST  
TRANSPORT OPERATORS) RULES, 1993
  
 <article><number>11</number> Age of the Tourist 
Coaches.—An All India Permit for 
Tourist Transport Operators shall be deemed to be invalid from the date on which 
the vehicle covered by the said permit completes nine years, in the case of a 
motor cab and eight years in the case of a vehicle other than a motor cab.
 Explanation.—For 
the purpose of this rule, the period of nine or eight years shall be computed 
from the date of initial registra­tion of the tourist vehicle concerned.
</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>12</number> </title>Every motor vehicle or motor cab under the Authorisation Certificate issued under these rules shall exhibit the words ‘All India Tourist Permit' on the back of the motor vehicle in contrasting colours, so as to be clearly visible.] 


 
 <title>“12. Distinguishing Particulars to be exhibited on Motor Vehicle. </title>—A motor vehicle or motor cab covered under the Au­thorisation Certificate issued under these rules shall be paint­ed in white colour with a blue ribbon of 10 centimetres width at the centre of the exterior of the body on both sides of the vehicle, and the word “Tourist” shall be painted inside a circle of 60 centimetres diameter. The permit holder shall also display on the front top of the tourist vehicle, other than a motor cab a board in yellow colour with letters in black colour with the inscription “Approved Tourist Transport Operator No....” in English and Hindi, and also if the permit holder so prefers, in the regional language of the Home State, with the logo Peacock', as specified in Annexure No. 1.” 

</article> 
 THE MOTOR VEHICLES (ALL INDIA PERMIT 
FOR TOURIST  
TRANSPORT OPERATORS) RULES, 1993
  
 <article><number>13</number> List of Tourists.—A 
tourist vehicle, other than motor cab, plying under an All India Permit for a 
Tourist Transport Operator shall at all times carry a list of tourist-passengers 
in respect of each trip, and the list shall be produced on demand by the 
offi­cers authorised to demand production of documents by or under the Act or 
the rules made thereunder.
</article> 
 THE MOTOR VEHICLES (ALL INDIA PERMIT 
FOR TOURIST  
TRANSPORT OPERATORS) RULES, 1993
  
 <article><number>14</number> Quarterly Returns to be 
filed by an All India Tourist Permit Holder.—An 
All India Tourist Permit holder shall file a quar­terly return, in respect of 
the motor vehicle covered by these rules, in the Form set forth in the Third 
Schedule to the appro­priate authority of the State by which the All India 
Permit is granted and the said authority, in turn shall forward copies thereof 
to the appropriate authorities of other States concerned.
</article> 
 THE MOTOR VEHICLES (ALL INDIA PERMIT 
FOR TOURIST  
TRANSPORT OPERATORS) RULES, 1993
  
 <article><number>15</number> Certificate of 
Recognition.—
<section><number>1</number> The eligibility 
conditions for a Certificate of Recognition shall be as set forth in Fourth 
Schedule.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every application for a 
Certificate of Recognition by the Depa­rtment of Tourism, Government of India, 
shall be submitted in the Form prescribed in the Fifth Schedule to the Director 
General of Tourism, Department of Tourism, Government of India, New 
Delhi-110001.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Certificate of 
Recognition shall be granted in the Form prescribed in the Sixth Schedule.
  
</section></article><form>
 

THE MOTOR VEHICLES (ALL INDIA PERMIT 
FOR TOURIST  

TRANSPORT OPERATORS) RULES, 1993
 

 
 



1[FOURTH SCHEDULE
 

[See rule 15(1)]
 

A. Eligibility condition for 
Recognition as approved Tourist  

Transport Operator
 

1. All applications for recognition shall be addressed to the 
Director-General of Tourism, Transport Bhawan, No. 1, Parliament Street, New 
Delhi-110001.
 

     2. (i)  The applications for grant of recognition 
shall be in the prescribed form.
 

        (ii)  The applicant has been in the tourist 
transport hire business for a minimum period of 2 years at the time of 
applica­tion.
 

        (iii)  The Tourist Transport Operator has operated 
in the above 2 years period a minimum number of 3 tourist permits issued by the 
concerned State Transport Authority/Road Transport Author­ity for tourist 
vehicles. Out of these three tourist vehicles at least one must be a car.
 

       (iv)  The applicant has adequate knowledge of 
handling the tourist transport vehicles for transferring tourist from the 
Airport, Railway Stations, etc. and for sight-seeing of tourists both 
foreign and domestic.
 

        (v)  The drivers of the tourist vehicles have 
proper uniform and adequate knowledge of taking the tourist for sight-seeing,
 

       (vi)  The applicant has proper parking space for the 
vehi­cles.
 

       (vii) The Tourist Transport Operator is registered 
with the appro­priate authority for carrying on the business of operating 
tour­ist transport vehicles.
 

    3. (a)  The two years period of operating the Tourist 
Transport business may be relaxable to 1 year in the case of those appli­cants 
who have operated 5 tourist vehicles with the proper State Transport 
Authority/Road Transport Authority permits for 1 year. These 5 tourist vehicles 
should be in any combination of cars/Air-conditioned Coaches/Mini Coaches 
provided there are minimum of at least 2 cars in the fleet of tourist vehicles.
 

        (b)  For Ex-Defence personnel the condition of 
being in the business of tourist transport vehicles for two years and having 3 
vehicles is relaxable provided the candidate is sponsored by the Director 
General of Resettlement, Ministry of Defence, New Delhi. In the case of such 
personnel they can operate the tourist trans­port business with 1 tourist 
vehicle only. However, the Ex-Defence personnel who apply under this scheme must 
themselves operate the tourists transport business and should not be hiremen of 
other Financiers.
 

        (c)  The condition of being in operation for 2 
years’ period for tourist transport operator’s approval may also be relaxable in 
the case of those applicants who have located their business at the cities 
mentioned below:—
 

              (i) Amritsar (Punjab)
 

             (ii) Bodhgaya (Bihar)
 

            (iii) Bhopal (Madhya Pradesh)
 

            (iv) Bhubaneshwar (Orissa)
 

             (v) Chandigarh
 

            (vi) Goa
 

           (vii) Hyderabad (Andhra Pradesh)
 

           (viii) Hardwar (Uttar Pradesh)
 

            (ix) Khajuraho (Madhya Pradesh)
 

             (x) Port Blair (The Andaman and Nicobar 
Island)
 

            (xi) Pathankot (Punjab)
 

           (xii) Srinagar (Jammu &amp; Kashmir)
 

           (xiii) Tiruchirapalli (Tamil Nadu)
 

          (xiv) Udaipur (Rajasthan)
 

           (xv) Visakhapatnam (Andhra Pradesh)
 

4. The Tourist Transport Operation will be required to pay a 
non-refundable one time fee of Rs. 500 while applying for the recognition. The 
fee will be made payable to the Pay and Accounts Officer, Department of Tourism 
in the form of a Bank Draft.
 

5. The applicant should be income-tax assessee and should 
submit copy of acknowledgment Certificate as proof having filed income-tax 
return for current assessment year.
 


2[6. The 
decision of the Department of Tourism, Government of India, in the matter of 
recognition shall be final. The Govern­ment of India may in its discretion 
refuse to recognise any Tour Operator or withdraw or withhold at any time 
recognition granted to any Tour Operator, but before applying such discretion, 
it shall be lawful for the Government of India to issue show cause notice to the 
aggrieved Tour Operator and to consider his reply on merit and to communicate 
him the decision taken on such con­sideration.]
 

7. Recognition once granted shall continue unless revoked and 
subject to their continuance in this business and their submit­ting the 
requisite return of Income-tax and other particulars.
 

8. Tourist Transport Operator granted recognition shall be 
enti­tled to such incentives and concessions as may be granted by Government 
from time to time and shall abide by the terms and conditions of recognition as 
prescribed from time to time.
 

 
 

B. Eligibility conditions for 
recognition as approved travel agency
 

1. All applications for recognition shall be addressed to the 
Director General of Tourism, Transport Bhavan, No. 1, Parliament Street, New 
Delhi-110001.
 

2. The following conditions must be fulfilled by the Travel 
Agency for grant of recognition by Department of Tourism:—
 

         (i)  The application for grant of recognition 
shall be in the prescribed form.
 

        (ii)  The Travel Agency has a minimum paid-up 
capital of Rs. 2.00 lakh duly supported by the audited balance sheet/Chartered 
Ac­countant’s certificate.
 

        (iii)  The Travel Agency should be approved by 
Interna­tional Air Transport Association (IATA) or General Sales Agent (GSA) of 
an International Air Transport Association member Air­lines.
 

       (iv)  The Travel Agency has an office under the 
charge of a full time member of their staff, who is adequately 
trained/ex­perienced in matters regarding ticketing, itineraries, accommoda­tion 
facilities, currency, customs relations and other travel and tourism related 
services.
 

        (v)  The Travel Agency has been in operation for a 
period of one year before the date of application.
 

       (vi)  The Travel Agency is an income-tax assessee 
and has filed Income-tax Return for the current assessment year.
 

3. Recognition as Travel Agency once granted shall continue 
unless withdrawn and subject to their continued membership of International Air 
Transport Association or continuance as General Sales Agent of an International 
Air Transport Association member airlines, as the case may be, and their 
submitting the requisite annual return of Income-tax and other particulars.
 

4. The Travel Agency will be required to pay a non-refundable 
one time fee of Rs.1000/- while applying for the recognition. The fee will be 
payable to the Pay and Accounts Officer, Department of Tourism, in the form of a 
Bank Draft. Fee for recognition of each Branch Office will be Rs. 500/-.
 

5. Recognition will be granted to the Headquarters office of 
the Travel Agency. Branch Offices will be approved alongwith the contractors 
office or subsequently, provided the particulars of Branch Offices are submitted 
to Department of Tourism and ac­cepted by it.
 

6. The decision of the Department of Tourism, Government of 
India, in the matter of recognition shall be final. The Govern­ment of India 
may, in their discretion refuse to recognise any time or withdraw/withhold at 
any time recognition already granted without assigning any reason.
 

7. Travel Agency granted recognition shall be entitled to such 
incentives and concessions as may be granted by the Government of India from 
time to time and shall abide by the terms and condi­tions of recognition as 
prescribed from time to time.
 

 
 

C. Eligibility conditions for 
recognition as approved tour opera­tor
 

1. All applications for recognition shall be addressed to the 
Director-General of Tourism, Transport Bhawan, No. 1, Parliament Street, New 
Delhi-110001.
 

        2.   (i) The application for grant of recognition 
shall be in the prescribed form.
 

             (ii) The Tour Operator should have a minimum 
paid-up capital of Rs. 1.00 lakh fully supported by the latest audited balance 
sheet/Chartered Accountant’s Certificate.
 

            (iii) The turn-over in terms of foreign 
exchange or Indian rupees by the firm from tour operation only should be a 
minimum of Rs. 5.00 lakh duly supported by Chartered Accountant’s Certificate.
 

            (iv) The Tour Operator has an office under the 
charge of a full time member of their staff, who is adequately 
trained/ex­perienced in matters regarding transport, accommodation, currency, 
customs regulations and General information about travel and tourism related 
services.
 

             (v) The Tour Operator should have been in 
operation for a minimum period of one year before the date of application.
 

            (vi) The Tour Operator will have to be 
Income-tax assessee and should have filed Income-tax return for the current 
assess­ment year.
 

3. The recognition as approved Tour Operator once granted 
shall continue unless withdrawn subject to their continuance in this business 
and their submitting the requisite annual return of Income-tax particulars.
 

4. The Tour Operator will be required to pay a non-refundable 
one time fee of Rs. 1,000 while applying for the recognition. The fee will be 
made payable to the Pay and Accounts Officer, Depart­ment of Tourism in the form 
of a Bank Draft. The fee for recogni­tion of each Branch Office will be Rs. 500.
 

5. Recognition will be granted to the Headquarters Office of 
Tour Operators. Branch Offices will be approved alongwith the Head-Quarters 
office or subsequently, provided the particulars of the Branch Offices submitted 
to Department of Tourism and accepted by it.
 


3[6. The 
decision of the Department of Tourism, Government of India, in the matter of 
recognition shall be final. The Government of India may, in its discretion, 
refuse to recognise any Tour Operator or withdraw or withhold at any time 
recognition granted to any Tour Operator, but before applying such discretion, 
it shall be lawful for the Government of India to issue show cause notice to the 
aggrieved Tour Operator and to consider his reply on merit and to communicate 
him the decision taken on such consideration.]
 

7. Tour Operator granted recognition shall be entitled to such 
incentives and concessions as may be granted by Government from time to time and 
shall abide by the terms and conditions of recognition as prescribed from time 
to time by the Department of Tourism, Government of India.
 


 
 


—————
 

   1.  Schedules Fourth, Fifth and Sixth subs. by G.S.R. 286 
(E), dated 22nd March, 1995 (w.e.f. 22-3-1995).
 

   2.  Subs. by G.S.R. 83(E), dated 23rd February, 1998 (w.e.f. 
23-2-1998).
 

   3.  Subs. by G.S.R. 83(E), dated 23rd February, 1998 (w.e.f. 
23-2-1998).
 


 
</form><form>
 

THE MOTOR VEHICLES (ALL INDIA PERMIT 
FOR TOURIST  

TRANSPORT OPERATORS) RULES, 1993
 

 
 

FIFTH SCHEDULE
 

[See rule 15(2)]
 

A. Application form for Recognition 
as approved  

Tourist Transport Operator
 

1. Name of the firm with address, telephone, telex and fax 
number.
 

2. Nature of the firm and date of registration/commencement of 
business with documentary proof.
 

3. Whether the office is located in 
residential/commercial/indus­trial area.
 

4. Name, experience, qualifications of the proprietor/Managing 
Director.
 

5. Total number of staff including drivers.
 

6. Name of the Travel Agents/Tour Operators/Hotels/Airlines 
with whom most business is transacted.
 

7. Please attach a copy of the audited balance sheet and 
profit and loss statement duly certified by the Chartered Accountant for the 
year preceding the date of application alongwith copy of acknowledgement 
certificate, in respect of Income-tax Return for current assessment year.
 

8. Please indicate the loans and mortgages as on the date of 
application.
 

9. Number of vehicles viz., Air-conditioned coaches, 
non-Air condi­tioned Coaches, Mini Coaches, Cars and Boats operated as tourist 
vehicles with their make, model and registration.
 

10. Attested copies of valid permits issued by Road Transport 
Authority/State Transport Authority for tourist vehicles and Registered 
Certificate Books of Tourist vehicles should be fur­nished.
 

11. Number and date of Bank Demand Draft for Rs. 500/- in 
favour of Pay and Accounts Officer, Department of Tourism, New Delhi.
 


Signature................
 


Designation..........................
 

Rubber stamp of 
company...........
 

 
 

B. APPLICATION FORM FOR RECOGNITION 
AS APPROVED TRAVEL AGENCY
 

1. Name and address of Head Office and Branch Offices.
 

2. Nature of the firm and the year when the firm was 
registered or commenced business with documentary proof.
 

3. Name of Directors/Partners etc. The details of their 
inter­ests, if any, in other business may also be indicated.
 

4. Give particulars of staff employed, their qualifications, 
experience, salary and length of service with the firm.
 

5. Name of Bankers (Please attach a reference from your 
ban­kers).
 

6. Name of Audtors. A balance-sheet and profit and loss 
statement pertaining to the travel business, as prescribed under Company Law, 
must be submitted by each applicant. These audited statements should be in 
respect of your establishment for the last completed financial year or for the 
calendar year immediately preceding the date of submission of your application. 
Also furnish details of your turnover in the following statement:—
 

Name and particulars of the Travel Agency concerned
 

        (a)  Paid up capital
 

        (b)  Loans
 

              (i) Secured
 

             (ii) Unsecured
 

        (c)  Reserves
 

        (d)  Current liabilities and provision
 

        (e)  Fixed Assets (excluding Intangible assests)
 

         (f)  Investment
 

        (g)  Current Assets
 

        (h)  Intangible assets.
 


Total................
 

Notes.—(i) Reserves would include balance of Profit 
and Loss Account and would exclude taxation reserve.
 

             (ii) Current liabilities and provisions would 
include taxa­tion reserve.
 

            (iii) Current assets would include sundry 
debts, loans and advances, cash and bank balance.
 

            (iv) Intangible assets would include goodwill, 
preliminary expenses, tendency and business rights, deferred Revenue expenditure 
accumulated loss, etc.
 

7. Copy of acknowledgement certificate in respect of 
Income-tax return for the current assessment year should be enclosed.
 

8. Whether any other activities are undertaken by the firm 
besides travel related activities.
 

9. Please indicate the air/shipping/railway ticketing held by 
the firm.
 

10. Please indicate membership of International Travel 
Organisa­tion, if any.
 

11. Letter of approval of International Air Transport 
Associa­tion and certificate of endorsement for current year should be enclosed. 
General Sales Agents of any International Air Transport Association Airlines 
should enclose documentary proof in this regard.
 

12. Please enclose a Demand Draft of Rs. 1000 for Head Office 
and Rs. 500 for each Branch Office as fee for recognition, and mention the 
Demand Draft number, date and amount in this column.
 

Signature of the 
Proprietor/Partner/Managing Director..........
 

Rubber 
Stamp................
 

 
 

C. APPLICATION FORM FOR RECOGNITION 
AS APPROVED TOUR OPERATOR
 

1. Name and address of Head Office and Branch Office.
 

2. Nature of the firm and the year when the firm was 
registered or commenced business, with documentary proof.
 

3. Name  of Directors/Partners, etc. The details of 
their interests, if any, in other business may also be indicated.
 

4. Give particulars of staff employed, their qualifications, 
experience, salary and length of service with the firm.
 

5. Name of Bankers (Please attach a reference from your 
ban­kers).
 

6. Name of Auditors. A balance-sheet and Profit and Loss 
state­ment pertaining to tour operation business, as prescribed under Company 
Law, must be submitted by each applicant. These audited statements should be in 
respect of your establishment for the last completed financial year or for the 
calendar year immediate­ly preceding the date of submission of your application. 
Also furnish details of your turnover in the following statement:—
 

Name and particulars of the operator concerned:
 

        (a)  Paid up capital
 

        (b)  Loans
 

              (i) Secured
 

             (ii) Unsecured
 

        (c)  Reserves
 

        (d)  Current liabilities and provisions
 

        (e)  Fixed assets (excluding intangible assets)
 

         (f)  Investment
 

        (g)  Current Assets
 

        (h)  Intangible assets
 


                              Total:
 

Notes.— (i) Reserves would include balance of 
Profit and Loss Account and would exclude taxation reserve.
 

             (ii) Current liabilities and provisions would 
include taxa­tion reserve.
 

            (iii) Current assets would include sundry 
debts, loans and advances, cash and bank balance.
 

            (iv) Intangible assets would include goodwill, 
preliminary expenses, balance and business rights, deferred revenue 
expendi­ture, accumulated loss, etc.
 

7. Copy of acknowledgement certificate in respect of 
income-tax return for the current assessment year should be enclosed.
 

8. Whether any other activities are undertaken by the firm 
besides Tour Operation.
 

9. Member of International Travel Operations.
 

       10. (a) Give details of volume of tourist traffic 
handled upto the date of application showing foreign and internal tourist 
traffic separately. Please submit a certificate from Chartered Accountant. This 
certificate should show the receipts from tour operation only during the 
financial year or the calendar year immediately preceding the date of submission 
of your applica­tion.
 

             (b) Clientale : Special tourist groups 
handled, if any, their size, frequency, etc.
 

             (c) Steps taken to promote domestic tourist 
traffic and details of groups handled if any.
 

             (d) Special programmes, if any, arranged for 
foreign tour­ists.
 

11. Number of Conferences handled, if any, and the total 
number of passengers for such Conferences with details of location, etc.
 

12. Number of incentive tours handled.
 

13. Please enclose a Demand Draft of Rs. 1,000 for Head Office 
and Rs. 500 for each Branch office as fee for recognition and mention the Demand 
Draft Number, date and amount in this column.
 

Signature of 
Proprietor/Partner/Managing Director
 

Rubber Stamp of the 
firm:
 

 
 

 
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 444(E), dated 26th June, 2007, for ‘rule 12' (w.e.f. 26-6-2007). Rule 12, before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>