<act><tid>1551389</tid>
<title>THE REFORMATORY SCHOOLS ACT, <year>1897</year></title>

ACT NO. 8 OF <year>1897</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 11th March, <year>1897</year>.]

An Act to amend the law relating to Reformatory Schools and to 
make further provisions for dealing with youthful offenders.

WHEREAS it is expedient to amend the law relating to Reformatory 
Schools and to make further provision for dealing with youthful 
offenders; It is hereby enacted as follows:--





<article><tid>209856</tid>
<number> 1</number> Title and extent.
<section><tid>1906347</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Reformatory  
Schools Act, <year>1897</year>
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>


</section>

<section><tid>1335024</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> It extends to the whole of India except <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> the territories 
which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in 
Part B States].]
 2 an

Repeals.

 2 and 3.[ Repeals.] Rep. by the Repealing Act, <year>1938</year> (1 of <year>1938</year>), 
s. 2 and Sch.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1460</tid>
<number> 4</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant 
in the subject or context,-
<section><tid>139751</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>" youthful offender" means any boy who has been con- 
victed of any offence punishable with transportation or 
imprisonment and who, at the time of such conviction, was 
under the age of fifteen years:

</section>

<section><tid>1207722</tid>
<number>b</number>" Inspector General" includes any officer appointed by 
the State Government to perform all or any of the duties 
imposed by this Act on the Inspector General: and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>30</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Rep. in W. Bengal by W. Bengal 30 of <year>1959</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>1</number>The provisions of this Act, except s. 15, cease to be in force 
in the areas where the Madras Children Act, <year>1920</year> (Mad. 4 of <year>1920</year>), or 
the Bengal Children Act, <year>1922</year> (Ben. 2 of <year>1922</year>), is in force.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The word" and" and sub- section (2) rep. by Act 10 of <year>1914</year>, s. 3 
and Sch. II.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1948</year>, for the original sub- section (3) as 
amended by the A. O. <year>1937</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" Part 
B States".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>In Bombay the age- limit has been raised to 16; see the Bombay 
Children Act, <year>1924</year> (Bom. 13 of <year>1924</year>), s. 4. In the C. P. this 
definition has been replaced by another; see the C. P. children Act, 
<year>1928</year> (C. P. Act 10 of <year>1928</year>), s. 3.

Extended to the whole of Madhya Pradesh by Madhya Pradesh Act 23 of 
<year>1958</year> (When notified).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1287373</tid>
<number>c</number>" District Magistrate" shall include a Chief Presidency 
Magistrate.
II.- REFORMATORY SCHOOLS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1301735</tid>
<number> 5</number> Power to establish and discontinue reformatory schools. <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 
The State Government may-
<section><tid>58308</tid>
<number>a</number>establish and maintain Reformatory Schools at such 
places as it may think fit;

</section>

<section><tid>1349553</tid>
<number>b</number>use as Reformatory Schools schools kept by persons 
willing to act in conformity with such rules, consistent with 
this Act, as the State Government may prescribe in this 
behalf;

</section>

<section><tid>961385</tid>
<number>c</number>direct that any school so established or used shall 
cease to exist as a Reformatory School or to be used as such.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>995600</tid>
<number> 6</number> Requisites of Schools. Every school so established or used must 
provide-
<section><tid>367818</tid>
<number>a</number>sufficient means of separating the inmates at night;

</section>

<section><tid>1332711</tid>
<number>b</number>proper sanitary arrangements, water- supply, food, 
clothing and bedding for the youthful offenders detained 
therein;

</section>

<section><tid>1164518</tid>
<number>c</number>the means of giving such youthful offenders industrial 
training;

</section>

<section><tid>770491</tid>
<number>d</number>an infirmary or proper place for the reception of such 
youthful offenders when sick.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1469390</tid>
<number> 7</number> Inspection of Reformatory Schools.
<section><tid>1410667</tid>
<number>1</number>Every school intended to  
be established or used as a Reformatory School shall, before being 
used as such, be inspected by the Inspector General, and if he finds 
that the requirements of section 6 have been complied with, and that, 
in his opinion, such school is fitted for the reception of such 
youthful offenders as may be sent there under this Act, he shall 
certify to that effect, and such certificate <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> shall be published in 
the Official Gazette, together with an order of the State Government 
establishing the school as a Reformatory School or directing that it 
shall be used as such, and the school shall thereupon be deemed to be 
a Reformatory School.

</section>

<section><tid>681570</tid>
<number>2</number>Every such school shall, from time to time, and at least 
once in every year, be visited by the said Inspector General, who 
shall

<pagefootnote><pagenum>31</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" With the previous sanction of the G. G. in C." rep. 
by Act 4 of <year>1914</year>, s. 2 and Sch., Pt. I.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>For instance of the publication of such a certificate, see C. 
P. R. and O.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

send to the State Government a report on the condition of the school 
in such form as the State Government may prescribe.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>618302</tid>
<number> 8</number> Power to Courts to direct youthful offenders to be sent to 
Reformatory Schools.
<section><tid>443998</tid>
<number>1</number>Whenever any youthful offender is sentenced  
to transportation or imprisonment, and is, in the judgment of the 
Court by Co which he is sentenced, a proper person to be an inmate of 
a Reformatory School, the Court may, subject to any rules made by 
the State Government, direct that, instead of undergoing his sentence, 
he shall be sent to such a school, and be there detained for a period 
which shall be not less than <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> three or more than seven years.

</section>

<section><tid>403565</tid>
<number>2</number>The powers so conferred on the Court by this section shall 
be exercised only by (a) the High Court, (b) a Court of Session, (c) a 
District Magistrate, and (d) any Magistrate specially empowered by the 
State Government in this behalf, and may be exercised by such Courts 
whether the case comes before them originally or on appeal.

</section>

<section><tid>1467336</tid>
<number>3</number>The State Government may make rules for-

<subsection><tid>175072</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> defining what youthful offenders should be sent to Re- 
formatory Schools, having regard to the nature of their 
offences or other considerations, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1078658</tid>
<number>b</number>regulating the periods for which youthful offenders may 
be sent to such schools according to their ages or other con- 
siderations. <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1574959</tid>
<number> 9</number> Procedure where Magistrate is not empowered to pass an order 
under section 8.
<section><tid>1970148</tid>
<number>1</number>When any Magistrate not empowered to pass an  
order under the last foregoing section is of opinion that a youthful 
offender convicted by him is a proper person to be an inmate of a 
Reformatory School, he may, without passing sentence, record such 
opinion and submit his proceedings and forward the youthful offender 
to the District Magistrate to whom he is subordinate.

</section>

<section><tid>1425248</tid>
<number>2</number>The Magistrate to whom the proceedings are so submitted may 
make such further inquiry (if any) as he may think fit and pass such 
sentence and order for the detention in a Reformatory School of the 
youthful offender, or otherwise, as he might have passed if such 
youthful offender had been originally tried by him.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>32</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This part of the section has been amended in Bombay by the 
Bombay Children Act, <year>1924</year> (Bom. 13 of <year>1924</year>), s. 4, and in the C. P. by 
the C. P. Children Act, <year>1928</year> (C. P. 10 of <year>1928</year>), s. 3.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>For rules made under this clause by the Punjab Government, see 
Punjab Gazette, Extraordinary, dated 2nd October. <year>1903</year>, p. 3.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>For rules regulating the period for which youthful offenders 
may be sent to Reformatories, see different local R. and O.





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>255399</tid>
<number>10</number>Power of Magistrates to direct boys under fifteen sentenced to 
imprisonment to be sent to Reformatory Schools. The officer in charge 
of a prison in which a youthful offender is confined, in execution of 
a sentence of imprisonment, may bring him, if he has not then attained 
the age of fifteen years, before the District Magistrate within whose 
jurisdiction such prison is situate; and such Magistrate may, if such 
youthful offender appears to be a proper person to be an inmate of a 
Reformatory School, direct that, instead of undergoing the residue of 
his sentence, he shall be sent to a Reformatory School, and there 
detained for a period which shall be subject to the same limitations 
as are prescribed by or under section 8, with reference to the period 
of detention thereby authorised.


</article>



<article><tid>1885752</tid>
<number> 11</number> Preliminary inquiry and finding as to age of youthful 
offender.
<section><tid>1042823</tid>
<number>1</number>Before directing any youthful offender to be sent to a  
Reformatory School under section 8, section 9 or section 10, the Court 
or Magistrate shall inquire into the question of his age and, after 
taking such evidence (if any) as may be deemed necessary, shall record 
a finding thereon, stating his age as nearly as may be.

</section>

<section><tid>919276</tid>
<number>2</number>A similar inquiry shall be made and finding recorded by every 
Magistrate not empowered to pass an order under section 8 before 
submitting his proceedings and forwarding the youthful offender to the 
District Magistrate as required by section 9, sub- section (1),



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1760863</tid>
<number> 12</number> Government to determine Reformatory School to which such 
offenders shall be sent. Every youthful offender directed by a Court 
or Magistrate to be sent to a Reformatory School shall be sent to such 
Reformatory School as the State Government may, by general or special 
order, appoint for the reception of youthful offenders so dealt with 
by such Court or Magistrate:
Provided that, if accommodation in a Reformatory School is not 
immediately available for such youthful offender, he may be detained 
in the juvenile ward or such other suitable part of a prison as the 
State Government may direct-

<section><tid>781965</tid>
<number>a</number>until he can be sent to a Reformatory School, or

</section>

<section><tid>848654</tid>
<number>b</number>until the term of his original sentence expires,
whichever event may first happen. Should the term of his original 
sentence first expire, he shall thereupon be released, but, should he 
be sent to a Reformatory School, then the period of detention 
previously undergone shall be treated as detention in a Reformatory 
School.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1109054</tid>
<number> 13</number> Persons found to be over eighteen years not to be detained in 
Reformatory School.
<section><tid>775474</tid>
<number>1</number>If at any time after a youthful offender has  
been sent to a Reformatory School it appears to the Committee of 
Visitors or Board of Management, as the case may be, that the age of 
such youthful

<pagefootnote><pagenum>33</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

offender has been understated in the order for detention, and that he 
will attain the age of eighteen years before the expiration of the 
period for which he has been ordered to be detained, they shall report 
the case for the orders of the State Government.


</section>

<section><tid>229836</tid>
<number>2</number>No person shall be detained in a Reformatory School after he 
has been found by the State Government to have attained the age of 
eighteen years.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>352735</tid>
<number> 14</number> Discharge or removal by order of Government. The State 
Government may at any time order any youthful offender-
<section><tid>1598311</tid>
<number>a</number>to be discharged from a Reformatory School;

</section>

<section><tid>453045</tid>
<number>b</number>to be removed from one Reformatory School to another 
such school situate within the territories subject to such 
Government: Provided that the whole period of his detention 
in a Reformatory School shall not be increased by such 
removal.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>128618</tid>
<number>15</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Agreement between States. The State Governments of any two 
States may after mutual agreement, generally or specially, notify in 
their respective Official Gazettes that any Reformatory School 
situated in one of the States shall be available for the reception of 
youthful offenders directed to be sent to a Reformatory School by any 
Court or Magistrate in the other State and may thereupon make 
provision for the removal of youthful offenders accordingly.]


</article>



<article><tid>1164924</tid>
<number>16</number>Certain orders not subject to appeal or revision. Nothing 
contained in the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1882</year> (10 of <year>1882</year>), 
shall be construed to authorise any Court or Magistrate to alter or 
reverse in appeal or revision any order passed with respect to the age 
of a youthful offender or the substitution of an order for detention 
in a Reformatory School for transportation or imprisonment.
III.- MANAGEMENT OF REFORMATORY SCHOOLS



</article>



<article><tid>606764</tid>
<number> 17</number> Appointment of Superintendent and Committee of Visitors or 
Board of Management.
<section><tid>745102</tid>
<number>1</number>For the control and management of every  
Reformatory School, the State Government shall <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> appoint either (a) a 
Superintendent and a Committee of Visitors, or (b) a Board of 
Management.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>34</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for the original s. 15.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>See now the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1898</year> (5 of <year>1898</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>For notification making such appointments, see different local 
Rules an Orders.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>802566</tid>
<number>2</number>Every Committee and every Board so appointed must consist of 
not less than five persons <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>.

</section>

<section><tid>1583649</tid>
<number>3</number>The State Government may suspend or remove any Super 
intendent or any Member of a Committee or Board so appointed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1987250</tid>
<number> 18</number> Superintendent may license youthful offenders to employers of 
labour.
<section><tid>381467</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Superintendent so appointed may, with the sanction  
of the Committee, by license under his hand, permit any youthful 
offender sent to a Reformatory School, who has attained the age of 
fourteen years, to live under the charge of any trustworthy an 
respectable person named in the license, or any officer of Government 
or of a Municipality, being an employer of labour and willing to 
receive and take charge of him, on the condition that the employer 
shall keep such youthful offender employed at some trade, occupation 
or calling.

</section>

<section><tid>1247078</tid>
<number>2</number>The license shall be in force for three months and no longer 
but may, at any time and from time to time until the expiration of the 
period for which the youthful offender has been directed to be 
detained, be renewed for three months at a time.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>459311</tid>
<number>19</number>Cancellation of license. The license shall be cancelled at the 
desire of the employer named in the license.


</article>



<article><tid>1234509</tid>
<number>20</number>Determination of license. If during the term of the license 
the employer named therein dies, or ceases from business or to employ 
labour, or the period for which the youthful offender has been 
directed to be detained in the Reformatory School expires, the license 
shall thereupon cease and determine.


</article>



<article><tid>169198</tid>
<number>21</number>Cancellation of license in case of ill- treatment. If it 
appears to the Superintendent that the employer has illtreated the 
youthful offender, or has not adequately provided for his lodging and 
maintenance, the Superintendent may cancel the license.


</article>



<article><tid>1763519</tid>
<number> 22</number> Superintendent to be deemed guardian of youthful offenders.

<section><tid>223830</tid>
<number>1</number>The Superintendent of a Reformatory School shall be deemed to be  
the guardian of every youthful offender detained in such school, 
within the meaning of <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Act No. 19 of <year>1850</year> (concerning the binding of  
  apprentices).

</section>

<section><tid>844988</tid>
<number>2</number>Power to apprentice youthful offender. If it appears to the 
Superintendent that any youthful offender licensed under section 18 
has behaved well during one or more periods

<pagefootnote><pagenum>35</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" of whom two at least shall be Natives of India 
omitted by the A. O. <year>1950</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The Apprentices Act, <year>1850</year>.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

of his license, the Superintendent may, with the sanction of the Com- 
mittee, apprentice him under the provisions of the said Act, and on 
such apprenticement the right to detain such youthful offender in a 
Reformatory School shall cease and the unexpired term (if any) of his 
sentence shall be cancelled.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>399284</tid>
<number> 23</number> Duties of Committee of Visitors.
<section><tid>1245739</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Committee of  
Visitors appointed under section 17 for a Reformatory School shall. at 
least once in every month,--

<subsection><tid>1236846</tid>
<number>a</number>visit the school, to hear complaints and see that the 
requirements of section 6 have been complied with, and that 
the at management of the school is proper in all respects

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1962085</tid>
<number>b</number>examine the punishment- book;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>282942</tid>
<number>c</number>bring any special cases to the notice of the Inspector- 
General; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1688923</tid>
<number>d</number>see that no person is illegally detained in the school.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1883721</tid>
<number>2</number>If any member of a Committee of Visitors so appointed fails 
or neglects, during a period of six consecutive months, to visit the 
school and assist in the discharge of the duties aforesaid, he shall 
cease to be a member of such Committee.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1614883</tid>
<number>24</number>Powers of Board of management. If, in exercise of the power 
conferred by section 17, the State Government appoints a Board of 
Management for any Reformatory School, such Board shall have the 
powers and perform the functions of the Superintendent under sections 
 18 to 22, both inclusive; an the license mentioned in section 18 may 
be under the hand of their chairman; and they shall be deemed to be 
the guardians of the youthful offenders detained in such school.


</article>



<article><tid>154961</tid>
<number>25</number>power to appoint trustees or other managers of a school to be 
a Board of Management. The State Government may declare any body of 
trustees or managers of a school, who are willing to act in conformity 
with the rules referred to in section 5, clause (b), to be a Board of 
Management under this Act, and thereupon such body or manager shall 
have all the powers and perform all the functions of such Board of 
Management.


</article>



<article><tid>974907</tid>
<number> 26</number> Power of Board to make rules.
<section><tid>1980792</tid>
<number>1</number>With the previous sanction  
of the State Government, every Board of Management of a Reformatory 
School may from time to time make rules consistent with this Act-

<subsection><tid>302356</tid>
<number>i</number>to prescribe the articles which are to be deemed to be 
" prohibited articles"; and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>36</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>104915</tid>
<number>ii</number>to regulate-

<subsubsection><tid>1021750</tid>
<number>a</number>the conduct of business of the Board; 
 (b) the management of the school; 
 (c) the education and industrial training of youthful 
offenders;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1926306</tid>
<number>d</number>visits to, and communication with, youthful offenders;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1735377</tid>
<number>e</number>the terms and conditions under which any articles 
declared by the Board to be" prohibited articles" may be 
introduced into or removed out of the school;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>754053</tid>
<number>f</number>the manner in which such articles are to be removed 
when introduced without due authority;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>695208</tid>
<number>g</number>the conditions and limitations under which such 
articles may be supplied outside the school to any youthful 
offender under order of detention therein;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1964626</tid>
<number>h</number>the conditions on which the possession by any such 
youthful offender of such articles may be sanctioned;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>231995</tid>
<number>i</number>the penalties to be imposed for the supply or pos- 
session of such articles when supplied or possessed without 
due authority;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>328951</tid>
<number>j</number>the punishment of offences committed by youthful 
offenders; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>993673</tid>
<number>k</number>the granting of licenses for the employment of youthful 
offenders.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>219729</tid>
<number>2</number>In the absence of a Board of Management the State Government 
may make rules consistent with this Act to regulate for any 
Reformatory School the matters mentioned in any clause of sub- section 
 (1), other than clause (ii) a, and also the mode in which the 
Committee of Visitors shall conduct their business.
IV.- OFFENCES IN RELATION TO REFORMATORY SCHOOLS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1180511</tid>
<number>27</number>Penalty for introduction or removal or supply of prohibited 
articles and communication with youthful offenders. Whoever, contrary 
to any rule made under section 26, introduces or removes or attempts 
by any means whatever to introduce or remove into or from any 
Reformatory School, or supplies or attempts to supply outside the 
limits of any Reformatory School to any youthful offender under order 
of detention therein, any prohibited article,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>37</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

and every officer or person in charge of a Reformatory School 
who, contrary to any such rule, knowingly suffers any such article to 
be introduced into or removed from any Reformatory School, to be 
possessed by any youthful offender detained therein, or to be supplied 
to any such youthful offender outside its limits,

and whoever, contrary to any such rule, communicates or attempts 
to communicate with any such youthful offender,

and whoever abets any offence made punishable under this section, 
shall, on conviction before a Magistrate, be liable to imprisonment 
for a term not exceeding six months, or to fine not exceeding two 
hundred rupees, or to both.



</article>



<article><tid>74</tid>
<number>28</number>Penalty for abetting escape of youthful offender. Whoever 
abets an escape, or an attempt to escape, on the part. of a youthful 
offender from a Reformatory School, or from the employer of such 
youthful offender, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term 
which may extend to six months, or with fine not exceeding two hundred 
rupees, or with both.


</article>



<article><tid>171589</tid>
<number>29</number>Arrest of escaped youthful offender. A Police- officer may, 
without orders from a Magistrate and without a warrant, arrest any 
youthful offender sent to a Reformatory School under this Act, who has 
escaped from such school or from his employer, and take him back to 
such school or to his employer.
V.- MISCELLANEOUS



</article>



<article><tid>1137419</tid>
<number>30</number>[ Application of Act 15 of <year>1869</year> to youthful offenders 
detained in Reformatory Schools.] Rep. by the Prisons Act, <year>1900</year> (3 of  
  <year>1900</year>), s. 53 and Sch. III.


</article>



<article><tid>950075</tid>
<number> 31</number> Power to deal in other ways with youthful offenders, 
includind girls.
<section><tid>421041</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act  
or in any other enactment for the time being in force, any Court may, 
if it shall think fit, instead of sentencing any youthful offender to 
transportation or imprisonment or directing him to be detained in a 
Reformatory School, order him to be-

<subsection><tid>921380</tid>
<number>a</number>discharged after due admonition, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>53019</tid>
<number>b</number>delivered to his parent or to his guardian or nearest 
adult relative, on such parent, guardian or relative 
executing a bond, with or without sureties, as the Court may 
require, to be responsible for the good behaviour of the 
youthful offender for any period not exceeding twelve months.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>38</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>775145</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes of this section the term" youthful 
offender shall include a girl.

</section>

<section><tid>297032</tid>
<number>3</number>The powers conferred on the Court by this section shall be 
exercised only by Courts empowered by or under section 8.

</section>

<section><tid>386345</tid>
<number>4</number>When any youthful offender is convicted by a Court not 
empowered to act under this section and the Court is of opinion that 
the powers conferred by this section should be exercised in respect of 
such youthful offender, it may record such opinion and submit the 
proceedings and forward the youthful offender to the District 
Magistrate to whom such Court is subordinate.

</section>

<section><tid>1252762</tid>
<number>5</number>The District Magistrate to whom the proceedings are so sub- 
mitted may thereupon make such order or pass such sentence as he might 
have made or passed if the case had originally been tried by him.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>231476</tid>
<number>32</number>Procedure when youthful offender under detention in a 
Reformatory School is again convicted and sentenced. When a youthful 
offender during his period of detention in a Reformatory School is 
again convicted by a Criminal Court, the sentence of such Court shall 
commence at once, notwithstanding anything to the contrary in section 
 397 of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1882</year> (10 of <year>1882</year>), but the 
Court shall forthwith report the matter to the State Government, which 
shall have power to deal with the matter in any way in which it thinks 
fit,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>39</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The relevant provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1898</year> 
 (5 of <year>1898</year>) may now be referred to.

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>