<act><title>


    The Dangerous Machines (Regulation) Act, 1983</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Dangerous Machines (Regulation) Act, 1983.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends 
    to the whole of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> This 
    section and clause (c) of section 3 shall come into force at once in all the 
    States and the remaining provisions of this Act shall come into force in a 
    State on such date as the State Government may, by notification in the 
    Official Gazette, appoint, and different dates may, be appointed for 
    different provisions of this Act; and any reference in any provision of this 
    Act to the commencement of this Act shall in relation to any State be 
    construed as a reference to the commencement of that provision in that 
    State.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Declaration as to expediency of control by Union.—It 
    is hereby declared that it is expedient in the public interest that the 
    Union should take under its control the industries engaged in the 
    manufacture or production of power threshers or any other machines which are 
    intended to be used in the agricultural or rural sector and which are of 
    such nature that any accident in the course of operation thereof may cause 
    its operator death, dismemberment of any limb or other bodily injury.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Definitions.—In this Act, unless 
    the context otherwise requires,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   “child” means a person who has not 
    completed his fourteenth year of age; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   “Controller” means the person appointed 
    by the State Government to give effect to the provisions of this Act, and 
    includes every Additional, Deputy or Assistant Controller who may be 
    authorised by the Controller under sub-section (3) of section 5 to exercise 
    any power under this Act; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   “dangerous machine” means a power 
    thresher, and includes any such machine intended to be used in the 
    agricultural or rural sector as the Central Government, being of opinion 
    that it is of such a nature that any accident in the course of operation 
    thereof is likely to cause to its operator death. dismemberment of any limb 
    or other bodily injury, may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    specify as dangerous machine; 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   “day” means a period of twenty-four 
    hours beginning at midnight; 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   “dealer”, in relation to any dangerous 
    machine or any part thereof, means a person who, or a firm or a Hindu 
    undivided family which, carries on, directly or otherwise, the business of 
    buying, selling, supplying or distributing any dangerous machine or any part 
    thereof, whether for cash or for deferred payment or for commission, 
    remuneration or other valuable consideration, and includes— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   a commission agent who carries on such 
    business on behalf of any principal; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   an importer who sells, supplies, 
    distributes or otherwise delivers any dangerous machine to any user, 
    manufacturer, repairer, consumer or any other person, 
 
but does not include a manufacturer who sells, 
    supplies, distributes or otherwise delivers any dangerous machine or any 
    part thereof to any person or category of persons referred to in this 
    clause. 
 
Explanation.—For the removal of doubts 
    it is hereby declared that a manufacturer who sells, supplies, distributes, 
    or otherwise delivers any dangerous machine or any part thereof to any 
    person other than a dealer, shall be deemed to be a dealer, and shall in 
    addition to his liability to comply with the provisions of this Act relating 
    to manufacturers, also be liable to comply with the provisions of this Act 
    relating to dealers; 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>f</number>   “employer”, in relation to the operator 
    of any dangerous machine means the person by whom such operator has been 
    employed, whether for any remuneration or otherwise, for operating such 
    machine; 
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>   “family”, in relation to an operator, 
    means his wife and dependent children and includes his dependent parents; 
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>   “Inspector” means an Inspector appointed 
    under this Act; 
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>   “machine” includes prime movers, 
    transmission machinery and all other appliances whereby power is generated, 
    transferred, transmitted or applied to a dangerous machine; 
 </section><section>
<number>j</number>   “manufacturer”, in relation to any 
    dangerous machine or any part thereof, means a person who, or a firm or a 
    Hindu undivided family which,— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   makes or manufactures such dangerous 
    machine or part thereof, 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   makes or manufactures one or more 
    parts, and acquires the other parts of such dangerous machine and, after 
    assembling those parts, claims the end product to be a product manufactured 
    by himself, or itself, as the case may be, 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   does not make or manufacture any part 
    of such dangerous machine but assembles parts thereof made or manufactured 
    by others and claims the end product to be a product manufactured by 
    himself, or itself, as the case may be, 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   puts, or causes to be put, his or its 
    own mark on any complete dangerous machine made or manufactured by any other 
    person and claims such product to be a product made or manufactured by 
    himself, or itself, as the case may be; 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>k</number>   “operator” means a person employed 
    directly or by or through any agency (including a contractor), whether as a 
    regular worker or as a casual worker, with or without the knowledge of the 
    principal employer, whether for remuneration or not, in the operation or 
    cleaning of any dangerous machine or any part thereof or in any other kind 
    of work incidental to, or connected with, the operation or cleaning of any 
    dangerous machines or any part thereof; 
 </section><section>
<number>l</number>   “power” means electrical or mechanical 
    energy, or any other form of energy which is mechanically transmitted into a 
    dangerous machine; 
 </section><section>
<number>m</number>   “power thresher” means a machine, 
    operated with the aid of power for threshing one or more kinds of 
    agricultural produce; 
 </section><section>
<number>n</number>   “prescribed” means prescribed by rules 
    made under this Act; 
 </section><section>
<number>o</number>   “prime mover” means an engine, motor or 
    other appliance which generates or otherwise provides power to a dangerous 
    machine. 
 </section><section>
<number>p</number>   “transmission machinery” means any 
    shaft, wheel, drum, pulley, system of pulleys, coupling, clutch, driving 
    belt or other appliance or device by which the motion of a prime mover is 
    transmitted to, or receiver by, any dangerous machine. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Act to 
    override all other enactments.—The 
    provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
    inconsistent therewith contained in any other law for the time being in 
    force or in any contract or instrument having effect by virtue of any law 
    other than this Act or any decree or order of any court, tribunal or 
    authority.
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Appointment and functions of Controllers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint 
    a Controller for carrying out the provisions of this Act, and may also by 
    the same or subsequent notification appoint such number of Additional, 
    Deputy or Assistant Controllers as it may deem fit. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Controller shall discharge his functions under this Act subject to the 
    general control and directions of the State Government. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Controller may authorise such persons as he thinks fit also to exercise all 
    or any of the powers exercisable by him under this Act other than the powers 
    under sub-section (5) and different persons may be authorised to exercise 
    different powers. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Subject to 
    any general or special direction given or imposed by the Controller, any 
    person authorised by the Controller to exercise any powers may exercise 
    those powers in the same manner and with the same effect as if they have 
    been conferred on that person directly by this Act and not by way of 
    authorisation. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Controller may also— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   perform all or any of the functions of, 
    and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   exercise all or any of the powers 
    conferred by this Act or any rule or order made thereunder on, 
 
any officer lower in rank than himself.
 

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Power of 
    Controller to issue orders.—The 
    Controller may, if he thinks fit, make orders, not inconsistent with the 
    provisions of this Act, for carrying out the provisions of this Act. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Appointment of Inspectors.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint as 
    many Inspectors as it deems fit to carry out the provisions of this Act 
    relating to inspection, search, seizure of dangerous machines and 
    examination of the records of manufacturers, dealers and users relating to 
    such machines. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    Inspector shall discharge his functions subject to the general direction and 
    control of the Controller. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Controller, etc., to be public servant.—The 
    Controller, and any person authorised by the State Government or the 
    Controller to perform any functions under this Act, and every Inspector, 
    shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of 
    the Indian Penal Code, (45 of 1860). 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Licensing 
    of manufacturers and dealers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Save as otherwise provided in this section, no person shall manufacture, or 
    commence or carry on business as a manufacturer or dealer of, any dangerous 
    machine unless he holds a valid licence issued in this behalf by the 
    Controller: 
 
Provided that a 
    person engaged in the manufacture of, or carrying on business as a 
    manufacturer or dealer of, any dangerous machines of any class immediately 
    before the appointed day in relation to dangerous machines of such class may 
    continue to manufacture such machines or carry on such business without such 
    a licence for a period of one month from that date, and if he makes an 
    application for such licence under this section within the said period of 
    one month, till the communication to him of the order of the Controller 
    disposing of such application. 
 
Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this proviso, “appointed day” means,— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   in relation to the class of dangerous 
    machines being power threshers, the date of commencement of this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   in relation to any other class of 
    dangerous machines, the date with effect from which such machines have been 
    specified to the dangerous machines by the Central Government by 
    notification under clause (c) of section 3, or in the case of a State in 
    which this section has come into force with effect from a later date, such 
    later date.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A licence 
    issued under this section— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   shall be valid for a period of five 
    years; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   may be renewed from time to time, for a 
    like period; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   shall be in such form, and shall be 
    subject to such conditions, as may be prescribed by the Central Government. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> A person 
    who intends to commence the manufacture, or carry on business as 
    manufacturer or dealer, of any dangerous machine shall make an application 
    in such form and on payment of such fees, not exceeding five hundred rupees, 
    as may be prescribed, for the issue of a licence. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> No 
    application for the issue of a licence to commence the manufacture. or to 
    carry on business as a manufacturer or dealer, of any dangerous machine 
    shall be granted unless the Controller, after making such injury as he 
    thinks fit, is satisfied— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   in the case of a manufacturer carrying 
    on business at the commencement of this Act, of manufacturing any dangerous 
    machine, that such machine complies with the standards prescribed under 
    section 13; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   in the case of a person who intends to 
    commence business after such commencement, as a manufacturer of a dangerous 
    machine, that the applicant has declared that he would manufacture such 
    machine in accordance with the standards laid down by or under this Act. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> An 
    application for the renewal of a licence issued under this section shall be 
    made not less than forty-five days before the date of expiry of the period 
    of validity thereof and shall be accompanied by such fees, not exceeding two 
    hundred rupees, as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> No 
    application for the renewal of a licence for the manufacture, or for the 
    carrying on the business as a manufacturer, of a dangerous machine shall be 
    rejected unless— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the holder of such licence has been 
    given a reasonable opportunity of presenting his case; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   the Controller is satisfied that— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   the application for such renewal has 
    been made after the expiry of the period specified therefor: 
 
Provided that an application for the renewal 
    of a licence made after the expiry of the specified period may be 
    entertained on payment of such late fees, not exceeding one hundred rupees, 
    as may be prescribed; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   any statement made by the applicant at 
    the time of the issue or renewal of the licence was incorrect or false in 
    material particulars; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>   the applicant has omitted or failed to 
    manufacture any dangerous machine in accordance with the prescribed 
    standards; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iv</number>   the applicant has contravened any term 
    or condition of the licence or any provision of this Act, or any rule or 
    order made thereunder or of any law for the time being in force in so far as 
    such law prohibits the bringing into or taking out of India, any dangerous 
    machine. 
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>7</number> Every 
    person to whom a licence has been issued or renewed under this section shall 
    comply with the terms and conditions specified in the licence and the 
    provisions of this Act and the rules and orders made thereunder. 
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> Every 
    person to whom a licence has been granted or renewed under this section 
    shall ensure that every person employed by him complies in the course of 
    such employment, with the provisions of this Act or any rule or order made 
    thereunder.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> Every order 
    granting to rejecting any application for the issue or renewal of a licence 
    under this section shall be made in writing. 
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> Every 
    licensed dealer and every licensed manufacturer shall display his licence at 
    a conspicuous place of the premises in which he carries on business as such 
    licensed dealer. or manufacturer. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Suspension and cancellation of licences.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Controller may, if he has any reasonable cause to believe that the 
    holder of a licence granted under section 9 has made a statement in, or in 
    relation to, any application for the issue or renewal of a licence, which is 
    incorrect or false in material particulars, or has contravened any provision 
    of this Act or any rule or order made thereunder or of any other law for the 
    time being in force which regulates the bringing into or taking out of India 
    any dangerous machine, suspend such licence pending the completion of any 
    inquiry or trial against the holder of such licence, for making such 
    incorrect or false statement or for such contravention, as the case may be: 
 
Provided that 
    no such licence shall be suspended for a period exceeding ten days unless 
    the holder thereof has been given a reasonable opportunity of showing cause 
    against the proposed action. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Controller may, if he is satisfied after making such inquiry as he may think 
    fit, that the holder of any licence issued or renewed under this Act has 
    made such incorrect or false statement as is referred to in sub-section (1), 
    or has omitted or failed to manufacture any dangerous machine in accordance 
    with the prescribed standards or has contravened the provisions of such law, 
    rule or order, as is referred to in that sub-section, cancel such licence: 
 
Provided that 
    no licence shall be cancelled unless the holder thereof has been given a 
    reasonable opportunity of showing cause against the proposed action. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every 
    person whose licence has been suspended or cancelled shall, immediately 
    after such suspension or cancellation, stop functioning as such licensee and 
    shall not resume business as such licensee until the order of such 
    suspension or cancellation has been vacated.   
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every 
    person who holds a licence which is suspended or cancelled shall, 
    immediately after such suspension or cancellation, surrender such licence to 
    the Controller.
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Cancellation of licence on application by manufacturer or dealer.—A 
    person licensed to manufacture or carry on business as a manufacturer or 
    dealer of any dangerous machines who discontinues such manufacture or 
    business or who intends to discontinue such manufacture or business, may 
    make an application to the Controller for the cancellation of his licence, 
    and thereupon, the Controller may cancel such licence. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Licence 
    to a firm to be invalid on the change of partnership.—When 
    any firm has been licensed under this Act to manufacturer or carry on 
    business as a dealer or manufacturer of a dangerous machine, such licence 
    shall, notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, become invalid on and 
    from the date on which there is a change in the partnership of such firm, 
    unless such change in the partnership of the firm has been approved by the 
    Controller. 
  
  
  
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Manufacturer to ensure that every part of a dangerous machine conforms to 
    prescribed standards.—
<section><number>1</number> Every 
    manufacturer of a dangerous machine shall ensure that such machine and every 
    part thereof complies with such standards, conforming to the standards laid 
    down therefor by the Indian Standards Institution, as may be prescribed by 
    the Central Government. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
    provisions, the manufacturer of a dangerous machine shall ensure that the 
    following parts are secured by safeguards of substantial construction, 
    namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the prime mover and every part thereof, 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   the transmission machinery and every 
    part thereof, 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   every other dangerous part, such as, 
    rollers, blowers, sieves, elevator and the like. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Every 
    manufacturer of a dangerous machine shall also clearly and legibly provide 
    such machine with danger signals indicating the point beyond which no limb 
    shall be inserted for the purpose of feeding the machine or for any other 
    purpose. 
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Particulars to be specified on every dangerous machine.—The 
    manufacturer shall ensure that the following particulars are legibly and 
    conspicuously marked or inscribed on every dangerous machine by such method 
    as would make it indelible, namely:— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   the direction of the rotation and the 
    number of rotations per minute; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   its power requirement; and 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   the name and correct, address of the 
    manufacturer, the year of its manufacture, and the date, number and other 
    particulars of the licence of the manufacturer. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> Duties 
    of the manufacturer to supply operator’s manual with each dangerous machine.—Every 
    manufacturer shall supply along with each dangerous machine a manual 
    containing general instructions regarding the operation of such machine, and 
    shall also include therein such cautions, as may be prescribed. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> Duties 
    of the manufacturer to supply operator’s manual with each dangerous machine.—Every 
    manufacturer shall supply along with each dangerous machine a manual 
    containing general instructions regarding the operation of such machine, and 
    shall also include therein such cautions, as may be prescribed. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Certificate and guarantee by manufacturers and dealers.—Before 
    transferring the possession of any dangerous machine, whether by sale, 
    lease, hire or otherwise, every manufacturer and every dealer shall deliver, 
    to the person acquiring the possession of such machine, a declaration to the 
    effect that the machine conforms to the standards laid down by or under this 
    Act and also complies with in all respects, the provisions of this Act and 
    the rules and orders made thereunder. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Liability of the manufacturer for reimbursement.—Whenever 
    any person operating a dangerous machine suffers death or dismemberment of 
    any limb or any other bodily injury— 
 <section>
<number>i</number>   by reason of any manufacturing defect in 
    the machine whereby such death, dismemberment or injury was caused, or 
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>   by reason of the omission of the 
    manufacturer to comply with the provisions of this Act and the rules and 
    orders made thereunder, 
 
such manufacturer shall be liable to reimburse 
    the person by whom compensation had to be paid under this Act to the members 
    of the family of the person whose death was caused by such machine or, as 
    the case may be, to the person by whom such dismemberment or bodily injury 
    was suffered.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Manufacturers and dealers to maintain records.—Every 
    manufacturer and every dealer shall maintain such registers, records and 
    accounts as may be prescribed. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> User to 
    get each dangerous machine registered.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every person who owns a dangerous machine or acquires control over such 
    machine whether as a lessee or hirer or otherwise (in this Act referred to 
    as the user) shall make, before beginning to operate such machine, and 
    application to the Controller, on payment of such fees, not exceeding five 
    rupees, as may be prescribed, for the registration of such machine. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On receipt 
    of an application made under sub-section (1), the Controller shall, if he is 
    satisfied that the machine complies with, in all respects, the provisions of 
    this Act and the rules and orders made thereunder, register the same and 
    grant to the applicant a certificate showing such registration. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Controller shall maintain a register containing the particulars of the 
    dangerous machines registered by him and the names and addresses and other 
    particulars of the persons on whose application such registration has been 
    made. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> No 
    dangerous machine shall be operated until it has been registered in 
    accordance with the provisions of this section. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> Matters 
    to be ensured by users.—Every user 
    of a dangerous machine shall ensure that— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   such machine conforms to the standards 
    laid down by or under this Act and also complies with, in all respects, the 
    provisions of this Act and the rules and orders made thereunder; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   no child is employed for the operation 
    of such machine; and 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   adequate arrangements exist for 
    rendering first aid to any person who may suffer any injury while operating 
    any such machine. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>21</number> 
    Modification of existing dangerous machine.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every person who has, immediately before the commencement of this Act, in 
    his custody or control, and dangerous machine which does not comply with, in 
    all respects, the provisions of this Act and the rules and orders made 
    thereunder, shall, within such time, not being less than one hundred and 
    eighty days from such commencement, as the State Government may, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, specify, get the same modified in 
    accordance with such rules as may be made by the Central Government in this 
    behalf. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No such 
    machine shall be used or operated, after the expiry of the period specified 
    under sub-section (1), unless the modifications referred to in sub-section 
    (1) have been made. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Employer’s liability for compensation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If, during his employment as an operator of a dangerous machine, death or 
    dismemberment of any limb or any other bodily injury is caused to such 
    operator, his employer shall be liable to pay compensation— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   in the case of death of the operator, to 
    his family, and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   in any other case, to the operator: 
 
Provided that 
    where the operator does not have a family, the compensation shall be paid to 
    the person or persons nominated in this behalf by the operator in writing 
    and notified to the Controller: 
 
Provided 
    further that the employer shall not be so liable— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   in respect of any injury which does not 
    result in the total or partial disablement of the operator for a period 
    exceeding three days; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   in respect of any injury, not resulting 
    in death, caused by an accident which is directly attributable to— 
 <subsubsubsection>
<number>a</number>   the operator having been at the time 
    thereof under the influence of any intoxicant or drug, or 
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
<number>b</number>   the wilful removal by the worker of any 
    safety guard or other device which he knew to have been provided in the 
    machine for the purpose of securing the safety of the operator. 
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The amount 
    of the compensation payable under sub-section (1) shall be determined and 
    paid in accordance with the provisions of the Workmen’s Compensation Act, 
    1923 ( 8 of 1923), as if the operator were a workman within the meaning of 
    that Act, and, for this purpose, the provisions of the said Act shall apply 
    to him as they apply to a workman within the meaning of that Act.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Employer’s liability for compensation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If, during his employment as an operator of a dangerous machine, death or 
    dismemberment of any limb or any other bodily injury is caused to such 
    operator, his employer shall be liable to pay compensation— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   in the case of death of the operator, to 
    his family, and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   in any other case, to the operator: 
 
Provided that 
    where the operator does not have a family, the compensation shall be paid to 
    the person or persons nominated in this behalf by the operator in writing 
    and notified to the Controller: 
 
Provided 
    further that the employer shall not be so liable— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   in respect of any injury which does not 
    result in the total or partial disablement of the operator for a period 
    exceeding three days; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   in respect of any injury, not resulting 
    in death, caused by an accident which is directly attributable to— 
 <subsubsubsection>
<number>a</number>   the operator having been at the time 
    thereof under the influence of any intoxicant or drug, or 
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
<number>b</number>   the wilful removal by the worker of any 
    safety guard or other device which he knew to have been provided in the 
    machine for the purpose of securing the safety of the operator. 
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The amount 
    of the compensation payable under sub-section (1) shall be determined and 
    paid in accordance with the provisions of the Workmen’s Compensation Act, 
    1923 ( 8 of 1923), as if the operator were a workman within the meaning of 
    that Act, and, for this purpose, the provisions of the said Act shall apply 
    to him as they apply to a workman within the meaning of that Act.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> Notice 
    of accident.—
<section><number>1</number> Where the death 
    or dismemberment of any limb or any other bodily injury has been caused to 
    an operator, during the course of his employment, notice of such death, 
    dismemberment or injury shall be given to the employer within three days 
    from date on which such death, dismemberment or injury was caused. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Such notice 
    shall be given by the operator if he is alive or by any member of his family 
    or any other person interested in him. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Omission to 
    give the notice referred to in sub-section (2) shall not disentitle the 
    operator or the members of his family, as the case may be, to receive the 
    compensation payable under this Act. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> Duty of 
    employer to take out insurance policies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every employer shall take out, as soon as may be practicable after the 
    commencement of this Act, one or more insurance policies providing for 
    contracts of insurance whereby he is insured against any liability arising 
    out of sub-section (1) of section 22 to make payment of compensation to any 
    operator of a dangerouss machine and such contract of insurance may provide 
    for the payment of annuities to the operator, or in case of his death, to 
    the members of his family or to his nominee, if he does not have a family. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    employer shall get the insurance policy referred to in sub-section (1) 
    renewed from time to time before the expiry of the period of validity, 
    thereof so that the policy of insurance may remain in force throughout the 
    period during which any person is employed by him to operate any dangerous 
    machine. 
  
  
  
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>25</number> Omission 
    or failure of the employer to take out insurance policies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In the event of the omission or failure of the employer to take out an 
    insurance policy referred to in section 24 or in the event of the omission, 
    failure or inability of the employer to keep such insurance policy in force 
    or to obtain, from the insurer, any amount required to be paid as 
    compensation to an operator, or to the members of his family or nominee, as 
    the case may be, the employer shall make payment of compensation from his 
    own funds, to the operator, or to the members of his family or his nominee, 
    as the case may be, as soon as possible after the date on which the operator 
    suffers death or dismemberment of limb or other bodily injury but not later 
    than thirty days from such date and on such payment the employer’s liability 
    for payment of compensation to the operator or to the members of his family 
    shall stand fully discharged. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    discharge of the liability referred to in sub-section (1) shall not take 
    away or abridge the right of, the employer to receive, from the insurer, 
    such payment as may be due to him under the policy of insurance taken out or 
    renewed by him. 
  
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>26</number> 
    Examination of machine causing death or injury.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    As soon as the employer comes to know, whether on receipt of a notice under 
    section 23 or otherwise, that the operator has suffered death, dismemberment 
    of any limb or other bodily injury during the operation of any dangerous 
    machine, he shall forthwith give notice of such death or injury to the 
    Inspector. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Whenever an 
    Inspector comes to know about any death or injury, whether on receipt of a 
    notice referred to under sub-section (1) or otherwise, he shall, as soon as 
    practicable, enter into the premises where the dangerous machine whereby 
    such death, dismemberment of limb or other bodily injury has been caused, is 
    located and examine the machine with a view to finding out whether the 
    machine conforms to the standards laid down by or under this Act and 
    contains all the prescribed safety devices, and, where, after such 
    examination, he is of the opinion that the machine is unsafe, he shall, by 
    an order, prohibit the use of such machine until it is certified by him to 
    be safe. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No machine 
    shall be operated during the period of operation of the prohibitory order 
    made under sub-section (2). 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>27</number> 
    Inspection of records, etc.—Every 
    register, record and accounts maintained under this Act and every licence 
    issued or renewed under this Act shall be open to the inspection of the 
    Inspector. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>28</number> Power to 
    enter and search.—An Inspector 
    authorised in this behalf by the Controller may, if he has any reason to 
    suspect that any provision of this Act has been, or is being, or is about to 
    be, contravened, enter and search, at any reasonable time of the day, any 
    premises in which any dangerous machine is operated. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>29</number> Power of 
    seizure.—Whenever the Inspector is 
    satisfied that any dangerous machine, which does not comply with, in all 
    respects, the provisions of this Act or the rules or orders made thereunder, 
    is being operated in contravention of the provisions of this Act, he may 
    seize such dangerous machine and the records and registers connected 
    therewith. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>30</number> Search 
    and seizure to be made in accordance with the Code of Criminal Procedure, 
    1973.—Every search and seizure 
    made under this Act shall be made in accordance with the provisions of the 
    Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>31</number> 
    Punishment for contravention of the provisions of the Act.—Whoever, 
    in contravention of the provisions of this Act, or any rule or order made 
    thereunder— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   manufactures, or carries on business as 
    a manufacturer or dealer of, any dangerouss machine without being in 
    possession of valid licence issued or renewed, under this Act; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   employs a child in the operation of any 
    dangerous machine; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   causes any person to operate a dangerous 
    machine which does not conform to the standards specified by or under this 
    Act; 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   causes any person to operate any 
    dangerous machine referred to in section 21, without carrying out the 
    prescribed modifications; 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   omits to take out or renew an insurance 
    policy ass required by section 24; 
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   sells or otherwise transfers any 
    dangerous machine which does not conform to the provisions of this Act or 
    the rules made thereunder; 
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>   operates or causes any person to operate 
    any dangerous machine during the period of operation of a prohibitory order 
    made under sub-section (2) of section 26; or 
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>   contravenes any other provision of this 
    Act, or rule or order made thereunder, 
 
shall be punishable with imprisonment for a 
    term which may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to one 
    thousand rupees, or with both, and in the case of a second or subsequent 
    offence, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which shall not be 
    less than three months and also with fine which shall not be less than five 
    hundred rupees but not more than one thousand rupees.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>32</number> Offences 
    by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> Where an offence 
    under this Act has been committed by a company, every person who at the time 
    the offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible to, the 
    company for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as the 
    company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to 
    be proceeded against and punished accordingly: 
 
Provided that 
    nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to 
    any punishment, if he proves that the offence was committed without his 
    knowledge or that he had exercised all due diligence to prevent the 
    commission of such offence. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence 
    under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the 
    offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is 
    attributable to any neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary 
    or other officer of the company, such director, manger, secretary or other 
    officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be 
    liable to be proceeded against and published accordingly: 
 
Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   “company” means any body corporate and 
    includes a firm or other association of individuals; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   “director”, in relation to a firm, means 
    a partner in the firm. 
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>33</number> 
    Cognizance and trial of offences.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 
    (2 of 1974), no court shall take cognizance of an offence punishable under 
    this Act except on a complaint in writing made by the Controller or any 
    person authorised by him in this behalf. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    offence under this Act may be tried summarily by a Magistrate. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>34</number> Appeals.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person aggrieved by any order granting or refusing to issue or renew a 
    licence under this Act or refusing to register a dangerous machine, may 
    prefer an appeal against the order to the State Government. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every such 
    appeal shall be filled within thirty days from the date of the order: 
 
Provided that 
    the State Government may entertain the appeal after the expiry of the said 
    period of thirty days, if it is satisfied that the appellant was prevented 
    by sufficient cause from filing the appeal within the said period. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>35</number> 
    Protection of action taken in good faith.—No 
    suit, prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against the State 
    Government, the Controller, any Inspector or any other person authorised by 
    the Controller for exercising any powers or discharging any functions under 
    this Act for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in 
    pursuance of this Act or any rule or order made thereunder. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>36</number> Power of 
    Central Government to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make 
    rules to carry out the provisions of sub-section (2) of section 9, and the 
    provisions of sections 13 and 21. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    notification made by the Central Government under clause (c) of section 3, 
    and every rule made by it under sub-section (1), shall be laid, as soon as 
    may be after it is made, before each Houses of Parliament, while it is in 
    session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one 
    session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of 
    the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
    aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the notification 
    or rule, or both Houses agree that the notification or rule should not be 
    made, the notification or rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
    modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
    such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of 
    anything previously done under that notification or rule. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>37</number> Power of 
    State Government to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make 
    rules to carry out the provisions of this Act other than those specified in 
    sub-section (1) of section 36. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   all matters specified in section 9 
    except those specified in sub-section (2) thereof; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   the fees (including late fees), within 
    the limits specified in section 9, for the issue and renewal of licences 
    under that section and for the registration of dealers, as provided in 
    section 19; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   the cautions to be specified in the 
    manual of instructions as required by section 15; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   the registers, records and accounts 
    which are required to be maintained under section 18; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   the arrangement required to be made 
    under section 20 for rendering first aid to any injured operator of a 
    dangerous machine: and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   any other matter which is required to 
    be, or may be, prescribed. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Every rule 
    made by the State Government under this section shall be laid, as soon as 
    may be after it is made, before each House of the State Legislature where it 
    consists of two Houses, or where such Legislature consists of one House, 
    before that House. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>38</number> Power to 
    give directions.—The Central 
    Government may give directions to any State Government as to the carrying 
    into execution in the State of any of the provisions of this Act or of any 
    rule or order made thereunder. 
  
  
  
 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>