<act><title>
THE
PAYMENT OF GRATUITY ACT, 1972</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article><number>1</number>
Short title, extent, application and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
This Act may be called the Payment of Gratuity Act, 1972.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
It extends to the whole of India:
 Provided
that in so far as it relates to plantations or ports, it shall not extend to the
State of Jammu and Kashmir.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
It shall apply to—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>
every factory, mine, oilfield, plantation, port and railway company;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
every shop or establishment within the meaning of any law for the time
being in force in relation to shops and establishments in a State, in which ten
or more persons are employed, or were employed, on any day of the preceding
twelve months;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>
such other establishments or class of establishments, in which ten or
more employees are employed, or were employed, on any day of the preceding
twelve months, as the Central Government may, by notification, specify in this
behalf.
 </subsection></section><section><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>3A</number>
A shop or establishment to which this Act has become applicable shall continue
to be governed by this Act notwithstanding that the number of persons employed
therein at any time after it has become so applicable falls below ten.]
 </section><section><number>4</number>
It shall come into force on such date<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>
as the Central Government may, by notification, appoint.
  












 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In
this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>  “appropriate Government” means,—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number> in
relation to an establishment—
 <subsubsection>
<number>a</number> belonging
to, or under the control of, the Central Government,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>b</number> having
branches in more than one State,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>c</number> of a
factory belonging to, or under the control of, the Central Government,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>d</number> of a
major port, mine, oilfield or railway company, the Central Government,
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number> in
any other case, the State Government;
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number>
“completed year of service” means continuous service for one year;
 </section><section><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>c</number>
“continuous service” means continuous service as defined in section
2A;]
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>
“controlling authority” means an authority appointed by the
appropriate Government under section 3;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>
“employee” means any person (other than an apprentice) employed on
wages, <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[***] in any
establishment, factory, mine, oilfield, plantation, port, railway company or
shop to do any skilled, semi-skilled, or unskilled, manual, supervisory,
technical or clerical work, whether the terms of such employment are express or
implied, <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[and whether or
not such person is employed in a managerial or administrative capacity, but does
not include any such person who holds a post under the Central Government or a
State Government and is governed by any other Act or by any rules providing for
payment of gratuity].
 <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[***]
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>
“employer” means, in relation to any establishment, factory, mine,
oilfield, plantation, port, railway company or shop—
 <subsection> <number>i</number> belonging
to, or under the control of, the Central Government or a State Government a
person or authority appointed by the appropriate Government for the
supervision and control of employees, or where no person or authority has been
so appointed, the head of the Ministry or Department concerned,
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number> belonging
to, or under the control of, any local authority, the person appointed by such
authority for the supervision and control of employees or where no person has
been so appointed, the chief executive officer of the local authority,
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number> in
any other case, the person, who, or the authority which, has the ultimate
control over the affairs of the establishment, factory, mine, oilfield,
plantation, port, railway company or shop, and where the said affairs are
entrusted to any other person, whether called a manager, managing director or by
any other name, such person;
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>g</number> “factory”, has the meaning assigned to it in clause (m) of section 2
of the Factories Act, 1948 (63 of 1948);
 </section><section>
<number>h</number> “family” in relation to an employee, shall be deemed to consist of—
 </section><section> <number>i</number> in
the case of a male employee, himself, his wife, his children, whether married or
unmarried, his dependent parents <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[and
the dependent parents of his wife and the widow] and children of his predeceased
son, if any,
 <subsection> <number>ii</number> in
the case of a female employee, herself, her husband, her children, whether
married or unmarried, her dependent parents and the dependent parents of her
husband and the widow and children of her predeceased son, if any;
  <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[***]
 Explanation.—Where
the personal law of an employee permits the adoption by him of a child, any
child lawfully adopted by him shall be deemed to be included in his family, and
where a child of an employee has been adopted by another person and such
adoption is, under the personal law of the person making such adoption, lawful,
such child shall be deemed to be excluded from the family of the employee;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>
“major port” has the meaning assigned to it in clause (8) of section
3 of the Indian Ports Act, 1908 (15 of 1908);
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>
“mine” has the meaning assigned to it in clause (j) of sub-section
(1) of section 2 of the Mines Act, 1952 (35 of 1952);
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>
“notification” means a notification published in the Official
Gazette;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>
“oilfield” has the meaning assigned to it in clause (e) of section 3
of the Oilfields (Regulation and Development) Act, 1948 (53 of 1948);
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number>
“plantation” has the meaning assigned to it in clause (f) of section
2 of the Plantations Labour Act, 1951 (69 of 1951);
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>n</number>
“port” has the meaning assigned to it in clause (4) of section 3 of
the Indian Ports Act, 1908 (15 of 1908);
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>o</number>
“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>p</number>
“railway company” has the meaning assigned to it in clause (5) of
section 3 of the Indian Railways Act, 1890 (9 of 1890);
 </subsection><subsection><number>q</number>
“retirement” means termination of the service of an employee
otherwise than on superannuation;
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[<number>r</number>
“superannuation”, in relation to an employee, means the attainment by
the employee of such age as is fixed in the contract or conditions of service as
the age on the attainment of which the employer shall vacate the employment;]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>s</number>
“wages” means all emoluments which are earned by an employee while on
duty or on leave in accordance with the terms and conditions of his employments
and which are paid or are payable to him in cash and includes dearness allowance
but does not include any bonus, commission, house rent allowance, overtime wages
and any other allowance.
  





















 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article> <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[<number>3</number>
Responsibility for payment of wages.—
<section><number>1</number> Every employer shall be
responsible for the payment of all wages required to be paid under this Act to
persons employed by him and in case of persons employed,— 
 <subsection><number>a</number>
in factories, if a person has been named as the manager of the factory
under clause (f) of sub-section (1) of section 7 of the Factories Act, 1948 (63
of 1948);
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> in industrial or other establishments, if there is a person responsible
to the employer for the supervision and control of the industrial or other
establishment;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> upon railways (other than
in factories), if the employer is the railway administration and the railway
administration has nominated a person in this behalf for the local area
concerned;
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> in the case of contractor, a person designated by
such contractor who is directly under his charge; and
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> in any other case, a person designated by the
employer as a person responsible for complying with the provisions of the Act;
 the
person so named, the person responsible to the employer, the person so nominated
or the person so designated, as the case may be, shall be responsible for such
payment.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), it shall be the
responsibility of the employer to make payment of all wages required to be made
under this Act in case the contractor or the person designated by the employer
fails to make such payment.]
   


 
Statement
of Objects and Reasons [The Payment of Wages
(Amendment) Act, 2005]
   

Removing
the ambiguities/weakness from the extant provisions of the Act and prescribing
more effective grievance redresal: Over the years, it has been noticed that
certain provisions of the Act have been differently interpreted thus leading to
administrative difficulties in implementing the same. In order to remove
ambiguities, appropriate changes are being proposed in sections 3, 7, 8 and 15
of the Act which respectively deal with responsibility for payment of wages,
deductions from wages fines and claims in certain cases. 
   


 
State
Amendments
 <subsection>
<number>Gujarat</number>—Same
as that of Maharashtra.
 
[Vide
Gujarat Act 26 of 1961, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 12-6-1961)].
 
  


 
Madhya
Pradesh.—In section 3, for the proviso the following proviso shall be
substituted, namely,—
 

“Provided that, in the case
of a person employed (otherwise than by a contractor)—
 <subsubsection>

<number>a</number>
in factories, if a person has been named as the manager of the factory
under clause (j) of sub-section (1) of section 7 of the Factories Act, 1948 
(63 of 1948), then the person so named and the employer jointly and severally;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

<number>b</number>
in industrial establishments, if there is a person responsible to the
employer for the supervision and control of the industrial establishment, then
the person so responsible and the employer jointly and severally;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

<number>c</number>
upon railways (otherwise than in factories) if the employer is the
railway administration and the railway administration has nominated a person in
this behalf for the local area concerned, then the person so nominated,
 
shall
be responsible for such payment.”
 
[Vide
Madhya Pradesh Act 9 of 1964, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 15-5-1964)].
 
  


 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—In
section 3, for the proviso the following shall be substituted, namely,—
 



“Provided
that, in the case of persons employed otherwise than by a contractor—
 <subsubsection>

<number>a</number>
in factories, if a person has been named as the manager of the factory
under clause (j) of sub-section (1) of section 7 of the Factories Act, 1948 (63
of 1948) then the person so named, the employer, jointly severally;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

<number>b</number>
in industrial establishments, if there is a person responsible to the
employer for the supervision and control of the industrial establishment then
the person so responsible and employer, jointly and severally;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

<number>c</number>
upon railways (otherwise than in factories) if the employer is the
railway administration and the railway administration has nominated a person in
this behalf for the local area concerned, then the person so nominated,
 
shall
be responsible for such payment.”
 
[Vide
Bombay Act 62 of 1953, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 10-5-1954), Maharashtra Act 13 of 1961,
sec. 2 (w.e.f. 4-3-1961)].
 
  


 
  












 



</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>4</number>
Fixation of wage-periods.—
<section><number>1</number>
Every person responsible for the payment of wages under section 3 shall fix
periods (in this Act referred to as wage-period) in respect of which such wages
shall be payable.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
No wage-period shall exceed one month.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>5</number>
Time of payment of wages.—
<section><number>1</number> The wages of every person employed upon or
in—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
any railway, factory or <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[industrial
or other establishment] upon or in which less than one thousand persons are
employed, shall be paid before the expiry of the seventh day,
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
any other railway, factory or <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[industrial
or other establishment], shall be paid before the expiry of the tenth day,
 after
the last day of the wage-period in respect of which the wages are payable:
 <footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[Provided
that in the case of persons employed on a dock, wharf or jetty or in a mine, the
balance of wages found due on completion of the final tonnage account of the
ship or wagons loaded or unloaded, as the case may be, shall be paid before the
expiry of the seventh day from the day of such completion.]
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
Where the employment of any person is terminated by or on behalf of the
employer, the wages, earned by him shall be paid before the expiry of the second
working day from the day on which his employment is terminated:
 <footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[Provided
that where the employment of any person in an establishment is terminated due to
the closure of the establishment for any reason other than a weekly or other
recognised holiday, the wages earned by him shall be paid before the expiry of
the second day from the day on which his employment is so terminated.]
 </section><section><number>3</number>
The <footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[<footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[The
appropriate Government] may, by general or special order, exempt, to such extent
and subject to such conditions as may be specified in the order, the person
responsible for the payment of wages to persons employed upon any railway
(otherwise than in a factory) <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[or
to persons employed as daily-rated workers in the Public Works Department of the
Central Government or the State Government] from the operation of this section
in respect of the wages of any such persons or class of such persons:
 <footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[Provided
that in the case of persons employed as daily-rated workers as aforesaid, no
such order shall be made except in consultation with the Central Government.]
 </section><section><number>4</number><footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[Save
as otherwise provided in sub-section (2), all payments] of wages shall be made
on a working day.
   


 
State
Amendments
 
Andaman
and Nicobar Islands.—In section 5, for sub-section (1), the following
sub-section shall be substituted, namely:—
 

“(1)
The wages of every person employed upon or in any railway, factory or
industrial establishment shall be paid before the expiry of such number of days
after the last day of the wage-period in respect of which the wages are payable
as the State Government may be general or special order, specify and different
number of days may be specified for different areas; so, however, that the
number of days so specified shall not exceed the wage-period next following the
wage-period in respect of which the wages are payable.”
 [Vide
Regulation 5 of 1965, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 8-7-1965)].
  
 <subsection>
Lakshadweep.—In
section 5, for sub-section (1), substitute the following, namely:—
 

“(1)
The wages of every person employed in any factory or industrial
establishment shall be paid before the expiry of such number of days, after the
last day of the wage-period in respect of which the wages are payable, as the
State Government may, by general or special order, specify, and different number
of days may be specified for different areas, so, however, that the number of
days so specified shall not exceed the wage-period next following the
wage-period in respect of which the wages are payable.”
 [Vide
Regulation 2 of 1974, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 8-4-1974)].
   


   












 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>6</number>
Wages to be paid in current coin or currency notes.—All
wages shall be paid in current coin or currency notes or in both:
 <footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[Provided
that the employer may, after obtaining the written authorisation of the employed
person, pay him the wages either by cheque or by crediting the wages in his bank
account.]
   


 
State
Amendments
   


 
Andhra
Pradesh.—In section 6, after the existing proviso add further proviso
namely:—
 
 “Provided further that the State Government may, by notification in the
Andhra Pradesh Gazette, specify the industrial establishments, the employers of
which shall pay to the persons employed therein, the wages either by cheque or
by crediting the wages in their bank account”—
 
[Vide
Andhra Pradesh Act 15 of 1982, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 7-10-1982)].
 
  


 <section>
<number>Assam</number>—In
section 6, add the following proviso and Explanation—
 
 “Provided that notwithstanding anything contained in the Payment of
Bonus Act, 1965, one-third of the amount of bonus payable to an employed person
in a particular year in excess of rupees forty may be paid or invested into the
National Defence Certificates or National Savings Certificates (First Issue), if
the employed person records his assent by furnishing a no-objection certificate
in the manner to be prescribed, to his employer.
 
 Explanation.—For the purposes of this section, the expression (1)
‘wages’ shall include any bonus of the description given in sub-clause (1)
of clause (vi) of section 2; and (2) ‘bonus’ mean bonus payable to an
employed person under the terms of employment or under an award or settlement or
order of a Court, and also includes any bonus of the description given in
sub-clause (1) of clause (vi) of section 2.“
 
[Vide
Assam Act 1 of 1970, sec. 2].
 
  


 </section><section>
<number>Bihar</number>—In
section 6, the following proviso shall be added, namely:—
 
 “Provided that where the amount of entire bonus payable during a year
to an employed person under the terms of employment or under any award or
settlement or orders of a Court exceeds an amount equal to one-forth of his
earnings (exclusive of dearness allowance) for that year such excess shall be
paid to him or invested on his behalf in the manner prescribed.”
 
[Vide
Bihar Act 4 of 1961, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 9-3-1961) as amended by Bihar Act 4 of 1963,
sec. 2].
 
  


 </section><section>
<number>Gujarat</number>—Same
as that of Maharashtra.
 
[Vide
Gujarat Act 26 of 1961, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 12-6-1961)].
 
  


 </section><section>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—For
section 6, the following shall be substituted—
 
 “6. Wages to be paid in
current coins or currency notes.—All wages shall be paid in current coins or
currency notes, or in both:
 
 Provided that, where the amount of any bonus payable to an employed
person exceeds an amount equal to one-forth of his earnings (exclusive of
dearness allowance) for the year to which the bonus relates, such excess shall
be paid or invested in the manner prescribed.”
 
 Explanation.—For the purpose of this section, the expression—
 <subsection><number>1</number>
‘wages’ shall include any bonus of the description given in
sub-clause (1) of clause (iv) of section 2, and
 </subsection><subsection><number>2</number>
‘bonus’ means any bonus payable to an employed person under the terms
of employment or under an award or settlement or order of a Court and also
includes any bonus of the description given in sub-clause (1) of clause (vi) of
section 2.”
 
[Vide
Maharashtra Act 13 of 1961, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 4-3-1961).
 
  


 </subsection></section><section>
<number>Orissa</number>—In
section 6, the following proviso shall be added, namely:—
 
 “Provided that when the amount of bonus payable to an employed person
exceeds an amount equal to one-fourth of his earnings (exclusive of dearness
allowance) for the year to which the bonus relates, such excess shall be paid or
invested in the manner prescribed.”
 
[Vide
Orissa Act 4 of 1961, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 11-2-1961)].
 
  


 
  







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>7</number>
Deductions which may be made from wages.—
<section><number>1</number>
Notwithstanding the provisions of <footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[the
Railways Act, 1989 (24 of 1989)] the wages of an employed person shall be paid
to him without deductions of any kind except those authorised by or under this
Act.
 <footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[Explanation
I].—Every payment made by the employed person to the employer or his agent
shall, for the purposes of this Act, be deemed to be a deduction from wages.
 <footcitenum>20</footcitenum>[Explanation
II.—Any loss of wages resulting from the imposition, for good and sufficient
cause, upon a person employed of any of the following penalties, namely:—
 <subsection><number>i</number>
the withholding of increment or promotion (including the stoppage of
increment at an efficiency bar);
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>
the reduction to a lower post or time scale or to a lower stage in a time
scale; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number>
suspension;
 shall
not be deemed to be a deduction from wages in any case where the rules framed by
the employer for the imposition of any such penalty are in conformity with the
requirements, if any, which may be specified in this behalf by the State
Government by notification in the Official Gazette.]
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
Deductions from the wages of an employed person shall be made only in accordance
with the provisions of this Act, and may be of the following kinds only,
namely:—
 <subsection><number>a</number> fines;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> deductions for absence from duty;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> deductions for damage to or loss of goods expressly entrusted to the
employed person for custody, or for loss of money for which he is required to
account, where such damage or loss is directly attributable to his neglect or
default;
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>21</footcitenum>[<number>d</number> deductions for house-accommodation supplied by the employer or by
Government or any housing board set up under any law for the time being in force
(whether the Government or the board is the employer or not) or any other
authority engaged in the business of subsidising house-accommodation which may
be specified in this behalf by the State Government by notification in the
Official Gazette;]
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> deductions for such amenities and services supplied by the employer as
the <footcitenum>22</footcitenum>[***]
State Government <footcitenum>23</footcitenum>[or
any officer specified by it in this behalf] may, by general or special order,
authorise;
 
Explanation.—The word “services” in <footcitenum>24</footcitenum>[this
clause] does not include the supply of tools and raw materials required for the
purposes of employment;
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>25</footcitenum>[<number>f</number> deductions for recovery of advances of whatever nature (including
advances for travelling allowance or conveyance allowance), and the interest due
in respect thereof, or for adjustment of over-payments of wages;
 </subsection><subsection><number>ff</number> deductions for recovery of loans made from any fund constituted for the
welfare of labour in accordance with the rules approved by the State Government,
and the interest due in respect thereof;
 </subsection><subsection><number>fff</number> deductions for recovery of loans granted for house-building or other
purposes approved by the State Government, and the interest due in respect
thereof;]
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> deductions of income-tax payable by the employed person;
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> deductions required to be made by order of a Court or other authority
competent to make such order;
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> deductions for subscriptions to, and for repayment of advances from any
provident fund to which the Provident Funds Act, 1925 (19 of 1925), applies or
any recognized provident fund as defined <footcitenum>26</footcitenum>[in
clasue (38) of section 2 of the Income-tax Act, 1961 (43 of 1961)]
or any provident fund approved in this behalf by <footcitenum>27</footcitenum>[the
appropriate Government], during the continuance of such approval; <footcitenum>28</footcitenum>[***]
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> deductions for payments to co-operative societies as approved by <footcitenum>27</footcitenum>[the
appropriate Government] <footcitenum>29</footcitenum>[or
any officer specified by
it in this behalf] or to a scheme of insurance maintained by the Indian Post
Office; 5[and]
 

<footcitenum>30</footcitenum>[<footcitenum>31</footcitenum>[(k) deductions, made with the written authorisation of the person employed
for payment of any premium on his life insurance policy to the Life Insurance
Corporation of India established under the Life Insurance Corporation Act, 1956
(31 of 1956), or for the purchase of securities of the Government of India or of
any State Government or for being deposited in any Post Office Savings Bank in
furtherance of any savings scheme of any such Government;]]
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>32</footcitenum>[<number>kk</number> deductions made, with the written authorisation of the employed person,
for the payment of his contribution to any fund constituted by the employer or a
trade union registered under the Trade Unions Act, 1926 (16 of 1926), for the
welfare of the employed persons or the members of their families, or both, and
approved by 10[the appropriate
Government] or any officer specified by it in this behalf, during the
continuance of such approval;
 </subsection><subsection><number>kkk</number> deductions made, with the written authorisation of the employed person,
for payment of the fees payable by him for the membership of any trade union
registered under the Trade Unions Act, 1926 (16 of 1926);]
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>33</footcitenum>[<number>l</number> deductions, for payment of insurance premia on Fidelity Guarantee Bonds;
 </subsection><subsection><number>m</number> deductions for recovery of losses sustained by a railway administration
on account of acceptance by the employed person of counterfeit or base coins or
mutilated or forged currency notes; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>n</number> deductions for recovery of losses sustained by a railway administration
on account of the failure of the employed person to invoice, to bill, to collect
or to account for the appropriate charges due to that administration, whether in
respect of fares, freight, demurrage, wharfage and cranage or in respect of sale
of food in catering establishments or in respect of sale of commodities in grain
shops or otherwise;
 </subsection><subsection><number>o</number> deductions for recovery of losses sustained by a railway administration
on account of any rebates or refunds incorrectly granted by the employed person
where such loss is directly attributable to his neglect or default;]
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>34</footcitenum>[<number>p</number> deductions, made with the written authorisation of the employed person,
for contribution to the Prime Minister’s National Relief Fund or to such other
Fund as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette,
specify;]
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>35</footcitenum>[<number>q</number> deductions for contributions to any insurance scheme framed by the
Central Government for the benefit of its employees.]
 </subsection></section><section><footcitenum>36</footcitenum>[<number>3</number>
Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, the total amount of deductions
which may be made under sub-section (2) in any wage-period from the wages of any
employed person shall not exceed—
 <subsection><number>i</number> in cases where such deductions are wholly or partly made for payments to
co-operative societies under clause (j) of sub-section (2), seventy-five per
cent. of such wages, and
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> in any other case, fifty per cent. of such wages:
 Provided
that where the total deductions authorised under sub-section (2) exceed
seventy-five per cent. or, as the case may be, fifty per cent. of the wages, the
excess may be recovered in such manner as may be prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number>
Nothing contained in this section shall be construed as precluding the employer
from recovering from the wages of the employed person or otherwise any amount
payable by such person under any law for the time being in force other than <footcitenum>37</footcitenum>[the
Railways Act, 1989 (24 of 1989)].
   


 
Statement
of Objects and Reasons [The Payment of Wages
(Amendment) Act, 2005]
   

Removing
the ambiguities/weakness from the extant provisions of the Act and prescribing
more effective grievance redresal: Over the years, it has been noticed that
certain provisions of the Act have been differently interpreted thus leading to
administrative difficulties in implementing the same. In order to remove
ambiguities, appropriate changes are being proposed in sections 3, 7, 8 and 15
of the Act which respectively deal with responsibility for payment of wages,
deductions from wages fines and claims in certain cases.
   


 
State
Amendments
 <subsection>
<number>Bihar</number>—In
section 7, in sub-section (2), in clause (d), after the word ‘employer’ the
words “or by the State Government or by a statutory housing board or by such
an agency as the State Government notify” shall be inserted.
 
[Vide
Bihar Act 28 of 1956, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 23-11-1956)].
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>Gujarat</number>—In
section 7, in sub-section (2), in clause (k), the words “for being deposited
in any post office. Savings Bank” shall be deleted.
 
[Vide
Gujarat Act 26 of 1961, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 12-6-1961)].
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>Karnataka</number>—In
section 7, in sub-section (2), after clause (p) the following clauses shall be
added, namely:—
  “(q) deductions to recover
from a person re-employed after the termination of his former employment any
amount paid to him from a provident fund or as a gratuity on such termination:
  Provided that such recovery shall not exceed 20 per cent. of total
earnings. re-employment in this context means employment under the same
employer.”.
 <subsubsection> <number>r</number> [Omitted by Karnataka Act
2 of 1982, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 28-1-1982).]
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>Kerala</number>—In
section 7, in sub-section (2), after clause (o), the following clause shall be
inserted, namely,—
  “(p) deduction for
re-payment to the State Government of the amount of financial aid granted under
the Kerala Financial Aid to the Discharged or Dismissed Labour Rules, 1958.”
 
[Vide
Kerala Act 34 of 1959, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 8-10-1969)].
 
Madhya
Pradesh.—In section 7, in sub-section (2), after clause (e), insert the
following clause, namely:—
  “(ee) deduction with the
written authorization of the person employed for payment of any subscription to
any welfare scheme sponsored by the employees whether with or without
participation of employer, such as Employees’ Death Relief Scheme and approved
by such authority and in such manner as may be prescribed.”
 
[Vide
Madhya Pradesh Act 33 of 1976, sec. 3].
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—In
section 7, in sub-section (2), in clause (d), after the word “employer” the
following shall be added, namely:—
  “or the State Government,
or the Bombay Housing Board constituted under the Bombay Housing Board Act, 1948
(Bom LXIX of 1948), or such other agency as the State Government may, by
notification in the Official Gazette, direct.”
 
[Vide
Maharashtra Act 37 of 1956, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 19-7-1956)].
 
In
section 7, in sub-section (2)—
 <subsubsection>

<number>a</number>
in clause (j) the word “and” at the end shall be deleted;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

<number>b</number>
after clause (k) the following new clause shall be added, namely:—
  “(l)
deduction made, with the consent of the person employed, for contribution
towards any public charitable purpose which the State Government may by
notification in the Official Gazette specify in that behalf.”
 
[Vide
Maharashtra Act 42 of 1961, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 9-10-1961)].
 
In
section 7, in sub-section (2), in clause (k), the words for “being deposited
in any post office, Savings Bank” shall be deleted.
 
[Vide
Maharashtra Act 13 of 1961, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 4-3-1961)].
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>Orissa</number>—In
section 7, in sub-section (2), in clause (d), after the words “supplied by the
employers” the words “or by the State Government or by any Housing Board or
agency which the State Government may notify this behalf shall be inserted.
 
[Vide
Orissa Act 22 of 1956, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 29-10-1956)].
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>Pondicherry</number>—In
section 7, in sub-section (2) after clause (d), the following clause shall be
inserted, namely:—
  “(dd) deductions for
electricity supplied to the employed person by the Electricity Department of the
Government of Pondicherry.”
 
[Vide
Pondicherry Act 9 of 1970, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 25-5-1970)].
 
Tamil
Nadu.—In Section 7, in sub-section (2), after clause (d), insert the following
clause, namely:—
  “(dd) deductions for
electricity supplied to the employed person by the Tamil Nadu Electricity Board
under section 5 of the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1948 (Central Act 54 of 1948),
hereinafter in this Act referred to as the State Electricity Board.”
 
[Vide
Tamil Nadu Act 20 of 1963 and T.N.A.L.O. 1970].
 
In
section 7, in sub-section (2) after clause (g), the following clause shall be
inserted, namely:—
  “(gg) deductions of
profession tax payable by the employed person to any local authority.”
 
[Vide
Tamil Nadu Act 47 of 1974, sec. 2].
 
West
Bengal.—In section 7, in sub-section (2), after clause (e), the following
clause shall be inserted, namely:—
  “(ee) deductions for
contribution to a fund created under a ‘Death Benefit Scheme’ approved by
the State Government and designed to render pecuniary assistance to the nominees
of a deceased employed person nominated in such manner as may be prescribed who
had been a member of such a scheme:
  Provided that no deduction shall be made without written authorization of
the employed person in the form and manner prescribed in the scheme.
  Explanation I.—(1) Where the employed person has a family, a member of
the family, shall be nominated.
 </subsection></section><section> <number>2</number> Where the employed person
has no family, any person may be nominated.
  Explanation II.—For the purpose of Explanation I,—
 </section><section> <number>1</number> The family of a male
employed person shall include his wife, legitimate children, dependent parents,
the widow and legitimate children of his predeceased son:
  Provided that if such employed person proves that his wife has ceased,
under the personal law governing him or the customary law of the community to
which the spouses belong, to be entitled to maintenance from him, the wife shall
not be regarded as a member of his family:
  Provided further that such employed person may subsequently by a notice
in writing to such authority as may be specified by the State Government by
notification in this behalf declare that his wife may continue to be regarded as
a member of his family; 
 </section><section>
 <number>2</number>
The family of a female employed person shall include her husband, legitimate
children, dependent parents, husband’s dependent parents, the widow and
legitimate children of her predeceased son:
  Provided that such employed person may by a notice in writing to such
authority as may be specified by the State Government by notification in this
behalf declare that her husband and his dependent parents have been excluded
from her family:
  Provided further that such employed person may subsequently by a notice
in writing to such authority cancel the aforesaid notice; and
 </section><section> <number>3</number> If a legitimate child of
an employed person or of a predeceased son of an employed person is validily
adopted by any other person under any law in force for the time being, such
child shall not be a member of the family of such employed person.
 
[Vide
West Bengal Act 26 of 1975 as amended by West Bengal Act 19 of 1981 
(w.e.f. 4-7-1981)].
  



































 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>8</number>
Fines.—
<section><number>1</number>
No fine shall be imposed on any employed person save in respect of such acts and
omissions on his part as the employer, with the previous approval of <footcitenum>38</footcitenum>[the
appropriate Government] or of the prescribed authority, may have specified by
notice under sub-section (2).
 </section><section><number>2</number>
A notice specifying such acts and omissions shall be exhibited in the prescribed
manner on the premises in which the employment is carried on or in the case of
persons employed upon a railway (otherwise than in a factory), at the prescribed
place or places.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
No fine shall be imposed on any employed person until he has been given an
opportunity of showing cause against the fine, or otherwise, than in accordance
with such procedure as may be prescribed for the imposition of fines.
 </section><section><number>4</number>
The total amount of fine which may be imposed in any one wage-period on any
employed person shall not exceed an amount equal to <footcitenum>39</footcitenum>[three
per cent. of the wages] payable to him in respect of that wage-period.
 </section><section><number>5</number>
No fine shall be imposed on any employed person who is under the age of fifteen
years.
 </section><section><number>6</number>
No fine imposed on any employed person shall be recovered from him by
instalments or after the expiry of <footcitenum>40</footcitenum>[ninety
days] from the day on which it was imposed.
 </section><section><number>7</number>
Every fine shall be deemed to have been imposed on the day of the act or
omission in respect of which it was imposed.
 </section><section><number>8</number>
All fines and all realisations thereof shall be recorded in a register to be
kept by the person responsible for the payment of wages under section 3 in such
form as may be prescribed; and all such realisations shall be applied only to
such purposes beneficial to the persons employed in the factory or establishment
as are approved by the prescribed authority.
 Explanation.—When
the persons employed upon or in any railway, factory or <footcitenum>41</footcitenum>[industrial
or other establishment] are part only of a staff employed under the same
management, all such realisations may be credited to a common fund maintained
for the staff as a whole, provided that the fund shall be applied only to such
purposes as are approved by the prescribed authority.
   


 
Statement
of Objects and Reasons [The Payment of Wages
(Amendment) Act, 2005]
 
Removing
the ambiguities/weakness from the extant provisions of the Act and prescribing
more effective grievance redresal: Over the years, it has been noticed that
certain provisions of the Act have been differently interpreted thus leading to
administrative difficulties in implementing the same. In order to remove
ambiguities, appropriate changes are being proposed in sections 3, 7, 8 and 15
of the Act which respectively deal with responsibility for payment of wages,
deductions from wages fines and claims in certain cases.
 
  


 
State
Amendments
 
Andhra
Pradesh.—In section 8, in sub-section (8), before the Explanation insert the
following, namely:—
 

“but in the case of any
establishment to which the Andhra Pradesh Labour Welfare Fund Act, 1987 applies,
all such realizations shall be paid into the fund constituted under the said
Act.”
 
[Vide
Andhra Pradesh Act 34 of 1987, sec. 39 (w.e.f. 1-5-1988)].
 
  


 
Gujarat
(Bombay Area).—Same as that of Maharashtra.
 
  


 <subsection>
<number>Karnataka</number>—In
section 8, in sub-section (8), add the following before the Explanation,
namely:—
 

“but in the case of any
factory establishment to which the Mysore Labour Welfare Fund Act, 1965 applies,
all such realizations shall be paid into the fund constituted under the said
Act.”
 
[Vide
Mysore Act 15 of 1965. sec. 25 (w.e.f. 5-8-1965)].
 
  


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>Kerala</number>—In
section 8, in sub-section (8), before the Explanation, the following proviso
shall be inserted, namely:—
 


“Provided that in the case of any establishment to which the Kerala
Labour Welfare Fund Act, 1975, applies, all such realizations shall be paid into
the fund constituted under that Act.”
 
[Vide
Kerala Act 11 of 1977, sec. 43 (w.e.f. 1-5-1977)].
 
  


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—In
its application to the Bombay Area of the State of Maharashtra, in section 8, in
sub-section (8), before the Explanation add the following namely:—
 

“but in the case of any
factory or establishment to which the Bombay Labour Welfare Fund Act, 1953,
applies, all such realizations shall be paid into the fund constituted under the
said Act.”
 
[Vide
Bombay Act 40 of 1953, sec. 23].
 
  


 
Punjab,
Haryana.—See Proviso II to section 10(2) of the Punjab Labour Welfare Fund
Act, 1965 (Punjab Act 17 of 1965) and Act 31 of 1966, sec. 88.
 
  


 
Tamil
Nadu.—In section 8, in sub-section (8), in the last sentence the following
shall be added at the end, namely:—
 

“but in the case of any
establishment to which the Tamil Nadu Labour Welfare Fund Act, 1972 applies all
such realization shall be paid into the Fund constituted under the aforesaid
Act.”
 
[Vide
Tamil Nadu Act 36 of 1972, sec. 43 (w.e.f. 1-1-1973)].
 
  


 
Uttar
Pradesh.—In section 8, in sub-section (8), add the following proviso,
namely:—
 


“Provided that in the case of any factory or establishment to which the
U.P. Welfare Fund Act, 1965, applies, all such realization shall be paid into
the fund established under the said Act.”
 
[Vide
Uttar Pradesh Act 14 of 1965, sec. 23 (w.e.f. 26-7-1965)].
 
  


 
  










 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>9</number>
Deductions for absence from duty.—
<section><number>1</number>
Deductions may be made under clause (b) of sub-section (2) of section 7 only on
account of the absence of an employed person from the place or places where, by
the terms of his employment, he is required to work, such absence being for the
whole or any part of the period during which he is so required to work.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The amount of such deduction shall in no case bear to the wages payable to the
employed person in respect of the wage-period for which the deduction is made a
large proportion than the period for which he was absent bears to the total
period, within such wage-period, during which by the terms of his employment, he
was required to work:
 Provided
that, subject to any rules made in this behalf by <footcitenum>42</footcitenum>[the
appropriate Government], if ten or more employed persons acting in concert
absent themselves without due notice (that is to say without giving the notice
which is required under the terms of their contracts of employment) and without
reasonable cause, such deduction from any such person may include such amount
not exceeding his wages for eight days as may by any such terms be due to the
employer in lieu of due notice.
 <footcitenum>43</footcitenum>[Explanation.—For
the purposes of this section, an employed person shall be deemed to be absent
from the place where he is required to work if, although present in such place,
he refuses, in pursuance of a stay-in strike or for any other cause which is not
reasonable in the circumstances, to carry out his work.] 


  






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>10</number>
Deductions for damage or loss.—<footcitenum>44</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number>
A deduction under clause (c) or clause (o) of sub-section (2) of section 7 shall
not exceed the amount of the damage or loss caused to the employer by the
neglect or default of the employed person.
 </section><section><number>1A</number>
A deduction shall not be made under clause (c) or clause (m) or clause (n) or
clause (o) of sub-section (2) of section 7 until the employed person has been
given an opportunity of showing cause against the deduction, or otherwise than
in accordance with such procedure as may be prescribed for the making of such
deductions.] 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
All such deductions and all realisations thereof shall be recorded in a register
to be kept by the person responsible for the payment of wages under section 3 in
such form as may be prescribed.
   








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>11</number>
Deductions for services rendered.—A
deduction under clause (d) or clause (e) of sub-section (2) of section 7 shall
not be made from the wages of an employed person, unless the house-accommodation
amenity or service has been accepted by him, as a term of employment or
otherwise, and such deduction shall not exceed an amount equivalent to the value
of the house-accommodation amenity or service supplied and, in the case of a
deduction under the said clause (e), shall be subject to such conditions as <footcitenum>45</footcitenum>[***]
<footcitenum>46</footcitenum>[the
appropriate Government] may impose.
  
 
State
Amendments
 
Section
11A
 <section>
<number>Pondicherry</number>—After
section 11, insert the following section, namely:—
 
       “11A. The employer shall,
if so required by a requisition in writing, by the Electricity Department of the
Government of Pondicherry or by an officer authorized by it in this behalf, make
the deductions authorized under clause (dd) of sub-section (2) of Section 7 from
the wages of the employed person and remit the amount so deducted in such manner
as the State Government may, by general or special order, specify.”
 
[Vide
Pondicherry Act 9 of 1970, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 25-5-1970)].
 
Tamil
Nadu.—After section 11, insert the following section, namely:—
 
       “11A. Deductions in respect
of house accommodation.—The employer shall make the deductions authorized
under clause (d) of sub-section (2) of 
section 7 from the wages of the employed person and remit the amount so deducted
in such manner as the State Government may, by general or special order
specify.”
 
[Vide
Tamil Nadu Act 9 of 1959, sec. 4 and Act 14 of 1962, sec. 2 and First Sch. (w.e.f.
9-1-1963)].
 
Section
11B

 
Tamil
Nadu.—Same as section 11A in Pondicherry.
 
[Vide
Tamil Nadu Act 20 of 1963, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 6-11-1963)].
 
Section
11C

 
Tamil
Nadu.—After section 11B, insert the following section, namely:—
 
       “11C. Deductions in respect
of profession tax.—The employer shall, if so required by a requisition in
writing, by the local authority concerned or by an officer authorized by it in
this behalf, make the deductions authorized under clause (gg) of sub-section (2)
of section 7 from the wages of the employed person and remit the amount so
deducted to the credit of the local authority concerned in such manner as the
State Government may, by general or special order, specify.”
 
[Vide
Tamil Nadu Act 47 of 1974, sec. 3].
 
  








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>12</number>
Deductions for recovery of advances.—Deductions
under clause (f) of sub-section (2) of section 7 shall be subject to the
following conditions, namely:—
 <section><number>a</number>
recovery of an advance of money given before employment began shall be
made from the first payment of wages in respect of a complete wage-period, but
no recovery shall be made of such advances given for travelling expenses;
 </section><section><footcitenum>47</footcitenum>[<number>aa</number>
recovery of an advance of money given after employment began shall be
subject to such conditions as 2[the
appropriate Government] may impose;]
 </section><section><number>b</number>
recovery of advances of wages not already earned shall be subject to any
rules made by <footcitenum>48</footcitenum>[the
appropriate Government] regulating the extent to which such advances may be
given and the instalments by which they may be recovered.
   


 
  








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>49</footcitenum>[<number>12A</number>
Deductions for recovery of loans.—Deductions for recovery of loans granted
under clause (fff) of sub-section (2) of section 7 shall be subject to any rules
made by <footcitenum>50</footcitenum>[the
appropriate Government] regulating the extent to which such loans may be granted
and the rate of interest payable thereon.]
   









 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>13</number>
Deductions for payments to co-operative societies and insurance schemes.—Deductions under clause (j) <footcitenum>51</footcitenum>[and
clause (k)] of sub-section (2) of section 7 shall be subject to such conditions
as <footcitenum>52</footcitenum>[the
appropriate Government] may impose.
  
 

State
Amendment
 <section>
<number>Karnataka</number>—In
section 13,
 <subsection>
<number>1</number>
for the headline the following heading shall be substituted, namely—
 

“13. Other deductions.”
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>2</number>
for the words, letters and brackets, “under clause (j) and clause (k)” the
words, letters and brackets, “under clause (j), clause (k) and clause (q)”
shall be substituted.
 
[Vide
Karnataka Act 2 of 1977 as amended by Karnataka Act 2 of 1982 sec. 3 (w.e.f.
28-1-1982)].
 
  








 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><footcitenum>53</footcitenum>[<number>13A</number>
Maintenance of registers and records.—
<section><number>1</number> Every employer shall maintain
such registers and records giving such particulars of persons employed by him,
the work performed by them, the wages paid to them, the deductions made from
their wages, the receipts given by them and such other particulars and in such
form as may be prescribed.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Every register and record required to be maintained under this section shall,
for the purposes of this Act, be preserved for a period of three years after the
date of the last entry made therein.]
   







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>14</number>
Inspectors.—
<section><number>1</number>
An Inspector of Factories appointed under <footcitenum>54</footcitenum>[sub-section
(1) of section 8 of the Factories Act, 1948 (63 of 1948)], shall be an Inspector
for the purposes of this Act in respect of all factories within the local limits
assigned to him.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
<footcitenum>55</footcitenum>[The
appropriate Government] may appoint Inspectors for the purposes of this Act in
respect of all persons employed upon a railway (otherwise than in a factory) to
whom this Act applies.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
<footcitenum>55</footcitenum>[The
appropriate Government] may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint
such other persons as it thinks fit to be Inspectors for the purposes of this
Act, and may define the local limits within which and the class of factories and
<footcitenum>56</footcitenum>[industrial
or other establishments] in respect of which they shall exercise their
functions.
 </section><section><footcitenum>57</footcitenum>[<number>4</number>
An Inspector may,—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
make such examination and inquiry as he thinks fit in order to ascertain
whether the provisions of this Act or rules made thereunder are being observed;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
with such assistance, if any, as he thinks fit, enter, inspect and search
any premises of any railway, factory or <footcitenum>56</footcitenum>[industrial
or other establishment] at any reasonable time for the purpose of carrying out
the object of this Act;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
supervise the payment of wages to persons employed upon any railway or in
any factory or 3[industrial or other
establishment;]
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
require by a written order the production at such place, as may be
prescribed, of any register or record maintained in pursuance of this Act and
take on the spot or otherwise statements of any persons which he may consider
necessary for carrying out the purposes of this Act;
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>
seize or take copies of such registers or documents or portions thereof
as he may consider relevant in respect of an offence under this Act which he has
reason to believe has been committed by an employer;
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>
exercise such other powers as may be prescribed: 
 Provided
that no person shall be compelled under this sub-section to answer any question
or make any statement tending to incriminate himself.
 </subsection></section><section><number>4A</number>
The provisions of the <footcitenum>58</footcitenum>[Code
of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974)] shall, so far as may be, apply to any
search or seizure under this sub-section as they apply to any search or seizure
made under the authority of a warrant issued under <footcitenum>59</footcitenum>[section
94] of the said Code.]
 </section><section><number>5</number>
Every Inspector shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of the
Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860). 


   













 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>60</footcitenum>[<number>14A</number>
Facilities to be afforded to Inspectors.—Every employer shall afford an
Inspector all reasonable facilities for making any entry, inspection,
supervision, examination or inquiry under this Act.]
   







 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>15</number>
Claims arising out of deductions from wages or delay in payment of wages and
penalty for malicious or vexatious claims.—<footcitenum>61</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number>
The appropriate Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette,
appoint— 
 <subsection><number>a</number>
any Commissioner for Workmen’s Compensation; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
any officer of the Central Government exercising functions as,—
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> Regional
Labour Commissioner; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> Assistant
Labour Commissioner with at least two years’ experience; or
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
any officer of the State Government not below the rank of Assistant
Labour Commissioner with at least two years’ experience; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
a presiding officer of any Labour Court or Industrial Tribunal,
constituted under the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 (14 of 1947), or under any
corresponding law relating to the investigation and settlement of industrial
disputes in force in the State; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>
any other officer with experience as a Judge of a Civil Court or a
Judicial Magistrate,
 as
the authority to hear and decide for any specified area all claims arising out
of deductions from the wages, or delay in payment of the wages, of persons
employed or paid in that area, including all matters incidental to such claims:
 Provided
that where the appropriate Government considers it necessary so to do, it may
appoint more than one authority for any specified area and may, by general or
special order, provide for the distribution or allocation of work to be
performed by them under this Act.]
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
Where contrary to the provisions of this Act any deduction has been made from
the wages of an employed person, or any payment of wages has been delayed, such
person himself, or any legal practitioner or any official of a registered trade
union authorised in writing to act on his behalf, or any Inspector under this
Act, or any other person acting with the permission of the authority appointed
under sub-section (1), may apply to such authority for a direction under
sub-section (3):
 Provided
that every such application shall be presented within <footcitenum>62</footcitenum>[twelve
months] from the date on which the deduction from the wages was made or from the
date on which the payment of the wages was due to be made, as the case may be:
 Provided
further that any application may be admitted after the said period of <footcitenum>62</footcitenum>[twelve
months] when the applicant satisfies the authority that he had sufficient cause
for not making the application within such period.
 </section><section><footcitenum>63</footcitenum>[<number>3</number>
When any application under sub-section (2) is entertained, the authority shall
hear the applicant and the employer or other person responsible for the payment
of wages under section 3, or give them an opportunity of being heard, and, after
such further inquiry, if any, as may be necessary, may, without prejudice to any
other penalty to which such employer or other person is liable under this Act,
direct the refund to the employed person of the amount deducted, or the payment
of the delayed wages, together with the payment of such compensation as the
authority may think fit, not exceeding ten times the amount deducted in the
former case and not exceeding three thousand rupees but not less than one
thousand five hundred rupees in the latter, and even if the amount deducted or
delayed wages are paid before the disposal of the application, direct the
payment of such compensation, as the authority may think fit, not exceeding two
thousand rupees:
 Provided
that a claim under this Act shall be disposed of as far as practicable within a
period of three months from the date of registration of the claim by the
authority:
 Provided
further that the period of three months may be extended if both parties to the
dispute agree for any bona fide reason to be recorded by the authority that the
said period of three months may be extended to such period as may be necessary
to dispose of the application in a just manner:
 Provided
also that no direction for the payment of compensation shall be made in the case
of delayed wages if the authority is satisfied that the delay was due to—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
a bona fide error or bona fide dispute as to the amount payable to the
employed person; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
the occurrence of an emergency, or the existence of exceptional
circumstances, the person responsible for the payment of the wages was unable,
in spite of exercising reasonable diligence; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
the failure of the employed person to apply for or accept payment.]
 </subsection></section><section><footcitenum>64</footcitenum>[<number>4</number>
If the authority hearing an application under this section is satisfied—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
that the application was either malicious or vexatious, the authority may
direct that a penalty 5[not exceeding
three hundred seventy five rupees] be paid to the employer or other person
responsible for the payment of wages by the person presenting the application;
or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
that in any case in which compensation is directed to be paid under
sub-section (3), the applicant ought not to have been compelled to seek redress
under this section, the authority may direct that a penalty <footcitenum>65</footcitenum>[not
exceeding three hundred seventy five rupees] be paid to 6[the
appropriate Government] by the employer or other person responsible for the
payment of wages.
 </subsection></section><section><number>4A</number>
Where there is any dispute as to the person or persons being the legal
representative or representatives of the employer or of the employed person, the
decision of the authority on such dispute shall be final.
 </section><section><number>4B</number>
Any inquiry under this section shall be deemed to be a judicial proceeding
within the meaning of sections 193, 219 and 228 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of
1860).]
 </section><section><number>5</number>
Any amount directed to be paid under this section may be recovered—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
if the authority is a Magistrate, by the authority as if it were a fine
imposed by him as Magistrate, and
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
if the authority is not a Magistrate, by any Magistrate to whom the
authority makes application in this behalf, as if it were a fine imposed by such
Magistrate.
   


 

Statement
of Objects and Reasons [The Payment of Wages
(Amendment) Act, 2005]
 
Removing
the ambiguities/weakness from the extant provisions of the Act and prescribing
more effective grievance redresal: Over the years, it has been noticed that
certain provisions of the Act have been differently interpreted thus leading to
administrative difficulties in implementing the same. In order to remove
ambiguities, appropriate changes are being proposed in sections 3, 7, 8 and 15
of the Act which respectively deal with responsibility for payment of wages,
deductions from wages fines and claims in certain cases.
 
  


 
State
Amendments
 
  


 <subsubsection>
<number>Gujarat</number>—Same
as that of Maharashtra.
 
[Vide
Gujarat Act 26 of 1961, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 12-6-1961)].
 
  


 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>Haryana</number>—In
section 15, in sub-section (1), after the proviso, the following further proviso
shall be added:—
 
“Provided
further that the State Government may transfer any matter from one authority to
the another authority.”
 
[Vide
Haryana Act 5 of 1985, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 12-4-1985)].
 
  


 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>Karnataka</number>—(1)
In its application to the State of Mysore, in section 15 for the words
‘stipendiary Magistrate’, substitute the words ‘Judicial Magistrate’.
 
[Vide
Mysore Act 13 of 1965, sec. 66 and Sch. (w.e.f. 1-10-1965)].
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number>
In section 15—
 </section><section>

<number>1</number> in sub-section (2), after the word, brackets and figure
“sub-section (3)”, the following shall be inserted, namely:—
 

“and in case of death of the employed
person, it shall be lawful for his legal representatives to make an application
for such direction”;
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> for sub-section (5), the following sub-section shall be
substituted, namely:—
 

“(5) Any amount directed to be paid under
this section may be recovered by the authority as an arrear of land revenue and
the authority shall for that purpose be deemed to be a public officer within the
meaning of section 5 of the Revenue Recovery Act, 1890”.
 
[Vide
Karnataka Act 2 of 1977, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-2-1982)].
 
  


 
Madhya
Pradesh.—In section 15,
 <subsection>

<number>i</number> in sub-section (1), for the words beginning with “any
Commissioner” and ending with “to be the authority”, substitute the words
“one or more persons to be the authority or authorities”;
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>ii</number> after sub-section (1), insert the following sub-sections,
namely:—
 

“(1A) A person shall not be qualified for appointment as an authority
under this Act, unless he is a Commissioner for Workmen’s Compensation or any
other officer with experience as a Judge of a Civil Court or of a Labour Court
constituted under the Madhya Pradesh Industrial Relations Act, 1960.
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>1B</number> Where more than one persons are appointed for any specified area as
authorities under sub-section (1), the State Government may, by general or
special order, make arrangement as it thinks fit for the distribution of the
work among the authorities so appointed”.;
 <subsection>

<number>iii</number> in sub-section (2),—
 <subsubsection>

<number>a</number> after the words “to act on his behalf”,
insert the words “or a representative union recognised as such under the
Madhya Pradesh Industrial Relations Act, 1960”;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

<number>b</number>
after the words “sub-section (3)”, insert the words “and in case of
death of the employed person, it shall be lawful for his legal representative to
make an application for such direction”;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>

<number>iv</number>
in sub-section (3),—
 <subsubsection>

<number>a</number>
after the words “employed person”, insert the words “or his legal
representative, as the case may be”;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

<number>b</number>
for the words “ten rupees in the latter”, substitute the words
“twenty-five rupees in the latter case and the authority may direct the
payment of such compensation in cases, where the amount deducted or delayed
wages are paid by the employer to the employed person or his legal
representative before the disposal of the application”;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

<number>c</number>
in the proviso, after the words “employed person” occurring twice,
insert the words “or legal representative”;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>

<number>v</number>
for sub-section (4), substitute the following, namely:—
 

“(4)
the authority hearing an application under this section is satisfied,—
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>i</number>
that the application was either malicious or vexatious, the authority may
direct that any penalty not exceeding fifty rupees be paid to the employer or
other person responsible for the payment of wages by the person presenting the
application; or
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>ii</number>
that, in any case in which compensation is directed to be paid under
sub-section (3), the applicant ought not to have been compelled to seek redress
under this section, the authority may direct that a penalty not exceeding fifty
rupees be also paid by the employer or other person responsible for the payment
of wages which shall, when paid or recovered, be credited to the State
Government.
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>4a</number>
Where a question arises as to whether any person is or is not a legal
representative of the deceased employed person, such question shall be
determined by the authority appointed under sub-section (1) and his decision
shall be final.
 </section><section>

<number>4b</number>
The payment of the amount directed to be paid under this section to the
employed person or his legal representative, as the case may be, shall be a full
and complete discharge of the employer from the liability to make such payment
under this Act, and no further claim shall lie against the employer in respect
thereof”.
 
[Vide
Madhya Pradesh Act 11 of 1964, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 15-5-1964)].
 
  


 <subsection>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—In
its application to the State of Bombay (which term shall stand
unmodified—(Gujarat and Maharashtra A.L.O., 1960), in section 15,—
 <subsubsection>

<number>a</number>
in sub-section (1), for the words and figures beginning with “appoint
any” and ending with “to be the authority”, substitute the words
“appoint one or more persons to be the authority or authorities”.
 [Vide Bombay Act 48 of 1955, sec. 3(a), w.e.f. 1-7-1956; Maharashtra Act 
13 of 1961 sec. 2 (w.e.f. 4-3-1961)].
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

<number>b</number>
after sub-section (1), insert the following new sub-sections, namely:—
 

“(1A)
A person shall not be qualified for appointment as an authority under
this Act unless he is a Commissioner for Workmen’s Compensation or any other
officer with experience as a Judge of a Civil Court or as a stipendiary Judicial
Magistrate or as a Judge of a Labour Court or as a judicial member of the
Industrial Court constituted under the Bombay Industrial Relations Act, 1946, or
as a presiding officer of a Tribunal constituted under the Industrial Disputes
Act, 1947.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>

<number>1B</number>
Where more than one person are appointed for any specified area as
authorities under sub-section (1), the State Government may by general or
special order make such arrangements as it thinks fit for the distribution of
the work among the authorities so appointed.
 

[Vide Bombay Act 48 of 1955,
sec. 3(b), (w.e.f. 1-7-1956); Maharashtra Act 13 of 1961, sec. 2 (w.e.f.
4-3-1961)].
 <subsection>

<number>c</number>
in sub-section (2),—
 <subsubsection>

<number>i</number>
after the words “to act on his behalf”, insert the words and figures
“or a representative union registered as such under the Bombay Industrial
Relations Act, 1946,”;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

<number>ii</number>
after the word, brackets and figure “sub-section (3)”, insert the
following, namely, “and in case of death of the employed person, it shall be
lawful for his legal representative to make an application for such
direction”;
 

[Vide Bombay Act 48 of 1955,
sec. 3(c), (w.e.f. 1-7-1956)].
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

<number>iii</number>
in both the provisos, for the words “six months”, substitute the
words “one year”,
 

[Vide Bombay Act 62 of 1953,
sec. 4(2) (w.e.f. 10-5-1954); Maharashtra Act 13 of 1961, sec. 6 (w.e.f.
4-3-1961)].
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>

<number>d</number>
in sub-section (3)—
 <subsubsection>

<number>i</number>
for the words “refund to the employed person”, substitute the words
“refund to the employed person or his legal representative, as the case may
be”;
 

[Vide Bombay Act 48 of 1955, sec. 3(d) (w.e.f. 1-7-1956); Maharashtra Act
13 of 1961, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 4-3-1961)].
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

<number>ii</number>
for the words “ten rupees”, substitute the words “twenty-five
rupees”;
 

[Vide Bombay Act 62 of 1953, sec. 4 (3) (w.e.f. 10-5-1954); Maharashtra
Act 13 of 1961, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 4-3-1961)].
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

<number>iii</number>
after the words “twenty-five rupees in the latter”, insert the
following words, namely:—
 

“and the authority may direct the payment of such compensation in
cases, where the amount deducted or delayed wages are paid by the employer to
the employed person or his legal representative before the disposal of the
application”;
 

[Vide Bombay Act 48 of 1955, sec. 3(d); Maharashtra Act 13 of 1961, 
sec. 2 (w.e.f. 4-3-1961)].
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

<number>iv</number>
in the proviso, after the words “employed person”, at both the places
where they occur, insert the words “or his legal representative”.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>

<number>e</number>
for sub-section (4), substitute the following namely:—
 

“(4) If the authority
hearing any application under this section is satisfied,—
 <subsubsection>

<number>i</number>
that the application was either malicious or vexatious, the authority may
direct that a penalty not exceeding fifty rupees be paid to the employer or
other person responsible for the payment of wages by the person presenting the
application; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

<number>ii</number>
that, in any case in which compensation is directed to be paid under
sub-section (3), the applicant ought not to have been compelled to seek redress
under this section, the authority may direct that a penalty not exceeding fifty
rupees be also paid by the employer or other person responsible for the payment
of wages. The amount of such penalty when paid or recovered shall be credited to
the State Government”;
 

[Vide Bombay Act 62 of 1953, sec. 4(5) (w.e.f. 10-5-1954); Maharashtra 
Act 13 of 1961, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 4-3-1961)].
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>

<number>f</number>
for sub-section (5), substitute the following, namely:—
 

“(5) Any amount directed to be paid under this section may be recovered
by the authority as an arrear of land revenue and the authority shall for that
purpose be deemed to be a public officer within the meaning of section 5 of
Revenue Recovery Act, 1890”;
 

[Vide Bombay Act 70 of 1954, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 15-11-1954); Maharashtra Act
13 of 1961, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 4-3-1961)].
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>g</number>
after sub-section (5), add the following sub-section, namely:—
 

“(6) Where a question arises as to whether any person is or is not a
legal representative of the deceased employed person, such question shall be
determined by the authority and the decision of the authority shall be final”.
 

[Vide Bombay Act 48 of 1955, sec. 3(e) (w.e.f. 1-7-1956); Maharashtra Act
13 of 1961, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 4-3-1961)].
 
  


 <subsubsection>
<number>Rajasthan</number>—In
sub-section (1), after the expression “stipendiary Magistrate” the
expression “or a Vikas Adhikari appointed under the Rajasthan Panchayat
Samitis and Zila Parishads Act, 1959 (Rajasthan Act 37 of 1959) shall be
inserted.
 
[Vide
Rajasthan Act 11 of 1976, sec. 2].
 
  


 
Tamil
Nadu.—In section 15, for sub-section (5), the following sub-section shall be
substituted, namely:—
 

“(5) If any amount directed to be paid under this section is not paid
by the employer or by other person responsible for payment of wages under
section 3 to the person entitled thereto, the authority shall, on an application
made to it by such person himself, or any legal practitioner, or any official of
a registered trade union authorised in writing to act on his behalf, or any
Inspector under this Act, issue a certificate for that amount to the Collector,
who shall recover the same, as arrears of land revenue and pay the same to the
person entitled thereto.”
 
[Vide
Tamil Nadu Act 27 of 1986].
 
Section
15A

 
  


 
Andhra
Pradesh.—After section 15, insert the following section, namely:—
 

“15A. Exemption of court-fees in respect of proceedings under section
15.—(1) In respect of any proceedings under section 15, the applicant shall
not be liable to pay any court-fees, other than fees, payable for service of
process:
 

Provided that, where the
application is presented by an Inspector or any person acting with the
permission of the authority appointed under sub-section (1) of section 15, he
shall not also be liable to pay the fees for service of process.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>

<number>2</number> Where the applicant
succeeds in such proceedings, the authority hearing the application shall
calculate in the manner prescribed the amount of court-fees which would have
been payable by the applicant but for sub-section (1) and direct the employer or
other person responsible for payment of wages under section 3 to pay the amount
to the State Government. Where the amount is not so paid, it shall, without
prejudice to any other mode of recovery, be recoverable as if it were an arrear
of land revenue.
 
[Vide
Andhra Pradesh Act 21 of 1968, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 26-10-1968)].
 
  


 <subsection>
<number>Gujarat</number>—Same
as that of Maharashtra.
 
[Vide
Gujarat Act 26 of 1961, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 12-6-1961)].
 
  


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>Karnataka</number>—After
section 15, the following section shall be inserted, namely:—
 

“15A. Liability for payment of court-fees.—(1) In any proceedings
under section 15, the applicant shall not be liable to pay any court-fees (other
than fees payable for the service of process in respect of such proceedings):
 

Provided that when the application is presented by an Inspector he shall
not be liable to pay the process fees also.
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>2</number> Where the applicant
succeeds in such proceedings, the authority hearing the application shall
calculate the amount of court-fees which would have been payable by the
applicant but for sub-section (1) and direct the employee or other person
responsible for the payment of wages under section 3 to pay such amount to the
State Government. Such amount shall, without prejudice to any other mode of
recovery, be recoverable as an arrear of land revenue.
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> When an appeal is
preferred under section 17 by a person making an application under section 15,
the provisions of sub-sections (1) and (2) shall mutatis mutandis apply with the
modification that such person, not being an Inspector, shall pay court-fees of
an amount of five rupees, but that such amount shall be refunded to him in the
event of his succeeding in the appeal.”
 
[Vide
Karnataka Act 2 of 1997, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 1-12-1982)].
 
  


 <subsection>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—In
its application to the State of Bombay, after section 15, insert the following
section, namely:—
 

“15A. Liability for payment of court-fees.—(1) In any proceedings
under section 15, the applicant shall not be liable to pay any court-fees (other
than fees payable for the service of process) in respect of such proceedings:
 

Provided that when the
application is presented by an Inspector he shall not be liable to pay the
process fees also.
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>2</number> Where the applicant
succeeds in such proceedings, the authority hearing the application shall
calculate the amount of court-fees which would have been payable by the
applicant but for sub-section (1) and direct the employee or other person
responsible for the payment of wages under section 3 to pay such amount to the
State Government. Such amount shall, without prejudice to any other mode of
recovery, be recoverable as an arrear of land revenue.”
 
[Vide
Bombay Act 62 of 1953, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 10-5-1994); Maharashtra Act 13 of 1961,
sec. 2 (w.e.f. 4-3-1961)].
 
  


 <subsection>
<number>Rajasthan</number>—Same
as that of Maharashtra, except that in the proviso, for the word ‘also’ at
the end, word ‘even’ is used.
 
[Vide
Rajasthan Act 13 of 1970, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 3-12-1970)].
 


























 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>16</number>
Single application in respect of claims from unpaid group.—
<section><number>1</number> Employed persons are said to belong to the same
unpaid group if they are borne on the same establishment and if <footcitenum>67</footcitenum>[deductions,
have been made from their wages in contravention of this Act for the same cause
and during the same wage-period or periods or if] their wages for the same
wage-period or periods have remained unpaid after the day fixed by section 5.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
A single application may be presented under section 15 on behalf or in respect
of any number of employed persons belonging to the same unpaid group, and in
such case <footcitenum>68</footcitenum>[every
person on whose behalf such application is presented may be awarded maximum
compensation to the extent specified in sub-section (3) of section 15].
 </section><section><number>3</number>
The authority may deal with any number of separate pending applications,
presented under section 15 in respect of persons belonging to the same unpaid
group, as a single application presented under sub-section (2) of this section,
and the provisions of that sub-section shall apply accordingly. 


   









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>17</number>
Appeal.—
<section><number>1</number>
<footcitenum>69</footcitenum>[An appeal against an order
dismissing either wholly or in part an application made under sub-section (2) of
section 15, or against a direction made under sub-section (3) or sub-section (4)
of that section] may be preferred, within thirty days of the date on which <footcitenum>70</footcitenum>[the
order or direction] was made, in a Presidency-town <footcitenum>71</footcitenum>[***]
before the Court of Small Causes and elsewhere before the District Court—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
by the employer or other person responsible for the payment of wages
under section 3, if the total sum directed to be paid by way of wages and
compensation exceeds three hundred rupees <footcitenum>72</footcitenum>[or
such direction has the effect of imposing on the employer or the other person a
financial liability exceeding one thousand rupees], or
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>73</footcitenum>[<number>b</number>
by an employed person or any legal practitioner or any official of a
registered trade union authorised in writing to act on his behalf or any
Inspector under this Act, or any other person permitted by the authority to make
an application under sub-section (2) of section 15, if the total amount of wages
claimed to have been withheld from the employed person exceeds twenty rupees or
from the unpaid group to which the employed person belongs or belonged exceeds
fifty rupees, or]
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
by any person directed to pay a penalty under <footcitenum>74</footcitenum>[sub-section
(4)] of
section 15.
 </subsection></section><section><footcitenum>75</footcitenum>[<number>1A</number>
No appeal under clause (a) of sub-section (1)] shall lie unless the memorandum
of appeal is accompanied by a certificate by the authority to the effect that
the appellant has deposited the amount payable under the direction appealed
against.]
 </section><section><footcitenum>76</footcitenum>[<number>2</number>
Save as provided in sub-section (1), any order dismissing either wholly or in
part an application made under sub-section (2) of section 15, or a direction
made under sub-section (3) or sub-section (4) of that section shall be final.]
 </section><section><footcitenum>75</footcitenum>[<number>3</number>
Where an employer prefers an appeal under this section, the authority against
whose decision the appeal has been preferred may, and if so directed by the
court referred to in sub-section (1) shall, pending the decision of the appeal,
withhold payment of any sum in deposit with it.
 </section><section><number>4</number>
The court referred to in sub-section (1) may, if it thinks fit, submit any
question of law for the decision of the High Court and, if it so does, shall
decide the question in conformity with such decision.]
   


 
State
Amendments  


 <subsection>
<number>Gujarat</number>—In
section 17, in sub-section (1),—
 <subsubsection>
       <number>1</number>
Same as that of Maharashtra (1).
 
       [Vide Bombay Act 62 of 1953,
sec. 6 (w.e.f. 1-6-1961)].
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>2</number>(i)
for clause (b), substitute the following namely:—
 
       “(b) by an employed person, or any legal practitioner or any official
of a registered trade union authorised in writing to act on his behalf, or a
representative union registered as such under the Bombay Industial Relations
Act, 1946, or any Inspector under this Act, or any other person authorised by an
authority to make an application under sub-section (2) of section 15, and in the
case of death of the employed person, by his legal representative, as the case
may be, if the total amount of wages claimed to have been withheld from the
employed person, or from the unpaid group to which the employed person belonged,
exceed fifty rupees, or”;
 <subsubsubsection>
       <number>ii</number>
after the first proviso, add the following proviso, namely:—
 
       “Provided further that, when the order or direction appealed against
was made by any person who holds or has held office of or above the rank of a
District Judge or the Judicial Member of the Industial Court constituted under
the Bombay Industrial Relations Act, 1946, or the presiding officer of a
Tribunal constituted under the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947, an appeal under
this section shall lie to the High Court”.
 
[Vide
Gujarat Act 26 of 1961, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 12-6-1961)].
 
  


 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>Karnataka</number>—(1)
In section 17,—
 <subsubsection>
       <number>1</number>
in sub-section (2), after the words, brackets and figure “sub-section
(4) of that section” the words, brackets, figures, and letter, “or any order
made under sub-section (1) of section 17A” shall be inserted;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>2</number>
after sub-section (4), the following sub-section shall be added,
namely,—
 
       “(5) the provisions of
section 5 of the Limitation Act, 1963, shall be applicable to appeals unde this
section”.
 
       [Vide Karnataka Act 2 of
1977, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 1-12-1982)].
 
  


 
Madhya
Pradesh.—In section 17,—
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>1</number>
in sub-section (1), for the words beginning with “in a Presidency
town” and ending with “before the District Court” substitute the words
“before the Industrial Court”;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>2</number>
in clause (b) (which has now been substituted by Act 53 of 1964), after
the words “by an employed person”, insert the words “or his legal
representative or any Inspector under this Act”;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>3</number>
after clause (c), insert the following proviso:—
 
                  Same as in Maharashtra (1);
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>4</number>
after sub-section (2), insert the following sub-section:—
 
       “(3) The provisions of
section 5 of the Indian Limitation Act, 1908* shall be applicable to appeals
under this section”.
  *
Now see section 5 of the Limitation Act, 1963 [Vide Madhya Pradesh Act 11 of
1964, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 15-5-1964)].
 
  


 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—In
section 17, in sub-section (1),—
 <subsubsection>
       <number>1</number>
Add the following proviso, namely:—
 
       “Provided that no appeal by an employer or other person responsible for
the payment of wages under section 3 under clause (a) shall lie unless the
memorandum of appeal is accompanied by a certificate by the authority to the
effect that the appellant has deposited with it the amount payable under the
order appealed against”.
 
       [Vide Bombay Act 62 of 1953,
sec. 6 (w.e.f. 10-5-1954); Maharashtra Act 13 of 1961, sec. 2 (w.e.f.
4-3-1961)].
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>2</number>
Same as that of Gujarat (2).
 
[Vide
Maharashtra Act 13 of 1961, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 4-3-1961)].
 
  
























 



</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><footcitenum>77</footcitenum>[<number>17A</number>
Conditional attachment of property of employer or other person responsible for
payment of wages.—
<section><number>1</number> Where at any time after an application has been made
under sub-section (2) of section 15 the authority, or where at any time after an
appeal has been filed under section 17 by an employed person or <footcitenum>78</footcitenum>[any
legal practitioner or any official of a registered trade union authorised in
writing to act on his behalf or any Inspector under this Act or any other person
permitted by the authority to make an application under sub-section (2) of
section 15] the Court referred to in that section, is satisfied that the
employer or other person responsible for the payment of wages under section 3 is
likely to evade payment of any amount that may be directed to be paid under
section 15 or section 17, the authority or the Court, as the case may be, except
in cases where the authority or Court is of opinion that the ends of justice
would be defeated by the delay, after giving the employer or other person an
opportunity of being heard, may direct the attachment of so much of the property
of the employer or other person responsible for the payment of wages as is, in
the opinion of the authority or Court, sufficient to satisfy the amount which
may be payable under the direction.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The provisions of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), relating to
attachment before judgment under that Code shall, so far as may be, apply to any
order for attachment under sub-section (1).]
   


 
State
Amendments
 <subsection>
  

Gujarat.—Same
as that of Maharashtra.
 
[Vide
Gujarat Act 26 of 1961, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 12-6-1961)].
 
  


 </subsection><subsection>
Maharashtra.—In
section 17A, for the words “any official of a registered trade Union
authorised in writing to act on his behalf”, read the words “any other
person or a representative union competent to present such appeal”.
 
[Vide
Maharashtra Act 13 of 1961, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 4-3-1961)].
 
Section
17B

 
  


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>Gujarat</number>—Same
as that of Maharashtra.
 
[Vide
Bombay Act 70 of 1954, sec. 3 and Gujarat Act 26 of 1961, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 
12-6-1961)].
 
  


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—In
its application to the State of Bombay, after section 17A, the following new
section shall be inserted, namely:—
 
       “17B. Provisions of section 15A to apply to appeals preferred under
section 17 with modification.—When an appeal is preferred under section 17 by
a person making an application under section 15, the provisions of Section 15A
shall mutatis mutandis apply, with the modification that such person, not being
an Inspector, shall pay court-fees of an amount of five rupees, but that such
amount shall be refunded to him in the event of his succeeding in the appeal.”
 
[Vide
Maharashtra Act 13 of 1961, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 4-3-1961)].
 
  


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>Rajasthan</number>—Same
as that of Maharashtra.
 
[Vide
Rajasthan Act 13 of 1970, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 3-12-1970)].
 
  


 
  








 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>18</number>
Powers of authorities appointed under section 15.—Every
authority appointed under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 15 shall have all the
powers of a Civil Court under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), for
the purpose of taking evidence and of enforcing the attendance of witnesses and
compelling the production of documents, and every such authority shall be deemed
to be a Civil Court for all the purposes of section 195 and of 1[Chapter
XXVI of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974)].
   


 

State
Amendments
 
  

Tamil
Nadu.—After section 18, insert the following section, namely:—
 
       “18A. Transfer of cases.—(1) The State Government may, either on
their own motion or on an application made in this behalf, order the transfer of
any matter arising out of any proceedings pending before an authority to such
other authority for disposal. Such authority to whom the matter is so
transferred may, subject to any direction in the order of transfer, proceed
either de novo or from the stage at which it is so transferred.
 </section><section>
       <number>2</number> The State Government may,
by general or special order, authorise any officer of the Labour Department not
below the rank of Deputy Commissioner of Labour to exercise such of their powers
specified in sub-section (1)”.
 
[Vide
Tamil Nadu Act 38 of 1999, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 1-10-1999)].
 
  










 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>19</number>
Power to recover from employer in certain cases.—[Rep. by the Payment of
Wages (Amendment) Act, 1964 (53 of 1964), sec. 17 (w.e.f. 1-2-1965).] 


  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>20</number>
Penalty for offences under the Act.—
<section><number>1</number> Whoever being responsible for the
payment of wages to an employed person contravenes any of the provisions of any
of the following sections, namely, <footcitenum>80</footcitenum>[section
5 except sub-section (4) thereof, section 7, section 8 except sub-section (8)
thereof, section 9, section 10 except sub-section (2) thereof, and sections 11
to 13], both inclusive, shall be punishable <footcitenum>81</footcitenum>[with
fine which shall not be less than one thousand five hundred rupees but which may
extend to seven thousand five hundred rupees].
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Whoever contravenes the provisions of section 4, <footcitenum>82</footcitenum>[sub-section
(4) of 
section 5, section 6, sub-section (8) of section 8, sub-section (2) of section
10] or section 25 shall be punishable <footcitenum>83</footcitenum>[with
fine which may extend to three thousand seven hundred fifty rupees].
 </section><section><footcitenum>84</footcitenum>[<number>2A</number>
Whoever being required to nominate or designate a person under section 3 fails
to do so, such person shall be punishable with fine which may extend to three
thousand rupees.]
 </section><section><footcitenum>85</footcitenum>[<number>3</number>
Whoever being required under this Act to maintain any records or registers or to
furnish any information or return—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
fails to maintain such register or record; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
wilfully refuses or without lawful excuse neglects to furnish such
information or return; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
wilfully furnishes or causes to be furnished any information or return
which he knows to be false; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
refuses to answer or wilfully gives a false answer to any question
necessary for obtaining any information required to be furnished under this Act,
 shall,
for each such offence, be punishable with fine
<footcitenum>86</footcitenum>[with
fine which shall not be less than one thousand five hundred rupees but which may
extend to seven thousand five hundred rupees].
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number>
Whoever—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
wilfully obstructs an Inspector in the discharge of his duties under this
Act; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
refuses or wilfully neglects to afford an Inspector any reasonable
facility for making any entry, inspection, examination, supervision, or inquiry
authorised by or under this Act in relation to any railway, factory or <footcitenum>87</footcitenum>[industrial
or other establishment]; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
wilfully refuses to produce on the demand of an Inspector any register or
other document kept in pursuance of this Act; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
prevents or attempts to prevent or does anything which he has any reason
to believe is likely to prevent any person from appearing before or being
examined by an Inspector acting in pursuance of his duties under this Act,
 shall
be punishable with fine <footcitenum>88</footcitenum>[with
fine which shall not be less than one thousand five hundred rupees but which may
extend to seven thousand five hundred rupees].
 </subsection></section><section><number>5</number>
If any person who has been convicted of any offence punishable under this Act is
again guilty of an offence involving contravention of the same provision, he
shall be punishable on a subsequent conviction with imprisonment for a term <footcitenum>89</footcitenum>[which
shall not be less than one month but which may extend to six months and <footcitenum>90</footcitenum>[with
fine which shall not be less than three thousand seven hundred fifty rupees but
which may extend to twenty two thousand five hundred rupees] or with both:
 Provided
that for the purpose of this sub-section, no cognizance shall be taken of any
conviction made more than two years before the date on which the commission of
the offence which is being punished came to the knowledge of the Inspector.
 </section><section><number>6</number>
If any person fails or wilfully neglects to pay the wages of any employed person
by the date fixed by the authority in this behalf, he shall, without prejudice
to any other action that may be taken against him, be punishable with an
additional fine which may extend to <footcitenum>91</footcitenum>[seven
hundred fifty rupees] for each day for which such failure or neglect continues.]
   


 

Statement
of Objects and Reasons [The Payment of Wages
(Amendment) Act, 2005]
 
Strengthening
compensation and penal provisions of the Act: The penal provisions of the Act
have become almost insignificant due to passage of time as well as decrease in
money value since these provisions were last amended in 1982. It is, therefore,
proposed to make the penal provisions more stringent by enhancing the quantum of
penalties by amending section 20 of the Act.
 
  


 
State
Amendments
 
  

West
Bengal.—In section 20, in sub-section (1),—
 <subsection>

<number>a</number>
for the words “two hundred rupees”, the words “five hundred
rupees” shall be substituted, and
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>b</number>
for the words “one thousand rupees”, words “five thousand rupees”
shall be substituted.
 
[Vide
West Bengal Act 28 of 1993, sec. 4].
 
  



















 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>21</number>
Procedure in trial of offences.—
<section><number>1</number>
No Court shall take cognizance of a complaint against any person for an offence
under sub-section (1) of
section 20 unless an application in respect of the facts constituting the
offence has been presented under section 15 and has been granted wholly or in
part and the authority empowered under the latter section or the Appellate Court
granting such application has sanctioned the making of the complaint.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Before sanctioning the making of a complaint against any person for an offence
under sub-section (1) of section 20, the authority empowered under section 15 or
the Appellate Court, as the case may be, shall give such person an opportunity
of showing cause against the granting of such sanction, and the sanction shall
not be granted if such person satisfies the authority or Court that his default
was due to—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
a bona fide error or bona fide dispute as to the amount payable to the
employed person, or
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
the occurrence of an emergency or the existence of exceptional
circumstances, such that the person responsible for the payment of the wages was
unable, though exercising reasonable diligence, to make prompt payment, or
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
the failure of the employed person to apply for or accept payment.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number>
No Court shall take cognizance of a contravention of section 4 or of section 6
or of a contravention of any rules made under section 26 except on a complaint
made by or with the sanction of an Inspector under this Act.
 </section><section><footcitenum>92</footcitenum>[<number>3A</number>
No Court shall take cognizance of any offence punishable under sub-section (3)
or sub-section (4) of section 20 except on a complaint made by or with the
sanction of an Inspector under this Act.]
 </section><section><number>4</number>
In imposing any fine for an offence under sub-section (1) of section 20 the
court shall take into consideration the amount of any compensation already
awarded against the accused in any proceedings taken under section 15.
   


 
State
Amendments  


 <subsection>
<number>Gujarat</number>—Same
as that of Maharashtra.
 
[Vide
Gujarat Act 26 of 1961, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 12-6-1961)].
 
  


 </subsection><subsection>
Karnataka.—In
section 21,—
 <subsubsection>
       <number>1</number>
in sub-section (1), for the words “and the authority empowered under
the latter section or the appellate Court granting such application”, the
words “by the authority or the appellate Court or the State Government or any
officer authorised by it in his behalf” shall be substituted;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>2</number>
in sub-section (2) for the words and figure “the authority empowered
under section 15 or the appellate Court”, the words “the State Government or
the officer authorised by it in this behalf” shall be substituted.
 
[Vide
Karnataka Act 2 of 1977, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-2-1982)].
 
  


 
Madhya
Pradesh.—In section 21, in sub-section (2), in clauses (a) and (c), after the
words “employed person” insert the words “or his legal representative”.
 
[Vide
Madhya Pradesh Act 11 of 1964, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 15-5-1964)].
 
  


 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—In
section 21,—
 <subsubsection>
       <number>a</number>
in sub-section (1), for the words and figure “and the authority
empowered under section 15 or the appellate Court granting such application”,
substitute the words “by the authoity or the appellate Court and the State
Government or any officer authorised by it in this behalf”;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>b</number>
in sub-section (2)—
 <subsubsubsection>
       <number>i</number>
for the words and figure “the authority empowered under section 15 or
the appellate Court”, substitute the words “the State Government or the
office authorised by it in this behalf”;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
       <number>ii</number>
for the words “the authority or Court”, substitute the words “the
State Government or the authorised officer; and”
 
       [Vide Bombay Act 62 of 1953, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 10-5-1954); Maharashtra Act
13 of 1961, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 4-3-1961)].
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
       <number>iii</number>
in clauses (a) and (c), after the words “employed person”, in both
the places where they occur, insert the words “or his legal representative”.
 
[Vide
Bombay Act 48 of 1955, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-7-1956); Maharashtra Act 13 of 1961,
sec. 2 (w.e.f. 4-3-1961)].
  









 



</subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>22</number>
Bar of suits.—No
Court shall entertain any suit for the recovery of wages or of any deduction
from wages insofar as the sum so claimed—
 <section><number>a</number>
forms the subject of an application under section 15 which has been
presented by the plaintiff and which is pending before the authority appointed
under that section or of an appeal under section 17; or
 </section><section><number>b</number>
has formed the subject of a direction under section 15 in favour of the
plaintiff; or
 </section><section><number>c</number>
has been adjudged, in any proceeding under section 15, not to be owed to
the plaintiff; or
 </section><section><number>d</number>
could have been recovered by an application under section 15.
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>93</footcitenum>[<number>22A</number>
Protection of action taken in good faith.—No suit, prosecution or other legal
proceeding shall lie against the Government or any officer of the Government for
anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act.] 


   







 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>23</number>
Contracting out.—Any contract or agreement, whether made before or after
the commencement of this Act, whereby an employed person relinquishes any right
conferred by this Act shall be null and void in so far as it purports to deprive
him of such right.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>94</footcitenum>[<number>24</number>
Delegation of powers.—The appropriate Government may, by notification in the
Official Gazette, direct that any power exercisable by it under this Act shall,
in relation to such matters and subject to such conditions, if any, as may be
specified in the direction, be also exercisable—
 <section><number>a</number>
where the appropriate Government is the Central Government, by such
officer or authority subordinate to the Central Government or by the State
Government or by such officer or authority subordinate to the State Government,
as may be specified in the notification;
 </section><section><number>b</number>
where the appropriate Government is a State Government, by such officer
or authority subordinate to the State Government as may be specified in the
notification.]
   







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>25</number>
Display by notice of abstracts of the Act.—The person responsible for the
payment of wages to persons <footcitenum>95</footcitenum>[employed
in a factory or an industrial or other establishment] shall cause to be <footcitenum>96</footcitenum>[displayed
in such factory or industrial or other establishment] a notice containing such
abstracts of this Act and of the rules made thereunder in English and in the
language of the majority of the persons employed <footcitenum>97</footcitenum>[in
the factory, or industrial or other establishment], as may be prescribed. 


   










 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>98</footcitenum>[<number>25A</number>
Payment of undisbursed wages in cases of death of employed person.—
<section><number>1</number> Subject
to the other provisions of the Act, all amounts payable to an employed person as
wages shall, if such amounts could not or cannot be paid on account of his death
before payment or on account of his whereabouts not being known,—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
be paid to the person nominated by him in this behalf in accordance with
the rules made under this Act; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
where no such nomination has been made or where for any reasons such
amounts cannot be paid to the person so nominated, be deposited with the
prescribed authority who shall deal with the amounts so deposited in such manner
as may be prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
Where, in accordance with the provisions of sub-section (1), all amounts payable
to an employed person as wages—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
are paid by the employer to the person nominated by the employed person,
or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
are deposited by the employer with the prescribed authority, or
 the
employer shall be discharged of his liability to pay those wages.]
   








 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>26</number>
Rule-making power.—
<section><number>1</number>
<footcitenum>99</footcitenum>[<footcitenum>100</footcitenum>[The
appropriate Government] may make rules to regulate the procedure to be followed
by the authorities and Courts referred to in sections 15 and 17.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
<footcitenum>99</footcitenum>[<footcitenum>100</footcitenum>[The
appropriate Government] may, <footcitenum>101</footcitenum>[***]
by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for the purpose of carrying
into effect the provisions of this Act.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power,
rules made under sub-section (2) may—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
require the maintenance of such records, registers, returns and notices
as are necessary for the enforcement of the Act <footcitenum>102</footcitenum>[prescribe
the form thereof and the particulars to be entered in such registers or
records];
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
require the display in a conspicuous place or premises where employment
is carried on of notices specifying rates of wages payable to persons employed
on such premises;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
provide for the regular inspection of the weights, measures and weighing
machines used by employers in checking or ascertaining the wages of persons
employed by them;
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
prescribe the manner of giving notice of the days on which wages will be
paid;
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>
prescribe the authority competent to approve under sub-section (1) of
section 8 acts and omissions in respect of which fines may be imposed;
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>
prescribe the procedure for the imposition of fines under section 8 and
for the making of the deductions referred to in section 10;
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number>
prescribe the conditions subject to which deductions may be made under
the proviso to sub-section (2) of section 9;
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number>
prescribe the authority competent to approve the purposes on which the
proceeds of fines shall be expended;
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number>
prescribe the extent to which advances may be made and the instalments by
which they may be recovered with reference to clause (b) of section 12;
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>103</footcitenum>[<number>ia</number>
prescribe the extent to which loans may be granted and the rate of
interest payable thereon with reference to section 12A;
 </subsection><subsection><number>ib</number>
prescribe the powers of Inspectors for the purposes of this Act;]
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number>
regulate the scales of costs which may be allowed in proceedings under
this Act;
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number>
prescribe the amount of court-fees payable in respect of any proceedings
under this Act; <footcitenum>104</footcitenum>[***]
 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number>
prescribe the abstracts to be contained in the notices required by
section 25; <footcitenum>105</footcitenum>[***]
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>106</footcitenum>[<number>la</number>
prescribe the form and manner in which nominations may be made for the
purposes of sub-section (1) of section 25A, the cancellation or variation of any
such nomination, or the making of any fresh nomination in the event of the
nominee predeceasing the person making nomination, and other matters connected
with such nominations;
 </subsection><subsection><number>lb</number>
specify the authority with whom amounts required to be deposited under
clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 25A shall be deposited, and the manner
in which such authority shall deal with the amounts deposited with it under that
clause;]
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>107</footcitenum>[<number>m</number>
provide for any other matter which is to be or may be prescribed.]
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number>
In making any rule under this section the State Government may provide that a
contravention of the rule shall be punishable with fine<footcitenum>108</footcitenum>[which shall not be less than
seven hundred fifty rupees but which may extend to one thousand and five hundred
rupees].
 </section><section><number>5</number>
All rules made under this section shall be subject to the condition of previous
publication, and the date to be specified under clause (3) of section 23 of the
General Clauses Act, 1897 (10 of 1897), shall not be less than three months from
the date on which the draft of the proposed rules was published.
 </section><section><footcitenum>107</footcitenum>[<number>6</number>
Every rule made by the Central Government under this section shall be laid, as
soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament while it is in
session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session
or in <footcitenum>109</footcitenum>[two
or more successive sessions,] and if, before the expiry of the session <footcitenum>110</footcitenum>[immediately
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid,] both Houses agree
in making any modification in the rule, or both Houses agree that the rule
should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such
modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything
previously done under that rule.]
 </section><section><footcitenum>111</footcitenum>[<number>7</number>
All rules made under this section by the State Government shall, as soon as
possible after they are made, be laid before the State Legislature.]
   


 
State
Amendments
 <subsection>
<number>Bihar</number>—In
section 26, after clause (d), insert the following clause namely:—
 
       “(dd) prescribe the manner
in which the excess amount of the bonus shall be paid or invested under section
6”.
 
[Vide
Bihar Act 4 of 1963, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 29-3-1963)].
 
  


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>Gujarat</number>—Same
as that of Maharashtra.
 
[Vide
Gujarat Act 26 of 1961, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 12-6-1961)].
 
  


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>Karnataka</number>—In
section 26, in sub-section (3), in clause (k), for the words “court-fees”,
the words “ad valorem or fixed court-fees” shall be substituted.
 
[Vide
Karnataka Act 2 of 1977, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 1-2-1982)].
 
  


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—In
section 26, in sub-section (3),—
 <subsubsection>
       <number>1</number>
after clause (d), insert the following clause, namely:—
 
       “(da) prescribe the manner
in which the excess amount of the bonus shall be paid or invested under section
6”;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>2</number>
in clause (k),—
 <subsubsubsection>
       <number>a</number>
for the word “court-fees” substitute the words “ad valorem or fixed
court-fees”;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
       <number>b</number>
the word “and” shall be deleted.
 
[Vide
Bombay Act 62 of 1953, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 10-5-1954); Maharashtra Act 13 of 1961,
sec. 2 (w.e.f 4-3-1961)].
  
















 



</subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection></section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Ins.
by Act 26 of 1984, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 18-5-1984).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Came
into force on 16-9-1972, vide S.O. 601(E), dated 16th September, 1972,
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(ii), p. 1641.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Subs.
by Act 26 of 1984, sec. 3, for clause (c) (w.r.e.f. 11-2-1981). tc
"	1.	Subs. by Act 26 of 1984, sec. 3, for clause (c) (w.r.e.f.
11-2-1981)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Certain
words omitted by Act 34 of 1994, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 24-5-1994). tc
"	2.	Certain words omitted by Act 34 of 1994, sec. 2 (w.e.f.
24-5-1994)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Subs.
by Act 25 of 1984, sec. 2, for certain words (w.e.f. 1-7-1984). tc
"	3.	Subs. by Act 25 of 1984, sec. 2, for certain words (w.e.f.
1-7-1984)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Explanation
omitted by Act 34 of 1994, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 24-5-1994).  tc "	4.	Explanation omitted by Act 34 of 1994,
sec. 2 (w.e.f. 24-5-1994). "</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Subs.
by Act 22 of 1987, sec. 2, for “and the widow” (w.e.f. 1-10-1987). tc
"	1.	Subs. by Act 22 of 1987, sec. 2, for “and the widow” (w.e.f.
1-10-1987)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> The
proviso omitted by Act 22 of 1987,
sec. 2 (w.e.f. 1-10-1987). tc "	2.	The proviso omitted by  Act 22 of 1987, sec. 2 (w.e.f.
1-10-1987)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> Subs.
by Act 25 of 1984, sec. 2, for clause (r) (w.e.f. 1-7-1984). tc
"	3.	Subs. by Act 25 of 1984, sec. 2, for clause (r) (w.e.f.
1-7-1984)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> Subs. by Act 41 of 2005, sec. 5, for section “3.
Responsibility for payment of wages.—Every employer shall be responsible for
the payment to persons employed by him of all wages required to be paid under
this Act:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number> Subs. by Act 38 of 1982, sec. 6, for “industrial
establishment” (w.e.f. 15-10-1982).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number> Added by Act 53 of 1964, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-2-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number> Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “Governor-General in
Council”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number> Subs. by Act 41 of 2005, sec. 3, for “the State
Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number> Ins. by Act 53 of 1964, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-2-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number> Subs. by Act 53 of 1964, sec. 5, for “All payments” (w.e.f.
1-2-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number> Ins. by Act 29 of 1976, sec. 3 (w.r.e.f. 12-11-1975).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number> Subs. by Act 41 of 2005, sec. 6(a) for “sub-section (2)
of section 47 of the Indian Railways Act, 1890 (9 of 1890)” (w.e.f.
9-11-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number> Explanation re-numbered as Explanation I by Act 68 of
1957, sec. 5 (w.e.f 1-4-1958).  tc "	2.	Explanation re-numbered
as Explanation I by Act 68 of 1957, sec. 5 (w.e.f 1-4-1958)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number> Ins. by Act 68 of 1957, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-4-1958).  tc "	3.	Ins. by Act 68 of 1957,
sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-4-1958)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number> Subs. by Act 68 of 1957, sec. 5, for clause (d) (w.e.f.
1-4-1958).  tc "	1.	Subs. by Act 68 of 1957,
sec. 5, for clause (d) (w.e.f. 1-4-1958)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number> The words “Governor-General in Council or” omitted by
the A.O. 1937.  tc
"	2.	The words “Governor-General in Council or” omitted by the A.O.
1937."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number> Ins. by Act 53 of 1964, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 1-2-1965).  tc "	3.	Ins. by Act 53 of 1964,
sec. 6 (w.e.f. 1-2-1965)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number> Subs. by Act 56 of 1974, sec. 3 and Sch. II, for “this
sub-clause”.   tc  "	4.	Subs. by Act 56 of 1974, sec. 3 and Sch. II,
for “this sub-clause”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number> Subs. by Act 53 of 1964, sec. 6, for clause (f) (w.e.f.
1-2-1965).  tc "	5.	Subs. by Act 53 of 1964,
sec. 6, for clause (f) (w.e.f. 1-2-1965)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number> Subs. by Act 41 of 2005, sec. 6(b), for “in section 58A
of the Indian Income-tax Act, 1922
(11 of 1922)” (w.e.f. 9-11-2005).  tc "	1.	Subs. by Act 41 of 2005,
sec. 6(b), for “in section 58A of the 
Indian Income-tax Act, 1922 (11 of 1922)” (w.e.f. 9-11-2005)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number> Subs. by Act 41 of 2005, sec. 3, for “the State
Government”.   tc  "	2.	Subs. by Act 41 of 2005,
sec. 3, for “the State Government”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>28</number> The word “and” omitted by Ordinance 3 of 1940, sec.
2.  tc "	3.	The word “and” omitted by
Ordinance 3 of 1940, sec. 2."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>29</number> Ins. by Act 53 of 1964, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 1-2-1965).  tc "	4.	Ins. by Act 53 of 1964,
sec. 6 (w.e.f. 1-2-1965)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>30</number> Added by Ordinance 3 of 1940, sec. 2.  tc "	5.	Added by Ordinance 3 of
1940, sec. 2."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>31</number> Subs. by Act 68 of 1957, sec. 5, for clause (k) (w.e.f.
1-4-1958).  tc "	6.	Subs. by Act 68 of 1957,
sec. 5, for clause (k) (w.e.f. 1-4-1958)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>32</number> Ins. by Act 38 of 1982, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 15-10-1982).  tc "	7.	Ins. by Act 38 of 1982,
sec. 7 (w.e.f. 15-10-1982)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>33</number>
Ins. by Act 53 of 1964, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 1-2-1965).  tc "	1.	Ins. by Act 53 of 1964, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 1-2-1965)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>34</number>
Ins. by Act 29 of 1976, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 12-11-1976).  tc "	2.	Ins. by Act 29 of 1976, sec. 4 (w.e.f.
12-11-1976)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>35</number>
Ins. by Act 19 of 1977, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 30-6-1977).  tc "	3.	Ins. by Act 19 of 1977, sec. 2 (w.e.f.
30-6-1977)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>36</number>
Ins. by Act 53 of 1964, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 1-2-1965).  tc "	4.	Ins. by Act 53 of 1964, sec. 7 (w.e.f.
1-2-1965)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>37</number>
Subs. by Act 41 of 2005, sec. 6(c), for “the Indian Railways Act, 1890
(9 of 1890)” (w.e.f. 9-11-2005).  tc "	5.	Subs. by Act 41 of 2005,
sec. 6(c), for “the Indian Railways Act, 1890 (9 of 1890)” (w.e.f.
9-11-2005)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>38</number> Subs. by Act 41 of 2005, sec. 3, for “the State
Government” (w.e.f. 9-11-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>39</number>
Subs. by Act 38 of 1982, sec. 8, for “half-an-anna in the rupee” (w.e.f.
15-10-1982).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>40</number>
Subs. by Act 41 of 2005, sec. 7, for “sixty days” (w.e.f. 9-11-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>41</number> Subs. by Act 38 of 1982, sec. 8, for “industrial
establishment” (w.e.f. 15-10-1982).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>42</number> Subs. by Act 41 of 2005, sec. 3, for “the State
Government” (w.e.f. 9-11-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>43</number> Added by Act 22 of 1937, sec. 2.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>44</number> Subs. by Act 53 of 1964, sec. 7, for sub-section (1) (w.e.f.
1-2-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>45</number> The words “the
Governor-General in Council or” omitted by the A.O. 1937.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>46</number> Subs. by Act 41 of 2005, sec. 3, for “the State
Government” (w.e.f. 9-11-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>47</number> Ins. by Act 53 of 1964, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-2-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>48</number> Subs. by Act 41 of 2005, sec. 3, for “the State
Government” (w.e.f. 9-11-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>49</number> Ins. by Act 53 of 1964, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 1-2-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>50</number> Subs. by Act 41 of 2005, sec. 3, for “the State
Government” (w.e.f. 9-11-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>51</number> Ins. by Ordinance 3 of 1940, sec. 3.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>52</number> Subs. by Act 41 of 2005, sec. 3, for “the State
Government” (w.e.f. 9-11-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>53</number> Ins. by Act 53 of 1964, sec. 10 (w.e.f. 1-2-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>54</number> Subs. by Act 68 of 1957, sec. 6, for “sub-section (1) of 
section 10 of the Factories Act, 1934 (25 of 1934)” (w.e.f. 1-4-1958).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>55</number> Subs. by Act 41 of 2005, sec. 3, for “The State 
Government” (w.e.f. 9-11-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>56</number> Subs. by Act 38 of 1982, sec. 9, for “industrial 
establishments” (w.e.f. 15-10-1982).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>57</number> Subs. by Act 53 of 1964, sec. 11, for sub-section (4) (w.e.f. 
1-2-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>58</number> Subs. by Act 38 of 1982, sec. 9, for “Code of Criminal 
Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898)” (w.e.f. 15-10-1982).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>59</number> Subs. by Act 38 of 1982, sec. 9, for “section 98” (w.e.f. 
15-10-1982).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>60</number> Ins. by Act 53 of 1964, sec. 12 (w.e.f. 1-2-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>61</number> Subs. by Act 41 of 2005, sec. 8(i), for sub-section
“(1) The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette,
appoint a presiding officer of any Labour Court or Industrial Tribunal,
constituted under the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 (14 of 1947), or under any
corresponding law relating to the investigation and settlment of industrial
disputes in force in the State or any Commisioner for Workmen’s Compensation
or other officer with experience as a Judge of a Civil Court or as a Stipendiary
Magistrate to be the authority to hear and decide for any specified area all
claims arising out of deductions from the wages, or delay in payment of the
wages, of persons employed or paid in that area, including all matters,
incidental to such claims:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>62</number> Subs. by Act 53 of 1964, sec. 13, for “six months” (w.e.f.
1-2-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>63</number> Subs. by the Payment of Wages (Amendment) Act, 2005, sec.
8 (ii), for sub-section “(3) When any application under sub-section (2) is
entertained, the authority shall hear the applicant and the employer or other
person responsible for the payment of wages under section 3, or give them an
opportunity of being heard, and, after such further inquiry (if any) as may be
necessary, may, without prejudice to any other penalty to which such employer or
other person is liable under this Act, direct the refund to the employed person
of the amount deducted, or the payment of the delayed wages, together with the
payment of such compensation as the authority may think fit, not exceeding ten
times the amount deducted in the former case and not exceeding twenty-five
rupees in the latter, and even if the amount deducted or the delayed wages are
paid before the disposal of the application, direct the payment of such
compensation, as the authority may think fit, not exceeding twenty-five rupees:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>64</number> Subs. by Act 53 of 1964, sec. 13, for sub-section (4) (w.e.f.
1-2-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>65</number> Susb. by Act 41 of 2005, sec. 8(iii), for “not
exceeding fifty rupees” (w.e.f. 9-11-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>66</number> Subs. by Act 41 of 2005, sec. 3, for “The State
Government” (w.e.f. 9-11-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>67</number> Ins. by Act 53 of 1964, sec. 14 (w.e.f. 1-2-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>68</number> Subs. by Act 53 of 1964, sec. 14, for certain words (w.e.f.
1-2-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>69</number> Subs. by Act 68 of 1957, sec. 7, for “An appeal against
a direction made under sub-section (3) or sub-section (4) of section 15” (w.e.f.
1-4-1958).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>70</number> Subs. by Act 68
of 1957, sec. 7, for “the direction” (w.e.f. 1-4-1958).  tc "	4.	Subs. by Act  68 of 1957, sec. 7, for “the direction”
(w.e.f. 1-4-1958)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>71</number> The words “or in Rangoon” omitted by the A.O. 1937.  tc "	5.	The words “or in Rangoon”
omitted by the A.O. 1937."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>72</number> Ins. by Act 53 of 1964, sec. 15 (w.e.f. 1-2-1965).  tc "	1.	Ins. by Act 53 of 1964,
sec. 15 (w.e.f. 1-2-1965)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>73</number> Subs. by Act 53 of 1964, sec. 15, for clause (b) (w.e.f.
1-2-1965).  tc "	2.	Subs. by Act 53 of 1964,
sec. 15, for clause (b) (w.e.f. 1-2-1965)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>74</number> Subs. by Act 20 of 1937, sec. 2 and Sch. I, for
“sub-section (5)”.  tc "	3.	Subs. by Act 20 of 1937,
sec. 2 and Sch. I, for “sub-section (5)”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>75</number> Ins. by Act 53 of 1964, sec. 15 (w.e.f. 1-2-1965 ). tc "	4.	Ins. by Act 53 of 1964,
sec. 15 (w.e.f. 1-2-1965)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>76</number> Subs. by Act 68 of 1957, sec. 7, for sub-section (2) (w.e.f.
1-4-1958).  tc "	5.	Subs. by Act 68 of 1957, sec. 7, for
sub-section (2) (w.e.f. 1-4-1958)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>77</number> Ins. by Act 68 of 1957, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-4-1958).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>78</number> Subs. by Act 53 of 1964, sec. 16, for certain words (w.e.f.
1-2-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>79</number> Subs. by Act 38 of 1982, sec. 10, for “Chapter XXV of
the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898)” (w.e.f. 15-10-1982).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>80</number> Subs. by Act 53 of 1964, sec. 18, for “section 5 and
sections 7 to 13” (w.e.f. 1-2-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>81</number> Subs. by Act 41 of 2005, sec. 9(a), for “with fine
which shall not be less than two hundred rupees but which may extend to one
thousand rupess” (w.e.f. 9-11-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>82</number> Subs. by Act 53 of 1964, sec. 18, for “section 6” (w.e.f.
1-2-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>83</number> Subs. by Act 41 of 2005, sec. 9(b), for “with fine
which may extend to five hundred rupees (w.e.f. 9-11-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>84</number> Ins. by Act 41 of 2005, sec. 9(c) (w.e.f. 9-11-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>85</number> Ins. by Act 53 of 1964, sec. 18 (w.e.f 1-2-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>86</number> Subs. by Act 41 of 2005, sec. 9(d), for “with fine
which shall not be less than two hundred rupees but which may extend to one
thousand rupess” (w.e.f. 9-11-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>87</number> Subs. by Act 38 of 1982, sec. 11, for “industrial
establishment” (w.e.f. 15-10-1982).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>88</number> Subs. by Act 41 of 2005, sec. 9(e), for “with fine
which shall not be less than two hundred rupees but which may extend to one
thousand rupess” (w.e.f. 9-11-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>89</number> Subs. by Act 38 of 1982, sec. 11, for “which may extend
to three months or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with
both” (w.e.f. 15-10-1982).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>90</number> Subs. by Act 41 of 2005, sec. 9(f), for “with fine
which shall not be less than five hundred rupees but which may extend to three
thousand rupees” (w.e.f. 9-11-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>91</number> Subs. by Act 41 of 2005, sec. 9(g), for “one hundred
rupees” (w.e.f. 9-11-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>92</number> Ins. by Act 53
of 1964, sec. 19 (w.e.f. 1-2-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>93</number> Ins. by Act 53 of 1964, sec. 20 (w.e.f. 1-2-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>94</number> Subs. by Act 41 of 2005, sec. 10, for section “24.
Application of Act to railways, air transport services, mines and
oil-fields.—The powers by this Act conferred upon the State Government shall,
in relation to railways, air transport services, mines and oil-fields; be powers
of the Central Government” (w.e.f. 9-11-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>95</number>  Subs. by Act 38 of 1982, sec. 12, for “employed in a
factory” (w.e.f. 15-10-1982).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>96</number> Subs. by Act 38 of 1982, sec. 12, for “displayed in
such factory” (w.e.f. 15-10-1982).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>97</number> Subs. by Act 38 of 1982, sec. 12, for “in the
factory” (w.e.f. 15-10-1982).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>98</number> Ins. by Act 38 of 1982, sec. 13 (w.e.f. 1-3-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>99</number> Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “Governor-General in
Council”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>100</number> Subs. by Act 41 of 2005, sec. 3, for “The State
Government” (w.e.f. 9-11-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>101</number> The words “subject to the control of the
Governor-General in Council” omitted by the A.O. 1937.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>102</number> Subs. by Act 53 of 1964, sec. 22, for “and prescribe
the form thereof” (w.e.f. 1-2-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>103</number> Ins. by Act 53 of 1964, sec. 22 (w.e.f. 1-2-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>104</number> The word “and” omitted by Act 53 of 1964, sec. 22 (w.e.f.
1-2-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>105</number> The word “and” ins. by Act 53 of 1964. sec. 22 (w.e.f.
1-2-1965) and omitted by Act 38 of 1982, sec. 14 (w.e.f. 15-10-1982).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>106</number> Ins. by Act 38 of 1982, sec. 14 (w.e.f. 15-10-1982).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>107</number> Ins. by Act 53 of 1964, sec. 22 (w.e.f. 1-2-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>108</number> Subs. by Act 41 of 2005, sec. 11(a), for “which may
extend to two hundred rupees” (w.e.f. 9-11-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>109</number> Subs. by Act 38 of 1982, sec. 14, for “two successive
sessions” (w.e.f. 15-10-1982).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>110</number> Subs. by Act 38 of 1982, sec. 14, for “in which it is
so laid or session immediately following” (w.e.f. 15-10-1982).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>111</number> Ins. by Act 41 of 2005,
sec. 11(b) (w.e.f. 9-11-2005).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>