<act><tid>483117</tid>
<title>THE CUSTOMS AND EXCISE REVENUES APPELLATE TRIBUNAL ACT, <year>1986</year></title>

ACT NO. 62 OF <year>1986</year>
[ 23rd December, <year>1986</year>.]

An Act to provide for the adjudication, by an appellate tribunal, of 
disputes with respect to the determination of the rates of duties of 
customs and Central excise on goods and to the valuation of goods for 
the purposes of assessment of such duties, in pursuance of article 
 323B of the Constitution and for matters connected therewith or 
incidental thereto.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty- seventh Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1159604</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1197286</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Customs and Excise Revenues Appellate Tribunal Act, <year>1986</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1214915</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.

</section>

<section><tid>890162</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1307041</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1163301</tid>
<number>a</number>" Appellate Tribunal" means the Customs and Excise 
Revenues Appellate Tribunal constituted under section 3;

</section>

<section><tid>65854</tid>
<number>b</number>" appointed day" means the date with effect from which 
the Appellate Tribunal is established, by notification, under 
section 3;

</section>

<section><tid>1205953</tid>
<number>c</number>" Bench" means a Bench of the Appellate Tribunal;

</section>

<section><tid>765057</tid>
<number>d</number>" Board" means the Central Board of Excise and Customs 
constituted under the Central Boards of Revenue Act, <year>1963</year> (54 of  
  <year>1963</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>184505</tid>
<number>e</number>" Central Excises Act" means the Central Excises and Salt 
Act, <year>1944</year> (1 of <year>1944</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>387418</tid>
<number>f</number>" Central Excise Tariff Act" means the Central Excise 
Tariff Act, <year>1985</year> (5 of <year>1986</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>74578</tid>
<number>g</number>" Customs Act" means the Customs Act, <year>1962</year> (52 of <year>1962</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1013410</tid>
<number>h</number>" Customs, Excise and Gold (Control) Appellate Tribunal" 
means the Customs, Excise and Gold (Control) Appellate Tribunal 
constituted under section 129 of the Customs Act;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1258</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1260779</tid>
<number>i</number>" Customs Tariff Act" means the Customs Tariff Act, <year>1975</year> 
 (51 of <year>1975</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1676949</tid>
<number>j</number>" Judicial Member" means a Member of the Appellate 
Tribunal appointed as such under this Act, and includes the 
President who possesses any of the qualifications specified in 
sub- section (2) of section 5;

</section>

<section><tid>909421</tid>
<number>k</number>" Member" means a Member (whether Judicial or Technical) 
of the Appellate Tribunal and includes the President;

</section>

<section><tid>282207</tid>
<number>l</number>" notification" means a notification published in the 
Official Gazette;

</section>

<section><tid>137414</tid>
<number>m</number>" President" means the President of the Appellate 
Tribunal;

</section>

<section><tid>1449368</tid>
<number>n</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules;

</section>

<section><tid>749524</tid>
<number>o</number>" rules" means rules made under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>408757</tid>
<number>p</number>" Supreme Court" means the Supreme Court of India;

</section>

<section><tid>258109</tid>
<number>q</number>" Technical Member" means a Member of the Appellate 
Tribunal who is not a Judicial Member within the meaning of 
clause (j);

</section>

<section><tid>367642</tid>
<number>r</number>words and expressions used in this Act but not defined 
herein and defined in the Central Excises Act, Central Excise 
Tariff Act, Customs Act or Customs Tariff Act, or the rules made 
thereunder, shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them 
by such Act or the rules made thereunder.
CHAP

ESTABLISHMENT OF THE APPELLATE TRIBUNAL AND BENCHES THEREOF

CHAPTER II

ESTABLISHMENT OF THE APPELLATE TRIBUNAL AND BENCHES THEREOF




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>408772</tid>
<number>3</number>Establishment of the Appellate Tribunal. The Central 
Government shall by notification, establish an Appellate Tribunal, to 
be known as the Customs and Excise Revenues Appellate Tribunal, to 
exercise the jurisdiction, powers and authority conferred on such 
Appellate Tribunal by or under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1065411</tid>
<number> 4</number> Composition of the Appellate Tribunal and Benches thereof.
<section><tid>1290464</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The Appellate Tribunal shall consist of a President and such number of 
Judicial and Technical Members as the Central Government may deem fit, 
and subject to the other provisions of this Act, the jurisdiction, 
powers and authority of the Appellate Tribunal may be exercised by 
Benches thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>394590</tid>
<number>2</number>A Bench shall consist of one Judicial Member and one 
Technical Member.

</section>

<section><tid>1355362</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), the 
President--

<subsection><tid>1461177</tid>
<number>a</number>may, in addition to discharging the functions of the 
Judicial Member or the Technical Member of the Bench to which he 
is appointed, discharge the functions of the Judicial Member or, 
as the case may be, the Technical Member, of any other Bench;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1413583</tid>
<number>b</number>may transfer a Member from one Bench to another Bench; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>137806</tid>
<number>c</number>may authorise the Judicial Member or the Technical 
Member appointed to one Bench to discharge also the functions of 
the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1259</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Judicial Member or the Technical Member, as the case may be, of 
another Bench.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>59759</tid>
<number>4</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing 
provisions of this section, it shall be competent for the President or 
any other Member authorised by the President in this behalf to 
function as a Bench consisting of a single Member and exercise the 
jurisdiction, powers and authority of the Appellate Tribunal in 
respect of such classes of cases or such matters pertaining to such 
classes of cases as the President may by general or special order 
specify:
Provided that if at any stage of the hearing of any such case or 
matter it appears to the President or Member that the case or matter 
is of such a nature that it ought to be heard by a Bench consisting of 
two Members, the case or matter may be transferred by the President 
or, as the case may be, referred to him for transfer, to such Bench as 
the President may deem fit.


</section>

<section><tid>923578</tid>
<number>5</number>Subject to the other provisions of this Act, the Benches of 
the Appellate Tribunal shall ordinarily sit at New Delhi and at such 
other places as the President may deem fit.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1902892</tid>
<number> 5</number> Qualifications for appointment as President or Member.
<section><tid>977107</tid>
<number>1</number>A  
person shall not be qualified for appointment as the President unless 
he--

<subsection><tid>1144913</tid>
<number>a</number>is, or has been, a Judge of a High Court; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>275670</tid>
<number>b</number>has, for at least two years, held the office of a 
Judicial Member or a Technical Member.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>889643</tid>
<number>2</number>A person shall not be qualified for appointment as a Judicial 
Member unless he--

<subsection><tid>1064172</tid>
<number>a</number>is, or has been, or is qualified to be, a Judge of a 
High Court; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>415242</tid>
<number>b</number>has been a member of the Indian Legal Service and has 
held a post in Grade I of that Service or any equivalent or 
higher post for at least five years.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>547980</tid>
<number>3</number>A person shall not be qualified for appointment as a 
Technical Member unless he has been a member of the Indian Customs and 
Central Excise Service, Group' A', for a period of at least thirty 
years, and has held during this period the post of Collector of 
Customs or Central Excise or any equivalent or higher post for at 
least ten years.
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Explanation.-- For the purposes of sub- section (3), in 
computing the period during which a person has been a member of the 
Indian Customs and Central Excise Service, Group' A' there shall be 
included any period during which the person has been a member of the 
Indian Customs Service Class I, or the Central Excise Service Class I, 
as the case may be, of the Indian Revenue Service immediately before 
the constitution of the Indian Customs and Central Excise Service, 
Group' A'.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>813215</tid>
<number> 6</number> Appointment of President and Members.
<section><tid>1264060</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the  
provisions of sub- section (2), the President and every Member shall be 
appointed by the President of India.

</section>

<section><tid>209050</tid>
<number>2</number>Appointment of a person as the President or a Member shall be 
made in consultation with a Selection Committee consisting of--

<subsection><tid>238505</tid>
<number>a</number>a Chairman who shall be nominated by the Chief Justice 
of India; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1850092</tid>
<number>b</number>such other members as may be nominated by the Central 
Government.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>1260</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 11 of <year>1987</year>, s. 107.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1156614</tid>
<number> 7</number> Member to act as President or to discharge his functions in 
certain circumstances.
<section><tid>229138</tid>
<number>1</number>In the event of the occurrence of any  
vacancy in the office of the President by reason of his death, 
resignation or otherwise, such one of the Members as the Central 
Government may, by notification, authorise in this behalf, shall act 
as the President until the date on which a new President, appointed in 
accordance with the provisions of this Act to fill such vacancy enters 
upon his office.

</section>

<section><tid>1803908</tid>
<number>2</number>When the President is unable to discharge his functions owing 
to absence, illness or any other cause, such one of the Members as the 
Central Government may, by notification, authorise in this behalf, 
shall discharge the functions of the President until the date on which 
the President resumes his duties.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1440605</tid>
<number>8</number>Term of office. The President or other Member shall hold 
office as such for a term of three years from the date on which he 
enters upon his office or until he attains the age of sixty- five 
years, whichever is earlier.


</article>



<article><tid>1619058</tid>
<number> 9</number> Resignation and removal.
<section><tid>1958708</tid>
<number>1</number>The President or other Member  
may, by notice in writing under his hand addressed to the President of 
India, resign his office:
Provided that the President or other Member shall, unless he is 
permitted by the President of India to relinquish his office sooner, 
continue to hold office until the expiry of three months from the date 
of receipt of such notice or until a person duly appointed as his 
successor enters upon his office or until the expiry of his term of 
office, whichever is the earliest.


</section>

<section><tid>277892</tid>
<number>2</number>The President or any other Member shall not be removed from 
his office except by an order made by the President of India on the 
ground of proved misbehaviour or incapacity after an inquiry made by a 
Judge of the Supreme Court in which such President or other Member had 
been informed of the charges against him and given a reasonable 
opportunity of being heard in respect of those charges.

</section>

<section><tid>632158</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government may, by rules, regulate the procedure 
for the investigation of misbehaviour or incapacity of the President 
or other Member referred to in sub- section (2).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>691860</tid>
<number>10</number>Salaries and allowances and other terms and conditions of 
service of President and other Members. The salaries and allowances 
payable to, and the other terms and conditions of service (including  
  pension, gratuity and other retirement benefits) of, the President and 
other Members shall be such as may be prescribed by the Central 
Government:
Provided that neither the salary and allowances nor the other 
terms and conditions of service of the President or other Member shall 
be varied to his disadvantage after his appointment.



</article>



<article><tid>1564205</tid>
<number> 11</number> Provision as to the holding of offices by President and 
Members on ceasing to be such President or Member. On ceasing to hold 
office,--
<section><tid>1837856</tid>
<number>a</number>the President shall be ineligible for further employment 
either under the Government of India or under the Government of a 
State;

</section>

<section><tid>290679</tid>
<number>b</number>a Member (other than the President) shall, subject to 
the other provisions of this Act, be eligible for appointment as 
the President, but not for any employment either under the 
Government of India or under the Government of a State;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1261</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>380176</tid>
<number>c</number>the President or other Member shall not appear, act or 
plead before the Appellate Tribunal or the Customs, Excise and 
Gold (Control) Appellate Tribunal.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section, employment under 
the Government of India or under the Government of a State includes 
employment under any local or other authority within the territory of 
India or under the control of the Government of India or under any 
corporation or society owned or controlled by the Government.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1300180</tid>
<number>12</number>Financial and adminitrative powers of President. The 
President shall exercise such financial and administrative powers over 
the Benches as may be vested in him under the rules:
Provided that the President shall have authority to delegate such 
of his financial and administrative powers as he may think fit to any 
Member or officer of the Appellate Tribunal, subject to the condition 
that the Member or such officer shall, while exercising such delegated 
powers, continue to act under the direction, control and supervision 
of the President.



</article>



<article><tid>1342508</tid>
<number> 13</number> Staff of the Appellate Tribunal.
<section><tid>645873</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government  
shall determine the nature and categories of the officers and other 
employees required to assist the Appellate Tribunal in the discharge 
of its functions and provide the Appellate Tribunal with such officers 
and other employees as it may think fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1491629</tid>
<number>2</number>The officers and other employees of the Appellate Tribunal 
shall discharge their functions under the general superintendence of 
the President.

</section>

<section><tid>584902</tid>
<number>3</number>The salaries and allowances and conditions of service of the 
officers and other employees of the Appellate Tribunal shall be such 
as may be specified by rules.
CHAP

JURISDICTION, POWERS AND AUTHORITY OF THE APPELLATE TRIBUNAL

CHAPTER III

JURISDICTION, POWERS AND AUTHORITY OF THE APPELLATE TRIBUNAL




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1251996</tid>
<number> 14</number> Jurisdiction, powers and authority of the Appellate Tribunal.

<section><tid>1521109</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as otherwise expressly provided in this Act, the Appellate  
Tribunal shall exercise, on and from the appointed day, all the 
jurisdiction, powers and authority exercisable in relation to an 
appeal against--

<subsection><tid>374184</tid>
<number>a</number>a decision or order passed by the Collector of Central 
Excise as an adjudicating authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>95535</tid>
<number>b</number>an order passed by the Collector (Appeals) under section 
 35A or section 35E of the Central Excises Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1738246</tid>
<number>bb</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> a decision or order passed by the Board or the 
Collector of Central Excise under section 35EA of the Central 
Excises Act;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>487134</tid>
<number>c</number>a decision or order passed by the Collector of Customs 
as an adjudicating authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>302410</tid>
<number>d</number>an order passed by the Collector (Appeals) under section 
 128A or section 129D of the Customs Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>228650</tid>
<number>e</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> a decision or order passed by the Board or the 
Collector of Customs under section 129DA of the Customs Act,]
in which the determination of any question having a relation to--


<subsubsection><tid>1191599</tid>
<number>i</number>the rate of duty of excise for the time being in force, 
whether under the Central Excise Tariff Act or under any other 
Central Act providing for the levy and collection of any duty of 
excise, in relation to any goods on or after the 28th day of 
February, <year>1986</year>; or
<pagefootnote><pagenum>1262</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 29 of <year>1988</year>, S. 16 (w. e. f........).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>427540</tid>
<number>ii</number>the rate of duty of customs for the time being in 
force, whether under the Customs Tariff Act or under any other 
Central Act providing for the levy and collection of any duty of 
customs, in relation to any goods on or after the 28th day of 
February, <year>1986</year>; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>316025</tid>
<number>iii</number>the value of goods for the purposes of assessment of 
any duty of excise in cases where the assessment is made on or 
after the 28th day of February, <year>1986</year>; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1202419</tid>
<number>iv</number>the value of goods for the purposes of assessment of 
any duty of customs in cases where the assessment is made on or 
after the 28th day of February, <year>1986</year>, is in issue or is one of 
the points in issue.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this sub- section, the 
determination of a rate of duty in relation to any goods or valuation 
of any goods for the purposes of assessment of duty includes the 
determination of a question--


<subsubsubsection><tid>1914074</tid>
<number>a</number>whether any goods are excisable goods or whether the 
rate of duty on any goods is nil;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1790222</tid>
<number>b</number>whether any goods fall under a particular heading or 
sub- heading of the Schedule to the Central Excise Tariff Act or 
the Additional Duties of Excise (Goods of Special Importance) 
Act, <year>1957</year> (58 of <year>1957</year>) or the Additional Duties of Excise 
 (Textiles and Textile Articles) Act, <year>1978</year> (40 of <year>1978</year>) or fall 
under the First Schedule or the Second Schedule to the Customs 
Tariff Act, as the case may be, or that any goods are or not 
covered by a particular notification or order issued by the 
Central Government or the Board, granting total or partial 
exemption from a duty of excise or customs, as the case may be;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1066863</tid>
<number>c</number>whether the value of any goods for the purposes of 
assessment of a duty of excise or customs shall be enhanced or 
reduced by the addition or reduction of the amounts in respect of 
such matters as are specifically provided in the Central Excises 
Act or the Customs Act.

</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1895650</tid>
<number>2</number>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that nothing 
in sub- section (1) shall preclude the entertainment of an appeal in 
relation to any of the matters dealt with in sub- section (1) by the 
Customs, Excise and Gold (Control) Appellate Tribunal or the disposal 
thereof during the period commencing on and from the 28th day of 
February, <year>1986</year> and ending with the appointed day and any order passed 
by the said Tribunal on such appeal during that period shall, for all 
purposes, have effect as an order of the Appellate Tribunal 
constituted under this Act and all the provisions of this Act shall 
apply to such order.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1442684</tid>
<number> 15</number> Bar of jurisdiction of the Appellate Tribunal in certain 
cases. Notwithstanding anything contained in section 14, no appeal 
shall lie to the Appellate Tribunal and the Appellate Tribunal shall 
not have jurisdiction to decide any appeal in respect of any decision 
or order referred to in section 14 if such decision or order relates 
only to--
<section><tid>981449</tid>
<number>a</number>a case of loss of goods, where the loss occurs in 
transit from a factory to a warehouse or to another factory, or 
from one warehouse

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1263</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

to another, or during the course of processing of the goods in a 
warehouse or in storage, whether in a factory or in a warehouse;


</section>

<section><tid>1439187</tid>
<number>b</number>a rebate of duty of excise on goods exported to any 
country or territory outside India or on excisable materials used 
in the manufacture of goods which are exported to any country or 
territory outside India;

</section>

<section><tid>277637</tid>
<number>c</number>goods exported outside India (except to Nepal or Bhutan) 
without payment of duty;

</section>

<section><tid>1095135</tid>
<number>d</number>any goods imported or exported as baggage or by post;

</section>

<section><tid>1787709</tid>
<number>e</number>any goods loaded, or deemed to have been loaded in 
accordance with an import manifest or import report, in a 
conveyance for importation into India, but which are not unloaded 
at their place of destination in India, or so much of the 
quantity of such goods as has not been unloaded at any such 
destination if goods unloaded at such destination are short of 
the quantity required to be unloaded at that destination or any 
goods which have been lost or destroyed after being unloaded at 
any such destination;

</section>

<section><tid>1813253</tid>
<number>f</number>payment of drawback as provided in Chapter X of the 
Customs Act and the rules made thereunder.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>763547</tid>
<number> 16</number> Power to punish for contempt. The Appellate Tribunal shall 
have, and exercise, the same jurisdiction, powers and authority in 
respect of contempt of itself as a High Court has and may exercise, 
and, for this purpose, the provisions of the Contempt of Courts Act, 
 <year>1971</year> (70 of <year>1971</year>), shall have effect subject to the modifications 
that--
<section><tid>619748</tid>
<number>a</number>the references therein to a High Court shall be 
construed as including a reference to the Appellate Tribunal;

</section>

<section><tid>405157</tid>
<number>b</number>the references to the Advocate- General in section 15 of 
the said Act shall be construed, in relation to the Appellate 
Tribunal, as a reference to the Attorney- General or the 
Solicitor- General or the Additional Solicitor- General.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>421537</tid>
<number> 17</number> Distribution of business amongst the Appellate Tribunal and 
its Benches.
<section><tid>158221</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any Benches of the Appellate Tribunal are  
constituted, the President may, from time to time, by order, make 
provisions as to the distribution of the business of the Appellate 
Tribunal amongst the Benches and specify the matters which may be 
dealt with by each Bench.

</section>

<section><tid>1183960</tid>
<number>2</number>If any question arises as to whether any matter falls within 
the purview of the business allocated to a Bench of the Appellate 
Tribunal, the decision of the President thereon shall be final.
CHAP

PROCEDURE

CHAPTER IV

PROCEDURE




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>247593</tid>
<number> 18</number> Appeals to Appellate Tribunal.
<section><tid>1761424</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the other  
provisions of this Act, every appeal to the Appellate Tribunal under 
this Act shall be filed within three months from the date on which the 
decision or order sought to be appealed against is communicated to the 
person aggrieved by the decision or order or to the Collector of 
Central Excise or the Collector of Customs as the case may be.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1264</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>787509</tid>
<number>2</number>On receipt of notice that an appeal has been preferred under 
this section, the party against whom the appeal has been preferred 
may, notwithstanding that he may not have appealed against such 
decision or order or any part thereof, file within forty- five days of 
the receipt of the notice a memorandum of cross- objections verified in 
such manner as may be specified by rules made in this behalf against 
any part of the order appealed against and such memorandum shall be 
disposed of by the Appellate Tribunal as if it were an appeal 
presented within the time specified in sub- section (1).

</section>

<section><tid>1942966</tid>
<number>3</number>The Appellate Tribunal may admit an appeal or permit the 
filing of a memorandum of cross- objections after the expiry of the 
relevant period referred to in sub- section (1) or sub- section (2), if 
it is satisfied that there was sufficient cause for not presenting it 
within that period.

</section>

<section><tid>963901</tid>
<number>4</number>Every appeal to the Appellate Tribunal shall be in such form 
and shall be verified in such manner as may be specified by rules made 
in this behalf and shall, except in the case of an appeal preferred by 
the proper officer or a memorandum of cross- objections referred to in 
sub- section (2), be accompanied by a fee of two hundred rupees.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1463512</tid>
<number> 19</number> Procedure and powers of the Appellate Tribunal.
<section><tid>493441</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Appellate Tribunal shall not be bound by the procedure laid down in 
the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>), but shall be guided by 
the principles of natural justice and subject to the other provisions 
of this Act and of any rules made by the Central Government, the 
Appellate Tribunal shall have power to regulate its own procedure, 
including the fixing of places and times of its hearing.

</section>

<section><tid>1531378</tid>
<number>2</number>The Appellate Tribunal shall have, for the purposes of 
discharging its functions under this Act, the same powers as are 
vested in a civil court under the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of  
  <year>1908</year>), while trying a suit, in respect of the following matters, 
namely:--

<subsection><tid>612808</tid>
<number>a</number>summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person and 
examining him on oath;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1126896</tid>
<number>b</number>requiring the discovery, inspection and production of 
books of account and other documents;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1855468</tid>
<number>c</number>reviewing its decisions;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1368765</tid>
<number>d</number>dismissing an appeal for default or deciding it ex 
parte; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1900420</tid>
<number>e</number>any other matter which may be prescribed.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>815808</tid>
<number>20</number>Deposit, pending appeal, of duty demanded or penalty levied. 
Where in any appeal under this Act, the decision or order appealed 
against relates to any duty demanded in respect of goods which are not 
under the control of the central excise authorities or the customs 
authorities, as the case may be, or any penalty levied under the 
Central Excises Act or the Customs Act, the person desirous of 
appealing against such decision or order shall, pending the appeal, 
deposit with the proper officer the duty demanded or the penalty 
levied:
Provided that where in any particular case, the Appellate 
Tribunal is of opinion that the deposit of duty demanded or penalty 
levied would cause undue hardship to such person, the Appellate 
Tribunal may dispense with such deposit subject to such conditions as 
it may deem fit to impose so as to safeguard the interests of revenue.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>1265</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>111267</tid>
<number> 21</number> Right of applicant to take assistance of legal practitioner 
and Government to appoint representing officers.
<section><tid>653060</tid>
<number>1</number>A person  
preferring an appeal to the Appellate Tribunal under this Act may 
either appear in person or take the assistance of a legal practitioner 
of his choice to present his case before the Appellate Tribunal.

</section>

<section><tid>1373960</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may authorise one or more legal 
practitioners or any of its officers to act as presenting officer and 
any person so authorised by it may present its case with respect to 
any appeal before the Appellate Tribunal.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1539253</tid>
<number> 22</number> Conditions as to making of interim orders. Notwithstanding 
anything contained in any other provisions of this Act or in any other 
law for the time being in force, no interim order (whether by way of  
  injunction or stay or in any other manner) shall be made on, or in any 
proceedings relating to, an appeal under this Act unless--
<section><tid>365732</tid>
<number>a</number>copies of such appeal and of all documents in support of 
the plea for such interim order are furnished to the party 
against whom such appeal is preferred; and

</section>

<section><tid>562174</tid>
<number>b</number>opportunity is given to such party to be heard in the 
matter:
Provided that the Appellate Tribunal may dispense with the 
requirements of clauses (a) and (b) and make an interim order as an 
exceptional measure if it is satisfied, for reasons to be recorded in 
writing, that it is necessary so to do for preventing any loss being 
caused to the appellant which cannot be adequately compensated in 
money but any such interim order shall, if it is not sooner vacated, 
cease to have effect on the expiry of a period of fourteen days from 
the date on which it is made unless the said requirements have been 
complied with before the expiry of that period and the Appellate 
Tribunal has continued the operation of the interim order.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1088188</tid>
<number>23</number>Power of President to transfer cases from one Bench to 
another. On the application of any of the parties and after notice to 
the parties, and after hearing such of them as he may desire to be 
heard, or on his own motion without such notice, the President may 
transfer any case pending before one Bench, for disposal, to any other 
Bench.


</article>



<article><tid>146751</tid>
<number>24</number>Procedure for deciding the case where the Members of a Bench 
differ in opinion. If the Members of a Bench differ in opinion on any 
point, they shall state the point or points on which they differ, and 
make a reference to the President who shall either hear the point or 
points himself or refer the case for hearing on such point or points 
by one or more of the other Members and such point or points shall be 
decided according to the opinion of the majority of the Members who 
have heard the case, including those who first heard it.


</article>



<article><tid>456746</tid>
<number> 25</number> Orders of the Appellate Tribunal.
<section><tid>1901682</tid>
<number>1</number>The Appellate Tribunal  
may, after giving the parties to the appeal an opportunity of being 
heard, pass such orders thereon as it thinks fit, confirming, 
modifying or annulling the decision or order appealed against or may 
refer the case back to the authority which passed such decision or 
order with such directions as the Appellate Tribunal may think fit, 
for a fresh adjudication or decision, as the case may be, after taking 
additional evidence, if necessary.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1266</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1903034</tid>
<number>2</number>The Appellate Tribunal may, at any time within four years 
from the date of the order, with a view to rectifying any mistake 
apparent from the record, amend any order passed by it under sub- 
section (1) and shall make such amendments if the mistake is brought 
to its notice by the Collector of Central Excise or the Collector of 
Customs, as the case may be, or the other party to the appeal:
Provided that an amendment which has the effect of enhancing the 
assessment or reducing a refund or otherwise increasing the liability 
of the other party shall not be made under this sub- section, unless 
the Appellate Tribunal has given notice to him of its intention to do 
so and has allowed him a reasonable opportunity of being heard.


</section>

<section><tid>804393</tid>
<number>3</number>The Appellate Tribunal shall send a copy of every order 
passed under this section to the Collector of Central Excise or the 
Collector of Customs, as the case may be, and the other party to the 
appeal.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER V

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1064591</tid>
<number>26</number>Exclusion of jurisdiction of courts, etc., except the Supreme 
Court. On and from the appointed day, no court (except the Supreme  
  Court) or the Customs, Excise and Gold (Control) Appellate Tribunal 
shall have, or be entitled to exercise, any jurisdiction, powers or 
authority in relation to matters in respect of which appeals would lie 
to the Appellate Tribunal under section 14.


</article>



<article><tid>1304930</tid>
<number> 27</number> Transfer of pending cases.
<section><tid>245938</tid>
<number>1</number>Every suit, appeal or other  
proceeding pending before any court or other authority or the Customs, 
Excise and Gold (Control) Appellate Tribunal, immediately before the 
appointed day, being a suit, appeal or other proceeding which would 
have been within the jurisdiction of the Appellate Tribunal, if it had 
arisen after such day, shall stand transferred on that day to the 
Appellate Tribunal:
Provided that nothing in this sub- section shall apply to any 
appeal pending as aforesaid before a High Court.


</section>

<section><tid>1415342</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any suit, appeal or other proceeding stands transferred 
from any court, tribunal or other authority to the Appellate Tribunal 
under sub- section (1),--

<subsection><tid>830913</tid>
<number>a</number>the court or other authority or the Customs, Excise and 
Gold (Control) Appellate Tribunal shall, as soon as may be after 
such transfer, forward the records of such suit, appeal or other 
proceeding to the Appellate Tribunal; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>731884</tid>
<number>b</number>the Appellate Tribunal may, on receipt of such records, 
proceed to deal with such suit, appeal or other proceeding, so 
far as may be, in the same manner as in the case of an appeal 
under section 18 from the stage which was reached before such 
transfer or from any earlier stage or de novo as the Appellate 
Tribunal may deem fit.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1267</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1202790</tid>
<number>3</number>Any person, who immediately before the appointed day, is an 
advocate or authorised representative entitled to practice in any 
court or other authority or the Customs, Excise and Gold (Control) 
Appellate Tribunal and was authorised to appear or to act in any 
prceedings transferred from the said court, other authority or 
Tribunal to the Appellate Tribunal under this section shall have the 
right to appear or to act, as the case may be, before the Appellate 
Tribunal in relation to the said suit, appeal or other proceeding.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>455218</tid>
<number>28</number>Proceedings before the Appellate Tribunal to be judicial 
proceedings. All proceedings before the Appellate Tribunal shall be 
deemed to be judicial proceedings within the meaning of sections 193, 
 219 and 228 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>160517</tid>
<number>29</number>Members and staff of the Appellate Tribunal to be public 
servants. The president and other Members and the officers and other 
employees of the Appellate Tribunal shall be deemed to be public 
servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code 
 (45 of <year>1860</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>1059432</tid>
<number>30</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit prosecution 
or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central Government or 
against the President or other Member, or any other person authorised 
by such President or other Member for anything which is in good faith 
done or intended to be done in persuance of this Act or any rule or 
order made thereunder.


</article>



<article><tid>776854</tid>
<number>31</number>Act to have overriding effect. The provisions of this Act 
shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith 
contained in any other law for the time being in force or any 
instrument having effect by virtue of any law other than this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1892966</tid>
<number> 32</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>286220</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification, make rules to carry out the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1852014</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, 
namely:--

<subsection><tid>1288875</tid>
<number>a</number>the salaries and allowances and other terms and 
conditions of service of the President and other Members under 
section 10;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1059053</tid>
<number>b</number>the financial and administrative powers which the 
President may exercise over the Benches under section 12;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>478389</tid>
<number>c</number>the salaries and allowances and conditions of service of 
the officers and other employees of the Appellate Tribunal under 
sub- section (3) of section 13;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1748098</tid>
<number>d</number>the form in which every appeal to the Appellate Tribunal 
shall be filed and the manner in which such appeal shall be 
verified under sub- section (4) of section 18;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1268</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1881627</tid>
<number>e</number>the rules subject to which the Appellate Tribunal shall 
have power to regulate its own procedure under sub- section (1) of 
section 19 and the additional matters in respect of which the 
Appellate Tribunal may exercise the powers of a civil court under 
clause (e) of sub- section (2) of that section; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>241019</tid>
<number>f</number>any other matter which has to be, or may be, prescribed 
by rules under this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>93546</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made under this Act by the Central Government 
shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House 
of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty 
days which may be comprised in one session, or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>664300</tid>
<number> 33</number> Power to remove difficulties.
<section><tid>300191</tid>
<number>1</number>If any difficulty arises in  
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions, 
not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act as appear to it to be 
necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty:
Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a 
period of three years from the appointed day.


</section>

<section><tid>287842</tid>
<number>2</number>Every order made under this section shall, as soon as may be 
after it is made, be laid before each House of Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1617448</tid>
<number> 34</number> Consequential amendments in the Central Excises Act and the 
Customs Act. On and from the appointed day, the following amendments 
 (being amendments of a consequential nature) shall be made in the 
Central Excises Act and the Customs Act, namely:--
<section><tid>481119</tid>
<number>a</number>in the Central Excises Act,--

<subsection><tid>1980020</tid>
<number>i</number>for sub- section (2) of section 35B, the following 
sub- section shall be substituted, namely:--
" (2) The Collector of Central Excise may, if he is 
of opinion that an order passed by--


<subsubsection><tid>476986</tid>
<number>a</number>the Appellate Collector of Central Excise 
under section 35, as it stood immediately before 
the appointed day, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>208645</tid>
<number>b</number>the Collector (Appeals) under section 
35A, is not legal or proper, direct any Central 
Excise Officer authorised by him in this behalf 
 (hereafter in this Chapter referred to as the  
  authorised officer) to appeal on his behalf to the 
Appellate Tribunal or, as the case may be, the 
Customs and Excise Revenues Appellate Tribunal 
established under section 3 of the Customs and 
Excise Revenues Appellate Tribunal Act, <year>1986</year>, 
against such order";

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1269</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1914749</tid>
<number>ii</number>in section 35E,--

<subsubsection><tid>208931</tid>
<number>A</number>after the words" Appellate Tribunal", wherever 
they occur, the words and figures" or, as the case may 
be, the Customs and Excise Revenues Appellate Tribunal 
established under section 3 of the Customs and Excise 
Revenues Appellate Tribunal Act, <year>1986</year> shall be 
inserted;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>645183</tid>
<number>B</number>in sub- section (4), after the word, figures 
and letter" section 35B", the words and figures" or, as 
the case may be, the provisions of the Customs and 
Excise Revenues Appellate Tribunal Act, <year>1986</year> shall be 
inserted;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>176227</tid>
<number>b</number>in the Customs Act,--

<subsection><tid>1974453</tid>
<number>i</number>for sub- section (2) of section 129A, the following 
sub- section shall be substituted, namely:--
" (2) The Collector of Customs may, if he is of 
opinion that an order passed by--


<subsubsection><tid>825802</tid>
<number>a</number>the Appellate Collector of Customs under 
section 128, as it stood immediately before the 
appointed day, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>72053</tid>
<number>b</number>the Collector (Appeals) under section 
128A, is not legal or proper, direct the proper 
officer to appeal on his behalf to the Appellate 
Tribunal or, as the case may be, the Customs and 
Excise Revenues Appellate Tribunal established 
under section 3 of the Customs and Excise Revenues 
Appellate Tribunal Act, <year>1986</year>, against such 
order.";

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1865827</tid>
<number>ii</number>in section 129D,--

<subsubsection><tid>1429175</tid>
<number>A</number>after the words" Appellate Tribunal", wherever 
they occur, the words and figures" or, as the case may 
be, the Customs and Excise Revenues Appellate Tribunal 
established under section 3 of the Customs and Excise 
Revenues Appellate Tribunal Act, <year>1986</year> shall be 
inserted;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>418020</tid>
<number>B</number>in sub- section (4), after the word, figures 
and letter" section 129A", the words and figures" or, 
as the case may be, the provisions of the Customs and 
Excise Revenues Appellate Tribunal Act, <year>1986</year> shall be 
inserted.


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



 </act>