<act><title>
THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951</title> 
 
 THE STATE FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS
ACT, 1951
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title, extent and
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> This Act may be
called the State Financial Corporations Act, 1951. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> It extends to the whole of   India <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[***]. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> It shall come into force in
any State on such dateas the Central Government may, by
notification in the Official Gazette, appoint. 




</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS
ACT, 1951
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In this Act, unless the context otherwise re­quires,— 
        
<section><number>a</number> “Board” means the Board of directors of the
Financial Corpo­ration; 
 </section><section><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>aa</number> “Development
Bank” means the Industrial Development Bank of India established under the
Industrial Development Bank of India Act, 1964 (18 of 1964);] 
 </section><section>[<number>b</number> “Financial
Corporation” means a Financial Corporation established under section 3 and
includes a Joint Financial Corpo­ration established under section 3A;] 
 </section><section>[<number>c</number> “industrial
concern” means any concern engaged or to be engaged in— 
              (i) the manufacture, preservation or processing of
goods; 
 <subsection>[<number>ii</number> mining or development of mines;] 
             (iii) the hotel industry: 
            (iv) the transport of passengers or goods by road or
by water or by air [or by
ropeway or by lift]; 
             (v) the generation or distribution of electricity
or any other form of power; 
            (vi) the maintenance, repair, testing or servicing
of ma­chinery of any description or vehicles or vessels or motor boats or
trailers or tractors; 
            (vii) assembling, repairing or packing any article
with the aid of machinery or power; 
 </subsection><subsection>[<number>viii</number>  the setting up or development of an industrial area or industrial
estate;] 
             (ix) fishing or providing shore facilities for
fishing or maintenance thereof; [***] 
           [(x)  providing
weight bridge facilities; 
 </subsection></section><section>[<number>xi</number>  providing engineering, technical, financial, management, marketing
or other services or facilities for industry; 
            (xii)  providing medical, health or other allied,
services; 
           (xiii)  providing software or hardware services
relating to information technology, telecommunications or electronics including
satellite linkage and audio or visual cable communication;]] 
 </section><section>[<number>xiv</number>  setting up or development of tourism related facilities including
amusement parks, convention centres, restaurants, travel and transport (including
those at airports), tourist service agencies and guidance and counselling
services to the tourists; 
            (xv)  construction; 
           (xvi)  development, maintenance and construction of
roads; 
          (xvii)  providing commercial complex facilities and
community centres including conference halls; 
          (xviii)  floriculture; 
           (xix)  tissue culture, fish culture, poultry farming,
breeding and hatcheries; 
            (xx)  service industry, such as altering,
ornamenting, polishing, finishing, oiling, washing, cleaning or otherwise
treating or adapting any article or substance with a view to its use, sale,
transport, delivery or disposal; 
           (xxi)  research and development of any concept,
technology, design, process or product, whether in relation to any of the
matters aforesaid, including any activities approved by the Small Industries
Bank; or 
           (xxii)  such other activity as may be approved by the
Small Industries Bank;] 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[Explanation
1.—The expression “processing of goods” includes any art or process for
producing, preparing or making an article by subjecting any material to a
manual, mechanical, chemical, electrical or any other like operation.] 
 [Explanation
2.—If any doubt arises as to whether a concern is an industrial concern or
not, the same shall be referred to the [Small
Industries Bank] for its decision and the decision of the [Small Industries Bank] thereon shall be
final;] 
        (d) “prescribed” means prescribed by rules or
regulations made under this Act; 
 </section><section>[<number>da</number>  the
expression "public sector bank" means the State Bank of India constituted
under the State Bank of India Act, 1955 (23 of 1955), a subsidiary bank as
defined in the State Bank of India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, 1959 (38 of 1959), a
corresponding new bank constituted under section 3 of the Banking Companies
(Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings) Act, 1970 (5 of 1970) or under
section 3 of the Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings)
Act, 1980 (40 of 1980);] 
        (e) “Reserve Bank” means the Reserve Bank of India
constituted under the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934); 
         (f) “scheduled bank” means a bank for the time
being included in the Second Schedule to the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2
of 1934); 
 </section><section>[<number>fa</number>  "Small
Industries Bank" means the Small Industries Development Bank of India
established under sub-section (l) of section 3 of the Small Industries
Development Bank of India Act, 1989 (39 of 1989);] 
 </section><section>[<number>fb</number> “State
Co-operative Bank” shall have the meaning as­signed to it in clause (f) of
section 2 of the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934); 
     [(fc) “State
Government”, in relation to a   Union
 Territory,
means the Administrator thereof;] 
        (g) “underwriting” means contract, with or without
conditions, to subscribe for stocks, shares, bonds or debentures of an indus­trial
concern with a view to the resale of the whole or any part thereof. 

















</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS
ACT, 1951
  
 <article><number>3</number> Establishment of State Financial
Corporations.—
<section><number>1</number> The State
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, estab­lish a Financial
Corporation for the State under such name as may be specified in the
notification. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Financial Corporation
shall be a body corporate by the name notified under sub-section (1), having
perpetual succession and a common seal, with power, subject to the provisions
of this Act, to <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[acquire, hold and dispose of] property and shall by
the said name sue and be sued. 




</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS
ACT, 1951
  
 <article>[<number>3A</number> Establishment 
of Joint Financial Corporations.—
<section><number>1</number> Not­withstanding anything contained in section 3, 
two or more States may, after consultation with the <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[Small Industries Bank], enter into 
an agreement that there shall be one Financial Corporation for the group of 
States participating in the agreement and if the agreement is published in the 
Official Gazette of each of those States, the Central Government may, by 
notification in the Offi­cial Gazette, establish a Joint Financial Corporation 
to serve the needs of those States under such name as may be specified in the 
notification. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> An 
inter-State agreement under sub-section (1) among the participating States may— 
 <subsection> 
<number>a</number> provide for the fixation of the authorised capital of the Joint Financial 
Corporation, the number of fully paid-up shares into which it shall be divided 
and the allocation among the participating States of the shares to be 
distributed under clause (a) of sub-section (3) of  
section 4; 
 </subsection><subsection> 
<number>b</number> provide for the sharing of the liability for the guarantee under section 6 
or section 7 [or section 8]; 
 </subsection><subsection> 
<number>c</number> provide for the number of directors to be nominated to the Board by each 
participating State Government; 
 </subsection><subsection> 
<number>d</number> provide for the apportionment among the participating States of expenditure 
in connection with the Joint Financial Corpora­tion; 
 [***] 
 </subsection><subsection> 
<number>f</number> determine which of the participating State Governments shall exercise the 
several functions of the State Government under this Act, and references in 
this Act to the State Government, in relation to the Joint Financial 
Corporation, shall, save as otherwise expressly provided, be construed 
accordingly; 
 </subsection><subsection> 
<number>g</number> provide for consultation among the participating States either generally or 
with reference to particular matters arising under this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection> 
<number>h</number> make such incidental and consequential provisions, not inconsistent with 
this Act, as may be deemed necessary or expedi­ent for giving effect to the 
agreement. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> The 
Joint Financial Corporation shall be a body corporate by the name notified 
under sub-section (1), having perpetual succes­sion and a common seal, with 
power, subject to the provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of 
property and shall, by the said name sue and be sued. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Any 
reference in this Act to “State” in relation to a Joint Financial Corporation 
established for two or more States, shall be construed as a reference to each 
such State.] 







</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS
ACT, 1951
  
 <article><number>4</number> Share capital and
share-holders.—<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number>
The authorised capital of the Financial Corporation shall be such sum as may be
fixed by the State Government in this behalf, but it shall not, be less than
fifty lakhs of rupees, or exceed five hundred crores of rupees: 
 Provided that the State Government
may, on the recommendation of the Small Industries Bank, by notification in the
Official Gazette, increase the authorised capital up to one thousand crores of
rupees. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Subject to the provisions of
section 4D, the authorised capital shall be divided into such number of fully
paid-up shares of the same face value and such number of fully paid-up
redeemable preference shares of the same face value and shall be issued to the
parties mentioned in clauses (a), (b) and (c) of sub-section (3) and in the
case of parties referred to in clause (d) of that sub-section, such shares
shall be issued at such times and in such manner as the State Government may,
by notification in the Official Gazette, determine. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Subject to the approval of the
State Government and the Small Industries Bank, the Board shall determine the
number of shares which may, respectively, be distributed among— 
        (a)  the State Government; 
        (b)  the Small Industries Bank; 
        (c)  public sector banks, the Life Insurance
Corporation of India established under section 3 of the Life Insurance
Corporation Act, 1956 (31 of 1956), other insurance companies owned or
controlled by the Central Government, other institutions owned or controlled by
the Central Government or the State Government, as the case may be; and 
        (d)  parties other than those referred to in clause
(a), or clause (b) or 
clause (c): 
 Provided that the number of shares
which may be allocated to parties referred to in clause (d) shall in no case
exceed forty-nine per cent. of the total number of issued equity shares: 
 Provided further that no increase
in the issued equity capital shall be made in such a manner that the parties
referred to in clause (a) or clause (b) or clause (c) hold in aggregate, at any
time less than fifty-one per cent. of the issued equity capital of the
Financial Corporation.] 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Subject to the other
provisions contained in this section, the allocation of shares among the
parties referred to in clauses (c) and (d) of sub-section (3) and the allotment
of such shares shall be made by the Financial Corporation in such manner as may
be prescribed. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>5</number> If any shares allocated to any of the parties
referred to in clauses (c) and (d) of sub-section (3) remain unsubscribed, they
shall be subscribed for equally by the State Government and the [Small
Industries Bank].] 







</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[<number>4A</number> Special class of 
   shares.—<footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number> 
   The State Government may, in consultation with the <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[Small Industries Bank], specify 
   from time to time such part of the unissued capital of the Financial 
   Corpora­tion as shall be allocated for the issue of a special class of 
   shares.]
 </section><section><number>2</number> The special class of 
   shares so allocated under sub-section (1), shall be,—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> divided into such number of shares of the 
   same face value as the State Government may, in consultation with the <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[Small Industries Bank], 
   determine;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> subscribed by the State Government and the
   <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[Small Industries Bank] and 
   they may do so in such proportion as may be agreed upon by and between them 
   and the Financial Corporation shall make allotment of such shares 
   accordingly.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> The funds representing 
   the capital subscribed as aforesaid shall be used only for such purposes, in 
   such manner and for rendering assistance to such class or category of 
   industrial concerns, as the <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[Small 
   Industries Bank] may, in consultation with and after obtaining the advice of 
   the State Government, specify in this behalf from time to time and nothing 
   contained in <footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[***] section 
   48 shall apply thereto.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The rate of dividend 
   declared on the special class of shares in respect of any accounting year of 
   a Financial Corporation shall not exceed the rate of dividend in respect of 
   its other shares.
 </section><section><number>5</number> Nothing contained in 
   sub-sections 
 (2) to (5) 
   of section 4, section 5, and <footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[sub-sections 
   (1) to (4) of section 6], shall apply to the special class of shares.]








</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[<number>4B</number> 
   Transfer of share capital to Development Bank.—On 
   such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the Offi­cial 
   Gazette, specify (hereinafter referred to as the specified date), all the 
   shares of every Financial Corporation subscribed by the Reserve Bank as on 
   the date immediately preceding the specified date, shall, stand transferred 
   to, and vested in, the Development Bank.



</article> 
 
  
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[<number>4C</number> Payment of amount.—The 
   Reserve Bank shall be given by the Development Bank, in cash, for the 
   transfer to, and vesting in, the Development Bank of the shares of every 
   Financial Corporation which have been subscribed by the Reserve Bank, an 
   amount equal to the face value of the shares of the Financial Corporation so 
   subscribed.]




</article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[<number>4D</number> 
   Issue of redeemable preference shares.—
<section><number>1</number> 
   On and after the commencement of the State Financial Corporations 
   (Amendment) Act, 2000, the Financial Corporation may—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  issue redeemable preference shares on such 
   terms and in such manner as the Board may decide; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  convert, such number of equity shares as it 
   may decide into redeemable preference shares, with the prior approval of the 
   State Government and the Small Industries Bank, by a resolution passed in 
   the general meeting of the shareholers:
 Provided that such 
   conversion shall in no case reduce the equity shares held by the parties 
   referred to in clauses (a), (b) and (c) of sub-section (3) of section 4 to 
   less than fifty-one per cent. of the issued equity capital of the Financial 
   Corporation.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The redeemable 
   preference shares referred to in sub-section (1) shall—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  carry such fixed rate of dividend as the 
   Financial Corporation may specify at the time of such issue or conversion; 
   and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  neither be transferable nor carry any voting 
   rights.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> The redeemable 
   preference shares referred to in sub-section (1) shall be redeemed by the 
   Financial Corporation in such instalments and in such manner as the Board 
   may determine.]




</section></article> 
 
  
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[<number>4E</number> 
   Reduction of share capital.—
<section><number>1</number> 
   The Financial Corporation, with the prior approval of the State Government 
   and the Small Industries Bank, may, by resolution passed in a general 
   meeting of the shareholders, reduce its share capital in any way.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Without prejudice to the 
   generality of the foregoing power, the share capital may be reduced by—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  extinguishing or reducing the liability on 
   any of its equity shares in respect of share capital not paid-up; or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  either with or without extinguishing or 
   reducing liability on any of its equity shares, cancelling any paid-up share 
   capital which is lost or is unrepresented by available assets; or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  either with or without extinguishing or 
   reducing liability on any of its equity shares, paying off any paid-up share 
   capital which is in excess of the wants of the Financial Corporation.]




</subsection></section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[<number>4F</number> 
   Restriction on exercising of voting right.—Every 
   shareholder of the Financial Corporation holding equity shares shall have a 
   right to vote in respect of such shares on every resolution and his voting 
   right on a poll shall be in proportion to his share of the paid-up equity 
   capital of the Financial Corporation:
 Provided, however, that no 
   shareholder, other than a shareholder referred to in clauses 
<section><number>a</number>, (b) and 
   (c) of sub-section (3) of section 4, shall be entitled to exercise voting 
   rights in respect of any equity share held by him in excess of ten per cent. 
   of the issued equity capital.]




</section></article> 
 
  
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[<number>4G</number> 
   Proxy voting.—In a general 
   meeting referred to in clause (b) of sub- 
   section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 4D and sub-section (1) of section 4E, the resolution 
   for conversion or reduction of share capital shall be passed by shareholders 
   entitled to vote, voting in person, or, where proxies are allowed, by proxy, 
   and the votes cast in favour of the resolution are not less than three times 
   the number of votes, if any, cast against the resolution by shareholders so 
   entitled and voting.]




</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><footcitenum>20</footcitenum>[<number>4H</number> 
   Transfer of share capital to Small Industries Bank.—On 
   such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
   Gazette, notify (hereinafter referred to as the notified date) all the 
   shares of every Financial Corporation subscribed by the Development Bank and 
   the amount outstanding in respect of loans in lieu of capital provided by 
   the Development Bank as on the date immediately preceding the notified date, 
   shall stand transferred to, and vested in, the Small Industries Bank, such 
   transfer shall be at such rate and be paid in cash or such other manner as 
   may be mutually agreed upon between the Development Bank and the Small 
   Industries Bank.]




</article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><footcitenum>21</footcitenum>[<number>5</number> 
   Transfer of shares.—
<section><number>1</number> Save as 
   otherwise provided in sub-section (2), the shares of the Financial 
   Corporation shall be freely transferable.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Nothing contained in 
   sub-section (1) shall entitle the parties referred to in clauses (a) (b) and 
   (c) of sub-section (3) of section 4 to transfer any of the shares held by 
   them in the Financial Corporation if such transfer will result in reducing 
   the aggregate value of shares held by them to less than fifty-one per cent. 
   of the issued equity capital of the Financial Corporation.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Board may refuse to 
   register the transfer of any shares in the name of the transferee on any one 
   or more of the following grounds, and on no other ground, namely:—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  the transfer of the shares is in 
   contravention of the provisions of the Act or regulations made thereunder or 
   any other law;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  the transfer of the shares, in the opinion 
   of the Board, is prejudicial to the interests of the Financial Corporation 
   or to the public interest;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  the transfer of shares is prohibited by an 
   order of a court, tribunal or any other authority under any law for the time 
   being in force.
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number> The Board shall, before 
   the expiry of two months from the date on which the instrument of transfer 
   of shares of the Financial Corporation is lodged with it for the purpose of 
   registration of such transfer, not only form, in good faith, its opinion as 
   to whether such registration ought not or ought to be refused on any of the 
   grounds referred to in sub-section (3) but also,—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  if it has formed the opinion that such 
   registration ought not to be so refused, effect such registration; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  if it has formed the opinion that such 
   registration ought to be refused on any of the grounds mentioned in 
   sub-section (3), intimate the transferor and the transferee by notice in 
   writing.
 </subsection></section><section><number>5</number> An appeal against the 
   order of refusal of the Board under sub-section (4) shall lie to the Central 
   Government and the procedure for filing and hearing of such appeal shall be 
   in accordance with the rules made by the Central Government in this behalf.]




</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><footcitenum>22</footcitenum>[<number>6</number> 
   Conversion of shares guaranteed by State Government.—
<section><number>1</number> 
   On the commencement of the State Financial Corporations (Amendment) Act, 
   2000, every shareholder shall be given by the Financial Corporation an 
   option to require the Financial Corporation to convert the shares held by 
   him into shares of the same nominal value without the State Government 
   guarantee and issue fresh share certificate or to pay the amount paid in 
   respect of such shares not exceeding the face value of the shares held by 
   him.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The option referred to 
   in sub-section (1) shall be given by the Financial Corporation to every 
   existing shareholder before the expiry of three months from the commencement 
   of the State Financial Corporations (Amendment) Act, 2000 and shall be 
   exercised by the shareholder within three months from the date of receipt of 
   such option.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The option exercised 
   under sub-section (2) shall be final and shall not be altered or rescinded 
   after it has been exercised.
 </section><section><number>4</number> If, a shareholder 
   exercises option for receiving the payment within the stipulated time, the 
   Financial Corproation shall on surrender of the share certificate held by 
   him, pay him the amount paid in respect of such shares not exceeding the 
   face value thereof:
 Provided that if any 
   shareholder fails to exercise the option given to him under sub-section (1), 
   within the time stipulated in sub-section (2), he shall be deemed to have 
   exercised the first option.
 </section><section><number>5</number> Nothing contained in 
   sub-section (4) shall be deemed to result in reduction of the share capital 
   and the Financial Corporation may, subject to the provisions of sub-section 
   (3) of section 4, allot the shares surrendered by any shareholder, to any 
   other person.
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Financial 
   Corporation shall keep at its head office a register, in one or more books, 
   of shareholders and shall enter therein the following particulars so far as 
   they may be available, namely:—
 <subsection>        <number>i</number>  the names, addresses and occupations, if 
   any, of the shareholders and a statement of the shares held by each 
   shareholder, distinguishing each share by its denoting number;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>ii</number>  the date on which each person is so 
   entered as a shareholder;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number>  the date on which any person ceases to be 
   a shareholder; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iv</number>  such other particulars as may be 
   prescribed:
 Provided that nothing in 
   this sub-section shall apply to the shares held with a depository under the 
   Depositories Act, 1996 (22 of 1996).
 </subsection></section><section><number>7</number> Notwithstanding anything 
   contained in sub-section (6), it shall be lawful for the Financial 
   Corporation to keep the register of the shareholders in computer floppies or 
   diskettes, compact disk or any other electronic form subject to such 
   safeguards as may be prescribed.
 </section><section><number>8</number> Notwithstanding anything 
   contained in the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 
   (1 of 1872), a copy of, or extract from, the register of shareholders, 
   certified to be a true copy under the hand of an officer of the Financial 
   Corporation authorised in this behalf, shall, in all legal proceedings, be 
   admissible in evidence.
 </section><section><number>9</number> The register of 
   beneficial owners maintained by a depository under section 11 of the 
   Depositories Act, 1996 (22 of 1996) shall be deemed to be a register of 
   shareholders for the purposes of this Act.
 </section><section><number>10</number> Notwithstanding 
   anything contained in sub-sections (6), (7) and (8), no notice of any trust, 
   express, implied or constructive, shall be entered on the register of 
   shareholders or be receivable by the Financial Corporation:
 Provided that nothing in 
   this sub-section shall apply to a depository in respect of shares held by it 
   as a registered owner on behalf of a beneficial owner.
 Explanation.—For 
   the purposes of sub-sections (6), (9) and this sub-section, the expressions 
   "beneficial owner", "depository" and "registered owner" shall have the 
   meanings respectively assigned to them in clauses (a), (e) and (j) of 
   sub-section (l) of section 2 of the Depositories Act, 1996 (22 of 1996).
 </section><section><number>11</number> Notwithstanding 
   anything contained in the Indian Trusts Act, 1882 (2 of 1882), the shares of 
   the Financial Corporation shall be deemed to be included among the 
   securities enumerated in section 20 of that Act.]




</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><footcitenum>23</footcitenum>[<number>7</number> 
   Additional capital of Financial Corporation and its borrowing powers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
   The Financial Corporation may issue and sell bonds and debentures for the 
   purpose of increasing its working capital.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The State Government 
   may, on a request being made to it by the Financial Corporation, guarantee 
   the bonds and debentures issued by the Financial Corporation as to the 
   repayment of principal and the payment of interest at such rate as may be 
   fixed by that Government.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Notwithstanding anything 
   contained in the Acts hereinafter mentioned in this sub-section, such of the 
   bonds and debentures issued by the Financial Corporation as are guaranteed 
   by the State Government as to the repayment of the principal and payment of 
   interest and receipts issued by it for such of deposits as are guaranteed by 
   the State Government as to the repayment of the principal and payment of 
   interest shall be deemed to be included among the securities enumerated in 
   section 20 of the Indian Trusts Act, 1882 (2 of 1882) and also to be 
   approved securities for the purpose of the Insurance Act, 1938  
   (4 of 1938) and the Banking Regulation Act, 1949 (10 of 1949).
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Financial 
   Corporation may, for the purposes of carrying out its functions under this 
   Act, borrow money from the Reserve Bank—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  repayable on demand or on the expiry of a 
   fixed period not exceeding ninety days from the date on which the money is 
   so borrowed against the security of—
 <subsubsection>             <number>i</number>  stocks, funds and securities (other 
   than immovable property) in which a trustee is authorised to invest trust 
   money by any law for the time being in force in India, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            <number>ii</number>  such bills of exchange and promissory 
   notes as are eligible for purchase or re-discount by the Reserve Bank or as 
   are fully guaranteed as to the repayment of the principal and payment of 
   interest by a State Government;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  repayable on the expiry of a fixed period 
   not exceeding eighteen months from the date on which the money is so 
   borrowed, against securities of the Central Government or of any State 
   Government of the maturity, or subject to the previous approval of the State 
   Government, against bonds and debentures issued by the Financial Corporation 
   and maturing within a period not exceeding eighteen months from the date on 
   which the money is so borrowed and every such bond and debenture shall be 
   guaranteed by the State Government:
 Provided that the amount 
   borrowed by the Financial Corporation under clause (b) shall not at any time 
   exceed in the aggregate twice the paid-up share capital thereof.
 </subsection></section><section><number>5</number> The Financial 
   Corporation may, for the purpose of carrying out its functions under this 
   Act, borrow money from the State Government, any financial institution, 
   scheduled bank, insurance company or any other person approved by the Board 
   on such terms and conditions as may be agreed upon.
 </section><section><number>6</number> The total amount of 
   bonds and debentures issued and outstanding, the amounts borrowed by the 
   Financial Corporation under clause (b) of sub-section (4) and sub-section 
   (5) and of the contingent liabilities of the Financial Corporation in the 
   form of guarantees given by it or underwriting agreements entered into by 
   it, shall not exceed ten times the amount of the paid-up share capital and 
   reserve fund of the Financial Corporation:
 Provided that the Financial 
   Corporation may, with the prior approval of the Small Industries Bank, 
   exceed the aforesaid limit up to thirty times the amount of the paid-up 
   share capital and reserve fund of the Financial Corporation.]




</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><footcitenum>24</footcitenum>[<number>8</number> 
   Deposits with Financial Corporation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
   The Financial Corporation may accept from the State Government, or with the 
   prior approval of the Reserve Bank, from a local authority or any other 
   person deposits repayable after the expiry of a period which shall not be 
   less than twelve months from the date of the making of the deposit and on 
   such other terms as the Board thinks fit:
 Provided that the total 
   amount of such deposits shall not exceed twice the paid-up share capital of 
   the Financial Corporation:
 Provided further that the 
   State Government may permit the Financial Corporation to accept deposits up 
   to a higher limit not exceeding ten times the paid-up share capital of the 
   Financial Corporation.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any depsoit accepted 
   under sub-section (1), other than a deposit from the State Government may, 
   if so required by the Financial Corporation, be guaranteed by the State 
   Government as to the repayment of the principal and payment of interest.]



</section></article> 
 

  
 <article><footcitenum>25</footcitenum>[<number>9</number> 
   Managements.—
<section><number>1</number> The general superintendence, direction and management 
   of affairs and business of the Financial Corporation shall vest in a Board 
   of Directors which may exercise all powers and do all such acts and things, 
   as may be exercised or done by the Financial Corporation and are not by this 
   Act expressly directed or required to be done by the Financial Corporation 
   in general meeting.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Board may direct 
   that any power exercisable by it under this Act shall also be exercisable in 
   such cases and subject to such conditions, if any, as may be specified by 
   it, by the chairman, managing director or the whole-time director.



</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><footcitenum>26</footcitenum>[<number>10</number> 
   Board of directors.—The Board of 
   directors shall consist of the following, namely:—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  a director to be nominated as chairman under 
   sub-section (1) of 
   section 15;
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  two directors nominated by the State 
   Government of whom one director shall be a person who has special knowledge 
   of or experience in small-scale industries:
                  Provided that in the case of a Joint 
   Financial Corporation, the number of directors shall be such as the State 
   Governments of the participating States may, by agreement among themselves, 
   think fit to nominate each participating State Government nominating not 
   more than two directors:
                  Provided further that in the case of a 
   Joint Financial Corporation, the director, who shall have special knowledge 
   of, or exprience in, small-scale industries, shall be nominated by that 
   participating State which, according to the terms of agreement between the 
   participating States, is entitled to make such nomination;
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  two directors nominated by the Small 
   Industries Bank;
 </section><section>       <number>d</number>  two directors nominated in the prescribed 
   manner by the parties mentioned in clause (c) of sub-section (3) of section 
   4;
 </section><section>       <number>e</number>  such number of directors elected, in the 
   prescribed manner, by share-holders, other than those mentioned in clauses 
   (a), (b) and (c) of sub-section (3) of section 4, whose names are entered on 
   the register of shareholders of the Financial Corporation, ninety days 
   before the date of the meeting in which such election takes place on the 
   following basis, namely:—
 <subsection>             <number>i</number>  where the total amount of issued 
   equity share capital held by such shareholders is ten per cent. or less of 
   the total issued equity capital, two diectors;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>ii</number>  where the total amount of issued 
   equity share capital held by such shareholders is more than ten per cent. 
   but less than twenty-five per cent. of total issued equity capital, three 
   directors;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>iii</number>  where the total amount of issued 
   equity share capital held by such shareholders is twenty-five per cent. or 
   more of total issued equity capital, four directors; and
 </subsection><subsection>           <number>iv</number>  where the total amount of issued equity 
   share capital held by equity shareholders referred to in this clause does 
   not permit election of all the four directors, the Board shall co-opt such 
   number of directors as is required to make up the said number who shall 
   retire in equal number on the assumption of charge by the elected directors 
   in the order of their co-option;
 </subsection></section><section>        <number>f</number>  a managing director appointed in accordance 
   with the provisions of sub-section (1) of section 17:
 Provided that on the first 
   constitution of the Board, the directors referred to in clause (d) shall be 
   nominated by the State Government and directors so nominated shall, for the 
   purpose of this Act, be deemed to be elected directors:
 Provided further that all 
   the directors of the Board first constituted, other than the managing 
   director, shall retire at the end of the first year.]
 <footcitenum>27</footcitenum>[***]





</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><footcitenum>28</footcitenum>[<number>11</number> 
   Term of office and retirement of directors.—
<section><number>1</number> 
   A nominated director shall hold office during the pleasure of the authority 
   nominating him.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Subject to the 
   provisions of sub-section (1), a nominated director shall hold office for 
   such term not exceeding three years and shall also be eligible for 
   re-nomination:
 Provided that no such 
   director shall hold office continuously for a period exceeding six years.
 </section><section><number>3</number> An elected director 
   other than a director deemed to be elected under the first proviso to clause 
   (d) of section 10 shall hold office for three years and shall also be 
   eligible for re-election:
 Provided that no such 
   director shall hold office continuously for a period exceeding six years.




</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><number>12</number> Disqualifications for 
   being a director.—No person shall 
   be a director, if he—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  has been found to be of unsound mind by a 
   court of competent jurisdiction and the finding is in force; or
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  is or at any time has been, adjudicated as 
   insolvent or has suspended payment of his debts or has compounded with his 
   creditors; or
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  has been convicted by a court of any offence 
   involving moral turpitude and sentenced in respect thereof to imprisonment 
   of not less than six months and a period of five years has not elapsed from 
   the date of expiry of the sentence; or
 </section><section>       <number>d</number>  is elected by the persons referred to in 
   clause (d) of sub-section (3) of section 4 but not registered as shareholder 
   in his own right of unencumbered shares of a nominal value of not less than 
   ten thousand rupees in the Financial Corporation; or
 </section><section>       <number>e</number>  has not paid any call in respect of shares 
   of the Financial Corporation held by him, whether alone or jointly with 
   others, and six months have elapsed from the last day fixed for the payment 
   of the call.]
  

</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><number>13</number> Removal of director 
   from office.—<footcitenum>29</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number>] 
   The State Government may remove from office any director who—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  is, or has become, subject to any of the 
   disqualifications mentioned in section 12; or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  without excuse sufficient in the opinion of 
   the State Government to exonerate it, is absent without leave of the Board 
   from more than three consecutive meetings of the Board.
 </subsection></section><section><footcitenum>30</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> 
   The shareholders, other than those mentioned in clauses (a), (b) and (c) of 
   sub-section (3) of section 4, whose names are entered on the register of 
   shareholders, may, after giving to the director a resonable opportunity of 
   being heard in the manner as may be prescribed, by resolution passed by 
   majority of the votes of such shareholders holding in the aggregate not less 
   than one-half of the total issued equity share capital held by all such 
   shareholders, remove any director elected under clause (d) of section 10 and 
   elect in his place another person to fill the vacancy so caused.]





</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><number>14</number> 
Resignation of office by director and filling up of casual 
vacancies.—<footcitenum>31</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number> Any director elected under clause (d) 
of section 10 may, by giving notice in writing to the Chairman of the Board, 
resign from his office and on such resignation being accepted, shall be deemed 
to have vacated his office.]
 </section><section><number>2</number> A 
casual vacancy in the office of an elected director shall be filled by election 
and a director so elected shall hold office for the unexpired portion of the 
term of his predecessor.
 </section><section><number>3</number> No 
act or proceeding of the Board shall be questioned on the ground merely of the 
existence of any vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution of the 
Board.


</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><footcitenum>32</footcitenum>[<number>15</number> 
   Chairman of Board.—
<section><number>1</number> The Small 
   Industries Bank shall, in consultation with the State Government nominate a 
   director as a Chairman of the Board for such period not exceeding three 
   years and on such terms and conditions as the Small Industries Bank may 
   specify:
 Provided that the Chairman 
   shall not be a whole-time director unless he is also appointed to function 
   as the managing director:
 Provided further that the 
   Chairman shall so long as he remains a director be eligible for 
   re-appointment as Chairman.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Chairman shall 
   preside over the meetings of the Board and the general meetings of the 
   Financial Corporation.]




</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>33</footcitenum>[<number>16</number> Remuneration of 
   directors.—The directors other 
   than the managing director and not being servants of the Government shall be 
   paid such fees as may be prescribed for attending meetings of the Board and, 
   if they are members of the Executive Committee, or any other committee 
   appointed by the Financial Corporation, for attending meetings of such 
   committee.]




</article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><number>17</number> Managing director.—<footcitenum>34</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number> 
   The managing director shall—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  be appointed, in consultation with the Small 
   Industries Bank, by the State Government;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  be a whole-time officer of the Financial 
   Corporation;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  perform such duties as the Board, by 
   regulations, entrust or delegate to him;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  hold office for such term not exceeding 
   three years as the State Government may specify and shall be eligible for 
   re-appointment;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number>  receive such salary and allowances and be 
   subject to other terms and conditions of service as the Board may, with the 
   previous approval of the State Government, determine.]
 </subsection></section><section><footcitenum>35</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> 
   The State Government may, after consulting the Board, remove the managing 
   director from office:
 Provided that no managing 
   director shall be so removed unless he has been given an opportunity of 
   showing cause against his remov­al.]
 </section><section><footcitenum>36</footcitenum>[<number>3</number> 
   Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), the State Government, 
   with prior consultation of the Small Industries Bank, shall have the right 
   to terminate the term of office of the managing director at any time, before 
   the expiry of the term specified under clause (d) of sub-section (1) by 
   giving him notice of not less than three months in writing or three months 
   salary and allowances in lieu of such notice and the managing director shall 
   also have right to relinquish his office at any time before the expiry of 
   term specified under clause (d) of sub-section (1) by giving to the State 
   Government notice of not less than three months in writing.]






</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><footcitenum>37</footcitenum>[<number>18</number> 
   Executive Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
   Board shall constitute an Executive Committee consisting of the chairman and 
   managing director, the whole-time directors and such other directors as it 
   may deem fit:
 Provided that in the case of 
   a Joint Financial Corporation, if the directors nominated under clause (b) 
   of section 10 represent different State Governments then, all of them shall 
   be members of the Executive Committee.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Executive Committee 
   shall discharge such functions as may be prescribed or as may be delegated 
   to it by the Board.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Board may constitute 
   such other committees whether consisting wholly of directors or wholly of 
   other persons or partly of directors and partly of other persons for such 
   purpose or purposes as it may think fit.]




</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><number>19</number> Meetings of the Board 
   and Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> The Board and 
   the Executive Committee shall meet at such times and places and shall 
   observe such rules of procedure in regard to transaction of business at its 
   meetings as may be provided by regulation made under this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> All questions at a 
   meeting shall be decided by a majority of votes of the members present, and, 
   in the case of equality of votes, the Chairman or in his absence, any other 
   person presid­ing, shall have a second or casting vote.
 </section><section><number>3</number> No director shall vote 
   on any matter in which he is interest­ed.
 <footcitenum>38</footcitenum>[***]
 <footcitenum>39</footcitenum>[***]
 </section><section><footcitenum>40</footcitenum>[<number>5</number> 
   If for any reason the Chairman of the Board or the Chairman of the Executive 
   Committee is unable to attend any meeting of the Board or, as the case may 
   be, of the Executive Committee,—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> in the case of the meeting of the Board, a 
   director <footcitenum>41</footcitenum>[***] authorised 
   by the Chairman of the Board in writing shall preside at such meeting, but 
   if the director so authorised is absent or if no such authorisation has been 
   made, the Board may elect a director to preside at that meeting; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> in the case of the meeting of the Executive 
   Committee, a member authorised in writing by the Chairman of that Committee 
   shall preside at that meeting, but if the member so authorised is absent or 
   if no such authorisation has been made, the Committee may elect any of its 
   members to preside at that meeting.]







</subsection></section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><number>20</number> Powers of Executive 
   Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> Subject to such 
   general or special directions as the Board may from time to time give, the 
   Executive Committee may deal with any matter within the com­petence of the 
   Board.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The minutes of every 
   meeting of the Executive Committee <footcitenum>42</footcitenum>[shall, 
   after confirmation thereof at the next meeting of the Executive Committee, 
   be laid] before the Board at the next fol­lowing meeting of the Board.




</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><number>21</number> Advisory Committee.—The 
   Financial Corporation may appoint <footcitenum>43</footcitenum>[one 
   or more committee or committees consisting wholly of direc­tors or wholly of 
   other persons or partly of directors and partly of other persons] for the 
   purpose of assisting the Financial Corporation in the efficient discharge of 
   its functions and, in particular, for the purpose of securing that those 
   functions are exercised with due regard to the circumstances and conditions 
   prevailing in, and the requirements of, particular areas or industries.



</article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><footcitenum>44</footcitenum>[<number>22</number> 
   Offices and agencies.—The 
   Financial Corporation shall establish its head office and other offices and 
   agencies at such places as the State Government may, from time to time 
   specify and save as aforesaid, the Financial Corporation may establish 
   addi­tional offices or agencies in such other places within the State as it 
   may consider necessary.]




</article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><number>23</number> Officers and other 
   employees of the Financial Corporation.—The 
   Financial Corporation may appoint such offic­ers, advisers and employees as 
   it considers necessary for the efficient performance of its functions, and 
   determine, by regula­tions, their conditions of appointment and service and 
   the remu­neration payable to them:
 <footcitenum>45</footcitenum>[***] 



</article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><number>24</number> General duty of the 
   Board.—The Board in discharging 
   its functions under this Act shall act on business principles due regard 
   being had by it to the interests of industry, commerce and the general 
   public.

</article> 
 
 THE STATE 
FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><footcitenum>46</footcitenum>[<number>25</number> Business which Financial 
Corporation may transact.—<footcitenum>47</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number> The Financial Corporation may, subject 
to the provisions of this Act, carry on and transact any of the following kinds 
of business, namely:—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  guaranteeing, 
on such terms and conditions as may be agreed upon,—
 <subsubsection>             
<number>i</number>  loans raised by industrial concerns which are repayable within a 
period not exceeding twenty years, and are floated in the public market;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            
<number>ii</number>  loans raised by industrial concerns from scheduled banks or State 
co-operative banks or other financial institutions;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  guaranteeing, 
on such terms and conditions as may be agreed upon, deferred payments due from 
any industrial concern in connection with its purchase of capital goods within 
India;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  underwriting of 
the issue of stock, shares, bonds or debentures by industrial concerns;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  transferring 
for consideration any instruments relating to loans and advances granted by it 
to industrial concerns;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number>  acting as agent 
of the Central Government or the State Government or the Development Bank or the 
Small Industries Bank or the IFCI Limited formed and registered under the 
Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) or any other financial institution notified in 
this behalf by the Central Government in respect of any matter connected with, 
or arising out of, the grant of loans or advances to an industrial concern, or 
subscription to debentures of an industrial concern or relating to the business 
of the Development Bank, Small Industries Bank, IFCI Limited or financial 
institution;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>f</number>  
subscribing to, or purchasing of, the stock, shares, bonds or debentures of an 
industrial concern or any other concern;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>g</number>  retaining as 
part of its assets any stock, shares, bonds or debentures which it may acquire 
by subscription or in fulfilment of its underwriting liabilities and disposing 
of the stock, shares, bonds or debentures so acquired;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>h</number>  granting loans 
or advances to, or subscribing to debentures of, an industrial concern, 
repayable within a period not exceeding twenty years from the date on which they 
are granted or subscribed to, as the case may be:
                  
Provided that the Financial Corporation may, with the prior approval of the 
Small Industries Bank, exceed the said limit of twenty years up to a further 
period of ten years:
                  
Provided further that nothing contained in this clause shall be deemed to 
preclude the Financial Corporation from granting loans or advances to, or 
subscribing to debentures of, and industrial concern to which may be attached an 
option to convert such debentures or loans into stock or shares of the 
industrial concern:
                  
Provided also that the Financial Corporation may, in the exercise of such 
option, convert the amounts outstanding on such debentures or loans into stock 
or shares of the industrial concern if such concern increases its subscribed 
capital by the issue of further stock or shares in accordance with and subject 
to, the provisions of section 81 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956).
                  
Explanation.—In this clause, the expression "the amounts outstanding on such 
debentures or loans" shall mean the principal, interest and other charges 
payable on such debentures or loans as at the time when the amounts are sought 
to be converted into stock or shares;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>i</number>  accepting 
or discounting promissory notes and bills of exchange made, drawn, accepted or 
endorsed by industrial concerns or by any person selling capital goods 
manufactured by one industrial concern to another industrial concern;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>j</number>  
undertaking research and surveys for evaluating or dealing with marketing or 
investments or undertaking and carrying on techno-economic studies or other 
activities in connection with the development of any industry;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>k</number>  providing 
technical and administrative assistance to any industrial concern or any person 
for the promotion, management or expansion of any industry;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>l</number>  planning 
and assisting in the promotion and development of industries;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>m</number>  providing 
consultancy and merchant banking services;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>n</number>  acting as the 
trustee for the holders of debentures or other securities;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>o</number>  leasing, 
sub-leasing or giving on hire or hire-purchase of industrial plant, equipment, 
machinery or any other asset;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>p</number>  factoring;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>q</number>  providing 
export related credit and services;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>r</number>  
undertaking money market related activities;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>s</number>  setting up of 
mutual funds and undertaking asset management activity;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>t</number>  
promoting, forming or conducting or assisting in the promotion, formation, or 
conduct of companies, subsidiaries, societies, trusts or such other associations 
of persons as it may deem fit;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>u</number>  opening or 
confirming or endorsing letters of credit and negotiating or collecting bills 
and other documents drawn thereunder;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>v</number>  doing such 
other business as the Small Industries Bank may authorise, and or generally the 
doing of such acts and things as may be incidental to or consequential upon, the 
exercise of its powers or the discharge of its duties under this Act.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The 
Financial Corporation may receive, in consideration of any of the services 
mentioned in sub-section (1), such commission, brokerage, interest, remuneration 
or fee as may be agreed upon.]
 <footcitenum>48</footcitenum>[***]
 </section><section><number>3</number> 
Subject to the provisions of sub-section (5) of section 7, the aggregate of 
contingent liabilities of the Financial Corporation under clauses (a), (b) 
<footcitenum>49</footcitenum>[(c) and (ca)] of sub-section 
(1) shall not at any time exceed twice the paid-up share capital and reserve 
fund of the Corporation except with the prior approval of the State Government 
and in consultation with the <footcitenum>50</footcitenum>[Small Industries Bank] but in no case 
shall exceed thrice the paid-up share capital and reserve fund of the 
Corporation.]
 </section><section><footcitenum>51</footcitenum>[<number>4</number> Nothing contained in this section 
shall entitle any Financial Corporation to hold shares in any company, whether 
as pledgee, mortgagee or absolute owner, of an amount exceeding thirty per cent. 
of the subscribed share capital of that company or thirty per cent. of its own 
paid-up share capital and free reserves, whichever is less.
 </section><section><number>5</number> If, 
on the commencement of the State Financial Corporations (Amendment) Act, 1972 
(77 of 1972), any Financial Corporation is holding shares in excess of the 
limits specified in sub-section (4), the Corproation shall report the matter 
forthwith to the Reserve Bank and shall, within such period as the Reserve Bank 
may allow, so reduce its share holdings as to conform to the provisions of that 
sub-section.]







</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>52</footcitenum>[<number>25A</number> Power to acquire 
   rights.—The Financial Corporation 
   shall have the right to acquire, by transfer or assignment, the rights and 
   interests of any such financial institution as may be noti­fied by the 
   Central Government (including any other rights inci­dental thereto) in 
   relation to any loan or advance granted or any amount recoverable by such 
   institution, either in whole or in part, by the execution or issue of any 
   instrument or by the transfer of any instrument by endorsement or in any 
   other manner:
 Provided that such loan or 
   advance or amount relates to any business which the Financial Corporation 
   may transact under this Act.]




</article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><footcitenum>53</footcitenum>[<number>25B</number> 
   Gifts, grants etc.—The 
   Financial Corporation may receive gifts, grants, donations or benefactions 
   from Government or any other source.]




</article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><footcitenum>54</footcitenum>[<number>26</number> 
   Limit of accommodation.—On and 
   from the commencement of the State Financial Corporations (Amendment) Act, 
   2000, the Financial Corporation shall not enter into any arrangements under 
   clause 
<section><number>a</number>, (d) or (h) of  
   sub-section (l) of section 25 with any industrial concern so that the total 
   amount outstanding against that concern in respect of all such arrangements 
   together with the amount of the face value of the shares and stocks of that 
   concern whether subscribed or agreed to be subscribed and the outstanding 
   liabilities on account of underwriting agreements and the deferred payments 
   guarantees is more than—
 <subsection>        <number>i</number>  five hundred lakhs of rupees in the case of 
   a corporation established by or under any other law or a company as defined 
   in section 3 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) or a co-operative 
   society registered under the Co-operative Societies Act, 1912 (2 of 1912) or 
   any other law relating to co-operative societies for the time being in 
   force; and
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>ii</number>  two hundred lakhs of rupees in any other 
   case:
 Provided that the Financial 
   Corporation may, with the prior approval of the Small Industries Bank, 
   exceed the limit under clause (i) or clause (ii) up to four times.]




</subsection></section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><number>27</number> Power to impose 
   conditions for accommodation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
   In enter­ing into any arrangement under section 25 with an industrial 
   concern, the Financial Corporation may impose such conditions as it may 
   think necessary or expedient for protecting the interests of the Financial 
   Corporation and securing that the accommodation granted by it is put to the 
   best use by the industrial concern.
 </section><section><footcitenum>55</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> 
   Where any arrangement entered into by the Financial Corpo­ration with an 
   industrial concern provides for the appointment by the Financial Corporation 
   of one or more directors of such indus­trial concern, such provision and any 
   appointment of directors made in pursuance thereof shall be valid and 
   effective notwith­standing anything to the contrary contained in the 
   Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) or in any other law for the time being in 
   force or in the memorandum, articles of association or any other in­strument 
   relating to the industrial concern, and any provision regarding share 
   qualification, age limit, number of director­ships, removal of office of 
   directors and such like conditions contained in any such law or instrument 
   aforesaid shall not apply to any director appointed by the Financial 
   Corporation in pur­suance of the arrangement as aforesaid.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Any director appointed 
   in pursuance of sub-section (2) shall—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> hold office during the pleasure of the 
   Financial Corporation and may be removed or substituted by any person by 
   order in writing by the Financial Corporation;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> not incur any obligation or liability by 
   reason only of his being a director or for anything done or omitted to be 
   done in good faith in the discharge of his duties as a director or any­thing 
   in relation thereto;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number> not be liable to retirement by rotation and 
   shall not be taken into account for computing the number of directors liable 
   to such retirement.]




</subsection></section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><number>28</number> Prohibited business.—<footcitenum>56</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number>] 
   The Financial Corporation shall not—
 <subsection><footcitenum>57</footcitenum>[<number>a</number>  
   except as provided in section 8, accept deposits;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  except as provided in clauses <footcitenum>58</footcitenum>[(da)], (f) and (g) of 
   sub-section (1) of section 25, subscribe to the shares or stock of any 
   company;]
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number> grant any loan or advance on the security of 
   its own shares;
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>59</footcitenum>[<number>d</number> 
   grant any form of assistance to any industrial concern in respect of which 
   the aggregate of the paid-up share capital and free reserves exceeds ten 
   crores of rupees or such higher amount not exceeding thirty crores of rupees 
   as the State Government, on the recommendation of the Small Industries Bank, 
   may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify.]
 </subsection></section><section><footcitenum>58</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> 
   The Financial Corporation shall not enter into any kind of business with any 
   industrial concern, of which any of the direc­tors of the Financial 
   Corporation is a proprietor, partner, director, manager, agent, employee or 
   guarantor, or in which one or more directors of the Financial Corporation 
   together hold substantial interest:
 Provided that this section 
   shall not apply to any industrial concern if any director of the Financial 
   Corporation—
 <subsection>        <number>i</number> is nominated as a director of the Board of 
   such concern by the Government or a Government company as defined in section 
   617 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) or by a Corporation estab­lished 
   by or under any other law; or
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>ii</number> is elected on the Board of such concern by 
   virtue of shares held in the concern by Government or a Government company 
   as defined in section 617 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) or by a 
   Corporation established by or under any other law, by reason only of such 
   nomination or election, as the case may be.
 Explanation.—“Substantial 
   interest” in relation to an industrial concern means the beneficial interest 
   held by one or more of the directors of the Financial Corporation or by any 
   relative as defined in clause (41) of section 2 of the Companies Act, 1956 
   (1 of 1956) of such director whether singly or taken together, in the shares 
   of the industrial concern, the aggregate amount paid-up on which either 
   exceeds five lakhs of rupees or five per cent. of the paid-up share capital 
   of the industrial concern, whichever is less.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> The provisions of 
   sub-section (2)—
 <subsection>        <number>i</number> shall not apply to any transaction relating 
   to the business entered into prior to the commencement of the State 
   Financial Corporations (Amendment) Act, 1972 (77 of 1972) and all such 
   business and any transaction in relation thereto may be imple­mented or 
   continued as if that Act had not come into force;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>ii</number> shall apply only so long as the conditions 
   precedent to such disability as set out in the sub-section continue.]







</subsection></section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
  
  
 <article><number>29</number> Rights of Financial 
   Corporation in case of default.—
<section><number>1</number> 
   Where any industrial concern, which is under a liability to the Financial 
   Corporation under an agreement, makes any default in repayment of any loan 
   or advance or any instalment thereof <footcitenum>60</footcitenum>[or 
   in meeting its obligations in relation to any guarantee given by the 
   Corporation] or otherwise fails to comply with the terms of its agreement 
   with the Financial Corporation, the Financial Corpo­ration shall have the
   <footcitenum>61</footcitenum>[right 
   to take over the management orpos­session or both of the industrial 
   concerns], as well as the <footcitenum>62</footcitenum>[right 
   to transfer by way of lease or sale] and realise the property pledged, 
   mortgaged, hypothecated or assigned to the Financial Corporation.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any transfer of property 
   made by the Financial Corporation, in exercise of its powers <footcitenum>63</footcitenum>[***] 
   under sub-section (1), shall vest in the transferee all rights in or to the 
   property trans­ferred <footcitenum>64</footcitenum>[as 
   if the transfer] had been made by the owner of the property.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Financial 
   Corporation shall have the same rights and powers with respect to goods 
   manufactured or produced wholly or partly from goods forming part of the 
   security held by it as it had with respect to the original goods.
 </section><section><footcitenum>65</footcitenum>[<number>4</number>
   <footcitenum>66</footcitenum>[Where 
   any action has been taken against an industrial concern] under the 
   provisions of sub-section (1), all costs, <footcitenum>67</footcitenum>[charges 
   and expenses which in the opinion of the Financial Corporation have been 
   properly incurred] by it <footcitenum>68</footcitenum>[as 
   incidental thereto] shall be recoverable from the industrial concern and the 
   money which is received by it <footcitenum>69</footcitenum>[***] 
   shall, in the absence of any contract to the contrary, be held by it in 
   trust to be ap­plied firstly, in payment of such costs, charges and expenses 
   and, secondly, in discharge of the debt due to the Financial Corporation, 
   and the residue of the money so received shall be paid to the person 
   entitled thereto.]
 </section><section><number>5</number> <footcitenum>66</footcitenum>[Where the Financial Corporation 
   has taken any action against an industrial concern] under the provisions of 
   sub-section (1), the Financial Corporation shall be deemed to be the owner 
   of such concern, for the purposes of suits by or against the concern, and 
   shall sue and be sued in the name of <footcitenum>70</footcitenum>[the 
   concern].



























</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article>
<number>30</number> Power to call for repayment before 
   agreed period.—Notwith­standing 
   anything in any agreement to the contrary, the Financial Corporation may, by 
   notice in writing, require any industrial concern to which it has granted 
   any loan or advance to discharge forthwith in full its liabilities to the 
   Financial Corporation,—
 <section>       <number>a</number> if it appears to 
   the Board that false or misleading informa­tion in any material particular 
   was given by the industrial concern in its application for the loan or 
   advance; or
 </section><section>       <number>b</number> if the 
   industrial concern has failed to comply with the terms of its contract with 
   the Financial Corporation in the matter of the loan or advance; or
 </section><section>       <number>c</number> if there is a 
   reasonable apprehension that the industrial concern is unable to pay its 
   debts or that proceedings for liqui­dation may be commenced in respect 
   thereof; or
 </section><section>       <number>d</number> if the property 
   pledged, mortgaged, hypothecated or assigned to the Financial Corporation as 
   security for the loan or advance is not insured and kept insured by the 
   industrial concern to the satisfaction of the Financial Corporation or 
   depreciates in value to such an extent that, in the opinion of the Board, 
   fur­ther security to the satisfaction of the Board should be given and such 
   security is not given; or
 </section><section>       <number>e</number> if, without the permission of the Board, any 
   machinery, plant or other equipment, whether forming part of the security or 
   otherwise, is removed from the premises of the industrial concern without 
   being replaced; or
 </section><section>        <number>f</number> if for any reason it is necessary to protect 
   the interests of the Financial Corporation.
  
  

</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><number>31</number> Special provisions 
   for enforcement of claims by Financial Corporation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
   Where an industrial concern, in breach of any agreement, makes any default 
   in repayment of any loan or advance or any instalment thereof <footcitenum>71</footcitenum>[or 
   in meeting its obligations in relation to any guarantee given by the 
   Corporation] or otherwise fails to comply with the terms of its agreement 
   with the Finan­cial Corporation or where the Financial Corporation requires 
   an industrial concern to make immediate repayment of any loan or advance 
   under section 30 and the industrial concern fails to make such repayment,
   <footcitenum>72</footcitenum>[then, 
   without prejudice to the provisions of section 29 of this Act and of section 
   69 of the Transfer of Property Act, 1882 (4 of 1882)] any officer of the 
   Financial Corporation, generally or specially authorised by the Board in 
   this behalf, may apply to the district judge within the limits of whose 
   jurisdiction the industrial concern carries on the whole or a substantial 
   part of its business for one or more of the follow­ing reliefs, namely:—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> for an order for the sale of the property 
   pledged, mort­gaged, hypothecated or assigned to the <footcitenum>73</footcitenum>[Financial Corporation] as 
   security for the loan or advance; or
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>74</footcitenum>[<number>aa</number> 
   for enforcing the liability of any surety; or]
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> for transferring the management of the 
   industrial concern to the Financial Corporation; or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number> for an ad interim injunction 
   restraining the industrial concern from transferring or removing its 
   machinery or plant or equipment from the premises of the industrial concern 
   without the permission of the Board, where such removal is apprehended.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> An application under 
   sub-section (1) shall state the nature and extent of the liability of the 
   industrial concern to the Financial Corporation, the ground on which it is 
   made and such other particulars as may be prescribed.














</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
  
 <article><number>32</number> Procedure of district 
   judge in respect of applications under  
   section 31.—
<section><number>1</number> When the 
   application is for the reliefs men­tioned in clauses 
<subsection><number>a</number> and (c) of 
   sub-section (1) of section 31, the district judge shall pass an ad 
   interim order attaching the security, or so much of the property of the 
   industrial concern as would on being sold realise in his estimate an amount 
   equivalent in value to the outstanding liability of the industrial concern 
   to the Financial Corporation, together with the costs of the proceedings 
   taken under section 31, with or without an ad interim injunction 
   restraining the industrial concern from transferring or removing its 
   machinery, plant or equipment.
 </subsection></section><section><footcitenum>75</footcitenum>[<number>1A</number> 
   When the application is for the relief mentioned in clause (aa) of 
   sub-section (1) of section 31, the district judge shall issue a notice 
   calling upon the surety to show cause on a date to be specified in the 
   notice why his liability should not be enforced.]
 </section><section><number>2</number> When the application is 
   for the relief mentioned in clause (b) of sub- 
   section (1) of section 31, the district judge shall grant an ad interim 
   injunction restraining the industrial concern from transferring or removing 
   its machinery, plant or equipment and issue a notice calling upon the 
   industrial concern to show cause, on a date to be specified in the notice, 
   why the manage­ment of the industrial concern should not be transferred to 
   the Financial Corporation.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Before passing any order 
   under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) <footcitenum>75</footcitenum>[or 
   issuing a notice under sub-section (1A),] the district judge may, if he 
   thinks fit, examine the officer making the application.
 </section><section><footcitenum>76</footcitenum>[<number>4</number> 
   At the same time as he passes an order under sub-section (1), the district 
   judge shall issue to the industrial concern or to the owner of the security 
   attached a notice accompanied by copies of the order, the application and 
   the evidence, if any, recorded by him calling upon it or him to show cause 
   on a date to be specified in the notice why the ad interim order of 
   attachment should not be made absolute or the injunction confirmed.
 </section><section><number>4A</number> If no cause is shown on 
   or before the date specified in the notice under sub-section (1A) the 
   district judge shall forthwith order the enforcement of the liability of the 
   surety.]
 </section><section><number>5</number> If no cause is shown on 
   or before the date specified in the notice under sub-sections (2) and (4), 
   the district Judge shall forthwith make the ad interim order absolute 
   and direct the sale of the attached property or transfer the management of 
   the indus­trial concern to the Financial Corporation or confirm the 
   injunc­tion.
 </section><section><number>6</number> If cause is shown, the 
   district judge shall proceed to inves­tigate the claim of the Financial 
   Corporation in accordance with the provisions contained in the Code of Civil 
   Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) insofar as such provisions may be applied 
   thereto.
 </section><section><number>7</number> After making an 
   investigation under sub-section (6), the district judge may—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> confirm the order of attachment and direct 
   the sale of the attached property;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> vary the order of attachment so as to release 
   a portion of the property from attachment and direct the sale of the 
   remainder of the attached property;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number> release the property from attachment;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number> confirm or dissolve the injunction; <footcitenum>77</footcitenum>[***];
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>75</footcitenum>[<number>da</number> direct the enforcement of 
   the liability of the surety or reject the claim made in this behalf; or]
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number> transfer the management of the industrial 
   concern to the Financial Corporation or reject the claim made in this 
   behalf:
 Provided that when making an 
   order under clause (c) <footcitenum>75</footcitenum>[or 
   making an order rejecting the claim to enforce the liability of the surety 
   under clause (da) or making an order rejecting the claim to transfer the 
   management of the industrial concern to the Financial Corporation under 
   clause (e)], the district judge may make such further orders as he thinks 
   necessary to protect the interests of the Financial Corporation and may 
   apportion the costs of the proceedings in such manner as he thinks fit:
 Provided further that unless 
   the Financial Corporation intimates to the district judge that it will not 
   appeal against any order releasing any property from attachment <footcitenum>75</footcitenum>[or rejecting the claim to 
   enforce the liability of the surety or rejecting the claim to transfer the 
   industrial concern to the Financial Corporation], such order shall not be 
   given effect to, until the expiry of the period fixed under sub-section (9) 
   within which an appeal may be preferred or, if an appeal is preferred, 
   unless the High Court otherwise directs until the appeal is disposed of.
 </subsection></section><section><number>8</number> An order of attachment 
   or sale of property under this section shall be carried into effect as far 
   as practicable in the manner provided in the Code of Civil Procedure 1908 (5 
   of 1908) for the attachment or sale of property in execution of a decree as 
   if the Financial Corporation were the decree-holder.
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>78</footcitenum>[<number>8A</number> An order under this 
   section transferring the management of an industrial concern to the 
   Financial Corporation shall be carried into effect, as far as may be 
   practicable, in the manner provided in the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 
   of 1908) for the possession of immovable property or the delivery of movable 
   property in execution of a degree, as if the Financial Corpora­tion were the 
   decree-holder.]
 </section><section><number>9</number> Any party aggrieved by 
   an order <footcitenum>79</footcitenum>[under sub-section 
   (4A), sub-section (5)] or sub-section (7) may, within thirty days from the 
   date of the order, appeal to the High Court, and upon such appeal the High 
   Court may, after hearing the parties, pass such orders thereon as it thinks 
   proper.
 </section><section><number>10</number> Where proceedings for 
   liquidation in respect of an industri­al concern have commenced before an 
   application is made under sub-section (1) of section 31, nothing in this 
   section shall be construed as giving to the Financial Corporation any 
   preference over the other creditors of the industrial concern not conferred 
   on it by any other law.
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>80</footcitenum>[<number>11</number> The functions of a 
   district judge under this section shall be exercisable—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> in a presidency town, where there is a city 
   civil court having jurisdiction, by a judge of that court and in the absence 
   of such court, by the High Court; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> elsewhere, also by an additional district 
   judge <footcitenum>77</footcitenum>[or by any judge of 
   the principal court of civil jurisdiction].]
 </subsection></section><section><footcitenum>81</footcitenum>[<number>12</number> 
   For the removal of doubts it is hereby declared that any court competent to 
   grant an ad interim injunction under this section shall also have the 
   power to appoint a Receiver and to exercise all the other powers incidental 
   thereto.]

















</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><footcitenum>82</footcitenum>[<number>32A</number> 
   Power of Financial Corporation to appoint directors or administrators of an 
   industrial concern when management is taken over.—
<section><number>1</number> 
   When the management of an industrial concern is taken over by the Financial 
   Corporation, the Financial Corporation may, by order notified in the 
   Official Gazette, appoint as many per­sons as it thinks fit,—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> in any case in which the industrial concern 
   is a company as defined in the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) to be 
   directors of that industrial concern; or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> in any other case, to be administrators of 
   that industrial concern. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The power to appoint 
   directors or administrators under this section includes the power to appoint 
   any individual, firm or company to be the managing agent or manager of the 
   industrial concern on such terms and conditions as the Financial Corporation 
   may think fit.]
 </section><section><footcitenum>83</footcitenum>[<number>3</number> 
   Nothing in the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) or in any other law for the 
   time being in force or in any instrument relat­ing to the industrial concern 
   shall, in so far as it makes in relation to a director, any provision for 
   the holding of any share qualification, age limit, restriction on the number 
   of directorships, retirement by rotation or removal from office, apply to 
   any director appointed by the Financial Corporation under this section.]
  





</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><footcitenum>84</footcitenum>[<number>32B</number> 
   Effect of notified order under section 32A.—On 
   the issue of a notified order under section 32A.—
 <section>       <number>a</number> in any case in which the industrial concern 
   is a company as defined in the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) all persons 
   hold­ing office as directors of the industrial concern and in any other 
   case, all persons holding any office having the powers of superintendence, 
   direction and control of the industrial concern, immediately before the 
   issue of the notified order, shall be deemed to have vacated their offices 
   as such;
 </section><section>       <number>b</number> any contract of management between the 
   industrial concern and any managing agent or any director or manager thereof 
   holding office as such immediately before the issue of the notified order 
   shall be deemed to have terminated;
 </section><section>       <number>c</number> in the case of an industrial concern which is 
   a company as defined in the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) the managing 
   agent, if any, appointed under section 32A shall be deemed to have been duly 
   appointed in pursuance of the said Act and the memorandum and articles of 
   association of the industrial concern and the provisions of the said Act and 
   the memorandum and arti­cles shall, subject to the other provisions 
   contained in this Act, apply accordingly, but no such managing agent shall 
   be removed from office except with the previous consent of the Financial 
   Corporation;
 </section><section>       <number>d</number> the directors or the administrators appointed 
   under section 32A shall take such steps as may be necessary to take into 
   their custody or under their control all the property, effects and 
   actionable claims to which the industrial concern is, or appears to be, 
   entitled, and all the property and effects of the indus­trial concern shall 
   be deemed to be in the custody of the direc­tors or administrators as the 
   case may be, as from the date of the notified order;
 </section><section>       <number>e</number> the directors appointed under section 32A 
   shall, for all purposes, be the directors of the industrial concern duly 
   consti­tuted under the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) and such direc­tors, 
   or as the case may be, the administrators appointed under section 32A, shall 
   alone be entitled to exercise all the powers of the directors or as the case 
   may be, of the persons exercising powers of superintendence, direction and 
   control, of the indus­trial concern, whether such powers are derived from 
   the said Act or from the memorandum or articles of association of the 
   indus­trial concern or from any other source whatsoever.]
  




</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><footcitenum>85</footcitenum>[<number>32C</number> 
   Powers and duties of directors and administrators.—
<section><number>1</number> 
   Sub­ject to the control of the Financial Corporation, the directors, or as 
   the case may be, the administrators appointed under section 32A, shall take 
   such steps as may be necessary for the purpose of efficiently managing the 
   business of the industrial concern and shall exercise such powers and have 
   such duties as may be pre­scribed.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Without prejudice to the 
   generality of the powers vested in them under sub-section (1), the directors 
   or as the case may be, the administrators appointed under section 32A, may, 
   with the previous approval of the Financial Corporation, make an 
   applica­tion to a court for the purpose of cancelling or varying any 
   contract or agreement entered into at any time before the issue of the 
   notified order under section 32A, between the industrial concern and any 
   other person and the court may, if satisfied after due inquiry that such 
   contract or agreement had been en­tered into in bad faith and is detrimental 
   to the interests of the industrial concern, make an order cancelling or 
   varying (either unconditionally or subject to such conditions as it may 
   think fit to impose) that contract or agreement and the contract or 
   agreement shall have effect accordingly.]
  




</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><footcitenum>86</footcitenum>[<number>32D</number> No right to compensation for termination of 
contract of managing agent, managing director, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding any­thing to the contrary 
contained in any contract or in any law for the time being in force, no managing 
agent, managing director or any other director or a manager or any person in 
charge of man­agement of an industrial concern shall be entitled to any 
compen­sation for the loss of office or for the premature termination under 
this Act of any contract of management entered into by him with such 
concern.
 </section><section><number>2</number> 
Nothing contained in sub-section (1) shall affect the right of any such managing 
agent or managing director, or any other director or manager or any such person 
in charge of management to recover from the industrial concern, moneys 
recoverable otherwise than by way of such compensation.]
  


</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><footcitenum>87</footcitenum>[<number>32D</number> No right to compensation for termination of 
contract of managing agent, managing director, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding any­thing to the contrary 
contained in any contract or in any law for the time being in force, no managing 
agent, managing director or any other director or a manager or any person in 
charge of man­agement of an industrial concern shall be entitled to any 
compen­sation for the loss of office or for the premature termination under 
this Act of any contract of management entered into by him with such 
concern.
 </section><section><number>2</number> 
Nothing contained in sub-section (1) shall affect the right of any such managing 
agent or managing director, or any other director or manager or any such person 
in charge of management to recover from the industrial concern, moneys 
recoverable otherwise than by way of such compensation.]
  


</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><footcitenum>88</footcitenum>[<number>32E</number> Application of Act 1 of 1956.—
<section><number>1</number> Where the management of an industrial concern, 
being a company as defined in the Compa­nies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), is taken 
over by the Financial Corporation, then, notwithstanding anything contained in 
the said Act or in the memorandum or articles of association of such 
concern,—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> it shall not be 
lawful for the shareholders of such concern or any other person to nominate or 
appoint any person to be a director of the concern;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> no resolution passed 
at any meeting of the shareholders of such concern shall be given effect to 
unless approved by the Financial Corporation;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number> no proceeding for the 
winding up of such concern or for the appointment of receiver in respect thereof 
shall lie in any court, except with the consent of the Financial 
Corporation.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> 
Subject to the provisions contained in sub-section (1) and to the other 
provisions contained in this Act and subject to such other exceptions, 
restrictions and limitations, if any, as the Central Government in consultation 
with the State Government, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify in 
this behalf, the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) shall continue to apply to such 
concern in the same manner as it applied thereto before the issue of the 
notified order under section 32A.]
  


</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><footcitenum>89</footcitenum>[<number>32F</number> 
   Restriction on filing of suits for dissolution, etc., of an 
   industrial concern not being a company when its management is taken over.—
<section><number>1</number> 
   Where the management of an industrial concern not being a company as defined 
   in the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) is taken over by the Financial 
   Corporation, no suit or proceedings for dissolution or for partition shall, 
   insofar as it relates to that industrial concern, lie in any court or before 
   any trib­unal or other authority except with the consent of the Financial 
   Corporation.
 </section><section><number>2</number> No proceeding for the 
   appointment of any official assignee or receiver in relation to any 
   industrial concern the management of which has been taken over by the 
   Financial Corporation shall lie in any court except with consent of the 
   Financial Corporation.]
  




</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>90</footcitenum>[<number>32G</number> Recovery of amounts 
   due to the Financial Corporation as an arrear of land revenue.—Where 
   any amount is due to the Financial Corporation in respect of any 
   accommodation granted by it to any industrial concern, the Financial 
   Corporation or any person authorised by it in writing in this behalf, may, 
   without preju­dice to any other mode of recovery, make an application to the 
   State Government for the recovery of the amount due to it, and if the State 
   Government or such authority, as that Government may specify in this behalf, 
   is satisfied, after following such proce­dure as may be prescribed, that any 
   amount is so due, it may issue a certificate for that amount to the 
   Collector, and the Collector shall proceed to recover that amount in the 
   same manner as an arrear of land revenue.]
  




</article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><number>33</number> Funds of the 
   Financial Corporation.—
<section><number>1</number> Every 
   Financial Corporation shall have its own fund, and all receipts of the 
   Financial Corporation shall be carried thereto and all payments by the 
   Corporation shall be made therefrom.
 </section><section><number>2</number> All moneys belonging to 
   the fund shall be deposited in the Reserve Bank <footcitenum>91</footcitenum>[or 
   the State Bank of India or a subsidiary bank as defined in the State Bank of 
   India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, 1959 (38 of 1959)] <footcitenum>92</footcitenum>[or 
   in any of the banks specified in column 2 of the First Schedule to the 
   Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings) Act, 1970 (5 of 
   1970) <footcitenum>93</footcitenum>[or 
   any of the banks specified in column 2 of the First Schedule to the Banking 
   Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings) Act, 1980 (40 of 1980)]
   <footcitenum>94</footcitenum>[or, 
   in consultation with the Reserve Bank, in a scheduled bank or a State 
   Co-operative Bank].
  







</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>95</footcitenum>[<number>34</number> Investment of funds.—The 
   Financial Corporation may invest its funds in accordance with applicable 
   guidelines and prudential norms as may be prescribed and in such securities 
   as the Board may decide from time to time.]
  




</article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><number>35</number> Disposal of profits.—
<section><number>1</number> 
   The Financial Corporation shall establish a reserve fund.
 </section><section><number>2</number> After making provision 
   for bad and doubtful debts, deprecia­tion of assets and all other matters 
   which are usually provided for by banking companies, the Financial 
   Corporation may out of its net annual profits declare a dividend:
 <footcitenum>96</footcitenum>[***]
 <footcitenum>97</footcitenum>[***]
  





</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>98</footcitenum>[<number>35A</number> Special reserve fund.—
<section><number>1</number> 
   the Financial Corporation may establish a special reserve fund, to which 
   shall be transferred such portion of the dividends accruing to the State 
   Government Development Bank and the Small Industries Bank on the shares of 
   the Financial Coporation as may be fixed by agreement between the State 
   Government, Development Bank and the Small Industries Bank:
 Provided that after the 
   notified date this sub-section shall have effect as if for the words "the 
   State Government, the Development Bank and the Small Industries Bank", the 
   words "the State Government and the Small Industries Bank" have been 
   substituted except as regards all dividends accruing in respect of any 
   completed accounting period prior to the notified date.
 </section><section><number>2</number> No shareholder of the 
   Financial Corporation, other than the State Government or the Small 
   Industries Bank, shall have any claim to the special reserve fund.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The amount standing to 
   the credit of the special reserve fund may be utilised by the Financial 
   Coporation for only such purposes as are approved by the State Government 
   and the Small Industries Bank.]
  




</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><number>36</number> General meetings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
   A general meeting (hereinafter re­ferred to as the annual general meeting) 
   shall be held annually at a place in the State where there is an office of 
   the Financial Corporation within <footcitenum>99</footcitenum>[four 
   months] from the date on which the annual accounts of the Financial 
   Corporation are closed, and a general meeting may be convened by the Board 
   at any other time.
 </section><section><footcitenum>100</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> 
   The shareholders present at the annual general meeting shall be entitled to 
   discuss and adopt—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  the balance-sheet and profit and loss 
   account of the Financial Corporation made up to the date on which its 
   accounts are closed and balanced;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  the report of working of the Financial 
   Corporation for the period covered by the accounts;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  the auditor's report on the balance-sheet 
   and accounts; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  proposals for declaration of dividend and 
   capitalisation of reserves.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> The shareholders present 
   at an annual general meeting may also discuss any other matter to be 
   transacted at such meetings in accordance with the provisions of this Act.]
  





</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><number>37</number> Audit.—<footcitenum>101</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number> 
   The accounts of the Financial Corporation shall be audited by auditors duly 
   qualified to act as the auditors under sub-section (1) of section 226 of the 
   Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), who shall be appointed by the Financial 
   Corporation in general meeting of shareholders out of the panel of auditors 
   approved by the Reserve Bank of India for such terms and on such 
   remuneration as the Reserve Bank may fix.]
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every auditor shall be 
   supplied with a copy of the annual balance-sheet of the Financial 
   Corporation, and it shall be his duty to examine it, together with the 
   accounts and vouchers relating thereto, and every auditor shall have a list 
   delivered to him of all books kept by the Financial Corporation and shall at 
   all reasonable times have access to the books, accounts and other documents 
   of the Financial Corporation and may in relation to such accounts examine 
   any director or officer of the Financial Corporation.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The auditors shall make 
   a report to the shareholders upon the annual balance-sheet and accounts, and 
   in every such report they shall state whether in their opinion the 
   balance-sheet is a full and fair balance-sheet containing all necessary 
   particulars and properly drawn up so as to exhibit a true and correct view 
   of the state of affairs of the Financial Corporation, and in case they had 
   called for any explanation or information from the Board, whether it has 
   been given and whether it is satisfactory.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The State Government 
   may, in consultation with the Comptroll­er and Auditor-General of India, at 
   any time issue directions to the auditors requiring them to report to it 
   upon the adequacy of measures taken by the Financial Corporation for the 
   protection of its shareholders and creditors or upon the sufficiency of 
   their procedure in auditing the affairs of the Financial Corporation and may 
   enlarge or extend the scope of the audit or direct that a different 
   procedure in audit be adopted, or direct that any other examination be made 
   by the auditors, if in its opinion public interest so requires.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Financial 
   Corporation shall send a copy of every report of the auditors to the 
   Comptroller and Auditor-General of India at least one month before it is 
   placed before the shareholders.
 </section><section><number>6</number> Notwithstanding anything 
   contained in the preceding sub-sections, the Comptroller and Auditor-General 
   of India may, either of his own motion or on a request received in this 
   behalf from a State Government, undertake such audit and at such times as he 
   may consider necessary:
 
<footcitenum>102</footcitenum>[***]
 </section><section><number>7</number> Every audit report under 
   sub-section (6) shall be forwarded to the State Government and the 
   Government shall cause the same to be laid before the Legislature of the 
   State.
  





</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>103</footcitenum>[<number>37A</number> Inspection.—
<section><number>1</number> 
   The [Small 
   Industries Bank] at any time may, with the approval of the Central 
   Government, and on being direct­ed so to do by that Government shall cause 
   an inspection to be made by one or more of its officers of the working of 
   any Finan­cial Corporation and its books and accounts; and the <footcitenum>104</footcitenum>[Small Industries Bank] shall 
   send the report of such inspection to the Cen­tral Government and to the 
   State Government and shall supply a copy thereof to the Financial 
   Corporation.
 </section><section><number>2</number> It shall be the duty of 
   every director or every officer of the Financial Corporation to produce to 
   any officer making an inspection under sub-section (1) all such books, 
   accounts and other documents in his custody or power and to furnish him with 
   any statement and information relating to the affairs of the Financial 
   Corporation as the said officer may require of him within such time as the 
   said officer may specify.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Notwithstanding anything 
   contained in the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872) or in any other law 
   for the time being in force, no court, tribunal or other authority shall 
   have power to require the <footcitenum>104</footcitenum>[Small 
   Industries Bank] or any of its officers to produce before such court, 
   tribunal or other authority the report of the inspection made by it under 
   sub-section (1) or any copy thereof.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The State Government 
   may, after considering any report sent to it under sub-section (1), give 
   such instructions to the Board as it considers necessary and it shall be the 
   duty of the Board to comply with such instructions.]
  





</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><number>38</number> Returns.—<footcitenum>105</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number> 
   The Financial Corporation shall furnish to the State Government, the 
<footcitenum>106</footcitenum>[Small 
   Industries Bank] and the Reserve Bank such statements and returns in such 
   form as the State Government, the <footcitenum>106</footcitenum>[Small 
   Industries Bank] or the Reserve Bank may require from time to time.]
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Financial 
   Corporation shall furnish <footcitenum>107</footcitenum>[to 
   the State Gov­ernment, the <footcitenum>106</footcitenum>[Small 
   Industries Bank] and the Reserve Bank] within <footcitenum>108</footcitenum>[four 
   months] of the close of each financial year a statement in the prescribed 
   form of its assets and liabilities as at the close of that year, together 
   with a profit and loss account for the year, the auditors’ report and a 
   report of the working of the Financial Corporation during the year and 
   copies of the said statement, account and reports shall be published in the 
   Official Gazette and shall also be laid before the Legislature of the State.
  






</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><number>39</number> Power to give 
   instructions to Financial Corporation on ques­tions of policy.—
<section><number>1</number> 
   In the discharge of its functions, the Board shall be guided by such 
   instructions on questions of policy as may be given to it by the State 
   Government <footcitenum>109</footcitenum>[in consultation 
   with <footcitenum>110</footcitenum>[and after obtaining 
   the advice of,] the <footcitenum>111</footcitenum>[Small 
   Industries Bank]].
 </section><section><number>2</number> If any dispute arises 
   between the State Government and the Board as to whether a question is or is 
   not a question of policy, the decision of the State Government shall be 
   final.
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>112</footcitenum>[<number>2A</number> Nothing contained in 
   sub-section (1) and sub-section (2) shall apply in a case where a State 
   Government holds less than fifty-one per cent. of the equity shares in the 
   Financial Corporation.
 </section><section><number>2B</number> Notwithstanding the 
   equity share holding of a Financial Corporation by a State Government, the 
   State Government may advise the Financial Corporations on the matters of 
   policy.]
 </section><section><number>3</number> If the Board fails to 
   carry out the instructions on the question of policy laid down by the State 
   Government <footcitenum>109</footcitenum>[under 
   sub-section (1) of this section or the instructions given to the Board under 
   sub-section (4) of section 37A], the State Government shall have the power 
   to supersede the Board and appoint a new Board in its place to function 
   until a properly constituted Board is set up, and the decision of the State 
   Government as to the grounds for superseding the Board shall not be 
   questioned in any court.
  







</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article>
<number>40</number> Declaration of fidelity and secrecy.—<footcitenum>113</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number> 
   The Financial Corporation shall not, except as otherwise required by this 
   Act or any other law for the time being in force, divulge any infor­mation 
   relating to, or to the affairs of, its constituents except in circumstances 
   in which it is, in accordance with the law or practice and usage, customary 
   among bankers, necessary or appro­priate for the Financial Corporation to 
   divulge such information.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Financial Corporation may, for the 
   purpose of efficient discharge of its functions under this Act, collect 
   from, or furnish to—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> the Central 
   Government;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> the State Bank 
   of India constituted under section 3 of the State Bank of India Act, 1955 
   (23 of 1955), any subsidiary bank within the meaning of the State Bank of 
   India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, 1959 (38 of 1959), any corresponding new bank 
   constituted under section 3 of the Banking Companies (Acquisition and 
   Trans­fer of Undertakings) Act, 1970 (5 of 1970) or under section 3 of the 
   Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings) Act, 1980 (40 
   of 1980) any other scheduled bank, any <footcitenum>114</footcitenum>[State 
   Co-operative Bank, the Small Industries Bank or the Development Bank],
 such credit information or other 
   information as it may consider useful for the purpose, in such manner and at 
   such time as it may think fit.
 
Explanation.—For 
   the purposes of this sub-section, the expression “credit information” shall 
   have the same meaning as in clause (c) of section 45A of the Reserve Bank of 
   India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934) subject to the modification that the banking 
   company referred to therein shall mean a bank referred to in clause (b) of 
   this sub-section.]
 </subsection></section><section><footcitenum>115</footcitenum>[<number>3</number>] 
   Every director, auditor, officer or other employee of the Financial 
   Corporation shall, before entering upon his duties, make a declaration of 
   fidelity and secrecy in the form set out in the Schedule.
 </section><section><footcitenum>116</footcitenum>[<number>4</number> 
   Nothing contained in this section shall apply to the credit information 
   disclosed under the Credit Information Companies (Regulation) Act, 2005.]
  







</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article>
<number>41</number> Indemnity of directors.—
<section><number>1</number> 
   Every director shall be indemni­fied by the Financial Corporation against 
   all losses and expenses incurred by him in the discharge of his duties 
   except such as are caused by his own wilful act or default.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A director shall not be responsible for 
   any other director or for any officer or other employee of the Financial 
   Corporation or for any loss or expenses resulting to the Financial 
   Corporation by the insufficiency or deficiency of value of or title to any 
   property or security acquired or taken on behalf of the Financial 
   Corporation or by the wrongful act of any person under obligation to the 
   financial corporation or by anything done in good faith in the execution of 
   the duties of his office or in relation thereto.
  

</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><footcitenum>117</footcitenum>[<number>41A</number> 
Protection of action taken by persons appointed under section 27 or section 
32A.—No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any 
person appointed as director, administrator, managing agent or manager by the 
Financial Corpo­ration in pursuance of section 27 or section 32A for 
anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done by him as such 
director, administrator, managing agent or manager.]
  


</article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><footcitenum>118</footcitenum>[<number>41B</number> 
   Nomination in respect of deposits, bonds, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
   Notwitstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being in 
   force, where a nomination in respect of any deposits, bonds or other 
   securities is made in the prescribed manner, the amount due on such 
   deposits, bonds or securities shall, on the death of the depsoitor or holder 
   thereof, vest in, and be payable to, the nominee subject to any right, title 
   or interest of any other person to such deposits, bonds or securities.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any payment by the 
   Financial Corporation in accordance with the provisions of sub-section (1) 
   shall constitute a full discharge to the Financial Corporation of its 
   liability in respect of such depsoits, bonds or securities.]
  




</section></article> 
 
  
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><number>42</number> Offences.—
<section><number>1</number> 
   Whoever, in any bill of lading, warehouse re­ceipt or other document given 
   to the Financial Corporation, whereby security is given or is purported to 
   be given to the Financial Corporation for any accommodation granted by it 
   under this Act, wilfully makes any false statement or knowingly permits any 
   false statement to be made shall be punishable with imprison­ment for a term 
   which may extend to two years, or with fine which may extend to two thousand 
   rupees, or with both.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Whoever, without the 
   consent in writing of the Financial Corporation, uses the name of the 
   Financial Corporation in any prospectus or advertisement shall be punishable 
   with imprisonment which may extend to six months, or with fine which may 
   extend to one thousand rupees, or with both.
 </section><section><number>3</number> No court shall take 
   cognizance of any offence punishable under this Act otherwise than on a 
   complaint in writing signed by an officer of the Financial Corporation 
   authorised by the Board in this behalf.
  

</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><number>43</number> Provisions relating 
   to income-tax and super-tax.—For 
   the purposes of the <footcitenum>119</footcitenum>[Income-tax 
   Act, 1961(43 of 1961)], the Financial Corpora­tion shall be deemed to be a 
   company within the meaning of that Act and shall be liable to income-tax and 
   super-tax accordingly on its income, profits and gains:
 
   Provided that any sum paid by the State Government under the guarantee given 
   in pursuance of <footcitenum>120</footcitenum>[***] <footcitenum>121</footcitenum>[section 7 or section 8] shall 
   not be treated as the income, profits and gains of the Financial Corporation 
   and any interest on debentures, <footcitenum>122</footcitenum>[bonds 
   or deposits] paid by the Financial Corporation out of such sum shall not be 
   treated as expenditure incurred by it:
 
   Provided further that in the case of any shareholder such portion of a 
   dividend as has been paid out of any such sum advanced by the State 
   Government shall be deemed to be <footcitenum>123</footcitenum>[his] income from “interest on 
   securities” <footcitenum>124</footcitenum>[and the 
   income-tax shall be payable thereon as if it were the interest receivable on 
   any security of a State Government issued income-tax free] within the 
   meaning of section 8 of that Act.
  









</article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>125</footcitenum>[<number>43A</number> Delegation of powers.—The 
   Board may, by general or spe­cial order, delegate to the managing director 
   or to any other officer of the Financial Corporation <footcitenum>126</footcitenum>[or to any committee ap­pointed 
   under section 21] subject to such conditions and limita­tions, if any, as 
   may be specified in the order such of its powers and duties under this Act 
   as it may deem necessary.]
  





</article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>127</footcitenum>[<number>43B</number> Reports to the Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
   The minutes of every meeting of the committee appointed under section 21 
   shall, after confirma­tion thereof at the next meeting of the committee, be 
   laid before the Board at the next following meeting of the Board.
 
<footcitenum>128</footcitenum>[***]]
  





</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><number>44</number> 
Act 18 of 1891 to apply to the books of the Financial 
Corpo­ration.—The Financial 
Corporation shall be deemed to be a bank for the purposes of the Bankers' Books 
Evidence Act, 1891 (18 of 1891).</article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><number>45</number> Liquidation of 
   Financial Corporation.—No 
   provision of law relating to winding up of companies or corporations shall 
   apply to the Financial Corporation, and the Financial Corporation shall not 
   be placed in liquidation, save by order of the State Government and in such 
   manner as it may direct.
  

</article> 
 
 THE STATE 
FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><number>46</number> 
Power to apply Act to certain financial institutions in existence at 
commencement of Act.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
Government may by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that all or any 
of the provisions of this Act shall, subject to such exceptions and restrictions 
as may be specified, apply to <footcitenum>129</footcitenum>[any institution established by a State 
Government] which has for its object the financing of industrial concerns, and 
on the issue of such no­tification, the institution shall be deemed to be a 
Financial Corporation established by the State Government for the State within 
the meaning of this Act, and the provisions of this Act shall become applicable 
thereto according to the tenor of the notification:
 <footcitenum>130</footcitenum>[Provided that no notification shall 
be issued under this sub-section in respect of any institution unless a request 
is made in that behalf by the State Government concerned.]
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any 
notification issued under sub-section (1) may suspend the operation of any 
enactment applicable to any such institution immediately before the issue of the 
notification.
  


</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>131</footcitenum>[<number>46A</number> Extension of 
   jurisdiction of the Financial Corporation to other States by agreement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
   Where a Financial Corporation has been established for any State <footcitenum>132</footcitenum>[and one or more other States not 
   served in whole or in part by a Financial Corporation] desires that the 
   Financial Corporation <footcitenum>133</footcitenum>[should 
   serve the needs of those States or of any area therein], and the States, 
   after consulta­tion with the <footcitenum>134</footcitenum>[Small 
   Industries Bank], enter into an agreement which is published in the Official 
   Gazettes of each of those States, then the Financial Corporation shall, on 
   the issue of a notifica­tion in the Official Gazette by the Central 
   Government, serve the needs of those States <footcitenum>135</footcitenum>[or, as the case may be, of the 
   area therein] in terms of the agreement <footcitenum>135</footcitenum>[and 
   any Financial Corpora­tion or any State may enter into separate or 
   successive agree­ments as aforesaid with one another or with other Financial 
   Corporations of States and in relation to different areas of the States].
 </section><section><footcitenum>134</footcitenum>[<number>1A</number> 
   Any agreement entered into under sub-section (1) may be modified or 
   rescinded by mutual agreement between the parties thereto and every such 
   mutual agreement shall also provide for the apportionment of assets and 
   liabilities].
 </section><section><number>2</number> An inter-State agreement 
   among the participating States may, as far as may be, make all such 
   provisions as are referred to in sub-section (2) of section 3A.







</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951 
  
 <article><number>46B</number> 
Effect of Act on other laws.—The 
provision of this Act and of any rule or orders made thereunder shall have 
effect notwith­standing anything inconsistent therewith contained in any 
other law for the time being in force or in the memorandum or articles of 
association of an industrial concern or in any other instru­ment having 
effect by virtue of any law other than this Act, but save as aforesaid, the 
provisions of this Act shall be in addi­tion to, and not in derogation of, 
any other law for the time being applicable to an industrial 
concern.]
  </article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951 
  
 1[***]
 
 





 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><number>48</number> Power of Board to 
   make regulations.—
<section><number>1</number> The Board 
   may, after consultation with the <footcitenum>137</footcitenum>[Small 
   Industries Bank] and with the previous sanction of the State Government, 
   make regulations not inconsist­ent with this Act and the rules made 
   thereunder to provide for all matters for which provision is necessary or 
   expedient for the purpose of giving effect to the provisions of this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> In particular, and 
   without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such regulations 
   may provide for—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> the holding and conduct of elections under 
   this Act, includ­ing the final decision on doubts or disputes regarding the 
   valid­ity of elections; 
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> the manner in which, and the conditions 
   subject to which, the first allotment of the shares of the Financial 
   Corporation shall be made;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number> the manner in which, and the conditions 
   subject to which, the shares of the Financial Corporation may be held and 
   trans­ferred and generally all matters relating to the rights and duties of 
   shareholders;
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>138</footcitenum>[<number>ca</number>  the maintenance of 
   register of shareholders, particulars to be entered in such register, the 
   safeguards to be observed in the maintenance of register of shareholders on 
   computer floppies or diskettes, compact disk or any other electronic form 
   the inspection and closure of the register of shareholders and all other 
   matters connected therewith under section 6;
 </subsection><subsection>      <number>cb</number>  the manner of nomination of directors under 
   clause (d) of section 10;
 </subsection><subsection>      <number>cc</number>  the entrusting or delegation of duties to 
   the managing director by the Board under clause (c) of sub-section (1) of 
   section 17;
 </subsection><subsection>      <number>cd</number>  the functions of Executive Committee under 
   sub-section (2) of section 18;
 </subsection><subsection>      <number>ce</number>  the guidelines and prudential norms in 
   accordance with which investment may be made under section 34;
 </subsection><subsection>      <number>cf</number>  the manner in which nomination may be made 
   under section 41B; and
 </subsection><subsection>      <number>cg</number>  the investments (whether by way of deposits 
   in bank or otherwise) of the amounts which are not for the time being 
   required for transaction of business;]
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number> the manner in which general meetings shall be 
   convened, the procedure to be followed thereat and the manner in which 
   voting rights may be exercised;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number> the calling of meetings of the Board, and of 
   the Executive Committee, fees for attending meetings thereof and the conduct 
   of business thereat;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>f</number> the manner and terms of issue and repayment 
   of bonds and debentures by the Financial Corporation;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>g</number> the conditions which the Financial 
   Corporations may impose in granting loans or advances;
 <footcitenum>139</footcitenum>[***]
 <subsubsection>        <number>i</number> the forms of returns and statements required 
   under this Act;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>        <number>j</number> the duties and conduct of officers, other 
   employees, advis­ers and agents of the Financial Corporation;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>       <number>k</number> the establishment and maintenance of 
   provident or other benefit funds for employees of the Financial Corporation;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>        <number>l</number> the taking over of the management of any 
   industrial concern on a breach of its agreement with the Financial 
   Corporation;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>       <number>m</number> the appointment of <footcitenum>140</footcitenum>[committees] for the purposes of 
   this Act, <footcitenum>141</footcitenum>[fees for 
   attending meetings thereof and the conduct of business thereat]; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>       <number>n</number> generally, the efficient conduct of the 
   affairs of the Financial Corporation.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><footcitenum>142</footcitenum>[<number>o</number>  the form and manner in 
   which the balance-sheet and the accounts of the Financial Corporation shall 
   be prepared;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>       <number>p</number>  any other matter which is to be, or may be, 
   prescribed.]
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<footcitenum>143</footcitenum>[<number>3</number> All regulations made 
   under this section shall be published in the Official Gazette and any such 
   regulation shall have effect from such earlier or later date as may be 
   specified in the regu­lations.]










</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article><footcitenum>144</footcitenum>[<number>48A</number> 
   Laying of rules and regulations before State Legislature.—<footcitenum>145</footcitenum>[***] 
   and every regula­tion made under section 48 shall be laid, as soon as may be 
   after it is made, before the State Legislature.]
 






</article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>146</footcitenum>[<number>48B</number> Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
   The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make 
   rules for carrying out the provisions of this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> In particular, and 
   without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power such rules may 
   provide for the procedure for filing and hearing of appeals under 
   sub-section (5) of section 5.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every rule made under 
   this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each 
   House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty 
   days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive 
   sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the 
   session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making 
   any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
   be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or 
   be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification 
   or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
   previously done under that rule.]
 





</section></article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>147</footcitenum>[<number>49</number> Power to remove 
   difficulty.—If any difficulty 
   arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, as amended by the 
   Public Financial Institutions Laws (Amendment) Act, 1975 (52 of 1975), the 
   Central Government may, by order, do anything, not inconsistent with such 
   provisions, for the purpose of removing the difficulty:
 Provided that no such order 
   shall be made after the expiration of three years from the commencement of 
   the said Amendment Act.]
 





</article> 
 
 THE STATE 
   FINANCIAL CORPORATIONS ACT, 1951
  
 THE SCHEDULE
 [See
   section 40(3)]
 DECLARATION OF FIDELITY AND SECRECY
 I, ................., do hereby declare that I will 
   faithfully, truly and to the best of my skill and ability execute and 
   perform the duties required of me as a director, officer, employee or 
   auditor (as the case may be) of the Financial Corporation and which properly 
   relate to any office or position in the said Financial Corporation held by 
   me.
 I further declare that I will not communicate or allow to 
   be communicated to any person not legally entitled thereto any information 
   relating to the affairs of the Financial Corporation, nor will I allow any 
   such person to inspect or have access to any books or documents belonging to 
   or in the possession of the Financial Corporation and relating to the 
   business of the Finan­cial Corporation.
  
 Signed before me  
   Signature. 
 




<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>    The words “except the State of  Jammu
  and Kashmir ” omitted by Act 62 of 1956, sec. 2 and
Sch. (w.e.f.  1-11-1956 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>    Ins. by Act 77 of 1972, sec. 2 (w.e.f.  30-12-1972 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>    Explanation  renumbered as  Explanation
1  by Act 43 of 1985, sec. 2 (w.e.f.  21-8-1985 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>    Subs. by Act 56 of 1956, sec. 3, for
"acquire and to hold" (w.e.f.  1-10-1956 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>   Subs. by Act 52 of 1975, sec. 24, for 
"Reserve Bank" (w.e.f. 16-2-1976) and again subs. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 3, 
for   "Development Bank" (w.e.f. 
5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>    Subs. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 4, for
sub-sections (1), (2) and (3) (w.e.f.  5-9-2000 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>    Subs. by Act 43 of 1985, sec. 4, for
sub-section (5) (w.e.f.  21-8-1985 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>  Ins. by Act 77 of 1972, sec. 4 (w.e.f.
    30-12-1972 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>  Subs. by Act 52 of 1975, sec. 26, for sub-section 
   (1) (w.e.f.
    16-2-1976 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>  Subs. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 5, for "Development 
   Bank" (w.e.f.
    5-9-2000 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>  Subs. by Act 52 of 1975, sec. 26, for "Reserve 
   Bank" (w.e.f. 16-2-1976) and again subs. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 5, for 
   "Development Bank" (w.e.f. 5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>  The words "section 47 or" omitted by Act 39 of 
   2000, sec. 5 (w.e.f.
    5-9-2000 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>  Subs. by Act, 39 of 2000, sec. 5, for 
   "sub-section (1) of section 6" (w.e.f.
    5-9-2000 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>  Ins. by Act 52 of 1975, sec. 27 (w.e.f.
    16-2-1976 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>  Ins. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 6 (w.e.f.
    5-9-2000 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>  Ins. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 6 (w.e.f.
    5-9-2000 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number>  Ins. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 6 (w.e.f.
    5-9-2000 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number>  Ins. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number>  Ins. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number>  Ins. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number>  Subs. by Act, 39 of 2000, sec. 7, for section 5 (w.e.f. 
   5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number>  Subs. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 7, for section 6 (w.e.f 
   5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number>  Section 7 subs. by Act 6 of 1962, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 
   16-4-1962) and again subs. by Act. 39 of 2000, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number>  Section 8 subs. by Act 6 of 1962, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 
   16-4-1962) and again subs. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number>  Subs. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 7, for section 9 (w.e.f. 
   5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number>  Subs. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 7, for section 10 (w.e.f. 
   5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number>  Section 10A ins by Act 43 of 1985, sec. 10 (w.e.f. 
   21-8-1985), and omitted by Act 39 of 2000,</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>28</number>  Subs. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 9, for sections 11 
   and 12 (w.e.f. 5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>29</number>  Section 13 renumbered as sub-section (1) thereof 
   by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 10 (w.e.f. 5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>30</number>  Ins. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 10 (w.e.f. 
   5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>31</number>  Subs. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 11, for 
sub-sections (1)  and (1A) (w.e.f. 5-9-2000). Sub-section (1A) was ins. by 
Act 56 of 1956, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-10-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>32</number>  Subs. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 12, for section 15 
   (w.e.f. 5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>33</number>  Subs. by Act 6 of 1962, sec. 7, for section 16 (w.e.f. 
   16-4-1962).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>34</number>  Section 17 renumbered as sub-section (1) of that 
   section by Act 56 of 1956, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 1-10-1956) and subs. by Act 39 of 
   2000, sec. 13 (w.e.f. 5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>35</number> Ins. by Act 56 of 1956, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 1-10-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>36</number>  Ins. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 13 (w.e.f. 
   5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>37</number>  Subs. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 14, for section 18 
   (w.e.f. 5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>38</number>  Sub-section (3A) ins. by Act 56 of 1956, sec. 11 
   (w.e.f. 1-10-1956) and omitted by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 15 (w.e.f. 5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>39</number>  Sub-section (4) subs. by Act 6 of 1962, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 
   16-4-1962) and omitted by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 15 (w.e.f. 5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>40</number>  Ins. by Act 6 of 1962, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 16-4-1962).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>41</number>  The words ", not being the managing director" 
   omitted by Act 43 of 1985, sec. 12 (w.e.f. 21-8-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>42</number>  Subs. by Act 43 of 1985, sec. 13, for "shall be 
   laid" (w.e.f. 21-8-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>43</number>  Subs. by Act 43 of 1985, sec. 14, for "one or 
   more advisory committee or committees" (w.e.f. 21-8-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>44</number>  Subs. by Act 77 of 1972, sec. 13, for section 22 
   (w.e.f. 30-12-1972).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>45</number>  Proviso added by Act 77 of 1972, sec. 14 (w.e.f. 
   30-12-1972) and omitted by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 16 (w.e.f. 5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>46</number>  Subs. by Act 6 of 1962, sec. 10, for 
section 25 (w.e.f. 16-4-1962).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>47</number>  Subs. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 17, for 
sub-section (1) (w.e.f. 5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>48</number> Sub-section (2) of section 25 as it stood 
before its substitution by Act 39 of 2000 was omitted by Act 43 of 1985, sec. 15 
(w.e.f. 21-8-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>49</number> Subs. by Act 77 of 1972, sec. 15, for “and 
(c)” (w.e.f. 30-12-1972).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>50</number>  Subs. by Act 52 of 1975, sec. 35, for 
“Reserve Bank” (w.e.f. 16-2-1976) and again subs. by Act 39 of 2000 sec. 17, for 
"Development Bank" (w.e.f. 5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>51</number>  Ins. by Act 77 of 1972, sec. 15 (w.e.f. 
30-12-1972).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>52</number>  Ins. by Act 43 of 1985, sec. 16 (w.e.f. 
   21-8-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>53</number>  Ins. by Act, 39 of 2000, sec. 18 (w.e.f. 
   5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>54</number>  Section 26 subs. by Act 6 of 1962, sec. 11 (w.e.f. 
   16-4-1962) and again subs. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 19 (w.e.f. 5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>55</number>  Subs. by Act 77 of 1972, sec. 17, for sub-section 
   (2) (w.e.f. 30-12-1972).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>56</number>  Section 28 re-numbered as sub-section (1) thereof 
   by Act 77 of 1972, sec. 18  (w.e.f.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>57</number>  Subs. by Act 6 of 1962, sec. 13, for clauses (a) 
   and (b) (w.e.f. 16-4-1962).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>58</number>  Ins. by Act 77 of 1972, sec. 18 (w.e.f. 
   30-12-1972).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>59</number>  Clause (d) ins. by Act 77 of 1972, sec. 18 (w.e.f. 
   30-12-1972) and subs. by Act 39 of 2000,</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>60</number> Ins. by Act 77 of 1972, sec. 19 (w.e.f. 
   30-12-1972).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>61</number> Subs. by Act 77 of 1972, sec. 19, for “right to 
   take over the management of the industrial concern" (w.e.f. 30-12-1972).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>62</number>  Subs. by Act 56 of 1956, sec. 14, for “right to 
   sell” (w.e.f. 1-10-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>63</number>  The words “of sale and realisation” omitted by 
   Act 56 of 1956, sec.14 (w.e.f. 1-10-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>64</number>  Subs. by Act 56 of 1956, sec. 14, for “as if the 
   sale” (w.e.f. 1-10-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>65</number>  Subs. by Act 56 of 1956, sec. 14, for sub-section 
   (4) (w.e.f. 1-10-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>66</number>  Subs. by Act 77 of 1972, sec. 19, for certain 
   words (w.e.f. 30-12-1972).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>67</number>  Subs. by Act 6 of 1962, sec. 14, for “charges and 
   expenses properly incurred” (w.e.f.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>68</number>  Subs by Act 77 of 1972, sec. 19, for "as 
   incidental to such management, or transfer and realisation".</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>69</number>  The words “from such management, or transfer and 
   realisa­tion” omitted by Act 77 of 1972, sec. 19 (w.e.f. 30-12-1972).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>70</number>  Subs. by Act 6 of 1962, sec. 14, for “the owner 
   of the con­cern” (w.e.f. 16-4-1962).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>71</number> Ins. by Act 77 of 1972, sec. 20 (w.e.f. 
   30-12-1972).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>72</number> Ins. by Act 56 of 1956, sec. 15 (w.e.f 1-10-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>73</number> Subs. by Act 56 of 1956, sec. 15, for 
   “Corporation” (w.e.f. 1-10-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>74</number> Ins. by Act 43 of 1985, sec. 19 (w.e.f 21-8-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>75</number> Ins. by Act 43 of 1985, sec. 20 (w.e.f. 
   21-8-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>76</number> Subs. by Act 43 of 1985, sec. 20, for sub-section 
   (4) (w.e.f. 21-8-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>77</number> The word “or” omitted by Act 43 of 1985, sec. 20 (w.e.f. 
   21-8-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>78</number> Ins. by Act 56 of 1956, sec. 16 (w.e.f. 
   1-10-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>79</number> Subs. by Act 43 of 1985, sec. 20, for “under 
   sub-section (5)” (w.e.f. 21-8-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>80</number> Subs. by Act 6 of 1962, sec. 15, for sub-section 
   (11) (w.e.f. 16-4-1962).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>81</number> Ins. by Act 77 of 1972, sec. 21 (w.e.f. 
   30-12-1972).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>82</number> Ins. by Act 56 of 1956, sec. 17 (w.e.f. 
   1-10-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>83</number> Ins. by Act 6 of 1962, sec. 16 (w.e.f. 16-4-1962).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>84</number> Ins. by Act 56 of 1956, sec. 17 (w.e.f. 
   1-10-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>85</number>  Ins. by Act 56 of 1956, sec. 17 (w.e.f. 
   1-10-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>86</number>  Ins. by Act 56 of 1956, sec. 17 (w.e.f. 
1-10-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>87</number>  Ins. by Act 56 of 1956, sec. 17 (w.e.f. 
1-10-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>88</number>  Ins. by Act 56 of 1956, sec. 17 (w.e.f. 
1-10-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>89</number>  Ins. by Act 56 of 1956, sec. 17 (w.e.f. 
   1-10-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>90</number> Ins. by Act 43 of 1985, sec. 21 (w.e.f. 
   21-8-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>91</number> Subs. by Act 6 of 1962, sec. 17, for “or with any 
   agency of the Reserve Bank other than a Government treasury” (w.e.f. 
   16-4-1962).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>92</number> Ins. by Act 77 of 1972, sec. 22 (w.e.f 
   30-12-1972).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>93</number> Ins. by Act 43 of 1985, sec. 22 (w.e.f. 
   21-8-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>94</number> Subs. by Act 56 of 1956, sec. 18, for “or in a 
   scheduled bank in consultation with the Reserve Bank” (w.e.f. 1-10-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>95</number> Subs. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 21, for section 34 (w.e.f. 
   5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>96</number>  The proviso omitted by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 22 (w.e.f. 
   5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>97</number> Sub-section (3) omitted by Act 77 of 1972, sec. 23 
   (w.e.f. 30-12-1972).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>98</number> Section 35A ins. by Act 6 of 1962, sec. 19 (w.e.f. 
   16-4-1962) and subs. by Act 39 of 2000,</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>99</number> Subs. by Act 43 of 1985, sec. 24, for “three 
   months” (w.e.f. 21-8-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>100</number>  Subs. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 24, for sub-section 
   (2) (w.e.f. 5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>101</number>  Sub-section (1) subs. by Act 77 of 1972, sec. 25 (w.e.f. 
   3-12-1972) and again subs. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 25 (w.e.f. 5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>102</number> Proviso omitted by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 25 (w.e.f. 
   5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>103</number> Ins. by Act 56 of 1956, sec. 21 (w.e.f. 
   1-10-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>104</number> Subs. by Act 52 of 1975, sec. 37, for “Reserve 
   Bank” (w.e.f. 16-2-1976) and again subs. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 26, for 
   "Development Bank" (w.e.f. 5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>105</number>  Subs by Act 43 of 1985, sec. 25, for sub-sections 
   (1) and (2) (w.e.f. 21-8-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>106</number>  Subs. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 27, for 
   "Development Bank" (w.e.f. 5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>107</number>  Subs. by Act 52 of 1975, sec. 38, for "to the 
   State Government and to the Reserve Bank" (w.e.f. 16-2-1976).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>108</number>  Subs. by Act 56 of 1956, sec. 22, for "three 
   months" (w.e.f. 1-10-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>109</number>  Ins. by Act 56 of 1956, sec. 23 (w.e.f. 
   1-10-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>110</number>  Ins. by Act 77 of 1972, sec. 26 (w.e.f. 
   30-12-1972).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>111</number>  Subs. by Act 52 of 1975, sec. 37, for "Reserve 
   Bank" (w.e.f. 16-2-1976) and again subs by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 28, for 
   "Development Bank" (w.e.f. 5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>112</number>  Ins. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 28 (w.e.f. 
   5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>113</number>  Ins. by Act 48 of 1983, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 
   30-12-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>114</number>  Subs. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 29, for "State 
   Co-operative Bank or the Development Bank" (w.e.f. 5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>115</number> Section 40 renumbered as sub-section (3) thereof 
   by Act 48 of 1983, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 30-12-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>116</number>  Ins. by Act 30 of 2005, sec. 34 and Sch., Pt. 
   III.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>117</number> Ins. by Act 6 of 1962, sec. 21 (w.e.f. 
16-4-1962).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>118</number>  Ins. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 30 (w.e.f. 
   5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>119</number> Subs. by Act 43 of 1985, sec. 26, for “Indian 
   Income-tax Act, 1922 (11 of 1922)” (w.e.f. 21-8-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>120</number>  The words "Section 6 or" omitted by Act 39 of 
   2000, sec. 31 (w.e.f. 5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>121</number> Subs. by Act 6 of 1962, sec. 22, for certain 
   words  (w.e.f. 16-4-1962).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>122</number> Subs. by Act 6 of 1962, sec. 22, for “or bonds” (w.e.f.  
   16-4-1962).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>123</number> Subs. by Act 48 of 1952, sec. 3 and Sch. II, for 
   “its” (w.e.f. 2-8-1952).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>124</number> Subs. by Act 6 of 1962, sec. 22, for “declared to 
   be income-tax free” (w.e.f. 16-4-1962).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>125</number> Ins. by Act 6 of 1962, sec. 23 (w.e.f. 16-4-1962).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>126</number> Ins. by Act 43 of 1985, sec. 27 (w.e.f. 
   21-8-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>127</number> Ins. by Act 43 of 1985, sec. 28 (w.e.f. 
   21-8-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>128</number>  Sub-section (2) omitted by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 
   32 (w.e.f. 5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>129</number>  Subs. by Act 43 of 1985, sec. 29, for 
"any institution in existence at the commencement of this Act"  
(w.e.f.  21-8-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>130</number> Ins. by Act 43 of 1985, sec. 29 (w.e.f. 
21-8-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>131</number> Ins. by Act 56 of 1956, sec. 24 (w.e.f. 
   1-10-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>132</number> Subs. by Act 77 of 1972, sec. 27, for “and any 
   other State” (w.e.f. 30-12-1972).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>133</number> Subs. by Act 77 of 1972, sec. 27, for “should 
   serve its needs” (w.e.f. 30-12-1972).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>134</number> Subs. by Act 52 of 1975, sec. 37, for "Reserve 
   Bank" (w.e.f. 16-2-1976) and again subs. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 33, for 
   "Development Bank" (w.e.f. 5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>135</number> Ins. by Act 77 of 1972, sec. 27 (w.e.f. 
   30-12-1972).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>136</number>     
   Section 47 omitted by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 34 (w.e.f. 5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>137</number> Subs. by Act 52 of 1975, sec. 37, for “Reserve 
   Bank” (w.e.f. 16-2-1976) and again subs by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 35, for 
   "Development Bank" (w.e.f. 5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>138</number>  Ins. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 35 (w.e.f. 
   5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>139</number> Clause (h) omitted by Act 43 of 1985, sec. 30 (w.e.f. 
   21-8-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>140</number> Subs. by Act 43 of 1985, sec. 30, for  "advisory 
   committees for techincal and other advice"  (w.e.f. 21-8-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>141</number> Ins. by Act 56 of 1956, sec. 25 (w.e.f. 
   1-10-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>142</number>  Ins. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 35 (w.e.f. 
   5-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>143</number> Subs. by Act 77 of 1972, sec. 28, for sub-section 
   (3) (with retrospective effect).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>144</number> Ins. by Act 4 of 1986, sec. 2 and Sch. (w.e.f. 
   15-5-1986).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>145</number>  The words "Every rule made under section 47 and 
   "omitted by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 36</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>146</number>  Ins. by Act 39 of 2000, sec. 37 (w.e.f.
    5-9-2000 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>147</number> Ins. by Act 52 of 1975, sec. 39 (w.e.f.
    16-2-1976 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>148</number> Subs. by Act 48 of 1983, sec. 6, for "(See 
   section 40)" (w.e.f. 30-12-1983).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>