<act><tid>1231980</tid>
<title>THE JAWAHARLAL NEHRU UNIVERSITY ACT, <year>1966</year></title>

ACT NO. 53 OF <year>1966</year>
[ 22nd December, <year>1966</year>].

An Act to establish and incorporate a university in Delhi.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Seventeenth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-





<article><tid>1885962</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>232457</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Jawaharlal Nehru University Act, <year>1966</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>694514</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1470663</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>744858</tid>
<number>a</number>" College" means a college maintained by the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1893410</tid>
<number>b</number>" Hall" means a unit of residence, by whatever name 
called, for students of the University provided, 
maintained or recognised by it;

</section>

<section><tid>1390956</tid>
<number>c</number>" recognised institution" means an institution of higher 
learning maintained or recognised by, or associated 
with, the University;

</section>

<section><tid>303421</tid>
<number>d</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by Statutes, Ordinances 
or Regulations;

</section>

<section><tid>1408007</tid>
<number>e</number>" Statutes"," Ordnances" and" Regulations" mean, 
respectively, the Statutes, Ordinances and Regulations 
of the University made under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1588282</tid>
<number>f</number>" University" means the Jawaharlal Nehru University.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>250720</tid>
<number> 3</number> The University.
<section><tid>1885959</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be constituted in the Union  
territory of Delhi a University by the name of" Jawaharlal Nehru 
University".

</section>

<section><tid>1710858</tid>
<number>2</number>The first Chancellor and the first Vice- Chancellor of the 
University and the first members of the Court, the Executive Council 
and the Academic Council and all persons who may hereafter become such 
officers of members so long as they continue to hold such office or 
membership are hereby constituted a body corporate by the name of 
" Jawaharlal Nehru University".

</section>

<section><tid>1334047</tid>
<number>3</number>The University shall have perpetual succession and a common 
seal, and shall sue and be sued by the said name.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>184</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 22nd April, <year>1969</year>: See Notification No. S. O. 1525, dated the 21st 
April, <year>1969</year>, Gazette of India, <year>1969</year>, Pt. II, Sec. 3 (ii), p. 1443.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1162904</tid>
<number>4</number>Objects. The objects of the University shall be to disseminate 
and advance knowledge, wisdom and understanding by teaching and 
research and by the example and influence of its corporate life and in 
particular the objects set out in the First Schedule.


</article>



<article><tid>1938235</tid>
<number> 5</number> Powers of the University. The University shall have the 
following powers, namely:-
<section><tid>1509514</tid>
<number>1</number>to provide for instruction including the method of 
correspondence courses in such branches of learning as 
the University may from time to time determine, and to 
make provision for research and for the advancement and 
dissemination of knowledge;

</section>

<section><tid>1940571</tid>
<number>2</number>to establish within the Union territory of Delhi or 
outside that territory such Special Centres and 
Specialised Laboratories and such other units for 
research and instruction as are necessary for the 
furtherance of its objects;

</section>

<section><tid>1333497</tid>
<number>3</number>to organise and to undertake extra- mural teaching and 
extension services;

</section>

<section><tid>1239450</tid>
<number>4</number>to hold examinations and grant diplomas or certificates 
to, and confer degrees and other academic distinctions 
on, persons and to withdraw any such diplomas, 
certificates, degrees or other academic distinctions 
for good and sufficient cause;

</section>

<section><tid>1213686</tid>
<number>5</number>to confer honorary degrees or other academic 
distinctions in the manner laid down in the Statutes;

</section>

<section><tid>1999293</tid>
<number>6</number>to create such teaching, administrative and other posts 
as the University may deem necessary, from time to 
time, and to make appointments thereto;

</section>

<section><tid>1608267</tid>
<number>7</number>to appoint or recognise persons as Professors, Readers 
or Lecturers or otherwise as teachers of the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>1162523</tid>
<number>8</number>to institute and award Fellowships, Scholarships, 
Exhibitions and prizes;

</section>

<section><tid>730752</tid>
<number>9</number>to establish and maintain Colleges and Halls, to 
recognise, guide, supervise and control Halls not 
maintained by the University and other accommodation 
for students, and to withdraw any such recognition;

</section>

<section><tid>494461</tid>
<number>10</number>to regulate and enforce discipline among students and 
employees of the University and to take such 
disciplinary measures in this regard as may be deemed 
necessary;

</section>

<section><tid>1947791</tid>
<number>11</number>to make arrangements for promoting health and general 
welfare of students and employees of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>25463</tid>
<number>12</number>to determine and provide for examinations for admission 
into the University;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>185</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1028652</tid>
<number>13</number>to recognise for any purpose, either in whole or in 
part, any institution or members or students thereof on 
such terms and conditions as may, from time to time, be 
prescribed and to withdraw such recognition;

</section>

<section><tid>263839</tid>
<number>14</number>to co- operate with any other University, authority or 
association or any other public or private body having 
in view the promotion of purposes and objects similar 
to those of the University for such purposes as may be 
agreed upon, on such terms and conditions as may, from 
time to time, be prescribed;

</section>

<section><tid>654903</tid>
<number>15</number>to enter into any agreement for the incorporation in 
the University of any other institution and for taking 
over its rights, properties and liabilities and for any 
other purpose not repugnant to this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1848053</tid>
<number>16</number>to demand and receive payment of such fees and other 
charges as may be prescribed, from time to time;

</section>

<section><tid>879231</tid>
<number>17</number>to receive donations and to acquire, hold, manage and 
dispose of any property movable or immovable, including 
trust or endowed property within or outside the Union 
territory of Delhi, for the purposes or objects of the 
University, and to invest funds in such manner as the 
University thinks fit;

</section>

<section><tid>1724669</tid>
<number>18</number>to make provision for research and advisory services; 
and for that purpose to enter into such arrangements 
with other institutions or bodies as the University may 
deem necessary;

</section>

<section><tid>1604855</tid>
<number>19</number>to provide for the printing, reproduction and 
publication of research and other work which may be 
issued by the University:

</section>

<section><tid>231878</tid>
<number>20</number>to borrow, with the approval of the Central Government, 
on the security of the University property, money for 
the purposes of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1099000</tid>
<number>21</number>to do all such things as may be necessary, incidental 
or conducive to the attainment of all or any of the 
objects of the University.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>797102</tid>
<number> 6</number> Jurisdiction of the University.
<section><tid>1920973</tid>
<number>1</number>The jurisdiction of the  
University shall extend to all Colleges and recognised institutions.

</section>

<section><tid>1174809</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in clause (13) of section 
5, the Jawaharlal Nehru University shall not grant recognition, either 
in whole or in part, to any institution which has already been 
recognised by the University of Delhi unless the Central Government,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>186</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

after consultation with the University of Delhi, authorises the 
Jawaharlal Nehru University to do so.


</section>

<section><tid>614830</tid>
<number>3</number>On and from the date of the recognition either in whole or in 
part of an institution by the Jawaharlal Nehru University under sub- 
section (2), the University of Delhi shall to the extent of such 
recognition cease to have jurisdiction over that institution.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>793208</tid>
<number> 7</number> Powers and Jurisdiction in respect of institution or body 
outside the Union territory of Delhi. Notwithstanding anything 
contained in section 5,-
<section><tid>651066</tid>
<number>a</number>where any institution or body established outside the 
Union territory of Delhi seeks recognition from the 
University, or

</section>

<section><tid>632489</tid>
<number>b</number>where the University establishes and maintains any 
institution or body outside the Union territory of 
Delhi,
then the powers and jurisdiction of the University shall extend to 
such institution or body subject to-


<subsection><tid>380345</tid>
<number>i</number>the laws in force in the State within which, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1984607</tid>
<number>ii</number>the rules and regulations of the University within 
whose jurisdiction,
the said institution or body is situated.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1227643</tid>
<number> 8</number> Visitor.
<section><tid>1968874</tid>
<number>1</number>The President of India shall be the Visitor of  
the University.

</section>

<section><tid>124640</tid>
<number>2</number>The Visitor may, from time to time, appoint one or more 
persons to review the work and progress of the University and to 
submit a report thereon; and upon receipt of that report, the Visitor 
may, after obtaining the views of the Executive Council thereon, take 
such action and issue such directions as he considers necessary in 
respect of any of the matters dealt with in the report and the 
University shall be bound to comply with such directions.

</section>

<section><tid>1085568</tid>
<number>3</number>The Visitor shall also have the right to cause an inspection 
to be made by such person or persons as he may direct of the 
University, its buildings, laboratories and equipment and of any 
institution maintained by the University, and also of the 
examinations, teaching and other work conducted or done by the 
University and to cause an inquiry to be made in respect of any matter 
connected with the University.

</section>

<section><tid>186921</tid>
<number>4</number>The Visitor shall in every case give notice to the University 
of his intention to cause an inspection or inquiry to be made, and the 
University shall be entitled to appoint a representative who shall 
have the right to be present and be heard at such inspection or 
inquiry.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>187</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>72692</tid>
<number>5</number>The Visitor may address the Vice- Chancellor with reference to 
the result of such inspection and inquiry, and the Vice- Chancellor 
shall communicate to the Executive Council the views of the Visitor 
with such advice as the Visitor may offer upon the action to be taken 
thereon.

</section>

<section><tid>398770</tid>
<number>6</number>The Executive Council shall communicate through the Vice- 
Chancellor to the Visitor such action, if any, as it is proposed to 
take or has been taken upon the result of such inspection or inquiry.

</section>

<section><tid>184928</tid>
<number>7</number>Where the Executive Council does not, within a reasonable 
time, take action to the satisfaction of the Visitor, the Visitor may, 
after considering any explanation furnished or representation made by 
the Executive Council, issue such directions as he may think fit and 
the Executive Council shall be bound to comply with such directions.

</section>

<section><tid>307006</tid>
<number>8</number>The Visitor may be order in writing annul any proceeding of 
the University which is not in conformity with this Act, the Statutes 
or the Ordinances.

</section>

<section><tid>1795244</tid>
<number>9</number>The Visitor shall also have such other powers as may be 
prescribed by the Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1057066</tid>
<number> 9</number> Officers of the University.
<section><tid>1790672</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be a Chancellor  
appointed in the manner prescribed by the Statutes who shall be the 
Head of the University.

</section>

<section><tid>918749</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chancellor shall, if present, preside at convocation of 
the University for conferring degrees and all meetings of the Court.

</section>

<section><tid>349742</tid>
<number>3</number>There shall be a Vice- Chancellor appointed in the manner 
prescribed by the Statutes who shall be the principal executive and 
Academic Officer of the University and ex officio Chairman of the 
Executive Council, Academic Council and Finance Committee and he 
shall, in the absence of the Chancellor preside at any convocation for 
conferring degrees and also at any meeting of the Court.

</section>

<section><tid>1012020</tid>
<number>4</number>There shall be one or more Rectors who shall be appointed in 
such manner and with such powers and duties as may be prescribed by 
the Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>1092372</tid>
<number>5</number>There shall be a Dean for each School of Study who shall be 
appointed in such manner and with such powers and duties as may be 
prescribed by the Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>291495</tid>
<number>6</number>There shall be a Registrar who shall act as Secretary of the 
Court, the Executive Council and the Academic Council and he shall be 
appointed in such manner and with such powers and duties as may be 
prescribed by the Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>1194593</tid>
<number>7</number>There shall be a Finance Officer who shall be the Secretary 
of the Finance Committee and exercise such powers and perform such 
duties as may be prescribed by the Statutes.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>188</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>566232</tid>
<number>8</number>There shall be such other officers as provided for in the 
Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1458110</tid>
<number>10</number>Authorities of the University. The authorities of the 
University shall be the Court, the Executive Council, the Academic 
Council, the Schools of Studies, the Finance Committee and such other 
authorities as may be declared by the Statutes to be authorities of 
the University.


</article>



<article><tid>101660</tid>
<number> 11</number> The Court.
<section><tid>1722745</tid>
<number>1</number>The Court shall be the supreme authority of  
the University, and its constitution and the terms of office of its 
members shall be prescribe by the Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>764439</tid>
<number>2</number>The Court shall have the power to review the acts of the 
Executive Council and the Academic Council (save when these  
authorities have acted in accordance with the powers conferred upon 
  them under this Act, the Statutes or the Ordinances) and shall 
exercise all the powers of the University not otherwise provided for 
by this Act or the Statutes:
Provided that the power of review under this sub- section shall 
not be exercised except by a majority of the total membership of the 
Court and by a majority of not less than two- thirds of the members of 
the Court present and voting.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1688164</tid>
<number> 12</number> The Executive Council.
<section><tid>1564534</tid>
<number>1</number>The Executive Council shall be the  
executive body of the University, and its constitution and the terms 
of office of its members, other than ex officio members, shall be 
prescribed by the Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>1935134</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be in charge of the general management and 
administration (including the revenue and property) of the University.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1844761</tid>
<number> 13</number> The Academic Council.
<section><tid>138085</tid>
<number>1</number>The Academic Council shall be the  
academic body of the University, and its constitution and the terms of 
office of its members, other than ex officio members, shall be 
prescribed by the Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>747451</tid>
<number>2</number>The Academic Council shall, subject to the provisions of this 
Act, the Statutes and the Ordinances, have the control and general 
regulation, and be responsible for the maintenance, of standards of 
instruction, education and examination within the University, and 
shall exercise such other powers and perform such other duties as may 
be conferred or imposed upon it by the Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>143126</tid>
<number> 14</number> The Academic Advisory Committee.
<section><tid>635250</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be  
constituted an Academic Advisory Committee of the University which 
shall advise generally on the planning and development to the 
University and keep under review the standard of education and 
research in the University.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>189</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>836004</tid>
<number>2</number>The Committee shall consist of-

<subsection><tid>125833</tid>
<number>a</number>not more than seven persons of high academic standing 
who shall be appointed in such manner as may be 
prescribed by the statutes, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1853886</tid>
<number>b</number>the Vice- Chancellor.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>815092</tid>
<number>3</number>The Visitor may determine a date with effect from which the 
Academic Advisory Committee shall stand dissolved.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>755835</tid>
<number> 15</number> Statutes. Subject to the provisions of this Act, the statutes 
may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:-
<section><tid>268245</tid>
<number>a</number>the constitution, powers and duties of the authorities 
and other bodies of the University, the qualifications 
and disqualifications for membership of such 
authorities and other bodies, appointment and removal 
of members thereof and other matters connected 
therewith;

</section>

<section><tid>240642</tid>
<number>b</number>the appointment, powers and duties of the officers of 
the University;

</section>

<section><tid>224061</tid>
<number>c</number>the appointment, terms and conditions of service and 
the powers and duties of the employees of the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>1428750</tid>
<number>d</number>the terms and conditions under which institution may be 
associated with the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1529335</tid>
<number>e</number>the administration of the University, the establishment 
and abolition of Colleges, institutions and Halls, the 
grant and withdrawal of recognition to institutions, 
the institution of Fellowships, Awards and the like, 
the conferment of degrees and other academic 
distinctions and the grant of diplomas and 
certificates;

</section>

<section><tid>561639</tid>
<number>f</number>any other matter which is necessary for the proper and 
effective management and conduct of the affairs of the 
University and which by this Act is to be or may be 
provided by the Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>13267</tid>
<number> 16</number> Statutes, how made.
<section><tid>458705</tid>
<number>1</number>The first Statutes are those set out  
in the Second Schedule.

</section>

<section><tid>306013</tid>
<number>2</number>The Executive Council may, from time to time, make new or 
additional Statutes or may amend or repeal the Statutes in the manner 
hereafter in this section provided:
Provided that the Executive Council shall not make any Statute or 
any amendment of a Statute affecting the status, powers or 
constitution of any existing authority of the University until such 
authority has been given an opportunity of expressing an opinion on 
the proposal, and any opinion so expressed shall be in writing and 
shall be considered by the Executive Council:


<pagefootnote><pagenum>190</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Provided further that no Statute shall be made by the Executive 
Council affecting the discipline of students, and standards of 
instruction, education and examination except after consultation with 
the Academic Council.


</section>

<section><tid>1559571</tid>
<number>3</number>Every new Statute or addition to the Statutes or any 
amendment or repeal of a Statute shall require the approval of the 
Visitor who may assent thereto or withhold assent on remit to the 
Executive Council for consideration.

</section>

<section><tid>1360146</tid>
<number>4</number>A new Statute or a Statute amending or repealing an existing 
Statute shall have no validity unless it has been assented to by the 
Visitor.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1095740</tid>
<number> 17</number> Ordinances.
<section><tid>681419</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act and the  
Statutes, the Ordinances may provide for all or any of the following 
matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1059250</tid>
<number>a</number>the admission of students, the courses of study and the 
fees therefor, the qualifications pertaining to 
degrees, diplomas, certificates and other academic 
distinctions, the conditions for the grant of 
Fellowships, Awards and the like;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1083238</tid>
<number>b</number>the conduct of examinations, including the terms of 
office and appointment of examiners, and the conditions 
of residence of students and their general discipline;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>300903</tid>
<number>c</number>the management of colleges and institutions maintained 
by the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1212871</tid>
<number>d</number>any other matter which by this Act or the Statutes is 
to be or may be provided by the Ordinances.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1628603</tid>
<number>2</number>The first Ordinances shall be made by the Vice- Chancellor 
with the previous approval of the Central Government and the 
Ordinances so made may be amended, repealed or added to at any time by 
the Executive Council in the manner prescribed by the Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>46743</tid>
<number>18</number>Regulations. The authorities of the University may make 
Regulations consistent with this Act, the Statutes and the Ordinances 
for the conduct of their own business and that of the committees 
appointed by them and not provided for by this Act, the Statutes or 
the Ordinances in the manner prescribed by the Statutes.


</article>



<article><tid>1761783</tid>
<number> 19</number> Annual report.
<section><tid>1138787</tid>
<number>1</number>The annual report of the University shall  
be prepared under the direction of the Executive Council and shall be 
submitted to the Court on or before such date as may be prescribed by 
the Statutes and shall be considered by the Court at its annual 
meeting.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>191</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1368109</tid>
<number>2</number>The Court may communicate its comments thereon to the 
Executive Council.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1601713</tid>
<number> 20</number> Audit of accounts.
<section><tid>90265</tid>
<number>1</number>The accounts of the University shall,  
once at least in every year and at intervals of not more than fifteen 
months, be audited by the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India, or 
any person authorised by him in this behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>1533695</tid>
<number>2</number>The accounts, when audited shall be published in the Gazette 
of India, and a copy of the accounts together with the audit report 
shall be submitted by the Registrar to the Visitor and to the Court.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>945152</tid>
<number>21</number>Disputes as to constitution of University authorities and 
bodies. If any question arises whether any person has been duly 
elected or appointed as, or is entitled to be, a member of any 
authority or other body of the University, the matter shall be 
referred to the Visitor whose decision thereon shall be final.


</article>



<article><tid>565262</tid>
<number>22</number>Constitution of committees. Where any authority of the 
University is given power by this Act or the Statutes to appoint 
committees, such committees shall, save as otherwise provided, consist 
of members of the authority concerned and of such other persons (if  
  any) as the authority in each case may think fit.


</article>



<article><tid>1878378</tid>
<number>23</number>Filling of casual vacancies. All casual vacancies among the 
members (other than ex officio members) of any authority or other body 
of the University shall be filled, as soon as conveniently may be, by 
the person or body who appointed, elected or co- opted the member whose 
place has become vacant, and the person appointed, elected or co- opted 
to a casual vacancy shall be a member of such authority or body for 
the residue of the term for which the person whose place he fills 
would have been a member.


</article>



<article><tid>1016728</tid>
<number>24</number>Proceedings of the University authorities and bodies not 
invalidated by vacancies. No act or proceedings of any authority or 
other body of the University shall be invalidated merely by reason of 
the existence of a vacancy or vacancies among its members.


</article>



<article><tid>637036</tid>
<number>25</number>Removal of difficulties. If any difficulty arises in giving 
effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government may, by 
order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions not 
inconsistent with the purposes of this Act, as appear to it to be 
necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>192</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>53517</tid>
<number> 26</number> Transitional provisions. Notwithstanding anything contained 
in this Act and the Statutes-
<section><tid>1273359</tid>
<number>a</number>the first Chancellor, members of the Court, the 
Executive Council and the Academic Council shall be 
nominated by the Visitor and shall hold office for a 
term of three years;

</section>

<section><tid>1166489</tid>
<number>b</number>the first Vice- Chancellor shall be appointed by the 
Visitor and he shall hold office for a term of five 
years.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1540241</tid>
<number>27</number>Amendment of Act 8 of <year>1922</year>. In the Delhi University Act, 
<year>1922</year>, in sub- section (2) of section 5, after the words" for the time 
being in force", the words and figures" but subject to the provisions 
contained in the Jawaharlal Nehru University Act, <year>1966</year>" shall be 
inserted.

</article>



 </act>