<act><title>

THE 
    CINE-Workers and cinema theatre workers (regulation of employment) act, 1981</title> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Cine-workers and Cinema Theatre Workers 
    (Regulation of Employment) Act, 1981. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    extends to the whole of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It 
    shall come into force on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central Government 
    may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint; and different dates 
    may be appointed for different provisions of this Act and for different 
    areas.
 





  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>  “cinema theatre” 
      means a place which is licenced under Part III of the Cinematograph Act, 
      1952, (37 of 1952), or under any other law for the time being in force in 
      a State for the exhibition of a cinematograph film;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>  “cinematograph 
      film” has the same meaning as in the Cinematograph Act, 1952; (37 of 
      1952).
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>  “cine-worker”, 
      means an individual—
 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>  who is employed, 
        directly or through any contractor or other person, in or in connection 
        with the production of a feature film to work as an artiste (including 
        actor, musician or dancer) or to do any work, skilled, unskilled, 
        manual, supervisory, technical, artistic or otherwise; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>  whose 
        remuneration with respect to such employment in or in connection with 
        the production of such feature film does not exceed, where such 
        remuneration is by way of monthly wages, a sum of one thousand six 
        hundred rupees per month, and where such remuneration is by way of a 
        lump sum, a sum of fifteen thousand rupees;
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>  “competent 
      authority” means any authority authorised by the Central Government by 
      notification in the Official Gazette to perform all or any of the 
      functions of the competent authority under this Act;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>  “contractor” means 
      a person who furnishes or undertakes to furnish cine-workers for being 
      employed in or in connection with the production of a feature film, and 
      includes a sub-contractor or agent;
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>  “feature film” 
      means a full length cinematograph film produced wholly or partly in India 
      with a format and a story woven around a number of characters where 
      the plot is revealed mainly through dialogues and not wholly through 
      narration, animation or cartoon depiction, and does not include an 
      advertisement film;
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>  “prescribed” means 
      prescribed by rules made under this Act;
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>  “producer”, in 
      relation to a feature film, means the person by whom the arrangements 
      necessary for the making of such film (including the raising of finances 
      and engaging cine-workers for the making of such film) are undertaken;
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>  “production”, in 
      relation to a feature film, includes any of the activities in respect of 
      the making thereof;
 </section><section>
<number>j</number>  “Tribunal” means 
      Cine-workers’ Tribunal constituted under section 7;
 </section><section>
<number>k</number>  “wages” means all 
      emoluments which are payable to a worker in accordance with the terms of 
      the contract of employment in cash, but does not include—
 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>  the cash value 
        of any food concession;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>  any dearness 
        allowance (that is to say, all cash payments, by whatever name called, 
        paid to a worker on account of a rise in the cost of living or on 
        account of his being required to work in a place other than the place 
        where he is normally residing), house rent allowance, overtime 
        allowance, bonus, commission or any other similar allowance payable to 
        the worker in respect of his employment or of work done in such 
        employment;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>  any 
        contribution paid or payable by the employer to any pension fund or 
        provident fund or for the benefit of the worker under any law for the 
        time being in force;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>  any gratuity 
        payable on the termination of his contract.
</subsection>
</section>
 
 

  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Prohibition of employment of cine-worker without agreement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No person shall be employed as a cine-worker in or in connection with the 
    production of any feature film unless,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>  an agreement in writing is entered 
    into with such person by the producer of such film; or, where such person is 
    employed through a contractor or other person, by the producer of such film 
    and such contractor or other person; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>  such agreement is registered with 
    the competent authority by the producer of such film.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every agreement, 
    referred to in sub-section (1) shall,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>  be in the prescribed form;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>  specify the name of and such other 
    particulars as may be prescribed with respect to, the person to whose 
    employment it relates (hereafter in this sub-section referred to as the 
    employee);
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>  specify the nature of assignment of 
    the employee, his hours of work, the wages and other benefits (including 
    benefits by way of provident fund, if any), to which he is entitled; the 
    mode of payment of such wages and contributions to such provident fund and 
    all other terms and conditions of employment;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>  include, where such employee is 
    employed through a contractor or other person, a specific condition to the 
    effect that in the event of the contractor or other person failing to 
    discharge his obligations under the agreement to the employee with respect 
    to payment of wages or any other matter, the producer of the film concerned 
    shall be liable to discharge such obligations and shall be entitled to be 
    reimbursed with respect thereto by the contractor or other person.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> A copy of the agreement 
    referred to in sub-section (1) with respect to the employment of any person 
    as a cine-worker shall, if such person is entitled to the benefits of 
    provident fund under section 16, also be forwarded by the producer of the 
    film to the Regional Provident Fund Commissioner concerned under the 
    Employees’ Provident Funds and Miscellaneous Provisions Act, 1952 (19 of 
    1952).
 
 



  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Conciliation officers.—The 
    Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint 
    such number of persons as it thinks fit to be conciliation officers charged 
    with the duty of mediating and promoting the settlement of any dispute 
    (hereinafter referred to as the dispute) between a cine-worker and the 
    producer of the film in, or in connection with, which he has been employed 
    or the contractor or other person through whom he has been so employed, with 
    respect to the terms and conditions or termination, of employment of such 
    cine-worker.
  



  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Duties of conciliation 
    officers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where any dispute exists or is apprehended, the conciliation officer may 
    hold conciliation proceedings in the prescribed manner.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The conciliation 
    officer shall, for the purpose of bringing about a settlement of the 
    dispute, without delay, investigate the dispute and all matters affecting 
    the merits and the right settlement thereof and may do all such things as he 
    thinks fit for the purpose of inducing the parties to come to a fair and 
    amicable settlement of the dispute.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If a settlement of the 
    dispute or of any of the matters in dispute is arrived at in the course of 
    the conciliation proceedings, the conciliation officer shall send a report 
    thereof to the Central Government together with a memorandum of the 
    settlement signed by the parties to the dispute.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If no such settlement 
    is arrived at, the conciliation officer shall, as soon as practicable, after 
    the close of the investigation, send to the Central Government a full report 
    setting forth the steps taken by him for ascertaining the facts and 
    circumstances relating to the dispute and for brining about a settlement 
    thereof, together with a full settlement of such facts and circumstances and 
    the reasons on account of which, in his opinion a settlement could not be 
    arrived at.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If, on a consideration 
    of the report referred to in sub-section (4), the Central Government is 
    satisfied that there is case for reference to a Tribunal, it may make such 
    reference under section 11 and where that Government does not make such 
    reference, it shall record and communicate to the parties concerned its 
    reasons therefor.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> A report under this 
    section shall be submitted within three months of the commencement of the 
    conciliation proceedings or within such shorter period as may be fixed by 
    the Central Government: 
 
Provided that, subject to 
    the approval of the conciliation officer, the time for the submission of the 
    report may be extended by such period as may be agreed upon in writing by 
    all the parties to the dispute.
 
 

  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Settlement to be binding 
    and to be enforced by the competent authority.—Every 
    settlement arrived at in the course of a conciliation proceeding under this 
    Chapter shall be binding on all the parties to the dispute and shall not be 
    called in question in any court and it shall be the duty of the competent 
    authority to enforce the terms of the said settlement.
  




  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Constitution of 
    Tribunals.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    constitute one or more Tribunals, to be called the Cine-workers Tribunals, 
    with headquarters at such place as may be specified in the notification, for 
    the adjudication of disputes relating to any matter specified in agreement 
    of the nature referred to in section 3.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A Tribunal shall 
    consist of one person only to be appointed by the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A person shall not be 
    qualified for appointment as the presiding officer of a Tribunal unless—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>  he is, or has been, or is qualified 
    to be, a Judge of a High Court; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>  he has, for a period of not less 
    than three years, been a District Judge or an Additional District Judge; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>  he has held the office of the 
    presiding officer of an Industrial Tribunal constituted under the Industrial 
    Disputes Act, 1947 (14 of 1947) for a period of not less than two years.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The Central Government 
    may, if it so thinks fit, appoint two persons as assessors to advise the 
    Tribunal in any proceedings before it.
 
 



  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Disqualification for the 
    presiding officers of Tribunals.—No 
    person shall be appointed to, or continue in, the office of the presiding 
    officer of a Tribunal, if—
 <section>
<number>a</number>  he is not an independent person; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>  he has attained the age of 
    sixty-five years.
 
 

  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Filling of vacancies.—If, 
    for any reason, a vacancy (other than a temporary absence) occurs in the 
    office of the presiding officer of a Tribunal, the Central Government shall 
    appoint another person in accordance with the provisions of this Act to fill 
    the vacancy, and the proceeding may be continued before the Tribunal from 
    the stage at which the vacancy is filled.
 
 
 
 

  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Finality of orders 
    constituting Tribunals, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No order of the Central Government appointing any person as the presiding 
    officer of a Tribunal shall be called in question in any manner; and no act 
    or proceeding before any Tribunal shall be called in question in any manner 
    on the ground merely of any defect in the constitution of such Tribunal.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No settlement arrived 
    at in the course of a conciliation proceeding shall be invalid by reason 
    only of the fact that such settlement was arrived at after the expiry of the 
    period referred to in sub-section (6) of section 5.
 
 

  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Reference of disputes 
    to Tribunals.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where, on a consideration of the report referred to in sub-section (4) of 
    section 5, the Central Government is satisfied that it is necessary so to 
    do, it may, by order in writing, refer the dispute or any matter appearing 
    to be connected with, or relevant to, the dispute, to a Tribunal for 
    adjudication.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where in an order 
    referred to in sub-section (1) or in a subsequent order, the Central 
    Government has specified the points of dispute for adjudication, the 
    Tribunal shall confine its adjudication to those points and matters 
    incidental thereto.
  
 
 
 
 

  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Procedure and powers of 
    conciliation officers and Tribunals.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to any rules that may be made in this behalf, a conciliation officer 
    or a Tribunal shall follow such procedure as the officer or Tribunal may 
    think fit.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A conciliation officer 
    or a Tribunal may, for the purpose of inquiry into any existing or 
    apprehended dispute, after giving reasonable notice, enter any premises in 
    the occupation of any party to the dispute.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every Tribunal shall 
    have the same powers as are vested in a Civil Court under the Code of Civil 
    Procedure, 1908, (5 of 1908) when trying a suit, in respect of the following 
    matters, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>  enforcing the attendance of any 
    person and examining him on oath;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>  compelling the production of 
    documents and material objects;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>  issuing commissions for the 
    examination of witnesses; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>  in respect of such other matters as 
    may be prescribed;
 
and every inquiry or investigation by a 
    Tribunal shall be deemed to be a judicial proceeding within the meaning of 
    section 193 and 228 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860) and the Tribunal 
    shall be deemed to be a Civil Court for the purposes of section 195 and 
    Chapter XXVI of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> A conciliation officer 
    may call for and inspect any document which has ground for considering to be 
    relevant to the dispute or to be necessary for the purpose of verifying the 
    implementation of any award or carrying out any other duty imposed on him 
    under this Chapter, and for the aforesaid purposes, the conciliation officer 
    shall have the same powers as are vested in a Civil Court under the Code of 
    Civil Procedure, 1908, (5 of 1908), in respect of compelling the production 
    of documents.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> A Tribunal may, if it 
    so thinks fit, appoint one or more persons having special knowledge of the 
    matter under consideration as assessor or assessors to advise it in the 
    proceeding before it.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> A Tribunal may grant to 
    any party to any proceeding before it, such interim or other reliefs 
    (whether subject to any conditions or not), including stay of any order, 
    issue of any injunction or direction in regard to payment of wages or other 
    amounts payable under the agreement referred to in section 3, setting aside 
    any unilateral termination of contract or the dismissal of a worker or 
    reinstating a worker, as it deems just and proper in the circumstances of 
    the case:
 
Provided that the Tribunal 
    shall not grant any such interim relief unless all the parties to the 
    proceeding have been served with a notice on the application for such 
    interim relief and have been given a reasonable opportunity of being heard:
 
Provided further that the 
    Tribunal may, having regard to the nature of the interim relief sought and 
    the circumstances of the case, pass appropriate orders granting such interim 
    relief as it deems just and proper in the circumstances of the case before 
    the notice referred to in the preceding proviso is served on the parties to 
    the proceeding:
 
Provided also that where 
    the Tribunal makes any order under the proviso immediately preceding, it 
    shall record the reasons for making the order before complying with the 
    requirements specified in the first proviso.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Subject to any rules 
    that may be made in this behalf, the awarding of damages in, and the cost 
    of, and incidental to, any proceeding before a Tribunal shall be in the 
    discretion of that Tribunal and the Tribunal shall have full power to 
    determine by and to whom and to what extent and subject to what conditions, 
    if any, such damages or costs are to be paid, and to give all necessary 
    directions for the purposes aforesaid and such damages or costs may, on an 
    application made to the Central Government by the person entitled, be 
    directed to be recovered by that Government in the same manner as an arrear 
    of land revenue.
 
 

  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Duties of Tribunals.—Where 
    a dispute has been referred to a Tribunal for adjudication, it shall hold 
    its proceedings expeditiously and shall submit its award to the Central 
    Government ordinarily within a period of three months from the date on which 
    such industrial dispute is referred to it:
 
Provided that in computing 
    the period of three months under this section, the period for which the 
    proceedings before the Tribunal have been stayed by any injunction or order 
    shall be excluded.
 
 

  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Publication of awards 
    of Tribunals.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every award of a Tribunal shall, within a period of thirty days from the 
    date of its receipt by the Central Government, be published in such manner 
    as that Government thinks fit.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to the 
    provisions of section 15, the award shall be final and binding on all the 
    parties to the dispute and shall not be called in question in any Court in 
    any manner whatsoever.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The award of a Tribunal 
    shall be executed in the same manner as if it were a decree of a Civil 
    Court.
  




  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>15</number> Revision.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The High Court may, on the application of any person aggrieved by the award 
    of a Tribunal, call for and examine the record of the Tribunal, to satisfy 
    itself as to the regularity of the proceeding before such Tribunal or the 
    correctness, legality or propriety of any award passed therein and if, in 
    any case, it appears to the High Court that any such award should be 
    modified, annulled or reversed, it may pass such orders accordingly:
 
Provided that where the 
    presiding officer of the Tribunal is a Judge of a High Court, such 
    application shall be heard and disposed of by not less than two Judges of 
    the High Court:
 
Provided further that where 
    the award of the Tribunal provides for the payment by the producer of any 
    film or, as the case may be, the contractor or other person of any amount 
    either by way of compensation to the cine-worker or by way of damages, no 
    such application by the producer, contractor or other person shall be 
    entertained by the High Court unless the applicant deposits with the High 
    Court or with such other authority as may be prescribed the amount ordered 
    to be paid:
 
Provided also that where, 
    in any particular case, the High Court is of opinion that the deposit of any 
    amount ordered to be paid would cause undue hardship to the applicant, the 
    High Court may dispense with such deposit subject to such conditions as it 
    may deem fit to impose so as to safeguard the interests of the cine-worker 
    concerned.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every application to 
    the High Court under sub-section (1) shall be preferred within ninety days 
    from the date on which the award was passed by the Tribunal:
 
Provided that the High 
    Court may, in its discretion, allow further time not exceeding one month for 
    the filing of any such application, if it is satisfied that the applicant 
    had sufficient cause for not preferring the application within the time 
    specified in this sub-section.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In this section, “High 
    Court” means the High Court within the local limits of whose jurisdiction, 
    the headquarters of the Tribunal is situated.
 

 



  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>16</number> 
      Application of Act 19 of 1952 to cine-workers.—The Employees’ Provident Funds 
      and Miscellaneous Provisions Act, 1952, as in force for the time being, 
      shall apply to every cine-worker who has worked in not less than three 
      feature films with one or more producers, as if such cine-worker were an 
      employee within the meaning of that Act.
   
  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Penalties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whoever contravenes the provisions of section 3 shall be punishable with 
    fine which shall not be less than ten thousand rupees but which may extend 
    to fifty thousand rupees:
 
Provided that the Court 
    may, for any adequate and special reasons to be mentioned in the judgment, 
    impose a fine of less than ten thousand rupees.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any person 
    convicted of an offence under sub-section (1) is again convicted of an 
    offence under the same provision, he shall be punishable with fine which 
    shall not be less than twenty thousand rupees but which may extend to one 
    lakh rupees:
 
Provided that the Court 
    may, for any adequate and special reasons to be mentioned in the judgment, 
    impose a fine of less than twenty thousand rupees.
 
 

  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Offences by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where an offence under this Act has been committed by a company, every 
    person who, at the time the offence was committed, was in charge of, and was 
    responsible to, the company for the conduct of the business of the company, 
    as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and 
    shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
 
Provided that nothing 
    contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to any 
    punishment if he proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge 
    or that he had exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such 
    offence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in sub-section (1), where any offence under this Act has 
    been committed by a company and it is proved that the offence has been 
    committed with the consent or connivance of, or is attributable to any 
    neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary or other officer of 
    the company, such director, manager, secretary or other officer shall be 
    deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded 
    against and punished accordingly.
 
Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>  “company” means any body corporate 
    and includes a firm or other association of individuals; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>  “director”, in relation to a firm, 
    means a partner in the firm.
 
 

  

 
  
 

  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Cognizance of offences.—No 
    court shall take cognizance of any offence under this Act except on a 
    complaint made by, or with the permission in writing of, the Central 
    Government or an officer empowered by it in this behalf and no court 
    inferior to that of a Metropolitan Magistrate or a Judicial Magistrate of 
    the first class shall try an offence punishable under this Act.
 
 




  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>20</number> Magistrate’s power to 
    impose enhanced penalties.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in section 29 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 ( 2 
    of 1974) it shall be lawful for any Metropolitan Magistrate or any Judicial 
    Magistrate of the first class to pass any sentence authorised by this Act.
  
 
 
 
 

  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>21</number> Effect of laws and 
    agreements inconsistent with this Chapter.—The 
    provisions of this Chapter shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
    inconsistent therewith contained in any other law for the time being in 
    force or in the terms of any agreement or contract of service.
  
 
 
 
 

  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>22</number> 
      Protection of action taken under this Chapter.—
<section><number>1</number> No suit, prosecution or 
      other legal proceedings shall lie against any competent authority, 
      conciliation officer, or any other employee of the Central Government or 
      the presiding officer of a Tribunal, for anything which is in good faith 
      done, or intended to be done, in pursuance of this Act or any rule or 
      order made thereunder.
 </section><section><number>2</number> No suit 
      or other legal proceedings shall lie against the Central Government for 
      any damage caused or likely to be caused by anything which is in good 
      faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any rule or 
      notification or order made or issued thereunder.
  
  
   
  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

    1[<number>22A</number> Delegation of 
    Powers.—The 
    Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that 
    any power exercisable by it under this Act or rules made thereunder (other 
    than the powers conferred by this section and section 23) shall, in relation 
    to such matters and subject to such conditions, if any, as may be specified 
    in the notification be exercisable also by the State Government or by such 
    officer or authority subordinate to the State Government as may be specified 
    in the notification.]







  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>23</number> Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make 
    rules for carrying out the provisions of this Chapter.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular, and 
    without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may 
    provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>  the form in which an agreement may 
    be entered into by a producer with a cine-worker under section 3 and the 
    other conditions of employment;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>  the manner in which proceedings may 
    be held by a conciliation officer under sub-section (1) of section 5;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>  the procedure to be followed by a 
    conciliation officer or Tribunal under section 12.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>  the matters referred to in clause 
    (d) of sub-section (3) of section 12;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>  the damages or costs that may be 
    awarded by a Tribunal under sub-section (7) of section 12;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>  any other matter which is required 
    to be, or may be, prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Every rule made by the 
    Central Government under this Chapter shall be laid, as soon as may be after 
    it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a 
    total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two 
    or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
    immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both 
    Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree 
    that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only 
    in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, 
    that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
    validity of anything previously done under that rule.
 
 

  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>25</number> Application of Act 39 of 1972. 
</title>—The provisions of the Payment of Gratuity Act, 1972, as in force for 
the time being, shall apply to or in relation to, every worker employed in a 
cinema theatre in which five or more workers are employed or were employed on 
any day of the preceding twelve months, as they apply to, or in relation to, 
employees within the meaning of that Act. 

</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>     
 Came into force on 
    1-10-1984 vide G.S.R. 676(E), dated 21st September, 1984, published 
    in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 21st September, 
    1984.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> 
 Ins. by Act 35 of 
    1988, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 12-8-1988).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>