<act><title>THE NATIONAL INVESTIGATION AGENCY (MANNER OF 
CONSTITUTION) RULES, 20081</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the National Investigation Agency (Manner of Constitution) Rules, 2008. 

 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of their publication 
in the Official Gazette. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definition. </title>
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, unless the context 
otherwise requires, 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> Act means the National Investigation Agency Act, 2008 (34 of 2008); 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> Agency means the National Investigation Agency constituted under 
  section 3 of the National Investigation Agency Act, 2008 (34 of 2008); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> Code means the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> Director General means the Director General appointed by the Central 
  Government; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> Schedule means the Schedule to the National Investigation Agency Act, 
  2008. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Words and expressions used herein and not defined in these rules, but 
defined in the Act, shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the 
Act, or in the Police Act, or in the Code, as the case may be. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Constitution of the National Investigation Agency </title>.The 
National Investigation Agency shall consist of the following, namely: 
 
 <section><number>a</number> A Director-General, not below the rank of Additional Director General 
  of Police, to be appointed by the Central Government on the same terms and 
  conditions as are applicable to officers of the corresponding rank in the 
  Central Government; and 
 </section><section><number>b</number> Such number of officers and employees as may be specified by the 
  Central Government from time to time. </section>


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Head Quarter.</title>The headquarters of the Agency shall be at 
Delhi.


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Administration of the Agency. </title>The Administration of the 
Agency shall vest in the Director General. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Powers and functions of the Director-General. </title>The 
Director-General shall exercise in respect of the Agency such powers exercisable 
by a Director-General of Police in respect of the Police force in a State, as 
may be specified by the Central Government from time to time. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Powers and functions of the Agency. </title>The Agency shall 
have the following powers and functions, Namely: 
 
 <section><number>a</number> to investigate and prosecute offences in respect of the Acts specified 
  in the Schedule; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> to provide assistance to, and seek assistance from, other intelligence 
  and investigation agencies of the Central Government and State Governments; 
  and 
 </section><section><number>c</number> to take such other measures which may be necessary for speedy and 
  effective implementation of the provisions of the Act. </section>


</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Came into force on 31-12-2008.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>