<act><title>
THE UNLAWFUL 
    ACTIVITIES (PREVENTION) RULES, 19681</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>1</number> Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Unlawful Activities (Prevention) Rules, 1968.
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the 
    Official Gazette. 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>1A</number> 
    Rules also to extend to the State of Jammu and Kashmir.—These 
    rules shall be deemed to have also extended to, and come into force in the 
    State of Jammu and Kashmir on the first day of September, 1969, the date on 
    which the Unlawful Activities (Prevention) Act, 1967 (37 of 1967), came into 
    force in that State.] 
 







 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
    these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 <section>


    <number>a</number>    "the Act" means the Unlawful Activities (Prevention) Act, 1967 (37 of 
    1967);
 </section><section>


    <number>b</number>    "section" means a section of the Act;
 </section><section>


    <number>c</number>    words and expressions used in these rules but not defined, and 
    defined in the Act, shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in 
    the Act.
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>3</number> Tribunal and District Judge to follow rules of evidence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In holding an inquiry under sub-section (3) of section 4 or disposing of any 
    application under sub-section (4) of section 7 or sub-section (8) of section 
    8, the Tribunal or the District Judge, as the case may be, shall, subject to 
    the provisions of sub-rule (2), follow, as far as practicable, the rules of 
    evidence laid down in the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872). 
 </section><section>


<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in the Indian Evidence 
    Act, 1872 (1 of 1872), where any books of acount or other documents have 
    been produced before the Tribunal or the Court of the District Judge by the 
    Central Government and such books of account or other documents are claimed 
    by that Government to be of a confidential nature then, the Tribunal or the 
    Court of the District Judge, as the case may be, shall not,—  
 <subsection>


    <number>a</number>    make such books of account or other documents a part of the records 
    of the proceedings before it; or  
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>b</number>    allow inspection of, or grant a copy of, the whole of or any extract 
    from, such books of account or other documents by or to any person other 
    than a party to the proceedings before it.]
 








 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>4</number> Additional modes of service of notification made under section 3.—Without 
    prejudice to the generality of the provisions of sub-section (4) of section 
    3, all or any of the following modes may also be followed in effecting 
    service of a notification made under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 3, namely:—  
 <subsection>


    <number>a</number>    by making an announcement over the radio from the local or nearest 
    broadcasting station of the All-India Radio, or  
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>b</number>    by pasting the notification on the notice board of the office of the 
    District Magistrate or the Tehsildar at the headquarters of the district or 
    the tehsil, as the case may be, in which the principal office of the 
    association affected is situated.  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>5</number> Documents which should accompany a reference to the Tribunal.—Every 
    reference made to the Tribunal under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 4 shall be 
    accompanied by—  
 <subsection>


    <number>i</number>    a copy of the notification made under sub-section (1) of section 3, 
    and  
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>ii</number>    all the facts on which the grounds specified in the said 
    notification are based:  
 


    Provided that nothing in this rule shall require the Central Government to 
    disclose any fact to the Tribunal which that Government considers against 
    the public interest to disclose.  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>6</number> Service of notice issued by the Tribunal.—Every 
    notice referred to in sub-section (2) of section 4 shall be served on the 
    affected association in such manner as the Tribunal may think fit and all or 
    any of the following modes may be followed by the Tribunal in effecting 
    service of such notice, namely:—  
 <section>


    <number>a</number>    by affixing a copy of the notice to some conspicuous part of the 
    office, if any, of the association; or  
 </section><section>


    <number>b</number>    by serving a copy of the notice, where possible, on the principal 
    office bearers, if any, of the association, by registered post or otherwise; 
    or  
 </section><section>


    <number>c</number>    by proclaiming by beat of drum or by means of loudspeakers the 
    contents of the notification in the area in which the activities of the 
    association are ordinarily carried on.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>7</number> Tribunal to have a seal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Tribunal shall have a seal of such dimensions and in such form as it may 
    think fit.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> Every order made or notice issued by the Tribunal  shall be 
    authenticated by affixing its seal thereon.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>8</number> Tribunal to have a Registrar.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Tribunal shall have a Registrar who shall be either a whole-time or 
    part-time officer of the Government.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> The Registrar shall have the custody of the seal and the records of the 
    Tribunal and shall exercise such other functions as may be assigned to him 
    by the Tribunal.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>9</number> Reference to the Tribunal to be addressed to the Registrar.—Every 
    reference made to the Tribunal under section 4 shall be addressed and sent 
    to the Registrar who shall, immediately after the receipt of such reference 
    or as soon as possible thereafter, place the same before the Chairman for 
    his orders.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>10</number> 
    Issuing of summons.—The 
    Tribunal or the District Judge, as the case may be, may issue summons to 
    persons whose attendance is required either to give evidence or to produce 
    documents.
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>11</number> The mode of issuing the summons.—Every 
    summons shall be in duplicate and signed by the Registrar of the Tribunal or 
    the District Judge, as the case may be, and sealed with the seal of the 
    Tribunal or the Court of the District Judge, as the case may be, and it 
    shall specify the time and place at which the person summoned is required to 
    attend and also whether his attendance is required for the purposes of 
    giving evidence or to produce a document, or for both purposes.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>12</number> Summons for the production of documents.—A 
    person may be summoned to produce a document, when being summoned to give 
    evidence; and any person summoned merely to produce document shall be deemed 
    to have complied with the summons if he cause such document to be produced 
    instead of attending presonally to produce the same.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>13</number> The mode of service of summons.—A 
    summon may be served by sending it <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[by registered post with 
    acknowledgement due] to the person for whom it is intended or any such other 
    manner as may be directed by the Tribunal or the District Judge, as the case 
    may be.
 








 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>14</number> Power of Tribunal or District Judge to sit in private.—Where 
    any request is made by the Central Government so to do, it shall be lawful 
    for the Tribunal or the District Judge, as the case may be, to sit in 
    private and to admit at such sitting such persons whose presence is 
    considered by the Tribunal or the District Judge, as the case may be, to be 
    necessary for the proper determination of the matter before it or him. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>15</number> Other provisions of the Civil Procedure Code, 1908, to apply.—The 
    provisions of the Civil Procedure Code, 1908 (5 of 1908), shall, in so far 
    as they relate to any other matter with regard to the service of summons, 
    shall, as far as may be, apply to the service of any summons issued by any 
    Tribunal or District Judge under the Act.]  
 
 

 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Ins. by S.O. 359, 
    dated 18th January, 1971.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Subs. by S.O. 473, 
    dated 3rd February, 1970.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   Ins. by S.O. 109, 
    dated 4th January, 1971 (w.e.f. 4-1-1971).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   Subs. by S.O. 346 (E), 
    dated 21st June, 1973.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>