<act><tid>996474</tid>
<title>THE SUGAR- CANE ACT, <year>1934</year></title>

ACT NO. 15 OF <year>1934</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 1st May, <year>1934</year>.]

An Act to regulate the price of sugar- cane intended for use in sugar 
factories.





<article><tid>1097734</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>170662</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Sugar- cane Act, <year>1934</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>859578</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> It extends to the whole of India, except <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the 
territories which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were 
comprised in Part B States].]

</section>

<section><tid>1705323</tid>
<number>3</number>This section shall come into force at once; the remaining 
sections of this Act shall come into force in any State <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> or part of 
a State] on such date as the State Government may, by notification in 
the Official Gazette, appoint in that behalf.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>528112</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant 
in the subject or context,--
<section><tid>205167</tid>
<number>1</number>" controlled area" means any area specified in a 
notification issued under sub- section (1) of section 3;

</section>

<section><tid>1702436</tid>
<number>2</number>" factory" means any premises (including the precincts  
  thereof) wherein twenty or more workers are working or 
were working on any day of the preceding twelve months 
and in any part of which any manufacturing process 
connected with the production of sugar is being carried 
on or is ordinarily carried on with the aid of power; 
and

</section>

<section><tid>981564</tid>
<number>3</number>" sugar" means any form of sugar containing more than 
ninety per cent. of sucrose.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>34</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been rep. in Bihar by Bihar Act 7 of <year>1937</year>, in U. P. 
by U. P. Act 1 of <year>1938</year>; in certain districts of Madras and Andhra by 
Madras Act 20 of <year>1949</year> and in Punjab by Punjab Act 40 of <year>1953</year>. 
2 Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for the former sub- section. 
3 Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" Part B 
States". 
4 Ins., ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>696027</tid>
<number> 3</number> Declaration of controlled areas and fixing of prices.
<section><tid>1987448</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare 
any area specified in the notification to be a controlled area for the 
purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>288736</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The State Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, fix a minimum price or minimum prices for the purchase in any 
controlled area of sugar- cane intended for use in any factory.

</section>

<section><tid>1440878</tid>
<number>3</number>The State Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, prohibit in any controlled area the purchase of sugar- cane 
intended for use in any factory otherwise than from the grower of the 
sugar- cane or from a person licensed by the State Government to act as 
a purchasing agent.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1468386</tid>
<number> 4</number> Previous publication of notifications under section 3. Not 
less than thirty days before the issue of any notification under sub- 
section
<section><tid>1957869</tid>
<number>1</number>or sub- section (2) of section 3, the State Government  
shall publish in the Official Gazette and in such other manner (if  
  any) as it thinks fit a draft of the proposed notification specifying 
a date on or after which the draft will be taken into consideration, 
and shall consider any objection or suggestion which may be received 
from any person with respect to the draft before the date so 
specified.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1150827</tid>
<number>5</number>Penalty for purchase of sugar- cane in contravention of 
notification under section 3. Whoever in any controlled area purchases 
any sugar- cane intended for use in a factory at a price less than the 
minimum price fixed therefor by notification under sub- section (2) of 
section 3 or in contravention of any prohibition made under sub- 
section (3) of section 3 shall be punishable with fine which may 
extend to two thousand rupees.


</article>



<article><tid>586027</tid>
<number>6</number>Sanction for prosecution under this Act. No Court shall take 
cognizance of any offence punishable under section 5 except upon 
complaint made by order of, or under authority from, the District 
Magistrate.


</article>



<article><tid>322603</tid>
<number> 7</number> Power of State Government to make rules.
<section><tid>689629</tid>
<number>1</number>The State  
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules 
for the purpose of carrying into effect the objects of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>497901</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for--

<subsection><tid>1749960</tid>
<number>a</number>the carrying out of inquiries preliminary to the 
exercise of the powers conferred by section 3;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>34A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" Subject to the control of the G. G. in C." omitted by 
the A. O. <year>1937</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>661384</tid>
<number>b</number>establishing Advisory Committees for any purpose 
connected with the administration of this Act and 
defining the powers, functions and procedure of such 
Committees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>184824</tid>
<number>c</number>the issue of licences to purchasing agents, the fees for 
such licences, and the regulation of the purchase and 
sale of sugar- cane by and to such agents;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>541405</tid>
<number>d</number>the organisation of growers of sugar- cane into societies 
for the sale of sugar- cane to factories;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1878134</tid>
<number>e</number>the authorities by which any functions under this Act or 
the rules made thereunder are to be performed; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>793878</tid>
<number>f</number>the records, registers and accounts to be maintained for 
ensuring compliance with the provisions of this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1342409</tid>
<number>3</number>In making any rule under sub- section (1) or under clause (c) 
or clause (f) of sub- section (2), the State Government may provide 
that a breach of the rule shall, where no other penalty is provided by 
this Act, be punishable with fine not exceeding two thousand rupees.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1299396</tid>
<number>8</number>Power of State Government to make rules. The State Government 
after previous publication may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, make rules providing for the exemption of factories or any 
class of factories from the provisions of this Act.
</article>



 </act>