<act><tid>49194</tid>
<title>THE EXCHANGE OF PRISONERS ACT, <year>1948</year></title>

ACT NO. 58 OF <year>1948</year>
[ 10th September, <year>1948</year>.]

An Act to provide, in pursuance of an agreement with Pakistan for the 
exchange of prisoners, for the transfer of certain prisoners from 
India to Pakistan and the reception in India of certain prisoners from 
Pakistan.

WHEREAs an agreement has been reached between the Government of 
India and the Government of Pakistan for the exchange of certain 
classes of prisoners between the two countries;

AND WHEREAS it is necessary to provide in pursuance of the said 
agreement for the transfer of certain prisoners from India to Pakistan 
and for the reception in India of certain prisoners from Pakistan;

It is hereby enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>995955</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>520878</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Exchange  
of Prisoners Act, <year>1948</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1984573</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>854824</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless there in anything repugnant in 
the subject or context,-
<section><tid>679307</tid>
<number>a</number>" prison" includes any subsidiary jail, judicial lock- 
up or police lock- up, and any place used for the custody of 
persons who are ordered to be detained under any law for the 
time being in force;

</section>

<section><tid>672712</tid>
<number>b</number>" prisoner" means any person committed to custody in a 
prison on or before the 1st day of August, <year>1948</year> under the 
writ, warrant or order of any Court or authority other than a 
civil Court or Court- martial,
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>.


</section>

<section><tid>1934771</tid>
<number>d</number>" transferable prisoner" means-

<subsection><tid>1901329</tid>
<number>i</number>in the State of Punjab <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as it existed before the 1st 
November, <year>1956</year>], any prisoner who, being a Muslim, is willing 
to be transferred to Pakistan under the provisions of this 
Act, and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>58</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Cl. (c) omitted by the A. O. <year>1950</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>214756</tid>
<number>ii</number>in any other part of India, any prisoner of such 
category as the Central Government may specify by 
notification in the Official Gazette who, being a Muslim, is 
willing to be transferred to Pakistan under the provisions of 
this Act.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1781544</tid>
<number>3</number>Issue of warrants for transfer of prisoners. The State 
Government may issue a warrant addressed to the officer in charge of a 
prison to deliver to the person presenting the warrant any 
transferable prisoner confined or detained in the prison, together 
with all the records relating to such prisoner and the personal 
effects taken from him at the time of his admission into the prison.


</article>



<article><tid>1272230</tid>
<number>4</number>Removal and delivery of prisoners. Upon the presentation of a 
warrant issued under section 3, the officer in charge of the prison 
shall forthwith comply with the warrant and obtain thereon the 
signature of the person to whom delivery of the prisoner, records and 
articles is made in pursuance of the warrant; and that person shall 
cause the prisoner, records and articles to be removed from the prison 
and delivered at such place, and to such authorised officer of 
Pakistan, as the State Government may, by general or special order, 
specify in this behalf,


</article>



<article><tid>1188248</tid>
<number>5</number>Casser of jurisdiction of Indian Courts and authorities over 
prisoners. Upon the delivery of custody of a prisoner to an officer of 
Pakistan in accordance with the provisions of section 4, all Courts 
and authorities in India shall, save as otherwise provided in section 
 8 or for the purposes of that section, cease to have or exercise, in 
relation to the prisoner, any jurisdiction in respect of the offence 
or other matter which was the cause of his confinement or detention in 
the prison.


</article>



<article><tid>54641</tid>
<number>6</number>Lawfulness of custody and retaking upon escape. It shall be 
lawful for any officer of Pakistan to whom the custody of a prisoner 
is delivered under the provisions of section 4 to receive and hold in 
custody such prisoner and to convey him out of India, and if the 
prisoner escapes from such custody within India he may be retaken as a 
person accused of an offence may be retaken upon an escape.


</article>



<article><tid>1453556</tid>
<number>7</number>Tranfer of records relating to transferable prisoners. Where 
a prisoner is or is to be transferred to Pakistan under the provisions 
of this Act, the State Government may requisition the record of any 
proceedings, including judicial proceedings, relating to that prisoner 
from any Court or office, and may direct that such record shall be 
sent to the Government of Pakistan or the Government of any' Province 
in Pakistan.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>59</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The word" Province" stands unmodified, cf. the A. O, <year>1950</year>.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>423262</tid>
<number> 8</number> Prohibition of return to India of transferred prisoners.
<section><tid>608254</tid>
<number>1</number> 
No person who has been transferred to Pakistan under the provisions of 
this Act shall return to India except with the permission in writing 
of the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>507541</tid>
<number>2</number>If any person contravenes the provisions of sub- section (1), 
he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to three years, and if, at the time of his transfer to Pakistan, he 
was undergoing a sentence of imprisonment in India, he shall further 
be sentenced to undergo the unexpired portion of such sentence without 
taking into account any period for which he may have been detained or 
confined in Pakistan after the transfer.

</section>

<section><tid>1564149</tid>
<number>3</number>If at the time of his transfer to Pakistan, the person 
contravening the provisions of sub- section (1) was undergoing trial in 
any Court in India for any offence, he shall, without prejudice to the 
provisions of sub- section (2), be liable to be tried for such offence 
by the same or any other Court having jurisdiction:
Provided that if such person has, before his return to India, 
been tried for the offence by a Court of competent jurisdiction in 
Pakistan and convicted or acquitted of the offence, he shall not be 
liable to be tried again for the same offence by any Court in India.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>477096</tid>
<number> 9</number> Reception in India of prisoners transferred from Pakistan.
<section><tid>917995</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, by general or special order, specify the 
place or places at which, and the officer or officers to whom, the 
custody of prisoners confined or detained in Pakistan is to be 
delivered in pursuance of the agreement reached in this behalf between 
the Government of India and the Government of Pakistan.

</section>

<section><tid>455997</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be lawful for any such officer as aforesaid to 
receive and hold in custody any prisoner so delivered and to convey 
such prisoner to any prison in a State of India for being dealt with 
in accordance with law; and if the prisoner escapes from such custody 
he may be retaken as a person accused of an offence against an Indian 
law may be retaken upon an escape.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>616401</tid>
<number> 10</number> Repeal of Ordinance 6 of <year>1948</year>.
<section><tid>1781428</tid>
<number>1</number>The Exchange of Prisoners  
Ordinance, <year>1948</year> is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>766048</tid>
<number>2</number>The repeal by this Act of the said Ordinance shall not 
affect the previous operation thereof, and any order made, action 
taken, or thing done, in the exercise of any powers conferred by or 
under the said Ordinance shall for all purposes be deemed to have been 
made, taken or done in the exercise of powers conferred by this Act as 
if this Act had commenced on the 20th day of April, <year>1948</year>.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>60</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>