<act><title>THE CENTRAL SALES TAX (REGISTRATION AND 
TURNOVER) RULES, 19571</title> 
 The Central 
Sales Tax (Registration and  Turnover) Rules, 19571
  
 <article><number>1</number> These rules may be called the Central Sales Tax 
(Registration and Turnover) Rules, 1957.
  


</article> 
 The Central 
Sales Tax (Registration and  Turnover) Rules, 1957
  
 <article><number>2</number> In these rules, unless the context otherwise 
requires,—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  ‘Act’ means the 
Central Sales Tax Act, 1956 (74 of 1956);
      
1[(aa)  ‘authorised officer’ means an officer authorised by the 
Central Government under clause (b) of sub-section (4) of section 8;]
   
2[(aaa)  ‘company’ means a company as defined in section 3 of the 
Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) and includes a foreign company within the 
meaning of section 591 of that Act;]
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  ‘Form’ means a 
form appended to these rules;
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  ‘notified 
authority’ means the authority specified under sub-section (1) of section 7;
      
1[(cc)  ‘prescribed authority’ means the authority empowered by the 
Central Government under 3[sub-section (2) 
of section 9], or the authority prescribed by a State Government under clause 
(e) of sub-section (4) of section 13, as the case may be;]
 </section><section>       <number>d</number>  ‘section’ means 
a section of the Act;
 </section><section>       <number>e</number>  ‘warehouse’ 
means any enclosure, building or vessel in which a dealer keeps a stock of goods 
for sale.
  




</section></article> 
 The 
Central Sales Tax (Registration and  
Turnover) Rules, 1957
  
 <article><number>3</number> Certificate of 
registration.—
<section><number>1</number> An application for 
registration under 
section 7 shall be made by a dealer to the notified authority in Form A and 
shall be—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  signed by the proprietor of the business, or, in 
the case of a firm, by one of its partners, or, in the case of a Hindu undivided 
family, by the karta or manager of the family, or, in the case of a company by a 
director, managing agent or principal officer thereof, or, in the case of a 
Government, by an officer duly authorised by that Government, or, in the case of 
any other association of individuals by the principal officer managing the 
business, and 
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  verified in the manner provided in the said Form 
A.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Where a dealer has more than 
one place of business within a State, he shall make a single application in 
respect of all such places, name in such application one of such places as the 
principal place of business for the purposes of these rules and submit such 
application to the notified authority specified in respect of the principal 
place of business so named:
 Provided that any place so named 
shall not in any case be different from the place, if any, declared by him to be 
the principal place of business, by whatever name called, under the general 
sales tax law of the State.
  
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> </title>
<section><number>1</number> An application for registration under sub-section (1) 
of section 7 shall be made not later than thirty days from the date on which the 
dealer becomes liable to pay tax under the Act. 
 
 
 __________
 </section><section><number>2</number> An application for registration under sub-section (2) of section 7 may 
  be made at any time after the commencement of the Act. 
 </section><section>[<number>3</number> A fee of 2 [rupees twenty-five] shall be payable in 
  respect of every application for registration under sub-rule (1) or sub-rule 
  (2) and such fee may be paid in the form of court-fee stamps affixed to such 
  application. </section><section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 644, dated 28th February, 1957, published in 
Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II,  Sec. 3, dated 28th February, 1957.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Ins. by S.R.O. 896, dated 23rd September, 1957 (w.e.f. 
1-10-1958 ). 
  </section></article> 
 The Central 
Sales Tax (Registration and  Turnover) Rules, 1957
  
 <article><number>5</number> 
<section><number>1</number> When the notified authority is satisfied, after 
making such enquiry as it thinks necessary, that the particulars contained in 
the application are correct and complete 1[and the fee referred to in sub-rule (3) of rule 4 has 
been paid], it shall register the dealer and grant him a certificate of 
registration in Form ‘B’ and also a copy of such certificate for every place of 
business within the State other than the principal place of business mentioned 
therein.
 1[(2) When the said authority is not satisfied that the 
particulars contained in the application are correct and complete, or where the 
fee referred to in sub-rule (3) of rule 4 has not been paid, he shall reject the 
application for reasons to be recorded in writing:
 Provided that before the 
application is rejected, the applicant shall be given an opportunity of being 
heard in the matter and, as the case may be, or correcting and completing the 
said particulars or complying with the requirements of sub-rule (3) of rule 
4.]
  


</section></article> 
 The Central 
Sales Tax (Registration and  Turnover) Rules, 1957
  
 <article><number>6</number> The certificate of registration granted under 
sub-rule 
<section><number>1</number> of rule 5 shall be kept at the principal place of business 
mentioned in such certificate and a copy of such certificate granted under the 
said sub-rule shall be kept at every place of business within the State other 
than the principal place of business, mentioned in certificate.
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> </title>
<section><number>1</number> Where a dealer desires the certificates of 
registration granted to him under these rules to be amended, he shall submit an 
application for this purpose to the notified authority setting out the specific 
matters in respect of which he desires such amendment and the reasons therefor, 
together with the certificate of registration and the copies thereof, if any, 
granted to him; and such authority may, if satisfied with the reasons given, 
make such amendments as it thinks necessary, in the certificate of registration 
and the copies thereof, if any, granted to him
 . (2) The provisions of rule 6 shall apply in relation to such amended 
certificate and copies thereof, as they apply in relation to the original 
certificate and copies thereof. 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 644, dated 28th February, 1957, 
published in Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3, dated 28th February, 
1957. </section></article> 
 The Central 
Sales Tax (Registration and  Turnover) Rules, 1957
  
 <article>1[<number>8</number> 
<section><number>1</number> Where the certificate of registration 
granted to a dealer is lost, destroyed, defaced or mutilated, he may on 
application made in this behalf to the notified authority and payment of a fee 
of 2[rupees five] obtain a duplicate copy of such 
certificate.
 3[(2) The fee payable under sub-rule (1) shall be paid 
in the form of court-fee stamps.]




</section></article> 
 The 
Central Sales Tax (Registration and  
Turnover) Rules, 1957
  
 <article>

1[<number>9</number> Amendment or cancellation of 
certificate of registration.—
<section><number>1</number> A notified authority shall, before amending 
or cancelling, as the case may be, the certificate of registration of a dealer 
under sub-section (4) of section 7 give him an opportunity of being heard in the 
matter.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If the certificate of 
registration is proposed to be amended, the dealer shall forthwith produce to 
the notified authority the certificate of registration and the copies thereof, 
if any, granted to him, for having them amended.
 </section><section><number>3</number> If the certificate of 
registration is cancelled, the dealer shall forthwith surrender to the notified 
authority the certificate of registration and the copies thereof, if any granted 
to him.]
  



</section></article> 
 The Central 
Sales Tax (Registration and  Turnover) Rules, 1957
  
 <article><number>10</number> If any dealer desires to apply under sub-section (5) 
of section 7 for the cancellation of his registration, he shall submit within 
the time specified in that sub-section to the notified authority an application 
in that behalf together with the certificate of registration and copies thereof, 
if any, granted to him; and such application shall be dealt with in accordance 
with the provisions of that sub-section.</article> 
 The 
Central Sales Tax (Registration and  
Turnover) Rules, 1957
  
 <article><number>11</number> Determination of turnover.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The period of turnover in relation to any dealer liable to pay tax under this 
Act shall be the same as the period in respect of which he is liable to submit 
returns under the general sales tax law of the appropriate State:
 Provided that in relation to a 
dealer who is not liable to submit returns under the general sales tax law of 
the appropriate State, the period of turnover shall be a quarter ending on the 
30th June, 30th September, 31st December and 31st March, as the case may be, in 
a financial year.
</section></article> 
 The Central 
Sales Tax (Registration and  Turnover) Rules, 1957
  
 <article>1[<number>12</number> 
<section><number>1</number> The declaration and the certificate 
referred to in sub-section (4) of section 8 shall be in Forms C and D 
respectively:
 2[Provided that Form C in force before the commencement 
of the Central Sales Tax (Registration and Turnover) (Amendment) Rules, 1974, or 
before the commencement of the Central Sales Tax (Registration and Turnover) 
(Amendment) Rules, 1976, may also be used upto the 3[31st December, 1979] with suitable 
modifications:]]
 4[***]
 5[Provided further that a single declaration may cover 
all transactions of sale, which take place in a quarter of a financial year 
between the same two dealers:
 Provided also that where, in the 
case of any transaction of sale, the delivery of goods is spread over to 
different quarters in a financial year or of different financial years, it shall 
be necessary to furnish a separate declaration or certificate in respect of 
goods delivered in each quarter of a financial year.]
 6[(2) Where a blank or duly completed form of 
declaration is lost, whether such loss occurs while it is in the custody of the 
purchasing dealer or in transit to the selling dealer, the purchasing dealer 
shall furnish in respect of every such form so lost an indemnity bond 
6[in Form G] to the notified authority from whom the 
said form was obtained, for such sum as the said authority may having regard to 
the circumstances of the case, fix. Such indemnity bond shall be furnished by 
the selling dealer to the notified authority of his State if a duly completed 
form of declaration received by him is lost, whether such loss occurs while it 
is in his custody or while it is in transit to the notified authority of his 
State:]
 7[Provided that where more than one form of declaration 
is lost, the purchasing dealer or the selling dealer, as the case may be, may 
furnish one such indemnity bond to cover all the forms of declarations so 
lost.]
 6[(3) Where a declaration form furnished by the dealer 
purchasing the goods or the certificate furnished by the Government has been 
lost, the dealer selling the goods, may demand from the dealer who purchased the 
goods or, as the case may be, from the Government, which purchased the goods, a 
duplicate of such form or certificate, and the same shall be furnished with the 
following declaration recorded in red ink and signed by the dealer or authorised 
officer or the Government, as the case may be, on all the three portions of such 
form or certificate:—
             
“I hereby declare that this is the duplicate of the declaration form/certificate 
No............. signed on.................and issued 
to................................... who is registered dealer 
of.................. (State) and whose registration certificate number 
is..................”]
 8[(4) The certificate referred to in sub-section (2) of 
section 6 shall be in Form E I or Form E II, as the case may be.]
 9[(5) The declaration referred to in sub-section (1) of 
section 6A shall be in Form F.
 10[Provided that a single declaration may cover transfer 
of goods, by a dealer, to any other place of his business or to his agent or 
principal, as the case may be, effected during a period of one calendar 
month:
 Provided further that if the space 
provided in Form F is not sufficient for making the entries, the particulars 
specified in Form ‘F’ may be given in separate annexures attached to that form 
so long as it is indicated in the form that the annexures form part thereof and 
every such annexure is also signed by the person signing the declaration in Form 
F:
 Provided further that Form F in 
force/before the commencement of the Central Sales Tax (Registration and 
Turnover) (Second Amendment) Rules, 1973 may continue to be used up to 31st day 
of December, 11[1980] with suitable modifications.]
 12[(6) Form C referred to in sub-rule (1) or, as the 
case may be, Form F referred to in sub-rule (5), shall be the one obtained by 
the purchasing dealer or, as the case may be, the transferee in the State in 
which the goods covered by such form are delivered.]
 13[Explanation.—Where, by reason of the 
purchasing dealer not being registered under section 7 in the State in which the 
goods covered by Form C referred to in sub-rule (1) are delivered, he is not 
able to obtain the said form in that State, Form C may be the one obtained by 
him in the State in which he is registered under the said section.]
 14[(7) The declaration in Form C or Form F or the 
certificate in Form E-I or Form E-II shall be furnished to the prescribed 
authority within three months after the end of the period to which the 
declaration or the certificate relates:
 Provided that if the prescribed 
authority is satisfied that the person concerned was prevented by sufficient 
cause from furnishing such declaration or certificate within the aforesaid time, 
that authority may allow such declaration or certificate to be furnished within 
such further time as that authority may permit.]
 12[(8) (a) The person referred to in clause (a) of 
sub-rule (1) of rule 3 shall alone be competent to sign the declaration in Form 
C or Form F or the certificate in Form E I or Form E II]:
 15[Provided that where such person is a proprietor of 
any business or a partner of a firm or a karta or manager of a Hindu Undivided 
Family, any other person authorised by him in writing may also sign such 
declaration or certificate:]
 10[Provided further that in the case of a company 
16[such declaration or certificate] can also be signed 
by any other officer of the company authorised under the Memorandum or Articles 
of Association of the company or under any other special or general resolution 
of the company or under a resolution passed by the Board of Directors of the 
company, to authenticate any document on behalf of such company.]
 17[(b) Such person shall signify on such declaration or 
certificate his status and shall make a verification in the manner provided in 
such declaration or certificate.]
 </section><section><number>9</number> 18[(a)] The provisions of 19[***] sub-rule (2) and sub-rule (3) shall, with 
necessary modifications, apply to the declaration in Form F or the certificate 
in Form E I or Form E II.
 20[(b) The provisions of the second and third provisos 
to sub-rule (1) shall, with necessary modifications, apply to certificates in 
Form E I or Form E II.]
 21[(10) 22[(a) the declaration referred to in sub-section (4) of 
section 5 shall be in Form H and shall be furnished to the prescribed authority 
upto the time of assessment by the first assessing authority.]
 23[***]
 <subsection><number>b</number> The provisions of the rules 
framed by the respective State Governments under sub-sections (3), (4) and (5) 
of section 13 relating to authority from whom and the conditions subject to 
which any form of certificate in Form H may be obtained, the manner in which 
such form shall be kept in custody and records relating thereto maintained and 
the manner in which any such forms may be used and any such certificate may be 
furnished insofar as they apply to declaration in Form C prescribed under these 
rules shall mutatis mutandis apply to certificate in Form H.]
 24[(11) The declaration referred to in sub-section (8) 
of section 8 of the Act, shall be in Form I.]
 25[(11A) The certificate referred to in sub-section (4) 
of section 6 shall be in Form J and shall be furnished to the prescribed 
authority upto the time of assessment by the first assessing 
authority.]
 17[(12) If any person commits a breach of any of these 
rules, he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees 
and when the offence is a continuing offence, with a daily fine which may extend 
to fifty rupees for every day during which the offence continues.]
  






























</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article>[ <title><number>13</number> Prescription of goods for certain purposes 
</title>.—The goods referred to in clause (b) of sub-section (3) of section 8 
which a registered dealer may purchase, shall be goods intended for use by him 
as raw materials, processing materials, 11 [machinery, plant,] equipment, tools, 
stores, spare parts, accessories, fuel or lubricants, in the manufacture or 
processing of goods for sale, or in mining, or in the generation or distribution 
of electricity or any other form of power.] 
 ___________
 <section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 644, dated 28th February, 1957, 
published in Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3, dated 28th February, 
1957. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 896, dated 23rd September, 1958 . 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article>[ <title><number>14</number> </title>If any person commits a breach of any of 
these rules, he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to five hundred 
rupees and when the offence is a continuing offence, with a daily fine which may 
extend to fifty rupees for every day during which the offence continues.] 
 ___________
 <section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 644, dated 28th February, 1957, 
published in Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3, dated 28th February, 
1957.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 56(E), dated 9th February, 1973 (w.e.f. 
1-4-1973 ). </section></article><form>
 


THE CABLE TELEVISION NETWORKS
RULES, 1994
 


 
 



1[FORM 1
 


[See rule 3(1)]
 


(To be submitted in duplicate)
 


Form of 
application for *registration/renewal of  

registration/issue of duplicate certificate of  

registration as a cable operator
 


To
 


The Head Postmaster
 


Head Post Office
 


...............................
 


Application for *registration/renewal of 
registration/issue of duplicate certificate of registration as a cable 
operator.
 


         1. (a) Name of Applicant 
(individual/firm/company/association of persons/body of individuals)*
 


             (b) Age/Date of 
establishment/Date of incorporation.
 


         2. (a) Address (Office)
 


 
(b)     Telephone number (if any).
 


         3. (a) Nationality (for individual 
applicants/body of individuals)
 


             (b) By birth/domicile
 


         
4. (a) Amount of fee paid for *registration/renewal/issue of duplicate 
certificate Rs..........
 


             (b)     Name of Head Post 
Office..................................................................
 


              (Attach copy of challan 
vide which the fees have been deposited)
 


         5. Area in which cable television 
network is working/proposed to be set up.
 


         6.  Date from which the cable 
television network is operating/proposed to be set up..............
 


         7. Number of channels being 
provided/proposed to be provided (with names).
 


         8. (a) Whether using Television 
Receive Only (TVRO)                  Yes/No
 


             (b) If Yes, number and size of 
TVRO.............................
 


             (c) 
Location...................................
 


         9. Names of Doordarshan satellite 
channels included in cable service.....................
 


       10. Copy of earlier registration 
certificate enclosed.                    Yes/No
 


              (To be filled in only for 
renewal of registration).
 


       11. (a) State reasons for issue of 
duplicate certificate of registration.......................
 


                  (Attach mutilated or 
defaced original certificate of registration/copy of report made to the police 
in case of theft or loss of the original certificate)
 


             (b) Period validity of the 
original Registration Certificate for which the duplicate Registration 
Certificate is being sought........................
 


              (To be filled in only for 
issue of duplicate Registration Certificate)]
 


       12.  Declaration if Form 2 enclosed. 
                                 Yes/No
 


I/We ................................ the 
applicant(s) *(individual/firm/company/association of persons/body of 
individuals) do hereby declare that the above facts are correct in all respect.
 




 
 


 
 



                                                                                                                                Signature of Applicant
 



                                                                                                                           
*(individual/firm/company/
 



                                                                                                                             
association of persons/
 



                                                                                                                                
body of individuals)
 



Place.............................                                                                                            
Name................................
 



Date..............................                                                                                            Address.............................
 


* Score out the word or words which are not 
applicable.]
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Subs. by G.S.R. 459(E), dated 8th 
October, 1996 (w.e.f. 8-10-1996).
 


 
 


 
</form><form>
 

The 
Central Sales Tax (Registration and  

Turnover) Rules, 1957
 

 
 

FORM B
 

[See rule 5(1)]
 


Certificate of registration
 

No. .......................... 
(Central)
 

This is to certify that 
................... whose principal place of business within the State of 
................ is situated at .............. has been registered as a dealer 
under section 7(1)/ 7(2) of the Central Sales Tax Act, 1956.
 

The business is:
 

      wholly *
 

      mainly
 

      partly
 

      partly
 

      partly
 


1[The 
class(es) of goods specified for the purposes of sub-sections (1) and (3) of 
section 8 of the said Act is/are as follows and the sales of these goods in the 
course of inter-State trade to the dealer shall be taxable at the rate specified 
in that sub-section subject to the provisions of sub-section (4) of the said 
section:—
 

       (a)  for re-sale
 

       (b)  for use in manufacture or processing of goods 
for sale
 

       (c)  for use in mining
 

       (d)  for use in the generation or distribution of 
electricity or any other form of power
 

       (e)  for use in the packing of goods for sale/resale.
 

The dealer manufactures, 
processes, or extracts in mining the following classes of goods or generates or 
distributes the following form of power, namely:—
 


.............................................................................................................................................
 


........................................................................................................................................]
 

The dealer’s year for the purpose 
of accounts runs from ........... day of ............. to the ............... 
day of ..........
 

The dealer has no additional place 
of business/has additional place(s) of business as stated below:
 

(a)  in the State of registration
 

(b)  in other States.
 

The dealer keeps warehouses at the 
following places within the State of registration:—
 

(1)
 

(2)
 

(3)
 

This certificate is valid from 
................. until cancelled.      
 


                                                                                      
Signed ..................
 


                                                                                      
(Notified authority)
 

Date .................. (Seal)
 

—————
 

    *  Enter here whether 
business is wholly agriculture, horticulture, mining, manufacturing, wholesale 
distribution, retail distribution, contracting or catering, etc., or any 
combination of two or more of them.
 

   1. Subs. by S.R.O. 896, dated 
23rd September, 1958 (w.e.f. 1-10-1958).
 

 
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 395 
(E), dated 14th April, 1987.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>  Subs. by 
G.S.R. 962 (E), dated 30th December, 1976.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>