<act><tid>206650</tid>
<title>THE CODE OF CIVIL PROCEDURE (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 22 OF <year>2002</year>
[ 23rd May, <year>2002</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> and to 
provide for matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>695605</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>610637</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Code  
of Civil Procedure (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>457938</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint, and different 
dates may be appointed for different provisions of this Act and for 
different States or for different parts thereof.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>30062</tid>
<number>2</number>Amendment of section 39.- In section 39 of the Code of Civil 
Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the principal  
  Act), after sub- section (3), the following sub- section shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (4) Nothing in this section shall be deemed to authorise the Court 
which passed a decree to execute such decree against any person or 
property outside the local limits of its jurisdiction.".



</article>



<article><tid>1961567</tid>
<number> 3</number> Amendment of section 64.- Section 64 of the principal Act shall be 
renumbered as sub- section
<section><tid>712762</tid>
<number>1</number>of that section and after sub- section  
 (1) as so renumbered, the following sub- section shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" (2) Nothing in this section shall apply to any private transfer or 
delivery of the property attached or of any interest therein, made in 
pursuance of any contract for such transfer or delivery entered into 
and registered before the attachment.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>304643</tid>
<number>4</number>Substitution of new section for section 100A.- For section 100A of 
the principal Act[ as substituted by section 10 of the Code of Civil 
Procedure (Amendment) Act, <year>1999</year> (46 of <year>1999</year>)], the following section 
shall be substituted, namely:-
" 100A. No further appeal in certain cases.- Notwithstanding anything 
contained in any Letters Patent for any High Court or in any 
instrument having the force of law or in any other law for the time 
being in force, where any appeal from an original or appe late decree 
or order is heard and decided by a Single Judge of a High Court, no 
further appeal shall lie from the judgment and decree of such Single 
Judge.".



</article>



<article><tid>763353</tid>
<number>5</number>Substitution of new section for section 102.- For section 102 of 
the principal Act[ as substituted by section 11 of the Code of Civil 
Procedure (Amendment) Act, <year>1999</year> (46 of <year>1999</year>)], the following section 
shall be substituted, namely:-
" 102. No second appeal in certain cases.- No second appeal shall lie 
from any decree, when the subject matter of the original suit is for 
recovery of money not exceeding twenty- five thousand rupees.".



</article>



<article><tid>1140974</tid>
<number> 6</number> Amendment of Order V.- In the First Schedule to the principal Act 
 (hereinafter referred to as the First Schedule), in Order V,-
<section><tid>156584</tid>
<number>i</number>in rule 1, for sub- rule (1)[ as substituted by clause (i) of 
section 15 of the Code of Civil Procedure (Amendment) Act, <year>1999</year> (46 of  
  <year>1999</year>)], the following sub- rule shall be substituted, namely:-
" (1) When a suit has been duly instituted, a summons may be issued to 
the defendant to appear and answer the claim and to file the written 
statement of his defence, if any, within thirty days from the date of 
service of summons on that defendant:

Provided that no such summons shall be issued when a defendant has 
appeared at the presentation of plaint and admitted the plaintiff' s 
claim: Provided further that where the defendant fails to file the 
written statement within the said period of thirty days, he shall be 
allowed to file the same on such other day as may be specified by the 
Court, for reasons to be recorded in writing, but which shall not be 
later than ninety days from the date of service of summons.";


</section>

<section><tid>879627</tid>
<number>ii</number>for rule <footcitenum>9</footcitenum> as substituted by clause (v) of section 15 of the 
Code of Civil Procedure (Amendment) Act, <year>1999</year> (46 of <year>1999</year>)], the 
following rules shall be substituted, namely:-
" 9. Delivery of summons by Court.- (1) Where the defendant resides 
within the jurisdiction of the Court in which the suit is instituted, 
or has an agent resident within that jurisdiction who is empowered to 
accept the service of the summons, the summons s all, unless the Court 
otherwise directs, be delivered or sent either to the proper officer 
to be served by him or one of his subordinates or to such courier 
services as are approved by the Court.


<subsection><tid>1497799</tid>
<number>2</number>The proper officer may be an officer of a Court other than that in 
which the suit is instituted, and, where he is such an officer, the 
summons may be sent to him in such manner as the Court may direct.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>862147</tid>
<number>3</number>The services of summons may be made by delivering or transmitting 
a copy thereof by registered post acknowledgment due, addressed to the 
defendant or his agent empowered to accept the service or by speed 
post or by such courier services as are approv d by the High Court or 
by the Court referred to in sub- rule (1) or by any other means of 
transmission of documents (including fax message or electronic mail  
  service) provided by the rules made by the High Court:
Provided that the service of summons under this sub- rule shall be made 
at the expenses of the plaintiff.


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1262553</tid>
<number>4</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- rule (1), where a 
defendant resides outside the jurisdiction of the Court in which the 
suit is instituted, and the Court directs that the service of summons 
on that defendant may be made by such mode of servi e of summons as is 
referred to in sub- rule (3)  (except by registered post acknowledgment  
  due), the provisions of rule 21 shall not apply.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>527650</tid>
<number>5</number>When an acknowledgment or any other receipt purporting to be 
signed by the defendant or his agent is received by the Court or 
postal article containing the summons is received back by the Court 
with an endorsement purporting to have been made by a po tal employee 
or by any person authorised by the courier service to the effect that 
the defendant or his agent had refused to take delivery of the postal 
article containing the summons or had refused to accept the summons by 
any other means specified in s b- rule (3) when tendered or transmitted 
to him, the Court issuing the summons shall declare that the summons 
had been duly served on the defendant:
Provided that where the summons was properly addressed, pre- paid and 
duly sent by registered post acknowledgment due, the declaration 
referred to in this sub- rule shall be made notwithstanding the fact 
that the acknowledgment having been lost or mislaid, or for any other 
reason, has not been received by the Court within thirty days from the 
date of issue of summons.


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>527537</tid>
<number>6</number>The High Court or the District Judge, as the case may be, shall 
prepare a panel of courier agencies for the purposes of sub- rule (1).

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>418265</tid>
<number> 9A</number> Summons given to the plaintiff for service.-
<section><tid>937678</tid>
<number>1</number>The Court may, in  
addition to the service of summons under rule 9, on the application of 
the plaintiff for the issue of a summons for the appearance of the 
defendant, permit such plaintiff to effect ser ice of such summons on 
such defendant and shall, in such a case, deliver the summons to such 
plaintiff for service.

</section>

<section><tid>1603407</tid>
<number>2</number>The service of such summons shall be effected by or on behalf of 
such plaintiff by delivering or tendering to the defendant personally 
a copy thereof signed by the Judge or such officer of the Court as he 
may appoint in this behalf and sealed with th seal of the Court or by 
such mode of service as is referred to in sub- rule (3) of rule 9.

</section>

<section><tid>400154</tid>
<number>3</number>The provisions of rules 16 and 18 shall apply to a summons 
personally served under this rule as if the person effecting service 
were a serving officer.

</section>

<section><tid>1362321</tid>
<number>4</number>If such summons, when tendered, is refused or if the person served 
refuses to sign an acknowledgment of service or for any reason such 
summons cannot be served personally, the Court shall, on the 
application of the party, re- issue such summons to be erved by the 
Court in the same manner as a summons to a defendant.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>804955</tid>
<number>7</number>Amendment of Order VI.- In the First Schedule, in Order VI, for 
rules 17 and <footcitenum>18</footcitenum> as they stood immediately before their omission by 
clause (iii) of section 16 of the Code of Civil Procedure (Amendment) 
Act, <year>1999</year> (46 of <year>1999</year>)], the following rules shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 17. Amendment of pleadings.- The Court may at any stage of the 
proceedings allow either party to alter or amend his pleadings in such 
manner and on such terms as may be just, and all such amendments shall 
be made as may be necessary for the purpose of de ermining the real 
questions in controversy between the parties:

Provided that no application for amendment shall be allowed after the 
trial has commenced, unless the Court comes to the conclusion that in 
spite of due diligence, the party could not have raised the matter 
before the commencement of trial.

</article>



<article><tid>649919</tid>
<number>18</number>Failure to amend after Order.- If a party who has obtained an 
order for leave to amend does not amend accordingly within the time 
limited for that purpose by the order, or if no time is thereby 
limited then within fourteen days from the date of the or er, he shall 
not be permitted to amend after the expiration of such limited time as 
aforesaid or of such fourteen days, as the case may be, unless the 
time is extended by the Court.".


</article>



<article><tid>1229568</tid>
<number> 8</number> Amendment of Order VII.- In the First Schedule, in Order VII,-
<section><tid>1823851</tid>
<number>i</number>for rule <footcitenum>9</footcitenum> as substituted by clause (i) of section 17 of the Code 
of Civil Procedure (Amendment) Act, <year>1999</year> (46 of <year>1999</year>)], the following 
rule shall be substituted, namely:-
" 9. Procedure on admitting plaint.- Where the Court orders that the 
summons be served on the defendants in the manner provided in rule 9 
of Order V, it will direct the plaintiff to present as many copies of 
the plaint on plain paper as there are defendant within seven days 
from the date of such order along with requisite fee for service of 
summons on the defendants.";


</section>

<section><tid>436178</tid>
<number>ii</number>in rule 11, for sub- clauses (f) and (g)[ as inserted by clause 
 (ii) of section 17 of the Code of Civil Procedure (Amendment) Act, 
 <year>1999</year> (46 of <year>1999</year>)], the following sub- clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (f) where the plaintiff fails to comply with the provisions of rule 
9.";


</section>

<section><tid>600494</tid>
<number>iii</number>in rule <footcitenum>14</footcitenum> as substituted by clause (iii) of section 17 of the 
Code of Civil Procedure (Amendment) Act, <year>1999</year> (46 of <year>1999</year>)], for 
sub- rule (3), the following sub- rule shall be substituted, namely:-
" (3) A document which ought to be produced in Court by the plaintiff 
when the plaint is presented, or to be entered in the list to be added 
or annexed to the plaint but is not produced or entered accordingly, 
shall not, without the leave of the Court, be received in evidence on 
his behalf at the hearing of the suit.";


</section>

<section><tid>1403676</tid>
<number>iv</number>rule <footcitenum>18</footcitenum> as amended by clause (v) of section 17 of the Code of 
Civil Procedure (Amendment) Act, <year>1999</year> (46 of <year>1999</year>)] shall be omitted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>981126</tid>
<number> 9</number> Amendment of Order VIII.- In the First Schedule, in Order VIII,- 
 (i) for rule <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as substituted by clause (i) of section 18 of the Code 
of Civil Procedure (Amendment) Act, <year>1999</year> (46 of <year>1999</year>)], the following 
rule shall be substituted, namely:-
" 1. Written statement.- The defendant shall, within thirty days from 
the date of service of summons on him, present a written statement of 
his defence: Provided that where the defendant fails to file the 
written statement within the said period of thirty days, he shall be 
allowed to file the same on such other day, as may be specified by the 
Court, for reasons to be recorded in writing, but which shall ot be 
later than ninety days from the date of service of summons.";

<section><tid>91502</tid>
<number>ii</number>in rule 1A[ as inserted by clause (ii) of section 18 of the Code 
of Civil Procedure (Amendment) Act, <year>1999</year> (46 of <year>1999</year>)], for sub- rule 
 (3), the following sub- rule shall be substituted, namely:-
" (3) A document which ought to be produced in Court by the defendant 
under this rule, but, is not so produced shall not, without the leave 
of the Court, be received in evidence on his behalf at the hearing of 
the suit.";


</section>

<section><tid>1421393</tid>
<number>iii</number>for rules 9 and <footcitenum>10</footcitenum> as they stood immediately before their 
omission by clause (iii) of section 18 of the Code of Civil Procedure 
 (Amendment) Act, <year>1999</year> (46 of <year>1999</year>)], the following rules shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" 9. Subsequent pleadings.- No pleading subsequent to the written 
statement of a defendant other than by way of defence to set off or 
counter- claim shall be presented except by the leave of the Court and 
upon such terms as the Court thinks fit; but the Cou t may at any 
time require a written statement or additional written statement from 
any of the parties and fix a time of not more than thirty days for 
presenting the same.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>144109</tid>
<number>10</number>Procedure when party fails to present written statement called 
for by Court.- Where any party from whom a written statement is 
required under rule 1 or rule 9 fails to present the same within the 
time permitted or fixed by the Court, as the case may b, the Court 
shall pronounce judgment against him, or make such order in relation 
to the suit as it thinks fit and on the pronouncement of such judgment 
a decree shall be drawn up.".


</article>



<article><tid>144109</tid>
<number>10</number>Amendment of Order IX.- In the First Schedule, in Order IX, for 
rule <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> as substituted by clause (i) of section 19 of the Code of 
Civil Procedure (Amendment) Act, <year>1999</year> (46 of <year>1999</year>)], the following 
rule shall be substituted, namely:-
" 2. Dismissal of suit where summons not served in consequence of 
plaintiff' s failure to pay costs.- Where on the day so fixed it is 
found that the summons has not been served upon the defendant in 
consequence of the failure of the plaintiff to pay the cou t- fee or 
postal charges, if any, chargeable for such service, or failure to 
present copies of the plaint as required by rule 9 of Order VII, the 
Court may make an order that the suit be dismissed:

Provided that no such order shall be made, if notwithstanding such 
failure, the defendant attends in person or by agent when he is 
allowed to appear by agent on the day fixed for him to appear and 
answer.".



</article>



<article><tid>711331</tid>
<number> 11</number> Amendment of Order XIV.- In the First Schedule, in Order XIV, for 
rule <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> as it stood immediately before its omission by clause (ii) of 
section 24 of the Code of Civil Procedure (Amendment) Act, <year>1999</year> (46 of  
  <year>1999</year>)], the following rule shall be substitu ed, namely:-
" 5. Power to amend, and strike out, issues.- (1) The Court may at any 
time before passing a decree amend the issues or frame additional 
issues on such terms as it thinks fit, and all such amendments or 
additional issues as may be necessary for determining the matters in 
controversy between the parties shall be so made or framed.

<section><tid>993054</tid>
<number>2</number>The Court may also, at any time before passing a decree, strike 
out any issues that appear to it to be wrongly framed or introduced.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1796361</tid>
<number> 12</number> Amendment of Order XVIII.- In the First Schedule, in Order XVIII,- 
 (a) in rule 2, after sub- rule (3), the following sub- rules shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (3A) Any party may address oral arguments in a case, and shall, 
before he concludes the oral arguments, if any, submit if the Court so 
permits concisely and under distinct headings written arguments in 
support of his case to the Court and such written a guments shall form 
part of the record.

<section><tid>798327</tid>
<number>3B</number>A copy of such written arguments shall be simultaneously 
furnished to the opposite party.

</section>

<section><tid>1160084</tid>
<number>3C</number>No adjournment shall be granted for the purpose of filing the 
written arguments unless the Court, for reasons to be recorded in 
writing, considers it necessary to grant such adjournment.

</section>

<section><tid>1437266</tid>
<number>3D</number>The Court shall fix such time- limits for the oral arguments by 
either of the parties in a case, as it thinks fit.";

<subsection><tid>1553483</tid>
<number>b</number>for rule <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> as substituted by clause (ii) of section 27 of the 
Code of Civil Procedure (Amendment) Act, <year>1999</year> (46 of <year>1999</year>)], the 
following rule shall be substituted, namely:-
" 4. Recording of evidence.- (1) In every case, the 
examination- in- chief of a witness shall be on affidavit and copies 
thereof shall be supplied to the opposite party by the party who calls 
him for evidence:

Provided that where documents are filed and the parties rely upon the 
documents, the proof and admissibility of such documents which are 
filed along with affidavit shall be subject to the orders of the 
Court.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>792440</tid>
<number>2</number>The evidence (cross- examination and re- examination) of the witness 
in attendance, whose evidence (examination- in- chief) by affidavit has 
been furnished to the Court, shall be taken either by the Court or by 
the Commissioner appointed by it:
Provided that the Court may, while appointing a commission under this 
sub- rule, consider taking into account such relevant factors as it 
thinks fit.


</section>

<section><tid>978594</tid>
<number>3</number>The Court or the Commissioner, as the case may be, shall record 
evidence either in writing or mechanically in the presence of the 
Judge or of the Commissioner, as the case may be, and where such 
evidence is recorded by the Commissioner he shall retur such evidence 
together with his report in writing signed by him to the Court 
appointing him and the evidence taken under it shall form part of the 
record of the suit.

</section>

<section><tid>572110</tid>
<number>4</number>The Commissioner may record such remarks as it thinks material 
respecting the demeanour of any witness while under examination: 
Provided that any objection raised during the recording of evidence 
before the Commissioner shall be recorded by him and decided by the 
Court at the stage of arguments.

</section>

<section><tid>1407204</tid>
<number>5</number>The report of the Commissioner shall be submitted to the Court 
appointing the commission within sixty days from the date of issue of 
the commission unless the Court for reasons to be recorded in writing 
extends the time.

</section>

<section><tid>661057</tid>
<number>6</number>The High Court or the District Judge, as the case may be, shall 
prepare a panel of Commissioners to record the evidence under this 
rule.

</section>

<section><tid>1675161</tid>
<number>7</number>The Court may by general or special order fix the amount to be 
paid as remuneration for the services of the Commissioner.

</section>

<section><tid>524817</tid>
<number>8</number>The provisions of rules 16, 16A, 17 and 18 of Order XXVI, in so 
far as they are applicable, shall apply to the issue, execution and 
return of such commission under this rule.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>112876</tid>
<number>13</number>Amendment of Order XX.- In the First Schedule, in Order XX, in 
rule 1, for sub- rule 1, the following sub- rule shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (1) The Court, after the case has been heard, shall pronounce 
judgment in an open Court, either at once, or as soon thereafter as 
may be practicable and when the judgment is to be pronounced on some 
future day, the Court shall fix a day for that purpose of which due 
notice shall be given to the parties or their pleaders:

Provided that where the judgment is not pronounced at once, every 
endeavour shall be made by the Court to pronounce the judgment within 
thirty days from the date on which the hearing of the case was 
concluded but, where it is not practicable so to do on he ground of 
the exceptional and extraordinary circumstances of the case, the Court 
shall fix a future day for the pronouncement of the judgment, and such 
day shall not ordinarily be a day beyond sixty days from the date on 
which the hearing of the case as concluded, and due notice of the day 
so fixed shall be given to the parties or their pleaders.".



</article>



<article><tid>651074</tid>
<number> 14</number> Amendment of Order XXI.- In the First Schedule, in Order XXI,- (a) 
in rule 32, in sub- rule (5), the following Explanation shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" Explanation.- For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that 
the expression" the act required to be done" covers prohibitory as 
well as mandatory injunctions.";

<section><tid>775618</tid>
<number>b</number>in rule 92, in sub- rule (2),-

<subsection><tid>568021</tid>
<number>i</number>for the words" thirty days", the words" sixty days" shall be 
substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1274935</tid>
<number>ii</number>after the first proviso, the following proviso shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" Provided further that the deposit under this sub- rule may be made 
within sixty days in all such cases where the period of thirty days, 
within which the deposit had to be made, has not expired before the 
commencement of the Code of Civil Procedure (Amend ent) Act, <year>2002</year>.".




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>299466</tid>
<number> 15</number> Amendment of the Code of Civil Procedure (Amendment) Act, 
<year>1999</year>.- In the Code of Civil Procedure (Amendment) Act, <year>1999</year> (46 of  
  <year>1999</year>),-
<section><tid>1032856</tid>
<number>a</number>section 30 shall be omitted;

</section>

<section><tid>1747155</tid>
<number>b</number>in section 32, in sub- section (2),-

<subsection><tid>66131</tid>
<number>i</number>clauses (g) and (h) shall be omitted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1254724</tid>
<number>ii</number>for clause (j), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (j) the provisions of rules 1, 2, 6, 7, 9, 9A, 19A, 21, 24 and 25 of 
Order V of the First Schedule as amended or, as the case may be, 
substituted or omitted by section 15 of this Act, and by section 6 of 
the Code of Civil Procedure (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year> shall not apply to 
in respect of any proceedings pending before the commencement of 
section 15 of this Act and section 6 of the Code of Civil Procedure 
 (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>;";


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>660820</tid>
<number>iii</number>for clause (k), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (k) the provisions of rules 9, 11, 14, 15 and 18 of Order VII of the 
First Schedule as amended or, as the case may be, substituted or 
omitted by section 17 of this Act and by section 8 of the Code of 
Civil Procedure (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>, shall not appl to in respect of 
any proceedings pending before the commencement of section 17 of this 
Act and section 8 of the Code of Civil Procedure (Amendment) Act, 
<year>2002</year>;";


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>345667</tid>
<number>iv</number>for clause (l), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (l) the provisions of rules 1, 1A, 8A, 9 and 10 of Order VIII of the 
First Schedule as substituted or, as the case may be, inserted or 
omitted by section 18 of this Act and by section 9 of the Code of 
Civil Procedure (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>, shall not app y to a written 
statement filed and presented before the commencement of section 18 of 
this Act and section 9 of the Code of Civil Procedure (Amendment) Act, 
<year>2002</year>;";


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>57965</tid>
<number>v</number>for clause (q), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (q) the provisions of rules 4 and 5 of Order XIV of the First 
Schedule as amended or, as the case may be, substituted by section 24 
of this Act and section 11 of the Code of Civil Procedure (Amendment) 
Act, <year>2002</year>, shall not affect any order made by the ourt adjourning the 
framing of the issues and amending and striking out issues before the 
commencement of section 24 of this Act and section 11 of the Code of 
Civil Procedure (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>;";


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1357773</tid>
<number>vi</number>in clause (s), for the figures" 25", at both the places, the 
figures" 26" shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1793704</tid>
<number>vii</number>clause (u) shall be omitted.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>273116</tid>
<number> 16</number> Repeal and savings.-
<section><tid>481088</tid>
<number>1</number>Any amendment made, or any provision  
inserted in the principal Act by a State Legislature or High Court 
before the commencement of this Act shall, except in so far as such 
amendment or provisions are consistent with the princi al Act as 
amended by this Act, stand repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>580761</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding that the provisions of this Act have come into 
force or repeal under sub- section (1) has taken effect, and without 
prejudice to the generality of the provisions of section 6 of the 
General Clauses Act, <year>1897</year> (10 of <year>1897</year>),-

<subsection><tid>706012</tid>
<number>a</number>the provisions of section 102 of the principal Act as substituted 
by section 5 of this Act, shall not apply to or affect any appeal 
which had been admitted before the commencement of section 5; and 
every such appeal shall be disposed of as if section 5 had not come 
into force;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1727853</tid>
<number>b</number>the provisions of rules 5, 15, 17 and 18 of Order VI of the First 
Schedule as omitted or, as the case may be, inserted or substituted by 
section 16 of the Code of Civil Procedure (Amendment) Act, <year>1999</year> (46 of  
  <year>1999</year>) and by section 7 of this Act shall n t apply to in respect of 
any pleading filed before the commencement of section 16 of the Code 
of Civil Procedure (Amendment) Act, <year>1999</year> and section 7 of this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1859536</tid>
<number>c</number>the provisions of rule 1 of Order XX of the First Schedule as 
amended by section 13 of this Act shall not apply to a case where the 
hearing of the case had concluded before the commencement of section 
 13 of this Act.
SUBHASH C. JAIN, 
Secy. to the Govt. of India.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



 </act>