<act><tid>500379</tid>
<title>THE INDUSTRIAL DISPUTES ACT, <year>1947</year></title>

ACT NO. 14 OF <year>1947</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 11th March, <year>1947</year>.]

An Act to make provision for the investigation and settlement of 
industrial disputes, and for certain other purposes.

WHEREAS it is expedient to make provision for the investigation 
and settlement of industrial disputes, and for certain other purposes 
hereinafter appearing;

It is hereby enacted as follows:--

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>100925</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.-
<section><tid>35271</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Industrial Disputes Act, <year>1947</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>529153</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> It extends to the whole of India:
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>


</section>

<section><tid>1866540</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on the first day of April, <year>1947</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1418464</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.- In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant 
in the subject or context,--
<section><tid>1737494</tid>
<number>a</number>" appropriate Government" means--

<subsection><tid>466914</tid>
<number>i</number>in relation to any industrial dispute 
concerning <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> any industry carried on by or under the 
authority of the Central Government, <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> or by a 
railway company <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> or concerning any such controlled 
industry as may be specified in this behalf by the 
Central Government] <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> or in relation to an industrial 
dispute concerning <footcitenum>8</footcitenum> <footcitenum>9</footcitenum> <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>
<pagefootnote><pagenum>146</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been extended to Goa, Daman and Diu by Reg. 12 of 
<year>1962</year>, to Pondicherry (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1963</year>) by Reg. 7 of <year>1963</year> and 
Laccadive, Minicoy and Amindivi Islands by Reg. 8 of <year>1965</year>, s. 3 and 
Sch. 
2. Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 2, for the former sub- section (w. e. f.  
  29- 8- <year>1956</year>). 
3. Proviso omitted by Act 51 of <year>1970</year>, s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 1- 9-  
  <year>1971</year>). 
4. Certain words and figures inserted by Act 10 of <year>1963</year>, s. 47 and 
Sch. II, Pt. II have been omitted by Act 36 of <year>1964</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f.  
  19- 12- <year>1964</year>). 
5. The words" by the Federal Railway Authority" omitted by the A. O. 
<year>1948</year>. 
6. Ins. by Act 65 of <year>1951</year>, s. 32. 
7. The words" operating a Federal Railway" omitted by the A. O. 
<year>1950</year>. 
8. Ins. by Act 47 of <year>1961</year>, s. 51 and Sch. II, Pt. III (w. e. f. 1- 1-  
  <year>1962</year>). 
9. Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1964</year>, s. 2, for" the Deposit Insurance 
Corporation established" (w. e. f. 19- 12- <year>1964</year>). 
10. Subs. by Act 45 of <year>1971</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 15- 12- <year>1971</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


[ a Dock Labour Board established under section 5A of the Dock Workers 
 (Regulation of Employment) Act, <year>1948</year> (9 of <year>1940</year>), or the Industrial 
Finance Corporation of India established under section 3 of the 
Industrial Finance Corporation Act, <year>1948</year> (15 of <year>1948</year>), or the 
Employees' State Insurance Corporation established under section 3 of 
the Employees' State Insurance Act, <year>1948</year> (34 of <year>1948</year>), or the Board of 
Trustees constituted under section 3A of the Coal Mines Provident Fund 
and Miscellaneous Provisions Act, <year>1948</year> (46 of <year>1948</year>), or the Central 
Board of Trustees and the State Boards of Trustees constituted under 
section 5A and section 5B, respectively, of the Employees' Provident 
Fund and Miscellaneous Provisions Act, <year>1952</year> (19 of <year>1952</year>), or the 
" Indian Airlines" and" Air India" Corporations established under 
section 3 of the Air Corporations Act, <year>1953</year> (27 of <year>1953</year>), or the Life 
Insurance Corporation of India established under section 3 of the Life 
Insurance Corporation Act, <year>1956</year> (31 of <year>1956</year>), or the Oil and Natural 
Gas Commission established under section 3 of the Oil and Natural Gas 
Commission Act, <year>1959</year> (43 of <year>1959</year>), or the Deposit Insurance and Credit 
Guarantee Corporation established under section 3 of the Deposit 
Insurance and Credit Guarantee Corporation Act, <year>1961</year> (47 of <year>1961</year>), or 
the Central Warehousing Corporation established under section 3 of the 
Warehousing Corporations Act, <year>1962</year> (58 of <year>1962</year>), or the Unit Trust of 
India established under section 3 of the Unit Trust of India Act, <year>1963</year> 
 (52 of <year>1963</year>), or the Food Corporation of India established under 
section 3, or a Board of Management established for two or more 
contiguous States under section 16, of the Food Corporations Act, <year>1964</year> 
 (37 of <year>1964</year>), or the International Airports Authority of India 
constituted under section 3 of the International Airports Authority of 
India Act, <year>1971</year> (48 of <year>1971</year>), or a Regional Rural Bank established 
under section 3 of the Regional Rural Banks Act, <year>1976</year> (21 of <year>1976</year>), or 
the Export Credit and Guarantee Corporation Limited or the Industrial 
Reconstruction Bank of India <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[ the National Housing Bank established 
under section 3 of the National Housing Bnak Act, <year>1987</year> (53 of <year>1987</year>) 
or] <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> a banking or an insurance company, a mine, an oil- field] <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>, a 
Cantonment Board,] or a major port, the Central Government, and


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1604812</tid>
<number>ii</number>in relation to any other industrial dispute, the 
State Government;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1086345</tid>
<number>aa</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>" arbitrator" includes an umpire;]

</section>

<section><tid>1060177</tid>
<number>aaa</number>]" average pay" means the average of the wages payable 
to a workman--

<subsection><tid>1520375</tid>
<number>i</number>in the case of monthly paid workman, in the three 
complete calendar months,
<pagefootnote><pagenum>147</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1982</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 21- 8- <year>1984</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 53 of <year>1987</year>, s. 56 and Sch. II (w. e. f. 9- 7- <year>1988</year>). 
3. Subs. by Act 54 of <year>1949</year>, s. 3, for" a mine, oil- field". 
4. Ins. by Act 36 of <year>1964</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 19- 12- <year>1964</year>). 
5. Ins. by Act 43 of <year>1953</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 24- 10- <year>1953</year>). 
6. Cl. (aa) relettered as" (aaa)" by Act 36 of <year>1964</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f.  
  19- 12- <year>1964</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1851363</tid>
<number>ii</number>in the case of weekly paid workman, in the four 
complete weeks,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1744572</tid>
<number>iii</number>in the case of daily paid workman, in the twelve 
full working days,
preceding the date on which the average pay becomes payable 
if the workman had worked for three complete calendar 
months or four complete weeks or twelve full working 
days, as the case may be, and where such calculation 
cannot be made, the average pay shall be calculated as 
the average of the wages payable to a workman during 
the period he actually worked;]


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1068433</tid>
<number>b</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>" award" means an interim or a final determination of 
any industrial dispute or of any question relating 
thereto by any Labour Court, Industrial Tribunal or 
National Industrial Tribunal and includes an 
arbitration award made under section 10A;]

</section>

<section><tid>1481351</tid>
<number>bb</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>" banking company" means a banking company as defined 
in section 5 of the Banking Companies Act, <year>1949</year> (10 of  
  <year>1949</year>), having branches or other establishments in more 
than one State, and includes <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Export- Import Bank 
of India <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>, the Industrial Reconstruction Bank of 
India,] <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> the Industrial Development Bank of India,] 
 <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> the Small Industries Development Bank of India 
established under section 3 of the Small Industries 
Development Bank of India Act, <year>1989</year> (39 of <year>1989</year>),] the 
Reserve Bank of India, the State Bank of India <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> a 
corresponding new bank constituted under section 3 of 
the Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of  
  Undertakings) Act, <year>1970</year> (5 of <year>1970</year>), <footcitenum>8</footcitenum> a 
corresponding new bank constituted under section 3 
of the Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer  
  of Undertakings) Act, <year>1980</year> (40 of <year>1980</year>), and any 
subsidiary bank]] as defined in the State Bank of 
India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, <year>1959</year> (38 of <year>1959</year>);]

</section>

<section><tid>929424</tid>
<number>c</number>" Board" means a Board of Conciliation constituted under 
this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1554465</tid>
<number>cc</number><footcitenum>9</footcitenum>" closure" means the permanent closing down of a place of 
employment or part thereof;]

</section>

<section><tid>1738814</tid>
<number>d</number>" conciliation officer" means a conciliation officer 
appointed under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>210486</tid>
<number>e</number>" conciliation proceeding" means any proceeding held by a 
conciliation officer or Board under this Act;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>148</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 3, for cl. (b)  (w. e. f. 10- 3- <year>1957</year>). 
2. Subs. by Act 38 of <year>1959</year>, s. 64 and Sch. III, Pt. II, for cl. (bb) 
which was ins. by Act 54 of <year>1949</year>, s. 3. 
3. Ins. by Act 28 of <year>1981</year>, s. 40 and Sch. II (w. e. f. 1- 1- <year>1982</year>). 
4. Ins. by Act 62 of <year>1984</year>, s. 71 and Sch. III (w. e. f. 20- 3- <year>1985</year>). 
5. Ins. by Act 18 of <year>1964</year>, s. 38 and Sch. II, Pt. II (w. e. f. 1- 7-  
  <year>1964</year>). 
6. Ins. by Act 39 of <year>1989</year>, s. 53 and 2nd Sch. (w. e. f. 7- 3- <year>1990</year>). 
7. Subs. by Act 5 of <year>1970</year>, s. 20, for" and any subsidiary bank" 
 (w. e. f. 19- 7- <year>1969</year>). 
8. Subs. by Act 40 of <year>1980</year>, s. 20 (w. e. f. 15- 4- <year>1980</year>). 
9. Ins. by Act 46 of <year>1982</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 21- 8- <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1498831</tid>
<number>ee</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>" controlled industry" means any industry the control 
of which by the Union has been declared by any Central 
Act to be expedient in the public interest;]
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>


</section>

<section><tid>1275963</tid>
<number>f</number>" Court" means a Court of Inquiry constituted under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>780861</tid>
<number>g</number>" employer" means--

<subsection><tid>180997</tid>
<number>i</number>in relation to an industry carried on by or 
under the authority of any department of <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Central 
Government or a State Government], the authority 
prescribed in this behalf, or where no authority is 
prescribed, the head of the department;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>887857</tid>
<number>ii</number>in relation to an industry carried on by or 
on behalf of a local authority, the chief executive 
officer of that authority;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1971608</tid>
<number>gg</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>" executive", in relation to a trade union, means the 
body, by whatever name called, to which the management 
of the affairs of the trade union is entrusted;]
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum>


<subsection><tid>521141</tid>
<number>i</number>a person shall be deemed to be" independent" for the 
purpose of his appointment as the chairman or other 
member of a Board, Court or Tribunal, if he is 
unconnected with the industrial dispute referred to 
such Board, Court or Tribunal or with any industry 
directly affected by such dispute:
<footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Provided that no person shall cease to be independent by 
reason only of the fact that he is a shareholder of an 
incorporated company which is connected with, or likely 
to be affected by, such industrial dispute; but in such 
a case, he shall disclose to the appropriate Government 
the nature and extent of the shares held by him in such 
company;]


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>942539</tid>
<number>j</number><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>" industry" means any systematic activity carried on 
by co- operation between an employer and his workmen 
 (whether such workmen are employed by such employer  
directly or by or through any agency, including a 
  contractor) for the production, supply or distribution 
of goods or services with a view to satisfy human wants 
or wishes (not being wants or wishes which are merely  
  spiritual or religious in nature), whether or not,--

<subsubsection><tid>1222502</tid>
<number>i</number>any capital has been invested for the purpose 
of carrying on such activity; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1533081</tid>
<number>ii</number>such activity is carried on with a motive to 
make any gain or profit,
and includes--


<subsubsubsection><tid>675344</tid>
<number>a</number>any activity of the Dock Labour Board 
established under section 5A of the Dock Workers 
 (Regulation of Employment) Act, <year>1948</year> (9 of <year>1948</year>);

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>408366</tid>
<number>b</number>any activity relating to the promotion of 
sales or business or both carried on by an 
establishment.
but does not include--


<subsubsubsubsection><tid>1932548</tid>
<number>1</number>any agricultural operation except where such agricultural 
operation is carried on in an integrated manner with any other 
activity (being any such activity as is referred to in the foregoing  
  provisions of this clause) and such other activity is the predominant 
one.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this sub- clause," agricultural 
operation" does not include any activity carried on in a plantation as 
defined in clause (f) of section 2 of the Plantations Labour Act, 
 <year>1951</year> (69 of <year>1951</year>); or


</subsubsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsubsection><tid>1231377</tid>
<number>2</number>hospitals or dispensaries; or

</subsubsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsubsection><tid>1553235</tid>
<number>3</number>educational, scientific, research or training institutions; 
or

</subsubsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsubsection><tid>1117070</tid>
<number>4</number>institutions owned or managed by organisations wholly or 
substantially engaged in any charitable, social or philanthropic 
service; or

</subsubsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsubsection><tid>877675</tid>
<number>5</number>khadi or village industries; or

</subsubsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsubsection><tid>1685215</tid>
<number>6</number>any activity of the Government relatable to the sovereign 
functions of the Government including all the activities carried on by 
the departments of the Central Government dealing with defence 
research, atomic energy and space; or

</subsubsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsubsection><tid>127396</tid>
<number>7</number>any domestic service; or

</subsubsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsubsection><tid>1685898</tid>
<number>8</number>any activity, being a profession practised by an individual 
or body or individuals, if the number of persons employed by the 
individual or body of individuals in relation to such profession is 
less than ten; or

</subsubsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsubsection><tid>504833</tid>
<number>9</number>any activity, being an activity carried on by a co- operative 
society or a club or any other like body of individuals, if the number 
of persons employed by the co- operative society, club or other like 
body of individuals in relation to such activity is less than ten;]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>149</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 65 of <year>1951</year>, s. 32. 
2. Cl. (eee) ins. by Act 43 of <year>1953</year>, s. 2 omitted by Act 36 of <year>1964</year>, 
s. 2 (w. e. f. 19- 12- <year>1964</year>). 
3. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1948</year>, for" a Government in British India". 
4. Ins. by Act 45 of <year>1971</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 15- 12- <year>1971</year>). 
5. Cl. (h) omitted by the A. O. <year>1950</year>. 
6. Ins. by Act 18 of <year>1952</year>, s. 2. 
7. Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1982</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f.-------).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsubsubsubsection>

</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>134216</tid>
<number>k</number>" industrial dispute" means any dispute or difference 
between employers and employers or between employers 
and workmen, or between workmen and workmen, which is 
connected with the employment or non- employment or the 
terms of employment or with the conditions of labour, 
of any person;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1061665</tid>
<number>ka</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>" industrial establishment or undertaking" means an 
establishment or undertaking in which any industry is 
carried on:
Provided that where several activities are carried on in an 
establishment or undertaking and only one or some of such activities 
is or are an industry or industries, then,--


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1566698</tid>
<number>a</number>if any unit of such establishment or undertaking 
carrying on any activity, being an industry, is 
severable from the other unit or units of such 
establishment or undertaking, such unit shall be deemed 
to be a separate industrial establishment or 
undertaking;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>719624</tid>
<number>b</number>if the predominant activity or each of the predominant 
activities carried on in such establishment or 
undertaking or any unit thereof is an industry and the 
other activity or each of the other activities carried 
on in such establishment or undertaking or unit thereof 
is not severable from and is, for the purpose of 
carrying on, or aiding the carrying on of, such 
predominant activity or activities, the entire 
establishment or undertaking or, as the case may be, 
unit thereof shall be deemed to be an industrial 
establishment or undertaking;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>300816</tid>
<number>kk</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>" insurance company" means an insurance company as 
defined in section 2 of the Insurance Act, <year>1938</year> (4 of  
  <year>1938</year>), having branches or other establishments in more 
than one State;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1962971</tid>
<number>kka</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>" khadi" has the meaning assigned to it in clause (d) of 
section 2 of the Khadi and Village Industries Commission Act, <year>1956</year> 
 (61 of <year>1956</year>);]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1503642</tid>
<number>kkb</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>]" Labour Court" means a Labour Court constituted under 
section 7:]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>388557</tid>
<number>kkk</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>" lay- off" (with its grammatical variations and  
  cognate expressions) means the failure, refusal or 
inability of an employer on account of shortage of 
coal, power or raw materials or the accumulation of 
stocks or the breakdown of machinery <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> or natural 
calamity or for any other connected reason] to give 
employment to a workman whose name is borne on the 
muster rolls of his industrial establishment and who 
has not been retrenched.
Explanation.-- Every workman whose name is borne on the 
muster rolls of the industrial establishment and who 
presents himself for work at the establishment at the 
time appointed for the purpose during normal working 
hours on any day and is not given employment by the 
employer within two hours of his so presenting himself 
shall be deemed to have been laid- off for that day 
within the meaning of this clause:

Provided that if the workman, instead of being given 
employment at the commencement of any shift for any day 
is asked to present himself for the purpose during the 
second half of the shift for the day and is given 
employment then, he shall be deemed to have been laid- 
off only for one- half of that day:

Provided further that if he is not given any such employment 
even after so presenting himself, he shall not be 
deemed to have been laid- off for the second half of the 
shift for the day and shall be entitled to full basic 
wages and dearness allowance for that part of the day;]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>150B</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 46 of <year>1984</year> s. 2 (w. e. f. 21- 8- <year>1984</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 54 of <year>1949</year>, s. 3. 
3. Relettered by Act 46 of <year>1984</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 21- 8- <year>1984</year>). 
4. Ins. by Act 43 of <year>1953</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 24- 10- <year>1953</year>). 
5. Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1984</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 21- 8- <year>1984</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>150</number>- 150A

(l) " lock- out" means the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> temporary closing of a place of 
employment] or the suspension of work, or the refusal 
by an employer to continue to employ any number of 
persons employed by him;

(la) <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>" major port" means a major port as defined in clause 
 (8) of section 3 of the Indian Ports Act, <year>1908</year> (15 of  
  <year>1908</year>);

(lb) " mine" means a mine as defined in clause (j) of sub- 
section (1) of section 2 of the Mines Act, <year>1952</year> (35  
  of <year>1952</year>)];

(ll) <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>" National Tribunal" means a National Industrial 
Tribunal constituted under section 7B;]

(lll) <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>" office bearer", in relation to a trade union, 
includes any member of the executive thereof, but does 
not include an auditor;]

(m) " prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

(n) " public utility service" means--

(i) any railway service <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or any transport 
service for the carriage of passengers or goods by air];

(ia) <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> any service in, or in connection with the 
working of, any major port or dock;]

(ii) any section of an industrial establishment, 
on the working of which the safety of the establishment 
or the workmen employed therein depends;

(iii) any postal, telegraph or telephone service;

(iv) any industry which supplies power, light or 
water to the public;

(v) any system of public conservancy or 
sanitation;

(vi) any industry specified in the <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> First 
Schedule] which the appropriate Government may, if 
satisfied that public emergency or public interest so 
requires, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
declare to be a public utility service for the purposes 
of this Act, for such period as may be specified in the 
notification:

Provided that the period so specified shall not, in the 
first instance, exceed six months but may, by a like noti- 
1. Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1982</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 21- 8- <year>1984</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 36 of <year>1964</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 19- 12- <year>1964</year>). 
3. Ins. by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 10- 3- <year>1957</year>). 
4. Ins. by Act 45 of <year>1971</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 15- 12- <year>1971</year>). 
5. Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1964</year>, s. 2, for" Schedule" (w. e. f. 19- 12-  
  <year>1964</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


fication, be extended from time to time, by any period 
not exceeding six months, at any one time if in the 
opinion of the appropriate Government public emergency 
or public interest requires such extension;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>942190</tid>
<number>o</number>" railway company" means a railway company as defined in 
section 3 of the Indian Railways Act, <year>1890</year> (9 of  
  <year>1890</year>);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1462003</tid>
<number>oo</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>" retrenchment means the termination by the employer 
of the service of a workman for any reason whatsoever, 
otherwise than as a punishment inflicted by way of 
disciplinary action, but does not include--

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1566698</tid>
<number>a</number>voluntary retirement of the workman; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>719624</tid>
<number>b</number>retirement of the workman on reaching the age 
of superannuation if the contract of employment between 
the employer and the workman concerned contains a 
stipulation in that behalf; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>623616</tid>
<number>bb</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> termination of the service of the workman 
as a result of the non- renewal of the contract of 
employment between the employer and the workman 
concerned on its expiry or of such contract being 
terminated under a stipulation in that behalf contained 
therein; or] 
 (c) termination of the service of a workman on the 
ground of continued ill- health;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>627438</tid>
<number>p</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>" settlement" means a settlement arrived at in the 
course of conciliation proceeding and includes a 
written agreement between the employer and workmen 
arrived at otherwise than in the course of conciliation 
proceeding where such agreement has been signed by the 
parties thereto in such manner as may be prescribed and 
a copy
<pagefootnote><pagenum>151</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 43 of <year>1953</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 24- 10- <year>1953</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 49 of <year>1984</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 18- 8- <year>1984</year>). 
3. Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 3, for cl. (p)  (w. e. f. 7- 10- <year>1956</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


thereof has been sent to <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> an officer authorised in 
this behalf by] the appropriate Government and the 
conciliation officer;]


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>7552</tid>
<number>q</number>" strike" means a cessation of work by a body of persons 
employed in any industry acting in combination or a 
concerted refusal, or a refusal under a common 
understanding, of any number of persons who are or have 
been so employed to continue to work or to accept 
employment;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>765744</tid>
<number>qq</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>" trade union" means a trade union registered under 
the Trade Unions Act, <year>1926</year> (16 of <year>1926</year>);]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>861177</tid>
<number>r</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>" Tribunal" means an Industrial Tribunal constituted 
under section 7A and includes an Industrial Tribunal 
constituted before the 10th day of March, <year>1957</year>, under 
this Act;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>13713</tid>
<number>ra</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>" unfair labour practice" means any of the practices 
specified in the Fifth Schedule;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>805086</tid>
<number>rb</number>" village industries" has the meaning assigned to it in 
clause (h) of section 2 of the Khadi and Village 
Industries Commission Act, <year>1956</year> (61 of <year>1956</year>);]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1266650</tid>
<number>rr</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>" wages" means all remuneration capable of being 
expressed in terms of money, which would, if the terms 
of employment, expressed or implied, were fulfilled, be 
payable to a workman in respect of his employment or of 
work done in such employment, and includes--

<subsubsection><tid>1030972</tid>
<number>i</number>such allowances (including dearness allowance) 
as the workman is for the time being entitled to;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>426761</tid>
<number>ii</number>the value of any house accommodation, or of 
supply of light, water, medical attendance or other 
amenity or of any service or of any concessional supply 
of food- grains or other articles;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>940903</tid>
<number>iii</number>any travelling concession;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1089253</tid>
<number>iv</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> any commission payable on the promotion 
of sales or business or both;]
but does not include--


<subsubsubsection><tid>243921</tid>
<number>a</number>any bonus;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>869514</tid>
<number>b</number>any contribution paid or payable by the 
employer to any pension fund or provident fund or for the 
benefit of the workman under any law for the time being in 
force;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>569593</tid>
<number>c</number>any gratuity payable on the termination of his 
service;]

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1622002</tid>
<number>s</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>" workman" means any person (including an apprentice) 
employed in any industry to do any manual, unskilled, skilled, 
technical, operational, clerical or supervisory work for hire or 
reward, whether the terms of employment be express or implied, and for 
the purposes of any proceeding under this Act in relation to an 
industrial dispute, includes any such person who has been dismissed, 
discharged or retrenched in connection with, or as a consequence of, 
that dispute, or whose dismissal, dischasrge or retrenchment has led 
to that dispute, but does not include any such person--

</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1030972</tid>
<number>i</number>who is subject to the Air Force Act, <year>1950</year> (45 of <year>1950</year>), 
or the Army Act, <year>1950</year> (46 of <year>1950</year>), or the Navy Act, 
 <year>1957</year> (62 of <year>1957</year>); or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>426761</tid>
<number>ii</number>who is employed in the police service or as an officer 
or other employee of a prison; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>940903</tid>
<number>iii</number>who is employed mainly in a managerial or 
administrative capacity; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1089253</tid>
<number>iv</number>who, being employed in a supervisory capacity, draws 
wages exceeding one thousand six hundred rupees per 
mensem or exercises, either by the nature of the duties 
attached to the office or by reason of the powers 
vested in him, functions mainly of a managerial 
nature.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>152</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 35 of <year>1965</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 12- <year>1965</year>). 
2. Ins. and Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1982</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 21- 8- <year>1984</year>). 
3. Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1957</year>, s. 2, for cl. (r)  (w. e. f. 10- 3- <year>1957</year>). 
4. Ins. by Act 43 of <year>1953</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 24- 10- <year>1953</year>). 
5. Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1982</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 21- 8- <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1377486</tid>
<number>2A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Dismissal, etc., of an individual workman to be deemed to 
be an industrial dispute.- Where any employer discharges, dismisses, 
retrenches, or otherwise terminates the services of an individual 
workman, any dispute or difference between that workman and his 
employer connected with, or arising out of, such discharge, dismissal, 
retrenchment or termination shall be deemed to be an industrial 
dispute notwithstanding that no other workman nor any union of workmen 
is a party to the dispute.]
CHAP

AUTHORITIES UNDER THIS ACT

CHAPTER II

AUTHORITIES UNDER THIS ACT



</article>



<article><tid>452505</tid>
<number> 3</number> Works Committee.-
<section><tid>136693</tid>
<number>1</number>In the case of any industrial  
establishment in which one hundred or more workmen are employed or 
have been employed on any day in the preceding twelve months, the 
appropriate Government may by general or special order require the 
employer to constitute in the prescribed manner a Works Committee 
consisting of representatives of employers and workmen engaged in the 
establishment so however that the number of representatives of workmen 
on the Committee shall not be less than the number of representatives 
of the
<pagefootnote><pagenum>153</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 35 of <year>1965</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 1- 12- <year>1965</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


employer. The representatives of the workmen shall be chosen in the 
prescribed manner from among the workmen engaged in the establishment 
and in consultation with their trade union, if any, registered under 
the Indian Trade Unions Act, <year>1926</year> (16 of <year>1926</year>).


</section>

<section><tid>1589950</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be the duty of the Works Committee to promote 
measures for securing and preserving amity and good relations between 
the employer and workmen and, to that end, to comment upon matters of 
their common interest or concern and endeavour to compose any material 
difference of opinion in respect of such matters.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>185363</tid>
<number> 4</number> Conciliation officers.-
<section><tid>1984843</tid>
<number>1</number>The appropriate Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, appoint such number of persons 
as it thinks fit, to be conciliation officers, charged with the duty of 
mediating in and promoting the settlement of industrial disputes.

</section>

<section><tid>472538</tid>
<number>2</number>A conciliation officer may be appointed for a specified area 
or for specified industries in a specified area or for one or more 
specified industries and either permanently or for a limited period.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>746513</tid>
<number> 5</number> Boards of Conciliation.-
<section><tid>295741</tid>
<number>1</number>The appropriate Government may as  
occasion arises by notification in the Official Gazette constitute a 
Board of Conciliation for promoting the settlement of an industrial 
dispute.

</section>

<section><tid>842032</tid>
<number>2</number>A Board shall consist of a chairman and two or four other 
members, as the appropriate Government thinks fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1348151</tid>
<number>3</number>The chairman shall be an independent person and the other 
members shall be persons appointed in equal numbers to represent the 
parties to the dispute and any person appointed to represent a party 
shall be appointed on the recommendation of that party:
Provided that, if any party fails to make a recommendation as 
aforesaid within the prescribed time, the appropriate Government shall 
appoint such persons as it thinks fit to represent that party.


</section>

<section><tid>1390260</tid>
<number>4</number>A Board, having the prescribed quorum, may act 
notwithstanding the absence of the chairman or any of its members or 
any vacancy in its number:
Provided that if the appropriate Government notifies the Board 
that the services of the chairman or of any other member have ceased 
to be available, the Board shall not act until a new chairman or 
member, as the case may be, has been appointed.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1080978</tid>
<number> 6</number> Courts of Inquiry.-
<section><tid>1112581</tid>
<number>1</number>The appropriate Government may as  
occasion arises by notification in the Official Gazette constitute a 
Court of Inquiry for inquiring into any matter appearing to be 
connected with or relevant to an industrial dispute.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>154</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>331762</tid>
<number>2</number>A Court may consist of one independent person or of such 
number of independent persons as the appropriate Government may think 
fit and where a Court consists of two or more members, one of them 
shall be appointed as the chairman.

</section>

<section><tid>1146987</tid>
<number>3</number>A Court, having the prescribed quorum, may act 
notwithstanding the absence of the chairman or any of its members or 
any vacancy in its number:
Provided that, if the appropriate Government notifies the Court 
that the services of the chairman have ceased to be available, the 
Court shall not act until a new chairman has been appointed.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1150040</tid>
<number> 7</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Labour Courts.-
<section><tid>1733215</tid>
<number>1</number>The appropriate Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, constitute one or more Labour 
Courts for the adjudication of industrial disputes relating to any 
matter specified in the Second Schedule and for performing such other 
functions as may be assigned to them under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1046242</tid>
<number>2</number>A Labour Court shall consist of one person only to be 
appointed by the appropriate Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1027647</tid>
<number>3</number>A person shall not be qualified for appointment as the 
presiding officer of a Labour Court, unless--

<subsection><tid>1494230</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> he is, or has been, a Judge of a High Court; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1906883</tid>
<number>b</number>he has, for a period of not less than three years, been 
a District Judge or an Additional District Judge; or
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1928474</tid>
<number>d</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>] he has held any judicial office in India for not 
less than seven years; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1379056</tid>
<number>e</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>] he has been the presiding officer of a Labour Court 
constituted under any Provincial Act or State Act for 
not less than five years.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>658901</tid>
<number> 7A</number> Tribunals.-
<section><tid>794361</tid>
<number>1</number>The appropriate Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, constitute one or more 
Industrial Tribunals for the adjudication of industrial disputes 
relating to any matter, whether specified in the Second Schedule or 
the Third Schedule <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> and for performing such other functions as may 
be assigned to them under this Act].
<pagefootnote><pagenum>155</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 4, for s. 7 (w. e. f. 10- 3- <year>1957</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 36 of <year>1964</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 19- 12- <year>1964</year>). 
3. Omitted by Act 46 of <year>1982</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 21- 8- <year>1984</year>). 
4. Clauses (a) and (b) relettered as (d) and (e) respectively by 
Act 36 of <year>1964</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 19- 12- <year>1964</year>). 
5 Ins. by Act 46 of <year>1982</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 21- 8- <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>474720</tid>
<number>2</number>A Tribunal shall consist of one person only to be appointed 
by the appropriate Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1494163</tid>
<number>3</number>A person shall not be qualified for appointment as the 
presiding officer of a Tribunal unless--

<subsection><tid>1790848</tid>
<number>a</number>he is, or has been, a Judge of a High Court; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1851950</tid>
<number>aa</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> he has, for a period of not less than three years, 
been a District Judge or an Additional District Judge; 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> xxx]
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1064899</tid>
<number>4</number>The appropriate Government may, if it so thinks fit, appoint 
two persons as assessors to advise the Tribunal in the proceeding 
before it.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>835880</tid>
<number> 7B</number> National Tribunals.-
<section><tid>105264</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, constitute one or more National 
Industrial Tribunals for the adjudication of industrial disputes 
which, in the opinion of the Central Government, involve questions of 
national importance or are of such a nature that industrial 
establishments situated in more than one State are likely to be 
interested in, or affected by, such disputes.

</section>

<section><tid>1767251</tid>
<number>2</number>A National Tribunal shall consist of one person only to be 
appointed by the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1942373</tid>
<number>3</number>A person shall not be qualified for appointment as the 
presiding officer of a National Tribunal <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> unless he is, or has been, 
a Judge of a High Court].

</section>

<section><tid>1951303</tid>
<number>4</number>The Central Government may, if it so thinks fit, appoint two 
persons as assessors to advise the National Tribunal in the proceeding 
before it.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1090754</tid>
<number> 7C</number> Disqualifications for the presiding officers of Labour 
Courts, Tribunals and National Tribunals.- No person shall be appointed 
to, or continue in, the office of the presiding officer of a Labour 
Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal, if--
<section><tid>1219202</tid>
<number>a</number>he is not an independent person; or

</section>

<section><tid>649362</tid>
<number>b</number>he has attained the age of sixty- five years.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>156</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 36 of <year>1964</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 19- 12- <year>1964</year>). 
2. Omitted by Act 46 of <year>1982</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 21- 8- <year>1984</year>). 
3. Subs. by s. 5, ibid (w. e. f. 21- 8- <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>310761</tid>
<number>8</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Filling of vacancies.- If, for any reason a vacancy (other  
  than a temporary absence) occurs in the office of the presiding 
officer of a Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal or in the 
office of the chairman or any other member of a Board or Court, then, 
in the case of a National Tribunal, the Central Government and in any 
other case, the appropriate Government, shall appoint another person 
in accordance with the provisions of this Act to fill the vacancy, and 
the proceeding may be continued before the Labour Court, Tribunal, 
National Tribunal, Board or Court, as the case may be, from the stage 
at which the vacancy is filled.


</article>



<article><tid>1376184</tid>
<number> 9</number> Finality of orders constituting Boards, etc.-
<section><tid>1780845</tid>
<number>1</number>No order of  
the appropriate Government or of the Central Government appointing any 
person as the chairman or any other member of a Board or Court or as 
the presiding officer of a Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal 
shall be called in question in any manner; and no act or proceeding 
before any Board or Court shall be called in question in any manner on 
the ground merely of the existence of any vacancy in, or defect in the 
constitution of, such Board or Court.

</section>

<section><tid>1106012</tid>
<number>2</number>No settlement arrived at in the course of a conciliation 
proceeding shall be invalid by reason only of the fact that such 
settlement was arrived at after the expiry of the period referred to 
in sub- section (6) of section 12 or sub- section (5) of section 13, as 
the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>210927</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the report of any settlement arrived at in the course 
of conciliation proceeding before a Board is signed by the chairman 
and all the other members of the Board, no such settlement shall be 
invalid by reason only of the casual or unforeseen absence of any of 
the members (including the chairman) of the Board during any stage of 
the proceeding.]
CHAP

NOTICE OF CHANGE

<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> CHAPTER IIA

NOTICE OF CHANGE




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>620295</tid>
<number> 9A</number> Notice of change.- No employer, who proposes to effect any 
change in the conditions of service applicable to any workman in 
respect of any matter specified in the Fourth Schedule, shall effect 
such change,--
<section><tid>1234967</tid>
<number>a</number>without giving to the workmen likely to be affected by 
such change a notice in the prescribed manner of the 
nature of the change proposed to be effected; or
<pagefootnote><pagenum>157</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 5, for ss. 8 and 9 (w. e. f. 10- 3-  
  <year>1957</year>). 
2. Ins. by s. 6, ibid. (w. e. f. 10- 3- <year>1957</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>557901</tid>
<number>b</number>within twenty- one days of giving such notice:
Provided that no notice shall be required for effecting any 
such change--


</section>

<section><tid>1234967</tid>
<number>a</number>where the change is effected in pursuance of any 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> settlement or award]; or

</section>

<section><tid>557901</tid>
<number>b</number>where the workmen likely to be affected by the change 
are persons to whom the Fundamental and Supplementary 
Rules, Civil Services (Classification, Control and  
  Appeal) Rules, Civil Services (Temporary Service) 
Rules, Revised Leave Rules, Civil Service Regulations, 
Civilians in Defence Services (Classification, Control  
  and Appeal) Rules or the Indian Railway Establishment 
Code or any other rules or regulations that may be 
notified in this behalf by the appropriate Government 
in the Official Gazette, apply.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1549308</tid>
<number>9B</number>Power of Government to exempt.- Where the appropriate 
Government is of opinion that the application of the provisions of 
section 9A to any class of industrial establishments or to any class 
of workmen employed in any industrial establishment affect the 
employers in relation thereto so prejudicially that such application 
may cause serious repercussion on the industry concerned and that 
public interest so requires, the appropriate Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, direct that the provisions of 
the said section shall not apply or shall apply, subject to such 
conditions as may be specified in the notification, to that class of 
industrial establishments or to that class of workmen employed in any 
industrial establishment.]
CHAP

REFERENCE OF CERTAIN INDIVIDUAL DISPUTES TO GRIEVANCE SETTLEMENTAUTHORITIES

<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> CHAPTER IIB

REFERENCE OF CERTAIN INDIVIDUAL DISPUTES TO GRIEVANCE SETTLEMENT 
AUTHORITIES



</article>



<article><tid>292819</tid>
<number> 9C</number> Setting up of Grievance Settlement Authorities and reference 
of certain individual disputes to such authorities.-
<section><tid>816729</tid>
<number>1</number>The employer  
in relation to every industrial establishment in which fifty or more 
workmen are employed or have been employed on any day in the preceding 
twelve months, shall provide for, in accordance with the rules made in 
that behalf under this Act, a Grievance Settlement Authority for the 
settlement of industrial disputes connected with an individual workman 
employed in the establishment.

</section>

<section><tid>634794</tid>
<number>2</number>Where an industrial dispute connected with an individual 
workman arises in an establishment referred to in sub- section (1), a 
workman or any trade union of workmen of which such workman is a 
member, refer, in such manner as may be prescribed such dispute to the 
Grievance Settlement Authority provided for by the employer under that 
sub- section for settlement.

</section>

<section><tid>1543801</tid>
<number>3</number>The Grievance Settlement Authority referred to in sub- section 
 (1) shall follow such procedure and complete its proceedings within 
such period as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1171093</tid>
<number>4</number>No reference shall be made under Chapter III with respect to 
any dispute referred to in this section unless such dispute has been 
referred to the Grievance Settlement Authority concerned and the 
decision of the Grievance Settlement Authority is not acceptable to 
any of the parties to the dispute.]
CHAP

REFERENCE OF DISPUTES TO BOARDS, COURTS OR TRIBUNALS

CHAPTER III

REFERENCE OF DISPUTES TO BOARDS, COURTS OR TRIBUNALS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1669932</tid>
<number> 10</number> Reference of disputes to Boards, Courts or Tribunals.-
<section><tid>760439</tid>
<number>1</number> 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Where the appropriate Government is of opinion that any industrial 
dispute exists or is apprehended, it may at any time], by order in 
writing,--

<subsection><tid>630305</tid>
<number>a</number>refer the dispute to a Board for promoting a settlement 
thereof; or
<pagefootnote><pagenum>158</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1982</year>, s. 6 (w. e. f. 21- 8- <year>1984</year>). 
2. Ins. by s. 7, ibid. (w. e. f..........). 
3. Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1952</year>, s. 3, for" If any industrial dispute 
exists or is apprehended, the appropriate Government may".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1552619</tid>
<number>b</number>refer any matter appearing to be connected with or 
relevant to the dispute to a Court for inquiry; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1218044</tid>
<number>c</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> refer the dispute or any matter appearing to be 
connected with, or relevant to, the dispute, if it 
relates to any matter specified in the Second Schedule, 
to a Labour Court for adjudication; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1869167</tid>
<number>d</number>refer the dispute or any matter appearing to be 
connected with, or relevant to, the dispute, whether it 
relates to any matter specified, in the Second Schedule 
or the Third Schedule, to a Tribunal for adjudication:
Provided that where the dispute relates to any matter 
specified in the Third Schedule and is not likely to 
affect more than one hundred workmen, the appropriate 
Government may, if it so thinks fit, make the reference 
to a Labour Court under clause (c):]

<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Provided further that] where the dispute relates to a 
public utility service and a notice under section 22 
has been given, the appropriate Government shall, 
unless it considers that the notice has been 
frivolously or vexatiously given or that it would be 
inexpedient so to do, make a reference under this sub- 
section notwithstanding that any other proceedigns 
under this Act in respect of the dispute may have 
commenced:

<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Provided also that where the dispute in relation to which the 
Central Government is the appropriate Government, it shall be 
competent for that Government to refer the dispute to a Labour Court 
or an Industrial Tribunal, as the case may be, constituted by the 
State Government;]


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1224721</tid>
<number>1A</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Where the Central Government is of opinion that any 
industrial dispute exists or is apprehended and the dispute involves 
any question of national importance or is of such a nature that 
industrial establishments situated in more than one State are likely 
to be interested in, or affected by, such dispute and that the dispute 
should be adjudicated by a National Tribunal, then, the Central 
Government may, whether or not it is the appropriate Government in 
relation to that dispute, at any time, by order in writing, refer the 
dispute or any matter appearing to be connected with, or relevant to, 
the dispute, whether it relates to any matter specified in the Second 
Schedule or the Third Schedule, to a Natoinal Tribunal for 
adjudication.]

</section>

<section><tid>1871842</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the parties to an industrial dispute apply in the 
prescribed manner, whether jointly or separately, for a reference of 
the dispute to a Board, Court <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Labour Court, Tribunal or National
<pagefootnote><pagenum>159</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 7, for cl. (c)  (w. e. f. 10- 3- <year>1957</year>). 
2. Subs. by s. 7, ibid., for" Provided that" (w. e. f. 10- 3- <year>1957</year>). 
3. Ins. by Act 46 of <year>1982</year>, s. 8 (w. e. f. 21- 8- <year>1984</year>). 
4. Ins. by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 7 (w. e. f. 10- 3- <year>1957</year>). 
5. Subs. by s. 7, ibid., for" or Tribunal" (w. e. f. 10- 3- <year>1957</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Tribunal], the appropriate Government, if satisfied that the persons 
applying represent the majority of each party, shall make the 
reference accordingly.


</section>

<section><tid>510565</tid>
<number>2A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> An order referring an industrial dispute to a Labour 
Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal under this section shall specify 
the period within which such Labour Court, Tribunal or National 
Tribunal shall submit its award on such dispute to the appropriate 
Government:
Provided that where such industrial dispute is connected with an 
individual workman, no such period shall exceed three months:

Provided further that where the parties to an industrial dispute 
apply in the prescribed manner, whether jointly or separately, to the 
Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal for extension of such 
period or for any other reason, and the presiding officer of such 
Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal considers it necessary or 
expedient to extend such period, he may for reasons to be recorded in 
writing, extend such period by such further period as he may think 
fit:

Provided also that in computing any period specified in this sub- 
section, the period, if any, for which the proceedings before the 
Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal had been stayed by any 
injunction or order of a Civil Court shall be excluded:

Provided also that no proceedings before a Labour Court, Tribunal 
or National Tribunal shall lapse merely on the ground that any period 
specified under this sub- section had expired without such proceedings 
being completed.]


</section>

<section><tid>352098</tid>
<number>3</number>Where an industrial dispute has been referred to a Board, 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal] under this section, 
the appropriate Government may by order prohibit the continuance of 
any strike or lock- out in connection with such dispute which may be in 
existence on the date of the reference.

</section>

<section><tid>506329</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Where in an order referring an industrial dispute to <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> a 
Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal] under this section or in 
a subsequent order, the appropriate Government has specified the 
points of dispute for adjudication, <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> the Labour Court or the 
Tribunal or the National Tribunal, as the case may be] shall confine 
its adjudication to those points and matters incidental thereto.

</section>

<section><tid>922839</tid>
<number>5</number>Where a dispute concerning any establishment or establishments 
has been, or is to be, referred to a <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Labour Court, Tribunal or 
National Tribunal] under this section and the appropriate Government 
is of opinion, whether on an application made to it in this behalf or 
otherwise, that the dispute is of such a nature that any other 
establishment, group or class of establishments of a similar nature is 
likely to be interested in, or affected by, such dispute, the 
appropriate Government may, at the time of making the reference or at 
any time thereafter but before the submission of the award, include in 
that reference such establishment, group or class of establishments, 
whether or not at the time of such inclusion any dispute exists or is 
apprehended in that establishment, group or class of establishments.]

</section>

<section><tid>1773426</tid>
<number>6</number><footcitenum>7</footcitenum> Where any reference has been made under sub- section (1A) 
to a National Tribunal, then notwithstanding anything contained in 
this Act, no Labour Court or Tribunal shall have jurisdiction to 
adjudicate upon any matter which is under adjudication before the 
National Tribunal, and accordingly,--

<subsection><tid>1519367</tid>
<number>a</number>if the matter under adjudication before the National 
Tribunal is pending in a proceeding before a Labour 
Court or Tribunal, the proceeding before the Labour 
Court or the Tribunal, as the case may be, in so far as 
it relates to
<pagefootnote><pagenum>160</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 46 of <year>1982</year>, s. 8 (w. e. f. 21- 8- <year>1984</year>). 
2. Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 7, for" or Tribunal" (w. e. f. 10- 3-  
  <year>1957</year>). 
3. Ins. by Act 18 of <year>1952</year>, s. 3. 
4. Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 7, for" a Tribunal" (w. e. f. 10- 3-  
  <year>1957</year>). 
5. Subs. by s. 7, ibid., for" the Tribunal" (w. e. f. 10- 3- <year>1957</year>). 
6. Subs. by s. 7. ibid., for" Tribunal" (w. e. f. 10- 3- <year>1957</year>). 
7. Ins. by s. 7, ibid. (w. e. f. 10- 3- <year>1957</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


such matter, shall be deemed to have been quashed on 
such reference to the National Tribunal; and


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>722617</tid>
<number>b</number>it shall not be lawful for the appropriate Government to 
refer the matter under adjudication before the National 
Tribunal to any Labour Court or Tribunal for 
adjudication during the pendency of the proceeding in 
relation to such matter before the National Tribunal.
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Explanation.-- In this sub- section," Labour Court" or 
" Tribunal" includes any Court or Tribunal or other authority 
constituted under any law relating to investigation and settlement of 
industrial disputes in force in any State.]


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1865483</tid>
<number>7</number>Where any industrial dispute, in relation to which the 
Central Government is not the appropriate Government, is referred to a 
National Tribunal, then notwithstanding anything contained in this 
Act, any reference in section 15, section 17, section 19, section 33A, 
section 33B and section 36A to the appropriate Government in relation 
to such dispute shall be construed as a reference to the Central 
Government but, save as aforesaid and as otherwise expressly provided 
in this Act, any reference in any other provision of this Act to the 
appropriate Government in relation to that dispute shall mean a 
reference to the State Government.]

</section>

<section><tid>180489</tid>
<number>8</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> No proceedings pending before a Labour Court, Tribunal or 
National Tribunal in relation to an industrial dispute shall lapse 
merely by reason of the death of any of the parties to the dispute 
being a workman, and such Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal 
shall complete such proceedings and submit its award to the 
appropriate Government.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>483312</tid>
<number> 10A</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Voluntary reference of disputes to arbitration.-
<section><tid>1563477</tid>
<number>1</number>Where  
any industrial dispute exists or is apprehended and the employer and 
the workmen agree to refer the dispute to arbitration, they may, at 
any time before the dispute has been referred under section 10 to a 
Labour Court or Tribunal or National Tribunal, by a written agreement, 
refer the dispute to arbitration and the reference shall be to such 
person or persons (including the presiding officer of a Labour Court  
  or Tribunal or National Tribunal) as an arbitrator or arbitrators as 
may be specified in the arbitration agreement.

</section>

<section><tid>177355</tid>
<number>1A</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Where an arbitration agreement provides for a reference 
of the dispute to an even number of arbitrators, the agreement shall 
provide for the appointment of another person as umpire who shall 
enter upon the reference, if the arbitrators are equally divided in 
their opinion, and the award of the umpire shall prevail and shall be 
deemed to be the arbitration award for the purposes of this Act.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>161</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 36 of <year>1964</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 19- 12- <year>1964</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 46 of <year>1982</year>, s. 8 (w. e. f. 21- 8- <year>1984</year>). 
3. Ins. by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 8 (w. e. f. 10- 3- <year>1957</year>). 
4. Ins. by s. 6, ibid. (w. e. f. 19- 12- <year>1964</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>834531</tid>
<number>2</number>An arbitration agreement referred to in sub- section (1) shall 
be in such form and shall be signed by the parties thereto in such 
manner as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>990253</tid>
<number>3</number>A copy of the arbitration agreement shall be forwarded to the 
appropriate Government and the conciliation officer and the 
appropriate Government shall, within <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> one month] from the date of 
the receipt of such copy, publish the same in the Official Gazette.

</section>

<section><tid>791878</tid>
<number>3A</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Where an industrial dispute has been referred to 
arbitration and the appropriate Government is satisfied that the 
persons making the reference represent the majority of each party, the 
appropriate Government may, within the time referred to in sub- section 
 (3) issue a notification in such manner as may be prescribed; and when 
any such notification is issued, the employers and workmen who are not 
parties to the arbitration agreement but are concerned in the dispute, 
shall be given an opportunity of presenting their case before the 
arbitrator or arbitrators.]

</section>

<section><tid>271873</tid>
<number>4</number>The arbitrator or arbitrators shall investigate the dispute 
and submit to the appropriate Government the arbitration award signed 
by the arbitrator or all the arbitrators, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1381872</tid>
<number>4A</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Where an industrial dispute has been referred to 
arbitration and a notification has been issued under sub- section (3A), 
the appropriate Government may, by order, prohibit the continuance of 
any strike or lock- out in connection with such dispute which may be in 
existence on the date of the reference.]

</section>

<section><tid>685822</tid>
<number>5</number>Nothing in the Arbitration Act, <year>1940</year> (10 of <year>1940</year>), shall 
apply to arbitrations under this section.]
CHAP

PROCEDURE, POWERS AND DUTIES OF AUTHORITIES

CHAPTER IV

PROCEDURE, POWERS AND DUTIES OF AUTHORITIES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>31217</tid>
<number> 11</number> Procedure and powers of conciliation officers, Boards, Courts 
and Tribunals.- <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1453874</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to any rules that may be made in this  
behalf, an arbitrator, a Board, Court, Labour Court, Tribunal or 
National Tribunal shall follow such procedure as the arbitrator or 
other authority concerned may think fit.]

</section>

<section><tid>195886</tid>
<number>2</number>A conciliation officer or a member of a Board, <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> or Court or 
the presiding officer of a Labour Court, Tribunal or National 
Tribunal]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>162</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1964</year>, s. 6, for" fourteen days" (w. e. f. 19- 12-  
  <year>1964</year>). 
2. Ins. by s. 6, ibid. (w. e. f. 19- 12- <year>1964</year>). 
3. Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 9, for sub- section (1)  (w. e. f. 10- 3-  
  <year>1957</year>). 
4. Subs. by s. 9, ibid., for" Court or Tribunal" (w. e. f. 10- 3- <year>1957</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


may for the purpose of inquiry into any existing or apprehended 
industrial dispute, after giving reasonable notice, enter the premises 
occupied by any establishment to which the dispute relates.


</section>

<section><tid>867674</tid>
<number>3</number>Every Board, Court, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Labour Court, Tribunal and National 
Tribunal] shall have the same powers as are vested in a Civil Court 
under the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>), when trying a 
suit, in respect of the following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1320185</tid>
<number>a</number>enforcing the attendance of any person and examining him 
on oath;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>492842</tid>
<number>b</number>compelling the production of documents and material 
objects;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>448816</tid>
<number>c</number>issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>838694</tid>
<number>d</number>in respect of such other matters as may be prescribed;
and every inquiry or investigation by a Board, Court, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Labour Court, 
Tribunal or National Tribunal], shall be deemed to be a judicial 
proceeding within the meaning of sections 193 and 228 of the Indian 
Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>).


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>450810</tid>
<number>4</number>A conciliation officer <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> may enforce the attendance of any 
person for the purpose of examination of such person or call for] and 
inspect any document which he has ground for considering to be 
relevant to the industrial dispute <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> or to be necessary for the 
purpose of verifying the implementation of any award or carrying out 
any other duty imposed on him under this Act, and for the aforesaid 
purposes, the conciliation officer shall have the same powers as are 
vested in a Civil Court under the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of  
  <year>1908</year>), <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> in respect of enforcing the attendance of any person and 
examining him or of compelling the production of documents].

</section>

<section><tid>235818</tid>
<number>5</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> A Court, Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal may, 
if it so thinks fit, appoint one or more persons having special 
knowledge of the matter under consideration as assessor or assessors 
to advise it in the proceeding before it.

</section>

<section><tid>1776670</tid>
<number>6</number>All conciliation officers, members of a Board or Court and 
the presiding officers of a Labour Court, Tribunal or National 
Tribunal shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of 
section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>1203418</tid>
<number>7</number>Subject to any rules made under this Act, the costs of, and 
incidental to, any proceeding before a Labour Court, Tribunal or 
National Tribunal shall be in the discretion of that Labour Court,
<pagefootnote><pagenum>163</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 9, for" and Tribunal" (w. e. f. 10- 3-  
  <year>1957</year>). 
2. Subs. by s. 9, ibid., for" or Tribunal" (w. e. f. 10- 3- <year>1957</year>). 
3. Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1982</year>, s. 9 (w. e. f. 21- 8- <year>1984</year>). 
4. Ins. by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 9 (w. e. f. 17- 9- <year>1956</year>). 
5. Subs. by s. 9, ibid., for sub- sections (5) to (7)  (w. e. f. 10- 3-  
  <year>1957</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Tribunal or National Tribunal and the Labour Court, Tribunal or 
National Tribunal, as the case may be, shall have full power to 
determine by and to whom and to what extent and subject to what 
conditions, if any, such costs are to be paid, and to give all 
necessary directions for the purposes aforesaid and such costs may, on 
application made to the appropriate Government by the person entited, 
be recovered by that Government in the same manner as an arrear of 
land revenue.]


</section>

<section><tid>1443737</tid>
<number>8</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Every <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal] 
shall be deemed to be Civil Court for the purposes of <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> sections 345, 
 346 and 348 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (5 of <year>1898</year>).]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1968818</tid>
<number>11A</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Powers of Labour Courts, Tribunals and National Tribunals 
to give appropriate relief in case of discharge or dismissal of 
workmen.- Where an industrial dispute relating to the discharge or 
dismissal of a workman has been referred to a Labour Court, Tribunal 
or National Tribunal for adjudication and, in the course of the 
adjudication proceedings, the Labour Court, Tribunal or National 
Tribunal, as the case may be, is satisfied that the order of discharge 
or dismissal was not justified, it may, by its award, set aside the 
order of discharge or dismissal and direct reinstatement of the 
workman on such terms and conditions, if any, as it thinks fit, or 
give such other relief to the workman including the award of any 
lesser punishment in lieu of discharge or dismissal as the 
circumstances of the case may require:
Provided that in any proceeding under this section the Labour 
Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal, as the case may be, shall rely 
only on the materials on record and shall not take any fresh evidence 
in relation to the matter.]



</article>



<article><tid>1570927</tid>
<number> 12</number> Duties of conciliation officers.-
<section><tid>1949741</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any industrial  
dispute exists or is apprehended, the conciliation officer may, or 
where the dispute relates to a public utility service and a notice 
under section 22 has been given, shall hold conciliation proceedings 
in the prescribed manner.

</section>

<section><tid>287797</tid>
<number>2</number>The conciliation officer shall, for the purpose of bringing 
about a settlement of the dispute, without delay, investigate the 
dispute and all matters affecting the merits and the right settlement 
thereof and may do all such things as he thinks fit for the purpose of 
inducing the parties to come to a fair and amicable settlement of the 
dispute.

</section>

<section><tid>1724112</tid>
<number>3</number>If a settlement of the dispute or of any of the matters in 
dispute is arrived at in the course of the conciliation proceedings 
the conciliation
<pagefootnote><pagenum>164</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 48 of <year>1950</year>, s. 34 and Sch. 
2. Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 9, for" Tribunal" (w. e. f. 10- 3- <year>1957</year>). 
3. Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1982</year>, s. 9 (w. e. f. 21- 8- <year>1984</year>). 
4. Ins. by Act 45 of <year>1971</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 15- 12- <year>1972</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


officer shall send a report thereof to the appropriate Government 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or an officer authorised in this behalf by the appropriate 
Government] together with a memorandum of the settlement signed by the 
parties to the dispute.


</section>

<section><tid>625936</tid>
<number>4</number>If no such settlement is arrived at, the conciliation officer 
shall, as soon as practicable after the close of the investigation, 
send to the appropriate Government a full report setting forth the 
steps taken by him for ascertaining the facts and circumstances 
relating to the dispute and for bringing about a settlement thereof, 
together with a full statement of such facts and circumstances, and 
the reasons on account of which, in his opinion, a settlement could 
not be arrived at.

</section>

<section><tid>347928</tid>
<number>5</number>If, on a consideration of the report referred to in sub- 
section (4), the appropriate Government is satisfied that there is a 
case for reference to a Board, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Labour Court, Tribunal or National 
Tribunal,] it may make such reference. Where the appropriate 
Government does not make such a reference it shall record and 
communicate to the parties concerned its reasons therefor.

</section>

<section><tid>1139033</tid>
<number>6</number>A report under this section shall be submitted within 
fourteen days of the commencement of the conciliation proceedings or 
within such shorter period as may be fixed by the appropriate 
Government:
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Provided that, <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> subject to the approval of the conciliation 
officer,] the time for the submission of the report may be extended by 
such period as may be agreed upon in writing by all the parties to the 
dispute.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1877749</tid>
<number> 13</number> Duties of Board.-
<section><tid>1648697</tid>
<number>1</number>Where a dispute has been referred to a  
Board under this Act, it shall be the duty of the Board to endeavour 
to bring about a settlement of the same and for this purpose the Board 
shall, in such manner as it thinks fit and without delay, investigate 
the dispute and all matters affecting the merits and the right 
settlement thereof and may do all such things as it thinks fit for the 
purpose of inducing the parties to come to a fair and amicable 
settlement of the dispute.

</section>

<section><tid>460795</tid>
<number>2</number>If a settlement of the dispute or of any of the matters in 
dispute is arrived at in the course of the conciliation proceedings, 
the Board shall send a report thereof to the appropriate Government 
together with a memorandum of the settlement signed by the parties to 
the dispute.

</section>

<section><tid>931411</tid>
<number>3</number>If no such settlement is arrived at, the Board shall, as soon 
as practicable after the close of the investigation, send to the 
appropriate
<pagefootnote><pagenum>164A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 35 of <year>1965</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 1- 12- <year>1965</year>). 
2. Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 10. for" or Tribunal" (w. e. f. 10- 3-  
  <year>1957</year>). 
3. Ins. by s. 10, ibid. (w. e. f. 17- 9- <year>1956</year>). 
4. Ins. by Act 36 of <year>1964</year>, s. 8 (w. e. f. 19- 12- <year>1964</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Government a full report setting forth the proceedings and steps taken 
by the Board for ascertaining the facts and circumstances relating to 
the dispute and for bringing about a settlement thereof, together with 
a full statement of such facts and circumstances, its findings 
thereon, the reasons on account of which, in its opinion, a settlement 
could not be arrived at and its recommendations for the determination 
of the dispute.


</section>

<section><tid>852616</tid>
<number>4</number>If, on the receipt of a report under sub- section (3) in 
respect of a dispute relating to a public utility service, the 
appropriate Government does not make a reference to a <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Labour Court, 
Tribunal
<pagefootnote><pagenum>165</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 11, for" Tribunal" (w. e. f. 10- 3-  
  <year>1957</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


or National Tribunal] under section 10, it shall record and 
communicate to the parties concerned its reasons therefor.


</section>

<section><tid>1768926</tid>
<number>5</number>The Board shall submit its report under this section within 
two months of the date, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> on which the dispute was referred to it] or 
within such shorter period as may be fixed by the appropriate 
Government:
Provided that the appropriate Government may from time to time 
extend the time for the submission of the report by such further 
periods not exceeding two months in the aggregate:

Provided further that the time for the submission of the report 
may be extended by such period as may be agreed on in writing by all 
the parties to the dispute.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>203293</tid>
<number>14</number>Duties of Courts.- A Court shall inquire into the matters 
referred to it and report thereon to the appropriate Government 
ordinarily within a period of six months from the commencement of its 
inquiry.


</article>



<article><tid>206658</tid>
<number>15</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Duties of Labour Courts, Tribunals and National Tribunals.- 
Where an industrial dispute has been referred to a Labour Court, 
Tribunal or National Tribunal for adjudication, it shall hold its 
proceedings expeditiously and shall, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> within the period specified in 
the order referring such industrial dispute or the further period 
extended under the second proviso to sub- section (2A) of section 10], 
submit its award to the appropriate Government.


</article>



<article><tid>1603215</tid>
<number> 16</number> Form of report or award.-
<section><tid>768724</tid>
<number>1</number>The report of a Board or Court  
shall be in writing and shall be signed by all the members of the 
Board or Court, as the case may be:
Provided that nothing in this section shall be deemed to prevent 
any member of the Board or Court from recording any minute of dissent 
from a report or from any recommendation made therein.


</section>

<section><tid>1125628</tid>
<number>2</number>The award of a Labour Court or Tribunal or National Tribunal 
shall be in writing and shall be signed by its presiding officer.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>678364</tid>
<number> 17</number> Publication of reports and awards.-
<section><tid>1905977</tid>
<number>1</number>Every report of a  
Board or Court together with any minute of dissent recorded therewith, 
every arbitration award and every award of a Labour Court, Tribunal or 
National Tribunal shall, within a period of thirty days from the date 
of its receipt by the appropriate Government, be published in such 
manner as the appropriate Government thinks fit.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>166</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 40 of <year>1951</year>, s. 6, for" of the notice under section 
22". 
2. Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 12, for ss. 15, 16, 17 and 17A 
 (w. e. f. 10- 3- <year>1957</year>). S. 17A was ins. by Act 48 of <year>1950</year>, s. 34 and Sch. 
3. Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1982</year>, s. 10 (w. e. f. 21- 8- <year>1984</year>)


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1632564</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions of section 17A, the award published 
under sub- section (1) shall be final and shall not be called in 
question by any Court in any manner whatsoever.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1216362</tid>
<number> 17A</number> Commencement of the award.-
<section><tid>958632</tid>
<number>1</number>An award (including an   
  arbitration award) shall become enforceable on the expiry of thirty 
days from the date of its publication under section 17:
Provided that--


<subsection><tid>1083995</tid>
<number>a</number>if the appropriate Government is of opinion, in any case 
where the award has been given by a Labour Court or 
Tribunal in relation to an industrial dispute to which 
it is a party; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>270252</tid>
<number>b</number>if the Central Government is of opinion, in any case 
where the award has been given by a National Tribunal,
that it will be inexpedient on public grounds affecting national 
economy or social justice to give effect to the whole or any part of 
the award, the appropriate Government, or as the case may be, the 
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
declare that the award shall not become enforceable on the expiry of 
the said period of thirty days.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1132777</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any declaration has been made in relation to an award 
under the proviso to sub- section (1), the appropriate Government or 
the Central Government may, within ninety days from the date of 
publication of the award under section 17, make an order rejecting or 
modifying the award, and shall, on the first available opportunity, 
lay the award together with a copy of the order before the Legislature 
of the State, if the order has been made by a State Government, or 
before Parliament, if the order has been made by the Central 
Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1217572</tid>
<number>3</number>Where any award as rejected or modified by an order made 
under sub- section (2) is laid before the Legislature of a State or 
before Parliament, such award shall become enforceable on the expiry 
of fifteen days from the date on which it is so laid; and where no 
order under sub- section (2) is made in pursuance of a declaration 
under the proviso to sub- section (1), the award shall become 
enforceable on the expiry of the period of ninety days referred to in 
sub- section (2).

</section>

<section><tid>1993121</tid>
<number>4</number>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (1) and sub- section 
 (3) regarding the enforceability of an award, the award shall come 
into operation with effect from such date as may be specified therein, 
but where no date is so specified, it shall come into operation on the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>167</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

date when the award becomes enforceable under sub- section (1) or sub- 
section (3), as the case may be.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>770112</tid>
<number>17B</number><footcitenum>8</footcitenum> Payment of full wages to workman pending proceedings in 
higher courts.- Where in any case, a Labour Court, Tribunal or National 
Tribunal by its award directs reinstatement of any workman and the 
employer prefers any proceedings against such award in a High Court or 
the Supreme Court, the employer shall be liable to pay such workman, 
during the period of pendency of such proceedings in the High Court or 
the Supreme Court, full wages last drawn by him, inclusive of any 
maintenance allowance admissible to him under any rule if the workman 
had not been employed in any establishment during such period and an 
affidavit by such workman had been filed to that effect in such Court:
Provided that where it is proved to the satisfaction of the High 
Court or the Supreme Court that such workman had been employed and had 
been receiving adequate remuneration during any such period or part 
thereof, the Court shall order that no wages shall be payable under 
this section for such period or part, as the case may be.]



</article>



<article><tid>509428</tid>
<number> 18</number> Persons on whom settlements and awards are binding.- <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>
<section><tid>664381</tid>
<number>1</number>A  
settlement arrived at by agreement between the employer and workman 
otherwise than in the course of conciliation proceeding shall be 
binding on the parties to the agreement.

</section>

<section><tid>1970451</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Subject to the provisions of sub- section (3), an 
arbitration award] which has become enforceable shall be binding on 
the parties to the agreement who referred the dispute to arbitration.]

</section>

<section><tid>902131</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>] A settlement arrived at in the course of conciliation 
proceedings under this Act <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> or an arbitration award in a case where 
a notification has been issued under sub- section (3A) of section 10A] 
or <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> an award <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> of a Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal] 
which has become enforceable] shall be binding on--

<subsection><tid>1284026</tid>
<number>a</number>all parties to the industrial dispute;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>247028</tid>
<number>b</number>all other parties summoned to appear in the proceedings 
as parties to the dispute, unless the Board, 
 <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> arbitrator,] <footcitenum>8</footcitenum> Labour Court, Tribunal or National 
Tribunal], as the case may be, records the opinion that 
they were so summoned without proper cause;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>527399</tid>
<number>c</number>where a party referred to in clause (a) or clause (b) is 
an employer, his heirs, successors or assigns in 
respect of the establishment to which the dispute 
relates;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>108584</tid>
<number>d</number>where a party referred to in clause (a) or clause (b) is 
composed of workmen, all persons who were employed in 
the establishment or part of the establishment, as the 
case may be, to which the dispute relates on the date 
of the dispute and all persons who subsequently become 
employed in that establishment or part.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>168</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 46 of <year>1982</year>, s. 11 (w. e. f. 21- 8- <year>1984</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 13 (w. e. f. 7- 10- <year>1956</year>). 
3. Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1964</year>, s. 9, for" An arbitration award" (w. e. f.  
  19- 12- <year>1964</year>). 
4. S. 18 renumbered as sub- section (3) of that section by Act 36 of 
<year>1956</year>, s. 13 (w. e. f. 7- 10- <year>1956</year>). 
5. Ins. by Act 36 of <year>1964</year>, s. 9 (w. e. f. 19- 12- <year>1964</year>). 
6. Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1950</year>, s. 34 and Sch., for" an award which is 
declared by the appropriate Government to be binding under 
sub- section (2) of section 15". 
7. Ins. by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 13 (w. e. f. 10- 3- <year>1957</year>). 
8. Subs. by s. 13, ibid., for" or Tribunal" (w. e. f. 10- 3- <year>1957</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1993072</tid>
<number> 19</number> Period of operation of settlements and awards.-
<section><tid>172713</tid>
<number>1</number>A  
settlement <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> shall come into operation on such date as is agreed 
upon by the parties to the dispute, and if no date is agreed upon, on 
the date on which the memorandum of the settlement is signed by 
the parties to the dispute.

</section>

<section><tid>325738</tid>
<number>2</number>Such settlement shall be binding for such period as is agreed 
upon by the parties, and if no such period is agreed upon, for a 
period of six months <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> from the date on which the memorandum of 
settlement is signed by the parties to the dispute], and shall 
continue to be binding on the parties after the expiry of the period 
aforesaid, until the expiry of two months from the date on which a 
notice in writing of an intention to terminate the settlement is given 
by one of the parties to the other party or parties to the settlement.

</section>

<section><tid>1439055</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> An award shall, subject to the provisions of this section, 
remain in operation for a period of one year <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> from the date on which 
the award becomes enforceable under section 17A]:
Provided that the appropriate Government may reduce the said 
period and fix such period as it thinks fit:

Provided further that the appropriate Government may, before the 
expiry of the said period, extend the period of operation by any 
period not exceeding one year at a time as it thinks fit so, however, 
that the total period of operation of any award does not exceed three 
years from the date on which it came into operation.


</section>

<section><tid>776635</tid>
<number>4</number>Where the appropriate Government, whether of its own motion 
or on the application of any party bound by the award, considers that 
since the award was made, there has been a material change in the 
circumstances on which it was based, the appropriate Government may 
refer the award or a part of it <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> to a Labour Court, if the award was 
that of a Labour Court or to a Tribunal, if the award was that of a 
Tribunal or of a National Tribunal] for decision whether the period of 
operation should not, by reason of such change, be shortened and the 
decision of <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Labour Court or the Tribunal, as the case may be] on 
such reference shall, <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> be final.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>169</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" arrived at in the course of a conciliation proceeding 
under this Act" omitted by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 14 (w. e. f.  
  7- 10- <year>1956</year>). 
2. Ins. by s. 14, ibid. (w. e. f. 7- 10- <year>1956</year>). 
3. Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1950</year>, s. 34 and Sch., for sub- section (3). 
4. Ins. by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 14 (w. e. f. 17- 9- <year>1956</year>). 
5. Subs. by s. 14, ibid., for" to a Tribunal" (w. e. f. 10- 3- <year>1957</year>). 
6. Subs. by s. 14, ibid., for" the Tribunal" (w. e. f. 10- 3- <year>1957</year>). 
7. The words" subject to the provision for appeal" omitted by s. 14, 
ibid. (w. e. f. 10- 3- <year>1957</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>5601</tid>
<number>5</number>Nothing contained in sub- section (3) shall apply to any award 
which by its nature, terms or other circumstances does not impose, 
after it has been given effect to, any continuing obligation on the 
parties bound by the award.

</section>

<section><tid>122004</tid>
<number>6</number>Notwithstanding the expiry of the period of operation under 
sub- section (3), the award shall continue to be binding on the parties 
until a period of two months has elapsed from the date on which notice 
is given by any party bound by the award to the other party or parties 
intimating its intention to terminate the award.

</section>

<section><tid>1380150</tid>
<number>7</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> No notice given under sub- section (2) or sub- section (6) 
shall have effect, unless it is given by a party representing the 
majority of persons bound by the settlement or award, as the case may 
be.]]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>63501</tid>
<number> 20</number> Commencement and conclusion of proceedings.-
<section><tid>293903</tid>
<number>1</number>A  
conciliation proceeding shall be deemed to have commenced on the date 
on which a notice of strike or lock- out under section 22 is received 
by the conciliation officer or on the date of the order referring the 
dispute to a Board, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>307924</tid>
<number>2</number>A conciliation proceeding shall be deemed to have concluded--

<subsection><tid>1518017</tid>
<number>a</number>where a settlement is arrived at, when a memorandum of 
the settlement is signed by the parties to the dispute;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1617936</tid>
<number>b</number>where no settlement is arrived at, when the report of 
the conciliation officer is received by the appropriate 
Government or when the report of the Board is published 
under section 17, as the case may be; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1464199</tid>
<number>c</number>when a reference is made to a Court, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Labour Court, 
Tribunal or National Tribunal] under section 10 during 
the pendency of conciliation proceedings.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>542185</tid>
<number>3</number>Proceedings <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> before an arbitrator under section 10A or 
before a Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal] shall be deemed 
to have commenced on the date of the <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> reference of the dispute for 
arbitration or adjudication, as the case may be] and such proceedings 
shall be deemed to have concluded <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> on the date on which the award 
becomes enforceable under section 17A].
<pagefootnote><pagenum>170</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 36 of <year>1964</year>, s. 10 (w. e. f. 19- 12- <year>1964</year>). The former 
sub- section (7) was omitted by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 14 (w. e. f.  
  17- 9- <year>1956</year>). 
2. Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 15, for" or Tribunal" (w. e. f. 10- 3-  
  <year>1957</year>). 
3. Subs. by s. 15, ibid., for" before a Tribunal" (w. e. f. 10- 3-  
  <year>1957</year>). 
4. Subs. by s. 15, ibid., for" reference of a dispute for 
adjudication" (w. e. f. 10- 3- <year>1957</year>). 
5. Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1952</year>, s. 4, for certain words and figures.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1306271</tid>
<number>21</number>Certain matters to be kept confidential.- There shall not be 
included in any report or award under this Act any information 
obtained by a conciliation officer, Board, Court, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Labour Court, 
Tribunal, National Tribunal or an arbitrator] in the course of any 
investigation or inquiry as to a trade union or as to any individual 
business (whether carried on by a person, firm or company) which is 
not available otherwise than through the evidence given before such 
officer, Board, Court, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Labour Court, Tribunal, National Tribunal or 
arbitrator], if the trade union, person, firm or company, in question 
has made a request in writing to the conciliation officer, Board, 
Court, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Labour Court, Tribunal, National Tribunal or arbitrator], as 
the case may be, that such information shall be treated as 
confidential; nor shall such conciliation officer or any individual 
member of the Board, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or Court or the presiding officer of the 
Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal or the arbitrator] or any 
person present at or concerned in the proceedings disclose any such 
information without the consent in writing of the secretary of the 
trade union or the person, firm or company in question, as the case 
may be:
Provided that nothing contained in this section shall apply to a 
disclosure of any such information for the purposes of a prosecution 
under section 193 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>).

CHAP

STRIKES AND LOCK- OUTS

CHAPTER V

STRIKES AND LOCK- OUTS



</article>



<article><tid>1950513</tid>
<number> 22</number> Prohibition of strikes and lock- outs.-
<section><tid>281370</tid>
<number>1</number>No person employed  
in a public utility service shall go on strike in breach of contract--

<subsection><tid>580662</tid>
<number>a</number>without giving to the employer notice of strike, as 
herein- after provided, within six weeks before 
striking; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1830925</tid>
<number>b</number>within fourteen days of giving such notice; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>994658</tid>
<number>c</number>before the expiry of the date of strike specified in any 
such notice as aforesaid; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1392829</tid>
<number>d</number>during the pendency of any conciliation proceedings 
before a conciliation officer and seven days after the 
conclusion of such proceedings.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1169790</tid>
<number>2</number>No employer carrying on any public utility service shall 
lock- out any of his workmen--

<subsection><tid>1049551</tid>
<number>a</number>without giving them notice of lock- out as hereinafter 
provided, within six weeks before locking out; or
<pagefootnote><pagenum>171</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 16, for" or Tribunal" (w. e. f. 10- 3-  
  <year>1957</year>). 
2. Subs. by s. 16, ibid., for" Court or Tribunal" (w. e. f. 10- 3-  
  <year>1957</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1500347</tid>
<number>b</number>within fourteen days of giving such notice; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>391878</tid>
<number>c</number>before the expiry of the date of lock- out specified in 
any such notice as aforesaid; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1423572</tid>
<number>d</number>during the pendency of any conciliation proceedings 
before a conciliation officer and seven days after the 
conclusion of such proceedings.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1903929</tid>
<number>3</number>The notice of lock- out or strike under this section shall not 
be necessary where there is already in existence a strike or, as the 
case may be, lock- out in the public utility service, but the employer 
shall send intimation of such lock- out or strike on the day on which 
it is declared, to such authority as may be specified by the 
appropriate Government either generally or for a particular area or 
for a particular class of public utility services.

</section>

<section><tid>1347917</tid>
<number>4</number>The notice of strike referred to in sub- section (1) shall be 
given by such number of persons to such person or persons and in such 
manner as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>892929</tid>
<number>5</number>The notice of lock- out referred to in sub- section (2) shall 
be given in such manner as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>650649</tid>
<number>6</number>If on any day an employer receives from any persons employed 
by him any such notices as are referred to in sub- section (1) or gives 
to any persons employed by him any such notices as are referred to in 
sub- section (2), he shall within five days thereof report to the 
appropriate Government or to such authority as that Government may 
prescribe the number of such notices received or given on that day.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>708192</tid>
<number> 23</number> General prohibition of strikes and lock- outs.- No workman who 
is employed in any industrial establishment shall go on strike in 
breach of contract and no employer of any such workman shall declare a 
lock- out--
<section><tid>1514473</tid>
<number>a</number>during the pendency of conciliation proceedings before a 
Board and seven days after the conclusion of such 
proceedings;

</section>

<section><tid>1728537</tid>
<number>b</number>during the pendency of proceedings before <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> a Labour 
Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal] and two months 
after the conclusion of such proceedings; <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>

</section>

<section><tid>1605743</tid>
<number>bb</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> during the pendency of arbitration proceedings 
before an arbitrator and two months after the 
conclusion of such proceedings, where a notification 
has been issued under sub- section (3A) of section 10A; 
or]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>172</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 17, for" a Tribunal" (w. e. f. 10- 3-  
  <year>1957</year>). 
2. The word" or" omitted by Act 36 of <year>1964</year>, s. 11 (w. e. f. 19- 12-  
  <year>1964</year>). 
3. Ins. by s. 11, ibid. (w. e. f. 19- 12- <year>1964</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>447368</tid>
<number>c</number>during any period in which a settlement or award is in 
operation, in respect of any of the matters covered by 
the settlement or award.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1042042</tid>
<number> 24</number> Illegal strikes and lock- outs.-
<section><tid>353064</tid>
<number>1</number>A strike or a lock- out  
shall be illegal if--

<subsection><tid>693025</tid>
<number>i</number>it is commenced or declared in contravention of section 
 22 or section 23; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>448368</tid>
<number>ii</number>it is continued in contravention of an order made under 
sub- section (3) of section 10 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or sub- section (4A) of 
section 10A].

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>134194</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a strike or lock- out in pursuance of an industrial 
dispute has already commenced and is in existence at the time of the 
reference of the dispute to a Board, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> an arbitrator, a] <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Labour 
Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal], the continuance of such strike 
or lock- out shall not be deemed to be illegal, provided that such 
strike or lock- out was not at its commencement in contravention of the 
provisions of this Act or the continuance thereof was not prohibited 
under sub- section (3) of section 10 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or sub- section (4A) of section 
10A].

</section>

<section><tid>1268417</tid>
<number>3</number>A lock- out declared in consequence of an illegal strike or a 
strike declared in consequence of an illegal lock- out shall not be 
deemed to be illegal.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>607947</tid>
<number>25</number>Prohibition of financial aid to illegal strikes and lock- 
outs.- No person shall knowingly expend or apply any money in direct 
furtherance of support of any illegal strike or lock- out.
CHAP

LAY- OFF AND RETRENCHMENT

<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> CHAPTER VA

LAY- OFF AND RETRENCHMENT



</article>



<article><tid>234923</tid>
<number> 25A</number> Application of sections 25C to 25E.-
<section><tid>1314055</tid>
<number>1</number>Sections 25C to 25E  
inclusive <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> shall not apply to industrial establishments to which 
Chapter VB applies, or--]

<subsection><tid>622021</tid>
<number>a</number>to industrial establishments in which less than fifty 
workmen on an average per working day have been 
employed in the preceding calendar month; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>619138</tid>
<number>b</number>to industrial establishments which are of a seasonal 
character or in which work is performed only 
intermittently.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>173</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 36 of <year>1964</year>, s. 12 (w. e. f. 19- 12- <year>1964</year>). 
2. Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 18, for" or Tribunal" (w. e. f. 10- 3-  
  <year>1957</year>). 
3. Ins. by Act 43 of <year>1953</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 24- 10- <year>1953</year>). 
4. Subs. by Act 32 of <year>1976</year>, s. 2, for" shall not apply--" (w. e. f.  
  5- 3- <year>1976</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1017616</tid>
<number>2</number>If a question arises whether an industrial establishment is 
of a seasonal character or whether work is performed therein only 
intermittently, the decision of the appropriate Government thereon 
shall be final.
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Explanation.-- In this section and in sections 25C, 25D and 
25E," industrial establishment" means--


<subsection><tid>195614</tid>
<number>i</number>a factory as defined in clause (m) of section 2 of the 
Factories Act <year>1948</year> (63 of <year>1948</year>); or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>341913</tid>
<number>ii</number>a mine as defined in clause (j) of section 2 of the 
Mines Act, <year>1952</year> (35 of <year>1952</year>); or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>928433</tid>
<number>iii</number>a plantation as defined in clause (f) of section 2 of 
the Plantations Labour Act, <year>1951</year> (69 of <year>1951</year>).]



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>288001</tid>
<number> 25B</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Definition of continuous service.- For the purposes of 
this Chapter,--
<section><tid>1097956</tid>
<number>1</number>a workman shall be said to be in continuous service for 
a period if he is, for that period, in uninterrupted 
service, including service which may be interrupted on 
account of sickness or authorised leave or an accident 
or a strike which is not illegal, or a lock- out or a 
cessation of work which is not due to any fault on the 
part of the workman;

</section>

<section><tid>1440121</tid>
<number>2</number>where a workman is not in continuous service within the 
meaning of clause (1) for a period of one year or six 
months, he shall be deemed to be in continuous service 
under an employer--

<subsection><tid>1013014</tid>
<number>a</number>for a period of one year, if the workman, 
during a period of twelve calendar months 
preceding the date with reference to which 
calculation is to be made, has actually worked 
under the employer for not less than--

<subsubsection><tid>1525592</tid>
<number>i</number>one hundred and ninety days in the case 
of a workman employed below ground in a mine; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>661337</tid>
<number>ii</number>two hundred and forty days, in any other 
case;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1288577</tid>
<number>b</number>for a period of six months, if the 
workman, during a period of six calendar months 
preceding the date with reference to which 
calculation is to be made, has actually worked 
under the employer for not less than--

<subsubsection><tid>1355526</tid>
<number>i</number>ninety- five days, in the case of a 
workman employed below ground in a mine; and
<pagefootnote><pagenum>174</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1954</year>, s. 2, for the former Explanation (w. e. f.  
  1- 4- <year>1954</year>). 
2. Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1964</year>, s. 13, for s. 25B (w. e. f. 19- 12- <year>1964</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>273861</tid>
<number>ii</number>one hundred and twenty days, in any 
other case.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of clause (2), the number of days 
on which a workman has actually worked under an employer shall include 
the days on which--


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1355526</tid>
<number>i</number>he has been laid- off under an agreement or as permitted 
by standing orders made under the Industrial Employment 
 (Standing Orders) Act, <year>1946</year> (20 of <year>1946</year>), or under 
this Act or under any other law applicable to the 
industrial establishment;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>273861</tid>
<number>ii</number>he has been on leave with full wages, earned in the 
previous years;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1863904</tid>
<number>iii</number>he has been absent due to temporary disablement caused 
by accident arising out of and in the course of his 
employment; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1210093</tid>
<number>iv</number>in the case of a female, she has been on maternity 
leave; so, however, that the total period of such 
maternity leave does not exceed twelve weeks.]



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>763410</tid>
<number>25C</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Right of workmen laid- off for compensation.- Whenever a 
workman (other than a badli workman or a casual workman) whose name is 
borne on the muster rolls of an industrial establishment and who has 
completed not less than one year of continuous service under an 
employer is laid- off, whether continuously or intermittently, he shall 
be paid by the employer for all days during which he is so laid- off, 
except for such weekly holidays as may intervene, compensation which 
shall be equal to fifty per cent. of the total of the basic wages and 
dearness allowance that would have been payable to him had he not been 
so laid- off:
Provided that if during any period of twelve months, a workman is 
so laid- off for more than forty- five days, no such compensation shall 
be payable in respect of any period of the lay- off after the expiry of 
the first forty- five days, if there is an agreement to that effect 
between the workman and the employer:

Provided further that it shall be lawful for the employer in any 
case falling within the foregoing proviso to retrench the workman in 
accordance with the provisions contained in section 25F at any time 
after the expiry of the first forty- five days of the lay- off and when 
he does so, any compensation paid to the workman for having been laid- 
off during the preceding twelve months may be set off against the 
compensation payable for retrenchment.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>175</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 35 of <year>1965</year>, s. 5, for the former section (w. e. f. 1-  
  12- <year>1965</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Explanation.--" Badli workman" means a workman who is employed in 
an industrial establishment in the place of another workman whose name 
is borne on the muster rolls of the establishment, but shall cease to 
be regarded as such for the purposes of this section, if he has 
completed one year of continuous service in the establishment.]



</article>



<article><tid>1652330</tid>
<number>25D</number>Duty of an employer to maintain muster rolls of workmen. 
Notwithstanding that workmen in any industrial establishment have been 
laid- off, it shall be the duty of every employer to maintain for the 
purposes of this Chapter a muster roll and to provide for the making 
of entries therein by workmen who may present themselves for work at 
the establishment at the appointed time during normal working hours.


</article>



<article><tid>1729102</tid>
<number> 25E</number> Workmen not entitled to compensation in certain cases.- No 
compensation shall be paid to a workman who has been laid- off--
<section><tid>1157344</tid>
<number>i</number>if he refuses to accept any alternative employment in 
the same establishment from which he has been laid- off, 
or in any other establishment belonging to the same 
employer situate in the same town or village or situate 
within a radius of five miles from the establishment to 
which he belongs, if, in the opinion of the employer, 
such alternative employment does not call for any 
special kill or previous experience and can be done by 
the workman, provided that the wages which would 
normally have been paid to the workman are offered for 
the alternative employment also;

</section>

<section><tid>730952</tid>
<number>ii</number>if he does not present himself for work at the 
establishment at the appointed time during normal 
working hours at least once a day;

</section>

<section><tid>1812190</tid>
<number>iii</number>if such laying- off is due to a strike or slowing- down 
of production on the part of workmen in another part of 
the establishment.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1056316</tid>
<number> 25F</number> Conditions precedent to retrenchment of workmen.- No workman 
employed in any industry who has been in continuous service for not 
less than one year under an employer shall be retrenched by that 
employer until--
<section><tid>1211873</tid>
<number>a</number>the workman has been given one month' s notice in writing 
indicating the reasons for retrenchment and the period 
of notice has expired, or the workman has been paid in 
lieu of such notice, wages for the period of the 
notice:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>176</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>


</section>

<section><tid>1944207</tid>
<number>b</number>the workman has been paid, at the time of retrenchment, 
compensation which shall be equivalent to fifteen days' 
average pay <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> for every completed year of continuous 
service] or any part thereof in excess of six months; 
and

</section>

<section><tid>608778</tid>
<number>c</number>notice in the prescribed manner is served on the 
appropriate Government <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> or such authority as may be 
specified by the appropriate Government by notification 
in the Official Gazette].

<pagefootnote><pagenum>25FF</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Compensation to workmen in case of transfer of undertakings.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1836267</tid>
<number> 25FF</number> <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Compensation to workmen in case of transfer of 
undertakings.- Where the ownership or management of an undertaking is 
transferred, whether by agreement or by operation of law, from the 
employer in relation to that undertaking to a new employer, every 
workman who has been in continuous service for not less than one year 
in that undertaking immediately before such transfer shall be entitled 
to notice and compensation in accordance with the provisions of 
section 25F, as if the workman had been retrenched:
Provided that nothing in this section shall apply to a workman in 
any case where there has been a change of employers by reason of the 
transfer, if--

<section><tid>426375</tid>
<number>a</number>the service of the workman has not been interrupted by 
such transfer;

</section>

<section><tid>447481</tid>
<number>b</number>the terms and conditions of service applicable to the 
workman after such transfer are not in any way less 
favourable to the workman than those applicable to him 
immediately before the transfer; and

</section>

<section><tid>1400211</tid>
<number>c</number>the new employer is, under the terms of such transfer or 
otherwise, legally liable to pay to the workman, in the 
event of his retrenchment, compensation on the basis 
that his service has been continuous and has not been 
interrupted by the transfer.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>176A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Omitted by Act 49 of <year>1984</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 18- 8- <year>1984</year>). 
2. Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1964</year>, s. 14, for" for every completed year of 
service" (w. e. f. 19- 12- <year>1964</year>). 
3. Ins. by s. 14, ibid. (w. e. f. 19- 12- <year>1964</year>). 
4. Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1957</year>, s. 3, for the former section (w. e. f. 28-  
  11- <year>1956</year>). S. 25FF was ins. by Act 41 of <year>1956</year>, s. 3.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



<pagefootnote><pagenum>25FF</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Sixty days' notice to be given of intention to close down 
anyundertaking.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>529505</tid>
<number> 25FFA</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Sixty days' notice to be given of intention to close 
down any undertaking.-
<section><tid>1196745</tid>
<number>1</number>An employer who intends to close down an  
undertaking shall serve, at least sixty days before the date on which 
the intended closure is to become effective, a notice, in the 
prescribed manner, on the appropriate Government stating clearly the 
reasons for the intended closure of the undertaking:
Provided that nothing in this section shall apply to--


<subsection><tid>847833</tid>
<number>a</number>an undertaking in which--

<subsubsection><tid>779809</tid>
<number>i</number>less than fifty workmen are employed, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>450368</tid>
<number>ii</number>less than fifty workmen were employed on an 
average per working day in the preceding twelve months,

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1669865</tid>
<number>b</number>an undertaking set up for the construction of buildings, 
bridges, roads, canals, dams or for other construction 
work or project.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1159375</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), the 
appropriate Government may, if it is satisfied that owing to such 
exceptional circumstances as accident in the undertaking or death of 
the employer or the like it is necessary so to do, by order, direct 
that provisions of sub- section (1) shall not apply in relation to such 
undertaking for such period as may be specified in the order.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>25FF</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Compensation to workmen in case of closing down of undertakings.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1183163</tid>
<number> 25FFF</number> Compensation to workmen in case of closing down of 
undertakings.-
<section><tid>1027749</tid>
<number>1</number>Where an undertaking is closed down for any reason  
whatsoever, every workman who has been in continuous service for
<pagefootnote><pagenum>177</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 32 of <year>1972</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 14- 6- <year>1972</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


not less than one year in that undertaking immediately before such 
closure shall, subject to the provisions of sub- section (2), be 
entitled to notice and compensation in accordance with the provisions 
of section 25F, as if the workman had been retrenched:

Provided that where the undertaking is closed down on account of 
unavoidable circumstances beyond the control of the employer, the 
compensation to be paid to the workman under clause (b) of section 25F 
shall not exceed his average pay for three months.

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Explanation.-- An undertaking which is closed down by reason 
merely of--


<subsection><tid>448194</tid>
<number>i</number>financial difficulties (including financial losses); or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1367196</tid>
<number>ii</number>accumulation of undisposed of stocks; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1456318</tid>
<number>iii</number>the expiry of the period of the lease or licence 
granted to it; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>856666</tid>
<number>iv</number>in a case where the undertaking is engaged in mining 
operations, exhaustion of the minerals in the area in 
which such operations are carried on;
shall not be deemed to be closed down on account of unavoidable 
circumstances beyond the control of the employer within the meaning of 
the proviso to this sub- section.]


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1163116</tid>
<number>1A</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), 
where an undertaking engaged in mining operations is closed down by 
reason merely of exhaustion of the minerals in the area in which such 
operations are carried on, no workman referred to in that sub- section 
shall be entitled to any notice or compensation in accordance with the 
provisions of section 25F, if--

<subsection><tid>103427</tid>
<number>a</number>the employer provides the workman with alternative 
employment with effect from the date of closure at the 
same remuneration as he was entitled to receive, and on 
the same terms and conditions of service as were 
applicable to him, immediately before the closure;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>899927</tid>
<number>b</number>the service of the workman has not been interrupted by 
such alternative employment; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1712221</tid>
<number>c</number>the employer is, under the terms of such alternative 
employment or otherwise, legally liable to pay to the 
workman, in the event of his retrenchment, compensation 
on the basis that his service has been continuous and 
has not been interrupted by such alternative 
employment.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>178</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 45 of <year>1971</year>, s. 4, for the original Explanation 
 (w. e. f. 15- 12- <year>1971</year>). 
2. Ins. by s. 4, ibid. (w. e. f. 15- 12- <year>1971</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1957038</tid>
<number>1B</number>For the purposes of sub- sections (1) and (1A), the 
expressions" minerals" and" mining operations" shall have the meanings 
respectively assigned to them in clauses (a) and (d) of section 3 of 
the Mines and Minerals (Regulation and Development) Act, <year>1957</year> (67 of  
  <year>1957</year>).]

</section>

<section><tid>1322919</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any undertaking set- up for the construction of 
buildings, bridges, roads, canals, dams or other construction work is 
closed down on account of the completion of the work within two years 
from the date on which the undertaking had been set- up, no workman 
employed therein shall be entitled to any compensation under clause 
 (b) of section 25F, but if the construction work is not so completed 
within two years, he shall be entitled to notice and compensation 
under that section for every <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> completed year of continuous service] 
or any part thereof in excess of six months.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>41851</tid>
<number>25G</number>Procedure for retrenchment.- Where any workman in an 
industrial establishment, who is a citizen of India, is to be 
retrenched and he belongs to a particular category of workmen in that 
establishment, in the absence of any agreement between the employer 
and the workman in this behalf, the employer shall ordinarily retrench 
the workman who was the last person to be employed in that category, 
unless for reasons to be recorded the employer retrenches any other 
workman.


</article>



<article><tid>1476304</tid>
<number>25H</number>Re- employment of retrenched workmen.- Where any workmen are 
retrenched, and the employer proposes to take into his employ any 
persons, he shall, in such manner as may be prescribed, give an 
opportunity <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> to the retrenched workmen who are citizens of India to 
offer themselves for re- employment and such retrenched workman] who 
offer themselves for re- employment shall have preference over other 
persons.





</article>



<article><tid>1865755</tid>
<number> 25J</number> Effect of laws inconsistent with this Chapter.-
<section><tid>1584330</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
provisions of this Chapter shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
inconsistent therewith contained in any other law[ including standing 
orders made under the Industrial Employment (Standing Orders) Act, 
 <year>1946</year> (20 of <year>1946</year>)]:
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Provided that where under the provisions of any other Act or 
rules, orders or notifications issued thereunder or under any standing 
orders or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>178A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 36, of <year>1964</year>, s. 15, for" completed year of service" 
 (w. e. f. 19- 12- <year>1964</year>). 
2. Subs. by s. 16, ibid. for certain words (w. e. f. 19- 12- <year>1964</year>). 
3. Subs. by s. 17, ibid., for the proviso (w. e. f. 19- 12- <year>1964</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


under any award, contract of service or otherwise, a workman is 
entitled to benefits in respect of any matter which are more 
favourable to him than those to which he would be entitled under this 
Act, the workman shall continue to be entitled to the more favourable 
benefits in respect of that matter, notwithstanding that he receives 
benefits in respect of other matters under this Act.]


</section>

<section><tid>948567</tid>
<number>2</number>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that nothing 
contained in this Chapter shall be deemed to affect the provisions of 
any other law for the time being in force in any State in so far as 
that law provides for the settlement of industrial disputes, but the 
rights and liabilities of employers and workmen in so far as they 
relate to lay- off and retrenchment shall be determined in accordance 
with the provisions of this Chapter.]
CHAP

SPECIAL PROVISIONS RELATING TO LAY- OFF, RETRENCHMENT AND CLOSURE INCERTAIN 
ESTABLISHMENTS

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> CHAPTER VB

SPECIAL PROVISIONS RELATING TO LAY- OFF, RETRENCHMENT AND CLOSURE 
IN CERTAIN ESTABLISHMENTS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1834455</tid>
<number> 25K</number> Application of Chapter VB.-
<section><tid>1931760</tid>
<number>1</number>The provisions of this  
Chapter shall apply to an industrial establishment (not being an  
establishment of a seasonal character or in which work is performed 
  only intermittently) in which not less than <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> one hundred] workmen 
were employed on an average per working day for the preceding twelve 
months.

</section>

<section><tid>1176356</tid>
<number>2</number>If a question arises whether an industrial establishment is 
of a seasonal character or whether work is performed therein only 
intermittently, the decision of the appropriate Government thereon 
shall be final.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1064357</tid>
<number> 25L</number> Definitions.- For the purposes of this Chapter,--
<section><tid>1311207</tid>
<number>a</number>" industrial establishment" means--

<subsection><tid>470901</tid>
<number>i</number>a factory as defined in clause (m) of 
section 2 of the Factories Act, <year>1948</year> (63 of  
  <year>1948</year>);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1669134</tid>
<number>ii</number>a mine as defined in clause (i) of sub- 
section (1) of section 2 of the Mines Act, <year>1952</year> 
 (35 of <year>1952</year>); or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1037918</tid>
<number>iii</number>a plantation as defined in clause (f) 
of section 2 of the Plantations Labour Act, <year>1951</year> 
 (69 of <year>1951</year>);
<pagefootnote><pagenum>178B</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 32 of <year>1976</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 5- 3- <year>1976</year>). 
2. Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1982</year>, s. 12 (w. e. f. 21. 8. <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>642969</tid>
<number>b</number>notwithstanding anything contained in sub- clause (ii) of 
clause (a) of section 2,--

<subsection><tid>695203</tid>
<number>i</number>in relation to any company in which not 
less than fifty- one per cent. of the paid- up share 
capital is held by the Central Government, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1411155</tid>
<number>ii</number>in relation to any corporation[ not 
being a corporation referred to in sub- clause (i) 
of clause (a) of section 2] established by or 
under any law made by Parliament,
the Central Government shall be appropriate Government.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1900929</tid>
<number> 25M</number> Prohibition of lay- off.-
<section><tid>1901112</tid>
<number>1</number>No workman (other than a badli   
  workman or a casual workman) whose name is borne on the muster rolls 
of an industrial establishment to which this Chapter applies shall be 
laid- off by his employer except <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> with the prior permission of the 
appropriate Government or such authority as may be specified by that 
Government by notification in the Official Gazette (hereinafter in  
  this section referred to as the specified authority), obtained on an 
application made in this behalf, unless such lay- off is due to 
shortage of power or to natural calamity, and in the case of a mine, 
such lay- off is due also to fire, flood, excess of inflammable gas or 
explosion].

</section>

<section><tid>1237804</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> An application for permission under sub- section (1) shall 
be made by the employer in the prescribed manner stating clearly the 
reasons for the intended lay- off and a copy of such application shall 
also be served simultaneously on the workmen concerned in the 
prescribed manner.

</section>

<section><tid>1376276</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the workman (other than badli workmen or casual  
  workmen) of an industrial establishment, being a mine, have been laid- 
off under sub- section (1) for reasons of fire, flood or excess of 
inflammable gas or explosion, the employer, in relation to such 
establishment, shall, within a period of thirty days from the date of 
commencement of such lay- off, apply, in the prescribed manner, to the 
appropriate Government or the specified authority for permission to 
continue the lay- off.

</section>

<section><tid>1744276</tid>
<number>4</number>Where an application for permission under sub- section (1) or 
sub- section (3) has been made, the appropriate Government or the 
specified authority, after making such enquiry as it thinks fit and 
after giving a reasonable opportunity of being heard to the employer, 
the workmen concerned and the persons interested in such lay- off, may, 
having regard to the genuineness and adequacy of the reasons for such 
lay- off, the interests of the workmen and all other relevant factors, 
by order and for reasons to be recorded in writing, grant or refuse to 
grant such permission and a copy of such order shall be communicated 
to the employer and the workmen.

</section>

<section><tid>1686437</tid>
<number>5</number>Where an application for permission under sub- section (1) or 
sub- section (3) has been made and the appropriate Government or the 
specified authority does not communicate the order granting or 
refusing to grant permission to the employer within a period of sixty 
days from the date on which such application is made, the permission 
applied for shall be deemed to have been granted on the expiration of 
the said period of sixty days.

</section>

<section><tid>497557</tid>
<number>6</number>An order of the appropriate Government or the specified 
authority granting or refusing to grant permission shall, subject to 
the provisions of sub- section (7), be final and binding on all the 
parties concerned and shall remain in force for one year from the 
date of such order.

</section>

<section><tid>253560</tid>
<number>7</number>The appropriate Government or the specified authority may, 
either on its own motion or on the application made by the employer or 
any workman, review its order granting or refusing to grant permission 
under sub- section (4) or refer the matter or, as the case may be, 
cause it to be referred, to a Tribunal for adjudication:
Provided that where a reference has been made to a Tribunal under 
this sub- section, it shall pass an award within a period of thirty 
days from the date of such reference.


</section>

<section><tid>68450</tid>
<number>8</number>Where no application for permission under sub- section (1) is 
made, or where no application for permission under sub- section (3) is 
made within the period specified therein, or where the permission for 
any lay- off has been refused, such lay- off shall be deemed to be 
illegal from the date on which the workmen had been laid- off and the 
workmen shall be entitled to all the benefits under any law for the 
time being in force as if they had not been laid- off.

</section>

<section><tid>1624927</tid>
<number>9</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing 
provisions of this section, the appropriate Government may, if it is 
satisfied that owing to such exceptional circumstances as accident in 
the establishment or death of the employer or the like, it is 
necessary so to do, by order, direct that the provisions of sub- 
section (1), or, as the case may be, sub- section (3) shall not apply 
in relation to such establishment for such period as may be specified 
in the order.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>178C</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 49 of <year>1984</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 18. 8. <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1617607</tid>
<number>10</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>] The provisions of section 25C (other than the second  
  proviso thereto) shall apply to cases of lay- off referred to in this 
section.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section, a workman shall 
not be deemed to be laid- off by an employer if such employer offers 
any alternative employment (which in the opinion of the employer does  
not call for any special skill or previous experience and can be done 
  by the workman) in the same establishment from which he has been 
laid- off or in any other establishment belonging to the same employer, 
situate in the same town or village, or situate within such distance 
from the establishment to which he belongs that the transfer will not 
involve undue hardship to the workman having regard to the facts and 
circumstances of his case, provided that the wages which would 
normally have been paid to the workman are offered for the alternative 
appointment also.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>700346</tid>
<number> 25N</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Conditions precedent to retrenchment of workmen.-
<section><tid>1775162</tid>
<number>1</number>No  
workman employed in any industrial establishment to which this Chapter 
applies, who has been in continuous service for not less than one year 
under an employer shall be retrenched by that employer until,--

<subsection><tid>1623414</tid>
<number>a</number>the workman has been given three months' notice in 
writing indicating the reasons for retrenchment and the 
period of notice has expired, or the workman has been 
paid in lieu of such notice, wages for the period of 
the notice; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>170018</tid>
<number>b</number>the prior permission of the appropriate Government or 
such authority as may be specified by that Government 
by notification in the Official Gazette (hereafter in  
  this section referred to as the specified authority) 
has been obtained on an application made in this 
behalf.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1899970</tid>
<number>2</number>An application for permission under sub- section (1) shall be 
made by the employer in the prescribed manner stating clearly the 
reasons for the intended retrenchment and a copy of such application 
shall also be served simultaneously on the workmen concerned in the 
prescribed manner.

</section>

<section><tid>1770563</tid>
<number>3</number>Where an application for permission under sub- section (1) has 
been made, the appropriate Government or the specified authority, 
after making such enquiry as it thinks fit and after giving a 
reasonable opportunity of being heard to the employer, the workmen 
concerned and the persons interested in such retrenchment, may, having 
regard to the genuineness and adequacy of the reasons stated by the 
employer, the interests of the workmen and all other relevant factors, 
by order and for reasons to be recorded in writing, grant or refuse to 
grant such permission and a copy of such order shall be communicated 
to the employer and the workmen.

</section>

<section><tid>1343916</tid>
<number>4</number>Where an application for permission has been made under sub- 
section (1) and the appropriate Government or the specified authority 
does not communicate the order granting or refusing to grant 
permission to the employer within a period of sixty days from the date 
on which such application is made, the permission applied for shall be 
deemed to have been granted on the expiration of the said period of 
sixty days.

</section>

<section><tid>37977</tid>
<number>5</number>An order of the appropriate Government or the specified 
authority granting or refusing to grant permission shall, subject to 
the provisions of sub- section (6), be final and binding on all the 
parties concerned and shall remain in force for one year from the date 
of such order.

</section>

<section><tid>1019915</tid>
<number>6</number>The appropriate Government or the specified authority may, 
either on its own motion or on the application made by the employer or 
any workman, review its order granting or refusing to grant permission 
under sub- section (3) or refer the matter or, as the case may be, 
cause it to be referred, to a Tribunal for adjudication:
Provided that where a reference has been made to a Tribunal under 
this sub- section, it shall pass an award within a period of thirty 
days from the date of such reference.


</section>

<section><tid>755448</tid>
<number>7</number>Where no application for permission under sub- section (1) is 
made, or where the permission for any retrenchment has been refused, 
such retrenchment shall be deemed to be illegal from the date on which 
the notice of retrenchment was given to the workman and the workman 
shall be entitled to all the benefits under any law for the time being 
in force as if no notice had been given to him.

</section>

<section><tid>883719</tid>
<number>8</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing 
provisions of this section, the appropriate Government may, if it is 
satisfied that owing to such exceptional circumstances as accident in 
the establishment or death of the employer or the like, it is 
necessary so to do, by order, direct that the provisions of sub- 
section (1) shall not apply in relation to such establishment for such 
period as may be specified in the order.

</section>

<section><tid>199204</tid>
<number>9</number>Where permission for retrenchment has been granted under sub- 
section (3) or where permission for retrenchment is deemed to be 
granted under sub- section (4), every workman who is employed in that 
establishment immediately before the date of application for 
permission under this section shall be entitled to receive, at the 
time of retrenchment, compensation which shall be equivalent to 
fifteen days' average pay for every completed year of continuous 
service or any part thereof in excess of six months.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>178E</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Re- numbered by Act 49 of <year>1984</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 18. 8. <year>1984</year>). 
2. Subs. by s. 5, ibid., (w. e. f. 18. 8. <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>














<pagefootnote><pagenum>178F</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1982</year>, s. 14 (w. e. f. 21. 8. <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>529421</tid>
<number> 25P</number> Special provision as to restarting of undertakings closed 
down before commencement of the Industrial Disputes (Amendment) Act, 
<year>1976</year>.- If the appropriate Government is of opinion in respect of any 
undertaking of an industrial establishment to which this Chapter 
applies and which closed down before the commencement of the 
Industrial Disputes (Amendment) Act, <year>1976</year> (32 of <year>1976</year>),--
<section><tid>1156680</tid>
<number>a</number>that such undertaking was closed down otherwise than on 
account of unavoidable circumstances beyond the control 
of the employer;

</section>

<section><tid>398933</tid>
<number>b</number>that there are possibilities of restarting the 
undertaking;

</section>

<section><tid>771783</tid>
<number>c</number>that it is necessary for the rehabilitation of the 
workmen employed in such undertaking before its closure 
or for the maintenance of supplies and services 
essential to the life of the community to restart the 
undertaking or both; and

</section>

<section><tid>147149</tid>
<number>d</number>that the restarting of the undertaking will not result 
in hardship to the employer in relation to the 
undertaking,
it may, after giving an opportunity to such employer and workmen, 
direct, by order published in the Official Gazette, that the 
undertaking shall be restarted within such time (not being less than  
  one month from the date of the order) as may be specified in the 
order.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>178G</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1207376</tid>
<number>25Q</number>Penalty for lay- off and retrenchment without previous 
permission.- Any employer who contravenes the provisions of section 25M 
or <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of section 25N shall be punishable with imprisonment for a 
term which may extend to one month, or with fine which may extend to 
one thousand rupees, or with both.


</article>



<article><tid>182185</tid>
<number> 25R</number> Penalty for closure.-
<section><tid>1934647</tid>
<number>1</number>Any employer who closes down an  
undertaking without complying with the provisions of sub- section (1) 
of section 25-O shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which 
may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to five 
thousand rupees, or with both.

</section>

<section><tid>1050993</tid>
<number>2</number>Any employer, who contravenes <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> an order refusing to grant 
permission to close down an undertaking under sub- section (2) of 
section 25-O or a direction given under section 25P], shall be 
punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, 
or with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees, or with both, 
and where the contravention is a continuing one, with a further fine 
which may extend to two thousand rupees for every day during which the 
contravention continues after the conviction.
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>941038</tid>
<number>25S</number>Certain provisions of Chapter VA to apply to an industrial 
establishment to which this Chapter applies.- The provisions of 
sections 25B, 25D, 25FF, 25G, 25H, and 25J in Chapter VA shall, so far 
as may be, apply also in relation to an industrial establishment to 
which the provisions of this Chapter apply.]
CHAP

UNFAIR LABOUR PRACTICES

<footcitenum>4</footcitenum> CHAPTER VC

UNFAIR LABOUR PRACTICES



</article>



<article><tid>1679083</tid>
<number>25T</number>Prohibition of unfair labour practice.- No employer or 
workman or a trade union, whether registered under the Trader Unions 
Act, <year>1926</year> (16 of <year>1926</year>), or not, shall commit any unfair labour practice.


</article>



<article><tid>687096</tid>
<number>25U</number>Penalty for committing unfair labour practices.- Any person 
who commits any unfair labour practice shall be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months or with fine 
which may extend to one thousand rupees or with both.]
CHAP

PENALTIES

CHAPTER VI

PENALTIES



</article>



<article><tid>1847629</tid>
<number> 26</number> Penalty for illegal strikes and lock- outs.-
<section><tid>551784</tid>
<number>1</number>Any workman  
who commences, continues or otherwise acts in furtherance of, a strike 
which is illegal under this Act, shall be punishable with imprisonment 
for a term which may extend to one month, or with fine which may 
extend to fifty rupees, or with both.

</section>

<section><tid>130095</tid>
<number>2</number>Any employer who commences, continues, or otherwise acts in 
furtherance of a lock- out which is illegal under this Act, shall be 
punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one month, 
or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>179</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Omitted by Act 49 of <year>1984</year>, s. 6 (w. e. f. 18. 8. <year>1984</year>). 
2. Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1982</year>, s. 15 (w. e. f. 21. 8. <year>1984</year>). 
3. Omitted by s. 15, ibid. (w. e. f. 21- 8- <year>1984</year>). 
4. Ins. by s. 16, ibid. (w. e. f. 21. 8. <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>728172</tid>
<number>27</number>Penalty for instigation, etc. Any person who instigates or 
incites others to take part in, or otherwise acts in furtherance of, a 
strike or lock- out which is illegal under this Act, shall be 
punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six 
months, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with 
both.


</article>



<article><tid>1765644</tid>
<number>28</number>Penalty for giving financial aid to illegal strikes and 
lock- outs.- Any person who knowingly expends or applies any money in 
direct furtherance or support of any illegal strike or lock- out shall 
be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six 
months, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with 
both.


</article>



<article><tid>226033</tid>
<number>29</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Penalty for breach of settlement or award.- Any person who 
commits a breach of any term of any settlement or award, which is 
binding on him under this Act, shall be punishable with imprisonment 
for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine, or with both, 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> and where the breach is a continuing one, with a further fine which 
may extend to two hundred rupees for every day during which the breach 
continues after the conviction for the first] and the Court trying the 
offence, if it fines the offender, may direct that the whole or any 
part of the fine realised from him shall be paid, by way of 
compensation, to any person who, in its opinion, has been injured by 
such breach.]


</article>



<article><tid>1574478</tid>
<number>30</number>Penalty for disclosing confidential information.- Any person 
who wilfully discloses any such information as is referred to in 
section 21 in contravention of the provisions of that section shall, 
on complaint made by or on behalf of the trade union or individual 
business affected, be punishable with imprisonment for a term which 
may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to one 
thousand rupees, or with both.


</article>



<article><tid>753030</tid>
<number>30A</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Penalty for closure without notice.- Any employer who 
closes down any undertaking without complying with the provisions of 
section 25FFA shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which 
may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to five 
thousand rupees, or with both.]


</article>



<article><tid>1701494</tid>
<number> 31</number> Penalty for other offences.-
<section><tid>1081292</tid>
<number>1</number>Any employer who contravenes  
the provisions of section 33 shall be punishable with imprisonment for 
a term which may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend 
to one thousand rupees, or with both.

</section>

<section><tid>380605</tid>
<number>2</number>Whoever contravenes any of the provisions of this Act or any 
rule made thereunder shall, if no other penalty is elsewhere provided 
by or under this Act for such contravention, be punishable with fine 
which may extend to one hundred rupees.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>180</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 20, for s. 29 (w. e. f. 17- 9- <year>1956</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 35 of <year>1965</year>, s. 6 (w. e. f. 1- 12- <year>1965</year>). 
3. Ins. by Act 32 of <year>1972</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 14- 6- <year>1972</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER VII

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>592257</tid>
<number>32</number>Offence by companies, etc.- Where a person committing an 
offence under this Act is a company, or other body corporate, or an 
association of persons (whether incorporated or not), every director, 
manager, secretary, agent or other officer or person concerned with 
the management thereof shall, unless he proves that the offence was 
committed without his knowledge or consent, be deemed to be guilty of 
such offence.


</article>



<article><tid>1774629</tid>
<number> 33</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Conditions of service, etc., to remain unchanged under 
certain circumstances during pendency of proceedings.-
<section><tid>1544515</tid>
<number>1</number>During the  
pendency of any conciliation proceeding before a conciliation officer 
or a Board or of any proceeding before <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> an arbitrator or] a Labour 
Court or Tribunal or National Tribunal in respect of an industrial 
dispute, no employer shall--

<subsection><tid>886678</tid>
<number>a</number>in regard to any matter connected with the dispute, 
alter, to the prejudice of the workmen concerned in 
such dispute, the conditions of service applicable to 
them immediately before the commencement of such 
proceeding; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>462483</tid>
<number>b</number>for any misconduct connected with the dispute, discharge 
or punish, whether by dismissal or otherwise, any 
workmen concerned in such dispute,
save with the express permission in writing of the authority before 
which the proceeding is pending.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>210468</tid>
<number>2</number>During the pendency of any such proceeding in respect of an 
industrial dispute, the employer may, in accordance with the standing 
orders applicable to a workman concerned in such dispute <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or, where 
there are no such standing orders, in accordance with the terms of the 
contract, whether express or implied, between him and the workman],--

<subsection><tid>1332049</tid>
<number>a</number>alter, in regard to any matter not connected with the 
dispute, the conditions of service applicable to that 
workman immediately before the commencement of such 
proceeding; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>535397</tid>
<number>b</number>for any misconduct not connected with the dispute, or 
discharge or punish, whether by dismissal or otherwise, 
that workman:
Provided that no such workman shall be discharged or dismissed, 
unless he has been paid wages for one month and an application has 
been made by the employer to the authority before which the proceeding 
is pending for approval of the action taken by the employer.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>181</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 21, for s. 33 (w. e. f. 10- 3- <year>1957</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 36 of <year>1964</year>, s. 18 (w. e. f. 19- 12- <year>1964</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>956447</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (2), no 
employer shall, during the pendency of any such proceeding in respect 
of an industrial dispute, take any action against any protected 
workman concerned in such dispute--

<subsection><tid>114772</tid>
<number>a</number>by altering, to the prejudice of such protected workman, 
the conditions of service applicable to him immediately 
before the commencement of such proceedings; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1084104</tid>
<number>b</number>by discharging or punishing, whether by dismissal or 
otherwise, such protected workman,
save with the express permission in writing of the authority before 
which the proceeding is pending.

Explanation.-- For the purposes of this sub- section, a" protected 
workman", in relation to an establishment, means a workman who, being 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> a member of the executive or other office bearer] of a registered 
trade union connected with the establishment, is recognised as such in 
accordance with rules made in this behalf.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>226771</tid>
<number>4</number>In every establishment, the number of workmen to be 
recognised as protected workmen for the purposes of sub- section (3) 
shall be one per cent. of the total number of workmen employed therein 
subject to a minimum number of five protected workmen and a maximum 
number of one hundred protected workmen and for the aforesaid purpose, 
the appropriate Government may make rules providing for the 
distribution of such protected workmen among various trade unions, if 
any, connected with the establishment and the manner in which the 
workmen may be chosen and recognised as protected workmen.

</section>

<section><tid>105993</tid>
<number>5</number>Where an employer makes an application to a conciliation 
officer, Board, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> an arbitrator, a] labour Court, Tribunal or 
National Tribunal under the proviso to sub- section (2) for approval of 
the action taken by him, the authority concerned shall, without delay, 
hear such application and pass, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> within a period of three months 
from the date of receipt of such application], such order in relation 
thereto as it deems fit:]
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Provided that where any such authority considers it necessary 
or expedient so to do, it may, for reasons to be recorded in writing, 
extend such period by such further period as it may think fit:

Provided further that no proceedings before any such authority 
shall lapse merely on the ground that any period specified in this 
sub- section had expired without such proceedings being completed.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>365858</tid>
<number> 33A</number> <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Special provision for adjudication as to whether 
conditions of service, etc., changed during pendency of proceedings.- 
Where an employer contravenes the provisions of section 33 during the 
pendency of proceedings <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> before a conciliation officer, Board, an 
arbitrator, a Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal], any 
employee aggrieved by such contravention may, make a camplaint in 
writing,
<pagefootnote><pagenum>182</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 45 of <year>1971</year>, s. 5, for" an officer" (w. e. f. 15- 12-  
  <year>1971</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 36 of <year>1964</year>, s. 18 (w. e. f 19- 12- <year>1964</year>). 
3. Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1982</year>, s. 17 (w. e. f. 21- 8- <year>1984</year>). 
4. Ins. by by s. 17, ibid. (w. e. f. 10- 3- <year>1957</year>) 
5. Ins. by Act 48 of <year>1950</year>, s. 34 and Sch. 
6. Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1982</year>, s. 18 (w. e. f. 21. 8. <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in the prescribed manner,--

<section><tid>373251</tid>
<number>a</number>to such conciliation officer or Board, and the 
conciliation officer or Board shall take such complaint into 
account in inediating in, and promoting the settlement of, such 
industrial dispute; and

</section>

<section><tid>1922488</tid>
<number>b</number>to such arbitrator, Labour Court, Tribunal or National 
Tribunal and on receipt of such complaint, the arbitrator, 
Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal, as the case may 
be, shall adjudicate upon the complaint as if it were a dispute 
referr ed to or pending before it, in accordance with the 
provisions of this Act and shall submit his or its award to the 
appropriate Government and the provisions of this Act shall apply 
accordingly.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1747031</tid>
<number> 33B</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Power to transfer certain proceedings.-
<section><tid>472421</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
appropriate Government may, by order in writing and for reasons to be 
stated therein, withdraw any proceeding under this Act pending before 
a Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal and transfer the same to 
another Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal, as the case may 
be, for the disposal of the proceeding and the Labour Court, Tribunal 
or National Tribunal to which the proceeding is so transferred may, 
subject to special directions in the order of transfer, proceed either 
de novo or from the stage at which it was so transferred:
Provided that where a proceeding under section 33 or section 33A 
is pending before a Tribunal or National Tribunal, the proceeding may 
also be transferred to a Labour Court.


</section>

<section><tid>1218840</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the provisions of sub- section (1), any 
Tribunal or National Tribunal, if so authorized by the appropriate 
Government, may transfer any proceeding under section 33 or section 
 33A pending before it to any one of the Labour Courts specified for 
the disposal of such proceedings by the appropriate Government by 
notification in the Official Gazette and the Labour Court to which the 
proceeding is so transferred shall dispose of the same.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>759209</tid>
<number> 33C</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Recovery of money due from an employer.-
<section><tid>485232</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any  
money is due to a workman from an employer under a settlement or an 
award or under the provisions of <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Chapter VA or Chapter VB], the 
workman himself or any other person authorised by him in writing in 
this behalf, or, in the case of the death of the workman, his assignee 
or heirs may, without prejudice to any other mode of recovery, make an 
application to the appropriate Government for the recovery of the 
money due to him, and if the appropriate Government is satisfied that 
any money is so due, it
<pagefootnote><pagenum>183</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 46 of <year>1982</year>, s. 18 (w. e. f. 21. 8. <year>1984</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 23 (w. e. f. 10- 3- <year>1957</year>). 
3. Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1964</year>, s. 19, for the former section (w. e. f.  
  19- 12- <year>1964</year>). 
4. Subs. by Act 32 of <year>1976</year>, s. 4, for" Chapter VA" (w. e. f. 5- 3-  
  <year>1976</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


shall issue a certificate for that amount to the Collector who shall 
proceed to recover the same in the same manner as an arrear of land 
revenue:

Provided that every such application shall be made within one 
year from the date on which the money became due to the workman from 
the employer:

Provided further that any such application may be entertained 
after the expiry of the said period of one year, if the appropriate 
Government is satisfied that the applicant had sufficient cause for 
not making the application within the said period.


</section>

<section><tid>483633</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any workman is entitled to receive from the employer 
any money or any benefit which is capable of being computed in terms 
of money and if any question arises as to the amount of money due or 
as to the amount at which such benefit should be computed, then the 
question may, subject to any rules that may be made under this Act, be 
decided by such Labour Court as may be specified in this behalf by the 
appropriate Government; <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> within a period not exceeding three months:]
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Provided that where the presiding officer of a Labour Court 
considers it necessary or expedient so to do, he may, for reasons to 
be recorded in writing, extend such period by such further period as 
he may think fit.]


</section>

<section><tid>1129026</tid>
<number>3</number>For the purposes of computing the money value of a benefit, 
the Labour Court may, if it so thinks fit, appoint a commissioner who 
shall, after taking such evidence as may be necessary, submit a report 
to the Labour Court and the Labour Court shall determine the amount 
after considering the report of the commissioner and other 
circumstances of the case.

</section>

<section><tid>1988576</tid>
<number>4</number>The decision of the Labour Court shall be forwarded by it to 
the appropriate Government and any amount found due by the Labour 
Court may be recovered in the manner provided for in sub- section (1).

</section>

<section><tid>116341</tid>
<number>5</number>Where workmen employed under the same employer are entitled 
to receive from him any money or any benefit capable of being computed 
in terms of money, then, subject to such rules as may be made in this 
behalf, a single application for the recovery of the amount due may be 
made on behalf of or in respect of any number of such workmen.
Explanation.-- In this section" Labour Court" includes any court 
constituted under any law relating to investigation and settlement of 
industrial disputes in force in any State.]]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1757864</tid>
<number> 34</number> Cognizance of offences.-
<section><tid>383726</tid>
<number>1</number>No Court shall take cognizance of  
any offence punishable under this Act or of the abetment of any such 
offence, save on complaint made by or under the authority of the 
appropriate Government.

</section>

<section><tid>951302</tid>
<number>2</number>No Court inferior to that of <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> a Metropolitan Magistrate or 
a Judicial Magistrate of the first class], shall try any offence 
punishable under this Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>184</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 46 of <year>1982</year> s. 19 (w. e. f. 21- 8- <year>1984</year>). 
2. Added by s. 19, ibid. (w. e. f. 21- 8- <year>1984</year>) 
3. Subs. by s. 20, ibid. (w. e. f. 21. 8. <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>24279</tid>
<number> 35</number> Protection of persons.-
<section><tid>552887</tid>
<number>1</number>No person refusing to take part or  
to continue to take part in any strike or lock- out which is illegal 
under this Act shall, by reason of such refusal or by reason of any 
action taken by him under this section, be subject to expulsion from 
any trade union or society, or to any fine or penalty, or to 
deprivation of any right or benefit to which he or his legal 
representatives would otherwise be entitled, or be liable to be placed 
in any respect, either directly or indirectly, under any disability or 
at any disadvantage as compared with other members of the union or 
society, anything to the contrary in the rules of a trade union or 
society notwithstanding.

</section>

<section><tid>363871</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing in the rules of a trade union or society requiring 
the settlement of disputes in any manner shall apply to any proceeding 
for enforcing any right or exemption secured by this section, and in 
any such proceeding the Civil Court may, in lieu of ordering a person 
who has been expelled from membership of a trade union or society to 
be restored to membership, order that he be paid out of the funds of 
the trade union or society such sum by way of compensation or damages 
as that Court thinks just.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1280894</tid>
<number> 36</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Representation of parties.-
<section><tid>1568420</tid>
<number>1</number>A workman who is a party to  
a dispute shall be entitled to be represented in any proceeding under 
this Act by--

<subsection><tid>879546</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> any member of the executive or office bearer] of a 
registered trade union of which he is a member:

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>637568</tid>
<number>b</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> any member of the executive or other office bearer] 
of a federation of trade unions to which the trade 
union referred to in clause (a) is affiliated;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1492135</tid>
<number>c</number>where the worker is not a member of any trade union, by 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> any member of the executive or other office bearer] 
of any trade union connected with, or by any other 
workman employed in, the industry in which the worker 
is employed and authorized in such manner as may be 
prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1367207</tid>
<number>2</number>An employer who is a party to a dispute shall be entitled to 
be represented in any proceeding under this Act by--

<subsection><tid>76731</tid>
<number>a</number>an officer of an association of employers of which he is 
a member;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>495095</tid>
<number>b</number>an officer of a federation of association of employers 
to which the association referred to in clause (a) is 
affiliated;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1220304</tid>
<number>c</number>where the employer is not a member of any association of 
employers, by an officer of any association of 
employers connected with, or by any other employer 
engaged in,
<pagefootnote><pagenum>184A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1950</year>, s. 34 and Sch., for s. 36. 
2. Subs. by Act 45 of <year>1971</year>, s. 6 (w. e. f. 15- 12- <year>1971</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


the industry in which the employer is engaged and 
authorized in such manner as may be prescribed.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>940286</tid>
<number>3</number>No party to a dispute shall be entitled to be represented by 
a legal practitioner in any conciliation proceedings under this Act or 
in any proceedings before a Court.

</section>

<section><tid>1560826</tid>
<number>4</number>In any proceeding <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> before a Labour Court, Tribunal or 
National Tribunal], a party to a dispute may be represented by a legal 
practitioner with the consent of the other parties to the proceeding 
and <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> with the leave of the Labour Court, Tribunal or National 
Tribunal, as the case may be].]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>302995</tid>
<number> 36A</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Power to remove difficulties.-
<section><tid>221709</tid>
<number>1</number>If, in the opinion of  
the appropriate Government any difficulty or doubt arises as to the 
interpretation of any provision of an award or settlement, it may 
refer the question to such Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal 
as it may think fit.

</section>

<section><tid>26480</tid>
<number>2</number>The Labour Court, Tribunal or National Tribunal to which such 
question is referred shall, after giving the parties an opportunity of 
being heard, decide such question and its decision shall be final and 
binding on all such parties.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>594065</tid>
<number>36B</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Power to exempt.- Where the appropriate Government is 
satisfied in relation to any industrial establishment or undertaking 
or any class of industrial establishments or undertakings carried on 
by a department of that Government that adequate provisions exist for 
the investigation and settlement of industrial disputes in respect of 
workmen employed in such establishment or undertaking or class of 
establishments or undertakings, it may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, exempt, conditionally or unconditionally such 
establishment or undertaking or class of establishments or 
undertakings from all or any of the provisions of this Act.].


</article>



<article><tid>1995154</tid>
<number>37</number>Protection of action taken under the Act.- No suit, 
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any person for 
anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in 
pursuance of this Act or any rules made thereunder.


</article>



<article><tid>1295761</tid>
<number> 38</number> Power to make rules.-
<section><tid>499228</tid>
<number>1</number>The appropriate Government may,  
subject to the condition of previous publication, make rules for the 
purpose of giving effect to the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>220907</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>468481</tid>
<number>a</number>the powers and procedure of conciliation officers, 
Boards, Courts, <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Labour Courts, Tribunals and 
National Tribunals] including rules as to the summoning 
of witnesses, the production of documents relevant to 
the subject- matter of an inquiry or investigation, the 
number of members necessary to form a quroum and the 
manner of submission of reports and awards;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>184B</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 24, for" before a Tribunal" (w. e. f.  
  10- 3- <year>1957</year>). 
2. Subs. by s. 24, ibid., for" with the leave of the Tribunal" 
 (w. e. f. 10- 3- <year>1957</year>). 
3. Ins. by s. 25, ibid. (w. e. f. 10- 3- <year>1957</year>). 
4. Subs. by s. 26, ibid., for" and Tribunals" (w. e. f. 10- 3- <year>1957</year>). 
5. Ins. by Act 46 of <year>1982</year>, s. 21 (w. e. f. 21- 8- <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>594914</tid>
<number>aa</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the form of arbitration agreement, the manner in 
which it may be signed by the parties, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the manner in 
which a notification may be issued under sub- section 
 (3A) of section 10A,] the powers of the arbitrator 
named in the arbitration agreement and the procedure to 
be followed by him;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>344362</tid>
<number>aaa</number>the appointment of assessors in proceedings under this 
Act;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1198797</tid>
<number>ab</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the constitution of Grievance Settlement 
Authorities referred to in section 9C, (section 38.) 
the manner in which industrial disputes may be referred 
to such authorities for settlement, the procedure to be 
followed by such authorities in the proceedings in 
relation to disputes referred to them and the period 
within which such preceedings shall be completed;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>509983</tid>
<number>b</number>the constitution and functions of and the filling of 
vacancies in Works Committees, and the procedure to be 
followed by such Committees in the discharge of their 
duties;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1764014</tid>
<number>c</number>the allowances admissible to members of Courts <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> and 
Boards and presiding officers of Labour Courts, 
Tribunals and National Tribunals] and to assessors and 
witnesses;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1253667</tid>
<number>d</number>the ministerial establishment which may be allotted to a 
Court, Board, <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Labour Court, Tribunal or National 
Tribunal] and the salaries and allowances payable to 
members of such establishments;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1442447</tid>
<number>e</number>the manner in which and the persons by and to whom 
notice of strike or lock- out may be given and the 
manner in which such notices shall be communicated;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1932956</tid>
<number>f</number>the conditions subject to which parties may be 
represented by legal practitioners in proceedings under 
this Act before a Court, <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Labour Court, Tribunal or 
National Tribunal];

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>639620</tid>
<number>g</number>any other matter which is to be or may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1117485</tid>
<number>3</number>Rules made under this section may provide that a 
contravention thereof shall be punishable with fine not exceeding 
fifty rupees.

</section>

<section><tid>1929296</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> All rules made under this section shall, as soon as 
possible after they are made, be laid before the State Legislature or, 
where the appropriate Government is the Central Government, before 
both Houses of Parliament.]

</section>

<section><tid>1986325</tid>
<number>5</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Every rule made by the Central Government under this 
section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each
<pagefootnote><pagenum>184C</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 26 (w. e. f. 10- 3- <year>1957</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 36 of <year>1964</year>, s. 20 (w. e. f. 19- 12- <year>1964</year>). 
3. Ins. by Act 46 of <year>1982</year>, s. 22 (w. e. f...) 
4. Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 26, for" Boards and Tribunals" 
 (w. e. f. 10- 3- <year>1957</year>). 
5. Subs. by s. 26, ibid., for" or Tribunal" (w. e. f. 10- 3- <year>1957</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


House of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of 
thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid] both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule, 
or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1022486</tid>
<number> 39</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Delegation of powers.- The appropriate Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, direct that any power 
exercisable by it under this Act or rules made thereunder shall, in 
relation to such matters and subject to such conditions, if any, as 
may be specified in the direction, be exercisable also,--
<section><tid>1814017</tid>
<number>a</number>where the appropriate Government is the Central 
Government, by such officer or authority subordinate to 
the Central Government or by the State Government or by 
such officer or authority subordinate to the State 
Government, as may be specified in the notification; 
and

</section>

<section><tid>216553</tid>
<number>b</number>where the appropriate Government is a State Government, 
by such officer or authority subordinate to the State 
Government as may be specified in the notification.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>254439</tid>
<number> 40</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Power to amend Schedules.-
<section><tid>1053709</tid>
<number>1</number>The appropriate Government  
may, if it is of opinion that it is expedient or necessary in the 
public interest so to do, by notification in the Official Gazette, add 
to the First Schedule any industry, and on any such notification being 
issued, the First Schedule shall be deemed to be amended accordingly.

</section>

<section><tid>660735</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, add to or alter or amend the Second Schedule or the Third 
Schedule and on any such notification being issued, the Second 
Schedule or the Third Schedule, as the case may be, shall be deemed to 
be amended accordingly.

</section>

<section><tid>1137152</tid>
<number>3</number>Every such notification shall, as soon as possible after it 
is issued, be laid before the Legislature of the State, if the 
notification has been issued by a State Government, or before 
Parliament, if the notification has been issued by the Central 
Government.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>184D</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 32 of <year>1976</year>, s. 5, for certain words (w. e. f. 5- 3-  
  <year>1976</year>). 
2. Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 27, for s. 39 (w. e. f. 17- 9- <year>1956</year>). 
3. Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1964</year>, s. 21, for s. 40 (w. e. f. 19- 12- <year>1964</year>), 
which was ins by Act 36 of <year>1956</year>, s. 28. Original s. 40 was rep. 
by Act 35 of <year>1950</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



 </act>