<act><title>THE LIMITED LIABILITY PARTNERSHIP RULES, 
20091</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number>Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the Limited Liability Partnership Rules, 2009. 
 
 
 ____________
 </section><section><number>2</number> (a) Rules 1 to 31, rules 34 to 37 and rule 41 of these rules shall come 
  into force on the 1st day of April, 2009; 
 <subsection><number>b</number> Rules 32 and 33, and rules 38 to 40 of these rules shall come into 
  force on such date as the Central Government may, by notification 
  in the Official Gazette, appoint. </subsection></section></article><article><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
 </article><article><number>2</number> Came into force on 31-5-2009, vide S.O. 1324(E), 
dated 22nd May, 2009, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 
3(ii), dated 22nd May, 2009. 
  </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number>Definitions. </title>
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, unless the context 
otherwise requires, <title></title>
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> Act means the Limited Liability Partnership Act, 2008 (6 of 2009); 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> Annexure means Annexure to these rules; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> Certifying Authority means a person who has been granted a license 
  to issue a Digital Signature Certificate under section 24 of the Information 
  Technology Act, 2000 (21 of 2000); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> Designated Partner Identification Number (DPIN) means an 
  identification number which the Central Government may allot to any individual 
  or nominee of a body corporate, intending to be appointed as designated 
  partner of a limited liability partnership (LLP), for the purpose of his 
  identification as such; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> digital signature means authentication of any electronic record by a 
  subscriber by means of an electronic method or procedure in accordance with 
  the provisions of section 3 of the Information Technology Act, 2000; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vi</number> Digital Signature Certificate means a Digital Signature Certificate 
  issued under sub-section (4) of section 35 of the Information Technology Act, 
  2000; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vii</number> electronic record means electronic record as defined under clause 
  (t) of section 2 of the Information Technology Act, 2000; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>viii</number> electronic registry means an electronic repository or storage 
  system in which the information or documents are received, stored, protected 
  and preserved in electronic form; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ix</number> Electronic mail (E-mail) means message sent, received or forwarded 
  in digital form via a computer-based communication mechanism; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>x</number> Officer' includes any partner, designated partner, employee of the 
  LLP, any person in accordance with whose directions or instructions the 
  partners of the LLP have been accustomed to act and any person authorized to 
  accept any service on behalf of a foreign Limited Liability Partnership and 
  partners of such foreign Limited Liability Partnership; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>xi</number> Pre-fill means the automated process of data input by the computer 
  system from the database maintained in electronic registry; 
 <subsubsection><number>xii</number> Provisional Designated Partner Identification Number refers to the 
  provisional identification number generated by the electronic system setup by 
  the Ministry of Corporate Affairs; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>xiii</number> Registrar means a Registrar as defined under clause (s) of 
  sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Act; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>xiv</number> Registrar's Front Office means an office maintained by the Central 
  Government or an agency authorized by it to facilitate e-filing of documents 
  into the electronic registry and their inspection and viewing; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>xv</number> section' means section of the Act; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>xvi</number> website means a location connected to the internet that maintains 
  one or more web pages; </subsubsection></subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Words and expressions used in these rules and not defined shall have the 
meaning respectively assigned to them in the Limited Liability Partnership Act, 
2008 (6 of 2009) and the Information Technology Act, 2000 (21 of 2000). 
 nd rules 38 to 40 of these rules shall come into force on such date as the 
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint. 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number>Forms. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Every LLP shall use the forms annexed to these 
rules for the purposes of the Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every LLP shall specify therein its limited liability partnership 
identification number (LLPIN). 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number>Authentication of electronic forms. </title>The electronic form 
shall be authenticated by authorized signatories using digital signatures, as 
defined under the Information Technology Act, 2000 (21 of 2000). 
 ___________
 <section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number>Fees. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The fees payable in pursuance of the various 
provisions of the Act and these rules shall be as mentioned in Annexure A'. 

 </section><section><number>2</number> The fees payable in pursuance of the Act or any rule made or notification 
issued thereunder shall be paid into the Public Account of India: 
 Provided that the fees payable to the Registrar may be paid also through 
postal orders (where the amount involved does not exceed fifty rupees) or 
through bank drafts payable at and/or drawn on post offices or banks, as the 
case may be, located at the same city or town where the office of the Registrar 
is situated: 
 Provided further that, where a fee payable to the Registrar is paid through 
postal orders or bank drafts as aforesaid, it shall not be deemed to have been 
paid unless and until the relevant postal orders or drafts are cashed and the 
amount credited: 
 Provided also that, where application is filed through electronic media or 
through any other computer readable media, the user may choose any one of the 
following payment options namely, (i) Credit Card; or (ii) Internet Banking; or 
 (iii) Remittance at the Bank Counter; or (iv) any other mode as approved by 
the Central Government. 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number></title>The manner and conditions of filing, recording or 
registering of documents, forms, notices, statements, returns, etc., shall be as 
laid down in Chapter XIII of these rules. 
 ___________
 <section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> </title>For the purposes of sub-section (3) of section 7, an 
individual shall give his prior consent to act as a designated partner to the 
limited liability partnership in Form 9. 
 ___________
 <section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number> </title>For the purposes of sub-section (4) of section 7, the 
particulars of an individual who has given his consent to act as designated 
partner shall be filed in Form 4 along with fee as mentioned in Annexure A'. 

 ___________
 <section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>9</number> </title>
<section><number>1</number> A person shall not be capable of being appointed as a 
designated partner of a limited liability partnership, if he 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> has at any time within the preceding five years been adjudged 
  insolvent; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> suspends, or has at any time within the preceding five years suspended 
  payment to his creditors and has not at any time within the preceding five 
  years made, a composition with them; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> has been convicted by a Court for any offence involving moral turpitude 
  and sentenced in respect thereof to imprisonment for not less than six months; 
  or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> has been convicted by a Court for an offence involving section 30 of 
  the Act. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
remove the disqualification incurred by any person by virtue of clause (a) or 
(b) of sub-rule (1), either generally or in relation to any limited liability 
partnership or limited liability partnerships specified in the notification. 

 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title>[<number>10</number> </title>
<section><number>1</number> Every individual or nominee of a body 
corporate who is intending to be appointed as designated partner of a limited 
liability partnership shall submit an application electronically to the Central 
Government for allotment of Designated Partner Identification Number (DPIN) in 
the manner as provided in Form 7 along with fee as mentioned in Annexure A'. 

 </section><section><number>2</number> (i) For making an application under sub-rule (1), the applicant shall 
attach the following: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> attested or certified copy of the proof of identity containing 
  self-photograph, date of birth and father's name; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> attested or certified copy of the proof of residence; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> attested recent self-photograph pasted on a plain paper and mentioning 
  on that paper his or her name and affixing his or her two signatures thereon. 
  
 
 <subsubsection><number>ii</number> In case the applicant is a foreign national, a copy of the valid 
    passport shall be proof of identity. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number> In case the applicant is nominee of a body corporate, a copy of 
    resolution or authorization on the letterhead of the body corporate 
    mentioning the name and address of an individual nominated to act as 
    Designated Partner on its behalf shall also be attached: 
</subsubsection></subsection>
 Provided that in case the proof of identity and proof of residence is in a 
language other than Hindi or English, a certified copy of translation of the 
same either in Hindi or English shall be attached. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The documents referred in sub-rule (2) shall be attested or certified by 
any one of the following authorities: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> Gazetted Officer of the Central or State Government, 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> Notary Public, 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> Company Secretary, Chartered Accountant, Cost and Works Accountant 
  holding a certificate of Practice under the Company Secretaries Act, 1980, 
  Chartered Accountants Act, 1949, and the Cost and Works Accountants Act, 1959 
  respectively: </subsection>
 Provided that in the case of foreign nationals residing outside India or 
foreign body corporate(s) registered outside India, the documents referred to in 
sub-rule (2) shall be duly certified and the provisions of sub-rule (2) of rule 
34 of these rules, shall apply mutatis mutandis for this purpose. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Central Government shall process the application received for 
allotment of DPIN under sub-rule (1) and shall decide on the approval or 
rejection thereof and communicate the same along with the DPIN allotted in the 
case of approval to the applicant by way of a letter by post or electronically 
or in any other mode, within a period of thirty days from the receipt of such 
application. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Designated Partner Identification Number allotted under sub-rule (4) 
is valid for the lifetime of the applicant. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> Every Designated Partner shall, along with his consent to be a designated 
partner, intimate his or her DPIN to the Limited Liability Partnership in Form 
9. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> (i) Every Designated Partner, who has been allotted a DPIN under these 
rules, in the event of any change in the particulars of such Designated Partner, 
shall intimate such change(s) to the Central Government within a period of 30 
days of such change(s) in Form 10. 
 
 <subsection><number>ii</number> The Designated Partners shall attach certified copies of the proof of 
  the changed particulars from any of the authorities specified in sub-rule (3). 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> There shall be no fee for intimating the change(s) of particulars in 
   Form 10. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>8</number> The concerned designated partner, shall also intimate change(s) in 
particulars in Form 6 to the Limited Liability Partnership or Limited Liability 
Partnership(s) in which he is a designated partner within 15 days of such 
change(s).] ---------- 
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 
2009. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 24(E), dated 11th January, 2010, for rule 10 
(w.e.f. 15-1-2010). Rule 10, before substitution, stood as under: 
 <title>10. </title>(1) Every individual or nominee of a body 
corporate, who is intending to be appointed as designated partner of a limited 
liability partnership shall make an application electronically in Form 7 to the 
Central Government for obtaining Designated Partner Identification Number 
(DPIN). 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Central Government shall provide an electronic system to 
facilitate submission of application for the allotment of DPIN through a portal 
on the website of the Ministry of Corporate Affairs. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The applicant shall access the Form 7 from the portal, 
fill-in the required particulars sought therein and use submit' function 
provided therein upon which the system will electronically generate and indicate 
in the space provided a Provisional DPIN. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> A provisional DPIN generated online under sub-rule (3) by 
the applicant will remain valid for a period of sixty days from the date on 
which it was generated. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> (i) The applicant shall, after the allotment of provisional 
DPIN, submit an application to the Central Government along with the fee as 
mentioned in Annexure A' for the allotment of regular DPIN within sixty days 
from the date on which provisional DPIN was generated on-line, failing which the 
provisional DPIN will lapse. 
 <subsection><number>ii</number> For making an application under sub-rule (i), the applicant 
shall take a print out of  Form 7, affix his photograph in the space provided 
in that Form, enclose true copies of the proof of identity and proof of 
residence and physically sign the form at the place specified therein. The 
photograph and the proof of identity and residence shall be certified by any one 
of the following authorities: 
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> Gazetted Officer of the Central or State Government, 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> Notary Public, 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>c</number> Chartered Accountant, Cost Accountant or Company Secretary 
holding a certificate of practice under the Chartered Accountants Act, 1949, the 
Cost and Works Accountants Act, 1959 and the Company Secretaries Act, 1980 
respectively. 
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section><number>6</number> The Central Government shall process the applications 
received for allotment of DPIN under sub-rule (5), decide on such application 
and communicate approval along with the DPIN allotted or rejection thereof to 
the applicant by way of a letter by post or electronically or in any other mode, 
within a period of one month from the receipt of such application. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> The DPIN so allotted is valid for the life time of such 
applicant and shall not be allotted to any other person in any case. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> Every designated partner shall intimate his consent to 
become a designated partner to the limited liability partnership and DPIN in 
Form 9 and the LLP shall intimate such DPIN to Registrar in Form 4. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> (a) (i) Every designated partner, who has been allotted a 
DPIN under these rules shall, in the event of any change in his particulars as 
stated in Form 7 under sub-rule (5), intimate such change(s) to the Central 
Government within a period of 30 days of such change(s) in Form 10: 
 <subsection><number>ii</number> The concerned designated partner shall also intimate such 
changes to the limited liability partnership or limited liability partnership(s) 
on which he is a designated partner within 30 days of such changes. 
 <subsubsection><number>b</number> The designated partners shall fill-in the relevant change(s) 
in prescribed Form 10, enclose a copy of the proof of the changed particulars 
duly certified in the manner specified in clause (ii) of sub-rule (5), affix 
signature at the place specified, and file the same to the Central Government. 
There shall be no fee for intimating the changes in particulars in Form 10. 
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section><number>10</number> The Central Government, after being satisfied, through 
verification of such changed particulars from the enclosed copy of proof, shall 
incorporate the said change and inform the designated partner by way of a letter 
issued by post or electronically or in any other mode confirming the effect of 
such change in the electronic database maintained by the Ministry of Corporate 
Affairs.. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>11</number> </title>For the purposes of section 11, the incorporation 
document shall be filed in Form 2 with the Registrar having jurisdiction over 
the State in which the registered office of the limited liability partnership is 
to be situated alongwith the fee as provided in Annexure A'. 
 ___________
 <section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title>[</title><title><number>12</number> </title>Where the intending 
partner is a body corporate, copy of Resolution on the letterhead of such body 
corporate to become a partner in the proposed LLP and a copy of resolution or 
authorization of such body corporate also on letterhead mentioning the name and 
address of an individual nominated to act as nominee or nominee and Designated 
Partner on its behalf, shall be attached: 
 Provided that in the case of foreign nationals residing outside India or 
foreign body corporate(s) registered outside India, seeking to register a LLP in 
India , the name, address and signature of an individual or nominee or nominee 
and Designated Partner of a body corporate on the incorporation document, proof 
of identity, where required and documents referred in this rule, shall be duly 
certified and the provisions of sub-rule (2) of rule 34 of these rules, shall 
apply mutatis mutandis for this purpose.] ---------- 
 <section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 
2009. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 24(E), dated 11th January, 2010, for rule 12 
(w.e.f. 15-1-2010). Rule 12, before substitution, stood as under: 
  <title>12. </title>In case of foreign nationals residing 
outside India in countries signatory to the Hague Apostile Convention, 1961 and 
seeking to register a LLP in India, their signatures and address on the 
incorporation documents and proof of identity, where required, shall be 
notarized before the notary of the country of their origin and be duly 
apostillised in accordance with the said Hague Convention.. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>13</number> </title>The statement to be filed along with the incorporation 
document under clause (c) of sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 11 shall be in the 
format provided in  Part B of Form 2. 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>14</number> </title>
<section><number>1</number> In the office of Registrar there shall be maintained 
a Register of LLPs in which the names of LLPs shall be entered in the order in 
which they are registered. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every LLP so registered shall be assigned a LLP identification number 
(LLPIN) in one consecutive series. 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>15</number> </title>
<section><number>1</number> A document can be served on a limited liability 
partnership or a partner or designated partner thereof through the following 
other modes 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> electronic transmission; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> courier </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> For the purposes of this rule, 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> electronic transmission means a communication 
 
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> delivered by 
 
 <subsubsubsection><number>A</number> facsimile telecommunication or electronic mail when directed to the 
      facsimile number of electronic mail address, respectively, which the 
      partnership or the partner or the designated partner has provided from 
      time to time for sending communications to the partnership or the partner 
      or the designated partner respectively; 
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>B</number> posting on an electronic message board or network that the 
      partnership or the partner or the designated partner has designated for 
      those communications, and which transmission shall be validly delivered 
      upon the posting; or 
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>C</number> other means of electronic communication, as to which the LLP or the 
      partner or the designated partner has placed in effect reasonable measures 
      to verify that the sender is the person purporting to send the 
      transmission, and </subsubsubsection>
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> that creates a record that is capable of retention, retrieval and 
    review, and that may thereafter be rendered into clearly legible tangible 
    form; </subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> Courier means a document sent through a courier which provides the 
  proof of delivery. </subsection>
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>16</number> </title>
<section><number>1</number> A limited liability partnership shall give an 
address for service of documents within the jurisdiction of the Registrar where 
its registered office is situate. Such address shall include the postal code and 
e-mail address. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The limited liability partnership, may, in addition to the registered 
office address, declare any other address as its address for service of 
documents, under sub-section (2) of section 13, in the manner as laid down in 
the limited liability partnership agreement. Where the limited liability 
partnership agreement does not provide for such manner, consent of all partners 
shall be required for declaring any other address as the address for service of 
documents. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The intimation of other address for service of documents to LLP shall be 
given to the Registrar in Form 12, within thirty days of complying with the 
requirements of sub-rule (2) above along with the fee as mentioned in 
 Annexure A'. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The effective date for the service of documents to LLP at the other 
address declared by the LLP cannot be prior to the date of filing of document 
under sub rule (3). 
  
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>17</number> </title>
<section><number>1</number> The limited liability partnership may change its 
registered office from one place to another by following the procedure as laid 
down in the limited liability partnership agreement. Where the limited liability 
partnership agreement does not provide for such procedure, consent of all 
partners shall be required for changing the place of registered office of 
limited liability partnership to another place: 
 Provided that where the change in place of registered office is from one 
State to another State, the limited liability partnership having secured 
creditors shall also obtain consent of such secured creditors. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> For the purposes of sub-section (3) of section 13, notice of change of 
place of registered office shall be given to Registrar in Form 15, within 30 
days of complying with the requirements of sub-rule (1), in case of change of 
registered office within the same state, and within 30 days of complying with 
sub-rule (4) in case of change of registered office from one state to another 
state, along with fee mentioned in Annexure A'. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where there is any conviction, ruling, order or judgment of any Court, 
tribunal or other authority against the limited liability partnership, the 
particulars of such prosecutions initiated against or show cause notices 
received by the limited liability partnership for the alleged offences under the 
LLP Act shall be stated in the notice of change of place of registered office to 
be filed with the Registrar. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Where the change in place of registered office is from one state to 
another state, the limited liability partnership shall publish a general notice, 
not less than 21 days before filing any notice with Registrar, in a daily 
newspaper published in English and in the principal language of the district in 
which the registered office of the limited liability partnership is situated and 
circulating in that district giving notice of change of registered office. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Where the change in place of registered office is from one place to 
another place within the state from the jurisdiction of one Registrar to the 
jurisdiction of another Registrar or from one state to another state, the 
limited liability partnership shall file the notice in Form 15 with the 
Registrar from where the limited liability partnership proposes to shift its 
registered office with a copy thereof for the information to the Registrar under 
whose jurisdiction the registered office is proposed to be shifted. 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>18</number> </title>
<section><number>1</number> The name of the limited liability partnership shall 
not be one prohibited under the Emblems and Names (Prevention of Improper Use) 
Act, 1950. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> A name shall not generally be reserved, if 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> it includes any word or words which are offensive to any section of the 
  people; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> the proposed name is the exact Hindi or English translation of the 
  name of an existing limited liability partnership in English or Hindi, as the 
  case may be; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> the proposed name has a close phonetic resemblance to the name of a 
  LLP in existence, for example, J.K. LLP., Jay Kay LLP; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> it includes the word Co-operative, Sahakari or the equivalent of word 
  co-operative' in the regional languages of the country; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> it connotes the participation or patronage of the Central or State 
  Government, unless circumstances justify to, e.g. , a name may be 
  deemed undesirable in certain context if it includes any of the words such as 
  National, Union, Central, Federal, Republic, President, Rashtrapati, etc; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vi</number> the proposed name contains the words  British India '; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vii</number> the proposed name implies association or connection with any Embassy 
  or Consulate or of a foreign government which suggests connection with local 
  authorities such as Municipal, Panchayat, Zila Parishad or any other body 
  connected with the Union or State Government; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>viii</number> the proposed name is vague like D.I.M.O. Limited liability 
  partnership or I.V.N.R. Limited liability partnership or S.S.R.P Limited 
  liability partnership; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ix</number> it is different from the name or names of the existing limited 
  liability partnership only to the extent of having the name of a place within 
  brackets before the word limited liability partnership', for example, Indian 
  Press (Delhi) LLP should not be allowed in view of the existence of the LLP 
  named Indian Press LLP; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>x</number> it includes name of registered Trade mark, unless the consent of the 
  owner of the trade mark has been produced; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>xi</number> the proposed name is identical with or too nearly resembles the name 
  of a firm or LLP or company <title></title>incorporated outside India and 
  reserved by such firm, LLP or company with the registrar in accordance with 
  these rules; 
 <subsubsection><number>xii</number> it is identical with or too nearly resembles the name of the limited 
  liability partnership or a company in liquidation or it is 
  <title></title>identical with or too nearly resembles names of the LLP or a 
  company which is struck off, up to the period of 5 years; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>xiii</number> it includes words like Bank', Insurance' and Banking', Venture 
  capital' or mutual fund' or such similar names without the approval of the 
  regulatory authority; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>xiv</number> it is intended or likely to produce a misleading impression regarding 
  the scope or scale of its activities which would be beyond the resources at 
  its disposal; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>xv</number> the proposed name includes words like French, British, German etc., 
  unless the partners satisfy that there is some form of collaboration and 
  connection with the foreigners of that particular country or place, the name 
  of which is incorporated in the name; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>xvi</number> the proposed name of limited liability partnership includes the words 
  company secretary, chartered accountant, advocates or such similar words as 
  indicative of a profession, as part of the proposed name, the same shall be 
  allowed only after obtaining approval from the Council governing such 
  profession or such authority as may be nominated by the Central Government, in 
  this behalf. </subsubsection></subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> A foreign LLP or a foreign company may on payment of fee as mentioned in 
Annexure A', apply in Form 25 to the Registrar for reserving its existing name 
by which it is registered in the country of its regulation or incorporation: 

 Provided that such reservation shall be valid for three years but may be 
renewed on a fresh application along with payment of fee as provided in Annexure 
A'. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> An application for reservation of name with which the proposed limited 
liability partnership is to be registered or for change of name, as the case may 
be, shall be made to the Registrar having jurisdiction where the registered 
office of the limited liability partnership is to be situate. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Every such application shall be in Form 1 and be accompanied by fee as 
mentioned in Annexure A' and the Registrar shall inform to the applicant for 
reservation or non reservation of the changed name or the name with which the 
proposed LLP is to be registered ordinarily within seven days of the receipt of 
application. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> Where the Registrar informs applicant about reservation of name with 
which the LLP is to be registered or changed name, as the case may be, such name 
shall be available for reservation for a period of three months from the date of 
intimation by the Registrar. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>19</number> </title>
<section><number>1</number> A limited liability partnership or a body corporate 
or any other entity which already has a name which is similar to or which too 
nearly resembles the name of a limited liability partnership incorporated 
subsequently, may apply to the Registrar in Form 23 to give a direction to that 
limited liability partnership incorporated subsequently to change its name. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The application under sub-rule (1) shall state 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> the LLPIN of limited liability partnership, or the CIN of the company 
  or the registration number of the other entity as the case may be; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> the name with which the limited liability partnership or the company 
  or any other entity was incorporated or registered; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> the grounds of objection to the name of the limited liability 
  partnership incorporated subsequently. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> The application shall be verified by the person making it. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The person making the application shall attach 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the authority under which he is making such an application; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> a copy of the incorporation certificate of the limited liability 
  partnership or the company or the registration certificate of the entity, as 
  the case may be. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>5</number> The application shall be accompanied by a fee as mentioned in 
 Annexure A'. <title></title>
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>20</number> </title>
<section><number>1</number> <title></title>The limited liability partnership 
may change its name by following the procedure as laid down in the limited 
liability partnership agreement. Where the limited liability partnership 
agreement does not provide such procedure, consent of all partners shall be 
required for changing the name of the limited liability partnership. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notice of change of name shall be given to the Registrar in Form 5, 
within 30 days of complying with requirement of sub-rule (1), along with a fee 
as mentioned in Annexure A'. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Registrar on being satisfied that the changed name is the one as 
reserved by him shall issue a fresh certificate of incorporation in the new name 
and the changed name shall be effective from the date of such certificate. 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>21</number> </title>
<section><number>1</number> For the purposes of sub-section (2) of 
section 23, every limited liability partnership shall file information with 
regard to the limited liability partnership agreement in Form 3 with the 
Registrar within thirty days of the date of incorporation alongwith the fee as 
provided in Annexure A': 
 Provided that any change made in the limited liability partnership agreement 
shall be filed in Form 3 within thirty days of such change alongwith the fee as 
provided in Annexure A'. 
 </section><section>[<number>2</number> For the purposes of sub-section (3) of section 23, every 
limited liability partnership shall get the limited liability partnership 
agreement, referred to in that sub-section, rectified by all the partners 
immediately after incorporation and shall file information contained therein in 
Form 3 with the Registrar within thirty days of the incorporation of the limited 
liability partnership alongwith the fee as provided in Annexure A'.] 
---------- 
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 
2009. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 24(E), dated 11th January, 2010, for sub-rule 
(2) (w.e.f. 15-1-2010). Sub-rule (2), before substitution, stood as under: 
 (2) For the purposes of sub-section (3) of section 23, every 
limited liability partnership shall file information with regard to the limited 
liability partnership agreement referred to in such sub-section, in Form 3 with 
the Registrar within thirty days of the ratification by all the partners 
alongwith the fee as provided in Annexure A'.. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>22</number> </title>
<section><number>1</number> <title></title>For the purposes of sub-section (1) 
of section 25, every partner  shall intimate change in his name or address to 
the limited liability partnership in Form 6. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> For the purposes of sub-section (2) of section 25, where a person becomes 
or ceases to be a partner or where there is any change in the name or address of 
a partner, the limited liability partnership shall file with the Registrar, a 
notice in Form 4. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> For the purposes of sub-section (3) of section 25, in respect of notice 
of a person becoming a partner, the Form 4 shall include a statement signed by 
the incoming partner that he consents to become a partner. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The form shall be accompanied by a certificate from a Chartered 
Accountant <title></title>in practice or Cost Accountant in practice 
or a Company Secretary in practice that he has verified the particulars from the 
books and records of the limited liability partnership and found them to be true 
and correct. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The fees to be paid to the registrar in pursuance of sub-section (3) of 
section 25 shall be as mentioned in Annexure A'. 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>23</number> </title>
<section><number>1</number> The contribution of each partner shall be accounted 
for and disclosed in the Accounts of the LLP along with nature of contribution 
and amount. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The contribution of a partner consisting of tangible, movable or 
immovable or intangible property or other benefits brought or contribution by 
way of an agreement or contract for services shall be valued by a practicing 
Chartered Accountant or by a practicing Cost Accountant or by approved valuer 
from the panel maintained by the Central Government. 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>24</number> </title>
<section><number>1</number> Every limited liability partnership shall keep books of accounts which are sufficient to show and explain the limited liability partnership's transactions and are such as to 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number>  disclose with reasonable accuracy, at any time, the financial position of the limited liability partnership at that time; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> enable the designated partners to ensure that any Statement of Account and Solvency prepared under this rule <title></title>complies with the requirements of the Act. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The books of account shall contain 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> particulars of all sums of money received and expended by the limited liability partnership and the matters in respect of which the receipt and expenditure takes place; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> a record of the assets and liabilities of the limited liability partnership;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> statements of cost of goods purchased, inventories, work-in- progress, finished goods and cost of goods sold; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> any other particulars which the partners may decide. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> The books of account which a limited liability partnership is required to keep shall be preserved for eight years from the date on which they are made. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> For the purposes of sub-section (3) of section 34, every limited liability partnership shall file the Statement of Account and Solvency in Form 8 with the Registrar, within a period of thirty days from the end of six months of the financial year to which the Statement of Account and Solvency relates: 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[Provided that if a limited liability partnership has closed the financial year on the 31st March, 2011, it shall file the Statement of Account and Solvency in Form 8 with the Registrar, within a period of sixty days from the end of six months of the financial year to which the Statement of Account and Solvency relates.] 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The fees to be paid to the Registrar in pursuance of sub-section (3) of section 34 for filing the Statement of Account and Solvency shall be as mentioned in Annexure A'. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> A limited liability partnership's Statement of Account and Solvency shall be signed on behalf of the limited liability partnership by its designated partners. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> The Statement of Account and Solvency of a limited liability partnership shall be signed by the designated partners of the LLP and each designated partner shall be taken to be a party to its approval unless he shows that he took all reasonable steps to prevent their being approved and signed. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> The accounts of every limited liability partnership shall be audited in accordance with these rules: 
 Provided that a limited liability partnership whose turnover does not exceed, in any financial year, forty lakh rupees, or whose contribution does not exceed twenty-five lakh rupees shall not be required to get its accounts audited: 
 Provided further that if partners of such limited liability partnership decide to get the accounts of such LLP audited, the accounts shall be audited in accordance with these rules: 
 Provided also that where the partners of such LLP do not decide for audit of the accounts of the LLP, such LLP shall include in the Statement of Account and Solvency a statement by the partners to the effect that the partners acknowledge their responsibilities for complying with the requirements of the Act and the Rules with respect to preparation of books of account and a certificate in the form specified in Form 8. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> A person shall not be qualified for appointment as an auditor of a limited liability partnership unless he is a Chartered Accountant in practice. 
 </section><section><number>10</number> An auditor or auditors of a limited liability partnership shall be appointed for each financial year of the LLP for auditing its accounts. 
 </section><section><number>11</number> The designated partners may appoint an auditor or auditors 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> at any time for the first financial year but before the end of the first financial year, 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> at least 30 days prior to the end of the each financial year (other than the first financial year), 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> to fill a casual vacancy in the office of auditor, including in the case when the turnover or contribution of a limited liability partnership exceeds the limits specified under sub-rule (8), or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> to fill up the vacancy caused by removal of an auditor. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>12</number> The partners may appoint an auditor or auditors where the designated partners have power to appoint under sub-rule (11) and have failed to appoint. 
 </section><section><number>13</number> An auditor or auditors of an LLP shall hold office in accordance with the terms of his or their appointment and shall continue to hold such office till the period 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the new auditors are appointed, or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> they are re-appointed. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>14</number> Where no auditor has been appointed under sub-rule (11), any auditor in office shall be deemed to be re-appointed, unless 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the limited liability partnership agreement requires actual re-appointment, or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the majority of partners have determined that he should not be re-appointed and have given a notice to this effect to the LLP. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>15</number> Provisions of sub-rule (14) shall be applicable without prejudice to the provisions of the rules relating to removal and resignation of auditors under this Chapter. 
 </section><section><number>16</number> A notice specified under clause (b) of sub-rule 14 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> may be in hard copy or electronic form, and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> must be authenticated by the person or persons giving it. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>17</number> The remuneration of an auditor appointed by the limited liability partnership may be fixed by the designated partners or by following the procedure as laid down in the limited liability partnership agreement. 
 </section><section><number>18</number> (a) The partners of a limited liability partnership may remove an auditor from office at any time by following the procedure as laid down in the limited liability partnership agreement. 
 
 <subsection><number>b</number> Where the limited liability partnership agreement does not provide for removal of an auditor, consent of all the partners shall be required for removal of the auditor from his office. <title></title>
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>19</number> (a) An auditor of an LLP may resign his office by depositing a notice in writing to that effect at the LLP's registered office. <title></title>
 
 <subsection><number>b</number> Where an auditor is unwilling to be re-appointed, he shall give a notice in writing to that effect at the LLP's registered office, not less than 14 days before the end of the time allowed for appointing the new auditor. <title></title>
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> The notice under clause (a) or (b) is not effective unless it is accompanied by the statement of the circumstances connected with his ceasing to hold office. <title></title>
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> The auditor's term comes to an end as on the date on which the notice is deposited or on such later date as may be specified in the notice. 
</subsection>



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>25</number> </title>
<section><number>1</number> For the purposes of sub section (1) of section 35, 
every limited liability partnership <title></title>shall file 
<title></title>an annual return with the Registrar in Form 11. 
<title></title>
 </section><section><number>2</number> <title></title>The annual return of an LLP having turnover upto five 
crore rupees during the corresponding financial year or contribution upto fifty 
lakh rupees shall be accompanied with a certificate from a designated partner, 
other than the signatory to the annual return, to the effect that annual return 
contains true and correct information. In all other cases, the annual return 
shall be accompanied with a certificate from a Company Secretary in practice to 
the effect that he has verified the particulars from the books and records of 
the limited liability partnership and found them to be true and correct. 
<title></title>
 </section><section><number>3</number> <title></title>The fees to be paid to the Registrar in pursuance of 
sub-section (1) of section 35 for filing the annual return shall be as mentioned 
in Annexure A'. <title></title>
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>26</number> </title>The documents to be kept by the Registrar under section 
36 <title></title>shall be available in the registry on payment of fee as 
mentioned in Annexure 'A' for inspection by any person and for obtaining any 
certified copy thereof. 
 ___________
 <section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>27</number> </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Registrar shall preserve the documents 
permanently as specified in Annexure B' to these rules. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Subject to previous order of the Registrar, the records in the office of 
Registrar may be destroyed after the expiry of the period of their preservation 
as specified below: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> Records to be preserved for 21 years: 
 All papers, registers, refund orders and correspondence relating to the 
  limited liability partnership liquidation accounts. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> Records to be preserved for 5 years: 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> copies of Government orders relating to limited liability 
    partnership; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> registered documents of limited liability partnership which have 
    been fully wound up and finally dissolved together with correspondence 
    relating to such limited liability partnership; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number> papers relating to legal proceedings from the date of disposal of 
    the case and appeal, if any; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iv</number> copies of statistical returns furnished to Government; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>v</number> all correspondences including correspondences relating to scrutiny of 
    accounts, annual returns, prosecutions, reports to the Central Government 
    and the Tribunal and the correspondences relating to complaints: 
  </subsubsection></subsection>
 Provided <title></title>that in case of prosecution matter, the date is to 
be recorded from the date of disposal of the case and appeal, if any. 
 
 <subsection><number>c</number> Records to be preserved for three years: 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> all books, records and papers, other than those specified in sub-rule 
    (1), clauses (a) and (b) of sub-rule (2), sub-rule (3) and sub-rule (4); 

 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> routine correspondence regarding payment of fees, additional filing 
    fees and correspondence about the return of documents. 
</subsubsection></subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> The registered documents specified in Annexure C' to these rules 
relating to any limited liability partnership in operation shall be preserved 
for the period indicated against them in the said Annexure. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Registered documents of foreign limited liability partnerships which 
cease to have any place of business in India shall be destroyed after expiry of 
three years from the date such limited liability partnerships cease to have any 
place of business in India . 
 </section><section><number>5</number> <title></title>The Registrar shall maintain a Register of destroyed 
documents in two parts, in the form set out in the Annexure D' to these rules, 
wherein he shall enter brief particulars of the records destroyed and shall 
certify therein the date and mode of destruction. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The provisions of these rules shall be in addition to and not in 
derogation of the rules for the destruction of office records connected with 
accounts (containing in Appendix 13 to the Compilation of the General Financial 
Rules) and the period prescribed under Record Retention Schedule for Records 
common to all departments and such other rules. 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>29</number> </title>For the purposes of section 44, an application by the 
partners under clause 
<section><number>a</number> of sub section (1) of section 43 to investigate the 
affairs of the limited liability partnership, shall be made alongwith the 
deposit of such security as calculated in the manner specified in rule 28. 
 ___________
 <subsection><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
  </subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>30</number> </title>The fee payable for furnishing a copy of the Inspector's 
report in pursuance of clause (b), sub-section (2), section 49 shall be five 
rupees per page or fractional part thereof. 
 ___________
 <section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>31</number> </title>For the purposes of section 54, a copy of the report of 
any inspector or inspectors, shall be authenticated either 
 <section><number>a</number> by the common seal, if any, of the limited liability partnership whose 
affairs have been investigated into; or 
 </section><section><number>b</number> by a certificate of a public officer having the custody of the report, 
under and in accordance with the provisions of section 76 of the Indian Evidence 
Act, 1872 (1 of 1872). 
 ___________
 <subsection><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
  </subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>32</number> </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Registrar shall, on conversion of a firm, 
private company or an unlisted public company into limited liability 
partnership, issue a Certificate of Registration under his seal in Form 19. 
 
 
 ____________
 </section><section><number>2</number> In the event, Registrar has refused the registration, the applicant 
  firm or private company or unlisted public company, as the case may be, may 
  apply  to the Tribunal within sixty days from the date of receipt of such 
  intimation of refusal: 
 [Provided that until the Tribunal is constituted under the 
  Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), the application under this sub-rule may be 
  made to the Company Law Board.] </section><section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 385(E), dated 4th June, 2009 (w.e.f. 4-6-2009 
). 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>33</number> </title>For the purposes of the proviso to sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of 
section 58, where the firm, private company or unlisted public company has been 
converted into limited liability partnership, an intimation of such conversion 
to the concerned Registrar of firms or Registrar of Companies, as the case may 
be, shall be given in Form 14 within fifteen days of the date of registration of 
the LLP. 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>34</number> </title>
<section><number>1</number> A foreign limited liability partnership shall, 
within thirty days of establishing a place of business in India , file with the 
Registrar in Form 27 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> a copy of the certificate of incorporation or registration and other 
  instrument(s) constituting or defining the constitu­tion of the limited 
  liability partnership; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the full address of the registered or principal office of the limited 
  liability partnership in the country of its incorporation; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the full address of the office of the limited liability partnership in 
  India which is to be deemed as its principal place of business in India ; and 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> list of partners and designated partners, if any, and the names and 
  addresses of two or more persons resident in India, authorized to accept on 
  behalf of the limited liability partnership, service of process and any 
  notices or other documents required to be served on the limited liability 
  partnership. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> (i) If the limited liability partnership is incorporated in any country 
which is a part of the Commonwealth, the copies of the documents referred to in 
sub-rule (1) shall be certified as true copies 
 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> by an official of the Government to whose custody the original is 
    committed; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> by a Notary (Public) in that Part of the Commonwealth; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> by an officer of the limited liability partnership, on oath before a 
    person having authority to administer an oath in that part of the 
    Commonwealth. </subsection>
 <subsection><number>ii</number> If the Limited Liability Partnership is incorporated in a country that 
  falls outside the Commonwealth but is a party to the Hague Apostile 
  Convention, 1961 
 
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> the copies of the documents referred to in sub-rule (1) shall be 
    certified by an official of the Government to whose custody the original is 
    committed and be duly apostillised in accordance with Hague Convention; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> a list of the partners and designated partners of the LLP, if any, 
    the name and address of persons resident in India, authorized to accept 
    notice on behalf of the Limited Liability Partnership shall be duly 
    notarized and be apostillised in the country of their origin in accordance 
    with Hague Convention. </subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> If the limited liability partnership is incorporated in a country 
  outside the Commonwealth and is not a party to the Hague Convention, the copy 
  of the incorporation documents referred in sub-rule (1) shall be certified 
  
 
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> by an official of the Government to whose custody the original is 
    committed; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> a Notary (Public) of such country; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>c</number> by an officer of the limited liability partnership. </subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> The signature or seal of the official referred to in sub-clause (a) of 
  clause (iii) or the certificate of the Notary (Public) referred to in 
  sub-clause (b) of that clause shall be authenticated by a Diplomatic or 
  Consular Officer empowered in this behalf under section 3 of the Diplomatic 
  and Consular Officers (Oaths and Fees) Act, 1948 (XL of 1948), or where there 
  is no such officer, by any of the officials mentioned in section 6 of the 
  Commissioners of Oaths Act, 1889 (52 and 53 Vic. C. 10), or in any Act 
  amending the same. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> The certificate of the officer of the limited liability partnership 
  referred to in sub-clause (c) of clause (iii) shall be signed before a person 
  having authority to administer an oath as provided under section 3 of the 
  Diplomatic and Consular Officers (Oaths and Fees) Act, 1948 (XL of 1948), or 
  as the case may be, by section 3 of the Commissioners of Oaths Act, 1889 (52 
  and 53 Vic, C. 10) the status of the person administering the oath in the 
  latter case being authenticated by any official specified in section 6 of the 
  Commissioners of Oaths Act, 1889 (52 and 53 Vic. C. 10) or in any Act amending 
  the same. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> (i) If any alteration is made or occurs in 
 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the instrument constituting or <title></title>defining the 
    constitution of a limited liability partnership incorporated or registered 
    outside India ; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the registered or principal office of a limited liability partnership 
    incorporated or registered outside India ; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the partner or designated partner, if any, of a limited liability 
    partnership incorporated or registered outside India , 
</subsection>
 the foreign limited liability partnership shall file in Form 28 such 
alterations with the Registrar within sixty days of the close of the financial 
year. 
 
 <subsection><number>ii</number> If any alteration is made or occurs in 
 
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> the certificate of incorporation or registration of limited liability 
    partnership incorporated or registered outside India ; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> the name or address of any of the persons authorized to accept 
    service on behalf of a foreign limited liability partnership in India; or 
    
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>c</number> the principal place of business of foreign limited liability 
    partnership in India , 
 the foreign limited liability partnership shall file in Form 29 such 
    alterations with the Registrar within thirty days from the date on which the 
    alteration was made or occurred. </subsubsection></subsection>
 </section><section><number>4</number> Every foreign limited liability partnership shall file with the Registrar 
the Statement of Account and Solvency in Form 8 in accordance with provisions of 
rule 24 duly signed by the authorized representatives within a period of 30 days 
from the end of six months of the financial year. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> (i) If any document as is mentioned in sub-rule (1) or (3) is not in the 
English language, there shall be annexed to it a certified translation thereof. 

 
 <subsection><number>ii</number> The translation of documents into English required to be filed with 
  the Registrar in pursuance of sub-rule (1) or (3) shall be certified to be 
  correct in the manner as provided in clause (iii) or clause (iv) of this 
  sub-rule, as the case may be. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> Where any translation is made outside India , it shall be 
  authenticated in the manner specified in sub-rule (2). 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> Where such translation is made within India , it shall be 
  authenticated 
 
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> by an Advocate, Chartered Accountant, Company Secretary or Cost 
    Accountant; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> by an affidavit of a person who, in the opinion of the Registrar has 
    adequate knowledge of the language of the original and of English. 
  </subsubsection></subsection>
 </section><section><number>6</number> Every foreign limited liability partnership shall cause the name of the 
foreign limited liability partnership and of the country in which the limited 
liability partnership is incorporated, to be stated in legible English 
characters in all invoices, official correspondence and publications of the 
limited liability partnership. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> (a) Where any such limited liability partnership makes default in 
delivering to the Registrar the names and addresses of persons resident in India 
who are authorized to accept on behalf of the limited liability partnership 
service of process, notices or other documents; or 
 
 <subsection><number>b</number> If at any time all the persons whose names and addresses have been so 
  delivered are dead or have ceased so to reside, or refuse to accept service on 
  behalf of the limited liability partnership or for any reason, cannot be 
  served; </subsection>
 a document may be served on the limited liability partnership by leaving it 
at, or sending it by post to, any place of business established by the limited 
liability partnership in India . 
 </section><section><number>8</number> If any foreign limited liability partnership ceases to have a place of 
business in India, it shall give notice to the Registrar in Form 29 within 30 
days of its intention to close the place of business and as from the date on 
which notice is so given, the obligation of the limited liability partnership to 
file any document to the Registrar shall cease, provided it has no other place 
of business in India and it has filed all the documents due for filing as on the 
date of the notice. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> Every document which is required to be filed by any foreign limited 
liability partnership shall be filed in the electronic form to the Registrar 
having jurisdiction over New Delhi, through the portal maintained by the 
Ministry of Corporate Affairs on its website www.mca.gov.in . 
 </section><section><number>10</number> The Registrar shall, on registration of Form 27, issue a certificate for 
establishment of place of business in India by the foreign limited liability 
partnership in Form 30. 
 </section><section><number>11</number> There shall be paid to Registrar for filing or delivery or registering 
any form or document required by this Chapter the fee as mentioned in Annexure 
A'. 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title>35 </title>. 
<section><number>1</number> An application under sub-section (1) of section 60 
for an order convening a meeting of creditors or partners or creditors and 
partners shall be supported by an affidavit. A copy of the proposed compromise 
or arrangement shall be annexed to the affidavit as an exhibit thereto. The 
affidavit in support thereof shall be in Form 20. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where the limited liability partnership is not the applicant, a copy of 
the summons and of the affidavit shall be served on the limited liability 
partnership, or, where the limited liability partnership is being wound-up, on 
its liquidator, not less than 14 days before the date fixed for the hearing of 
the summons. The summons shall be in Form 21. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> (a) Upon the hearing of the summons or any adjourned hearing thereof, the 
Tribunal shall, by order, unless it thinks fit for any reason to dismiss the 
summons, give such directions as it may think necessary in respect of the 
following matters: 
 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> determining the creditors and/or of partners whose meeting or 
    meetings have to be held for considering the proposed compromise or 
    arrangement; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> fixing the time and place of such meeting or meetings; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> appointing a chairman for the meeting or chairmen for the meetings 
    to be held; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> fixing the quorum and the procedure to be followed at the meeting or 
    meetings, including voting by proxy; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> determining the values of the creditors and/or the partners, as the 
    case may be, whose meetings have to be held; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vi</number> notice to be given of the meeting or meetings and the advertisement, 
    if any, of such notice; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vii</number> the time within which the chairman of the meeting is to report to 
    the Tribunal the result of the meeting; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>viii</number> such other matters as the Tribunal may deem necessary. 
  </subsection>
 <subsection><number>b</number> The order made under clause (a) shall be in accordance with the rules 
  as may be laid down in this behalf. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>4</number> (i) Voting by proxy shall be permitted, provided a proxy in Form 26 duly 
signed by the person entitled to attend and vote at the meeting is filed with 
the limited liability partnership at its registered office not later than 48 
hours before the meeting. 
 
 <subsection><number>ii</number> Where a body corporate which is a partner or creditor of a limited 
  liability partnership, authorizes any person to act as its representative at 
  the meeting of the partners or creditors of the limited liability partnership, 
  as the case may be, a copy of the authorization of such person to act as its 
  representative at the meeting, and certified to be a true copy by a designated 
  partner or other authorised officer of such body corporate, shall be lodged 
  with the limited liability partnership at its registered office not later than 
  48 hours before the meeting. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>5</number> The notice of the meeting to be given to the creditors and/or partners, 
shall be in accordance with the rule laid down in this behalf, and shall be sent 
to them individually by the chairman appointed for the meeting, or, if the 
Tribunal so directs, by the limited liability partnership (or its Liquidator), 
or any other person as the Tribunal may direct, by post under certificate of 
posting to their last known address not less than 21 clear days before the date 
fixed for the meeting. It shall be accompanied by a copy of the proposed 
compromise or arrangement alongwith statement showing material interest of the 
designated partners, if any, and a form of proxy. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The notice of the meeting shall be advertised, if so decided by the 
Tribunal, in such newspapers and in such manner as the Tribunal may direct. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> Every creditor or partner entitled to attend the meeting shall be 
furnished by the limited liability partnership, free of charge and within 48 
hours of a requisition made for the same, with a copy of the proposed compromise 
or arrangement. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> The chairman appointed for the meeting or the limited liability 
partnership or other person directed to issue the advertisement and the notices 
of the meeting shall file an affidavit not less than 7 days before the date 
fixed for the holding of the meeting or the holding of the first of the 
meetings, as the case may be, showing that the directions regarding the issue of 
notices and the advertisement have been duly complied with. In default thereof, 
the summons shall be posted before the Tribunal for such orders as it may think 
fit to make. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> The chairman of the meeting, or where there are separate meetings, the 
chairman of each meeting shall, within the time fixed by the Tribunal, or where 
no time has been fixed, within seven days after the conclusion of the meeting, 
report the result thereof to the Tribunal. The report shall state accurately the 
number of creditors or the partners, as the case may be, who were present and 
who voted at the meeting either in person or by proxy, their individual values 
and the way they voted. 
 </section><section><number>10</number> (i) Where the proposed compromise or arrangement is agreed to, with or 
without modification, as provided in sub-section (2) of section 60, the limited 
liability partnership, or its Liquidator, as the case may be, shall, within 
seven days of the filing of the report by the chairman, present a petition to 
the Tribunal for confirmation of the compromise or arrangement: 
 Provided that where a compromise or arrangement is proposed for the purposes 
of, or in connection with, a scheme for the reconstruction of any limited 
liability partnership or the amalgamation of any two or more limited liability 
partnerships, the petitioner shall pray for appropriate orders and directions 
under section 62. 
 
 <subsection><number>ii</number> Where the limited liability partnership fails to present the petition 
  under clause (i) for confirmation of the compromise or arrangement as 
  aforesaid, it shall be open to any creditor or partner as the case may be, 
  with the leave of the Tribunal, to present the petition for confirmation and 
  the limited liability partnership shall be liable for the costs thereof. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> Where no petition for confirmation of the compromise or arrangement 
  is presented to, or where the compromise or arrangement has not been approved 
  by the requisite majority under sub-section (2) of section 60 and consequently 
  no petition for confirmation could be presented, the report of the chairman as 
  to the result of the meeting made under sub-rule (9) shall be placed for 
  consideration before the Tribunal for such orders as may be necessary. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>11</number> An order made by the Tribunal as mentioned in sub-section (3) of section 
60 and sub-section (3) of section 62 shall be filed with Registrar concerned in 
Form 22 along with fee as mentioned in Annexure A'. 
 Explanation. In computing the period of 30 days from the date of 
order, the requisite time for obtaining a certified copy of order shall be 
excluded. 
 </section><section><number>12</number> (i) An arrangement for revival and rehabilitation of any LLP may be 
proposed, 
 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> where on a demand by the creditors of the LLP representing fifty per 
    cent or more of its outstanding amount of debt the LLP has failed to pay the 
    debt, within thirty days of the service of the notice of demand or to secure 
    or compound it to the reasonable satisfaction of the creditors; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> where a petition for winding up of a LLP is pending before the 
    Tribunal, in terms of the directions given by the Tribunal on the winding up 
    petition; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> where the liquidator has filed his report before the Tribunal, in 
    terms of directions given by the Tribunal on the report of the Liquidator. 
    </subsection>
 <subsection><number>ii</number> Without prejudice to clause (i), the LLP or any creditor or partner of 
  the LLP, or in the case of a LLP which is being wound up, the Liquidator, may 
  make an application for sanction of the arrangement for revival and 
  rehabilitation before the Tribunal. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>13</number> (i) An application under sub-rule (12) shall be accompanied by 
 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> a statement of account and solvency of LLP for the immediately 
    preceding financial year, in case the application under sub-rule (12) is 
    made by the LLP; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> particulars and documents relevant to the scheme including 
    commitments whether financial or otherwise expected from various parties or, 
    proposed restructuring or rescheduling of the debts, or any undertaking or 
    understanding, in case from bank or financial institution through a letter 
    or in any other case through an affidavit of concerned party or parties, or 
    in any other form as may be directed by the Tribunal; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> proposed scheme of revival and rehabilitation of the LLP including 
    proposal for appointment of an LLP Administrator. </subsection>
 <subsection><number>ii</number> An application under sub-rule (12) shall be made to the Tribunal 
  within 90 days from the date of expiry of demand notice or from the date of 
  the direction of the Tribunal referred to under clause (i) of sub-rule (12). 
  </subsection>
 </section><section><number>14</number> (a) Within 60 days of receipt of an application under sub-rule (12), the 
Tribunal may hear all the parties concerned and admit or dismiss the 
application; 
 
 <subsection><number>b</number> where the Tribunal admits the application, it may make an order to that 
  effect and make provisions in such order, for all or any of the following 
  matters: 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> holding of meetings of the creditors for approval of scheme proposed 
    for revival and rehabilitation of LLP; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> procedure to be followed by the LLP Administrator proposed in the 
    scheme in connection with holding of the meeting including the appointment 
    of chairman for such meeting; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number> any other direction(s) or order(s) as may be considered necessary. 
    </subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> The LLP Administrator proposed in the scheme shall submit his 
  preliminary report including the decision of the meeting to the Tribunal 
  within 60 days of order made under clause (b) of sub-rule (14). 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>15</number> (i) On consideration of the report of the LLP Administrator under clause 
(c) of sub-rule (14), and other materials available, if the Tribunal is 
satisfied that the creditors representing three-fourths in value of the amount 
outstanding against that LLP have, with or without modification of the scheme, 
resolved that it is not possible to revive and rehabilitate the LLP, the 
Tribunal may, within 60 days of the receipt of such report, order 
 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> that the proceedings for the winding up of the LLP be initiated; or 
    
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the LLP be wound up, or the liquidator to continue; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> sanction the arrangement for revival and rehabilitation of LLP as 
    approved by such creditors with such modifications as may be considered 
    necessary by the Tribunal, and make orders for continuation of the LLP 
    Administrator or appointment of a new LLP Administrator: 
</subsection>
 Provided that Tribunal may consider for its approval, the arrangement for 
revival and rehabilitation including the proposal for appointment of any other 
LLP Administrator moved by the LLP in the meeting of the creditors, in place of 
the arrangement proposed by the creditors or the Liquidator, provided the 
arrangement is approved by three-fourth majority, in value, of creditors: 
 Provided further that where the arrangement of revival and rehabilitation 
relates to amalgamation of the LLP with any other LLP, no such scheme shall be 
sanctioned by the Tribunal unless the said scheme is approved with, or without 
modification by three-fourth majority of respective partners of transferor and 
transferee LLPs. 
 
 <subsection><number>ii</number> The order of sanction of the arrangement by the Tribunal under clause 
  (i) may make provisions, for all or any of the following matters: 
 
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> powers and functions of the LLP Administrator; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> the time period within which various actions proposed in the 
    arrangement to be completed; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>c</number> any such direction to the LLP or its officers or to the creditors, or 
    to the LLP Administrator or to any other person, as may be considered 
    necessary, for the purpose of implementation of the arrangement of revival 
    and rehabilitation; and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>d</number> any other order or orders as may be considered necessary. 
  </subsubsection></subsection>
 </section><section><number>16</number> The LLP Administrator shall complete all the actions relating to 
implementation of the revival and rehabilitation arrangement and submit his 
final report before the Tribunal within such time directed by the Tribunal but 
not exceeding 180 days of the order under clause (i) of sub-rule (15); 
 </section><section><number>17</number> (i) The LLP administrator shall be appointed from a panel maintained by 
the Central Government for winding up and dissolution of LLPs. 
 
 <subsection><number>ii</number> The terms and conditions of the appointment including fee of LLP 
  Administrator shall be such as may be ordered by the Tribunal. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> The Tribunal may, on a reasonable cause being shown and for reasons 
  to be recorded in writing, remove the LLP Administrator and may appoint 
  another LLP Administrator. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> In case of removal, death or incapacity of the LLP Administrator, the 
  Tribunal may appoint another LLP Administrator. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> The LLP Administrator shall, within 30 days of the making of order or 
  orders under sub-rule (15) cause certified copy thereof to be filed with the 
  Registrar concerned in Form 22 along with fee as mentioned in Annexure A'. 
  </subsection>
 Explanation. In computing the period of 30 days from the date of 
order, the requisite time for obtaining a certified copy of order shall be 
excluded. 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>36</number> </title>
<section><number>1</number> (i) Every form or application or document or 
declaration required to be filed or delivered under the Act and rules made 
thereunder, shall be filed in computer readable electronic form, in portable 
document format (pdf) to the Registrar through the portal maintained by the 
Ministry of Corporate Affairs on its web-site www.mca.gov.in or through any 
other website approved by the Central Government and authenticated by a partner 
or designated partner of the limited liability partnership for such purpose by 
the use of a valid digital signature: 
 Provided that where documents are required to be filed on Non-Judicial Stamp 
Paper, the LLP shall submit such documents in the physical form, in addition to 
their submission in electronic form, unless the Central Government, by an order, 
does not require submission in physical form. 
 
 <subsection><number>ii</number> Every designated partner, partner or person specified in the Act for 
  authentication of e-form, documents or application etc., which are required to 
  be filed or delivered under the Act or rules made thereunder, shall obtain a 
  digital signature certificate from the Certifying Authority for the purpose of 
  such authentication and such certificate shall not be valid unless it is of 
  Class II or  Class III specification under the Information Technology Act, 
  2000. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Central Government shall set up and maintain 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> a website or portal to provide access to the electronic registry; and, 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> as many Registrar's Front Offices as may be necessary and at such 
  places and for such time as Central Government may determine from time to 
  time, </subsection>
 for filing of e-Forms, documents and applications, etc., viewing and 
inspection of documents in the electronic registry. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> (i) The Central Government shall set up and maintain a secure electronic 
registry in which all the documents filed electronically shall be stored. The 
electronic registry so set up shall enable public access and inspection of such 
documents as are required to be in the public domain under the Act on payment of 
the fees as mentioned in Annexure A. 
 
 <subsection><number>ii</number> Every document or application or certificate or notice etc., required 
  to be signed by the Registrar or an officer of the Central Government under 
  the Act or rules made thereunder, shall be authenticated through a valid 
  digital signature of such person or a system generated digital signature. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> The Registrar or an officer of the Central Government, as the case 
  may be, may send any communication either to the Limited Liability Partnership 
  or its authorized representative, partners or both in the electronic manner 
  for which the LLP shall create and maintain at all times a valid electronic 
  address ( e.g. E-mail, user Identification, etc.) capable of 
  receiving and acknowledging the receipt of such communication, automated or 
  otherwise. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Registrar or an officer of the Central Government shall issue 
certificate, receipt, approval or communicate endorsement or acknowledgement in 
the electronic manner: 
 Provided that where the Registrar or an officer of the Central Government, as 
the case may be, is not able to issue any certificate, receipt, endorsement, 
acknowledgement or approval in electronic manner for the reasons to be recorded 
in writing, he may issue such certificate, receipt, or communicate endorsement, 
acknowledgement or approval in the physical form under manual signature affixing 
seal of his office. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Registrar shall examine or cause to be examined every application or 
e-Form or document required or authorized to be filed by or delivered under the 
Act and rules made thereunder for approval, registration, taking on record or 
rectification by the Registrar as the case may be: 
 Provided that the e-Forms or documents identified as informatory in nature 
and filed under Straight Through Process (STP) may be examined by the Registrar 
any time after its filing. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> Where the Registrar, on examining any application or e-Form or document 
referred to in sub-rule (5), finds it necessary to call further information or 
finds such application or e-Form or document to be defective or incomplete in 
any respect, he shall give intimation of such information called for or defects 
or incompleteness noticed electronically, by placing it on the website and also 
by  e-mail on the last intimated e-mail address of the person or the limited 
liability partnership, which has filed such application or e-Form or document, 
directing him or it to furnish such information or to rectify such defects or 
incompleteness or to re-submit such application or e-Form or document within the 
period allowed under sub-rule (7): 
 Provided that in case the e-mail address of the person or the Limited 
Liability Partnership in question is not available, such intimation shall be 
given by the Registrar by post at the last intimated address given in Form 12, 
or registered office address of the Limited Liability Partnership or the address 
of such person, as the case may be,. The Registrar shall preserve the facts of 
such intimation in the electronic record. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> The Registrar shall allow such period or periods but not exceeding thirty 
days in aggregate to such person or LLP which has filed such application or 
 e-Form or document under sub-rule (5) for furnishing further information or 
for rectification of the defects or incompleteness or for re-submission of such 
application or e-Form or document. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> In case where such further information called for has not been provided 
or has been furnished partially or has not been provided or defects or 
incompleteness has not been rectified or has been rectified partially or has not 
been rectified to the satisfaction of the Registrar within the period allowed 
under sub-rule (7), the Registrar shall either reject or treat and label such 
application or e-Form or document as the case may be as invalid in the 
electronic record, and shall not take on record such invalid application or 
e-Form or document and shall inform such person or limited liability partnership 
as the case may be in the manner specified in sub-rule (6) . 
 </section><section><number>9</number> Where any document has been recorded as invalid by the Registrar, such 
document may be rectified by the limited liability partnership only through 
fresh filing with payment of fee and additional fee as applicable, without 
prejudice to any other liability under the Act. 
 </section><section><number>10</number> Save as otherwise provided in the Act, the Registrar shall not keep any 
document pending for approval and registration or for taking on record or for 
rejection or otherwise for more than one hundred twenty days, from the date of 
its filing. 
 </section><section><number>11</number> The Registrar in case finds any e-Form or document filed under Straight 
Through Process (STP), referred to in proviso under sub-rule (5), as defective 
or incomplete in any respect, at any time, he shall treat and label such e-Form 
or document as defective in the electronic registry and shall also issue a 
notice pointing out such defects or incompleteness in such e-Form or document at 
the last intimated e-mail address (if available) of the person or the LLP which 
has filed the document and also in writing by post at the address of such person 
or address of such LLP or registered office address of LLP, calling upon such 
person or LLP to file such e-Form or document afresh with fee and additional fee 
as applicable, after rectifying such defects or incompleteness within a period 
of thirty days from the date of such notice. 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>37</number> </title>
<section><number>1</number> Where a limited liability partnership is not 
carrying on any business or operation 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> for a period of two years or more and the Registrar has reasonable 
  cause to believe the same, for the purpose of taking suo motu action 
  for striking off the name of the LLP; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> for a period of one year or more and has made an application in Form 24 
  to the Registrar, with the consent of all partners of the limited liability 
  partnership for striking off its name from the register, </subsection>
 the Registrar shall send a notice to the limited liability partnership and 
all its partners, of his intention to strike off the name of the limited 
liability partnership from the register and requesting them to send their 
representations along with copies of the relevant documents, if any, within a 
period of one month from the date of the notice: 
 Provided that no such notice by Registrar shall be required under clause (b): 

 Provided further that where the limited liability partnership is regulated 
under a special law, the application for removal of its name shall be 
accompanied by approval of the regulatory body constituted or established under 
that law. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> A notice issued under sub-rule (1) or contents of an application made by 
the LLP shall also be placed on the website of the Ministry of Corporate Affairs 
for the information of the general public for a period of one month. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> At the expiry of the time mentioned in the notice under sub-rule (1), or 
one month under sub-rule (2) above, the Registrar may, by an order, unless cause 
to the contrary is shown by the limited liability partnership, or the Registrar 
is satisfied that the name should not be struck off from the register, strike 
its name off the register, and shall publish notice thereof in the Official 
Gazette, and on the publication in the Official Gazette of this notice, the 
limited liability partnership shall stand dissolved. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Registrar, before passing an order under sub-rule (3), shall , where 
he has sufficient cause to believe that the limited liability partnership has 
any asset or liability, satisfy himself that sufficient provision has been made 
for the realization of all amount due to the limited liability partnership and 
for the payment or discharge of its liabilities and obligations by the limited 
liability partnership within a reasonable time and, if necessary, obtain 
necessary undertakings from the designated partner or partner or other persons 
in charge of the management of the limited liability partnership: 
 Provided that notwithstanding the undertakings referred to in this sub-rule, 
the assets of the limited liability partnership shall be made available for the 
payment or discharge of all its liabilities and obligations even after the date 
of the order removing the name of the limited liability partnership from the 
register. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The liability, if any, of every designated partner of the limited 
liability partnership dissolved under sub-rule (3), shall continue and may be 
enforced as if the limited liability partnership had not been dissolved. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> Nothing in this rule shall affect the power of the Tribunal to wind up a 
limited liability partnership the name of which has been struck off the 
register. 
 Explanation .In computing the period of 30 days from the date of 
order, the requisite time for obtaining a certified copy of order shall be 
excluded. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>38</number> </title>
<section><number>1</number> For the purposes of the Second Schedule, an 
application shall be made in the format provided in Part A of Form 17 together 
with the statement of partners in format provided in Part B of Form 17 alongwith 
the fee as mentioned in Annexure A'. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Registrar shall, on conversion of the firm into the limited liability 
partnership shall issue a certificate of registration under his seal in Form 19. 

 </section><section><number>3</number> For the purposes of para 5 of the Second Schedule, the limited liability 
partnership shall inform the concerned Registrar of firms about conversion of 
firm into limited liability partnership in Form 14. 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>39</number> </title>
<section><number>1</number> For the purposes of the Third Schedule, an 
application shall be made in the format provided in Part A of Form 18 together 
with the statement of shareholders in format provided in Part B of Form 18 
alongwith the fee as mentioned in Annexure A'. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Registrar shall, on conversion of any private company into limited 
liability partnership shall issue a certificate of registration under his seal 
in Form 19. (3) For the purposes of para 4 of the Third Schedule, the 
limited liability partnership shall inform the concerned Registrar of Companies 
about conversion of private company into limited liability partnership in Form 
14 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>40</number> </title>
<section><number>1</number> For the purposes of the Fourth Schedule, an 
application shall be made in the format provided in Part A of Form 18 together 
with the statement of shareholders in format provided in Part B of Form 18 
alongwith the fee as mentioned in Annexure A'. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Registrar shall, on conversion of any unlisted public company into 
limited liability partnership shall issue a certificate of registration under 
his seal in Form 19. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> For the purposes of para 5 of the Fourth Schedule, the limited liability 
partnership shall inform the concerned Registrar of Companies about conversion 
of unlisted public company into limited liability partnership in Form 14. 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>41</number> </title>
<section><number>1</number> Every application for the compounding of an offence 
shall be made in Form 31 to the Registrar who shall forward the same, together 
with his comments thereon, to the Central Government. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where any offence is compounded before the institution of any 
prosecution, no prosecution shall be instituted in relation to such offence, 
against the offender in relation to whom the offence is so compounded. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where the composition of any offence is made after the institution of any 
prosecution, such composition shall be brought by the Registrar in writing, to 
the notice of the Court in which the prosecution is pending . 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Where any offence is compounded under section 39, whether before or after 
the institution of any prosecution, intimation thereof shall be given by the LLP 
to the Registrar in Form 22 within seven days from the date on which the offence 
is so compounded. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Central Government while dealing with an application for the 
compounding of the offence for a default in compliance with any provision of the 
Act which requires a LLP or its partner or partners or designated partner or 
designated partners to file or register with, or send to, the Registrar any 
return, statement of account and solvency or other document, may, if it thinks 
fit to do so, direct, before allowing compounding under this rule, by order, any 
partner or designated partner of the LLP to file or register with, or on payment 
of the fee, and the additional fee, required to be paid under section 69, such 
return, statement of account and solvency or other document within such time as 
may be specified in the order. 
 ___________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 229(E), dated 1st April, 2009 . 
  </section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 796(E), dated 4th November, 2011 (w.e.f. 4-11-2011).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>