<act><tid>223852</tid>
<title>THE REHABILITATION COUNCIL OF INDIA ACT, <year>1992</year></title>

NO. 34 OF <year>1992</year> 
[ 1st September, <year>1992</year>.]
An Act to provide for the constitution of the Rehabilitation Council 
of India for regulating the training of rehabilitation professionals 
and the maintenance of a Central Rehabilitation Register and for 
matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- third Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--

CHAP 
PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY




<article><tid>420853</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1434561</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Rehabilitation Council of India Act, <year>1992</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>158301</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>183878</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.
<section><tid>842955</tid>
<number>1</number>In this Act, unless the context otherwise  
requires,--

<subsection><tid>651101</tid>
<number>a</number>" Chairperson" means the Chairperson of the Council 
appointed under sub- section (3) of section 3;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>146903</tid>
<number>b</number>" Council" means the Rehabilitation Council of India 
constituted under section 3;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>430046</tid>
<number>c</number>" handicapped" means a person--

<subsubsection><tid>132640</tid>
<number>i</number>visually handicapped;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>54292</tid>
<number>ii</number>hearing handicapped;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>564365</tid>
<number>iii</number>suffering from locomotor disability; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>768688</tid>
<number>iv</number>suffering from mental retardation;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>694738</tid>
<number>d</number>" hearing handicap" means deafness with hearing 
impairment of 70 decibels and above, in the better ear or total 
loss of hearing in both ears;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>487383</tid>
<number>e</number>" locomotor disability" means a person' s inability to 
execute distinctive activities associated with moving, both 
himself and objects, from place to place, and such inability 
resulting from affliction of either bones, joints, muscles or 
nerves;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1158233</tid>
<number>f</number>" member" means a member appointed under sub- section (3) 
of section 3 and includes the Chairperson;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>482628</tid>
<number>g</number>" Member- Secretary" means the Member- Secretary appointed 
under sub- section (1) of section 8;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>210</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 31- 7- <year>1993</year>: Vide Notfin NO s. O. 288 (E), dt. 28- 4- <year>1993</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1781375</tid>
<number>h</number>" mental retardation" means a condition of arrested or 
incomplete development of mind of a person which is specially 
characterised by sub- normality of intelligence;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>660378</tid>
<number>i</number>" notification" means a notification published in the 
Official Gazette;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>167456</tid>
<number>j</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by regulations;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1109098</tid>
<number>k</number>" recognised rehabilitation qualifications" means any of 
the qualifications included in the Schedule;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1901264</tid>
<number>l</number>" Register" means the Central Rehabilitation Register 
maintained under sub- section (1) of section 23;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>665499</tid>
<number>m</number>" regulations" means regulations made under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1550684</tid>
<number>n</number>" rehabilitation professionals" means--

<subsubsection><tid>1674617</tid>
<number>i</number>audiologists and speech therapists;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1492615</tid>
<number>ii</number>clinical psychologists;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>2937</tid>
<number>iii</number>hearing aid and ear mould technicians;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>534573</tid>
<number>iv</number>rehabilitation engineers and technicians;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>910954</tid>
<number>v</number>special teachers for educating and training the 
handicaped;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>922879</tid>
<number>vi</number>vocational counsellors, employment officers and 
placement officers dealing with handicapped;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1839014</tid>
<number>vii</number>multi- purpose rehabilitation therapists, 
technicians; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>897251</tid>
<number>viii</number>such other category of professionals as the 
Central Government may, in consultation with the Council, 
notify from time to time;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>185182</tid>
<number>o</number>" visually handicapped" means a person who suffers from 
any of the following conditions, namely:--

<subsubsection><tid>1463506</tid>
<number>i</number>total absence of sight;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>871332</tid>
<number>ii</number>visual acquity not exceeding 6 60 or 20 200 
 (snellen) in the better eye with the correcting lenses; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>109076</tid>
<number>iii</number>limitation of the field of vision subtending and 
angle of degree or worse.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1313471</tid>
<number>2</number>Any reference in this Act to any enactment or any provision 
thereof shall, in relation to an area in which such enactment or such 
provision is not in force, be construed as a reference to the 
corresponding law or the relevant provision of the corresponding law, 
if any, in force in that area.
CHAP 
THE REHABILITATION COUNCIL OF INDIA

CHAPTER II

THE REHABILITATION COUNCIL OF INDIA



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1946293</tid>
<number> 3</number> Constitution and incorporation of Rehabilitation Council of 
India.
<section><tid>1318375</tid>
<number>1</number>With effect from such date as the Central Government may,  
by notification appoint in this behalf, there shall be constituted for 
the purposes of this Act a Council to be called the Rehabilitation 
Council of India.

</section>

<section><tid>1681030</tid>
<number>2</number>The Council shall be a body corporate by the name aforesaid, 
having perpetual succession and a common seal, with power, subject to 
the provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of property, 
both

<pagefootnote><pagenum>211</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

movable and immovable, and to contract and shall by the said name 
sue and be sued.


</section>

<section><tid>444951</tid>
<number>3</number>The Council shall consist of the following members, namely:--

<subsection><tid>652406</tid>
<number>a</number>a Chaiperson, from amongst the persons having experience 
in social work or rehabilitation, to be appointed by the Central 
Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>9224</tid>
<number>b</number>three members to be appointed by the Central Government 
to represent respectively the Ministries of the Central 
Government dealing with--

<subsubsection><tid>1435421</tid>
<number>i</number>Welfare;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>489478</tid>
<number>ii</number>Health; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1696745</tid>
<number>iii</number>Finance;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1869600</tid>
<number>c</number>one member to be appointed by the Central Government to 
represent the University Grants Commission;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1754772</tid>
<number>d</number>one member to be appointed by the Central Government to 
represent the Directorate General of Indian Council of Medical 
Research;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>355861</tid>
<number>e</number>two members to be appointed by the Central Government to 
represent the Ministry or department of the States or the Union 
territories dealing with Social Welfare by rotation in 
alphabetical order;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>890937</tid>
<number>f</number>such number of members not exceeding six as may be 
appointed by the Central Government from amongst the 
rehabilitation professionals working in voluntary organisations;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1028506</tid>
<number>g</number>such number of members not exceeding four as may be 
appointed by the Central Government from amongst the medical 
practitioners enrolled under the Indian Medical Council Act <year>1956</year> 
 (102 of <year>1956</year>), and engaged in rehabilitation of the handicapped;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1044059</tid>
<number>h</number>three Members of Parliament of whom two shall be elected 
by the House of the People and one by the Council of States;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1852836</tid>
<number>i</number>such number of members not exceeding three as may be 
nominated by the Central Government from amongst the social 
workers who are actively engaged in assisting the disabled;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>736747</tid>
<number>j</number>the Member- Secretary, ex officio.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>232407</tid>
<number>4</number>The office of member of the Board shall not disqualify its 
holder for being chosen as, or for being, a Member of either House of 
Parliament.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>119099</tid>
<number> 4</number> Term of office of Chairperson and members.
<section><tid>29436</tid>
<number>1</number>The Chairperson  
or a member shall hold office for a term of two years from the date of 
his appointment or until his successor shall have been duly appointed, 
whichever is longer.

</section>

<section><tid>902748</tid>
<number>2</number>A casual vacancy in the Council shall be filled in accordance 
with the provisions of section 3 and the person so appointed shall 
hold office only for the remainder of the term for which the member in 
whose place he was appointed would have held that office.

</section>

<section><tid>1867262</tid>
<number>3</number>The Council shall meet at least once in each year at such 
time and place as may be appointed by the Council and shall observe 
such rules of procedure in the transaction of business at a meeting as 
may be prescribed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>212</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>639060</tid>
<number>4</number>The Chairperson or, if for any reason, he is unable to attend 
the meeting of the Council, any member elected by the members present 
from amongst themselves at the meeting, shall preside at the meeting.

</section>

<section><tid>413380</tid>
<number>5</number>All questions which come up before any meeting of the Council 
shall be decided by a majority of votes of the members present and 
voting, and in the event of an equality of votes, the Chairperson, or 
in his absence, the person presiding shall have a second or casting 
vote.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>460227</tid>
<number> 5</number> Disqualifications. No person shall be a member if he--
<section><tid>1060135</tid>
<number>a</number>is, or becomes, of unsound mind or is so declared by a 
competent court; or

</section>

<section><tid>446645</tid>
<number>b</number>is, or has been, convicted of any offence which, in the 
opinion of the Central Government, involves moral turpitude; or

</section>

<section><tid>525450</tid>
<number>c</number>is, or at any time has been, adjudicated as insolvent.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1635431</tid>
<number> 6</number> Vacation of office by members. If a member--
<section><tid>1555095</tid>
<number>a</number>becomes subject to any of the disqualifications 
mentioned in section 5; or

</section>

<section><tid>229410</tid>
<number>b</number>is absent without excuse, sufficient in the opinion of 
the Council, from three consecutive meetings of the Council; or

</section>

<section><tid>29361</tid>
<number>c</number>ceases to be enrolled on the Indian Medical Register in 
the case of a member referred to in clause (g) of sub- section (3) 
of section 3, his seat shall thereupon become vacant,


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>83866</tid>
<number> 7</number> Executive Committee and other committees.
<section><tid>517937</tid>
<number>1</number>The Council  
shall constitute from amongst its members an Executive Committee and 
such other committees for general or special purposes as the Council 
deems necessary to carry out the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>839504</tid>
<number>2</number>The Executive Committee shall consist of the Chairperson who 
shall be member ex officio and not less then seven and not more than 
ten members who shall be nominated by the Council from amongst its 
members.

</section>

<section><tid>1239998</tid>
<number>3</number>The Chairperson shall be the Chairperson of the Executive 
Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>432682</tid>
<number>4</number>In addition to the powers and duties conferred and imposed 
upon it by this Act, the Executive Committee or any other committee 
shall exercise and discharge such powers and duties as the Council may 
confer or impose upon it by any regulations which may be made in this 
behalf.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1989277</tid>
<number> 8</number> Member- Secretary and employees of Council.
<section><tid>1210406</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government shall appoint the Member- Secretary of the Council to 
exercise such powers and perform such duties under the direction of 
the Council as may be prescribed or as may be delegated to him by the 
Chairperson.

</section>

<section><tid>263225</tid>
<number>2</number>The Council shall, with the previous sanction of the Central 
Government, employ such officers and other employees as it deems 
necessary to carry out the purpose of this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>213</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>734770</tid>
<number>3</number>The Council shall, with the previous sanction of the Central 
Government, fix the allowances to be paid to the Chairperson and other 
members and determine the conditions of service of the Member- 
Secretary, officers and other employees of the Council.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1056477</tid>
<number>9</number>Vacancies in the Council not to invalidate acts, etc. No act 
or proceeding of the Council or any committee thereof shall be called 
in question on the ground merely of the existence of any vacancy in, 
or any defect in the constitution of, the Council or a committee 
thereof, as the case may be.

</article>



<article><tid>1905202</tid>
<number> 10</number> Dissolution of Rehabilitation Council and transfer of rights 
liabilities and employees of Rehabilitation Council to Council.
<section><tid>1427296</tid>
<number>1</number>On  
and from the date of the constitution of the Council, the 
Rehabilitation Council shall stand dissolved and on such dissolution,-

<subsection><tid>1174752</tid>
<number>a</number>all properties and assets, movable and immovable, of, or 
belonging to, the Rehabilitation Council shall vest in the 
Council;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1150293</tid>
<number>b</number>all the rights and liabilities of the Rehabilitation 
Council shall be transferred to, and be the rights and 
liabilities of, the Council;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>157432</tid>
<number>c</number>without prejudice to the provisions of clause (b), all 
liabilities incurred, all contracts entered into and all matters 
and things engaged to be done by, with or for the Rehabilitation 
Council immediately before that date, for or in connection with 
the purposes of the said Rehabilitation Council shall be deemed 
to have been incurred, entered into, or engaged to be done by, 
with or for, the Council;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>475656</tid>
<number>d</number>all sums of money due to the Rehabilitation Council 
immediately before that date shall be deemed to be due to the 
Council;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>979323</tid>
<number>e</number>all suits and other legal proceedings instituted or 
which could have been instituted by or against the Rehabilitation 
Council immediately before that date may be continued or may be 
instituted by or against the Council; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1529704</tid>
<number>f</number>every employee holding any office under the 
Rehabilitation Council immediately before that date shall hold 
his office in the Council by the same tenure and upon the same 
terms and conditions of service as respects remuneration, leave, 
provident fund, retirement and other terminal benefits as he 
would have held such office as if the Council had not been 
constituted and shall continue to do so as an employee of the 
Council or until the expiry of a period of six months from that 
date if such employee opts not to be the employee of the Council 
within such period.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>402269</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial Disputes 
Act, <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>) or any other law for the time being in force, 
absorption of any employee by the Council in its regular service under 
this section shall not entitle such employee to any compensation under 
that Act or other law and no such claim shall be entertained by any 
court, tribunal or other authority.
Explanation.-- In this section," Rehabilitation Council" means the 
Rehabilitation Council, a society formed and registered under the 
Societies Registration Act, <year>1860</year> (21 of <year>1860</year>) and functioning as such 
immediately before the constitution of the Council.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>214</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

CHAP 
FUNCTIONS OF THE COUNCIL

CHAPTER III

FUNCTIONS OF THE COUNCIL



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1124387</tid>
<number> 11</number> Recognition of qualifications granted by University, etc. in 
India for rehabilitation professionals.
<section><tid>1217892</tid>
<number>1</number>The qualifications granted  
by any University or other institution in India which are included in 
the Schedule shall be recognised qualifications for rehabilitation 
professionals.

</section>

<section><tid>1725152</tid>
<number>2</number>Any University or other institution which grants 
qualification for the rehabilitation professionals not included in the 
Schedule may apply to the Central Government to have any such 
qualification recognised, and the Central Government, after consulting 
the Council may, by notification, amend the Schedule so as to include 
such qualification therein and any such notification may also direct 
that an entry shall be made in the last column of the Schedule against 
such qualification only when granted after a specified date.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1894960</tid>
<number>12</number>Recognition of qualifications granted by institutions outside 
India. The Council may enter into negotiations with the authority in 
any country outside India for settling of a scheme of reciprocity for 
the recognition of qualifications, and in pursuance of any such 
scheme, the Central Government may, by notification, amend the 
Schedule so as to include therein any qualification which the Council 
has decided should be recognised, and by such notification may also 
direct that an entry shall be made in the last column of the Schedule 
declaring that it shall be the recognised qualification only when 
granted after a specified date.

</article>



<article><tid>1708129</tid>
<number> 13</number> Rights of persons possessing qualifications included in the 
Schedule to be enrolled.
<section><tid>960489</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the other provisions contained  
in this Act, any qualification included in the Schedule shall be 
sufficient qualification for enrolment on the Register.

</section>

<section><tid>1778831</tid>
<number>2</number>No person, other than the rehabilitation professional who 
possesses a recognised rehabilitation qualification and is enrolled on 
the Register,--

<subsection><tid>1349539</tid>
<number>a</number>shall hold office as rehabilitation professional or any 
such office (by whatever designation called) in Government or in 
any institution maintained by a local or other authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1789518</tid>
<number>b</number>shall practice as rehabilitation professional anywhere 
in India;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1290950</tid>
<number>c</number>shall be entitled to sign or authenticate any 
certificate required by any law to be signed or authenticated by 
a rehabilitation professional;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>80363</tid>
<number>d</number>shall be entitled to give any evidence in any court as 
an expert under section 45 of the Indian Evidence Act, <year>1872</year> (1 of  
  <year>1872</year>) on any matter relating to the handicapped:
Provided that if a person possesses the recognised rehabilitation 
professional qualifications on the date of commencement of this Act, 
he shall be deemed to be an enrolled rehabilitation professional for a 
period of six months from such commencement, and if he has made an 
application for enrolment on the Register within said period of six 
months, till such application is disposed of.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1227909</tid>
<number>3</number>Any person who acts in contravention of any provision of 
sub- section (2) shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which 
may extend to one year, or with fine which may extend to one thousand 
rupees, or with both.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>215</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1455173</tid>
<number>14</number>Power to require information as to courses of study and 
examinations. Every University or institution in India which grants a 
recognised qualification shall furnish such information as the Council 
may, from time to time, require as to the courses of study and 
examinations to be undergone in order to obtain such qualification, as 
to the ages at which such courses of study and examinations are 
required to be undergone and such qualification is conferred and 
generally as to the requisites for obtaining such qualification.

</article>



<article><tid>1595908</tid>
<number> 15</number> Inspectors as examinations.
<section><tid>174384</tid>
<number>1</number>The Council shall appoint  
such number of Inspectors as it may deem requisite to inspect any 
University or institution where education for practising as 
rehabilitation professionals is given or to attend any examination 
held by any University or institution for the purpose of recommending 
to the Central Government recognition of qualifications granted by 
that University or institution as recognised rehabilitation 
qualifications.

</section>

<section><tid>1603556</tid>
<number>2</number>The Inspectors appointed under sub- section (1) shall not 
interfere with the conduct of any training or examination but shall 
report to the Council on the adequacy of the standards of education 
including staff, equipment, accommodation, training and other 
facilities prescribed for giving such education or of the sufficiency 
of every examination which they attend.

</section>

<section><tid>1565905</tid>
<number>3</number>The Council shall forward a copy of the report of the 
Inspector under sub- section (2) to the University or institution 
concerned and shall also forward a copy, with the remarks of the 
University or the institution thereon, to the Central Government.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>481104</tid>
<number> 16</number> Visitors at examinations.
<section><tid>1662455</tid>
<number>1</number>The Council may appoint such  
number of Visitors as it may deem requisite to inspect any University 
or institution wherein education for rehabilitation professionals is 
given or attend any examination for the purpose of granting recognised 
rehabilitation qualifications.

</section>

<section><tid>228080</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person, whether he is a member of the Council or not, may 
be appointed as a Visitor under sub- section (1) but a person who is 
appointed as an Inspector under sub- section (1) of section 15 for any 
inspection or examination shall not be appointed as a Visitor for the 
same inspection or examination.

</section>

<section><tid>934380</tid>
<number>3</number>The Visitor shall not interfere with the conduct of any 
training or examination but shall report to the Chairperson on the 
adequacy of the standards of education including staff, equipment, 
accommodation, training and other facilities prescribed for giving 
education to the rehabilitation professionals or on sufficiency of 
every examination which they attend.

</section>

<section><tid>309878</tid>
<number>4</number>The report of a Visitor shall be treated as confidential 
unless in any particular case the Chairperson otherwise, directs:
Provided that if the Central Government requires a copy of the 
report of a Visitor, the Council shall furnish the same.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>859637</tid>
<number> 17</number> Withdrawal of recognition.
<section><tid>527914</tid>
<number>1</number>When upon report by the  
Inspector or the Visitor it appears to the Council--

<subsection><tid>1542650</tid>
<number>a</number>that the courses of study and examination to be 
undergone in or the proficiency required from candidates at any 
examination held by any University or institution, or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>216</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>21948</tid>
<number>b</number>that the staff, equipment, accommodation training and 
other facilities for instruction and training provided in such 
University or institution, do not conform to the standard 
prescribed by the Council, the Council shall make a 
representation to that effect to the Central Government.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1674076</tid>
<number>2</number>After considering such representation, the Central Government 
may send it to the University or institution with an intimation of the 
period within which the University or institution may submit its 
explanation to that Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1248563</tid>
<number>3</number>On the receipt of the explanation or where no explanation is 
submitted within the period fixed then, on the expiry of that period, 
the Central Government after making such further inquiry, if any, as 
it may think fit, may, by notification, direct that an entry shall be 
made in the Schedule against the said recognised rehabilitation 
qualification declaring that it shall be the recognised rehabilitation 
qualification only when granted before a specified date or that the 
said recognised rehabilitation qualification if granted to students of 
a specified University or institution shall be recognised 
rehabilitation qualification only when granted before a specified 
date, or as the case may be, that the said recognised rehabilitation 
qualification shall be recognised rehabilitation qualification in 
relation to a specified University or institution only when granted 
after a specified date.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1918200</tid>
<number>18</number>Minimum standards of education. The Council may prescribe the 
minimum standards of education required for granting recognised 
rehabilitation qualification by Universities or institutions in India.

</article>



<article><tid>1122078</tid>
<number>19</number>Registration in Register. The Member- Secretary of the Council 
may, on receipt of an application made by any person in the prescribed 
manner enter his name in the Register provided that the Member- 
Secretary is satisfied that such person possesses the recognised 
rehabilitation qualification.

</article>



<article><tid>458493</tid>
<number>20</number>Privileges of persons who are registered on Register. Subject 
to the conditions and restrictions laid down in this Act regarding 
engagement in the area of rehabilitation of the handicapped by persons 
possessing the recognised rehabilitation qualifications, every person 
whose name is for the time being borne on the Register shall be 
entitled to practise as a rehabilitation professional in any part of 
India and to recover in due course of law in respect of such practice 
any expenses, charges in respect of medicaments or other appliances or 
any fees to which he may be entitled.

</article>



<article><tid>856541</tid>
<number> 21</number> Professional conduct and removal of names from Register.
<section><tid>1071057</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The Council may prescribe standards of professional conduct and 
etiquette and a code of ethics for rehabilitation professionals.

</section>

<section><tid>68651</tid>
<number>2</number>Regulations made by the Council under sub- section (1) may 
specify which violations thereof shall constitute infamous conduct in 
any professional respect, that is to say, professional misconduct, and 
such provision shall have effect notwithstanding anything contained in 
any other law for the time being in force.

</section>

<section><tid>327585</tid>
<number>3</number>The Council may order that the name of any person shall be 
removed from the Register where it is satisfied, after giving that 
person a

<pagefootnote><pagenum>217</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

reasonable opportunity of being heard, and after such further inquiry, 
if any, as it may deem fit to make,--


<subsection><tid>1391140</tid>
<number>i</number>that his name has been entered in the Register by error 
or on account of misrepresentation or suppression of a material 
fact;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>296290</tid>
<number>ii</number>that he has been convicted of any offence or has been 
guilty of any infamous conduct in any professional respect, or 
has violated the standards of professional conduct and etiquette 
or the code of ethics prescribed under sub- section (1) which, in 
the opinion of the Council, renders him unfit to be kept in the 
Register.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>453113</tid>
<number>4</number>An order under sub- section (3) may direct that any person 
whose name is ordered to be removed from the Register shall be 
ineligible for registration under this Act either permanently or for 
such period of years as may be specified.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1115177</tid>
<number> 22</number> Appeal against order of removal from Register.
<section><tid>378313</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the  
name of any person has been removed from the Register on any ground 
other than that he is not possessed of the requisite rehabilitation 
qualifications, he may appeal, in the prescribed manner and subject to 
such conditions, including conditions as to the payment of a fee, as 
may be prescribed to the Central Government whose decision thereon 
shall be final.

</section>

<section><tid>11383</tid>
<number>2</number>No appeal under sub- section (1) shall be admitted if it is 
preferred after the expiry of a period of thirty days from the date of 
the order under sub- section (3) of section 21:
Provided that an appeal may be admitted after the expiry of the 
said period of thirty days if the appellant satisfies the Central 
Government that he had sufficient cause for not preferring the appeal 
within the said period.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>736413</tid>
<number> 23</number> Register.
<section><tid>619645</tid>
<number>1</number>It shall be the duty of the Member- Secretary to  
keep and maintain the Register in accordance with the provisions of 
this Act and any order made by the Council and from time to time to 
revise the Register and publish it in the Official Gazette.

</section>

<section><tid>1438656</tid>
<number>2</number>The Register shall be deemed to be a public document within 
the meaning of the Indian Evidence Act, <year>1872</year> (1 of <year>1872</year>) and may be 
proved by a copy thereof.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>103632</tid>
<number> 24</number> Information to be furnished by Council and publication 
thereof.
<section><tid>604116</tid>
<number>1</number>The Council shall furnish such reports, copies of its  
minutes, abstracts of its accounts, and other information to the 
Central Government as that Government may require.

</section>

<section><tid>910970</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may publish in such manner as it may 
think fit, any report, copy, abstract or other information furnished 
to it by the Council under this section or under section 16.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>527635</tid>
<number>25</number>Cognizance of offences. Notwithstanding anything contained in 
the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>), no court shall take 
cognizance of an offence punishable under this Act except upon a 
complaint, in writing, made by any person authorised in this behalf by 
the Council.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>218</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</article>



<article><tid>537969</tid>
<number>26</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit, 
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central 
Government, Council, Chairperson, members, Member- Secretary or any 
officer or other employee of the Council for anything which is in good 
faith done or intended to be done under this Act.

</article>



<article><tid>960678</tid>
<number>27</number>Employees of Council to be public servants. The Chairperson, 
members, Member- Secretary, officers and other employees of the Council 
shall, while acting or purporting to act in pursuance of the 
provisions of this Act or of any rule and regulation made thereunder, 
be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of 
the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>).

</article>



<article><tid>1468622</tid>
<number>28</number>Power to make rules. The Central Government may, by 
notification, make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.

</article>



<article><tid>730908</tid>
<number> 29</number> Power to make regulations. The Council may, with the previous 
sanction of the Central Government, make, by notification, regulations 
generally to carry out the purposes of this Act, and without prejudice 
to the generality of the foregoing power, such regulations may provide 
for--
<section><tid>1723269</tid>
<number>a</number>the management of the property of the Council;

</section>

<section><tid>1098831</tid>
<number>b</number>the maintenance and audit of the accounts of the 
Council;

</section>

<section><tid>308815</tid>
<number>c</number>the resignation of members of the Council;

</section>

<section><tid>1142935</tid>
<number>d</number>the powers and duties of the Chairperson;

</section>

<section><tid>1074345</tid>
<number>e</number>the rules of procedure in the transaction of business 
under sub- section (3) of section 4;

</section>

<section><tid>1381478</tid>
<number>f</number>the function of the Executive Committee and other 
committees, constituted under section 7;

</section>

<section><tid>60850</tid>
<number>g</number>the powers and duties of the Member- Secretary under sub- 
section (1) of section 8;

</section>

<section><tid>567557</tid>
<number>h</number>the qualifications, appointment, powers and duties of, 
and procedure to be followed by, Inspectors and Visitors;

</section>

<section><tid>1810127</tid>
<number>i</number>the courses and period of study or of training, to be 
undertaken, the subjects of examination and standards of 
proficiency therein to be obtained in any University or any 
institution for grant of recognised rehabilitation qualification;

</section>

<section><tid>1040654</tid>
<number>j</number>the standards of staff, equipment, accommodation, 
training and other facilities for study or training of the 
rehabilitation professionals;

</section>

<section><tid>1796326</tid>
<number>k</number>the conduct of examinations, qualifications of 
examiners, and the condition of the admission to such 
examinations;

</section>

<section><tid>981087</tid>
<number>l</number>the standards of professional conduct and etiquette and 
code of ethics to be observed by rehabilitation professionals 
under sub- section (1) of section 21;

</section>

<section><tid>1706737</tid>
<number>m</number>the particulars to be stated, and proof of 
qualifications to be given, in application for registration under 
this Act;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>219</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>800810</tid>
<number>n</number>the manner in which and the conditions subject to which 
an appeal may be preferred under sub- section (1) of section 22;

</section>

<section><tid>1224022</tid>
<number>o</number>the fees to be paid on applications and appeals under 
this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1367822</tid>
<number>p</number>any other matter which is to be, or may be, prescribed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>30</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Laying of rules and regulations before Parliament.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>475174</tid>
<number>30</number>Laying of rules and regulations before Parliament. Every rule 
and every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may 
be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in 
session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the 
expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or regulation, or both Houses agree that the 
rule or regulation should not be made, the rule or regulation shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule or regulation.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>220</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</article>



 </act>