<act><title>THE CIGARETTES AND OTHER TOBACCO PRODUCTS (DISPLAY OF BOARD BY EDUCATIONAL INSTITUTIONS) RULES, 20091</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title, extent and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be called the Cigarettes and Other Tobacco Products (Display of Board by Educational Institutions) Rules, 2009. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall extend to the whole of India . 
 </section><section><number>3</number> They shall come into force on the date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of their publication in the Official Gazette. 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires, 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> Act means the Cigarettes and Other Tobacco Products (Prohibition of Advertisement and Regulation of Trade and Commerce, Production, Supply and Distribution) Act, 2003 (34 of 2003); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> educational institution means any place or centre where educational institutions are imparted according to the specific norms and include any school/college and institution of higher learning established or recognized by an appropriate authority; 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Words and expression used and not defined in these rules but defined in the Act shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Display of Board by Educational Institutions. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The owner or manager or any person incharge of affairs of the educational institution shall display and exhibit a board at a conspicuous place outside the premises, prominently stating that sale of cigarettes and other tobacco products in an area within a radius of one hundred yards of educational institution is strictly prohibited and that it is an offence punishable under section 24 of the Act with fine which may extend to two hundred rupees. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The distance of one hundred yards referred to in sub-rule (1), shall be measured radially starting from the outer limit of the boundry wall or fence, as the case may be, of the educational institution. 


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Came into force on 19-1-2010.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>