<act><tid>1275048</tid>
<title>THE HAJ COMMITTEE ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 35 OF <year>2002</year>
[ 11th June, <year>2002</year>.]

An Act to establish a Haj Committee of India and State Haj Committees 
for making arrangements for the pilgrimage of Muslims for Haj, and for 
matters connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1932106</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>568810</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Haj  
Committee Act, <year>2002</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>4928</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date or dates as the Central 
Government may, by notification, appoint, and different dates may be 
appointed for different provisions of this Act and for different 
States.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1940950</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-
<section><tid>1530853</tid>
<number>a</number>'' bye- laws'' means the bye- laws made under section 45;

</section>

<section><tid>1179397</tid>
<number>b</number>'' Chief Executive Officer or the Executive Officer'' means the 
Chief Executive Officer of the Committee or the Executive Officer of 
the State Committee appointed under sub- section (1) of section 16 or 
sub- section (1) of section 29, as the case may be

</section>

<section><tid>1565268</tid>
<number>c</number>'' Committee'' means the Haj Committee of India constituted under 
section 3;

</section>

<section><tid>266437</tid>
<number>d</number>'' member'' means a member of the Haj Committee of India nominated 
under section 4 or of a State Haj Committee nominated under section 
18, as the case may be, and includes the Chairperson and a 
Vice- Chairperson;

</section>

<section><tid>1077601</tid>
<number>e</number>'' notification'' means a notification published in the Gazette of 
India or the Official Gazette of a State, as the case may be;

</section>

<section><tid>1425331</tid>
<number>f</number>'' pilgrim'' means a Muslim proceeding to, or returning from, Haj;

</section>

<section><tid>451470</tid>
<number>g</number>'' prescribed'' means prescribed by rules made under section 44 by 
the Central Government or, as the case may be, under section 47 by the 
State Government;

</section>

<section><tid>1884971</tid>
<number>h</number>'' State Committee'' means a State Haj Committee constituted under 
section 18 and includes Joint State Committee;

</section>

<section><tid>1934716</tid>
<number>i</number>'' State Government'', in relation to a Union territory, means the 
Administrator of that Union territory appointed by the President under 
article 239 of the Constitution.
CHAP

HAJ COMMITTEE OF INDIA

CHAPTER II

HAJ COMMITTEE OF INDIA




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1001684</tid>
<number> 3</number> Constitution and incorporation of Haj Committee of India.-
<section><tid>167568</tid>
<number>1</number>With  
effect from such date as the Central Government may, by notification 
in the Official Gazette, appoint in this behalf, there shall be 
constituted a Committee by the name of the Ha Committee of India.

</section>

<section><tid>622267</tid>
<number>2</number>The Committee shall be a body corporate, by the name aforesaid, 
having perpetual succession and a common seal with power, subject to 
the provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of property, 
both movable and immovable, to create a charita le trust or endowment, 
and to contract and shall by the said name sue and be sued.

</section>

<section><tid>1964494</tid>
<number>3</number>The Committee shall have its headquarters at Mumbai and as and 
when the Committee considers it functionally necessary, additional 
regional offices may be opened in consultation with the Central 
Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1788246</tid>
<number> 4</number> Composition of Committee.- The Committee shall consist of the 
following members, namely:-
<section><tid>153436</tid>
<number>i</number>three members of Parliament of whom two are to be nominated by the 
Speaker of the House of the People from among its Muslim members, and 
one by the Chairman of the Council of States from among its Muslim 
members:
Provided that a member of Parliament shall, upon ceasing to be a 
member, cease to be a member of the Committee and the Speaker of the 
House of the People or the Chairman of the Council of States, as the 
case may be, shall make a fresh nomination upon req est by the Central 
Government;


</section>

<section><tid>1709681</tid>
<number>ii</number>nine Muslim members of the Committee shall be elected, three from 
those States sending largest number of pilgrims during last three 
years and one each from the zones as specified in the Schedule, in 
such manner as may be prescribed:
Provided that not more than one member shall be elected from a State 
falling in the zone as specified in the Schedule;


</section>

<section><tid>826155</tid>
<number>iii</number>four persons not below the rank of Joint Secretary to the 
Government of India nominated by that Government to represent the 
Ministries of External Affairs, Home, Finance and Civil Aviation, as 
ex officio members;

</section>

<section><tid>1040235</tid>
<number>iv</number>seven Muslim members shall be nominated by the Central Government 
from among the following categories of persons, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1372726</tid>
<number>a</number>two members who have special knowledge of public administration, 
finance, education, culture or social work and out of whom one shall 
be a Shia Muslim;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>709755</tid>
<number>b</number>two women members, out of them one shall be Shia Muslim;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>787762</tid>
<number>c</number>three members who have special knowledge of Muslim theology and 
law, out of them one shall be a Shia Muslim.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>551015</tid>
<number>5</number>Notification of members.- As soon as may be after the nomination of 
the members of the Committee under section 4, the Central Government 
shall publish in the Official Gazette the names of all such members.


</article>



<article><tid>1043032</tid>
<number> 6</number> Term of office.-
<section><tid>798039</tid>
<number>1</number>The term of office of the members of the  
Committee (other than the ex officio members and members filling  
  casual vacancies) shall be three years, commencing on the day 
following the publication of the list of members under section:
Provided that the term of the members of the Committee may be extended 
by the Central Government by a notification in the Official Gazette 
for a period not exceeding six months at a time but, in any case, not 
exceeding beyond a total period of one year.


</section>

<section><tid>1527474</tid>
<number>2</number>The allowances payable to, and the other terms and conditions of, 
the Chairperson, Vice- Chairpersons and members shall be such as may be 
prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>562720</tid>
<number> 7</number> Chairperson and Vice- Chairperson.-
<section><tid>1599460</tid>
<number>1</number>After the publication of the  
names of members of the Committee under section 5, the Central 
Government shall convene within forty- five days of such publication 
the first meeting of the Committee at which the Commi tee shall elect 
a Chairperson and two Vice- Chairpersons from amongst its members:
Provided that a Minister shall not be the Chairperson of the Committee 
and ex officio members shall not take part in the election of the 
Chairperson or of the Vice- Chairpersons.


</section>

<section><tid>1620089</tid>
<number>2</number>If the Committee fails to elect the Chairperson or the 
Vice- Chairpersons the Central Government may appoint a member of the 
Committee to be the Chairperson thereof or Vice- Chairpersons, as the 
case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1259278</tid>
<number>3</number>The Chairperson shall exercise such powers and discharge such 
duties as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1796735</tid>
<number>4</number>The Vice- Chairpersons shall exercise such powers and discharge 
such duties as may be determined by bye- laws made in this behalf by 
the Committee: Provided that till such bye- laws are made, the 
Vice- Chairpersons shall exercise such powers and discharge such duties 
as may be determined by an order made by the Chairperson in this 
regard.

</section>

<section><tid>1011231</tid>
<number>5</number>The election of the Chairperson and the Vice- Chairpersons shall be 
notified by the Central Government in the Official Gazette.

</section>

<section><tid>242487</tid>
<number>6</number>The term of office of the Chairperson and the Vice- Chairpersons, 
as the case may be, shall be co- terminus with the term of the 
Committee and no person shall hold office of the Chairperson or the 
Vice- Chairpersons, as the case may be, for more than two consecutive 
terms.

</section>

<section><tid>526234</tid>
<number>7</number>Any casual vacancy in the office of the Chairperson or a 
Vice- Chairperson shall be filled for the remainder of the term in 
accordance with sub- section (1) or sub- section (2), as the case may 
be.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1633252</tid>
<number> 8</number> Reconstitution of Committee.-
<section><tid>300790</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government shall take  
or cause to be taken all necessary steps for the reconstitution of a 
new Committee at least four months before the expiry of the term, or 
the extended term, as the case may be, of the ommittee.

</section>

<section><tid>1773425</tid>
<number>2</number>An outgoing member shall be eligible for renomination on the 
Committee for not more than two terms:
Provided that not more than fifty per cent. of the members may be 
renominated for a second term in such manner as may be prescribed.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>49496</tid>
<number> 9</number> Duties of Committee.-
<section><tid>782308</tid>
<number>1</number>The duties of the Committee shall be- 

<subsection><tid>1853131</tid>
<number>i</number>to collect and disseminate information useful to pilgrims, and to 
arrange orientation and training programmes for pilgrims;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1422982</tid>
<number>ii</number>to advise and assist pilgrims during their stay at the 
embarkation points in India, while proceeding to or returning from 
pilgrimage, in all matters including vaccination, inoculation, medical 
inspection, issue of pilgrim passes and foreign exchange and to liaise 
with the local authorities concerned in such matters;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>333861</tid>
<number>iii</number>to give relief to pilgrims in distress;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>470155</tid>
<number>iv</number>to finalise the annual Haj plan with the approval of the Central 
Government, and execute the plan, including the arrangements for 
travel by air or any other means, and to advise in matters relating to 
accommodations;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1730722</tid>
<number>v</number>to approve the budget estimates of the Committee and submit it to 
the Central Government at least three months before the beginning of 
the financial year for its concurrence;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>963314</tid>
<number>vi</number>to co- ordinate with the Central Government, railways, airways and 
travel agencies for the purpose of securing travelling facilities for 
pilgrims;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>177462</tid>
<number>vii</number>to generally look after the welfare of the pilgrims;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1402693</tid>
<number>viii</number>to publish such proceedings of the Committee and such matters 
of interest to pilgrims as may be determined by bye- laws made in this 
behalf by the Committee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1707008</tid>
<number>ix</number>to discharge such other duties in connection with Haj as may be 
prescribed by the Central Government.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>618833</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government shall afford all reasonable assistance to 
the Committee in the discharge of the duties specified in sub- section 
 (1).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>412088</tid>
<number> 10</number> Meetings of Committee.-
<section><tid>145967</tid>
<number>1</number>The Committee shall meet at least  
three times in a year before the commencement of the Haj season to 
plan and make arrangements for Haj and once after that to review all 
arrangements made by the Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>612125</tid>
<number>2</number>In addition to the meetings specified in sub- section (1), the 
Committee may hold meetings as and when requisitioned by at least 
one- third of its members or when considered necessary by the 
Chairperson.

</section>

<section><tid>415845</tid>
<number>3</number>The number of members required to make a quorum at any meeting of 
the Committee shall be one- third of its members.

</section>

<section><tid>1348070</tid>
<number>4</number>All matters shall be decided by a majority of votes of the members 
present and, in the event of an equality of votes, the Chairperson or 
other person presiding shall have a casting vote.

</section>

<section><tid>1669027</tid>
<number>5</number>The Committee shall observe such rules of procedure in regard to 
the transaction of business at its meetings as may be determined by 
bye- laws.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>512900</tid>
<number> 11</number> Appointment of Standing Committees and sub- committees.-
<section><tid>687921</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Committee shall appoint two Standing Committees, each headed by a 
Vice- Chairperson of the Committee, to deal with matters relating to 
finance and Haj arrangements, from amongst its member consisting of 
such number of members and with such powers and functions as may be 
determined by bye- laws made in this behalf by the Committee:
Provided that the Chairperson shall preside over the meeting of the 
Standing Committee in case he attends the meeting.


</section>

<section><tid>1771885</tid>
<number>2</number>The Committee may also appoint other sub- committees for such 
purposes as it may think fit and any such sub- committee shall consist 
of such number of members and other persons as may be determined by 
bye- laws made in this behalf by the Committee.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>754916</tid>
<number> 12</number> Disqualification for being nominated, or for continuing, as a 
member of Committee.- A person shall be disqualified for being 
nominated, or for continuing as a member of the Committee, if he-
<section><tid>229622</tid>
<number>i</number>is not a citizen of India;

</section>

<section><tid>1644237</tid>
<number>ii</number>is not a Muslim, except for ex officio members as provided in 
clause (iii) of section 4;

</section>

<section><tid>988905</tid>
<number>iii</number>is less than twenty- five years of age;

</section>

<section><tid>221811</tid>
<number>iv</number>is of unsound mind and stands so declared by a competent court;

</section>

<section><tid>241566</tid>
<number>v</number>is an undischarged insolvent;

</section>

<section><tid>1327502</tid>
<number>vi</number>has been convicted of an offence which, in the opinion of the 
Central Government, involves a moral turpitude;

</section>

<section><tid>792198</tid>
<number>vii</number>has been on a previous occasion-

<subsection><tid>1847371</tid>
<number>a</number>removed from his office as a member; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>82829</tid>
<number>b</number>removed by an order of a competent authority either for not acting 
in the interest of the pilgrims or for corruption.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>378888</tid>
<number>13</number>Resignation of Chairperson, Vice- Chairperson and members.- The 
Chairperson, the Vice- Chairperson or any other member may resign his 
office by writing under his hand addressed to the Central Government 
and it shall be effective from the date of such re ignation.


</article>



<article><tid>1415161</tid>
<number> 14</number> Removal of Chairperson, Vice- Chairperson and members.-
<section><tid>1078238</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
remove the Chairperson, a Vice- Chairperson of the Committee or any 
member thereof, if he-

<subsection><tid>1689986</tid>
<number>i</number>is or becomes subject to any of the disqualifications specified in 
section 12; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>294231</tid>
<number>ii</number>refuses to act or is incapable of acting or acts in a manner 
which the Central Government, after hearing any explanation that he 
may offer, considers to be prejudicial to the interests of the 
Committee or the interests of the pilgrims; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1142280</tid>
<number>iii</number>fails, in the opinion of the Committee, to attend three 
consecutive meetings of the Committee, without sufficient excuse.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1257174</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the Chairperson or a Vice- Chairperson of the Committee is 
removed under sub- section (1), he shall also cease to be a member of 
the Committee.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>643999</tid>
<number> 15</number> Filling of a casual vacancy.-
<section><tid>1216412</tid>
<number>1</number>When the seat of a member  
becomes vacant by his removal, resignation, death or otherwise, a new 
member shall be nominated or elected, as the case may be, in his place 
and such member shall hold office so long as the m mber whose place he 
fills would have been entitled to hold office if such vacancy had not 
occurred.

</section>

<section><tid>1232474</tid>
<number>2</number>Any casual vacancy under sub- section (1) shall be filled up by the 
same category to which the former member belonged.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1710968</tid>
<number> 16</number> Chief Executive Officer and other employees.-
<section><tid>429531</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government shall appoint a person, from a panel of Muslim officers of 
the Central Government and of the State Governments not below the rank 
of Deputy Secretary to the Government of India, o be the Chief 
Executive Officer of the Committee on such terms and conditions as may 
be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>518396</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chief Executive Officer shall be the ex officio Secretary of 
the Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>1077396</tid>
<number>3</number>The Chief Executive Officer shall be appointed for a period of 
three years, which may be extended by a maximum period of one year by 
the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1379232</tid>
<number>4</number>The Chief Executive Officer shall execute the decisions of the 
Committee and perform such other functions as may be prescribed:
Provided that in case of any difference of opinion between the Chief 
Executive Officer and the Committee, he shall bring the matter to the 
notice of the Central Government, whose decision thereon shall be 
final.


</section>

<section><tid>1699967</tid>
<number>5</number>The Committee may, with the previous sanction of the Central 
Government, employ such other officers and employees as it deems 
necessary to carry out the purposes of this Act, on such terms and 
conditions as may be prescribed.
CHAP

STATE HAJ COMMITTEES

CHAPTER III

STATE HAJ COMMITTEES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>527477</tid>
<number> 17</number> Establishment and incorporation of State Haj Committee.-
<section><tid>503854</tid>
<number>1</number>With  
effect from such date as the Central Government may, by notification 
in the Official Gazette, appoint in this behalf, the Government of a 
State shall constitute a Committee by the name of the......[ name of 
the State] Haj Committee:
Provided that in case it appears to the Central Government for any 
reasons that it is not necessary for a State or Union territory to 
establish a Haj Committee, it may authorise the State Haj Committee of 
a contiguous State to deal with those pilgrims an suggest suitable 
representation of those States and Union territories.


</section>

<section><tid>1014159</tid>
<number>2</number>The State Committee shall be a body corporate, by the name 
aforesaid, having perpetual succession and a common seal with power, 
subject to the provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of 
property, both movable and immovable, to create a c aritable trust or 
endowment, and to contract and shall by the said name sue and be sued.

</section>

<section><tid>1194368</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, an agreement may 
be entered into-

<subsection><tid>1272688</tid>
<number>a</number>by two or more Governments of contiguous States, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>42553</tid>
<number>b</number>by the Central Government (in respect of one or more Union  
  territories) and one or more Governments of States contiguous to such 
Union territory or Union territories,
to be in force for such period and to be subject to renewal for such 
further period, if any, as may be specified in the agreement to 
provide for the constitution of a Joint State Committee,-


<subsubsection><tid>509261</tid>
<number>i</number>in a case referred to in clause (a), for all the participating 
States, and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>832041</tid>
<number>ii</number>in a case referred to in clause (b), for the participating Union 
territory or Union territories and the State or States.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>810659</tid>
<number>4</number>An agreement under this section shall be published, in a case 
referred to in clause (a) of sub- section (2), in the Official Gazette 
of the participating States and in a case referred to in clause (b) of 
that sub- section, in the Official Gazette of th participating Union 
territory or Union territories and participating State or States.

</section>

<section><tid>1402377</tid>
<number>5</number>Any reference in this Act to the State Committee shall, unless the 
context otherwise requires, be construed as including a Joint State 
Committee.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>362810</tid>
<number> 18</number> Composition of State Committee.-
<section><tid>232321</tid>
<number>1</number>A State Committee shall  
consist of sixteen members, to be nominated by the State Government, 
namely:-

<subsection><tid>1169021</tid>
<number>i</number>three members from the Muslim members of-

<subsubsection><tid>293892</tid>
<number>a</number>Parliament representing the State;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1581516</tid>
<number>b</number>State Legislative Assembly; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1139824</tid>
<number>c</number>Legislative Council, where it exists;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1767568</tid>
<number>ii</number>three members from Muslim members representing local bodies in 
the State;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>603932</tid>
<number>iii</number>three members having expertise in Muslim theology and law 
including one who shall be a Shia Muslim;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1119284</tid>
<number>iv</number>five members representing Muslim voluntary organisations working 
in the fields of public administration, finance, education, culture or 
social work;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1126930</tid>
<number>v</number>the Chairperson of the State Wakf Board; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>897364</tid>
<number>vi</number>Executive Officer of the State Committee, who shall be the ex 
officio member of the State Committee:
Provided that a Committee for any Union territory or a Joint State 
Committee shall consist of such number of members as may be 
prescribed.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1058582</tid>
<number>2</number>In case where there is no Muslim member in any of the categories 
mentioned in clauses (i) and (ii) of sub- section (1), or where there 
is no Legislative Council in a State, nomination may be made in such 
manner as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>609165</tid>
<number> 19</number> Notification of members.- As soon as may be after the nomination 
of the members of a State Committee under sub- section
<section><tid>189176</tid>
<number>1</number>of section  
18, the State Government shall publish, in the Official Gazette of 
that State, the names of all such members.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>444224</tid>
<number> 20</number> Term of office.-
<section><tid>1899886</tid>
<number>1</number>The term of office of the members of the  
State Committee (other than the ex officio members and members filling  
  casual vacancies) shall be three years, commencing on the day 
following the publication of the list of members under section 19.

</section>

<section><tid>1294881</tid>
<number>2</number>The allowances payable to, and the other terms and conditions of 
the Chairperson and members shall be such as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>389974</tid>
<number> 21</number> Chairperson.-
<section><tid>12462</tid>
<number>1</number>After the publication of the names of members of  
the State Committee under section 19, the State Government shall 
convene within forty- five days the first meeting of the State 
Committee at which the State Committee shall elect a Cha rperson from 
amongst its members:
Provided that an ex officio member shall not take part in the election 
of the Chairperson.


</section>

<section><tid>901538</tid>
<number>2</number>If the State Committee fails to elect a Chairperson, the State 
Government may appoint a member of the State Committee to be the 
Chairperson thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>1365017</tid>
<number>3</number>The election of the Chairperson shall be notified by the State 
Government in the Official Gazette of the State.

</section>

<section><tid>246198</tid>
<number>4</number>The term of office of the Chairperson shall be three years and no 
person shall hold the office of the Chairperson for more than two 
consecutive terms.

</section>

<section><tid>1978425</tid>
<number>5</number>Any casual vacancy in the office of the Chairperson shall be 
filled in accordance with sub- section (1) or sub- section (2), as the 
case may be.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1674409</tid>
<number> 22</number> Reconstitution of a State Committee.-
<section><tid>707577</tid>
<number>1</number>The State Government  
shall take or cause to be taken all necessary steps for the 
reconstitution of a new State Committee at least four months before 
the expiry of the term of the State Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>1437577</tid>
<number>2</number>An outgoing member shall be eligible for re- nomination of the 
State Committee for not more than two terms: Provided that fifty per 
cent of the nominees may be re- nominated for a second term in such 
manner as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>975366</tid>
<number> 23</number> Disqualification for being nominated, or for continuing, as a 
member of the Committee.- A person shall be disqualified for being 
nominated, or for continuing, as a member of the State Committee, if 
he-
<section><tid>340331</tid>
<number>i</number>is not a citizen of India;

</section>

<section><tid>277514</tid>
<number>ii</number>is not a resident of that State;

</section>

<section><tid>943135</tid>
<number>iii</number>is not a Muslim, except for an Executive Officer as provided in 
clause

</section>

<section><tid>1516609</tid>
<number>vi</number>of sub- section (1) of section 18;

</section>

<section><tid>854448</tid>
<number>iv</number>is less than twenty- five years of age;

</section>

<section><tid>712791</tid>
<number>v</number>is of unsound mind and stands so declared by a competent court;

</section>

<section><tid>1516609</tid>
<number>vi</number>is an undischarged insolvent;

</section>

<section><tid>1180416</tid>
<number>vii</number>has been convicted of an offence which, in the opinion of the 
State Government, involves a moral turpitude;

</section>

<section><tid>1941935</tid>
<number>viii</number>has been on a previous occasion-

<subsection><tid>167687</tid>
<number>a</number>removed from his office as a member; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1146766</tid>
<number>b</number>removed by an order of a competent authority either for not acting 
in the interest of the pilgrims or for corruption.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>706989</tid>
<number>24</number>Resignation of Chairperson and members.- The Chairperson or any 
other member may resign his office by writing under his hand addressed 
to the State Government and it shall be effective from the date of 
such resignation.


</article>



<article><tid>81664</tid>
<number> 25</number> Removal of Chairperson and members.-
<section><tid>1340046</tid>
<number>1</number>The State Government may,  
by notification in the Official Gazette, remove the Chairperson of the 
State Committee or any member thereof, if he-

<subsection><tid>904673</tid>
<number>i</number>is or becomes subject to any of the disqualifications specified in 
section 23; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1588556</tid>
<number>ii</number>refuses to act or is incapable of acting or acts in a manner 
which the State Government, after hearing any explanation that he may 
offer, considers to be prejudicial to the interests of the State 
Committee or the interests of the pilgrims; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>322277</tid>
<number>iii</number>fails, in the opinion of the State Committee, to attend three 
consecutive meetings of the State Committee, without sufficient 
excuse.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>685032</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the Chairperson of the State Committee is removed under 
sub- section (1), he shall also cease to be a member of the State 
Committee.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1002088</tid>
<number> 26</number> Filling of casual vacancy.-
<section><tid>1469091</tid>
<number>1</number>When the seat of a member becomes  
vacant by his removal, resignation, death or otherwise, a new member 
shall be nominated in his place and such member shall hold office so 
long as the member whose place he fills would have been entitled to 
hold office if such vacancy had not occurred.

</section>

<section><tid>160030</tid>
<number>2</number>Any casual vacancy under sub- section (1) shall be filled up by the 
same category to which the former member belonged.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1555794</tid>
<number> 27</number> Duties of State Committee.-
<section><tid>1982164</tid>
<number>1</number>It shall be the duty of a State  
Committee to implement the policy and directions of the Committee in 
the interests of Haj pilgrims.

</section>

<section><tid>1829905</tid>
<number>2</number>The State Committee shall provide assistance to the Haj pilgrims 
including in the matter of their transport between their home States 
and the point of exit from India and their transit accommodation at 
points of exit.

</section>

<section><tid>1756255</tid>
<number>3</number>The State Committee shall discharge such other duties in 
connection with Haj as may be prescribed by the State Government 
concerned, in consultation with the Central Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1066788</tid>
<number> 28</number> Meetings of State Committee.-
<section><tid>955049</tid>
<number>1</number>A State Committee shall meet at  
least twice in a year before the Haj day and once after the Haj is 
over.

</section>

<section><tid>1059746</tid>
<number>2</number>The number of members required to make a quorum at any meeting of 
the State Committee shall be one- third of its members.

</section>

<section><tid>432285</tid>
<number>3</number>In addition to the number of meetings specified in sub- section 
 (1), the State Committee may hold meetings as and when requisitioned 
by at least one- third of its members or when considered necessary by 
the Chairperson.

</section>

<section><tid>274950</tid>
<number>4</number>All matters shall be decided by a majority of votes of the members 
present and, in the event of an equality of votes, the Chairperson or 
other person presiding shall have a casting vote.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>227149</tid>
<number> 29</number> Executive Officer and other employees of State Committee.-
<section><tid>764283</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
State Government shall appoint a person, from amongst its officers not 
below the rank of Deputy Secretary, to be the Executive Officer of the 
State Committee:
Provided that the person so appointed shall preferably be a Muslim.


</section>

<section><tid>1070177</tid>
<number>2</number>The Executive Officer of the State Committee shall act as its 
Secretary.

</section>

<section><tid>1229506</tid>
<number>3</number>The Executive Officer shall execute the decisions of the State 
Committee and perform such other functions as may be prescribed:
Provided that in case of any difference of opinion between the 
Executive Officer and the State Committee, he shall bring the matter 
to the notice of the State Government whose decision thereon shall be 
final.


</section>

<section><tid>1870954</tid>
<number>4</number>The State Committee shall, with the previous sanction of the State 
Government, employ such officers and other employees as it deems 
necessary to carry out the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1930126</tid>
<number>5</number>The term of office and conditions of service of officers and other 
employees shall be such as may be prescribed.
CHAP

FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT

CHAPTER IV

FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1175170</tid>
<number> 30</number> Central Haj Fund.- The Committee shall have its own Fund to be 
called the Central Haj Fund, and there shall be placed to the credit 
thereof the following sums, namely:-
<section><tid>781799</tid>
<number>a</number>sums realised from any fees and service charges which may be 
levied by the Committee:-

<subsection><tid>127709</tid>
<number>i</number>for registration of applications for Haj; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>887475</tid>
<number>ii</number>for issue of Haj pilgrim travel passes;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>710182</tid>
<number>b</number>money collected from pilgrims for performance of Haj;

</section>

<section><tid>965399</tid>
<number>c</number>the income from all deposits and investment of the Committee' s 
funds;

</section>

<section><tid>163145</tid>
<number>d</number>the sums realised from the sale of the effects of deceased 
pilgrims and sums of money left by them, which are unclaimed and have 
lapsed to the Central Government;

</section>

<section><tid>535537</tid>
<number>e</number>any sums loaned by the Central or a State Government, or any other 
source approved by the Government;

</section>

<section><tid>365549</tid>
<number>f</number>any amount that may be legally due to the Committee from any 
source; and

</section>

<section><tid>213625</tid>
<number>g</number>the amount standing at the commencement of this Act to the credit 
of the Haj Fund or the Indigent Pilgrims Fund established under the 
Haj Committee Act, <year>1959</year> (51 of <year>1959</year>).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1452174</tid>
<number> 31</number> Application of Central Haj Fund.- The Central Haj Fund shall, 
subject to the provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder, 
be under the control and management of the Committee, and shall be 
applied to the following purposes, namely:-
<section><tid>699898</tid>
<number>a</number>pay and allowances of the Chief Executive Officer and other 
employees of the Committee;

</section>

<section><tid>1517293</tid>
<number>b</number>payment of charges and expenses incidental to the objects 
specified in section 9; and

</section>

<section><tid>848319</tid>
<number>c</number>any other expenses which are required to be met by the Committee 
or a State Committee, as approved by the Central Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1842465</tid>
<number> 32</number> State Haj Fund.- The State Committee shall have its own fund to be 
called the State Haj Fund and the following sums shall be placed to 
the credit thereof, namely:-
<section><tid>836903</tid>
<number>i</number>all sums of money paid to it or any grant made by the Committee 
for the purposes of this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>128313</tid>
<number>ii</number>any grant or loan that may be made to the State Committee by the 
State Government, or any other source for the purposes of this Act, as 
approved by the State Government;

</section>

<section><tid>185673</tid>
<number>iii</number>any amount that may be legally due to the State Committee from 
any source; and

</section>

<section><tid>910248</tid>
<number>iv</number>the moneys, if any, standing to the credit of a State Haj 
Committee, at the commencement of this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1549601</tid>
<number> 33</number> Application of State Haj Fund.- The State Haj Fund shall, subject 
to any rules that may be made under this Act, be under the control and 
management of the State Committee and shall be applied to the 
following purposes, namely:-
<section><tid>120037</tid>
<number>i</number>pay and allowances of the employees of the State Committee other 
than its Executive Officer whose pay and allowances shall be borne by 
the State Government;

</section>

<section><tid>347873</tid>
<number>ii</number>payment of charges and expenses incidental to the due performance 
of its duties by the State Committee for the objects specified in 
section 27; and

</section>

<section><tid>1189886</tid>
<number>iii</number>any other expenses, as approved by the State Government which 
are required to be met by the State Committee.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1832242</tid>
<number> 34</number> Accounts and audit.-
<section><tid>820796</tid>
<number>1</number>The Committee and every State Committee  
shall maintain proper accounts and other relevant records and prepare 
an annual statement of accounts, in such form as may be prescribed by 
the Central Government, or as the case may be, the State Government.

</section>

<section><tid>17344</tid>
<number>2</number>The accounts shall be examined and audited annually by such 
auditors as the Central Government or, as the case may be, the State 
Government may approve.

</section>

<section><tid>1961939</tid>
<number>3</number>The accounts of the Committee or the State Committee as certified 
by the auditor together with the audit report thereon shall be 
forwarded annually by the said Committee to the Central Government, or 
as the case may be, the State Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1838445</tid>
<number>4</number>The Central Government shall, as soon as may be after the receipt 
of the audit report under sub- section (3), cause the same to be laid 
before each House of Parliament.

</section>

<section><tid>1014357</tid>
<number>5</number>The State Government shall, as soon as may be, after the receipt 
of the audit report under sub- section (3), cause the same to be laid 
before the State Legislature.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER V

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1799528</tid>
<number> 35</number> Powers of Committee to issue Pilgrim Passes and levy fees.-
<section><tid>1587433</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The Committee shall have the power to issue a travel document called 
" Pilgrim Pass" to a Haj pilgrim for his departure from India as a bona 
fide pilgrim to Saudi Arabia and the said Pil rim shall be deemed to 
be exempted from the provisions of section 3 of the Passports Act, 
 <year>1967</year> (15 of <year>1967</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>863441</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Passports Act, <year>1967</year> (15  
  of <year>1967</year>), the Central Government may, in consultation with the 
Committee, levy such fees for registration of Haj pilgrims, issuance 
of Pilgrim Pass by the Committee and other related m tters, as may be 
prescribed in connection with rendering of such services.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>589889</tid>
<number> 36</number> Supersession of Committee.-
<section><tid>1402380</tid>
<number>1</number>If, in the opinion of the Central  
Government, the Committee is unable to perform, or persistently makes 
default in the performance of the duties imposed on it by or under 
this Act or exceeds or abuses its powers, the C ntral Government may, 
by an order published, together with a statement of the reasons 
therefor, in the Official Gazette, supersede it for such period as may 
be specified in the order:
Provided that before making an order of supersession as aforesaid, the 
Central Government shall give a reasonable opportunity to the 
Committee to show cause why it should not be superseded.


</section>

<section><tid>1843837</tid>
<number>2</number>When the Committee is superseded by an order under sub- section 
 (1),-

<subsection><tid>135467</tid>
<number>a</number>all members shall, on such date as may be specified in the order, 
vacate their offices as such members without prejudice to their 
eligibility for nomination under clause (d);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>652793</tid>
<number>b</number>during the period of supersession of the Committee, all powers and 
duties conferred and imposed upon the Committee by or under this Act 
shall be exercised and performed by such officer or authority as the 
Central Government may appoint in that behalf

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>560180</tid>
<number>c</number>all property vested in the Committee shall, until it is 
reconstituted, vest in the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1041765</tid>
<number>d</number>before the expiry of the period of supersession, nominations shall 
be made by the Central Government for the purpose of reconstituting 
the Committee.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1039632</tid>
<number>3</number>An order of supersession made under this section together with a 
statement of the reasons therefor shall be laid before each House of 
Parliament as soon as may be after it has been made.

</section>

<section><tid>1839228</tid>
<number>4</number>A State Government may exercise the same powers and duties in 
respect of a State Committee as mentioned in sub- sections (1), (2) and 
 (3) of this section subject to the conditions mentioned therein and 
any directions issued by the Central Government i this regard.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>235118</tid>
<number>37</number>Membership of Committee or State Committee not to constitute 
office of profit.- Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law 
for the time being in force, the office of a member of the Committee 
or State Committee shall not be deemed to be an o fice of profit.


</article>



<article><tid>336568</tid>
<number>38</number>Vacancies, etc., not to invalidate proceedings of Committee.- No 
act or proceeding of the Committee or of a State Committee or of a 
Joint State Committee, as the case may be, shall be invalid by reason 
only of the existence of any vacancy amongst its embers, or any defect 
in the constitution thereof.


</article>



<article><tid>1077089</tid>
<number>39</number>Officers and employees of Committee to be public servants.- The 
officers and employees of the Committees and other persons duly 
appointed to discharge any duty under this Act or rules or bye- laws 
made thereunder, shall be deemed to be public servants ithin the 
meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>1175997</tid>
<number>40</number>Indemnity.- No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall 
lie against the Chairperson, Vice- Chairpersons or any member of the 
Committee or a State Committee in respect of anything in good faith 
done or purporting to have been done under this Ac, except with the 
prior permission of the Central or State Government, as the case may 
be.


</article>



<article><tid>1578298</tid>
<number> 41</number> Power to amend Schedule.-
<section><tid>935094</tid>
<number>1</number>If the Central Government is  
satisfied that it is necessary or expedient so to do, it may, by 
notification published in the Official Gazette, amend the Schedule and 
thereupon the Schedule shall be deemed to have been amen ed 
accordingly.

</section>

<section><tid>117307</tid>
<number>2</number>A copy of every notification made under sub- section (1) shall be 
laid before each House of Parliament as soon as may be after it is 
made.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>538279</tid>
<number>42</number>Redressal of grievances.- Any Haj pilgrim, who is aggrieved by the 
discharge of any of the duties performed by the Haj Committee or the 
State Haj Committee, shall make a representation for the redressal of 
his grievance to the Haj Committee or the Sta e Haj Committee, as the 
case may be, and the same shall be disposed of by the said Committee, 
if necessary, after hearing the aggrieved person.


</article>



<article><tid>360646</tid>
<number> 43</number> Vesting of properties and other rights, etc., in Committees.-
<section><tid>961670</tid>
<number>1</number> 
On and from the commencement of this Act, all assets, rights, 
leaseholds, powers, authorities and privileges and all properties, 
movable and immovable, including lands, buildings, stor s, cash 
balances, cash on hand, reserve funds, investments and all other 
rights and interests in or arising out of such properties as were 
immediately before such commencement in the ownership, power or 
control of Haj Committee, Mumbai, constituted under the Haj Committee 
Act, <year>1959</year> (51 of <year>1959</year>) and all books of account, registers and all 
other documents of whatever nature relating thereto shall vest 
absolutely in and belong to the Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>1237121</tid>
<number>2</number>On and from the commencement of this Act, all assets, rights, 
leaseholds, powers, authorities and privileges and all properties, 
movable and immovable, including lands, buildings, stores, cash 
balances, cash on hand, reserve funds, investments and al other rights 
and interests in or arising out of such properties as were immediately 
before such commencement in the ownership, power or control of Haj 
Committee of a State and, all books of account, registers and all 
other documents of whatever nature r lating thereto shall vest 
absolutely in and belong to the Haj Committee of a State.

</section>

<section><tid>1487061</tid>
<number>3</number>All debts, obligations and liabilities incurred, all contracts 
entered into and all matters and things engaged to be done by, with or 
for the Committee or a State Committee immediately before such 
commencement for or in connection with the purposes o the Committee or 
a State Committee shall be deemed to have been incurred, entered into 
and engaged to be done by, with or for the Committee or a State 
Committee, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>180802</tid>
<number>4</number>All sums of money due to the Committee or a State Committee 
immediately before such commencement shall be deemed to be due to the 
Committee or a State Committee, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>172613</tid>
<number>5</number>All contracts made with and all instruments executed on behalf of 
the Haj Committee, Mumbai or the Haj Committee of a State shall be 
deemed to have been made or executed on behalf of the Committee, or as 
the case may be, the State Committee and shall be performed 
accordingly.

</section>

<section><tid>1459252</tid>
<number>6</number>In all suits and legal proceedings pending on the commencement of 
this Act in or to which the Haj Committee, Mumbai or the Haj Committee 
of a State was a party, the Committee, or as the case may be, the 
State Committee shall be deemed to have been su stituted therefor.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>620967</tid>
<number> 44</number> Power to make rules.-
<section><tid>180293</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification, make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>457827</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing powers, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1960823</tid>
<number>i</number>the manner of election of members of the Committee under clause 
 (ii) of section 4;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>286537</tid>
<number>ii</number>the terms and conditions of the Chairperson and members under 
sub- section (2) of section 6;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1716127</tid>
<number>iii</number>the powers and duties of the Chairperson under sub- section (3) 
of section 7;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1613753</tid>
<number>iv</number>the manner in which the members may be re- nominated under the 
proviso to sub- section (2) of section 8;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1886614</tid>
<number>v</number>duties in connection with Haj under clause (ix) of sub- section (1) 
of section 9;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1530094</tid>
<number>vi</number>the functions of the Chief Executive Officer and the terms and 
conditions of service of the Chief Executive Officer and other 
employees of the Committee under section 16;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1348087</tid>
<number>vii</number>the number of members of a Joint State Committee or of a 
Committee for Union territory under the proviso to clause (vi) of 
sub- section (1) of section 18;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>758575</tid>
<number>viii</number>the manner in which the accounts shall be maintained by the 
Committee and the State Committees and the audit of such accounts 
under section 34;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1776669</tid>
<number>ix</number>issue of Haj Pilgrim Pass under sub- section (1) of section 35;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>977900</tid>
<number>x</number>amendment of the Schedule relating to the zones comprising 
contiguous States or Union territories under section 41;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1101058</tid>
<number>xi</number>any other matter which may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>896235</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may 
be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in 
session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or in two or more successive session, and if, before the 
expiry of the session in which it is so laid, or the session 
immediately following, both Houses agree in making any modification in 
the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the 
rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of 
no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such 
modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity 
of anything previously done under that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>539249</tid>
<number> 45</number> Power to make bye- laws.-
<section><tid>346744</tid>
<number>1</number>The Committee may, by notification,  
make bye- laws consistent with the provisions of the Act and the rules 
made thereunder in respect of the following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>367402</tid>
<number>i</number>powers and duties of the Vice- Chairpersons under sub- section (4) 
of section 7;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1631332</tid>
<number>ii</number>providing for the publication of the proceedings of the Committee 
and any matter of interests to pilgrims under clause (viii) of 
sub- section (1) of section 9;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1537101</tid>
<number>iii</number>laying down the rules of procedure for transaction of business 
at meeting of the Committee under sub- section (5) of section 10;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1638824</tid>
<number>iv</number>powers and functions of the Standing Committee and determination 
of number of members and other persons in sub- committees under section 
11.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>132338</tid>
<number>v</number>providing for any other matter which the Committee deems necessary 
for giving effect to the provisions of this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1410244</tid>
<number>2</number>Bye- laws made by the Committee under this section shall be 
submitted to the Central Government and shall not take effect until 
they have been confirmed by the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1087759</tid>
<number>3</number>Bye- laws which have been confirmed by the Central Government shall 
be published in the Official Gazette.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>407143</tid>
<number>46</number>Power to delegate.- Subject to the provisions of this Act and the 
rules made thereunder, the Committee may, by general or special order 
in writing, with the prior approval of the Central Government, 
delegate to any member or Chief Executive Officer o the Committee, and 
subject to such conditions and limitations, as may be specified in the 
order, such of its powers under this Act (except the powers to make  
  bye- laws under section 45) as it may deem necessary.


</article>



<article><tid>1082296</tid>
<number> 47</number> Power to make rules by State Governments.-
<section><tid>816710</tid>
<number>1</number>The State  
Governments may, in consultation with the Central Government, by 
notification make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act in 
respect of the State Committees.

</section>

<section><tid>585242</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing powers, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>952941</tid>
<number>i</number>terms and conditions of the Chairperson and members of the State 
Committee under sub- section (2) of section 20;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1408066</tid>
<number>ii</number>the manner in which the members may be re- nominated under the 
proviso to sub- section (2) of section 22;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1291076</tid>
<number>iii</number>duties of the State Committee under sub- section (3) of section 
27;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>101023</tid>
<number>iv</number>the functions of the Executive Officer and the terms and 
conditions of service of officers and other employees under section 
29;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1534202</tid>
<number>v</number>any other matter which is required to be or may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1469979</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may 
be after it is made, before the State Legislature.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>853100</tid>
<number>48</number>Provisions as to employees of the existing Committee before the 
commencement of this Act.- Every officer and other employee of any of 
the existing Committee and the State Committee, as the case may be, 
shall, on and from the commencement of this Act, tand transferred to 
or become an officer or other employee of the Committee or the State 
Committee, as the case may be, with such designation as such Committee 
may determine and shall hold office or service therein by the same 
tenure, at the same remuner tion, upon the same terms and conditions 
of service as he would have held under the Haj Committee constituted 
under the Haj Committee Act, <year>1959</year> (51 of <year>1959</year>) and shall continue to 
do so as an officer or other employee of the Committee till such time 
the t rms and conditions are duly altered by such Committee:
Provided that the tenure, remuneration and terms and conditions of 
service of any such officer or other employee of the Committee or of a 
State Committee, as the case may be, shall not be altered to his 
disadvantage without the previous sanction of the C ntral Government 
or State Government, as the case may be: Provided further that any 
service rendered by any such officer or other employee before the 
commencement of this Act shall be deemed to be the service rendered 
under the Committee or, as the case may be, the State Committee.



</article>



<article><tid>1849683</tid>
<number>49</number>Protection of action taken in good faith.- No suit, prosecution or 
other legal proceedings shall lie against the Government or any 
officer or other employee of the Government or the Committee 
constituted under this Act in respect of anything which is n good 
faith done or intended to be done under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1335596</tid>
<number> 50</number> Power to remove difficulties.-
<section><tid>1129521</tid>
<number>1</number>If any difficulty arises in  
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, remove 
the difficulty: Provided that no such order shall be made after the 
expiry of a period of two years from the commencement of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1879169</tid>
<number>2</number>Any order made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be 
after it is made, before each House of Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>82779</tid>
<number>51</number>Powers to give directions.- The Central Government may, in 
exercise of its powers and performance of its functions under this 
Act, issue directions in writing to the Committee or the State 
Government or the State Committee and such Committee, State G vernment 
or State Committee, as the case may be, shall be bound to comply with 
such directions.


</article>



<article><tid>1410838</tid>
<number> 52</number> Repeal.-
<section><tid>1321295</tid>
<number>1</number>The Haj Committee Act, <year>1959</year> (51 of <year>1959</year>) is hereby  
repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>89703</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, the Haj Committee constituted under 
the said Act shall, until the establishment of the Committee under 
this Act, continue to function as if this Act had not been passed and 
on such notification under section 5 on the esta lishment of the 
Committee, the former Committee shall stand dissolved.

</section>

<section><tid>1965137</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken 
under the Haj Committee Act, <year>1959</year> (51 of <year>1959</year>) shall be deemed to have 
been done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.


</section>

</article>



 </act>