<act><tid>195458</tid>
<title>THE TAMIL NADU LEGISLATIVE COUNCIL (ABOLITION) ACT, <year>1986</year>.</title>

ACT NO. 40 OF <year>1986</year>
[ 30th August, <year>1986</year>.]

An Act to provide for the abolition of the Legislative Council of the 
State 
of Tamil Nadu and for matters supplemental, incidental and 
consequential 
thereto.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty- seventh Year of the 
Republic of 
India as follows:--





<article><tid>1185873</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>452095</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Tamil Nadu  
Legislative Council (Abolition) Act, <year>1986</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>457818</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date 1 as the Central Government may, 
by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>981635</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-
<section><tid>531524</tid>
<number>a</number>" appropriate Government" means, as respects a law relating to a matter 
enumerated in List I in the Seventh Schedule to the Constitution, the 
Central Government, and as respects any other law, the State Government;

</section>

<section><tid>1722039</tid>
<number>b</number>" article" means an article of the Constitution;

</section>

<section><tid>1802860</tid>
<number>c</number>" Council" Means the Legislative Council of the State of Tamil Nadu;

</section>

<section><tid>761675</tid>
<number>d</number>" law" includes any enactment, ordinance, regulation, order, bye- law, 
rule, scheme, notification or other instrument having the force of law in 
the whole or any part of the State of Tamil Nadu;

</section>

<section><tid>1219299</tid>
<number>e</number>" Legislative Assembly" means the Legislative Assembly of the State of 
Tamil Nadu.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1800148</tid>
<number> 3</number> Abolition of the Council.-
<section><tid>1472134</tid>
<number>1</number>The Legislative Council of the State of  
Tamil Nadu is hereby abolished.

</section>

<section><tid>1499422</tid>
<number>2</number>On the abolition of the Council, every member thereof shall cease to be 
such member.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1312751</tid>
<number> 4</number> Amendment of article 168.- In sub- clause (a) of clause
<section><tid>1727018</tid>
<number>1</number>of article  
168, the word", Tamil Nadu," shall be omitted. 1. 1- 11- <year>1986</year>: vide 
Notification No. G. S. R. 1154 (E), dated 20- 10- <year>1986</year>, Gazette of India, 
<year>1986</year>, Extraordinary, Part II, Section 3 (i).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1148762</tid>
<number> 5</number> Amendment of Act 43 of <year>1950</year>.- In the Representation of the People Act, 
<year>1950</year>,-
<section><tid>1018468</tid>
<number>a</number>in the Third Schedule, entry No. 4 relating to Tamil Nadu shall be 
omitted;

</section>

<section><tid>1053370</tid>
<number>b</number>in the Fourth Schedule, the heading" Tamil Nadu" and the entries 
thereunder shall be omitted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>543582</tid>
<number>6</number>Repeal of Delimitation of Council Constituencies (Madras) Order, 
<year>1951</year>.- The Delimitation of Council Constituencies (Madras) Order, <year>1951</year>, is 
hereby repealed.


</article>



<article><tid>888593</tid>
<number> 7</number> Provision as to pending Bills.-
<section><tid>1281154</tid>
<number>1</number>A Bill pending in the Council  
immediately before the Commencement of this Act which has not been passed 
by the Legislative Assembly shall lapse on the abolition of the Council.

</section>

<section><tid>1724786</tid>
<number>2</number>A Bill pending in the Council immediately before the Commencement of 
this Act which has been passed by the Legislative Assembly shall lapse on 
the abolition of the Council, but on such abolition shall be deemed to have 
the State of Tamil Nadu in the form in which it was passed by the 
Legislative Assembly. been passed before such commen ement by both Houses 
of the Legislature of

</section>

<section><tid>148814</tid>
<number>3</number>If a Bill which having been passed by the Legislative Assembly is, 
before the commencement of the this Act, either rejected by the Council or 
passed by the Council with amendments, the legislative Assembly may, after 
such commencement, pass the Bill again with or without such amendments, if 
any, as have been made by the Council and the Bill so passed shall be 
deemed to be a Bill introduced in and passed by the Legislative Assembly 
after the commencement of this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1828480</tid>
<number>8</number>Power to adapt laws.- The appropriate Government may, before the 
expiration of one year from the commencement of this Act, by order, 
published in the Official Gazette, make such adaptations and modifications 
of any law made before such commencement, wh ther by way of repeal or 
amendment as may be necessary or expedient in consequence of the abolition 
of the Council under section 3, and thereupon every such law shall have 
effect subject to the adaptations and modifications so made.


</article>



<article><tid>1616367</tid>
<number>9</number>Power to construe laws.- Notwithstanding that 
no provision orinsufficient provision has been made under section 8 for the 
adaptation ormodification of a law made

</article>



 </act>