<act><title>

    THE LEGAL SERVICES AUTHORITIES ACT, 1987</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Legal Services Authorities Act, 1987.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends 
    to the whole of India, except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It 
    shall come into force on such date* as the Central Government may, by 
    notification, appoint; and different dates1 may 
    be appointed for different provisions of this Act and for different States, 
    and any reference to commencement in any provision of this Act in relation 
    to any State shall be construed as a reference to the commencement of that 
    provision in that State. 
 
 
 
 

































 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> In this Act, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 

1[(a)    
    “case” includes a suit or any proceeding before a court; 2[(a) 
    “case” includes a suit or any proceeding before a court;" 
 <subsection>
<number>aa</number>    “Central Authority” means the National 
    Legal Services Authority constituted under section 3; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>aaa</number>    “court” means a civil, criminal or 
    revenue court and includes any tribunal or any other authority constituted 
    under any law for the time being in force, to exercise judicial or 
    quasi-Judicial functions;] 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    “District Authority” means a District 
    Legal Services Authority constituted under section 9; 
 

2[(bb)    
    “High Court Legal Services Committee” means a High Court Legal Services 
    Committee constituted under section 8A;]
1[(bb) 
    “High Court Legal Services Committee” means a High Court Legal Services 
    Committee constituted under section 8A;]" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    “legal service” includes the rendering 
    of any service in the conduct of any case or other legal proceeding before 
    any court or other authority or tribunal and the giving of advice on any 
    legal matter; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    “Lok Adalat” means a Lok Adalat 
    organised under Chapter VI; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    “notification” means a notification 
    published in the Official Gazette; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    “prescribed” means prescribed by rules 
    made under this Act; 
 

2[(ff)    
    “regulations” means regulations made under this Act;] 1[(ff) 
    “regulations” means regulations made under this Act;]" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    “scheme” means any scheme framed by the 
    Central Authority, a State Authority or a District Authority for the purpose 
    of giving effect to any of the provisions of this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    “State Authority” means a State Legal 
    Services Authority constituted under section 6; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    “State Government” includes the 
    administrator of a Union Territory appointed by the President under Article 
    239 of the Constitution; 
 

2[(j)    
    “Supreme Court Legal Services Committee” means the Supreme Court Legal 
    Services Committee constituted under section 3A; 
    1[(j) “Supreme Court Legal Services Committee” means 
    the Supreme Court Legal Services Committee constituted under section 3A;" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>    “Taluk Legal Services Committee” means 
    a Taluk Legal Services Committee constituted under section 11A.] 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Any 
    reference in this Act to any other enactment or any provision thereof shall, 
    in relation to an area in which such enactment or provision is not in force, 
    be construed as a reference to the corresponding law or the relevant 
    provision of the corresponding law, if any, in force in that area.
 
 
  





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>3</number> Constitution of 
    the National Legal Services Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government shall constitute a body to be called the National 
    Legal Services Authority to exercise the powers and perform the functions 
    conferred on, or assigned to, the Central Authority under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Central Authority shall consist of— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the Chief Justice of India who shall be 
    the Patron-in-Chief; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    a serving or retired Judge of the 
    Supreme Court to be nominated by the President, in consultation with the 
    Chief Justice of India, who shall be the Executive Chairman; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    such number of other members, 
    possessing such experience and qualifications, as may be prescribed by the 
    Central Government, to be nominated by that Government in consultation with 
    the Chief Justice of India. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Central Government shall, in consultation with the Chief Justice of India, 
    appoint a person to be the Member-Secretary of the Central Authority, 
    possessing such experience and qualifications as may be prescribed by that 
    Government, to exercise such powers and perform such duties under the 
    Executive Chairman of the Central Authority as may be prescribed by that 
    Government or as may be assigned to him by the Executive Chairman of that 
    Authority. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The terms 
    of office and other conditions relating thereto, of members and the 
    Member-Secretary of the Central Authority shall be such as may be prescribed 
    by the Central Government in consultation with the Chief Justice of India. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Central Authority may appoint such number of officers and other employees as 
    may be prescribed by the Central Government, in consultation with the Chief 
    Justice of India, for the efficient discharge of its functions under this 
    Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    officers and other employees of the Central Authority shall be entitled to 
    such salary and allowances and shall be subject to such other conditions of 
    service as may be prescribed by the Central Government in consultation with 
    the Chief Justice of India. 
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The 
    administrative expenses of the Central Authority, including the salaries, 
    allowances and pensions payable to the Member- Secretary, officers and other 
    employees of the Central Authority, shall be defrayed out of the 
    Consolidated Fund of India. 
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> All orders 
    and decisions of the Central Authority shall be authenticated by the 
    Member-Secretary or any other officer of the Central Authority duly 
    authorised by the Executive Chairman of that Authority. 
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> No act or 
    proceeding of the Central Authority shall be invalid merely on the ground of 
    the existence of any vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution of the 
    Central Authority. 
 
 
  





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3A</number> Supreme 
    Court Legal Services Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Authority shall constitute a committee to be called the Supreme 
    Court Legal Services Committee for the purpose of exercising such powers and 
    performing such functions as may be determined by regulations made by the 
    Central Authority. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Committee shall consist of— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    a sitting Judge of the Supreme Court 
    who shall be the Chairman; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    such number of other members possessing 
    such experience and qualifications as may be prescribed by the Central 
    Government, 
 
to be 
    nominated by the Chief Justice of India. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The Chief 
    Justice of India shall appoint a person to be the Secretary to the 
    Committee, possessing such experience and qualifications as may be 
    prescribed by the Central Government. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The terms 
    of Office and other conditions relating thereto, of the members and 
    Secretary of the Committee shall be such as may be determined by regulations 
    made by the Central Authority. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Committee may appoint such number of officers and other employees as may be 
    prescribed by the Central Government, in consultation with the Chief Justice 
    of India, for the efficient discharge of its functions. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    officers and other employees of the Committee shall be entitled to such 
    salary and allowances and shall be subject to such other conditions of 
    service as may be prescribed by the Central Government in consultation with 
    the Chief Justice of India.] 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Functions of the Central Authority.—The 
    Central Authority shall 

    1[***] perform all or 
    any of the following functions, namely:——The 
    Central Authority shall 

    1[***] perform all or 
    any of the following functions, namely\:—" 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    lay down policies and principles for 
    making legal services available under the provisions of this Act; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    frame the most effective and economical 
    schemes for the purpose of making legal services available under the 
    provisions of this Act; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    utilise the funds at its disposal and 
    make appropriate allocations of funds to the State Authorities and District 
    Authorities; 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    take necessary steps by way of social 
    justice litigation with regard to consumer protection, environmental 
    protection or any other matter of special concern to the weaker sections, of 
    the society and for this purpose, give training to social workers in legal 
    skills; 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    organise legal aid camps, especially in 
    rural areas, slums or labour colonies with the dual purpose of educating the 
    weaker sections of the society as to their rights as well as encouraging the 
    settlement of disputes through Lok Adalats; 
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    encourage the settlement of disputes by 
    way of negotiations, arbitration and conciliation; 
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    undertake and promote research in the 
    field of legal services with special reference to the need for such services 
    among the poor; 
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>    to do all things necessary for the 
    purpose of ensuring commitment to the fundamental duties of citizens under 
    Part IVA of the Constitution; 
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>    monitor and evaluate implementation of 
    the legal aid programmes at periodic intervals and provide for independent 
    evaluation of programmes and schemes implemented in whole or in part by 
    funds provided under this Act; 
 

2[(j)    
    provide grants-in-aid for specific schemes to various voluntary social 
    service institutions and the State and District Authorities, from out of the 
    amounts placed at its disposal for the implementation of legal services 
    schemes under the provisions of this Act;] 
    1[(j) provide grants-in-aid for specific schemes to 
    various voluntary social service institutions and the State and District 
    Authorities, from out of the amounts placed at its disposal for the 
    implementation of legal services schemes under the provisions of this Act;]" 
 </section><section>
<number>k</number>    develop, in consultation with the Bar 
    Council of India, programmes for clinical legal education and, promote 
    guidance and supervise the establishment and working of legal services 
    clinics in universities, law colleges and other institutions; 
 </section><section>
<number>l</number>    take appropriate measures for spreading 
    legal literacy and legal awareness amongst the people and, in particular, to 
    educate weaker sections of the society about the rights, benefits and 
    privileges guaranteed by social welfare legislations and other enactments as 
    well as administrative programmes and measures; 
 </section><section>
<number>m</number>    make special efforts to enlist the 
    support of voluntary social welfare institutions, working at the grass-root 
    level, particularly among the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled Tribes, 
    women and rural and urban labour; and 
 </section><section>
<number>n</number>    coordinate and monitor the 
    functioning of 
3[State 
    Authorities, District Authorities, Supreme Court Legal Services Committee, 
    High Court Legal Services Committees, Taluk Legal Services Committees and 
    voluntary social service institutions] and other legal services 
    organisations and give general directions for the proper implementation of 
    the legal services programmes.
2[State 
    Authorities, District Authorities, Supreme Court Legal Services Committee, 
    High Court Legal Services Committees, Taluk Legal Services Committees and 
    voluntary social service institutions] and other legal services 
    organisations and give general directions for the proper implementation of 
    the legal services programmes." 
 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Central 
    Authority to work in coordination with other agencies.—In 
    the discharge of its function under this Act, the Central Authority shall, 
    wherever appropriate, act in coordination with other governmental and 
    non-governmental agencies, universities and others engaged in the work of 
    promoting the cause of legal services to the poor. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>6</number> Constitution of 
    State Legal Services Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every State Government shall constitute a body to be called the Legal 
    Services Authority for the State to exercise the powers and perform the 
    functions conferred on, or assigned to, a State Authority under this Act.3[6. 
    Constitution of State Legal Services Authority.—(1) 
    Every State Government shall constitute a body to be called the Legal 
    Services Authority for the State to exercise the powers and perform the 
    functions conferred on, or assigned to, a State Authority under this Act." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A State 
    Authority shall consist of— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the Chief Justice of the High Court who 
    shall be the Patron-in-Chief; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    a serving or retired Judge of the High 
    Court, to be nominated by the Governor, in consultation with the Chief 
    Justice of the High Court, who shall be the Executive Chairman; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    such number of other members, 
    possessing such experience and qualifications as may be prescribed by the 
    State Government, to be nominated by that Government in consultation with 
    the Chief Justice of the High Court. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The State 
    Government shall, in consultation with the Chief Justice of the High Court, 
    appoint a person belonging to the State Higher Judicial Service, not lower 
    in rank than that of a District Judge, as the Member-Secretary of the State 
    Authority, to exercise such powers and perform such duties under the 
    Executive Chairman of the State Authority as may be prescribed by that 
    Government or as may be assigned to him by the Executive Chairman of that 
    Authority: 
 
Provided that 
    a person functioning as Secretary of a State Legal Aid and Advice Board 
    immediately before the date of constitution of the State Authority may be 
    appointed as Member-Secretary of that Authority, even if he is not qualified 
    to be appointed as such under this sub-section, for a period not exceeding 
    five years. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The terms 
    of Office and other conditions relating thereto, of members and the 
    Member-Secretary of the State Authority shall be such as may be prescribed 
    by the State Government in consultation with the Chief Justice of the High 
    Court. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The State 
    Authority may appoint such number of officers and other employees as may be 
    prescribed by the State Government, in consultation with the Chief Justice 
    of the High Court, for the efficient discharge of its functions under this 
    Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    officers and other employees of the State Authority shall be entitled to 
    such salary and allowances and shall be subject to such other conditions of 
    service as may be prescribed by the State Government in consultation with 
    the Chief Justice of the High Court. 
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The 
    administrative expenses of the State Authority, including the salaries, 
    allowances and pensions payable to the Member-Secretary, officers and other 
    employees of the State Authority shall be defrayed out of the Consolidated 
    Fund of the State. 
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> All orders 
    and decisions of the State Authority shall be authenticated by the 
    Member-Secretary or any other officer of the State Authority duly authorised 
    by the Executive Chairman of the State Authority. 
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> No act or 
    proceeding of a State Authority shall be invalid merely on the ground of the 
    existence of any vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution of, the State 
    Authority.] 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Functions of the State Authority—
<section><number>1</number> 
    It shall be the duty of the State Authority to give effect to the policy and 
    directions of the Central Authority. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Without 
    prejudice to the generality of the functions referred to in sub-section (1), 
    the State Authority shall perform all or any of the following functions, 
    namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    give legal service to persons who 
    satisfy the criteria laid down under this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    conduct 
1[Lok 
    Adalats; including Lok Adalats for High Court cases];
1[Lok 
    Adalats; including Lok Adalats for High Court cases];" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    undertake preventive and strategic 
    legal aid programmes; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    perform such other functions as 
    the State Authority may, in consultation with the 
2[Central 
    Authority,] fix by regulations.
 
 






 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>1[<number>8</number> State Authority to act in 
      coordination with other agencies etc., and be subject to directions given 
      by Central Authority.—In the discharge of its functions the State 
      Authority shall appropriately act in coordination with other governmental 
      agencies, non-governmental voluntary social service institutions, 
      universities and other bodies engaged in the work of promoting the cause 
      of legal services to the poor and shall also be guided by such directions 
      as the Central Authority may give to it in writing.3[8. 
    State Authority to act in coordination with other agencies etc., and be 
    subject to directions given by Central Authority.—In 
    the discharge of its functions the State Authority shall appropriately act 
    in coordination with other governmental agencies, non-governmental voluntary 
    social service institutions, universities and other bodies engaged in the 
    work of promoting the cause of legal services to the poor and shall also be 
    guided by such directions as the Central Authority may give to it in 
    writing." 
  





 
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8A</number> High 
    Court Legal Services Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Authority shall constitute a Committee to be called the High Court 
    Legal Services Committee for every High Court, for the purpose of exercising 
    such powers and performing such functions as may be determined by 
    regulations made by the State Authority. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Committee shall consist of— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    a sitting Judge of the High Court who 
    shall be the Chairman; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    such number of other members possessing 
    such experience and qualifications as may be determined by regulations made 
    by the State Authority, 
 
to be nominated by the Chief Justice of the 
    High Court.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The Chief 
    Justice of the High Court shall appoint a Secretary to the Committee 
    possessing such experience and qualifications as may be prescribed by the 
    StateGovernment. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The terms 
    of office and other conditions relating thereto, of the members and 
    Secretary of the Committee shall be such as may be determined by regulations 
    made by the State Authority. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Committee may appoint such number of officers and other employees as may be 
    prescribed by the State Government in consultation with the Chief Justice of 
    the High Court for the efficient discharge of its functions. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    officers and other employees of the Committee shall be entitled to such 
    salary and allowances and shall be subject to such other conditions of 
    service as may be prescribed by the State Government in consultation with 
    the Chief Justice of the High Court.] 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>9</number> District Legal 
    Services Authority—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government shall, in consultation with the Chief Justice of the 
    High Court, constitute a body to be called the District Legal Services 
    Authority for every district in the State to exercise the powers and perform 
    the functions conferred on, or assigned to, the District Authority under 
    this Act.1[9. 
    District Legal Services Authority—(1) 
    The State Government shall, in consultation with the Chief Justice of the 
    High Court, constitute a body to be called the District Legal Services 
    Authority for every district in the State to exercise the powers and perform 
    the functions conferred on, or assigned to, the District Authority under 
    this Act." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A District 
    Authority shall consist of— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the District Judge who shall be its 
    Chairman; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    such number of other members, 
    possessing such experience and qualifications, as may be prescribed by the 
    State Government, to be nominated by that Government in consultation with 
    the Chief Justice of the High Court. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The State 
    Authority shall, in consultation with the Chairman of the District 
    Authority, appoint a person belonging to the State Judicial Service not 
    lower in rank than that of a Subordinate Judge or Civil Judge posted at the 
    seat of the District Judiciary as Secretary of the District Authority to 
    exercise such powers and perform such duties under Chairman of that 
    Committee as may be assigned to him by such Chairman. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The terms 
    of office and other conditions relating thereto, of members and Secretary of 
    the District Authority shall be such as may be determined by regulations 
    made by the State Authority in consultation with the Chief Justice of the 
    High Court. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    District Authority may appoint such number of officers and other employees 
    as may be prescribed by the State Government in consultation with the Chief 
    Justice of the High Court for the efficient discharge of its functions. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    officers and other employees of the District Authority shall be entitled to 
    such salary and allowances and shall be subject to such other conditions of 
    service as may be prescribed by the State Government in consultation with 
    the Chief Justice of the High Court. 
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The 
    administrative expenses of every District Authority, including the salaries, 
    allowances and pensions payable to the Secretary, officers and other 
    employees of the District Authority shall be defrayed out of the 
    Consolidated Fund of the State. 
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> All orders 
    and decisions of the District Authority shall be authenticated by the 
    Secretary or by any other officer of the District Authority duly authorised 
    by the Chairman of that Authority. 
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> No act or 
    proceeding of a District Authority shall be invalid merely on the ground of 
    the existence of any vacancy in, or any defect in the Constitution of, the 
    District Authority.] 
 
 

 
 

 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Functions of District Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    It shall be the duty of every District Authority to perform such of the 
    functions of the State Authority in the District as may be delegated to it 
    from time to time by the State Authority. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Without 
    prejudice to the generality of the functions referred to in sub-section (1), 
    the District Authority may perform all or any of the following functions, 
    namely:— 
 

1[(a)    
    co-ordinate the activities of the Taluk Legal Services Committee and other 
    Legal Services in the District;]
 <subsection>
<number>b</number>    organise Lok Adalats within the 
    District; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    perform such other functions as 
    the State Authority may 
2[***] 
    fix by regulations.
2[***] 
    fix by regulations." 
 
 
 
 





 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>11</number> District Authority to act in coordination 
      with other agencies and be subject to directions given by the Central 
      Authority, etc.—In the 
      discharge of its functions under this Act, the District Authority shall, 
      wherever appropriate, act in coordination with other governmental and 
      non-governmental institutions, universities and others engaged in the work 
      of promoting the cause of legal services to the poor and shall also be 
      guided by such directions as the Central Authority or the State Authority 
      may give to it in writing. 
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>11A</number> Taluk Legal 
    Services Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Authority may constitute a Committee, to be called the Taluk Legal 
    Services Committee, for each taluk or mandal or for group of taluks or 
    mandals.3[11A. 
    Taluk Legal Services Committee.—(1) 
    The State Authority may constitute a Committee, to be called the Taluk Legal 
    Services Committee, for each taluk or mandal or for group of taluks or 
    mandals." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Committee shall consist of— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    The 
2[Senior-most 
    Judicial Officer] operating within the jurisdiction of the Committee who 
    shall be the ex officio Chairman; and4[Senior-most 
    Judicial Officer] operating within the jurisdiction of the Committee who 
    shall be the ex officio Chairman; and" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    such number of other members, 
    possessing such experience and qualifications, as may be prescribed by the 
    State Government, to be nominated by that Government in consultation with 
    the Chief Justice of the High Court. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Committee may appoint such number of officers and other employees as may be 
    prescribed by the State Government in consultation with the Chief Justice of 
    the High Court for the efficient discharge of its functions. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    officers and other employees of the Committee shall be entitled to such 
    salary and allowances and shall be subject to such other conditions of 
    service as may be prescribed by the State Government in consultation with 
    the Chief Justice of the High Court. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    administrative expenses of the Committee shall be defrayed out of the 
    District Legal Aid Fund by the District Authority.]
 
 






 



</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>11B</number> Functions of Taluk Legal Services Committee. </title>—The Taluk Legal Services Committee may perform all or any of the following functions, namely:— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> coordinate the activities of legal services in the taluk; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> organise Lok Adalats within the taluk; and 
 </section><section><number>c</number> perform such other functions as the District Authority may assign to it.]
</section>


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Criteria for giving legal services.—Every 
    person who has to file or defend a case shall be entitled to legal services 
    under this Act if that person, is— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    a member of a Scheduled Caste or 
    Scheduled Tribe; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    a victim of trafficking in human beings 
    or beggar as referred to in Article 23 of the Constitution;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    a women or a child; 
 

1[(d) 
       a person with disability as defined in clause (i) of section 2 of the 
    Persons with Disabilities (Equal Opportunities, Protection of Rights and 
    Full Participation) Act, 1995 (1 of 1996);] 
    1[(d) a person with disability as defined in clause 
    (i) of section 2 of the Persons with Disabilities (Equal Opportunities, 
    Protection of Rights and Full Participation) Act, 1995 (1 of 1996);]" 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    a person under circumstances of 
    undeserved want such as being a victim of a mass disaster, ethnic violence, 
    caste atrocity, flood, drought, earthquake or industrial disaster; or 
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    an industrial workman; or 
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    in custody, including custody in a 
    protective home within the meaning of clause (g) of section 2 of the Immoral 
    Traffic (Prevention) Act, 1956 (104 of 1956) or in a juvenile home within 
    the meaning of clause (j) of section 2 of the Juvenile Justice Act, 1986 (53 
    of 1986) or in a psychiatric hospital or psychiatric nursing home within the 
    meaning of clause (g) of section 2 of the Mental Health Act, 1987 (14 of 
    1987); or  
 

2[(h)    
    in receipt of annual income less than rupees nine thousand or such other 
    higher amount as may be prescribed by the State Government, if the case is 
    before a court other than the Supreme Court, and less than rupees twelve 
    thousand or such other higher amount as may be prescribed by the Central 
    Government, if the case is before the Supreme Court.] 2[(h) 
    in receipt of annual income less than rupees nine thousand or such other 
    higher amount as may be prescribed by the State Government, if the case is 
    before a court other than the Supreme Court, and less than rupees twelve 
    thousand or such other higher amount as may be prescribed by the Central 
    Government, if the case is before the Supreme Court.]" 
 
 
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Entitlement to legal services.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Persons who satisfy all or any of the criteria specified in section 12 shall 
    be entitled to receive legal services provided that the concerned Authority 
    is satisfied that such person has a prima facie case to prosecute or 
    to defend. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An 
    affidavit made by a person as to his income may be regarded as sufficient 
    for making him eligible to the entitlement of legal services under this Act 
    unless the concerned Authority has reason to disbelieve such affidavit. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> Grants 
    by Central Government.—The 
    Central Government shall, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law 
    in this behalf pay to the Central Authority, by way of grants, such sums of 
    money as the Central Government may think fit for being utilised for the 
    purposes of this Act. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    National Legal Aid Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Central Authority shall establish a fund to be called the National Legal Aid 
    Fund and there shall be credited thereto— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    all sums of money given as grants by 
    the Central Government under section 14;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    any grants or donations that may be 
    made to the Central Authority by any other person for the purposes of this 
    Act; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    any amount received by the Central 
    Authority under the orders of any court or from any other source. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    National Legal Aid Fund shall be applied for meeting— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the cost of legal services provided 
    under this Act including grants made to State Authorities; 
 

1[(b)    
    the cost of legal services provided by the Supreme Court Legal Services 
    Committee; 
    1[(b) the cost of legal services provided by the 
    Supreme Court Legal Services Committee;" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    any other expenses which are required 
    to be met by the Central Authority.] 
 
 




 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> State 
    Legal Aid Fund.—A State Authority 
    shall establish a fund to be called the State Legal Aid Fund and there shall 
    be credited thereto— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    all sums of money paid to it or any 
    grants made by the Central Authority for the purposes of this Act; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    any grants or donations that may be 
    made to the State Authority by the State Government or by any person for the 
    purposes of this Act; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    any other amount received by the State 
    Authority under the orders of any court or from any other source. 
 <subsection>
<number>2</number> A State 
    Legal Aid Fund shall be applied for meeting— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>a</number>    the cost of functions referred to in 
    section 7; 
 

1[(b)    
    the cost of legal services provided by the High Court Legal Services 
    Committees; 
    2[(b) the cost of legal services provided by the High 
    Court Legal Services Committees;" 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>c</number>    any other expenses which are required 
    to be met by the State Authority.] 
 
 
 
 




 



</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    District Legal Aid Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every District Authority shall establish a fund to be called the District 
    Legal Aid Fund and there shall be credited thereto— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    all sums of money paid or any grants 
    made by the State Authority to the District Authority for the purposes of 
    this Act; 
 

1[(b)    
    any grants or donations that may be made to the District Authority by any 
    person, with the prior approval of the State Authority, for the purposes of 
    this Act; 
    3[(b) any grants or donations that may be made to the 
    District Authority by any person, with the prior approval of the State 
    Authority, for the purposes of this Act;" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    any other amount received by the 
    District Authority under the orders of any court or from any other source.] 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    District Legal Aid Fund shall be applied for meeting— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the cost of functions referred to 
    in section 10 
2[and 
    11B];
1[and 
    11B];" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    any other expenses which are required 
    to be met by the District Authority. 
 
 






 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Accounts and audit.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Central Authority, State Authority or the District Authority (hereinafter 
    referred to in this section as ‘the Authority’), as the case may be, shall 
    maintain proper accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual 
    statement of accounts including the income and expenditure account and the 
    balance-sheet in such form and in such manner as may be prescribed by the 
    Central Government in consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor-General 
    of India. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    accounts of the Authorities shall be audited by the Comptroller and 
    Auditor-General of India at such intervals as may be specified by him and 
    any expenditure incurred in connection with such audit shall be payable by 
    the Authority concerned to the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Comptroller and Auditor-General of India and any other person appointed by 
    him in connection with the auditing of the accounts of an Authority under 
    this Act shall have the same rights and privileges and authority in 
    connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India 
    has in connection with the auditing of the Government accounts and, in 
    particular, shall have the right to demand the production of books, 
    accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and to inspect 
    any of the offices of the Authorities under this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    accounts of the Authorities, as certified by the Comptroller and 
    Auditor-General of India or any other person appointed by him in this behalf 
    together with the audit report thereon, shall be forwarded annually by the 
    Authorities to the Central Government or the State Governments as the case 
    may be. 
 


    1[(5) The Central 
    Government shall cause the accounts and the audit report received by it 
    under sub-section (4) to be laid, as soon as may be after they are received, 
    before each House of Parliament. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The State 
    Government shall cause the accounts and the audit report received by it 
    under sub-section (4) to be laid, as soon as may be after they are received, 
    before the State Legislature.] 
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>19</number> Organisation of 
    Lok Adalats.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every State Authority or District Authority or the Supreme Court Legal 
    Services Committee or every High Court Legal Services Committee or, as the 
    case may be, Taluk Legal Services Committee may organise Lok Adalats at such 
    intervals and places and for exercising such jurisdiction and for such areas 
    as it thinks fit.3[19. 
    Organisation of Lok Adalats.—(1) 
    Every State Authority or District Authority or the Supreme Court Legal 
    Services Committee or every High Court Legal Services Committee or, as the 
    case may be, Taluk Legal Services Committee may organise Lok Adalats at such 
    intervals and places and for exercising such jurisdiction and for such areas 
    as it thinks fit." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every Lok 
    Adalat organised for an area shall consist of such number of— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    serving or retired judicial officers; 
    and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    other persons, 
 
of the area as may be specified by the State 
    Authority or the District Authority or the Supreme Court Legal Services 
    Committee or the High Court Legal Services Committee, or as the case may be, 
    the Taluk Legal Services Committee, organising such Lok Adalat.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    experience and qualifications of other persons referred to in clause (b) of 
    sub-section (2) for Lok Adalats organised by the Supreme Court Legal 
    Services Committee shall be such as may be prescribed by the Central 
    Government in consultation with the Chief Justice of India. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    experience and qualifications of other persons referred to in clause (b) of 
    sub-section (2) for Lok Adalats other than referred to in sub-section (3) 
    shall be such as may be prescribed by the State Government in consultation 
    with the Chief Justice of the High Court. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> A Lok 
    Adalat shall have jurisdiction to determine and to arrive at a compromise or 
    settlement between the parties to a dispute in respect of— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    any case pending before; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    any matter which is falling within the 
    jurisdiction of, and is not brought before, 
 
any court for which the Lok Adalat is 
    organised:
 
Provided that 
    the Lok Adalat shall have no jurisdiction in respect of any case or matter 
    relating to an offence not compoundable under any law.] 
 





 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>20</number> Cognizance of 
    cases by Lok Adalats.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where in any case referred to in clause (i) of sub-section (5) of section 
    19—1[20. 
    Cognizance of cases by Lok Adalats.—(1) 
    Where in any case referred to in clause (i) of sub-section (5) of section 
    19—" 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>  (a)    the parties thereof agree; or 
 <subsubsection>
<number>b</number>    one of the parties thereof makes an 
    application to the court, 
 
for referring the case to the Lok Adalat for 
    settlement and if such court is prima facie satisfied that there are 
    chances of such settlement; or 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    the court is satisfied that the matter 
    is an appropriate one to be taken cognizance of by the Lok Adalat, 
 
the court shall refer the case to the Lok 
    Adalat:
 
Provided that 
    no case shall be referred to the Lok Adalat under sub-clause (b) of clause 
    (i) or clause (ii) by such court except after giving a reasonable 
    opportunity of being heard to the parties. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being in 
    force, the Authority or Committee organising the Lok Adalat under 
    sub-section (1) of section 19 may, on receipt of an application from any one 
    of the parties to any matter referred to in clause (ii) of sub-section (5) 
    of section 19 that such matter needs to be determined by a Lok Adalat, refer 
    such matter to the Lok Adalat, for determination: 
 
Provided that 
    no matter shall be referred to the Lok Adalat except after giving a 
    reasonable opportunity of being heard to the other party. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where any 
    case is referred to a Lok Adalat under sub-section (1) or where a reference 
    has been made to it under sub-section (2), the Lok Adalat shall proceed to 
    dispose of the case or matter and arrive at a compromise or settlement 
    between the parties. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every Lok 
    Adalat shall, while determining any reference before it under this Act, act 
    with utmost expedition to arrive at a compromise or settlement between the 
    parties and shall be guided by the principles of justice, equity, fair play 
    and other legal principles. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where no 
    award is made by the Lok Adalat on the ground that no compromise or 
    settlement could be arrived at between the parties, the record of the case 
    shall be returned by it to the court, from which the reference has been 
    received under sub-section (1) for disposal in accordance with law. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Where no 
    award is made by the Lok Adalat on the ground that no compromise or 
    settlement could be arrived at between the parties, in a matter referred to 
    in sub-section (2), that Lok Adalat shall advice the parties to seek remedy 
    in a court. 
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Where the 
    record of the case is returned under sub-section (5) to the court, such 
    court shall proceed to deal with such case from the stage which was reached 
    before such reference under sub-section (1).] 
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
 <number>21</number> 
    Award of Lok Adalat.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every award of the Lok Adalat shall be deemed to be a decree of a civil 
    court or, as the case may be, an order of any other court and where a 
    compromise or settlement has been arrived at, by a Lok Adalat in a case 
    referred to it under sub-section (1) of section 20, the court-free paid in 
    such case shall be refunded in the manner provided under the Court Fees Act, 
    1870 (7 of 1870).]—1[(1) 
    Every award of the Lok Adalat shall be deemed to be a decree of a civil 
    court or, as the case may be, an order of any other court and where a 
    compromise or settlement has been arrived at, by a Lok Adalat in a case 
    referred to it under sub-section (1) of section 20, the court-free paid in 
    such case shall be refunded in the manner provided under the Court Fees Act, 
    1870 (7 of 1870).]" 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    award made by a Lok Adalat shall be final and binding on all the parties to 
    the dispute, and no appeal shall lie to any court against the award. 
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Powers of 

    1[Lok Adalat or 
    Permanent Lok Adalat].—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The 

    1[Lok Adalat or 
    Permanent Lok Adalat] shall, for the purposes of holding any determination 
    under this Act, have the same powers as are vested in a civil court under 
    the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) while trying a suit in respect 
    of the following matters, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the summoning and enforcing the 
    attendance of any witness and examining him on oath; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the discovery and production of any 
    document; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the reception of evidence on 
    affidavits; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the requisitioning of any public record 
    or document or copy of such record or document from any court or office; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    such other matters as may be 
    prescribed. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Without prejudice to the generality of the powers contained in sub-section 
    (1), every 

    1[Lok Adalat or 
    Permanent Lok Adalat] shall have the requisite powers to specify its own 
    procedure for the determination of any dispute coming before it. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All 
    proceedings before a 

    1[Lok Adalat or 
    Permanent Lok Adalat] shall be deemed to be judicial proceedings within the 
    meaning of sections 193, 219 and 228 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860) 
    and every 

    1[Lok Adalat or 
    Permanent Lok Adalat] shall be deemed to be a civil court for the purpose of 
    section 195 and Chapter XXVI of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 
    1974).  
 
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
*<number>22A</number> 
    Definitions.—In this Chapter and 
    for the purposes of section 22 and 23, unless the context otherwise 
    requires,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    "Permanent Lok Adalat" means a 
    Permanent Lok Adalat established under sub-section (1) of section 22B. 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    "public utility service" means any— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    transport service for the carriage of 
    passengers or goods by air, road or water; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    postal, telegraph or telephone 
    service; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    supply of power, light or water to 
    the public by any establishment; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    system of public conservancy or 
    sanitation; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>    service in hospital or dispensary; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vi</number>    insurance service, 
 
and includes any service which the Central 
    Government or the State Government, as the case may be, may, in the public 
    interest, by notification, declare to be a public utility service for the 
    purposes of this Chapter. 



 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
*<number>22B</number> 
    Establishment of Permanent Lok Adalats.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in section 19, the Central Authority or, 
    as the case may be, every State Authority shall, by notification, establish 
    Permanent Lok Adalats at such places and for exercising such jurisdiction in 
    respect of one or more public utility services and for such areas as may be 
    specified in the notification. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    Permanent Lok Adalat established for an area notified under sub-section (1) 
    shall consist of—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    a person who is, or has been, a 
    district judge or additional district judge or has held judicial office 
    higher in rank than that of a district judge, shall be the Chairman of the 
    Permanent Lok Adalat; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    two other persons having adequate 
    experience in public utility service to be nominated by the Central 
    Government or, as the case may be, the State Government on the 
    recommendation of the Central Authority or, as the case may be, the State 
    Authority, 
 
appointed by the Central Authority or, as the 
    case may be, the State Authority, establishing such Permanent Lok Adalat and 
    the other terms and conditions of the appointment of the Chairman and other 
    persons referred to in clause (b) shall be such as may be prescribed by the 
    Central Government. 



 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
*<number>22C</number> 
    Cognizance of cases by Permanent Lok Adalat.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any party to a dispute may, before the dispute is brought before any court, 
    make an application to the Permanent Lok Adalat for the settlement of 
    dispute: 
 
Provided that 
    the Permanent Lok Adalat shall not have jurisdiction in respect of any 
    matter relating to an offence not compoundable under any law: 
 
Provided 
    further that the Permanent Lok Adalat shall also not have jurisdiction in 
    the matter where the value of the property in dispute exceeds ten lakh 
    rupees: 
 
Provided also 
    that the Central Government, may, by notification, increase the limit of ten 
    lakh rupees specified in the second proviso in consultation with the Central 
    Authority. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> After an 
    application is made under sub-section (1) to the Permanent Lok Adalat, no 
    party to that application shall invoke jurisdiction of any court in the same 
    dispute. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where an 
    application is made to a Permanent Lok Adalat under sub-section (1), it—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    shall direct each party to the 
    application to file before it a written statement, stating therein the facts 
    and nature of dispute under the application points or issues in such dispute 
    and grounds relied in support of, or in opposition to, such points or 
    issues, as the case may be, and such party may supplement such statement 
    with any document and other evidence which such party deems appropriate in 
    proof of such facts and grounds and shall send a copy of such statement 
    together with a copy of such document and other evidence, if any, to each of 
    the parties to the application; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    may require any party to the 
    application to file additional statement before it at any stage of the 
    conciliation proceedings; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    shall communicate any document or 
    statement received by it from any party to the application to the other 
    party, to enable such other party to present reply thereto. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> When 
    statement, additional statement and reply, if any, have been filed under 
    sub-section (3), to the satisfaction of the Permanent Lok Adalat, it shall 
    conduct conciliation proceedings between the parties to the application in 
    such manner as it thinks appropriate taking into account the circumstances 
    of the dispute. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Permanent Lok Adalat shall, during conduct of conciliation proceedings under 
    sub-section (4), assist the parties in their attempt to reach an amicable 
    settlement of the dispute in an independent and impartial manner. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> It shall 
    be the duty of every party to the application to cooperate in good faith 
    with the Permanent Lok Adalat in conciliation of the dispute relating to the 
    application and to comply with the direction of the Permanent Lok Adalat to 
    produce evidence and other related documents before it. 
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> When a 
    Permanent Lok Adalat, in the aforesaid conciliation proceedings, is of 
    opinion that there exist elements of settlement in such proceedings which 
    may be acceptable to the parties, it may formulate the terms of a possible 
    settlement of the dispute and give to the parties concerned for their 
    observations and in case the parties reach at an agreement on the settlement 
    of the dispute, they shall sign the settlement agreement and the Permanent 
    Lok Adalat shall pass an award in terms thereof and furnish a copy of the 
    same to each of the parties concerned. 
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> Where the 
    parties fail to reach at an agreement under sub-section (7), the Permanent 
    Lok Adalat shall, if the dispute does not relate to any offence, decide the 
    dispute.  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
*<number>22D</number> 
    Procedure of Permanent Lok Adalat.—The 
    Permanent Lok Adalat shall, while conducting conciliation proceedings or 
    deciding a dispute on merit under this Act, be guided by the principles of 
    natural justice, objectivity, fair play, equity and other principles of 
    justice, and shall not be bound by the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 
    1908) and the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872).  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
*<number>22E</number> Award 
    of Permanent Lok Adalat to be final.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every award of the Permanent Lok Adalat under this Act made either on merit 
    or in terms of a settlement agreement shall be final and binding on all the 
    parties thereto and on persons claiming under them.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    award of the Permanent Lok Adalat under this Act shall be deemed to be a 
    decree of a civil court. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The award 
    made by the Permanent Lok Adalat under this Act shall be by a majority of 
    the persons constituting the Permanent Lok Adalat. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every 
    award made by the Permanent Lok Adalat under this Act shall be final and 
    shall not be called in question in any original suit, application or 
    execution proceeding. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Permanent Lok Adalat may transmit any award made by it to a civil court 
    having local jurisdiction and such civil court shall execute the order as if 
    it were a decree made by that court. 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>23</number> Members and 
    staff of Authorities, Committees and Lok Adalats to be public servants.—The 
    members including Member-Secretary or, as the case may be, Secretary of 
    Central Authority, the State Authorities, the District Authorities, the 
    Supreme Court Legal Services Committee, High Court Legal Services 
    Committees, Taluk Legal Services Committees and officers and other employees 
    of such Authorities, Committees and the 

    2[members of the Lok 
    Adalats or persons constituting Permanent Lok Adalats] shall be deemed to be 
    public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code 
    (45 of 1860).]
 

 
 





 



</article> 

  
  
 <title></title>
 <article><title><footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[<number>24</number> Protection of 
action taken in good faith. </title>—No suit, 
prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> the Central Government or the State Government; 
  
 </section><section><number>b</number> the Patron-in-Chief, Executive Chairman, 
  members of, Members-Secretary or officers or other employees of the Central 
  Authority; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> Patron-in-Chief, Executive Chairman, Member, 
  Member-Secretary or officers or other employees of the State Authority; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> Chairman, Secretary, members or officers or 
  other employees of the Supreme Court Legal Services Committee, High Court 
  Legal Services Committees, Taluk Legal Services Committees or the District 
  Authority; or 
 </section><section><number>e</number> any other person authorised by any of the 
  Patron-in-Chief, Executive Chairman, Chairman, members, Member-Secretary 
  referred to in sub-clauses (b) to (d), </section>
 for anything which is in good faith done or intended 
to be done under the provisions of this Act or any rule or regulation made 
thereunder.] 

</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>25</number> Act to have overriding 
      effect.—The provisions of this 
      Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith 
      contained in any other law for the time being in force or in any 
      instrument having effect by virtue of any law other than this Act. 
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>26</number> Power 
    to remove difficulties.—
<section><number>1</number> If 
    any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provision of this Act, the 
    Central Government may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make 
    such provisions not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act as appear 
    to it to be necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty: 
 
Provided that 
    no such order shall be made after the expiry of a period of two years from 
    the date on which this Act receives the assent of the President. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    order made under this section shall, as soon as may be after it is made, be 
    laid before each House of Parliament. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>27</number> Power of Central 
    Government to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government in consultation with the Chief Justice of India may, 
    by notification, make rules to carry out the provisions of this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the number, experience and 
    qualifications of other members of the Central Authority under clause (c) of 
    sub-section (2) of section 3; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the experience and qualifications of 
    the Member-Secretary of the Central Authority and his powers and functions 
    under sub-section (3) of section 3; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the terms of office and other 
    conditions relating thereto, of members and Member-Secretary of the Central 
    Authority under sub-section (4) of section 3; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the number of officers and other 
    employees of the Central Authority under sub-section (5) of section 3; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the conditions of service and the 
    salary and allowances of officers and other employees of the Central 
    Authority under sub-section (6) of section 3;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    the number, experience and 
    qualifications of members of the Supreme Court Legal Services Committee 
    under clause (b) of sub-section (2) of section 3A; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    the experience and qualifications of 
    Secretary of the Supreme Court Legal Services Committee under sub-section 
    (3) of section 3A; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    the number of officers and other 
    employees of the Supreme Court Legal Services Committee under sub-section 
    (5) of section 3A and the conditions of service and the salary and 
    allowances payable to them under sub-section (6) of that section; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    the upper limit of annual income of a 
    person entitling him to legal services under clause (h) of section 12, if 
    the case is before the Supreme Court; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>    the manner in which the accounts of the 
    Central Authority, the State Authority or the District Authority shall be 
    maintained under section 18; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>    the experience and qualifications of 
    other persons of the Lok Adalats organised by the Supreme Court Legal 
    Services Committee specified in sub-section (3) of section 19; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>    other matters under clause (e) of 
    sub-section (1) of section 22; 
 

2[(la)    
    the other terms and conditions of appointment of the Chairman and other 
    persons under sub-section (2) of section 22B;] 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number>    any other matter which is to be, or may 
    be prescribed. ]
 
 
 
 





 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[<number>28</number> Power 
    of State Government to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government in consultation with the Chief Justice of the High 
    Court may, by notification, make rules to carry out the provisions of this 
    Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing powers, 
    such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>
              <number>a</number>    the number, experience 
    and qualifications of other members of the State Authority under clause (c) 
    of sub-section (2) of section 6; 
 </subsection><subsection>
              <number>b</number>    the powers and functions 
    of the Member-Secretary of the State Authority under sub-section (3) of 
    section 6; 
 </subsection><subsection>
              <number>c</number>    the terms of office and 
    other conditions relating thereto, of members and Member-Secretary of the 
    State Authority under sub-section (4) of 
    section 6; 
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>d</number>    the number of officers and 
    other employees of the State Authority under sub-section (5) of section 6; 
 </subsection><subsection>
              <number>e</number>    the conditions of service 
    and the salary and allowances of officers and other employees of the State 
    Authority under sub-section (6) of 
    section 6; 
 </subsection><subsection>
               <number>f</number>    the experience and 
    qualifications of Secretary of the High Court Legal Services Committee under 
    sub-section (3) of section 8A; 
 </subsection><subsection>
              <number>g</number>    the number of officers 
    and other employees of the High Court Legal Services Committee under 
    sub-section (5) of section 8A and the conditions of service and the salary 
    and allowances payable to them under sub-section (6) of that section; 
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>h</number>    the number, experience and 
    qualifications of members of the District Authority under clause (b) of 
    sub-section (2) of section 9; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    the number of officers and other 
    employees of the District Authority under sub-section (5) of section 9; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>    the conditions of service and the 
    salary and allowances of the officers and other employees of the District 
    Authority under sub-section (6) of section 9;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>    the number, experience and 
    qualifications of members of the Taluk Legal Services Committee under clause 
    (b) of sub-section (2) of section 11A; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>    the number of officers and other 
    employees of the Taluk Legal Services Committee under sub-section (3) of 
    section 11A; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number>    the conditions of service and the 
    salary and allowances of officers and other employees of the Taluk Legal 
    Services Committee under sub-section (4) of section 11A; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>n</number>    the upper limit of annual income of a 
    person entitling him to legal services under clause (h) of section 12, if 
    the case is before a court, other than the Supreme Court; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>o</number>    the experience and qualifications of 
    other persons of the Lok Adalats other than referred to in sub-section (4) 
    of section 19; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>p</number>    any other matter which is to be, or may 
    be, prescribed. ] 



 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[<number>29</number> Power 
    of Central Authority to make regulations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Authority may, by notification, make regulations not 
    inconsistent with the provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder, 
    to provide for all matters for which provision is necessary or expedient for 
    the purposes of giving effect to the provisions of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such regulations may provide for all or any of the following matters, 
    namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the powers and functions of the Supreme 
    Court Legal Services Committee under sub-section (1) of section 3A; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the terms of office and other 
    conditions relating thereto, of the members and Secretary of the Supreme 
    Court Legal Services Committee under sub-section (4) of section 3A. ] 



 



</subsection></section></article> 

  
  
 <title></title>
 <article><title><number>29A</number> Power of State Authority to make regulations. </title> —
<section><number>1</number> The State Authority may, by notification, make regulations not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder, to provide for all matters for which provision is necessary or expedient for the purposes of giving effect to the provisions of this Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such regulations may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely: — 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the other functions to be performed by the State Authority under clause (d) of sub-section (2) of section 7; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the powers and functions of the High Court Legal Services Committee under sub-section (1) of section 8A; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the number, experience and qualifications of members of the High Court Legal Services Committee under clause (b) of sub-section (2) of  
    section 8A; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> the terms of office and other conditions relating thereto, of the members and Secretary of the High Court Legal Services Committee under sub-section (4) of section 8A; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> the terms of office and other conditions relating thereto, of the members and Secretary of the District Authority under sub-section (4) of section 9; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> the number, experience and qualifications of members of the High Court Legal Services Committee under clause (b) of sub-section (2) of  
    section 8A; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> other functions to be performed by the District Authority under clause (c) of sub-section (2) of section 10; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> the terms of office and other conditions relating thereto, of members and Secretary of the Taluk Legal Services Committee under sub-section (3) of section 11A.] 
</subsection>
 <title></title>
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>30</number> Laying 
    of rules and regulations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every rule made under this Act by the Central Government and every 
    regulation made by the Central Authority thereunder shall be laid, as soon 
    as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in 
    session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one 
    session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of 
    the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
    aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
    regulation, or both Houses agree that the rule or regulation should not be 
    made, the rule or regulation shall thereafter have effect only in such 
    modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
    such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of 
    anything previously done under that rule or regulation. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every rule 
    made under this Act by a State Government and every regulation made by a 
    State authority thereunder shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is 
    made, before the State Legislature. 
  
  
  
 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 59 of 1994, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 29-10-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Subs. by Act 1 of 
    1996, sec. 74, for clause (d)  (w.e.f. 7-2-1996). tc " 
    1. Subs. by Act 1 of 1996, sec. 74, for clause (d)  (w.e.f. 7-2-1996)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   Subs. by Act 59 of 
    1994, sec. 11, for clause (b) (w.e.f. 29-10-1994). tc 
    " 1. Subs. by Act 59 of 1994, sec. 11, for clause (b) (w.e.f. 29-10-1994)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   Subs. by Act 59 of 
    1994, sec. 12, for clause (b) (w.e.f. 29-10-1994). tc 
    " 2. Subs. by Act 59 of 1994, sec. 12, for clause (b) (w.e.f. 29-10-1994)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>   Subs. by Act 59 of 
    1994, sec. 13, for clause (b) (w.e.f. 29-10-1994). tc 
    " 3. Subs. by Act 59 of 1994, sec. 13, for clause (b) (w.e.f. 29-10-1994)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>   Ins. by Act 59 of 1994, sec. 14 (w.e.f. 29-10-1994). tc 
    " 2. Ins. by Act 59 of 1994, sec. 14 (w.e.f. 29-10-1994)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>   Subs. by Act 59 of 1994, sec. 15, for section 19 (w.e.f. 
    29-10-1994). tc 
    " 3. Subs. by Act 59 of 1994, sec. 15, for section 19 (w.e.f. 29-10-1994)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>   Subs. by Act 59 of 1994, sec. 15, for section 20 (w.e.f. 
    29-10-1994). tc 
    " 1. Subs. by Act 59 of 1994, sec. 15, for section 20 (w.e.f. 29-10-1994)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>   Subs by Act 59 of 1994, sec. 16, for sub-section (1) (w.e.f. 
    29-10-1994). tc 
    " 1. Subs by Act 59 of 1994, sec. 16, for sub-section (1) (w.e.f. 
    29-10-1994)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>   Subs. by Act 37 of 2002, sec. 3, for "Lok Adalat" (w.e.f. 
    11-6-2002). tc 
    " 1. Subs. by Act 37 of 2002, sec. 3, for \"Lok Adalat\" (w.e.f. 
    11-6-2002)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>   Subs. by Act 59 of 1994, sec. 17, for section 23 
    (w.e.f. 
    29-10-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number> Subs. by Act 59 of 1994, sec. 17, for 
sections 23 and 24 (w.e.f. 29-10-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>  Subs. by Act 59 of 1994,  sec. 18, for section 27 
    (w.e.f. 29-10-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>  Subs. by Act 59 of 1994,  sec. 18, for section 
    28 (w.e.f. 29-10-1994).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>  Subs. by Act 59 of 1994,  sec. 18, for section 
    29 (w.e.f. 29-10-1994).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>