<act><tid>688958</tid>
<title>THE WEST BENGAL LEGISLATIVE COUNCIL (ABOLITION) ACT, <year>1969</year>.</title>

ACT NO. 20 OF <year>1969</year>
[ 25th July, <year>1969</year>.]

An Act to provide for the abolition of the Legislative Council of the 
State of West Bengal and for matters supplemental, incidental and 
consequential thereto.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twentieth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:--





<article><tid>1045684</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>1217557</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the West  
Bengal Legislative Council (Abolition) Act, <year>1969</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>226871</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date 1 as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>133470</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-
<section><tid>1623002</tid>
<number>a</number>" appropriate Government" means, as respects a law relating to a 
matter enumerated in List I in the Seventh Schedule to the 
Constitution, the Central Government, and as respects any other law, 
the State Government;

</section>

<section><tid>1046905</tid>
<number>b</number>" article" means an article of the Constitution;

</section>

<section><tid>206262</tid>
<number>c</number>" Council" means the Legislative Council of the State of West 
Bengal;

</section>

<section><tid>1463015</tid>
<number>d</number>" law" includes any enactment, ordinance, regulation, order, 
bye- law, rule, scheme, notification or other instrument having the 
force of law in the whole or any part of the State of West Bengal;

</section>

<section><tid>1612099</tid>
<number>e</number>" Legislative Assembly" means the Legislative Assembly of the State 
of West Bengal.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1944156</tid>
<number> 3</number> Abolition of the Council.-
<section><tid>446196</tid>
<number>1</number>The Legislative Council of the State  
of West Bengal is hereby abolished.

</section>

<section><tid>1333307</tid>
<number>2</number>On the abolition of the Council, every member thereof shall cease 
to be such member.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>891024</tid>
<number> 4</number> Amendment of article 168.- In sub- clause (a) of clause
<section><tid>992474</tid>
<number>1</number>of  
article 168, for the words" Uttar Pradesh and West Bengal", the words 
" and Uttar Pradesh" shall be substituted. 1. 1st August, <year>1969</year>: vide 
Notifn. No. G. S. R. 1791, dated 28th July, <year>1969</year>, see Gazette of 
India, <year>1969</year>, Extraordinary, Pt. II, Sec. 3 (i), p. 549.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>216843</tid>
<number> 5</number> Amendment of Act 43 of <year>1950</year>.- In the Representation of the People 
Act, <year>1950</year>,-
<section><tid>661561</tid>
<number>a</number>in the Third Schedule, entry No. 9 relating to West Bengal shall 
be omitted;

</section>

<section><tid>1885604</tid>
<number>b</number>in the Fourth Schedule, the heading" West Bengal" and the entries 
thereunder shall be omitted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>245177</tid>
<number>6</number>Repeal of Delimitation of Council Constituencies (West Bengal) 
Order, <year>1951</year>.- The Delimitation of Council Constituencies (West Bengal) 
Order, <year>1951</year>, is hereby repealed.


</article>



<article><tid>1216750</tid>
<number> 7</number> Provision as to pending Bills.-
<section><tid>1242377</tid>
<number>1</number>A Bill pending in the Council  
immediately before the commencement of this Act which has not been 
passed by the Legislative Assembly shall lapse on the abolition of the 
Council.

</section>

<section><tid>1236931</tid>
<number>2</number>A Bill pending in the Council immediately before the commencement 
of this Act which has been passed by the Legislative Assembly shall 
not lapse on the abolition of the Council, but on such abolition shall 
be deemed to have been passed before such com encement by both Houses 
of the Legislature of the State of West Bengal in the form in which it 
was passed by the Legislative Assembly.

</section>

<section><tid>1912383</tid>
<number>3</number>If a Bill which having been passed by the Legislative Assembly is, 
before the commencement of this Act, either rejected by the Council or 
passed by the Council with amendments, the legislative Assembly may, 
after such commencement, pass the Bill aga n with or without such 
amendments, if any, as have been made by the Council and the Bill so 
passed shall be deemed to be a Bill introduced in and passed by the 
Legislative Assembly after the commencement of this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1364286</tid>
<number>8</number>Power to adapt laws.- The appropriate Government may, before the 
expiration of one year from the commencement of this Act, by order, 
make such adaptations and modifications of any law made before such 
commencement, whether by way of repeal or amendment as may be 
necessary or expedient in consequence of the abolition of the Council 
under section 3, and thereupon every such law shall have effect 
subject to the adaptations and modifications so made.


</article>



<article><tid>9537</tid>
<number>9</number>Power to construe laws.- Notwithstanding that no provision or 
insufficient provision has been made under section 8 for the 
adaptation or modification of a law made before the commencement of 
this Act, any court, tribunal or authority required or empowe ed to 
enforce such law may construe the law in such manner, without 
affecting the substance, as may be necessary or proper on account of 
the abolition of the Council, in regard to the matter before the 
court, tribunal or authority.

</article>



 </act>