<act><title>THE ENERGY CONSERVATION ACT, 2001 </title> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.- </title>
<section><number>1</number> This Act may be called the Energy Conservation Act, 2001. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> It shall come into force on such date 1 as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint; and different dates may be appointed for different provisions of this Act and any reference in any such provision to the commencement of this Act shall be construed as a reference to the coming into force of that provision. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>-In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,- 
 
 <section><number>a</number> "accredited energy auditor" means <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[an energy auditor accredited in accordance with the provisions of ] clause (p) of sub-section (2) of  
    section 13; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> "Appellate Tribunal" means the Appellate Tribunal for Energy Conservation <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[referred to in section 30]; 
 </section><section><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>c</number> "building" means any structure or erection or part of structure or erection after the rules relating to energy conservation building codes have been notified under clause (p) of section 14 and clause (a) of section 15 and includes any existing structure or erection or part of structure or erection, which is having a connected load of 100 kilowatt (kw) or contract demand of 120 Kilo-volt Ampere (kVa) and above and is used or intended to be used for commercial purposes;] 
 </section><section><number>d</number> "Bureau" means the Bureau of Energy Efficiency established under sub-section (1) of section 3; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> "Chairperson" means the Chairperson of the Governing Council; 
 </section><section><number>f</number> "designated agency" means any agency designated under clause (d) of section 15; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> "designated consumer" means any consumer specified under clause (e) of section 14; 
 </section><section><number>h</number> "energy" means any form of energy derived from fossil fuels, nuclear substances or materials, hydro-electricity and includes electrical energy or electricity generated from renewable sources of energy or bio-mass connected to the grid; 
 </section><section><number>i</number> "energy audit" means the verification, monitoring and analysis of use of energy including submission of technical report containing recommendations for improving energy efficiency with cost benefit analysis and an action plan to reduce energy consumption; 
 </section><section><number>j</number> "energy conservation building codes" means the norms and standards of energy consumption expressed in terms of per square metre of the area wherein energy is used and includes the location of the building; 
 </section><section><number>k</number> "energy consumption standards" means the norms for process  
    and energy consumption standards specified under clause (a) of section 14; 
 </section><section><number>l</number> "Energy Management Centre" means the Energy Management Centre set up under the Resolution of the Government of India in the erstwhile Ministry of Energy, Department of Power No. 7(2)/87-EP(Vol.IV), dated the 5th July, 1989 and registered under the Societies Registration Act, 1860 (21 of 1860); 
 </section><section><number>m</number> "energy manager" means any individual possessing the qualifications prescribed under clause (m) of section 14; 
 </section><section><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>ma</number> "energy savings certificate" means any energy savings certificate issued to the designated consumers under sub-section (1) of  
    section 14A;] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>maa</number> "equipment or appliance" means any equipment or appliance which consumes, generates, transmits or supplies energy and includes any device that consumes any form of energy and produces a desired work;] 
 </section><section><number>n</number> "Governing Council" means the Governing Council referred to in section 4; 
 </section><section><number>o</number> "member" means the member of the Governing Council and includes the Chairperson; 
 </section><section><number>p</number> "notification" means a notification in the Gazette of India or, as the case may be, the Official Gazette of a State; 
 </section><section><number>q</number> "prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act; 
 </section><section><number>r</number> "regulations" means regulations made by the Bureau under this Act; 
 </section><section><number>s</number> "Schedule" means the Schedule to this Act; 
 </section><section><number>t</number> "State Commission" means the State Electricity Regulatory Commission established under sub-section (1) of section 17 of the Electricity Regulatory Commissions Act, 1998 (14 of 1998); 
</section>






</article> 

  
  
  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Establishment and incorporation of Bureau of Energy Efficiency.- </title>
<section><number>1</number> With effect from such date 1 as the Central Government may, by notification, appoint, there shall be established, for the purposes of this Act, a Bureau to be called the Bureau of Energy Efficiency. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Bureau shall be a body corporate by the name aforesaid having perpetual succession and a common seal, with power subject to the provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of property, both movable and immovable, and to contract, and shall, by the said name, sue or be sued. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The head office of the Bureau shall be at Delhi. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Bureau may establish offices at other places in India. 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Management of Bureau.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    The general superintendence, direction and management of the affairs of the 
    Bureau shall vest in the Governing Council which shall consist of not less 
    than twenty, but not exceeding twenty-six, members to be appointed by the 
    Central Government. tc 
    "4. Management of Bureau.-(1) 
    The general superintendence, direction and management of the affairs of the 
    Bureau shall vest in the Governing Council which shall consist of not less 
    than twenty, but not exceeding twenty-six, members to be appointed by the 
    Central Government." 
 
 
 
 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Governing Council shall consist of the following members, namely:-
 
 
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> the Minister in charge of the Ministry  or 
        Department of the Central Government dealing with the Power
 


 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> the Secretary to the Government of India, in 
        charge of the Ministry or Department of the Central Government dealing 
        with the Power tc 
        " (b) the Secretary to the Government of 
        India, in charge of the Ministry or Department of the Central Government 
        dealing with the Power" 
 

 
 

 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> the Secretary to the Government of India, in 
        charge of the Ministry or Department of the Central Government dealing 
        with the Petroleum and Natural Gas
 

 
 

 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> the Secretary to the Government of India, in 
        charge of the Ministry or Department of the Central Government dealing 
        with the Coal  
 
        (d) the Secretary to the Government of India, in charge of the Ministry 
        or Department of the Central Government dealing with the Coal " 
 

 
 

 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number> the Secretary to the Government of India, in 
        charge of the Ministry or Department of the Central Government dealing 
        with the Non-conventional Energy Sources tc 
        " (e) the Secretary to the Government of 
        India, in charge of the Ministry or Department of the Central Government 
        dealing with the Non-conventional Energy Sources" 
 

 
 

 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number> the Secretary to the Government of India, in 
        charge of the Ministry or Department of the Central Government dealing 
        with the Atomic Energy
 

 
 

 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number> the Secretary to the Government of India, in 
        charge of the Ministry or Department of the Central Government dealing 
        with the Consumer Affairs tc 
        " (g) the Secretary to the Government of 
        India, in charge of the Ministry or Department of the Central Government 
        dealing with the Consumer Affairs" 
 

 
 

 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number> Chairman of the Central Electricity Authority 
        established under the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1948 (54 of 1948)  (h) Chairman of the Central 
        Electricity Authority established under the Electricity (Supply) Act, 
        1948 (54 of 1948)" 
 

 
 

 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number> Director-General of the Central Power Research 
        Institute registered under the Karnataka Societies Act, 1960 (Karnataka 
        Act 17 of 1960)
 

 
 

 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number> Executive Director of the Petroleum 
        Conservation Research Association, a society registered under the 
        Societies Registration 
        Act, 1860 (xxi of 1860)  (j) Executive Director of the 
        Petroleum Conservation Research Association, a society registered under 
        the Societies Registration 
        Act, 1860 (xxi of 1860)" 
 

 
 

 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number> Chairman-cum-Managing Director of the Central 
        Mine Planning and Design Institute Limited, a company incorporated under 
        the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956)  (k) Chairman-cum-Managing Director of 
        the Central Mine Planning and Design Institute Limited, a company 
        incorporated under the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956)" 
 

 
 

 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number> Director-General of the Bureau of Indian 
        Standards established under the Bureau of Indian Standards Act, 1986 (63 
        of 1986)  (l) Director-General of the Bureau of 
        Indian Standards established under the Bureau of Indian Standards Act, 
        1986 (63 of 1986)" 
 

 
 

 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number> Director-General of the National Test House, 
        Department of Supply, Ministry of Commerce and Industry, Kolkata tc 
        " (m) Director-General of the National 
        Test House, Department of Supply, Ministry of Commerce and Industry, 
        Kolkata" 
 

 
 

 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>n</number> Managing Director of the Indian Renewable 
        Energy Development Agency Limited, a company incorporated under the 
        Companies 
        Act, 1956 (1 of 1956)  (n) Managing Director of the Indian 
        Renewable Energy Development Agency Limited, a company incorporated 
        under the Companies 
        Act, 1956 (1 of 1956)" 
 

 
 

 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>o</number> one member each from the five power regions 
        reprsenting the States of the region to be appointed by the Central 
        Government
 

 
 

 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>p</number> such number of persons, not exceeding four as 
        may be prescribed, to be appointed by the Central Government as members 
        from amongst persons who are in the opinion of the Central Government 
        capable of representing industry, equipment and appliance manufacturers, 
        architects and consumers tc 
        " (p) such number of persons, not 
        exceeding four as may be prescribed, to be appointed by the Central 
        Government as members from amongst persons who are in the opinion of the 
        Central Government capable of representing industry, equipment and 
        appliance manufacturers, architects and consumers" 
 

 
 

 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>q</number> such number of persons, not exceeding two as 
        may be nominated by the Governing Council as members
 

 
 

 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>r</number> Director-General of Bureau
 

 
 


  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Governing Council may exercise all powers and do all acts and things which 
    may be exercised or done by the Bureau.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Every member referred to in clauses (o), (p) and (q) of sub-section (2) 
    shall hold office for a term of three years from the date on which he enters 
    upon his office.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    fee and allowances to be paid to the members referred to in clauses (o), (p) 
    and (q) of sub-section (2) and the manner of filling up of vacancies and the 
    procedure to be followed in the discharge of their functions shall be such 
    as may be prescribed.
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Meetings of Governing Council.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Governing Council shall meet at such times and places, and shall observe 
    such rules of procedure in regard to the transaction of business at its 
    meetings (including quorum at such meetings) as may be provided by 
    regulations. -(1) 
    The Governing Council shall meet at such times and places, and shall observe 
    such rules of procedure in regard to the transaction of business at its 
    meetings (including quorum at such meetings) as may be provided by 
    regulations." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Chairperson or, if for any reason, he is unable to attend a meeting of the 
    Governing Council, any other member chosen by the members present from 
    amongst themselves at the meeting shall preside at the meeting.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All 
    questions which come up before any meeting of the Governing Council shall be 
    decided by a majority vote of the members present and voting, and in the 
    event of an equality of votes, the Chairperson or in his absence, the person 
    presiding, shall have a second or casting vote.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Vacancies, etc., not to invalidate proceedings of Bureau, Governing Council 
    or Committee.-No 
    act or proceeding of the Bureau or the Governing Council or any Committee 
    shall be invalid merely by reason of- -No 
    act or proceeding of the Bureau or the Governing Council or any Committee 
    shall be invalid merely by reason of-" 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    any vacancy in, or any defect in the 
    constitution of, the Bureau or the Governing Council or the Committee; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    any defect in the appointment of a 
    person acting as a Director-General or Secretary of the Bureau or a member 
    of the Governing Council or the Committee; or
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    any irregularity in the procedure of 
    the Bureau or the Governing Council or the Committee not affecting the 
    merits of the case.
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Removal of member from office.-The 
    Central Government shall remove a member referred to in clauses (o), (p) and 
    (q) of sub-section (2) of section 4 from office if he- -The 
    Central Government shall remove a member referred to in clauses (o), (p) and 
    (q) of sub-section (2) of section 4 from office if he-" 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    is, or at any time has 
    been, adjudicated as insolvent;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    is of unsound mind and 
    stands so declared by a competent court;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    has been convicted of an 
    offence which, in the opinion of the Central Government, involves a moral turpitude;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    has, in the opinion of the 
    Central Government, so abused his position as to render his continuation in 
    office detrimental to the public interest:
 
Provided 
    that no member shall be removed under this clause unless he has been given a 
    reasonable opportunity of being heard in the matter.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Constitution of Advisory Committees and other committees.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to any regulations made in this behalf, the Bureau shall, within six 
    months from the date of commencement of this Act, constitute Advisory 
    Committees for the efficient discharge of its functions. -(1) 
    Subject to any regulations made in this behalf, the Bureau shall, within six 
    months from the date of commencement of this Act, constitute Advisory 
    Committees for the efficient discharge of its functions." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Each 
    Advisory Committee shall consist of a Chairperson and such other members as 
    may be determined by regulations.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Without prejudice to the powers contained in sub-section (1), the Bureau may 
    constitute, such number of technical committees of experts for the 
    formulation of energy consumption standards or norms in respect of equipment 
    or processes, as it considers necessary.

 
  


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>9</number> Director-General of Bureau. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government shall, by notification, appoint a Director-General from amongst persons of ability and standing, having adequate knowledge and experience in dealing with the matters relating to energy production, supply and energy management, standardisation and efficient use of energy and its conservation. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Central Government shall, by notification, appoint any person not below the rank of Deputy Secretary to the Government of India as Secretary of the Bureau. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Director-General shall hold office for a term of 1 [five years] from the date on which he enters upon his office or until he attains the age of sixty years, whichever is earlier. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The salary and allowances payable to the Director-General and other terms and conditions of his service and other terms and conditions of service of the Secretary of the Bureau shall be such as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Subject to general superintendence, direction and management of the affairs by the Governing Council, the Director-General of the Bureau shall be the Chief Executive Authority of the Bureau. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Director-General of the Bureau shall exercise and discharge such powers and duties of the Bureau as may be determined by regulations. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>10</number> Officers and employees of Bureau. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[The Bureau] may appoint such other officers and employees in the Bureau as it considers necessary for the efficient discharge of its functions under this Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The terms and conditions of service of officers and other employees of the Bureau appointed under sub-section (1) shall be such as may be prescribed. 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Authentication of orders and decisions of Bureau.-All 
    orders and decisions of the Bureau shall be authenticated by the signature 
    of the Director-General or any other officer of the Bureau authorised by the 
    Director-General in this behalf. -All 
    orders and decisions of the Bureau shall be authenticated by the signature 
    of the Director-General or any other officer of the Bureau authorised by the 
    Director-General in this behalf." 
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Transfer of assets, liabilities and employees of Energy Management Centre.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    On and from the date of establishment of the Bureau- -(1) 
    On and from the date of establishment of the Bureau-" 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    any reference to the Energy Management 
    Centre in any law other than this Act or in any contract or other instrument 
    shall be deemed as a reference to the Bureau;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    all properties and assets, movable and 
    immovable of, or belonging to, the Energy Management Centre shall vest in 
    the Bureau;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    all the rights and liabilities of the 
    Energy Management Centre shall be transferred to, and be the rights and 
    liabilities of, the Bureau;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    without prejudice to the provisions of 
    clause (c), all debts, obligations and liabilities incurred, all contracts 
    entered into and all matters and things engaged to be done by, with or for 
    the Energy Management Centre immediately before that date, for or in 
    connection with the purposes of the said Centre shall be deemed to have been 
    incurred, entered into, or engaged to be done by, with or for, the Bureau;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    all sums of money due to the Energy 
    Management Centre immediately before that date shall be deemed to be due to 
    the Bureau;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    all suits and other legal proceedings 
    instituted or which could have been instituted by or against the Energy 
    Management Centre immediately before that date may be continued or may be 
    instituted by or against the Bureau; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    every employee holding any office under 
    the Energy Management Centre immediately before that date shall hold his 
    office in the Bureau by the same tenure and upon the same terms and 
    conditions of service as respects remuneration, leave, provident fund, 
    retirement or other terminal benefits as he would have held such office if 
    the Bureau had not been established and shall continue to do so as an 
    employee of the Bureau or until the expiry of six months from that date if 
    such employee opts not to be the employee of the Bureau within such period.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 
    (14 of 1947), or in any other law for the time being in force, the 
    absorption of any employee by the Bureau in its regular service under this 
    section shall not entitle such employee to any compensation under that Act 
    or other law and no such claim shall be entertained by any court, tribunal 
    or other authority.

 
  


</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>13</number> Powers and functions of Bureau. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> The Bureau shall, effectively co-ordinate with designated consumers, designated agencies and other agencies, recognise and utilise the existing resources and infrastructure, in performing the functions assigned to it by or under this Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Bureau may perform such functions and exercise such powers as may be assigned to it by or under this Act and in particular, such functions and powers include the function and power to- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> recommend to the Central Government the norms for processes and energy consumption standards required to be notified under clause (a) of section 14; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<number>aa</number> recommend to the Central Government for issuing of the energy savings certificate under section 14A;] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> recommend to the Central Government the particulars required to be displayed on label on equipment or on appliances and manner of their display under clause (d) of section 14; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> recommend to the Central Government for notifying any user or class of users of energy as a designated consumer under clause (e) of section 14; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> take suitable steps to prescribe guidelines for energy conservation building codes under clause (p) of section 14; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> take all measures necessary to create awareness and disseminate information for efficient use of energy and its conservation; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> arrange and organise training of personnel and specialists in the techniques for efficient use of energy and its conservation; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> strengthen consultancy services in the field of energy conservation; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> promote research and development in the field of energy conservation; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> develop testing and certification procedure and promote testing facilities for certification and testing for energy consumption of equipment and appliances; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> formulate and facilitate implementation of pilot projects and demonstration projects for promotion of efficient use of energy and its conservation; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number> promote use of energy efficient processes, equipment, devices and systems; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number> promote innovative financing of energy efficiency projects; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>m</number> give financial assistance to institutions for promoting efficient use of energy and its conservation; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>n</number> levy fee, as may be determined by regulations, for services provided for promoting efficient use of energy and its conservation; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>o</number> maintain a list of accredited energy auditors as may be specified by regulations; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>p</number> specify, by regulations, the qualifications, criteria and conditions subject to which a person may be accredited as an energy auditor and the procedure for such accreditation;] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>q</number> specify, by regulations, the manner and intervals of time in which the energy audit shall be conducted; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>r</number> specify, by regulations, certification procedures for <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[energy auditors and energy managers] to be designated or appointed by designated consumers; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>s</number> prepare educational curriculum on efficient use of energy and its conservation for educational institutions, boards, universities or autonomous bodies and coordinate with them for inclusion of such curriculum in their syllabus; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[<number>sa</number> conduct examination for capacity building and strengthening of services in the field of energy conservation including certification of energy managers and energy auditors;] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>t</number> implement international co-operation programmes relating to efficient use of energy and its conservation as may be assigned to it by the Central Government; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>u</number> perform such other functions as may be prescribed. 
 <title>COMMENTS </title><title></title>
</subsection>
 The Bureau is to effectively coordinate with designated consumers, designated agencies and other agencies, recognise and utilise the existing resources and infrastructure. 






</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[<title><number>14A</number> Power of Central Government to issue energy savings certificate</title>. -
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government may issue the energy savings certificate to the designated consumer whose energy consumption is less than the prescribed norms and standards in accordance with the procedure as may be prescribed. <title></title>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The designated consumer whose energy consumption is more than the prescribed norms and standards shall be entitled to purchase the energy savings certificate to comply with the prescribed norms and standards.] 


</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>14</number> Power of Central Government to enforce efficient use of energy and its conservation. </title>-The Central Government may, by notification, in consultation with the Bureau,- 
 
 <section><number>a</number> specify the norms for processes and energy consumption standards for any equipment, appliance which consumes, generates, transmits or supplies energy; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> specify equipment or appliance or class of equipments or appliances, as the case may be, for the purposes of this Act; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> prohibit manufacture or sale or purchase or import of equipment or appliance specified under clause (b), unless such equipment or appliance conforms to energy consumption standards: 
</section>
 <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[Provided that no notification prohibiting manufacture or sale or purchase or import of equipment or appliance shall be issued within a period of six months from the date of notification issued under clause 
<section><number>a</number> of this section: 
 Provided further that the Central Government may, having regard to the market share and the technological development having impact on equipment or appliance, and for reasons to be recorded in writing, extend the said period of six months referred to in the first proviso by a further period not exceeding six months;] 
 
 
 Provided that the Central Government may prescribe different norms and standards for different designated consumers having regard to such factors as may be prescribed; 
 
 






</section><section><number>d</number> direct display of such particulars on label on equipment or on appliance specified under clause (b) and in such manner as may be specified by regulations; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> specify, having regard to the intensity or quantity of energy consumed and the amount of investment required for switching over to energy efficient equipments and capacity of industry to invest in it and availability of the energy efficient machinery and equipment required by the industry, <footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[any user or class of users of energy in the energy intensive industries and other establishments as specified in the Schedule as a designated consumer] for the purposes of this Act; 
 </section><section><number>f</number> alter the list of Energy Intensive Industries specified in the Schedule; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> establish and prescribe such energy consumption norms and standards for designated consumers as it may consider necessary: 
</section><section><number>h</number> direct, having regard to quantity of energy consumed or the norms and standards of energy consumption specified under clause (a), the Energy Intensive Industries specified in the Schedule to get energy audit conducted by an accredited energy auditor in such manner and intervals of time as may be specified by regulations; 
 </section><section><number>i</number> direct, if considered necessary for efficient use of energy and its conservation, any designated consumer to get energy audit conducted by an accredited energy auditor; 
 </section><section><number>j</number> specify the matters to be included for the purposes of inspection under sub-section (2) of section 17; 
 </section><section><number>k</number> direct any designated consumer to furnish to the designated agency, in such form and manner and within such period, as may be prescribed, the information with regard to the energy consumed and action taken on the recommendation of the accredited energy auditor; 
 </section><section><number>l</number> direct any designated consumer to designate or appoint energy manager in charge of activities for efficient use of energy and its conservation and submit a report, in the form and manner as may be prescribed, on the status of energy consumption at the end of every financial year to the designated agency; 
 </section><section><number>m</number> prescribe minimum qualification for <footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[energy auditors and energy managers] to be designated or appointed under clause (l); 
 </section><section><number>n</number> direct every designated consumer to comply with energy consumption norms and standards; 
 </section><section><number>o</number> direct any designated consumer, who does not fulfil the energy consumption norms and standards prescribed under clause (g), to prepare a scheme for efficient use of energy and its conservation and implement such scheme keeping in view of the economic viability of the investment in <footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[such form, the time within which and the manner] as may be prescribed; 
 </section><section><number>p</number> prescribe energy conservation building codes for efficient use of energy and its conservation in the building or building complex; 
 </section><section><number>q</number> amend the energy conservation building codes to suit the regional and local climatic conditions; 
 </section><section><number>r</number> direct every owner or occupier of the building or building complex, being a designated consumer to comply with the provisions of energy conservation building codes for efficient use of energy and its conservation; 
 </section><section><number>s</number> direct, any designated consumer referred to in clause (r), if considered necessary, for efficient use of energy and its conservation in his building to get energy audit conducted in respect of such building by an accredited energy auditor in such manner and intervals of time as may be specified by regulations; 
 </section><section><number>t</number> take all measures necessary to create awareness and disseminate information for efficient use of energy and its conservation; 
 </section><section><number>u</number> arrange and organise training of personnel and specialists in the techniques for efficient use of energy and its conservation; 
 </section><section><number>v</number> take steps to encourage preferential treatment for use of energy efficient equipment or appliances: 
 Provided that the powers under clauses (p) to (s) shall be exercised in consultation with the concerned State. 
</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[<title><number>14B</number> Power of Central Government to specify value of energy. </title>-The Central Government may, in consultation with the Bureau, prescribe the value of per metric ton of oil equivalent of energy consumed for the purposes of this Act.] 


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Power of State Government to enforce certain provisions for efficient use of 
    energy and its conservation.-The 
    State Government may, by notification, in consultation with the Bureau- -The 
    State Government may, by notification, in consultation with the Bureau-" 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    amend the energy conservation building 
    codes to suit the regional and local climatic conditions and may, by rules 
    made by it, specify and notify energy conservation building codes with 
    respect to use of energy in the buildings;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    direct every owner or occupier of a 
    building or building complex being a designated consumer to comply with the 
    provisions of the energy conservation building codes;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    direct, if considered necessary for 
    efficient use of energy and its conservation, any designated consumer 
    referred to in clause (b) to get energy audit conducted by an accredited 
    energy auditor in such manner and at such intervals of time as may be 
    specified by regulations;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    designate any agency as designated 
    agency to coordinate, regulate and enforce provisions of this Act within the 
    State;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    take all measures necessary to create 
    awareness and disseminate information for efficient use of energy and its 
    conservation;
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    arrange and organise training of 
    personnel and specialists in the techniques for efficient use of energy and 
    its conservation;
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    take steps to encourage preferential 
    treatment for use of energy efficient equipment or appliances;
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>    direct, any designated consumer to 
    furnish to the designated agency, in such form and manner and within such 
    period as may be specified by rules made by it, information with regard to 
    the energy consumed by such consumer;
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>    specify the matters to be included for 
    the purposes of inspection under sub-section (2) of section 17.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Establishment of Fund by State Government.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government shall constitute a Fund to be called the State Energy 
    Conservation Fund for the purposes of promotion of efficient use of energy 
    and its conservation within the State. -(1) 
    The State Government shall constitute a Fund to be called the State Energy 
    Conservation Fund for the purposes of promotion of efficient use of energy 
    and its conservation within the State." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> To 
    the Fund shall be credited all grants and loans that may be made by the 
    State Government or, Central Government or any other organisation or 
    individual for the purposes of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Fund shall be applied for meeting the expenses incurred for implementing the 
    provisions of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Fund created under sub-section (1) shall be administered by such persons or 
    any authority and in such manner as may be specified in the rules made by 
    the State Government.
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Power of inspection.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    The designated agency may appoint, after the expiry of five years from the 
    date of commencement of this Act, as many inspecting officers as may be 
    necessary for the purpose of ensuring compliance with energy consumption 
    standards specified under clause 
<subsection><number>a</number> of section 14 or ensure display of 
    particulars on label on equipment or appliance specified under clause (b) of 
    section 14 or for the purpose of performing such other functions as may be 
    assigned to them. -(1) 
    The designated agency may appoint, after the expiry of five years from the 
    date of commencement of this Act, as many inspecting officers as may be 
    necessary for the purpose of ensuring compliance with energy consumption 
    standards specified under clause (a) of section 14 or ensure display of 
    particulars on label on equipment or appliance specified under clause (b) of 
    section 14 or for the purpose of performing such other functions as may be 
    assigned to them." 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Subject to any rules made under this Act, an inspecting officer shall have 
    power to-
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    inspect any operation carried on or in 
    connection with the equipment or appliance specified under clause (b) of 
    section 14 or in respect of which energy standards under clause (a) of 
    section 14 have been specified;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    enter any place of designated consumer 
    at which the energy is used for any activity and may require any proprietor, 
    employee, director, manager or secretary or any other person who may be 
    attending in any manner to or helping in, carrying on any activity with the 
    help of energy-
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    to afford him necessary facility to 
    inspect-
 <subsubsubsection>
<number>A</number>    any equipment or appliance as he may 
    require and which may be available at such place;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
<number>B</number>    any production process to ascertain the 
    energy consumption norms and standards;
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    to make an inventory of stock of any 
    equipment or appliance checked or verified by him;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>    to record the statement of any person 
    which may be useful for, or relevant to, for efficient use of energy and its 
    conservation under this Act.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> An 
    inspecting officer may enter any place of designated consumer-
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    where any activity with the help of 
    energy is carried on; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    where any equipment or appliance 
    notified under clause (b) of section 14 has been kept,
 
during the hours at which such place is open 
    for production or conduct of business connected therewith.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> An 
    inspecting officer acting under this section shall, on no account, remove or 
    cause to be removed from the place wherein he has entered, any equipment or 
    appliance or books of account or other documents.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Power of Central Government or State Government to issue directions.-The 
    Central Government or the State Government may, in the exercise of its 
    powers and performance of its functions under this Act and for efficient use 
    of energy and its conservation, issue such directions in writing as it deems 
    fit for the purposes of this Act to any person, officer, authority or any 
    designated consumer and such person, officer or authority or any designated 
    consumer shall be bound to comply with such directions. -The 
    Central Government or the State Government may, in the exercise of its 
    powers and performance of its functions under this Act and for efficient use 
    of energy and its conservation, issue such directions in writing as it deems 
    fit for the purposes of this Act to any person, officer, authority or any 
    designated consumer and such person, officer or authority or any designated 
    consumer shall be bound to comply with such directions." 
 

    Explanation.-For 
    the avoidance of doubts, it is hereby declared that the power to issue 
    directions under this section includes the power to direct-
 <section>
<number>a</number>    regulation of norms for process and 
    energy consumption standards in any industry or building or building 
    complex; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    regulation of the energy consumption 
    standards for equipment and appliances.
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Grants and loans by Central Government.-The 
    Central Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in 
    this behalf, make to the Bureau or to the State Governments grants and loans 
    of such sums of money as the Central Government may consider necessary. -The 
    Central Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in 
    this behalf, make to the Bureau or to the State Governments grants and loans 
    of such sums of money as the Central Government may consider necessary." 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> 
    Establishment of Fund by Central Government.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    There shall be constituted a Fund to be called as the Central Energy 
    Conservation Fund and there shall be credited thereto- -(1) 
    There shall be constituted a Fund to be called as the Central Energy 
    Conservation Fund and there shall be credited thereto-" 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    any grants and loans made to the Bureau 
    by the Central Government under section 19;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    all fees received by the Bureau under 
    this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    all sums received by the Bureau from 
    such other sources as may be decided upon by the Central Government.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Fund shall be applied for meeting-
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the salary, allowances and other 
    remuneration of Director-General, Secretary, officers and other employees of 
    the Bureau;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    expenses of the Bureau in the discharge 
    of its functions under section 13;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    fee and allowances to be paid to the 
    members of the Governing Council under sub-section (5) of section 4;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    expenses on objects and for purposes 
    authorised by this Act.
  



 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>21</number> 
    Borrowing powers of Bureau.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Bureau may, with the consent of the Central Government or in accordance 
    with the terms of any general or special authority given to it by the 
    Central Government, borrow money from any source as it may deem fit for 
    discharging all or any of its functions under this Act. -(1) 
    The Bureau may, with the consent of the Central Government or in accordance 
    with the terms of any general or special authority given to it by the 
    Central Government, borrow money from any source as it may deem fit for 
    discharging all or any of its functions under this Act." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Central Government may guarantee, in such manner as it thinks fit, the 
    repayment of the principal and the payment of interest thereon with respect 
    to the loans borrowed by the Bureau under sub-section (1).

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Budget.-The 
    Bureau shall prepare, in such form and at such time in each financial year 
    as may be prescribed, its budget for the next financial year, showing the 
    estimated receipts and expenditure of the Bureau and forward the same to the 
    Central Government. -The 
    Bureau shall prepare, in such form and at such time in each financial year 
    as may be prescribed, its budget for the next financial year, showing the 
    estimated receipts and expenditure of the Bureau and forward the same to the 
    Central Government." 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> 
    Annual report.-The 
    Bureau shall prepare, in such form and at such time in each financial year 
    as may be prescribed, its annual report, giving a full account of its 
    activities during the previous financial year, and submit a copy thereof to 
    the Central Government. -The 
    Bureau shall prepare, in such form and at such time in each financial year 
    as may be prescribed, its annual report, giving a full account of its 
    activities during the previous financial year, and submit a copy thereof to 
    the Central Government." 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Annual report to be laid before Parliament.-The 
    Central Government shall cause the annual report referred to in section 23 
    to be laid, as soon as may be after it is received, before each House of 
    Parliament. -The 
    Central Government shall cause the annual report referred to in section 23 
    to be laid, as soon as may be after it is received, before each House of 
    Parliament." 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Accounts and audit.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Bureau shall maintain proper accounts and other relevant records and 
    prepare an annual statement of accounts in such form as may be prescribed by 
    the Central Government in consultation with the Comptroller and 
    Auditor-General of India. -(1) 
    The Bureau shall maintain proper accounts and other relevant records and 
    prepare an annual statement of accounts in such form as may be prescribed by 
    the Central Government in consultation with the Comptroller and 
    Auditor-General of India." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    accounts of the Bureau shall be audited by the Comptroller and 
    Auditor-General of India at such intervals as may be specified by him and 
    any expenditure incurred in connection with such audit shall be payable by 
    the Bureau to the Comptroller and Auditor-General.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Comptroller and Auditor-General of India and any other person appointed by 
    him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the Bureau shall have 
    the same rights and privileges and authority in connection with such audit 
    as the Comptroller and Auditor-General generally has in connection with the 
    audit of the Government accounts, and in particular, shall have the right to 
    demand the production of books, accounts, connected vouchers and other 
    documents and papers and to inspect any of the offices of the Bureau.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    accounts of the Bureau as certified by the Comptroller and Auditor-General 
    of India or any other person appointed by him in this behalf together with 
    the audit report thereon shall be forwarded annually to the Central 
    Government and that Government shall cause the same to be laid before each 
    House of Parliament.
  

 
  


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>26</number> Penalty. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> If any person fails to comply with the provisions of clause (c) or clause (d) or clause (h) or clause (i) or clause (k) or clause (l) <footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[***] or clause (r) or clause (s) of section 14 or clause (b) or clause (c) or clause (h) of 
section 15, he shall be liable to a penalty which shall not exceed <footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[ten lakh rupees] for each such failure and, in the case of continuing failure, with an additional penalty which may extend to <footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[ten thousand rupees] for every day during which such failure continues: 
 Provided that no person shall be liable to pay penalty within five years from the date of commencement of this Act. 
 <subsection><footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[<number>IA</number> If any person fails to comply with the provisions of clause (n) of section 14, he shall be liable to a penalty which shall not exceed ten lakh rupees and, in the case of continuing failure, with an additional penalty which shall not be less than the price of every metric ton of oil equivalent of energy, prescribed under this Act, that is in excess of the prescribed norms.] 
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Any amount payable under this section, if not paid, may be recovered as if it were an arrear of land revenue. ] 





</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>27</number> 
    Power to adjudicate.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    For the purpose of adjudging under section 26, the State Commission shall 
    appoint any of its members to be an adjudicating officer for holding an 
    inquiry in such manner as may be prescribed by the Central Government, after 
    giving any person concerned a reasonable opportunity of being heard for the 
    purpose of imposing any penalty. -(1) 
    For the purpose of adjudging under section 26, the State Commission shall 
    appoint any of its members to be an adjudicating officer for holding an 
    inquiry in such manner as may be prescribed by the Central Government, after 
    giving any person concerned a reasonable opportunity of being heard for the 
    purpose of imposing any penalty." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    While holding an inquiry the adjudicating officer shall have power to summon 
    and enforce the attendance of any person acquainted with the facts and 
    circumstances of the case to give evidence or produce any document which in 
    the opinion of the adjudicating officer, may be useful for or relevant to 
    the subject-matter of the inquiry, and if, on such inquiry, he is satisfied 
    that the person has failed to comply with the provisions of any of the 
    clauses of the sections specified in section 26, he may impose such penalty 
    as he thinks fit in accordance with the provisions of any of those clauses 
    of that section:
 
Provided 
    that where a State Commission has not been established in a State, the 
    Government of that State shall appoint any of its officers not below the 
    rank equivalent to a Secretary dealing with legal affairs in that State to 
    be an adjudicating officer for the purposes of this section and such officer 
    shall cease to be an adjudicating officer immediately on the appointment of 
    an adjudicating officer by the State Commission on its establishment in that 
    State:
 
Provided 
    further that where an adjudicating officer appointed by a State Government 
    ceased to be an adjudicating officer, he shall transfer to the adjudicating 
    officer appointed by the State Commission all matters being adjudicated by 
    him and thereafter the adjudicating officer appointed by the State 
    Commission shall adjudicate the penalties on such matters.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>28</number> Factors to be taken into account by adjudicating 
      officer.-While adjudicating the quantum of penalty under 
      section 26, the adjudicating officer shall have due regard to the 
      following factors, namely:- -While 
    adjudicating the quantum of penalty under section 26, the adjudicating 
    officer shall have due regard to the following factors, namely\:-" 
 <section><number>a</number>    the amount 
      of disproportionate gain or unfair advantage, wherever quantifiable, made 
      as a result of the default;
 </section><section><number>b</number>    the 
      repetitive nature of the default.
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>29</number> 
    Civil court not to have jurisdiction.-No 
    civil court shall have jurisdiction to entertain any suit or proceeding in 
    respect of any matter which an adjudicating officer appointed under this Act 
    or the Appellate Tribunal is empowered by or under this Act to determine and 
    no injunction shall be granted by any court or other authority in respect of 
    any action taken or to be taken in pursuance of any power conferred by or 
    under this Act. -No 
    civil court shall have jurisdiction to entertain any suit or proceeding in 
    respect of any matter which an adjudicating officer appointed under this Act 
    or the Appellate Tribunal is empowered by or under this Act to determine and 
    no injunction shall be granted by any court or other authority in respect of 
    any action taken or to be taken in pursuance of any power conferred by or 
    under this Act." 
  

 
  


</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>20</footcitenum>[<number>30</number> Appellate Tribunal. </title>-The Appellate Tribunal established under 
section 110 of the Electricity Act, 2003 (36 of 2003) shall, without prejudice to the provisions of the Electricity Act, 2003, be the Appellate Tribunal for the purposes of this Act and hear appeals against the orders of the adjudicating officer or the Central Government or the State Government or any other authority under this Act.] 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>31</number> 
    Appeal to Appellate Tribunal.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person aggrieved, by an order made by an adjudicating officer or the 
    Central Government or the State Government or any other authority under this 
    Act, may prefer an appeal to the Appellate Tribunal for Energy Conservation: -(1) 
    Any person aggrieved, by an order made by an adjudicating officer or the 
    Central Government or the State Government or any other authority under this 
    Act, may prefer an appeal to the Appellate Tribunal for Energy 
    Conservation\:" 
 
Provided 
    that any person, appealing against the order of the adjudicating officer 
    levying any penalty, shall, while filing the appeal, deposit the amount of 
    such penalty:
 
Provided 
    further that where in any particular case, the Appellate Tribunal is of the 
    opinion that the deposit of such penalty would cause undue hardship to such 
    person, the Appellate Tribunal may dispense with such deposit subject to 
    such conditions as it may deem fit to impose so as to safeguard the 
    realisation of penalty.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every appeal under sub-section (1) shall be filed within a period of 
    forty-five days from the date on which a copy of the order made by the 
    adjudicating officer or the Central Government or the State Government or 
    any other authority is received by the aggrieved person and it shall be in 
    such form, verified in such manner and be accompanied by such fee as may be 
    prescribed:
 
Provided 
    that the Appellate Tribunal may entertain an appeal after the expiry of the 
    said period of forty-five days if it is satisfied that there was sufficient 
    cause for not filing it within that period.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On 
    receipt of an appeal under sub-section (1), the Appellate Tribunal may, 
    after giving the parties to the appeal an opportunity of being heard, pass 
    such orders thereon as it thinks fit, confirming, modifying or setting aside 
    the order appealed against.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Appellate Tribunal shall send a copy of every order made by it to the 
    parties to the appeal and to the concerned adjudicating officer or the 
    Central Government or the State Government or any other authority.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    appeal filed before the Appellate Tribunal under sub-section (1) shall be 
    dealt with by it as expeditiously as possible and endeavour shall be made by 
    it to dispose of the appeal finally within one hundred and eighty days from 
    the date of receipt of the appeal:
 
Provided 
    that where an appeal could not be disposed of within the said period of one 
    hundred and eighty days, the Appellate Tribunal shall record its reasons in 
    writing for not disposing of the appeal within the said period.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    Appellate Tribunal may, for the purpose of examining the legality, propriety 
    or correctness of any order made by the adjudicating officer or the Central 
    Government or the State Government or any other authority under this Act, as 
    the case may be, in relation to any proceeding, on its own motion or 
    otherwise, call for the records of such proceedings and make such order in 
    the case as it thinks fit.

 
  


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>21</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>31A</number> Procedure and powers of Appellate Tribunal. </title>-The provisions of sections 120 to 123 (both inclusive) of the Electricity Act, 2003 (36 of 2003) shall, mutatis mutandis, apply to the Appellate Tribunal in the discharge of its functions under this Act as they apply to it in the discharge of its function under the Electricity Act, 2003.] 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>22</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>32</number> Composition of Appellate Tribunal. </title>-[ Rep. by the Energy Conservation (Amendment) Act, 2010 (28 of 2010), sec. 11 (w.e.f. 24-8-2010) .] 




 
 <section><number>a</number> the jurisdiction of the Appellate Tribunal may be exercised by Benches thereof; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> a Bench may be constituted by the Chairperson of the Appellate Tribunal with two or more Members of the Appellate Tribunal as the Chairperson of the Appellate Tribunal may deem fit: 
 Provided that every Bench constituted under this clause shall include at least one Judicial Member and one Technical Member; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> the Benches of the Appellate Tribunal shall ordinarily sit at Delhi and such other places as the Central Government may, in consultation with the Chairperson of the Appellate Tribunal, notify. 
 </section><section><number>d</number> the Central Government shall notify the areas in relation to which each Bench of the Appellate Tribunal may exercise jurisdiction. 
</section>


 
 <section><number>i</number> "Judicial Member" means a Member of the Appellate Tribunal appointed as such under item (i) or item (ii) of clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 33, and includes the Chairperson of the Appellate Tribunal; 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> "Technical Member" means a Member of the Appellate Tribunal appointed as such under item (iii) or item (iv) or item (v) or item (vi) of clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 33.". 
</section>
</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>23</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>33</number> Qualifications for appointment of Chairperson and Members of Appellate Tribunal. </title>-[ Rep. by the Energy Conservation (Amendment) Act, 2010  
(28 of 2010), sec. 11 (w.e.f. 24-8-2010) .] 



 
 <section><number>a</number> in the case of Chairperson of the Appellate Tribunal, is, or has been, a Judge of the Supreme Court or the Chief Justice of a High Court; and 
 </section><section><number>b</number> in the case of a Member of the Appellate Tribunal,- 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> is, or has been, or is qualified to be, a Judge of a High Court; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> is, or has been, a Member of the Indian Legal Service and has held a post in Grade I in that service for at least three years; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> is, or has been, a Secretary for at least one year in the Ministry or Department of the Central Government dealing with the Power, or Coal, or Petroleum and Natural Gas, or Atomic Energy; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> is or has been Chairman of the Central Electricity Authority for at least one year; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> is, or has been, Director-General of Bureau or Director-General of the Central Power Research Institute or Bureau of Indian Standards for at least three years or has held any equivalent post for at least three years; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vi</number> is, or has been, a qualified technical person of ability and standing, having adequate knowledge and experience in dealing with the matters relating to energy production and supply, energy management, standardisation and efficient use of energy and its conservation, and has shown capacity in dealing with problems relating to engineering, finance, commerce, economics, law or management.". 
</subsection>
</section>
</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>24</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>34</number> Term of office. </title>-[ Rep. by the Energy Conservation (Amendment) Act, 2010 (28 of 2010), sec. 11 (w.e.f. 24-8-2010) .] 




 
 <section><number>a</number> in the case of the Chairperson of the Appellate Tribunal, the age of seventy years; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> in the case of any Member of the Appellate Tribunal, the age of sixty-five years.". 
</section>
</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>25</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>35</number> Terms and conditions of service. </title>-[ Rep. by the Energy Conservation (Amendment) Act, 2010 (28 of 2010), sec. 11 (w.e.f. 24-8-2010) .] 




</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>26</footcitenum>[<number>36</number> Vacancies.</title>[Rep. by the Energy Conservation (Amendment) Act, 2010 
(28 of 2010), sec. 11 (w.e.f. 24-8-2010).]



</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>27</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>37</number> Resignation and removal. </title>-[ Rep. by the Energy Conservation (Amendment) Act, 2010 (28 of 2010), sec. 11 (w.e.f. 24-8-2010) .] 





</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>28</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>38</number> Member to act as Chairperson in certain circumstances. </title>-[ Rep. by the Energy Conservation (Amendment) Act, 2010 (28 of 2010), sec. 11 (w.e.f. 24-8-2010) .] 




</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>29</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>39</number> Staff of Appellate Tribunal. </title>-([ Rep. by the Energy Conservation (Amendment) Act, 2010 (28 of 2010), sec. 11 (w.e.f. 24-8-2010) .] 





</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>30</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>40</number> Procedure and powers of Appellate Tribunal. </title>-[ Rep. by the Energy Conservation (Amendment) Act, 2010 (28 of 2010), sec. 11 (w.e.f. 24-8-2010) .] 




 
 <section><number>a</number> summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person and examining him on oath; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> requiring the discovery and production of documents; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> receiving evidence on affidavits; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> subject to the provisions of sections 123 and 124 of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872), requisitioning any public record or document or copy of such record or document from any office; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses or documents; 
 </section><section><number>f</number> reviewing its decisions; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> dismissing a representation of default or deciding it, ex parte ; 
 </section><section><number>h</number> setting aside any order of dismissal or any representation for default or any order passed by it, ex parte ; 
 </section><section><number>i</number> any other matter which may be prescribed by the Central Government. 
</section>



</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>31</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>41</number> Distribution of business amongst Benches. </title>-[ Rep. by the Energy Conservation (Amendment) Act, 2010 (28 of 2010), sec. 11 (w.e.f. 24-8-2010) .] 




</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>32</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>42</number> Power of Chairperson to transfer cases. </title>-[ Rep. by the Energy Conservation (Amendment) Act, 2010 (28 of 2010), sec. 11 (w.e.f. 24-8-2010) .] 




</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>33</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>43</number> Decision to be by majority. </title>-[ Rep. by the Energy Conservation (Amendment) Act, 2010 (28 of 2010), sec. 11 (w.e.f. 24-8-2010) .] 




</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>44</number> Right of appellant to take assistance of legal practitioner or 
      accredited auditor and of Government to appoint presenting 
      officers.-
<section><number>1</number> A person preferring an appeal to the 
      Appellate Tribunal under this Act may either appear in person or take the 
      assistance of a legal practitioner or an accredited energy auditor of his 
      choice to present his case before the Appellate Tribunal, as the case may 
      be. -(1) 
    A person preferring an appeal to the Appellate Tribunal under this Act may 
    either appear in person or take the assistance of a legal practitioner or an 
    accredited energy auditor of his choice to present his case before the 
    Appellate Tribunal, as the case may be." 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Central Government or the State Government may authorise 
      one or more legal practitioners or any of its officers to act as 
      presenting officers and every person so authorised may present the case 
      with respect to any appeal before the Appellate Tribunal, as the case may 
      be.
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>45</number> 
    Appeal to Supreme Court.-Any 
    person aggrieved by any decision or order of the Appellate Tribunal, may, 
    file an appeal to the Supreme Court within sixty days from the date of 
    communication of the decision or order of the Appellate Tribunal to him, on 
    any one or more of the grounds specified in section 100 of the Code of Civil 
    Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908): -Any 
    person aggrieved by any decision or order of the Appellate Tribunal, may, 
    file an appeal to the Supreme Court within sixty days from the date of 
    communication of the decision or order of the Appellate Tribunal to him, on 
    any one or more of the grounds specified in section 100 of the Code of Civil 
    Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908)\:" 
 
Provided 
    that the Supreme Court may, if it is satisfied that the appellant was 
    prevented by sufficient cause from filing the appeal within the said period, 
    allow it to be filed within a further period not exceeding sixty days.
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>46</number> 
    Power of Central Government to issue directions to Bureau.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    Without prejudice to the foregoing provisions of this Act, the Bureau shall, 
    in exercise of its powers or the performance of its functions under this 
    Act, be bound by such directions on questions of policy as the Central 
    Government may give in writing to it from time to time: -(1) 
    Without prejudice to the foregoing provisions of this Act, the Bureau shall, 
    in exercise of its powers or the performance of its functions under this 
    Act, be bound by such directions on questions of policy as the Central 
    Government may give in writing to it from time to time\:" 
 
Provided 
    that the Bureau shall, as far as practicable, be given an opportunity to 
    express its views before any direction is given under this sub-section.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    decision of the Central Government, whether a question is one of policy or 
    not, shall be final.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>47</number> 
    Power of Central Government to supersede Bureau.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    If at any time the Central Government is of opinion- -(1) 
    If at any time the Central Government is of opinion-" 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    that on account of grave emergency, the 
    Bureau is unable to discharge the functions and duties imposed on it by or 
    under the provisions of this Act; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    that the Bureau has persistently made 
    default in complying with any direction issued by the Central Government 
    under this Act or in discharge of the functions and duties imposed on it by 
    or under the provisions of this Act and as a result of such default, the 
    financial position of the Bureau had deteriorated or the administration of 
    the Bureau had deteriorated; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    that circumstances exist which render 
    it necessary in the public interest so to do,
 
the Central Government may, by notification, 
    supersede the Bureau for such period, not exceeding six months, as may be 
    specified in the notification.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Upon 
    the publication of a notification under sub-section (1) superseding the 
    Bureau,-
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    all the members referred to in clauses 
    (o), (p) and (q) of sub-section (2) of section 4 shall, as from the date of 
    supersession, vacate their offices as such;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    all the powers, functions and duties 
    which may, by or under the provisions of this Act, be exercised or 
    discharged by or on behalf of the Bureau, shall until the Bureau is 
    reconstituted under sub-section (3), be exercised and discharged by such 
    person or persons as the Central Government may direct; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    all property owned or controlled by the 
    Bureau shall, until the Bureau is reconstituted under sub-section (3), vest 
    in the Central Government.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> On 
    the expiration of the period of supersession specified in the notification 
    issued under sub-section (1), the Central Government may reconstitute the 
    Bureau by a fresh appointment and in such case any person or persons who 
    vacated their offices under clause (a) of sub-section (2), shall not be 
    deemed disqualified for appointment:
 
Provided 
    that the Central Government may, at any time, before the expiration of the 
    period of supersession, take action under this sub-section.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Central Government shall cause a notification issued under sub- 
    section (1) and a full report of any action taken under this section and the 
    circumstances leading to such action to be laid before each House of 
    Parliament at the earliest.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>48</number> 
    Default by companies.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where a company makes a default in complying with the provisions of clause 
    (c) or clause (d) or clause (h) or clause (i) or clause (k) or clause (l) or 
    clause (n) or clause (r) or clause (s) of section 14 or clause (b) or clause 
    (c) or clause (h) of section 15, every person who at the time of such 
    contravention was incharge of, and was responsible to the company for the 
    conduct of the business of the company, as well as the company, shall be 
    deemed to have acted in contravention of the said provisions and shall be 
    liable to be proceeded against and imposed penalty under section 26 
    accordingly: -(1) 
    Where a company makes a default in complying with the provisions of clause 
    (c) or clause (d) or clause (h) or clause (i) or clause (k) or clause (l) or 
    clause (n) or clause (r) or clause (s) of section 14 or clause (b) or clause 
    (c) or clause (h) of section 15, every person who at the time of such 
    contravention was incharge of, and was responsible to the company for the 
    conduct of the business of the company, as well as the company, shall be 
    deemed to have acted in contravention of the said provisions and shall be 
    liable to be proceeded against and imposed penalty under section 26 
    accordingly\:" 
 
Provided 
    that nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person 
    liable for penalty provided in this Act if he proves that the contravention 
    of the aforesaid provisions was committed without his knowledge or that he 
    exercised all due diligence to prevent the contravention of the aforesaid 
    provision.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where any 
    contravention of the provisions of clause (c) or clause (d) or clause (h) or 
    clause (i) or clause (k) or clause (l) or clause (n) or clause (r) or clause 
    (s) of section 14 or clause (b) or clause (c) or clause (h) of section 15 
    has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is attributable to, 
    any neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary or other 
    officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary or other officer 
    shall also be deemed to have contravened the said provisions and shall be 
    liable to be proceeded for imposition of penalty accordingly.
 

    Explanation.-For 
    the purposes of this section, "company" means a body corporate and includes 
    a firm or other association of individuals.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>49</number> 
    Exemption from tax on income.-Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in the Income-tax Act, 1961 (43 of 1961) or any other 
    enactment for the time being in force relating to tax on income, profits or 
    gains- -Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in the Income-tax Act, 1961 (43 of 1961) or any other 
    enactment for the time being in force relating to tax on income, profits or 
    gains-" 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    the Bureau;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    the existing Energy Management Centre 
    from the date of its constitution to the date of establishment of the 
    Bureau,
 
shall not be liable to pay any income-tax or 
    any tax in respect of their income, profits or gains derived.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>50</number> Protection of action taken in good 
      faith.-No 
      suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central 
      Government or Director-General or Secretary or State Government or any 
      officer of those Governments or State Commission or its members or any 
      member or officer or other employee of the Bureau for anything which is in 
      good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or the rules or 
      regulations made thereunder. -No 
    suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central 
    Government or Director-General or Secretary or State Government or any 
    officer of those Governments or State Commission or its members or any 
    member or officer or other employee of the Bureau for anything which is in 
    good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or the rules or 
    regulations made thereunder." 
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>51</number> 
    Delegation.-The 
    Bureau may, by general or special order in writing, delegate to any member, 
    member of the committee, officer of the Bureau or any other person subject 
    to such conditions, if any, as may be specified in the order, such of its 
    powers and functions under this Act (except the powers under section 58) as 
    it may deem necessary. -The 
    Bureau may, by general or special order in writing, delegate to any member, 
    member of the committee, officer of the Bureau or any other person subject 
    to such conditions, if any, as may be specified in the order, such of its 
    powers and functions under this Act (except the powers under section 58) as 
    it may deem necessary." 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>52</number> 
    Power to obtain information.-Every 
    designated consumer or manufacturer of equipment or appliance specified 
    under clause (b) of section 14 shall supply the Bureau with such 
    information, and with such samples of any material or substance used in 
    relation to any equipment or appliance, as the Bureau may require. -Every 
    designated consumer or manufacturer of equipment or appliance specified 
    under clause (b) of section 14 shall supply the Bureau with such 
    information, and with such samples of any material or substance used in 
    relation to any equipment or appliance, as the Bureau may require." 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>53</number> 
    Power to exempt.-If 
    the Central Government or the State Government is of the opinion that it is 
    necessary or expedient so to do in the public interest, it may, by 
    notification and subject to such conditions as may be specified in the 
    notification, exempt any designated consumer or class of designated 
    consumers from application of all or any of the provisions of this Act: -If 
    the Central Government or the State Government is of the opinion that it is 
    necessary or expedient so to do in the public interest, it may, by 
    notification and subject to such conditions as may be specified in the 
    notification, exempt any designated consumer or class of designated 
    consumers from application of all or any of the provisions of this Act\:" 
 
Provided 
    that the Central Government or the State Government, as the case may be, 
    shall not grant exemption to any designated consumer or class of designated 
    consumers for a period exceeding five years:
 
Provided 
    further that the Central Government or the State Government, as the case may 
    be, shall consult the Bureau of Energy Efficiency before granting such 
    exemption.

 
  


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>54</number> Chairperson, Members, officers and employees of the Appellate Tribunal, Members of State Commission, Director-General, Secretary, members, officers and employees of the Bureau to be public servants. </title>-The <footcitenum>34</footcitenum>[***] Members, Director-General, Secretary, officers and other employees of the Bureau shall be deemed, when acting or purporting to act in pursuance of any of the provisions of this Act, to be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860). 


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>55</number> 
    Power of Central Government to issue directions.-The 
    Central Government may give directions to a State Government or the Bureau 
    as to carrying out into execution of this Act in the State. -The 
    Central Government may give directions to a State Government or the Bureau 
    as to carrying out into execution of this Act in the State." 

 
  


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>56</number> Power of Central Government to make rules. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government may, by notification, make rules for carrying out the provisions of this Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> such number of persons to be appointed as members by the Central Government under clauses (o), (p) and (q) of sub-section (2) of  
    section 4; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the fee and allowances to be paid to the members under sub-section (5) of section 4; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the salary and allowances payable to the Director-General and other terms and conditions of his service and other terms and conditions of service of the Secretary of the Bureau under sub-section (4) of  
    section 9; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> the terms and conditions of service of officers and other employees of the Bureau under sub-section (2) of section 10; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> performing such other functions by the Bureau, as may be prescribed, under clause (u) of sub-section (2) of section 13; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> the energy consumption norms and standards for designated consumers under clause (g) of section 14; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> prescribing the different norms and standards for different designated consumers under the proviso to clause (g) of section 14; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> the form and manner and the time within which information with regard to energy consumed and the action taken on the recommendations of the accredited energy auditor be furnished under clause (k) of section 14; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> the form and manner in which the status of energy consumption be submitted under clause (l) of section 14; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> the minimum qualifications for <footcitenum>35</footcitenum>[energy auditors and energy managers] under clause (m) of section 14; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number> the form and manner for preparation of scheme and its implementation under clause (o) of section 14; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number> the energy conservation building codes under clause (p) of section 14; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>36</footcitenum>[<number>la</number> prescribing the procedure for issuing the energy savings certificate under sub-section (1) of section 14A;] 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>36</footcitenum>[<number>laa</number> the value of per metric ton of oil equivalent of energy consumed under, section 14B;] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>m</number> the matters relating to inspection under sub-section (2) of section 17; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>n</number> the form in which, and the time at which, the Bureau shall prepare its budget under section 22; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>o</number> the form in which, and the time at which, the Bureau shall prepare its annual report under section 23; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>p</number> the form in which the accounts of the Bureau shall be maintained under section 25; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>q</number> the manner of holding inquiry under sub-section (l) of section 27; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>r</number> the form of and fee for filing such appeal under sub-section (2) of section 31; 
 <footcitenum>37</footcitenum>[***] 
 <subsubsection><number>v</number> any other matter which is to be, or may be, prescribed, or in respect of which provision is to be made, or may be made, by rules. 
</subsubsection></subsection>







</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>57</number> 
    Power of State Government to make rules.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government may, by notification, make rules for carrying out the 
    provisions of this Act and not inconsistent with the rules, if any, made by 
    the Central Government. -(1) 
    The State Government may, by notification, make rules for carrying out the 
    provisions of this Act and not inconsistent with the rules, if any, made by 
    the Central Government." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:-
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    energy conservation 
    building codes under clause (a) of section 15;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the form, the manner and 
    the period within which information with regard to energy consumption shall 
    be furnished under clause (h) of section 15;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the person or any 
    authority who shall administer the Fund and the manner in which the Fund 
    shall be administered under sub-section (4) of section 16;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the matters to be 
    included for the purposes of inspection under sub-section (2) of section 17;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    any other matter which 
    is to be, or may be, prescribed, or in respect of which provision is to be 
    made, or may be made, by rules.

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>58</number> Power of Bureau to make regulations. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> The Bureau may, with the previous approval of the Central Government and subject to the condition of previous publication, by notification, make regulations not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder to carry out the purposes of this Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such regulations may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the times and places of the meetings of the Governing Council and the procedure to be followed at such meetings under sub-section (1) of section 5; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the members of advisory committees constituted under sub-section (2) of section 8; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the powers and duties that may be exercised and discharged by the Director-General of the Bureau under sub-section (6) of section 9; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> the levy of fee for services provided for promoting efficient use of energy and its conservation under clause (n) of sub-section (2) of section 13; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> the list of accredited energy auditors under clause (o) of sub-section (2) of section 13; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>38</footcitenum>[<number>f</number> the qualifications, criteria and conditions subject to which a person may be accredited as an energy auditor and the procedure for such accreditation under clause (p) of sub-section (2) of section 13;] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> the manner and the intervals of time in which the energy audit shall be conducted under clause (q) of sub-section (2) of section 13; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> certification procedure for <footcitenum>39</footcitenum>[energy auditors and energy managers] under clause (r) of sub-section (2) of section 13; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> particulars required to be displayed on label and the manner of their display under clause (d) of section 14; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> the manner and the intervals of time for conduct of energy audit under clause (h) or clause (s) of section 14; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number> the manner and the intervals of time for conducting energy audit by an accredited energy auditor under clause (c) of section 15; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number> any other matter which is required to be, or may be, specified. 
</subsection>




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>59</number> 
    Rules and regulations to be laid before Parliament and State Legislature.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every rule made by the Central Government and every regulation made under 
    this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each 
    House of Parliament while it is in session, for a total period of thirty 
    days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive 
    sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the 
    session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making 
    any modification in the rule or regulation, or both Houses agree that the 
    rule or regulation should not be made, the rule or regulation shall 
    thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the 
    case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be 
    without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that 
    rule or regulation. -(1) 
    Every rule made by the Central Government and every regulation made under 
    this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each 
    House of Parliament while it is in session, for a total period of thirty 
    days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive 
    sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the 
    session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making 
    any modification in the rule or regulation, or both Houses agree that the 
    rule or regulation should not be made, the rule or regulation shall 
    thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the 
    case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be 
    without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that 
    rule or regulation." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every rule made by the State Government shall be laid, as soon as may be 
    after it is made, before each House of the State Legislature where it 
    consists of two Houses, or where such Legislature consists of one House, 
    before that House.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>60</number> 
    Application of other laws not barred.-The 
    provisions of this Act shall be in addition to, and not in derogation of, 
    the provisions of any other law for the time being in force. -The 
    provisions of this Act shall be in addition to, and not in derogation of, 
    the provisions of any other law for the time being in force." 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>61</number> Provisions of Act not to apply in certain 
      cases.-The 
      provisions of this Act shall not apply to the Ministry or Department of 
      the Central Government dealing with Defence, Atomic Energy or such other 
      similar Ministries or Departments or under- takings or Boards or 
      institutions under the control of such Ministries or Deparments as may be 
      notified by the Central Government. -The 
    provisions of this Act shall not apply to the Ministry or Department of the 
    Central Government dealing with Defence, Atomic Energy or such other similar 
    Ministries or Departments or under- takings or Boards or institutions under 
    the control of such Ministries or Deparments as may be notified by the 
    Central Government." 
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>62</number> 
    Power to remove difficulty.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the 
    Central Government may, by order, published in the Official Gazette, make 
    such provisions not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act as may 
    appear to be necessary for removing the difficulty: -(1) 
    If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the 
    Central Government may, by order, published in the Official Gazette, make 
    such provisions not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act as may 
    appear to be necessary for removing the difficulty\:" 
 
Provided 
    that no such order shall be made under this section after the expiry of two 
    years from the date of the commencement of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every order made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after 
    it is made, before each House of Parliament.
  

 
  


</section></article> 

  
 <title>THE SCHEDULE </title>
 [ See  section 2(s)] 
 <title>LIST OF ENERGY INTENSIVE INDUSTRIES AND  
  OTHER ESTABLISHMENTS </title><title>1 </title><title>[***] </title>
 <article><number>1</number> Aluminium; 
 </article><article><number>2</number> Fertilizers; 
 </article><article><number>3</number> Iron and Steel; 
 </article><article><number>4</number> Cement; 
 </article><article><number>5</number> Pulp and paper; 
 </article><article><number>6</number> Chlor Alkali; 
 </article><article><number>7</number> Sugar; 
 </article><article><number>8</number> Textile; 
 </article><article><number>9</number> Chemicals; 
 </article><article><number>10</number> Railways; 
 </article><article><number>11</number> Port Trust; 
 </article><article><number>12</number> Transport Sector (industries and services); 
 </article><article><number>13</number> Petrochemical, Gas Crackers, Naphtha Crackers and Petroleum Refineries; 
 </article><article><number>14</number> Thermal power stations, hydel power stations, electricity transmission companies and distribution companies; 
 </article><article><number>15</number> Commercial buildings or establishments. 


</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by Act 28 of 2010, sec. 2(i), for "an auditor possessing qualifications specified under" (w.e.f. 24-8-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Subs. by Act 28 of 2010, sec. 2(ii), for "established under section 30" (w.e.f. 24-8-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Subs. by Act 28 of 2010, sec. 2(iii), for clause (c) (w.e.f. 24-8-2010). Clause (c), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Ins. by Act 28 of 2010, sec. 2(iv) (w.e.f. 24-8-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Subs. by Act 28 of 2010, sec. 4, for The Central Government (w.e.f. 24-8-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Ins. by Act 28 of 2010, sec. 5(i) (w.e.f. 24-8-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Subs. by Act 28 of 2010, sec. 5(ii), for clause (p) (w.e.f. 24-8-2010). Clause (p), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Subs. by Act 28 of 2010, sec. 5(iii), for "energy managers" (w.e.f. 24-8-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> Ins. by Act 28 of 2010, sec. 5(iv) (w.e.f. 24-8-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> Ins. by Act 28 of 2010, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 24-8-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number> Subs. by Act 28 of 2010, sec. 6(i), for the proviso (w.e.f. 24-8-2010). The proviso, before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number> Subs. by Act 28 of 2010, sec. 6(ii), for "any user or class of users of energy as a designated consumer" (w.e.f. 24-8-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number> Subs. by Act 28 of 2010, sec. 6(iii), for "energy managers" (w.e.f. 24-8-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number> Subs. by Act 28 of 2010, sec. 6(iv), for "such form and manner" (w.e.f. 24-8-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number> Ins. by Act 28 of 2010, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 24-8-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number> The words "or clause (n)" omitted by Act 28 of 2010, sec. 8(a)(i) (w.e.f. 24-8-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number> Subs. by Act 28 of 2010, sec. 8(a)(ii), for "ten thousand rupees" (w.e.f. 24-8-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number> Subs. by Act 28 of 2010, sec. 8(a)(iii), for "one thousand rupees" (w.e.f. 24-8-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number> Ins. by Act 28 of 2010, sec. 8(b) (w.e.f. 24-8-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number> Subs. by Act 28 of 2010, sec. 9, for section 30 (w.e.f. 24-8-2010). Section 30, before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number> Ins. by Act 28 of 2010, sec. 10 (w.e.f. 24-8-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number> Section 32, before omission, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number> Section 33, before omission, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number> Section 34, before omission, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number> Section 35, before omission, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number> Section 36, before omission, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number> Section 37, before omission, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>28</number> Section 38, before omission, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>29</number> Section 39, before omission, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>30</number> Section 40, before omission, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>31</number> Section 41, before omission, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>32</number> Section 42, before omission, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>33</number> Section 43, before omission, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>34</number> The words "Chairperson of the Appellate Tribunal or the members of the Appellate Tribunal or officers or employees of the Appellate Tribunal or the Members of the State Commission or the" omitted by Act 28 of 2010, sec. 12 (w.e.f. 24-8-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>35</number> Subs. by Act 28 of 2010, sec. 13(i), for "energy managers" (w.e.f. 24-8-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>36</number> Ins. by Act 28 of 2010, sec. 13(ii) (w.e.f. 24-8-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>37</number> Clauses (s), (t) and (u) omitted by Act 28 of 2010, sec. 13(iii) (w.e.f. 24-8-2010). Clauses (s), (t) and (u), before omission, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>38</number> Subs. by Act 28 of 2010, sec. 14(a), for clause (f) (w.e.f. 24-8-2010). Clause (f), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>39</number> Subs. by Act 28 of 2010, sec. 14(b), for "energy managers" (w.e.f. 24-8-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>40</number> The words specified as designated consumers omitted by Act 28 of 2010, sec. 15 (w.e.f. 24-8-2010).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>