<act><tid>327662</tid>
<title>THE RAJGHAT SAMADHI ACT, <year>1951</year></title>

ACT NO. 41 OF <year>1951</year>
[ 29th June, <year>1951</year>.]

An Act to provide for the administration and control of the Rajghat 
Samadhi in Delhi.

BE it enacted by Parliament as follows:-





<article><tid>1396911</tid>
<number> 1</number> 
<section><tid>1047751</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title and commencement. This Act may be called the  
Rajghat Samadhi Act, <year>1951</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1210863</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date 1 as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1672431</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act,-
<section><tid>1281588</tid>
<number>a</number>" Committee" means the Rajghat Samadhi Committee 
constituted under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1871231</tid>
<number>b</number>" Samadhi" means the structure built in token of 
reverence for Mahatma Gandhi at Rajghat on the Western bank 
of the Jamuna in Delhi, and includes the premises described 
in the Schedule with all buildings contained therein, 
together with all additions thereto or alterations thereof 
which may be made after the commencement of this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1939715</tid>
<number> 3</number> 
<section><tid>1080692</tid>
<number>1</number>The Rajghat Samadhi Committee. The administration and  
control of the Samadhi shall be vested in a Committee constituted in 
the manner hereinafter provided.

</section>

<section><tid>1205317</tid>
<number>2</number>The Committee shall by the name of" the Rajghat Samadhi 
Committee", be a body corporate and shall have perpetual succession 
and a common seal and shall by the said name sue and be sued through 
its Chairman.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1749091</tid>
<number> 4</number> 
<section><tid>1514944</tid>
<number>1</number>Composition of the Committee. The Committee shall consist of  
the following members, namely:-

<subsection><tid>22843</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the Mayor of the Municipal Corporation of Delhi, ex- 
fficio;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1842482</tid>
<number>b</number>three officials nominated by the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1109828</tid>
<number>c</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> four non- officials nominated by the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>143604</tid>
<number>d</number>three members of Parliament of whom two shall be 
elected from among themselves by members of the House of the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>26</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 7th June, <year>1952</year>, see Notification No. S. R. O. 1018, dated 3rd June, 
<year>1952</year>, Gazette of India, <year>1952</year>, Pt. 11, Sec. 3, p. 894.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 37 of <year>1958</year>, s. 2, for the original clauses (a), (c) and 
 (d), respectively (w. e. f. 9- 3- <year>1959</year>).





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

People and one from among themselves by members of the 
Council of States.]


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1595828</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may appoint any person referred to in 
sub- section (1) or any other person to be the Chairman of the 
Committee, and if any other person is so appointed, he shall be deemed 
to be a member of the Committee within the meaning of sub- section (1).

</section>

<section><tid>818815</tid>
<number>3</number>All persons nominated by the Central Government to be members 
of the Committee shall hold office during the pleasure of the Central 
Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1719255</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The term of office of a member elected under clause (d) of 
sub- section (1) shall come to an end as soon as he ceases to be a 
member of the House from which he was elected.]

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>175396</tid>
<number>5</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Powers and duties of the Committee. Subject to such rules as 
may be made under this Act, the powers and duties of the Committee 
shall be--








</article>



<article><tid>254471</tid>
<number>6</number>Power of Central Government to make rules. The Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules 3 
to carry out the objects of this Act, and to regulate access to the 
Samadhi or to any portion thereof.


</article>



<article><tid>961903</tid>
<number> 7</number> 
<section><tid>625154</tid>
<number>1</number>Power of Committee to make bye- laws. The Committee may <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>, by  
notification in the Official Gazette,] make byelaws consistent with 
this Act and the rules made thereunder for all or any of the following 
purposes, namely:-

<subsection><tid>599419</tid>
<number>a</number>the manner in which meetings of the Committee shall be 
convened, the quorum for the transaction of any business 
thereat and the procedure at such meetings;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>6454</tid>
<number>b</number>the appointment of such persons as may be necessary to 
assist the Committee in the efficient performance of its 
duties and the terms and conditions of service of such 
employees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1873799</tid>
<number>c</number>the duties and powers of the employees of the 
Committee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>86912</tid>
<number>d</number>the submission of accounts, returns and reports to the 
Committee by any of its employees.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>27</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 37 of <year>1958</year>, S. 2 (w. e. f. 9- 3- <year>1959</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by Act 30 of <year>1988</year>, s. 2.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>For Rajghat Samadhi Rules, <year>1952</year>, see Gazette of India, <year>1952</year>, Pt. II, 
Sec. 3, p. 948.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Ins. by s. 3



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

 (The Schedule.)


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1817277</tid>
<number>2</number>All bye- laws made under this section shall be subject to the 
condition of previous publication and shall not have effect until they 
are approved by the Central Government.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>713587</tid>
<number>7A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Rule and bye- laws to be laid before Parliament. Every rule 
and every bye- law made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be 
after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in 
session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the 
expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or the bye- law or both Houses agree that the 
rule or bye- law should not be made, the rule or bye- law shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule or bye- law.]


</article>



<article><tid>1653606</tid>
<number>8</number>Validity of acts of Committee not to be questioned by reason 
of vacancy, etc. No act or proceeding of the Committee shall be deemed 
to be invalid merely by reason of any vacancy in, or any defect in the 
constitution of, the Committee.

</article>



 </act>