<act><title>THE HAZARDOUS WASTES (MANAGEMENT, HANDLING AND TRANSBOUNDARY MOVEMENT) RULES, 20081</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be called the Hazardous Wastes (Management, Handling and Transboundary Movement) Rules, 2008. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of their publication in the Official Gazette. 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number>Application. </title>These rules shall apply to the handling of hazardous wastes as specified in the Schedules and shall not apply to 
 
 <section><number>a</number> waste-water and exhaust gases as covered under the provisions of the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1974 (6 of 1974) and the Air (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1981 (14 of 1981) and rules made thereunder; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> wastes arising out of the operation from ships beyond five kilometres of the relevant baseline as covered under the provisions of the Merchant Shipping Act, 1958 (44 of 1958), and the rules made thereunder; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> radio-active wastes as covered under the provisions of the Atomic Energy Act, 1962 (33 of 1962), and the rules made thereunder; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> bio-medical wastes covered under the Bio-Medical Wastes (Management and Handling) Rules, 1998 made under the Act; and 
 </section><section><number>e</number> wastes covered under the Municipal Solid Wastes (Management and Handling) Rules, 2000 made under the Act. 
</section>


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Definitions. </title>
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires, 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> Act means the Environment (Protection) Act, 1986 (29 of 1986); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> authorisation means permission for generation, handling, collection, reception, treatment, transport, storage, recycling, reprocessing, recovery, reuse and disposal of hazardous wastes granted under sub-rule (4) of rule 5; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> Basel Convention is the United Nations Environment Programme Convention on the Control of Transboundary Movement of Hazardous Wastes and their Disposal; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> Central Pollution Control Board means the Central Pollution Control Board constituted under sub­-section (1) of section 3 of the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1974 (6 of 1974); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> disposal means any operation which does not lead to recycling, recovery or reuse and includes physico chemical, biological treatment, incineration and disposal in secured landfill; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> export with its grammatical variations and cognate expressions, means taking out of India to a place outside India ; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> exporter means any person under the jurisdiction of the exporting country who exports hazardous waste including the country, which exports hazardous waste ; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> environmentally sound management of hazardous wastes means taking all steps required to ensure that the hazardous wastes are managed in a manner which shall protect health and the environment against the adverse effects which may result from such waste; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> environmentally sound technologies means any technology approved by the Central Government from time to time; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> facility means any establishment wherein the processes incidental to the handling, collection, reception, treatment, storage, recycling, recovery, reuse and disposal of hazardous wastes are carried out; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number> Form means a form appended to these rules; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number> hazardous waste means any waste which by reason of any of its physical, chemical, reactive, toxic, flammable, explosive or corrosive characteristics causes danger or in likely to cause danger to health or environment, whether alone or when in contact with other wastes or substances, and shall include 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> waste specified under column (3) of Schedule I, 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> wastes having constituents specified in Schedule II if their concentration is equal to or more than the limit indicated in the said Schedule, and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number> waster specified in Part A or Part B of the Schedule III in respect of import or export of such wastes in accordance with rules 12, 13 and 14 or the wastes other than those specified in Part A or  
      Part B if they possess any of the hazardous characteristics specified in Part C of that Schedule; 
</subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>m</number> hazardous waste site means a place of collection, reception treatment, storage of hazardous wastes and its disposal to the environment which is approved by the competent authority; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>n</number> import with its grammatical variations and cognate expressions, means bringing into India from a place outside India ; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>o</number> importer means an occupier or any person who imports hazardous waste; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>p</number> manifest means transporting document prepared and signed by the occupier or his representative authorized in accordance with the provision of these rules. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>q</number> occupier in relation to any factory or premises, means a person who has control over the affairs of the factory or the premises and includes in relation to any hazardous waste the person in possession of the hazardous waste; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>r</number> operator of disposal facility means a person who owns or operates a facility for collections, reception, treatment, storage or disposal of hazardous wastes; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>ra</number> other wastes  wastes specified in Part D of Schedule III shall not be Hazardous waste unless they possess any of the Hazardous characteristics specified in Part C of the Schedule in respect of import or export of such wastes in accordance with rules 12, 13 and 14.] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>s</number> recycler or reprocessor or actual user means an occupier who procures and processes hazardous waste for recycling or recovery or re-use; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>t</number> recycling means reclamation and reprocessing of hazardous waste in an environmentally sound manner for the original purpose or for other purposes; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>u</number> reuse means use of hazardous waste for the purpose of its original use or other use; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> recovery means any operation in the recycling activity wherein specific materials are recovered; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>w</number> Schedule means a Schedule appended to these rules; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>x</number> State Government in relation to a Union territory means, the Administrator thereof appointed under Article 239 of the Constitution; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>y</number> State Pollution Control Board means the State Pollution Control Board or the Pollution Control Committee constituted under sub-section (1) of section 4 of the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution Act, 1974 (6 of 1974); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>z</number> storage means storing any hazardous waste for a temporary period, at the end of which such waste is processed or disposed of; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>za</number> transboundary movement means any movement of hazardous wastes from an area under the jurisdiction of one country to or through an area under the jurisdiction of another country or to or through an area not under the jurisdiction of any country, provided at least two countries are involved in the movement; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>zb</number> transport means off-site movement of hazardous wastes by air, rail, road or water; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>zc</number> transporter means a person engaged in the off-site transportation of hazardous waste by air, rail, road or water; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>zd</number> treatment means a method, technique or process, designed to modify the physical, chemical or biological characteristics or 
 composition of any hazardous waste so as to reduce its potential to cause harm; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ze</number> used oil means any oil 
 </subsection><subsection><number>a</number> derived from crude oil or mixtures containing synthetic oil including used engine oil, gear oil, hydraulic oil, turbine oil, compressor oil, industrial gear oil, heat transfer oil, transformer oil, spent oil and their, tank bottom sludges; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> suitable for reprocessing, if it meets the specification laid down in Part A of Schedule V but does not include waste oil; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>zf</number> waste oil means any oil which includes spills of crude oil, emulsions, tank bottom sludge and slop oil generated from petroleum refineries, installation or ships and can be used as fuel in furnaces for energy recovery, if it meets the specifications laid down in Part B of Schedule 5 either as such or after reprocessing. 
</subsection>
 Words and expressions used in these rules and not defined but defined in the Act shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act. 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number>Responsibility of the occupier for handling of hazardous wastes. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The occupier shall be responsible for safe and environmentally sound handling of hazardous wastes generated in his establishment. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The hazardous wastes generated in the establishment of an occupier shall be sent or sold to a recycler or re-processor or re-user registered or authorized under these rules or shall be disposed of in an authorized disposal facility. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The hazardous wastes transported from an occupier's establishment to a recycler for recycling or reuse or reprocessing or to an authorized facility for disposal shall be transported in accordance with the provisions of these rules. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The occupier or any other person acting on his behalf who intends to get his hazardous wastes treated and disposed of by the operator of a Treatment, Storage and Disposal Facility shall give to the operator of a facility, such information as may be determined by the State Pollution Control Board. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The occupier shall take all adequate steps while handling hazardous wastes to 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> contain contaminants and prevent accidents and limit their consequences on human beings and the environment; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> provide person workings on the site with the training, equipment and the information necessary to ensure their safety. 
</subsection>


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number>Grant of authorization for handling hazardous wastes. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Every person who is engaged in generation, processing, treatment, package, storage, transportation, use, collection, destruction, conversion, offering for sale, transfer or the like of the hazardous waste shall require to obtain an authorization from the State Pollution Control Board. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The hazardous waste shall be collected, treated, re-cycled, re-processed, stored or disposed of only in such facilities as may be authorized by the State Pollution Control Board for the purpose. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every person engaged in generation, processing, treatment, package storage, transportation, use, collection, destruction, conversion, offering for sale, transfer or the like of the hazardous waste or occupier of the facility shall make an application in Form 1 to the State Pollution Control Board for authorization within a period of sixty days from the date of commencement of these rules: 
 Provided that any person authorized under the provisions of the Hazardous Waste (Management and Handling) Rules, 1989, prior to the date of coming into force of these rules, shall not require to make an application for authorization till the period of expiry of such authorization. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> On receipt of the application complete in all respects for the authorization, the State Pollution Control Board may, after such inquiry as it considers necessary and on being satisfied that the applicant possesses appropriate facilities, technical capabilities and equipment to handle hazardous waste safely, grant within a period of one hundred and twenty days an authorization in Form 2 to the applicant which shall be valid for a period for five years and shall be subject to such conditions as may be laid down therein. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The State Pollution Control Board may after giving reasonable opportunity of being heard to the applicant refuse to grant any authorization. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> Every person authorized under these rules shall maintain the record of hazardous wastes handles by him in Form 3 and prepare and submit to the State Pollution Control Board, an annual return containing the details specified in Form 4 on or before the 30th day of June following to the financial year to which that return relates. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> An application for the renewal of an authorization shall be made in Form 1, before its expiry and the State Pollution Control Board may renew the authorization after examining each case on merit subject to the conditions that there has been no report of violation of the provisions of the Act or the rules made thereunder or conditions specified in the authorization. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> The occupier or operator of the facility shall take all the steps, wherever required, for reduction and prevention of the waste generated or for recycling or reuse and comply the conditions specified in the authorization. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> The State Pollution Control Board shall maintain a register containing particulars of the conditions imposed under these rules for management of hazardous waste, and it shall be open for inspection during office hours to any person interested or affected or a person authorized by him on his behalf. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number>Power to suspend or cancel an authorisation. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The State Pollution Control Board, may, if in its opinion the holder of the authorization has failed to comply with any of the conditions of the authorisation or with any provisions of the Act or these rules, and after giving him a reasonable opportunity of being heard and after recording reasons therefor in writing cancel or suspend the authorization issued under rule 4 for such period as it considers necessary in the public interest. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Upon suspension or cancellation of the authorization the State Pollution Control Board may give directions to the persons whose authorization has been suspended or cancelled for the safe storage of the hazardous wastes, and such person shall comply with such directions. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number>Storage of Hazardous Waste. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The occupier, recyclers, re-processors, re-users, and operators of facilities may store the hazardous wastes for a period not exceeding ninety days and shall maintain a record of sale, transfer, storage, recycling and reprocessing of such wastes and make these records available for inspection: 
 Provided that the State Pollution Control Board may extend the said period in following cases, namely: 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> small generators up to ten tonnes per annum; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> recyclers, re-processors and facility operators up to six months of their annual capacity; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> generators who do not have access to any Treatment, Storage, Disposal Facility in the concerned State; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> the waste which needs to be specifically stored for development of a process for its recycling, reuse. 
</subsection>


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number> Procedure for grant of registration. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Every person desirous of recycling or reprocessing the hazardous waste specified in Schedule IV may make an application in Form 5 accompanied with a copy each of the following documents for the grant or renewal of the registration: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> consent to establish grated by the State Pollution Control Board under the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1974 (25 of 1974) and the Air (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1981, (21 of 1981). 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> certificate of registration issued by the District Industries Centre or any other government agency authorised in this regard; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> proof of installed capacity of plant and machinery issued by the District Industries Centre or any other Government agency authorised in this behalf; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> in case of renewal, certificate of compliance of effluent, emission standards and treatment and disposal of hazardous wastes, as applicable from the State Pollution Control Board or the Concerned Zonal Office of Central Pollution Control Board. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Central Pollution Control Board, on being satisfied that the applicant is utilizing environmentally sound technologies and possesses adequate technical capabilities requisite facilities, and equipment to recycle, reprocess or reuse hazardous wastes, may grant registration to such applicants stipulation therein necessary conditions for carrying out safe operations in the authorized place only. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Central Pollution Control Board shall dispose of the application for registration within a period of one hundred twenty days from the date of the receipt of such application complete in all respects. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The registration, issued under sub-rule (2) shall be valid for a period of five years from the date of its issue, unless the operation is discontinued by the unit or the registration is suspended or cancelled by the Central Pollution Control Board. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Central Pollution Control Board may cancel or suspend the registration granted under these rules, if it has reasons to believe that the recycler or re-processor has failed to comply with any of the conditions of the registration, or with any provisions of the Act or rules made thereunder. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Central Pollution Control Board may after giving a reasonable opportunity of being heard to the applicant, by order, refuse to grant or renew the registration. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> The recycler or re-processor shall maintain records of hazardous wastes purchased and processed and shall file an annual return of its activities of previous year in Form 6 to the State Pollution Control Board, on or before the 30th day of June of every year. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>8</number> Every trader desirous of import of metal scrap, paper waste and other wastes as listed in Schedule III (Part D) may make an application in Form 16 to any of the State Pollution Control Boards or Pollution Control Committees. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> The State Pollution Control Boards or Pollution Control Committees will register the trader on a one time basis and registration would be considered as deemed if not objected to within a period of 30 days. 
 </section><section><number>10</number> The registered trader shall be required to submit details of such import and particulars of the actual users along with quantities to the concerned State Pollution Control Board or Pollution Control Committees on a quarterly basis and registration would be liable for cancellation on failure to furnish these details to the State Pollution Control Boards or Pollution Control Committees: 
 Provided that the registration granted to the trader shall not be cancelled unless he has been given a reasonable opportunity of hearing. 
 </section><section><number>11</number> An appeal shall lie against any order of suspension or cancellation or refusal of registration passed by the Member-Secretary of the State Pollution Control Board or Pollution Control Committees or any other officer designated by the State Pollution Control Boards or Pollution Control Committees as laid down in rule 26 of the said rules. 
 </section><section><number>12</number> The appeal shall be in writing and shall be accompanied with a copy of the order appealed against and shall be made within period of thirty days from the date of passing of the order.] 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>9</number>Conditions for sale or transfer of Hazardous Wastes for recycling. </title>The occupier generating the hazardous wastes specified in Schedule IV may sell it only to the recycler having a valid registration from the Central Pollution Control Board for recycling or recovery. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>10</number> Standards for recycling. </title>The Central Government and Central Pollution Control Board may issue the guidelines for standards of performance for recycling processes from time to time. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>11</number>Utilization of hazardous wastes. </title>The utilization of hazardous wastes as a supplementary resource or for energy recovery, or after processing shall be carried out by units only after obtaining approval from the Central Pollution Control Board. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>12</number>Import and export (transboundary movement) of hazardous wastes. </title>The Ministry of Environment and Forests shall be the nodal Ministry to deal with the transboundary movement of the hazardous wastes and to grant permission for transit of the hazardous wastes through any part of India. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>13</number>Import and export of hazardous wastes. </title>
<section><number>1</number> No import of the hazardous wastes from any country to India for disposal shall be permitted. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The import of hazardous waste from any country shall be permitted only for the recycling or recovery or reuses. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The export of hazardous wastes from India may be allowed to an actual user of the wastes or operator of a disposal facility with the Prior Informed Consent of the importing country to ensure environmentally sound management of the hazardous waste in question. 

 </section><section><number>4</number> No import or export of the hazardous wastes specified in Schedule VI shall be permitted. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>14</number>Import or export of hazardous waste for recycling, recovery and reuses. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The import and export of the hazardous wastes specified in Schedule III, shall be regulated in accordance with the conditions laid down in the said Schedule. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Subject to the provisions contained in sub-rule (1), 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> the import or export of the hazardous wastes specified in Part A of Schedule III shall require Prior Informed Consent of the country from where it is imported or exported to, and shall require the licence from the Directorate-General of Foreign Trade and the prior written permission of the Central Government; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> the import of the hazardous wastes specified in Part B of Schedule III shall not require Prior Informed Consent of the country from where it is imported; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> the import and export of the hazardous wastes not specified in Part A and Part B of Schedule III but having the hazardous characteristics outlined in Part C of the said Schedule shall require the prior written permission of the Central Government, before it is imported into or exported from India, as the case may be. 
</subsection>


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>15</number>Procedure for export of hazardous wastes from India. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Any person intending to export hazardous wastes specified in Schedule III shall apply in Form 7 and Form 8 along with full cover insurance policy for consignment to the Central Government for the proposed transboundary movement of the hazardous wastes together with the Prior Informed Consent in writing from the importing country. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> On receipt of such application, the Central Government may give a No Objection Certificate' for the proposed export within a period of sixty days from the date of submission of the application and may impose conditions as it may consider necessary. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Central Government, shall forward a copy of the No Objection Certificate' granted under sub-rule (2), to the Central Pollution Control Board, the concerned State Pollution Control Board and the concerned Port and Customs authorities for ensuring compliance of the conditions, if any, of the export and to take appropriate steps for the safe handling of the waste shipment. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The exporter shall ensure that no consignment is shipped before the No Objection Certificate' is received from the importing country. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The exporter shall also ensure that the shipment is accompanied with the Movement Document in Form 9. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The exporter shall inform the Ministry of Environment and Forest upon completion of the transboundary movement. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> The exporter of the hazardous wastes shall maintain the records of the hazardous wastes exported by him in Form 10 and the record so maintained shall be available for inspection.. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>16</number> Procedure for import of Hazardous Waste. </title>
<section><number>1</number> A person intending to import or transit for transboundary movement of hazardous wastes specified in Schedule III shall apply in Form 7 and Form 8 to the Central Government of the proposed import wherever applicable, together with the Prior Informed Consent, which ever applicable and shall send a copy of the application, simultaneously, to the concerned State Pollution Control Board to enable them to send their comments and observations, if any, to the Ministry of Environment and Forests within a period of thirty days. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> On receipt of the application in complete, the Ministry of Environment and Forests shall examine the application considering the comments and observations, if any, received from the State Pollution Control Boards, and may grant the permission for import within a period of sixty days subject to the condition that the importer has 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> the environmentally sound recycling, recovery or reuse facilities; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> adequate facilities and arrangement for treatment and disposal of wastes generated; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> a valid registration from the Central Pollution Control Board and a proof of being an actual user, if required under these rules. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Ministry of Environment and Forests shall forward a copy of the permission granted under sub-rule (2) to the Central Pollution Control Board, the concerned State Pollution Control Board and the concerned Port and Customs authorities for ensuring compliance of the conditions of imports and safe handling of the hazardous waste. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Ministry of Environment and Forests shall communicate the permission to the importer. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Port and Customs authorities shall ensure that shipment is accompanied by the Movement Document in Form 9 and the test report of analysis of the hazardous waste consignment in question, from a laboratory accredited by the exporting country: 
 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[Provided that the Port or Customs authorities shall, in case of import of <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[Metal scrap, paper waste and other wastes] covered under Basel numbers B1010, B1040, B1050, B1100, B1230 and B 3020 as specified in <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[Part D] of the Schedule III, ensure that shipment is accompanied by the Movement Document in Form 9 and preshipment inspection certificate issued by the inspection agency certified by the exporting country <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[or the inspection and certification agency approved by the Director General of Foreign Trade].] 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Customs authority shall collect three randomly drawn samples of the consignment (prior to clearing the consignment as per the provisions laid down under the Customs Act, 1962) for analysis and retain the report for a period of two years, in order to ensure that in the event of any dispute, as to whether the consignment conforms or not to the declaration made in the application and Movement Document. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[<number>6A</number> Nothing contained in sub-rule (6) shall apply to the <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[metal scrap, paper waste and other wastes] covered under the Basel number B1010, B1040, B1050, B1100, B1230, and B3020 as specified in <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[Part D] of the Schedule III: 
 Provided that the customs authority may, at any time if it considers necessary, make random inspection of the consignment prior to clearing the consignment.] 
 </section><section><number>7</number> The importer of the hazardous waste shall maintain records of the hazardous waste imported by him in Form 10 and the record so maintained shall be available for inspection. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> The importer shall also inform the concerned State Pollution Control Board and the Central Pollution Control Board, the date and time of the arrival of the consignment of the hazardous waste ten days in advance. 









</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>17</number>Illegal Traffic. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The export and import of hazardous wastes from and into India shall be deemed illegal if 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> it is without permission of the Central Government in accordance with these rules; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> the permission has been obtained through falsification, mis-representation or fraud; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> it does not conform to the shipping details provided in the movement documents; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> it results in deliberate disposal ( i.e. , dumping) of hazardous wastes in contravention of the Basel Convention and of general principles of International or National Law. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> In case of illegal import of the hazardous wastes, the importer shall re-export the waste in question at his cost within a period of ninety days from the date of its arrival into India and its implementation will be ensured by the concerned State Pollution Control Board. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>18</number> Treatment, Storage and Disposal Facility for hazardous wastes. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The State Government, occupier, operator of a facility or any association of occupiers shall individually or jointly or severally be responsible for, and identify sites for establishing the facility for treatment, storage and disposal of the hazardous wastes in the State. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The operator of common facility or occupier of a captive facility, shall design and set up the Treatment, Storage and Disposal Facility as per technical guidelines issued by the Central Pollution Control Board in this regard from time to time and shall obtain approval from the State Pollution Control Board for design and layout in this regard from time to time. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The State Pollution Control Board shall monitor the setting up and operation of the Treatment, Storage and Disposal Facilities regularly. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The operator of the Treatment, Storage and Disposal Facility shall be responsible for safe and environmentally sound operation of the Treatment, the Storage and Disposal Facility and its closure and post closure phase, as per guidelines issued by the Central Pollution Control Board from time to time. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The operator of the Treatment, Storage and Disposal Facility shall maintain records of hazardous wastes handled by him in [Form 3]. 


2. Subs. by S.O. 1799(E), dated 21st July, 2009, for “Form 10” (w.e.f. 21-7-2009). 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>19</number>Packaging and labelling. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The occupier or operator of the Treatment, Storage and Disposal Facility or recycler shall ensure that the hazardous waste are packaged and labelled, based on the composition in a manner suitable for safe handling, storage and transport as per the guidelines issued by the Central Pollution Control Board from time to time. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The labelling and packaging shall be easily visible and be able to withstand physical conditions and climatic factors. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>20</number>Transportation of Hazardous waste. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The transport of the hazardous wastes shall be in accordance with the provisions of these rules and the rules made by the Central Government under the Motor Vehicles Act, 1988 and other guidelines issued from time to time in this regard. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The occupier shall provide the transporter with the relevant information in Form 11, regarding the hazardous nature of the wastes and measures to be taken in case of an emergency and shall mark the hazardous wastes containers as per Form 12. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> In case of transport of hazardous wastes for final disposal to a facility for treatment, storage and disposal existing in a State other than the State where the hazardous waste is generated, the occupier shall obtain No Objection Certificate' from the State Pollution Control Board of both the States. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> In case of transportation of hazardous wastes through a State other than the State of origin or destination, the occupier shall intimate the concerned State Pollution Control Boards before he hands over the hazardous wastes to the transporter. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>22</number>Records and returns. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The occupier generating hazardous wastes and operator of the facility for disposal of hazardous waste shall maintain records of such operations in Form 3. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The occupier and operator of a facility shall send annual returns to the State Pollution Control Board in Form 4. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The State Pollution Control Board shall prepare an inventory of the hazardous wastes within its jurisdiction and compile other related information like recycling of the hazardous wastes and treatment and disposal of the hazardous wastes based on the returns filed by respective occupier and operator of the facility. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>23</number>Responsibility of Authorities. </title>The Authority specified in column 2 of the Schedule VII shall perform the duties as specified in column 3 of the Schedule subject to the provisions of these rules. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>24</number>Accident reporting and follow-up. </title>Where an accident occurs at the facility or on a hazardous waste site or during transportation of the hazardous waste, the occupier or operator of the facility or the transporter, as the case may be, shall report immediately to the State Pollution Control Board about the accident in Form 14. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>25</number>Liability of occupier, transporter, operator of a facility and importer. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The occupier, importer, transporter and operator of the facility shall be liable for all damages caused to the environment or third party due to improper handling of the hazardous wastes or disposal of the hazardous wastes. 
(2) The occupier and the operator of the facility shall be liable to pay financial penalties as levied for any violation of the provisions under these rules by the State Pollution Control Board with the prior approval of the Central Pollution Control Board.


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>26</number>Appeal. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Any person aggrieved by an order of suspension or cancellation or refusal of authorization or its renewal passed by the State Pollution Control Board, may, within a period of thirty days from the date on which the order is communicated to him, prefer an appeal in Form 15 to the Appellate Authority comprising of the Environment Secretary of the State. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any person aggrieved by an order of suspension or cancellation or refusal of registration or its renewal passed by the Central Pollution Control Board, may, within a period of thirty days from the date on which the order is communicated to him, prefer an appeal in Form 15 to the Appellate Authority comprising of the Secretary, to the Government of India in the Ministry of Environment and Forests. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Appellate Authority may entertain the appeal after the expiry of the said period of thirty days if it is satisfied that the appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from filing the appeal in time. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Every appeal filed under this rule shall be disposed of within a period of sixty days from the date of its filing. 


</section></article><form>
 

THE HAZARDOUS WASTES (MANAGEMENT, HANDLING AND TRANSBOUNDARY MOVEMENT) RULES, 20081
 

 
 

FORM 15 
 

[ See  rules 26(1) and (2)] 
 

APPLICATION FOR FILING APPEAL AGAINST THE ORDER PASSED  

  BY CPCB/SPCB/PCc OF THE UNION TERRITORY 
 

1. Name and address of the person making the appeal : 
 

2. Number, date of order and address of the authority : (certified copy 
  order to which passed the order, against which appeal of the order 
  is being made be attached). 
 

3. Ground on which the appeal is being made : 
 

4. Relief sought for : 
 

5. List of enclosures other than the order referred 
  in para 2 against which the appeal is being filed. : 
 

Signature........................................
 

Name and address....................... 
 

Date.................... 
 

-------- 
 

1. Vide S.O. 2265(E), dated 24th September, 2008, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(ii), dated 24th September, 2008. 
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Came into force on 24-9-2008 .</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Ins. by S.O. 710(E), dated 30th March, 2010 (w.e.f. 30-3-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Ins. by S.O. 710(E), dated 30th March, 2010 (w.e.f. 30-3-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Ins. by S.O. 1799(E), dated 21st July, 2009 (w.e.f. 21-7-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Subs. by S.O. 710(E), dated 30th March, 2010, for hazardous wastes (w.e.f. 30-3-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Subs. by S.O. 710(E), dated 30th March, 2010, for Part B (w.e.f. 30-3-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Ins. by S.O. 2447(E), dated 23rd September, 2009 (w.e.f. 23-9-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Ins. by S.O. 1799(E), dated 21st July, 2009 (w.e.f. 21-7-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> Subs. by S.O. 710(E), dated 30th March, 2010 for hazardous wastes (w.e.f. 30-3-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> Subs. by S.O. 710(E), dated 30th March, 2010, for Part B (w.e.f. 30-3-2010).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>