<act><title>


The Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) Rules, 19711</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title.—These 
rules may be called the Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) 
Rules, 1971.
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Form of notices or 
orders.—A 
notice or order under the Act shall be in one of the appropriate Forms appended 
to these rules.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Form of notices or 
orders.—A 
notice or order under the Act shall be in one of the appropriate Forms appended 
to these rules.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Manner of service of 
notices and orders.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In addition to any mode of service specified in the Act, 

1[a notice issued 
under sub-section (1) of section 4 or sub-section (2) of section 5A or 
sub-section (1) of section 5B or sub-section (1) or sub-section (1A) of section 
6 

2[or an order 
issued under section 3A or sub-section (1) of section 5] or sub-section (1) or 
sub-section (2) or sub-section (5) of section 5B or sub-section (1) or 
sub-section (2) of section 5C or sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) of section 7 
of the said Act shall be served by delivering, or tendering a copy of the notice 
or order, as the case may be,] to the person for whom it is intended or to any 
adult member of his family, or by sending it by registered post acknowledgement 
due in a letter addressed to that person at his usual or last-known place of 
residence or business.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the copy of


1[the notice or the 
order, as the case may be,] under sub-rule (1) is delivered or tendered the 
signature of the person to whom the copy is so delivered or tendered should be 
obtained in token of acknowledgement of the service.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In respect of a 

1[notice issued 
under sub-section (1) of section 4 or sub-section (2) of section 5A or 
sub-section (1) or sub-section (1A) of section 6 

2[or an order 
issued under section 3A or sub-section (1) or sub-section (3) of section 5A] or 
sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) or sub-section (5) of section 5B or 
sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) of section 5C or sub-section (1) or 
sub-section (2) of section 7 of the said Act] where the person or the adult 
member of the family of such person refuses to sign the acknowledgement, or 
where such person cannot be found after using all due and reasonable diligence, 
and there is no adult member of the family of such person, a copy of 

1[the notice or the 
order, as the case may be], shall be affixed on the outer door or some other 
conspicuous part of the ordinary residence or usual place of business of such 
person and the original shall be re­turned to the estate officer who issued


1[the notice or the 
order, as the case may be] with a report endorsed thereon or annexed thereto 
stating that a copy has been so affixed, the circumstances under which it was 
done so and the name 

3[and] address of 
the person, if any, by whom the ordinary residence or usual place of business 
was identified and in whose presence the copy was affixed.
 

4[(4) If a notice 
under sub-section (1) of section 4 or sub-section (2) of section 5A or 
sub-section (1) or sub-section (1A) of section 6 or an order issued under 
sub-section (1) of section 5 or sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) or 
sub-section (5) of section 5B or sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) of section 
5E or sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) of section 7 of the said Act cannot be 
served in the manner provided in sub-rule(1), the estate officer may, if he 
thinks fit, direct that such notice or order, as the case may be, shall also be 
published in at least one newspaper having circulation in the locality and he 
may also proclaim the contents of any notice or order in the locality by beat of 
drum.]
 
 






</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Holding of 
inquiries.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where any person on whom a notice or order under this Act has been served 
desires to be heard through his representative he should authorise such 
representa­tive in writing.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The estate officer 
shall record the summary of the evidence tendered before him. The summary of 
such evidence and any rele­vant documents filed before him shall form part of 
the records of the proceedings.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Transfer of pending 
proceedings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
On the application of any person to whom a notice under the Act has been served 
and after hearing him, if he desires to be heard, or of its or his own motion, 
the Central Government or any Gazetted officer especially authorised by the 
Central Government in this behalf by notifica­tion in the Official Gazette
may at any stage transfer any proceeding before an estate officer for 
disposal of the same.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any proceeding 
has been transferred under sub-rule (1), the estate officer who thereafter is in 
charge of such proceeding may, subject to any special directions in the order of 
transfer, either re-start it or proceed from the point at which it was 
transferred.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Manner of taking 
possession of public premises.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
If any obstruction is offered, or is in the opinion of the estate offi­cer 
likely to be offered—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> to the taking 
possession of any public premises; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> to the sealing 
of erection or work or of the public premises, under the said Act, the estate 
officer or any other officer duly authorised by him in this behalf may obtain 
necessary police assistance:
 
Provided that no sealing 
or taking possession of the unauthorised construction shall be made before 
sunrise or after sunset.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any public 
premises of which possession is to be taken under the Act is found locked, the 
estate officer or any other officer duly authorised by him in this behalf may 
either seal the premises or in the presence of two witnesses break open the 
locks or open or cause to be opened any door, gate or other barrier and enter 
the premises:
 
Provided that,—
 </section><section>
       <number>1</number>  no entry shall 
be made into, or possession taken of a public premises before sunrise or after 
sunset;
 </section><section>
       <number>2</number>  where any 
public premises is forced open, an inventory of the articles found in the 
premises shall be taken in the presence of two witnesses.
 

2[(3) The sealing 
under sub-section (1) of section 5C of the Act shall be made in the following 
manners, namely:—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number> affixing the 
office seal on outer door or any erection or work of any public premises after 
all other outlets and inlets to the erection or work or public premises have 
been properly bolt­ed, locked or encircled with rope, wire or wire mesh;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number> where doors 
and windows have not been fixed to any erection or work or public premises or 
where the erection of work on public premises is of such a nature that it cannot 
be encircled with rope, wire or wire-mesh in that case such erection or work or 
public premises shall be covered by wooden planks, iron or cement sheets and 
office seal affixed in a manner that no person can enter into or upon the 
erection or work or public premises without tampering the office seal:
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number> where any 
erection or work or any public premises is found locked, the lock may be broken 
or any door, gate or any other barrier caused to be opened in the presence of 
two witnesses and an inventory of the articles found in the premises shall be 
prepared in the presence of the two witnesses before affixing the seal in the 
manner aforesaid.]
 
 




</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Assessment of 
damages.—In 
assessing damages for unauthorised use and occupation of any public premises the 
estate officer shall take into consideration the following matters, namely:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number> the purpose and 
the period for which the public premises were in unauthorised occupation;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number> the nature, 
size and standard of the accommodation available in such premises;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number> the rent that 
would have been realised if the premises had been let on rent for the period of 
unauthorised occupation to a private person;
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number> any damage done 
to the premises during the period of unautho­rised occupation;
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number> any other 
matter relevant for the purpose of assessing the damages.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Procedure in 
appeals.—
<section><number>1</number> An 
appeal preferred under section 9 of the Act shall be in writing, shall set forth 
concisely the grounds of objection to the order appealed against, and shall be 
accompanied by a copy of such order.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On receipt of the 
appeal and after calling for and perusing the record of the proceedings before 
the estate officer, the appellate officer shall appoint a time and place for the 
hearing of the appeal and shall give notice thereof to the estate officer 
against whose order the appeal is preferred, to the appellant and to the head of 
the department or authority in administrative control of the premises.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Repeal.—The 
Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occu­pants) Rules, 1958, is hereby 
repealed.
 
 
</article><form>
 




The Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) Rules, 1971
 


 
 




1[FORM 
A
 


Form of notice under 
sub-section (1) and clause (b) (ii) of sub-section (2) of section 4 of the 
Public Premises (Eviction of Unau­thorised Occupants) Act, 1971
 


To
 



Shri/Smt./Km...............................................................................
 


Whereas I, the undersigned, 
am of opinion, on the grounds speci­fied below that you are in unauthorised 
occupation of the Public Premises mentioned in the Schedule below and that you 
should be evicted from the said premises:
 


Grounds
 


Now, therefore, in 
pursuance of sub-section (1) of section 4 of the Act, I hereby call upon you to 
show cause on or before the*...................................... why such an 
order of eviction should not be made.
 


And in pursuance of clause 
(b) (ii) of sub-section (2) of section 4, I also call upon you to appear before 
me in person or through a duly authorised representative capable to answer all 
material questions connected with the matter along the evidence which you intend 
to produce in support of the cause shown, 
on...................at..................for personal hearing. In case, you fail 
to appear on the said date and time, the case will be decided ex parte.
 


Schedule
 



Date..................                                                       
Signature and seal of the Estate Officer]
 


      
......................................................................
 


          *  This date 
should be a date later than 7 days from the date of issue of this notice.
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Subs. by G.S.R. 41, 
dated 4th July, 1981 (w.e.f. 8-8-1981).
 


 
</form><form>
 




The Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) Rules, 1971
 


 
 




1[FORM 
AA
 


Form of notice under 
sub-section (2) of section, 5A of the Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised 
Occupants) Act, 1971
 


To
 



Shri/Smt./Km...............................................................................
 


Whereas I, the undersigned, 
am of the opinion on the grounds specified below, that the 
building/structure/fixture erected, goods displayed/spread, cattle/animal 
brought on the public premises mentioned in the Schedule below is/are in 
contravention of the provisions of sub-section (1) of section 5A and that the 
said building/structure/fixture, erected, goods displayed/spread, cattle/animal 
brought on the said public premises should be removed from the said premises.
 


Grounds
 


Now, therefore, in 
pursuance of sub-section (2) of section 5A of the Act, I hereby call upon you to 
remove the said building/structure/fixture erected, goods displayed spread, 
cattle/animal brought on the public premises mentioned in the Schedule below on 
or before the*......................or 
to show cause why this should not be removed on or before the above mentioned 
date. In the event of your refusal or failure to comply with this notice within 
the period specified above, the said goods/animal, cattle/work, etc., shall be 
removed by the Estate Officer autho­rised by him and the cost of such removal 
shall be recovered from you as arrears of land revenue.
 


Schedule
 



Date..................                                                       
Signature and seal of the Estate Officer]
 


      
......................................................................
 


      *  This date should 
be a date later than 7 days from the date of issue of this notice.
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Added by G.S.R. 41, 
dated 4th July, 1981 (w.e.f. 8-8-1981).
 


 
</form><form>
 




The Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) Rules, 1971
 

 
 

1[FORM AAI 
 

Order under sub-section (2) of section 5A of the said Act 
 

To 
 

Shri/Smt./Km............................................................................... 
 

Whereas, I the undersigned, is of the opinion on the grounds specified below that you have erected/placed/raised the building/immovable structure/fixture on the public premises mentioned in the Schedule below in contravention of the provisions of sub-section (1) of section 5A of the said Act; 
 

2. And whereas, by a written notice dated .................................. you were called upon to remove or to show cause by ............................. why you should not remove such building/immovable structure/fixture from the said public premises; 
 

And whereas you have omitted/refused to show cause/remove such building/immovable structure/fixture from the said public premises; 
 

And whereas I have considered the causes shown by you for not removing the said building/immovable structure/fixture from the said public premises. 
 

Grounds 
 

Now, therefore, in exercise of the powers conferred by sub-section (2) of section 5A of the said Act, I hereby order that the said building/immovable structure/fixture be removed form the said public premises. I also hereby order Shri/Smt./Km....................................... to pay a sum of Rs.............../- (Rupees..................................) assessed by me as cost of removal of the said building/immovable structure/fixture from the said public premises as an arrear of land revenue. 
 

Schedule 
 

Date.................. 
 

Signature and seal of the Estate Officer] 
 

...................................................................... 
 

 
 


—————
 


   1.  Ins. by G.S.R. 114 
(E), dated 23rd September, 1986 (w.e.f. 29-9-1986).
 


 
</form><form>
 




The Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) Rules, 1971
 


 
 




1[FORM 
AAII
 


Order under sub-section 
(3) of section 5A of the said Act
 


To
 



Shri/Smt./Km...............................................................................
 


Whereas, I the undersigned 
on the grounds specified below is of the opinion that the movable 
structure/fixture erected/placed/raised, goods displayed/spread, cattle/animal, 
brought/kept on the public premises mentioned in the Schedule below by 
Shri/Smt./Km.....................is/are contravention of the provi­sions of 
sub-section (1) of section 5A of the said Act and that the said movable 
structure/fixture erected/placed/raised, goods displayed/spread, cattle/animal 
brought on the said public premises be removed from the said premises;
 


Grounds
 


Now, therefore, in exercise 
of powers conferred by sub-section (3) of section 5A of the said Act, I hereby 
order that the said movable structure fixture, erected/placed, raised, goods 
dis­played spread, cattle/animal brought kept on the said public premises be 
removed from the said public premises. I also hereby order Shri/Smt./Km. 
.............. to pay a sum of Rs. ....................... (Rupees 
...................) assessed by me as cost of removal of movable 
structure/fixture erected placed/raised, goods displayed/spread, cattle/animal 
brought/kept on the said public premises as an arrear of land revenue.
 


Schedule
 



Date..................                                                       
Signature and seal of the Estate Officer]
 


      
......................................................................
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Ins. by G.S.R. 114 
(E), dated 23rd September, 1986 (w.e.f. 29-9-1986).
 


 
</form><form>
 




The Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) Rules, 1971
 


 
 




1[FORM 
AB
 


Form of notice under 
proviso to sub-section (1) of section 5B of the Act
 


To
 



Shri/Smt./Km...............................................................................
 


Whereas I, the undersigned 
is of the opinion on the grounds specified below, that you have 
erected/completed/commenced the work on the public premises specified below in 
the Schedule in contravention of, or not authorised by the competent authority 
and that the said work be demolished in the said premises.
 


Grounds
 


Now, therefore, in 
pursuance of proviso to sub-section (1) of section 5B of the said Act, I hereby 
call upon to show cause on or before the*

........................ why an order for demolition of such erec­tion work may 
not be made.
 


Schedule
 



Date..................                                                       
Signature and seal of the Estate Officer]
 


      
......................................................................
 


          *  This date 
should be a date after expiry of 7 days from the date of publication of the 
notice.
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Added by G.S.R. 41, 
dated 4th July, 1981.
 


 
</form><form>
 




The Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) Rules, 1971
 


 
 




1[FORM 
B
 


Order under sub-section 
(1) of section 5 of the Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) 
Act, 1971
 


Whereas I, the undersigned, 
am satisfied for the reasons recorded below that Shri/Smt./Km. 
............................... is/are in unauthorised occupation of the public 
premises specified in the Schedule below:
 


Reasons
 


Now, therefore, in exercise 
of the powers conferred on me under sub-section (1) of section 5 of the Public 
Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) Act, 1971, I hereby order the said 
Shri/Smt./Km. ........................ and all persons who may be in occupation 
of the said premises or any part thereof to vacate the said premises within 15 
days of the date of publication of this order. In the event of refusal or 
failure to comply with this order within the period specified above the said 
Shri/Smt./Km...........................and all other persons, concerned are 
liable to be evicted from the said prem­ises, if need be, by the use of such 
force as may be necessary.
 


Schedule
 



Date..................                                                       
Signature and seal of the Estate Officer]
 


      
......................................................................
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Subs. by G.S.R. 41, 
dated 4th July, 1981.
 


 
</form><form>
 




The Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) Rules, 1971
 


 
 




1[FORM 
BB
 


Notice/Order under 
sub-section (1) of section 5B of the said Act
 


To
 



Shri/Smt./Km...............................................................................
 


Whereas, I the undersigned, 
is satisfied for the reasons recorded below that the work 
created/completed/commenced by Shri/Smt./Km. ......................... on the 
public premises specified in the Schedule is in contravention of the provisions 
of the said Act, or not authorised by the competent authority;
 


And whereas, by a written 
notice dated*.................................. you were called upon to remove 
or to show cause by ............................... why you should not remove 
such building/immovable structure/fixture from the said public premises;
 


And whereas you have 
omitted/refused to show cause/remove such building/immovable structure/fixture 
from the said public prem­ises.
 


And whereas I have 
considered the cause shown by you for not removing the said building/immovable 
structure/fixture from the said public premises.
 


Reasons
 


Now, therefore, in exercise 
of the powers conferred by sub-section (1) of section 5B of the said Act, I 
hereby order Shri/Smt./Km. ........................that the said work shall be 
demolished. In the event of your refusal or failure to comply with this order, 
the said work shall be demolished by the Estate Officer or the officer 
authorised by him and the expenses of such demolition shall be recovered from 
you.
 


Schedule
 



Date..................                                                       
Signature and seal of the Estate Officer]
 


      
......................................................................
 


      *  This date should 
be a date after expiry 7 days from the date of publication of the notice.
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Ins. by G.S.R. 41, 
dated 4th July, 1981 and subs. by G.S.R. 114 (E), dated 23rd September, 1986.
 


 
</form><form>
 




The Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) Rules, 1971
 


 
 




1[FORM 
BBI
 


Order under sub-section 
(2) of section 5B of the said Act
 


To
 



Shri/Smt./Km...............................................................................
 


Whereas, I the undersigned, 
is of the opinion that the work erected/commenced by 
Shri/Smt./Km.......................on the public premises specified in the 
Schedule is in contravention of the Act or not authorised by the competent 
authority.
 


Reasons
 


Now, therefore, in exercise 
of the powers conferred by sub-section (2) of section 5B of the said Act, I 
hereby direct Shri/Smt./Km.......................... to stop the erection or 
work until the expiry of the period within which an appeal against the order of 
demoli­tion, if made may be preferred under section 9.
 


Schedule
 



Date..................                                                       
Signature and seal of the Estate Officer]
 


      
......................................................................
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Ins. by G.S.R. 114 
(E), dated 23rd September, 1986.
 


 
</form><form>
 




The Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) Rules, 1971
 


 
 




FORM BBII
 


Order under sub-section 
(5) of section 5B of the Act
 


Whereas in pursuance of the 
order under sub-section (1) of section 5B of the Public Premises (Eviction of 
Unauthorised Occupants) Act, 1971, the work erected/completed/commenced by Shri/Smt./Km......................on 
the public premises specified in the Schedule was demolished and the expenditure 
of such demolition are recoverable from the said Shri/Smt./Km............................
 


Now, therefore in exercise 
of the powers conferred by sub-section (5) of section 5B of the said Act, I 
hereby order Shri/Smt./Km.......................to pay a sum of Rs...................(Rupees...................) 
as expenses of such demolition within........(Date to be specified in order No. 
...............................of instalments.
 


Schedule
 



Date..................                                                       
Signature and seal of the Estate Officer]
 


      
......................................................................
 


 
</form><form>
 




The Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) Rules, 1971
 


 
 




1[FORM 
BC
 


Order under sub-section 
(1) of section 5C of the Act
 


Whereas, I the undersigned, 
is satisfied that the work erected/completed/commenced by 
Shri/Smt./Km...................on the public specified in the Schedule below is 
in contravention of the provi­sions of the said Act, or not authorised by the 
competent author­ity.
 


Now, therefore, in exercise 
of the powers conferred by sub-section (1) of section 5C of the said Act, I 
hereby order that the said work shall be sealed forthwith.
 


Schedule
 



Date..................                                                       
Signature and seal of the Estate Officer]
 


      
......................................................................
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Ins. by G.S.R. 114 
(E), dated 23rd September, 1986.
 


 
</form><form>
 




The Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) Rules, 1971
 


 
 




1[FORM 
BD
 


Order under sub-section 
(2) of section 5C of the Act
 


Whereas, the 
work/erected/completed/commenced by Shri/Smt./Km.......................... in 
contravention of the provisions of the said Act, or not authorised by the 
competent authority on the public premises specified in the Schedule below was 
sealed on.................in pursuance of order under sub-section (1) of section 
5C of the said Act.
 


And whereas it is necessary 
for such seal to be removed for the purpose of demolition of such work 
erected/completed commenced by Shri/Smt./Km. .....................in 
contravention of or not authorised by the competent authority for the purpose of 
demolition of such work erected/completed/commenced by Shri/Smt./Km. 
...................
 


Now, therefore, in exercise 
of the powers conferred by sub-sec­tion (2) of section 5C of the said Act, I 
hereby order that the said seal from the said public premises be removed 
forthwith for demolition of such work erected/completed/commenced on the said 
public premises.
 


Schedule
 



Date..................                                                       
Signature and seal of the Estate Officer]
 


      
......................................................................
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Ins. by G.S.R. 114 
(E), dated 23rd September, 1986.
 


 
</form><form>
 




The Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) Rules, 1971
 


 
 




FORM C
 


Form of notice under 
sub-section (1) of section 6 of the Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised 
Occupants) Act, 1971
 



Shri/Smt./Km...............................................................................
 


Whereas, on the........you 
were evicted from the public premises described in the Schedule below which was 
unauthorisedly occupied by you;
 


Now, therefore, in exercise 
of the powers conferred on me by sub-section (1) of section 6 of the Act, I 
hereby give you notice that after fourteen days of the service of this notice on 
you, any property remaining on the said premises will be liable to be removed or 
disposed of by public auction. In case you desire to take possession of your 
property and to remove the same from the said premises you will be permitted to 
do so on written authority from the undersigned provided any arrears of 
rent/damage/costs due from you are paid within the said period of fourteen days.
 


Schedule
 



Date..................                                                       
Signature and seal of the Estate Officer]
 


      
.....................................................................
 


 
</form><form>
 




The Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) Rules, 1971
 


 
 




1[FORM 
CC
 


Form of notice under 
sub-section (1A) of section 6 of the said Act
 


To
 


Shri/Smt./Km...............................................................................
 


Whereas in compliance of 
the order made under sub-section (2) of section 5A of the said Act, the Estate 
Officer has removed the goods described in the Schedule below from the Public 
Premises No.......
 


Now, therefore, in exercise 
of the powers conferred on me by sub-section (1A) of section 6 of the said Act, 
I hereby give you notice, that after fourteen days of the service of the notice 
on you such goods as described in the Schedule below shall be dis­posed of by 
public auction. In case you desire to take possession of your such goods, you 
will be permitted to do so on written authority from the undersigned provided 
any arrears for rent/damages/cost due from you are paid within the said period 
of fourteen days.
 


Schedule
 



Date..................                                                       
Signature and seal of the Estate Officer]
 


      
.....................................................................
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Ins. by G.S.R. 41, 
dated 4th July, 1981 and subs. by G.S.R. 114 (E), dated 23rd September, 1986.
 


 
</form><form>
 




The Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) Rules, 1971
 


 
 




1[FORM 
D
 


Form of notice under 
sub-section (3) of section 7 of Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised 
Occupants) Act, 1971
 


To
 


Shri/Smt./Km...............................................................................
 


Whereas I, the undersigned, 
am satisfied that you are/were in occupation of the public premises described in 
the Schedule below;
 


And whereas in exercise of 
the powers conferred on me by sub-section (1) of section 7 of the Public 
Premises (Eviction of Unau­thorised Occupants) Act, 1971, I consider that a sum 
of Rs...............(Rupees........................) being arrears of rent from 
the ...................day of ......20....., upto the ...... day of ......20 
.....(both days inclusive) in respect of the said premises is due and payable by 
you to the Government Statutory Authority;
 


And whereas in exercise of 
the powers conferred on me by sub-section (2A) of section 7 of the Public 
Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) Act, 1971, I consider that you are 
also liable to pay simple interest to the Government/Statutory Author­ity on the 
said arrears at the rate determined by the undersigned till its final payment;
 


Now, therefore, in 
pursuance of sub-section (3) of section 7 of the Public Premises (Eviction of 
Unauthorised Occupants) Act, 1971, I hereby call upon you to show cause on or 
before the .................. why an order requiring you to pay the said arrears 
of rent together with simple interest should not be made.
 


Schedule
 



Date..................                                                       
Signature and seal of the Estate Officer]
 


      
.....................................................................
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Subs. by G.S.R. 41, 
dated 4th July, 1981 (w.e.f. 8-8-1981).
 


 
</form><form>
 




The Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) Rules, 1971
 


 
 




1[FORM 
E
 


Form of Order under 
sub-sections (1) and (2A) of section 7 of the Public Premises (Eviction of 
Unauthorised Occupants) Act, 1971
 


To
 



Shri/Smt./Km...............................................................................
 


Whereas you are/were in 
occupation of the public premises de­scribed in the Schedule below.
 


And whereas, by a written 
notice dated.........................you are/were called upon to show cause 
on/or before..........................why an order requiring you to pay a sum of 
Rs.......................(Rupees.....................) being the rent payable 
together with simple interest in respect of the said premises should not be 
made;
 


And whereas I have 
considered you objections and/or the evidence produced by you;
 


And whereas you have not 
made any objections or produced any evidence before the said date;
 


Now, therefore, in exercise 
of the powers conferred by sub-section (1) of section 7 of the Public Premises 
(Eviction of Unau­thorised Occupants) Act, 1971, I hereby require you to pay the 
sum of Rs.......
 


In exercise of the powers 
conferred by sub-section (2A) of section 7 of the said Act, I also hereby 
require you to simple interest @ Rs. .............. per annum on the above sum 
w.e.f. ............... till its final payment.
 


In case the said sum is not 
paid within the said period or in the said manner, it will be recovered as 
arrears of land revenue through the Collector.
 


Schedule
 



Date..................                                                       
Signature and seal of the Estate Officer]
 


      
.....................................................................
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Subs. by G.S.R. 41, 
dated 4th July, 1981 (w.e.f. 8-8-1981).
 


 
</form><form>
 




The Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) Rules, 1971
 


 
 




1[FORM 
F
 


Form of notice under 
sub-section (3) of section 7 of the Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised 
Occupants) Act, 1971
 


To
 



Shri/Smt./Km...............................................................................
 


Whereas I, the undersigned, 
am satisfied that you are/were in unauthorised occupation of the public premises 
mentioned in the Schedule I below:
 


And whereas, in exercise of 
the powers conferred on me by sub-section (2) of section 7 of the Public 
Premises (Eviction of Unau­thorised Occupants) Act, 1971, I consider the 
damages, amounting to Rs.........................(Rupees...............) are due 
for the period(s) and at the rate (s) sown in Schedule II below on account of 
unauthorised use and occupation of the said premises;
 


And, whereas, in exercise 
of the powers conferred on me sub-section (2A) of section 7 of the Public 
Premises (Eviction of Unau­thorised Occupants) Act, 1971, I consider that you 
are also liable to pay simple interest to the Govern­ment/Statutory Authority on 
the said arrears at the rate deter­mined by the undersigned till its final 
payment.
 


Now, therefore, under the 
provisions of sub-section (3) of section 7 of the Act, I hereby call upon you to 
show-cause on or before ........... why an order requiring you to pay the said 
dam­ages together with interest should not be made.
 


Schedule I
 


Schedule II
 


 


Period                  
  Rate at                        Amount                     
  Amount                Balance in
 


 


                      
  which assessed                assessed                      
  paid                     arrears
 


 
 


 


 
 



Date..................                                                       
Signature and seal of the Estate Officer]
 


      
.....................................................................
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Subs. by G.S.R. 41, 
dated 4th July, 1981 (w.e.f. 8-8-1981).
 


 
</form><form>
 




The Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) Rules, 1971
 


 
 




1[FORM 
G
 


Form of Order under 
sub-sections (2) and (2A) of section 7 of the Public Premises (Eviction of 
Unauthorised Occupants) Act, 1971
 


To
 


Shri/Smt./Km...............................................................................
 


Whereas I, the undersigned, 
am satisfied that you are/were in unauthorised occupation of the public premises 
mentioned in the schedule below:
 


And whereas by a written 
notice dated.......................you are/were called upon to show cause on or 
before....................why an order requiring you to pay damages of Rs. 
........................together with simple interest for unauthorised use and 
occupation of the said premises should not be made;
 


And whereas I have 
considered your objections and/or the evidence produced by you;
 


And whereas you have not 
any objections or produced any evidence before the said date;
 


Now, therefore, in exercise 
of the powers conferred on me by sub-section (2) of section 7 of the Public 
Premises (Eviction of Unau­thorised Occupants) Act, 1971, I hereby order you to 
pay the sum of Rs................. (Rupees.................) assessed by me as 
damages on account of your unauthorised occupation of the premises.
 


In exercise of the powers 
conferred by sub-section (2A) of section 7 of the said Act, I also hereby 
require you to pay simple inter­est at the rate of Rs. ....................per 
annum on the above sum w.e.f.............. till its final payment.
 


In the event of your 
refusal or failure to pay the damages or any instalment thereof within the said 
period or in the manner afore­said the amount will be recovered as an arrear of 
land revenue.
 


Schedule
 



Date..................                                                       
Signature and seal of the Estate Officer]
 


      
.....................................................................
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Subs. by G.S.R. 41, 
dated 4th July, 1981 (w.e.f. 8-8-1981).
 


 
</form><form>
 




The Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) Rules, 1971
 





 




FORM H
 


Form of Order under 
section 12 of the Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) Act, 1971
 


To
 


Shri/Smt./Km...............................................................................
 


Whereas, there are reasons 
to believe that certain persons are in unauthorised occupation of the public 
premises described in the Schedule hereto annexed.
 


Now, therefore, in exercise 
of the powers conferred by section 12 of the Public Premises (Eviction of 
Unauthorised Occupants) Act, 1971 read with the notification of the Estate 
Officer .................. I hereby require you to furnish the information in 
the form speci­fied in Schedule II hereto annexed on or before 
...................
 


Schedule I
 


Schedule II
 



Date..................           Signature and Seal of the Estate Officer or the 
Signature of the Officer authorised by the Estate Officer.
 


Note.—Failure 
to comply with this order is an offence under the Indian Penal Code.
 


 
</form><form>
 




The Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) Rules, 1971
 


 
 




1[FORM 
I
 


Certificate under 
section 14 of the Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) Act, 
1971, from the Estate Officer to the Collector
 


This is to certify that an 
amount of Rs. ...................... (Rupees...................) is due to 
Central Government/Statutory authority from 
Shri/Smt./Km............................in respect of 
............................for the period from ........... to .............on 
account of rent/damages/expenses/costs/interest.
 


In pursuance of section 14 
of the Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) Act, 1971, I, 
..............................., Estate Officer, request you to proceed to 
recover the same as arrears of land revenue.]
 





 


—————
 


   1.  Subs. by G.S.R. 41, 
dated 4th July, 1981 (w.e.f. 8-8-1981).
 


 
</form><form>
 




The Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) Rules, 1971
 





 




FORM J
 


Notice under sub-section 
(2) of section 13 of the Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) 
Act, 1971
 


To
 



Shri/Smt./Km...............................................................................
 


Whereas Shri/Smt./Km. 
....................................... (now deceased) was in 
occupation/unauthorised occupation of the public premises de­scribed in the 
Schedule below:
 


And whereas the amount of 
Rs. ......................being arrears of rent/damages from............ day of 
......20....., upto the ........day of ......20......., in respect of the said 
premises had become due and payable by the said Shri......to the Government:
 


And whereas you are the 
heir/legal representative of the de­ceased, Shri.................;
 


Now, therefore, in 
pursuance of sub-section (2) of section 13 of the Act, I hereby call upon you to 
show cause on or before the* .....why an order requiring you to pay the said 
arrears of rent/damages should not be made against you.
 


Schedule
 



Date..................                                                       
Signature and seal of the Estate Officer]
 


      
.....................................................................
 


      *  This date should 
be a date later than 7 days from the date of issue of the notice.
 





</form><form>
 




The Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) Rules, 1971
 





 




1[Form 
K
 


Form of Order under 
section ‘3A’ of the Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) Act, 
1971
 


All persons concerned and 
in particular
 


Shri/Smt.......................................................................
 


Suit/Flat No. 
...............................................................
 


Servant Qtr. No. 
..........................................................
 


Motor Garrage No. 
......................................................
 


Whereas, I, the undersigned 
am satisfied for the reasons recorded below that Shri/Smt. 
.........................is in unauthorised occupation of the public premises 
specified in the Schedule below.
 


Reasons
 


Shri/Smt. 
.......................................................................was 
allowed temporary occupation of Public Premises specified in the Schedule below 
for the period from..........................to.......................
 


He/She has been continuing 
to occupy the same even after the expiry of the said period of allotment without 
any authority.
 


Now, therefore, in exercise 
of the powers conferred on me under section 3A of the Public Premises (Eviction 
of Unauthorised Occupants) Act, 1971, I hereby order that the said Shri/Smt 
...................................and all other persons who may be in 
occupation of the said premises or any part thereof to vacate the premises 
forthwith. In the event of refusal or failure to comply with this order, the 
said Shri/Smt............................and all other concerned are liable to 
be evicted from the said premises, if need be, by use of such force as may be 
necessary.
 


Schedule
 


Suit Flat No. 
...................................................
 


Servant Quarter/Garrage..............................
 


            Signature and 
seal of the Estate Officer]
 


      
.....................................................................
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Ins. by G.S.R. 3 (E) 
dated 19th December, 1997 (w.e.f. 2-1-1998).
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>