<act><title>


The Procedure for conducting Inquiry Against a 
    Member of Appropriate Commission Rules, 20041</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Procedure for Conducting Inquiry Against a 
    Member of Appropriate Commission Rules, 2004.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They 
    shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official 
    Gazette.
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “Act” means the Electricity Act, 2003; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    “section” means a section of the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    “Registrar” means Registrar of the 
    Appellate Tribunal.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Words and expression used herein and not defined but defined in the Act 
    shall have the meaning respectively assigned to them in the Act. 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Procedure for conducting inquiry.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Appropriate Government shall make a reference alongwith imputation of 
    charges and other relevant information for the purpose of conducting such 
    inquiry to the Chairperson of the Appellate Tribunal in pursuance of the 
    provisions of sub-section (2) of section 90 of the Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On 
    receipt of a reference under sub-rule (1) Chairperson of the Appellate 
    Tribunal shall issue a notice to the Member concerned to appear before him 
    on the time and date specified in the notice. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A 
    copy of the charges preferred against the Member shall be supplied along 
    with the notice. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Chairperson of the Appellate Tribunal may seek assistance of an expert or 
    expert agency for investigating into the charges against the Member. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> For 
    the purposes of discharging his functions under these rules, the Chairperson 
    of the Appellate Tribunal may summon such witnesses or records as he may 
    consider necessary. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> 
    After hearing the views of the Member, Chairperson shall forward his 
    findings to the Appropriate Government. 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>