<act><title>

THE STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES ACT, 
    1976</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Standards of Weights and Measures Act, 1976. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    extends to the whole of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It 
    shall come into force on such date1 as 
    the Central Govern­ment may, by notification, appoint, and different dates 
    may be appointed for different—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    provisions of this Act1, 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    areas, 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    classes of undertakings, 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    classes of goods, 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    classes of weights and measures, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    classes of users of weights and 
    measures, 
 
and any reference in any such provision to the 
    commencement of this Act shall be construed as a reference to the coming 
    into force of that provision in such areas, or in respect of such classes of 
    undertakings, goods, weights and measures or users of weights and measures 
    in relation to which this Act has been brought into force:
 
Provided 
    that the provisions of this Act (including the stan­dards established by or 
    under this Act) shall come into force in the State of Sikkim on such date, 
    not being later than five years from the passing of this Act, as the Central 
    Government may, by notification, appoint, and different dates may be 
    appointed for different provisions of this Act or for different areas or for 
    different classes of undertakings or for different classes of goods, or for 
    different classes of weights and measures or for different classes of users 
    of weights and measures. 
 





 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    this Act, unless the context otherwise re­quires,——In 
    this Act, unless the context otherwise re­quires,—"
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “calibration” means all the operations 
    which are necessary for the purpose of determining the values of the errors 
    of a weight or measure and, if necessary, to determine the other 
    metrological properties of such weight or measure, and includes the actual 
    fixing of the positions of the gauge-marks or scale-marks of a weight or 
    measure or in some cases, of certain principal marks only, in relation to 
    the corresponding values of the quantity to be measured. 
 
Explanation.— Calibration may also be 
    carried out with a view to permitting the use of a weight or measure as a 
    standard; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “commodity in packaged form” means 
    commodity packaged, wheth­er in any bottle, tin, wrapper or otherwise, in 
    units suitable for sale, whether wholesale or retail; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “dealer”, in relation to any weight or 
    measure, means a person who, or a firm or a Hindu undivided family which, 
    carries on, directly or otherwise, the business of buying, selling, 
    supplying or distributing any such weight or measure, whether for cash or 
    for deferred payment or for commission, remuneration or other valuable 
    consideration, and includes— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    a commission agent who carries on such 
    business on behalf of any principal, 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    an importer who sells, supplies, 
    distributes or otherwise delivers any weight or measure to any user, 
    manufacturer, repair­er, consumer or any other person, 
 
but does not include a manufacturer who sells, 
    supplies, distrib­utes or otherwise delivers any weight or measure to any 
    person or category of persons referred to in this clause. 
 
Explanation.—For the removal of doubts, 
    it is hereby declared that a manufacturer, who sells, supplies, distributes 
    or otherwise delivers any weight or measure to any person other than a 
    dealer, shall be deemed to be a dealer; 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>d</number>    “Director” means the Director of Legal 
    Metrology appointed under section 28; 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    “export” with its grammatical 
    variations and cognate expres­sions, means taking out of India to a place 
    outside India; 
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    “false package” means any package which 
    does not conform to the provisions of this Act or any rule or order made 
    thereunder in relation to such package; 
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    “false weight or measure” means any 
    weight or measure which does not conform to the standards established by or 
    under this Act in relation to that weight or measure; 
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>    “General Conference on Weights and 
    Measures” means the Con­ference General des Poids et Mesures established 
    under the Con­vention du Metre; 
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>    “import”, with its grammatical 
    variations and cognate expres­sions, means bringing into India from a place 
    outside India; 
 </section><section>
<number>j</number>    “International Bureau of Weights and 
    Measures” means the Bureau International des Poids et Mesures, established 
    under the Convention due Metre, at Severs in France; 
 </section><section>
<number>k</number>    “International Organisation of Legal 
    Metrology” means the Organisation International de Metrologie Legal 
    established under the Convention Instituant Une Organisation International 
    de Metrologie Legale; 
 </section><section>
<number>l</number>    “international prototype of the 
    kilogram” means the prototype sanctioned by the First General Conference on 
    Weights and Meas­ures held in Paris in 1889, and deposited at the 
    International Bureau of Weights and Measures; 
 </section><section>
<number>m</number>    “inter-State trade or commerce”, in 
    relation to any weight or measure or other goods which are bought, sold 
    supplied, distrib­uted or delivered by weight, measure or number, means the 
    pur­chase, sale, supply, distribution or delivery which— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    occasions the movement of such weight, 
    measure or other goods from one State to another, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    is effected by a transfer of documents 
    of title to such weight, measure or other goods during its movement from one 
    State to another. 
 
Explanation I.—Where any such 
    weight or measure is, or other goods are, delivered to a carrier or other 
    bailee for transmis­sion, the movement of such weight, measure or other 
    goods shall, for the purposes of sub-clause (ii), be deemed to commence at 
    the time of such delivery and terminate at the time when delivery is taken 
    from such carrier or bailee. 
 
Explanation II.— Where the 
    movement of any such weight, measure or other goods commences and terminates 
    in the same State, it shall not be deemed to be a movement of such weight, 
    measure or other goods from one State to another merely by reason of the 
    fact that in the course of such movement it passes through the territory of 
    any other State; 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>n</number>    “level” means any written, marked, 
    stamped, printed, or graphic matter affixed to or appearing upon, any 
    commodity or package containing any commodity; 
 </section><section>
<number>o</number>    “manufacturer”, in relation to any 
    weight or measure, means a person who, or a firm or a Hindu undivided family 
    which,— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    makes or manufactures such weight or 
    measure, 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    makes or manufactures one or more 
    parts, and acquires the other parts, of such weight or measure and, after 
    assembling those parts, claims the end product to be a weight or measure 
    manufactured by himself or itself, as the case may be, 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    does not make or manufacture any part 
    of such weight or measure but assembles parts thereof made or manufactured 
    by others and claims the end product to be a weight or measurer manufactured 
    by himself or itself, as the case may be, 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    puts, or causes to be put, his own 
    mark on any complete weight or measure made or manufactured by any other 
    person and claims such product to be a weight or measure made or 
    manufac­tured by himself or itself, as the case may be. 
 
Explanation.—Where any manufacturer 
    despatches any weight or measure or any part thereof to any branch office 
    maintained by him or it, such branch office shall not be deemed to be a 
    manu­facturer even though the parts so despatched to it are assembled at 
    such branch office; 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>p</number>    “notification” means a notification 
    published in the Official Gazette; 
 </section><section>
<number>q</number>    “person” includes— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    every department of office, 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    every organisation established or 
    constituted by Government, 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    every local authority within the 
    territory of India, 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    every co-operative society, 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>    every other society registered under 
    the Societies Registra­tion Act, 1860 (21 of 1860); 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>r</number>    “premises”includes— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    a place where any business, industry, 
    production or trade is carried on by a person, whether by himself or through 
    an agent, by whatever name called, 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    a warehouse, godown or other place 
    where any weight, measure or other goods are stored or exhibited, 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    a place where any books of account or 
    other documents pertaining to any trade or transaction are kept, 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    a dwelling house if any part thereof 
    is used for the purpose of carrying on any business, industry, production or 
    trade. 
 
Explanation.-—“Place” includes a 
    vehicle or vessel or any other mobile device, with the help of which any 
    trade or business in carried on, and also includes any measuring instrument 
    mounted on a vehicle, vessel or other mobile device; 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>s</number>    “prescribed” means prescribed by rules 
    made under this Act and “prescribed authority” means such authority as may 
    be speci­fied by such rules; 
 </section><section>
<number>t</number>    “reference standard” means the set of 
    standard weight or measure which is made or manufactured by or on behalf of 
    the Central Government for the verification of any secondary stan­dard; 
 </section><section>
<number>u</number>    “repairer” includes a person who 
    adjusts, cleans, lubricates or paints any weight or measure or renders any 
    other service to such weight or measure to ensure that such weight or 
    measure conforms to the standards established by or under this Act; 
 </section><section>
<number>v</number>    “sale”, with its grammatical variations 
    and cognate expressions, means transfer of property in any weight, measure 
    or other goods by one person to another for cash or for deferred payment or 
    for any other valuable consideration, and includes a transfer of any weight, 
    measure or other goods on the hire-purchase system or any other system of 
    payment by instalments, but does not include a mortgage or hypothecation of, 
    or a charge or pledge on, such weight, measure or other goods; 
 </section><section>
<number>w</number>    “seal” means a device or process by 
    which a stamp is made, and includes any wire or other accessory which is 
    used for ensur­ing the integrity or any stamp; 
 </section><section>
<number>x</number>    “secondary standard” means the set of 
    standard weight or measure which is made or manufactured by or on behalf of 
    the Central or State Government for the verification of any working 
    standard; 
 </section><section>
<number>y</number>    “stamp” means a mark, which is made on, 
    or in relation to, any weight or measure with a view to— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    certifying that such weight or measure 
    conforms to the stan­dard specified by or under this Act, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    indicating that any mark which was 
    previously made thereon certifying that such weight or measure conforms to 
    the standards specified by or under this Act, has been obliterated. 
 
Explanation.—A stamp may be made by 
    impressing, casting, engrav­ing, etching, branding or any other process; 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>z</number>    ‘transaction” means— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    any contract, whether for sale, 
    purchase, exchange or any other purpose, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    any assessment of royalty, toll, duty 
    or other dues, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    the assessment of any work done, 
    wages due or services rendered; 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>za</number>    “unverified weight or measure” means a 
    weight or measure which, being required to be verified and stamped under 
    this Act, has not been so verified and stamped; 
 </section><section>
<number>zb</number>    “verification”, with its grammatical 
    variation and cognate expressions, includes, in relation to any weight or 
    measure, the process of comparing, checking, testing or adjusting such 
    weight or measure with a view to ensuring that such weight or measure 
    conforms to the standards established by or under this Act, and also 
    includes re-verification and calibration; 
 </section><section>
<number>zc</number>    “weighing or measuring instrument” 
    means any object, in­strument, apparatus or device, or any combination 
    thereof, which is, or is intended to be used, exclusively or additionally, 
    for the purpose of making any weighment or measurement, and includes any 
    appliance, accessory or part associated with any such object, instrument, 
    apparatus or device; 
 </section><section>
<number>zd</number>    “weight or measure” means a weight or 
    measure specified by or under this Act, and includes a weighing or measuring 
    instru­ment; 
 </section><section>
<number>ze</number>    “working standard” means the set of 
    standard weight or measure which is made or manufactured by or on behalf of 
    Gov­ernment for the verification of any standard weight or measure, other 
    than a national prototype or national reference or second­ary standard. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>3</number> Provisions of this Act to override the provisions of any other 
      law.—The 
      provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
      inconsistent therewith contained in any enactment other than this Act or 
      in any instrument having effect by virtue of any enactment other than this 
      Act.—The 
    provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
    inconsistent therewith contained in any enactment other than this Act or in 
    any instrument having effect by virtue of any enactment other than this 
    Act." 
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Units of weight or measure to be based on metric system.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every unit of weight or measure shall be based on the units of the metric 
    system.—(1) 
    Every unit of weight or measure shall be based on the units of the metric 
    system."
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> For 
    the purpose of sub-section (1),— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the international system of units as 
    recommended by the General Conference on Weights and Measures, and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    such additional units as may be 
    recommended by the Interna­tional Organisation of Legal Metrology, 
 
shall be the units of the metric system.
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Base unit of length.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The base unit of length shall be the metre.—(1) 
    The base unit of length shall be the metre." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    “metre” is the length equal to 1650 763.73 wave lengths in vacuum of the 
    radiation corresponding to the transition between the levels 2p10 and 
    5d5 of 
    the krypton-86 atom. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Base unit of mass.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The base unit of mass shall be the kilogram.—(1) 
    The base unit of mass shall be the kilogram." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    “kilogram” is the unit of mass; it is equal to the mass of the international 
    prototype of the kilogram. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Base unit of time.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The base unit of time shall be the second.—(1) 
    The base unit of time shall be the second." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    “second” is the duration of 9 192 631 770 periods of the radiation 
    corresponding to the transition between the two hyperfine levels of the 
    ground state of the caesium-133 atom. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Base unit of electric current.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The base unit of electric current shall be the ampere.—(1) 
    The base unit of electric current shall be the ampere." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    “ampere” is that constant current which if maintained in two straight 
    parallel conductors of infinite length, of negligible circular 
    cross-section, and placed one metre apart in vacuum, would produce between 
    these conductors a force equal to 2 x 107 newton 
    per metre of length. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Base unit of thermodynamic temperature.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The base unit of thermodynamic temperature shall be the kelvin.—(1) 
    The base unit of thermodynamic temperature shall be the kelvin." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    “kelvin” is the fraction 1/273.16 of the thermodynamic temperature of the 
    triple point of water. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    kelvin shall also be used for expressing the interval or difference of 
    temperature. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Zero 
    degree Celsius corresponds to 273.15 kelvin. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    degree Celsius may also be used for expressing the interval or difference of 
    temperature, unit degree Celsius being equal to unit kelvin. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Base unit of luminous intensity.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The base unit of luminous intensity shall be the candela.—(1) 
    The base unit of luminous intensity shall be the candela." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    “candela” is the luminous intensity, in the perpendicular direction, of a 
    surface of 1/600,000 square metre of a black body at the temperature of 
    freezing platinum under a pressure of 101 325 newtons per square metre. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Base unit of amount of substance.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The base unit of amount of substance shall be the mole.—(1) 
    The base unit of amount of substance shall be the mole." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    “mole” is the amount of substance of a system which contains as many 
    elementary entities as there are atoms in 0.012 kilogram of carbon 12. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> When 
    the mole is used, the elementary entities shall invariably be specified and 
    may be atoms, molecules ions, electrons, other particles, or specified 
    groups of such particles. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Supplementary, derived, special and other units of weight or measure—their 
    symbols, definitions, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government may, by rules made 
    in this behalf, specify, in relation to the base units of weight or measure, 
    such supplementary, derived, or other units or standard symbols or 
    definitions as the General Conference on Weights and Measures or the 
    International Organisation of Legal Metrology may recommend.—their 
    symbols, definitions, etc.—(1) The Central Government may, by rules made 
    in this behalf, specify, in relation to the base units of weight or measure, 
    such supplementary, derived, or other units or standard symbols or 
    definitions as the General Conference on Weights and Measures or the 
    International Organisation of Legal Metrology may recommend." 
 

    Explanation.—“Derived 
    unit” means a unit which is derived from the base, or supplementary, units, 
    or both.—“Derived 
    unit” means a unit which is derived from the base, or supplementary, units, 
    or both." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Central Government may, by rules made in this behalf, specify such multiples 
    and sub-multiples of, and physical constants, and ratios or co-efficients in 
    relation to, units of weight or measure as the General Conference on Weights 
    and Measures or the International Organisation of Legal Metrology may 
    recommend. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Central Government may, by notification, declare, for such period as it may 
    consider necessary such special units of weight or measure as the General 
    Conference on Weights and Measures or the International Organisation of 
    Legal Metrology may recommend. 
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Base unit of numeration.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The base unit of numeration shall be the unit of the international form of 
    Indian numerals.—(1) 
    The base unit of numeration shall be the unit of the international form of 
    Indian numerals." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every numeration shall be made in accordance with the decimal system. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    decimal multiples and sub-multiples of the numerals shall be of such 
    denominations and be written in such manner as the Central Government may, 
    after previous publication, specify by rules made in this behalf: 
 
Provided 
    that no such rule shall be made before the expiry of six months from the 
    date on which the draft of the proposed rules was first published in the 
    Official Gazette. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Standard unit of weight or measure.—

<section><number>1</number> The base unit of mass specified in section 6 and base units of 
    measures specified in sections 5 and sections 7 to 11 (both inclusive) and 
    the supplementary and other units specified by rules made under section 12, 
    shall be the standard units of weight or measure, as the case may be.—
(1) The base unit of mass specified in section 6 and base units of 
    measures specified in sections 5 and sections 7 to 11 (both inclusive) and 
    the supplementary and other units specified by rules made under section 12, 
    shall be the standard units of weight or measure, as the case may be." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    units of numeration specified by or under section 13 shall be the standard 
    units of numeration. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    National prototypes.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    For the purpose of deriving the value of the kilogram, the Central 
    Government shall cause to be prepared a national prototype of the kilogram 
    and shall cause its accuracy to be certified by the International Bureau of 
    Weights and Measures in terms of the international prototype of the kilogram 
    and shall deposit the same in such custody and at such place as that 
    Government may think fit.—(1) 
    For the purpose of deriving the value of the kilogram, the Central 
    Government shall cause to be prepared a national prototype of the kilogram 
    and shall cause its accuracy to be certified by the International Bureau of 
    Weights and Measures in terms of the international prototype of the kilogram 
    and shall deposit the same in such custody and at such place as that 
    Government may think fit." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> For 
    the purpose of deriving the value of the metre, the Central Government may 
    cause to be prepared a national prototype of the metre and, where such 
    prototype is caused to be made, shall also cause its accuracy to be 
    certified by the International Bureau of Weights and Measures and deposit 
    the same in such custody and at such place as that Government may think fit. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    National standards.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    For the purpose of deriving the value of the base units, other than the base 
    unit of mass, the Central Government shall cause to be prepared such objects 
    or equipments, or both, as may be necessary for the purpose and shall cause 
    the accuracy of such objects or equipments, or both, to be certified by the 
    International Bureau of Weights and Measures at such periodical intervals as 
    may be prescribed, and, shall, after such certification, deposit such 
    objects or equipments, or both, in such custody and at such place as that 
    Government may think fit.—(1) 
    For the purpose of deriving the value of the base units, other than the base 
    unit of mass, the Central Government shall cause to be prepared such objects 
    or equipments, or both, as may be necessary for the purpose and shall cause 
    the accuracy of such objects or equipments, or both, to be certified by the 
    International Bureau of Weights and Measures at such periodical intervals as 
    may be prescribed, and, shall, after such certification, deposit such 
    objects or equipments, or both, in such custody and at such place as that 
    Government may think fit." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> For 
    the purpose of deriving the value of the supplementary and other units 
    specified under section 12, the Central Government shall cause to be 
    prepared such objects or equipments, or both, as may be necessary for the 
    purpose and shall cause the accuracy of such objects or equipments, or both, 
    to be certified at such periodical intervals and by such authority as may be 
    prescribed, and, shall, after such certification, deposit such objects or 
    equipments, or both, in such custody and at such place as that Government 
    may think fit. 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    National prototype and national standard how to be kept.— 
    Every national prototype specified in section 15 and every object or 
    equipment, or both, referred to in section 16, shall be kept in such manner 
    and under such conditions as may be prescribed.— 
    Every national prototype specified in section 15 and every object or 
    equipment, or both, referred to in section 16, shall be kept in such manner 
    and under such conditions as may be prescribed." 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Reference, secondary and working standards.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every——(1) 
    Every—" 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    reference standard, 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    secondary standard, and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    working standard, 
 
shall conform to the standards established by 
    or under this Act and be verified and authenticated at such periodical 
    intervals and in such manner as may be prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every reference standard, every secondary standard and every working 
    standard shall be kept in such manner and under such conditions as may be 
    prescribed. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Power of Central Government to prescribe physical characteristics, etc., 
    of weights and measures.—

<section><number>1</number> The Central Government shall, in relation to any weight or measure, 
    prescribe the physical characteristics, configuration, constructional 
    details, materials, equipment, performance, tolerances, methods or 
    procedures of tests in accordance with the recommendations made by the 
    International Organisation of Legal Metrology:—
(1) The Central Government shall, in relation to any weight or measure, 
    prescribe the physical characteristics, configuration, constructional 
    details, materials, equipment, performance, tolerances, methods or 
    procedures of tests in accordance with the recommendations made by the 
    International Organisation of Legal Metrology\:" 
 
Provided 
    that where no such recommendation has been made, the Central Government 
    shall prescribe such physical characteristics, configuration, constructional 
    details, materials, equipment, performance, tolerances, method or procedures 
    of tests in relation to any weight or measure as it may think fit. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where it is not reasonably practicable to give effect to any recommendation 
    made by the International Organisation of Legal Metrology, the Central 
    Government may make such changes of a minor nature in the recommendation of 
    the International Organisation of Legal Metrology as may appear to it to be 
    necessary. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Power of Central Government to prescribe physical characteristics, etc., 
    of weights and measures.—

<section><number>1</number> The Central Government shall, in relation to any weight or measure, 
    prescribe the physical characteristics, configuration, constructional 
    details, materials, equipment, performance, tolerances, methods or 
    procedures of tests in accordance with the recommendations made by the 
    International Organisation of Legal Metrology:—
(1) The Central Government shall, in relation to any weight or measure, 
    prescribe the physical characteristics, configuration, constructional 
    details, materials, equipment, performance, tolerances, methods or 
    procedures of tests in accordance with the recommendations made by the 
    International Organisation of Legal Metrology\:" 
 
Provided 
    that where no such recommendation has been made, the Central Government 
    shall prescribe such physical characteristics, configuration, constructional 
    details, materials, equipment, performance, tolerances, method or procedures 
    of tests in relation to any weight or measure as it may think fit. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where it is not reasonably practicable to give effect to any recommendation 
    made by the International Organisation of Legal Metrology, the Central 
    Government may make such changes of a minor nature in the recommendation of 
    the International Organisation of Legal Metrology as may appear to it to be 
    necessary. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> 
    Standard weight or measure.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any weight or measure which conforms to the standard unit of such weight or 
    measure and also conforms to such of the provisions of sections 15 to 19 
    (both inclusive) as are applicable to it shall be the standard weight or 
    measure.—(1) 
    Any weight or measure which conforms to the standard unit of such weight or 
    measure and also conforms to such of the provisions of sections 15 to 19 
    (both inclusive) as are applicable to it shall be the standard weight or 
    measure." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any 
    numeral which conforms to the provisions of section 13 shall be the standard 
    numeral. 
 
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>21</number> 
    Use of non-standard weight or measure prohibited.—No 
    weight, measure or numeral, other than the standard weight, measure or 
    numeral, shall be used as a standard weight, measure or numeral.—No 
    weight, measure or numeral, other than the standard weight, measure or 
    numeral, shall be used as a standard weight, measure or numeral." 
 
  


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>22</number> Manufacture of non-standard weight or measure prohibited.</title>—No weight or measure shall be made or manufactured unless it conforms to the standards of weight or measure established by or under this Act:  
 Provided that the Central Government may permit the making or manufacturing of any weight or measure which does not conform to the standards established by or under this Act, if such weight or measure is made or manufactured exclusively for the purpose of any scientific investigation or research or for export and is made or manufactured under such conditions and restrictions as may be prescribed. 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> 
    Prohibition with regard to inscriptions etc.—No 
    weight, measure or other goods shall bear thereon any inscription or 
    indication or weight, measure or number except in accordance with the 
    standard unit of such weight, measure or numeration established by or under 
    this Act:—No 
    weight, measure or other goods shall bear thereon any inscription or 
    indication or weight, measure or number except in accordance with the 
    standard unit of such weight, measure or numeration established by or under 
    this Act\:" 
 
Provided 
    that in relation to any weight, measure or other goods which are 
    manufactured for scientific investigation or research or for export, 
    inscription or indication thereon of any weight, measure or number may also 
    be made in accordance with any other system of weight, measure or numeration 
    if such inscription or indication is demanded by the person by whom such 
    scientific investigation or research is to be made or by the person to whom 
    the export is to be made. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Supply, etc., of reference standards.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government shall cause to be prepared, for the purposes of this 
    Act, as many sets of reference standards as it may think necessary and shall 
    supply to each State Government as many sets of reference standards as it 
    may think fit. —(1) 
    The Central Government shall cause to be prepared, for the purposes of this 
    Act, as many sets of reference standards as it may think necessary and shall 
    supply to each State Government as many sets of reference standards as it 
    may think fit. " 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Central Government shall keep in its custody, for the purposes of this Act, 
    such number of reference standards as may be necessary. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Every reference standard referred to in sub-section (2) shall be kept at 
    such place and in such custody as may be prescribed and no such reference 
    standard shall be deemed to be a reference standard and shall be used as 
    such unless it has been verified and authenticated in accordance with the 
    rules made under this Act. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Preparation and custody or secondary or working standards.—The 
    Central Government shall cause to be prepared, for the purposes of this Act, 
    as many sets of secondary standard or working standard as it may think 
    necessary and shall keep such sets of secondary standard or working standard 
    at such place and in such custody as may be prescribed.—The 
    Central Government shall cause to be prepared, for the purposes of this Act, 
    as many sets of secondary standard or working standard as it may think 
    necessary and shall keep such sets of secondary standard or working standard 
    at such place and in such custody as may be prescribed." 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>26</number> 
    Verification, stamping, etc.,
    of secondary or working 
    standards.—
<section><number>1</number> Every secondary 
    standard referred to in section 25 shall be verified with the reference 
    standard by such authority as may be prescribed and shall, if found on such 
    verification to conform to the standards established by or under this Act, 
    be stamped by that authority.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every working standard referred to in section 25 shall be verified with the 
    secondary standard which has been stamped in accordance with the provisions 
    of sub-section (1), by such authority as may be prescribed and shall, if 
    found on such verification to conform to the standards established by or 
    under this Act, be stamped by that authority. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Where any secondary standard or working standard is stamped in accordance 
    with the provisions of sub-section (1), or sub-section (2), as the case may 
    be, a certificate shall be separately given showing the date on which such 
    weight or measure was stamped. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Every secondary standard or working standard which is not verified and 
    stamped in accordance with the provisions of sub-section (1) or sub-section 
    (2), as the case may be, shall not be deemed to be a secondary standard or 
    working standard and shall not be used as such. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>27</number> 
    Secondary or working standard which may be stamped.—Where 
    the Central Government is of opinion that by reason of the size or nature of 
    any secondary standard or working standard referred to in section 25, it is 
    not desirable or practicable to put a stamp thereon, it may direct that 
    instead of putting stamp on such secondary standard or working standard, a 
    certificate may be issued to the effect that such secondary standard or 
    working standard conforms to the standards established by or under this Act 
    and every secondary standard or working standard so certified shall be 
    deemed to have been duly stamped under this Act on the date on which such 
    certificate was issued.—Where 
    the Central Government is of opinion that by reason of the size or nature of 
    any secondary standard or working standard referred to in section 25, it is 
    not desirable or practicable to put a stamp thereon, it may direct that 
    instead of putting stamp on such secondary standard or working standard, a 
    certificate may be issued to the effect that such secondary standard or 
    working standard conforms to the standards established by or under this Act 
    and every secondary standard or working standard so certified shall be 
    deemed to have been duly stamped under this Act on the date on which such 
    certificate was issued." 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>28</number> 
    Appointment of Director and other staff.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by notification, appoint a Director of Legal 
    Metrology and as many Additional, Joint, Deputy or Assistant Directors and 
    other officers and staff as may be necessary for exercising the powers and 
    efficiently discharging the duties conferred or imposed on them by or under 
    this Act.—(1) 
    The Central Government may, by notification, appoint a Director of Legal 
    Metrology and as many Additional, Joint, Deputy or Assistant Directors and 
    other officers and staff as may be necessary for exercising the powers and 
    efficiently discharging the duties conferred or imposed on them by or under 
    this Act." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every Additional, Joint, Deputy or Assistant Director and other officer, 
    appointed under sub-section (1), shall exercise such powers, and discharge 
    such functions of the Director as the Central Government may, by 
    notification, authorise in this behalf. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Director may, by general or special order, define the local limits within 
    which each Additional, Joint, Deputy or Assistant Director or other officer, 
    appointed under sub-section (1), shall exercise his powers and discharge the 
    duties conferred or imposed on him by or under this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Subject to the provision of this Act, every Additional, Joint, Deputy or 
    Assistant Director and every other officer, appointed under sub-section (1), 
    shall exercise his power and discharge the duties of his office under the 
    general superintendence, direction and control of the Director and shall 
    exercise those powers and discharge those duties in the same manner and with 
    the same effect as if they had been conferred or imposed on him directly by 
    this Act and not by way of authorisation. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Director and every Additional, Joint, Deputy and Assistant Director and 
    every other officer authorised to perform any duty by or under this Act 
    shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of section 21 of 
    the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860). 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> No 
    suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Director, 
    Additional, Joint, Deputy or Assistant Director or any other officer 
    authorised to perform any duty by or under this Act in respect of anything 
    which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or any 
    rule or order made thereunder. 
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The 
    Central Government may, with the consent of the State Government and subject 
    to such conditions, limitations and restrictions as it may specify in this 
    behalf, delegate such of the powers of the Director under this Act as it may 
    think fit to the person for the time being holding the office of the 
    Controller of Legal Metrology, in the State, and such Controller may, if he 
    is of opinion that it is necessary or expedient in the public interest so to 
    do, delegate such of the powers delegated to him as he may think fit to any 
    officer subordinate to him, not being an officer below the rank of an 
    Inspector, and where any such delegation of powers is made by such 
    Controller, the person to whom such powers are delegated shall exercise 
    those powers in the same manner and with the same effect as if they had been 
    conferred on him directly by this Act and not by way of delegation. 
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> 
    Where any delegation of powers is made under sub-section (7) the powers so 
    delegated shall be exercised under the general superintendence, direction 
    and guidance of the Director. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>29</number> 
    Power of inspection, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Director, or any person authorised to exercise the powers or discharge 
    the functions of the Director, may, if he has any reason to believe, whether 
    from any information given to him by any person and taken down in writing or 
    from personal knowledge or otherwise, that any weight or measure or other 
    goods in relation to which any inter-State trade or commerce has taken place 
    or is intended to take place and in respect of which an offence punishable 
    under this Act appears to have been, or is likely to be committed or either 
    kept or concealed in any premises or are in the course of transportation 
    from one State to another,——(1) 
    The Director, or any person authorised to exercise the powers or discharge 
    the functions of the Director, may, if he has any reason to believe, whether 
    from any information given to him by any person and taken down in writing or 
    from personal knowledge or otherwise, that any weight or measure or other 
    goods in relation to which any inter-State trade or commerce has taken place 
    or is intended to take place and in respect of which an offence punishable 
    under this Act appears to have been, or is likely to be committed or either 
    kept or concealed in any premises or are in the course of transportation 
    from one State to another,—" 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    enter at any reasonable time into any 
    such premises and search for and inspect any weight, measure or other goods 
    in relation to which inter-State trade or commerce has taken place, or is 
    intended to take place, and any record, register or other documents relating 
    thereto; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    seize any weight, measure or other 
    goods and any record, register or other document or article which he has 
    reason to believe may furnish evidence indicating that an offence punishable 
    under this Act has been, or is likely to be committed in the course of, or 
    in relation to, any inter-State trade or commerce. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where any goods seized under sub-section (1) are subject to speedy or 
    natural decay, the Director or the authorised person may dispose of such 
    goods in such manner as may be prescribed.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Every search or seizure made under this section shall be carried out in 
    accordance with the provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 
    1974), relating to searches and seizures made under that Code. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>30</number> 
    Forfeiture.—Every 
    false or unverified weight or measure, and every false package, used in the 
    course of, or in relation to any inter-State trade or commerce and seized 
    under section 29, shall be liable to be forfeited to the Central Government:—Every 
    false or unverified weight or measure, and every false package, used in the 
    course of, or in relation to any inter-State trade or commerce and seized 
    under section 29, shall be liable to be forfeited to the Central 
    Government\:" 
 
Provided 
    that such unverified weight or measure shall not be forfeited to Government 
    if the persons from whom such weight or measure was seized gets the same 
    verified and stamped within such time as may be prescribed. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>31</number> 
    Part IV to apply to inter-State trade or commerce only.—The 
    provisions of this Part shall apply to——The 
    provisions of this Part shall apply to—" 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    every weight or measure which is, or is 
    intended to be,— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    made or manufactured for the purpose of 
    inter-State trade or commerce, 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    used, sold, distributed, delivered or 
    otherwise transferred in the course of inter-State trade or commerce; 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number>    goods which are, or are intended to be, 
    sold, distributed, delivered or otherwise transferred by weight, measure or 
    number in the course of inter-State trade or commerce; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    every service which is rendered by 
    weight, measure or number in relation to, or in the course of, inter-State 
    trade or commerce. 
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>32</number> Use of 
    weights only or measures only in certain cases.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by rules made in this behalf, direct that in 
    respect of the class of goods or undertakings or users specified therein, no 
    transaction, dealing or contract shall be made or had except by such weight, 
    measure or number as may be specified in the said rules. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any rule 
    made under sub-section (1) shall take effect in such area, from such future 
    date and subject to such conditions, if any, as may be specified therein. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>33</number> 
    Prohibition of quotations, etc., otherwise than in terms of standard 
    units of weights, measures or numeration.—No 
    person shall, in relation to any goods, thing or service to which this part 
    applies,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    quote, or make announcement of, whether 
    by word of mouth or otherwise, any price or charge, or 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    issue or exhibit any price list, 
    invoice, cash memo or other document, or 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    prepare or publish any advertisement, 
    poster or other document, or 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    indicate the contents of any package 
    either on itself or on any label, carton or other thing, or 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    indicate the contents on any container, 
    or 
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    express any quantity or dimension, 
 
otherwise than in accordance with the standard 
    unit of weight, measure or numeration.
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>33</number> 
    Prohibition of quotations, etc., otherwise than in terms of standard 
    units of weights, measures or numeration.—No 
    person shall, in relation to any goods, thing or service to which this part 
    applies,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    quote, or make announcement of, whether 
    by word of mouth or otherwise, any price or charge, or 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    issue or exhibit any price list, 
    invoice, cash memo or other document, or 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    prepare or publish any advertisement, 
    poster or other document, or 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    indicate the contents of any package 
    either on itself or on any label, carton or other thing, or 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    indicate the contents on any container, 
    or 
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    express any quantity or dimension, 
 
otherwise than in accordance with the standard 
    unit of weight, measure or numeration.
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>34</number> Any 
    custom, usage, etc., contrary to standard weight, measure or 
    numeration to be void.—Any custom, 
    usage, practice or method of whatever nature which permits a person to 
    demand, receive, or cause to be demanded or received, any quantity of 
    article, thing or service (to which this Part applies) in excess of, or less 
    than the quantity specified by weight, measure or number in the contract or 
    other agreement in relation to the said article, thing or service, shall be 
    void. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>35</number> Manufacturers, etc., to maintain 
      records and registers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
      Every person who— 
 <subsection><number>a</number>    makes, 
      manufactures, sells, distributes or otherwise disposes of any weight or 
      measure or other goods which are sold, delivered or distributed by weight, 
      measure or number, or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>    repairs any 
      weight or measure, 
 to which this part applies, shall 
      maintain such records and registers as may be prescribed and if required 
      so to do by the Director, shall produce such records and registers before 
      the Director or such other officer as the Director may authorise in this 
      behalf, for inspection.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in 
      sub-section(1) if the Director is of opinion that having regard to the 
      nature or volume of the business carried on by any maker, manufacturer, 
      dealer or repairer, it is necessary so to do, he may, by order exempt such 
      maker, manufacturer, dealer or repairer from the operation of that 
      sub-section. 
 
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>36</number> Approval 
    of models.—
<section><number>1</number> Save as otherwise 
    provided in this section, this Chapter shall not apply to,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    any weight or measure which, being 
    subject to verification and stamping under the State law as in force 
    immediately before the commencement of this Act, is in use of such 
    commencement; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    any cast iron, brass, bullion, or carat 
    weight or any beam-scale, except those specified by rule made in this 
    behalf; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    length measures (not being measuring 
    tapes) ordinarily used in retail trade for measuring textiles or timber; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    capacity measures, not exceeding twenty 
    litres in capacity, which are ordinarily used in retail trade for measuring 
    kerosene, milk or potable liquors; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    any weighing or measuring instrument or 
    device which is made or manufactured exclusively for domestic use: 
 
Provided that such instrument of device is not 
    intended for the use of any member of the medical profession in the course 
    of such profession. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any 
    officer of the Central or State Government charged with the duty of 
    implementing the law relating to weights and measures has any reason to 
    believe that the model of any weight or measure referred to in sub-section 
    (1) requires a test by the prescribed authority he may acquire one such 
    weight or measure from the market and forward it to the prescribed authority 
    for test, the fees for which shall be payable by the Government employing 
    the officer by whom such weight or measure has been forwarded for test. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every 
    person shall, before making or manufacturing any weight or measure to which 
    this part applies, submit for approval of the prescribed authority, such 
    number of models, drawings and other information relating to such weight or 
    measure as may be pre­scribed: 
 
Provided that 
    in relation to any weight or measure, to which this Part applies, which has 
    already been made or manufactured, or which is in the process of being made 
    or manufactured, at the commencement of this part, models of such weight or 
    measure shall be submitted to the prescribed authority from out of the 
    weights or measures which have already been or which are in the process of 
    being, made or manufactured: 
 
Provided 
    further that in the case of a weight or measure the model whereof cannot be 
    submitted, whether by reason of its nature or otherwise, it shall be 
    sufficient if the drawings and other prescribed information about the weight 
    or measure is submitted to the prescribed authority and thereupon that 
    authori­ty shall test the models of such weight or measure at the place 
    where it is made or manufactured or at such other place as may be specified 
    by the Director: 
 
Provided also 
    that the prescribed authority may, if it is satis­fied that the model of any 
    weight or measure which has been approved in a country outside India 
    conforms to the standards established by or under this Act, approve such 
    model without any test or after such test as it may deem fit. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    prescribed authority shall levy and collect such fees for the testing of any 
    model, submitted under this section for appro­val, as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    prescribed authority shall test the models submitted to it with a view to— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    ascertaining whether such models 
    conform to the standards established by or under this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    finding out the ability of such models 
    to maintain accuracy over periods of sustained use; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    determining the performance of such 
    models under such varied conditions as may be prescribed. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    prescribed authority shall submit to the Central Govern­ment a detailed 
    report on the performance of the model submitted to it together with its 
    recommendations with regard to the desir­ability or otherwise of issuing a 
    certificate of approval in respect of that model. 
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The Central 
    Government may, if it is satisfied after considering the report submitted to 
    it by the prescribed authori­ty that the aforesaid model is in conformity 
    with the provision of this Act or any rule made thereunder and is likely to 
    maintain accuracy over periods of sustained use and to render accurate 
    service under varied conditions, issue a certificate of approval in respect 
    of that model. 
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> Every 
    certificate of approval of a model shall be published in the Official 
    Gazette and shall also be published in such other manner as the Central 
    Government may think fit. 
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> The Central 
    Government may, if it is satisfied that the product made or manufactured in 
    accordance with the model which was approved by it has failed to render the 
    expected performance or to conform to the standards established by or under 
    this Act, revoke the certificate of approval issued by it under sub-section 
    (7): 
 
Provided that 
    no such revocation shall be made except after giving the manufacturer of 
    such weight or measure a reasonable opportunity of being heard: 
 
Provided 
    further that where the Central Government is satisfied that as a result of 
    the alteration made by the manufacturer in the model of the weight or 
    measure, such model has become fit for approval, it may vacate the order of 
    revocation of the certifi­cate of approval issued by it. 
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> If for any 
    reason any material of the approved model of a weight or measure to which 
    this part applies becomes non-available in India, the manufacturer may 
    continue the manufactur­e of such weight or measure with such substitute 
    materials as may be, in his opinion, most suitable for the manufacture of 
    such weight or measure but where the manufacturer does so, he shall send 
    such substitute materials to the prescribed authority for test. 
 </section><section>
<number>11</number> If the 
    prescribed authority is of opinion that the substi­tute material referred to 
    in sub-section (10) is not suitable and that there is available in India any 
    other material which is more suitable, that authority shall intimate its 
    findings to the Central Government and also to the manufacturer, and 
    thereupon the manufacturer shall not manufacture the weight or measure with 
    any material other than the material recommended by the prescribed 
    authority, until the material which was originally approved by the 
    prescribed authority becomes available in India: 
 
Provided that 
    where, in the opinion of the prescribed authority the substitute material 
    referred to in sub-section (10) is not suitable and no other suitable 
    material is also available in India, the approval in relation to the model 
    shall stand sus­pended until a suitable material become available in India. 
 </section><section>
<number>12</number> Where the 
    model of any weight or measure to which this Part applies has been approved, 
    the models of different denominations of such weight or measure shall not 
    require any approval if such denominations are manufactured in accordance 
    with the same prin­ciples according to which and the same materials with 
    which, the approved model has been manufactured. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 THE STANDARDS OF 
WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>37</number> 
Penalty for counter-feiting of seals, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> Whoever,—
 <subsection>        <number>i</number> 
counterfeits any seal specified by or under this Act or the Standards Act, 
or
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>ii</number> sells 
or otherwise disposes of any counterfeit seal, or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number> possesses 
any counterfeit seal, or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iv</number> 
counterfeits any stamp, specified by or under this Act or the Standards Act or 
any rule made under either of those Acts, or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>v</number> removes any 
stamp made, whether under this Act or the Standards Act or any rule made under 
either of those Act, or tampers with any stamp so made, or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>vi</number> removes any 
stamp made, whether under this Act or the Standards Act or any rule made under 
either of those Acts, and affixes the stamp so removed on, or inserts the same 
into, any other weight or measure, or
 </subsection><subsection>      
<number>vii</number> increases or diminishes or alters in any way any weight or measure with a 
view to deceiving any person or knowing or having reason to believe that any 
person is likely to be deceived thereby,
 1[shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which 
shall not be less than six months but which may extend to two years, and for the 
second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term which shall not be 
less than one year but which may extend to five years and also with 
fine.]
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Whoever obtains, by unlawful 
means, possession of any seal specified by or under this Act or the Standards 
Act and uses, or causes to be used, any such seal for making any stamp on any 
weight or measure with a view to representing that the stamp made by such seal 
is authorised by or under this Act or the Standards Act,1[shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which 
shall not be less than six months but which may extend to who years, and, for 
the second or subsequent offence, with imprison­ment for a term which shall 
not be less than one year but which may extend to five years and also with 
fine.]
 </section><section><number>3</number> Whoever, being in lawful 
possession of a seal specified by or under this Act or the Standards Act uses, 
or causes to be used, such seal without any lawful authority for such use, 
1[shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which 
shall not be less than six months but which may extend to two years, and, for 
the second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term which shall not 
be less than one year but which may extend to five years and also with 
fine.]
 </section><section><number>4</number> Whoever sells, or offers or 
exposes for sale or otherwise disposes of any weight or measure which, he knows 
or has reason to believe, bears thereon a counterfeit stamp, 1[shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which 
shall not be less than six months but which may extend to two years, and, for 
the second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term which shall not 
be less than one year but which may extend to five years and also with 
fine.]


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>38</number> Weight 
    or measure to contain number of the approved model, etc.— 
    Every weight or measure to which this Part applies and for which a model has 
    been approved shall bear thereon, in such manner as may be prescribed, the 
    number of the approved model and the number of the certificate by or under 
    which such model was approved: 
 
Provided that 
    where the Central Government is of opinion that inclusion of any such 
    particulars on any weight or measure is not possible by reason of its size 
    or nature, that Government may exempt the inclusion of such particulars on 
    such weight or meas­ure. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>39</number> 
    Quantities and origin of commodities in packaged form to be declared.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No person shall,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    make, manufacture, pack, sell, or cause 
    to be packed or sold; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    distribute, deliver, or cause to be 
    distributed or delivered; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    offer, expose or possess for sale, 
 
any commodity in packaged form to which this 
    Part applies unless such package bears thereon or on a label securely 
    attached thereto a definite, plain and conspicuous declaration, made in the 
    prescribed manner, of—
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    the identity of the commodity in the 
    package; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    the net quantity, in terms of the 
    standard unit of weight or measure, of the commodity in the package; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>    where the commodity is packaged or 
    sold by number, the accurate number of the commodity contained in the 
    package; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iv</number>    the unit sale price of the commodity 
    in the package; and  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>v</number>    the sale price of the package. 
 
Explanation.— 
    In this sub-section, the expression “unit sale price” means the price 
    according to such unit or weight, measure or number as may be prescribed. 
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    package to which this Part applies shall bear thereon the name of the 
    manufacturer and also of the packer or distribu­tor. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the 
    package of a commodity to which this Part applies or the label thereon bears 
    a representation as to the number of servings, of the commodity contained 
    therein, such package or label shall also bear a statement as to the net 
    quantity (in terms of weight, measure or number) of each such serving. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    statement on a package or label as to the net weight, measure or number of 
    the contents thereof shall not include any expression which tends to qualify 
    such weight, measure or number: 
 
Provided that 
    the Central Government may, by rules, specify the commodities, the weight or 
    measure of which is likely to increase or decrease beyond the prescribed 
    tolerance limits by reason of climatic variations; and it shall be lawful 
    for the manufacturer or packer of the commodity so specified to qualify the 
    statement as to the net content of such commodity by the use of the words 
    “when packed”. 
 
Explanation.— 
    The words “when packed” shall not be used in any case except a case to which 
    the proviso to sub-section (4) applies. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where the 
    Central Government has reason to believe that there is undue proliferation 
    of weight, measure or number in which any commodity is, or reasonably 
    comparable commodities are, being packed for sale, distribution or delivery 
    and such undue proliferation impairs in the opinion of that Government, the 
    reasonable ability of the consumer to make a comparative assessment of the 
    prices after considering the net quantity or number of such commodity, that 
    Government may direct the manufacturers and also the packers or distributors 
    to sell, distribute or deliver such commodity in such standard quantities or 
    number as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Wherever 
    the retail price of a commodity in packaged form to which this Chapter 
    applies is stated in any advertisement, there shall be included in the 
    advertisement, a conspicuous declaration as to the net quantity or number of 
    the commodity contained in the package and retail unit sale price thereof. 
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> No person 
    shall sell, distribute or deliver for sale a package containing a commodity 
    which is filled less than the prescribed capacity of such package except 
    where it is proved by such person that the package was so filled with a view 
    to— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    giving protection to the contents of 
    such package, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    meeting the requirements of machines 
    used for enclosing the contents of such package. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>8</number> The Central 
    Government may, by rules, specify such reasonable variations in the net 
    contents of the commodity in a package as may be caused by the method of 
    packing or the ordinary exposure which may be undergone by such commodity 
    after it has been introduced in trade or commerce. 
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> The Central 
    Government may, by rules, specify the classes of commodities or packages in 
    relation to which all or any of the provisions of this section shall not 
    apply or shall apply with such exceptions or modifications as may be 
    specified therein. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>40</number> 
    Definitions.—In this Chapter, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “Controller” means the person appointed 
    as such by the State Government under the State law; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “Inspector” means the person appointed 
    as such by the State Government under the State law; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “local Inspector” means an Inspector 
    within the local limits of whose jurisdiction any weight or measure is made, 
    manufactured, received, delivered or kept for sale or use;  
    
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    “State law” means the law enacted by 
    the Legislature of a State, and for the time being in force in that State, 
    with regard to the enforcement of the standards of weight or measure 
    established by or under this Act; 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    “transferee State” means the State in 
    which any weight or measure is delivered or received for sale or use therein 
    from any other State; 
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    “transferor State” means the State from 
    which any weight or measure made or manufactured therein, or kept therein 
    for sale or use, is sent to or delivered in any other State. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>41</number> 
    Verification and stamping of weights and measures sent from one State to 
    another.—
<section><number>1</number> Where any weight or 
    measure, sent from a transferor State for delivery, sale or use in a 
    transferee State, is such that,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    it is not required to be dismantled 
    before its despatch to the transferee State and is not likely to lose its 
    accuracy by reason of such despatch, it shall be known, for the purposes of 
    this Chapter, as a weight or measure of the first category; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    it is required to be dismantled before 
    its despatch to the transferee State and reassembled and installed for use 
    in the transferee State, it shall be known, for the purposes of this 
    Chapter, as a weight or measure of the second category. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to 
    the provisions of sub-section (1), the Central Government may specify, by 
    rules made in this behalf, the classes of weights or measures which would 
    fall in the first category or the second category, and may, from time to 
    time, if the circumstances so require, alter the category in which any class 
    of weight or measure has been specified. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Weight or 
    measure of the first category shall, before it is despatched to any 
    transferee State, be produced before the local Inspector in the transferor 
    State and if such Inspector is, after verification of such weight or 
    measure, satisfied that such weight or measure conforms to the standards 
    established by or under this Act, stamp the same with such special seal as 
    may be specified by rules made under this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A weight or 
    measure of the second category shall not be verified and stamped in the 
    transferor State but shall be verified and stamped, after its re-assembly 
    and installation for use, by the local Inspector in the transferee State. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The fees 
    for the verification and stamping of every weight or measure of— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the first category shall be levied and 
    collected by the transferor State; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the first category shall be levied and 
    collected by the transferee State, 
 
in accordance with such scales as may be 
    specified by rules made under this Act.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>6</number> A weight or 
    measure, whether of the first or second category, shall not require 
    periodical re-verification if it is exclusively intended for domestic use 
    and is not used by any number of the medical profession in the course of 
    such profession. 
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> No weight 
    or measure, whether of the first or of the second category, shall be 
    verified and stamped unless fees for such verification and stamping have 
    been paid in accordance with the scales specified under sub-section (5). 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>42</number> Weight 
    or measure of the first category to be presumed to be correct throughout the 
    territory of India.—
<section><number>1</number> Every 
    weight or measure of the first category which is stamped with the special 
    seal referred to in sub-section (3) of section 41 shall be presumed to be 
    correct throughout the territory of India and shall not be required, until 
    its re-verification in the transferee State becomes due by efflux of time, 
    to be verified or stamped in the transferee State: 
 
Provided that 
    where the local Inspector in the transferee State has any reason to believe 
    that any weight or measure of the first category has lost its accuracy in 
    transit or has, for any other reason, ceased to conform to the standards of 
    weight or measure established by or under this Act, he may, for reasons to 
    be recorded by him in writing, and communicated to the Controller of the 
    transferor State, through the Controller of the transferee State— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    verify such weight or measure; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    if, on verification, such weight or 
    measure is found to be inaccurate— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    cause such adjustment as is necessary 
    to be made so as to make it conform to the standards established by or under 
    this Act, or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    where he is of opinion that such 
    adjustment is not possible, reject it and obliterate the stamp thereon: 
 
Provided 
    further that where any verification, adjustment or obliteration is made in 
    exercise of the powers conferred by the foregoing proviso, no fee shall be 
    charged for such verification, adjustment or obliteration. 
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    computing the time when the re-verification of a weight or measure of the 
    first category shall become due in the transferee State, the period during 
    which such weight or measure remains unsold or undistributed in the 
    transferee State, shall be excluded. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>42</number> Weight 
    or measure of the first category to be presumed to be correct throughout the 
    territory of India.—
<section><number>1</number> Every 
    weight or measure of the first category which is stamped with the special 
    seal referred to in sub-section (3) of section 41 shall be presumed to be 
    correct throughout the territory of India and shall not be required, until 
    its re-verification in the transferee State becomes due by efflux of time, 
    to be verified or stamped in the transferee State: 
 
Provided that 
    where the local Inspector in the transferee State has any reason to believe 
    that any weight or measure of the first category has lost its accuracy in 
    transit or has, for any other reason, ceased to conform to the standards of 
    weight or measure established by or under this Act, he may, for reasons to 
    be recorded by him in writing, and communicated to the Controller of the 
    transferor State, through the Controller of the transferee State— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    verify such weight or measure; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    if, on verification, such weight or 
    measure is found to be inaccurate— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    cause such adjustment as is necessary 
    to be made so as to make it conform to the standards established by or under 
    this Act, or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    where he is of opinion that such 
    adjustment is not possible, reject it and obliterate the stamp thereon: 
 
Provided 
    further that where any verification, adjustment or obliteration is made in 
    exercise of the powers conferred by the foregoing proviso, no fee shall be 
    charged for such verification, adjustment or obliteration. 
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    computing the time when the re-verification of a weight or measure of the 
    first category shall become due in the transferee State, the period during 
    which such weight or measure remains unsold or undistributed in the 
    transferee State, shall be excluded. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>43</number> Weight 
    or measure of the first category not to be sold or used in any State unless 
    it is stamped in the transferor State.—No 
    weight or measure of the first category shall be used, sold, purchased, 
    delivered or otherwise transferred in any transferee State unless such 
    weight or measure bears thereon the stamp made with the special seal 
    referred to in sub-section (3) of section 41. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>44</number> Weights 
    or measures of the second category received from transferor State to be 
    produced before the local Inspector of the transferee State.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every person in a transferee State who receives or delivers for sale or use 
    therein any weight or measure of the second category shall, after its 
    re-assembly and installation for use, have such weight or measure verified 
    and stamped by the local Inspector in the transferee State.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The local 
    Inspector in the transferee State shall verify every weight or measure of 
    the second category and shall if he is satisfied that such weight or measure 
    conforms to the standards established by or under this Act, stamp the same 
    with the seal prescribed by or under the State law in force in the 
    transferee State. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> For the 
    avoidance of doubts, it is hereby declared that where any weight or measure 
    of the second category is delivered or received in a State from any other 
    State, not for the purpose of sale or use therein but for the transmission 
    of such weight or measure to any other State, then, such other State, shall 
    be deemed for the purposes of this Chapter, to be the transferee State in 
    relation to such weight or measure and the provisions of sub-section (1) and 
    sub-section (2) shall apply accordingly. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>45</number> 
    Procedure when any weight or measure is transferred from a transferee State 
    to another State.— Where 
    any weight or measure, which being in use in a transferee State, is sent to, 
    or delivered in, any other State for sale or use in such other State, then, 
    such other state shall also be deemed to be the transferee State in relation 
    to such weight or measure and the provisions of this Chapter shall, so far 
    as may be, apply to the weight or measure sent to, or delivered in, such 
    other State. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>46</number> 
    Manufacturers, etc., who send any weight or measure to any other State to 
    submit return to the Controller.—
Every manufacturer, dealer or other person in a transferor State, who 
    sends to, or delivers in, any transferee State any weight or measure, 
    whether of the first or of the second category, shall— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    submit such periodical returns as may 
    be prescribed, to the Controller of the transferor State with regard to such 
    despatch, delivery or transfer and specify in such returns the particulars 
    of the weight or measure which has been sent to, or delivered in, the 
    transferee State; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    specify in such periodical returns the 
    particulars of the person to whom such weight or measure has been sent, or 
    delivered in the transferee State; and 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    forward a copy of such periodical 
    returns to the Controller of the transferee State. 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>46</number> 
    Manufacturers, etc., who send any weight or measure to any other State to 
    submit return to the Controller.—
Every manufacturer, dealer or other person in a transferor State, who 
    sends to, or delivers in, any transferee State any weight or measure, 
    whether of the first or of the second category, shall— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    submit such periodical returns as may 
    be prescribed, to the Controller of the transferor State with regard to such 
    despatch, delivery or transfer and specify in such returns the particulars 
    of the weight or measure which has been sent to, or delivered in, the 
    transferee State; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    specify in such periodical returns the 
    particulars of the person to whom such weight or measure has been sent, or 
    delivered in the transferee State; and 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    forward a copy of such periodical 
    returns to the Controller of the transferee State. 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>47</number> Persons 
    exporting or importing any weight or measure to get themselves registered.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No dealer or manufacturer shall export or import any weight or measure 
    unless he is registered under this section as such exporter or importer, as 
    the case may be. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    person who intends to commence or continue business as an exporter or 
    importer of any weight or measure shall make, within such time from the 
    commencement of this Act as may be prescribed, an application for the 
    inclusion of his name in the register to be maintained for the purpose. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    application referred to in sub-section (2) shall be made to the Director and 
    every such application shall be made in such form, in such manner and on 
    payment of such fees, not exceeding ten rupees, as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> On receipt 
    of an application referred to in sub-section (2), the Director shall, if he 
    is satisfied after such inquiry as he may think fit, that it is expedient in 
    the public interest so to do, include the name of the applicant in the 
    register referred to in sub-section (2) and issue to the applicant a 
    certificate to the effect that his name has been so included and send a copy 
    of the said certificate to the Controller of Legal Metrology in the State in 
    which such exporter or importer is carrying on his business. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> A 
    certificate granted under sub-section (4) shall be valid for the period 
    specified therein and may be renewed, from time to time, for such further 
    period as may be prescribed. 
  
  
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>48</number> 
    Conditions under which export of non-standard weights and measures and other 
    goods may be made.—
<section><number>1</number> Subject to 
    such conditions, limitations and restrictions as may be prescribed, the 
    Central Government may allow the export of any weight or measure which has 
    been made or manufactured exclusively for export with the previous 
    permission of that Government notwithstanding that such weight or measure 
    does not conform to the standards established by or under this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any 
    commodity in packaged form is exported and the person to whom such export is 
    to be made so requires, the exporter may, in addition to specifying the net 
    contents of such package in terms of the standards unit of weight or measure 
    established by or under this Act, also specify the weight or the net 
    contents thereof in terms of such units of weight or measure as may be 
    specified by the person to whom such commodity is to be exported. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained elsewhere in this Act, in relation to any 
    goods which are exported,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    quotation of any price; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    issue of any price list, invoice or 
    cash memo; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    indication of the weight or measure or 
    number of net contents of any package on any label, carton or other thing; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    expression of any dimension, 
 
may be made in accordance with any other 
    system of weight, measure or numeration, if the person to whom the export is 
    to be made so, requires.
  
  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>48</number> 
    Conditions under which export of non-standard weights and measures and other 
    goods may be made.—
<section><number>1</number> Subject to 
    such conditions, limitations and restrictions as may be prescribed, the 
    Central Government may allow the export of any weight or measure which has 
    been made or manufactured exclusively for export with the previous 
    permission of that Government notwithstanding that such weight or measure 
    does not conform to the standards established by or under this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any 
    commodity in packaged form is exported and the person to whom such export is 
    to be made so requires, the exporter may, in addition to specifying the net 
    contents of such package in terms of the standards unit of weight or measure 
    established by or under this Act, also specify the weight or the net 
    contents thereof in terms of such units of weight or measure as may be 
    specified by the person to whom such commodity is to be exported. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained elsewhere in this Act, in relation to any 
    goods which are exported,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    quotation of any price; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    issue of any price list, invoice or 
    cash memo; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    indication of the weight or measure or 
    number of net contents of any package on any label, carton or other thing; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    expression of any dimension, 
 
may be made in accordance with any other 
    system of weight, measure or numeration, if the person to whom the export is 
    to be made so, requires.
  
  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>49</number> 
    Non-metric weight or measure not to be imported.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Save as otherwise provided in sub-section (2), no weight or measure, whether 
    singly or as a part or component or any machine or machinery, shall be 
    imported unless it conforms to the standards of weight or measure 
    established by or under this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any 
    commodity, machinery or any part or component of any machinery is imported 
    from a country in which the metric system of weight or measure is not in 
    force, or in which such system being in force, such commodity, machinery, 
    part or component of any machinery has not been made or manufactured in 
    accordance with such system, the importer shall, before making such import, 
    make an endeavour to obtain, on such commodity, machinery, part or 
    component, and also on the drawings thereof, the weight or measurement 
    thereof expressed in terms of the standard unit of weight or measure 
    established by or under this Act: 
 
Provided that 
    where any weight or measure has not been expressed in terms of the standard 
    unit of weight or measure established by or under this Act, on any 
    commodity, machinery, part or component or on any drawings thereof the 
    importer shall, within six months from the date of import, get the weight or 
    measure thereof expressed on such commodity, machinery, part or component 
    and on the drawings thereof in terms of the standard unit of weight or 
    measure established by or under this Act. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>50</number> Penalty 
    for use of non-standard weights or measures.—Whoever 
    uses any weight or measure or makes any numeration otherwise than in 
    accordance with the standards of weight or measure or the standards of 
    numeration, as the case may be, established by or under this Act, shall be 
    punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or 
    with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both, and for the 
    second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term which may extend 
    to two years and also with fine. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>51</number> Penalty 
    for contravention of section 18.—Whoever 
    tampers with, or alters, in any way, any reference standard, secondary 
    standard, or working standard except where such alteration is made for the 
    correction of any error noticed therein on verification, shall be punished 
    with imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years, or with fine 
    which may extend to five thousand rupees, or with both. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 
52 Penalty 
    for contravention of section 22.—Except 
    where any weight or measure is made or manufactured, with the permission of 
    the Central Government, exclusively for export, every person who makes or 
    manufactures any weight or measure which does not conform to the standards 
    of weight or measure established by or under this Act, shall, where such 
    offence is not punishable under any other law relating to weights and 
    measures for the time being in force, be punished with imprisonment for a 
    term which may extend to one year, or with fine which may extend to two 
    thousand rupees, or with both, and, for the second or subsequent offence 
    with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years and also with 
    fine. 
 
  


 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>53</number> Penalty 
    for contravention of section 23.—Except 
    where any weight or measure is made or manufactured, with the permission of 
    the Central Government, exclusively for export, every person who makes or 
    manufactures any weight or measure which bears thereon any inscription of 
    weight, measure or number which does not conform to the standards of weight 
    or measure or numeration established by or under this Act, shall, where such 
    offence is not punishable under any other law relating to weights and 
    measures for the time being in force, be punished with imprisonment for a 
    term which may extend to one year, or with fine which may extend to two 
    thousand rupees, or with both, and, for the second or subsequent offence, 
    with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years and also with 
    fine. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>54</number> Penalty 
    for contravention of section 29.—Whoever 
    obstructs the Director or any person authorised to exercise the powers or 
    discharge the functions of the Director (hereafter, in this Part, referred 
    to as the “authorised officer”) in the exercise of his powers or discharge 
    of his functions as such Director or authorised officer, or with intent to 
    prevent or deter the Director or such authorised officer from exercising his 
    powers or discharging his functions, or in consequence of any thing done or 
    attempted to be done by the Director or such authorised officer in the 
    lawful exercise of his powers or discharge of his functions as such, shall 
    be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years, and, 
    for the second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term which may 
    extend to five years. 
  
  
  
  
  
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>55</number> Penalty 
    for contravention of section 32.—Whoever 
    in the course of any inter-State trade or commerce, makes any transaction, 
    deal or contract in contravention of the provisions of section 32 shall be 
    punished with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees, and, for the 
    second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term which may extend 
    to one year and also with fine. 
  
  
  
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>56</number> Penalty 
    for contravention of section 33.—Whoever 
    in the course of any inter-State trade or commerce, contravenes the 
    provisions of section 33 shall be punished with fine which may extend to two 
    thousand rupees, and, for the second or subsequent offence, with 
    imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years and also with fine. 
  
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>57</number> Penalty 
    for contravention of section 34.—Whoever, 
    in the course of any inter-State trade or commerce,— 
 <section>
<number>i</number>    sells, delivers, or causes to be sold 
    or delivered , to the purchaser any quantity or number of any article or 
    thing, less than the quantity or number contracted for or paid for; or  
    
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    renders any service by weight, measure 
    or number, less than the service contracted for or paid for; or 
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>    demands, or causes to be demanded, or 
    receives, or causes to be received, while buying any article or thing, any 
    quantity or number of goods in excess of the quantity or number contracted 
    for or paid for; or 
 </section><section>
<number>iv</number>    obtains any service in excess of the 
    service contracted for or paid for,  
 
shall be punished with fine which may extend 
    to five thousand rupees, and, for the second or subsequent offence, with 
    imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years and also with fine.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>58</number> Penalty 
    for contravention of section 35.—Whoever, 
    being required by or under this Act so to do, without any reasonable excuse, 
    omits or fails to maintain any record or register, or being required by the 
    Director or the authorised officer, to produce any record or register for 
    his inspection, omits or fails, without any reasonable excuse, so to do, 
    shall be punished with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, and, 
    for the second or subsequent offence , with imprisonment for a term which 
    may extend to six months and also with fine. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>59</number> Penalty 
    for contravention of section 36.—Whoever, 
    being required by section 36 to submit the model of any weight or measure 
    for approval, omits, or fails, without any reasonable excuse, so to do, 
    shall be punished with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees, and, 
    for the second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term which may 
    extend to five years and also with fine. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>60</number> Penalty for manufacture of weights or 
      measures unless approval of model is in force.—
<section><number>1</number> Whoever makes or manufactures any weight or 
      measure which is, or is intended to be, sold, distributed, delivered or 
      otherwise transferred in the course of inter-State trade or commerce, 
      shall, unless a certificate of approval of the model of such weight or 
      measure granted under section 36 is in force, be punished with 
      imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years and shall also be 
      liable to fine, and, for the second or subsequent offence, with 
      imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years and also with 
      fine. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Whoever, without any reasonable excuse, 
      manufactures any weight or measure in accordance with an approved model 
      with any material other than the material approved or recommended by the 
      prescribed authority, shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which 
      may extend to five years and also with fine. 
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>61</number> Penalty 
    for contravention of section 38.—Whoever 
    makes or manufactures any weight or measure without complying with the 
    requirements of section 38 shall be punished with fine which may extend to 
    five thousand rupees, and, for the second or subsequent offence, with 
    imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years and also with fine. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>62</number> Penalty 
    for sale, etc., of unverified weights or measures in the course of 
    inter-State trade or commerce.—Whoever, 
    in the course of inter-State trade or commerce, sells, distributes, delivers 
    or otherwise transfers any weight or measure which does not conform to the 
    standards of weight or measure established by or under this Act or which has 
    not been duly verified under any other law relating to weights and measures 
    for the time being in force, shall be punished with fine which may extend to 
    ten thousand rupees, and, for the second or subsequent offence, with 
    imprisonment for a term which may extend to seven years and also with fine. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>63</number> Penalty 
    for contravention of section 39.—Whoever, 
    in the course of inter-State trade or commerce, sells, distributes, delivers 
    or otherwise transfers, or causes to be sold, distributed, delivered or 
    otherwise transferred any commodity in a packaged form which does not 
    conform to the provisions of this Act or any rule made thereunder , shall be 
    punished with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees, and, for the 
    second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term which may extend 
    to five years and also with fine. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>64</number> Penalty 
    for contravention of section 47.—Whoever 
    exports or imports any weight or measure without being registered under this 
    Act shall be punished with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, 
    and, for the second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term 
    which may extend to six months and also with fine. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>65</number> Penalty 
    for contravention of section 48.—Every 
    person who exports any weight or measure or commodity in packaged form which 
    does not conform to the standards of weight or measure established by or 
    under this Act, shall, except where such export has been made with the 
    previous approval of the Central Government, be punished with fine which may 
    extend to five thousand rupees, and, for the second or subsequent offence 
    with imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years and also with 
    fine. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>66</number> Penalty 
    for contravention of section 49.—Whoever 
    contravenes, without any reasonable excuse, the provisions of section 49, 
    shall be punished with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees, and, 
    for the second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term which may 
    extend to five years and also with fine. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>67</number> Penalty 
    where no specific penalty is provided.—Whoever 
    contravenes any provisions of this Act for the contravention of which no 
    punishment has been separately provided in any of the provisions of this 
    Act, shall be punished with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>68</number> 
    Presumption to be made in certain cases.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If any person, in the course of inter- State trade or commerce, uses, or 
    causes to be used, sells distributes, delivers or otherwise transfers, or 
    causes to be sold, distributed, delivered or otherwise transferred, any 
    false or unverified weight or measure, it shall be presumed, until the 
    contrary is proved, that he had done so with the knowledge that the weight 
    or measure was a false or unverified weight or measure. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any 
    person makes or manufactures or has in his possession, custody or control 
    any false or unverified weight or measure in such circumstances as to 
    indicate that such weight or measure is likely to be used in the course of 
    inter-State trade or commerce, it shall be presumed, until the contrary is 
    proved, that such false or unverified weight or measure was made, 
    manufactured, possessed, held or controlled by such person with the 
    knowledge that the same would be, or is intended to be, used in the course 
    of inter-State trade or commerce. 
  
  
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>69</number> Penalty 
    for personation of officials.—Whoever 
    personates, in any way, the Director, or any authorised officer, shall be 
    punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>70</number> Penalty 
    for giving false information or false returns.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whoever gives information to the Director or the authorised officer which he 
    may require or ask for in the course of his duty and which such person 
    either knows or has reason to believe to be false shall be punished with 
    imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine which 
    may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Whoever, 
    being required by or under this Act so to do, submits a return which is 
    false in material particulars, shall be punished with fine which may extend 
    to two thousand rupees, and, for the second or subsequent offence, with 
    imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year and also with fine. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>71</number> Vexatious actions.—
<section><number>1</number> An authorised officer who knows that there 
      are no reasonable grounds for so doing, and yet,— 
 <subsection><number>a</number>    searches, or 
      causes to be searched, any house, conveyance or place; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>    searches any 
      person; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>    seizes any 
      weight, measure or other movable property, 
 shall, for every such offence, be 
      punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or 
      with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees, or with 
both.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> If a local Inspector, as defined in section 
      40,— 
 <subsection><number>a</number>    without any 
      reasonable cause verifies any weight or measure of first category, within 
      the meaning of section 41, 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>    without any 
      reasonable cause obliterates any stamp on any such weight or measure, 
 in contravention of the provisions 
      of the first proviso to section 42, he shall, for every such offence be 
      punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or 
      with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees, or with 
    both.
 
  </subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>72</number> 
    Cognizance of offences, etc.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974),— 
 

1[
<section><number>a</number>    
    no court shall take cognizance of an offence punishable under this Act 
    except upon a complaint, in writing, made by— 
    1[(a) no court shall take cognizance of an offence 
    punishable under this Act except upon a complaint, in writing, made by—" 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    the Director; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    any other authorised officer; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    any person aggrieved; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    a recognised consumer association 
    whether the person aggrieved is a member of such association or not. 
 
Explanation.—For the purposes of this 
    clause “recognised consumer association” means a voluntary consumer 
    association registered under the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) or any 
    other law for the time being in force;] 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number>    no court inferior to that a 
    Metropolitan Magistrate or a Judicial Magistrate of the first class shall 
    try any offence under this Act; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    an offence punishable under section 50, 
    section 52, section 53, section 56, section 58, section 60, section 61, 
    section 63, section 64, section 65, or section 66, may be tried summarily by 
    a Magistrate and no sentence of imprisonment for a term exceeding one year 
    shall be passed in the case of any conviction for an offence which is 
    summarily tried under this section. 
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>73</number> 
    Compounding of offences.—
<section><number>1</number> Any 
    offence punishable under section 50, section 55, section 56, section 57, 
    section 58, section 59, section 60, section 63, section 64, section 65, 
    section 66, or section 67 may, either before or after the institution of the 
    prosecution , be compounded by the Director or such other officer as may be 
    specially authorised by him in this behalf, on payment for credit to the 
    Government of such sum as the Director or such other officer may specify: 
 
Provided that 
    such sum shall not, in any case, exceed the maximum amount of the fine which 
    may be imposed under this Act for the offence so compounded. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Nothing in 
    sub-section (1) shall apply to a person who commits the same or similar 
    offence within a period of three years from the date on which the first 
    offence, committed by him, was compounded. 
 
Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this sub-section, any second or subsequent offence committed 
    after the expiry of a period of three years from the date on which the 
    offence was previously compounded, shall be deemed to be a first offence. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where an 
    offence has been compounded under sub-section (1), no proceeding or further 
    proceeding, as the case may be, shall be taken against the offender in 
    respect of the offence so compounded, and the offender, if in custody, shall 
    be discharged forthwith. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> No offence 
    under this Act shall be compounded except as provided by this section. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>74</number> Offences 
    by companies and power of court to publish name, place of business, etc., of 
    companies convicted.—
<section><number>1</number> If an 
    offence under this Act is committed by a company, every person who, at the 
    time the offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible to the 
    company for the conduct of the business of the company as well as the 
    company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to 
    be proceeded against and punished accordingly: 
 
Provided that 
    nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to 
    punishment if he proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge 
    or that he had exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such 
    offence. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence 
    under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the 
    offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is 
    attributable to the neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary 
    or other officer, such director, manager, secretary or other officer shall 
    also be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be 
    proceeded against and punished accordingly. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where any 
    company is convicted under this Act for contravention of any of the 
    provisions thereof, it shall be competent for the court convicting the 
    company to cause the name and place of business of the company, nature of 
    the contravention, the fact that the company has been so convicted and such 
    other particulars as the court may consider to be appropriate in the 
    circumstances of the case, to be published at the expense of the company in 
    such newspapers or in such other manner as the court may direct. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> No 
    publication under sub-section (3) shall be made until the period for 
    preferring an appeal against the orders of the court has expired without any 
    appeal having been preferred, or such an appeal, having been preferred, has 
    been disposed of. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    expenses of any publication under sub-section (3) shall be recoverable from 
    the company as if it were a fine imposed by the court. 
 
Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “ company” means any body corporate and 
    includes a firm or other association of individuals; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    “ director”, in relation to a firm, 
    means a partner in the firm. 
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 THE STANDARDS OF 
WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>75</number> 
Repeal and savings.—
<section><number>1</number> On the 
commencement of any provisions of this Act in a State, the corresponding 
provisions of any law in force for the time being in that State shall stand 
repealed, and on such repeal, the provisions of section 6 of the General Clauses 
Act, 1897 (10 of 1897), shall apply as if the provisions so repealed were the 
provisions of a Central Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> 
Notwithstanding such repeal, any appointment, notification, rule, order, 
registration, licence, certificate, notice, decision, approval, authorisation or 
consent made, issued or given under such law shall, if in force at the 
commencement of this Act, continue to be in force and have effect as if it were 
made, issued or given under the corresponding provisions of this 
Act. </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>76</number> 
    Establishment of a training Institute and provisions for training thereat.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    There shall be established by the Central Government, at such place as it 
    may think fit, an Institute to be known as the “Indian Institute of Legal 
    Metrology” (hereafter referred to as the “Institute”) for imparting training 
    in legal metrology and other allied branches of knowledge. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    management and control of the Institute, which shall vest in the Central 
    Government, shall be carried on in accordance with such regulations as may 
    be made by the Central Government. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Central 
    Government shall provide the Institute with such teaching staff and other 
    employees, and with such equipments and other facilities as it may think fit 
    to enable the Institute to function effectively as an institution for 
    imparting adequate training in legal metrology and other allied branches of 
    knowledge. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The courses 
    and curricula for training at the Institute and the period for which the 
    training may be imparted thereat for each course shall be such as may be 
    prescribed. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Central 
    Government shall prescribe the minimum qualifications which a person shall 
    possess in order to be eligible for admission to the Institute for receiving 
    training thereat and different qualifications may be prescribed for 
    different courses of training imparted at the Institute. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The Central 
    Government and every State Government may depute, in such batches as may be 
    convenient to the Institute, employees of, or above, the rank of an 
    Inspector for receiving training at the Institute and the Central Government 
    may also arrange for the training, at the Institute, of such other person as 
    it may think fit. 
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The 
    Institute may,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    carry out such researches in legal 
    metrology and other allied branches of knowledge as may be entrusted to it 
    by the Central Government, and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    hold such seminars, meetings or other 
    gatherings as it may think fit. 
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>77</number> Training 
    at other places.—Where the Central 
    Government is of opinion that in addition to the training imparted at the 
    Institute, it is necessary to impart to an employee, not below the rank of 
    an Inspector, further specialised training which is not provided for at the 
    Institute, it may send such employee to such other place, authority or 
    institution as it may think fit for receiving such specialised training. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>78</number> Survey 
    and statistics.—The Central 
    Government shall make, or cause to be made, such surveys and collect, or 
    cause to be collected , such statistics as it may consider necessary with a 
    view to ascertaining the extent to which any standard of weight, measure or 
    numeration established by or under this Act has been implemented in any area 
    or in relation to any class of undertakings, users of goods and it shall be 
    the duty of every person using weight or measure or making any numeration to 
    render such assistance as the person making such survey or collecting such 
    statistics may require. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>79</number> 
    Conversion of non-metric weights and measures into standard units of weights 
    or measures.—
<section><number>1</number> The value 
    expressed in terms of any unit of weight or measure other than in terms of 
    the standard units of weight or measure may be converted into the value 
    expressed in terms of a standard unit of weight or measure at the rate 
    specified in the Schedule. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> All 
    references in any enactment or in any notification, rule or order made under 
    any enactment, or in any contract, deed or other instrument, for the time 
    being in force, to a value expressed in terms of any unit of weight, measure 
    or numeration other than that of a standard unit of weight, measure or 
    numeration shall be construed as references to that value expressed in terms 
    of standard units of weight, measure or numeration, as the case may be, 
    converted at the rates specified in the Schedule. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>80</number> Non-metric weight or measure not to be 
      mentioned in any document, etc., or to form the basis of any 
      contract after the commencement of this Act.— 
<section><number>1</number> No unit of weight, measure or 
      numeration shall, after the commencement of this Act, be stated in any 
      enactment, notification, rule, order, contract, deed or other instrument 
      in terms of any unit of weight, measure or numeration other than that of a 
      standard unit of weight, measure or numeration. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> On and from the commencement of this Act, no 
      weight, measure or number other than the standard weight, measure or 
      number shall be used in, or form the basis of, any contract or other 
      agreement in relation to any inter-State or international trade or 
      commerce: 
 Provided that in relation to any goods which are 
      exported, the weight, measure or number of such goods may be indicated 
      thereon, or in any contract, in addition to the standard units of weight, 
      measure or numeration, in accordance with any other system of weight, 
      measure or numeration if the person to whom the export is to be made so 
      requires. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Any contract or other agreement in 
      contravention of the provisions of sub-section (2) shall be void. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> No written record of the results of any 
      measurement shall be maintained in any unit other than the standard unit 
      of weight, measure or numeration established by or under this Act. 
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>81</number> Appeals.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of sub-section (2), any person aggrieved by an 
    order made under section 30 or section 36 may prefer an appeal against such 
    order to the Director, or where the order has been made by the Director, to 
    the Central Government. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every such 
    appeal shall be preferred within sixty days from the date on which the 
    impugned order was made: 
 
Provided that 
    the appellate authority may, if it is satisfied that the appellant was 
    prevented by sufficient cause from preferring the appeal within the said 
    period of sixty days, permit the appellant to prefer the appeal within a 
    further period of sixty days. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On receipt 
    of any such appeal, the appellate authority shall, after giving the parties 
    to the appeal a reasonable opportunity of being heard and after making such 
    inquiry as it deems proper, make such order, as it may think fit, confirming 
    , modifying or reversing the order appealed against or may send back the 
    case with such direction as it may think fit for a fresh order after taking 
    additional evidence, if necessary. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every 
    appeal shall be preferred on payment of such fee, as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Central 
    Government may, on its own motion or otherwise, call for and examine the 
    record of any proceeding (including a proceeding in appeal) in which any 
    decision or order has been made, for the purpose of satisfying itself as to 
    the correctness, legality or propriety of such decision or order and may 
    pass such order thereon as it may think fit: 
 
Provided that 
    no decision or order shall be varied under this sub-section so as to 
    prejudicially affect any person unless such person has been given a 
    reasonable opportunity of showing cause against the proposed action. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>82</number> Levy of 
    fees.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government 
    may, by rules made under section 83, specify such fees, not exceeding,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    five thousand rupees, for the approval 
    of the model of any weight or measure intended to be made or manufactured 
    for sale, purchase, distribution or delivery in the course of any 
    inter-State trade or commerce; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    one thousand rupees, for the 
    verification and stamping of a weight or measure of the first category 
    within the meaning of section 41; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    five thousand rupees, for the 
    verification and stamping of a weight or measure of the second category, 
    within the meaning of section 41; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    one rupee for every 100 words or less, 
    for the grant of copies of any document, not being a document of a 
    confidential nature; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    ten rupees, for the registration of 
    exporters or importers of weights and measures; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    twenty-five rupees for any appeal 
    preferred under this Act. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> No 
    approval, verification or stamping shall be made, copy granted , 
    registration made or appeal entertained unless the fee prescribed therefor 
    under sub-section (1) has been paid. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>83</number> Power to 
    make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
    Government may, by notification, make rules for carrying out the provisions 
    of this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:- 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    supplementary, derived, special or 
    other units of weight or measure, standard symbols or definitions, as 
    recommended by the General Conference on Weights and Measures or the 
    International Organisation of Legal Metrology; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    multiples and sub-multiples of, and 
    physical constants, ratios or co-efficients in relation to units of weight 
    or measure, as recommended by the General Conference on Weights and Measures 
    or the International Organisation of Legal Metrology; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    denomination of decimal multiples and 
    sub-multiples of numerals and the manner in which they shall be written; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    periodical intervals at which the 
    accuracy of the objects or equipments referred to in sub-section (1) or 
    sub-section (2) of section 16 shall be certified;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the manner in which and the conditions 
    under which every national prototype, referred to in section 15, and every 
    object or equipment referred to in section 16, shall be kept; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    the manner in which and the conditions 
    under which every reference standard, secondary standard or working standard 
    shall be kept; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    the place at which, the authority by 
    which , the manner in which, and the periodical intervals at which, every 
    reference standard, secondary standard and working standard shall be 
    verified and authenticated; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    the custody in which every reference 
    standard, secondary standard or working standard shall be kept; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    the physical characteristics, 
    configuration, constructional details, materials, equipment, performance, 
    tolerances, methods or procedures of tests, in relation to weights or 
    measures; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>    the conditions, limitations and 
    restrictions under which non-standard weights or measures may be 
    manufactured for export or may be exported; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>    the manner of disposal of any commodity 
    which is subject to speedy or natural decay; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>    class of goods or undertaking in 
    relation to which, or class of users in relation to whom, no transaction, 
    dealing or contract shall be made or had except by specified weight, measure 
    or number; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number>    registers and records to be maintained 
    by persons referred to in section 35; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>n</number>    the authority to whom models are to be 
    submitted for approval; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>o</number>    the number of models, drawings and 
    other information which are to be submitted for the approval of the model; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>p</number>    the conditions under which the 
    performance of any model is to be tested; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>q</number>    the manner in which the number of model 
    and certificate shall be inscribed on every weight or measure; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>r</number>    the manner of declaration of the 
    contents of a package and specification of the unit of weight, measure or 
    number in accordance with which the retail sale price shall be declared on 
    the package; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>s</number>    the standard quantities or number in 
    which commodities may be packed; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>t</number>    the capacity up to which a package 
    shall be filled; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>u</number>    the reasonable variations in the net 
    contents of a packaged commodity which may be caused by the method of 
    packing or ordinary exposure; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>    the classes of weights or measures 
    which would fall in the first category or the second category; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>w</number>    the special seal by which weights or 
    measures of the first category shall be stamped; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>x</number>    periodical returns to be submitted by 
    every manufacturer, dealer or other person in a transferor State; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>y</number>    the form and manner in which, and the 
    time within which, applications for inclusion of a name in the register of 
    exporters and importers of weights and measures shall be made; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>z</number>    the period for which certificate of 
    registration of an exporter or importer of weights or measures may be 
    renewed; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>za</number>    the courses and curricula for, and the 
    period of, training at the Institute; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>zb</number>    the minimum qualifications for 
    admission to the Institute; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>zc</number>    the scales in accordance with which 
    fees may be collected under section 82; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>zd</number>    any other matter which is required to 
    be, or may be, prescribed. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> In making 
    any rule under this section, the Central Government may provide that a 
    breach thereof shall be punishable with fine which may extend to two 
    thousand rupees. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every rule 
    made by the Central Government under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may 
    be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in 
    session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one 
    session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of 
    the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
    aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both 
    Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter 
    have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may 
    be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without 
    prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>84</number> 
    Continuance of certain weights and measures during transitional period.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding that this Act has come into force in respect of any area or 
    class of goods or undertakings or class of weights and measures or users of 
    weights and measures in the State of Sikkim, the Central Government may, by 
    notification, permit the continuance of the use, after such commencement, in 
    respect of that area or class of goods or undertakings, or for classes of 
    users of weights and measures, of such weights and measures, in addition to 
    the standard weights or measures, and for such period, not exceeding five 
    years, as may be specified in the notification. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Nothing in 
    sub-section (1) shall be deemed to empower the Central Government to issue 
    any notification in respect of any weight or measure which was not in use in 
    the State of Sikkim immediately before the commencement of this Act. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>85</number> Repeal 
    and savings.—
<section><number>1</number> The Standards of 
    Weights and Measures Act, 1956 (89 of 1956), is hereby repealed. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Without 
    prejudice to the provisions contained in the General Clauses Act, 1897 (10 
    of 1897), with respect to repeals, any notification , rule or order made 
    under the Standards of Weights and Measures Act, 1956 (89 of 1956), shall, 
    if in force, at the commencement of this Act, continue to be in force and 
    have effect as if made under the corresponding provision of this Act. 
  
  
  
  
 
  


</section></article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



THE STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES ACT, 
    1976
 

 
 


THE SCHEDULE
 


(See section 79)
 

 
 
 
 
 


(1) Length:
 


1 inch
 


1 foot
 


1 yard
 


1 mile
 


1 nautical mile (UK)
 
 


 
 


= 0.025 4 metre
 


= 0.304 8 metre
 


= 0.914 4 metre
 


= 1 609.344 metres
 


= 1 853.18 metres

 
 
 


For Survey of India Only 

 
 
 


1 foot
 


(2) Area:
 


1 square inch
 


1 square foot
 


1 square yard
 


1 square mile
 
 


= 0.304 799 6 metre
 


 
 


= 0.000 645 16 square metre
 


= 0.092 903 04 square metre
 


= 0.836 127 36 square metre
 


= 2589 988.110 336 square metres

 
 
 


For Survey of India Only 

 
 
 


1 square foot
 


1 acre
 


 
 


(3) Volume:
 


1 cubic inch
 


1 cubic foot
 


1 cubic yard
 


1 gallon (UK)
 


1 gallon (USA)
 


1 bushel (USA)
 


   (2 150.42 cubic inches)
 


1 barrel (for petroleum)
 


1 acre-foot
 


 
 


(4) Mass: 
 


1 grain
 


1 tola
 


1 seer
 


1 maund
 


1 ounce(troy)
 


1 pound (avoirdupois)
 


1 hundredweight (UK)
 


1 
        hundredweight(USA)
 


1 ton (UK)
 


1 ton (USA)
 


 
 


(5) Temperature:
 


1 degree Fahrenheit (unit)
 


temperature in degrees
 


Fahrenheit (t0
        F)
 


 
 


(6) Force:
 


1 pound-force
 


1 poundal
 


 
 


(7) Pressure:
 


1 barometric inch of mercury
 


1 inch of water
 


 
 


(8) Energy :
 


1 British thermal unit
 


1 foot-pound-force
 


 
 


(9) Power:
 


1 horse-power (UK)
 


1 horse-power (European)
 


1 ton of refrigeration
 
 


= 0.092 903 square metre
 


= 4046.856 1 square metres
 


= 0.404 685 61 hectare
 


 
 


= 0.000 016 387 064 cubic metre
 


= 0.028 316 846 592 cubic metre
 


= 0.764 554 857 984 cubic metre
 


= 0.004 546 087 cubic metre
 


= 0.003 785 411 784 cubic metre
 


 
 


= 0.035 239 070 17 cubic metre
 


= 0.158 987 294 928 cubic metre
 


= 1 233.482 cubic metres
 


 
 


 
 


= 0.000 064 798 91 kilogram
 


= 0.011 663 803 9 kilogram
 


= 0.933 104 304 kilogram
 


= 37.324 172 16 kilograms
 


= 0.031 103 476 8 kilogram
 


= 0.453 592 37 kilogram
 


= 50.802 345 44 kilograms
 


= 45.359 237 
        kilograms
 


= 1 016.046 908 8 kilograms
 


= 907.184 74 kilograms
 


 
 


 
 


= 5/9 kelvin or degree(celsius)
 


= 5/9 (t0 F+459.67) 
        kelvins
 


= 5/9 (t0 F-32) 
        degree celsius)
 


 
 


 
 


= 4.448 221 615 260 5 newtons
 


= 0.138 254 954 376 newton
 


 
 


 
 


= 3 386.388 640 341 pascals
 


= 249.088 91 pascals
 


 
 


 
 


= 1 055.055 852 62 joules
 


= 1.355 817 948 331 400 4 joules
 


 
 


 
 


= 745.699 871 582 270 22 watts
 


= 735.498 75 watts
 


=3516.852 67 watts.



 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>