<act><tid>544981</tid>
<title>THE PARLIAMENTARY PROCEEDINGS (PROTECTION OFPUBLICATION) ACT, <year>1977</year></title>

ACT NO. 15 OF <year>1977</year>
[ 18th. April, <year>1977</year>.]

An Act to protect the publication of reports of proceedings of 
Parliament.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- eighth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-


<pagefootnote><pagenum>1</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Short title, extent and commencement.



<article><tid>1616741</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>370809</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Parliamentary Proceedings (Protection of Publication) Act, 
<year>1977</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1744220</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu 
and Kashmir.

</section>

<section><tid>488091</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 25th day 
of March, <year>1977</year>.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Definition.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>504330</tid>
<number>2</number>Definition. In this Act," newspaper" means any printed 
periodical work containing public news or comments on public news, and 
includes a news agency supplying material for publication in a 
newspaper.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Publication of reports of Parliamentary proceedings privileged.

</article>



<article><tid>983147</tid>
<number> 3</number> Publication of reports of Parliamentary proceedings 
privileged.
<section><tid>1357656</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as otherwise provided in sub- section (2), no  
person shall be liable to any proceedings, civil or criminal, in any 
court in respect of the publication in a newspaper of a substantially 
true report of any proceedings of either House of Parliament, unless 
the publication is proved to have been made with malice.

</section>

<section><tid>1912251</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing in sub- section (1) shall be construed as protecting 
the publication of any matter, the publication of which is not for the 
public good.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Act also to apply to Parliamentary proceedings broadcast by 
wirelesstelegraphy.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>779576</tid>
<number>4</number>Act also to apply to Parliamentary proceedings broadcast by 
wireless telegraphy. This Act shall apply in relation to reports or 
matters broadcast by means of wireless telegraphy as part of any 
programme or service provided by means of a broadcasting station 
situate within the territories to which this Act extends as it applies 
in relation to reports or matters published in a newspaper.

</article>



 </act>