<act><title>


The Tea Act, 1953</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Tea Act, 1953. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends 
    to the whole of India: 
 
Provided that 
    it shall not apply to the State of Jammu and Kashmir except to the extent to 
    which the provisions of this Act relate to the control of the export of tea 
    from, and the cultivation of tea in, India. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It 
    shall come into force on such date1 as 
    the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    appoint. 
 
 
  






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Declaration as to expediency of control by the Union.—It 
    is hereby declared that it is expedient in the public interest that the 
    Union should take under its control the tea industry. 
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Definitions.—In this Act, unless 
    the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “Board” means the Tea Board constituted 
    under section 4;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “broker” means a broker of tea;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “cess” means 
1[the 
    duty of excise] imposed by section 25; 
4[the 
    duty of excise] imposed by section 25;" 
 
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[d]    
    “Commissioner of Customs” means a Commissioner of Customs as specified in 
    clause (b) of section 3 of the Customs Act, 1962 (52 of 1962);] 
5[d] 
    “Commissioner of Customs” means a Commissioner of Customs as specified in 
    clause (b) of section 3 of the Customs Act, 1962 (52 of 1962);]" 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    “dealer” means a dealer in tea;  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    “export” means to take out of India by 
    land, sea or air to any place outside India other than a country or 
    territory notified in this behalf by the Central Government by notification 
    in the Official Gazette;  
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    “export allotment” means the total 
    quantity of tea which may be exported during any one financial year;  
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>    “Fund” means the Tea Fund referred to 
    in section 27;  
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>    “manufacturer” means a manufacturer of 
    tea;  
 </section><section>
<number>j</number>    “member” means a member of the Board;  
 </section><section>
<number>k</number>    “owner”—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    with reference to a tea estate or 
    garden or a sub-division thereof the possession of which has been 
    transferred by lease, mortgage or otherwise, means the transferee so long as 
    his right to possession subsists; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    with reference to a tea estate or a 
    garden or a sub-division for which an agent is employed means the agent if, 
    and in so far as, he has been duly authorised by the owner in that behalf;  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>l</number>    “prescribed” means prescribed by rules 
    made under this Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>m</number>    “standard export figure” means such 
    quantity as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
    Gazette, specify pursuant to any international agreement in this behalf;  
 </section><section>
<number>n</number>    “tea” means the plant Camellia 
    Sinensis (L) O. Kuntze as well as all varieties of the product known 
    commercially as tea made from the leaves of the plant Camellia Sinensis 
    (L) O. Kuntze including green tea;  
 </section><section>
<number>o</number>    “tea seed” includes seeds, roots, 
    stumps, cuttings, buds, and any living portion of the plant Camellia 
    Sinensis (L) O. Kuntze which may be used to propagate that plant.
 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Establishment and constitution of the Tea Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    With effect from such date as the Central Government may, by notification in 
    the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf, there shall be established for 
    the purposes of this Act a Board to be called the Tea Board.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Board 
    shall be a body corporate by the name aforesaid, having perpetual succession 
    and a common seal, with power to acquire, hold and dispose of property, both 
    movable and immovable, and to contract, and shall by the said name sue and 
    be sued.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Board 
    shall consist of a chairman and such number of other members not exceeding 
    forty as the Central Government may think expedient, to be appointed by that 
    Government by notification in the Official Gazette from among persons who 
    are in its opinion capable of representing,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    owners of tea estates and gardens and 
    growers of tea;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    persons employed in tea estates and 
    gardens;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    manufacturers of tea;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    dealers including both exporters and 
    internal traders of tea;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    consumers;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    Parliament;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    the Governments of the principal tea 
    growing States;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    such other persons or class of persons, 
    who, in the opinion of the Central Government, ought to be represented on 
    the Board.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>3A</number> 
    It is hereby declared that the office of member of the Board shall not 
    disqualify its holder for being chosen as, or for being, a member of either 
    House of Parliament.]  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The number 
    of persons to be appointed as members from each of the categories specified 
    in sub-section (3), the term of office of, the procedure to be followed in 
    the discharge of their functions by, and the manner of filling vacancies 
    among, the members of the Board shall be such as may be prescribed.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Any 
    officer of the Central Government when deputed by that Government in this 
    behalf shall have the right to attend meetings of the Board and take part in 
    the proceedings thereof but shall not be entitled to vote.
 
 
  






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Vacancies, etc., not to invalidate acts and proceedings.—No 
    act done or proceeding taken by the Board under this Act shall be questioned 
    on the ground merely of the existence of any vacancy in, or defect in the 
    constitution of, the Board.  
 
 
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Salary 
    and allowances of Chairman.—The 
    Chairman shall be entitled to such salary and allowances and such conditions 
    of service in respect of leave, pension, provident fund and other matters as 
    may from time to time be fixed by the Central Government.  
 
 
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Vice-Chairman.—The Board shall 
    elect from among its members a Vice-Chairman who shall exercise such of the 
    powers and discharge such of the duties of the Chairman as may be prescribed 
    or as may be delegated to him by the Chairman.  
 
 
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Executive and other Committees.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    There shall be an Executive Committee of the Board constituted in the 
    manner, prescribed.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Executive Committee shall exercise such of the powers and perform such of 
    the duties of the Board as may be prescribed, or as the Board may delegate 
    to it.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Subject to 
    such control and restrictions as may be prescribed, the Board may constitute 
    other standing Committees or ad hoc Committees for exercising any 
    power or discharging any duty of the Board or for enquiring into or 
    reporting and advising on any matter which the Board may refer to them.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A Standing 
    Committee shall consist exclusively of members of the Board.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> An ad 
    hoc Committee may include persons who are not members of the Board, but 
    their number shall not exceed one half of its strength.  
 
 
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Secretary and staff.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Central Government shall appoint—  
 <subsection>
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>a</number>    
    a Deputy Chairman to the Board who shall assist the Chairman in the 
    performance of his duties and exercise such of the powers and perform such 
    of the duties as may be prescribed or as may be delegated to him by the 
    Board or by a Committee constituted by the Board under section 8 or by the 
    Chairman;] 2[(a) 
    a Deputy Chairman to the Board who shall assist the Chairman in the 
    performance of his duties and exercise such of the powers and perform such 
    of the duties as may be prescribed or as may be delegated to him by the 
    Board or by a Committee constituted by the Board under section 8 or by the 
    Chairman;]" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>aa</number>]    
    a Secretary to the Board who shall exercise such powers and perform such 
    duties as may be prescribed or as may be delegated to him by the Board or 
    the Chairman. 
1[(aa)] 
    a Secretary to the Board who shall exercise such powers and perform such 
    duties as may be prescribed or as may be delegated to him by the Board or 
    the Chairman." 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    all other officers of the Board 
    drawing 
3[a 
    salary exceeding rupees one thousand seven hundred per month.] 
2[a 
    salary exceeding rupees one thousand seven hundred per month.]" 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to 
    such control and restrictions as may be prescribed, the Board may appoint 
    such other officers and employees as may be necessary for the efficient 
    performance of its functions and pay them such salaries and allowances as it 
    may determine from time to time.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Chairman, <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[Deputy Chairman, Secretary and other employees] of 
    the Board shall not undertake any work unconnected with their duties under 
    this Act except with the permission of the Central Government. 
 
 
  








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Functions of the Board.—
<section><number>1</number> It 
    shall be the duty of the Board to promote, by such measures as it thinks 
    fit, the development under the control of the Central Government of the tea 
    industry.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Without 
    prejudice to the generality of the provisions of sub-section (1), the 
    measures referred to therein may provide for—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    regulating the production and extent of 
    cultivation of tea;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    improving the quality of tea;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    promoting co-operative efforts among 
    growers and manufacturers of tea;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    undertaking, assisting or encouraging 
    scientific, technological and economic research and maintaining or assisting 
    in the maintenance of demonstration farms and manufacturing stations;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    assisting in the control of insects and 
    other pests and diseases affecting tea;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    regulating the sale and export of tea;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    training in tea tasting and fixing 
    grade standards of tea;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    increasing the consumption in India and 
    elsewhere of tea and carrying on propaganda for that purpose;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    registering and licensing of 
    manufacturers, brokers, tea waste dealers and persons engaged in the 
    business of blending tea;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>    improving the marketing of tea in India 
    and elsewhere;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<number>jj</number>    
    subscribing to the share capital of, or entering into any agreement or other 
    arrangement (whether by way of partnership, joint venture or in any other 
    manner) with, anybody corporate for the purpose of promoting the development 
    of tea industry or for promotion and marketing of tea, in India or 
    elsewhere;] 
4[(jj) 
    subscribing to the share capital of, or entering into any agreement or other 
    arrangement (whether by way of partnership, joint venture or in any other 
    manner) with, anybody corporate for the purpose of promoting the development 
    of tea industry or for promotion and marketing of tea, in India or 
    elsewhere;]" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>    collecting statistics from growers, 
    manufacturers, dealers and such other persons as may be prescribed on any 
    matter relating to the tea industry; the publication of statistics so 
    collected or portions thereof or extracts therefrom;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>    securing better working conditions and 
    the provisions and improvement of amenities and incentives for workers;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number>    such other matters as may be 
    prescribed.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The Board 
    shall perform its functions under this section in accordance with and 
    subject to such rules as may be made by the Central Government.
  









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Dissolution of the Board.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that 
    the Board shall be dissolved from such date and for such period as may be 
    specified in the notification.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When the 
    Board is dissolved under the provisions of sub-section (1)—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    all members shall, from the date of 
    dissolution, vacate their offices as such members;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    all powers and duties of the Board 
    shall, during the period of dissolution, be exercised and performed by such 
    person or persons as the Central Government may appoint in this behalf;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    all funds and other property vested in 
    the Board shall, during the period of dissolution, vest in the Central 
    Government; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    as soon as the period of dissolution 
    expires, the Board shall be reconstituted in accordance with the provisions 
    of this Act.  
 
 
  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Method 
    of control of extension of tea cultivation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No one shall plant tea on any land not planted with tea on the date of 
    commencement of this Act unless permission has been granted to him in 
    writing by or on behalf of the Board.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No tea 
    area shall be replaced by planting tea on area not planted with tea unless 
    permission has been granted in writing by or on behalf of the Board.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Nothing in 
    this section shall prohibit the infilling or supplying of vacancies on land 
    planted with tea on the date of commencement of this Act or the replanting 
    of tea upon—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    land planted with tea on the 31st day 
    of March, 1950, from which original bushes have been uprooted, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    land planted with tea on the 31st day 
    of March, 1948, from which the original bushes have been uprooted.  
 
 
  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Limitations to the extension of tea cultivation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions contained in sections 15 and 16, the total area of 
    land in respect of which the permission referred to in section 12 may be 
    granted, shall not exceed such area as may be determined by the Board under 
    the general instructions of the Central Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The total 
    area of land in any State in respect of which such permission may be granted 
    shall be such as may be determined by the Board:  
 
Provided that 
    the Board may vary the total area so determined for any State in order to 
    increase or diminish for another State the area in respect of which such 
    permission may be granted by an amount corresponding to the extent to which 
    the area in the first mentioned State has been diminished or increased.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Board 
    shall publish the total area determined for India as well as the total areas 
    determined for the various States by notification in the Official Gazette of 
    the Central Government as soon as may be after the commencement of this Act 
    and shall in like manner published any subsequent variation of such total 
    areas.  
 
 
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>14</number> Grant 
    of permission to plant tea.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Applications for permission to plant tea on any land not planted with tea on 
    the date of commencement of this Act shall be made to the Board and shall 
    contain a clear statement of all special circumstances justifying the 
    application.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Board 
    may require an applicant to supply such information as it thinks necessary 
    to enable the Board to deal with the application.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Subject to 
    such conditions and restrictions as may be prescribed, the Board may by 
    order grant or refuse the permission applied for, or may in like manner 
    grant it in part only or may call for further information from the 
    applicant.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> No order 
    by the Board under sub-section (3) shall be called in question by any court.  
 
 
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>15</number> Grant 
    of permission to plant tea in special circumstances.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where any land which was on the 31st day of March, 1933, planted with tea 
    (including land planted with tea on the 31st day of March, 1931, from which 
    the original bushes had been uprooted and which had not been replanted with 
    tea on the said 31st day of March, 1933), or where any land planted with tea 
    after the 31st day of March, 1933—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    has since become wholly incapable of 
    carrying tea through circumstances due to war, or through subsidence, flood, 
    erosion, earthquake or other irresistible superhuman cause, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    has since been compulsorily acquired 
    under the provisions of the Land Acquisition Act, 1894 (1 of 1894), or of 
    any other law for the time being in force and no longer carries tea, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    has since been transferred to the 
    Central or a State Government or to local authority and no longer carries 
    tea, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    has since been resumed by the lessor 
    under the terms of any lease and no longer carries tea,  
     
 
wherever of the tea estate in which such land 
    is situated may apply to the Board for permission to plant tea on land not 
    planted with tea.  
 

    Explanation.—Land taken for 
    purposes connected with the prosecution of war on which tea bushes have been 
    allowed to remain for protective purposes though no longer cultivated shall 
    be deemed for the purposes of this section to be incapable of carrying or no 
    longer to carry tea.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Upon such 
    application being made and upon proof to the satisfaction of the Board that 
    the application is entitled to the benefit of sub-section (1) the Board may 
    by order grant permission to plant tea on land not planted with tea:  
 
Provided that 
    the area of land in respect of which such permission is granted shall be 
    within the same or an adjacent district and shall belong to the same or an 
    adjacent tea estate and shall not exceed in extent the area of the land  
    incapable of carrying tea or compulsorily acquired, transferred or resumed, 
    as the case may be.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All areas 
    of land in respect of which permission to plant tea is granted under this 
    section shall be excluded when computing for the purpose of section 13 the 
    total area of land in respect of which the permission referred to in section 
    12 may be granted.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If any 
    land falling within the Explanation to sub-section (1) is 
    subsequently restored to the tea estate from which it was substracted, the 
    owner of the estate shall either uproot the tea planted thereon, or uproot 
    any tea planted by him in pursuance of a permission granted under 
    sub-section (2).  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>16</number> Tea 
    nurseries.—
<section><number>1</number> The owner of a tea 
    estate may establish nurseries on land not previously planted with tea for 
    the growing of plants intended for infilling or supplying vacancies or for 
    replanting land planted with tea within the area of the estate or for any 
    other purpose approved by the Board.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> All areas 
    of land utilised for nurseries in accordance with this section shall be 
    excluded when computing for the purpose of section 13 the total area of land 
    in respect of which the permissions referred to in section 12 may be 
    granted.  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
*<number>16A</number> 
    Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> In this Chapter, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “authorised person” means the person or 
    body of persons authorised, or appointed, by the Central Government under 
    this Act to take over the management of any tea undertaking or tea units;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    “company” means a company within the 
    meaning of section 3 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956);  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    “district average yield” means the 
    average yield or tea in the district in which one or more tea units are 
    located, as published by the Board;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    “notified order” means an order 
    notified in the Official Gazette;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    “tea undertaking” means an undertaking 
    engaged in the production or manufacture, or both, of tea through one or 
    more tea units;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    “tea unit” means a tea estate or 
    garden, including a sub-division thereof, which has a distinct entity for 
    which accounts are kept and has a factory of its own for the production and 
    manufacture of tea. 
 





 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
*<number>16B</number> Power 
    to cause investigation to be made in relation to a tea undertaking or tea 
    unit.—
<section><number>1</number> Where the Central 
    Government is of opinion in respect of a tea undertaking or a tea unit that—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the tea undertaking or, as the case may 
    be, the tea unit, has made losses in three out of five years immediately 
    preceding the year in which such opinion is formed; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the average yield of the tea 
    undertaking, or, as the case may be, the tea units, during three years out 
    of five years immediately preceding the year in which such opinion is 
    formed, has been lower than the district average yield by twenty-five per 
    cent. or more; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the persons owning the tea undertaking, 
    or, as the case may be, the tea unit, have habitually made default in the 
    payment of wages, or provident fund dues of workers and other employees, or 
    rent of the land, or duties of excise, or such other dues as they are under 
    an obligation to pay under any law for the time being in force; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the tea undertaking, or, as the case 
    may be, the tea unit, is being managed in a manner highly detrimental to the 
    tea industry or to public interest,  
 
the Central Government may make, or cause to 
    be made, a full and complete investigation into the affairs of the tea 
    undertaking or, as the case may be, the tea unit, by such person or body of 
    persons as it may appoint for the purpose.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where a 
    company owning a tea undertaking is being wound up by or under the 
    supervision of the Court and the business of such company is not being 
    continued, the Central Government may, if it is of opinion that it is 
    necessary, in the interests of the general public, and, in particular, in 
    the interest of production, supply or distribution of tea, to investigate 
    into the possibility of running or restarting the tea undertaking, make an 
    application to the Court, praying for permission to make, or cause to be 
    made, an investigation into such possibility by such person or body of 
    persons as that Government may appoint for the purpose; and, where such an 
    application is made, the Court shall, notwithstanding anything contained in 
    the Companies Act, 1956  (1 of 1956), or in any other law for the time being 
    in force, grant the permission prayed for.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The person 
    or body of persons appointed to make any investigation under sub-section (1) 
    or, as the case may be, sub-section (2), shall have the same powers as are 
    specified in section 18 of the Industries (Development and Regulation) Act, 
    1951 (65 of 1951).
  







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
*<number>16C</number> Power 
    of Central Government on completion of investigation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If, after making or causing to be made any such investigation as is referred 
    to in sub-section (1) of section 16B, the Central Government is satisfied 
    that action under this section is desirable, it may issue such directions to 
    the tea undertaking or tea unit concerned, as may be appropriate in the 
    circumstances, for all or any of the following purposes, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    regulating the production of tea by the 
    tea undertaking or, as the case may be, tea unit and fixing the standards of 
    production;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    requiring the tea undertaking or, as 
    the case may be, tea unit to take such steps as the Central Government 
    considers necessary to stimulate the production, manufacture or plantation, 
    of tea;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    prohibiting the tea undertaking or, as 
    the case may be, tea unit from resorting to any act or practice which might 
    reduce its production, capacity or economic value;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    controlling the prices, or regulating 
    the distribution, of tea produced or manufactured by the tea undertaking or, 
    as the case may be, tea unit.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where a 
    case relating to any tea undertaking or tea unit is under investigation, the 
    Central Government may issue, at any time, any direction of the nature 
    referred to in sub-section (1) to the tea undertaking or the tea unit 
    concerned and any such direction shall have effect until it is varied or 
    revoked by the Central Government. 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
*<number>16D</number> Power 
    of Central Government to assume management or control of tea undertaking or 
    tea unit in certain cases.—
<section><number>1</number> If 
    the Central Government is of opinion that—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    a tea undertaking or tea unit, to which 
    directions have been issued in pursuance of section 16C, has failed to 
    comply with such directions, or the tea undertaking, or, as the case may be, 
    the tea unit, has made losses in three out of five years immediately 
    preceding the year in which such opinion is formed; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the average yield of the tea 
    undertaking, or, as the case may be, the tea unit, during three years out of 
    five years immediately preceding the year in which such opinion is formed, 
    has been lower than the district average yield by twenty-five per cent. or 
    more; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the persons owning the tea undertaking, 
    or, as the case may be, the tea unit, have habitually made default in the 
    payment of wages, or provident fund dues, of workers and other employees, or 
    rent of the land, or duties of excise, or in the payment of such other dues 
    as are obligatory under any law for the time being in force; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the undertaking, or, as the case may 
    be, the tea unit, is being managed in a manner highly detrimental to the tea 
    industry or to public interest,  
 
the Central Government may, by notified order, 
    authorise any person or body of persons to take over the management of the 
    whole or any part of the tea undertaking or tea unit, as the case may be, or 
    to exercise in respect of the whole or any part of the tea undertaking or, 
    as the case may be, tea unit, such functions of control as may be specified 
    in the order.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Any 
    notified order issued under sub-section (1) shall have effect for such 
    period, not exceeding five years, as may be specified in the order:  
 
Provided 
    that if the Central Government is of opinion that it is expedient in the 
    public interest that any such notified order should continue to have effect 
    after the expiry of the period of five years aforesaid, it may from time to 
    time issue directions for such continuance for such period, not exceeding 
    one year at a time, as may be specified in the direction, so, however, that 
    the total period of such continuance (after the expiry of the said period of 
    five years) does not exceed 

    1[six years]; and 
    where any such direction is issued a copy thereof shall be laid, as soon as 
    may be, before both Houses of Parliament. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any 
    notified order issued under sub-section (1) shall have the same effect as if 
    it were an order made under sub-section (1) of section 18A of the Industries 
    (Development and Regulation) Act, 1951 (65 of 1951), and the provisions of 
    section 18B of that Act shall apply accordingly.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time being in force, 
    no person, who ceases to hold any office by reason of the provisions 
    contained in clause (a), or whose contract of management is terminated by 
    reason of the provisions contained in clause (b), of section 18B of the 
    Industries (Development and Regulation) Act, 1951 (65 of 1951), as 
    applicable to a tea undertaking or tea unit by virtue of the provisions of 
    sub-section (3), shall be entitled to any compensation for the loss of 
    office or for the premature termination of his contract of management:  
 
Provided that 
    nothing contained in this section shall affect the right of any such person 
    to recover from the tea undertaking or the tea unit, as the case may be, 
    monies recoverable otherwise than by way of such compensation.
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
*<number>16E</number> Power 
    to take over tea undertaking or tea unit without investigation under certain 
    circumstances.—
<section><number>1</number> Without 
    prejudice to any other provision of this Act, if, from the documentary or 
    other evidence in its possession, the Central Government is satisfied, in 
    relation to a tea undertaking or tea unit, that— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the persons in charge of such tea 
    undertaking or tea unit have, by reckless investments or 
1[by] 
    creation of incumbrances on the assets of the tea undertaking or tea unit, 
    or by diversion of funds, brought about a situation which is likely to 
    affect the production of tea, manufactured or produced by the tea 
    undertaking or tea unit and that immediate action is necessary to prevent 
    such a situation; or 
2[by] 
    creation of incumbrances on the assets of the tea undertaking or tea unit, 
    or by diversion of funds, brought about a situation which is likely to 
    affect the production of tea, manufactured or produced by the tea 
    undertaking or tea unit and that immediate action is necessary to prevent 
    such a situation; or" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    it has been closed for a period of not 
    less than three months (whether by reason of the voluntary winding up of the 
    company owning the tea undertaking or tea unit or for any other reason) and 
    such closure is prejudicial to the concerned tea undertaking or tea unit and 
    that the financial condition of the company owning the tea undertaking or 
    tea unit and the plant and machinery of such tea undertaking or tea unit are 
    such that it is possible to restart the tea undertaking or tea unit and such 
    restarting is necessary in the interests of the general public,
 
it may, by notified order, authorise any 
    person or body of persons to take over the management of the whole or any 
    part of the tea undertaking or tea unit or to exercise in respect of the 
    whole or any part of the tea undertaking or tea unit such functions of 
    control as may be specified in the order.  
 
<footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this sub-section, “incumbrances” includes any liability 
    which may be recovered or satisfied from the assets of the tea undertaking 
    or, as the case may be, tea unit or the person owning the tea undertaking or 
    tea unit.]  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> On the 
    issue of a notified order under sub-section (1) in respect of a tea 
    undertaking or tea unit,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the provisions of sub-sections (2), (3) 
    and (4) of section 16D, and the provisions of section 16G, shall apply to a 
    notified order made under sub-section (1) as they apply to a notified order 
    made under sub-section (1) of section 16D; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the provisions of sub-sections (3) and 
    (4) of section 18AA of the Industries (Development and Regulation) Act, 1951 
    (65 of 1951), shall apply to the tea undertaking or tea unit, as the case 
    may be, to the same extent as they apply to an industrial undertaking.  
  








 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
*<number>16F</number> 
    Contracts in bad faith, etc., may be cancelled or varied.—Without 
    prejudice to the provisions of section 18B of the Industries (Development 
    and Regulation) Act, 1951 (65 of 1951), as applicable to a tea undertaking 
    or tea unit, as the case may be, the person or body of persons authorised 
    under section 16D, or, as the case may be, section 16E, to take over the 
    management of a tea undertaking or tea unit may, with the previous approval 
    of the Central Government, make an application to any court having 
    jurisdiction in this behalf for the purpose of cancelling or varying any 
    contract or agreement entered into, at any time before the issue of the 
    notified order under section 16D or section 16E, between the tea undertaking 
    or the tea unit and any other person; and the court may, if satisfied after 
    due inquiry that such contract or agreement had been entered into in bad 
    faith or is detrimental to the interests of the tea undertaking or tea unit, 
    make an order cancelling or varying (either unconditionally or subject to 
    such conditions as it may think fit to impose) that contract or agreement, 
    and the contract or agreement shall have effect accordingly. 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
*<number>16G</number> 
    Application of Act 1 of 1956.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the management of a tea undertaking or tea unit owned by a company has 
    been taken over by any person or body of persons authorised by the Central 
    Government under this Act, then, notwithstanding anything contained in the 
    said Act or in the memorandum or articles of association of such company,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    it shall not be lawful for the 
    shareholders of such company or any other person to nominate or appoint any 
    person to be a director of the company;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    no resolution passed in a meeting of 
    the shareholders of such company shall be given effect to unless approved by 
    the Central Government;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    no proceeding for the winding up of 
    such company or for the appointment of receiver in respect thereof shall lie 
    in any court except with the consent of the Central Government.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to 
    the provisions contained in sub-section (1), and to the other provisions 
    contained in this Act, and subject to such other exceptions, restrictions 
    and limitations, if any, as the Central Government may, by notification in 
    the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf, the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 
    1956), shall continue to apply to such company in the same manner as it 
    applied thereto before the issue of the notified order. 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
*<number>16H</number> Power 
    of Central Government to cancel notified order under  section 16D or 
    16E.—If, at any time, it appears 
    to the Central Government on the application of the owner of a tea 
    undertaking or tea unit or otherwise that the purpose of the order made 
    under section 16D or section 16E, has been fulfilled or that for any other 
    reason it is not necessary that the order should remain in force, the 
    Central Government may, by notified order, cancel such order and, on the 
    cancellation of any such order, the management or control, as the case may 
    be, of the tea undertaking or tea unit, as the case may be, shall vest in 
    the owner of that undertaking or unit.
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
*<number>16-I</number> Power 
    of Central Government to authorise, with the permission of the court, 
    persons to take over management or control of tea undertakings or tea units.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If the Central Government is of opinion that there are possibilities of 
    running or restarting a tea undertaking or tea unit in relation to which an 
    investigation has been made under sub-section (2) of section 16B, and that 
    such tea undertaking or tea unit should be run or restarted for maintaining 
    or increasing the production, supply or distribution of tea, that Government 
    may make an application to the Court by which the company owning such tea 
    undertaking or tea unit has been ordered to be wound up, praying for 
    permission to appoint any person or body of persons to take over the 
    management of the tea undertaking or, as the case may be, tea unit, or to 
    exercise in respect of the whole or any part of the tea undertaking or tea 
    unit, such functions of control as may be specified in the application. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where an 
    application is made under sub-section (1),—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the provisions of sub-section (2) 
    of section 18FA of the Industries (Development and Regulation) Act, 1951 (65 
    of 1951) shall apply to the tea undertaking or tea unit, as the case may be, 
    subject to the modification that for the words “twelve years” occurring in 
    the second proviso thereto, the words 
1[six 
    years] shall be substituted; 
1[six 
    years] shall be substituted;" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the provisions of sub-sections (3) to 
    (10) (both inclusive) of section 18FA of the Industries (Development and 
    Regulation) Act, 1951 (65 of 1951) shall apply to the tea undertaking or tea 
    unit referred to in sub-section (1), to the same extent as they apply to an 
    industrial undertaking.
 
 





 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
*<number>16J</number> Power 
    of Central Government to make certain declarations in relation to tea 
    undertakings or tea units.—The 
    Central Government may, if it is satisfied in relation to a tea undertaking, 
    tea unit or any part thereof, the management or control of which has been 
    taken over under section 16D or under section 16E or under section 16-I, 
    that it is necessary so to do in the interests of the general public with a 
    view to preventing fall in the volume of the production of tea, exercise in 
    relation to such tea undertaking or tea unit or part thereof the same powers 
    as are exercisable by it in relation to an industrial undertaking under 
    section 18FB of the Industries (Development and Regulation) Act, 1951 (65 of 
    1951), and the said section and the Third Schedule referred to therein shall 
    apply to a tea undertaking or tea unit accordingly.
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
*<number>16K</number> Power 
    of Central Government to call for report on the affairs and working of a 
    managed tea undertaking or tea unit.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the management or control of a tea undertaking or tea unit, as the 
    case may be, has been taken over under section 16D or under section 16E or 
    under section 16-I, the Central Government may, at any time during the 
    continuance of such management or control, call for a report from the 
    authorised person on the affairs and working of the tea undertaking or tea 
    unit, and in submitting the report the authorised person shall take into 
    account the inventory and list of members and creditors prepared under 
    section 16L. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On receipt 
    of the report submitted by the authorised person, the Central Government may 
    exercise all or any of the powers conferred on it by sections 18FD, 18FE and 
    18FF of the Industries (Development and Regulation) Act, 1951 (65 of 1951), 
    to the same extent and subject to the same conditions, limitations or 
    restrictions as are specified in the said sections, and the provisions of 
    the said sections shall become applicable to a tea undertaking or tea unit, 
    as the case may be.
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
*<number>16L</number> 
    Preparation of an inventory of the assets and liabilities and list of 
    members and creditors of managed tea undertaking or tea unit.—For 
    the purposes of this Act, the authorise person shall, as soon as may be 
    after taking over the management of a tea undertaking or tea unit, prepare a 
    complete inventory of the properties, belongings, liabilities and 
    obligations of such tea undertaking or tea unit, as the case may be, and a 
    list of members and creditors of such tea undertaking or tea unit, in 
    accordance with the provisions of
    section 18FG of the Industries (Development and Regulation) Act, 1951 (65 of 
    1951), and the said section shall apply to a tea undertaking or tea unit 
    accordingly. 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>


    1[<number>16LL</number> Debts 
    incurred and investments made by the authorised person to have priority.—Every 
    debt arising out of any loan or any other financial accommodation obtained 
    by the authorised person for carrying on the management of, or exercising 
    functions of control in relation to, the whole or any part of a tea 
    undertaking or tea unit, the management of which has been taken over or is 
    purported to have been taken over under section 16D or section 16E or 
    section 16-I,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    shall have priority over all other 
    debts, whether secured or unsecured, incurred before the management of such 
    tea undertaking or tea unit was taken over;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    shall be a preferential debt within the 
    meaning of section 530 of the Companies Act, 1956  (1 of 1956),  
     
 
and all such debts; shall rank equally among 
    themselves and be paid in full out of the assets of the tea undertaking or 
    tea unit, unless such assets are insufficient to meet them, in which case 
    they shall be recoverable from the owner of the tea undertaking or tea unit 
    as arrears of land revenue notwithstanding that the period of management or 
    control has ended due to expiry of the period for which it was taken over or 
    due to cancellation of the order under section 16H or in pursuance of the 
    order of any court.]
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
*<number>16M</number> Bar of 
    suits and other proceedings in relation to the tea undertakings or tea 
    units.—No suit or other legal 
    proceedings shall be instituted or continued against a tea undertaking or 
    tea unit in respect of which an order has been made under section 16D or 
    section 16E, except with the previous permission of the Central Government 
    or of any officer authorised by the Government in this behalf. 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
*<number>16N</number> Rules 
    made under Act 65 of 1951 to apply.—Until 
    any rule is made in relation to any matter referred to in this Chapter, the 
    rules made by the Central Government under the Industries (Development and 
    Regulation) Act, 1951, in relation to such matter shall, as far as may be, 
    apply, to the extent they are not repugnant to any provision of this Act or 
    any rule made thereunder and references in such rules to the provisions of 
    that Act shall be construed accordingly.
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>17</number> Control 
    of export of tea and tea seed.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No tea shall be exported unless covered by a licence issued by or on behalf 
    of the Board.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No tea 
    seed shall be exported unless covered by a permit issued by or on behalf of 
    the Central Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No 
    tea or tea seed shall be taken by land, sea or air out of any State to any 
    of the 

    1[***] Portuguese 
    Settlements bounded by India, unless covered by a permit issued by or on 
    behalf of the Board. 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Tea or tea seed for export to be covered by licence or permit.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No consignment of tea or tea seed shall be shipped or waterborne to be 
    shipped for export or shall be exported until the owner has delivered to the
    

    1[Commissioner of 
    Customs] a valid export licence or special export licence or a valid permit 
    issued by or on behalf of the Board or the Central Government, as the case 
    may be, covering the quantity to be shipped. —(1) 
    No consignment of tea or tea seed shall be shipped or waterborne to be 
    shipped for export or shall be exported until the owner has delivered to the
    

    1[Commissioner of 
    Customs] a valid export licence or special export licence or a valid permit 
    issued by or on behalf of the Board or the Central Government, as the case 
    may be, covering the quantity to be shipped." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No 
    consignment of tea or tea seed shall be shipped or waterborne to be shipped 
    for carriage (or shall be taken by land or air) to any of the 

    2[***] Portuguese 
    Settlements bounded by India until the owner has delivered to the 


    1[Commissioner of 
    Customs] a permit issued by or on behalf of the Board covering the quantity 
    to be shipped. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No 
    permit for the passage of any tea or tea seed by land into any of the 


    2[***] Portuguese 
    Settlements bounded by India shall be granted under sub-section (1) of 
    section 5 of the Land Customs Act, 1924 (19 of 1924) unless the application 
    for such permit is accompanied by a permit granted in this behalf by the 
    Board covering the quantity to be passed.
  








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>19</number> Export 
    allotment.—The Central Government 
    shall, after consulting the Board and paying due regard to all interests 
    concerned and to the standard export figure, declare by notification in the 
    Official Gazette, the export allotment for each financial year:  
 
Provided that 
    the Central Government may by subsequent notification at any time during the 
    financial year alter the export allotment and thereupon the export allotment 
    as so altered shall be the export allotment for that year.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>20</number> Export 
    quotas and licences.—
<section><number>1</number> Subject 
    to such conditions as may be prescribed, any tea estate or any sub-division 
    of a tea estate shall have the right to receive under this Act on export 
    quota for each financial year.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The export 
    quota of a tea estate, or a sub-division of a tea estate, that is, the total 
    quantity of tea which may be exported by the owner of a tea estate or a 
    sub-division of a tea estate during the financial year, shall be an amount 
    determined by the Board in accordance with such principles as may be 
    prescribed:  
 
Provided that 
    when an export allotment is altered under the provisions of section 19, the 
    export quota shall be liable to be altered accordingly.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The total 
    export quotas allotted to tea estates and to sub-divisions thereof at any 
    time during any financial year shall not exceed the export allotment for the 
    time being for that year.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>21</number> Right 
    to export licences.—
<section><number>1</number> The owner 
    of a tea estate or a sub-division of a tea estate to which an export quota 
    has been allotted for any financial year shall have the right to obtain at 
    any time export licences during that year to cover the export of tea up to 
    the amount of the unexhausted balance of the quota, that is, up to the 
    amount of the quota less the amount for which the export licences have 
    already been issued against it.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The right 
    of the owner of a tea estate or a sub-division of a tea estate under this 
    section may be transferred subject to such conditions as may be prescribed, 
    and the transferee of any such right may again transfer the whole or any 
    part of his right to the owner of a tea estate, or a sub-division of a tea 
    estate but not to any other person:  
 
Provided that 
    nothing in this sub-section shall operate to restrict the issue of licences 
    for the export of tea expressed to be sold with export rights.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The owner 
    of any tea estate or any sub-division of a tea estate to which an export 
    quota has been allotted or any person to whom he has transferred his rights 
    may at any time before the 21st day of March of the financial year to which 
    the quota relates apply in writing to the Board for an export licence to 
    cover the export of tea up to the amount of the unexhausted balance of the 
    quota.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every 
    licence shall be in duplicate in the prescribed form, shall bear the date of 
    its issue and shall be valid up to the end of the financial year in which it 
    is issued:  
 
Provided that, 
    save as provided in section 22, the Board shall not issue any export licence 
    after the end of the financial year in which the application for licence was 
    made.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>22</number> Special 
    export licences.—
<section><number>1</number> Where tea in 
    respect of which an export licence has been or could have been granted under 
    this Act has not been exported before the end of the financial year in which 
    the licence was or could have been issued, the person to whom the licence 
    was or could have been granted may, before the 14th day of April of the 
    following financial year forward an application to the Board for a special 
    export licence covering the same quantity of tea, and the Board shall, on 
    receipt of the prescribed fee, if any, issue a special export licence 
    accordingly.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A person 
    to whom a special export licence has been issued under sub-section (1) may 
    transfer the special export licence with all the rights conferred thereby to 
    a person or persons nominated by him, but a licence once so transferred 
    shall not be further transferable.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A special 
    export licence shall be in duplicate in the prescribed form, shall bear the 
    date of its issue and shall be valid up to the 31st day of May of the 
    financial year in which it was issued.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    quantity of tea covered by a special export licence shall be accounted for 
    against the export quota of the year in which the original licence was or 
    could have been issued under this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing sub-sections the Board 
    may, with the general or special previous sanction of the Central Government 
    refuse to issue a special export licence or postpone for so long as the 
    Central Government may require the issue of any special export licence.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>23</number> Board 
    to maintain accounts quotas.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Board shall maintain an account of every export quota showing, in 
    addition to such other particulars as the Board may think fit, the licences 
    issued against it and the unexhausted balance.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any owner 
    of a tea estate or a sub-division of a tea estate shall be entitled, on 
    payment of the requisite fee, to a copy of the account relating to his 
    quota, certified in the manner laid down in the by-laws made by the Board.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Limitation of application of Chapter.—Nothing 
    in this Chapter shall apply to tea—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    proved to the satisfaction of the
    1[Commissioner 
    of Customs] to have been imported into India from any part outside India; or 
1[Commissioner 
    of Customs] to have been imported into India from any part outside India; 
    or" 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    shipped as stores on board any 
    vessel or aircraft in such quantity as the 
<footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[Commissioner 
    of Customs] considers reasonable having regard to the number of the crew and 
    passengers and length of the voyage on which the vessel or aircraft is about 
    to depart; or
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    exported by post in packages <footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[not 
    exceeding five kilograms] in weight; or
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    exported with the previous sanction of 
    the Central Government, within the limits prescribed in this behalf, by a 
    Red Cross Society or by any organisation for providing amenities for troops 
    overseas, or  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    taken as part of the personal luggage 
    of a passenger.
  
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>


    1[<number>25</number> Imposition of 
    cess on tea produced in India.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    There shall be levied and collected as a cess for the purposes of this Act a 
    duty of excise on all tea produced in India 

    2[at such rate not 
    exceeding fifty paise per kilogram as the Central Government may, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, fix]:
 


    3[Provided that 
    different rates may be fixed for different varieties or grades of tea having 
    regard to the location of, and the climatic conditions prevailing in, the 
    tea estates or gardens producing such varieties or grades of tea and any 
    other circumstances applicable to such production.]  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The duty 
    of excise levied under sub-section (1) shall be in addition to the duty of 
    excise leviable on tea under the Central Excises and Salt Act, 1944 (1 of 
    1944), or any other law for the time being in force.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    provisions of the Central Excises and Salt Act, 1944 (1 of 1944), and the 
    rules made thereunder, including those relating to refund and exemption from 
    duty, shall, so far as may be, apply in relation to the levy and collection 
    of the duty of excise under this section as they apply in relation to the 
    levy and collection of the duty of excise on tea under the said Act.]  
 
 
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>26</number> Payment 
    of proceeds of cess to the Board.—The 
    proceeds of the cess levied under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 25 shall first 
    be credited to the Consolidated Fund of India, and the Central Government 
    may thereafter, from time to time, pay to the Board from and out of such 
    proceeds such sums of money as it may think fit after deducting the expenses 
    of collection.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[<number>26A</number> 
    Grant and loans by the Central Government to the Board.—The 
    Central Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in 
    this behalf, pay to the Board by way of grants or loans such sums of money 
    as the Central Government may consider necessary.]
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>27</number> 
    Constitution of Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> There 
    shall be formed a Fund to be called the Tea Fund, and there shall be 
    credited thereto—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the proceeds of the cess made over to 
    the Board by the Central Government;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[<number>aa</number>    
    any sum of money including dividend, if any, realised by the Board in 
    carrying out any measure referred to in clause (jj) of sub-section (2) of 
    section 10;] 
2[(aa) 
    any sum of money including dividend, if any, realised by the Board in 
    carrying out any measure referred to in clause (jj) of sub-section (2) of 
    section 10;]" 
 
<footcitenum>20</footcitenum>[<footcitenum>21</footcitenum>[(ab)]    
    any sum of money that may be paid to the Board by way of grants or loans 
    under section 26A;]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    all fees levied and collected in 
    respect of licences, permits and permissions issued under this Act; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    any other fee that may be levied and 
    collected under this Act or the rules made thereunder.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Fund 
    shall be applied towards meeting the expenses of the Board and the cost of 
    the measures referred to in section 10.  
 
 
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>28</number> 
    Borrowing powers of Board.—Subject 
    to such rules as may be made in this behalf, the Board shall have power to 
    borrow on the security of the Fund or any other asset for any purposes for 
    which the Fund may be applied.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<footcitenum>22</footcitenum>[<number>28A</number> 
    Writing off of losses.—Subject to such conditions as may be specified by 
    the Central Government, where the Board is of opinion that any amount due 
    to, or any loss, whether of money or of property, incurred by, the Board is 
    irrecoverable, the Board may, with the previous approval of the Central 
    Government, sanction the writing off finally of the said amount or loss:  
 
Provided that 
    no such approval of the Central Government shall be necessary where such 
    irrecoverable amount or loss does not exceed in any individual case and in 
    the aggregate in any year such amounts as may be prescribed.]  
 
 
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>29</number> 
    Accounts and audit.—
<section><number>1</number> The Board 
    shall cause accounts to be kept of all moneys received and expended by it.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    accounts shall be audited every year by auditors appointed in this behalf by 
    the Central Government and such auditors shall disallow every item, which in 
    their opinion is not authorised by this Act or any rule made or direction 
    issued thereunder.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Board 
    may, within three months from the date of communication to it of the 
    disallowance of any item, as aforesaid appeal against such disallowance to 
    the Central Government whose decision shall be final.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>30</number> Power 
    to control price and distribution of tea or tea waste.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by order notified in the Official Gazette, fix 
    in respect of tea of any description specified therein—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the maximum price or the minimum price 
    or the maximum and minimum prices which may be charged by a grower of tea, 
    manufacturer or dealer, wholesale or retail, whether for the Indian market 
    or for export;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the maximum quantity which may in one 
    transaction be sold to any person.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Any such 
    order may for reasons to be specified therein—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    fix prices for such tea differently in 
    different localities or for different classes of dealers, or for growers of 
    tea or manufacturers;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    instead of specifying the price or 
    prices to be charged, direct that price or prices shall be computed in such 
    manner and by reference to such matters as may be provided by the order.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Central Government may, by general or special order—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    prohibit the disposal of tea or tea 
    waste except in such circumstances and under such conditions as may be 
    specified in the order;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    direct any person growing, 
    manufacturing or holding in stock tea or tea waste to sell the whole or a 
    part of such tea or tea waste so grown or manufactured during any specified 
    period, or to sell the whole or a part of the tea or tea waste so held in 
    stock, to such person or class of persons and in such circumstances as may 
    be specified in the order;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    regulate by licences, permits or 
    otherwise the production, storage, transport or distribution of tea or tea 
    waste.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> Where in 
    pursuance of any order made with reference to clause (b) of sub-section (3), 
    any person sells the whole or a part of any quantity of tea or tea waste, 
    there shall be paid to him as price therefor—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    where the price can be fixed by 
    agreement consistently with the order, if any, relating to the fixation of 
    price issued under sub-section (1), the price so agreed upon;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    where no such agreement can be reached, 
    the price calculated with reference to any such order as is referred to in 
    clause (a);  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    where neither clause (a) nor clause (b) 
    applies, the price calculated at the market rate prevailing in the locality 
    at the date of sale.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> Without 
    prejudice to the generality of the powers conferred by sub-sections (1) and 
    (3), any order made thereunder may provide—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    for requiring persons engaged in the 
    production, supply or distribution of, or trade and commerce in, tea or tea 
    waste to maintain and produce for inspection such books, accounts and 
    records relating to their business and to furnish such information relating 
    thereto as may be specified in the order;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    for such other matters, including in 
    particular the entering and search of premises, vehicles, vessels and 
    aircraft, the seizure by a person authorised to make such search, of tea or 
    tea waste in respect of which such person has reason to believe that a 
    contravention of the order has been, is being or is about to be committed, 
    the grant or issue of licences, permits or other documents and the charging 
    of fees therefor.  
  



 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>31</number> General 
    control over acts and proceedings of the Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    All acts and proceedings of the Board shall be subject to the control of the 
    Central Government which may cancel, suspend or modify as it thinks fit any 
    action taken by the Board.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Board 
    shall carry out such directions as may be issued to it from time to time by 
    the Central Government for the efficient administration of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    records of the Board shall be open to inspection at all reasonable times by 
    any officer authorized in this behalf by the Central Government.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>32</number> Appeal 
    to Central Government.—Any person 
    aggrieved by an order of the Board under section 14, section 15 or section 
    20 may appeal to the Central Government within sixty days from the date 
    thereof and the Central Government may cancel, modify or suspend any such 
    order.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>33</number> 
    Licensing brokers, tea manufacturers, etc.—The 
    Central Government may whenever it thinks it necessary so to do, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette require that no person shall on and 
    from such date as may be specified in the notification engage himself as a 
    broker, manufacturers or dealer in tea waste or engage himself in the 
    business of blending tea except under and in accordance with the provisions 
    of a licence issued by the Board in accordance with the rules made under 
    this Act; and any person who on and after such date so engages himself 
    without obtaining a licence issued by the Board shall be deemed to have 
    contravened the provisions of this section.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>34</number> Power 
    of inspection.—Any person 
    authorised in this behalf by the Central Government or by the Board or any 
    member so authorised by the Chairman in writing or any officer of the Board 
    may enter at all reasonable times any tea estate or any place or premises 
    where tea or tea waste is stored, kept or exposed for sale and may require 
    the production for his inspection of any book, register, record or other 
    paper kept therein and ask for any information relating to the production, 
    storage or keeping for sale of tea or tea waste.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>35</number> Power 
    of Board to call for returns.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Board may serve by registered post a notice upon the owner of any tea 
    estate or any sub-division of a tea estate or upon his manager, requiring 
    him to furnish, within such period as it may specify in the notice, such 
    returns relating to the production, sale and export of tea produced on the 
    estate or to any other matter as it may deem necessary.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the 
    owner of any tea estate or any sub-division of a tea estate or his manager 
    being required under sub-section (1) to furnish any return fails to furnish 
    such return within the period specified in the notice or furnishes a return 
    containing any particular which is false and which he knows to be false or 
    does not believe to be true, the Board may refuse to allot an export quota 
    to that estate or sub-division under section 20, or where an export quota 
    has already been allotted, may cancel the unexhausted balance of that quota 
    and refuse to issue any further export licences against that quota or 
    recognise or give effect to any transfer of quota under section 21.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Board 
    may serve by registered post a notice upon any manufacturer, broker, dealer 
    or dealer in tea waste, requiring him to furnish, within such period as it 
    may specify in the notice, such returns relating to the manufacture, stock, 
    purchase, sale or export of tea or tea waste as it may deem necessary.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>36</number> Penalty 
    for illicit export.—A breach of 
    the provisions of sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> or sub-section (2) of section 18 shall be 
    punishable as if it were an offence under item No. 8 of section 167 of the 
    Sea Customs Act, 1878 (8 of 1878), and the provisions of section 168 and of 
    Chapter XVII of that Act shall apply accordingly.  
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>37</number> Penalty 
    for making false return.—Any 
    person who being required by or under this Act to furnish any return fails 
    to furnish such return or furnishes a return containing any particular which 
    is false and which he knows to be false or does not believe to be true shall 
    be punishable with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>38</number> Penalty 
    for obstructing an officer or member of the Board in the discharge of his 
    duties and for failure to produce books and records.—Any 
    person who—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    obstructs a member authorised by the 
    Chairman in writing or an officer of the Board or a person authorized in 
    this behalf by the Central Government or by the Board in the exercise of any 
    power conferred, or in the discharge of any duty imposed, on him by or under 
    this Act, or  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    having the control or custody of any 
    account book or other record, fails to produce such book or record when 
    required to do so by or under this Act.  
 
shall be punishable with imprisonment which 
    may extend to one year; or with fine which may extend to one thousand 
    rupees, or with both.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>39</number> Penalty 
    for illicit cultivation.—Whoever 
    knowingly plants tea or causes tea to be planted on any land in 
    contravention of section 12 shall be punishable with fine which may extend 
    to one thousand rupees for the first offence, and with fine which may extend 
    to five thousand rupees for any subsequent offence.  
  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>40</number> Removal 
    of tea planted without permission.—Where 
    any person has been convicted of any offence under section 39, the 
    convicting Court may direct that the tea in respect of which the offence was 
    committed shall be removed from the land within a specified time, and in the 
    event of the order not being duly complied with, may cause the tea to be 
    removed and may recover the cost from the person convicted as if it were an 
    arrear of land revenue due on the tea estate on which the offence was 
    committed.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>41</number> Penalty 
    for contravention of order relating to control of price and distribution.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If any person contravenes any order made under sub-section (1) or 
    sub-section (3) of section 30, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for 
    a term which may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to five 
    thousand rupees, or within both, and the property in respect of which the 
    order has been contravened or such part thereof as to the Court may seem 
    fit, shall be forfeited to the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person 
    who attempts to contravene or abets the contravention of, any order under 
    sub-section (1) or sub-section (3) of section 30 shall be deemed to have 
    contravened that order.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>42</number> Other 
    penalties.—Whoever contravenes or 
    attempts to contravene or abets the contravention of the provisions of this 
    Act or of any rules made thereunder other than the provisions, punishment 
    for the contravention whereof has been provided for in sections 36, 37, 38, 
    39 and 41 shall be punishable with imprisonment which may extend to six 
    months, or with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees, or with both, 
    and in the case of a continuing contravention with an additional fine which 
    may extend to five hundred rupees for every day during which such 
    contravention continues after conviction for the first such contravention.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>43</number> 
    Offences by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> If the 
    person committing an offence under this Act, or the rules thereunder is a 
    company, every person, who at the time the contravention was committed was 
    in-charge of, and was responsible to, the company for the conduct of the 
    business of the company, as well as the company, shall be deemed to be 
    guilty of the contravention and shall be liable to be proceeded against and 
    punished accordingly:  
 
Provided that 
    nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to 
    any punishment, if he proves that the offence was committed without his 
    knowledge or that he exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission 
    of such offence.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence 
    under this Act or the rules thereunder has been committed by a company and 
    it is proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or 
    connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of any director 
    or manager, secretary or other officer of the company such director, 
    manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of 
    that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished 
    accordingly.  
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    this section—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “company” means any body corporate and 
    includes a firm or other association of individuals; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    “director” in relation to a firm means 
    a partner in the firm.  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>44</number> 
    Jurisdiction of courts.—No court 
    inferior to that of a Presidency Magistrate or a Magistrate of the First 
    Class shall try any offence punishable under this Act.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>45</number> 
    Previous sanction of Central Government for prosecution.—No 
    prosecution for any offence punishable under this Act shall be instituted 
    except with the previous sanction of the Central Government.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>46</number> 
    Protection of action taken in good faith.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
    No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any person 
    for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this 
    Act or 

    2[any rule or order] 
    made thereunder. —1[(1)] 
    No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any person 
    for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this 
    Act or 

    2[any rule or order] 
    made thereunder." 
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>25</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> 
    No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central Government 
    for any damage caused or likely to be caused by anything which is in good 
    faith done or intended to be done under this Act or any rule or order made 
    thereunder.]
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>47</number> Power 
    to delegate.—The Central 
    Government may, by order notified in the Official Gazette, direct that any 
    power exercisable by it under this Act may also be exercised in such cases 
    and subject to such conditions, if any, as may be specified in the order by 
    such officer or authority as may be specified therein.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>48</number> 
    Suspension of operation of Act.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If the Central Government is satisfied that circumstances have arisen 
    rendering it necessary that certain of the restrictions imposed by this Act 
    should cease to be imposed or if it considers it necessary or expedient so 
    to do in the public interest, the Central Government may, by notification in 
    the Official Gazette, suspend or relax to a specified extent either 
    indefinitely or for such period as may be specified in the notification the 
    operation of all or any of the provisions of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the 
    operation of any provisions of this Act has under sub-section (1) been 
    suspended or relaxed indefinitely, such suspension or relaxation may at any 
    time while this Act remains in force be removed by the Central Government by 
    notification in the Official Gazette.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>49</number> Power 
    of Central Government to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, subject to the condition of previous 
    publication, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the constitution of the Board, the 
    number of persons to be appointed as members from each of the categories 
    specified in sub-section (3) of section 4, the term of office and the other 
    conditions of service of, the procedure to be followed by, and the manner of 
    filling vacancies among, the members of the Board;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the circumstances in which, and the 
    authority by which, members may be removed;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the holding of a minimum number of 
    meetings of the Board every year;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the pay, allowances and other 
    conditions of service of the 
1[Deputy 
    Chairman, Secretary] and other officers appointed by the Central Government; 1[Deputy 
    Chairman, Secretary] and other officers appointed by the Central 
    Government;" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the maintenance of records of all 
    business transacted at meetings of the Board and the submission of copies of 
    such records to the Central Government;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    the conditions subject to which, and 
    the mode in which, contracts may be made by or on behalf of the Board;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    the preparation of budget estimate of 
    the receipt and expenditure of the Board and the authority by which such 
    estimates shall be sanctioned;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    the powers of the Board and the 
    Executive Committee and the Chairman, in regard to the incurring of 
    expenditure; and the  
    reappropriation of estimated savings in any budget head to another such 
    head;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    the conditions subject to which the 
    Board may incur expenditure;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>    the conditions subject to which the 
    Board may borrow;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<footcitenum>27</footcitenum>[<number>ja</number>    
    the amounts for the purposes of the proviso to section 28A;] 
2[(ja) 
    the amounts for the purposes of the proviso to section 28A;]" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>    the form and the manner in which 
    accounts should be kept by the Board;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>    the basis on which the export quota of 
    a tea estate or a sub-division of a tea estate shall be determined;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number>    the conditions subject to which export 
    quota, export licences and special export licences shall be transferable;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>n</number>    the conditions subject to which permits 
    for the planting of tea on land not carrying tea shall be granted;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>o</number>    the collection of any information or 
    statistics in respect of the tea industry and the tea trade;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>p</number>    the fees to be levied in respect of 
    licences, permits and permissions issued under this Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>q</number>    the procedure for the grant or issue of 
    licences, permits and permissions under this Act, the time within which such 
    licences, permits or permissions shall be granted or issued including, in 
    particular, the publication of notices calling for applications and the 
    holding of such inquiry in regard thereto as may be necessary in the 
    circumstances;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>r</number>    the form of application for licences, 
    permits or permissions under this Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>s</number>    the manner in which a broker or a 
    dealer in tea waste or a manufacturer shall be licensed under this Act and 
    the levy of fees in respect of such licence;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>t</number>    the matters which may be taken into 
    account in the granting or issuing of any licence, permit or permission 
    under this Act including in particular the previous consultation with the 
    Central Government by the Board in regard to the grant or issue of any such 
    licences, permits or permissions;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>u</number>    the conditions which may be included in 
    any licences, permits or permissions;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>    the returns to be furnished by owners 
    of tea estates, or sub-divisions thereof, manufacturers, dealers and brokers 
    relating to the production, manufacture, stock, sale and export of tea and 
    tea waste and the form and manner in which such returns are to be furnished;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>w</number>    the fees to be charged for granting 
    certified copies of accounts of quotas;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>x</number>    any other fee that may be necessary for 
    the Board to levy in order to determine or redetermine the basis on which 
    export quota may be fixed;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>y</number>    any other matter which is to be or may 
    be prescribed.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<footcitenum>28</footcitenum>[<number>3</number> 
    Every rule made under this Act shall be laid as soon as may be after it is 
    made before each House of Parliament while it is in session for a total 
    period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or 


    4[in two or more 
    successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
    following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid] both houses 
    agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the 
    rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
    modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
    such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of 
    anything previously done under that rule.]
 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>50</number> Power 
    of Board to make by-laws.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Board may make by-laws consistent with this Act and the rules made 
    thereunder, to provide for—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the dates, times and places of its 
    meetings and of the meetings of the Executive and other Committees and 
    quorum for such meetings, and the procedure there at;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the delegation of powers and 
    duties to the Executive or any other Committee, or to its Chairman, 
    Vice-Chairman, 
1[Deputy 
    Chairman Secretary] or any other of its officers; 
3[Deputy 
    Chairman Secretary] or any other of its officers;" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the travelling allowances of members 
    and of members of Committees;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the appointment, promotion and 
    dismissal of its officers and other employees other than those appointed by 
    the Central Government and the creation and abolition of their posts;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the conditions of service of its 
    officers and other employees other than those appointed by the Central 
    Government, including their pay, leave, leave allowances, pensions, 
    gratuities, compassionate allowances and travelling allowances and the 
    establishment and maintenance of a provident fund for them;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    the maintenance of its accounts;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    the persons by whom, and the manner in 
    which payments, deposits and investments may be made on its behalf;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    the custody of moneys required for its 
    current expenditure and the investment of moneys not so required;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    the preparation of statements showing 
    the sums allotted to Departments of the Central and State Governments and 
    other institutions.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> No by-law 
    shall take effect until it has been confirmed by the Central Government and 
    published in the Official Gazette, and the Central Government, in confirming 
    a by-law may make any change therein which appears to be necessary.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, cancel any 
    by-law which it has confirmed and thereupon the by-law shall cease to have 
    effect.  
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>31</footcitenum>[<number>4</number> 
    Every rule made by this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is 
    made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total 
    period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or 
    more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
    immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both 
    Houses agree in making any modification in the by-law or both Houses agree 
    that the by-law should not be made, the by-law shall thereafter have effect 
    only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, 
    however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice 
    to the validity of anything previously done under that by-law.]
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>51</number> Repeals 
    and savings.—
<section><number>1</number> The Indian Tea 
    Control Act, 1938 (8 of 1938) and the Central Tea Board Act, 1949 (13 of 
    1949) are hereby repealed.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> All moneys 
    and other property and all rights and interests, of whatever kind, owned by, 
    vested in, used, enjoyed or possessed by, or held in trust by or for, the 
    Indian Tea Licensing Committee constituted under the Indian Tea Control Act, 
    1938 (8 of 1938), and the Central Tea Board constituted under the Central 
    Tea Board Act, 1949 (13 of 1949), as well as all liabilities legally 
    subsisting against that Committee or that Board shall pass to the Board with 
    effect from the commencement of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All 
    officers and other employees of the Indian Tea Licensing Committee and the 
    Central Tea Board who hold office as such immediately before the 
    commencement of this Act shall be deemed to have been appointed as officers 
    or other employees of the Board with effect from the commencement of this 
    Act and, notwithstanding anything contained in any contract of service 
    entered into by any such officer or other employee with the Indian Tea 
    Licensing Committee or the Central Tea Board, shall be entitled to such pay 
    and allowances and to such conditions of service in respect of other matters 
    as may be determined by the Board with the approval of the Central 
    Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Any 
    proceedings taken by the Indian Tea Licensing Committee or the Central Tea 
    Board before the commencement of this Act may be continued by the Board 
    after such commencement.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Until 
    action in that behalf is otherwise taken under the corresponding provisions 
    of this Act or the rules made thereunder, all licences, permits and 
    permissions issued or granted, all export quotas allotted and all fees fixed 
    under the provisions of the Indian Tea Control Act, 1938 (8 of 1938), shall, 
    unless inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, be deemed to have been 
    issued, granted, allotted or fixed under the corresponding provisions of 
    this Act and the rules made thereunder.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Any 
    offence punishable under the Indian Tea Control Act, 1938 (8 of 1938), or 
    the Central Tea Board Act, 1949 (13 of 1949), shall be punishable and may be 
    dealt with as if it were an offence punishable under the corresponding 
    provisions of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Any other 
    thing or action done or taken before the commencement of this Act by the 
    Indian Tea Licensing Committee or the Central Tea Board shall so long as it 
    is not inconsistent with any of the provisions of this Act, be as valid and 
    effectual as if it had been done or taken by the Board after the 
    commencement of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> For the 
    removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that the provisions contained in 
    sub-sections (2) to (7) inclusive shall be without prejudice to the general 
    application of section 6 of the General Clauses Act, 1897 (10 of 1897).  
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> If any 
    difficulty arises in giving effect to any of the provisions of this Act, the 
    Central Government may as occasion may arise, by order, do anything which 
    appears to be necessary for the purpose of removing the difficulty.  
 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Subs. by Act 22 of 
    1995, sec. 86, for clause (d) (w.e.f. 26-5-1995).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Ins. by Act 52 of 
    1954, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 25-12-1954).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   Ins. by Act 32 of 
    1977, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 12-8-1977).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   Clause (a) re-lettered as clause (aa) by Act 32 of 1977, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 
    12-8-1977).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>   Subs. by Act 32 of 1977, sec. 2, for “Secretary and other 
    employees” (w.e.f. 12-8-1977).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>   Ins. by Act 68 of 1980, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 27-12-1980).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>   Subs. by Act 38 of 1983, sec. 2, for “two years” (w.r.e.f. 
    7-10-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>   Ins. by Act 68 of 1980, sec. 3 (w.r.e.f. 11-6-1976).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>   Subs. by Act 38 of 1983, sec. 2, for “two years” (w.r.e.f. 
    7-10-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>   Ins. by Act 68 of 1980, sec. 4 (w.r.e.f. 11-6-1976).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>   The words “French or” omitted by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) 
    Order, 1956.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>   Subs. by Act 22 of 1995, sec. 86, for “Customs Collector” (w.e.f. 
    26-5-1995).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>   The words “French or” omitted by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) 
    Order, 1956.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>   Subs. by Act 22 of 1995, sec. 86, for “Customs Collector” (w.e.f. 
    26-5-1995).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>   Subs. by Act 40 of 1960, sec. 8, for “not exceeding ten pounds 
    avoirdupois” (w.e.f. 1-10-1960).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>   Subs. by Act 21 of 1967, sec. 4, for section 25 (w.e.f. 
    13-8-1967).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number>   Subs. by Act 24 of 1986, sec. 2, for “at the rate of four paise 
    per kilogram” (w.e.f. 15-8-1986).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number>   Ins. by Act 22 of 1970, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 23-5-1970).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number>   Ins. by Act 68 of 1980, sec. 5.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number>   Ins. by Act 22 of 1970, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 23-5-1970)</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number>   Clause (aa) re-lettered as clause (ab) by Act 68 of 1980, sec. 5.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number>   Ins. by Act 24 of 1986, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 15-8-1986).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number>   Section 46 renumbered as sub-section (1) thereof by Act 68 of 
    1980, sec. 6.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number>   Subs. by Act 68 of 1980, sec. 6, for “the rules”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number>   Ins. by Act 68 of 1980, sec. 6.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number>   Subs. by Act 32 of 1977, sec. 3, for “Secretary” (w.e.f. 
    12-8-1977).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number>   Ins. by Act 24 of 1986, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 15-8-1986).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>28</number>   Subs. by Act 22 of 1970, sec. 4, for sub-section (3) (w.e.f. 
    23-5-1970).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>29</number>   Subs. by Act 32 of 1977, sec. 3, for certain words (w.e.f. 
    12-8-1977).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>30</number>  Subs. by Act 32 of 1977, sec. 4, for “Secretary” (w.e.f. 12-8-1977).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>31</number>  Ins. by Act 4 of 1986, 
    sec. 2 and Sch. (w.e.f. 15-5-1986).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>