<act><title>


The National Rural Employment Guarantee 
(Central Council) Rules, 20061</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the National Rural Employment Guarantee (Central 
Council) Rules, 2006.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force from the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
       
<number>a</number>  “Act” means the National Rural Employment Guarantee Act, 2005 (42 of 
2005);
 </section><section>
       
<number>b</number>  “Central Council” means the Central Employment Guarantee Council 
constituted under sub-section (1) of section 10;
 </section><section>
       
<number>c</number>  “Chairperson” means the Chairperson of the Central Council;
 </section><section>
       
<number>d</number>  “District Panchayat” means an institution (by whatever name called) of 
self-government constituted under Article 243B of the Constitution, for the 
rural areas at the district levels in accordance with the provisions of Part IX 
of the Constitution;
 </section><section>
       
<number>e</number>  “Executive Committee” means the Executive Committee of the Central 
Council constituted under sub-rule (1) of rule 9;
 </section><section>
        
<number>f</number>  “Member-Secretary” means the Member-Secretary of the Central Council;
 </section><section>
       
<number>g</number>  “section” means a section of the Act;
 </section><section>
       
<number>h</number>  “Scheme” means a scheme notified by a State Government under 
sub-section (1) of section 4;
 </section><section>
        
<number>i</number>  “Technical Secretariat” means the Technical Secretariat of the Central 
Council;
 </section><section>
        
<number>j</number>  words and expressions used but not defined in these rules shall have 
the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act. 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> The Central Council.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to the provisions of sub-rule (2), the Central Council constituted under 
sub-section (1) of section 10 shall consist of the following, namely:—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  Union Minister for Rural Development………Chairperson, ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  (i)  Secretary to the Government of India, Department of Rural 
Development-member-ex officio;
 <subsubsection>
            
<number>ii</number>  a nominee of the Ministry of Women and Child Development not below 
the rank of Joint Secretary to the Government of India..........member;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>iii</number>  a nominee of the Ministry of Agriculture not below the rank of Joint 
Secretary to the Government of India..........member;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           
<number>iv</number>  a nominee of the Ministry of Environment and Forest not below the 
rank of Joint Secretary to the Government of India..........member;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>v</number>  a nominee of the Ministry of Statistics and Programme Implementation 
not below the rank of Joint Secretary to the Government of 
India..........member;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           
<number>vi</number> 

a nominee of the 
Ministry of Panchayat Raj not below the rank of Joint Secretary to the 
Government of India..........member;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           
<number>vii</number>  a nominee of the Ministry of Tribal Affairs not below the rank of 
Joint Secretary to the Government of India..........member;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
          
<number>viii</number>  a nominee of the Ministry of Social Justice and Empowerment not 
below the rank of Joint Secretary to the Government of India..........member;

 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>ix</number>  one representative of Planning Commission not below the rank of 
Advisor in the Planning Commission..........member;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
       
<number>c</number>  six representatives of the department of rural development of the 
State Governments who shall not be below the rank of Secretary to the concerned 
State Government to be nominated by the Central Government..........members;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>d</number>  twelve members to be nominated by the Central Government from 
Panchayati Raj Institutions, organisations of workers and disadvantaged groups, 
of whom four shall be women, and shall include—
 <subsubsection>
             
<number>i</number>  two representatives to be nominated by the Central Government from the 
Scheduled Caste, one representative each from Scheduled Tribes, Other Backward 
Classes and minorities;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>ii</number>  Chairpersons of two District Panchayats nominated by the Central 
Government by rotation for a period of one year at a time;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
       
<number>e</number>  three members representing the States to be nominated by the Central 
Government of whom—
 <subsubsection>
             
<number>i</number>  one shall be an expert in any of the areas of works, such as water 
conservation, land development, afforestation and plantation and rural 
engineering, listed or notified under Schedule I of the Act; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>ii</number>  one shall be an expert in social audit; and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>iii</number>  one shall be an expert on wage employment;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
        
<number>f</number>  Joint Secretary to the Government of India in the Ministry of Rural 
Development in charge of the National Rural Employment Act, 
2005……….Member-Secretary.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Not less than 
one-third of the total number of non-official members of the Central Council 
shall be women.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Terms and conditions 
of appointment of Members.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The members representing the Ministries or Departments of the Government of 
India shall hold their offices as long as they are serving in their respective 
Ministries or Departments or till the concerned Ministry or Department nominates 
any other officer.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The term of office of 
the official members representing the State Governments shall be for a period of 
one year.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The term of office of 
the non-official members nominated under clause (d) of sub-rule (1) of rule 3 
shall be appointed for a period of one year.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A non-official member 
nominated under clause (e) of sub-rule (1) shall be appointed for a period of 
two years or till any other member is appointed in his place takes charge, 
whichever is earlier.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The non-official 
members nominated under clauses (d) and (e) of sub-rule (1) shall be entitled to 
receive travelling allowance and dearness allowance for attending the meetings 
of the Central Council or the Executive Committee, as the case may be, at the 
rates admissible to the Central Government servants of the highest grade.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The non-official 
members shall also be entitled to receive honorarium at the rate of one thousand 
rupees per day for the days of the meeting of the Central Council or its 
Executive Committee or any other official work for which they attend to at the 
headquarters at New Delhi or at any other place on invitation by the Central 
Council.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Resignation, etc. of 
non-official members.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any non-official member may,—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number> by writing under his hand addressed to the Chairperson resign 
his office at any time;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  be removed from his office in case he incurs any disqualification 
mentioned in sub-rule (2).
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Central Government 
may, remove from office a non-official member if he,—
 <subsection>
        
<number>i</number>  has been adjudged as an insolvent; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  has been convicted of an offence which, in the opinion of the Central 
Government, involves moral turpitude; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iii</number>
has become 
physically or mentally incapable of acting as a member; or
 </subsection><subsection>
      
 <number>iv</number>  has acquired such financial or other interest as is likely to affect 
prejudicially his functions as a member; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>v</number>  has so abused his position as to render his continuance in office 
prejudicial to the public interest; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>vi</number>  remains absent for three consecutive meetings of the Central Council 
except for reasons beyond his control or without permission of the Chairperson.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Any vacancy caused in 
the Central Council due to resignation, death, removal or otherwise of a 
non-official member shall be filled from the same category to which such member 
was representing and the person newly nominated shall hold office so long as the 
member whose place he fills would have been entitled to hold office, if the 
vacancy had not occurred.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Meetings of the 
Central Council and its quorum.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Council shall meet at least two times in a year or more frequently 
as it may consider necessary, at such place and at such time, as may be decided 
upon by the Chairperson:
 
Provided that six months 
shall not intervene between two consecutive meetings of the Central Council.
 </section><section>
 <number>2</number> The Chairperson shall 
preside at every meeting of the Central Council at which he is present, and in 
his absence, the Secretary to the Government of India, Department of Rural 
Development shall preside.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Not less than 
one-third of the members shall constitute the quorum for the meetings of the 
Central Council.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Procedure of the 
meetings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Member-Secretary shall give at least fourteen clear days notice for a 
meeting of the Central Council, giving therein the date, time and place of the 
meeting.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the quorum in the 
meeting is not present, the Chairperson may postpone the meeting to another date 
and the Chairperson and the members present at the postponed meeting shall 
constitute the quorum.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every question brought 
before any meeting of the Central Council shall be decided upon by a majority of 
the members present and voting at the meeting before which the matter is brought 
and no member shall be allowed to vote by proxy.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> In the case of an 
equality of votes on any resolution or question, the Chairperson shall have a 
casting or a second vote.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Member-Secretary 
shall, within thirty days of a meeting, circulate the minutes of that meeting 
duly approved by the Chairperson.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Functions of the 
Central Council.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Council shall perform the duties and discharge the functions 
assigned to it under section 11.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Central Council 
may, subject to such control and directions, authorise the Member-Secretary to 
deal with such financial and administrative matters for the day-to-day 
functioning.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Central Council 
shall lay down the systems and procedures for maintenance of its accounts and 
other records.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Member-Secretary 
shall be responsible for the custody and maintenance of the minutes book and 
other records of the Central Council and those of the Executive Committee.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Executive Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Council shall constitute a Committee to be called the Executive 
Committee to assist it to discharge the duties and perform the functions 
assigned to it.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Executive 
Committee constituted under sub-rule (1) shall consist of the following, 
namely:—
 <subsection>
       
<number>i</number>  Secretary to the Government of India, Department of                                       
President;
 
            
Rural Development.                                                                   

 </subsection><subsection>
      
<number>ii</number>  The Financial Advisor, Ministry of Rural Development;                                        
Members;
 
            
representative of the Ministry of Panchayati Raj and 
 
            
two Members who are Secretaries of State Governments 
 
            
nominated by the Chairperson of the Executive 
 <subsubsection>
            
<number>Committee</number>
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
     
<number>iii</number>  Four non-official members of the Central Council                                               
Members. 
 

to be 
nominated by the Chairperson of the Central Council.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The Member-Secretary 
shall be the Member-Secretary of the Executive Committee.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Functions of the 
Executive Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to the general superintendence and directions of the Central Council, 
the Executive Committee shall perform the following duties and functions, 
namely:—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  take steps to give effect to the decisions of the Central Council;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  manage the administrative and financial affairs of the Central 
Council;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>c</number>  sanction expenditure in connection with the affairs of the Central 
Council;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>d</number>  appoint expert groups for technical support and advice to improve the 
quality of implementation of the Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>e</number>  exercise such powers and performs such functions as may be entrusted 
to it by the Central Council.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Executive 
Committee shall meet at least once in three months or more frequently, if 
required by the Central Council.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Technical 
Secretariat.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Council and the Executive Committee shall be assisted by a Technical 
Secretariat, which may be set up by the Central Government in accordance with 
these rules to provide logistic and technical support for the implementation of 
the provisions of the Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Technical 
Secretariat shall be headed by the Member-Secretary and persons of professional 
services enlisted on the basis of procedures, norms and terms decided by the 
Executive Committee.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The persons of 
professional services engaged for the Technical Secretariat shall pertain to 
services in functional areas specified in section 11.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Funds of the 
Central Council.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Council shall meet its expenses in connection with its affairs and 
the functions entrusted to it under the Act or these rules from the annual 
grants released to it by the Ministry of Rural Development out of the National 
Employment Guarantee Fund.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The funds of the 
Central Council shall be operated through a scheduled bank as approved by the 
Central Council.
 
 
 
 
</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>