<act><tid>169719</tid>
<title>THE DELHI METRO RAILWAY (OPERATION AND MAINTENANCE) ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 60 OF <year>2002</year>
[ 17th December, <year>2002</year>.]

An Act to provide for the operation and maintenance and to regulate 
the working of the metro railway in the metropolitan city of Delhi and 
for matters connected therewith and incidental thereto.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1858284</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>223228</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Delhi  
Metro Railway (Operation and Maintenance) Act, <year>2002</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1644882</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the National Capital Territory of Delhi.

</section>

<section><tid>141780</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 29th day of 
October, <year>2002</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1416726</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.-
<section><tid>1372135</tid>
<number>1</number>In this Act, unless the context otherwise  
requires,-

<subsection><tid>722765</tid>
<number>a</number>" Claims Commissioner" means a Claims Commissioner appointed under 
section 48;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>605200</tid>
<number>b</number>" Commissioner" means the Commissioner of the Metro Railway Safety 
appointed under section 7;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>275641</tid>
<number>c</number>" development" with its grammatical variations means the carrying 
out of building, engineering, mining or other operations in, on, over 
or under land or the making of any material change on any building, or 
land, or planting of any tree on land and in ludes redevelopment;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>399528</tid>
<number>d</number>" electric supply- line" shall have the meaning assigned to it under 
clause (f) of section 2 of the Indian Electricity Act, <year>1910</year> (9 of  
  <year>1910</year>);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1481479</tid>
<number>e</number>" fare" means the charge levied for the carriage of passengers;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1247639</tid>
<number>f</number>" Government metro railway" means a metro railway owned by the 
Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1011902</tid>
<number>g</number>" land" includes any right or interest in any land;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>939841</tid>
<number>h</number>" metropolitan city of Delhi" means the area of the National 
Capital Territory of Delhi;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1395824</tid>
<number>i</number>" metro railway" means rail- guided mass rapid transit system having 
dedicated right- of- way, with steel wheel or rubber- tyred wheel 
coaches, but excluding tramways, for carriage of passengers, and 
includes- 
 (A) all land within the boundary marks indicating the limits of the 
land appurtenant to a metro railway, 
 (B) all rails tracks, sidings, yards or branches worked over for the 
purposes of, or in connection with, a metro railway, 
 (C) all stations, offices, ventilation shafts and ducts, warehouses, 
workshops, manufactories, fixed plants and machineries, sheds, depots 
and other works constructed for the purpose of, or in connection with, 
a metro railway;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1421182</tid>
<number>j</number>" metro railway administration" in relation to-

<subsubsection><tid>373369</tid>
<number>i</number>a Government metro railway means the General Manager of that 
railway; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>762344</tid>
<number>ii</number>a non- Government metro railway means the person who is the owner 
or lessee of that metro railway or the person working that metro 
railway under an arrangement with the owner or lessee of that metro 
railway;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1503252</tid>
<number>k</number>" metro railway official" means any person employed by the Central 
Government or by a metro railway administration in connection with the 
services of a metro railway;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>444017</tid>
<number>l</number>" non- Government metro railway" means a metro railway other than a 
Government metro railway;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1516933</tid>
<number>m</number>" notification" means a notification published in the Official 
Gazette;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>329161</tid>
<number>n</number>" pass" means an authority given by the metro railway 
administration or by an officer appointed by that administration in 
this behalf, to a person allowing him to travel as a passenger on the 
metro railway, but does not include a ticket;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>912018</tid>
<number>o</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made by the Central 
Government under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>91598</tid>
<number>p</number>" railway" shall have the meaning assigned to it in clause (31) of 
section 2 of the Railways Act, <year>1989</year> (24 of <year>1989</year>);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>586396</tid>
<number>q</number>" regulations" means the regulations made by the Government metro 
railway administration under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>580731</tid>
<number>r</number>" rolling stock" includes locomotives, engines, carriages (whether  
  powered or not), wagons, trollies and vehicles of all kinds moving or 
intended to move on rails; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>598465</tid>
<number>s</number>" telegraph line" shall have the meaning assigned to it in clause 
 (4) of section 3 of the Indian Telegraph Act, <year>1885</year> (13 of <year>1885</year>).

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1273380</tid>
<number>2</number>All other words and expressions used herein and not defined but 
defined in the Metro Railways (Construction of Works) Act, <year>1978</year> (33 of  
  <year>1978</year>) shall have the meanings, respectively, assigned to them in that 
Act.
CHAP

GOVERNMENT METRO RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION

CHAPTER II

GOVERNMENT METRO RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>154130</tid>
<number> 3</number> Constitution of Government metro railway.-
<section><tid>127474</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may, for the purpose of efficient administration of a 
Government metro railway, in the metropolitan city of Delhi, by 
notification, constitute such railways as it may deem fit.

</section>

<section><tid>730073</tid>
<number>2</number>A Government metro railway administration may, for efficient 
performance of its functions under this Act, appoint such officers and 
other employees as it considers necessary on such terms and conditions 
of service as may be determined by regulation.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>242501</tid>
<number> 4</number> Appointment of General Manager.-
<section><tid>1927050</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government shall,  
by notification, appoint a person to be the General Manager of a 
Government metro railway.

</section>

<section><tid>1382375</tid>
<number>2</number>The general superintendence and control of a Government metro 
railway shall vest in the General Manager.
CHAP

FUNCTIONS AND POWERS OF THE METRO RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION

CHAPTER III

FUNCTIONS AND POWERS OF THE METRO RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1838880</tid>
<number> 5</number> Functions of metro railway administration.- The functions of a 
metro railway administration shall be-
<section><tid>1050059</tid>
<number>a</number>to maintain and operate metro railway, for public carriage of 
passengers, constructed in, upon, across, under or over any land, 
building, street, road or passage in the metropolitan city of Delhi; 
and

</section>

<section><tid>1741811</tid>
<number>b</number>to engage in any such other activities or perform such other 
functions as may be considered necessary for the purpose of the 
operation and maintenance of the metro railway in the metropolitan 
city of Delhi.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>370812</tid>
<number> 6</number> Powers of metro railway administration.-
<section><tid>164077</tid>
<number>1</number>The metro railway  
administration shall have the power to do anything which may be 
necessary or expedient for the purpose of carrying out its functions 
under the Act.

</section>

<section><tid>247201</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing provision, 
such power shall include the power to-

<subsection><tid>1325923</tid>
<number>a</number>acquire, hold and dispose of all kinds of properties owned by it, 
both movable and immovable;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>254677</tid>
<number>b</number>improve, develop or alter any property or asset held by it;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1096362</tid>
<number>c</number>enter temporarily in or upon the lands adjoining the metro railway 
alignment in order to remove obstruction, or prevent imminent danger 
from any source, such as tree, post or structure, which may obstruct 
the movement of the rolling stock, or passeng rs, or the view of the 
signal provided for movement of the rolling stock;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1518904</tid>
<number>d</number>execute any lease or grant any licence in respect of the property 
held by it;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1844332</tid>
<number>e</number>enter into, assign and rescind any contract or obligation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>417196</tid>
<number>f</number>employ an agent or contractor for discharging its functions;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>230006</tid>
<number>g</number>obtain licence from the Central Government to establish and 
maintain telegraph lines;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1352505</tid>
<number>h</number>lay down or place electric supply lines for conveyance and 
transmission of energy and to obtain licence for that purpose; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1911060</tid>
<number>i</number>do all incidental acts as are necessary for discharge of any 
function conferred, or imposed, on it by this Act.
CHAP

COMMISSIONER OF METRO RAILWAY SAFETY

CHAPTER IV

COMMISSIONER OF METRO RAILWAY SAFETY




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>84275</tid>
<number>7</number>Appointment of Commissioner of Metro Railway Safety.- The Central 
Government may appoint one or more Commissioners of Metro Railway 
Safety.


</article>



<article><tid>1583275</tid>
<number> 8</number> Duties of Commissioner.- The Commissioner shall-
<section><tid>460086</tid>
<number>a</number>inspect the metro railway with a view to determine whether it is 
fit to be opened for the public carriage of passengers and report 
thereon to the Central Government as required by or under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>554091</tid>
<number>b</number>make such periodical or other inspections of metro railway, its 
rolling stock used thereon and its other installations as the Central 
Government may direct;

</section>

<section><tid>351604</tid>
<number>c</number>make an inquiry under the provisions of this Act into the cause of 
any accident on the metro railway; and

</section>

<section><tid>854</tid>
<number>d</number>discharge such other duties as are conferred on him by or under 
this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1313842</tid>
<number> 9</number> Powers of Commissioner.- Subject to the control of the Central 
Government, the Commissioner, whenever it is necessary so to do for 
any of the purposes of this Act, may-
<section><tid>107479</tid>
<number>a</number>enter upon and inspect the metro railway or any rolling stock used 
thereon and its other installations;

</section>

<section><tid>1627587</tid>
<number>b</number>by order in writing addressed to the metro railway administration, 
require the attendance before him of metro railway official and to 
require answers or returns to such inquiries as he thinks fit to make 
from such metro railway official or from the m tro railway 
administration; and

</section>

<section><tid>989344</tid>
<number>c</number>require the production of any book, document or material object 
belonging to or in the possession or control of any metro railway 
administration which appears to him to be necessary to inspect.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1442671</tid>
<number>10</number>Commissioner to be public servant.- The Commissioner shall be 
deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of section 21 of the 
Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>1304688</tid>
<number>11</number>Facilities to be provided to Commissioner.- The metro railway 
administration shall provide to the Commissioner all reasonable 
facilities for the discharge of the duties or for the exercise of the 
powers imposed or conferred on him by or under this Act


</article>



<article><tid>1012460</tid>
<number>12</number>Annual report of Commissioner.- The Commissioner shall prepare, in 
such form and in such time, for each financial year, as may be 
prescribed, an annual report giving a full account of his activities 
during the previous financial year and forward copy hereof to the 
Central Government.


</article>



<article><tid>1744688</tid>
<number>13</number>Annual report to be laid before Parliament.- The Central 
Government shall cause the annual report of the Commissioner to be 
laid after its receipt before each House of Parliament.
CHAP

OPENING OF METRO RAILWAY

CHAPTER V

OPENING OF METRO RAILWAY



</article>



<article><tid>1232041</tid>
<number>14</number>Sanction of Central Government to the opening of metro 
railway.- The metro railway in the metropolitan city of Delhi shall not 
be opened for the public carriage of passengers except with the 
previous sanction of the Central Government.


</article>



<article><tid>883845</tid>
<number> 15</number> Formalities to be complied with before giving sanction to the 
opening of metro railway.-
<section><tid>829113</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government shall, before  
giving its sanction to the opening of the metro railway under section 
14, obtain a report from the Commissioner that-

<subsection><tid>1122071</tid>
<number>a</number>he has made a careful inspection of the metro railway and the 
rolling stock that may be used thereon;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>881737</tid>
<number>b</number>the moving and fixed dimensions as laid down by the Central 
Government have not been infringed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>617284</tid>
<number>c</number>the track structure, strength of bridges, standards of signalling 
system, traction system, general structural character of civil works 
and the size of, and maximum gross load upon, the axles of any rolling 
stock, comply with the requirements laid dow by the Central 
Government; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>157057</tid>
<number>d</number>in his opinion, metro railway can be opened for the public 
carriage of passengers without any danger to the public using it.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>204514</tid>
<number>2</number>If the Commissioner is of the opinion that the metro railway 
cannot be opened without any danger to the public using it, he shall, 
in his report, state the grounds therefor, as also the requirements 
which, in his opinion, are to be complied with befo e sanction is 
given by the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1564031</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government, after considering the report of the 
Commissioner, may sanction the opening of the metro railway under 
section 14 as such or subject to such conditions as may be considered 
necessary by it for the safety of the public.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1745604</tid>
<number> 16</number> Sections 14 and 15 to apply to the opening of certain works.- The 
provisions of sections 14 and 15 shall apply to the opening of the 
following works if they form part of, or are directly connected with, 
the metro railway used for the public carriage o passengers and have 
been constructed subsequent to the giving of a report by the 
Commissioner under section 15, namely:-
<section><tid>1214536</tid>
<number>a</number>opening of additional lines of metro railway;

</section>

<section><tid>424954</tid>
<number>b</number>opening of stations and junctions;

</section>

<section><tid>52110</tid>
<number>c</number>re- modelling of yards and re- building of bridges; and

</section>

<section><tid>386015</tid>
<number>d</number>any alteration or reconstruction materially affecting the 
structural character of any work to which the provisions of sections 
 14 and 15 apply or are extended by this section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1250324</tid>
<number> 17</number> Temporary suspension of traffic.- When an accident has occurred on 
the metro railway resulting in a temporary suspension of traffic, and 
either the original tracks and works have been restored to their 
original standard or a temporary diversion has be n laid for the 
purpose of restoring communication, the original tracks and works so 
restored, or the temporary diversion, as the case may be, may, without 
prior inspection by the Commissioner, be opened for the public 
carriage of passengers, subject to t e following conditions, namely:-
<section><tid>1973694</tid>
<number>a</number>the metro railway official in charge of the works undertaken by 
reasons of the accident has certified in writing that the opening of 
the restored tracks and works, or of the temporary diversion will not 
in his opinion be attended with danger to the p blic; and

</section>

<section><tid>1799995</tid>
<number>b</number>a notice of the opening of the tracks and works or the diversion 
shall be sent immediately to the Commissioner.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>776685</tid>
<number> 18</number> Power to close metro railway opened for public carriage of 
passengers.- Where, after the inspection of the metro railway opened 
and used for the public carriage of passengers or any rolling stock 
used thereon, the Commissioner is of the opinion that t e use of the 
metro railway or of any rolling stock will be attended with danger to 
the public using it, the Commissioner shall send a report to the 
Central Government who may thereupon direct that-
<section><tid>1934615</tid>
<number>i</number>the metro railway be closed for the public carriage of passengers; 
or

</section>

<section><tid>211439</tid>
<number>ii</number>the use of the rolling stock be discontinued; or

</section>

<section><tid>1817051</tid>
<number>iii</number>the metro railway or the rolling stock may be used for the 
public carriage of passengers subject to such conditions as it may 
consider necessary for the safety of the public.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>519291</tid>
<number> 19</number> Re- opening of closed metro railway.- When the Central Government 
has, under section 18 directed the closure of the metro railway or the 
discontinuance of the use of any rolling stock-
<section><tid>1271365</tid>
<number>a</number>the metro railway shall not be re- opened for the public carriage 
of passengers until it has been inspected by the Commissioner and its 
re- opening is sanctioned in accordance with the provisions of this 
Chapter; and

</section>

<section><tid>731105</tid>
<number>b</number>the rolling stock shall not be used until it has been inspected by 
the Commissioner and its re- use is sanctioned in accordance with the 
provisions of this Chapter.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1503734</tid>
<number>20</number>Use of rolling stock.- The metro railway administration may use 
such rolling stock as it may consider necessary for operation and 
working of the metro railway:
Provided that before using any rolling stock of a design or type 
different from that already running on any section of the metro 
railway, the previous sanction of the Central Government shall be 
obtained for such use: Provided further that before giving any such 
sanction, the Central Government shall obtain a report from the 
Commissioner that he has made a careful inspection of the rolling 
stock and, in his opinion, such rolling stock can be used.



</article>



<article><tid>338671</tid>
<number>21</number>Delegation of powers.- The Central Government may, by 
notification, direct that any of its powers or functions under this 
Chapter, except power to make rule under section 22, shall, in 
relation to such matters and subject to such conditions, if any, a may 
be specified in the notification, be exercised or discharged also by 
the Commissioner.


</article>



<article><tid>935708</tid>
<number> 22</number> Power to make rules in respect of matters in this Chapter.-
<section><tid>192342</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, by notification, make rules to carry out 
the provisions of this Chapter.

</section>

<section><tid>1288344</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1386447</tid>
<number>a</number>the duties of a metro railway administration and the Commissioner 
in regard to the opening of a metro railway for the public carriage of 
passengers;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>440778</tid>
<number>b</number>the arrangements to be made for and the formalities to be complied 
with before opening a metro railway for the public carriage of 
passengers;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1488199</tid>
<number>c</number>for regulating the mode in which, and the speed at which rolling 
stock used on metro railway is to be moved or propelled; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1811802</tid>
<number>d</number>the cases in which and the extent to which the procedure provided 
in this Chapter may be dispensed with.
CHAP

WORKING OF THE METRO RAILWAY.

CHAPTER VI

WORKING OF THE METRO RAILWAY




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>959496</tid>
<number> 23</number> Exhibition of fare tables at station and supply of tickets.-
<section><tid>271542</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The metro railway administration shall cause to be pasted in a 
conspicuous and accessible place at every station in Hindi and English 
a table of the fare chargeable for travelling from t e station to 
every place for which tickets are issued to passengers.

</section>

<section><tid>401003</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person desirous of travelling on the metro railway shall, upon 
payment of fare, be issued with a ticket by the metro railway 
administration or an agent authorised in this behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>1518504</tid>
<number>3</number>The ticket issued under sub- section (2) shall indicate its value, 
period of validity and such other particulars as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>779079</tid>
<number> 24</number> Exhibition and surrender of pass and ticket.- Every passenger 
shall, on demand by any metro railway official authorised in this 
behalf, present his pass or ticket to such metro railway official for 
examination at the beginning, or during or at the end of the journey 
and surrender such ticket,-
<section><tid>541924</tid>
<number>a</number>at the end of journey if the ticket is for a single journey, or

</section>

<section><tid>1255778</tid>
<number>b</number>if such ticket is issued for a particular amount, on the 
exhaustion of the amount for which the ticket was issued.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>70866</tid>
<number>25</number>Prohibition against traveling without pass or ticket.- No person 
shall enter or remain in any carriage on the metro railway, for the 
purpose of travelling therein as a passenger, unless he has with him a 
proper pass or ticket.


</article>



<article><tid>990234</tid>
<number> 26</number> Carriage of goods.-
<section><tid>62871</tid>
<number>1</number>No person shall, while travelling in the  
metro railway, carry with him any goods other than a small baggage 
containing personal belongings not exceeding such volume and weight as 
may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>404003</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any person travels on the metro railway in contravention of 
the provisions of sub- section (1), he shall, notwithstanding that he 
holds a valid pass or ticket for any travel in such railway, be liable 
to be removed from the train by any metro ra lway official authorised 
by the metro railway administration in this behalf or by any other 
person whom such metro railway official may call to his aid.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1792553</tid>
<number> 27</number> Prohibition against traveling of person suffering from infectious 
or contagious diseases and powers to remove them.-
<section><tid>1824552</tid>
<number>1</number>No person  
suffering from infectious or contagious diseases as may be prescribed, 
shall travel by the metro railway.

</section>

<section><tid>1949092</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person travelling in contravention of any rule made under 
sub- section (1) shall be liable to be removed from the metro railway.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1265388</tid>
<number>28</number>Communication between passengers and metro railway officials in 
charge of trains.- The metro railway administration shall provide and 
maintain in proper order, in any metro train, such efficient means of 
communication between the passengers and the me ro railway official in 
charge of the train as may be approved by the Central Government.


</article>



<article><tid>945509</tid>
<number>29</number>Right of metro railway administration to display commercial 
advertisements on metro railway or on the premises occupied by it.- The 
metro railway administration may use its premises, lands, buildings, 
posts, bridges, structures, vehicles, rolling stoc and other property 
for displaying commercial advertisements and for that purpose may 
erect or construct or fix any hoardings, billboards, show cases, and 
such other things for the display of posters or other publicity 
materials.


</article>



<article><tid>692662</tid>
<number> 30</number> Carriage of dangerous or offensive material.-
<section><tid>1101202</tid>
<number>1</number>No person shall  
take or cause to be taken on the metro railway such dangerous or 
offensive material as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>810027</tid>
<number>2</number>If any metro railway official has reason to believe that any 
person is carrying with him, in a container of any form, or otherwise, 
any dangerous or offensive material, he may cause such container to be 
opened by its carrier for the purposes of ascer aining its contents.

</section>

<section><tid>1693587</tid>
<number>3</number>Any metro railway official may remove from the metro railway any 
person taking with him any dangerous or offensive material.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>967890</tid>
<number>31</number>Power to remove persons from metro railway and its carriages.- Any 
person, entering upon or into any part of the metro railway without 
lawful authority, on being asked to leave the metro railway by any 
the metro railway by such metro railway official or by any other 
person whom such metro railway official may call to his aid. metro 
railway official, does not leave therefrom, may be removed from


</article>



<article><tid>627801</tid>
<number> 32</number> Power to make rules.-
<section><tid>1894679</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification, make rules to carry out the provisions of this Chapter.

</section>

<section><tid>1666574</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such 
rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>429286</tid>
<number>a</number>the particulars of the ticket such as the value, the period of 
validity and other particulars under sub- section (3) of section 23;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1434950</tid>
<number>b</number>the volume and weight of baggage under sub- section (1) of section 
26;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>640490</tid>
<number>c</number>diseases which are infectious or contagious under sub- section (1) 
of section 27;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1143681</tid>
<number>d</number>material which is dangerous or offensive under sub- section (1) of 
section 30; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1267070</tid>
<number>e</number>generally, for regulating the travelling upon, and the use, 
working and management of the metro railway.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>966201</tid>
<number>3</number>Every metro railway administration shall keep at every station on 
its metro railway a copy of all the rules made under this section and 
shall also allow any person to inspect it free of charge.
CHAP

FARE FIXATION

CHAPTER VII

FARE FIXATION




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1631454</tid>
<number> 33</number> Fixation of fare for carriage of passengers.- The metro railway 
administration shall, from time to time, on the recommendations made 
to it by the Fare Fixation Committee constituted under sub- section
<section><tid>435049</tid>
<number>1</number> 
travelling from one station to another of the metro railway: of 
section 34, fix, for the carriage of passeng rs, fare for
Provided that the metro railway administration may fix the fare under 
this section without recommendations of the Fare Fixation Committee on 
the initial opening of the metro railway.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>724502</tid>
<number> 34</number> Constitution of Fare Fixation Committee.-
<section><tid>1058553</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may, from time to time, constitute a Fare Fixation 
Committee for the purpose of recommending fare for the carriage of 
passengers by the metro railway.

</section>

<section><tid>1408739</tid>
<number>2</number>The Fare Fixation Committee shall consist of a Chairperson and two 
other members.

</section>

<section><tid>786463</tid>
<number>3</number>A person shall not be qualified for appointment as the Chairperson 
unless he is or has been a Judge of a High Court.

</section>

<section><tid>767413</tid>
<number>4</number>One member each shall be nominated by the Central Government and 
the Government of the National Capital Territory of Delhi 
respectively:
Provided that a person who is or has been an Additional Secretary to 
the Government of India or holds any equivalent post in the Central 
Government shall be qualified to be nominated by the said Government.


</section>

<section><tid>299905</tid>
<number>5</number>A sitting Judge of a High Court shall be appointed after 
consultation with the Chief Justice of that High Court.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1297772</tid>
<number> 35</number> Other terms and conditions and procedure to be followed.-
<section><tid>1124994</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
other terms and conditions of the Fare Fixation Committee, and the 
procedure to be followed by that committee shall be such as may be 
prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>507106</tid>
<number>2</number>The metro railway administration shall provide to the Fare 
Fixation Committee all reasonable facility for the discharge of its 
duties under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>752131</tid>
<number>36</number>Period for making recommendations.- The Fare Fixation Committee 
shall submit its report along with recommendations to the metro 
railway administration within such period, not exceeding three months, 
as may be specified by order made by the Central Gov rnment.


</article>



<article><tid>1011363</tid>
<number>37</number>Recommendations to be binding on metro railway 
administration.- The recommendations made by the Fare Fixation 
Committee shall be binding on the metro railway administration.
CHAP

ACCIDENTS

CHAPTER VIII

ACCIDENTS



</article>



<article><tid>1316791</tid>
<number> 38</number> Notice of metro railway accident.-
<section><tid>1458959</tid>
<number>1</number>Where, in the course of  
working a metro railway,-

<subsection><tid>1946919</tid>
<number>a</number>any accident attended with loss of any human life, or with 
grievous hurt, as defined in the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>); or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>553193</tid>
<number>b</number>any collision between trains; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>611057</tid>
<number>c</number>the derailment of any train carrying passengers, or of any part of 
such train; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>452875</tid>
<number>d</number>any accident of a description usually attended with loss of human 
life or with such grievous hurt as aforesaid; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1305898</tid>
<number>e</number>any accident of any other description which the Central Government 
may notify in this behalf,
occurs, the metro railway official in charge of the section of the 
metro railway on which the accident occurs, shall, without delay, give 
notice of the accident in such form and containing such particulars as 
may be prescribed to the Deputy Commissioner nd the Deputy 
Commissioner of Police, within whose jurisdiction the accident occurs, 
the officer in charge of the police station within the local limits of 
which the accident occurs and to such other Magistrate or police 
officer as may be appointed in th s behalf by the Central Government.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1721197</tid>
<number>2</number>The metro railway administration, within whose jurisdiction the 
accident occurs, shall, without delay, give notice of the accident to 
the Government of the National Capital Territory of Delhi and the 
Commissioner having jurisdiction over the place of the accident.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>645642</tid>
<number> 39</number> Inquiry by Commissioner.-
<section><tid>29499</tid>
<number>1</number>On the receipt of a notice under  
section 38 of the occurrence of an accident resulting in loss of human 
life or grievous hurt causing total or partial disablement of 
permanent nature to a passenger, the Commissioner shall as soon as may 
be, notify the metro railway administration in whose jurisdiction the 
accident occurred of his intention to hold an inquiry into the causes 
that led to the accident and shall at the same time fix and 
communicate the date, time and place o inquiry:
Provided that it shall be open to the Commissioner to hold an inquiry 
into any other accident which, in his opinion, requires the holding of 
such an inquiry. (2) If for any reason, the Commissioner is not able 
to hold an inquiry as soon as may be after the occurrence of the 
accident, he shall notify the metro railway administration 
accordingly.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1001594</tid>
<number> 40</number> Inquiry by metro railway administration.- Where no inquiry is held 
by the Commissioner under sub- section
<section><tid>960831</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 39 or where the  
Commissioner has informed the metro railway administration under 
sub- section (2) of that section that he is not abl to hold an inquiry, 
the metro railway administration within whose jurisdiction the 
accident occurs, shall cause an inquiry to be made in accordance with 
the prescribed procedure.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>310158</tid>
<number> 41</number> Powers of Commissioner in relation to inquiries.-
<section><tid>592853</tid>
<number>1</number>For the  
purpose of conducting an inquiry under this Chapter into the causes of 
any accident, the Commissioner shall, in addition to the powers 
while trying a suit under the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of  
  <year>1908</year>), in respect of the following matters, namely:- specified in 
section 9, have the powers as are vested n a Civil Court

<subsection><tid>1695556</tid>
<number>a</number>summoning and enforcing the attendance of persons and examining 
them on oath;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>931264</tid>
<number>b</number>requiring the discovery and production of documents;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>744018</tid>
<number>c</number>receiving evidence on affidavits;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>403405</tid>
<number>d</number>requisitioning any public record or copies thereof from any court 
or office; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1987215</tid>
<number>e</number>any other matter which may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>221753</tid>
<number>2</number>The Commissioner while conducting an inquiry under this Chapter 
shall be deemed to be a Civil Court for the purposes of section 195 
and Chapter XXVI of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1767670</tid>
<number> 42</number> Statement made before Commissioner.- No statement made by a person 
in the course of giving evidence in an inquiry before the Commissioner 
shall subject him to, or be used against him, in any civil or criminal 
proceeding, except in a prosecution for gi ing false evidence by such 
person: Provided that the statement is-
<section><tid>1975438</tid>
<number>a</number>made in reply to a question which is required by the Commissioner 
to answer; or

</section>

<section><tid>1130603</tid>
<number>b</number>relevant to the subject matter of the inquiry.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>219531</tid>
<number>43</number>Procedure for conducting inquiry.- The metro railway 
administration or the Commissioner conducting an inquiry under this 
Chapter may send notice of the inquiry to such persons, follow such 
procedure, and prepare the report in such manner as may be pre cribed.


</article>



<article><tid>236546</tid>
<number>44</number>No inquiry, investigation, etc., to be made if the Commission of 
Inquiry is appointed.- Notwithstanding anything contained in the 
foregoing provisions of this Chapter, where a Commission of Inquiry is 
appointed under the Commissions of Inquiry Act, 19 2 (60 of <year>1952</year>), to 
inquire into an accident, any inquiry, investigation or other 
proceeding pending in relation to that accident shall not be proceeded 
with, and all records or other documents relating to such inquiry 
shall be forwarded to such authority as may be specified by the 
Central Government in this behalf.


</article>



<article><tid>365445</tid>
<number>45</number>Inquiry into accident not covered by section 38.- Where any 
accident of the nature not specified in section 38 occurs in the 
course of working the metro railway, the metro railway administration 
within whose jurisdiction the accident occurs, may cause such inquiry 
to be made into the causes of the accident, as may be prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>1280673</tid>
<number>46</number>Returns.- The metro railway administration shall send to the 
Central Government a return of accidents occurring on its railway, 
whether attended with injury to any person or not, in such form and 
manner and at such intervals as may be prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>1355664</tid>
<number> 47</number> Power to make rules in respect of matters in this Chapter.-
<section><tid>48914</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, by notification, make rules to carry out 
the provisions of this Chapter.

</section>

<section><tid>160165</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>352639</tid>
<number>a</number>the forms of notice of accidents to be given under section 38 and 
the particulars of the accident such notices shall contain;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>732541</tid>
<number>b</number>the persons to whom notices in respect of any inquiry under this 
Chapter are to be sent, the procedure to be followed in such inquiry 
and the manner in which a report of such inquiry shall be prepared;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1132826</tid>
<number>c</number>the nature of inquiry to be made by the metro railway 
administration into the causes of an accident under section 40;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1206644</tid>
<number>d</number>for conducting an inquiry under clause (e) of sub- section (1) of 
section 41;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1926603</tid>
<number>e</number>the procedure of conducting inquiry and preparation of the report 
under section 43;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>851914</tid>
<number>f</number>the making of an inquiry into the causes of the accident under 
section 45; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1177719</tid>
<number>g</number>the form and manner of sending a return of accidents by the metro 
railway administration under section 46.
CHAP

CLAIMS COMMISSIONER

CHAPTER IX

CLAIMS COMMISSIONER




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>644960</tid>
<number>48</number>Claims Commissioner.- The Central Government may, by notification, 
appoint a Claims Commissioner for the purpose of adjudicating upon 
claims for compensation in respect of accidents involving the death 
of, or bodily injury to person, or damage to any roperty arising out 
of the working of the metro railway.


</article>



<article><tid>1702524</tid>
<number> 49</number> Qualifications for appointment as Claims Commissioner.- A person 
shall not be qualified for appointment as Claims Commissioner unless 
he-
<section><tid>345601</tid>
<number>a</number>is or has been, or is qualified to be, a Judge of a High Court; 
or

</section>

<section><tid>1123927</tid>
<number>b</number>has been a Member of the Indian Legal Service and has held a post 
in Grade I of that Service; or

</section>

<section><tid>1915105</tid>
<number>c</number>has, for at least three years, held a civil judicial post carrying 
a scale of pay which is not less than that of a Joint Secretary to the 
Government of India.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>503299</tid>
<number>50</number>Term of office.- The Claims Commissioner shall hold office as such 
for a term as may be specified by the Central Government.


</article>



<article><tid>352220</tid>
<number> 51</number> Resignation and removal.-
<section><tid>560862</tid>
<number>1</number>The Claims Commissioner may, by  
notice in writing under his hand addressed to the Central Government, 
resign his office.

</section>

<section><tid>1197513</tid>
<number>2</number>The Claims Commissioner may be removed from his office by an order 
of the Central Government on the ground of proved misbehaviour or 
incapacity after an inquiry in which he had been informed of the 
charges against him and given a reasonable opportuni y of being heard 
in respect of those charges.

</section>

<section><tid>1688708</tid>
<number>3</number>The procedure for the investigation of misbehaviour or incapacity 
of the Claims Commissioner referred to in sub- section (2) be such as 
may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1866861</tid>
<number>52</number>Salary and allowances and other conditions of Claims 
Commissioner.- The salary and allowances payable to, and the other 
terms and conditions of service of, the Claims Commissioner shall be 
such as may be prescribed: Provided that neither the salary and 
allowances nor the other terms and conditions of service of the Claims 
Commissioner shall be varied to his disadvantage after his 
appointment.


</article>



<article><tid>1496648</tid>
<number> 53</number> Procedure and powers of Claims Commissioner.-
<section><tid>498689</tid>
<number>1</number>The Claims  
Commissioner shall have all the powers of a civil court for the 
purpose of taking evidence on oath, enforcing attendance of witnesses 
and compelling the discovery or production of documents nd material 
objects.

</section>

<section><tid>596571</tid>
<number>2</number>The Claims Commissioner shall be deemed to be a civil court for 
all the purposes of section 195 and Chapter XXVI of the Code of 
Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>1339124</tid>
<number>3</number>In enquiring into and determining any claims for payment of 
compensation, the Claims Commissioner may, subject to any rules that 
may be made in this behalf, follow such summary procedure as he may 
deem fit.

</section>

<section><tid>129147</tid>
<number>4</number>Subject to any rules that may be made in this behalf, the Claims 
Commissioner may, for the purpose of determining any claim for 
compensation, choose one or more persons possessing special knowledge 
of any matter relevant to the enquiry, to assist him in holding the 
enquiry.

</section>

<section><tid>1088444</tid>
<number>5</number>The Claims Commissioner shall have powers to pass such interim and 
final order as the circumstance may require, including orders for 
payment of costs.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>183367</tid>
<number> 54</number> Decision of Claims Commissioner.-
<section><tid>92974</tid>
<number>1</number>Any question as to the  
liability of the metro railway administration to pay compensation or 
as to the person to whom such compensation is payable, shall be 
determined by an order of the Claims Commissioner.

</section>

<section><tid>660881</tid>
<number>2</number>Every order made under sub- section (1) shall be final.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1234085</tid>
<number> 55</number> Savings as to certain rights.-
<section><tid>1867755</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything  
contained in any other law for the time being in force, where the 
death of, or bodily injury to, any person gives rise to a claim for 
compensation under this Act and also under any other law n force, the 
person entitled to compensation may claim such compensation only once 
either under this Act or under any other law in force.

</section>

<section><tid>648979</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing in sub- section (1) shall affect the right of any person to 
claim compensation payable under any contract or scheme providing for 
compensation for death or personal injury or for damage to property or 
insura ce. Power to make rules. 56. any sum payable under any 
policy of



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1808336</tid>
<number> 56</number> Power to make rules.-
<section><tid>1309917</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification, make rules to carry out the provisions of this Chapter.

</section>

<section><tid>118218</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for-

<subsection><tid>561847</tid>
<number>i</number>the procedure for investigation of misbehaviour or incapacity of 
the Claims Commissioner under sub- section (3) of section 51;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1833734</tid>
<number>ii</number>the salary and allowances and the other terms and conditions of 
service of the Claims Commissioner under section 52; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>900841</tid>
<number>iii</number>any other purpose incidental to or connected with the objects of 
this Chapter.
CHAP

LIABILITY OF METRO RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION DUE TO ACCIDENTS

CHAPTER X

LIABILITY OF METRO RAILWAY ADMINISTRATION DUE TO ACCIDENTS




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1824901</tid>
<number>57</number>Extent of liability.- The metro railway administration shall, 
notwithstanding anything contained in any other law, be liable to pay 
compensation for loss occasioned by the death of, or bodily injury to 
any person to such extent as may be prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>644723</tid>
<number> 58</number> Application for compensation.- An application for compensation 
arising out of an accident may be made to the Claims Commissioner by,-
<section><tid>966384</tid>
<number>a</number>the person who has sustained the injury or suffered any loss; or

</section>

<section><tid>877688</tid>
<number>b</number>all or any of the dependants of the deceased where death has 
resulted from the accident; or

</section>

<section><tid>384531</tid>
<number>c</number>an agent duly authorised by the person injured or all or any of 
the dependants of the deceased, as the case may be:
Provided that where all the dependants of the deceased have not joined 
in any such application for compensation, the application shall be 
made on behalf of or for the benefit of all the dependants of the 
deceased and the dependants who have not so joined shall be impleaded 
as respondents to the application.

Explanation.- For the purpose of this section, the word" dependant" 
shall have the same meaning as given to it in clause (b) of section 
 123 of the Railways Act, <year>1989</year> (24 of <year>1989</year>).

CHAP

OFFENCES AND PENALTIES

CHAPTER XI

OFFENCES AND PENALTIES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>316791</tid>
<number> 59</number> Drunkenness or nuisance on metro railway.-
<section><tid>1316156</tid>
<number>1</number>If any person, in  
any carriage or upon any part of the metro railway,-

<subsection><tid>174789</tid>
<number>a</number>is in a state of intoxication; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>272881</tid>
<number>b</number>commits any nuisance or vandalism or act of indecency, or uses 
abusive or obscene language; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1203327</tid>
<number>c</number>wilfully or without excuse interferes in any way with the comfort 
of any passenger,
he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to five hundred 
rupees and shall also be liable to forfeiture of the fare which he may 
have paid or any pass or ticket which he may have obtained or 
purchased, or be removed from such carriage or part by ny metro 
railway official authorised by the metro railway administration in 
this behalf.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1497393</tid>
<number>2</number>If any metro railway official is in a state of intoxication while 
on duty, he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to two 
hundred and fifty rupees or, where the improper performance of the 
duty would be likely to endanger the safety of any assenger travelling 
or being upon the metro railway, with imprisonment for a term which 
may extend to two years, or with fine which may extend to five hundred 
rupees, or with both.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1740207</tid>
<number> 60</number> Penalty for taking or causing to take offensive material upon 
metro railway.-
<section><tid>1007437</tid>
<number>1</number>If, in contravention of sub- section (1) of section  
30, a person takes or causes to be taken any offensive material upon 
the metro railway, he shall be punishable with fi e which may extend 
to five hundred rupees.

</section>

<section><tid>1617164</tid>
<number>2</number>In addition to the penalties specified in sub- section (1), a 
person takes or causes to be taken any offensive material upon the 
metro railway shall be responsible also for any loss, injury or damage 
which may be caused by reason of such material havi g been so brought 
upon the metro railway.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>593906</tid>
<number> 61</number> Penalty for taking or causing to take dangerous material upon 
metro railway.-
<section><tid>1759620</tid>
<number>1</number>If, in contravention of sub- section (1) of section  
30, a person takes or causes to be taken any dangerous material upon 
the metro railway, he shall be punishable with im risonment for a term 
which may extend to four years and with fine which may extend to five 
thousand rupees.

</section>

<section><tid>462873</tid>
<number>2</number>In addition to the penalties specified in sub- section (1), a 
person takes or causes to be taken any dangerous material upon the 
metro railway shall be responsible also for any loss, injury or damage 
which may be caused by reason of such material havi g been so brought 
upon the metro railway.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1365947</tid>
<number> 62</number> Prohibition of demonstrations upon metro railway.-
<section><tid>1596986</tid>
<number>1</number>No  
demonstration of any kind whatsoever shall be held on any part of the 
metro railway or other premises thereof and it shall be open to the 
metro railway administration to exclude from such premi es any person 
attending such demonstrations whether or not he is in possession of a 
pass or ticket entitling him to be in the said premises.

</section>

<section><tid>211113</tid>
<number>2</number>No person shall paste or put up any poster or write or draw 
anything or matter in any compartment or carriage of the metro 
railway, or any premises thereof, without any lawful authority and any 
person found engaged in doing any such act may be remove from the 
compartment, carriage or premises by any metro railway official 
authorised by the metro railway administration in this behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>396105</tid>
<number>3</number>Whoever contravenes any of the provisions of sub- section (1) or 
sub- section (2), or on being asked by any metro railway official to 
leave any compartment, carriage or premises refuses to do so, shall be 
punishable with imprisonment for a term which m y extend to six 
months, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with 
both.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1945341</tid>
<number>63</number>Penalty for traveling on roof, etc., of a train.- If any passenger 
travels on the roof of a train or persists in travelling in any part 
of a train not intended for the use of passengers or projects any part 
of his body out of a train after being warne by any metro railway 
official to desist, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a 
term which may extend to one month, or with fine which may extend to 
fifty rupees, or with both, and shall also be liable to be removed 
from the train by any metro r ilway official authorised by the metro 
railway administration in this behalf.


</article>



<article><tid>352183</tid>
<number> 64</number> Penalty for unlawfully entering or remaining upon metro railway 
or walking on metro track.-
<section><tid>80774</tid>
<number>1</number>If a person enters into or upon the  
metro railway without any lawful authority or having entered with 
lawful authority remains there unlawfully and refuses to leave on 
being requested to do so by any metro railway official, he shall be 
punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three 
months, or with fine which may extend to two hundred and fifty rupees, 
or with both.

</section>

<section><tid>864042</tid>
<number>2</number>If any person walks on the metro track without any lawful 
authority, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which 
may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to five 
hundred rupees, or with both.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1383249</tid>
<number> 65</number> Endangering the safety of passengers by metro railway 
official.- If any metro railway official, when on duty endangers the 
safety of any passenger,-
<section><tid>1842707</tid>
<number>a</number>by any rash or negligent act or omission; or

</section>

<section><tid>1925451</tid>
<number>b</number>by disobeying any rule, regulation or order which such official 
was bound by the terms of his employment to obey, and of which he had 
notice, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may 
extend to five years, or with fine which may extend to six thousand 
rupees, or with both.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>656146</tid>
<number>66</number>Abandoning train, etc., without authority.- If any metro railway 
official, when on duty, is entrusted with any responsibility connected 
with the running of a train, or any other rolling stock from one 
station or place to another station or place, and e abandons his duty 
before reaching such station or place, without authority or without 
properly handing over such train or rolling stock to another 
authorised metro railway official, he shall be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend t four years, or with fine 
which may extend to five thousand rupees, or with both.


</article>



<article><tid>453489</tid>
<number>67</number>Obstructing running of train, etc.- If any person obstructs or 
causes to be obstructed or attempts to obstruct any train or rolling 
stock upon the metro railway by squatting, picketing or keeping 
without authority any rolling stock on the metro railwa or tampering 
with any signalling installations or by interfering with the working 
mechanism thereof, or otherwise, he shall be liable to be removed by 
any metro railway official, authorised by the metro railway 
administration in this behalf and shall al o be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to four years, or with fine 
which may extend to five thousand rupees, or with both.


</article>



<article><tid>219141</tid>
<number>68</number>Obstructing metro railway official in his duties.- If any person 
wilfully obstructs or prevents any metro railway official in the 
discharge of his duties, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for 
a term which may extend to one year, or with fine w ich may extend to 
one thousand rupees, or with both.


</article>



<article><tid>1263573</tid>
<number> 69</number> Travelling without proper pass or ticket or beyond authorized 
distance.-
<section><tid>1962185</tid>
<number>1</number>If any passenger- 

<subsection><tid>1144000</tid>
<number>a</number>travels in a train without having a proper pass or ticket with 
him; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1871841</tid>
<number>b</number>being in or having alighted from a train, fails or refuses to 
present for examination or to deliver up his pass or ticket 
immediately on requisition being made therefor under section 24, or 
travels in a train in contravention of the provisions of sec ion 25, 
he shall be liable to pay, on demand of any metro railway official 
appointed by the metro railway administration in this behalf, the 
excess charge mentioned in sub- section (3) in addition to the ordinary 
single fare for the distance which he has ravelled or, where there is 
any doubt as to the station from which he started, the ordinary single 
fare from the station from which the train originally started.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1549819</tid>
<number>2</number>If any passenger travels or attempts to travel in a carriage or by 
a train or travels in or on a carriage beyond the place authorised by 
his pass or ticket, he shall be liable to pay, on demand of any person 
appointed by the metro railway administrat on in this behalf, the 
excess charge mentioned in sub- section (3) in addition to any 
difference between any fare paid by him and the fare payable in 
respect of the journey he has made.

</section>

<section><tid>1597670</tid>
<number>3</number>The excess charge referred to in sub- sections (1) and (2) shall be 
fifty rupees.

</section>

<section><tid>164039</tid>
<number>4</number>If any passenger liable to pay the excess charge and fare 
mentioned in sub- section (1), or the excess charge and any difference 
of fare mentioned in sub- section (2), fails or refuses to pay the same 
on a demand being made therefor, any metro railway fficial authorised 
by the metro railway administration in this behalf may apply to any 
Metropolitan Magistrate for the recovery of the sum payable as if it 
were a fine, and the Magistrate if satisfied that the sum is payable 
shall order it to be so recov red, and may order that the person 
liable for the payment shall in default of payment suffer imprisonment 
for a term which may extend to one month.

</section>

<section><tid>1023377</tid>
<number>5</number>Any sum recovered under sub- section (4) shall, as and when it is 
recovered, be paid to the Consolidated Fund of India.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>191183</tid>
<number>70</number>Needlessly interfering with means of communication in a train.- If 
any passenger or any other person without reasonable and sufficient 
cause, makes use of, or interferes with, any means provided by the 
metro railway administration in a train for commu ication between 
passengers and metro railway official in charge of the train, or 
misuses alarm bell of the train, he shall be punishable with 
imprisonment which may extend to one year, or with fine which may 
extend to one thousand rupees, or with both.


</article>



<article><tid>1753239</tid>
<number>71</number>Altering or defacing or counterfeiting pass or ticket.- If any 
person wilfully breaks the security code of any pass or ticket, or 
defaces or alters or counterfeits or duplicates it or acts in any way 
to cause revenue loss to metro railway, he shall be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months.


</article>



<article><tid>1808571</tid>
<number> 72</number> Defacing public notices.- If any person without lawful authority-
<section><tid>457631</tid>
<number>a</number>in this behalf pulls down or wilfully damages any board or 
documents set up or posted by the order of the metro railway 
administration on the metro railway, or any rolling stock, or

</section>

<section><tid>1859218</tid>
<number>b</number>obliterates or alters any letters or figures upon any such board 
or document or upon any rolling stock,
he shall be punishable with imprisonment which may extend to two 
months or with fine up to two hundred and fifty rupees, or with both.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1596609</tid>
<number>73</number>Any sale of articles on metro railway.- If any person sells or 
exposes for sale, any article whatsoever in any metro railway carriage 
or upon any part of the metro premises not authorised by metro railway 
administration for such purpose, he shall be p nishable with fine 
which may extend to five hundred rupees, and in default of payment of 
fine, he shall be punishable with imprisonment which may extend to six 
months:
Provided that, in the absence of special and adequate reasons to the 
contrary to be mentioned in the judgment of the court, such fine shall 
not be less than one hundred rupees.



</article>



<article><tid>218580</tid>
<number> 74</number> Maliciously wrecking a train or causing sabotage.-
<section><tid>1789752</tid>
<number>1</number>If any  
person-

<subsection><tid>1200785</tid>
<number>a</number>loosens or displaces any rail or any other matter or thing 
belonging to the metro railway; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>881651</tid>
<number>b</number>turns, moves, unlocks or diverts any point or other machinery 
belonging to the metro railway; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>716176</tid>
<number>c</number>does or causes to be done any act of sabotage in relation to the 
metro railway with intent or with knowledge that it is likely to 
endanger safety of any person upon the metro railway,
he shall be punishable with imprisonment for life, or with rigorous 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to ten years:

Provided that, in the absence of special and adequate reasons to the 
contrary to be mentioned in the judgment of the court, where a person 
is punished with rigorous imprisonment, such imprisonment shall not be 
less than-


<subsubsection><tid>69607</tid>
<number>i</number>three years in the case of a first conviction; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>3785</tid>
<number>ii</number>seven years in the case of conviction for the second or 
subsequent offence.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1089927</tid>
<number>2</number>If a person unlawfully does any act of sabotage or any other act 
referred to in sub- section (1) with intent to cause the death of any 
person, or with knowledge that such act is so imminently dangerous 
that it must in all probability cause the death o any person or such 
bodily injury to any person as is likely to cause the death of any 
person, he shall be punishable with death or imprisonment for life.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1164272</tid>
<number>75</number>Penalty for unauthorized sale of tickets.- If any person not being 
a metro railway official, or an agent authorised in this behalf under 
sub- section (2) of section 23 sells or attempts to sell any ticket in 
order to enable any other person to travel t erewith, he shall be 
punishable for a term which may extend to three months, or fine which 
may extend to five hundred rupees, or with both, and shall also 
forfeit the ticket which he sells or attempts to sell.


</article>



<article><tid>373926</tid>
<number>76</number>Maliciously hurting or attempting to hurt persons traveling by 
metro railway.- If any person unlawfully throws or causes to fall or 
strike at, against, into or upon any rolling stock forming part of a 
train, any wood, stone or other matter or thing wi h intent, or with 
knowledge that it is likely to endanger the safety of any person being 
in or upon such rolling stock or in or upon any other rolling stock 
forming part of the same train, he shall be punishable with 
imprisonment for life or with impriso ment for a term which may extend 
to ten years.


</article>



<article><tid>1739562</tid>
<number>77</number>Endangering safety of persons traveling by metro railway by rash 
or negligent act or omission.- If any person in a rash or negligent 
manner does any act, or omits to do what he is legally bound to do, 
and the act or omission is likely to endanger the afety of any person 
travelling or being upon the metro railway, he shall be punishable 
with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or with 
fine, or with both.


</article>



<article><tid>920205</tid>
<number> 78</number> Damage to or destruction of certain metro railway properties.-
<section><tid>1779463</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Whoever, with intent to cause or knowing that he is likely to cause 
damage to or destruction of any of the properties of the metro railway 
referred to in sub- section (2), causes by fir, explosive substance or 
otherwise causes damage to such property, he shall be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to ten years.

</section>

<section><tid>943162</tid>
<number>2</number>The properties of the metro railway referred to in sub- section (1) 
are the metro railway track, tunnels, sub- way, box- structures, station 
buildings and installations, carriage and wagons, rolling stock, 
signalling, telecommunication, air- conditioning and ventilation 
equipments, electrical sub- station, drainage pump, escalators, lifts, 
lighting installations, ticket vending machine, ticket barriers, 
electric traction and block equipments, and such other properties as 
the Central Government may, by not fication, specify.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1101414</tid>
<number> 79</number> Endangering the safety of persons traveling by metro railway by 
willful act or omission.- If any person by unlawful act or by any 
wilful omission or neglect or by tampering with safety devices, 
endangers or causes to be endangered the safety of any pe son 
travelling on or being upon any metro railway, or obstructs or causes 
to be obstructed or attempts to obstruct any rolling stock upon any 
metro railway, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term 
which may extend to seven years:
Provided that, in the absence of special and adequate reasons to the 
contrary to be mentioned in the judgment of the court, such 
imprisonment shall not be less than-

<section><tid>1503130</tid>
<number>i</number>six months in the case of first conviction; and

</section>

<section><tid>951010</tid>
<number>ii</number>two years in the case of conviction for the second or subsequent 
offence.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>336571</tid>
<number>80</number>Penalty for making a false claim for compensation.- If any person 
requiring compensation from the metro railway administration under 
Chapter X makes a claim which is false or which he knows or believes 
to be false or does not believe to be true, he sh ll be punishable 
with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years, or with 
fine, or with both.


</article>



<article><tid>1510502</tid>
<number> 81</number> Offences by companies.-
<section><tid>222146</tid>
<number>1</number>Where an offence under this Act has  
been committed by a company, every person who, at the time the offence 
was committed, was in charge of, and was responsible to, the company, 
for the conduct of the business of the company as well as the company, 
shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be 
proceeded against and punished accordingly:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render any 
such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the offence 
was committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised all due 
diligence to prevent the commission of such offe ce.


</section>

<section><tid>1614771</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where any 
offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is 
proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or 
connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the p rt of, any 
director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such 
director, manager, secretary or other officer shall be deemed to be 
guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and 
punished accordingly.
Explanation.- For the purpose of this section,-


<subsection><tid>347886</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm or other 
association of individuals; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>213654</tid>
<number>b</number>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner in the firm.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1831329</tid>
<number> 82</number> Power of arrest without warrant.-
<section><tid>531351</tid>
<number>1</number>If a person commits any  
offence mentioned in sections 59, 61, 65 to 79, he may be arrested 
without warrant or other written authority by any metro railway 
official or by a police officer not below the rank of a he d constable 
or by any other person whom such metro railway official or police 
officer may call to his aid:
Provided that where a person has been arrested, by any person other 
than the police officer, he shall be made over to a police officer, 
or, in the absence of a police officer, take such person or cause him 
to be taken in custody to the nearest police sta ion.


</section>

<section><tid>923404</tid>
<number>2</number>A person so arrested under sub- section (1) shall be produced 
before the nearest Magistrate, having authority to try him or commit 
him for trial, as early as possible but within a period not exceeding 
twenty- four hours of such arrest exclusive of the ime necessary for 
the journey from the place of arrest to the court of the Magistrate.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1796640</tid>
<number> 83</number> Arrest of person likely to abscond, etc.-
<section><tid>681816</tid>
<number>1</number>If any person  
commits any offence under this Act, other than an offence mentioned in 
section 82 or fails or refuses to pay any excess charge or other sum 
demanded under section 69 and there is reason to be ieve that he may 
abscond, or his name and address are unknown and he refuses on demand 
to give his name and address, or there is reason to believe that name 
and address given by him is incorrect, any metro railway official or 
police officer not below the rank of head constable, or any other 
person whom such metro railway official may call to his aid, may, 
without warrant or written authority, arrest him.

</section>

<section><tid>1712954</tid>
<number>2</number>A person so arrested shall be produced before the nearest 
Magistrate, having authority to try him or commit him for trial, as 
early as possible but within a period not exceeding twenty- four hours, 
arrest to the court of the Magistrate. exclusive of the time 
necessary for the journey from he place of



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1484501</tid>
<number>84</number>Magistrate having jurisdiction under the Act.- Notwithstanding 
anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of  
  <year>1974</year>), no court inferior to that of a Metropolitan Magistrate shall 
try an offence under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>854635</tid>
<number> 85</number> Place of trial.-
<section><tid>753358</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person committing an offence under this  
Act, or any rule or regulation made thereunder, shall be triable for 
such offence in any place in which he may be, or which the Government 
of the National Capital Territory of Delhi may otify in this behalf, 
as well as any other place in which he is liable to be tried under any 
law for the time being in force.

</section>

<section><tid>1630838</tid>
<number>2</number>Every notification under sub- section (1) shall be published by the 
Government of the National Capital Territory of Delhi in the Delhi 
Gazette and a copy thereof shall be exhibited for the information of 
the public in some conspicuous place at such me ro railway stations as 
that Government may direct.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER XII

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>486212</tid>
<number>86</number>Power of Central Government to issue directions.- Without 
prejudice to the foregoing provisions of this Act, the metro railway 
administration in case of the non- Government metro railway shall, in 
the discharge of its duties and functions under this Ac, be bound by 
such directions on questions of policy as the Central Government may 
give in writing to it from time to time: Provided that the metro 
railway administration shall, as far as practicable, be given 
opportunity to express its views before any direction is given under 
this section.


</article>



<article><tid>276451</tid>
<number>87</number>Prohibition to work as non- Government metro railway.- No 
non- Government metro railway shall work without obtaining permission 
from the Central Government.


</article>



<article><tid>558470</tid>
<number>88</number>Protection of action taken in good faith.- No suit, prosecution or 
other legal proceedings shall lie against the Central Government, any 
metro railway administration, a metro railway official or against any 
other person, for anything which is in good aith done or intended to 
be done in pursuance of this Act or any rules, regulations or orders 
made thereunder.


</article>



<article><tid>621490</tid>
<number> 89</number> Restriction on execution against metro railway property.-
<section><tid>416163</tid>
<number>1</number>No  
rolling stock, metro railway tracks, machinery, plant, tools, 
fittings, materials or effects used or provided by a metro railway 
administration for the purpose of traffic on its railway, or its 
stations or workshops, or offices shall be liable to be taken in 
execution of any decree or order of any court or of any local 
authority or person having by law the power to attach or distrain 
property or otherwise to cause the property to be take in execution, 
without the previous sanction of the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1351629</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing in sub- section (1) is to be construed as affecting the 
authority of any court to attach the earnings of the metro railway 
administration in execution of a decree or order.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>915942</tid>
<number>90</number>Officials of metro railway administration to be public 
servants.- All persons in the employment of the metro railway 
administration shall, when acting or purporting to act in pursuance of 
the provisions of this Act, be deemed to be public servants wit in the 
meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>1465398</tid>
<number>91</number>Procedure for delivery to metro railway administration of 
property detained by a metro railway official.- If a metro railway 
official is discharged from service or is suspended, or dies or 
absconds or absents himself, and he or his spouse or widow or ny 
member of his family or his representative, refuses or neglects, after 
notice in writing for that purpose, to deliver up to the metro railway 
administration or to a person appointed by the metro railway 
administration, in this behalf, any station, dwe ling house, office or 
other building with its appurtenances, or any books, papers, keys, 
equipments or other matters, belonging to the metro railway 
administration and in the possession or custody of such metro railway 
official on the occurrence of any s ch event as aforesaid, any 
Metropolitan Magistrate may, on application made by or on behalf of 
the metro railway administration, order any police officer, with 
proper assistance, to enter upon the station, office or other building 
and remove any person f und therein and take possession thereof, or to 
take possession of the books, papers and other matters, and to deliver 
the same to the metro railway administration or to a person appointed 
by the metro railway administration in that behalf.


</article>



<article><tid>574680</tid>
<number> 92</number> Proof of entries in records and documents.-
<section><tid>440160</tid>
<number>1</number>Entries made in  
the records or other documents of the metro railway administration 
shall be admitted in evidence in all proceedings by or against the 
metro railway administration, and all such entries ma be proved either 
by the production of the records or other documents of the metro 
railway administration containing such entries or by the production of 
a copy of the entries certified by the officer having custody of the 
records or other documents unde his signature and stating that it is a 
true copy of the original entries and that such original entries are 
contained in the records or other documents of the metro railway 
administration in his possession.

</section>

<section><tid>658953</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law, a court shall 
presume that the entries in the records of the metro railway 
administration admitted in evidence under sub- section (1) are true, 
unless there is evidence to the contrary.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>855750</tid>
<number> 93</number> Service of notice, etc., on metro railway administration.- Any 
notice or other document required or authorised by this Act to be 
served on a metro railway administration may be served-
<section><tid>953856</tid>
<number>a</number>by leaving it at the office of the metro railway administration; 
or

</section>

<section><tid>562672</tid>
<number>b</number>by registered post to the office address of the metro railway 
administration.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1868393</tid>
<number> 94</number> Service of notice, etc., by metro railway administration.- Any 
notice or other document required or authorised by this Act to be 
served on any person by the metro railway administration may be served 
by-
<section><tid>1393956</tid>
<number>a</number>delivering it to the person; or

</section>

<section><tid>1937418</tid>
<number>b</number>leaving it at the usual or the last known place of abode of the 
person; or

</section>

<section><tid>277791</tid>
<number>c</number>registered post addressed to the person at his usual or the last 
known place of abode.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>558767</tid>
<number>95</number>Presumption where notice is served by registered post.- Where a 
notice or other document is served by registered post, it shall be 
deemed to have been served at the time when the letter containing it 
would be delivered in the ordinary course of post, nd in proving such 
service, it shall be sufficient to prove that the letter containing 
the notice or other document was properly addressed and registered.


</article>



<article><tid>1770482</tid>
<number> 96</number> Representation of metro railway administration.-
<section><tid>776456</tid>
<number>1</number>The metro  
railway administration may, by order in writing, authorise any of its 
official or other person to act for, or represent it, as the case may 
be, in any proceeding before any civil, criminal or other court.

</section>

<section><tid>480683</tid>
<number>2</number>A person authorised under sub- section (1) to conduct prosecution 
on its behalf shall, notwithstanding anything in section 302 of the 
Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>), be entitled to conduct 
such prosecutions without the permission of the agistrate.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1215266</tid>
<number>97</number>Appointment of security staff.- The metro railway administration 
may constitute and maintain security staff for its railway, and the 
powers, duties and functions of such staff shall be such as may be 
prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>998883</tid>
<number> 98</number> Delegation of powers.-
<section><tid>770747</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification, direct that all or any of the powers under this Act or 
rules made thereunder, except sections 22, 32, 47, 56, 99 and 100, 
exercisable by it, shall, in relation to such matters and subject to 
such conditions, if any, as may be specified in the notification, be 
exercisable also by such officer or authority subordinate to the 
Central Government or by such officer of the metro railway 
administration.

</section>

<section><tid>811795</tid>
<number>2</number>The metro railway administration may, by general or special order 
in writing, delegate to any of its official subject to such conditions 
and limitations, if any, as may be specified in the order, such of its 
powers and functions under this Act, excep its power under section 
101.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>323324</tid>
<number> 99</number> Power to remove difficulties.-
<section><tid>457858</tid>
<number>1</number>If any difficulty arises in  
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, 
remove the difficulty:
Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a period 
of two years from the commencement of this Act.


</section>

<section><tid>1772498</tid>
<number>2</number>Every order made under this section shall be laid before each 
House of Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1151226</tid>
<number> 100</number> Power of Central Government to make rules.-
<section><tid>1959528</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may, by notification, make rules for carrying out the 
purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1322012</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>411110</tid>
<number>a</number>the form and time for preparing and sending annual report under 
section 12;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>865770</tid>
<number>b</number>the terms and conditions of the Fare Fixation Committee under 
section 35;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>710613</tid>
<number>c</number>the procedure to be followed by the Fare Fixation Committee under 
section 35;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>470361</tid>
<number>d</number>the extent of compensation payable under section 57;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>429766</tid>
<number>e</number>the powers, duties and functions of the security staff of the 
Government metro railway under section 97; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>170696</tid>
<number>f</number>without prejudice to any power to make rules contained elsewhere 
in this Act, generally to carry out the purposes of this Act.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>438088</tid>
<number>101</number>Power of metro railway administration to make regulations.- The 
Government metro railway administration may, with the previous 
approval of the Central Government, make regulations not inconsistent 
with this Act and the rules made thereunder, to provi e for all 
matters for which provisions are necessary or expedient for the 
purpose of giving effect to the provisions of this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>812365</tid>
<number>102</number>Rules and regulations to be laid before Parliament.- Every rule 
made by the Central Government and every regulation made by a 
Government metro railway administration under this Act shall be laid, 
as soon as may be after it is made, before each House f Parliament, 
while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be 
comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and 
if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session 
or the successive sessions afo esaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or regulation or both Houses agree that the 
rule or regulation should not be made, the rule or regulation shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the c se may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule or regulation.


</article>



<article><tid>1652555</tid>
<number>103</number>Effect of Act inconsistent with other enactments.- The provisions 
of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent 
therewith contained in any enactment other than this Act or in any 
instrument having effect by virtue of any enactme t other than this 
Act.


</article>



<article><tid>299352</tid>
<number>104</number>Application of other Acts.- Save as otherwise provided in this 
Act, the provisions of this Act shall be in addition to and not in 
derogation of the Metro Railways (Construction of Works) Act, <year>1978</year> (33  
  of <year>1978</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>1181567</tid>
<number> 105</number> Repeal and savings.-
<section><tid>210309</tid>
<number>1</number>The Delhi Metro Railway (Operation and   
  Maintenance) Ordinance, <year>2002</year> (Ord. 7 of <year>2002</year>) is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1999873</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken 
under the said Ordinance, shall be deemed to have been done or taken 
under the corresponding provisions of this Act.
----

SUBHASH C. JAIN,

Secy. to the Govt. of India.



</section>

</article>



 </act>