<act><title>


The Competition Commission of India (Salary, 
    Allowances and other Terms and Conditions of Service of Chairperson and 
    other Members) Rules, 20031</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number>  Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Competition Commission of India (Salary, 
    Allowances and other Terms and Conditions of Service of Chairperson and 
    other Members) Rules, 2003.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number>  
    Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number>  In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—   
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “Act” means the Competition Act, 2002 
    (12 of 2003);  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    “Chairperson” means the Chairperson of 
    the Commission appointed under sub-section (1) of section 8 of the Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    “Commission” means the Competition 
    Commission of India established under sub-section (1) of section 7 of the 
    Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    “Member” means a Member of the 
    Commission appointed under sub-section (1) of section 8 of the Act and 
    includes the Chairperson.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> All other 
    words and expressions used in these rules but not defined, shall have the 
    same meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act.  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> Pay­.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of sub-rule (2), the Chairperson and every Member 
    shall be paid a salary of twenty six thousand rupees (fixed) per mensem.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If such 
    person at the time of his appointment as Chairperson or other Member is in 
    receipt of a pension in respect of any previous service under the Government 
    or any local body or authority owned or controlled by the Government, or a 
    High Court, or the Supreme Court, as the case may be, such salary shall be 
    reduced by the amount of pension and pension equivalent of any other form of 
    retirement benefits.  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number>  
    Contributory Provident Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Chairperson and other Members shall be governed by the provisions of the 
    Contributory Provident Fund Rules (India), 1962 and no option to subscribe 
    under the General Provident Fund (Central Services) Rules, 1960 shall be 
    available.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No 
    additional pension and gratuity shall be admissible for service rendered in 
    the Commission.  
  
 
  


</section></article> 

  
 <title>[</title>***] 



 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> Leave.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Chairperson and every other Member shall be entitled to thirty days of 
    Earned Leave for every year of service.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The payment 
    of leave salary during leave shall be governed by rule 40 of the Central 
    Civil Services (Leave) Rules, 1972.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Chairperson and every other Member shall be entitled to encashment of fifty 
    per cent of Earned Leave standing to their credit at any time.  
  
 
  


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number> Official visits abroad.</title>—Official visits abroad by the 
Chairperson or Members shall be undertaken only in accordance with orders issued 
by the Central Government and they shall be entitled to draw such allowances in 
respect of such visits <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[as applicable to officers of the Central 
Government in Apex Grade (rupees eighty thousand-fixed) in the case of 
Chairperson and Grade Pay of rupees twelve thousand in the Pay Band-4 (rupees 
37400-67000) in the case of Members].


</article> 

  
 <article><title> </title><title><number>8</number> Official visits abroad. </title>—Official visits abroad by the Chairperson or Members shall be undertaken only in accordance with orders issued by the Central Government and they shall be entitled to draw such allowances in respect of such visits [as are prescribed for the secretary to the Government of India]. 


2. Subs. by G.S.R 613(E), dated 28th August, 2009, for “as applicable to officers of the Central Government in Apex Grade (rupees eighty thousand-fixed) in the case of Chairperson and Grade Pay of rupees twelve thousand in the Pay Band-4 (rupees 37400-67000) in the case of Members.” (w.e.f. 28-8-2009). Earlier these words were substituted by G.S.R. 136(E), dated 27th February, 2009 (w.e.f. 27-2-2009). 
</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>9</number> Leave Travel Concession. </title>—The Chairperson and other 
Members of the Commission shall be entitled to Leave Travel Concession (LTC) at 
the same rates [as are prescribed for the secretary to the 
Government of India]. 

2. Subs. by G.S.R 613(E), dated 28th August, 2009, for “as 
applicable to officers of the Central Government in Apex Grade (rupees eighty 
thousand-fixed) in the case of Chairperson and Grade Pay of rupees twelve 
thousand in the Pay Band-4 (rupees 37400-67000) in the case of Members.” (w.e.f. 
28-8-2009). Earlier these words were substituted by G.S.R. 136(E), dated 27th 
February, 2009 (w.e.f. 27-2-2009). </article> 

  
 [***]





 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>11</number> Facility 
    for Medical Treatment.—The 
    Chairperson and other Members shall be entitled to medical treatment and 
    hospital facilities as provided in the Central Government Health Scheme 
    (CGHS) to a retired Government servant.  At places where the said Scheme is 
    not in operation, the Chairperson and other Members shall be entitled to the 
    facilities as provided in the Central Service (Medical Attendance) Rules, 
    1944.  
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>12</number> Other 
    Conditions of Service.—Matters 
    relating to the terms and conditions of service of the Chairperson or other 
    Members with respect to which no express provision has been made in these 
    rules, shall be referred by the Commission to the Central Government for its 
    decision, and the decision of the Central Government thereon shall be final. 
  
 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>  Vide  G.S.R. 784(E), dated 6th October, 2003, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 6th October, 
2003.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>  Vide  G.S.R. 784(E), dated 6th October, 2003, published in the Gazette of India, Extra.,</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>  Vide  G.S.R. 784(E), dated 6th October, 2003, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra.,</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>  Vide  G.S.R. 784(E), dated 6th October, 2003, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 6th October, 
2003.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Rule 10 omitted by G.S.R. 136(E), dated 27th February, 2009 
(w.e.f. 27-2-2009 ). Rule 10, before Omission, stood as Under:</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>