<act><tid>1710666</tid>
<title>THE DELHI (DELEGATION OF POWERS) ACT, <year>1964</year></title>

ACT NO. 23 OF <year>1964</year>
[ 16th June, <year>1964</year>]

All Act to provide for the delegation of certain powers vested 
in 
the Administrator of the Union territory of Delhi.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifteenth Year of the 
Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>874942</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>914418</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Delhi  
 (Delegation of Powers) Act, <year>1964</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>652311</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of the Union territory of Delhi.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>967663</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>115020</tid>
<number>a</number>" Administrator" means the Administrator of Delhi 
appointed by the President under article 239 of the 
Constitution;

</section>

<section><tid>627045</tid>
<number>b</number>" Chief Secretary" means the Chief Secretary of the 
Delhi Administration;

</section>

<section><tid>475437</tid>
<number>c</number>" Delhi" means the Union territory of Delhi;

</section>

<section><tid>567129</tid>
<number>d</number>" District Judge" means the District Judge, Delhi, and 
includes an Additional District Judge, Delhi.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>193667</tid>
<number> 3</number> Delegation of powers, etc., vested in Administrator under 
certain laws.
<section><tid>1897377</tid>
<number>1</number>Any power, authority or jurisdiction or any duty  
which the Administrator may exercise or discharge by or under the pro- 
visions of any enactment mentioned in column 1 of the Schedule may be 
exercised or discharged also-

<subsection><tid>1025564</tid>
<number>a</number>by any officer or authority mentioned in relation 
thereto in column 2 of the said Schedule;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1495189</tid>
<number>b</number>by such other officer or authority as may be specified 
in this behalf by the Central Government by notification in 
the Official Gazette.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1383423</tid>
<number>2</number>The Administrator may transfer any appeal or application for 
revision or any other matter pending before him for disposal to an 
officer or other authority competent under sub- section (1) to dispose 
of the same.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>213</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>566436</tid>
<number>3</number>The Administrator may withdraw for disposal by himself any 
appeal or application for revision or any other matter pending before 
an officer or other authority competent under sub- section (1) to 
dispose of the same.


</section>

</article>



 </act>