<act><title>

The 
    Sales Promotion Employees (Conditions of Service) 
    Act, 1976</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title, extent, commencement and application.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Sales Promotion Employees (Conditions of Service) 
    Act, 1976.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends 
    to the whole of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall 
    come into force on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 
    as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    appoint and different dates may be appointed for different States.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> It shall 
    apply in the first instance to every establishment engaged in pharmaceutical 
    industry.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Central 
    Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, apply the 
    provisions of this Act, with effect from such date as may be specified in 
    the notification, to any other establishment engaged in any notified 
    industry.
 
   




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>
“establishment” means an establishment engaged in pharmaceutical 
    industry or in any notified industry;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>
“notified industry” means an industry declared as such under section 
    3;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>
“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act;
 </section><section>

<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>d</number>
     “sales 
    promotion employees” means any person by whatever name called (including an 
    apprentice) employed or engaged in any establishment for hire or reward to 
    do any work relating to promotion of sales or business, or both, but does 
    not include any such person,—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number> who, 
    being employed or engaged in a supervisory capacity, draws wages exceeding 
    sixteen hundred rupees per mensem; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number> who 
    is employed or engaged mainly in a managerial or administrative capacity.
 
Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this clause, the wages per mensem of a person shall be 
    deemed to be the amount equal to thirty times his total wages (whether or 
    not including, or comprising only of, commission) in respect of the 
    continuous period of his service falling within the period of twelve months 
    immediately preceding the date with reference to which the calculation is to 
    be made, divided by the number of days comprising that period of service;]

 </subsection></section><section>
<number>e</number>
all words and expressions used but not defined in this Act and 
    defined in the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 (14 of 1947), shall have the 
    meanings respectively assigned to them in that Act.
 
   




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Power of 
    Central Government to declare certain industries to be notified industries.—The 
    Central Government may, having regard to the nature of any industry (not 
    being pharmaceutical industry), the number of employees employed in such 
    industry to do any work relating to promotion of sales or business or both, 
    the conditions of service of such employees and such other factors which, in 
    the opinion of the Central Government, are relevant, declare such industry 
    to be notified industry for the purposes of this Act.
  


 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Leave.—<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number>] 
    In addition to such holidays, casual leave or other kinds of leave as may be 
    prescribed, every sales promotion employee<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[***] 
    shall be granted, if requested for—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>
earned leave on full wages for not less than one-eleventh of the 
    period spent on duty, 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
leave on medical certificate on one-half of the wages for not less 
    than one-eighteenth of the period of service.
 </subsection></section><section>
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> 
    The maximum limit up to which a sales promotion employee may accumulate 
    earned leave shall be such as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The limit 
    up to which the earned leave may be availed of at a time by a sales 
    promotion employee and the reasons for which such limit may be exceeded 
    shall be such as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A sales 
    promotion employee shall,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>
when he voluntarily relinquishes his post or retires from service, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
when his services are terminated for any reason whatsoever (not being 
    termination as punishment),
 
be entitled to cash compensation, subject to 
    such conditions and restrictions as may be prescribed (including conditions 
    by way of specifying the maximum period for which such cash compensation 
    shall be payable), in respect of the earned leave earned by him and not 
    availed of.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> Where a 
    sales promotion employee dies while in service, his heirs shall be entitled 
    to cash compensation for the earned leave earned by him and not availed of.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The cash 
    compensation which will be payable to a sales promotion employee or, as the 
    case may be, his heirs in respect of any period of earned leave for which he 
    or his heirs, as the case may be, is or are entitled to cash compensation 
    under sub-section (4) or sub-section (5), as the case may be, shall be an 
    amount equal to the wages due to such sales promotion employee for such 
    period.]
  









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Issue of 
    appointment letter.—Every 
    employer in relation to a sales promotion employee shall furnish to such 
    employee a letter of appointment, in such form as may be prescribed,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>
in a case where he holds appointment as such at the commencement of 
    this Act, within three months of such commencement; and
 </section><section>
 <number>b</number>
in any other case, on his appointment as such.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>6</number> Application of certain Acts to sales 
      promotion employees.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
      provisions of the Workmen’s Compensation Act, 1923 (8 of 1923), as in 
      force for the time being, shall apply to, or in relation to, sales 
      promotion employees as they apply to, or in relation to, workmen within 
      the meaning of that Act.
 </section><section>[<number>2</number> The provisions of the 
      Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 (14 of 1947), as in force for the time 
      being, shall apply to, or in relation to, sales promotion employees as 
      they apply to, or in relation to, workmen within the meaning of that Act 
      and for the purposes of any proceeding under that Act in relation to an 
      industrial dispute, a sales promotion employee shall be deemed to include 
      a sales promotion employee who has been dismissed, discharged or 
      retrenched in connection with, or as a consequence of, that dispute or 
      whose dismissal, discharge or retrenchment had led to that 
dispute.]
 </section><section><number>3</number> The provisions of the Minimum Wages Act, 
      1948 (11 of 1948), as in force for the time being, shall apply to, or in 
      relation to, sales promotion employees as they apply to, or in relation 
      to, employees within the meaning of that Act.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The provisions of the Maternity Benefit Act, 
      1961(53 of 1961), as in force for the time being, shall apply to, or in 
      relation to, sales promotion employees, being women, as they apply to, or 
      in relation to, women employed, whether directly or through any agency, 
      for wages in any establishment within the meaning of that Act.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The provisions of the Payment of Bonus Act, 
      1965(21 of 1965), as in force for the time being, shall apply to, or in 
      relation to, sales promotion employees as they apply to, or in relation 
      to, employees within the meaning of that Act.
 </section><section><number>6</number> The provisions of the Payment of Gratuity 
      Act, 1972 (39 of 1972), as in force for the time being, shall apply to, or 
      in relation to, sales promotion employees as they apply to, or in relation 
      to, employees within the meaning of that Act.
 </section><section><footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<number>7</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in the 
      foregoing sub-sections,—
 <subsection><number>a</number> in the application of any Act 
      referred to in any of the said sub-sections to sales promotion employees, 
      the wages of a sales promotion employee for the purposes of such Act, 
      shall be deemed to be his wages as computed in accordance with the 
      provisions of this Act;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> where an Act 
      referred to in any of the said sub-sections provides for a ceiling limit 
      as to wages so as to exclude from the purview of the application of such 
      Act persons whose wages exceed such ceiling limit, such Act shall not 
      apply to any sales promotion employee whose wages as computed in 
      accordance with the provisions of this Act exceed such ceiling limit.]
  















 
</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Maintenance of registers.—Every 
    employer in relation to an establishment shall keep and maintain such 
    registers and other documents and in such manner as may be prescribed.
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Inspectors.—
<section><number>1</number> The State 
    Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint such 
    persons as it thinks fit to be Inspectors for the purposes of this Act and 
    may define the local limits within which they shall exercise their 
    functions.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any 
    Inspector appointed under sub-section (l) may, for the purpose of 
    ascertaining whether any of the provisions of this Act have been complied 
    with in respect of an establishment,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>
require an employer to furnish such information as he may consider 
    necessary;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
at any reasonable time enter the establishment or any premises 
    connected therewith and require any one found in charge thereof to produce 
    before him for examination any registers and other documents relating to the 
    employment of sales promotion employees;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>
examine with respect to any matter relevant to any of the purposes 
    aforesaid, the employer, his agent or servant or any other person found in 
    charge of the establishment or any premises connected therewith or any 
    person whom the Inspector has reasonable cause to believe to be or to have 
    been a sales promotion employee in the establishment;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>
make copies of or take extracts from any register or other documents 
    maintained in relation to the establishment under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>
exercise such other powers as may be prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Every 
    Inspector shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of 
    section 21 of the India Penal Code, 1860 (45 of 1860).
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Any person 
    required to produce any register or other document or to give information by 
    an Inspector under sub-section (2) shall be legally bound to do so.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Penalty.—If 
    any employer contravenes the provisions of section 4 or section 5 or section 
    7 or any rules made under this Act, he shall be punishable with fine which 
    may extend to one thousand rupees.
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Offences 
    by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> Where an offence 
    under this Act has been committed by a company, every person who, at the 
    time the offence was committed, was in charge of, and; was responsible to, 
    the company for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as the 
    company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to 
    be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
 
Provided that 
    nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to 
    any punishment provided in this section, if he proves that the offence was 
    committed without his knowledge or that he exercised all due diligence to 
    prevent the commission of such offence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (l), where an offence 
    under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the 
    offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is 
    attributable to, any neglect on the part of any director, manager, secretary 
    or other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary or other 
    officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of such offence and shall be 
    liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> For the 
    purposes of this section,—
 <subsection>
 <number>a</number>
“company” means any body corporate and includes a firm or other 
    association of individuals; and
 </subsection><subsection>
 <number>b</number>
“director”, in relation to a firm, means a partner in the firm.
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Cognizance of offences.—
<section><number>1</number> No 
    court inferior to that of a Metropolitan Magistrate or a Magistrate of the 
    first class shall try any offence punishable under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No court 
    shall take cognizance of an offence under this Act, unless the complaint 
    thereof is made within six months of the date on which the offence is 
    alleged to have been committed.
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>11A</number> Effect of laws and agreements inconsistent 
      with this Act.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
      provisions of this Act or of any rule made thereunder shall have effect, 
      notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained in any other law 
      or in the terms of any award, agreement, settlement or contract of 
      service, whether made before or after the coming into force of this 
      Act:
 Provided that where under any such law, award, 
      agreement, settlement or contract of service, a sales promotion employee 
      is entitled to benefits in respect of any matter which are more favourable 
      to him than those to which he would be entitled under this Act, the sales 
      promotion employee shall continue to be entitled to the more favourable 
      benefits in respect of that matter, notwithstanding that he is entitled to 
      receive benefits in respect of other matters under this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Nothing contained in this Act shall be 
      construed to preclude a sales promotion employee from entering into an 
      agreement with his employer for granting him rights or privileges in 
      respect of any matter which are more favourable to him than those to which 
      he would be entitled under this Act.]
  







 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Power to 
    make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make 
    rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>
the kinds of leave that may be granted to a sales promotion employee
    <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[the limit up to 
    which he may accumulate earned leave, the limit up to which he may avail of 
    earned leave at a time and the reasons for which such limit may be exceeded, 
    the conditions and restrictions subject to which he may be entitled to cash, 
    compensation] under section 4;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
the form of the letter of appointment to be furnished under section 
    5;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>
the registers and other documents to be kept and maintained under 
    section 7 and the manner in which such registers and other documents may be 
    kept and maintained;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>
any other matter which has to be, or may be prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Every rule 
    made by the Central Government under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may 
    be after it is made, before each House of Parliament while it is in session, 
    for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or 
    in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
    immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both 
    Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree 
    that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only 
    in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, 
    that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
    validity of anything previously done under that rule.
 
   






 



</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>
Came into force on 6-3-1976, vide S.O. 176(E), dated 6th March, 1976.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>
     Subs. by Act 48 of 1986, sec. 2, 
    for clause (d) (w.e.f. 6-5-1987).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>
     Section 4 re-numbered as 
    sub-section (1) thereof by Act 48 of 1986, sec. 3 (w.r.e.f.
8-3-1976). tc " 1. Section 4 re-numbered as 
    sub-section (1) thereof by Act 48 of 1986, sec. 3 (w.r.e.f.
8-3-1976)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>
     The words "drawing wages
(being wages not including any Commission)" omitted by Act 48
of 1986, sec. 3 (w.r.e.f. 
    8-3-1976).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>
Ins. by Act 48 of 1986, sec. 3 (w.r.e.f
8-3-1976).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Ins. by Act 48 of 1986, sec 
      4. (w.e.f. 6-5-1987).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>  Ins. by Act 69 of 1982, sec. 2 
      (w.e.f. 13-11-1982).  tc 
    " 1. Ins. by Act 69 of 1982, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 13-11-1982)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>
     Ins. by Act 48 of 1986, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 
    6-5-1987).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>