<act><title>THE JUVENILE JUSTICE (CARE AND PROTECTION OF 
CHILDREN) RULES, 20071</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the Juvenile Justice (Care and Protection of Children) Rules, 2007. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of their publication 
in the Official Gazette. 




</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definition. </title>In these rules, unless the context otherwise 
requires, 
 
 <section><number>a</number> abandoned means an unaccompanied and deserted child who is declared 
  abandoned by the Committee after due inquiry; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> Act means the Juvenile Justice (Care and Protection of Children) Act, 
  2000 (56 of 2000) as amended by the Juvenile Justice (Care and Protection of 
  Children) Amendment Act, 2006 (33 of 2006); 
 </section><section><number>c</number> best interest of the child means a decision taken to ensure the 
  physical, emotional, intellectual, social and moral development of juvenile or 
  child; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> child friendly means any process and interpretation, attitude, 
  environment and treatment, that is humane, considerate and in the best 
  interest of the child; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> community service implies service rendered to the society by 
  juveniles in conflict with law in lieu of other judicial remedies and 
  penalties, which is not degrading and dehumanizing. Examples of this may 
  include: 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> cleaning a park; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> getting involved with Habitat for Humanity; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> serving the elderly in nursing homes; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> helping out a local fire or police department; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> helping out at a local hospital or nursing home; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vi</number> serving disabled children. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>f</number> detention in case of juveniles in conflict with law means protective 
  custody in line with the principles of restorative justice; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> Form means the form annexed to these rules; 
 </section><section><number>h</number> individual care plan is a comprehensive development plan for a 
  juvenile or child based on age specific and gender specific needs and the case 
  history of the juvenile or child, prepared in consultation with the juvenile 
  or child, in order to restore the juvenile's or child's self-esteem, dignity 
  and self-worth and nurture him into a responsible citizen and accordingly the 
  plan shall address the following needs of a juvenile or a child: 
 </section><section><number>i</number> Health needs; 
 <subsection><number>ii</number> Emotional and psychological needs; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> Educational and training needs; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> Leisure, creativity and play; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> Attachments and relationships; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vi</number> Protection from all kinds of abuse, neglect and maltreatment; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vii</number> Social mainstreaming; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>viii</number> Follow-up post release and restoration. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> institution means an observation home, or a special home, or a 
  children's home or a shelter home set-up, certified or recognized and 
  registered under sections 8, 9, 34, sub-section (3) of section 34 and section 
  37 of the Act respectively; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> Officer-in-charge or such other nomenclature as issued by the State 
  Government, means a person appointed for the control and management of the 
  institution; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number> orphan means a child who is without parents or willing and capable 
  legal or natural guardian; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number> place of safety means any institution set-up and recognized under 
  sub-section (3) of section 12 and sub-section (1) of section 16 of the Act for 
  juvenile in conflict with law or children; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>m</number> recognised means a person found fit by the competent authority or, an 
  institution found fit by the State Government on the recommendation of the 
  competent authority as per clauses (h) and (i) of section (2) of the Act; or, 
  recognition of an institution or agency or voluntary organisation by the State 
  Government to operate as a children's home, observation home and special home; 
  or a shelter home, specialised adoption agency or after care organization 
  under sub-section (1) of section 37, sub-section (4) of section 41 and clause 
  (a) of section 44 of the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>n</number> registered means all institutions or agencies or voluntary 
  organisations providing residential care to children in need of care and 
  protection registered under sub-section (3) of section 34; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>o</number> State Government in relation to a Union territory means the 
  Administrator of that Union territory appointed by the President under article 
  239 of the Constitution; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>p</number> street and working children means children without ostensible means 
  of livelihood, care, protection and support in accordance with the provisions 
  laid down under clause (d)(1) of section 2 of the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>q</number> surrendered child means a child, who in the opinion of the Committee, 
  is relinquished on account of physical, emotional and social factors beyond 
  the control of the parent or guardian; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>r</number> all words and expressions defined in the Act and used, but not defined 
  in these rules, shall have the same meaning as assigned to them in the Act. 
  </subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Fundamental principles to be followed in administration of these 
rules. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The State Government, the Juvenile Justice Board, the Child 
Welfare Committee or other competent authorities or agencies, as the case may 
be, while implementing the provisions of these rules shall abide and be guided 
by the principles, specified in sub-rule (2). 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The following principles shall, inter alia, be fundamental to 
the application, interpretation and implementation of the Act and the rules made 
hereunder: 
 <subsection><title><number>I</number> Principle of presumption of innocence </title>
 
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> A juvenile or child or juvenile in conflict with law is presumed to be 
  innocent of any mala fide or criminal intent up to the age of 
  eighteen years. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> The juvenile's or juveniles in conflict with law or child's right to 
  presumption of innocence shall be respected throughout the process of justice 
  and protection, from the initial contact to alternative care, including 
  aftercare. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>c</number> Any unlawful conduct of a juvenile or a child or a juvenile in conflict 
  with law which is done for survival, or is due to environmental or situational 
  factors or is done under control of adults, or peer groups, is ought to be 
  covered by the principles of innocence. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>d</number> The basic components of presumption of innocence are: 
 </subsubsection>
 <title>II Principle of dignity and worth </title>
 
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> Treatment that is consistent with the child's sense of dignity and 
  worth is a fundamental principle of juvenile justice. This principle reflects 
  the fundamental human right enshrined in Article 1 of the Universal 
  Declaration of Human Rights that all human beings are born free and equal in 
  dignity and rights. Respect of dignity includes not being humiliated, personal 
  identity, boundaries and space being respected, not being labelled and 
  stigmatized, being offered information and choices and not being blamed for 
  their acts. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> The juvenile's or child's right to dignity and worth has to be 
  respected and protected throughout the entire process of dealing with the 
  child from the first contact with law enforcement agencies to the 
  implementation of all measures for dealing with the child. </subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> <title>Age of innocence 
  </title><title></title>
 
 Age of innocence is the age below which a juvenile or child or a juvenile 
    in conflict with law cannot be subjected to the criminal justice system. The 
    Beijing rule 4(1) clearly lays down that the beginning of the age of 
    criminal responsibility shall not be fixed at too low an age level bearing 
    in mind the facts of mental and intellectual maturity. In consonance with 
    this principle, the mental and intellectual maturity of juvenile or child or 
    a juvenile in conflict with law below eighteen years is considered 
    insufficient throughout the world. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> <title>Procedural protection of innocence </title>
 
 All procedural safeguards that are guaranteed by the Constitution and 
    other statutes to the adults and that go in to strengthen the juvenile's or 
    child's right to presumption of innocence shall be guaranteed to 
    juveniles or the children or juveniles in conflict with law. 
    
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> <title>Provisions of Legal aid and Guardian Ad Litem 
  </title>
 
 Juveniles in conflict with law have a right to be informed about the 
    accusations against them and a right to be legally represented. Provisions 
    must be made for guardian ad litem , legal aid and other such 
    assistance through legal services at State expense. This shall also include 
    such juveniles' right to present his case before the competent authority on 
    his own. </subsection><subsection><title><number>III</number> Principle of Right to be heard </title>
 
 Every child's right to express his views freely in all matters affecting 
  his interest shall be fully respected through every stage in the process of 
  juvenile justice. Children's right to be heard shall include creation of 
  developmentally appropriate tools and processes of interacting with the child, 
  promoting children's active involvement in decisions regarding their own lives 
  and providing opportunities for discussion and debate. 
 </subsection><subsection><title><number>IV</number> Principle of Best Interest </title>
 
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> In all decisions taken within the context of administration of juvenile 
  justice, the principle of best interest of the juvenile or the juvenile in 
  conflict with law or child shall be the primary consideration. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> The principle of best interest of the juvenile or juvenile in conflict 
  with law or child shall mean for instance that the traditional objectives of 
  criminal justice, retribution and repression, must give way to rehabilitative 
  and restorative objectives of juvenile justice. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>c</number> This principle seeks to ensure physical, emotional, intellectual, 
  social and moral development of a juvenile in conflict with law or child so as 
  to ensure the safety, well being and permanence for each child and thus enable 
  each child to survive and reach his or her full potential. </subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><title><number>V</number> Principle of family responsibility </title>
 
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> The primary responsibility of bringing up children, providing care, 
  support and protection shall be with the biological parents. However, in 
  exceptional situations, this responsibility may be bestowed on willing 
  adoptive or foster parents. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> All decision making for the child should involve the family of origin 
  unless it is not in the best interest of the child to do so. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>c</number> The family - biological, adoptive or foster (in that order), must be 
  held responsible and provide necessary care, support and protection to the 
  juvenile or child under their care and custody under the Act, unless the best 
  interest measures or mandates dictate otherwise. </subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><title><number>VI</number> Principle of Safety (no harm, no abuse, no neglect, no 
exploitation and no maltreatment) </title>
 
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> At all stages, from the initial contact till such time he remains in 
  contact with the care and protection system, and thereafter, the juvenile or 
  child or juvenile in conflict with law shall not be subjected to any harm, 
  abuse, neglect, maltreatment, corporal punishment or solitary or otherwise any 
  confinement in jails and extreme care shall be taken to avoid any harm to the 
  sensitivity of the juvenile or the child. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> The state has a greater responsibility for ensuring safety of every 
  child in its care and protection, without resorting to restrictive measures 
  and processes in the name of care and protection. </subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><title><number>VII</number> Positive measures </title>
 
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> Provisions must be made to enable positive measures that involve the 
  full mobilization of all possible resources, including the family, volunteers 
  and other community groups, as well as schools and other mainstream community 
  institutions or processes, for the purpose of promoting the well-being of the 
  juvenile or child through individual care plans carefully worked out. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> The positive measures shall aim at reducing vulnerabilities and 
  reducing the need for intervention under the law, as well as effective, fair 
  and humane dealing of the juvenile or child. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>c</number> The positive measures shall include avenues for health, education, 
  relationships, livelihoods, leisure, creativity and play. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>d</number> Such positive measures must facilitate the development of identity for 
  the child and provide them with an inclusive and enabling environment. 
</subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><title><number>VIII</number> Principle of non-stigmatizing semantics, decisions and actions 
</title>
 
 The non-stigmatizing semantics of the Act must be strictly adhered to, and 
  the use of adversarial or accusatory words, such as, arrest, remand, accused, 
  charge sheet, trial, prosecution, warrant, summons, conviction, inmate, 
  delinquent, neglected, custody or jail is prohibited in the processes 
  pertaining to the child or juvenile in conflict with law under the Act. 

 </subsection><subsection><title><number>IX</number> Principle of non-waiver of rights </title>
 
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> No waiver of rights of the child or juvenile in conflict with law, 
  whether by himself or the competent authority or anyone acting or claiming to 
  act on behalf of the juvenile or child, is either permissible or valid. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> Non-exercise of a fundamental right does not amount to waiver. 
</subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><title><number>X</number> Principle of equality and non-discrimination </title>
 
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> There shall be no discrimination against a child or juvenile in 
  conflict with law on the basis of age, sex, place of birth, disability, 
  health, status, race, ethnicity, religion, caste, cultural practices, work, 
  activity or behaviour of the juvenile or child or that of his parents or 
  guardians, or the civil and political status of the juvenile or child. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> Equality of access, equality of opportunity, equality in treatment 
  under the Act shall be guaranteed to every child or juvenile in conflict with 
  law. </subsubsection>
 <subsubsection><title><number>XI</number> Principle of right to privacy and confidentiality </title>
 
 The juvenile's or child's right to privacy and confidentiality shall be 
  protected by all means and through all the stages of the proceedings and care 
  and protection processes. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><title><number>XII</number> Principle of last resort </title>
 
 Institutionalization of a child or juvenile in conflict with law shall be a 
  step of the last resort after reasonable inquiry and that too for the minimum 
  possible duration. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><title><number>XIII</number> Principle of repatriation and restoration </title>
 
 <subsubsubsection><number>a</number> Every juvenile or child or juvenile in conflict with law has the right 
  to be re-united with his family and restored back to the same socio-economic 
  and cultural status that such juvenile or child enjoyed before coming within 
  the purview of the Act or becoming vulnerable to any form of neglect, abuse or 
  exploitation. 
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>b</number> Any juvenile or child, who has lost contact with his family, shall be 
  eligible for protection under the Act and shall be repatriated and restored, 
  at the earliest, to his family, unless such repatriation and restoration is 
  likely to be against the best interest of the juvenile or the child. 
</subsubsubsection>
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><title><number>XIV</number> Principle of Fresh Start </title>
 
 <subsubsubsection><number>a</number> The principle of fresh start promotes new beginning for the child or 
  juvenile in conflict with law by ensuring erasure of his past records. (b) 
  The State shall seek to promote measures for dealing with children alleged or 
  recognized as having impinged the penal law, without resorting to judicial 
  proceedings. </subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Juvenile Justice Boards. </title>There shall be one or more 
Juvenile Justice Boards in every district, which shall be constituted by the 
State Government as per section 4 of the Act. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Composition of the Juvenile Justice Board. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Board 
shall consist of a Metropolitan Magistrate or a Judicial Magistrate of the first 
class, as the case may be, and two social workers of whom at least one shall be 
a woman, forming a bench: 
 Provided that the Principal Magistrate of the Board shall review the pendency 
of cases before the Board and take such steps, as may be necessary in the 
expeditious disposal of the cases. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every such bench shall have the powers conferred by the Code of Criminal 
Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974). 
 </section><section><number>3</number> (i) A Magistrate with special knowledge or training in child psychology 
or child welfare shall be designated as the Principal Magistrate of the Board. 

 <subsection><number>ii</number> In case the Principal Magistrate with such special knowledge or training 
is not available, then, the State Government shall provide for such short-term 
training in child psychology or child welfare as it considers necessary. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number> The two social workers, of whom at least one shall be a woman, shall be 
appointed by the State Government on the recommendation of the Selection 
Committee set-up under rule 91 of these rules. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The State Government shall provide for such training and orientation in 
child psychology, child welfare, child rights, national and international 
standards for juvenile justice to all members of the Board as it considers 
necessary, in accordance with the Integrated Child Protection Scheme of the 
Central Government. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Tenure of the Board. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Board shall have a tenure 
of three years and the appointment of members shall be co-terminus with the 
tenure of the Board. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> A social worker being a member of the Board shall be eligible for 
appointment for a maximum of two consecutive terms. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Any extension of the tenure of members of the Board shall be on the basis 
of their performance appraisal by the District Child Protection Unit of the 
State Government and on the recommendation of a Selection Committee constituted 
for the purpose and the performance appraisal of members of the Board shall 
necessarily assess their participation in the proceedings of the Board and 
contribution in case disposal. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> A member may resign any time, by giving one month's advance notice in 
writing or may be removed from his office as provided in sub-section (5) of 
section 4 of the Act. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Any vacancy in the Board may be filled by appointment of another person 
from the panel of names prepared by the Selection Committee, and shall hold 
office for the remaining term of the Board. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Qualifications for Members of the Board. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The social 
worker to be appointed as a member of the Board shall be a person not less than 
35 years of age, who has a post-graduate degree in social work, health, 
education, psychology, child development or any other social science discipline 
and has been actively involved and engaged in planning, implementing and 
administering measures relating to child welfare for at least seven years. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> No person shall be considered for selection as a Member of the Board, if 
he, 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> has been convicted under any law; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> have ever indulged in child abuse or employment of child labour or any 
  other human rights violations or immoral act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> is holding such other occupation that does not allow him to give 
  necessary time and attention to the work of the Board; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> does not fulfil the qualification and experience prescribed in the Act 
  and the rules made thereunder and in such a case the Selection Committee shall 
  after due inquiry and on establishment of such fact, reject his application 
  and recommend the name of the next person from the list of names prepared for 
  filling the vacancies. </subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number> Sitting and conveyance allowances. </title>The social worker 
members of the Board shall be paid such travel and sitting allowance, as the 
State Government may determine, but it shall not be less than rupees five 
hundred per sitting. 
  </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>9</number> Sittings of the Board. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Board shall hold its 
sittings in the premises of an Observation Home or, at a place in proximity to 
the observation home or, at a suitable premise in any institution run under the 
Act, and in no circumstances shall the Board operate from within any court 
premises. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The premises where the Board holds its sittings shall be child-friendly 
and shall not look like a court room in any manner whatsoever; for example, the 
Board shall not sit on a raised platform and the sitting arrangement shall be 
uniform, and there shall be no witness boxes. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Board shall meet on all working days of a week, unless the case 
pendency is less in a particular district and concerned authority issues an 
order in this regard. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> A minimum of three-fourth attendance of the Chairperson and Members of 
the Board is necessary in a year. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Every member of the Board shall attend a minimum of five hours per 
sitting. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>10</number> Functions of the Board. </title>The Board shall perform the 
following functions to achieve the objectives of the Act, namely: 
 
 <section><number>a</number> adjudicate and dispose cases of juveniles in conflict with law; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> take cognizance of crimes committed under sections 23 to 28 of the Act; 
  
 </section><section><number>c</number> monitoring institutions for juveniles in conflict with law and seeking 
  compliance from them in cases of any noticeable lapses and improvement based 
  on suggestions of the Board; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> deal with non-compliance on the part of concerned government 
  functionaries or functionaries of voluntary organizations, as the case may be, 
  in accordance with due process of law; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> pass necessary direction to the district authority and police to create 
  or provide necessary infrastructure or facilities so that minimum standards of 
  justice and treatment are maintained in the spirit of the Act; 
 </section><section><number>f</number> maintain liaison with the Committee in respect of cases needing care 
  and protection; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> liaison with Boards in other districts to facilitate speedy inquiry and 
  disposal of cases through due process of law; 
 </section><section><number>h</number> take suitable action for dealing with unforeseen situations that may 
  arise in the implementation of the Act and remove such difficulties in the 
  best interest of the juvenile; 
 </section><section><number>i</number> send quarterly information about juveniles in conflict with law 
  produced before them, to the District, State Child Protection Unit, the State 
  Government and also to the Chief Judicial Magistrate or Chief Metropolitan 
  Magistrate for review under sub-section (2) of section 14 of the Act; 
 </section><section><number>j</number> any other function assigned by the State Government from time to time 
  relating with juveniles in conflict with law. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>11</number> Pre and Post-Production action of police and other agencies. 
</title>
<section><number>1</number> As soon as a juvenile alleged to be in conflict with law is 
apprehended by the police, the concerned police officer shall inform: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the designated Juvenile or the Child Welfare Officer in the nearest 
  police station to take charge of the matter; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the parents or guardian of the juvenile alleged to be in conflict with 
  law about the apprehension of the juvenile, about the address of the Board 
  where the juvenile will be produced and the date and time when the parents or 
  guardian need to be present before the Board; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the concerned probation officer, of such apprehension to enable him to 
  obtain information regarding social background of the juvenile and other 
  material circumstances likely to be of assistance to the Board for conducting 
  the inquiry. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Soon after apprehension, the juvenile shall be placed under the charge of 
the Juvenile or Child Welfare Officer from the nearest police station, who shall 
produce the juvenile before the Board within twenty-four hours as per 
sub-section (1) of section 10 of the Act and where such Juvenile or the Child 
Welfare Officer has not been designated as per provisions laid down under 
sub-section (2) of section 63 of the Act or is not available for some official 
reasons, the police officer who had apprehended the juvenile shall produce him 
before the Board. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The police apprehending a juvenile in conflict with law shall in no case 
send the juvenile in lock-up or delay his charge being transferred to the 
Juvenile or the Child Welfare Officer from the nearest police station, if such 
an officer has been designated. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> A list of all designated Juvenile or the Child Welfare Officers in a 
district and members of Special Juvenile Police Unit with contact details shall 
be prominently displayed in every police station. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> For gathering the best available information it shall be incumbent upon 
the Police or the Juvenile or the Child Welfare Officer from the nearest police 
station, to contact the parents or guardians of the juvenile and also apprise 
them of the juvenile's law breaking behaviour. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Police or the Juvenile or the Child Welfare Officer from the nearest 
police station, shall also record the social background of the juvenile and 
circumstances of apprehension and offence alleged to have been committed in the 
case diary of each juvenile, which shall be forwarded to the Board forthwith. 

 </section><section><number>7</number> The police or the Juvenile or the Child Welfare Officer from the nearest 
police station, shall exercise the power of apprehending the juvenile only in 
cases of his alleged involvement in serious offences (entailing a punishment of 
more than 7 years imprisonment for adults). 
 </section><section><number>8</number> In such cases where apprehension apparently seems to be in the interest 
of the juvenile, the police or the Juvenile or the Child Welfare Officer from 
the nearest police station, shall rather treat the juvenile as a child in need 
of care and protection and produce him before the Board, clearly explaining the 
juvenile's need for care and protection in its report and seek appropriate 
orders from the Board under rule 13(1)(b) of these rules. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> For all other cases involving offences of non-serious nature (entailing a 
punishment of less than 7 years imprisonment for adults) and cases where 
apprehension is not necessary in the interest of the juvenile, the police or the 
Juvenile or the Child Welfare Officer from the nearest police station, shall 
intimate the parents or guardian of the juvenile about forwarding the 
information regarding nature of offence alleged to be committed by their child 
or ward along with his socio-economic background to the Board, which shall have 
the power to call the juvenile for subsequent hearings. 
 </section><section><number>10</number> In case the Board is not sitting, the juvenile in conflict with law 
shall be produced before the single member of the Board as per the provisions 
laid down under the sub-section (2) of section 5 of the Act. 
 </section><section><number>11</number> In dealing with cases of juveniles in conflict with law the Police or 
the Juvenile or the Child Welfare Officer from the nearest police station, shall 
not be required to register an FIR or file a charge-sheet, except where the 
offence alleged to have been committed by the juvenile is of a serious nature 
such as rape, murder or when such offence is alleged to have been committed 
jointly with adults; instead, in matters involving simple offences, the Police 
or the Juvenile or the Child Welfare Officer from the nearest police station 
shall record information regarding the offence alleged to have been committed by 
the juvenile in the general daily diary followed by a report containing social 
background of the juvenile and circumstances of apprehension and the alleged 
offence and forward it to the Board before the first hearing. 
 </section><section><number>12</number> The State Government shall recognize only such voluntary organizations 
that are in a position to provide the services of probation, counselling, case 
work, a safe place and also associate with the Police or the Juvenile or the 
Child Welfare Officer from the Special Juvenile Police Unit, and have the 
capacity, facilities and expertise to do so as protection agencies that may 
assist the Police or the Juvenile or the Child Welfare Officer from the police 
at the time of apprehension, in preparation of the report containing social 
background of the juvenile and circumstances of apprehension and the alleged 
offence, in taking charge of the juvenile until production before the Board, and 
in actual production of the juvenile before the Board within twenty-four hours. 

 </section><section><number>13</number> The Police or the Juvenile or the Child Welfare Officer from the Special 
Juvenile Police Unit, or the recognized voluntary organization shall be 
responsible for the safety and provision of food and basic amenities to the 
juveniles apprehended or kept under their charge during the period such 
juveniles are with them. (14) When a juvenile is produced before an 
individual member of the Board, and an order obtained, such order shall need 
ratification by the Board in its next meeting. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>12</number> Procedure to be followed in determination of Age. </title>
<section><number>1</number> 
In every case concerning a child or a juvenile in conflict with law, the court 
or the Board or as the case may be the Committee referred to in rule 19 of these 
rules shall determine the age of such juvenile or child or a juvenile in 
conflict with law within a period of thirty days from the date of making of the 
application for that purpose. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Court or the Board or as the case may be the Committee shall decide 
the juvenility or otherwise of the juvenile or the child or as the case may be 
the juvenile in conflict with law, prima facie on the basis of physical 
appearance or documents, if available, and send him to the observation home or 
in jail. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> In every case concerning a child or juvenile in conflict with law, the 
age determination inquiry shall be conducted by the court or the Board or, as 
the case may be, the Committee by seeking evidence by obtaining 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> (i) the matriculation or equivalent certificates, if available; and in 
  the absence whereof; 
 <subsubsection><number>ii</number> the date of birth certificate from the school (other than a play 
  school) first attended; and in the absence whereof; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number> the birth certificate given by a corporation or a municipal authority 
  or a panchayat; 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>b</number> and only in the absence of either (i), (ii) or (iii) of clause (a) 
  above, the medical opinion will be sought from a duly constituted Medical 
  Board, which will declare the age of the juvenile or child. In case exact 
  assessment of the age cannot be done, the Court or the Board or, as the case 
  may be, the Committee, for the reasons to be recorded by them, may, if 
  considered necessary, give benefit to the child or juvenile by considering 
  his/her age on lower side within the margin of one year. </subsection>
 and, while passing orders in such case shall, after taking into consideration 
such evidence as may be available, or the medical opinion, as the case may be, 
record a finding in respect of his age and either of the evidence specified in 
any of the clauses (a)(i), (ii), (iii) or in the absence whereof, clause (b) 
shall be the conclusive proof of the age as regards such child or Ihe juvenile 
in conflict with law. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> If the age of a juvenile or child or the juvenile in conflict with law is 
found to be below 18 years on the date of offence, on the basis of any of the 
conclusive proof specified in sub-rule (3), the Court or the Board or as the 
case may be the Committee shall in writing pass an order stating the age and 
declaring the status of juvenility or otherwise, for the purpose of the Act and 
these rules and a copy of the order shall be given to such juvenile or the 
person concerned. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Save and except where, further inquiry or otherwise is required, 
inter alia , in terms of section 7A, section 64 of the Act and these 
rules, no further inquiry shall be conducted by the court or the Board after 
examining and obtaining the certificate or any other documentary proof referred 
to in sub-rule (3) of this rule. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The provisions contained in this rule shall also apply to those disposed 
of cases, where the status of juvenility has not been determined in accordance 
with the provisions contained in sub-rule (3) and the Act, requiring 
dispensation of the sentence under the Act for passing appropriate order in the 
interest of the juvenile in conflict with law. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>13</number> Post-production processes by the Board. </title>
<section><number>1</number> On 
production of the juvenile before the Board, the report containing social 
background of the juvenile and circumstances of apprehension and offence alleged 
to have been committed provided by the officers, individuals, agencies producing 
the juvenile shall be reviewed by the Board, and the Board shall pass the 
following order in the first summary inquiry on the same day, namely: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> dispose of the case, if the evidence of his conflict with law appears 
  to be unfounded or where the juvenile is involved in trivial law breaking; 

 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> transfer to the Committee, matters concerning juveniles clearly stated 
  to be in need of care and protection in the police report submitted to the 
  Board at the time of production of the juvenile; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> release the juvenile in the supervision or custody of fit persons or 
  fit institutions or probation officers as the case may be, through an order in 
  Form I, with a direction to appear or present a juvenile for an inquiry on a 
  next date; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> detain the juvenile in an Observation Home or fit institution pending 
  inquiry, only in cases of juvenile's involvement in serious offences as per an 
  order in Form II; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> in all cases of release pending inquiry, the Board shall notify the 
  next date of hearing, not later than 15 days of the first summary enquiry and 
  also seek social investigation report from the concerned Probation Officer 
  through an order in Form III; </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Board shall take the following steps to ensure fair and speedy 
inquiry, namely: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> at the time of initiating the inquiry, the Board shall satisfy itself 
  that the juvenile in conflict with law has not been subjected to any 
  ill-treatment by the police or by any other person, including a lawyer or 
  probation officer and take corrective steps in case of such ill-treatment; 

 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> in all cases under the Act the proceedings shall be conducted in as 
  simple a manner as possible and care shall be taken to ensure that the 
  juvenile, against whom the proceedings have been instituted, is given 
  child-friendly atmosphere during the proceedings; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> every juvenile brought before the Board shall be given the opportunity 
  to be heard and participate in his inquiry; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> cases of petty offences, if not disposed of by the Special Juvenile 
  Police Unit or at the police station itself, may be disposed of by the Board 
  through summary proceedings or inquiry, while in cases of heinous offences 
  entailing punishment of 7 years or more, due process of inquiry in detail may 
  follow; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> even in cases of inquiry pertaining to serious offences the Board shall 
  follow the procedure of trial in summons cases. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> When witnesses are produced for examination in inquiry relating to a 
juvenile in conflict with law, the Board shall keep in mind that the inquiry is 
not to be conducted in the spirit of strict adversarial proceedings and it shall 
use the powers conferred by section 165 of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 
1872) so as to question the juvenile and proceed with the presumptions that 
favour the juvenile's right to be restored. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> While examining a juvenile in conflict with law and recording his 
statement, the Board shall address the juvenile in a child-friendly manner in 
order to put the juvenile at ease and to encourage him to state the facts and 
circumstances without any fear, not only in respect of the offence of which the 
juvenile is accused, but also in respect of the home and social surroundings and 
the influence to which the juvenile might have been subjected. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Board may take into account the report of the police containing 
circumstances of apprehension and offence alleged to have been committed and the 
social investigation report in Form IV prepared by the Probation Officer or the 
voluntary organization on the orders of the Board as per Form III, along with 
the evidence produced by the parties for arriving at a conclusion about the 
juvenile. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> Every inquiry by the Board shall be completed within a period of four 
months after the first summary inquiry and only in exceptional cases involving 
trans-national criminality, large number of accused and inordinate delay in 
production of witnesses, the period of inquiry may be extended by two months on 
recording of reasons by the Board. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> In all other cases except where the nature of alleged offence is serious, 
delay beyond four to six months shall lead to the termination of the 
proceedings. (8) Where the proceedings are delayed beyond six months on 
account of serious nature of the offence alleged to have been committed by the 
juvenile, the Board shall send a periodic report of the case to the Chief 
Judicial Magistrate or Chief Metropolitan Magistrate stating the reason for 
delay as well as steps being taken to expedite the matter. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>14</number> Legal Aid. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The proceedings before the Board shall 
be conducted in non-adversarial environment, but with due regard to all the due 
process guarantees such as right to counsel and free legal aid. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Board shall ensure that the Legal Officer in the District Child 
Protection Unit and the State Legal Aid Services Authority shall extend free 
legal services to all the juvenile in conflict with law. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Legal Officer in the District Child Protection Unit and the State 
Legal Aid Services Authority shall be under an obligation to provide legal 
services sought by the Board. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> In the event of shortfall in the State Legal Aid Services support, the 
Board shall be responsible for seeking legal services from recognized voluntary 
legal services organisations or the university legal services clinics. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Board may also deploy the services of the student legal services 
volunteers and non­-governmental organisation volunteers in para-legal tasks 
such as contacting the parents of juveniles in conflict with law and gathering 
relevant social and rehabilitative information about the juveniles. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>15</number> Completion of Inquiry and Dispositional Alternatives. 
</title>
<section><number>1</number> The Board shall complete every inquiry within the stipulated time 
of four months and on recording a finding about juvenile's involvement in the 
alleged offence, pass one of the seven dispositional orders enumerated in 
section 15 of the Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Before passing an order, the Board shall obtain a social investigation 
report prepared by the probation officer or by a recognized voluntary 
organization ordered to do so by the Board, and take the findings of the report 
into account. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> All dispositional orders passed by the Board shall necessarily include an 
individual care plan for the concerned juvenile in conflict with law, prepared 
by a probation officer or voluntary organization on the basis of interaction 
with the juvenile and his family where possible. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Where the Board decides to release the juvenile after advice and 
admonition or after participation in group counselling or orders him to perform 
community service, necessary direction may also be made by the Board to the 
District or State Child Protection Unit or the State Government for arranging 
such individual counselling, group counselling and community service. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Where the Board decides to release the juvenile in conflict with law on 
probation and place him under the care of the parent or guardian or fit person, 
the person in whose custody the juvenile is released may be required to submit a 
written undertaking in Form V <title></title>for the good behaviour and 
well-being of the juvenile for a maximum period of three years. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Board may order release of a juvenile in conflict with law on 
execution of a personal bond without surety in Form VI. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> In the event of placement of a juvenile in conflict with law in care of a 
fit institution or special home, the Board shall keep in mind that the fit 
institution or special home is located nearest to the place of residence of the 
juvenile's parent or guardian. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> The Board, where it releases a juvenile in conflict with law on probation 
and places him under the care of parent or guardian or fit person or where the 
juvenile is released on probation and placed under the care of fit institution, 
may order that the juvenile be placed under the supervision of a probation 
officer. The period of supervision shall be a maximum of three years. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> Where the Board decides that a juvenile in conflict with law ought to be 
treated as a child in need of care and protection, it shall make necessary 
orders for production of such juvenile before the nearest Committee for suitable 
care, protection and rehabilitation. 
 </section><section><number>10</number> Where it appears to the Board that the juvenile in conflict with law has 
not complied with probation conditions, it may order the juvenile to be sent for 
detention in a special home. 
 </section><section><number>11</number> Where a juvenile in conflict with law who has attained the age of 
sixteen years and the offence committed by him is of such a serious nature that 
in the satisfaction of the Board, it is neither in the interest of the juvenile 
himself nor in the interest of other juveniles of the special home, the Board 
may order the juvenile to be kept in a place of safety and in a manner 
considered most appropriate by it. 
 </section><section><number>12</number> The State Government shall make arrangement for complying with the 
detention of special category of juveniles in conflict with law in place of 
safety other than the special home. 
 </section><section><number>13</number> In no case the period of detention shall exceed beyond the maximum 
period provided in clause (g) of sub-section (1) of section 15 of the Act. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>16</number> Institutions for juveniles in conflict with law. </title>
<section><number>1</number> 
The State Government or the voluntary organisation recognised by that State 
Government shall set-up separate observation homes or special homes for boys and 
girls. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The observation homes or special homes shall set-up separate residential 
facilities for boys and girls up to 12 years, 13-15 years and 16 years and 
above. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every institution shall keep a copy of the Act, the rules made by the 
Central Government and the State rules if any, for use by both staff, juveniles 
and children residing therein. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The State Governments in collaboration with civil society shall develop 
and make available simplified and child friendly versions of the Act and the 
rules in regional languages. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> All facilities and services for juveniles in conflict with law shall be 
made available and maintained as per the provisions of the Act and the State 
rules. In case the State Rules have not been notified, the provisions of these 
rules shall apply. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>17</number> Release. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Officer-in-charge shall maintain a 
roster of the cases of juveniles in conflict with law to be released on the 
expiry of the period of stay as ordered by the Board. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Each case shall be placed before the Management Committee set-up under 
rule 55 of these rules by the concerned probation officer or child welfare 
officer or case worker for ensuring proper release and social mainstreaming of 
the juvenile post-release. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The release shall be as per the pre-release and post-release plan 
prepared under the individual care plan and reviewed from time to time by the 
management committee set-up under rule 55 of these rules and in all cases of 
release, necessary action and preparation shall be initiated well before the 
time of release and shall include preparation for post-release follow-up. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The timely information of the release of a juvenile and of the exact date 
of release shall be given to the parent or guardian and the parent or guardian 
shall be invited to come to the institution to take charge of the juvenile on 
that date. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> If necessary, the actual expenses of the parent's or guardian's journey 
both ways and of the juvenile's journey from the institution shall be paid to 
the parent or guardian by the Officer-in-charge at the time of the release of 
the juvenile. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> If the parent or guardian, as the case may be, fails to come and take 
charge of the juvenile on the appointed date, the juvenile shall be taken by the 
escort of the institution; and in case of a girl, she shall be escorted by a 
female escort. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> At the time of release or discharge, a juvenile shall be provided with a 
set of summer or winter clothing and essential toiletries, if the 
Officer-in-charge considers it necessary. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> If the juvenile has no parent or guardian, he may be sent to an aftercare 
organization, or in the event of his employment, to the person who has 
undertaken to employ the juvenile. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> The Officer-in-charge of a girls' institution may, subject to the consent 
of the girl and the approval of the competent authority, help the girl with her 
social re-integration by way of sending a girl above the age of eighteen years 
to an after care programme or, helping her with some vocation or gainful 
employment or, helping her settle into family life according to the procedure 
laid down by the competent authority from time to time. 
 </section><section><number>10</number> The Officer-in-Charge shall order the discharge in Form VII 
<title></title>of any juvenile whose detention period has come to an end and 
inform the competent authority within seven days of the action taken and if the 
date of release falls on a Sunday or a public holiday, the juvenile may be 
discharged on the preceding day with an entry to that effect being made in the 
register of discharge. 
 </section><section><number>11</number> The Officer-in-charge shall in appropriate cases, order the payment of 
subsistence money, at such rates as may be fixed from time to time, by the State 
or the District Child Protection Unit or the State Government, and the railway 
or road, or both, fares, as the case may be. 
 </section><section><number>12</number> In deserving cases, the Officer-in-charge may provide the juvenile with 
such small tools, as may be necessary, to start a work or business subject to 
such maximum cost as may be fixed by the institution which shall also form part 
of the post-release plan. (13) Where a girl has no place to go after release 
and requests for stay in the institution after the period of her stay is over, 
the Officer-in-charge may, subject to the approval of the competent authority, 
allow her stay till the time some other suitable arrangements are made. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>18</number> Procedure to be followed in respect of sections 21, 22, 23, 24, 
25 and 26 of the Act. </title>
<section><number>1</number> In the event of violation of provisions laid 
down under section 21 of the Act, 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the Board shall take cognizance of such violation by print or 
  electronic media and shall initiate necessary inquiry and pass appropriate 
  orders as per provisions contained in sub­-section (2) of section 21 of 
  the Act; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> where the National or the State Commission for Protection of Child 
  Rights takes suo motu cognizance of violation under section 21 of the 
  Act, it shall inform the District or the State Child Protection Unit of the 
  concerned district and the State directing them to initiate necessary action 
  through the Board. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> In the event of an escape of a juvenile in conflict with law or a child, 
the following action shall be taken within twenty-four hours, 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the Officer-in-Charge of any institution shall immediately send a 
  report to the area Police Station or Special Juvenile Police Unit along with 
  the details and description of the juvenile or child, with identification 
  marks and a photograph, with a copy to the Board, District Child Protection 
  Unit and other authorities concerned; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the Officer-in-charge of institutions other than shelter homes or 
  drop-in-centres shall send the guards or concerned staff in search of the 
  juvenile, at places like railway stations, bus stands and other places where 
  the juvenile is likely to go; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the parents or guardians shall be informed immediately about such 
  escape; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> the Officer-in-Charge of an institution other than a shelter home or 
  drop-in-centre shall hold an inquiry about such escape and send his report to 
  the Board or Committee and the authorities concerned and the report shall be 
  placed before the Management Committee set-up under rule 55 of these rules in 
  the next meeting for review. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> The offences against a juvenile in conflict with law or a child specified 
in sections 23, 24, 25 and 26 shall be either bailable or non-bailable besides 
being cognizable under the provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 
 (2 of 1974) and the procedures shall apply on the Police, the Board and the 
concerned authorities and functionaries accordingly. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>19</number> Child Welfare Committee. </title>There shall be a Child Welfare 
Committee in every district, which shall be constituted by the State Government 
through a notification in the Official Gazette as per sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 
29 of the Act. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>20</number> Composition of the Child Welfare Committee. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The 
Committee shall consist of a Chairperson and four other members, of whom at 
least one shall be a woman. <title></title>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Chairperson and members of the Committee shall be appointed on the 
recommendation of a Selection Committee set-up by the State Government, for the 
purpose under rule 91. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Selection Committee, while selecting the Chairperson and Members of 
the Committee, shall as far as possible ensure that none of them are from any 
adoption agency. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The State Government shall provide for such training and orientation in 
child psychology, child welfare, child rights, national and international 
standards for juvenile justice to all members of the Committee as it considers 
necessary. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>21</number> Tenure of the Committee. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Committee shall have a 
tenure of three years and the tenure of Chairperson and Members shall be 
co-terminus with the tenure of the Committee. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Chairperson and Members of the Committee shall be eligible for 
appointment for a maximum of two consecutive terms. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Extension of the tenure of members of the Committee shall be on the basis 
of their performance appraisal by the District Child Protection Unit or the 
State Government and on the recommendation of the Selection Committee. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> With a view to ensuring continuity on completion of the tenure of a 
Committee, the State Government shall constitute a new Committee before the 
expiry of the term of the existing Committee; where after the existing Committee 
shall handover all records and information to the newly formed Committee. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Chairperson and Members may resign at any time by giving one month's 
notice in writing or may be removed from office as provided in sub-section (4) 
of section 29 of the Act. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> Any casual vacancy in the Committee may be filled by appointment of 
another person from the panel of names prepared by the Selection Committee, and 
shall hold office for the remaining term of the Committee. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>22</number> Qualifications for Chairperson and Members of the Committee. 
</title>
<section><number>1</number> A person to be selected as a Chairperson or Member of the 
Committee shall have either of the following qualifications, in addition to a 
minimum of seven years experience in their respective field: 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> a person with post graduate degree in social work, psychology, child 
  development, education, sociology, law, criminology and, where such a person 
  is not available, a person with at least a graduate degree in any of the 
  social science disciplines; </subsection>
 <subsection><number>ii</number> a teacher, doctor or a social worker who has been involved in work 
concerning children. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The Chairperson or Member of the Committee shall be a person not less 
than 35 years of age. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> No person shall be considered for Selection as a Chairperson or Member of 
the Committee, if he, 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> has a previous conviction record; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> has been involved in any immoral act or in an act of child abuse or 
  employment of child labour; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> is holding such full-time occupation that may not allow him to give 
  necessary time and attention to the work of the Committee as per the Act and 
  these rules; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> does not fulfil the qualification and experience prescribed in the Act 
  and the rules made thereunder, and in such a case the Selection Committee 
  shall after due inquiry and on establishment of such fact, reject his 
  application and recommend the name of the next person from the list of names 
  prepared for filling the vacancies. </subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>23</number> Sitting and conveyance allowances. </title>The Chairperson and 
Members of the Committee shall be paid such travel and sitting allowance, as the 
State Government may determine, but it shall not be less than rupees five 
hundred per sitting per member. 
  </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>24</number> Sitting of the Committee. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Committee shall hold 
its sittings in the premises of the children's home or, at a place in proximity 
to the children's home or, at a suitable premise in any institution run under 
the Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> On receiving information about child or children in need of care and 
protection, if circumstances are such that the child or children cannot be 
produced before the Committee, the Committee may move out to reach the child or 
children and hold its sitting at a place that is convenient for such child or 
children. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The premises where the Committee holds its sittings shall be 
child-friendly and shall not look like a court room in any manner whatsoever; 
for example, the Committee shall not sit on a raised platform and the sitting 
arrangement shall be uniform and there shall be no witness boxes. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Committee shall meet a minimum of three days a week, which may be 
extended by the State Government depending on case and pendency of work. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> A minimum of three-fourth attendance of the Chairperson and Members of 
the Committee is necessary in a year. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The duration of a sitting is dependent on the pendency of work before the 
Committee. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> Every member of the Committee shall attend a minimum of four hours per 
sitting. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>25</number> Functions and Powers of the Committee. </title>The Committee 
shall perform the following functions to achieve the objectives of the Act, 
namely: 
 
 <section><number>a</number> take cognizance of and receive children produced before the Committee; 
  
 </section><section><number>b</number> decide on the matters brought before the Committee; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> reach out to such children in need of care and protection who are not 
  in a position to be produced before the Committee, being in difficult 
  circumstances, with support from the District Child Protection Unit or State 
  Child Protection Unit or the State Government; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> conduct necessary inquiry on all issues relating to and affecting the 
  safety and well being of the child; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> direct the Child Welfare Officers or Probation Officers or 
  non-governmental organisations to conduct social inquiry and submit a report 
  to the Committee; 
 </section><section><number>f</number> ensure necessary care and protection, including immediate shelter; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> ensure appropriate rehabilitation and restoration, including passing 
  necessary directions to parents or guardians or fit persons or fit 
  institutions in this regard, in addition to follow-up and co-ordination with 
  District Child Protection Unit or State Adoption Resource Agency and other 
  agencies; 
 </section><section><number>h</number> direct the Officer-in-charge of children's homes to receive children 
  requiring shelter and care; 
 </section><section><number>i</number> document and maintain detailed case record along with a case summary of 
  every case dealt by the Committee; 
 </section><section><number>j</number> provide a child-friendly environment for children; 
 </section><section><number>k</number> recommend fit institutions' to the State Government for the care and 
  protection of children; 
 </section><section><number>l</number> declare'fit persons'; 
 </section><section><number>m</number> declare a child legally free for adoption; 
 </section><section><number>n</number> keep information about and take necessary follow-up action in respect 
  of missing children in their jurisdiction; 
 </section><section><number>o</number> maintain liaison with the Board in respect of cases needing care and 
  protection; 
 </section><section><number>p</number> visit each institution where children are sent for care and protection 
  or adoption at least once in three months to review the condition of children 
  in institutions, with support of the State Government and suggest necessary 
  action; 
 </section><section><number>q</number> monitor associations and agencies within their jurisdiction that deal 
  with children in order to check on the exploitation and abuse of children; 

 </section><section><number>r</number> co-ordinate with the Police, Labour Department and other agencies 
  involved in the care and protection of children with the support of District 
  Child Protection Unit or State Child Protection Unit or State Government; 
 </section><section><number>s</number> liaison and network with the corporate sector and non-governmental 
  organisations for any of the above, including for social inquiry, restoration 
  and rehabilitation, as and when required; and 
 </section><section><number>t</number> maintain a suggestion box to encourage inputs from children and adults 
  alike and take necessary action. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>26</number> Procedure in relation to Committee. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The quorum for 
the meeting shall be three members attending, which may include the Chairperson. 

 </section><section><number>2</number> Any decision taken by an individual member, when the Committee is not 
sitting, shall require ratification by the Committee in its next sitting. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Committee shall take into consideration the age, developmental stage, 
physical and mental health, opinion of the child and the recommendation of the 
child welfare officer or caseworker, prior to disposal of cases. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> For final disposal of a case, the order of the Committee shall be signed 
by at least two members, including the Chairperson. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>27</number> Production of a Child before the Committee. </title>
<section><number>1</number> A child 
in need of care and protection shall be produced before the Committee within 
twenty-four hours, excluding journey time, by one of the following persons 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> any police officer or Special Juvenile Police Unit or a designated 
  police officer; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> any public servant; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> childline, a registered voluntary organization or by such other 
  voluntary organization or an agency as may be recognized by the State 
  Government; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> social worker; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> any public spirited citizen; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> by the child himself. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> In case of a child under two years of age, who is medically unfit, the 
person or the organization shall send a written report along with the photograph 
of the child to the Committee within twenty-four hours and produce the child 
before the Committee as soon as the child is medically fit along with a medical 
certificate to that effect. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Committee can suo motu take cognizance of cases brought to 
their notice and reach out to a child in need of care and protection where 
necessary and the District or the State Child Protection Unit or the State 
Government shall provide necessary support and assistance to the Committee for 
carrying out such functions. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> In case the Committee is not sitting, the child may be produced before 
the single member of the Committee as per the provisions laid down under the 
sub-section (2) of section 30 of the Act for being placed in safe custody of 
parent or guardian or fit person or fit institutions, as the case may be, till 
such time that the child can be produced before the Committee. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> In case the single member is also not accessible, or that the hours are 
odd, the child shall be taken by an non-governmental organisation or Childline 
or Police to an appropriate institution for children registered under the Act 
with all the necessary documents, and placed in such institution till the time 
of production before the Committee. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The concerned institution shall inform the Chairperson or a member of the 
Committee about such child and produce the child before the Committee within 
twenty-four hours and in such cases, it may not be necessary for the person who 
brings a child in need of care and protection to an institution to be present at 
the time of production of the child before the Committee. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> Whoever produces a child before the Committee shall submit a report on 
the circumstances under which the child came to their notice and efforts made by 
them on informing the police and the missing persons squad and in cases where a 
recognized voluntary organization or any police personnel produce a child before 
the Committee, they shall also submit a report on the efforts made by them for 
tracing the family of the child. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> Any general medical or gynaecological examination of children shall not 
be a pre-requisite for production of the child before the Committee or admission 
in an institution. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> The Committee shall facilitate the filing of a police complaint and First 
Information Report in cases of missing children as well as matters of violence, 
exploitation and abuse of children and arrange for required legal aid through 
the Legal Officer in the District Child Protection Unit or District or State 
Legal Aid Services Authority or voluntary organisations. 
 </section><section><number>10</number> Each Committee shall send quarterly information about children in need 
of care and protection received by them to the District or State Child 
Protection Unit or State Government. 
 </section><section><number>11</number> Children shall be provided a child-friendly environment during the 
proceedings of the Committee. 
 </section><section><number>12</number> The Committee shall have an empanelled list of lawyers, social workers 
and mental health expert who may assist the Committee in dealing with cases of 
abused children and who may also interface with the Public Prosecutor or 
Assistant Public Prosecutor to facilitate legal services to the abused children, 
when the cases relating to such children are taken up in regular criminal 
courts. 
 </section><section><number>13</number> Every possible effort shall be made to trace the family with support 
from the District Child Protection Unit, and assistance of recognized voluntary 
organizations, childline or police may also be taken. 
 </section><section><number>14</number> The Committee shall send the child to the designated place of safety, 
with age and gender appropriate facilities, pending inquiry and in such 
eventuality, the District Child Protection Unit or State Child Protection Unit 
or State Government shall provide transport or make necessary budgetary 
allocations for such expenses based on the actual fare. 
 </section><section><number>15</number> The child may be escorted by the police officer or representative of the 
voluntary organization or by any other arrangement as considered appropriate by 
the Committee with support from the District Child Protection Unit and in case 
of a girl child, a female escort shall accompany the child. 
 </section><section><number>16</number> A list of all recognized child care institutions along with their 
capacity and appropriate facilities as prescribed under section 34 of the Act, a 
list of all childs related resource services and a list of contact details of 
all Child Welfare Committees across the country shall be provided to the 
Committee by the District Child Protection Unit or State Government. 
 </section><section><number>17</number> The Committee may, while making an order in Form VIII placing a child 
under the care of a parent, guardian or fit person pending inquiry or at the 
time of restoration, as the case may be, direct such parent, guardian or fit 
person to enter into an undertaking in Form IX. 
 </section><section><number>18</number> Whenever the Committee orders a child to be kept in an institution, it 
shall forward to the Officer-in-Charge of such institution a copy of the order 
of short-term placement pending inquiry, in Form X with particulars of the home 
and parents or guardian and previous record. 
 </section><section><number>19</number> Whenever the Committee orders a child to be kept in a fit institution as 
part of restoration under clause (f) of sub-section (3) of section 39 of the 
Act, it shall forward a copy of its order of restoration in Form XI to the 
Officer-in-Charge of such institution. (20) The child shall be placed in an 
institution closest to where his parents or guardians belong as far as possible, 
unless the child has been subjected to abuse or exploitation by parents or 
guardians. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>28</number> Procedure for inquiry. </title>
<section><number>1</number> When a child is brought 
before the Committee, the Committee shall assign the case to a social worker or 
caseworker or child welfare officer or Officer-in-Charge as the case may be, of 
the institution or any recognized agency for conducting the inquiry through an 
order in Form XII. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Committee shall direct the concerned person or organization about the 
details or particulars to be enquired into for developing an individual care 
plan and suitable rehabilitation. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> All inquiries conducted by a social worker or caseworker or child welfare 
officer or Officer-in-Charge of the institution or any recognized agency shall 
be as per Form XIII and must provide an assessment of the family situation of 
the child in detail, and explain in writing whether it will be in the best 
interest of the child to restore him to his family. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The inquiry must be completed within four months or within such shorter 
period as may be fixed by the Committee: 
 Provided that the Committee may, in the best interest of the child and for 
the reasons to be recorded in writing, extend the said period under special 
circumstances. (5) After completion of the inquiry, if, the child is under 
orders to continue in the children's home, the Committee shall direct the 
Officer-in-Charge of the home to submit quarterly progress report of such child 
and produce the child before the Committee for an annual review of the progress. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>29</number> Children's Homes. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The State Government itself or in 
association with voluntary organizations, shall set-up separate homes for 
children in need of care and protection, in the manner specified below: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> all children's homes shall be registered as child care institutions 
  under sub-section (3) of section 34 of the Act and rule 71 of these rules; 

 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> all children's homes shall be certified as per the procedure laid down 
  in rule 70; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> all children's homes shall report to the concerned Committee about 
  every child in need of care and protection received by them; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> children of both sexes below ten years may be kept in the same home but 
  separate facilities shall be maintained for boys and girls in the age group 5 
  to 10 years; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> every children's home shall include separate facilities for children in 
  the age group of 0-5 years with appropriate facilities for the infants; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> separate children's homes shall be set-up for boys and girls in the age 
  group 10 to 18 years; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> children in the age group of 10 to 18 shall be further segregated into 
  two groups of 10 to 15 years and 15 to 18 years. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Each children home shall be a comprehensive child care centre with the 
primary objective to promote an integrated approach to child care by involving 
the community and local Non-Governmental Organisations through the Management 
Committee set-up under rule 55 of these rules and the District Child Protection 
Unit or State Child Protection Unit or the State Government shall make an annual 
performance review of functioning of the children's homes. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The activities of such centre shall focus on: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> preparing and following individual care plans for every child, with 
  rights based approach, specifically addressing the child's physical and mental 
  health, emotional needs, education, skill development, protection and special 
  needs if any; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> family based non-institutional services, such as, foster family care, 
  adoption and sponsorship; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> specialized services in situations of conflict or disaster and for 
  juvenile or children affected by terminal or incurable disease to prevent 
  neglect by providing family counselling, nutrition, health interventions, 
  psycho-social interventions and sponsorship; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> emergency outreach service through childline (Toll free Help Line No. 
  1098); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> linkages with Integrated Child Development Services to cater to the 
  needs of children below six years; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> linkages with organizations and individuals who can provide support 
  services to children; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> opportunities to volunteers willing to provide various services for 
  children. </subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>30</number> Shelter Homes. </title>
<section><number>1</number> For children in urgent need of care 
and protection, such as street children and run-away children, the State 
Government shall support creation of requisite number of shelter homes or 
drop-in-centres through the voluntary organizations. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Shelter homes shall include: 
 
 *(g) short-stay homes for children needing temporary shelter, care and 
  protection for a maximum period of one year, 
 *(h) transitional homes providing immediate care and protection to a child 
  for a maximum period of four months, 
 *(i) 24 hour drop-in-centres for children needing day care or night shelter 
  facility. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The shelter homes or drop-in-centres shall have the minimum facilities of 
boarding and lodging, besides the provision for fulfilment of basic needs in 
terms of clothing, food, health care and nutrition, safe drinking water and 
sanitation. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> There shall be separate shelter homes for girls and boys as per rule 
40(2)(d) of these rules. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> All shelter homes shall provide requisite facilities for education, 
vocational training, counselling and recreation or make arrangements for it in 
collaboration with voluntary organizations or corporate sector. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Committee, Special Juvenile Police Units, public servants, 
childlines, voluntary organizations, social workers and the children themselves 
may refer a child to such shelter homes. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> All shelter homes shall submit a report of children using the shelter 
home facility along with a photograph of the child to the Committee, the missing 
persons bureau or special juvenile police unit and the District Child Protection 
Unit or the State Child Protection Unit. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> The requirements of producing a child received by a shelter home before 
the Committee, inquiry and disposal under sections 32, 33, 38 and 39 of the Act 
shall apply only to shelter homes other than drop-in-centres as specified in 
rule 30(2)(c) of these rules. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> The services of Officer-in-charge, child welfare officer, social worker 
shall be provided for the proper care, protection, development, rehabilitation 
and reintegration needs of children in shelter homes. 
 </section><section><number>10</number> No child shall ordinarily stay in a short stay home for more than a year 
except in special circumstances with the approval of the Committee. 


  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>31</number> Guidelines for prevention of sexual abuse of children. 
</title>The Central Government, State Government, the Juvenile Justice Board, 
the Child Welfare Committee, other competent authorities and agencies shall, in 
the best interest of children, ensure that every person, school or such other 
educational institutions abide by the guidelines issued from time to time by 
Central Government and State Government. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>32</number> Rehabilitation and Social Reintegration. </title>The primary 
aim of rehabilitation and social reintegration is to help children in restoring 
their dignity and self-worth and mainstream them through rehabilitation within 
the family where possible, or otherwise through alternate care programmes and 
long-term institutional care shall be of last resort. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>33</number> Adoption. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The primary aim of adoption is to provide 
a child who cannot be cared for by his biological parents with a permanent 
substitute family. <title></title>
 </section><section><number>2</number> For all matters relating to adoption, the guidelines issued by the 
Central Adoption Resource Agency and notified by the Central Government under 
sub-section (3) of section 41 of the Act, shall apply. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> In case of orphaned and abandoned children the following procedure shall 
apply, namely: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> Specialized Adoption Agencies shall produce all orphaned and abandoned 
  children who are to be declared legally free for adoption before the Committee 
  within twenty-four hours of receiving such children, excluding the time taken 
  for journey; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> a child becomes eligible for adoption when the Committee has completed 
  its inquiry and declares the child legally free for adoption; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> such declaration shall be made in Form XIV; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> a child must be produced before the Committee at the time of declaring 
  such child legally free for adoption; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> whenever intimation is received by the police about an abandoned 
  infant, the police shall take charge of the infant and arrange to provide 
  immediate medical assistance and care; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> subsequently, the child shall be placed in a specialized adoption 
  agency or recognized and certified children's home or in a paediatric unit of 
  a Government hospital followed by production of the child before the Committee 
  within twenty-four hours; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> procedure for declaring a child abandoned and certifying him legally 
  free for adoption: 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> in case of an abandoned child, the recognized agency shall within 
    twenty-four hours, report and produce the child before the Committee with 
    the copy of the report filed with the police station in whose jurisdiction 
    the child was found abandoned; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> the Committee will institute a process of inquiry, which shall 
    include a thorough inquiry conducted by the Probation Officer or Child 
    Welfare Officer, as the case may be and who shall give report in Form XIII 
    <title></title>to the Committee containing the findings within one month; 
    
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number> there shall be a declaration by the specialized adoption agency, 
    stating that there has been no claimant for the child even after making 
    notification in at least one leading national newspaper and one regional 
    language newspaper for children below two years of age and for children 
    above two years, an additional television or radio announcement and 
    notification to the missing persons squad or bureau shall be made; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iv</number> the steps stated in (iii) shall be taken within a period of sixty 
    days from the time when the child is found in case of a child below two 
    years of age and in case of children above two years of age, this period 
    shall be four months; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>v</number> the period of notification shall run concurrently with the inquiry to 
    be conducted and report submitted under clause (ii) of this sub-rule; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>vi</number> the Committee shall declare the child legally free for adoption on 
    completion of the process of inquiry, including declaration of the 
    specialized adoption agency made under clauses (ii) and (iii) of this 
    sub-rule; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>vii</number> no child above seven years who can understand and express his 
    opinion shall be declared free for adoption without his consent. 
  </subsubsection></subsection>
 </section><section><number>4</number> In case of surrendered children the following procedure shall apply, 
namely: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> a surrendered child is one who had been declared as such after due 
  process of inquiry by the Committee and in order to be declared legally free 
  for adoption, a surrendered' child shall be any of the following: 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> born as a consequence of non-consensual relationship; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> born of an unwed mother or out of wedlock; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number> a child in whose case one of the biological parents is dead and the 
    living parent is incapacitated to take care; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iv</number> a child where the parents or guardians are compelled to relinquish 
    him due to physical, emotional and social factors beyond their control; 
  </subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> serious efforts shall be made by the Committee for counselling the 
  parents, explaining the consequences of adoption and exploring the 
  possibilities of parents retaining the child and if, the parents are unwilling 
  to retain, then, such children shall be kept initially in foster care or 
  arranged for their sponsorship; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> if the surrender is inevitable, a deed of surrender in Form XV shall be 
  executed on a non-judicial stamp paper in the presence of the Committee; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> the adoption agencies shall wait for completion of two months 
  reconsideration time given to the biological parent or parents after 
  surrender; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> in case of a child surrendered by his biological parent or parents, the 
  document of surrender shall be executed by the parent or parents before the 
  Committee; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> after due inquiry, the Committee shall declare the surrendered child 
  legally free for adoption in Form XIII as the case may be after a sixty days' 
  reconsideration period as per Central Adoption Resource Agency guidelines. 
</subsection>(5) For the purposes of section 41 of the Act, court' implies 
a civil court, which has jurisdiction in matters of adoption and guardianship 
and may include the court of the district judge, family courts and city civil 
court. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>34</number> Foster Care. </title>
<section><number>1</number> For children who cannot be placed in 
adoption, order shall be issued by the competent authority in Form XVII for 
carrying out foster care, as given in sub-section (2) of section 42 of the Act 
and rule 35(1) of these rules, under the supervision of a probation officer or 
case worker or social worker, as the case may be, and the period of foster care 
shall depend on the need of the child. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every State Government shall design its own foster care programme so as 
to reduce institutionalization of children and enable a nurturing family 
environment for every child. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The State Government shall consult the Boards or Committees, 
non-governmental organisations, academicians and organisations working on 
alternative care for children in developing the foster care programme. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>35</number> Criteria for selection of families for foster care. </title>
<section><number>1</number> 
In case of the children covered under rule 34 of these rules, the following 
criteria shall apply for selection of families for foster care, namely: 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> foster parents should have stable emotional adjustment within the 
  family; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> foster parents should have an income in which they are able to meet 
  the needs of the child and are not dependent on the foster care maintenance 
  payment; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> the monthly family income shall be adequate to take care of foster 
  children and approved by the Committee; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> medical reports of all the members of the family residing in the 
  premises should be obtained including checks on Human Immuno Deficiency Virus 
  (HIV), Tuberculosis (TB) and Hepatitis B to determine that they are medically 
  fit; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> the foster parents should have experience in child caring and the 
  capacity to provide good child care; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vi</number> the foster parents should be physically, mentally and emotionally 
  stable; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vii</number> the home should have adequate space and basic facilities; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>viii</number> the foster care family should be willing to follow rules laid down 
  including regular visits to pediatrician, maintenance of child health and 
  their records; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ix</number> the family should be willing to sign an agreement and to return the 
  child to the specialized adoption agency whenever called to do so; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>x</number> the foster parents should be willing to attend training or orientation 
  programmes; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>xi</number> the foster parents should be willing to take the child for regular (at 
  least once a month in the case of infants) checkups to a pediatrician approved 
  by the agency. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> There shall be no discrimination in selection of foster-parents on the 
basis of caste, religion, ethnic status, disability, or health status and the 
best interest of the child shall be paramount in deciding foster care placement. 

 </section><section><number>3</number> The foster-parents shall be declared fit persons' by the Committee 
before placing the child as per the provisions laid down in clause (i) of 
section 2 of the Act after thorough assessment done by the Child Welfare Officer 
or Social Worker as per Form XVI. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>36</number> Pre-adoption Foster Care.</title>In case of pre-adoption foster 
care, the provisions contained in sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 42 and the 
corresponding guidelines notified under sub-section (3) of section 41 of the 
Act, shall apply.</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>37</number> Sponsorship. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The State Government shall prepare 
sponsorship programme in consultation with the Non-Governmental Organisations, 
Child Welfare Committees, other relevant government agencies and the corporate 
sector. <title></title>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The State Government, with the help of District or State Child Protection 
Units shall identify families and children at risk and provide necessary support 
services in the form of sponsorship for child's education, health, nutrition and 
other developmental needs. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The children's homes and special homes shall promote sponsorship 
programmes as laid down in section 43 of the Act. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The institutions receiving sponsorship, shall maintain proper and 
separate accounts of all the receipts and payments for the programme. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Board or the Committee shall make an order in Form XVIII for support 
to a juvenile or child through sponsorship and send a copy to the District or 
State Child Protection Unit or the State Government for appropriate action. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>38</number> After Care Organisation. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The State Government shall 
set-up an after care programme for care of juveniles or children after they 
leave special homes and children's homes with the objective to facilitate their 
transition from an institution-based life to mainstream society for social 
reintegration. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> After care programmes shall be made available for 18-21 years old 
persons, who have no place to go to or are unable to support themselves, by the 
District or State Child Protection Units in collaboration with voluntary 
organizations for the purpose of section 44 of the Act and this rule. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Once the Board or the Committee passes an order in Form XIX for placing a 
juvenile or a child completing 18 years of age under the after care programme, a 
copy of such order shall be sent to the District and the State Child Protection 
Unit and the State Government, who shall be responsible for arranging after 
care. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Board or the Committee shall have jurisdiction over persons placed in 
after care programme. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The objective of these organisations shall be to enable such children to 
adapt to the society and during their stay in these transitional homes these 
children will be encouraged to move away from an institution-based life to a 
normal one. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The key components of the programme shall include: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> community group housing on a temporary basis for groups of young 
  persons aged 18-21 years; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> encouragement to learn a vocation or gain employment and contribute 
  towards the rent as well as the running of the home; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> encouragement to gradually sustain themselves without state support and 
  move out of the group home to stay in a place of their own after saving 
  sufficient amount through their earnings; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> provision for a peer counsellor to stay in regular contact with these 
  groups to discuss their rehabilitation plans and provide creative outlets for 
  their energy and to tide over crisis periods in their life. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>7</number> During the course of vocational training a stipend may be provided till 
such time that the youth gets employment. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> Loans may be arranged for the youth in an after care programme aspiring 
to set-up entrepreneurial activities on the basis of an application made by them 
and due verification of the need for such a loan, and necessary professional 
advice and training shall be made available to the youth in the after care 
programme in this regard. (9) The structure shall include 6 to 8 youths in 
each group home who may opt to stay together on their own and one peer 
counsellor for a cluster of five group homes. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>39</number> Linkages and co-ordination. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The State Government 
shall circulate a copy of the Act and the rules framed thereunder to establish 
effective linkages between various government, non-government, corporate and 
other community agencies for facilitating the rehabilitation and social 
reintegration of juveniles or children through the Board or the Committee as the 
case may be. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The State Government with the help of State or District Child Protection 
Unit shall identify the roles and responsibilities of each department at State 
or district levels for effective implementation of the Act and the rules and 
inform them through a notification. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The State Government with the help of State or District Child Protection 
Unit shall arrange for appropriate training and sensitization of functionaries 
of these departments from time to time in co-ordination with National Institute 
of Public Co-operation and Child Development and its Regional Centres. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The State Government with the help of State or District Child Protection 
Unit shall develop effective networking and linkages with local non-governmental 
organisations for specialized services and technical assistance like vocational 
training, education, health care, nutrition, mental health intervention, drug 
de-addition and legal aid services. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>41</number> Clothing and Bedding. </title>The clothing and bedding shall be 
as per the scale and climatic conditions. The requirements of each juvenile or 
child and the minimum standards for clothing and bedding are laid down in 
Schedule I of these rules. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>41</number> Clothing and Bedding. </title>The clothing and bedding shall be 
as per the scale and climatic conditions. The requirements of each juvenile or 
child and the minimum standards for clothing and bedding are laid down in 
Schedule I of these rules. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>42</number> Sanitation and Hygiene. </title>Every institution shall have 
the following facilities, namely: <title></title>
 
 <section><number>a</number> sufficient treated drinking water; water filters shall be installed; 
  
 </section><section><number>b</number> sufficient water for bathing and washing clothes, maintenance and 
  cleanliness of the premises; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> proper drainage system; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> arrangements for disposal of garbage; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> protection from mosquitoes by providing mosquito nets; 
 </section><section><number>f</number> annual pest control; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> sufficient number of well lit and airy toilets in the proportion of at 
  least one toilet for seven children; 
 </section><section><number>h</number> sufficient number of well lit and airy bathrooms in the proportion of 
  at least one bath room for ten children; 
 </section><section><number>i</number> sufficient space for washing; 
 </section><section><number>j</number> clean and fly-proof kitchen and separate area for washing utensils; 

 </section><section><number>k</number> sunning of bedding and clothing; 
 </section><section><number>l</number> maintenance of cleanliness in the Medical Centre. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>43</number> Daily Routine. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Every institution shall have a daily 
routine for the juveniles or children developed in consultation with the 
Children's Committees, which shall be prominently displayed at various places 
within the institution. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The daily routine shall provide, inter alia, for a regulated and 
disciplined life, personal hygiene and cleanliness, physical exercise, yoga, 
educational classes, vocational training, organized recreation and games, moral 
education, group activities, prayer and community singing and special programmes 
for Sundays and holidays. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>44</number> Nutrition and Diet Scale. </title>The following nutrition and 
diet scale shall be followed by the institutions, namely: 
 
 <section><number>a</number> the children shall be provided four meals in a day including breakfast; 
  
 </section><section><number>b</number> the menu shall be prepared with the help of a nutritional expert or 
  doctor to ensure balanced diet and variety in taste as per the minimum 
  nutritional standard and diet scale set out in Schedule II of these rules; 

 </section><section><number>c</number> every institution under this Act shall strictly adhere to the minimum 
  nutritional standard and diet scale specified in Schedule II; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> juveniles or children may be provided special meals on holidays and 
  festivals; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> infants and sick juveniles or children shall be provided special diet 
  according to the advise of the doctor on their dietary requirement. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>45</number> Medical Care </title>.Every institution shall: 
 
 <section><number>a</number> maintain a medical record of each juvenile or child on the basis of 
  monthly medical check-up and provide necessary medical facilities; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> ensure that the medical record includes weight and height record, any 
  sickness and treatment, and other physical or mental problem; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> have arrangement for the medical facilities, including a doctor on call 
  available on all working days for regular medical check-ups and treatment of 
  juveniles or children; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> have sufficient medical equipments to handle minor health problems 
  including first aid kit with stock of emergency medicines and consumables; 

 </section><section><number>e</number> train all staff in handling first aid; 
 </section><section><number>f</number> tie-up with local Primary Health Centre, government hospital, medical 
  colleges, other hospitals, clinical psychologists and psychiatrists and mental 
  health institutes for regular visits by their doctors and students and for 
  holding periodic health camps within the institutions; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> make necessary arrangements made for the immunization coverage; 
 </section><section><number>h</number> take preventive measures in the event of out break of contagious or 
  infectious diseases; 
 </section><section><number>i</number> set-up a system for referral of cases with deteriorating health or 
  serious cases to the nearest civil hospital or recognised treatment centres; 
  
 </section><section><number>j</number> keep sick children under constant medical supervision; 
 </section><section><number>k</number> admit a juvenile or child without insisting on a medical certificate at 
  the time of admission; 
 </section><section><number>l</number> arrange for a medical examination of each juvenile or child admitted in 
  an institution by the Medical Officer within twenty-four hours and in special 
  cases or medical emergencies immediately; 
 </section><section><number>m</number> arrange for a medical examination of the juvenile or child by the 
  Medical Officer at the time of transfer within twenty-four hours before 
  transfer; 
 </section><section><number>n</number> not carry out any surgical treatment on any juvenile or child without 
  the previous consent of his parent or guardian, unless either the parent or 
  guardian cannot be found and the condition of the juvenile or child is such 
  that any delay shall, in the opinion of the medical officer, involve 
  unnecessary suffering or injury to the health of the juvenile or child, or 
  otherwise without obtaining a written consent to this effect from the 
  Officer-in-Charge of the institution; 
 </section><section><number>o</number> provide or arrange for regular counselling of every juvenile or child 
  and ensure specific mental health interventions for those in need of such 
  services, including separate rooms for counselling sessions within the 
  premises of the institution; 
 </section><section><number>p</number> refer such children who require specialized drug abuse prevention and 
  rehabilitation programme, to an appropriate centre administered by qualified 
  personnel where these programmes shall be adopted to the age, gender and other 
  specifications of the concerned child. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>46</number> Mental Health. </title>
<section><number>1</number> A mental health record of every 
juvenile or child shall be maintained by the concerned institutions. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Both milieu-based interventions that is creating an enabling environment 
for children and individual therapy are must for every child and shall be 
provided in all institutions. 
 Explanation. For the purpose of this sub-rule, milieu-based 
intervention is a process of recovery, which starts through providing an 
enabling culture and environment in an institution so as to ensure that each 
child's abilities are discovered and they have choices and right to take to 
decisions regarding their life and thus, they develop and identify beyond their 
negative experiences and such intervention has a critical emotional impact on 
the child. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The environment in an institution shall be free from abuse, allowing 
juveniles or children to cope with their situation and regain confidence. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> All persons involved in taking care of the juveniles or children in an 
institution shall participate in facilitating an enabling environment and work 
in collaboration with the therapists. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Individual therapy is a specialized process and each institution shall 
make provisions for it as a critical mental health intervention. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> Every institution shall have the services of trained counsellors or 
collaboration with external agencies such as child guidance centres, psychology 
and psychiatric departments or similar government and non-governmental agencies, 
for specialized and regular individual therapy for every juvenile or child in 
the institution. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> A mental health care plan shall be developed for every juvenile or child 
by the child welfare officers in consultation with mental health experts 
associated with the institution and integrated into the individual care plan of 
the concerned juvenile or child. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> The recommendations of mental health experts shall be maintained in every 
case file and integrated into the care plan for every child. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> All care plans shall be produced before the Management Committee set-up 
under rule 55 of these rules every month and before the Child Welfare Committee 
every quarter. 
 </section><section><number>10</number> No juvenile or child shall be administered medication for mental health 
problems without a psychological evaluation and diagnosis by appropriately 
trained mental health professionals. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>47</number> Education. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Every institution shall provide 
education to all juveniles or children according to the age and ability, both 
inside the institution or outside, as per the requirement. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> There shall be a range of educational opportunities including, mainstream 
inclusive schools, bridge school, open schooling, non-formal education and 
learning and input from special educators where needed. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Wherever necessary, extra coaching shall be made available to school 
going children in the institutions by encouraging volunteer services or tying up 
with coaching centers. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>48</number> Vocational Training. </title>
<section><number>a</number> Every institution shall 
provide gainful vocational training to juveniles or children. 
 </section><section><number>b</number> The institutions shall develop networking with Institute of Technical 
Instruction , Jan Shikshan Sansthan, Government and Private Organization or 
Enterprises, Agencies or non­-governmental organisations with expertise or 
placement agencies. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>49</number> Recreation facilities. </title>
<section><number>1</number> A provision of guided 
recreation shall be made available to all juveniles or children in the 
institutions. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> It shall include indoor and outdoor games, music, television, picnics and 
outings, cultural programmes and library. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>50</number> Institutional Management of juveniles or children. </title>
<section><number>1</number> 
The following procedure shall be followed in respect of the newly admitted 
juveniles: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> receiving and search; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> disinfection and storing of juvenile's personal belongings and other 
  valuables; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> bath and haircut (unless prohibited by religion); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> issue of toiletry items; new set of clothes, bedding and other outfit 
  and equipment (as per scales); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> medical examination and treatment where necessary and in case of every 
  juvenile suspected to be suffering from contagious or infectious diseases, 
  mental ailments or addiction; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> segregation in specially earmarked dormitories or wards or hospitals in 
  case of a child suffering from contagious disease requiring special care and 
  caution; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> attending to immediate and urgent needs of the juveniles like appearing 
  in examinations, interview letter to parents, personal problems and 
  verification by the Officer-in-Charge of age of juvenile as per order of the 
  Board. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every newly admitted juvenile or child shall be allotted a case worker 
from amongst the probation officers or child welfare officers or social workers 
or counsellors attached to the institutions or voluntary social workers or 
counsellors. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every newly admitted juvenile shall be familiarized with the institution 
and its functioning and shall receive orientation in the following areas: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> personal health, hygiene and sanitation; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> institutional discipline and standards of behaviour, respect for elders 
  and teachers; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> daily routine, peer interaction, optimum use of developmental 
  opportunities; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> rights, responsibilities and obligations within the institution. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>4</number> The designated officer shall enter the name of the juvenile or child in 
the Admission Register and allocate appropriate accommodation facility. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The photograph shall also be taken immediately for records and the case 
worker or probation officer or welfare officer shall begin the investigation and 
correspondence with the person, the juvenile or child might have named. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Officer-in-Charge shall see that the personal belongings of the 
juvenile or child received by the institution is kept in safe custody and 
recorded in the Personal Belonging Register and the item must be returned to the 
juvenile or child when he leaves the institution. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> The girl juvenile or child shall be searched by a female member of the 
staff, and with due regard to decency and dignity of the juvenile or child. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> The educational level and vocational aptitude of the juvenile admitted, 
may be assessed on the basis of test and interview conducted by the teacher, the 
workshop supervisor and other technical staff and necessary linkages may also be 
established with outside specialists and community-based welfare agencies, 
psychologist, psychiatrist, child guidance clinic, hospital and local doctors, 
open school or Jan Sikshan Sansthan. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> A case history of the juvenile or the child admitted to an institution 
shall be maintained as per Form XX, which shall contain information regarding 
his socio-cultural and economic background and these informations may invariably 
be collected through all possible and available sources, including home, parents 
or guardians, employer, school, friends and community. 
 </section><section><number>10</number> A well-conceived programme of pre-release planning and follow up of 
cases discharged from special homes shall be organized in all institutions in 
close collaboration with existing governmental and voluntary welfare 
organizations. 
 </section><section><number>11</number> In the event of a juvenile or child leaving the institution without 
permission or committing an offence within the institution, the information 
shall be sent by the Officer-in-Charge of the concerned institution to the 
police and the family, if known; and the detailed report of circumstances 
alongwith the efforts to trace the juvenile or child where the juvenile or child 
is missing, shall be sent to the Board or Committee, as the case may be. 
 </section><section><number>12</number> An individual care plan for every juvenile or child in institutional 
care shall be developed with the ultimate aim of the child being rehabilitated 
and re-integrated based on their case history, circumstances and individual 
needs and the individual care plan shall be based on following guidelines: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the Officer-in-Charge, counsellor along with the child welfare officer 
  or case worker, or social worker shall prepare an individual care plan for 
  every child in an institution within one month of his admittance as per Form 
  XXI; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> all care plans shall include a plan for the juvenile's or child's 
  restoration, rehabilitation, reintegration and follow-up; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the care plan shall be reviewed quarterly by the Management Committee 
  set-up under rule 55 of these rules for appropriate development and 
  rehabilitation including options for release or restoration to family or 
  foster care or adoption; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> juveniles or children shall be consulted while determining their care 
  plan; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> continuity of care plan shall be ensured in cases of transfer or 
  repatriation or restoration. </subsection></section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>51</number> Prohibited Articles. </title>No person shall bring into the 
institution the following prohibited articles, namely: 
 
 <section><number>a</number> fire-arms or other weapons, whether requiring license or not (like 
  knife, blades, lathi, spears and swords); 
 </section><section><number>b</number> alcohol and spirit of any description; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> bhang, ganja, opium or other narcotic or psychotropic substances; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> tobacco; or 
 </section><section><number>e</number> any other article specified in this behalf by the State Government by a 
  general or special order. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>52</number> Articles found on search and inspection. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The 
Officer-in-Charge shall see that every juvenile received in the institution is 
searched, his personal belongings inspected and money or any valuables found 
with the juvenile is kept in the safe custody of the Officer-in-Charge. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The girls shall be searched by a female member of the staff and both the 
girls and boys shall be searched with due regard to decency and dignity. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> In every institution, a record of money, valuables and other articles 
found with a juvenile shall be maintained in the Personal Belongings Register. 

 </section><section><number>4</number> The entries made in the Personal Belongings Register, relating to each 
juvenile, shall be read over to juvenile in the presence of a witness, whose 
signature shall be obtained in token of the correctness of such entries and it 
shall be countersigned by the Officer-in-Charge. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>53</number> Disposal of articles. </title>The money or valuables belonging 
to a juvenile received or retained in an institution shall be disposed of in the 
following manner, namely: 
 
 <section><number>a</number> on an order made by the competent authority in respect of any juvenile, 
  directing the juvenile to be sent to an institution, the Officer-in-Charge 
  shall deposit such juvenile's money together with the sale proceeds in the 
  manner laid down from time to ime in the name of the juvenile; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> the juvenile's money shall be kept with the Officer-in-Charge and 
  valuables, clothing, bedding and other articles, if any, shall be kept in safe 
  custody; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> when such juvenile is transferred from one institution to another, all 
  his money, valuables and other articles, shall be sent along with the juvenile 
  to the Officer-in-Charge of the institution to which he has been transferred 
  together with a full and correct statement of the description and estimated 
  value thereof; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> at the time of release of such juvenile, the valuables and other 
  articles kept in safe custody and the money deposited in name of the juvenile 
  shall be handed over to the parent or guardian, as the case may be, with an 
  entry made in this behalf in the register and signed by the Officer-in-Charge; 
  
 </section><section><number>e</number> when a juvenile in an institution dies, the valuable and other articles 
  left by the deceased and the money deposited in the name of the juvenile shall 
  be handed over by the Officer-in-Charge to any person who establishes his 
  claim thereto and executes an indemnity bond; 
 </section><section><number>f</number> a receipt shall be obtained from such person for having received such 
  valuables and other articles and the amount; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> if no claimant appears within a period of six months from the date of 
  death or escape of such juvenile, the valuables and other articles and amount 
  shall be disposed of as per the decision taken by Management Committee set-up 
  under rule 55 of these rules. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>54</number> Maintenance of case file. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The case file of each 
juvenile and child shall be maintained in the institution containing the 
following information: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> report of the person or agency who produced the juvenile before the 
  Board; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> Officer-in-Charge's, probation officer's or child welfare officer's, 
  counsellor's and case­-workers reports; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> information from previous institution; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> report of the initial interaction with the juvenile, information from 
  family members, relatives, community, friends and miscellaneous information; 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> source of further information; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> observation reports from staff members; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> regular health status reports from Medical Officer, drug de-addiction 
  progress reports, progress reports vis-a-vis psychological 
  counselling or any other mental health intervention, where applicable; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> Intelligence Quotient (I.Q.) testing, aptitude testing, educational or 
  vocational tests; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> social history; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> summary and analysis by case-worker and Officer-in-Charge; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number> instruction regarding training and treatment programme and about 
  special precautions to be taken; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number> leave and other privileges granted; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>m</number> special achievements and violation of rules, if any; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>n</number> quarterly progress report; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>o</number> individual care plan, including pre-release programme, post-release 
  plan and follow-up plan as prescribed in Form XXI; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>p</number> leave of absence or release under supervision; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>q</number> final discharge; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>r</number> follow-up reports; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>s</number> annual photograph; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>t</number> case history duly filled in prescribed Form XX; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>u</number> follow-up report of post-release cases as per direction of the 
  competent authority if any; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> remarks. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> All the case files maintained by the institutions and the Board or 
Committee shall, as far as possible, be computerised and networked so that the 
data is centrally available to the State and the District Child Protection Unit 
and the State Government. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>56</number> Children's Committees. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Officer-in-Charge of every 
institution for juveniles or children shall facilitate the setting up of 
Children's Committees for three different age groups of children, viz 
., 6-10 years, 11-15 years and 16-18 years and these Children's Committees 
shall be constituted solely by children. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Such Children's Committee shall be encouraged to participate in following 
activities: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> improvement of the condition of the institution; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> reviewing the standards of care being followed; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> preparing daily routine and diet scale; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> developing educational, vocational and recreation plans; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> supporting each other in managing crisis; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> reporting abuse and exploitation by peers and caregivers; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> creative expression of their views through wall papers or newsletters 
  or paintings or music or theater; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> management of institution through the Management Committee. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Officer-in-Charge shall ensure that the Children's Committees meet 
every month and maintain a register for recording its activities and 
proceedings, and place it before the Management Committee in their monthly 
meetings. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Officer-in-Charge shall ensure that the Children's Committees are 
provided with essential support and materials including stationary, space and 
guidance for effective functioning. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Officer-in-Charge shall, as far as possible, seek assistance from 
local voluntary organization or child participation experts for the setting up 
and functioning of the Children's Committees. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The local voluntary organization or child participation expert shall 
support the Children's Committees in the following: 
 
 *(j) selecting their leaders; 
 *(k) conducting the monthly meetings; 
 *(l) developing rules for the functioning of Children's Committees and 
  following it; 
 *(m) maintaining records and Children's Suggestion Book and other relevant 
  documents; 
 *(n) any other innovative activity. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> The Management Committee shall seek a report from the Officer-in-Charge 
on the setting up and functioning of the Children's Committees, review these 
reports in their monthly meetings and take necessary action where required. 


  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>57</number> Rewards and Earnings. </title>The rewards to a juvenile or 
child, at such rates as may be fixed by the management of the institution from 
time to time, may be granted by the Officer-in-Charge as an encouragement to 
steady work and good behaviour; and at the time of release, the reward shall be 
handed over after obtaining a receipt from the parent or the guardian who comes 
to take charge of the juvenile or child or juvenile or child himself. 
</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>58</number> Visits to and communication with juveniles or children. 
</title>
<section><number>1</number> The parents and relatives of the juveniles or children shall be 
allowed to visit once in a month or in special cases, more frequently at the 
discretion of the Officer-in-Charge as per the visiting hours laid down by him, 
except where parents or relatives or guardian have been found to be responsible 
for subjecting the juvenile or child to violence, abuse and exploitation. 
<title></title>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The receipt of letters by the juveniles or children of the institution 
shall not be restricted and they shall have freedom to write as many letters as 
they like at all reasonable times; and the institution shall ensure that where 
parents, guardians or relatives are known, at least one letter is written by the 
juvenile or children every month for which the postage shall be provided by the 
institution. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Officer-in-Charge may peruse any letter written by or to the juvenile 
or children, and may for the reasons that he considers sufficient refuse to 
deliver or issue the letter and forward it to the Committee after recording his 
reasons in a book maintained for the purpose. (4) The Officer-in-Charge 
shall, in special circumstances or as per orders of the Board or Committee, 
allow a juvenile or child to make telephonic communication with his parents or 
guardians or relatives. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>59</number> Death of a juvenile or child. </title>On the occurrence of any 
case of death or suicide in an institution the procedure to be adopted shall be 
as under: 
 <section><number>1</number> In the event of an unnatural death or suicide of a juvenile or child in 
an institution it is imperative for the institution to ensure that an inquest 
and post-mortem examination is held at the earliest. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In case of natural death or due to illness of a juvenile or child, the 
Officer-in-Charge shall obtain a report of the Medical Officer stating the cause 
of death and a written intimation about the death shall be given immediately to 
the nearest Police Station, the Board or Committee, the National or State 
Commission for Protection of Child Rights, District Child Protection Unit or 
State Child Protection Unit or any other concerned authority and the parents or 
guardians or relatives of the juvenile or child. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Whenever a sudden or violent death or death from suicide or accident 
takes place, immediate information shall be given by the case-worker or 
probation officer or welfare officer to the Officer-in-Charge and the Medical 
Officer and the Officer-in-Charge shall immediately inform the nearest police 
station, Board or Committee and parents or guardians or relatives of the 
deceased juvenile or child. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> If a juvenile or child dies within twenty-four hours of his admission to 
the institution, the Officer-in-Charge of the institution shall report the 
matter to the Officer-in-Charge of the Police Station having jurisdiction and 
the District Medical Officer or the nearest Government Hospital and the parents 
or guardians or relatives of such juvenile or child without delay. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Officer-in-Charge shall also immediately give intimation to nearest 
Magistrate empowered to hold inquests and to the Board or as the case may be the 
Committee. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Officer-in-Charge and the Medical Officer at the institution shall 
record the circumstances of the death of the child and send a report to the 
concerned Magistrate, the Officer-in-Charge of the police station having 
jurisdiction, the Committee and the District Medical Officer or the nearest 
government hospital where the dead body of the juvenile or child is sent for 
examination, inspection and determination of the cause of death and the 
Officer-in-Charge and the Medical Officer shall also record in writing their 
views on the cause of the death if any, and submit it to the concerned 
Magistrate and the Officer-in-Charge of the police station having jurisdiction. 

 </section><section><number>7</number> The Officer-in-Charge and the Medical Officer shall make themselves 
available for any inquiries initiated by the police or the Magistrate concerning 
the cause of death and other details regarding such juvenile or child. (8) 
As soon as the inquest is held, the body shall be handed over to the parents or 
guardian or relatives or, in the absence of any claimant, the last rituals shall 
be performed under the supervision of the Officer-in-Charge in accordance with 
the known religion of the juvenile or child. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>60</number> Abuse and exploitation of the juvenile or child. </title>
<section><number>1</number> 
Every institution shall have systems of ensuring that there is no abuse, neglect 
and maltreatment and this shall include the staff being aware of what 
constitutes abuse, neglect and maltreatment as well as early indicators of 
abuse, neglect and maltreatment and how to respond to these. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In the event of any physical, sexual or emotional abuse, including 
neglect of juveniles and children in an institution by those responsible for 
care and protection, the following action shall be taken: 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> the incidence of abuse and exploitation must be reported by any staff 
  member of the institution immediately to the Officer-in-Charge on receiving 
  such information; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> when an allegation of physical, sexual or emotional abuse comes to the 
  knowledge of the Officer-in-Charge, a report shall be placed before the Board 
  or Committee, who in turn, shall order for special investigation; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> the Board or Committee shall direct the local police station or 
  Special Juvenile Police Unit to register a case, take due cognizance of such 
  occurrences and conduct necessary investigations; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> the Board or Committee shall take necessary steps to ensure completion 
  of all inquiry and provide legal aid as well as counselling to the juvenile or 
  child victim; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> the Board or Committee shall transfer such a juvenile or child to 
  another institution or place of safety or fit person; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vi</number> the Officer-in-Charge of the institution shall also inform the 
  Chairperson of the management committee and place a copy of the report of the 
  incident and subsequent action taken before the management committee in its 
  next meeting; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vii</number> in the event of any other crime committed in respect of juveniles or 
  children in institutions, the Board or Committee shall take cognizance and 
  arrange for necessary investigation to be carried out by the local police 
  station or Special Juvenile Police Unit; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>viii</number> the Board or Committee may consult Children's Committee set-up in 
  each institution to enquire into the fact of abuse and exploitation as well as 
  seek assistance from relevant voluntary organizations, child rights experts, 
  mental health experts or crisis intervention centres in dealing with matters 
  of abuse and exploitation of juveniles or children in an institution. 
</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>61</number> Juvenile or Child suffering from dangerous diseases or mental 
health problems. </title>
<section><number>1</number> When a juvenile or a child placed under the care 
of a fit person or a fit institution under the provisions of the Act, is found 
to be suffering from a disease or physical or mental health problems requiring 
prolonged medical treatment, or is found addicted to a narcotic drug or 
psychotropic substance, the juvenile or the child may be sent by an order of the 
competent authority to an appropriate place for such period as may be certified 
by medical officer to be necessary for proper treatment of the juvenile or the 
child or for the remainder of the term for which he has to stay. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> When the juvenile or the child is cured of the disease or physical or 
mental health problems, the competent authority may, if the juvenile or child is 
still liable to stay, order the juvenile or the child to be placed back in the 
care of fit person or institution from where the juvenile or child was removed 
for treatment and if the juvenile or the child is no longer liable to be kept 
under the care of fit person or institution, the competent authority may order 
him to be discharged. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The order of restoration of a juvenile or a child suffering from an 
infectious or contagious disease to his parents or guardian shall be based on 
the principle of best interest of the juvenile or child, keeping in mind the 
risk of stigmatization and discrimination and discontinuation of treatment. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Where there is no organization either within the jurisdiction of the 
competent authority, or nearby District or State for care and protection of 
juveniles or children suffering from serious psychiatric or physical disorder 
and infection, as required under section 58 of the Act, necessary organization 
shall be set-up by the State Government at such places, as it may deem fit to 
cater to the special needs of such juveniles or children. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>62</number> Leave of absence of a juvenile or child. </title>
<section><number>1</number> A juvenile 
or child in an institution may be allowed to go on leave of absence or released 
under supervision for examination or admission, special occasions like marriage 
or emergencies like death or accident or serious illness in the family. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> While the leave of absence for short period generally not exceeding seven 
days excluding the journey time may be recommended by the Officer-in-Charge, but 
granting of such leave shall be by the Board or Committee. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The parents or guardian of the juvenile or the Officer-in-Charge on 
behalf of the juvenile or child may submit an application to the Board or 
Committee requesting for relieving the juvenile or child on leave, stating 
clearly the purpose for the leave and the period of leave. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> While considering the application of leave of absence, the Board or 
Committee shall hear the juvenile or child or the parents or guardians of the 
juvenile or child and if the Board or Committee considers that granting of such 
leave is in the interest of the juvenile or child, appropriate order shall be 
made and the Board or Committee may call for a report from the probation officer 
or child welfare officer in case the preliminary information gathered from the 
juvenile or child or concerned parent or guardian is not sufficient for the 
purpose. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> While issuing orders sanctioning the leave of absence or relieving under 
supervision, as the case may be, the competent authority shall mention the 
period of leave and the conditions attached to the leave order, and if any of 
these conditions are not complied with during the leave period, the juvenile or 
child may be called back to the institution. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The parent or guardian shall arrange to escort the juvenile or child from 
and to the institution and where this is not possible, the Officer-in-Charge may 
arrange to escort the juvenile or child to the place of the family and back. In 
case the parents or guardian is willing to arrange escort but does not have 
requisite financial means, the Officer-in-Charge shall arrange for the 
travelling expenses as admissible under the rules. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> If the juvenile or child runs away from the family during the leave 
period, the parent or guardian is required to inform the Officer-in-Charge of 
the institution immediately, and try to trace the juvenile or child and if 
found, the juvenile or child shall be brought back to the institution 
immediately. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> If the juvenile or child is not found within twenty-four hours, the 
Officer-in-Charge shall report the matter to the nearest police station and 
missing person's bureau, but no adverse disciplinary action shall be taken 
against the juvenile or child and procedure laid down under the Act shall be 
followed. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> If the parent or guardian does not take proper care of the juvenile or 
child during the leave period or does not bring the juvenile or child back to 
the institution within the stipulated period, such leave may be refused on later 
occasions. 
 </section><section><number>10</number> If the juvenile or child does not return to the institution on expiry of 
the sanctioned leave, the Board or Committee shall refer the case to police for 
taking charge of the juvenile and bring him back to the institution. (11) 
The period of such leave shall be counted as a part of the period of stay in the 
institution and the time which elapses after the failure of a juvenile to return 
to the institution within the stipulated period, shall be excluded while 
computing the period of his stay in the institution. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>63</number> Inspection. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The State Government shall constitute 
State, District or city level inspection committee on the recommendation of the 
Selection Committee constituted under rule 91 of these rules. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The inspection committees shall visit and oversee the conditions in the 
institutions and appropriateness of the processes for safety, well being and 
permanence, review the standards of care and protection being followed by the 
institutions, look out for any incidence of violation of child rights, look into 
the functioning of the Management Committee and Children's Committee set-up 
under rules 55 and 56 of these rules and give appropriate directions. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The team shall also make suggestions for improvement and development of 
the institution. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The team shall consist of a minimum of five members with representation 
from the State Government, the Board or Committee, the State Commission for the 
Protection of Child Rights or the State Human Rights Commission, medical and 
other experts, voluntary organizations and reputed social workers. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The inspection shall be carried out at least once in every three months. 

 </section><section><number>6</number> The inspection visit shall be carried out by not less than three members. 

 </section><section><number>7</number> The team may visit the institutions either by prior intimation or make a 
surprise visit. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> The team shall interact with the children during the visits to the 
institution, to determine their well-being and uninhibited feed back 
 </section><section><number>9</number> The follow-up action on the findings and suggestion of the children shall 
be taken by all concerned authorities. 
 </section><section><number>10</number> The action taken report, findings and suggestions from the Inspection 
Committee shall be sent to the District Child Protection Unit and the State 
Government. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>64</number> Social Audit. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government or the State 
Government shall monitor and evaluate the implementation of the Act annually by 
reviewing matters concerning establishment of Board or Committee or Special 
Juvenile Police Unit where required, functioning of Board or Committee or 
Special Juvenile Police Unit, functioning of institutions and staff, functioning 
of adoption agencies, child friendly administration of juvenile justice and any 
other matter concerning effective implementation of the Act in the State. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The social audit shall be carried out with support and involvement of 
organizations working in the field of mental health, child care and protection 
and autonomous bodies like the National Institute of Public Co-operation and 
Child Development, Indian Council for Child Welfare, Childline India Foundation, 
Central and State level Social Welfare Boards, School of Social Work and School 
of Law. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>65</number> Restoration and Follow-up. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The order for 
restoration of the juvenile or child shall be made by the Board or Committee on 
the basis of a fair hearing of the juvenile or child and his parents or 
guardian, as well as on the reports of the Probation Officers or Child Welfare 
Officers or non-governmental organisations directed by the Board or Committee to 
conduct the home study and any other relevant document or report brought before 
the Board or Committee for deciding the matter. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Board or Committee shall send a copy of the restoration order along 
with a copy of the order for escort as per Form XXII to the District Child 
Protection Unit or State Government who shall provide funds for restoration of 
the juvenile or child. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every restoration shall be planned for as part of the individual care 
plans prepared by the case-workers or counsellors or child welfare officers or 
probation officer, as the case may be, and shall be based on the review and 
recommendations of the Management Committee set-up under rule 55 of these rules. 

 </section><section><number>4</number> Besides police, the Board or Committee shall seek collaboration with 
non-governmental organisations to accompany juveniles or children back to their 
family for restoration. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> In case of girls, the juvenile or child shall necessarily be accompanied 
by female escorts. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The expenses incurred on restoration of a juvenile or child, including 
travel and other incidental expenses, shall be borne by the District Child 
Protection Unit or State Government. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> When a juvenile or child expresses his unwillingness to be restored back 
to the family, the Board or Committee shall make a note of it in its records in 
writing and such juvenile or child shall not be coerced or persuaded to go back 
to the family, particularly if the social investigation report of the child 
welfare officer or probation officer establishes that restoration to family may 
not be in the best interest of the juvenile or child or, if the parents or 
guardians refuse to accept the juvenile or child back. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> A follow-up plan shall be prepared as part of the individual care plans 
by the Child Welfare Officers or Probation Officers or non-governmental 
organisations assigned by the Board or Committee to assist in restoration of the 
child. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> A quarterly follow-up report shall be submitted to the Board or Committee 
by the concerned Child Welfare Officer or Probation Officer or non-governmental 
organisation for a period of two years with a copy to the Officer-in-Charge of 
the institution from where the juvenile or child is restored. 
 </section><section><number>10</number> The follow-up report shall clearly state the situation of the juvenile 
or child post restoration and the juvenile's or child's needs to be met by the 
State Gbvernment in order to reduce further vulnerability of the juvenile or 
child. 
 </section><section><number>11</number> The Officer-in-Charge shall file the follow-up report in the case-file 
of the juvenile or child and place the report before the management committee 
set-up under rule 55 of these rules in its next meeting. 
 </section><section><number>12</number> The Officer-in-Charge shall also send a copy of the follow-up reports to 
the District Child Protection Unit. 
 </section><section><number>13</number> Where a follow-up is not possible due to unavailability of government 
functionaries or non­-governmental organisations, the concerned District 
Child Protection Unit shall provide necessary assistance and support to the 
concerned Board or Committee. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>66</number> Visitor's Book. </title>
<section><number>1</number> A Visitor's Book shall be 
maintained, in every institution, in which the person visiting the home shall 
record the date of his visit with remarks or suggestions, which he may think 
proper. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Officer-in-Charge shall forward a copy of every such entry to the 
District Child Protection Unit or State Government, with such remarks as he may 
desire to offer in explanation or otherwise; and thereon, the designated 
authority shall issue such orders as he may consider necessary. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>67</number> Maintenance of Registers. </title>The Officer-in-Charge shall 
maintain in his office, such registers and forms, as required by the Act and as 
specified by these rules made thereunder and the list of registers or files or 
books to be maintained shall minimally comprise of: 
 
 <section><number>a</number> Admission and discharge register; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> Supervision register; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> Medical file or medical report; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> Nutrition diet file; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> Stock register; 
 </section><section><number>f</number> Log book; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> Order book; 
 </section><section><number>h</number> Meeting book; 
 </section><section><number>i</number> Cash book; 
 </section><section><number>j</number> Budget statement file; 
 </section><section><number>k</number> Inquiry report file; 
 </section><section><number>l</number> Individual case file with individual care plan; 
 </section><section><number>m</number> Children's Suggestion book; 
 </section><section><number>n</number> Visitor's book; 
 </section><section><number>o</number> Staff movement register; 
 </section><section><number>p</number> Personal belongings register; 
 </section><section><number>q</number> Minutes register of Management Committee; 
 </section><section><number>r</number> Minutes register of Children's Committees; and 
 </section><section><number>s</number> Attendance register for staff and juveniles or children. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>69</number> Recognition of fit persons or fit institution. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Any 
individual who is willing temporarily to receive a juvenile or child in need of 
care, protection or treatment for a period as may be necessary, may be 
recognized by the competent authority as a fit person after due verification of 
their credentials and reputation. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any suitable place or institution, the manager of which is willing 
temporarily to receive a juvenile or child in need of care and protection for a 
period as may be necessary, may be recognized by the State Government as a fit 
institution on the recommendation of the competent authority. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> An institution recognized as a fit institution shall, 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> meet the standards of care laid down in the Act and the rules made 
  thereunder; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> have the capacity and willingness to meet the standards of care laid 
  down in the Act and the rules; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> receive and provide basic services for care and protection of the 
  juveniles and children; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> prevent subjection of juvenile or child to any form of cruelty or 
  exploitation or neglect; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> abide by the orders of the competent authority. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>4</number> A list of fit institutions approved by the State Government shall be kept 
in the office of the Board and the Committee. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> A fit institution with collateral branches may send the juvenile or child 
placed therein by an order of the competent authority to any of its branches 
after seeking permission from the competent authority. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> Before declaring any person as a fit person or recommending an 
institution as a fit institution, the competent authority shall hold due enquiry 
and only on being satisfied, recognition shall be given. <title></title>
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>70</number> Certification or recognition and transfer of Management of 
Institutions and after care organizations. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Any organization 
desiring certification under the Act shall make an application together with a 
copy each of the rules, bye-laws articles of association, list of members of the 
society or the association running the organization, office bearers and a 
statement showing the status and past record of specialized childcare services 
provided by the organization, to the State Government, who shall after verifying 
the provisions made in the organization for the boarding and lodging, general 
health, educational facilities, vocational training and treatment services may 
grant certification or recognition under sections 8, 9, 34, 37, 41 or 44 of the 
Act, as the case may be, on the condition that the organization shall comply 
with the standards or services as laid down under the Act and the rules framed 
their under, from time to time and to ensure an all round growth and development 
of juvenile or child placed under its charge. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any organization desiring recognition under the Act shall make an 
application to the Competent Authority, who shall after due inquiry, recommend 
the State Government for such recognition. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The State Government may, transfer the management of any State run 
institution under the Act to a voluntary organization of repute, who has the 
capacity to run such an institution; and certify or recognize the said voluntary 
organization as a fit institution to own the requisite responsibilities under a 
Memorandum of Understanding for a specified period of time. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The State Government may, if dissatisfied with the conditions, rules, 
management of the organization certified or recognized under the Act, at any 
time, by notice served on the manager of the organization, declare that the 
certificate or recognition of the organization, as the case may be, shall stand 
withdrawn as from a date specified in the notice and from the said date, the 
organization shall cease to be an organization certified or recognised under 
sections 8, 9, 34, 37, 41 or 44 of the Act, as the case may be: 
 Provided that the concerned organization shall be given an opportunity of 
making a representation in writing, within a period of thirty days, against the 
grounds of withdrawal of certificate or recognition of that organization. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The decision to withdraw or to restore the certificate or recognition of 
the organization may be taken, on the basis of a thorough investigation by a 
specially constituted advisory board under section 62 of the Act. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> On the report of the advisory board, the Officer-in-Charge of the 
institution shall be asked to show cause so as to give an explanation within 
thirty days. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> When an organization ceases to be an organization, certified or 
recognised under sections 8, 9, 34, 37, 41 or 44 of the Act, the juvenile or the 
child kept therein shall, be transferred to some other institution of repute, 
certified or recognized under sections 8, 9, 34, 37, 41 or 44 of the Act or 
discharged, in accordance with the provisions of the Act and the rules relating 
to their discharge and transfer by giving intimation of such discharge or 
transfer to the Board or the Committee, as the case may be. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>71</number> Registration under the Act. </title>
<section><number>1</number> All institutions and 
organisations running institutional or non-institutional care services for 
children in need of care and protection, whether run by the government or 
voluntary organization, shall get themselves registered under sub-section (3) of 
section 34 of the Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> All such institutions shall make an application together with a copy each 
of rules, bye-laws, memorandum of association, list of governing body, office 
bearers, balance sheet of past three years, statement of past record of social 
or public service provided by the institution or organization to the State 
Government, who shall after verifying that provisions made in the institution or 
organization for the care and protection of children, health, education, 
boarding and lodging facilities, if any, vocational facilities and scope of 
rehabilitation, may issue a registration certificate to such organization under 
sub-section (3) of section 34 of the Act and as per this rule. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>72</number> Grant-in-aid to certified or recognized organization. 
</title>
<section><number>1</number> An organization certified or recognized or registered under 
sections 8, 9, 34, sub-section (3) of section 34, 37 or 44 of the Act, may 
during the period when certification or recognition or registration is in force, 
may apply for grants-in-aid by the State Government, for the maintenance of 
juvenile or child received by them under the provisions of the Act; and for 
expenses incurred on their education, treatment, vocational training, 
development and rehabilitation. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The grants-in-aid may be admissible, at such rates, which shall be 
sufficient to meet the prescribed norms, in such manner and subject to such 
conditions as may be mutually agreed to by both the parties. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> In case of transfer of management of government-run homes under sections 
8, 9, 34, sub­-section (3) of sections 34, 37 or 44 of the Act to a 
voluntary organization, the same budget which the Government was spending on 
that home, shall be given to the voluntary organization as grant-in-aid under 
the Memorandum of Understanding signed between both the parties describing their 
role and obligations. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>73</number> Admission of outsiders. </title>
<section><number>1</number> No stranger shall be 
admitted to the premises of the institution, except with the permission of the 
Officer-in-Charge or on an order from the Board or Committee. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In special cases, where parents or guardians have travelled a long 
distance from another state or district, the Officer-in-Charge shall allow 
parents or guardians entry into the premises and a meeting with their children, 
provided they possess proper identification and are not reported to have 
subjected the juvenile or child to abuse and exploitation. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>74</number> Identity Photos. </title>
<section><number>1</number> On admission to a home established 
under the Act, every juvenile or child shall be photographed. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> One photograph shall be kept in the case file of the juvenile or the 
child, one shall be fixed with the index card, a copy shall be kept in an album 
serially numbered with the negative in another album, and a copy of the 
photograph shall be sent to the Board or Committee as case may be, as well as to 
the district or State Child Protection Unit. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> In case of a child missing from an institution or in case of lost 
children received by an institution, a photograph of the child with relevant 
details shall be sent to the missing person's bureau and the local police 
station. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>75</number> Police Officers to be in plain clothes. </title>While dealing 
with a juvenile or a child under the provisions of the Act and the rules made 
thereunder, except at the time of arrest, the Police Officer shall wear plain 
clothes and not the police uniform. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>76</number> Prohibition on the use of handcuffs and fetters. </title>No 
child or the juvenile in conflict with law dealt with under the provisions of 
the Act and the rules made there under shall be handcuffed or fettered. 
</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>77</number> Procedure to be followed by a Magistrate not empowered under the 
Act. </title>
<section><number>1</number> When any juvenile or child is produced before a Magistrate 
other than Board or Committee, and the Magistrate is of the opinion that such 
person is a juvenile or child, he shall record his reasons and send the juvenile 
or child to the appropriate competent authority. <title></title>
 </section><section><number>2</number> In case of a juvenile produced before a Magistrate not empowered under 
this Act, such Magistrate shall direct the case to be transferred to the Board 
for inquiry and disposal. (3) In case of a child in need of care and 
protection produced as a victim of a crime before a Magistrate not empowered 
under the Act, such Magistrate shall transfer the matter concerning care and 
protection, rehabilitation and restoration of the child to the appropriate 
Committee. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>78</number> Transfer. </title>
<section><number>1</number> During the inquiry, if it is found that 
the juvenile or child hails from a place outside the jurisdiction of the Board 
or Committee, the Board or Committee shall order the transfer of the juvenile or 
child and send a copy of the order to the State Government or State or District 
Child Protection Unit: 
 Provided that: 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> such transfer is in the best interest of the juvenile or child; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> no child shall be transferred or proposed to be transferred only on 
  the ground that the child has created problems or, has become difficult to be 
  managed in the existing institution or, is suffering from a chronic or 
  terminal illness or, on account of disability; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> such transfer shall only take place after the completion of evidence 
  and cross-examination that may be required in a legal proceeding involving a 
  juvenile or child; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> the reasons for and circumstances of such transfer are recorded in 
  writing. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The State Government or State or District Child Protection Unit shall 
accordingly: 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> send the information of transfer to the appropriate competent authority 
  having jurisdiction over the area where the child is ordered to be transferred 
  by the Board or Committee; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> send a copy of the information to the Officer-in-Charge of the 
  institution where the child is placed for care and protection at the time of 
  the transfer order. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> On receipt of copy of the information from the State Government or State 
or District Child Protection Unit, the Officer-in-Charge shall arrange to escort 
the child at government expenses to the place or person as specified in the 
order. (4) On such transfer, case file and records of the juvenile or child 
shall be sent along with the juvenile or child. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>79</number> Procedure for sending a juvenile or child outside the 
jurisdiction of the competent authority. </title>
<section><number>1</number> In the case of a juvenile 
or a child whose ordinary place of residence lies outside the jurisdiction of 
the competent authority, and if the competent authority considers it necessary 
to take action under section 50 of the Act, it shall direct a probation officer 
or case worker or child welfare officer, as the case may be, to make enquiries 
as to the fitness and willingness of the relative or other person to receive the 
juvenile or the child at the ordinary place of residence, and whether such 
relative or other fit person can exercise proper care and control over the 
juvenile or the child. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where a juvenile or child is ordered to be sent to the ordinary place of 
residence or to a relative or fit person, execution of a bond by the juvenile or 
child without any surety, in Form VI, is necessary along with an undertaking by 
the said relative or fit person in Form V or IX as the case may be. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Any breach of a bond or undertaking or of both given under sub-rule (2) 
of this rule, shall render the juvenile liable to be brought before the 
competent authority, who may make an order directing the juvenile to be sent to 
an institution home. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Any juvenile or a child, who is a foreign national and who has lost 
contact with his family shall also be entitled for protection. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The juvenile or the child, who is a foreign national, shall be 
repatriated, at the earliest, to the country of his origin in co-ordination with 
the respective Embassy or High Commission. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Board or Committee shall keep the Ministry of External Affairs 
informed about repatriation of every juvenile or child of foreign nationality 
carried out on the orders of the Board or Committee. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> A copy of the order passed by the competent authority under section 50 of 
the Act shall be sent to 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the probation officer or child welfare officer who was directed to submit 
a report under sub-rule (1) of this rule; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the probation officer or child welfare officer, if any, having 
jurisdiction over the place where the juvenile or the child is to be sent; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the competent authority having jurisdiction over the place where the 
juvenile or the child is to be sent; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> the relative or the person who is to receive the juvenile or the child. 

 </subsection></section><section><number>8</number> During the pendency of the order under sub-rule (6) of this rule, the 
juvenile or the child shall be sent by the competent authority to an observation 
home or children's home as the case may be. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> Where the competent authority considers it expedient to send the juvenile 
or the child back to his ordinary place of residence under section 50, the 
competent authority shall inform the relative or the fit person, who is to 
receive the juvenile or the child accordingly; and shall invite the said 
relative or fit person to come to the home, to take charge of the juvenile or 
the child on such date, as may be specified by the competent authority. 
 </section><section><number>10</number> The competent authority inviting the said relative or fit person under 
sub-rule (8) of this rule may also direct, if necessary, the payment to be made 
by the Officer-in-Charge of the home, of the actual expenses of the relative or 
fit person's journey both ways, by the appropriate class and the juvenile's or 
child's journey from the home to his ordinary place of residence, at the time of 
sending the juvenile or the child. 
 </section><section><number>11</number> If the relative or the fit person fails to come to take charge of the 
juvenile or the child on the specified date, the juvenile or the child shall be 
taken to his ordinary place of residence by the escort of the observation home 
and in the case of a girl, at least one escort shall be a female. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>80</number> State Child Protection Unit. </title>The specific functions of 
the State Child Protection Unit shall include: 
 
 <section><number>a</number> implementation of the Act and supervision and monitoring of agencies 
  and institutions under the Act; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> set-up, support and monitor the District Child Protection Units; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> represent State Child Protection Unit as a member in the Selection 
  Committee for appointment of members of Boards or Committees; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> make necessary funds available to the District Child Protection Units 
  for providing or setting up required facilities to implementation the Act; 

 </section><section><number>e</number> network and co-ordinate with all government departments to build 
  inter-sectoral linkages on child protection issues, including Departments of 
  Health, Education, Social Welfare, Urban Basic Services, Backward Classes 
  &amp; Minorities, Youth Services, Police, Judiciary, Labour, State AIDS 
  Control Society, among others; 
 </section><section><number>f</number> network and co-ordinate with civil society organizations working for 
  the effective implementation of the Act; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> training and capacity building of all personnel (Government and 
  Non-government) working under the Act; 
 </section><section><number>h</number> establish Minimum Standards of Care and ensure its implementation in 
  all institutions set-up under the Act; 
 </section><section><number>i</number> review of the functioning of Committees; and 
 </section><section><number>j</number> all other functions necessary for effective implementation of the Act. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>81</number> District Child Protection Unit. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The District Child 
Protection Unit shall co-ordinate and implement all child rights and protection 
activities at district level. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The specific functions of the District Child Protection Unit shall 
include: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> ensure effective implementation of the Act at district or city levels 
  by supporting creation of adequate infrastructure, such as, setting up Boards, 
  Committees, Special Juvenile Police Units and homes in each district; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> identify families at risk and children in need of care and protection; 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> assess the number of children in difficult circumstances and creating 
  district-specific databases to monitor trends and patterns of children in 
  difficult circumstances; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> periodic and regular mapping of all child related services at district 
  for creating a resource directory and making the information available to the 
  Committees and Boards from time to time; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> implement family based non-institutional services including 
  sponsorship, foster care, adoption and after care; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> ensure setting up of District, Block and Village Level Child Protection 
  Committees for effective implementation of programmes as well as discharge of 
  its functions; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> facilitate transfer of children at all levels for either their 
  restoration to their families or placing the child in long or short-term 
  rehabilitation through institutionalization, adoption, foster care and 
  sponsorship; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> supporting State Adoption Resource Agency in implementation of family 
  based non-institutional services at district level; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> network and co-ordinate with all government departments to build 
  inter-sectoral linkages on child protection issues, including Departments of 
  Health, Education, Social Welfare, Urban Basic Services, Backward Classes 
  &amp; Minorities, Youth Services, Police, Judiciary, Labour, State AIDS 
  Control Society, among others; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> network and co-ordinate with civil society organizations working under 
  the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number> develop parameters and tools for effective monitoring and supervision 
  of agencies and institutions in the district in consultation with experts in 
  child welfare; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number> supervise and monitor all institutions or agencies providing 
  residential facilities to children in district; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>m</number> train and build capacity of all personnel (Government and 
  Non-government) implementing the Act to provide effective services to 
  children; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>n</number> organize quarterly meeting with all stakeholders at district level 
  including CHILDLINE, Specialised Adoption Agencies, Officer-in-Charges of 
  homes, non-governmental organisations and members of public to review the 
  progress and implementation of the Act; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>o</number> liaison with the State Child Protection Unit, State Adoption Resource 
  Agency at State level and District Child Protection Units of other districts. 
  </subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>82</number> Setting of the Child Welfare Committee. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The State 
Government shall set-up by notification in Official Gazette Child Welfare 
Committees under section 29 of the Act in every district with requisite 
infrastructure, personnel, and finances for smooth running, as listed below: 

 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the infrastructure shall consist of a sitting hall, a separate room for 
  the Committee, room for office staff, waiting room for children, waiting room 
  for parents or guardian, room for personal interaction between the child or 
  parents and the Committee, a record room, safe drinking water facility and 
  toilets; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the State Government shall provide necessary human resource support for 
  every Committee, including welfare officer, steno-typist or computer operator, 
  peon, safai karamchari. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The allowances of the Chairperson and Members shall be disbursed by the 
District Child Protection Unit or State Government as per rule 23 of these 
rules. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>83</number> Setting up of Juvenile Justice Board. </title>The State 
Government shall set-up by notification in Official Gazette, Juvenile Justice 
Board in every district, with requisite infrastructure, personnel, besides the 
Principal Magistrate and Members and Finances as listed below: 
 <section><number>1</number> Infrastructure shall consist of a Board Room, waiting room for children, 
a room for Principal Magistrate and Members, a record room, room for Probation 
Officers, waiting room for parents and visitors, safe drinking water facility 
and toilets. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The State Government shall provide necessary human resource support for 
every Board, including probation officer, steno-typist or computer operator, 
peon, safai karamchari. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>84</number> Special Juvenile Police Unit. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The State Government 
shall appoint a Special Juvenile Police Unit at the District level within four 
months of the notification of these rules and the unit shall consist of a 
juvenile or child welfare officer of the rank of police inspector and two paid 
social workers having experience of working in the field of child welfare, of 
whom one shall be a woman. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The District Child Protection Unit or the State Government shall provide 
services of its two social workers to the Special Juvenile Police Unit for 
discharging their duties. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The juvenile or child welfare officer at the police station shall be a 
person with aptitude and appropriate training and orientation to handle the 
cases of juveniles or children in terms of the provisions of the Act. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The transfer and posting of the designated Juvenile or Child Welfare 
Officer shall be within the Special Juvenile Police Units of other police 
stations or district unit, unless there is an exceptional case of promotion and 
in such cases, other police officer must be designated and deputed in the unit 
so that there is no shortfall. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Special Juvenile Police Unit at district level shall co-ordinate and 
function as a watch-dog for providing legal protection against all kinds of 
cruelty, abuse and exploitation of child or juvenile. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The unit shall take serious cognizance of adult perpetrators of crimes 
against children and see to it that they are without delay apprehended and 
booked under the appropriate provisions of the law and for this purpose the 
district level units shall maintain liaison with other units of police station. 

 </section><section><number>7</number> The Special Juvenile Police Units shall seek assistance from the 
voluntary organizations, panchayats and Gram Sabhas or Resident Welfare 
Associations in identifying juveniles in conflict with law as well as reporting 
cases of violence against children, child neglect and child abuse. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> The Special Juvenile Police Units shall particularly seek assistance from 
voluntary organizations recognized as protection agencies by the State 
Government for the purpose of assisting Special Juvenile Police Units and local 
police stations at the time of apprehension, in preparation of necessary 
reports, for taking charge of juveniles until production and at the time of 
production before the Board as per rule 11(12) of these rules. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> The Superintendent of Police in a district shall head the Special 
Juvenile Police Unit and oversee its functioning from time to time. 
 </section><section><number>10</number> A Nodal Officer from Police not less than the rank of Inspector-General 
of Police shall be designated in each State to co-ordinate and upgrade role of 
police on all issues pertaining to care and protection of children or juveniles 
under Act. 
 </section><section><number>11</number> Any police officer found guilty, after due inquiry, of torturing a 
child, mentally or physically, shall be liable to be removed from service, 
besides being prosecuted for the offence. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>85</number> Honorary or Voluntary Welfare Officers and Probation Officers. 
</title>To augment the existing probation service, honorary or voluntary 
welfare officers and probation officers may be appointed from the voluntary 
organization and social workers found fit for the purpose by the competent 
authority and their services may also be co-opted into the implementation 
machinery by the orders of the competent authority. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>86</number> Duties of the Officer-in-Charge of an institution. </title>
<section><number>1</number> 
The Officer-in-Charge shall have the primary responsibility of maintaining the 
institution and shall stay within the institutional premises to be readily 
available as and when required by the juveniles or children and the staff and in 
case where an accommodation is not available within the institutional premises, 
the Officer-in-Charge shall stay at a place in close proximity to the 
institution till such time that such an accommodation is made available within 
the institution. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The general duties and functions of the Officer-in-Charge shall include: 

 
 <subsection><number>a</number> compliance with provisions of the Act and the rules and orders made 
  thereunder; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> compliance with the orders of the Board or Committee; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> providing homely atmosphere of love, affection, care, development and 
  welfare for juveniles or children; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> maintaining minimum standards of care in the institution; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> proper maintenance of buildings and premises; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> security measures and periodical inspection, including daily inspection 
  and rounds of the institution, proper storage and inspection of food stuffs as 
  well as food being served; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> supervision and monitoring of juveniles' or children's discipline and 
  well being; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> planning implementation and co-ordination of all institutional 
  activities, programmes and operations, including training and treatment 
  programmes or correctional activities as the case may be; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> prompt action to meet emergencies; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> ensuring accident and fire preventive measures within the institutional 
  premises; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number> stand-by arrangements for water storage, power plant, emergency 
  lighting; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number> careful handling of plants and equipments; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>m</number> segregation of a juvenile or child suffering from contagious or 
  infectious diseases; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>n</number> observance and follow-up of daily routine; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>o</number> filing of monthly report of juvenile or child in the case file; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>p</number> organize local and national festivals in the institution; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>q</number> organize trips or excursions or picnics for juveniles or children; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>r</number> preparation of budget and control over financial matters; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>s</number> allocation of duties to personnel; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>t</number> supervision over office administration, including attending to 
  personnel welfare and staff discipline; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>u</number> prompt, firm and considerate handling of all disciplinary matters; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> organize the meetings of the Management Cbmmittee set-up under rule 55 
  of these rules and provide necessary support; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>w</number> maintenance of all records and registers required under the Act and the 
  rules and monthly verification of the same by the Management Committee set-up 
  under rule 55 of these rules; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>x</number> liaison, co-ordination and co-operation with the District Child 
  Protection Unit or State Government as and when required; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>y</number> co-ordination with the legal officer in the District Child Protection 
  Unit to ensure that every juvenile is legally represented and provided free 
  legal aid and other necessary support or, where the District Child Protection 
  Unit has not been set-up, services of the District or State Legal Services 
  Authority shall be made available. </subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>87</number> Duties of a Probation Officer or Child Welfare Officer or 
Case-Worker. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Every probation officer or child welfare officer or 
case-worker shall carry out all directions given by the Board or Committee or 
concerned authority and shall perform the following duties, functions and 
responsibilities: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> making social investigation of the juvenile (Form IV) or the child 
  (Form XIII) through personal interview and from the family, social agencies 
  and other sources; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> attending the proceedings of the Board or Committee and submitting 
  reports as and when required; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> clarifying problems of the juvenile or the child and dealing with their 
  difficulties in institutional life; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> participating in the orientation, monitoring, education, vocational and 
  rehabilitation programmes; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> establishing co-operation and understanding between the juvenile or the 
  child and the Officer-in-Charge; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> assisting the juvenile or the child to develop contacts with family and 
  also providing assistance to family members; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> developing a care plan for every child in consultation with the 
  juvenile or child and following up its implementation; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> participating in the pre-release programme and helping the juvenile or 
  the child to establish contacts which can provide emotional and social support 
  to juvenile or child after their release; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> establishing linkages with voluntary workers and organizations to 
  facilitate rehabilitation and social reintegration of juveniles and to ensure 
  the necessary follow-up; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> follow-up of juveniles after their release and extending help and 
  guidance to them; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number> visiting regularly the residence of the juvenile or child under their 
  supervision and also places of employment or school attended by such juvenile 
  or child and submitting fortnightly reports as prescribed in Form XXI; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number> accompanying juveniles or children wherever possible, from the office 
  of the Board to observation home, special home, children's home or fit person, 
  as the case may be; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>m</number> maintaining case file and such registers as may be specified from time 
  to time. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> On receipt of information from the Police or Juvenile or Child Welfare 
Officer of the Police under clause (b) of section 13 of the Act, the probation 
officer shall inquire into the antecedents and family history of the juvenile or 
the child and such other material circumstances, as may be necessary and submit 
a social investigation report as early as possible, in Form IV or XIII, to the 
Board. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>88</number> Duties of House Father or House Mother. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The general 
duties, functions and responsibilities of a house father, house mother and other 
care takers shall be as follows: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> handling juvenile or child with love and affection; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> taking proper care and welfare of juvenile or child; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> maintaining discipline among the juveniles or children; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> maintenance, sanitation and hygiene; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> implementing daily routine in an effective manner and ensuring 
  children's involvement; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> looking after the security and safety arrangements of the home; and 

 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> escorting juveniles or children, whenever they go out of the home. 
</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>89</number> Disqualification for Officer-in-Charge, probation officer or 
child welfare officer or case-worker, house father or house mother and other 
care givers and staff. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Officer-in-Charge, probation officer or 
child welfare officer or case-worker, house father or house mother and other 
care givers and staff shall not employ a juvenile or child under their 
supervision or care and protection for their own purposes or take any private 
service from them. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any report of physical, sexual or emotional abuse of a juvenile or a 
child in an institution or outside, by a caregiver, shall hold them liable for 
disqualification after due inquiry. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>90</number> Training of Personnel. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The State Government or the 
Officer-in-Charge shall provide for training of personnel of each category of 
staff, in keeping with their statutory responsibilities and specific jobs 
requirements. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The training programme shall include 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> orientation and induction training of the newly-recruited staff, 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> refresher training courses and skill enhancement programmes for all 
  care givers once a year, and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> staff conferences, seminars, workshops. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> The State Government with the help of the State Child Protection Unit, 
National Institute of Public Co-operation and Child Development and its Regional 
Centres shall organize regular training and capacity building of personnel 
involved in the implementation of the Act and the rules made thereunder. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>91</number> Selection Committee and its composition. </title>The State 
Government shall constitute a Selection Committee by notification in the 
Official Gazette, for a period of five years, consisting of the following seven 
members, namely: 
 
 <section><number>a</number> a retired judge of High Court as the Chairperson; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> one representative from the concerned Department of State Government 
  not below the rank of Director as the Member-Secretary; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> two representatives from a reputed non-governmental organization, 
  working in the area of child welfare; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> two representatives from academic bodies concerned with social work, 
  psychology, sociology, child development, education, law, criminology and with 
  experience of working on children's issues; and 
 </section><section><number>e</number> a representative of the National or State Human Rights Commission or, 
  National or State Commission for Protection of Child Rights or, National or 
  State Commission for Women. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>92</number> Functions of the Selection Committee. </title>
<section><number>1</number> 
<subsection><number>a</number> In making 
appointment of members of the Board or Committee, the Selection Committee shall 
take into consideration the applications received in this regard in response to 
a public advertisement to this effect by the District or State Child Protection 
Unit or the State Government; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> The Selection Committee shall select and recommend a panel of names to 
the State Child Protection Unit or State Government for appointment as members 
of the Board or Committee from amongst the applications received. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> In the event of any complaint against a member of the Board or Committee, 
the Selection Committee shall hold necessary inquiry and recommend termination 
of appointment of such member to the State Child Protection Unit or State 
Government, if required. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> (a) The Selection Committee, at the time of recommending names for 
appointment as member of Board or Committee shall also prepare a panel of names 
for each Board or Committee to fill in vacancies, which may arise during the 
tenure of the Board or Committee. 
 <subsection><number>b</number> In the event of a vacancy in the Board or Committee, the District Child 
Protection Unit shall inform the State Child Protection Unit or State Government 
for filling up such vacancy. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> The State Child Protection Unit or State Government shall fill the 
vacancies on the basis of the panel of names recommended by the Selection 
Committee. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number> The Selection Committee shall recommend names for constitution of the 
State or District or City Level Inspection Committees as required under section 
35 of the Act. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>93</number> Advisory Boards. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government and the 
State Government shall constitute Advisory Board at Central, State, District, 
City levels for a period of three years. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Central Advisory Board shall be constituted through the Union 
Ministry of Women and Child Development. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The State Government shall constitute the State Advisory Board, District 
Advisory Board and the City Advisory Board. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> All the Advisory Boards shall hold at least two meetings in a year. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> These Advisory Boards shall inspect the various institutional or 
non-institutional services in their respective jurisdictions; and the 
recommendations made by them, shall be acted upon by the Central Government and 
the State Government. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Central Government through the Central Ministry of Women and Child 
Development shall set-up the Central Advisory Board to be headed by the Minister 
concerned and shall consist of the Secretary of the Ministry aforesaid, 
representatives from State Governments, representative members from the 
competent authority, leading non-governmental organisations, experts in child or 
juvenile care, children's institution and academic institutions as members. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> A designated official of the Central Ministry of Women and Child 
Development shall function as the Member-Secretary of the Central Advisory 
Board. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> The State Government, through the Selection Committee constituted under 
rule 91 of these rules, shall set-up State, District and City level Advisory 
Boards, which shall consist of representatives of the State Government, members 
of the competent authority, academic institutions, locally respectable and 
spirited citizens, representatives of non-governmental organizations. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> The District or City level Advisory Board constituted in terms of 
sub-section (3) of section 62 of the Act shall also function as the inspection 
committee under section 35 of the Act. 
 </section><section><number>10</number> The termination, resignation, or other vacancy caused in an advisory 
board and appointment of new members therein shall be done in the same manner as 
is done in case of the competent authority. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>94</number> Openness &amp; Transparency. </title>
<section><number>1</number> All Children's homes 
shall be open to visitors with the permission of the Officer-in-Charge and the 
Committee or Officer-in-Charge as the case may be, may consider appropriate to 
allow representatives of local self-government, voluntary organizations, social 
workers, researchers, medicos, academicians, prominent personalities, media and 
any other persons as visitors, as the Officer-in-Charge considers appropriate 
keeping in view the security, welfare and the interest of the children. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Officer-in-Charge of the home shall encourage active involvement of 
local community in improving the conditions in the homes, if, the members of the 
community want to serve the institution or want to contribute through their 
expertise. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Officer-in-Charge shall maintain a visitors book and the remarks of 
the visitors given therein shall be considered by the advisory inspecting 
authority. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> While visiting an institution, the visitors will not say or do anything 
that undermines the authority of the Officer-in-Charge or is in contravention of 
the Act or rules or impinges on the dignity of the children. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The visitors may be allowed to visit observation homes and special homes 
with the permission of the competent authority. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>95</number> Juvenile Justice Fund. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The State Government shall 
create a Fund at the State level under section 61 of the Act to be called the 
Juvenile Justice Fund' (hereinunder referred to as the Fund) for the welfare 
and rehabilitation of the juvenile or the child dealt with under the provisions 
of the Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In addition to donations, contributions or subscriptions coming under 
sub-section (2) of section 61, the Central Government shall also make 
contribution to the Fund. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Fund shall be applied: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> to implement programmes for the welfare, rehabilitation and restoration 
  of juveniles or children; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> to pay grant-in-aid to non-governmental organizations; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> to meet the expenses of State Advisory Board and its purpose; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> to do all other things that are incidental and necessary for the above 
  purposes. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>4</number> The management and administration of the Fund shall be under the control 
of the State Advisory Board under sub-section (3) of section 61 of the Act. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The assets of the Fund shall include all such grants and contributions, 
recurring or non­-recurring, from the Central Government and State 
Government or any other statutory or non-statutory bodies set-up by the Central 
or State Government as well as the voluntary donations from any individual or 
organization. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> All withdrawals shall be made by cheques or requisitions, as the case may 
be, signed by the secretary-cum-treasurer and in the case of amounts exceeding 
rupees one thousand, they shall be signed duly by the secretary-cum-treasurer 
and a member of the board of management to be nominated by the State Advisory 
Board. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> The regular accounts shall be kept of all money and properties, and all 
incomes and expenditure of the Fund and shall be audited by a notified firm of 
Chartered Accountants, or any other recognized authorities as may be appointed 
by the Board. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> The auditors shall also certify the expenditure from the Fund made by the 
secretary-cum-treasurer. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> All contracts and other assurances shall be in the name of the board of 
management and signed on their behalf by the secretary-cum-treasurer and one 
member of the board of the management authorised by it for the purpose. 
 </section><section><number>10</number> The board of management shall invest for the time being the proceeds of 
sale or other disposal of the property, as well as any money or property not 
immediately required to be used to serve the objective of the Fund, in any one 
or more of the modes of investment authorised by law for the investment of trust 
moneys as the board of management may think proper. 
 </section><section><number>11</number> The board of management may delegate to one or more of the members such 
of its powers, which in its opinion are merely a procedural arrangement. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>96</number> Application of these rules. </title>It is hereby declared that 
until the new rules conforming to these rules are framed by the State Government 
concerned under section 68 of the Act, these rules shall mutatis mutandis 
apply in that State. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>97</number> Pending Cases. </title>
<section><number>1</number> No juvenile in conflict with law or 
a child shall be denied the benefits of the Act and the rules made thereunder. 
<title></title>
 </section><section><number>2</number> All pending cases which have not received a finality shall be dealt with 
and disposed of in terms of the provisions of the Act and the rules made 
thereunder. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Any juvenile in conflict with law, or a child shall be given the benefits 
under sub-rule (1) of this rule, and it is hereby clarified that such benefits 
shall be made available to all those accused who were juvenile or a child at the 
time of commission of an offence, even if they cease to be a juvenile or a child 
during the pendency of any inquiry or trial. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> While computing the period of detention or stay or sentence of a juvenile 
in conflict with law or of a child, all such period which the juvenile or the 
child has already spent in custody, detention, stay or sentence of imprisonment 
shall be counted as a part of the period of stay or detention or sentence of 
imprisonment contained in the final order of the court or the Board. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>98</number> Disposed off cases of juveniles in conflict with law. 
</title>The State Government or as the case may be the Board may, either 
suo motu or on an application made for the purpose, review the case of 
a person or a juvenile in conflict with law, determine his juvenility in terms 
of the provisions contained in the Act and rule 12 of these rules and pass an 
appropriate order in the interest of the juvenile in conflict with law under 
section 64 of the Act, for the immediate release of the juvenile in conflict 
with law whose period of detention or imprisonment has exceeded the maximum 
period provided in section 15 of the said Act. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>99</number> Disposal of records or documents. </title>The records or 
documents in respect of a juvenile or a child or a juvenile in conflict with law 
shall be kept in a safe place for a period of seven years and no longer, and 
thereafter be destroyed by the Officer-in-Charge or Board or Committee, as the 
case may be. </article> 

  
 <article><title><number>100</number> Repeal. </title>The Juvenile Justice (Care and Protection of 
Children) Rules, 2001, notified vide F.No.1-3/2001-SD, dated the 22nd 
June, 2001 in the Gazette of India, Extraordinary, Part I, Section 1 of the same 
date is hereby repealed. </article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Came into force on 26-10-2007.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>