<act><title>

THE PRESS AND REGISTRATION OF BOOKS ACT, 1867</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Interpretation-clause.—<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number>] 
    In this Act, unless there shall be something repugnant in the subject or 
    context,—
 
“Book” includes every volume, part or division 
    of a volume, and pamphlet, in any language, and every sheet of music, map, 
    chart or plan separately printed <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[***];
 
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[***]
 

4[“editor” 
    means the person who controls the selection of the matter that is published 
    in a newspaper;]
 

5[***] 8[***]"
 
“Magistrate” means any person exercising 
    the full powers of a 
6Magistrate, 
    and includes a <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>Magistrate of police <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[***];
 
<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[“newspaper” 
    means any printed periodical work containing public news or comments on 
    public news;]
 
<footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[***]
 
<footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[“paper” 
    means any document, including a newspaper, other than a book;
 
“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made by 
    the Central Government under section 20A;
 
“Press Registrar” means the Registrar of 
    newspapers for India appointed by the Central Government under section 19A 
    and includes any other person appointed by the Central Government to perform 
    all or any of the functions of the Press Registrar;
 
“printing” includes cyclostyling and printing 
    by lithography;
 
“Register” means the Register of newspapers 
    maintained under section 19B.]
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> 
    Any reference in this Act to any law which is not in force in the State of 
    Jammu and Kashmir shall, in relation to that State, be construed as a 
    reference to the corresponding law in force in that State.]
  




















 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> Repeal 
    of Act 11 of 1835.—[Rep. by 
    the Repealing Act, 1870 (14 of 1870), sec. 1 and Sch., Pt. II.] 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Particulars to be printed on books and papers.—Every 
    book or paper printed within <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[India] shall have printed legibly 
    on it the name of the printer and the place of printing, and (if the book or 
    paper be published) <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[the name] of the publisher, and the place 
    of publication.
  










 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Keeper of printing press to make declaration.—<footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number>] 
    No person shall within <footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[India], keep in his possession any press 
    for the printing of books or papers, who shall not have made and subscribed 
    the following declaration before 

    2[the District, 
    Presidency or Sub-divisional Magistrate] within whose local jurisdiction 
    such press may be:
 
“I, A.B., 
    declare that I have a press for printing at—”.
 
And this last 
    blank shall be filled up with a true and precise description of the place 
    where such press may be situate.
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[<number>2</number>] 
    As often as the place where a press is kept is changed, a new declaration 
    shall be necessary:
 
Provided that 
    where the change is for a period not exceeding sixty days and the place 
    where the press is kept after the change is within the local jurisdiction of 
    the Magistrate referred to in sub-section (1), no new declaration shall be 
    necessary if—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    a statement relating to the change is 
    furnished to the said Magistrate within twenty-four hours thereof; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the keeper of the press continues to be 
    the same.]
  








 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Rules as to publication of newspapers.—No
    <footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[newspaper] shall be published in <footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[India], except in 
    conformity with the rules hereinafter laid down:
 <section>
<footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[<number>1</number> 
    Without prejudice to the provisions of section 3, every copy of every such 
    newspaper shall contain the names of the owner and editor thereof printed 
    clearly on such copy and also the date of its publication.]
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[<number>2</number>] 
    The printer and the publisher of every such <footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[newspaper] shall 
    appear <footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[in person or by agent authorised in this behalf in 
    accordance with rules made under section 20, before a District, Presidency 
    or Sub-divisional Magistrate within whose local jurisdiction such newspaper 
    shall be printed or published <footcitenum>20</footcitenum>[***] and shall make and 
    subscribe, in duplicate, the following declaration:
 
“I A.B., 
    declare that I am the printer (or publisher, or printer and 
    publisher) of the <footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[newspaper] entitled—<footcitenum>21</footcitenum>[and to be 
    printed or published, or to be printed and published], as the case may be 
    at—”.
 
And the last 
    blank in this form of declaration shall be filled up with a true and precise 
    account of the premises where the printing or publication is conducted.
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>22</footcitenum>[<number>2A</number> 
    Every declaration under rule (2) shall specify the title of the newspaper, 
    the language in which it is to be published and the periodicity of its 
    publication and shall contain such other particulars as may be prescribed.]
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>23</footcitenum>[<number>2B</number> 
    Where the printer or publisher of a newspaper making a declaration under 
    rule (2) is not the owner thereof, the declaration shall specify the name of 
    the owner and shall also be accompanied by an authority in writing from the 
    owner authorising such person to make and subscribe such declaration.
 </section><section>
<number>2C</number> A 
    declaration in respect of a newspaper made under rule (2) and authenticated 
    under section 6 shall be necessary before the newspaper can be published.
 </section><section>
<number>2D</number> Where the 
    title of any newspaper or its language or the periodicity of its publication 
    is changed, the declaration shall cease to have effect and a new declaration 
    shall be necessary before the publication of the newspaper can be continued.
 </section><section>
<number>2E</number> As often 
    as the ownership of a newspaper is changed, a new declaration shall be 
    necessary.]
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>24</footcitenum>[<number>3</number>] 
    As often as the place of printing or publication is changed, a new 
    declaration shall be necessary:
 
<footcitenum>22</footcitenum>[Provided 
    that where the change is for a period not exceeding thirty days and the 
    place of printing or publication after the change is within the local 
    jurisdiction of the Magistrate referred to in rule (2), no new declaration 
    shall be necessary if—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    a statement relating to the change is 
    furnished to the said Magistrate within twenty-four hours thereof; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the printer or publisher or the printer 
    and publisher of the newspaper continues to be the same.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<footcitenum>25</footcitenum>[<number>4</number>] 
    As often as the printer or the publisher who shall have made such 
    declaration as is aforesaid shall leave India for a period exceeding ninety 
    days or where such printer or publisher is by infirmity or otherwise 
    rendered incapable of carrying out his duties for a period exceeding ninety 
    days in circumstances not involving the vacation of his appointment, a new 
    declaration shall be necessary.]
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>22</footcitenum>[<number>5</number> 
    Every declaration made in respect of a newspaper shall be void, where the 
    newspaper does not commence publication—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    within six weeks <footcitenum>26</footcitenum>[of the 
    authentication of the declaration under section 6], in the case of a 
    newspaper to be published once a week or oftener; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    within three months <footcitenum>26</footcitenum>[of 
    the authentication of the declaration under section 6], in the case of any 
    other newspaper,
 
and in every such case, a new declaration 
    shall be necessary before the newspaper can be published.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>6</number> Where, in 
    any period of three months, any daily, tri-weekly, bi-weekly, weekly or 
    fortnightly newspaper publishes issues the number of which is less than half 
    of what should have been published in accordance with the declaration made 
    in respect thereof, the declaration shall cease to have effect and a new 
    declaration shall be necessary before the publication of the newspaper can 
    be continued.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Where any 
    other newspaper has ceased publication for a period, exceeding twelve 
    months, every declaration made in respect thereof shall cease to have 
    effect, and a new declaration shall be necessary before the newspaper can be 
    re-published.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> Every 
    existing declaration in respect of a newspaper shall be cancelled by the 
    Magistrate before whom a new declaration is made and subscribed in respect 
    of the same:]
 
<footcitenum>27</footcitenum>[Provided 
    that no person <footcitenum>28</footcitenum>[who does not ordinarily reside in India, or] 
    who has not attained majority in accordance with the provisions of the 
    Indian Majority Act, 1875 (9 of 1875), or of the law to which he is subject 
    in respect of the attainment of majority, shall be permitted to make the 
    declaration prescribed by this section, nor shall any such person edit a 
    newspaper.]
 
 

















 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<footcitenum>29</footcitenum>[<number>5A</number> 
    Keepers of printing presses and printers and publishers of newspapers in 
    Jammu and Kashmir to make and subscribe fresh declarations within specified 
    period.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No person who has made and subscribed a declaration in respect of any press 
    under section 4 of the Jammu and Kashmir State Press and Publications Act, 
    S. 1989 (Jammu and Kashmir Act, No. I of S. 1989) shall keep the press in 
    his possession for the printing of books or papers <footcitenum>30</footcitenum>[after the 
    31st day of December, 1968, unless before the expiry of that date] he makes 
    and subscribes a fresh declaration in respect of that press under section 4 
    of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every person who has subscribed to any declaration in respect of a newspaper 
    under section 5 of the Jammu and Kashmir State Press and Publications Act, 
    S. 1989 (Jammu and Kashmir Act, No. 1 of S. 1989) shall cease to be the 
    editor, printer or publisher of the newspaper mentioned in such declaration
    

    2[after the 31st day 
    of December, 1968 unless before the expiry of that date] he makes and 
    subscribes a fresh declaration in respect of that newspaper under rule (2) 
    of the rules laid down in section 5 of this Act.]
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Authentication of declaration.—Each 
    of the two originals of every declaration so made and subscribed as is 
    aforesaid, shall be authenticated by the signature and official seal of the 
    Magistrate before whom the said declaration shall have been made:
 
<footcitenum>31</footcitenum>[Provided 
    that where any declaration is made and subscribed under section 5 in respect 
    of a newspaper, the declaration shall not, save in the case of newspapers 
    owned by the same person, be so authenticated unless the Magistrate <footcitenum>32</footcitenum>[is, 
    on inquiry from the Press Registrar, satisfied] that the newspaper proposed 
    to be published does not bear a title which is the same as, or similar to, 
    that of any other newspaper published either in the same language or in the 
    same State.]
 <section>

    <number>Deposit</number>—One 
    of the said originals shall be deposited among the records of the office of 
    the Magistrate, and the other shall be deposited among the records of the 
    High Court of Judicature, or <footcitenum>33</footcitenum>[other principal Civil Court of 
    original jurisdiction for the place where] the said declaration shall have 
    been made.
 
Inspection 
    and supply of copies.—The 
    Officer-in -charge of each original shall allow any person to inspect that 
    original on payment of a fee of one rupee, and shall give to any person 
    applying a copy of the said declaration, attested by the seal of the Court 
    which has the custody of the original, on payment of a fee of two rupees.
 
<footcitenum>34</footcitenum>[A 
    copy of the declaration attested by the official seal of the Magistrate, or 
    a copy of the order refusing to authenticate the declaration, shall be 
    forwarded as soon as possible to the person making and subscribing the 
    declaration and also to the Press Registrar.]
 
 
  






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Office copy of declaration to be prima facie evidence.—In 
    any legal proceeding whatever, as well civil as criminal, the production of 
    a copy of such declaration as is aforesaid, attested by the seal of some 
    Court empowered by this Act to have the custody of such declarations, 


    1[or, in the case of 
    the editor, a copy of the newspaper containing his name printed on it as 
    that of the editor] shall be held (unless the contrary be proved) to be 
    suficient evidence, as against the person whose name shall be subscribed to 
    such declaration, 

    1[or printed on such 
    newspaper, as the case may be] that the said person was printer or 
    publisher, or printer and publisher (according as the words of the said 
    declaration may be) of every portion of every 

    2[newspaper] whereof 
    the title shall correspond with the title of the 

    2[newspaper] mentioned 
    in the declaration, 

    5[or the editor of 
    every portion of that issue of the newspaper of which a copy is produced].
  











 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    New declaration by persons who have signed a declaration and subsequently 
    ceased to be printers or publishers.—<footcitenum>37</footcitenum>[If 
    any person has subscribed to any declaration in respect of a newspaper under 
    section 5 and the declaration has been authenticated by a Magistrate under 
    section 6 and subsequently that person ceases to be the printer or publisher 
    of the newspaper mentioned in such declaration, he shall appear before any 
    District, Presidency or Sub-divisional Magistrate, and make and subscribe in 
    duplicate the following declaration:—
 
“I, A.B., declare that I have ceased to be the 
    printer or publisher or printer and publisher of the newspaper entitled—”.]
 

    Authentication and filing.—Each 
    original of the latter declaration shall be authenticated by the signature 
    and seal of the Magistrate before whom the said latter declaration shall 
    have been made, and one original of the said latter declaration shall be 
    filed along with each original of the former declaration.
 
Inspection 
    and supply of copies.—The 
    Officer-in-charge of each original of the latter declaration shall allow any 
    person applying to inspect that original on payment of a fee of one rupee, 
    and shall give to any person applying a copy of the said latter declaration, 
    attested by the seal of the Court having custody of the original, on payment 
    of a fee of two rupees.
 

    Putting copy in evidence.—In 
    all trials in which a copy, attested as is aforesaid, of the former 
    declaration shall have been put in evidence, it shall be lawful to put in 
    evidence a copy, attested as is aforesaid, of the latter declaration, and 
    the former declaration shall not be taken to be evidence that the declarant 
    was, at any period subsequent to the date of the latter declaration, printer 
    or publisher of the <footcitenum>38</footcitenum>[newspaper] therein mentioned.
 
<footcitenum>39</footcitenum>[A 
    copy of the latter declaration attested by the official seal of the 
    Magistrate shall be forwarded to the Press Registrar.]
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>8A</number> Person 
    whose name has been incorrectly published as editor may make a declaration 
    before a Magistrate.—If 
    any person, whose name has appeared as editor on a copy of a newspaper, 
    claims that he was not the editor of the issue on which his name has so 
    appeared, he may, within two weeks of his becoming aware that his name has 
    been so published, appear before a District, Presidency or Sub-Divisional 
    Magistrate and make a declaration that his name was incorrectly published in 
    that issue as that of the editor thereof, and if the Magistrate after making 
    such inquiry or causing such inquiry to be made as he may consider necessary 
    is satisfied that such declaration is true, he shall certify accordingly, 
    and on that certificate being given the provisions of section 7 shall not 
    apply to that person in respect of that issue of the newspaper.
 
The Magistrate may 
    extend the period allowed by this section in any case where he is satisfied 
    that such person was prevented by sufficient cause from appearing and making 
    the declaration within that period.]






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>41</footcitenum>[<number>8B</number> 
    Cancellation of declaration.—If, 
    on an application made to him by the Press Registrar or any other person or 
    otherwise, the Magistrate empowered to authenticate a declaration under this 
    Act, is of opinion that any declaration made in respect of a newspaper 
    should be cancelled, he may, after giving the person concerned an 
    opportunity of showing cause against the action proposed to be taken, hold 
    an inquiry into the matter and if, after considering the cause, if any, 
    shown by such person and after giving him an opportunity of being heard, he 
    is satisfied that—
 <section>
<number>i</number>    the newspaper, in respect of which the 
    declaration has been made is being published in contravention of the 
    provisions of this Act or rules made thereunder; or
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    the newspaper mentioned in the 
    declaration bears a title which is the same as, or similar to, that of any 
    other newspaper published either in the same language or in the same State; 
    or
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>    the printer or publisher has ceased 
    to be the printer or publisher of the newspaper mentioned in such 
    declaration; or
 </section><section>
<number>iv</number>    the declaration was made on false 
    representation or on the concealment of any material fact or in respect of a 
    periodical work which is not a newspaper;
 
the Magistrate may, by order, cancel the 
    declaration and shall forward as soon as possible a copy of the order to the 
    person making or subscribing the declaration and also to the Press 
    Registrar.
  
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8C</number> 
    Appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person aggrieved by an order of a Magistrate refusing to authenticate a 
    declaration under section 6 or cancelling a declaration under section 8B 
    may, within sixty days from the date on which such order is communicated to 
    him, prefer an appeal to the Appellate Board to be called the Press and 
    Registration Appellate Board <footcitenum>42</footcitenum>[consisting of a Chairman and 
    another member to be nominated by the Press Council of India, established 
    under section 4 of the Press Council Act, 1978 (37 of 1978), from among its 
    members]:
 
Provided that 
    the Appellate Board may entertain an appeal after the expiry of the said 
    period, if it is satisfied that the appellant was prevented by sufficient 
    cause from preferring the appeal in time.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On receipt 
    of an appeal under this section, the Appellate Board may, after calling for 
    the records from the Magistrate and after making such further inquiries as 
    it thinks fit, confirm, modify or set aside the order appealed against.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Subject to 
    the provisions contained in sub-section (2), the Appellate Board may, by 
    order, regulate its practice and procedure.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    decision of the Appellate Board shall be final.]
 
 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Copies of books printed after commencement of Act to be delivered gratis 
    to Government.—Printed
    <footcitenum>43</footcitenum>[***] copies of the whole of every book which shall be printed
    <footcitenum>43</footcitenum>[***] in <footcitenum>44</footcitenum>[India] after this Act shall come into 
    force, together with all maps, prints or other engravings belonging thereto, 
    finished and coloured in the same manner as the best copies of the same, 
    shall, notwithstanding any agreement (if the book be published) between the 
    printer and publisher thereof, be delivered by the printer at such place and 
    to such officer as the State Government shall, by notification in the 
    Official Gazette, from time to time direct, and free of expense to the 
    Government, as follows, that is to say:—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    in any case, within one calendar month 
    after the day on which any such book shall first be delivered out of the 
    press, one such copy, and,
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    if within one calendar year from such 
    day the State Government shall require the printer to deliver other such 
    copies not exceeding two in number, then within one calendar month after the 
    day on which any such requisition shall be made by the State Government on 
    the printer, another such copy, or two other such copies, as the State 
    Government may direct,
 
the copies so delivered being bound, sewed or 
    stitched together and upon the best paper on which any copies of the book 
    shall be printed 
<footcitenum>43</footcitenum>[***].
 
The publisher 
    or other person employing the printer shall, at a reasonable time before the 
    expiration of the said month, supply him with all maps, prints and 
    engravings finished and coloured as aforesaid, which may be necessary to 
    enable him to comply with the requirements aforesaid.
 
Nothing in the 
    former part of this section shall apply to—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    any second or subsequent edition of a 
    book in which edition no additions or alterations either in the letter-press 
    or in the maps, prints or other engravings belonging to the book have been 
    made, and a copy of the first or some preceding edition of which book has 
    been delivered under this Act, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    any <footcitenum>45</footcitenum>[newspaper] published 
    in conformity with the rules laid down in section 5 of this Act.
 
 





 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Receipt 
    for copies delivered under section 9.—The 
    officer to whom a copy of a book is delivered under the last foregoing 
    section shall give to the printer a receipt in writing therefor. foregoing 
    section shall give to the printer a receipt in writing therefor."
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Disposal of copies delivered under section 9.—The 
    copy delivered pursuant to clause 
<section><number>a</number> of the first paragraph of section 9 of 
    this Act shall be disposed of as the State Government shall from time to 
    time determine.
 
Any copy 
    or copies delivered pursuant to clause (b) of the said paragraph shall be
    <footcitenum>46</footcitenum>[transmitted to the Central Government].
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>47</footcitenum>[<number>11A</number> 
    Copies of newspapers printed in India to be delivered gratis to 
    Government.—The 
    printer of every newspaper in <footcitenum>48</footcitenum>[India] shall deliver at such 
    place and to such officer as the State Government may, by notification in 
    the Official Gazette, direct, and free of expense to the Government, two 
    copies of each issue of such newspaper as soon as it is published.]
 



  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>49</footcitenum>[<number>11B</number> 
    Copies of newspapers to be delivered to Press Registrar.—Subject 
    to any rules that may be made under this Act, the publisher of every 
    newspaper in India shall deliver free of expense to the Press Registrar one 
    copy of each issue of such newspaper as soon as it is published.]
 
 



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Penalty for 
    printing contrary to rule in section 3.— 
    Whoever shall print or publish any book or paper otherwise than in 
    conformity with the rule contained in section 3 of this Act, shall, on 
    conviction before a Magistrate, be punished by fine not exceeding 
1[two 
    thousand] rupees, or by simple imprisonment for a term not exceeding 
2[six 
    months], or by both.







 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Penalty for keeping press without making declaration required by section 4.—
Whoever shall keep in his possession any such press as aforesaid. <footcitenum>52</footcitenum>[In 
    contravention of any of the provisions contained in section 4 of this Act], 
    shall, on conviction before a Magistrate, be punished by fine not exceeding
    <footcitenum>53</footcitenum>[two thousand] rupees, or by simple imprisonment for a term not 
    exceeding <footcitenum>54</footcitenum>[six months] or by both.
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Punishment for making false statement.—Any 
    person who shall, in making <footcitenum>57</footcitenum>[any declaration or other statement] 
    under the authority of this Act, make a statement which is false, and which 
    he either knows or believes to be false, or does not believe to be true, 
    shall, on conviction before a Magistrate, be punished by fine not exceeding
    <footcitenum>55</footcitenum>[two thousand] rupees, and imprisonment for a term not exceeding
    <footcitenum>56</footcitenum>[six months].
 
 





 



</article> 

  
 <article>
<number>15</number> Penalty for 
printing or publishing newspaper without conforming to rules.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
Whoever shall 

2[edit], print or 
publish any 

3[newspaper], 
without conforming to the rules hereinbefore laid down, or whoever shall 

2[edit], print or 
publish, or shall cause to be 

2[edited], printed 
or published, any 

4[newspaper], 
knowing that the said rules have not been observed with respect to 

5[that newspaper], 
shall, on conviction before a Magistrate, be punished with fine not exceeding


6[two thousand] 
rupees, or imprisonment for a term not exceeding 

7[six months] or 
both.
 

8[(2) Where an 
offence is committed in relation to a newspaper under sub-section (1), the 
Magistrate may, in addition to the punishment imposed under the said 
sub-section, also cancel the declaration in respect of the newspaper.]
 
 










</section></article> 

  
 <article>


1[<number>15A</number> Penalty for 
failure to make a declaration under section 8.—If 
any person who has ceased to be a printer or publisher of any newspaper fails or 
neglects to make a declaration in compliance with section 8, he shall, on 
conviction before a Magistrate, be punishable by fine not exceeding two hundred 
rupees.]
 
 



</article> 
 


The Press and Registration of Books Act, 1867
  
 <article>


1[<number>16</number> Penalty for 
not delivering books or not supplying printer with maps.—If 
any printer of any such book as is referred to in section 9 of this Act shall 
neglect to deliver copies of the same pursuant to that section, he shall for 
every such default forfeit to the Government such sum not exceeding fifty rupees 
as a Magistrate having jurisdiction in the place where the book was printed may, 
on the application of the officer to whom the copies should have been delivered 
or of any person authorised by that officer in this behalf, determine to be in 
the circumstances a reasonable penalty for the default, and, in addition to such 
sum, such further sum as the Magistrate may determine to be the value of the 
copies which the printer ought to have delivered.
 
If any publisher or other 
person employing any such printer shall neglect to supply him, in the matter 
prescribed in the second paragraph of section 9 of this Act with the maps, 
prints or engravings which may be necessary to enable him to comply with the 
provisions of that section, such publisher or other person shall for every such 
default forfeit to the Government such sum not exceeding fifty rupees as such a 
Magistrate as aforesaid may, on such an application as aforesaid, determine to 
be in the circumstances a reasonable penalty for the default, and, in addition 
to such sum, such further sum as the Magistrate may determine to be the value of 
the maps, prints or engravings which such publisher or other person ought to 
have supplied.]
 
 



</article> 

  
 <article>

1[<number>16A</number> Penalty 
for failure to supply copies of newspapers gratis to Government.—If 
any printer of any newspaper published in 

2[India] neglects 
to deliver copies of the same in compliance with section 11A, he shall, on the 
complaint of the officer to whom copies should have been delivered or of any 
person authorised by that officer in this behalf, be punishable, on conviction 
by a Magistrate having jurisdiction in the place where the newspaper was 
printed, with fine which may extend to fifty rupees for every default.]
 
 




</article> 

  
 <article>

1[<number>16B</number> Penalty 
for failure to supply copies of newspapers to Press Registrar.—If any 
publisher of any newspaper published in India neglects to deliver copies of the 
same in compliance with section 11B, he shall, on the complaint of the Press 
Registrar, be punishable, on conviction by a Magistrate having jurisdiction in 
the place where the newspaper was printed, by fine which may extend to fifty 
rupees for every default.]
 
 



</article> 

  
 <article>


1[<number>17</number> Recovery of 
forfeitures and disposal thereof and of fines.—Any 
sum forfeited to the Government under 

2[section 16] may 
be recovered, under the warrant of the Magistrate determining the sum, or of his 
successor in office, in the manner authorised by the Code of Criminal Procedure 
(10 of 1882)3 for 
the time being in force, and within the period prescribed by the Indian Penal 
Code (45 of 1860), for the levy of a fine.
 

4[***]
 
 






</article> 

  
 <article>
<number>18</number> Registration of 
memoranda of books.—There 
shall be kept at such office, and by such officer as the State Government shall 
appoint in this behalf, a book to be called a Catalogue of Books printed in


1[India], wherein 
shall be registered a memorandum of every book which shall have been delivered


2[pursuant to 
clause 
<section><number>a</number> of the first paragraph of section 9] of this Act. Such memorandum 
shall (so far as may be practicable) contain the following particulars (that is 
to say):—
 <subsection>
       <number>1</number>  the title of 
the book and the contents of the title-page, with a translation into English of 
such title and contents, when the same are not in the English language;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>2</number>  the language 
in which the book is written;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>3</number>  the name of 
the author, translator, or editor of the book or any part thereof;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>4</number>  the subject;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>5</number>  the place of 
printing and the place of publication;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>6</number>  the name of 
firm of the printer and the name of firm of the publisher;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>7</number>  the date of 
issue from the press or of the publication;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>8</number>  the number of 
sheets, leaves or pages;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>9</number>  the size;
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>10</number>  the first, 
second or other number of the edition;
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>11</number>  the number of 
copies of which the edition consists;
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>12</number>  whether the 
book is printed, 

3[cyclostyled or 
lithographed];
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>13</number>  the price at 
which the book is sold to the public; and
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>14</number>  the name and 
residence of the proprietor of the copyright or of any portion of such 
copyright.
 
Such memorandum shall be 
made and registered in the case of each book as soon as practicable after the 
delivery of the 

4[copy thereof 
pursuant to clause (a) of the first paragraph of section 9] 

5[***]
 
 







</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>19</number> Publication of 
memoranda registered.—The 
memoranda registered during each quarter in the said Catalogue shall be 
published in the Official Gazette, as soon as may be after the end of such 
quarter, and a copy of the memoranda so published shall be sent 

1[***] to the 
Central Government 

2[***].
 
 




</article> 

  
 <article>
*<number>19A</number> Appointment of 
Press Registrar and other officers.—The 
Central Government may appoint a Registrar of newspapers for India and such 
other officers under the general superintendence and control of the Press 
Registrar as may be necessary for the purpose of performing the functions 
assigned to them by or under this Act, and may, by general or special order, 
provide for the distribution or allocation of functions to be performed by them 
under this Act.



</article> 

  
 <article>
*<number>19B</number> Register of 
newspapers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Press Registrar shall maintain in the prescribed manner a Register of 
newspapers.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Register shall, as 
far as may be practicable, contain the following particulars about every 
newspaper published in India, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> the title of 
the newspaper;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the language 
in which the newspaper is published;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  periodicity of 
the publication of the newspaper;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  the name of 
the editor, printer and publisher of the newspaper;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  the place of 
printing and publication;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  the average 
number of pages per week;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>g</number>  the number of 
days of publication in the year;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>h</number>  the average 
number of copies printed, the average number of copies sold to the public and 
the average number of copies distributed free to the public, the average being 
calculated with reference to such period as may be prescribed;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>i</number>  retail 
selling price per copy;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>j</number>  the names and 
addresses of the owners of the newspaper and such other particulars relating to 
ownership as may be prescribed;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>k</number>  any other 
particulars which may be prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> On receiving 
information from time to time about the aforesaid particulars, the Press 
Registrar shall cause relevant entries to be made in the Register and may make 
such necessary alterations or corrections therein as may be required for keeping 
the Register up-to-date.
 
 



</section></article> 

  
 <article>
*<number>19C</number> Certificates of 
registration.—On 
receiving from the Magistrate under section 6 a copy of the declaration in 
respect of a newspaper 

1[and on the 
publication of such newspaper, the Press Registrar shall], as soon as 
practicable thereafter, issue a certificate of registration in respect of that 
newspaper to the publisher thereof.
 
 




</article> 

  
 <article>
*<number>19D</number> Annual statement, 
etc., to be furnished by newspapers.—It 
shall be the duty of the publisher of every newspaper—
 <section>
       <number>a</number> to furnish to 
the Press Registrar an annual statement in respect of the newspaper at such time 
and containing such of the particulars referred to in sub-section (2) of section 
19B as may be prescribed;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number> to publish in 
the newspaper at such times and such of the particulars relating to the 
newspaper referred to in sub-section (2) of section 19B as may be specified in 
this behalf by the Press Registrar.






</section></article> 

  
 <article>
*<number>19E</number> Returns and 
reports to be furnished by newspapers.—The 
publisher of every newspaper shall furnish to the Press Registrar such returns, 
statistics and other information with respect to any of the particulars referred 
to in sub- 
section (2) of section 19B as the Press Registrar may from time to time require.



</article> 

  
 <article>
*<number>19F</number> Right of access 
to records and documents.—The 
Press Registrar or any gazetted officer authorised by him in writing in this 
behalf shall, for the purpose of the collection of any information relating to a 
newspaper under this Act, have access to any relevant record or document 
relating to the newspaper in the possession of the publisher thereof, and may 
enter at any reasonable time any premises where he believes such record or 
document to be and may inspect or take copies of the relevant records or 
documents or ask any question necessary for obtaining any information required 
to be furnished under this Act.



</article> 

  
 <article>
*<number>19G</number> Annual report.—The 
Press Registrar shall prepare, in such form and at such time each year as may be 
prescribed, an annual report containing a summary of the information obtained by 
him during the previous year in respect of the newspapers in India and giving an 
account of the working of such newspapers, and copies thereof shall be forwarded 
to the Central Government.



</article> 

  
 <article>
*<number>19H</number> Furnishing of 
copies of extracts from Register.—On 
the application of any person for the supply of the copy of any extract from the 
Register and on payment of such fee as may be prescribed, the Press Registrar 
shall furnish such copy to the applicant in such form and manner as may be 
prescribed.
 
 



</article> 

  
 <article>
*<number>19-I</number> Delegation of 
powers.—Subject 
to the provisions of this Act and regulations made thereunder, the Press 
Registrar may delegate all or any of his powers under this Act to any officer 
subordinate to him.



</article> 

  
 <article>
*<number>19J</number> Press Registrar 
and other officers to be public servants.—The 
Press Registrar and all officers appointed under this Act shall be deemed to be 
public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 
1860).
 
 



</article> 

  
 <article>
*<number>19K</number> Penalty for 
contravention of section 19D or section 19E, etc.—If 
the publisher of any newspaper—
 <section>
       <number>a</number> refuses or 
neglects to comply with the provisions of section 19D or section 19E; or
 

   1[***]
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number> publishers in 
the newspaper in pursuance of clause (b) of section 19D any particulars relating 
to the newspaper which he has reason to believe to be false,
 
he shall be punishable 
with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees.
 
 




</section></article> 

  
 <article>
*<number>19L</number> Penalty for 
improper disclosure of information.—If 
any person engaged in connection with the collection of information under this 
Act wilfully discloses any information or the contents of any return given or 
furnished under this Act otherwise than in the execution of his duties under 
this Act or for the purposes of the prosecution of an offence under this Act or 
under the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860), he shall be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine which may 
extend to one thousand rupees, or with both.
 
 


</article> 

  
 <article>


1[<number>20</number> Power of 
State Government to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make such 
rules (not inconsistent with the rules made by the Central Government under 
section 20A) as may be necessary or desirable for carrying out the objects of 
this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every rule made by the 
State Government under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is 
made, before the State Legislature.]
 
 



</section></article> 

  
 <article>

1[<number>20A</number> Power of 
Central Government to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> prescribing the 
particulars which a declaration made and subscribed under section 5 may contain;


2[and the form and 
manner in which the names of the printer, publisher, owner and editor of a 
newspaper and the place of its printing and publication may be printed on every 
copy of such newspaper];
 

        3[(b) 
prescribing the manner in which copies of any declaration attested by the 
official seal of a Magistrate or copies of any order refusing to authenticate 
any declaration may be forwarded to the person making and subscribing the 
declaration and to the Press Registrar;]
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  prescribing 
the manner in which copies of any newspaper may be sent to the Press Registrar 
under section 11B;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  prescribing 
the manner in which a Register may be maintained under section 19B and the 
particulars which it may contain;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  prescribing 
the particulars in which an annual statement to be furnished by the publisher of 
a newspaper to the Press Registrar may contain;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  prescribing 
the form and manner in which an annual statement under clause (a) of section 
19D, or any returns, statistics or other information under section 19E, may be 
furnished to the Press Registrar;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>g</number>  prescribing 
the fees for furnishing copies of extracts from the Register and the manner in 
which such copies may be furnished;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>h</number>  prescribing 
the manner in which a certificate of registration may be issued in respect of a 
newspaper;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>i</number> prescribing 
the form in which, and the time within which, annual reports may be prepared by 
the Press Registrar and forwarded to the Central Government.
 

4[(2) Every rule 
made under this section shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made, before 
each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty 
days which may be comprised in one session or 

5[in two or more 
successive sessions and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid] both houses agree in 
making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should 
not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or 
be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done 
under that rule.]]
 
 







</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article>


1[<number>20B</number> Rules made 
under this Act may provide that contravention thereof shall be punishable.—
Any rule made 
under any provision of this Act may provide that any contravention thereof shall 
be punishable with fine which may extend to one hundred rupees.]
 
 



</article> 

  
 <article>
<number>21</number> Power to exclude 
any class of books from operation of Act.—1[The 
State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette], exclude any 
class of books 

2[or papers] from 
the operation of the whole or any part or parts of this Act:
 

3[Provided that no 
such notification in respect of any class of newspapers shall be issued without 
consulting the Central Government.]
 
 





</article> 

  
 <article>


1[<number>22</number> Extent.—This 
Act extends to the whole of India 

2[***].]
 
 




</article> 

  
 <article>
<number>23</number> Commencement of 
Act.—[Rep. 
by the Repealing Act, 1870 (14 of 1870), sec. 1 and Sch., Pt. II.]
 
 
</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Section 1 re-numbered as 
    sub-section (1) thereof by Act 16 of 1965, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 1-11-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   The words “or lithographed” 
    omitted by Act 55 of 1955, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 1-7-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   Definition of “British 
    India” rep. by the A.O. 1937 see now the definition in sec. 3 (5) of 
    the General Clauses Act, 1897 (10 of 1897).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   Now Presidency Magistrate,
    see Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>   The words “and a Justice of 
    the Peace” rep. by Act 10 of 1890, sec. 2.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>   Ins. by Act 14 of 1922, 
    sec. 3 and Sch. I.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>  Paragraphs relating to the 
    definitions of “Number” and “Gender” rep. by Act 10 of 1914, sec. 3 and Sch. 
    II; definition of “Local Government” rep. by the A.O. 1937 and the 
    definition of “States” ins. by the A.O. 1950 was rep. by Act 3 of 1951, sec. 
    3 and Sch.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>   Ins. by Act 55 of 1955, 
    sec. 4 (w.e.f. 1-7-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>   Ins. by Act 16 1965, sec.  
    2 (w.e.f. 1-11-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>   Subs. by Act 3 of 
    1951, sec. 3 and Sch., for “the States”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>   Ins. by Act 12 of 
    1891, sec. 2 and Sch. II, Pt. I.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>   Section 4 re-numbered 
    as sub-section (1) of that section by Act 55 of 1955, sec. 5 (w.e.f.  
    1-7-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>   Subs. by Act 56 of 
    1951, sec. 36, for “the Magistrate” (w.e.f. 1-2-1952).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>   Ins. by Act 55 of 
    1955, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-7-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>   Subs. by Act 14 of 
    1922, sec. 3 and Sch. I, for certain words.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>   Subs. by Act 3 of 
    1951, sec. 3 and Sch., for “the States”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number>   Subs. by Act 26 of 
    1960, sec. 2, for rule (1) (w.e.f. 1-10-1960) which was ins. by Act 14 of 
    1922, sec. 3 and Sch. I.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number>   Rule (1) re-numbered 
    as rule (2) by Act 14 of 1922, sec. 3 and Sch. I.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number>   Subs. by Act 14 of 
    1922, sec. 3 and Sch. I, for “periodical work”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number>   The words “, or such 
    printer or publisher resides,” omitted by Act 26 of 1960, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 
    1-10-1960).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number>   Subs. by Act 55 of 
    1955, sec. 6, for certain words (w.e.f. 1-7-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number>   Ins. by Act 55 of 
    1955, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 1-7-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number>   Ins. by Act 26 of 
    1960, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 1-10-1960).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number>   Rule (2) re-numbered as 
    rule (3) by Act 14 of 1922, sec. 3 and Sch, I.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number>   Subs. by Act 26 of 
    1960, sec. 2 for rule (4) (w.e.f. 1-10-1960) which had been re-numbered for 
    the original rule (3) by Act 14 of 1922, sec. 3 and Sch. I.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number>   Subs. by Act 26 of 
    1960, sec. 2, for “of the declaration” (w.e.f. 1-10-1960).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number>   Ins. by Act 14 of 1922, 
    sec. 3 and Sch. I</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>28</number>   Ins. by Act 26 of 1960, 
    sec. 2 (w.e.f. 1-10-1960).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>29</number>   Ins. by Act 16 of 
    1965, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-11-1965).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>30</number>   Subs. by Act 30 of 
    1968, sec. 2, for certain words (retrospectively).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>31</number>   Ins. by Act 55 of 
    1955, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 1-7-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>32</number>   Subs. by Act 26 of 
    1960, sec. 3, for certain words (w.e.f. 1-10-1960).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>33</number>   Subs. by Act 10 of 
    1890, sec. 3, for certain words.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>34</number>   Subs. by Act 26 of 
    1960, sec. 3, for the fourth paragraph (w.e.f. 1-10-1960) which was ins. by 
    Act 55 of 1955, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 1-7-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>35</number>   Ins. by Act 14 of 
    1922, sec. 3 and Sch. I.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>36</number>   Subs. by Act 14 of 
    1922, sec. 3 and Sch. I, for “periodical work”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>37</number>   Subs. by Act 55 of 
    1955, sec. 8, for the first paragraph (w.e.f. 1-7-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>38</number>   Subs. by Act 14 of 
    1922, sec. 3 and Sch. I, for “periodical work”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>39</number>   Ins. by Act 55 of 
    1955, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-7-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>40</number>   Ins. by Act 14 of 
    1922, sec. 3 and Sch. I.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>41</number>   Ins. by Act 26 of 
    1960, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 1-10-1960).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>42</number>   Subs. by Act 37 of 
    1978, sec. 27, for certain words.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>43</number>   The words “or 
    lithographed” omitted by Act 55 of 1955, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 1-7-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>44</number>   Subs. by Act 3 of 
    1951, sec. 3 and Sch., for “the States”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>45</number>   Subs. by Act 14 of 
    1922, sec. 3 and Sch. I, for “periodical work”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>46</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 
    1948, for certain words.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>47</number>   Ins. by Act 14 of 
    1922, sec. 3 and Sch. I.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>48</number>   Subs. by Act 3 of 
    1951, sec. 3 and Sch., for “the States”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>49</number>   Ins. by Act 55 of 
    1955, sec. 10 (w.e.f. 1-7-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>50</number>   Subs. by Act 14 of 
    1922, sec. 3 and Sch. I, for “five thousand”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>51</number>   Subs. by Act 14 of 
    1922, sec. 3 and Sch. I, for “two years”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>52</number>   Subs. by Act 55 of 
    1955, sec. 11, for “without making such a declaration as is required by 
    section 4 of this Act” (w.e.f. 1-7-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>53</number>   Subs. by Act 14 of 
    1922, sec. 3 and Sch. I, for “five thousand”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>54</number>   Subs. by Act 14 of 
    1922, sec. 3 and Sch. I, for “two years”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>55</number>   Subs. by Act 14 of 1922, sec. 3 and Sch. I, for “five thousand”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>56</number>   Subs. by Act 14 of 1922, sec. 3 and Sch. I, for “two years”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>57</number>   Subs. by Act 55 of 1955, sec. 12, for “any declaration” (w.e.f. 
    1-7-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>58</number>  Section 15 
re-numbered as sub-section (1) of that section by Act 26 of 1960, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 
1-10-1960).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>59</number>  Ins. by Act 14 of 
1922, sec. 3 and Sch. I.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>60</number>  Subs. by Act 14 of 
1922, sec. 3 and Sch. I, for “such periodical work as is hereinbefore 
described”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>61</number>  Subs. by Act 14 of 
1922, sec. 3 and Sch. I, for “such periodical work”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>62</number>  Subs. by Act 14 of 
1922, sec. 3 and Sch. I, for “that work”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>63</number>  Subs. by Act 14 of 
1922, sec. 3 and Sch. I, for “five thousand”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>64</number>  Subs. by Act 14 of 
1922, sec. 3 and Sch. I, for “two years”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>65</number>  Ins. by Act 26 of 
1960, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-10-1960).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>66</number>  Ins. by Act 55 of 
1955, sec. 13 (w.e.f. 1-7-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>67</number>  Subs. by Act 10 of 
1890, sec. 5, for sections 16.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>68</number>  Ins. by Act 14 of 
1922, sec. 3 and Sch. I.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>69</number>  Subs. by Act 3 of 
1951, sec. 3 and Sch., for “the States” (w.e.f. 1-4-1951).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>70</number>  Ins. by Act 55 of 
1955, sec. 14 (w.e.f. 1-7-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>71</number>  Subs. by Act 10 of 
1890, sec. 5, for section 17.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>72</number>  Subs. by Act 11 of 
1923, sec. 2 and Sch. I, for “the last foregoing section”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>73</number>  See Now the 
Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>74</number>  The second paragraph 
rep. by the A.O. 1937.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>75</number>  Subs. by Act 3 of 
1951, sec. 3 and Sch., for “the States” (w.e.f. 1-4-1951).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>76</number>  Subs. by Act 10 of 
1890, sec. 6, for “pursuant to section 9”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>77</number>  Subs. by Act 55 of 
1955, sec. 15, for “or lithographed” (w.e.f. 1-7-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>78</number>  Subs. by Act 10 of 
1890, sec. 6, for “copies thereof in manner aforesaid”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>79</number>  Last sentence of 
section 18 rep. by Act 3 of 1914, sec. 15 and Sch. II.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>80</number>  The words “to the 
said Secretary of State, and” rep. by the A.O. 1948.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>81</number>  The word 
“respectively” omitted by the A.O. 1948.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>82</number>  Subs. by Act 26 of 
1960, sec. 6, for certain words (w.e.f. 1-10-1960).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>83</number>  C1ause (b) omitted 
by Act 26 of 1960, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 1-10-1960).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>84</number>  Subs. by Act 20 of 
1983, sec. 2 and Sch., for section 20 (w.e.f. 15-3-1984).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>85</number>  Ins. by Act 55 of 
1955, sec. 18 (w.e.f. 1-7-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>86</number>  Ins. by Act 26 of 
1960, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-10-1960).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>87</number>  Subs. by Act 26 of 
1960, sec. 8, for clause (b) (w.e.f. 1-10-1960).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>88</number>  Subs. by Act 26 of 
1960, sec. 8, for sub-section (2) (w.e.f. 1-10-1960).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>89</number>  Subs. by Act 20 of 
1983, sec. 2 and Sch., for certain words (w.e.f. 15-3-1984).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>90</number>  Ins. by Act 26 of 
1960, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 1-10-1960).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>91</number>  Subs. by the A.O. 
1937, for certain words.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>92</number>  Ins. by Act 11 of 
1915, sec.2 and Sch. I.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>93</number>  Ins. by Act 26 of 
1960, sec. 10 (w.e.f. 1-10-1960).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>94</number>  Ins. by Act 55 of 
1955, sec. 19 (w.e.f. 1-7-1956). Earlier section 22 was repealed by Act 10 of 
1890, sec. 7.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>95</number>  The words “except 
the State of Jammu and Kashmir” omitted by Act 16 of 1965, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 
1-11-1965).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>