<act><title>


The National Highways Authority Of India 
(Budget, Accounts, Audit, Investment Of 
Funds, And Powers To Enter Premises) 
Rules, 19901</title> 

 



 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the National Highways Authority of India (Budget, 
Accounts, Audit, Investment of Funds, and Powers to Enter Premises) Rules, 1990.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 



</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires.—
 <section>
       
<number>a</number>  “Act” means the National Highways Authority of India Act, 1988 (68 of 
1988);
 </section><section>
       
<number>b</number>  “Annual Report” means the Annual Report referred to in section 22 of 
the Act;
 </section><section>
       
<number>c</number>  “Annual Statement of Accounts” means the Annual sketch of accounts 
referred to in section 23 of the Act;
 </section><section>
       
<number>d</number>  “Audit Officer” means the Comptroller and Auditor General of India and 
includes any person appointed by him in connection with the audit of accounts of 
the Authority;
 </section><section>
       
<number>e</number>  “Authority” means the National Highways Authority of India constituted 
under section 3 of the Act;
 </section><section>
        
<number>f</number>  “financial year” means the financial year of the Central Government 
starting from first day of April each year and ending on thirty-first day of 
March of the following year;
 </section><section>
       
<number>g</number>  “Form” means a form annexed to these rules;
 </section><section>
       
<number>h</number>  “Fund” means the National Highways Authority of India Fund constituted 
under section 18 of the Act.
</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>3</number> Preparation and 
submission of budget.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The budget estimates of the Authority for every financial year shall be prepared 
by the Chairman of such employee of the Authority as may be authorised by him in 
this behalf, in Forms A1 to A5.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A copy of the budget 
estimates so prepared shall be sent to each member at least fourteen days before 
the meeting of the Authority at which such estimates are to be considered.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Authority shall 
consider and sanction the budget estimates with such changes as it thinks fit at 
the meeting fixed for the purpose or at any other meeting to which the 
consideration of the budget estimates is adjourned.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The budget estimates 
prepared by the Authority shall be forwarded to the Central Government by the 
fifteenth day of October of the financial year preceding the financial year to 
which the consideration of the budget estimates relate:
 
Provided that the Central 
Government may at the request of the Authority fix such later date, but not 
beyond the 31st day of December, as the Government think fit.
</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>4</number> Supplementary 
budget.—The 
Authority shall, where necessary, also forward to the Central Government the 
Supplementary budget in respect of the financial year to which it relates, in 
Forms A1 to A5 before such date as may be specified by the Central Government.
</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>5</number> Accounts of 
Authority.—The 
accounts of the Authority including—
 <section>
       
<number>a</number>  all sums of money received and expended by the Authority;
 </section><section>
       
<number>b</number>  all sales and purchases of goods or services of the Authority;
 </section><section>
       
<number>c</number>  the assets and liabilities of the Authority; shall be maintained in 
such forms as may be specified by the Government from time to time in 
consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor General of India.
</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Preparation and submission of annual report and annual accounts:- </title>
  
<section><number>1</number> The Chairman or such employee of the Authority as may be authorised by him in this behalf, shall prepare, as soon as may be after the commencement of the each financial year— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the annual report; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the annual statement of accounts which shall include the profit and loss account and balance sheet and such other subsidiary accounts as the Central Government may, in consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor General of India , direct. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The annual report include an account of the activities of the Authority during the previous financial year on the following matters, namely:— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> a statement of corporate and operational goals and objectives of the Authority; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> annual targets and physical and financial terms set for various activities in the background of clause (1) above together with a brief review of the actual performance with reference to those targets; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> an administrative report on the activities of Authority during the previous financial year and an account of the activities which are likely to be taken up during the next financial year; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> a summary of the actual financial results during the previous financial year and year of report, as indicated by way of statement of (a) income and expenditure, (b) sources and applications of funds and (c) cash flow; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> important changes in policy and specific measures either taken or proposed to be taken, which have influenced or are likely to influence the profitability or functioning of the Authority; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vi</number> new projects or expansion schemes contemplated together with their advantages, financial implications and programme for execution; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vii</number> important changes in the organizational set up of the Authority; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>viii</number> report on employer-employee relations and welfare activities of the Authority; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ix</number> report on such other miscellaneous subjects as deemed fit by the Authority or the Central Government for reporting to the later. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> The annual report shall be placed for adoption in the meeting of the Authority and shall be signed by the Chairman or in his absence by two members authorized for the purpose by the Chairman and authenticated by fixing the common seal of the Authority and required copies thereof shall be submitted to the Central Government by the thirty-first day of December of the following year. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The annual accounts of the Authority, after approval of the Authority, shall be signed on behalf of the Authority by its Chairman or in his absence by two members authorized for purpose by the Authority and authenticated by affixing the common seal of the Authority and shall be forwarded for audit to the Comptroller and Auditor General <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[not later than the 31st July of each year] or by such date as extended by the Central Government. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Audit Officer shall audit and report on the annual accounts of the Authority and certify whether in his opinion the balance sheet and profit and loss account contain all particulars and are properly drawn up to as to exhibit a true and fair state of affairs of the Authority and in case he has called for any information from the Authority or any of its officers, whether it has been given and whether it is satisfactory. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Authority shall be bound to give information and explanation in its annual report containing inter alia duly audited accounts or in an addendum thereto on every reservation, qualification or adverse remarks contained in the Auditor reports duly signed by its Chairman or in his absence by two members so authorized by the Authority and authenticated by affixing common seal of the Authority. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> The annual accounts and the auditors report thereon alongwith the annual report shall be submitted to the Central Government by thirty-first day of December of the following year to which the accounts relate or by such date as extended by the Central Government. 



</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>7</number> Cost of Audit.—The 
Authority shall arrange to pay to the Comptroller and Auditor General of India 
the expenditure incurred by him in connection with the annual audit of its 
accounts, within three months from the date on which any demand is made by him.
</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>8</number> Manner of Investment 
Fund.—All money 
standing at the credit of the Fund which cannot immediately be applied for the 
purposes specified in sub-section (2) of section 18 of the Act shall be 
deposited in the State Bank of India or any Scheduled bank specified in the 
First Schedule to the Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of 
Undertakings) Act, 1970 (5 of 1970) or the Banking Companies (Acquisition and 
Transfer of Undertaking) Act, 1980 (40 of 1980).
</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>9</number> Reserve Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In respect of every loan raised by the Authority not being a loan repayable 
before the expiration of one year from the date of the loan, the Authority shall 
set apart a sum half yearly, out of its income in a reserve fund, sufficient to 
liquidate the loan within a period which shall not in any case exceed thirty 
years:
 
Provided that a reserve 
fund need not in the absence of any stipulation to that effect, be established 
in the case of loans taken by the Authority from the Central Government or any 
State Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The sums set apart by 
the Authority under sub-rule (1) shall invested in securities of the Central 
Government or in such other securities as the Central Government may approve in 
this behalf, and shall be held in trust for the purposes of the Act by the 
Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Authority may 
apply the whole or any part of the sums accumulated in any reserve fund in or 
towards the discharge of the loan liabilities for the repayment of which the 
fund has been established:
 
Provided that Authority 
pays into the fund each year, and accumulated until the whole of the money 
borrowed is discharged, a sum equivalent to the interest which would have been 
produced by the reserve fund or the part of the reserve fund so applied.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A reserve fund 
established for the liquidation of any loan shall be subject to annual 
examination by such person as may be appointed by the Central Government in this 
behalf and the person so appointed shall ascertain whether the cash and the 
current market value of the securities at the credit of the Fund are actually 
equal to the amount which would have accumulated had investments been regularly 
made and rate of interest as originally estimated obtained thereon.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Authority shall 
pay forthwith into the reserve fund any amount which the person appointed under 
sub-rule (4) of conduct the annual examination of the Fund may certify to be 
deficient unless the Central Government specifically sanctions a gradual 
readjustment.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> If the cash and 
current market value of the securities at the credit of a reserve fund are in 
excess of the amount which should be at its credit the person appointed under 
sub-rule (4) shall certify the amount of this excess and the Authority may, with 
the previous sanction of the Central Government reduce or discontinue the 
half-yearly contributions to the reserve fund.
</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>10</number> Mode of service of 
notice.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Before entering upon any land or premises under section 30 of the Act, the 
authorized person shall serve on the owner of the land or premises intended to 
be entered upon notice in Form B.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The notice may be 
served by delivering or tendering a copy of such notice to the person for whom 
it is intended or his servant or by sending it by registered post 
acknowledgement due addressed to that person at his usual or last known place of 
residence or business.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the serving 
officer delivers or tenders the copy of the notice under sub-rule (2), he shall 
require the signature of the person to whom the copy is delivered or tendered to 
an acknowledgement of service endorsed on the original.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where the person or 
the adult member(s) of the family of the person concerned or servant of such 
person refuses to sign the acknowledgement or where the serving officer, after 
using all the due and reasonable diligence, cannot find such person and there is 
no adult member of the family or servant of such person, the serving officer 
shall affix a copy of notice on the outer door or some other conspicuous part of 
the ordinary residence or usual place of business of such person and then shall 
return the original to the competent authority who served the notice, with a 
report endorsed thereon or annexed thereto stating that he has had to affix a 
copy, the circumstances under which he did so and the name and address of the 
person if any, by whom the usual or last known place of residence or business, 
as the case may be, was identified and in whose presence the copy was affixed.
 
 
</section></article> 

 <title>FORM B </title>
 NATIONAL HIGHWAYS AUTHORITY OF INDIA 
 To 
 Dear Sir/Madam, 
 In pursuance of section 30 of the National Highways Authority of India Act, 1988, I, 
 on behalf of the N.H.A.I., hereby authorise Shri...............................................................of 
 National Highways Authority of India to enter upon the undermentioned premises/land 
 located at...............................................................for the purpose of.......................................... 
 on the day of.....................at.....................hours. 
 For and on behalf of 
 National Highways Authority of India 
 

 <title>FORM B </title>
 NATIONAL HIGHWAYS AUTHORITY OF INDIA 
 To 
 Dear Sir/Madam, 
 In pursuance of section 30 of the National Highways Authority of India Act, 1988, I, 
 on behalf of the N.H.A.I., hereby authorise Shri...............................................................of 
 National Highways Authority of India to enter upon the undermentioned premises/land 
 located at...............................................................for the purpose of.......................................... 
 on the day of.....................at.....................hours. 
 For and on behalf of 
 National Highways Authority of India 

<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>	Subs. by G.S.R. 591(E), dated 5th July, 2010, for “not later than the 30th September of each year” (w.e.f. 8-7-2010).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>