<act><tid>1192190</tid>
<title>THE SCHEDULED CASTES AND SCHEDULED TRIBES ORDERS (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>1956</year></title>

ACT NO. 63 OF <year>1956</year>
[ 25th September, <year>1956</year>.]

An Act to provide for the inclusion in, and the exclusion from 
the lists of Scheduled Castes and of Scheduled Tribes, of certain 
castes and tribes and matters connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Seventh Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:--





<article><tid>219439</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Scheduled Castes and 
Scheduled Tribes Orders (Amendment) Act, <year>1956</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1589940</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act,--
<section><tid>1722657</tid>
<number>a</number>" article" means an article of the Constitution;

</section>

<section><tid>1985357</tid>
<number>b</number>" census authority" means the Deputy Registrar General, 
India;

</section>

<section><tid>1247621</tid>
<number>c</number>" last census" means the census held in <year>1951</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>751774</tid>
<number>d</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1791875</tid>
<number> 3</number> Amendment of Scheduled Castes Orders.
<section><tid>1656724</tid>
<number>1</number>The Constitution  
 (Scheduled Castes) Order, <year>1950</year>, is hereby amended in the manner and 
to the extent specified in Schedule I.

</section>

<section><tid>67387</tid>
<number>2</number>The Constitution (Scheduled Castes)  (Part C States) Order, 
<year>1951</year>, is hereby amended in the manner and to the extent specified in 
Schedule II.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1377679</tid>
<number> 4</number> Amendment of Scheduled Tribes Orders.
<section><tid>1096662</tid>
<number>1</number>The Schedule to the  
Constitution (Scheduled Tribes) Order, <year>1950</year>, is hereby amended in the 
manner and to the extent specified in Schedule III.

</section>

<section><tid>988219</tid>
<number>2</number>The Schedule to the Constitution (Scheduled Tribes)  (Part C  
  States) Order, <year>1951</year>, is hereby amended in the manner and to the extent 
specified in Schedule IV.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1534967</tid>
<number> 5</number> Determination of population of Scheduled Castes and Scheduled 
Tribes.
<section><tid>954069</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the list of Scheduled Castes or Scheduled Tribes in  
relation to any State is varied by this Act, the population as at the 
last census of the Scheduled Castes or, as the case may be, of the 
Scheduled Tribes in that State (including in relation to Assam, the  
population of the Scheduled Tribes in that State excluding the tribal 
  areas, and the population in each autonomous district thereof) shall 
be ascertained or estimated by the census authority in

<pagefootnote><pagenum>410</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

such manner as may be prescribed and shall be notified by that 
authority in the Gazette of India:

Provided that nothing in this section shall apply to any State in 
relation to which provision for redetermining the population of 
Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes is made in section 42 of the 
States Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year> (37 of <year>1956</year>), or in section 15 of the 
Bihar and West Bengal (Transfer of Territories) Act, <year>1956</year> (40 of  
  <year>1956</year>).


</section>

<section><tid>1337943</tid>
<number>2</number>The population figures so notified shall be taken to be the 
relevant population figures as ascertained at the last census and 
shall supersede any figures previously published.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>515774</tid>
<number> 6</number> Amendment of orders of the former Delimitation Commission. In 
addition to the duties imposed by section 44 of the States 
Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year> (37 of <year>1956</year>), and any other law on the 
Delimitation Commission constituted under section 43 of the said Act, 
it shall be the duty of that Commission--
<section><tid>1307523</tid>
<number>a</number>to redetermine, on the basis of the population figures 
notified under section 5 of this Act for any State, the 
number of seats to be reserved for the Scheduled Castes 
and Scheduled Tribes of that State in the House of the 
People and in the Legislative Assembly, if any, of that 
State, having regard to the relevant provisions of the 
constitution and of the States Reorganisation Act, 
 <year>1956</year> (37 of <year>1956</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>76199</tid>
<number>b</number>if on such redetermination the number of reserved seats 
of any class in any State is found to be different from 
the number fixed in Final Order No. 1 of the former 
Delimitation Commission, to make such amendments in any 
of the orders made by that Commission under section 8 
of the Delimitation Commission Act, <year>1952</year> (81 of <year>1952</year>), 
as may be necessary for the purpose of giving proper 
representation to the Scheduled Castes or the Scheduled 
Tribes, as the case may be, of that State; and

</section>

<section><tid>1865239</tid>
<number>c</number>to take into account the provisions of this section 
while preparing the Order referred to in sub- section 
 (2) of section 47 of the States Reorganisation Act, 
 <year>1956</year> (37 of <year>1956</year>).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>866596</tid>
<number> 7</number> Power to make rules. <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1909455</tid>
<number>1</number>] The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the 
purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>530077</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as 
may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is 
in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised 
in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule."]


</section>

</article>



 </act>