<act><title>THE ANTIQUITIES AND ART TREASURES ACT, 1972</title> 
 
 
  
 






 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called The Antiquities and Art Treasures Act, 1972.

 </section><section>
<number>2</number> it extends to the whole of India.

 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall come into force on such date1 as 
    the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint 
    and different dates may be appointed for different provisions of this Act 
    and for different States and any reference in any such provision to the 
    commencement of this Act shall be construed as a reference to the coming 
    into force of that provision.



 
 




  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 



 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—

 
 <subsection><number>a</number>    “antiquity” includes—</subsection>

 
 <subsection><number>I</number>  
        (i)    any coin, sculpture, painting, epigraph or other work of art or 
        craftsmanship;</subsection>

 <subsection><number>ii</number>    any 
        article, object or thing detached from a building or cave;

 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number>    any 
        article, object or thing illustrative of science, art, crafts, 
        literature, religion, customs, morals or politics in bygone ages;

 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number>    any 
        article, object or thing of historical interest;

 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number>    any 
        article, object or thing declared by the Central Government, by 
        notification in the Official Gazette, to be an antiquity for the 
        purposes of this Act,
    


 which has 
        been in existence for not less than one hundred years; and
    


 </subsection><subsection><number>II</number>    any 
        manuscript, record or other document which is of scientific historical, 
        literary or aesthetic value and which has been in existence for not less 
        than seventy-five years;


 <subsubsection><number>b</number>    “art 
      treasure” means any human work of art, not being an antiquity, declared by 
      the Central Government by notification in the Official Gazette, to be an 
      art treasure for the purposes of this Act having regard to its artistic or 
      aesthetic value.

 Provided that no declaration 
      under this clause shall be made in respect of any such work of art so long 
      as the author thereof is alive:

 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>c</number>    
      “export” means taking out of India to a place outside India;

 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>d</number>    
      “licensing officer” means an officer appointed as such under section 6;

 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>e</number>    
      “registering officer” means an officer appointed as such under section 15;

 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>f</number>    
      “prescribed; means prescribed by rules made under this Act.


 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section> <number>2</number> Any reference in this 
    Act to any law which is not in force in any area shall, in relation to that 
    area, be construed as a reference to the corresponding law, if any, in force 
    in that area.
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 



  
 <article><number>3</number> 
    Regulation of export trade in antiquities and art treasures.—
<section><number>1</number> On and 
    from the commencement of this Act, it shall not be lawful for any person, 
    other than the Central Government or any authority or agency authorized by 
    the Central Government in this behalf, to export any antiquity or art 
    treasure.
 </section><section><number>2</number> 
    Whenever the Central Government or any authority or agency referred to in 
    sub-section (1) intends to export any antiquity or art treasure such export 
    shall be made only under and in accordance with the terms and conditions of 
    a permit issued for the purpose by such authority as may be prescribed.
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article> <number>4</number> Application of Act 52 of 
      1962.—The Customs Act, 1962, shall have effect in relation to all 
      antiquities and art treasures, the export of which by any person (other 
      than the Central Government or any authority or agency authorized by the 
      Central Government) is prohibited under section 3 save in so far as that 
      Act is inconsistent with the provisions of this Act and except that 
      (notwithstanding anything contained in section 125 of that Act) any 
      confiscation authorized under that Act shall be made unless the Central 
      Government on an application made to it in this behalf, otherwise 
      directs.
  </article> 
 
 
  
 



  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Antiquities to be sold 
    only under a licence.—<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[As 
    from the date of expiry of a period of six months from the commencement of 
    this Act] no person shall, himself or by any other person on his behalf, 
    carry on the business of selling or offering to sell any antiquity except 
    under and in accordance with the terms and conditions of a licence granted 
    under section 8.
  Explanation.—In 
    this section and in sections 7, 8, 12, 13, 14, 17 and 18 “antiquity” does 
    not include ancient and historical records other than those declared by or 
    under law made by Parliament to be of national importance.





 Subs. 
    by Act 82 of 1976, sec. 2, for “On and from the expiry of period of two 
    months of the commencement of this Act” (w.r.e.f. 4-6-1976).





  


</article> 
 
 
  
 



  

 <article>
<number>6</number> Appointment of licensing officers.—The 
    Central Government may, by notified order,—


 
 <section><number>a</number>    appoint 
      such persons, being gazetted officers of Government, as it thinks fit, to 
      be licensing officers for the purposes of this Act;
 </section><section><number>b</number>    define 
      the limits of the area within which a licensing officer shall exercise the 
      powers conferred on licensing officers by or under this Act.
</section>

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 



  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Application for licence.—
<section><number>1</number> Any 
    person desiring to carry on, himself or by any other person on his behalf, 
    the business of selling or offering to sell antiquities may make an 
    application for the grant of a licence to the licensing officer having 
    jurisdiction.

 </section><section>
 <number>2</number> Every application under sub-section (1) 
    shall be made in such form and shall contain such particulars as may be 
    prescribed.
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 



  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Grant of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    On receipt of an application for the grant of a licence under section 7, the 
    licensing officer may, after holding such inquiry as he deems fit, grant a 
    licence to the applicant having regard to the following factors, namely:—

 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>  the experience of the applicant 
      with respect to trade in antiquities;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> the village, town or city where the 
      applicant intends to carry on business;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> the number of persons already 
      engaged in the business of selling, or offering for sale of antiquities in 
      the said village, town or city; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> such other factors as may be 
      prescribed:
</subsection>

 Provided 
    that no licence shall be granted to the applicant if he is convicted of an 
    offence punishable under the Antiquities (Export Control) Act, 1947 (31 of 
    1947) unless a period of ten years has elapsed since the date of the 
    conviction.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every licence granted 
    under this section shall be on payment of such fees as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every licence granted 
    under this section shall be for such period, subject to such conditions and 
    in such form and shall contain such particulars, as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> No application for 
    the grant of a licence made under section 7 shall be rejected unless the 
    applicant has been given a reasonable opportunity of being heard in the 
    matter.
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 



  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Renewal of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A licence granted under section 8 may, on an application made by the 
    licensee, be renewed by the licensing officer for such period and on payment 
    of such fees as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
 <number>2</number> No application 
    made under this section shall be rejected unless the applicant has been 
    given a reasonable opportunity of being heard in the matter.
  
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 



  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Maintenance of 
    records, photographs and registers by licensees.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every holder of a licence granted under section 8 or renewed under section 9 
    shall maintain such records, photographs and registers, in such manner and 
    containing such particulars, as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
 <number>2</number> Every record, 
    photograph and register maintained under sub-section (1) shall, at 
    all reasonable times, be open to inspection by the licensing officer or by 
    any other gazetted officer of Government authorised in writing by the 
    licensing officer in this behalf.
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 



  
 <article>
<number>11</number> Revocation, 
    suspension and amendment of licences.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If the licensing officer is satisfied either on a reference made to him in 
    this behalf or otherwise that—


 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>  a licence granted under section 8 
      has been obtained by misrepresentation of an essential fact, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>  the holder of a licence has, 
      without reasonable cause, failed to comply with the conditions subject to 
      which the licence has been granted or has contravened any of the 
      provisions of this Act or the rules made thereunder,
</subsection>
 then, without prejudice to 
    any other penalty to which the holder of the licence may be liable under 
    this Act, the licensing officer may, after giving the holder of the licence 
    an opportunity of showing cause, revoke or suspend the licence.


 </section><section>
 <number>2</number> Subject to any 
    rules that may be made in this behalf, the licensing officer may also vary 
    or amend a licence granted under section 8.
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 



  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Persons whose 
    licences have been revoked may sell antiquities to other licensees.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in section 5, any person whose licence has been revoked 
    under section 11 may, after making a declaration before the licensing 
    officer, within such period, in such form and in the such manner, as may be 
    prescribed, of all the antiquities in his ownership, control or possession 
    immediately before such revocation, sell such antiquities to any other 
    person holding a valid licence under this Act:
 
Provided that no such 
    antiquity shall be sold after the expiry of a period of six months from the 
    date of revocation of the licence.
  


</article> 
 
 
  
 



  
 <article>
<number>13</number> Power of Central 
    Government to carry on the business of selling antiquities to the exclusion 
    of others.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If the Central Government is of opinion that with a view to conserving 
    antiquities or in the public interest it is necessary or expedient so to do, 
    it may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare that with effect on 
    and from such date as may be specified in the notification, the Central 
    Government or any authority or agency authorised by the Central Government 
    in this behalf shall alone be entitled to carry on the business of selling 
    or offering for sale of antiquities.
 </section><section>
 <number>2</number> On the issue of a 
    notification under sub-section (1),—

 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>  it shall not be lawful for any 
      person, authority or agency, other than the Central Government or any 
      authority or agency authorized by the Central Government, to carry on the 
      business of selling or offering for sale any antiquity on and from the 
      date specified therein;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>  the provisions of this act, in so 
      far as they relate to the licensing of persons carrying on the business of 
      selling or offering for sale of antiquities shall cease to have effect 
      except as respects things done or omitted to be done before such cesser of 
      operation and section 6 of the General Clauses Act, 1897 (10 of 1897) 
      shall apply upon such cesser of operation as if those provisions had been 
      repealed by a Central Act:
</subsection>

 
Provided that every 
    licence granted under section 8 and in force on the date aforesaid shall, 
    notwithstanding that the period specified therein has not expired, cease to 
    be in force.
 </section><section>
 <number>3</number> Every person whose 
    licence has ceased to be in force under the proviso to clause (b) of 
    sub-section (2) shall, within such period, in such form and in such manner 
    as may be prescribed, make a declaration before the licensing officer of all 
    the antiquities in his ownership, control or possession immediately before 
    the date specified in the notification issued under sub-section (1).
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 



  
 <article>
<number>14</number> Registration of 
    antiquities.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government may, from time to time, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, specify those antiquities which shall 
    be registered under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In specifying the 
    antiquities under sub-section (1), the Central Government shall have 
    regard to the following factors, namely:—

 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>  the necessi</subsection>ty 
      for conserving the objects of art;
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number>  the need to preserve such objects 
      within India for the better appreciation of the cultural heritage of
      India;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>  such other factors as will, or 
      are likely to, contribute to the safeguarding of the cultural heritage of
      India.


 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Every person who 
    owns, controls or is in possession of any antiquity specified in the 
    notification issued under sub-section (1) shall register such antiquity 
    before the registering officer—

 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>  in the case of a person who owns, 
      controls or possesses such antiquity on the date of issue of such 
      notification, within three months of such date; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>  in the case of any other person, 
      within fifteen days of the date on which he comes into ownership, control 
      or possession of such antiquity, and obtain a certificate in token of such 
      registration.
</subsection>

 
 
Where it is clear that 
      the team of experts in the Archaeological Department have examined the 
      articles seized from petitioner and have arrived at a definite conclusion 
      that some of them were antiquities and they did not require to conduct 
      chemical test to prove that they were more than 100 years old and 
      petitioner did not make any attempt to show that these articles were not 
      100 years old, it was rightly concluded by courts below that these were 
      antiquities requiring registration and non-registration thereof, was an 
      offence under the Act; 1999 Cri LJ 3078.


  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 



  
 <article>
<number>15</number> Appointment of 
    registering officers.—The Central Government may, by notified order,—

 
 <section>
<number>a</number>  appoint such persons, as it thinks 
      fit, to be registering officers for the purposes of this Act; and
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>  define the limits of the area 
      within which a registering officer shall exercise the powers conferred on 
      registering officers by or under this Act.
</section>

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 



  
 <article>
<number>16</number> Application for 
    registration and grant of certificate of registration.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every person required to register any antiquities before the registering 
    officer under section 14 shall make an application to the registering 
    officer for the grant of a certificate of registration.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every application 
    under sub-section (1) 1[shall 
    in the case of such antiquities or class of antiquities as the Central 
    Government may, by notification in the official Gazette, specify, be 
    accompanied] by such photographs of the antiquity which is to be registered 
    and by such number or copies, not exceeding six, as may be prescribed and 
    shall be made in such form and shall contain such particulars as may be 
    prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On receipt of an 
    application under sub-section (1), the registering officer may, after 
    holding such inquiry as he deems fit, grant a certificate of registration 
    containing such particulars as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> No application made 
    under this section shall be rejected unless the applicant has been given a 
    reasonable opportunity of being heard in the matter.






Subs. by Act 82 of 
    1976, sec. 3 for “shall be accomplished “ (w.r.e.f. 4-6-1976).


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 



  
 <article>
<number>17</number> Transfer of 
    ownership, etc., of antiquities to be intimated to the registering officer.—Whenever 
    any person transfers the ownership, control or possession of any antiquity 
    specified in any notification issued under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 
    14 such person shall intimate, within such period and in such form as may be 
    prescribed the fact of such transfer to the registering officer. 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 



  
 <article>
<number>18</number> Provisions of 
    sections 14, 16 and 17 not to apply in certain cases.—Nothing 
    in section 14 or section 16 or section 17 shall apply to any antiquity kept—

 
 <section>        <number>i</number>  in a 
      museum; or
 </section><section>        <number>ii</number> in an 
      office; or
 </section><section>       <number>iii</number> in an 
      archive; or
 </section><section>       <number>iv</number> in an 
      educational or cultural institution,
</section>
 owned, controlled or managed 
    by the Government. <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[or 
    by any local authority or by any such body as the Central Government may, 
    for reasons to be recorded in writing approve for the purpose of this 
    section by general or special order].





Ins. by Act 82 of 
    1976, sec. 4 (w.r.e.f. 4-6-1976).


 
  


</article> 
 
 
  
 



  
 <article>
<number>19</number> Power of Central 
    Government to compulsorily acquire antiquities and art treasures.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If the Central Government is of opinion that it is desirable to preserve any 
    antiquity or art treasure in a public place, that Government may make an 
    order for the compulsory acquisition of such antiquity or art treasure.
 </section><section>
 <number>2</number> On the making of an 
    order under sub-section (1) the Collector of the district in which 
    such antiquity or art treasure is kept shall give notice to the owner 
    thereof intimating him of the decision of the Central Government to acquire 
    the same and it shall be lawful for the Collector to take possession of such 
    antiquity or art treasure, for which purpose the Collector may use such 
    force as may be necessary.
 </section><section>
 <number>3</number> Where the owner of 
    any antiquity or art treasure, the possession of which has been taken over 
    by the Collector under sub-section (2) objects to the taking over of 
    such possession, he may, within a period of thirty days from the date on 
    which such possession was taken over, make a representation to the Central 
    Government putting forth his objections.
 
Provided that the Central 
    Government may entertain the representation after the expiry of the said 
    period of thirty days, if it is satisfied that the owner of such antiquity 
    or art treasure was prevented by sufficient cause from making the 
    representation in time.
 </section><section>
 <number>4</number> On receipt of any 
    representation under sub-section (3), the Central Government, after 
    making such inquiry as it deems fit and after giving to the objector an 
    opportunity of being heard in the matter, shall, within a period of ninety 
    days from the date of receipt of the representation, either rescind or 
    confirm the order made by it under sub-section (1).
 </section><section>
 <number>5</number> Where any order made 
    by the Central Government under sub-section (1) is rescinded under 
    sub-section (4) the antiquity or art treasure shall be returned to the owner 
    thereof without delay and at the expenses of the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Where the order made 
    by the Central Government under sub-section (1) is confirmed under 
    sub-section (4) the antiquity or art treasure shall vest in the Central 
    Government with effect from the date on which the possession thereof has 
    been taken over by the Collector under sub-section (2).
 </section><section>
 <number>7</number> The power of 
    compulsory acquisition conferred by this section shall not extend to any 
    object, being an antiquity or art treasure, used for bona fide 
    religious observances.
 
    Explanation.—In 
    this section, “public place” means any place which is open to the use of the 
    public, whether on payment of fees or not, or whether it is actually used by 
    the public or not.


 
 
Antiquities and art 
      treasures are price less objects. They can provide immense material for 
      study of Hindu and Buddhist culture in the State of Orissa. Malkhana of 
      Courts are certainly not the places of storage of such articles. With a 
      view to provide, interested persons, materials for their study and 
      research, they can be handed over to the State Museum; In the matter of 
      Preservation of Antiquities involved in Criminal Trials, AIR 1999 Ori 
      53.


 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 



  

 <article>
<number>20</number> Payment 
    of compensation for antiquities and art treasures compulsorily acquired 
    under section 19.—
<section><number>1</number> Where any 
    antiquity or art treasure is compulsorily acquired under section 19, there 
    shall be paid compensation, the amount of which shall be determined in the 
    manner and in accordance with the principles hereinafter set out, that is to 
    say,—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    where the amount of compensation can 
      be fixed by agreement, it shall be paid in accordance with such agreement;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    where no such agreement can be 
      reached, the Central Government shall appoint as arbitrator a person who 
      is, or has been, or is qualified for appointment as, a Judge of a High 
      Court;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the Central Government may, in any 
      particular case, nominate a person having expert knowledge as to the 
      nature of the antiquity or art treasure compulsorily acquired to assist 
      the arbitrator and where such nomination is made, the person to be 
      compensated may also nominate an assessor for the same purpose;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    at the commencement of the 
      proceedings before the arbitrator, the Central Government and the person 
      to be compensated shall state what, in their respective opinion, is a fair 
      amount of compensation;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the arbitrator shall, after hearing 
      the dispute, make an award determining the amount of compensation which 
      appears to him to be just and specifying the person or persons to whom 
      such compensation shall be paid and in making the award he shall have 
      regard to the circumstances of each case and the provisions of sub-section 
      (2);
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    where there is any dispute as to the 
      person or persons who are entitled to the compensation, the arbitrator 
      shall decide such dispute and if the arbitrator finds that more persons 
      than one are entitled to compensation, he shall apportion the amount 
      thereof amongst such persons;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    nothing in the Arbitration Act, 1940 
      (10 of 1940) shall apply to arbitration under this section.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> While 
    determining the compensation under sub-section (1), the arbitrator shall 
    have regard to the following factors, namely:—
 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    the date or the period to which the 
      antiquity or art treasure belongs;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    the artistic, aesthetic, historical, 
      architectural, archaeological or anthropological importance of the 
      antiquity or art treasure;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    the rarity of the antiquity or art 
      treasure;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    such other matters as are relevant 
      to the dispute.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    arbitrator appointed under sub-section (1), while holding arbitration 
    proceedings under this section, shall have all the powers of a Civil Court, 
    while trying a suit, under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908, (5 of 1908) in 
    respect of the following matters, namely:—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    summoning and enforcing the 
      attendance of any person and examining him on oath;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    requiring the discovery and 
      production of any document;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    reception of evidence of affidavits;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    requisitions any public record from 
      any court or office;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    issuing commissions for the 
      examination of witnesses. 
</subsection>

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 



  
 <article>
    <number>21</number> Appeals against decisions of licensing officers and registering 
    officers.—
<section><number>1</number> Any person aggrieved 
    by a decision of a licensing officer under section 8 or section 9 or section 
    11 or by a decision of a registering officer under section 16 may, within 
    thirty days from the date on which the decision is communicated to him, 
    prefer an appeal to such authority as may be prescribed:
 
    Provided that the appellate authority may entertain the appeal after the 
    expiry of the said period of thirty days, if it is satisfied that the 
    appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from filing the appeal in time.
 </section><section> <number>2</number> 
    On receipt of an appeal under sub-section (1), the appellate 
    authority shall, after giving the appellant and opportunity of being heard, 
    pass such orders as it deems fit.
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 



  
 <article>
    <number>22</number> Appeals against awards of arbitrators.—Any 
    person aggrieved by an award of the arbitrator made under section 20 may, 
    within thirty days from the date on which the award is communicated to him, 
    prefer an appeal to the High Court within whose jurisdiction he resides:
 
    Provided that the High Court may entertain the appeal after the expiry of 
    the said period of thirty days if it is satisfied that the appellant was 
    prevented by a sufficient cause from filing the appeal in time.
  


</article> 
 
 
  
 



  
 <article>
<number>23</number> Powers of entry, search, seizure, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person, being an officer of Government, authorized in this behalf by the 
    Central Government, may, with a view to securing compliance with the 
    provisions of this Act or to satisfying himself that the provisions of this 
    Act have been complied with—

 
 <subsection><number>i</number>    enter 
      and search any place; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>    seize 
      any antiquity or art treasure in respect of which he suspects that any 
      provision of this Act has been, is being, or is about to be, contravened 
      and thereafter take all measures necessary for securing the production of 
      the antiquity or art treasure so seized in a court and for its safe 
      custody, pending such production.
</subsection>

 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The provisions of sections 102 and 103 of 
    the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898)* relating to search and 
    seizure shall, so far as may be, apply to searches and seizures under this 
    section.





  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 



  
 <article>
<number>24</number> Power to determine whether or not an 
    article, etc., is antiquity or art treasure.—If 
    any question arises whether any article, object or thing or manuscript, 
    record or other document is or is not an antiquity or is or is not an art 
    treasure for the purposes of this Act, it shall be referred to the Director 
    General, Archaeological Survey of India, or to an officer not below the rank 
    of a Director in the Archaeological Survey of India authorized by the 
    Director General, Archaeological Survey of India and the decision of the 
    Director General, Archaeological Survey of India or such officer, as the 
    case may be, on such question shall be final.
  


</article> 
 
 
  
 



  
 <article>
<number>25</number> Penalty.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If any person, himself or by any other person on his behalf, exports or 
    attempts to export any antiquity or art treasure in contravention of section 
    3, he shall, without prejudice to any confiscation or penalty to which he 
    may be liable under the provisions of the Customs Act, 1962 (52 of 1962) as 
    applied by section 4, be punishable with imprisonment for a term which shall 
    not be less than six months but which may extend to three years and with 
    fine.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> if any person contravenes the provisions 
    of section 5 or section 12 or sub-section (2) or sub-section 
    (3) of section 13 or section 14 or section 17, he shall be punishable 
    with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months or with fine or 
    with both and the antiquity in respect of which the offence has been 
    committed shall be liable to confiscation.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If any person prevents any licensing 
    officer from inspecting any record, photograph or register maintained under 
    section 10 or prevents any officer authorized by the Central Government 
    under sub-section (1) of section 23 from entering into or searching 
    any place under that sub-section, he shall be punishable with 
    imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine, or 
    with both.
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 



  
 <article>
<number>26</number> Cognizance of offences.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No prosecution for an offence under sub-section (1) of section 25 
    shall be instituted except by or with the sanction of such officer of 
    Government as may be prescribed in this behalf.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No court shall take cognizance of an 
    offence punishable under sub-section (2) or sub-section (3) or section 25 
    except upon complaint in writing made by an officer generally or specially 
    authorized in this behalf by the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No court inferior to that of a Presidency 
    Magistrate or a Magistrate of the First Class shall try any offence 
    punishable under this Act.



 
 Recovery of 
      antiquities articles from house of Petitioner, not registered as required 
      under section 14. Team of experts in the Archaeological Department 
      examined all the articles and found that few of them were antiquities. 
      Opinion filed by them is final under section 24. In respect of these 
      articles chemical test to prove that they were 100 years old was not 
      required to be conducted. Non-registration of antiquities in an offence 
      under the Act and imposition of fine not illegal or irregular. However, 
      petitioners were given an opportunity to make application for registration 
      of antiquities instead of confiscating them; 1999 Cri LJ 3079.


  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 



  
 <article>
<number>27</number> Magistrate’s power to impose enhanced 
    penalties.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in section 32 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898*, 
    it shall be lawful for any Presidency Magistrate or any Magistrate of the 
    First Class to pass any sentence under this Act in excess of his power under 
    section 32 of the said Code.*


 
 
   *     See Now section 29 of the Code of 
      Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).



  


</article> 
 
 
  
 



  
 <article>
<number>28</number> Offences by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where an offence under this Act has been committed by a company, every 
    person who at the time the offence was committed was in charge of, or was 
    responsible to, the company for the conduct of the business of the company, 
    as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and 
    shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
 
Provided that nothing contained in this sub-section 
    shall render any such person liable to any punishment under this Act if he 
    proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or that he 
    exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section 
    (1), where an offence under this Act has been committed with the consent or 
    connivance of, or is attributable to, any neglect on the part of any 
    director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such director, 
    manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of 
    that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished 
    accordingly.
 Explanation.—For 
    the purpose of this section,—

 
 <subsection><number>a</number>    “company” means any body 
      corporate and includes a firm or other association of individuals; and
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>    “director”, in relation to a 
      firm, means a partner in the firm.
</subsection>

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 



  
 <article>
 <number>29</number> Protection of action taken in good 
    faith.—No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against 
    the Government or any officer of the Government for anything which is in 
    good faith done or is intended to be done under this Act.
  


</article> 
 
 
  
 



  
 <article>
<number>30</number> Application of other laws not barred.—The 
    provisions of this Act shall be in addition to, and not in derogation of, 
    the provisions of the Ancient Monuments Preservation Act, 1904 (7 of 1904) 
    or the Ancient Monuments and Archaeological Sites and Remains Act, 1958, (24 
    of 1958) or any other law for the time being in force.
  


</article> 
 
 
  
 



  
 <article>
<number>31</number> Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make 
    rules for the purpose of giving effect to the provisions of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular and without prejudice to 
    the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for—

 
 <subsection><number>a</number>    the 
      authority for issue of permit under sub-section (2) of section 3;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>    the 
      form in which an application for the grant of a licence may be made under 
      sub-section (1) of section 7 and the particulars which such application 
      shall contain;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>    the 
      factors to which regard may be had while granting a licence under 
      sub-section (1) of section 8;
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>    the 
      fees on payment of which, the period for which, the conditions subject to 
      which and the form in which a licence may be granted under sub-section (1) 
      of section 8 and the particulars which such licence shall contain;
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>    the 
      fees on payment of which and the period for which a licence may be renewed 
      under sub-section (1) of section 9;
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>    the 
      records, photographs and registers which are to be maintained under 
      section 10 and the manner in which such records, photographs and registers 
      shall be maintained and the particulars which such records, photographs 
      and registers shall contain;
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number>    the 
      nature of the photographs of the antiquity and the number of copies 
      thereof which shall accompany an application for the grant of a 
      certificate of registration to be made under sub-section (1) of section 16 
      and the form in which such application may be made and the particulars 
      which such application shall contain;
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number>    the 
      particulars which a certificate of registration granted under sub-section 
      (3) of section 16 shall contain;
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number>    the 
      authority to which an appeal may be preferred under sub-section (1) of 
      section 21; and
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number>    any 
      other matter which has to be or may be prescribed.
</subsection>

 </section><section><number>3</number> 
    Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is 
    made, before each House of Parliament while it is in session for a total 
    period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or 
    more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
    immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both 
    Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree 
    that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only 
    in such modified from or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, 
    that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
    validity of anything previously done under that rule.
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 



  
 <article>
<number>32</number> Repeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Antiquities (Export Control) Act, 1947 (3 of 1947) is hereby repealed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> For the removal of doubts it is hereby 
    declared that every licence issued under section 3 of the Act repealed under 
    sub-section (1) and in force at the commencement of this Act shall, 
    notwithstanding that the period specified therein has no expired, cease to 
    be in force.
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>33</number> Amendment of Act 24 of 1958.—In the Ancient Monuments and Archaeological 
      Sites and Remains Act, 1958,.—
 
 <section><number>i</number>    in section 1, for sub-section 
        (2), the following sub-section shall be substituted, 
        namely:—
        “(2) It extends to 
        the whole of India.”,
 </section><section><number>ii</number>    after section 2, the following 
        section shall be inserted, 
        namely:—           “2A. 
        Construction of references to any law not in force in the State of Jammu 
        and Kashmir—Any reference in this Act to any law which is not in 
        force in the State of Jammu and Kashmir shall, in relation to that 
        State, be construed as a reference to the corresponding law, if any, in 
        force in that State.”;
 </section><section><number>iii</number>    in section 23,—
 <subsection><number>a</number>    in sub-sections (2) and (4), for the 
        words “compulsory purchase”, the words “compulsory acquisition” shall be 
        substituted;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>    in sub-section (3), for the words 
        “compulsory purchase of any such antiquities at their market value”, the 
        words “compulsory acquisition of any such antiquities” shall be 
        substituted;
 </subsection></section><section><number>iv</number>    in section 26,—
 <subsection><number>a</number>    in sub-section (1), for the 
        words “compulsory purchase of such antiquity at its market value”, the 
        words “compulsory acquisition of such antiquity” and for the words “to 
        be purchased”, the words “to be acquired” shall be substituted;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>    in sub-sections (2) and (3), for the 
        words “compulsory purchase”, the words “compulsory acquisition” shall be 
        substituted;
 </subsection></section><section><number>v</number>    in section 28, for sub-section (2), 
        the following sub-section shall be substituted, namely:—  “(2) For 
        every antiquity in respect of which an order for compulsory acquisition 
        has been made under sub-section (3) of section 23 or under 
        sub-section (1) of section 26, there shall be paid compensation 
        and the provisions of sections 20 and 22 of the Antiquities and Art 
        Treasures Act, 1972 shall, so far as may be, apply in relation to the 
        determination and payment of such compensation as they apply in relation 
        to the determination and payment of compensation for any antiquity or 
        art treasure compulsorily acquired under section 19 of that 
      Act.”</section>
  </article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number></pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number></pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number></pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>