<act><title>


    the Security interest (enforcement) rules, 20021</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Security Interest (Enforcement) Rules, 2002.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> They 
    shall come into force from the date of their publicaton in the Official 
    Gazette.
  



 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number> “authorised 
officer” means an officer not less than a chief manager of a public sector bank 
or equivalent, as specified by the Board of Directors or Board of Trustees of 
the secured creditor or any other person or authority exercising powers of 
superintendence, direction and control of the business or affairs of the secured 
creditor, as the case may be, to exercise the rights of a secured creditor under 
the 

1[Act];
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  demand notice 
means the notice in writing issued by a secured creditor or authorised officer, 
as the case may be, to any borrower pursuant to sub-section (2) of section 13 of 
the 

1[Act];
 
 

2[(c)  “Act” means 
the Securitisation and Reconstruction of Financial Assets and Enforcement of 
Security Interest Act, 2002 (54 of 2002);]
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  “approved 
valuer” means a valuer as approved by the Board of Directors or Board of 
Trustees of the secured creditor, as the case may be;
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number>  words and 
expressions used and not defined in these rules but defined in the 

1[Act] shall have 
the meanings respectively assigned to them in the 

1[Act].
 
 





</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Demand notice.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The service of demand notice as refereed to in sub-section (2) of section 13 of 
the 

1[Act] shall be 
made by delivering or transmitting at the place where the borrower or his agent, 
empowered to accept the notice or documents of behalf of the borrower, actually 
and voluntarily resides or carries on business or personally works for gain, by 
registered post with acknowledgement due, addressed to the borrower or his agent 
empowered to accept the service or by Speed Post or by courier or by any other 
means of transmission of documents like fax message or electronic mail service:
 
Provided that where 
authorised officer has reason to believe that the borrower or his agent is 
avoiding the service of the notice or that for any other reason, the service 
cannot be made as aforesaid, the service shall be effected by affixing a copy of 
the demand notice on the outer door or some other conspicuous part of the house 
or building in which the borrower or his agent ordinarily resides or carries on 
business or personally works for gain and also by publishing the contents of the 
demand notice in two leading newspapers, one in vernacular language, having 
sufficient circulation in that locality.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the borrower is 
a body corporate, the demand notice shall be served on the registered office or 
any of the branches of such body corporate as specified under sub-rule (1).
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any other notice in 
writing to be served on the borrower or his agent by authorised officer, shall 
be served in the same manner as provided in this rule.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where there are more 
than one borrower, the demand notice shall be served on each borrower.
 
 




</section></article> 
 the Security interest (enforcement) rules, 2002
 <article>
1[<number>3A</number> 
Reply to representation of the borrower.—
<section><number>a</number> 
After issue of demand notice under sub-section (2) of section 13, if the 
borrower makes any representation or raises any objection to the notice, the 
Authorised Officer shall consider such representation or objection and examine 
whether the same is acceptable or tenable.
 </section><section><number>b</number> If on examining the 
representation made or objection raised by the borrower, the secured creditor is 
satisfied that there is a need to make any changes or modifications in the 
demand notice, he shall modify the notice accordingly and serve a revised notice 
or pass such other suitable orders as deemed necessary, within seven days from 
the date of receipt of the representation or objection.
 </section><section><number>c</number> If on examining the 
representation made or objection raised, the Authorised Officer comes to the 
conclusion that such representation or objection is not acceptable or tenable, 
he shall communicate within one week of receipt of such representation or 
objection, the reasons for non-acceptance of the representation or objection, to 
the borrower.]
  



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>4</number>
Procedure after issue of notice.—If the amount mentioned in the 
    demand notice is not paid within the time specified therein, the authorised 
    officer shall proceed to realise the amount by adopting any one or more of 
    the measures specified in sub-section (4) of section 13 of the Ordinance for 
    taking possession of movable property, namely:—  
 <section>

<number>1</number>    
    Where the possession of the secured assets to be taken by the secured 
    creditor are movable property in possession of the borrower, the authorised 
    officer shall take possession of such movable property in the presence of 
    two witnesses after a Panchnama drawn and signed by the witnesses as nearly 
    as possible in Appendix I to these rules.  
 </section><section>

<number>2</number>    
    After taking possession under sub-rule (1) above, the authorised officer 
    shall make or cause to be made an inventory of the property as nearly as 
    possible in the form given in Appendix II to these rules and deliver or 
    cause to be delivered, a copy of such inventory to the borrower or to any 
    person entitled to receive on behalf of borrower.  
 </section><section>

<number>3</number>    
    The authorised officer shall keep the property taken possession under 
    sub-rule (1) either in his own custody or in the custody of any person 
    authorised or appointed by him, who shall take as much care of the property 
    in his custody as an owner of ordinary prudence would, under the similar 
    circumstances, take of such property:  
 

Provided 
    that if such property is subject to speedy or natural decay, or the expense 
    of keeping such property in custody is likely to exceed its value, the 
    authorised officer may sell it at once.  
 </section><section>

<number>4</number>    
    The authorised officer shall take steps for preservation and protection of 
    secured assets and insure them, if necessary, till they are sold or 
    otherwise disposed of.  
 </section><section>

<number>5</number>    
    In case any secured asset is—  
 <subsection>

<number>a</number>    
    a debt not secured by negotiable instrument; or 
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>b</number>    
    a share in a body corporate;  
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>c</number>    
    other movable property not in the possession of the borrower except the 
    property deposited in or in the custody of any court or any like authority, 
    the authorised officer shall obtain possession or recover the debt by 
    service of notice as under:  
 <subsubsection>

<number>i</number>    
    in the case of a debt, prohibiting the borrower from recovering the debt or 
    any interest thereon and the debtor from making payment thereof and 
    directing the debtor to make such payment to the authorised officer; or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

<number>ii</number>    
    in the case of the shares in a body corporate, directing the borrower to 
    transfer the same to the secured creditor and also the body corporate from 
    not transferring such shares in favour of any person other than the secured 
    creditor. A copy of the notice so sent may be endorsed to the concerned body 
    corporate’s Registrar to the issue or share transfer agents, if any;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

<number>iii</number>    
    in the case of other movable proerty (except as aforesaid), calling upon the 
    borrowers and the person in possession to hand over the same to the 
    authorised officer and the authorised officer shall take custody of such 
    movable property in the same manner as provided in sub-rules (1) to (3) 
    above;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

<number>iv</number>    
    movable secured assets other than those covered in this rule shall be taken 
    possession of by the authorised officer by taking possession of the 
    documents evidencing title to such secured assets.  
 
  


</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>5</number> 
    Valuation of movable secured assets.—After 
    taking possession under sub-rule 
<section><number>1</number> of rule 4 and in any case before sale, 
    the authorised officer shall obtain the estimated value of the movable 
    secured assets and thereafter, if considered necessary, fix in consultation 
    with the secured creditor, the reserve price of the assets to be sold in 
    realisation of the dues of the secured creditor.
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>6</number> Sale of 
    movable secured assets.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    the authorised officer may sell the movable secured assets taken possession 
    under sub-rule (1) of rule 4 in one or more lots by adopting any of the 
    following methods to secure maximum sale price for the assets, to be so 
    sold—  
 <subsection>

<number>a</number>    
    obtaining quotations from parties dealing in the secured assets or otherwise 
    interested in buying such assets; or
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>b</number>    
    inviting tenders from the public; or  
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>c</number>    
    holding public auction; or   
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>d</number>    
    by private treaty.  
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>2</number> The 
    authorised officer shall serve to the borrower a notice of thirty days for 
    sale of the movable secured assets, under sub-rule (1):  
 

Provided 
    that if the sale of such secured assets is being effected by either inviting 
    tenders from the public or by holding public auction, the secured creditor 
    shall cause a public notice in two leading newspapers, one in vernacular 
    language, having sufficient circulation in that locality by setting out the 
    terms of sale, which may include,—  
 <subsection>

<number>a</number>    
    details about the borrower and the secured creditor;  
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>b</number>    
    description of movable secured assets to be sold with identification marks 
    or numbers, if any, on them;  
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>c</number>    
    reserve price, if any, and the time and manner of payment;  
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>d</number>    
    time and place of public auction or the time after which sale by any other 
    mode shall be completed;  
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>e</number>    
    depositing earnest money as may be stipulated by the secured creditor;  
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>f</number>    
    any other thing which the authorised officer considers it material for a 
    purchaser to know in order to judge the nature and value of movable secured 
    assets.  
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>3</number> Sale by 
    any methods other than public auction or public tender, shall be on such 
    terms as may be settled between the parties in writing.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>7</number> Issue of 
    certificate of sale.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where movable secured assets is sold, sale price of each lot shall be paid 
    as per the terms of the public notice or on the terms as may be settled 
    between the parties, as the case may be and in the event of default of 
    payment, the movable secured assets shall be liable to be ordered for sale 
    again.  
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> On 
    payment of sale price, the authorised officer shall issue a certificate of 
    sale in the prescribed form as given in Appendix III to these rules 
    specifying the movable secured assets sold, price paid and the name of the 
    purchaser and thereafter the sale shall become absolute. The certificate of 
    sale so issued shall be prima facie evidence of title of the 
    purchaser.  
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> Where 
    the movable secured assets are those referred in sub-clauses (iii) to (v) of 
    clause (1) of sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Ordinance, the provisions 
    contained in these rules and rule 7 dealing with the sale of movable secured 
    assets shall, mutatis mutandis, apply to such assets.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>8</number> Sale of 
    immovable secured assets.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the secured asset is an immovable property, the authorised officer 
    shall take or cause to be taken possession, by delivering a possession 
    notice prepared as nearly as possible in Appendix IV to these rules, to the 
    borrower and by affixing the possession notice on the outer door or at such 
    conspicuous place of the property.  
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> The 
    possession notice as referred to in sub-rule (1) shall also be published in 
    two leading newspapers, one in vernacular language having sufficient 
    circulation in that locality, by the authorised officer.  
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> In the 
    event of possession of immovable property is actually taken by the 
    authorised officer, such property shall be kept in his own custody or in the 
    custody of any person authorised or appointed by him, who shall take as much 
    care of the property in his custody as a owner of ordinary prudence would, 
    under the similar circumstances, take of such property.  
 </section><section>

<number>4</number> The 
    authorised officer shall take steps for preservation and protection of 
    secured assets and insure them, if necessary, till they are sold or 
    otherwise disposed of.  
 </section><section>

<number>5</number> Before 
    effecting sale of the immovable property referred to in sub-rule (1) of rule 
    9, the authorised officer shall obtain valuation of the property from an 
    approved valuer and in consultation with the secured creditor, fix the 
    reserve price of the property and may sell the whole or any part of such 
    immovable secured asset by any of the following methods:—  
 <subsection>

<number>a</number>    
    by obtaining quotations from the persons dealing with similar secured assets 
    or otherwise interested in buying the such assets; or   
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>b</number>    
    by inviting tenders from the public;  
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>c</number>    
    by holding public auction; or  
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>d</number>    
    by private treaty.  
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>6</number> The 
    authorised officer shall serve to the borrower a notice of thirty days for 
    sale of the immovable secured assets, under sub-rule (5):  
 

Provided 
    that if the sale of such secured asset is being effected by either inviting 
    tenders from the public or by holding public auction, the secured creditor 
    shall cause a public notice in two leading newspapers one in vernacular 
    language having sufficient circulation in the locality by setting out the 
    terms of sale, which shall include,—  
 <subsection>

<number>a</number>    
    The description of the immovable property to be sold, including the details 
    of the encumbrances known to the secured creditor;   
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>b</number>    
    the secured debt for recovery of which the property is to be sold;  
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>c</number>    
    reserve price, below which the property may not be sold;  
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>d</number>    
    time and place of public auction or the time after which sale by any other 
    mode shall be completed;  
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>e</number>    
    depositing earnest money as may be stipulated by the secured creditor;  
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>f</number>    
    any other thing which the authorised officer considers it material for a 
    purchaser to know in order to judge the nature and value of the property.  
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>7</number> Every 
    notice of sale shall be affixed on a conspicuous part of the immovable 
    property and may, if the authorised officer deems if fit, put on the 
    web-site of the secured creditor on the Internet.  
 </section><section>

<number>8</number> Sale by 
    any method other than public auction or public tender, shall be on such 
    terms as may be settled between the parties in writing.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>9</number> Time of 
    sale, issues of sale certificate and delivery of possession, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No sale of immovable property under these rules shall take place before the 
    expiry of thirty days from the date on which the public notice of sale is 
    published in newspapers as referred to in the proviso to sub-rule (6) or 
    notice of sale has been served to the borrower.  
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> The 
    sale shall be confirmed in favour of the purchaser who has offered the 
    highest sale price in his bid or tender or quotation or offer to the 
    authorised officer and shall be subject to confirmation by the secured 
    creditor:  
 

Provided 
    that no sale under this rule shall be confirmed, if the amount offered by 
    sale price is less than the reserve price, specified under sub-rule (5) of 
    rule 9:  
 

Provided 
    further that if the authorised officer fails to obtain a price higher than 
    the reserve price, he may, with the consent of the borrower and the secured 
    creditor effect the sale at such price.  
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> On 
    every sale of immovable property, the purchaser shall immediately pay a 
    deposit of twenty-five per cent. of the amount of the sale price, to the 
    authorised officer conducting the sale and in default of such deposit, the 
    property shall forthwith be sold again.  
 </section><section>

<number>4</number> The 
    balance amount of purchase price payable shall be paid by the purchaser to 
    the authorised officer on or before the fifteenth day of confirmation of 
    sale of the immovable property or such extended period as may be agreed upon 
    in writing between the parties.  
 </section><section>

<number>5</number> In 
    default of payment within the period mentioned in sub-rule (4), the deposit 
    shall be forfeited and the property shall be resold and the defaulting 
    purchaser shall forfeit all claim to the property or to any part of the sum 
    for which it may be subsequently sold.  
 </section><section>

<number>6</number> On 
    confirmation of sale by the secured creditor and if the terms of payment 
    have been complied with, the authorised officer exercising the power of sale 
    shall issue a certificate of sale of the immovable property in favour of the 
    purchaser in the form given in Appendix V to these rules.  
 </section><section>

<number>7</number> Where 
    the immovable property sold is subject to any encumbrances, the authorised 
    officer may, if the thinks fit, allow the purchaser to deposit with him the 
    money required to discharge the encumbrances and any interest due thereon 
    together with such additional amount that may be sufficient to meet the 
    contingencies or further cost, expenses and interest as may be determined by 
    him.  
 </section><section>

<number>8</number> On such 
    deposit of money for discharge of the encumbrances, the authorised officer 
    may issue or cause the purchaser to issue notices to the persons interested 
    in or entitled to the money deposited with him and take steps to make the 
    payment accordingly.  
 </section><section>

<number>9</number> The 
    authorised officer shall deliver the property to the purchaser free from 
    encumbrances known to the secured creditor on deposit of money as specified 
    in sub-rule (7) above.  
 </section><section>

<number>10</number> The 
    certificate of sale issued under sub-rule (6) shall specifically mention 
    that whether the purchaser has purchased the immovable secured asset free 
    from any encumbrances known to the secured creditor or not.
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>10</number> 
    Appointment of Manager.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Board of Directors or Board of Trustees, as the case may be, may appoint 
    in consultation with the borrower any person (hereinafter referred to as the 
    Manager) to manage the secured assets the possession of which has been taken 
    over by the secured creditor.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> The 
    Manager appointed by the Board of Directors or Board of Trustees, as the 
    case may be, shall be deemed to be an agent of the borrower and the borrower 
    shall be solely responsible for the commission or omission of acts of the 
    Manager unless such commission or omission are due to improper intervention 
    of the secured creditor or the authorised officer.  
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> The 
    Manager shall have power by notice in writing to recover any money from any 
    person who has acquired any of the secured assets from the borrower, which 
    is due or may beocme due to the borrower.  
 </section><section>

<number>4</number> The 
    Manager shall give such person who has made payment under sub-rule (3) a 
    valid discharge as if he has made payments to the borrower.  
 </section><section>

<number>5</number> The 
    Manager shall apply all the monies received by him in accordance with the 
    provisions contained in sub-section (7) of section 13 of the Ordinance.
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>11</number> 
    Procedure for Recovery of shortfall of secured debt.—

<section><number>1</number> An application for recovery of balance amount by any secured 
    creditor pursuant to sub-section (10) of section 13 of the Ordinance shall 
    be presented to the Debt Recovery Tribunal in the form annexed as Appendix 
    VI to these rules by the authorised officer or his agent or by a duly 
    authorised legal practitioner, to the Registrar of the Bench within whose 
    jurisdiction his case falls or shall be sent by registered post addressed to 
    the Registrar of Debts Recovery Tribunal.  
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> The 
    provisions of the Debts Recovery Tribunal (Procedure) Rules, 1993 made under 
    Recovery of Debts Due to Banks and Financial institutions Act, 1993 (51 of 
    1993), shall mutatis mutandis apply to any application filed by under 
    sub-rule (1).  
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> An 
    application under sub-rule (1) shall be accompanied with fee as provided in 
    rule 7 of the Debts Recovery Tribunal (Procedure) Rules, 1993.  
  
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 the Security interest (enforcement) rules, 2002
 


 <article>

1[<number>12</number> Application to the 
Tribunal/Appellate Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> Any 
application to the Debt Recovery Tribunal under sub-section (1) of section 17 
shall be, as nearly as possible, in the form given in Appendix VII to the rules.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any application to the 
Appellate Tribunal under sub-section (6) of section 17 of the Act shall be, as 
nearly as possible, in the form given in Appendix VIII to the said rules. Any 
appeal to the Appellate Tribunal under section 18 of the Act shall be, as nearly 
as possible, in the form given in Appendix IX to the said rules.]
  




</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>