<act><tid>188168</tid>
<title>THE ACTING JUDGES ACT, <year>1867</year></title>

ACT NO. 16 OF <year>1867</year>
[ 1st March, <year>1867</year>.]

An Act to authorize the making of acting appointments to 
certain 
Judicial Offices. 1

Preamble.- WHEREAS the Governor General of India in Council 
or 
the Local Government, as the case may be, is empowered by 
divers 
enactments to appoint the Judges of certain Courts <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>: And 
whereas 
it has been doubted whether he or it is empowered to appoint 
persons 
to act temporarily as such Judges, and it is expedient to remove 
such 
doubts; It is hereby enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>117943</tid>
<number>1</number>Power to appoint acting Judges.- In every case in which the 
Central Government, or the State Government, as the case may be, has 
power under any Act or Regulation to appoint a Judge of any Court 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>, such power shall be taken to include the power to appoint any 
person capable of being appointed a permanent Judge of such Court, to 
act as Judge of' the same Court for such time as the Central 
Government or the State Government, as the case may be, shall direct. 
Every person so appointed to act temporarily as a Judge of any such 
Court shall have the powers and perform the duties which he would have 
had and been liable to perform in case he had been duly appointed a 
permanent Judge of the same Court.


</article>



<article><tid>699369</tid>
<number>2</number>Certain enactments to be construed as if they contained a 
clause like section 1 of this Act. Every such Act and Regulation shall 
be construed as if it contained a special clause to the purport or 
effect of the first section of this Act.
-------------


<pagefootnote><pagenum>999999</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been declared, by notification under s. 3 (a) of 
the Scheduled Districts Act, <year>1874</year> (14 of <year>1874</year>), to be in force in the 
following Scheduled Districts, namely:-

The Districts of Hazaribagh, Lohardaga now the Ranchi District, 
  see Calcutta Gazette, <year>1899</year>, Pt. 1, p. 44). and Manbhum. and Pargana 
Dhalbhum and the Kolhan in the District of Singbhum- see Gazette of 
India--, <year>1881</year>, Pt. 1, p. 504.

This Act has been extended to the new Provinces and Merged States 
by the Merged States (Laws) Act. <year>1949</year> (59 of <year>1949</year>) and to the States 
of Manipur, Tripura a and Vindhya Pradesh by the Part C States (Laws) 
  Act' <year>1950</year> of <year>1950</year>), s. 2.


</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The words" in the Provinces" were omitted by the A. O. <year>1950</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>The words" in British India" were rep. by the A. O. <year>1948</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>