<act><tid>1636063</tid>
<title>THE NATIONAL COMMISSION FOR MINORITY EDUCATIONAL INSTITUTIONS 
 (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2006</year></title>

NO. 18 OF <year>2006</year>
[ 28th March, <year>2006</year>.]

An Act to amend the National Commission for Minority Educational 
Institutions Act, <year>2004</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- seventh Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>33167</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>1725115</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
National Commission for Minority Educational Institutions (Amendment) 
Act, <year>2006</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1935264</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 23rd day of 
January, <year>2006</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1740571</tid>
<number> 2</number> Amendment of section 2.- In section 2 of the National Commission 
for Minority Educational Institutions Act, <year>2004</year> (2 of <year>2005</year>) 
 (hereinafter referred to as the principal Act),-
<section><tid>290828</tid>
<number>i</number>in clause (a), the word" Scheduled" shall be omitted;

</section>

<section><tid>759716</tid>
<number>ii</number>after clause (a), the following clause shall be inserted, 
namely:-
' (aa)" appropriate Government" means,-


</section>

<section><tid>290828</tid>
<number>i</number>in relation to an educational institution recognised for 
conducting its programmes of studies under any Act of Parliament, the 
Central Government; and

</section>

<section><tid>759716</tid>
<number>ii</number>in relation to any other educational institution recognised for 
conducting its programmes of studies under any State Act, a State 
Government in whose jurisdiction such institution is established;'; 
 (iii) after clause (c), the following clause shall be inserted, 
namely:-
' (ca)" Competent authority" means the authority appointed by the 
appropriate Government to grant no objection certificate for the 
establishment of any educational institution of their choice by the 
minorities;';


</section>

<section><tid>959230</tid>
<number>iv</number>after clause (d), the following clause shall be inserted, 
namely:-
' (da)" educational rights of minorities" means the rights of 
minorities to establish and administer educational institutions of 
their choice;';


</section>

<section><tid>108846</tid>
<number>v</number>clause (j) shall be omitted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>992534</tid>
<number>3</number>Substitution of new Chapter for Chapter III..- For Chapter III of 
the principal Act, the following Chapter shall be substituted, 
namely:-
' CHAPTER III

RIGHTS OF A MINORITY EDUCATIONAL INSTITUTION

</article>



<article><tid>26013</tid>
<number> 10</number> Right to establish a Minority Educational Institution.-
<section><tid>1010928</tid>
<number>1</number>Any  
person who desires to establish a Minority Educational Institution 
may apply to the Competent authority for the grant of no objection 
certificate for the said purpose.

</section>

<section><tid>465411</tid>
<number>2</number>The Competent authority shall,-

<subsection><tid>1658856</tid>
<number>a</number>on perusal of documents, affidavits or other evidence, if any; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1774282</tid>
<number>b</number>after giving an opportunity of being heard to the applicant, 
decide every application filed under sub- section (1) as expeditiously 
as possible and grant or reject the application, as the case may be:
Provided that where an application is rejected, the Competent 
authority shall communicate the same to the applicant.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1167678</tid>
<number>3</number>Where within a period of ninety days from the receipt of the 
application under sub- section (1) for the grant of no objection 
certificate,-

<subsection><tid>20649</tid>
<number>a</number>the Competent authority does not grant such certificate; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>180942</tid>
<number>b</number>where an application has been rejected and the same has not been 
communicated to the person who has applied for the grant of such 
certificate, 
it shall be deemed that the Competent authority has granted a no 
objection certificate to the applicant.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>630998</tid>
<number>4</number>The applicant shall, on the grant of a no objection certificate 
or where the Competent authority has deemed to have granted the no 
objection certificate, be entitled to commence and proceed with the 
establishment of a Minority Educational Institution in accordance 
with the rules and regulations, as the case may be, laid down by or 
under any law for the time being in force.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,-


<subsection><tid>901747</tid>
<number>a</number>" applicant" means any person who makes an application under sub- 
section (1) for establishment of a Minority Educational Institution;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1015561</tid>
<number>b</number>" no objection certificate" means a certificate stating therein, 
that the Competent authority has no objection for the establishment 
of a Minority Educational Institution.

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>473760</tid>
<number> 10A</number> Right of a Minority Educational Institution to seek 
affiliation.-
<section><tid>1245903</tid>
<number>1</number>A Minority Educational Institution may seek  
affiliation to any University of its choice subject to such 
affiliation being permissible within the Act under which the said 
University is established.

</section>

<section><tid>605063</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person who is authorised in this behalf by the Minority 
Educational Institution, may file an application for affiliation 
under sub- section (1) to a University in the manner prescribed by the 
Statute, Ordinance, rules or regulations, of the University:
Provided that such authorised person shall have right to know the 
status of such application after the expiry of sixty days from the 
date of filing of such application.'.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1400569</tid>
<number> 4</number> Amendment of section 11.- In section 11 of the principal Act, for 
clauses (b) and (c), the following clauses shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (b) enquire, suo motu, or on a petition presented to it by any 
Minority Educational Institution, or any person on its behalf into 
complaints regarding deprivation or violation of rights of minorities 
to establish and administer educational institutions of their choice 
and any dispute relating to affiliation to a University and report 
its finding to the appropriate Government for its implementation;

<section><tid>1996701</tid>
<number>c</number>intervene in any proceeding involving any deprivation or 
violation of the educational rights of the minorities before a court 
with the leave of such court;

</section>

<section><tid>871214</tid>
<number>d</number>review the safeguards provided by or under the Constitution, or 
any law for the time being in force, for the protection of 
educational rights of the minorities and recommend measures for their 
effective implementation;

</section>

<section><tid>38357</tid>
<number>e</number>specify measures to promote and preserve the minority status and 
character of institutions of their choice established by minorities;

</section>

<section><tid>624572</tid>
<number>f</number>decide all questions relating to the status of any institution as 
a Minority Educational Institution and declare its status as such;

</section>

<section><tid>1715779</tid>
<number>g</number>make recommendations to the appropriate Government for the 
effective, implementation of programmes and schemes relating to the 
Minority Educational Institutions; and

</section>

<section><tid>1877587</tid>
<number>h</number>do such other acts and things as may be necessary, incidental or 
conducive to the attainment of all or any of the objects of the 
Commission.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1208176</tid>
<number> 5</number> Amendment of section 12.- In section 12 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>767665</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1), the word" Scheduled" shall be omitted;

</section>

<section><tid>829655</tid>
<number>b</number>after sub- section (2), the following sub- section shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (3) Every proceeding before the Commission shall be deemed to be a 
judicial proceeding within the meaning of sections 193 and 228, and 
for the purposes of section 196, of the Indian Penal Code (45 of  
  <year>1860</year>) and the Commission shall be deemed to be a civil court for the 
purposes of section 195 and Chapter XXVI of the Code of Criminal 
Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>).".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>499629</tid>
<number> 6</number> Insertion of new sections 12A to 12F.- After section 12 of the 
principal Act, the following sections shall be inserted, namely:-
' 12A. Appeal against orders of the Competent authority.- (I) Any 
person aggrieved by the order of refusal to grant no objection 
certificate under sub- section (2) of section 10 by the Competent 
authority for establishing a Minority Educational Institution, may 
prefer an appeal against such order to the Commission.

<section><tid>10059</tid>
<number>2</number>An appeal under sub- section (I) shall be filed within thirty days 
from the date of the order referred to in sub- section (I) 
communicated to the applicant:
Provided that the Commission may entertain an appeal after the expiry 
of the said period of thirty days, if it is satisfied that there was 
sufficient cause for not filing it within that period.


</section>

<section><tid>741198</tid>
<number>3</number>An appeal to the Commission shall be made in such form as may be 
prescribed and shall be accompanied by a copy of the order against 
which the appeal has been filed.

</section>

<section><tid>992159</tid>
<number>4</number>The Commission, after hearing the parties, shall pass an order as 
soon as may be practicable, and give such directions as may be 
necessary or expedient to give effect to its orders or to prevent 
abuse of its process or to secure the ends of justice. 
 (5) An order made by the Commission under sub- section (4) shall be 
executable by the Commission as a decree of a civil court and the 
provisions of the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>), so far 
as may be, shall apply as they apply in respect of a decree of a 
civil court.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>726056</tid>
<number> 12B</number> Power of Commission to decide on the minority status of an 
educational institution.-
<section><tid>1485941</tid>
<number>1</number>Without prejudice to the provisions  
contained in the National Commission for Minorities Act, <year>1992</year> (19 of  
  <year>1992</year>), where an authority established by the Central Government or 
any State Government, as the case may be, for grant of minority 
status to any educational institution rejects the application for the 
grant of such status, the aggrieved person may appeal against such 
order of the authority to the Commission.

</section>

<section><tid>396992</tid>
<number>2</number>An appeal under sub- section (1) shall be preferred within thirty 
days from the date of the order communicated to the applicant: 
Provided that the Commission may entertain an appeal after the expiry 
of the said period of thirty days, if it is satisfied that there was 
sufficient cause for not filing it within that period.

</section>

<section><tid>1217868</tid>
<number>3</number>An appeal to the Commission shall be made in such form as may be 
prescribed and shall be accompanied by a copy of the order against 
which the appeal has been filed.

</section>

<section><tid>202413</tid>
<number>4</number>On receipt of the appeal under sub- section (3), the Commission 
may, after giving the parties to the appeal an opportunity of being 
heard, and in consultation with the State Government, decide on the 
minority status of the educational institution and shall proceed to 
give such directions as it may deem fit and, all such directions 
shall be binding on the parties.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section and section 12C, 
" authority" means any authority or officer or commission which is 
established under any law for the time being in force or under any 
order of the appropriate Government, for the purpose of granting a 
certificate of minority status to an educational institution.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1215126</tid>
<number> 12C</number> Power to cancel.- The Commission may, after giving a reasonable 
opportunity of being heard to a Minority Educational Institution to 
which minority status has been granted by an authority or Commission, 
as the case may be, cancel such status under the following 
circumstances, namely:-
<section><tid>478628</tid>
<number>a</number>if the constitution, aims and objects of the educational 
institution, which has enabled it to obtain minority status has 
subsequently been amended in such a way that it no longer reflects 
the purpose or character of a Minority Educational Institution;

</section>

<section><tid>1355497</tid>
<number>b</number>if, on verification of the records during the inspection or 
investigation, it is found that the Minority Educational Institution 
has failed to admit students belonging to the minority community in 
the institution as per rules and prescribed percentage governing 
admissions during any academic year.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>315134</tid>
<number> 12D</number> Power of Commission to investigate matters relating to 
deprivation of educational rights of minorities.-
<section><tid>1127197</tid>
<number>1</number>The Commission  
shall have the power to investigate into the complaints relating to 
deprivation of the educational rights of minorities.

</section>

<section><tid>1234566</tid>
<number>2</number>The Commission may, for the purpose of conducting any 
investigation pertaining to a complaint under this Act, utilise the 
services of any officer of the Central Government or any State 
Government with the concurrence of the Central Government or the 
State Government, as the case may be. 
 (3) For the purpose of investigation under sub- section (1), the 
officer whose services are utilised may, subject to the direction and 
control of the Commission,-

<subsection><tid>1795521</tid>
<number>a</number>summon and enforce the attendance of any person and examine him;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>782751</tid>
<number>b</number>require the discovery and production of any document; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1498694</tid>
<number>c</number>requisition any public record or copy thereof from any office.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>357443</tid>
<number>4</number>The officer whose services are utilised under sub- section (2) 
shall investigate into any matter entrusted to it by the Commission 
and submit a report thereon to it within such period as may be 
specified by the Commission in this behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>3053</tid>
<number>5</number>The Commission shall satisfy itself about the correctness of the 
facts stated and the conclusion, if any, arrived at in the report 
submitted to it under sub- section (4) and for this purpose the 
Commission may make such further inquiry as it may think fit.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1010080</tid>
<number> 12E</number> Power of Commission to call for information, etc.-
<section><tid>1566915</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Commission, while enquiring into the complaints of violation or 
deprivation of educational rights of minorities shall call for 
information or report from the Central Government or any State 
Government or any other authority or organisation subordinate 
thereto, within such time as may be specified by it: 
Provided that,-

<subsection><tid>1103505</tid>
<number>a</number>if the information or report is not received within the time 
stipulated by the Commission, it may proceed to inquire into the 
complaint;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>17764</tid>
<number>b</number>if, on receipt of information or report, the Commission is 
satisfied either that no further inquiry is required, or that the 
required action has been initiated or taken by the concerned 
Government or authority, it may not proceed with the complaint and 
inform the complainant accordingly.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>335271</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the inquiry establishes violation or deprivation of the 
educational rights of the minorities by a public servant, the 
Commission may recommend to the concerned Government or authority, 
the initiation of disciplinary proceedings or such other action 
against the concerned person or persons as may be deemed fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1343085</tid>
<number>3</number>The Commission shall send a copy of the inquiry report, together 
with its recommendations to the concerned Government or authority and 
the concerned Government or authority shall, within a period of one 
month, or such further time as the Commission may allow, forward its 
comments on the report, including the action taken, or proposed to be 
taken thereon, to the Commission.

</section>

<section><tid>993064</tid>
<number>4</number>The Commission shall publish its inquiry report and the action 
taken or proposed to be taken by the concerned Government or 
authority on the recommen- dations of the Commission.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>18280</tid>
<number>12F</number>Bar of jurisdiction.- No court (except the Supreme Court and a  
High Court exercising jurisdiction under articles 226 and 227 of the 
  Constitution) shall entertain any suit, application or other 
proceedings in respect of any order made under this Chapter.'.

</article>



<article><tid>616890</tid>
<number>7</number>Omission of section 18.- Section 18 of the principal Act shall be 
omitted.


</article>



<article><tid>317255</tid>
<number>8</number>Amendment of section 24.- In section 24 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (2), after clause (a), the following clause shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (aa) the forms in which appeal under sub- section (3) of section 12A 
and sub- section (3) of section 12B shall be made;".



</article>



<article><tid>1670993</tid>
<number>9</number>Omission of Schedule.- The Schedule to the principal Act shall be 
omitted.


</article>



<article><tid>26013</tid>
<number> 10</number> Repeal of Ordinance 1 of <year>2006</year> and saving.-
<section><tid>1010928</tid>
<number>1</number>The National  
Commission for Minority Educational Institutions (Amendment) 
Ordinance, <year>2006</year>, is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>465411</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken 
under the principal Act, as amended by the said Ordinance, shall be 
deemed to have been done or taken under the principal Act, as amended 
by this Act.
----

T. K. VISWANATHAN,

Secy. to the Govt. of India.





</section>

</article>



 </act>