<act><tid>1253669</tid>
<title>THE COINAGE ACT, <year>1906</year></title>

ACT NO. 3 OF <year>1906</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 2nd March, <year>1906</year>.]

An Act to consolidate and amend the law relating to Coinage and 
the Mint.

WHEREAS it is expendient to consolidate and amend the law 
relating to Coinage and the Mint; it is hereby enacted as follows:--





<article><tid>455212</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>1061563</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>  
Coinage Act <year>1906</year>; and <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> (2) It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1459615</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant 
in the subject or context,--
<section><tid>427864</tid>
<number>a</number>" deface", with its grammatical variations and cognate 
expressions, includes clipping, filing, stamping, or such 
other alteration of the surface or shape of a coin as is 
readily distinguishable from the effects of reasonable wear;

</section>

<section><tid>1944394</tid>
<number>b</number>" the Mint" includes the Mints now existing and any which 
may hereafter be established;

</section>

<section><tid>1010825</tid>
<number>c</number>" prescribed" includes prescribed by a rule made under 
this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1466914</tid>
<number>d</number>" remedy" means variation from the standard weight and 
fineness; and

</section>

<section><tid>710621</tid>
<number>e</number>" standard weight" means the weight prescribed for any 
coin.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1994393</tid>
<number> 3</number> Power to establish and abolish Mints. The Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette,--
<section><tid>994033</tid>
<number>a</number>establish a Mint at any place at which a Mint does not 
for the time being exist; and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>8</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been extended to Goa, Daman and Diu by Reg. 6 of 
<year>1962</year>, s. 6, to Dadra and Nagar Haveli by Reg. 6 of <year>1963</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I 
and to Laccadive, Minicoy and Amindivi Islands by Reg. 8 of <year>1965</year>, s. 3 
and Sch. and to the State of Sikkim vide Notifin. S. O. 4756, dated 
8- 8- <year>1975</year>, Gazette of India, Part II, Sec. 3 (ii), Page 3937 (w. e. f.  
  1- 7- <year>1975</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The word" Indian" omitted by Act 47 of <year>1975</year>, s. 2.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for the former sub- section 2.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>The words" except the State of Jammu and Kashmir" omitted by 
Act 62 of <year>1965</year> s. 2 and Sch.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>421049</tid>
<number>b</number>abolish any Mint, whether now existing or hereafter 
established.
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>760571</tid>
<number>4</number>[ Silver coins.] Rep. by the Indian Coinage (Amendment) Act, 
 <year>1947</year> (28 of <year>1947</year>), s. 2.


</article>



<article><tid>1528003</tid>
<number>5</number>[ Standard weight and fineness.] Rep. by s. 2, ibid.
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> COINAGE



</article>



<article><tid>461323</tid>
<number> 6</number> Denominations, dimensions, designs and composition of coins.

<section><tid>1085690</tid>
<number>1</number><footcitenum>8</footcitenum> Coins may be coined at the Mint for issue under the authority of  
the Central Government, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> of such denominations not higher than one 
thousand rupees], of such dimensions and designs, and of such metals 
or of mixed metals of such composition as the Central Government may 
by notification in the Official Gazette, determine.]

</section>

<section><tid>564755</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>8</footcitenum> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), if 
the Central Government is of opinion that it is necessary or expedient 
in the public intrest so to do, it may authorise the coining in like 
manner as is provided in that sub- section, of coins by any person 
 (including the Government of any foreign country), beyond the limits 
of India and import such coins for issue under its authority under 
that sub- section.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1975724</tid>
<number>7</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Standard weight and remedy. The standard weight of the 
coins of any denomination coine under the provisions of section 6, and 
the remedy allowed in the making of such coins shall be such as may be 
prescribed in this behalf by the Central Government.]
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum>.



</article>



<article><tid>202301</tid>
<number>10</number>[ Power to direct coining, and to prescribe dimensions and 
designs.] Rep. by the Indian Coinage (Amendment) Act, <year>1947</year> (28 of  
  <year>1947</year>), s. 4.


</article>



<article><tid>186782</tid>
<number>11</number>[ Demonetization of sovereign and half- sovereign.] Rep. by 
s. 4, ibid.


</article>



<article><tid>367424</tid>
<number>12</number>[ Silver coin when a legal tender.] Rep. by s. 4, ibid.


</article>



<article><tid>279234</tid>
<number> 13</number> <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>
<section><tid>492636</tid>
<number>1</number>The coins issued under the authority of section 6  
shall be a legal tender in payment or on account,---

<subsection><tid>70849</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>7</footcitenum> in the case of a coin of any denomination not lower than 
one rupee], for any sum;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>9</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The heading" silver coinage" rep. by Act 28 of <year>1947</year>, s. 2.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The heading" Coinage" and s. 6 subs. by s. 3 ibid., for the former 
heading and s. 6.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 47 of <year>1975</year>, s. 3 for certain words.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by Ordinance 4 of <year>1942</year>, s. 2, for the former ss. 7, 8 and 9.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>The heading" Dimensions and Designs of Coins" rep. by Act 28 
of <year>1947</year>, s. 4.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Subs. by s. 5, ibid., for the former s. 13, which had been subs. 
by Ordinance 4 of <year>1942</year>, s. 4, for ss. 13 and 14.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>7</number>Subs. by Act 28 of <year>1968</year>, s. 3, for certain words (w. e. f. 1- 11-  
  <year>1968</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>8</number>Renumbered and ins. by Act 33 of <year>1985</year>, s. 2.







</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1859610</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of a half- rupee coin, for any sum not 
exceeding ten rupees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>847023</tid>
<number>c</number>in the case of any other coin, for any sum not 
exceeding one rupee:
Provided that the coin has not been defaced and has not lost 
weight so as to be less than such weight as may be prescribed in its 
case.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>384635</tid>
<number>2</number>All silver coins issued under this Act after the 10th day of 
March, <year>1940</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> and before the commencement of the Indian Coinage 
 (Amendment) Act, <year>1947</year>] (28 of <year>1947</year>). shall continue as before to be a 
legal tender in payment or on account,-

<subsection><tid>475605</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of a rupee coin, for any sum;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>945179</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of a half- rupee coin, for any sum not 
exceeding ten rupees:

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>489366</tid>
<number>c</number>in the case of a quarter- rupee, for any sum not 
exceeding one rupee
Provided that the coin has not been defaced and has not lost 
weight so as to be less than-


<subsubsection><tid>333565</tid>
<number>i</number> 176. 4 grains Troy in the case of a rupee coin, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>803374</tid>
<number>ii</number> 88. 2 grains Troy in the case of a half- rupee coin, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1064580</tid>
<number>iii</number>such weight as may be prescribed in the case of a 
quarter- rupee coin.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>320823</tid>
<number>3</number>All nickel, copper and bronze coins which may have been 
issued under this Act before the 24th day of January, <year>1942</year> shall con- 
tinue as before to be a legal tender in payment or on account for any 
sum not exceeding one rupee.]

</section>

<section><tid>399395</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> All new coins in the naya paisa series, designated as such 
under the notification of the Government of India in the Ministry of 
Finance, Department of Economic Affairs, No. S. R. O. 1120, dated 11th 
May, <year>1956</year> which may have been issued under this Act prior to the 
commencement of the Indian Coinage (Amendment) Act, <year>1964</year> (17 of  
  <year>1964</year>). shall continue to be a legal tender in payment or on account,-

<subsection><tid>170039</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of a half- rupee or fifty naye paise coin, 
for any sum not exceeding ten rupees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>760141</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of any other coin, for any sum not 
exceeding one rupee.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>10</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 28 of <year>1968</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1968</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by Act 17 of <year>1964</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 6- <year>1964</year>).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1098355</tid>
<number> 14</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Decimal system of coinage.
<section><tid>433913</tid>
<number>1</number>The rupee shall be divided  
into one hundred units and the new coin representing such unit may 
be designated by the Central Government, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, under such name as it thinks fit, and the rupee, 
half- rupee and quarter- rupee shall be respectively equivalent to one 
hundred, fifty and twenty- five such new coins and shall, subject to 
the provisions of sub- section (1) and sub- section (2) of section 13 
and to the extent specified therein, be a legal tender in payment or 
on account accordingly.

</section>

<section><tid>83068</tid>
<number>2</number>All coins issued under the authority of this Act in any 
denominations of annas, pice and pies shall, to the extent specified 
in section 13, be a legal tender in payment or on account at the rate 
of sixteen annas, sixty- four pice or one hundred and ninety- two pies 
to one hundred new coins, referred to in sub- section (1), calculated 
in respect of any such single coin or number of such coins, tendered 
at one transaction, to the nearest new coin, or where the new coin 
above and the new coin below are equally near, to the new coin below.

</section>

<section><tid>1286766</tid>
<number>3</number>All references in any enactment or in any notification, rule 
or order under any enactment or in any contract, deed or other 
instrument to any value expressed in annas, pice and pies shall be 
construed as references to that value expressed in new coins referred 
to in sub- section (1) converted thereto at the rate specified in sub- 
section (2).]

</section>

<section><tid>608658</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> As from the commencement of the Indian Coinage (Amendment) 
Act, <year>1964</year> (17 of <year>1964</year>). all references in any enactment or in any 
notification, rule or order under any enactment or in any contract, 
deed or other instrument to any value in naya paisa or naye paise 
shall be construed as references to that value expressed respectively 
in paisa or paise, being the new coins designated as such from 1st day 
of June, <year>1964</year>.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1715610</tid>
<number>15</number>[ Coin made under former Acts.] Rep. by the Indian Coinage 
 (Amendment) Act, <year>1947</year> (28 of <year>1947</year>), s. 6.


</article>



<article><tid>60093</tid>
<number> 16</number> Power to certain persons to cut diminished or defaced 
silver coins. Where any silver coin which has been coined and issued 
under the authority of the Central Government is tendered to any 
person authorised by the Central Government <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> to act under this 
section, and such person has reason to believe that the coin-
<section><tid>117370</tid>
<number>a</number>has been diminished in weight so as to be more than 
such percentage below standard weight as may be prescribed as 
the limit of reasonable wear, or

</section>

<section><tid>53864</tid>
<number>b</number>has been defaced,
he shall, by himself or another, cut or break the coin.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>11</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 28 of <year>1947</year>, s. 7, for" any of those sections".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The words, brackets and figures" other than the rupee and half 
rupee referred to in sub- section (1) of section 12" omitted by 
Ordinance 12 of <year>1940</year>, s. 2.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by s. 2, ibid., for" save at a Govt. Currency Office".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>The proviso omitted by s. 2, ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>The word" Silver" omitted by Act 21 of 19 19, s. 6 (1).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>The words" or by the L. G." omitted by the A. O. <year>1937</year>.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1633442</tid>
<number> 17</number> Procedure in regard to coin cut under section 16 (a). A 
person cutting or breaking coin under the provisions of clause (a) of 
section 16 shall observe the following procedure, namely.:-
<section><tid>1793932</tid>
<number>a</number>if the coin has been diminished in weight so as to be 
more than such percentage below standard weight as may be 
prescribed as the limit of reasonable wear, but not more than 
such further percentage as may be prescribed in this behalf, 
he shall either return the pieces to the person tendering the 
coin, or, if such person so requests, shall receive and pay 
for the coin at such rates as may be prescribed in this 
behalf; and

</section>

<section><tid>1652542</tid>
<number>b</number>if the coin has been diminished in weight so as to be 
more than such further percentage below standard weight so 
prescribed as aforesaid, he shall return the pieces to the 
person tendering the coin, who shall bear the loss caused by 
such cutting or breaking.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>859518</tid>
<number> 18</number> Procedure in regard to coin cut under section 16 (b). A 
person cutting or breaking coin under the provisions of clause (b) of 
section 16 shall observe the following procedure, namely:-
<section><tid>167019</tid>
<number>a</number>ifsuch person has reason to believe that the coin 
has been fraudulently defaced, he shall return the pieces to 
the person tendering the coin, who shall bear the loss caused 
by such cutting or breaking;

</section>

<section><tid>747755</tid>
<number>b</number>ifsuch person has not reason to believe that the 
coin has been fraudulently defaced, he shall receive and pay 
for the coin at its nominal value.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section a coin which, there 
is reason to believe, has been defaced by sweating shall be deemed to 
have been fraudulently defaced.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1782987</tid>
<number> 19</number> Procedure in regard to coin which is liable to be cut under 
both clause (a) and clause (b) of section 16. If a coin is liable to 
be cut or broken under the provisions of both clause (a) and clause 
 (b) of section 16, the person cutting or breaking the coin shall deal 
with it,-
<section><tid>171255</tid>
<number>a</number>if he has reason to believe that the coin has been 
fraudulently defaced, under clause (a) of section 18, and

</section>

<section><tid>5049</tid>
<number>b</number>in other cases, under section 17.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>25191</tid>
<number>20</number>Power to certain persons to cut counterfeit or fraudulently 
defaced coin and procedure regard to coin so cut. Where any <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 
coin purporting to be coined or issued under the authority of the 
Central Government is tendered to any person <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> authorized by the 
Central Government <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> to act under

<pagefootnote><pagenum>12</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" silver or other" rep. by Act 28 of <year>1947</year>, s. 8.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>For persons so authorized, see Gen. R. and O., Supplementary 
Vol. VI, p. 232.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>The worlds" or by the L. G." rep. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

this section, and such person has reason to believe that the coin is 
counterfeit <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or has been fraudulently defaced], he shall by himself 
or another cut or break the coin, and may at his discretion either 
return the pieces to the tenderer, who shall bear the loss caused by 
such cutting or breaking, or <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> in the case of silver coin] receive and 
pay for the coin according to the value of the silver bullion 
contained in it.

SUPPLEMENTAL PROVISIONS



</article>



<article><tid>1208618</tid>
<number> 21</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1179513</tid>
<number>1</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules] to carry out the 
purposes and objects of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1035955</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may-
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>.


<subsection><tid>425944</tid>
<number>b</number>provide for the guidance of persons authorized to cut 
or break coin under sections 16 and 20;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>88478</tid>
<number>c</number>determine the percentage of diminution in weight below 
standard weight not being less <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> than two percent in the case 
of silver coins or five percent. in the case of pure nickel 
coin], which shall be the limit of reasonable wear;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>155004</tid>
<number>d</number>prescribe the further percentage referred to in clause 
 (a) of section 17, and the rates at which payments shall be 
made in the case of coins falling under the same clause; <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>
<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1508123</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>7</footcitenum> Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon 
as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it 
is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be 
comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and 
if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session 
or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>12A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 28 of <year>1947</year>, s. 8.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by Act 21 of <year>1919</year>, s. 6 (2).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 47 of <year>1975</year>, s. 4, for certain words.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Cl. (a) rep. by Act 28 of <year>1947</year>, s. 9.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Subs. by s. 9, ibid., for" in any case than two per cent."

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>The word" and" and cl. (e) rep. by Act 4 of <year>1927</year>, s. 2.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>7</number>Subs. by Act 47 of <year>1975</year>, s. 4, for sub- section (3).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1377215</tid>
<number>22</number>Bar of suits. No suit or other proceeding shall lie against 
any person in respect of anything in goods faith done, or Intended to 
be done, under or in pursuance of the provisions of this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1516349</tid>
<number>23</number>Saving of making of other coins at Mints. Nothing in this 
Act shall be deemed to prohibit or restrict the making at the Mint of 
coins intended for issue as money by the Government of any territories 
beyond the limits of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India.]


</article>



<article><tid>1033788</tid>
<number>24</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Temporary provisions with respect certain Hyderabad coins. 
Notwithstanding anything in section 6 of the Part B States (Laws) 
Act, <year>1951</year> (3 of <year>1951</year>), coins of such description as at the 
commencement of the said Act were in circulation as legal tender in 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the State of Hyderabad] shall continue to be legal tender in that 
State to the like extent and subject to the same conditions as 
immediately before the commencement of the said Act for such period, 
not exceeding <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> four years] from such commencement, as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, determine.]

</article>



 </act>