<act><title>


The 
    [Foreign] Jurisdiction Act, 1947</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title.—This 
    Act may be called The 

    1[Foreign] 
    Jurisdiction Act, 1947.
  
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    this Act,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>   “1[foreign] 
    jurisdiction” means any jurisdiction which by treaty, agreement, grant, 
    usage, sufferance or other lawful means the Central Government has for the 
    time being in or in relation to any area outside 
2[India];
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   “jurisdiction” 
    includes rights, powers and authority. 
  
  





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Exercise of jurisdiction.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    It shall be lawful for the Central Government to exercise 

    1[foreign] 
    jurisdiction in such manner as it thinks fit. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The Central Government may delegate any such jurisdiction as aforesaid to 
    any officer or authority in such manner and to such extent as it thinks fit.  
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Power to make orders.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make 
    such orders as may seem to it expedient for the effective exercise of any
    

    1[foreign] 
    jurisdiction of the Central Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Without prejudice to the generality of the powers conferred by sub-section 
    (1), any order made under that sub-section may provide—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   for determining the 
    law and procedure to be observed, whether by applying with or without 
    modifications all or any of the provisions of any enactment in force in any 
    State or otherwise;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   for determining the 
    persons who are to exercise jurisdiction, either generally or in particular 
    cases or classes of cases, and the powers to be exercised by them;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   for determining the 
    Courts, Judges, Magistrates and authorities by whom, and for regulating the 
    manner in which, any jurisdiction auxiliary or incidental to or 
    consequential on the jurisdiction exercised under this Act is to be 
    exercised within any State; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   for regulating the 
    amount, collection and application of fees.  
  
  




 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>5</number> Validity of acts done in 
      pursuance of jurisdiction.—Every act and thing done, 
      whether before or after the commencement of this Act, in pursuance of any 
      1[foreign] jurisdiction of the 
      Central Government in an area outside 2[India] shall be as valid as if 
      it had been done according to the local law then in force in that 
      area.
  
  





 
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Evidence as to existence or extent of jurisdiction.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If in any proceeding, civil or criminal, in a court established in 

    2[India] or by the 
    authority of the Central Government outside 

    2[India]; any 
    question arises as to the existence or extent of any 

    1[foreign] 
    jurisdiction of the Central Government, the Secretary to the Government of 
    India in the appropriate department shall, on the application of the Court, 
    send to the Court the decision of the Central Government on the question, 
    and that decision shall for the purposes of the proceeding be final.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The Court shall send to the said Secretary, in a document under the seal of 
    the court or signed by a Judge of the Court, questions framed so as properly 
    to raise the question, and sufficient answers to those questions shall be 
    returned to the Court by the Secretary and those answers shall on production 
    thereof be conclusive evidence of the matters therein contained.  
  





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Repeal and saving.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Extra-Provincial Jurisdiction Ordinance, 1947 is hereby repealed.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Any order made, anything done or any action taken in exercise of any power 
    conferred by or under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been made, 
    done or taken in exercise of power conferred by or under this Act as if this 
    Act had commenced on the 27th day of August, 1947.  
 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>