<act><title>


The appellate Tribunal For Forfeited Property 
    (Fees) Rules, 1989</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 



 



 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Appellate Tribunal for Forfeited Property (Fees) 
    Rules, 1989.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 



 



 <article>
<number>2</number> Scale of 
    fees for inspection of records and registers of the Appellate Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The fees which shall be paid for the inspection of the records and registers 
    of the Appellate Tribunal shall be the following, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    for the first hour of inspection or 
    part thereof:                  1 Rupee
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    for every additional hour of inspection 
    or part thereof:       50 Paise
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Fees for 
    the said inspection shall be paid in cash.
 
 
 
 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 



 



 <article>
<number>3</number> Scale of 
    fees for obtaining certified copies of records and registers of the 
    Appellate Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> Copying 
    fees for supply of copies shall be rupees two per page or part thereof.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Copying 
    fees for supply of photostat copies shall, however, be the actual expenses 
    incurred by the Appellate Tribunal for such copies.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>   A fee of 
    two rupees shall be levied for authenticating a copy to be a true copy.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number>   Copying 
    fees shall be recovered in advance in cash. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number>   Where a 
    party applies for immediate delivery of a copy of evidence taken down by a 
    Stenographer, the fee chargeable shall be 2½ times of those specified by 
    sub-rule (1), in such case, fifty per cent of the fees specified by sub-rule 
    (1) shall be paid to the Stenographer.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number>   When a 
    copy is sent by post, the applicant shall also be charged with the actual 
    postal charges which shall be recovered in advance in cash.
 
 
 
 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 



 



 <article>
<number>4</number> Saving.—Nothing 
    in these rules shall enable any person to inspect or to obtain a copy of any 
    register or document to which he is not otherwise entitled by or under any 
    law or order of the Appellate Tribunal.
 
 
 
 
 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>