<act><tid>1614619</tid>
<title>THE COMPANIES (TEMPORARY RESTRICTIONS ON DIVIDENDS) ACT, <year>1974</year></title>

ACT NO. 35 OF <year>1974</year>
[ 31st August, <year>1974</year>]

An Act to provide, in the interests of national economic 
development, for temporary restrictions on the power of certain 
companies to declare dividends out of profits and for matters 
connected therewith or incidental thereto.

BE, it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- fifth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-





<article><tid>382709</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title extent and commencement.
<section><tid>812571</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called  
the Companies (Temporary Restrictions on Dividends) Act, <year>1974</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>845516</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.

</section>

<section><tid>840316</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 6th day of 
July, <year>1974</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1736536</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>1018197</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means the 6th day of July, <year>1974</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>319797</tid>
<number>b</number>" company" has the meaning assigned to it in the 
Companies Act, <year>1956</year>, (1 OF <year>1956</year>) and includes a foreign 
company within the meaning of section 591 of the Companies 
Act, <year>1956</year>, which has made arrangements prescribed under the 
Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year>, (43 OF <year>1961</year>) for the declaration and 
payment of dividends within India;

</section>

<section><tid>1747110</tid>
<number>c</number>" distributable profits in relation to a company to 
which this Act applies, means,-

<pagefootnote><pagenum>488</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


<subsection><tid>345756</tid>
<number>i</number>one- third of the net profits of the company, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1210490</tid>
<number>ii</number>an amount required to pay twelve per cent. 
dividend on the face value of the equity shares of the 
company and dividend payable on its preference shares,
whichever is lower;


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>918158</tid>
<number>d</number>" financial year" has the meaning assigned to it in 
section 2 of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year>; (1 of <year>1956</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>1311994</tid>
<number>e</number>" net profits" means net profits of the company as 
computed in accordance with the provisions of section 349 of 
the Companies Act, <year>1956</year>, (1 of <year>1956</year>) subject to the 
modification that-

<subsection><tid>849963</tid>
<number>i</number>any income- tax payable under the Income- tax Act, 
<year>1961</year>, (43 of <year>1961</year>) in respect of the profits as so 
computed or any tax of a similar character payable in 
respect of such profits under any law in force in any 
country outside India, and surtax payable in respect of 
such profits under the Companies (Profits) Surtax Act, 
<year>1964</year>, (7 of <year>1964</year>) shall also be deducted; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>29440</tid>
<number>ii</number>depreciation shall be provided in accordance with 
the provisions of section 205 of the Companies Act, 
<year>1956</year>; (1 of <year>1956</year>)

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1702557</tid>
<number>f</number>" previous year" and" total income" have the meanings res- 
pectively assigned to them in the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year>. (43  
  of <year>1961</year>)



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1142465</tid>
<number> 3</number> Companies to which the Act applies. This Act shall apply to the 
following categorie' s of companies, namely:-
<section><tid>431142</tid>
<number>a</number>a company in which the public are substantially 
interested, as defined in clause (18) of section 2 of the 
Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year>; (43 of <year>1961</year>)

</section>

<section><tid>1370009</tid>
<number>b</number>a company, at least seventy- five per cent. of the share 
capital of which is, throughout the financial year for which 
any dividend is declared or paid, beneficially held by an 
institution or fund established in India for a charitable 
purpose, the income from dividend whereof is exempt from 
income- tax tinder section 11 of the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year>; (43  
  of <year>1961</year>)

</section>

<section><tid>269376</tid>
<number>c</number>an Indian company whose business consists mainly in the 
construction of ships or in the manufacture or processing of 
goods or in mining or in the generation or distribution of 
electricity or any other form of power;

</section>

<section><tid>270869</tid>
<number>d</number>an Indian company, the value of whose capital assets, 
being machinery or plant (other than office appliances or  
  road transport vehicles), as shown in its books on the last 
day of the financial year for which any dividend is declared 
or paid, is fifty lakhs of rupees or more;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>489</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1072030</tid>
<number>e</number>a company which has been exempted under sub- section (3) 
of section 104 of the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year>, (43 of <year>1961</year>) from 
the operation, of that section.
Explanation I.- For the purpose of clause (c), the business of a 
company shall be deemed to consist mainly in the construction of ships 
or in the manufacture or processing of goods or in mining or in the, 
generation or distribution of electricity or any other form of power, 
if the income attributable to any of the aforesaid activities included 
in its gross total income for the relevant financial year is not less 
than fifty- one per cent. of such total income.

Explanation II.- For the purposes of clauses (c) and (d)," Indian 
company" has the meaning assigned to it in clause (26) of section 2 of 
the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year>, (43 of <year>1961</year>.) but shall not include a 
corporation established by or under a Central, State or Provincial 
Act.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1808230</tid>
<number> 4</number> Restriction on declaration of dividends by companies to which 
the Act applies.
<section><tid>1780725</tid>
<number>1</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Save as otherwise provided in section 5A, for a  
period of two years] from the appointed day, no company to which this 
Act applies shall declare or pay dividends for any financial year 
except out of the profits of the company for that financial year and 
no such dividend shall exceed, in the aggregate, the distributable 
profits of the company for that financial year:
Provided that nothing in this sub- section shall apply to any 
dividend which was declared and paid, before the appointed day, to a 
section of the shareholders of a company but was not paid, before the 
appointed day, to another section of the shareholders of that 
company.


</section>

<section><tid>1219439</tid>
<number>2</number>In computing the aggregate amount which may be declared or 
paid by a company to which this Act applies as dividends in 
accordance with the provisions of this Act, for any financial year, 
any amount paid or promised or partly paid and partly promised by the 
company before the appointed day by way of interim dividends for that 
financial year shall be taken into account; but where the amount of 
the interim dividend paid by the company before the appointed day 
exceeds its distributable profits for the financial year for which the 
interim dividend was paid, no further dividend shall be declared or 
paid by the company. for that financial year.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1595509</tid>
<number> 5</number> Dividend in excess of distributable profits to be void and to 
be recovered. <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Save as otherwise provided in section 5A, for a period 
of two years] from the appointed day, any dividend declared. or paid 
after the appointed day by a company to which this Act applies,, in 
excess of its distributable profits for a financial year shall, to the 
extent of such excess, be void, and any amount paid by the company to 
any- shareholder in excess of its distributable profits for that year 
shall be recovered by the company and no such recovery shall be waived 
by the company:
Provided that where any such recovery is not practicable, the 
amount of dividend to the extent of such excess shall be adjusted 
against the dividend payable for the financial year next following the 
financial year for which such excess payment of dividend was made.

<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> 5A Restriction under which dividends in excess of 
distributable profits may be declared. (1) On and from the 
commencement of the Companies (Temporary Restrictions on Dividends) 
Amendment Act, <year>1975</year> and subject to the provisions of sub- section (2), 
it shall be lawful for a company to which this Act applies to declare, 
out of- its profits for any financial year, dividend exceeding, in the 
aggregate, its distributable profits for that financial year.

<section><tid>556462</tid>
<number>2</number>Where, after the commencement of the Companies (Temporary  
  Restrictions on Dividends) Amendment Act, <year>1975</year>, a company to which 
this Act applies declares dividend for any financial year exceeding, 
in the aggregate, its distributable profits for that financial year, 
such company shall not, for a period of two years from the appointed 
day, make payment of so much of such dividend as exceeds its 
distributable profits for that financial year and, on the expiry of 
the said period, so much of the dividend as is in excess of the dis- 
tributable profits of the company for- the financial year aforesaid 
 (the amount in excess as aforesaid being hereinafter, referred to as  
  the" deferred dividend"), shall be payable, together with interest due 
thereon at the rate of eight per cent. per annum, in two equal annual 
instalments, the first of which shall become due and payable on the 
date on which the said period of two years expires.

</section>

<section><tid>217034</tid>
<number>3</number>The provisions of sections 4 and 5 shall, except to the 
extent they are inconsistent with the provisions of this section, 
apply to a dividend declared under this section.

</section>

<section><tid>1505146</tid>
<number>4</number>No dividend shall be declared under sub- section (1) except 
after complying with the provisions of sub- section (2A) of section 205 
of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>191514</tid>
<number>5</number>The provisions, of section. 205A of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year>, 
shall not apply to any instalment of deferred dividend-
Provided that if the Whole or any part of an instalment of de- 
ferred dividend remains unpaid after the expiry of a period of thirty 
days from the date on which such instalment becomes due and payable, 
the provisions of the said section 205A shall apply to the amount so 
remaining unpaid.


</section>

<section><tid>1757061</tid>
<number>6</number>Where, after the commencement of the Companies (Temporary  
  Restrictions on Dividends) Amendment Act, <year>1975</year>, a company to which, 
this Act applies declares dividend for any financial. year exceeding 
in the aggregate, its distributable profits for that financial year, 
the provisions of the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year>, shall subject to the 
provisions of sub- section (10), apply in relation to the whole of the 
dividend so declared, as they apply in relation to dividend which is 
declared but payment of no part of which is deferred.

</section>

<section><tid>233008</tid>
<number>7</number>Where, after the commencement of the Companies (Temporary  
  Restrictions on Dividends) Amendment Act, <year>1975</year>, a company to which 
this Act applies declares dividend for a financial year exceeding, in 
the aggregate, its distributable profits for that financial year, the 
company shall post, within forty- two days from the date of such 
declaration, to every shareholder entitled to the payment of the 
dividend, a warrant authorising the payment of the dividend so de- 
clared, but the said warrant shall be so prepared as to authorise-

<subsection><tid>350346</tid>
<number>a</number>immediate payment of so much of the dividend as does 
not exceed the distributable profits of the company for the 
financial year aforesaid (hereinafter referred to as the  
 " immediate dividend"), and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>245063</tid>
<number>b</number>the payment of the deferred dividend on the respective 
dates on which each instalment of the deferred dividend 
becomes due and payable.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1049488</tid>
<number>8</number>Income- tax deducted under sub- section (6) from dividends 
shall be so apportioned between the immediate dividend and each in- 
stalment of the deferred dividend as to ensure that the income- tax 
deducted from the immediate dividend and each instalment of tile 
deferred dividend bears the same proportion to the gross amount of the 
immediate dividend and the gross amount of each instalment of the 
deferred dividend as the total amount of the income- tax so, deducted 
bears to the gross' amount of the total dividend declared by the 
company.

</section>

<section><tid>585502</tid>
<number>9</number>Every warrant issued tinder sub- section (7) shall be in such 
form and contain such particulars as may be specified by rules made 
under this Act,

</section>

<section><tid>942498</tid>
<number>10</number>Notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in the 
Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year>, the Income- tax Officer shall not, for the 
purposes of that Act, treat an assessee to whom any instalment of 
deferred dividend is payable as in default in respect of that part of 
income- tax which is due in respect of such instalment of deferred 
dividend, as reduced by the income- tax, if any, deducted at source 
from such instalment, and shall continue to treat the assessee as not 
in default in respect of the said part of the income- tax, as so 
reduced, until the expiry of thirty- five days from the date on which 
such instalment becomes due and payable to the assessee or the warrant 
in respect of such instalment is transferred by the assessee to any 
person, whichever is earlier, and no interest shall be chargeable 
under sub- section (2) of section 220 of that Act in respect of the 
said part of the income- tax, as so reduced, for the period during 
which the assessee is treated as not in default.
Explanation.- In this sub- section," assessee" has the meaning 
assigned to it in clause, (7) of section 2 of the Income- tax Act, 
<year>1961</year>,]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>260158</tid>
<number>6</number>Restriction on interim dividends. For a period of two years 
from the appointed day, no company to which this Act applies shall, 
except with the previous approval of the Central Government and 
subject to such conditions and limitations as may be specified by that 
Government, pay or distribute any Interim dividends for any financial 
year, whether ending before or after the pointed day,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>490</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 28 of <year>1975</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 3- <year>1975</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by S. 3, ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by s. 4, ibid.



</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>29</number>Law- 63.






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1512553</tid>
<number> 7</number> Restrictions on other distribution. For a period of two 
years from the appointed day, no company to which this Act applies 
shall, except with the previous approval of the Central Government, by 
general or special order,-
<section><tid>928586</tid>
<number>a</number>make any distribution out of its assets;

</section>

<section><tid>703690</tid>
<number>b</number>assume, whether conditionally or otherwise, any 
obligation to make distribution out of its assets;

</section>

<section><tid>1036217</tid>
<number>c</number>grant any lo- an to any shareholder of the company:
Provided that nothing in clause (c) shall apply to a company 
which is declared by the Central Government under sub- section 
 (1) of section 620A of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year>, (1 of <year>1956</year>) 
to be a Nidhi or Mutual Benefit Society.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>429683</tid>
<number>8</number>Act to have overriding effect. The pro- visions of this Act 
shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith 
contained in the Companies Act, <year>1956</year>, (1 of <year>1956</year>) or in any other 
enactment (other than this Act) or in any contract or instrument 
having effect by virtue of any enactment other than this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1463462</tid>
<number> 9</number> Penalties.
<section><tid>1217352</tid>
<number>1</number>Whoever contravenes any provision of this  
Act, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to three years, or with fine which may extend to twice the amount in 
relation to which such contravention has been made, or with both.

</section>

<section><tid>228083</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of section 621 of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year>, 
shall apply to the offences against this Act as they apply to the 
offences against the Companies Act, <year>1956</year>. (1 of <year>1956</year>.)



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>692198</tid>
<number> 10</number> Offences.
<section><tid>1788517</tid>
<number>1</number>Where an offence against this Act has been  
committed, every person who at the time the offence was committed was 
in charge of, and was responsible to, the company committing the 
offence for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as the 
company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be 
liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the 
offence was committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised 
all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.


</section>

<section><tid>1278737</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where 
any offence against this Act has been committed by a company and it is 
proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or con- 
nivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any 
director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company,, such 
director,- manager, secretary or other officer shall be deemed to be 
guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and 
punished accordingly.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1689705</tid>
<number> 11</number> Power to delegate. The Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, direct that any power which may 
be exercised by it under this Act (other than the power conferred by  
  section 12) shall, subject to such restrictions and conditions, if 
any, as it may specify in the notification, be exercised also by-
<section><tid>1471347</tid>
<number>a</number>such officer or authority subordinate to the Central 
Government; or

</section>

<section><tid>98193</tid>
<number>b</number>such other authority,
as may be specified in the notification.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>321902</tid>
<number> 12</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>862592</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the 
provisions of this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>491</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1530311</tid>
<number>2</number>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act 
shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House 
of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty 
days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of. the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything pre- 
viously done under that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>63052</tid>
<number>13</number>Act not to apply to companies in liquidation. Nothing in 
this Act shall apply to a company which is being wound up by the Court 
or voluntarily or subject to the supervision of the Court.


</article>



<article><tid>1403352</tid>
<number>14</number>Section 637 A of Act 1 of <year>1956</year>. to apply. Every approval 
referred to in this Act shall be obtained on an application made to 
the Central Government and the provisions of section 637A of the 
Companies Act, <year>1956</year>, shall apply to every such application as if such 
application were an application under the Companies Act, <year>1956</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>595971</tid>
<number>15</number>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in 
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, 
remove the difficulty.


</article>



<article><tid>897028</tid>
<number> 16</number> Repeal and saving.
<section><tid>1445556</tid>
<number>1</number>The Companies (Temporary Restrictions   
  on Dividends) Ordinance, <year>1974</year>, (1 of <year>1974</year>.) and the Companies 
 (Temporary Restrictions on Dividends) Amendment Ordinance, <year>1974</year>, (9  
  of <year>1974</year>.) are hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1095639</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action 
taken under the Companies (Temporary Restrictions on. Dividends) 
Ordinance, <year>1974</year>, (1 of <year>1974</year>.) as amended by the Companies (Temporary  
  Restrictions on Dividends) Amendment Ordinance, <year>1974</year> (9 of <year>1974</year>.) 
 (including any order or declaration made thereunder), shall be deemed 
to have been done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this 
Act.


</section>

</article>



 </act>