<act><tid>26312</tid>
<title>THE NORTH- EASTERN COUNCIL ACT, <year>1971</year></title>

ACT NO. 84 OF <year>1971</year>
[ 30th December, <year>1971</year>.]

An Act to provide for the setting up of a Council for the north- 
eastern areas of India to be called the North- Eastern Council 
and for matters connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- second Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--





<article><tid>917371</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1307909</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
North- Eastern Council Act, <year>1971</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1374715</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>, being a date not 
earlier than the day appointed under clause (b) of section 2 of the 
North- Eastern Areas (Reorganisation) Act, <year>1971</year>, as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>44922</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>323137</tid>
<number>a</number>" Council" means the North- Eastern Council set up under 
section 3;

</section>

<section><tid>1350012</tid>
<number>b</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>" north- eastern area" means the area comprising the 
States of Arunachal Pradesh, Assam, Manipur, Meghalaya, 
Mizoram, Nagaland and Tripura.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1659488</tid>
<number> 3</number> Setting up and composition of the North- Eastern Council.
<section><tid>750311</tid>
<number>1</number> 
There shall be a Council to be called the North- Eastern Council which 
shall consist of the following members, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1426453</tid>
<number>a</number>the person or persons for the time being holding the 
office of the Governor of the States or the office of 
Administrator of the Union territories in the north- 
eastern area;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1956794</tid>
<number>b</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the Chief Ministers of the States of Arunachal 
Pradesh, Assam, Manipur, Meghalaya, Mizoram, Nagaland 
and Tripura.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>1136</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1- 8- <year>1972</year>, vide Notifn. No. G. S. R. 359- (E), dated the 25th July, 
<year>1972</year>, Gazette of India, <year>1972</year>, Extraordinary, Pt. II, Sec. 3 (i), p. 
941. 
2. Subs. by Act 69 of <year>1986</year>, s. 45 (w. e. f. 20- 2- <year>1987</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>

Provided that if there is no Council of Ministers <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> in any State or 
Union territory referred to in clause (b)], the President may nominate 
not more than one person to represent such State or Union territory in 
the Council for so long as there is no Council of Ministers in such 
State or Union territory.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1807109</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), the 
President may, if he deems it necessary so to do, nominate a Union 
Minister to be a member of the Council.

</section>

<section><tid>1466457</tid>
<number>3</number>One of the members of the Council to be nominated by the 
President shall be the Chairman of the Council.

</section>

<section><tid>704182</tid>
<number>4</number>The President may, if he deems it necessary so to do, 
nominate another member of the Council to act as Vice- Chairman of the 
Council.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>872515</tid>
<number> 4</number> Functions of the Council.
<section><tid>1842462</tid>
<number>1</number>The Council shall be an advisory  
body and may discuss any matter in which some or all of the States 
represented in that Council, or the Union and one or more of the 
States represented in that Council, have a common interest and advise 
the Central Government and the Government of each State concerned as 
to the action to be taken on any such matter, and, in particular, may 
discuss and make recommendations with regard to,--

<subsection><tid>1289744</tid>
<number>i</number>any matter of common interest in the field of economic 
and social planning;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>409381</tid>
<number>ii</number>any matter concerning inter- State transport and 
communications;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>380041</tid>
<number>iii</number>any matter relating to power or flood control projects 
of common interest.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>373462</tid>
<number>2</number>For securing the balanced development of the north- eastern 
area, the Council shall forward proposals,--

<subsection><tid>54996</tid>
<number>a</number>formulating for the States represented in the Council a 
unified and co- ordinated regional plan (which will be  
in
<pagefootnote><pagenum>1136A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Clause (c) omitted by Act 29 of <year>1975</year>, s. 14 (w. e. f. 15- 8- <year>1975</year>). 
2. Subs. by s. 14, ibid., for certain words (w. e. f. 15- 8- <year>1975</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


  addition to the State Plan) in regard to matters of 
common importance to that area;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1988276</tid>
<number>b</number>regarding the priorities of the projects and schemes 
included in the regional plan and the stages in which 
the regional plan may be implemented; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>917368</tid>
<number>c</number>regarding the location of the projects and schemes 
included in the regional plan,
to the Central Government for its consideration.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>1137</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>271093</tid>
<number>3</number>The Council shall--

<subsection><tid>856554</tid>
<number>a</number>review, from time to time, the implementation of the 
projects and schemes included in the regional plan and 
recommend measures for effecting co- ordination among 
the Governments of the States concerned in the matter 
of implementation of such projects and schemes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>426957</tid>
<number>b</number>where a project or scheme is intended to benefit two or 
more States, recommend the manner in which,--

<subsubsection><tid>773375</tid>
<number>i</number>such project or scheme may be executed or 
implemented and managed or maintained; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1438902</tid>
<number>ii</number>the benefits therefrom may be shared; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>736699</tid>
<number>iii</number>the expenditure thereon may be incurred;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1514041</tid>
<number>c</number>on a review of progress of the expenditure, recommend to 
the Central Government the quantum of financial 
assistance to be given, from time to time, to the State 
or States entrusted with the execution or 
implementation of any project or scheme included in the 
regional plan;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>708259</tid>
<number>d</number>recommend to the Government of the State concerned or to 
the Central Government the undertaking of necessary 
surveys and investigation of projects in any State 
represented in the Council to facilitate consideration 
of the feasibility of including new projects in the 
regional plan.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1393318</tid>
<number>4</number>The Council shall review from time to time the measures taken 
by the States represented in the Council for the maintenance of 
security and public order therein and recommend to the Governments of 
the States concerned further measures necessary in this regard.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1244956</tid>
<number> 5</number> Meetings of the Council.
<section><tid>131562</tid>
<number>1</number>The Council shall meet at such  
times as the Chairman of the Council may appoint in this behalf and 
shall, subject to the other provisions of this section, observe such 
rules of procedure in regard to transaction of business at its 
meetings as it may lay down from time to time.

</section>

<section><tid>1332589</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chairman or in his absence the Vice- Chairman, if any, or 
in the absence of both the Chairman and the Vice- Chairman, any other 
member chosen by the members present from amongst themselves, shall 
preside at a meeting of the Council.

</section>

<section><tid>102441</tid>
<number>3</number>The proceedings of every meeting of the Council shall be 
forwarded to the Central Government and also to the Government of each 
State represented on the Council.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1138</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>333571</tid>
<number>6</number>Nomination of certain officers to attend the meetings of the 
Council. In order to assist the Council in the discharge of its 
functions, each of the Ministries of the Central Government dealing 
with matters relating to Defence, Finance, Home Affairs and Planning 
shall nominate an officer to attend the meetings of the Council.


</article>



<article><tid>316197</tid>
<number> 7</number> Officers and staff of the Council.
<section><tid>1444864</tid>
<number>1</number>The Council shall have  
a secretarial staff consisting of a Secretary, a Planning Adviser, a 
Financial Adviser and a Security Adviser and such other officers and 
employees as the Central Government may, by order, determine.

</section>

<section><tid>1174854</tid>
<number>2</number>The secretarial staff of the Council shall function under the 
direction, supervision and control of the Chairman of the Council.

</section>

<section><tid>1454981</tid>
<number>3</number>The office of the Council shall be located at such place as 
may be determined by the Council.

</section>

<section><tid>736554</tid>
<number>4</number>The administrative expenses of the said office, including the 
salaries and allowances payable to, or in respect of, members of the 
secretarial staff of the Council, shall be borne by the Central 
Government out of the moneys provided by Parliament for the purpose.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1693058</tid>
<number>8</number>Repeal. The North- Eastern Council Act, <year>1970</year> (26 of <year>1970</year>) is 
hereby repealed.

</article>



 </act>