<act> 
 
The Chandigarh 
Disturbed  
Areas Act, 1983 

  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title, extent 
and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
This Act may be called the Chandigarh Disturbed Areas Act, 1983.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends to the 
whole of the Union territory of Chandigarh.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall be deemed to 
have come into force on the 7th day of October, 1983.
</section></article> 
 
The Chandigarh 
Disturbed  
Areas Act, 1983 

  
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
this Act,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  “Administrator” means the 
Administrator of the Union territory of Chandigarh 
appointed under Article 239 of the Constitution;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  “disturbed area” means the area 
which is for the time being declared by notification under section 3 to be a 
disturbed area. 
</section></article> 
 
The Chandigarh 
Disturbed  
Areas Act, 1983 

  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Powers to declare 
areas to be disturbed areas.—The 
Administrator may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare that the 
whole or any part of the Union territory 
of Chandigarh 
as may be specified in the notification, is a disturbed area.
</article> 
 
The Chandigarh 
Disturbed  
Areas Act, 1983 

  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Power to fire upon 
persons contravening certain orders.—Any 
Magistrate or Police Officer not below the rank of Sub-Inspector or Havildar in 
case of the Armed Branch of the Police may, if he is of opinion that it is 
necessary so to do for the maintenance of public order, after giving such due 
warning, as he may consider necessary, fire upon, or otherwise use force, even 
to the causing of death, against any person who is acting in contravention of 
any law or order for the time being in force in the disturbed area, prohibiting 
the assembly of five or more persons or the carrying of weapons or of things 
capable of being used as weapons or of fire-arms, ammunition or explosive 
substances.


</article> 
 
The Chandigarh 
Disturbed  
Areas Act, 1983 

  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Powers to destroy arms 
dump, fortified positions, etc.—Any 
Magistrate or Police Officer not below the rank of a Sub-Inspector may, if he 
is of opinion that it is necessary so to do, destroy any arms dump, prepared or 
fortified position or shelter from which armed attacks are made or are likely 
to be made or are attempted to be made or any structure used as training camp 
for armed volunteers or utilised as a hide-out by armed gangs or absconders 
wanted for any offence.


</article> 
 The Chandigarh Disturbed  Areas Act, 
1983 
  
 <article><number>6</number> Protection of persons acting 
under sections 4 and 5.—No suit, prosecution or other 
legal proceedings shall be instituted except with the previous sanction of 
1[the Central Government] against 
any person in respect of anything done or purporting to be done in exercise of 
the powers conferred by sections 4 and 5.
  


</article> 
 
The Chandigarh 
Disturbed  
Areas Act, 1983 

  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Repeal and saving.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chandigarh Disturbed Areas Ordinance, 1983 (6 of 1983), is hereby repealed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding such 
repeal, anything done or any action taken under the said Ordinance shall be 
deemed to have been done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this 
Act.
 
 

</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>