<act><title>


The Citizenship Act, 1955</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title.—This 
    Act may be called the Citizenship Act, 1955. 
 
 
 
 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Interpretation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “a Government in India” means the 
    Central Government or a State Government; 
 

1[(b)    
    “illegal migrant” means a foreigner who has entered into India—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    without a valid passport or other 
    travel documents and such other document or authority as may be prescribed 
    by or under any law in that behalf; or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    with a valid passport or other 
    travel documents and such other document or authority as may be prescribed 
    by or under any law in that behalf but remains therein beyond the permitted 
    period of time;]  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    “Indian consulate” means the 
    office of any consular officer of the Government of India where a register 
    of births is kept, or where there is no such office, such office as may be 
    prescribed;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    “minor” means a person who has 
    not attained the age of eighteen years:  
 

2[(ee)    
    “overseas citizen of India” means a person registered as an overseas citizen 
    of India by the Central Government under section 7A;]  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    “person” does not include any 
    company or association or body of individuals, whether incorporated or not;
    
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    “prescribed” means prescribed by 
    rules made under this Act;  
 

3[***]  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    “undivided India” means India as 
    defined in the Government of India Act, 1935, as originally enacted. 
 
 
 
Statement of Objects 
      and Reasons 
      [The Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 2005]
 
To expand the scope of 
      grant of Overseas Citizenship of India to Persons of Indian Origin of all 
      countries except Pakistan and Bangladesh.  

 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> For 
    the purposes of this Act, a person born aboard a regis­tered ship or 
    aircraft, or aboard an unregistered ship or air­craft of the Government of 
    any country, shall be deemed to have been born in the place in which the 
    ship or aircraft was regis­tered or, as the case may be, in that country.
    
 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any 
    reference in this Act to the status or description of the father of a person 
    at the time of that person’s birth shall, in relation to a person born after 
    the death of his father, be construed as a reference to the status or 
    description of the father at the time of the father’s death; and where that 
    death occurred before, and the birth occurs after, the commencement of this 
    Act, the status or description which would have been appli­cable to the 
    father had he died after the commencement of this Act shall be deemed to be 
    the status or description applicable to him at the time of his death.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> For 
    the purposes of this Act, a person shall be deemed to be of full age if he 
    is not a minor and of full capacity if he is not of unsound mind.  
 













 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>


    1[<number>3</number> Citizenship by 
    birth.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Except as provided in sub-section (2), every person born in India,— 

 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    on or after the 26th day of 
    January, 1950, but before the 1st day of July, 1987;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    on or after the 1st day of July, 
    1987, but before the commencement of the Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 2003 
    and either of whose parents is a citizen of India at the time of his birth;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    on or after the commencement of 
    the Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 2003, where—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    both of his parents are citizens 
    of India; or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    one of whose parents is a 
    citizen of India and the other is not an illegal migrant at the time of his 
    birth,  
 
shall be a citizen of India by birth.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    person shall not be a citizen of India by virtue of this sec­tion if at the 
    time of his birth—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    either his father or mother 
    possesses such immunity from suits and legal process as is accorded to an 
    envoy of a foreign sovereign power accredited to the President of India and 
    he or she, as the case may be, is not a citizen of India; or 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    his father or mother is an enemy 
    alien and the birth occurs in a place then under occupation by the enemy.]  
 
 




 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Citizenship by descent.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    A person born outside India shall be a citizen of India by descent,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    on or after the 26th day of 
    January, 1950, but before the 10th day of December, 1992, if his father is a 
    citizen of India at the time of his birth; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    on or after the 10th day of 
    December, 1992, if either of his parents is a citizen of India at the time 
    of his birth:  
 
Provided 
    that if the father of a person referred to in clause (a) was a citizen of 
    India by descent only, that person shall not be a citizen of India by virtue 
    of this section un­less—  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>a</number>    his birth is registered at an 
    Indian consulate within one year of its occurrence or the commencement of 
    this Act, whichever is later, or, with the permission of the Central 
    Government, after the expiry of the said period; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    his father is, at the time of his 
    birth, in service under a Government in India:  
 
Provided 
    further that if either of the parents of a person referred to in clause (b) 
    was a citizen of India by descent only, that person shall not be a citizen 
    of India by virtue of this section un­less—  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>a</number>    his birth is registered at an 
    Indian consulate within one year of its occurrence or on or after the 10th 
    day of December, 1992, whichever is later, or, with the permission of the 
    Central Government, after the expiry of the said period; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    either of his parents is, at the 
    time of his birth, in service under a Government in India:  
 
Provided 
    also that on or after the commencement of the Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 
    2003, a person shall not be a citizen of India by virtue of this section, 
    unless his birth is registered at an Indian consulate in such form and in 
    such manner, as may be prescribed,—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    within one year of its occurrence 
    or the commencement of the Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 2003, whichever is 
    later; or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    with the permission of the 
    Central Government, after the expiry of the said period:  
 
Provided 
    also that no such birth shall be registered unless the parents of such 
    person declare, in such form and in such manner as may be prescribed, that 
    the minor does not hold the passport of another country.  
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>1A</number> A 
    minor who is a citizen of India by virtue of his section and is also a 
    citizen of any other country shall cease to be a citizen of India if he does 
    not renounce the citizenship or nationality of another country within six 
    months of attaining full age.]  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    the Central Government so directs, a birth shall be deemed for the purposes 
    of this section to have been registered with its permission, notwithstanding 
    that its permission was not obtained before the registration.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> For 
    the purposes of the proviso to sub-section (1), any 

    2[person] born outside 
    undivided India 
    who was, or was deemed to be, a citizen of India at the commencement of the 
    Constitution shall be deemed to be a citizen of India by descent only.  
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Citizenship by registration.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of this section and such other conditions and 
    restrictions as may be prescribed, the Central Government may, on an 
    application made in this behalf, register as a citizen of India any person 
    not being an illegal migrant who is not already such citizen by virtue of 
    the Constitution or of any other provision of this Act if he belongs to any 
    of the following categories, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    a person of Indian origin who are 
    ordinarily resident in India for seven years before making an application 
    for registration; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    a person of Indian origin who is 
    ordinarily resident in any country or place outside undivided India; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    a person who is married to a 
    citizen of India and is ordinarily resident in India for seven years before 
    making an application for registration; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    minor children of persons who are 
    citizens of India; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    a person of full age and capacity 
    whose parents are registered as citizens of India under clause (a) of this 
    sub-section or sub-section (1) of section 6;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    a person of full age and capacity 
    who, or either of his parents, was earlier citizen of independent India, and 
    has been residing in India for one year immediately before making an 
    application for registration;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    a person of full age and capacity 
    who has been registered as an overseas citizen of India for five years, and 
    who has been residing in India for 
2[one 
    year] before making an application for registration. 3[one 
    year] before making an application for registration." 
 
 
Statement of Objects 
      and Reasons 
      [The Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 2005]
 
To reduce the period of 
      residence in India from two years to one year for the persons registered 
      as Overseas Citizens of India to acquire Indian citizenship.  

 

    Explanation 1.—For 
    the purposes of clauses (a) and (c), an applicant shall be deemed to be 
    ordinarily resident in India if—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    he has resided in India 
    throughout the period of twelve months immediately before making an 
    application for registration; and  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    he has resided in India during 
    the eight years immediately preceding the said period of twelve months for a 
    period of not less than six years.  
 

    Explanation 2.—For 
    the purposes of this sub-section, a person shall be deemed to be of Indian 
    origin if he, or either of his parents, was born in undivided India or in 
    such other territory which became part of India after the 15th day of 
    August, 1947.]  
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> No 
    person being of full age shall be registered as a citizen of India under 
    sub-section (1) until he has taken the oath of allegiance in the form 
    specified in the Second Schedule. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No 
    person who has renounced, or has been deprived of, his Indian citizenship or 
    whose Indian citizenship has terminated, under this Act shall be registered 
    as a citizen of India under sub-section (1) except by order of the Central 
    Government. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Central Government may, if satisfied that there are special circumstances 
    justifying such registration, cause any minor to be registered as a citizen 
    of India. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> A 
    person registered under this section shall be a citizen of India by 
    registration as from the date on which he is so regis­tered; and a person 
    registered under the provisions of clause(b)(ii) of article 6 or article 8 
    of the Constitution shall be deemed to be a citizen of India by registration 
    as from the commencement of the Constitution or the date on which he was so 
    registered, whichever may be later.  
 


    3[(6) If the Central 
    Government is satisfied that circumstances exist which render it necessary 
    to grant exemption from the residential requirement under clause (c) of 
    sub-section (1) to any person or a class of persons, it may, for reasons to 
    be recorded in writing, grant such exemption.]  
 
 

 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Citizenship by naturalisation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where an application is made in the prescribed manner by any person of full 
    age and capacity 

    1[not being an illegal 
    migrant] for the grant of a certificate of naturalisation to him, the 
    Central Government may, if satisfied that the applicant is quali­fied for 
    naturalisation under the provisions of the Third Sched­ule, grant to him a 
    certificate of naturalisation: 
 
Provided 
    that, if in the opinion of the Central Government, the applicant is a person 
    who has rendered distinguished service to the cause of science, philosophy, 
    art, literature, world peace or human progress generally, it may waive all 
    or any of the condi­tions specified in the Third Schedule.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The person 
    to whom a certificate of naturalisation is granted under sub-section (1) 
    shall, on taking the oath of allegiance in the form specified in the Second 
    Schedule, be a citizen of India by naturalisation as from the date on which 
    that certificate is granted. 
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>


    1[<number>6A</number> Special 
    provisions as to citizenship of persons covered by the Assam Accord.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    For the purposes of this section—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “Assam” means the territories 
    included in the State of Assam immediately before the commencement of the 
    Citizenship (Amend­ment) Act, 1985;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    “detected to be a foreigner” 
    means detected to be a foreigner in accordance with the provisions of the 
    Foreigners Act, 1946 (31 of 1946) and the Foreigners (Tribunals) Order, 1964 
    by a Trib­unal constituted under the said Order;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    “specified territory” means the 
    territories included in Bangladesh immediately before the commencement of 
    the Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 1985;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    a person shall be deemed to be of 
    Indian origin, if he, or either of his parents for any of his grandparents 
    was born in undivided India;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    a person shall be deemed to have 
    been detected to be a for­eigner on the date on which a Tribunal constituted 
    under the Foreigners (Tribunals) Order, 1964 submits its opinion to the 
    effect that he is a foreigner to the officer or authority con­cerned. 
 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of sub-sections (6) and (7), all persons of Indian 
    origin who came before the 1st day of January, 1966 to Assam from the 
    specified territory (including such of those whose names were included in 
    the electoral rolls used for the purposes of the General Election to the 
    House of the People held in 1967) and who have been ordinarily resident in 
    Assam since the dates of their entry into Assam shall be deemed to be 
    citizens of India as from the 1st day of January, 1966. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of sub-sections (6) and (7), every person of 
    Indian origin who—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    came to Assam on or after the lst 
    day of January, 1966 but before the 25th day of March, 1971 from the 
    specified territory; and 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    has, since the date of his entry 
    into Assam, been ordinarily resident in Assam; and 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    has been detected to be a 
    foreigner, 
 
 
shall register himself in accordance with the 
    rules made by the Central Government in this behalf under section 18 with 
    such authority (thereafter in this sub-section referred to as the 
    registering authority) as may be specified in such rules and if his name is 
    included in any electoral roll for any Assembly or Parliamentary 
    constituency in force on the date of such detec­tion, his name shall be 
    deleted therefrom. 
 

    Explanation.—In 
    the case of every person seeking registration under this sub-section, the 
    opinion of the Tribunal constituted under the Foreigners (Tribunals) Order, 
    1964 holding such person to be a foreigner, shall be deemed to be sufficient 
    proof of the requirement under clause (c) of this sub-section and if any 
    question arises as to whether such person complies with any other 
    requirement under this sub-section, the registering authority shall,—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    if such opinion contains a 
    finding with respect to such other requirement, decide the question in 
    conformity with such finding;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    if such opinion does not contain 
    a finding with respect to such other requirement, refer the question to a 
    Tribunal consti­tuted under the said Order hang jurisdiction in accordance 
    with such rules as the Central Government may make in this behalf under 
    section 18 and decide the question in conformity with the opinion received 
    on such reference. 
 
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> A 
    person registered under sub-section (3) shall have, as from the date on 
    which he has been detected to be a foreigner and till the expiry of a period 
    of ten years from that date, the same rights and obligations as a citizen of 
    India (including the right to obtain a passport under the Passports Act, 
    1967 (15 of 1967) and the obligations connected therewith), but shall not be 
    enti­tled to have his name included in any electoral roll for any Assembly 
    or Parliamentary constituency at any time before the expiry of the said 
    period of ten years. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> A 
    person registered under sub-section (3) shall be deemed to be a citizen of 
    India for all purposes as from the date of expiry of a period of ten years 
    from the date on which he has been detected to be a foreigner. 

 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> 
    Without prejudice to the provisions of section 8,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    if any person referred to in 
    sub-section (2) submits in the prescribed manner and form and to the 
    prescribed authority within sixty days from the date of commencement of the 
    Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 1985, for year a declaration that he does not 
    wish to be a citizen of India, such person shall not be deemed to have 
    become a citizen of India under that sub-section; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    If any person referred to in 
    sub-section (3) submits in the prescribed manner and form and to the 
    prescribed authority within sixty days from the date of commencement the 
    Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 1985, for year or from the date on which he has 
    been detect­ed to be a foreigner, whichever is later, a declaration that he 
    does not wish to be governed by the provisions of that sub-sec­tion and 
    sub-sections (4) and (5), it shall not be necessary for such person to 
    register himself under sub-section (3). 
 
 

    Explanation.—Where 
    a person required to file a declaration under this sub-section does not have 
    the capacity to enter into a contract, such declaration may be filed on his 
    behalf by any person competent under the law for the time being in force to 
    act on his behalf.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>7</number> 
    Nothing in sub-sections (2) to (6) shall apply in relation to any person—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    who, immediately before the 
    commencement of the Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 1985, for year is a citizen 
    of India; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    who was expelled from India 
    before the commencement of the Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 1985, for year 
    under the Foreigners Act, 1946 (31 of 1946). 
 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>8</number> Save 
    as otherwise expressly provided in this section, the provisions of this 
    section shall have effect notwithstanding anything contained in any other 
    law for the time being in force.] 
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Citizenship by incorporation of territory.—If 
    any territory becomes a part of India, the Central Government may, by order 
    notified in the Official Gazette, specify the persons who shall be citizens 
    of India by reason of their connection with that territory; and those 
    persons shall be citizens of India as from the date to be specified in the 
    order.  
  
 
  


</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>7A</number> Registration of overseas citizens of India. 
</title>—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government may, subject to such conditions and 
restrictions as may be prescribed, on an application made in this behalf, 
register any person as an overseas citizen of India— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> any person of full age and capacity,— 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> who is citizen of another country, but was a citizen of India at the 
    time of, or at any time after, the commencement of the Constitution; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> who is citizen of another country, but was eligible to become a 
    citizen of India at the time of the commencement of the Constitution; or 

 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number> who is citizen of another country, but belonged to a territory that 
    became part of India after the 15th day of August, 1947; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iv</number> who is a child or a grand-child of such a citizen; or 
</subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> a person, who is a minor child of a person mentioned in clause (a): 
</subsection>
 Provided that no person, who is or had been a citizen of Pakistan, Bangladesh 
or such other country as the Central Government may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, specify, shall be eligible for registration as an overseas 
citizen of India.] 


 
 <subsection><number>a</number> grant of multiple entry lifelong visa for visiting India for any 
  purpose; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> exemption from registration with Foreign Regional Registration Officer 
  or Foreign Registration Officer for any length of stay in India ; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> parity with Non-Resident Indians in respect of all facilities available 
  to them in economic, financial and educational fields except in matters 
  relating to the acquisition of agricultural or plantation properties. 
</subsection>





 
 <subsection><number>a</number> parity with non-resident Indian in respect of,— 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> entry fees to be charged for visiting the national monuments, 
    historical sites and museums in India ; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> pursuing the following professions in India , in pursuance of the 
    provisions contained in the relevant Acts, namely:— 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>i</number> doctors, dentists, nurses and pharmacists; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> advocates; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number> architects; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iv</number> chartered accountants; </subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> to appear for the All India Pre-Medical Test or such other tests to 
  make them eligible for admission in pursuance of the provisions contained in 
  the relevant Acts. </subsection>













</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>


    1[<number>7B</number> Conferment of 
    rights on overseas citizens of India.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwith-standing anything 
    contained in any other law for the time being in force, an overseas citizen 
    of India shall be entitled to such rights [other than the rights specified 
    under sub-section (2)] as the Central Government may, by notification in the 
    Official Gazette, specify in this behalf.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An 
    overseas citizen of India shall not be entitled to the rights conferred on a 
    citizen of India—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    under article 16 of the 
    Constitution with regard to equality of opportunity in matters of public 
    employment;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    under article 58 of the 
    Constitution for election as President:  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    under article 66 of the 
    Constitution for election of Vice-President;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    under article 124 of the 
    Constitution for appointment as a Judge of the Supreme Court;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    under article 217 of the 
    Constitution for appointment as a Judge of the High Court;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    under section 16 of the 
    Representation of the People Act, 1950 (43 of 1950) in regard to 
    registration as a voter;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    under sections 3 and 4 of the 
    Representation of the People Act, 1951 (43 of 1951) with regard to the 
    eligibility for being a member of the House of the People or of the Council 
    of States, as the case may be;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    under sections 5, 5A and 6 of the 
    Representation of the People Act, 1951 (43 of 1951) with regard to the 
    eligibility for being a member of the Legislative Assembly or a Legislative 
    Council, as the case may be, of a State;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    for appointment to public 
    services and posts in connection with the affairs of the Union or of any 
    State except for appointment in such services and posts as the Central 
    Government may by special order in that behalf specify.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Every notification issued under sub-section (1) shall be laid before each 
    House of Parliament.]  
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>


    1[<number>7C</number> Renunciation 
    of overseas citizenship.—
<section><number>1</number> If any overseas citizen of India of full 
    age and capacity makes in the prescribed manner a declaration renouncing his 
    overseas citizenship of India, the declaration shall be registered by the 
    Central Government, and; upon such registration, that person shall cease to 
    be an overseas citizen of India.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where a person ceases to be an overseas citizen of India under sub-section 
    (1), every minor child of that person registered as an overseas citizen of 
    India, shall thereupon cease to be an overseas citizen of India.]  
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>


    1[<number>7D</number> Cancellation 
    of registration as overseas citizen of India.—The Central Government 
    may, by order, cancel the registration granted under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of 
    section 7A if it is satisfied that—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the registration as an overseas 
    citizen of India was obtained by means of fraud, false representation or the 
    concealment of any material fact; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the overseas citizen of India has 
    shown disaffection towards the Constitution of India as by law established; 
    or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the overseas citizen of India 
    has, during any war in which India may be engaged, unlawfully traded or 
    communicated with an enemy or been engaged in, or associated with, any 
    business or commercial activity that was to his knowledge carried on in such 
    manner as to assist an enemy in that war; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the overseas citizen of India 
    has, within five years after registration under sub-section (1) of section 
    7A has been sentenced to imprisonment for a term of not less than two years; 
    or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    it is necessary so to do in the 
    interest of the sovereignty and integrity of India, the security of India, 
    friendly relations of India with any foreign country, or in the interests of 
    the general public.]
 
 
 
 





 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Renunciation of citizenship.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If any citizen of India of full age and capacity, 

    1[***] makes in the 
    prescribed manner a declaration renouncing his Indian Citizenship, the 
    declaration shall be registered by the prescribed authority; and, upon such 
    registra­tion, that person shall cease to be a citizen of India:  
 
Provided 
    that if any such declaration is made during any war in which India may be 
    engaged, registration thereof shall be with­held until the Central 
    Government otherwise directs. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where 

    2[a person] ceases to 
    be a citizen of India under sub-section (1) every minor child of that person 
    shall thereupon cease to be a citizen of India: 
 
 
Provided 
    that any such child may, within one year after attaining full age, make a 
    declaration 

    3[in the prescribed 
    form and manner] that he wishes to resume Indian citizenship and shall 
    thereupon again become a citizen of India. 
 
 


    4[***]
 








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Termination of citizenship.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any citizen of India who by naturalisation, registration otherwise 
    voluntarily acquires, or has at any time between the 26th January, 1950 and 
    the commence­ment of this Act, voluntarily acquired the citizenship of 
    another country shall, upon such acquisition or, as the case may be, such 
    commencement, cease to be a citizen of India: 
 
 
Provided 
    that nothing in this sub-section shall apply to a citi­zen of India who, 
    during any war in which India may be engaged, voluntarily acquires, the 
    citizenship of another country, until the Central Government otherwise 
    directs. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    any question arises as to whether, when or how any 

    1[citizen of India] 
    has acquired the citizenship of another country, it shall be deter­mined by 
    such authority, in such manner, and having regard to such rules of evidence, 
    as may be prescribed in this behalf. 
 
 
 

 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Deprivation of citizenship.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A citizen of India who is such by naturalisation or by virtue only of clause 
    (c) of article 5 of the Constitution or by registration otherwise than under 
    clause (b) (ii) of article 6 of the Constitution or clause 
<subsection><number>a</number> of 
    sub-section (1) of section 5 of this Act, shall cease to be a citizen of 
    India, if he is deprived of that citizenship by an order of the Central 
    Government under this section.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of this section, the Central Gov­ernment may, by 
    order, deprive any such citizen of Indian citi­zenship, if it is satisfied 
    that—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the registration or certificate 
    of naturalisation was ob­tained by means of fraud, false representation or 
    the concealment of any material fact; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    that citizen has shown himself by 
    act or speech to be dis­loyal or disaffected towards the Constitution of 
    India as by law established; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    that citizen has, during any war 
    in which India may be en­gaged unlawfully traded or communicated with an 
    enemy or been engaged in, or associated with, any business that was to his 
    knowledge carried on in such manner as to assist an enemy in that war; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    that citizen has, within five 
    years after registration or naturalisation, been sentenced in any country to 
    imprisonment for a term of not less than two years; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    that citizen has been ordinarily 
    resident out of India for a continuous period of seven years, and during 
    that period, has neither been at any time a student of any educational 
    institution in a country outside India or in the service of a Government in 
    India or of an international organisation of which India is a member, nor 
    registered annually in the prescribed manner at an Indian consulate his 
    intention to retain his citizenship of India.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Central Government shall not deprive a person of citizen­ship under this 
    section unless it is satisfied that it is not conducive to the public good 
    that the person should continue to be a citizen of India.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Before making an order under this section, the Central Gov­ernment shall 
    give the person against whom the order is proposed to be made notice in 
    writing informing him of the ground on which it is proposed to be made and, 
    if the order is proposed to be made on any of the grounds specified in 
    sub-section (2) other than clause (e) thereof, of his right, upon making 
    application therefor in the prescribed manner, to have his case referred to 
    a committee of inquiry under this section.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If 
    the order is proposed to be made against a person on any of the grounds 
    specified in sub-section (2) other than clause (e) thereof and that person 
    so applies in the prescribed manner, the Central Government shall, and in 
    any other case it may, refer the case to a Committee of Inquiry consisting 
    of a chairman (being a person who has for at least ten years held a judicial 
    office) and two other members appointed by the Central Government in this 
    behalf.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    Committee of Inquiry shall, on such reference, hold the inquiry in such 
    manner as may be prescribed and submit its report to the Central Government; 
    and the Central Government shall ordinarily be guided by such report in 
    making an order under this section.  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Commonwealth citizenship.—[Rep. 
    by the Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 2003 (6 of 2004), sec. 10.]  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Power to confer rights of Indian citizen or citizens of certain countries.—[Rep. 
    by the Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 2003 (6 of 2004), sec. 10.]  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Certificate of Citizenship in case of doubt.—The 
    Central Government may, in such cases as it thinks fit, certify that a 
    person, with respect to whose citizenship of India a doubt ex­ists, is a 
    citizen of India; and a certificate issued under this section shall, unless 
    it is proved that it was obtained by means of fraud, false representation or 
    concealment of any material fact, be conclusive evidence that person was 
    such a citizen on the date thereof, but without prejudice to any evidence 
    that he was such a citizen at an earlier date. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Disposal of application under 

    1[sections 5, 6 and 
    7A].—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The prescribed authority or the Central Government may, in its dis­cretion, 
    grant or refuse an application under 

    2[section 5, 6 or 
    section 7A] and shall not be required to assign any reasons for such grant 
    or refusal. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to 
    the provisions of section 15 the decision of the prescribed authority or the 
    Central Government on any such appli­cation as aforesaid shall be final and 
    shall not be called in question in any court.
  






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>


    1[<number>14A</number> Issue of 
    national identity cards.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may compulsorily register every citizen of India and 
    issue national identity card to him.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Central Government may maintain a National Register of Indian Citizens and 
    for that purpose establish a National Registration Authority.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On 
    and from the date of commencement of the Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 2003, 
    the Registrar General, India, appointed under sub-section (1) of section 3 
    of the Registration of Births and Deaths Act, 1969 (18 of 1969) shall act as 
    the National Registration Authority and he shall function as the Registrar 
    General of Citizen Registration.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Central Government may appoint such other officers and staff as may be 
    required to assist the Registrar General of Citizen Registration in 
    discharging his functions and responsibilities.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    procedure to be followed in compulsory registration of the citizens of India 
    shall be such as may be prescribed.]  
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Revision.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person aggrieved by an order made under this Act by the prescribed 
    authority or any officer or other authority (other than the Central 
    Government) may, within a period of thirty days from the date of the order, 
    make an appli­cation to the Central Government for revision of that order:
 
Provided 
    that the Central Government may entertain the applica­tion after the expiry 
    of the said period of thirty days, if it is satisfied that the applicant was 
    prevented by sufficient cause from making the application in time. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On receipt 
    of any such application under sub-section (1), the Central Government shall, 
    after considering the application of the aggrieved person and any report 
    thereon which the officer or authority making the order may submit, make 
    such order in rela­tion to the application as it deems fit, and the decision 
    of the Central Government shall be final.
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>15A</number> Review.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person aggrieved by an order made by the Central Government, may within 
    thirty days from the date of such order, make an application for review of 
    such order: 
 
Provided 
    that the Central Government may entertain application after the expiry of 
    the said period of thirty days, if it is satisfied that the applicant was 
    prevented by sufficient cause from making the application in time:  
 
Provided 
    further that an application for a review of an order passed in terms of the 
    provisions of section 14A shall be disposed of in the manner provided for in 
    the procedure as may be laid down under clause (ia) of sub-section (2) of 
    section 18.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On 
    receipt of an application under sub-section (1), the Central Government 
    shall, make such order as it deems fit, and the decision of the Central 
    Government on such review shall be final.]  
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Delegation of power.—The 
    Central Government may, by order, direct that any power which is conferred 
    on it by any of the provisions of this Act other than those of section 10 
    and section 18 shall, in such circumstances and under such conditions, if 
    any, as may be specified in the order, be exercisable also by such officer 
    or authority as may be so specified. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Offences.—Any 
    person who, for the purpose of procuring anything to be done or not to be 
    done under this Act, knowingly makes any representation which is false in a 
    material particular shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which 
    may extend to 

    1[five years], or
    

    2[with fine which may 
    extend to fifty thousand rupees], or with both. 
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette make 
    rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the registration of anything 
    required or authorized under this Act to be registered, and the conditions 
    and restrictions in regard to such registration;  
 

1[(aa)    
    the form and manner in which a declaration under sub-section (1) of section 
    4 shall be made;]  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the forms to be used and the 
    registers to be maintained under this Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the administration and taking of 
    oaths of allegiance under this Act and the time within which, and the manner 
    in which, such oaths shall be taken and recorded;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the giving of any notice required 
    or authorized to be given by any person under this Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the cancellation of the 
    registration of, and the cancellation and amendment of certificate of 
    naturalisation relating to, persons deprived of citizenship under this Act, 
    and the deliver­ing up of such certificates for those purposes;  
 

2[(ee)    
    the manner and form in which and the authority to whom declarations referred 
    to in clauses (a) and (b) of sub-section (b) of section 6A shall be 
    submitted and other matters connected with such declarations;]  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    the registration at Indian 
    consulates of the births and deaths of persons of any class or description 
    born or dying outside India;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    the levy and collection of fees 
    in respect of applications, registrations, declarations and certificates 
    under this Act, in respect of the taking of an oath of allegiance, and in 
    respect of the supply of certified or other copies of documents;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    the authority to determine the 
    question of acquisition of citizenship of another country, the procedure to 
    be followed by such authority and rules of evidence relating to such cases;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    the procedure to be followed by 
    the committees of inquiry appointed under section 10 and the conferment on 
    such committees of any of the powers, rights and privileges of civil court;  
 

3[(ia)    
    the procedure to be followed in compulsory registration of the citizens of 
    India under sub-section (5) of section 14A;]  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>    the manner in which applications 
    for revision may be made and the procedure to be followed by the Central 
    Government in dealing with such applications; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>    any other matter which is to be, 
    or may be, prescribed under this Act.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> In 
    making any rule under this section, the Central Government may provide that 
    breach thereof shall be punishable with fine which may extend to one 
    thousand rupees:  
 


    4[Provided that any 
    rule made in respect of a matter specified in clause (ia) of sub-section (2) 
    may provide that a breach thereof shall be punishable with imprisonment for 
    a term which may extend to three months, or with fine which may extend to 
    five thousand rupees, or with both.]  
 


    5[(4) Every rule made 
    under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made before 
    each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of 
    thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
    successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
    following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses 
    agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the 
    rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
    modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
    such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of 
    anything previously done under that rule.]  
 
 








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Repeals.—[Repealed 
    by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1960 (Act 58 of 1960), sec. 2 and the 
    First Schedule (w.e.f. 
    26-10-1960).] 
  
 
  


</article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




The Citizenship Act, 1955
 

 
 

 
 



   
    1[***]
 


 
 


-------------------------
 


     1.   The First 
    Schedule omitted by Act 6 of 2004, sec. 16 (w.e.f. 3-12-2004). 

 


 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




The Citizenship Act, 1955
 

 
 

 
 




    1[The 
    Second Schedule
 


[See sections 5(2) and 6(2)]
 



    Oath of Allegiance
 

 
 


I, A/B.............................do solemnly 
    affirm (or swear) that i will 
    bear true faith and allegiance to the Constitution of India as by law 
    established, and that i will 
    faithfully observe the laws of India and fulfil my duties as a citizen of 
    India.]
 


 
 


-------------------------
 


     1.   Subs. by Act 6 
    of 2004, sec. 17, for the Second Schedule (w.e.f. 3-12-2004).
 


 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




The Citizenship Act, 1955
 

 
 

 
 



The Third Schedule
 


[See section 6(1)]
 



    Qualifications for naturalisation
 

 
 


The qualifications for naturalisation of 
    a person 
1[***] 
    are—
 


(a) that he is not a subject or citizen of any 
    country where citizens of India are prevented by law or practice of that 
    coun­try from becoming subjects or citizens of that country by 
    natu­ralisation;
 


(b) that, if he is a citizen of any 
    country, 
2[he 
    undertakes to renounce the citizenship of that country in the event of his 
    application for Indian citizenship being accepted];
 


(c) that he has either resided in India or 
    been in the service of a Government in India or partly the one and partly 
    the other, throughout the period of twelve months immediately preceding the 
    date of the application;
 


(d) that during the 
3[fourteen 
    years] immediately preceding the said period of twelve months, he has either 
    resided in India or been in the service of a Government in India, or partly 
    the one and partly the other, for periods amounting in the aggregate to not 
    less than 
4[eleven 
    years];
 


(e) that he is of good character;
 


(f) that he has an adequate knowledge of a 
    language specified in the Eighth Schedule to the Constitution; and
 


(g) that in the event of a certificate of 
    naturalisation being granted to him, he intends to reside in India, or to 
    enter into or continue in, service under a Government in India or under an 
    international organisation of which India is a member or under a society, 
    company or body of persons established in India:
 


Provided that the Central Government may, if 
    in the special circumstances of any particular case it thinks fit,—
 


(i)  allow a continuous period of twelve 
    months ending not more than six months before the date of the application to 
    be reckoned, for the purposes of clause (c) above, as if it had immediately 
    preceded that date;
 


(ii)  allow periods of residence or 
    service earlier than 
5[fif­teen 
    years] before the date of the application to be reckoned in computing the 
    aggregate mentioned in clause (d) above.
 


 
 





 




    ---------------------------------
 


     1.   The words “who 
    is not a citizen of a country specified in the First Schedule” omitted by 
    Act 6 of 2004, sec. 18 (w.e.f. 3-12-2004). tc 
    " 1. The words “who is not a citizen of 
    a country specified in the First Schedule” omitted by Act 6 of 2004, sec. 18 
    (w.e.f. 3-12-2004)." 
 


2.   Subs. by Act 6 of 
    2004, sec. 18, for “he has renounced the citizenship of that country in 
    accordance with the law therein in force in that behalf and has notified 
    such renunciation to the Central Government” (w.e.f. 3-12-2004). tc 
    " 2. Subs. by Act 6 of 2004, sec. 18, 
    for “he has renounced the citizenship of that country in accordance with the 
    law therein in force in that behalf and has notified such renunciation to 
    the Central Government” (w.e.f. 3-12-2004)." 
 


3.   Subs. by Act 6 of 
    2004, sec. 18, for “twelve years” (w.e.f. 3-12-2004). tc 
    " 3. Subs. by Act 6 of 2004, sec. 18, 
    for “twelve years” (w.e.f. 3-12-2004)." 
 


4.   Subs. by Act 6 of 
    2004, sec. 18, for “nine years” (w.e.f. 3-12-2004) tc 
    " 4. Subs. by Act 6 of 2004, sec. 18, 
    for “nine years” (w.e.f. 3-12-2004)" 
 


5.   Subs. by Act 6 of 
    2004, sec. 18, for “thirteen years” (w.e.f. 3-12-2004). tc 
    " 5. Subs. by Act 6 of 2004, sec. 18, 
    for “thirteen years” (w.e.f. 3-12-2004)." 
 




    ---------------------------------
 





 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




The Citizenship Act, 1955
 

 
 

 
 




    1[***]
 


 
 


————— 
 


   1.      The Fourth 
    Schedule omitted by Act 32 of 2005, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 28-6-2005). Earlier the Fourth Schedule was inserted by Act 6 of 2004, sec. 19 
    (w.e.f. 3-12-2004). 
    The Fourth Schedule, for omission, stood as under: 
 



“The 
    Fourth Schedule
 


        [See 
    section 2(1)(gg)]
 


             1.  
    Australia
 


             2.  Canada
 


             3.  Finland
 


             4.  France
 


             5.  Greece
 


             6.  Ireland
 


             7.  Israel
 


             8.  Italy
 


             9.  
    Netherlands
 


            10.  New 
    Zealand
 


            11.  
    Portugal
 


            12.  
    Republic of Cyprus
 


            13.  Sweden
 


            14.  
    Switzerland
 


            15.  United 
    Kingdom
 


            16.  United 
    States of America.” 
 

 
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by Act 32 of 2005, sec. 4, for section 7A (w.r.e.f. 
28-6-2005 ). Earlier section 7A was inserted by Act 6 of 2004 (w.e.f. 3-12-2004 
). Section 7A, before substitution by Act 32 of 2005, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Ins. by Act 6 of 
    2004, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 3-12-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   Ins. by Act 6 of 
    2004, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 3-12-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   Ins. by Act 6 of 
    2004, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 3-12-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>   The words “who 
    is also a citizen or national of another country”, omitted by Act 6 of 2004, 
    sec. 8 (w.e.f. 3-12-2004). tc 
    " 2. The words “who is also a citizen or 
    national of another country”, omitted by Act 6 of 2004, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 
    3-12-2004)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>   Subs. by Act 6 
    of 2004, sec. 9, for “person” (w.e.f. 3-12-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>   Subs. by Act 6 of 
    2004, sec. 11, for “sections 5 and 6” (w.e.f. 3-12-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>   Ins. by Act 6 of 
    2004, sec. 12 (w.e.f. 3-12-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>   Ins. by Act 6 of 
    2004, sec. 13 (w.e.f. 3-12-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>   Subs. by  Act 6 
    of 2004, sec. 14, for “six months” (w.e.f. 3-12-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>   Ins. by  Act 6 
    of 2004, sec. 15 (w.e.f. 3-12-2004).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>