<act><title>
THE WORKMEN’S 
    COMPENSATION RULES, 19241</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>1</number> Short title.—These 
    rules may be called the Workmen’s Compensation Rules, 1924.
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
    these rules unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,— 
 <section>


    <number>a</number>   the ‘Act’ means the Workmen’s Compensation Act, 1923;  
 </section><section>


    <number>b</number>   ‘Form’ means a form appended to these rules;  
 </section><section>


    <number>c</number>   ‘section’ means a section of the Act.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>3</number> When application may be made without medical certificate.—Application 
    for review of a half-monthly payment under section 6 may be made without 
    being accompanied by a medical certificate.—  
 <section>


    <number>a</number>   by the employer on the ground that since the right to compensation was 
    determined the workmen’s wages have increased;  
 </section><section>


    <number>b</number>   by the workman, on the ground that since the right to compensation was 
    determined his wages have diminished;  
 </section><section>


    <number>c</number>   by the workman, on the ground that the employer, having commenced to 
    pay compensation, has ceased to pay the same, notwithstanding the fact that 
    there has been no change in the workmen’s condition such as to warrant such 
    cessation;  
 </section><section>


    <number>d</number>   either by the employer or by the workman, on the ground that the 
    determination of the rate of compensation for the time being in force was 
    obtained by fraud or undue influence or other improper means;  
 </section><section>


    <number>e</number>   either by the employer or by the workman on the ground that in the 
    determination of compensation there is a mistake or error apparent on the 
    face of the record.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>4</number> Procedure on application for review.—If, 
    on examining an application for review by an employer in which the reduction 
    or discontinuance of half-monthly payments is sought it appears to the 
    Commissioner that there is reasonable ground for believing that the employer 
    has a right to such reduction or discontinuance, he may at any time issue an 
    order withholding the half-monthly payments in whole or in part pending his 
    decision on the application.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>5</number> Procedure on application for commutation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where application is made to the Commissioner under section 7 for the 
    redemption of a right to receive half-monthly payments by the payment of a 
    lump sum, the Commissioner shall form an estimate of the probable duration 
    of the disablement, and shall award a sum equivalent to the total of the 
    half-monthly payments which would be payable for the period during which he 
    estimates that the disablement will continue, less one-half per cent of that 
    total for each month comprised in that period:  
 


    Provided that fractions of a rupee included in the sum so computed shall be 
    disregarded.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> When, in any case to which sub-rule (1) applies, the Commissioner is 
    unable to form an approximate estimate of the probable duration of the 
    disablement, he may from time to time postpone a decision on the application 
    for a period not exceeding two months at any one time.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>6</number> Deposit under section 8 
<section><number>1</number>.—(1) 
    An employer depositing compensation with the Commissioner under sub-section 
    (1) of section 8, in respect of a workman whose injury has resulted in death 
    shall furnish therewith a statement in Form A, and shall be given a receipt 
    in Form B. In other cases of deposits with the Commissioner under 
    sub-section (1) of section 8, the employer shall furnish a statement in Form 
    AA, and shall be given a receipt in Form B.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> If, when depositing compensation in respect of fatal accidents, the 
    employer indicates in the statement referred to in sub-rule (1) that he 
    desires to be made a party to the distribution proceedings, the Commissioner 
    shall before allotting the sum deposited as compensation, afford to the 
    employer an opportunity of establishing that the person to whom he proposes 
    to allot such sum is not a dependant of the deceased workman or, as the case 
    may be, ‘that no one of such persons is a dependant’.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> The statement of disbursements to be furnished on application by the 
    employer under sub-section (4) of section 8, shall be in Form C.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>7</number> Publication of list of deposits.—The 
    Commissioner shall cause to be displayed, in a prominent position outside 
    his office, an accurate list of the deposits received by him under 
    sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 8, together with the names and addresses of, the 
    depositors and of the workman in respect of whose death or injury the 
    deposits have been made.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>8</number> Application by dependants for deposit of compensation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A dependant of a deceased workman may apply to the Commissioner for the 
    issue of an order to deposit compensation in respect of the death of the 
    workman. Such application shall be made in Form C.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> If compensation has not been deposited the Commissioner shall dispose of 
    such application in accordance with the provisions of Part V of these rules:  
 


    Provided that—  
 <subsection>


    <number>a</number>   the Commissioner may, at any time before issues are framed, cause 
    notice to be given in such manner as he thinks fit to all or any of the 
    dependants of the deceased workman who have not joined in the application, 
    requiring them, if they desire to join therein, to appear before him on a 
    date specified in this behalf;  
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>b</number>   any dependant to whom such notice has been given and who fails to 
    appear and to join in the application on the date specified in the notice 
    shall not be permitted thereafter to claim that the employer is liable to 
    deposit compensation unless he satisfies the Commissioner that he was 
    prevented by any sufficient cause from appearing when the case was called on 
    for hearing.  
 </subsection></section><section>


    <number>3</number> If, after completing the enquiry into the application, the Commissioner 
    issues an order requiring the employer to deposit compensation in accordance 
    with sub-section (1) of section 8, nothing in sub-rule (2) shall be deemed 
    to prohibit the allotment of any part of the sum deposited as compensation 
    to a dependant of the deceased workman who failed to join the application.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>9</number> Deposit under section 8(2).—An 
    employer depositing compensation in accordance with sub-section (2) of 
    section 8, shall furnish therewith a statement in Form D, and shall be given 
    a receipt in Form E.   

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>10</number> Investment of money.—Money 
    in the hands of Commissioner may be invested for the benefit of the 
    dependants of deceased workman in Government Securities or Post Office Cash 
    Certificates, or may be deposited in a Post Office Savings Bank.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>11</number> Reports of fatal accidents.—The 
    report required by section 10B shall, subject to such rules, if any, as may 
    be made by the State Government, be in Form EE.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>12</number> Right of employer to present memorandum when information received.— 
    
<section><number>1</number> Any employer who has received information of an accident may at any time 
    not-withstanding the fact that no claim for compensation has been instituted 
    in respect of such accident, present to the Commissioner a memorandum 
    supported by an affidavit made by himself or by any person subordinate to 
    him having knowledge of the facts stated in the memorandum, embodying the 
    results of any investigation or inquiry which has been made into the 
    circumstances or cause of the accident.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> A memorandum presented under sub-rule (1) shall, subject to the payment 
    of such fee as may be prescribed, be recorded by the Commissioner.   

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>13</number> Workman not to be required to submit to medical examination save in 
    accordance with rules.—A 
    workman who is required by sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 11 to submit himself 
    for medical examination shall be bound to do so in accordance with the rules 
    contained in this Part and not otherwise.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>14</number> Examination when workman and medical practitioner both on premises.—When 
    such workman is present at the employer’s premises, and the employer offers 
    to have him examined free of charge by a qualified medical practitioner who 
    is so present the workman shall submit himself for examination forthwith.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>15</number> Examination in other cases.—In 
    cases to which rule 14 does not apply, the employer may—  
 <section>


    <number>a</number>   send the medical practitioner to the place where the workman is 
    residing for the time being in which case the workman shall submit himself 
    for medical examination on being requested to do so by the medical 
    practitioner, or  
 </section><section>


    <number>b</number>   send to the workman an offer in writing to have him examined free of 
    charge by a qualified medical practitioner, in which case the workman shall 
    submit himself for medical examination at the employer’s premises or at such 
    other place in the vicinity as is specified in such offer and at such time 
    as is so specified:  
 


    Provided that—  
 <subsection>


    <number>i</number>   the time so specified shall not, save with the express consent of the 
    workman be between the hours of 7 p.m. and 6 a.m. and  
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>ii</number>   in cases were the workman’s condition renders it impossible or 
    inadvisable that he should leave the place where he is residing for the time 
    being, he shall not be required to submit himself for medical examination 
    save at such place.  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>16</number> Restriction on number of examinations.—A 
    workman who is in receipt of a half-monthly payment shall not be required to 
    submit himself for medical examination elsewhere than at the place where he 
    is residing for the time being more than twice in the first month following 
    the accident or more than once in any subsequent month.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>17</number> Examination after suspension of right to compensation.—If 
    a workman whose right to compensation has been suspended under sub-section 
    (2) or sub-section (3) of section 11 subsequently offers himself for medical 
    examination, his examination shall take place on the employer’s premises or 
    at such other place in the vicinity as may be fixed by the employer, and at 
    a time to be fixed by the employer not being save with the express consent 
    of the workman, more than 72 hours after the workman has so offered himself.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>18</number> Examination of women.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No woman shall without her consent be medically examined by a male 
    practitioner, save in the presence of another woman.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> No woman shall be required to be medically examined by a male 
    practitioner if she deposits a sum sufficient to cover the expenses of 
    examination by a female practitioner.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>19</number> Introductory.—Save 
    as otherwise provided in these rules the procedure to be followed by the 
    Commissioner in the disposal of cases under the Act, or these rules and by 
    the parties in such cases shall be regulated in accordance with the rules 
    contained in this part.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>20</number> Application.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any application of the nature referred to in section 22 may be sent to the 
    Commissioner by registered post or may be presented to him or to any of his 
    subordinates authorised by him in this behalf, and, if so sent or presented, 
    shall, unless the Commissioner otherwise directs, be made in duplicate in 
    the appropriate Form, if any, and shall be signed by the applicant.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> There shall be appended to every such application a certificate, which 
    shall be signed by the applicant, to the effect that the statement of facts 
    contained in the application is to the best of his knowledge and belief 
    accurate.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>21</number> Production of documents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    When the application for relief is based upon a document, the document shall 
    be appended to the application.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> Any other document which any party desires to tender in evidence shall 
    be produced at or before the first hearing.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> Any document which is not produced at or within the time specified in 
    sub-rule (1) or (2), as the case may be, shall not, without the sanction of 
    the Commissioner, be admissible in evidence on behalf of the party who 
    should have produced it.  
 </section><section>


    <number>4</number> Nothing in this rule applies to any document which is produced for the 
    purpose of cross-examining a witness or is handed to a witness to refresh 
    his memory.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>22</number> Application presented to wrong Commissioner.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If it appears to the Commissioner on receiving application that it should be 
    presented to another Commissioner he shall return it to the applicant after 
    endorsing upon it the date of the presentation and return, the reason for 
    returning it and designation of the Commissioner to whom it should be 
    presented.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> If it appears to the Commissioner at any subsequent stage that an 
    application should have been presented to another Commissioner, he shall 
    send the application to the Commissioner empowered to deal with it and shall 
    inform the applicant (and the opposite party, if he has received a copy of 
    the application under rule 26), accordingly.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> The Commissioner to whom an application is transferred under sub-rule 
    (2) may continue the proceedings as if the previous proceedings or any part 
    of them had been taken before him, if he is satisfied that the interests of 
    the parties will not thereby be prejudiced.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>23</number> Examination of applicant.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    On receiving application of the nature referred to in section 22, the 
    Commissioner may examine the applicant on oath, or may send the application 
    to any officer authorised by the State Government in this behalf and direct 
    such officer to examine the applicant and his witnesses and forward the 
    record thereof to the Commissioner.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> The substance of any examination made under sub-rule (1), shall be 
    recorded in the manner provided for the recording of evidence in section 25.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>24</number> Summary dismissal of application.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Commissioner may, after considering the application and the result of 
    any examination of the applicant under rule 23, summarily dismiss the 
    application, if, for reasons to be recorded, he is of opinion that there are 
    no sufficient grounds for proceeding thereon.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> The dismissal of the application under sub-rule (1) shall not of itself 
    preclude the applicant from presenting a fresh application for the 
    settlement of the same matter.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>25</number> Preliminary inquiry into application.—If 
    the application is not dismissed under rule 24, the Commissioner may for 
    reasons to be recorded, call upon the applicant to produce evidence in 
    support of the application before calling upon any other party, and, if upon 
    considering such evidence the Commissioner is of opinion that there is no 
    case for the relief claimed, he may dismiss the application with a brief 
    statement of his reasons for so doing.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>26</number> Notice to opposite party.—If 
    the Commissioner does not dismiss the application under rule 24 or rule 25, 
    he shall send to the party from whom the applicant claims relief 
    (hereinafter referred to as the opposite party) a copy of the application, 
    together with a notice of the date on which he will dispose of the 
    application, and may call upon the parties to produce upon that date any 
    evidence which they may wish to tender.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>27</number> Appearance and examination of opposite party.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The opposite party may, and if so required by the Commissioner, shall, at or 
    before the first hearing or within such time as the Commissioner may permit, 
    file a written statement dealing with the claim, raised in the application, 
    and any such written statement shall form part of the record.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> If the opposite party contests the claim, the Commissioner may, and, if 
    no written statement has been filed, shall proceed to examine him upon the 
    claim and shall reduce the result of examination to writing.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>28</number> Framing of issues.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    After considering any written statement and the result of any examination of 
    the parties, the Commissioner shall ascertain upon what material 
    propositions of fact or of law the parties are at variance and shall 
    thereupon proceed to frame and record the issues upon which the right 
    decision of the case appears to him to depend.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> In recording the issues, the Commissioner shall distinguish between 
    those issues which in his opinion concern points of facts and those which 
    concern points of law.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>29</number> Power to postpone trial of issues of fact where issues of law arise.—When 
    issues both of law and of fact arise in the same case, and the Commissioner 
    is of opinion that the case may be disposed of on the issues of law only, he 
    may try those issues first, and for that purpose may, if he thinks fit, 
    postpone the settlement of the issues of fact until after the issues of law 
    have been determined.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>30</number> Diary.—The 
    Commissioner shall maintain under his hand a brief diary of the proceedings 
    on an application.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>31</number> Reasons for postponement to be recorded.—If 
    the Commissioner finds it impossible to dispose of an application at one 
    hearing he shall record the reasons which necessitate a postponement.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>32</number> Judgment.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Commissioner, in passing orders, shall record concisely a judgment, his 
    finding on each of the issues framed and his reasons for such finding.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> The Commissioner, at the time of signing and dating his judgment, shall 
    pronounce, his decision, and thereafter no addition or alteration shall be 
    made to the judgment other than the correction of a clerical or arithmetical 
    mistake arising from any accidental slip or omission.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>33</number> Summoning of witnesses.—If 
    an application is presented to any party to the proceedings for the citation 
    of witnesses, the Commissioner shall, on payment of the prescribed expenses, 
    and fees, issue summonses for the appearance of such witnesses, unless he 
    considers that their appearance is not necessary for the just decision of 
    the case.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>34</number> Exemption from payment of costs.—If 
    the Commissioner is satisfied that the applicant is unable, by reason of 
    poverty, to pay the prescribed fees, he may remit any or all of such fees. 
    If the case is decided in favour of the applicant, the prescribed fees 
    which, had they not been remitted, would have been due to be paid, may be 
    added to the costs of the case and recovered in such manner as the 
    Commissioner in his order regarding costs may direct.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>35</number> Right of entry for local inspection.—A 
    Commissioner before whom any proceeding relating to an injury by accident is 
    pending may at any time enter the place where the workman was injured, or 
    where the workman ordinarily performed his work, for the purpose of making a 
    local inspection or of examining any person likely to be able to give 
    information relevant to the proceedings:  
 


    Provided that the Commissioner shall not enter any premises of any 
    industrial establishment except during the ordinary working hours of that 
    establishment, save with the permission of the employer or of some person 
    directly responsible to him for the management of the establishment.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>36</number> Procedure in connection with local inspection.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If the Commissioner proposes to conduct a local inspection with a view to 
    examining on the spot the circumstances in which an accident took place, he 
    shall give the parties or their representatives notice of his intention to 
    conduct such inspection, unless in his opinion the urgency of the case 
    renders the giving of such notice impracticable.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> Such notice may be given orally or in writing and, in the case of an 
    employer, may be given to any person upon whom notice of a claim can be 
    served under sub-section (2) of section 10, or the representative of any 
    such person.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> Any party, or the representative of any party, may accompany the 
    Commissioner at a local inspection.  
 </section><section>


    <number>4</number> The Commissioner, after making a local inspection, shall note briefly in 
    a memorandum any facts observed, and shall show the memorandum to any party 
    who desires to see the same, and, on payment of the prescribed fee, shall 
    supply any party with a copy thereof.  
 </section><section>


    <number>5</number> The memorandum shall form part of the record.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>37</number> Power of summary examination.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Commissioner during a local inspection or at any other time, save at a 
    formal hearing of a case pending before him, may examine summarily any 
    person likely to be able to give information relative to such case, whether 
    such person has been or is to be called as a witness in the case or not, and 
    whether any or all of the parties are present or not.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> No oath shall be administered to a person examined under sub-rule (1).  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> Statements made by persons examined under sub-rule (1), if reduced to 
    writing, shall not be signed by the person making the statement, nor shall 
    they, except as hereinafter provided, be incorporated in the record or 
    utilized by the Commissioner for the purpose of arriving at a decision in 
    the case.  
 </section><section>


    <number>4</number> If a witness who has been examined under sub-rule (1) makes in evidence 
    any material statement contradicting any statement made by him in such 
    examination and reduced to writing, the Commissioner may call his attention 
    to such statement, and shall in that case direct that the parties be 
    furnished with the relevant part of such statement for the propose of 
    examining or cross-examining the witness.  
 </section><section>


    <number>5</number> Any statements or part of a statement which is furnished to the parties 
    under sub-rule (4) shall be incorporated in the record.  
 </section><section>


    <number>6</number> Where a case is settled by agreement between the parties, the 
    Commissioner may incorporate in the record any statement made under sub-rule 
    (1) and may utilise such statement for the purpose of justifying his 
    acceptance of or refusal to accept the agreement reached.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>38</number> Agreement to abide by Commissioner’s decision.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If a party states in writing his willingness to abide by the decision of the 
    Commissioner, the Commissioner shall inquire whether the other party is 
    willing to abide by his decision.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> If the other party agrees to abide by the Commissioner’s decision, the 
    fact of his agreement shall be recorded in writing and signed by him.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> If the other party does not agree to abide by the Commissioner’s 
    decision, the first party shall not remain under an obligation so to abide.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>38</number> Agreement to abide by Commissioner’s decision.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If a party states in writing his willingness to abide by the decision of the 
    Commissioner, the Commissioner shall inquire whether the other party is 
    willing to abide by his decision.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> If the other party agrees to abide by the Commissioner’s decision, the 
    fact of his agreement shall be recorded in writing and signed by him.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> If the other party does not agree to abide by the Commissioner’s 
    decision, the first party shall not remain under an obligation so to abide.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>39</number> Procedure where indemnity claimed under section 12(2).—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the opposite party claims that if compensation is recovered against 
    him he will be entitled under sub-section (2) of section 12, to be 
    indemnified by a person not being a party to the case, he shall, when first 
    called upon answer the application, present a notice of such claim to the 
    Commissioner accompanied by the prescribed fee, and the Commissioner shall 
    thereupon issue notice to such person in Form J.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> If any person served with a notice under sub-section (1) desires to 
    contest the applicant’s claim for compensation or the opposite party’s claim 
    to be indemnified, he shall appear before the Commissioner on the date fixed 
    for the hearing of the case or on any date to which the case may be 
    adjourned and, if he so appears, shall have all the rights of a party to the 
    proceedings; in default of so appearing he shall be deemed to admit the 
    validity of any award made against the opposite party and to admit his own 
    liability to indemnify the opposite party for any compensation recovered 
    from him:  
 


    Provided that, if any person so served appear subsequently and satisfies the 
    Commissioner that he was prevented by any sufficient cause from appearing, 
    the Commissioner shall offer giving notice to the aforesaid opposite party, 
    hear such person and may set aside or vary any award made against such 
    person under this rule and upon such terms as may be just.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> If any person served with a notice under sub-rule (1) whether or not he 
    desires to contest the applicant’s claim for compensation or the opposite 
    party’s claim to be indemnified, claims that being a contractor he is 
    himself a principal and is entitled to be indemnified by a person standing 
    to him in the relation of a contractor from whom the workman could have 
    recovered compensation, he shall on or before the date fixed in the notice 
    under sub-rule (1) present a notice of such claim to the Commissioner 
    accompanied by the prescribed fee and the Commissioners shall thereupon 
    issue notice to such person in Form JJ.  
 </section><section>


    <number>4</number> If any person served with a notice under sub-rule (3) desires to contest 
    the applicant’s claim for compensation, or the claim under sub-rule (3) to 
    be indemnified, he shall appear before the Commissioner on the date fixed in 
    the notice in Form JJ or on any date to which the case may be adjourned and, 
    if he so appears, shall have all the rights of a party to the proceedings in 
    default of so appearing he shall be deemed to admit the validity of any 
    award made against the original opposite party or the person served with a 
    notice under sub-rule (1) and to admit his own liability to indemnify the 
    party against whom such award is made for any compensation recovered from 
    him:  
 


    Provided that, if any person so served appears subsequently and satisfies 
    the Commissioner that he was prevented by any sufficient cause from 
    appearing, the Commissioner shall, after giving notice to all parties on the 
    record, hear such person, and may set aside or vary any award made against 
    such person under this rule upon such terms as may be just.  
 </section><section>


    <number>5</number> In any proceeding in which a notice has been served on any person under 
    sub-rule (1) or sub-rule (3) the Commissioner shall, if he awards 
    compensation, record in his judgment a finding in respect of each of such 
    persons, whether he is or is not liable to indemnify any of the opposite 
    parties, and shall specify the party, if any whom he is liable to indemnify.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>40</number> Procedure in connected cases.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where two or more cases pending before a Commissioner arise out of the same 
    accident, and any issue involved is common to two or more such cases, such 
    cases may, so far as the evidence bearing on such issue is concerned, be 
    heard simultaneously.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> Where action is taken under sub-rule (1) the evidence bearing on the 
    common issue or issues shall be recorded on the record of one case, and the 
    Commissioner shall certify under his hand on the record on any such other 
    case, the extent to which the evidence so recorded applies to such other 
    case, and the fact that the parties to such other case had the opportunity 
    of being present, and if they were present, of cross-examining the 
    witnesses.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>41</number> Certain provisions of Code of Civil Procedure, 1908, to apply.—Save 
    as otherwise expressly provided in the Act or these Rules the following 
    provisions of the First Schedule to the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908, 
    namely, those contained in Order V, Rules 9 to 13 and 15 to 30: Order IX; 
    Order XIII, Rules 3 to 10; Order XVI, Rules 2 to 21; Order XVII; and Order 
    XXIII, Rules 1 and 2, shall apply to proceedings before Commissioners, in so 
    far as they may be applicable thereto:   
 


    Provided that—  
 <section>


    <number>a</number>   for the purpose of facilitating the application of the said provisions 
    the Commissioner may construe them with such alterations not affecting the 
    substance as may be necessary or proper to adapt them to the matter before 
    him;  
 </section><section>


    <number>b</number>   the Commissioner may, for sufficient reasons, proceed otherwise than 
    in accordance with the said provisions if he is satisfied that the interests 
    of the parties will not thereby be prejudiced.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>42</number> Provision regarding signature of forms.—Any 
    form other than a receipt for compensation, which is by these rules required 
    to be signed by a Commissioner may be signed under his direction and on his 
    behalf by any officer subordinate to him appointed by him in writing for 
    this purpose.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>43</number> Apportionment of compensation among dependants.—The 
    provisions of this Part, except those contained in rules 26, 27 and 39 
    shall, as far as may be, apply in the case of any proceedings relating to 
    the apportionment of compensation among the dependants of a deceased 
    workman.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>44</number> Transfer for report.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A Commissioner transferring any matter to another Commissioner for report in 
    accordance with sub-section (2) of section 21 shall, along with the 
    documents referred to in that sub-section, transmit to such other 
    Commissioner a concise statement in the form of questions for answer of the 
    matter on which report is required.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> A Commissioner to whom a case is so transferred for report shall not be 
    required to report on any question of law.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>45</number> Transmission of money.—Money 
    transmitted by one Commissioner, to another in accordance with sub-section 
    (2) of section 21 shall be transmitted either by remittance transfer 
    receipt, or by money order or by messenger, as the Commissioner transmitting 
    the money may direct.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>46</number> When representatives must be appointed.—Where 
    any party to a proceeding is under the age of 15 years or is unable to make 
    an appearance, the Commissioner shall appoint some suitable person, who 
    consents to the appointment, to represent such party for the purposes of the 
    proceeding.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>47</number> When new representative to be appointed.— 
    If the Commissioner considers that the interests of any party for whom a 
    representative has been appointed under rule 46 are not being adequately 
    protected by the representative or if a person appointed to act as 
    representative dies or becomes incapable of acting, or otherwise ceases to 
    act as such, the Commissioner shall appoint in his place another person who 
    consents to the appointment.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>48</number> Form of memorandum.—Memoranda 
    of agreement sent to the Commissioner under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 28 
    shall, unless the Commissioner otherwise directs, be in duplicate, and shall 
    be in as close conformity as the circumstances of the case admit with Form K 
    or Form L or Form M, as the case may be.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>49</number> Procedure where Commissioner does not consider that he should refuse to 
    record memorandum.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    On receiving a memorandum of agreement, the Commissioner shall, unless he 
    considers that there are grounds for refusing to record the memorandum, fix 
    a date for recording the same, and shall issue a notice in writing in Form N 
    to the parties concerned that in default of objections he proposes to record 
    the memorandum on the date so fixed:  
 


    Provided that the notice may be communicated orally to any parties who are 
    present at the time when notice in writing would otherwise issue.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> On the date so fixed, the Commissioner shall record the memorandum 
    unless, after hearing any of the parties who appear and desire to be heard 
    he considers that it ought not to be recorded:  
 


    Provided that the issue of a notice under sub-rule (1) shall not be deemed 
    to prevent the Commissioner from refusing to record the memorandum on the 
    date so fixed even if no objection be made by any party concerned.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> If on such date the Commissioner decides that the memorandum ought not 
    to be recorded, he shall inform the parties present of his decision and of 
    the reasons therefor, and, if any party desiring the memorandum to be 
    recorded is not present, he shall send information to that party in Form O.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>50</number> Procedure where Commissioner considers, he should refuse to record 
    memorandum.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If, on receiving a memorandum of agreement, the Commissioner considers that 
    there are grounds for refusing to record the same he shall fix a date for 
    hearing the party or parties desiring the memorandum to be recorded, and 
    shall inform such party or parties and, if he thinks fit, any other party 
    concerned, of the date so fixed and of the grounds on which he considers 
    that the memorandum should not be recorded.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> If the parties to be informed are not present a written notice shall be 
    sent to them in Form P or Form Q, as the case may be and the date fixed in 
    such notice shall be not less than seven days after the date of the issue of 
    the same.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> If on the date fixed under sub-rule (1) the party or parties desiring 
    the memorandum to be recorded show adequate cause for proceeding to record 
    the same, the Commissioner may, if information has already been given to all 
    the parties concerned, record the agreement. If information has not been 
    given to all such parties, he shall proceed in accordance with rule 49.  
 </section><section>


    <number>4</number> If, on the date so fixed, the Commissioner refuses to record the 
    memorandum, he shall send notice in Form O to any party who did not receive 
    information under sub-rule (1).  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>51</number> Procedure on refusal to record memorandum.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If in any case the Commissioner refuses to record a memorandum of agreement, 
    he shall briefly record his reason for such refusal.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> If the Commissioner refuses to record a memorandum of agreement, he 
    shall not pass any order directing the payment of any sum or amount over and 
    above the sum specified in the agreement, unless opportunity has been given 
    to the party liable to pay such sum to show cause why it should not be paid.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> Where the agreement is for the redemption of half-monthly payments by 
    the payments of a lump sum, and the Commissioner considers the memorandum of 
    agreement should not be recorded by reason of the inadequacy of the amount 
    of such sum as filed in the agreement he shall record his estimate of the 
    probable duration of the disablement of the workman.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>52</number> Registration of memorandum accepted for record.—In 
    recording a memorandum of agreement, the Commissioner shall cause the same 
    to be entered in a register in Form R and shall cause an endorsement to be 
    entered under his signature on a copy of the memorandum to be retained by 
    him in the following terms namely:—  
 


    “This memorandum of agreement bearing Serial No...............of 20..... in 
    the register has been recorded this................... day of........
 

 <section>
<number>Signature</number>..........................
 </section><section>
<number>Commissioner</number>"
  
 
  


</section></article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE 
    WORKMEN’S COMPENSATION RULES, 1924
 



 




    FORM A
 




    [See rule 6 (1)]
 




    Deposit of Compensation for Fatal Accident
 




    [Section 8 (1) of the Workmen's Compensation Act, 1923]
 

 
 




    Compensation amounting to Rs. ..............is hereby presented for deposit 
    in respect of injuries resulting in the death of the workman, whose 
    particulars are given below, which occurred on ........................
 




    Name ........................                                    

 




    Father’s Name ........................
 




    (Husband’s name in case of married woman and widow.)
 




    Caste........................
 




    Local address ..................................
 




    Permanent address  ..................................
 




    His/Her monthly wages are estimated at Rs.................. He/ She was 
    over/ under the age of 15 years at the time of his/her death.
 




    2. The said workman  had, prior to the date of his/her death, received the 
    following payments, namely:—
 




    Rs.   ................ on ........................ Rs. ................ on 
    ........................
 




    Rs.   ................ on .......................  Rs. ................ on 
    ........................
 




    Rs.   ................ on ........................ Rs. ................ on 
    .......................
 




    amounting in all to Rs.................
 




    3. An advance of Rs .............. has been made on account of compensation 
    to .................. being his/her dependant.
 




    4. *I do not desire to be made a party to the proceedings for distribution 
    of the aforesaid compensation.
 

 
 




    Dated .................... 20.....
 




    Employer.
 

 
 




    *An employer desiring to be made a party to the proceedings should strike 
    out the words “do not”.
 

 
 

 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE 
    WORKMEN’S COMPENSATION RULES, 1924
 



 




    FORM AA
 




    [See rule 6 (1)]
 




    Deposit of Compensation for Non-Fatal Accident to  

    a Woman or Person under Legal Disability
 




    [Section 8 (1) of the Workmen's Compensation Act, 1923]
 




    Compensation amounting to Rs ................ is hereby presented for 
    deposit in respect of injuries sustained by .........................  
    residing at ................................... on ............... 20..... 
    resulting in the loss of/temporary disablement. His/Her monthly wages are 
    estimated at Rs. ............... He/She was over/under the age of 15 years 
    at the time of the accident.
 




    2. The said injured workman has prior to the date of the deposit received 
    the following half- monthly payments, namely:—
 




    Rs.   ..............  on  ........................   Rs.  ..............  
    on ........................
 




    Rs.   ..............  on  ........................   Rs.  ..............  
    on ........................
 




    Rs.   ..............  on  ........................   Rs.  ..............  on 
    ........................
 





 




    Dated..............20.....              
 




    Employer.

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE 
    WORKMEN’S COMPENSATION RULES, 1924
 



 




    FORM B
 




    (See rule 6)
 




    Receipt For Compensation
 




    [Deposited under section 8 (1) of the Workmen’s Compensation Act, 1923]
 




    Book No.       .................................. Receipt No...............
 




    Register No. ..............
 




    Depositor ............................. Deceased or injured workman 
    .............................
 




    Date of deposit ............ 20.....
 




    Sum deposited Rs ...............
 




    Commissioner.
 

 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE 
    WORKMEN’S COMPENSATION RULES, 1924
 



 




    FORM C
 




    (See rule 6)
 




    Statement of  Disbursements
 




    [Section 8 (4) of the Workmen’s Compensation Act, 1923]
 




    Serial No. .............
 




    Depositor .......................................
 




    Date .....................20..........
 




    Amount deposited.......................
 




    Amount deducted and repaid to the employer under the proviso to section 8 
    (1) ........
 




    Funeral expenses paid ............
 




    Compensation paid to the following dependants :
 




            Name                                                     
    Relationship 
 




            ........................                        
    .....................
 




            ........................                        
    ......................
 





 




    Total —
 




    Dated .................. 20.....
 




    Commissioner.

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE 
    WORKMEN’S COMPENSATION RULES, 1924
 



 




    FORM D
 




    [See rule 9]
 




    Deposit of Compensation for Non-Fatal Accidents, other than to a Woman or 
    Person under Legal Disability
 




    [Section 8 (2) of the Workmen’s Compensation Act, 1923]
 




    Compensation amounting to Rs. .............. is hereby presented for deposit 
    in respect of permanent/temporary injuries sustained by .................. 
    residing at ....................... which occcurred on........... 20.....
 





 




    Dated .............. 20.....
 




    Employer.
 

 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE 
    WORKMEN’S COMPENSATION RULES, 1924
 



 




    FORM E
 




    (See rule 9)
 




    Receipt for Compensation
 




    [Deposited under section 8 (2) of the Workmen’s Compensation Act, 1923]
 




    Book No. ..............                          Receipt No. ..............
 




    Register No. ..............
 




    Depositor ............................
 




    In favour of ............................
 




    Date of deposit .............. 20.....
 




    Sum deposited Rs. ..............
 





 




    Commissioner. 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE 
    WORKMEN’S COMPENSATION RULES, 1924
 



 




    FORM EE
 




    [See rule 11]
 




    Report of Fatal Accidents
 




    To
 




    ...................
 




    ...................
 




    Sir,    
 




    I have the honour to submit the following report of an accident which 
    occurred on................... (date) at ................... (here enter 
    details of premises) and which resulted in the death of the workman/workmen 
    of whom particulars are given in the statement annexed.
 




    2. The circumstances attending the death of the workman/workmen were as 
    under : 
 




    (a)   Time of the accident 
 




    (b)   Place where the accident occurred 
 




    (c)   Manner in which deceased was/were employed at  time 
 




    (d)   Cause of the accident 
 




    (e)   Any other relevant particulars 
 




           I have etc.                                     
    
 






    (Signature and designation of person making the report.)
 

 
 




Statement 
 
 
  

 
 Name 

 Sex
 Age
 Nature of 
        Employment
 Full Postal 
        Address

 
  


 

 
 

 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 


THE 
    WORKMEN’S COMPENSATION RULES, 1924
 



 




    FORM F
 




    (See rule 20)
 




    Application for Compensation by Workman
 




    To
 




    The Commissioner for Workmen’s Compensation,
 




    .............................................................................
 




    .............................................................................
 




    .................... residing at..........................applicant,
 




Versus
 




    ..................residing at..........................opposite party.
 




    It is hereby submitted that—
 




    (1) the applicant, a workman employed by (a contractor with) the opposite 
    party on the .............. day of .............. 20.....,  received 
    personal injury by accident arising out of and in the course of his 
    employment.
 




    The cause of the injury was (here insert briefly in ordinary language the 
    cause of the injury)..................................................................................................................................................
 




    ....................................................................................................................................................................
 




    (2) The applicant sustained the following injuries, namely:—
 




    .............................................................................................................................................................
 




    .....................................................................................................................................................................
 




    (3) The monthly wages of the applicant amounts to Rs ..............
 




            The applicant is over/under the age of 15 years.
 




             *(4)    (a)   Notice of the accident was served on the 
    ..............  day of ........................
 




                       (b)   Notice was served as soon as practicable.
 




                        (c)   Notice of the accident was not served (in due 
    time) by reason of .......................
 




    (5) The applicant is accordingly entitled to receive —
 




                       (a)   half-monthly payment of Rs.......from 
    the............ day of 20..... to ..................
 




                       (b)   a lump sum payment of Rs ..........
 




    (6) The applicant has taken the following steps to secure a settlement by 
    agreement, namely .................................but it has proved 
    impossible to settle the questions in dispute  

    because...................................................................................................................................
 




    * You are therefore requested to determine the following questions in 
    dispute, namely:—
 




               (a)    whether the applicant is a workman within the meaning of 
    the Act ;
 




               (b)   whether the accident arose out of or in the course of the 
    applicant’s employment;
 




                (c)   whether the amount of compensation claimed is due, or any 
    part of that amount;
 




               (d)   whether the opposition party is liable to pay such 
    compensation as is due ;
 




               (e)  etc. (as required) .
 




    Dated ........................ 20....
 




                                                            Applicant.
 




    *Strike out the clauses which are not applicable.
 





</form><form>
 


THE 
    WORKMEN’S COMPENSATION RULES, 1924
 



 




    FORM G
 




    (See rule 20)
 




    Application for order to Deposit Compensation
 




    To 
 




    The Commissioner for Workmen’s Compensation, 
    .........................................................   
    .............................................................................................................................................................. 

    ........................ residing at ................................. 
    applicant, 
 





    versus
 




    ...................... residing at.................................  
    opposite party.
 




    It is hereby submitted that— 
 




    (1)   ........................ a workman employed by (a contractor with) the 
    opposite party on the ..............day of..............20....., reccived 
    personal injury by accident arising out of land in the course of his 
    employment resulting in his death on the ..............day of.............. 
    20....., The cause of the injury was (here insert briefly in ordinary 
    language the cause of the injury) 
    ................................................................................................................ 

    ...........................................................................................................................................
 




    (2)   The applicant(s) is/are dependant(s) of the deceased workman being 
    his  ......................   
 




    (3)   The monthly wages of the deceased amounts to Rs .............. The 
    deceased was over/under the age of 15 years at the time of his death.
 




    *(4)  (a)   Notice of the accident was served on the .............. day of 
    ......................
 




                        (b)   Notice was served as soon as practicable.
 




                        (c)   Notice of the accident was not served (in due 
    time) by reason of.................................
 




    (5)  The deceased before his death received as compensation the total sum of 
    Rs. .............. The applicant(s) is/are accordingly entitled to receive a 
    lump sum payment of Rs ..............
 




    You are therefore requested to award to the applicant the said compensation 
    or any other compensation to which he may be entitled.
 




    Dated ................... 20.....
 




    Applicant.
 

 
 




    *Strike out the clauses which are not applicable.
</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE 
    WORKMEN’S COMPENSATION RULES, 1924
 



 




    FORM H
 




    (See rule 20)
 




    Application for Commutation
 




    [Under section 7 of the Workmen’s Compensation Act, 1923]
 




    To 
 




    The Commissioner for Workmen’s Compensation, 
 




    ....................................................................................
 




    ....................................................................................
 




    ....................... residing at 
    ................................applicant,
 




                                            Versus
 




    ..................... residing  at .............................. opposite 
    party.
 




    It is hereby submitted that —
 




    (1)   The applicant/opposite party has been in respect of half-monthly 
    payments from ...................... to ..................... in respect of 
    temporary disablement by accident arising out of and in the course of his 
    employment.
 




    (2)   The applicant is desirous that the right to receive half-monthly 
    payments should be redeemed.
 




    (3)  (a)   The opposite party is unwilling to agree to the redemption of the 
    right to receive half-monthly payments.
 




    (b)   The parties have been unable to agree regarding the sum for which the 
    right to  receive half-monthly payments should be redeemed.
 




    You are therefore requested to pass orders —
 




               (a)   directing that the right to receive half-monthly payments 
    should be redeemed,
 




               (b)   fixing a sum for the redemption of the right to receive 
    half-monthly payments.
 




    Dated .................... 20.....
 




    Applicant.
 






 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE 
    WORKMEN’S COMPENSATION RULES, 1924
 



 




    FORM J
 




    (See rule 39)
 




    NOTICE
 




    Whereas a claim for compensation has been made by...................... 
    applicant, 

    against........................  and the said........................ has 
    claimed that you are liable under section 12(2) of the Workmen’s 
    Compensation Act, 1923, to indemnify him against any compensation which he 
    may be liable to pay in respect of the aforesaid claim, you are hereby 
    informed that you may appear before me on ...................... and contest 
    the claim for compensation made by the said applicant or the claim for 
    indemnity made by the opposite party. In default of your appearance you will 
    be deemed to admit the validity of any award made against the opposite party 
    and your liability to indemnify the opposite party for any compensation 
    recovered from him.
 




    Dated ................... 20.....
 




    Commissioner.

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE 
    WORKMEN’S COMPENSATION RULES, 1924
 



 




    FORM JJ
 




    (See rule 39)
 




    NOTICE
 




    Whereas a claim for compensation has been made by ........................ 
    applicant, against ........................and the 
    said........................ has claimed that........................is 
    liable under section 12(2) of the Workmen’s Compensation Act, 1923, to 
    indemnify him against any compensation which he may be liable to pay in 
    respect of the aforesaid claim, and whereas the said........................ 
    on notice served has claimed that you ........................stand to him 
    in the relation of a contractor from whom the applicant 
    ........................could  have recovered compensation you are hereby 
    informed that you may appear before me on........................on contest 
    the claim for compensation made by the said applicant or the claim for 
    indemnity made by the opposite party ........................ In default of 
    your appearance you will be deemed to admit the validity of any award made 
    against the opposite party........................and your liability to 
    indemnify the opposite party ........................ for any compensation 
    recovered from him.
 




    Dated ................... 20.....
 




    Commissioner.

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE 
    WORKMEN’S COMPENSATION RULES, 1924
 



 




    FORM K
 




    (See rule 48)
 




    Memorandum of Agreement
 




    It is hereby submitted that on the ........... day of .............. 20..... 
    personal injury was caused to........................residing 
    at................................ by accident arising out of and in the 
    course of employment in ........................ The said injury has 
    resulted in temporary disablement to the said workman whereby it is 
    estimated that he will be prevented from earning more than of his 
    previous/any wage for a period of........... months. The said workman has 
    been in receipt of half-monthly payments which have continued from the 
    ........... day of...........20 .....  until the ........... day 
    of...........20..... amounting to Rs . ...........  in all. The said 
    workmen’s monthly wages are estimated at Rs........... The workman is over 
    the age of 15 years/will reach the age of 15 years on ....................
 




    It is further submitted that .................... the employer of said 
    workman has agreed to pay, and the said workman has agreed to accept, the 
    sum of Rs ........... in full settlement of all and every claim under the 
    Workmen’s Compensation Act, 1923, in respect of all disablement of a  
    temporary nature arising out of the said accident, whether now or hereafter 
    to become manifest. It is, therefore, requested that this memorandum be duly 
    recorded.
 




    Dated.................20.......
 




    Signature of employer.......................................
 




    Witness........................
 




    Signature of workman........................
 




    Witness........................
 




    Note.—An 
    application to register an  agreement can be presented under the signature 
    of one party, provided that the other party has agreed to the terms. But 
    both signatures should be appended, whenever possible.
 




    Receipt to be filled in when the money has actually been paid
 




    In accordance with the above agreement, I have this day received the sum of
     

    Rs. ...............
 

 
 

 
 




    Revenue        

          Stamp    
 




    ........................Workman.
 




    Dated  ................... 20.....
 




    The money has been paid and this receipt signed in my presence. 

 




                                                                                                                                            
        ........................Witness.
 




    Note.—This 
    form may be varied to suit special cases, e.g., injury by 
    occupational diseases, agreement when workman is under legal disability, etc.

 
 

 


</form><form>
 


THE 
    WORKMEN’S COMPENSATION RULES, 1924
 



 




    FORM L
 




    (See rule 48)
 




    Memorandum on Agreement
 




    It is hereby submitted that on the day of  .................... 20..... 
    personal injury was caused to  ........................ residing at 
    ................................by accident arising out of and in the course 
    of his employment in  ...........  . The said injury has resulted in 
    permanent disablement to the said workman of the following nature, namely:—
 




     ....................................................................................................................................................
 




    The said workman’s monthly wages are estimated at Rs. ...............
 




    The workman is over the age of 15 years/will reach the age of 15 years on 
    ........................ The said workman has, prior to the date of this 
    agreement received the following payments namely:—
 




    Rs. ...............   on. ........................ Rs. .............  on  
    ........................
 




    Rs. ...............   on. ........................ Rs. .............  on  
    ........................
 




    Rs. ...............   on. ........................ Rs. .............  on  
    ........................
 




    It is further submitted that ........... the employer of the said workman, 
    had agreed to pay, and the said workman has agreed to accept the sum of Rs  
    .................in full settlement of all and every claim under the 
    Workmen’s Compensation Act, 1923, in respect of the disablement stated above 
    and all disablement now manifest. It is, therefore, requested that this 
    memorandum be duly recorded.
 




    Dated  ................... 20.....
 




    Signature of employer  ........................
 




    Witness  ........................
 




    Signature of workman  ........................
 




    Witness  ........................
 




    Note.—An 
    application to register an agreement can be presented  under the signature 
    of one party, provided that the other party has agreed to the terms. But 
    both signatures should be appended, whenever  possible.
 




    Receipt to be filled in when the money has actually been paid
 




    In accordance with the above agreement, I have this day received the sum of 
    Rs .....
 




    Revenue         

         Stamp                
 




     ....................Workman.
 




    Dated  ................... 20.....
 




    The money has been paid and this receipt signed in my presence.
 




    .......................Witness.
 




    Note.—This 
    form may be varied to suit special cases, e.g., injury by 
    occupational disease, agreement when workman is under legal disability. 
    etc.
</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE 
    WORKMEN’S COMPENSATION RULES, 1924
 



 




    FORM M
 




    (See rule 48)
 




    Memorandum of Agreement
 




    It is hereby submitted that on the ............... day of 
    ................20..... personal injury was caused to 
    ........................ residing at ................................ by 
    accident arising out of and in the course of employment in 
    ....................... The said injury has resulted in temporary 
    disablement to the said workman, who is at present in receipt of wages 
    amounting to Rs.  ........................ per month/ no wages . The said 
    workman’s monthly wages prior to the accident are estimated at Rs  
    ............ The workman is subject to a legal disability by reason 
    of........................................................................................................................................... 
    .....................................................................................................................
 




    It is further submitted that  ........................., the employer of the 
    workman has agreed to pay and ........................ on behalf of the said 
    workman has agreed to accept half-monthly payments at the rate of Rs.  
    .............. for the period of the said temporary disablement. This 
    agreement is subject to the condition that the amount of the half-monthly 
    payments may be varied in accordance with the provisions of the said Act, on 
    account of an alteration  in the earnings of the said workman during 
    disablement. It is further stipulated that all rights of commutation under 
    section 7 of the said Act are unaffected by this agreements. It is, 
    therefore, requested that this memorandum be duly recorded.
 




    Dated  .................. 20......
 




    Signature of employer.
 




    Witness  ........................
 




    Signature of workman  ........................
 




    Witness  ........................
 




    Note.—An 
    application  to register an agreement can be presented under the signature 
    of one party, provided that the other party has agreed to the terms. But 
    both signatures should be appended, whenever possible.
 




    Receipt to be filled in when the money has actually been paid
 




    In accordance with the above agreement, I have this day received the sum of 
    Rs.......
 




    Revenue
 




    Stamp             
 




    .....................Workman.
 





 





 




    Dated  ................... 20....
 




    The money has been paid and this receipt signed in my presence.
 




    ...................................Witness.
 




    Note.—This 
    form may be varied to suit special cases, e.g., injury by 
    occupational disease, etc.

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE 
    WORKMEN’S COMPENSATION RULES, 1924
 



 




    FORM N
 




    (See 
    rule 49)
 




    Whereas an agreement to pay compensation is said to have been reached 
    between  ........................ and  ........................and  whereas 
    ........................has/have applied for registration of the agreement 
    under section 28 of the Workmen’s Compensation Act, 1923, notice is hereby 
    given that the said agreement will be taken into consideration on  
    .................... 20...., and that any objections to the registration of 
    the said agreement should be made on that date. In the absence of valid 
    objections it is my intention to proceed to the registration of the 
    agreement.
 




    Dated ................... 20.....
 




    Commissioner. 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 


THE 
    WORKMEN’S COMPENSATION RULES, 1924
 



 




    FORM O
 




    (See rules 49 and 50)
 




    Take notice that registration of the agreement to  pay compensation is said 
    to have been reached between you ........................ 
    and........................on  the .................20.... has been refused 
    for the following reasons, namely :—
 




    ...............................................................................................................................................................
 




    ...............................................................................................................................................................
 




    Dated.................... 20....
 




    Commissioner
</form><form>
 


THE 
    WORKMEN’S COMPENSATION RULES, 1924
 



 


FORM P
 


(See rule 50)
 


Whereas an 
    agreement to pay compensation is said to have been reached between   
    ........................ and ........................ and whereas 
    ........................has /have applied for registration of the agreement 
    under section 28 of the Workmen’s Compensation Act, 1923, and whereas it 
    appears to me that the said agreement ought not to be registered for the 
    following reasons, namely:—
 



    ..................................................................................................................................................................... 
    an opportunity will be afforded to your showing of cause on 
    ..................19...../20....., why the said agreement should be 
    registered. If no adequate cause is shown on that date registration of the 
    agreement  will be refused.
 


Dated.................. 
 


Commissioner. 
</form><form>
 


THE 
    WORKMEN’S COMPENSATION RULES, 1924
 



 




    FORM Q
 




    (See rule 50)
 




    Whereas an agreement to pay compensation is said to have been reached 
    between ........................ and........................and whereas 
    ........................ has/have applied for registration of the agreement 
    under section 28 of the Workman’s Compensation Act, 1923, and whereas it 
    appears to me that the said agreement ought not to be registered for the 
    following reasons, namely:—
 




    ...........................................................................................................................................................   
    ...........................................................................................................................................................................
 




    an opportunity will be afforded to the said ........................of 
    showing cause on  ....................20..... why the said agreement should 
    be registered. Any representation which you have to make with regard to the 
    said agreement should be made on that date. If adequate cause is then shown, 
    the agreement may be registered.
 




    Dated  ...................20.....
 




    Commissioner
</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE 
    WORKMEN’S COMPENSATION RULES, 1924
 



 




    FORM R
 




    (See rule 52)
 




    Register of Agreements for the Year 20.............
 
 
 Serial 
        Number
 Date of 
        Agreement
 Date of 
        Registration
 Employer 
        Workman
 Initials 
        of Commissioner
 Reference to order rectifying the register

 
   

 
 

 
 

 
 

 
  
  
  
  
  


 

  




    Employer.
 

 
 




    *An employer desiring to be made a party to the proceedings should strike 
    out the words “do not”.
 

 

 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>