<act><title>


The Air Force Rules, 19691</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Air Force Rules, 1969. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    shall come into force on such date as the Central Government may, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, appoint in this behalf. 
 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “Act” means the Air Force Act, 
    1950;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “Form” means a Form set forth in 
    the Schedule;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “minor punishment” means 
    punishment inflicted without the intervention of the court-martial under 
    section 82 or section 86;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    “proper air force authority” when 
    used in relation to any power, duty, act or matter means such air force 
    authority as, in pursuance of the Act or these rules or the regulations for 
    the air force or the usages of the service, exercises or performs that power 
    or duty or is concerned with the Act or matter;  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    “Schedule” means a Schedule 
    appended to these rules;  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    “section” means a section of the 
    Act.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Reports and applications.—Any 
    report or application directed by these rules shall be made to a superior 
    authority, or proper air force authority, shall be made in writing through 
    the proper channel, unless the authority on account of exigencies of the 
    service or otherwise, dispenses with the writing.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Forms set forth in schedule.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Forms with such variations as the circumstances of each case require, 
    may be used for the respective purposes therein mentioned and if used shall 
    be sufficient, but a deviation from such forms shall not, by reason only of 
    such deviation, render any charge, warrant, order, proceedings or other 
    document invalid.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An 
    omission of any such Form shall not, by reason only of such omission, render 
    any act or thing invalid.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    notes to, and instructions in, the Forms shall be considered as instructions 
    which it is expedient to follow in all cases to which such notes and 
    instructions apply, but shall not have the force of the rules.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Exercise of power vested in holder of air force appointment.—Any 
    power or jurisdiction conferred on, and any act or thing to be done by, or 
    before any person holding any air force appointment may be exercised by, or 
    done by, or before any other person for the time being authorised in that 
    behalf according to the usages of the service.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Cases unprovided for.—In 
    any case not provided for these rules such cases shall be adopted as appears 
    best calculated to justice.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Enrolling officers and form of enrolment.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The following officers shall be enrolment officers for the purposes of 
    sections 13 and 14, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    all recruiting officers;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    all assistant recruiting 
    officers;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the Officer Commanding a unit of 
    the Air Force.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Form of enrolment set forth in the First Schedule is prescribed for the 
    purposes of sections 13 and 14.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Persons to be attested.—All 
    combatants shall, when reported fit for the duties of their trade, be 
    attested as provided in section 16.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Oath or affirmation to be taken on attestation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The oath or affirmation to be taken on attestation shall be in one of the 
    following form or in such other forms to the same purport as the attesting 
    officer ascertains to be in accordance with the religion of the person to be 
    attested or otherwise binding on his conscience.  
 
Form of Oath  
 
I 
    ..................do swear in the name of God that I will bear true faith 
    and allegiance to the Constitution of India as by law established and that I 
    will as in duty bound honestly and faithfully serve in the Air Force of the 
    Union of India, and go wherever ordered by air, land or sea, and that I will 
    observe and obey all commands of the President of the Union of India and the 
    commands of any officer set over me even to the peril of my life.  
  
 
Form of Affirmation  
 
I 
    ..................do solemnly affirm that I will bear true faith and 
    allegiance to the Constitution of India as by law established and that I 
    will as in duty bound, honestly and faithfully serve in the Air Force of the 
    Union of India and go wherever ordered by air, land or sea, and that I will 
    observe and obey all commands of the President of the Union of India and the 
    commands of any officer set over me even to the peril of my life.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    oath or affirmation prescribed in this rule shall, whenever practicable be 
    administered by the commanding officer of the person to be attested or in 
    the presence of such commanding officer by a person empowered by him to 
    administer it in the manner described in section 17. If it is not so 
    administered, it may be administered by a magistrate, a recruiting officer 
    or an assistant recruiting officer.  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>10</number> Discharge not to 
    be delayed.—Every 
    person enrolled under the Act shall as soon as he becomes entitled under the 
    conditions of his enrolment to be discharged, be so discharged with all 
    convenient speed:  
 
Provided 
    that a person shall not be so entitled to be discharged during period during 
    which the Central Government, by a notification in this behalf suspends the 
    entitlement to discharge in respect either of all the persons enrolled under 
    the Act, or of any class of such persons to which he belongs].  
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Discharge certificate.—A 
    certificate furnished in accordance with the provisions of section 23 
    hereinafter called a “discharge certificate”, may be so furnished either by 
    personal delivery thereof by or on behalf of the commanding officer of the 
    person dismissed, removed, discharged, retired or released or by its 
    transmission by registered post to such person.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Date from which retirement discharge, release, removal or dismissal 
    otherwise than by sentence of a court-martial takes effect.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The dismissal of a person subject to the Act, whose dismissal otherwise than 
    by sentence of court-martial is duly authorised, or the retirement, 
    discharge, release or removal of a person so subject, whose retirement 
    discharge, release or removal as the case may be, is duly authorised, shall 
    be carried out by the commanding officer of such person with all convenient 
    speed. The competent authority may, when authorising the dismissal 
    retirement, discharge, release or removal, specify any further date from 
    which it shall take effect:  
 
Provided 
    that if no such date is specified, it shall take effect from the date on 
    which it was duly authorised, or from the date on which the dismissed, 
    retired, discharged, released or removed person ceased to do air force duty, 
    whichever is later.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    retirement, removal, release discharge or dismissal of a person subject to 
    the Act shall not be retrospective.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Release.—A 
    person subject to the Act may be released from the air force in accordance 
    with these rules, or in accordance with any orders or instructions made in 
    that behalf by or under the authority of the Central Government.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Retirement.—Subject 
    to the other provisions of these rules, a person subject to the Act may be 
    retired in accordance with the terms and conditions of his service by or 
    under the authority of the Central Government.  
 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
    <number>15</number> Authorities empowered to authorize discharge. - 
<section><number>1</number> Each of the 
    authorised specified in column 3 of the Table below shall be the authority 
    competent in respect of persons subject to the Act specified in column 1 
    thereof for the cause specified in column 2 and in the manner specified in 
    column 4, to discharge such persons from the service.
 </section><section><number>2</number> 
    Any power conferred by this rule on any of the aforesaid authorities may 
    also be exercised by any other authority superior to it.
 
 
 


 
 
Clause 
 
Cause Discharge
 
Competent Authority to Authorize 
        discharge
 
Special Instructions

 
 
1
 
2
 
3
 
4

 
  
  
  
  

 
 
        Persons enrolled under the Act who have attested.
 
        (a) At his own request on transfer to the pension establishment 

 
        Commanding Office.
 
        To be carried out in accordance with the conditions of enrolment.

 
  
 
        (b) On fulfilling the conditions of the enrolment.
 
        Commanding Officer
 
        To be carried out in accordance with the conditions of enrolment.

 
  
 
        (c) Having been found medically unfit for further service.
 
        Commanding Officer
 
        To be carried out only on recommendations of the Invaliding Board.

 
  
 
        (d) On transfer to the pension establishment or on discharge with 
        gratuity otherwise than at his own request or under item (c)
 
        Officer Commanding, Air Force Record Office.
 
        .........

 
  
 
        (e) Having been found inefficient in his rank or trade and being 
        un-willing to accept reduction or remustering.
 
        Air Officer i/c Administrations.
 
An airman reported as inefficient will, as 
        far as vacancies allow be permitted to remuster and/or accept reduction 
        in any rank and trade for which he is reported as suitable. If no such 
        vacancy exists or if he declines to accept such remustering or reduction 
        he will be discharged under this item.

 
  
 
        (f) At his own request before fulfilling the conditions of the enrolment
 
        Director of Personnel (Airmen)

 
  
 
        (g) His services no longer required :
  
 
        ..................

 
  
 (i) 
        Due to reduction in establishment or to reorganization.
 
        Director of Personnel (Airmen).
 
        ................

 
  
 
        (ii) Unsuitable for retention in the Air Force.
 
        Air Office i/c Administration.
 
        .............

 
  
 
        (h) All other classes of discharge.
 
        Do
  

 
 
        Persons enrolled under the Act who have not been attested.
 (i) 
        At his own request before fulfilling the conditions of his enrolment.
 (i) 
        Air or other Officer i/c of Command
 
The Competent authority mentioned in the 
        preceding column will exercise this power only when he is satisfied as 
        to the bona fides of the application and that the total strength of the 
        Air Force will not thereby be unduly reduced.

 
  
  
 
        (ii) Director or Personnel (Airmen) in case of units directly under Air 
        Head-Quarters.

 
  
 
        (j) Unlikely to make an efficient airmen.
 
        Commanding Officer
 
        Applicable to airmen under going training for airmen

 
  
 
        (k) All other classes of discharge.
 
        Commanding Officer
  

 
  



  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Dismissal or removal of officers for misconduct.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    An officer may be dismissed or removed from service for misconduct by the 
    Central Government, but before doing so and subject to the provisions of 
    sub-rule (2) he shall be given an opportunity to show cause against such 
    action.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where the dismissal or removal of an officer is proposed on ground of 
    misconduct which has led to his conviction by a criminal court, or where the 
    Central Government is satisfied that for reasons to be recorded in writing, 
    it is not expedient or reasonably practicable to do so, it shall not be 
    necessary to give an opportunity to the officer of showing cause against his 
    dismissal or removal.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Where an officer has been convicted by a criminal court and the Central 
    Government after examining the judgment of the criminal court in his case 
    and considering the recommendation about him of the Chief of the Air Staff, 
    is of opinion that further retention of such officer in the service is 
    undesirable, that Government may dismiss or remove such officer from the 
    service.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> In 
    any case not falling under sub-rule (3), when the Chief of the Air Staff 
    after considering the reports on an officer’s misconduct, is of opinion that 
    the trial of the officer by a court-martial is inexpedient or impracticable 
    but the further retention of the officer in the service is undesirable, he 
    shall so inform the officer and subject to the provisions of sub-rule (5) 
    furnish to the officer all reports adverse to him calling upon him to submit 
    in writing within a reasonable period to be specified, his explanation in 
    defence and any reasons which he may wish to put forward against his 
    dismissal or removal.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Chief of the Air Staff may withhold from disclosure any report adverse to an 
    officer or any portion thereof, if in his opinion its disclosure is not in 
    the interests of the security of the State.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> If 
    no explanation is received from the officer within the specified period or 
    if the explanation received is considered to be not satisfactory or, when so 
    directed by the Central Government, the reports against the officer as well 
    as his explanation if any, shall be submitted to the Central Government by 
    the Chief of the Air Staff together with his recommendation as to the 
    dismissal or removal of the officer from the service.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The 
    Central Government may, after considering the reports against the officer 
    and his defence, if any, and the recommendations of the Chief of the Air 
    Staff, dismiss or remove the officer from service.  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> In 
    this rule and in rule 17 the Chief of the Air Staff while submitting a case 
    to the Central Government may recommend that instead of removing an officer 
    from service, he may be compulsorily retired or that he should be called 
    upon to resign his commission, and the Central Government in passing orders 
    may instead of removing an officer from service, compulsorily retire him or 
    give the officer an option to submit his resignation, and if he refuses to 
    do so, remove him from the service.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Removal from service of officers on grounds other than misconduct.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    When the Chief of the Air Staff is satisfied that an officer is unfit to be 
    retained in service due to inefficiency, physical disability or other ground 
    other than misconduct, the officer—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    shall be so informed;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    shall be furnished with the 
    particulars of all matters adverse to him; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    shall be called upon to submit in 
    writing, within a reasonable period, any reasons he may wish to urge for not 
    being removed from the service:  
 
Provided 
    that all or any of clauses (a), (b) and (c) shall not apply if the Central 
    Government is satisfied that for reasons, to be recorded by it in writing, 
    it is not expedient or reasonably practicable to comply with the provisions 
    thereof:  
 
Provided 
    further that the Chief of the Air Staff may withhold from disclosure the 
    particulars of any matter adverse to the officer, or any portion thereof, if 
    in his opinion, its disclosure is not in the interests of the security of 
    the State.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    no reply is received from the officer within the specified period, or the 
    reasons submitted by him are considered not satisfactory by the Chief of the 
    Air Staff, the matter shall be submitted to the Central Government for 
    orders, together with the explanation of the officer, if any, and the 
    recommendation of the Chief of the Air Staff for the removal of the officer 
    from the service.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Central Government may, after considering the explanation, if any, of the 
    officer and the recommendations of the Chief of the Air Staff, and after 
    satisfying itself that the failure, where applicable, to disclose matters 
    adverse to the officer was in the interests of the security of the State, 
    may remove or compulsorily retire the officer from the service.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Dismissal or removal of a person subject to the Act other than an officer.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Save in a case where a person subject to the Act other than an officer is 
    dismissed or removed from the service on the ground of conduct which had led 
    to his conviction by a criminal court or a court-martial, no such person 
    shall be dismissed or removed under sub-section (1) or sub-section (3) of 
    section 20 unless he has been informed of the particulars of the cause of 
    action against him and allowed reasonable time to state in writing any 
    reasons he may have to urge against his dismissal or removal from the 
    service.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rule (1), if in the opinion of the 
    officer competent to order the dismissal or removal of such person, it is 
    not expedient or reasonably practicable to comply with the provisions of 
    sub-rule (1), he may, after certifying to that effect, order the dismissal 
    or removal.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All 
    cases of dismissal or removal without complying with the procedure 
    prescribed in sub-rule (1) shall, without delay, be reported to the Central 
    Government.  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Membership of Organisations.—No 
    person subject to the Act shall, without the express sanction of the Central 
    Government,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    be a member of, or associated in 
    any way with, any society, institution, association or organisation that is 
    not recognised as part of the Armed Forces of the Union or is not of a 
    purely social, recreational or religious 
1[or 
    educational] nature.  
 
Explanation.—If 
    any question arises as to whether any society, institution, association or 
    organisation is of a purely social, recreational or religious nature, the 
    decision of the Central Government thereon shall be final.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    be a member of or be associate in any 
    way with any trade union or labour union, or any class of trade or labour 
    unions.
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>20</number> 
    Political and other activities.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No person subject to the Act shall attend, address, or take active part in, 
    any meeting or demonstration held for party or political purposes, or belong 
    to or join, or subscribe in aid of, any political association or movement.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No 
    person subject to the Act shall issue an address to electors or in any other 
    manner publicly announce himself or allow himself to be publicly announced 
    as a candidate or as a prospective candidate for election to Parliament, 
    Legislature of a State, local authority, or other public body, or act as a 
    member of a candidate’s election committee, or in any way actively prosecute 
    a candidate’s interest.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>21</number> 
    Communications to Press, Lectures etc.—No 
    person subject to the Act shall—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    publish in any form whatever or 
    communicate directly or indirectly to the press any matter on a service 
    subject or containing any service information, or publish or cause to be 
    published any book or letter or article or other document on such matter or 
    containing such information, without the previous sanction of the 
1[Central 
    Government]; or  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    deliver a lecture or wireless 
    address on a service subject or containing any information or views on any 
    service subject without the previous sanction of the 
1[Central 
    Government].  
 
Explanation.—For 
    the purpose of this rule, service information and service subject mean 
    information or subject, as the case may be, concerning the forces, the 
    defence or the external relation of the Union.
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Manner and extent of custody pending trial or confirmation of court-martial 
    proceedings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person subject to the Act who has been ordered into air force custody by 
    a competent authority may be taken into such custody in accordance with the 
    usages of the service:  
 
Provided 
    that while being held for trail or after trial pending confirmation of the 
    proceedings, the arrest or confinement imposed upon him shall not be more 
    rigorous than the circumstances require to ensure his physical fitness and 
    security.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Detention in air force custody beyond a total period of sixty days whether 
    continuously or in broken periods, of a person subject to the Act, who is 
    not on active service and for whose trial a court-martial has not assembled, 
    shall require the sanction of the Chief of the Air Staff or any other 
    officer duly authorised, with the approval of the Central Government, by the 
    Chief of the Air Staff in that behalf.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Chief of the Air Staff or such other officer may sanction further detention 
    of such person as is described in sub-rule (2) for a specific period, which 
    he may extend from time to time, provided that the total period of detention 
    under sub-rule (2) and this sub-rule, whether continuous or broken, shall 
    not exceed ninety days.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> No 
    such person as is described in sub-rule (2) shall be detained in air force 
    custody beyond a period of ninety days, whether continuously or in broken 
    period except with the approval of the Central Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> As 
    soon as the proceedings of a court-martial have been received by an officer 
    having powers to confirm them, that officer shall, as soon as may be, order 
    the release (without prejudice to re-arrest) of the accused if the finding 
    of the court-martial is “not guilty” on the charge, or where there are more 
    charges than one, on all the charges, on which he was tried.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> 
    Where the sentence awarded by a court-martial is lower in the scale of 
    punishments set out in section 73, than dismissal, the officer referred to 
    in sub-rule (5) shall either order the release of the accused person without 
    prejudice to re-arrest or at his discretion, order that the accused person 
    shall be kept under open arrest.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> No 
    person shall be detained in air force custody pending confirmation of the 
    proceedings of a court-martial, for a period in excess of the term of 
    imprisonment or detention to which the court-martial has sentenced him.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>23</number> 
    Delay report.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In every case where a person subject to the Act, who is not on active 
    service, is in air force custody for a period longer than eight days, 
    whether continuously or in broken periods, without a court-martial for his 
    trial having been assembled, or without a punishment having been awarded to 
    him under section 82 or section 86, the Commanding officer shall make a 
    report in the delay report form contained in the Second Schedule, to the 
    officer empowered to convene a general or district court-martial for the 
    trial of such person. Such report shall be made at interval of every eight 
    days until a court-martial is assembled or the case is disposed under 
    section 82, or section 86 or such person is released from custody, as the 
    case may be.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    copy of each of the third and subsequent reports submitted under sub-rule 
    (1) will be forwarded directly to the 

    1[Deputy Chief Legal 
    Adviser] of the command concerned, or in the case of persons belonging or 
    attached to the Air Headquarters or a unit directly under Air Headquarters, 
    to the 

    1[Chief Legal 
    Adviser].
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Disposal of the charge or adjournment for taking down the summary of 
    evidence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every charge against a person subject to the Act shall be heard in the 
    presence of the accused. The accused shall have full liberty to 
    cross-examine any witness against him, and to call any witnesses and make 
    any statement in his defence.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    commanding officer shall dismiss a charge brought before him if, in his 
    opinion, the evidence does not show that some offence under the Act has been 
    committed, and may do so if, in his discretion, he thinks the charge ought 
    not to be proceeded with.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> At 
    the conclusion of the hearing of a charge, if the commanding officer is of 
    opinion that the charge ought to be proceeded with, he shall, without 
    unnecessary delay, either:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    dispose of the case summarily; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    
1[refer 
    the case to the proper superior air force authority for sanction under 
    section 83; or]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    adjourn the case for the purpose 
    of having the evidence reduced to writing.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Where the case is adjourned for the purpose of having the evidence reduced 
    in writing, at the adjourned hearing the evidence of the witnesses who were 
    present and gave evidence before the commanding officer, whether against or 
    for the accused, and of any other person whose evidence appears to be 
    relevant shall be taken down in writing in the presence and hearing of the 
    accused before the commanding officer or such officer as he directs.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    accused may put questions in cross-examination to any witness, and the 
    questions with the answers shall be added in writing to the evidence taken 
    down.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    evidence of each witness when taken down, as provided in sub-rules (4) and 
    (5), shall be read over to him, and shall be signed by him, or if he cannot 
    write his name, shall be attested by his mark and witnessed. Any statement 
    of the accused 

    2[***] shall be added 
    in writing and read over to him.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The 
    evidence of the witnesses and the statement, if any, of the accused shall be 
    recorded in the English language. If the witness or accused, as the case may 
    be, does not understand English the evidence or statement, as recorded; 
    shall be interpreted to him in a language which he understands.  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> If a 
    person cannot be compelled to attend as a witness, or if owing to the 
    exigencies of service or any other grounds (including the expense and loss 
    of time involved), the attendance of any witness cannot, in the opinion of 
    the commanding officer or the officer taking the summary (to be certified in 
    writing by the commanding officer or such officer), be readily procured, a 
    written statement of his evidence purporting to be signed by him may be read 
    to the accused and included in the summary of evidence.  
 


    3[(9) (a) Any witness 
    who is not subject to the air force law may be summoned by order under the 
    hand of the Commanding Officer of the accused  to attend the hearing of the 
    charge under sub-rule (1) or to attend the adjourned hearing for the purpose 
    of having the evidence reduced to writing under sub- 
    rule (4).  
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The 
    summons shall be in Form ’C-1’ as provided in the Third Schedule.]
 
 







 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Remand of accused.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The evidence and statement, if any, taken down in writing in pursuance of 
    rule 24 (hereinafter referred to as the summary of evidence) shall be 
    considered by the commanding officer, who thereupon shall either—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    remand the accused for trial by 
    court-martial; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    
1[refer 
    the case to the proper superior air force authority for sanction under 
    section 83 or disposal under section 86; or]  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    if he thinks it desirable, 
    re-hear the case and dispose it of summarily.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    the accused is remanded for trial by court-martial, the commanding officer 
    shall without unnecessary delay apply to the proper air force authority to 
    convene a court-martial.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    summary of evidence, or a true copy thereof, shall be furnished to the 
    convening authority with the application to convene a court-martial, and 
    shall be laid before the court-martial before which the accused is tried on 
    the assembly of the court.
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>26</number> 
    Application of rules 24 and 25 to officers exercising powers of a commanding 
    officer.—The 
    provisions of rules 24 and 25 shall, so far as practicable, also apply to an 
    officer exercising the powers of a commanding officer.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>27</number> Action by 
    officer having power to convene a district court-martial.—An 
    officer having power to convene a district court martial to whom an 
    application for the convening of court martial is made or to whom a case is 
    referred under the provisions of clause (b) of sub-rule 
<section><number>1</number> of rule 25 may, 
    at his discretion,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    authorise in writing the 
    commanding officer or other officer exercising the powers of a commanding 
    officer to dismiss the charge or dispose of the case summarily; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    refer the case to a superior 
    authority; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    order the assembly of a district 
    court-martial for the trial of the accused person.]
 
 






 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>28</number> Action by 
    officer having power to convene a general court-martial.—An 
    officer having power to convene a general court-martial to whom application 
    for the convening of a court-martial is made, or to whom a case is referred 
    under the provisions of clause (b) of sub-rule 
<section><number>1</number> of rule 25, or of clause 
    (b) of rule 27, may, at his discretion,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    return the case to the Commanding 
    Officer or other officer exercising the powers of a Commanding Officer 
    authorising such officer in writing to dismiss the charge or dispose of the 
    case summarily; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    deal with the case summarily, as 
    provided in rule 31; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    order the assembly of a 
    court-martial for the trial of the accused person; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    refer the case to a superior 
    authority].
 
 





 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>29</number> 
    Limitation of powers of minor punishment according to rank.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A commanding officer or other officer exercising the powers of a commanding 
    officer, if of the rank of Squadron Leader or above, may, without the
    intervention of a court-martial, award the minor punishments specified in section 82.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    commanding officer, or other officer exercising the powers of a commanding 
    officer, of the rank of Flight Lieutenant, shall have the powers of 
    punishment specified in the said section, provided that he shall not award 
    detention or field punishment for a period exceeding seven days.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A 
    commanding officer, or other officer exercising the powers of a commanding 
    officer, who is below the rank of Flight Lieutenant shall have the powers of 
    imposing punishment specified in the said section, except the following in 
    the case of non-commissioned officers, namely,—  
 <subsection>
               <number>a</number>    severe reprimand;  
 </subsection><subsection>
               <number>b</number>    deprivation of 
    acting rank; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
               <number>c</number>    penal deduction 
    under clause (g) of section 92;  
 
and, in the case of persons below 
    non-commissioned ranks, forfeiture of badge pay:  
 
Provided 
    that such officer shall not award detention or field punishment for a period 
    exceeding seven days, or confinement to the camp for a period exceeding ten 
    days.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rules (2) and (3), where a 
    commanding officer or other officer exercising the powers of a commanding 
    officer below the rank of Squadron Leader, an officer superior in command to 
    such commanding or other officer, may, if he considers desirable, restrict 
    the powers under the said sub-rule of such commanding officer or other 
    officer to any extent as he thinks fit.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>30</number> Powers of minor punishment of 
    Subordinate Commanders. - 
<section><number>1</number> Subject to the provisions of the sub-rule 
    (2), an office other than a commanding officer, who has with the consent of 
    the Central Government been specified by the Chief of the Air Staff as a 
    "Subordinate Commander," may award such minor punishments and to such extent 
    as specified in this rule.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The subordinate commanders specified in 
    column 1 of the Table below if authorized in this behalf by the commanding 
    officer or other officer exercising the powers of commanding officer, may 
    award to the persons specified in column 2 the minor punishments specified 
    in the column 3 thereof provided that, then an officer of the rank of Flight 
    Lieutenant is officiating in an appointment normally held by an officer of 
    higher rank, or when no subordinate commander of the rank of Squadron Leader 
    or above is available, an officer of the rank of Flight Lieutenant shall not 
    be authorized to award the punishment of fine.
 
 
 
 

 
 
 
Authority Competent to award punishment
 
 
Person who may be punished
 
 
Punishment

 
 
 
1
 
 
2
 
 
3

 
 
  
 
  
 
  

 
 
 </section><section>
<number>1</number> Officer of the rank of Flight 
        Lieutenant or above.
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> Non-commissioned Officer.
 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number> Reprimand
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number> Admonition.

 
 
  
 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> Airman below non-commissioned rank of 
        the enrolment.
 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number> Confinement of the Camp for the period 
        not exceeding seven days.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number> Extra Guards or duties not exceeding 
        in 3 in numbers.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number> Admonition.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iv</number> Fine not exceeding 4 days pay 
        provided that an airman shall not be fined more that seven days pay in 
        anyone month.

 
 
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Officer below the rank of Flight 
        Lieutenant.
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> Non-commissioned Officer.
 
 
Admonition

 
 
  
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> Airmen below non-commissioned officer.
 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number> Confinement to the Camp for a period 
        not exceeding 3 days.

 
 
  
 
  
 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number> Extra Guards or duties not exceeding 
        3 in number

 
 
 
 
 
        (iii) Admonition.

 
 
 
        v



 
  


</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>31</number> 
    Summary disposal of charge against officers and warrant officers.—
<section><number>1</number>
    

    1[When a charge 
    against an officer or warrant officer is to be summarily disposed of under 
    section 86,] a copy of the summary of evidence shall be delivered to him 
    free of charge as soon as practicable after its preparation, and in any case 
    not less than forty-eight hours before such disposal.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    officer dealing with the case summarily under section 86 shall hear the 
    witnesses, if any, in the prensence of the accused, but may dispense with 
    the hearing of every or all witnesses if the accused person consents in 
    writing thereto.  
 


    1[(3) If the accused 
    person demands that the evidence be taken on oath, the officer dealing with 
    the case summarily shall administer to each witness before he gives his 
    evidence, the oath or affirmation as prescribed in rule 118, but the accused 
    person shall not be sworn.]  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    accused may put questions in cross-examination to any witness, call any 
    witnesses and make a statement in his defence.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    proceedings shall be recorded as far as practicable in accordance with Form 
    D.1 or Form D.2 (as may be appropriate) of the forms for use for summary 
    disposal of charges against officers and warrant officers contained in the 
    Fourth Schedule and in every case in which a punishment is awarded, the 
    original and a certified true copy of the proceedings together with the 
    summary of evidence shall be forwarded through the proper channel to the 
    superior air force authority as defined in section 89.
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>32</number> 
    Summary award of punishment by commanding or other officer.—When 
    a commanding officer, or other officer having power to dispose of an offence 
    summarily, has once awarded a punishment for that offence, he cannot 
    afterwards increase the punishment for that offence.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>33</number> Revision of 
    minor punishments awarded under section 82.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If a minor punishment awarded under section 82 appears to the Central 
    Government, the Chief of the Air Staff, or any officer superior in command 
    to the officer who awarded the punishment, to be wholly illegal, such 
    athority shall direct that the award be ancelled and the entry in the 
    records of the accused be expunged.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    such minor punishment appears to the authority specified in sub-rule (1) to 
    be in exess of the punishment authorised by law, such authority may vary the 
    punishment awarded so that it shall not be in excess of the punishment 
    authorised by law, and the entry in the records of the acused shall be 
    varied acordingly.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If 
    such minor punishment appears to the authority specified in sub-rule (1) to 
    be unjust or too severe having regard to all the circumstanes of the case, 
    such authority may mitigate or remit the punishment awarded or ommute that 
    punishment for any other punishment or punishments lower in the scale laid 
    down in section 82, which the commanding officer or other officer exercising 
    powers under that section could have validly awarded, and such mitigation, 
    remission or commutation shall be entered in the records of the accused:  
 
Provided 
    that for the purpose of this sub-rule, the punishment of field punishment 
    shall be deemed to be higher in scale than detention:  
 
Provided 
    further that the punishment of field punishment shall not be commuted for 
    punishment of detention for a term exceeding the term of such field 
    punishment or detention shall not be commuted for a punishment of 
    confinement to the camp for a term exceeding the term of such field 
    punishment or detention.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Any 
    authority specified in sub-rule (1) may, in addition to or without any order 
    passed under sub-rule (1), (2) or (3), issue such direction in any case as 
    may appear to such authority to be necessary for doing justice in the 
    matter.]
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>34</number> 
    Charge-sheet and charge.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    A charge-sheet shall, so far as practicable, conform to the form of 
    charge-sheet specified in the Fifth Schedule and shall contain the whole 
    issue or issues to be tried by a court-martial at one time.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    charge means an accusation contained in a charge-sheet that a person subject 
    to the Act has been guilty of an offence.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A 
    charge-sheet may contain one charge or several charges.
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>35</number> 
    Commencement of charge-sheet.—Every 
    charge-sheet shall begin with the name and description of the person 
    charged, and state, in the case of an officer, his rank, name, number, and 
    unit, and in the case of a warrant officer, or other enrolled person, his 
    number, rank, name and unit. When the accused person does not belong to the 
    regular air force, the charge-sheet shall show by the description of him, or 
    directly by an express averment, that he is subject to the Act in respect of 
    the offence charged.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>36</number> 
    Contents of charge.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Each charge shall state one offence only, and in no case shall an offence be 
    described in the alternative in the same charge.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Each 
    charge shall be divided into two parts—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   
    the statement of the offence; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   
    the statement of the particulars of the act, neglect, or omission 
    constituting the offence.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    offence shall be stated, if not a civil offence, as nearly as practicable, 
    in the words of the Act, and if a civil offence, in such words as 
    sufficiently describe that offence, but not necessarily in technical words.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    particulars shall state such circumstances respecting the alleged offence as 
    will enable the accused to know what act, neglect or omission is intended to 
    be proved against him as constituting the offence.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    particulars in one charge may be framed wholly or partly by a reference to 
    the particulars in another charge, and in that case so much of the latter 
    particulars as are so referred to shall be deemed to form part of the first 
    mentioned charge as well as of the other charge.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> 
    Where it is intended to prove any facts in respect of which any deduction 
    from pay and allowances can be awarded as a consequence of the offence 
    charged, the particulars shall state those facts, and the sum of the loss or 
    damage it is intended to charge.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>37</number> Signature on 
    charge-sheet.—The 
    charge-sheet shall be signed by the commanding officer of the accused or by 
    the officer who, in respect of the accused, is an officer empowered under 
    section 82 to exercise the powers of a commanding officer, and shall contain 
    the place and date of such signature.]
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>38</number> 
    Validity of charge-sheet.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A charge-sheet shall not be invalid by reason only of any mistake in the 
    name or description of the person charged, if he does not object to the 
    charge-sheet during the trial, and it is not shown that injustice has been 
    done to the person charged.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    the construction of a charge-sheet or charge, there shall be presumed in 
    favour of supporting the same every proposition which may reasonably be 
    presumed to be impliedly included though not expressed therein.  
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>39</number> 
    Opportunity for accused to prepare defence.—An 
    accused person for whose trial a court-martial has been ordered to assemble 
    shall be afforded proper opportunity of preparing his defence, and shall be 
    allowed free communication with his witnesses, and with any friend or legal 
    adviser whom he may wish to consult.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>40</number> 
    Warning of accused for trial.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The accused before he is arraigned shall be informed by an officer of every 
    charge on which he is to be tried; and also that, on his giving the names of 
    witnesses whom he desires to call in his defence, reasonable steps will be 
    taken for procuring their attendance, and those steps shall be taken 
    accordingly.  
 
The 
    interval between his being so informed of the charges against him and his 
    arraignment must be such as to allow him to have his witnesses present, and 
    to consider his defence.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    officer at the time of so informing the accused shall give him a copy of the 
    charge-sheet, 

    1[and if the recording 
    of summary of evidence has not been dispensed with under rule 42, a copy of 
    the smmary of evidence,] and, if he desires it, a vernacular translation of 
    the same, and shall, if necessary, read and explain to him the charges 
    brought against him.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If 
    he desires it, a list of the names, ranks, and units of the officers who are 
    to form the court, and where officers in waiting are named, also of these 
    officers, will be given to the accused.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If it 
    appears to the court that the accused is liable to be prejudiced at his 
    trial by any non-compliance with this rule, the court shall take steps and, 
    if necessary, adjourn to avoid the accused being so prejudiced.
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>41</number> Joint trial of 
    several accused persons.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any number of accused persons may be charged jointly and tried together for 
    an offence averred to have been committed by them colletively.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any 
    number of accused persons, whether charged, jointly or not, may be tried 
    together for an offence averred to have been committed by one or more of 
    them and to have been abetted by the other or others.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Where the accused persons are so charged under sub-rule (1) or (2), any one 
    or more of them may at the same time be charged with and tried for any other 
    offence averred to have been committed individually or collectively:  
 
Provided 
    that all the said offences are based on the same facts, or form, or are part 
    of, a series of offences of the same or similar character.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> In 
    the cases mentioned above, notice of the intention to try the accused 
    persons together shall be given to each of the accused persons at the time 
    of his being informed of the charge, and any accused person may claim, 
    either by notice to the authority convening the court or when arraigned 
    before the court, by notice to the court, that he or some other accused 
    person be tried separately on one or more of the charges included in the 
    charge-sheet, on the ground that the evidene of one or more of the other 
    accused persons proposed to be tried together with him will be material to 
    his defence, or that otherwise he would be prejudiced or embarrassed in his 
    defence, the convening authority or court, if satisfied that the evidence 
    will be material or that the accused person may be prejudiced or embarrassed 
    in his defence as aforesaid, and if the nature of the charge admits of this, 
    shall allow the claim, and such accused person, or, as the case may be, the 
    other accused person or persons whose separate trial has been claimed, shall 
    be tried separately.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> 
    Where any such claim as is referred to in sub-rule (4) has been made and 
    disallowed by the authority convening the court, or by the court, the 
    disallowance of such claim shall not be a ground for refusing confirmation 
    of the finding or sentence unless, in the opinion of the confirming 
    authority, substantial miscarriage of justice has occurred by reason of the 
    disallowance of such claim.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Where the 
    proceedings of any court-martial in respect of any charge against an accused 
    person are not confirmed on the ground stated in sub-rule (5) such accused 
    person may be tried again on that charge.]
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>42</number> 
    Suspension of rules on the ground of the exigencies of the service or the 
    necessities of discipline.—Where 
    it appears to the officer convening a court-martial, or to the senior 
    officer on the spot, that exigencies of the service or the necessities of 
    discipline, render it impossible or inexpedient to observe any of the 
    provisions of rule 24 sub-rule (4), sub-rule (5), sub-rule (6) and sub-rule 
    (7) and of rules 25, 39 and 40 he may, by order under his hand, make a 
    declaration to that effect specifying the nature of such exigencies or 
    necessities, and thereupon the trial or other proceedings shall be as valid 
    as if the rule mentioned in such declaration had not been contained herein; 
    and the declaration may be made with respect to all or any of the provisions 
    of the rules aforesaid mentioned:  
 
Provided 
    that the accused shall have full opportunity of making his defence, and 
    shall be afforded every facility for preparing it which is practicable, 
    having due regard to the said exigencies or necessities.  
  

 
  


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>43</number> Convening of general and district court-martial. </title>— <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> [
<section><number>1</number> An officer before convening a general or district Court-Martial shall first satisfy himself that the charges to be tried by the Court-Martial are for offences within the meaning of the Act, and framed in accordance with law, and that evidence justifies a trial on those charges he may amend the charges if he deems fit, and if not so satisfied order release of the accused, or refer the case to superior authority]. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> He shall also satisfy himself that the case is a proper one to be tried by the description of court-martial he proposes to convene. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The officer convening a court-martial shall appoint or detail the officers to form the court, and may also appoint or detail such waiting officers as he thinks expedient. He may also, where he considers the services of an interpreter to be necessary, appoint or detail an interpreter to the court. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> [<number>4</number> After the convening officer has appointed or detailed the officer to form a Court-Martial under sub-rule (3), convening order of the Court-Martial and endorsement on the charge-sheet for trial of the accused by court-martial may either be signed by convening officer or by a staff officer on his behalf. The charge sheet on which the accused to be tried, the summary of evidence and the convening order for assembly of Court-Martial shall then be sent to the senior officer of Court-Martial and the Judge Advocate, if appointed.] 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>44</number> 
    Adjournment for insufficient number of officers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If, before the accused is arraigned, the full number of officers detailed 
    are not available to serve by reason of non-eligibility, disqualification, 
    challenge or otherwise, and if there are not a sufficient number of officers 
    in waiting to take the place of those unable to serve, the court shall 
    ordinarily adjourn for the purpose of fresh members being appointed; but if 
    the court is of opinion that in the interests of justice, and for the good 
    of the service, it is inexpedient so to adjourn it may, if not reduced in 
    number below the required minimum, proceed recording their reasons for so 
    doing.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    the court adjourns for the purpose of the appointment of fresh members 
    whether under these rules or otherwise, the convening officer may, if he 
    thinks fit, convene another court.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>45</number> 
    Ineligibility and disqualification of officers for court-martial.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    An officer is not eligible to serve on a court-martial unless he is subject 
    to air force law.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An 
    officer is disqualified for serving on a general or district court-martial 
    if he—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    is the officer who convened the 
    court; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    is the prosecutor, or a witness 
    for the prosecution, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    investigated the charges before 
    trial, or took down the summary of evidence or was a member of a court of 
    inquiry respecting the matters on which the charges against the accused are 
    founded, or was the flight, squadron, station, unit, or other commander who 
    made preliminary inquiry into the case, or was a member of previous 
    court-martial which tried the accused in respect of the same offence; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    is the commanding officer of the 
    accused or of the unit to which the accused is attached or belongs; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    has a personal interest in the 
    case.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    provost-marshal or assistant provost-marshal is disqualified from serving on 
    a general or district court-martial.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>46</number> 
    Composition of general court-martial.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The senior member of a general court-martial shall be of a rank not below 
    that of a Group Captain, unless in the opinion of the convening officer, to 
    be stated in the order convening the court and to be conclusive, an officer 
    of that rank is not (having due regard to the public service) available.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> All 
    members of a general court-martial for the trial of an officer shall be of 
    equal if not superior rank to the accused, unless in the opinion of the 
    convening officer, to be stated in the order convening the court and to be 
    conclusive, officers of the required rank are not (having due regard to the 
    public service) available:  
 
Provided 
    that in no case shall an officer below the rank of Flight Lieutenant be 
    appointed a member of a court-martial for the trial of an officer of or 
    above the rank of Squadron Leader.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>47</number> 
    Composition of a district court-martial.—The 
    senior member of a district court-martial shall be of a rank not below that 
    of Squadron Leader, unless in the opinion of the convening officer, to be 
    stated in the order convening the court and to be conclusive, an officer of 
    that rank is not (having due regard to the public service) available.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>48</number> 
    Units of members of court-martial.—A 
    general or district court-martial shall not be composed exclusively of 
    officers of the same unit, unless the convening officer states in the order 
    convening the court that in his opinion other officers are not (having due 
    regard to the public service) available, and in no case shall it consist 
    exclusively of officers belonging to the same unit as the accused.  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>49</number> 
    Inquiry by court as to legal constitution.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    On the court assembling, the order convening the court shall be read, and 
    also the names, rank and unit of the officers appointed to serve on the 
    court; and it shall be the first duty of the court to satisfy itself that 
    the court is duly constituted that is to say—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    that, so far as the court can 
    ascertain, the court has been convened in accordance with the Act and these 
    rules;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    that the court consists of a 
    number of officers not less than the required minimum, and, save as 
    mentioned in rule 44, not less than the number detailed;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    that each of the officers so 
    assembled is eligible and not disqualified for serving on that court-martial.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    court shall, further, if it is a general or district court-martial to which 
    a judge-advocate has been appointed, ascertain that the judge-advocate is 
    duly appointed and is not disqualified for acting at that court-martial.  
 
The 
    court, if not satisfied on the above matters, shall report its opinion to 
    the convening authority, and may adjourn for that purpose.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>50</number> 
    Inquiry by court as to amenability of accused and validity of charge.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The court, when satisfied on the above matters, shall satisfy itself in 
    respect of each charge about to be brought before them—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    that it appears to be laid 
    against a person subject to the Act and to the jurisdiction of the court, 
    and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    that each charge discloses an 
    offence under the Act and is framed in accordance with these rules, and is 
    so explicit as to enable the accused readily to understand what he has to 
    answer.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    court, if not satisfied on the above matters, shall report its opinion to 
    the convening authority and may adjourn for that purpose.  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>51</number> 
    Appearance of accused and prosecutor.—When 
    the court is satisfied as to the above facts, it shall cause the accused to 
    be brought before the court, and the prosecutor who must be a person subject 
    to air force law, shall take his place.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>52</number> 
    Proceedings for challenges of members of court.—The 
    order convening the court and the names of the presiding officer and members 
    of the court shall then be read over to the accused and he shall be asked, 
    as required by section 129, whether he objects to be tried by any officer 
    sitting on the court. Any such objections shall be disposed of in accordance 
    with the provisions of section 129:  
 
Provided 
    that—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    the accused shall state the names 
    of all the officers to whom he objects before any objection is disposed of;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    the accused may call any person 
    to give evidence in support of his objection, and such person may be 
    questioned by the accused and by the court;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    if more than one officer is 
    objected to, the objection to each officer shall be disposed of separately, 
    and the objection in respect of that officer lowest in rank shall be 
    disposed of first; and on an objection to an officer, the remaining officers 
    of the court shall in the absence of the challenged officer, vote on the 
    disposal of such objection notwithstanding that objections have also been to 
    any of those officers;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    when an objection to an officer 
    is allowed that officer shall forthwith retire, and take no further part in 
    the proceedings;  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    when an officer objected to 
    retires, and there are any officers in waiting, the vacancy shall be 
    forthwith filled by one of the officers in waiting being directed by the 
    presiding officer to serve in lieu of the retiring officer. If there is no 
    officer in waiting available the court shall proceed as directed by rule 44;  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    the eligibility, absence of 
    disqualification, and freedom from objection of an officer filling a vacancy 
    shall be ascertained by the court, as in the case of other officers 
    appointed to serve on the court.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>53</number> 
    Swearing or affirming of members.—As 
    soon as the court is constituted with the proper number of officers who are 
    not objected to, or the objections in respect of whom have been overruled, 
    an oath or affirmation shall be administered to every member in one of the 
    following forms or in such other form as the same purport as the court 
    ascertains to be according to his religion or otherwise binding on his 
    conscience:—  
 
Form of Oath  
 
“I 
    ...................do swear by Almighty God that I will well and truly try 
    the accused (or accused persons) before the court according to the evidence, 
    and that I will duly administer justice according to the Air Force Act, 
    1950, without partiality, favour or affection; and if any doubt shall arise, 
    then, according to my conscience, the best of my understanding and the 
    custom of war in the like cases; and I do further swear that I will not, on 
    any account at any time, whatsoever, disclose, or discover the vote or 
    opinion of any particular member of this court-martial, unless required to 
    give evidence thereof by a court of justice or a court-martial in due course 
    of law.  
  
 
Form of Affirmation  
 

    “I................do solemnly, sincerely and truly declare and affirm that I 
    will well and truly try the accused (or accused persons) before the court 
    according to the evidence, and that I will duly administer justice according 
    to the Air Force Act, 1950, without partiality, favour or affection; and if 
    any doubt shall arise, then, according to my conscience, the best of my 
    understanding, and the custom of war in the like cases; and I do further 
    solemnly affirm that I will not, on any account at any time, whatsoever, 
    disclose, or discover the vote or opinion of any particular member of this 
    court-martial, unless required to give evidence thereof by a court of 
    justice or a court-martial in due course of law.”  
 

 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>54</number> 
    Swearing or affirming of judge advocate and others.—After 
    the members of the court are all sworn or have made affirmation, an oath or 
    affirmation shall be administered to the following persons or such of them 
    as are present at the court-martial, in such of the following forms as shall 
    be appropriate, or in such other form to the same purport as the court 
    ascertains to be according to the religion or otherwise bindng on the 
    conscience of the person to be sworn or affrmed:—  
  
 <section>
<number>A</number> Judge-Advocate
 
Form of Oath  
 
“I 
    .................., do swear by Almighty God that I will to the best of my 
    ability carry out the duties of Judge-Advocate in accordance with the Air 
    Force Act, 1950, and the rules made thereunder and without partiality, 
    favour or affection, and I do further swear that I will not on any account 
    at any time whatsoever, disclose or discover the vote or opinion on any 
    matter of any particular member of this court-martial, unless required to 
    give evidence thereof by a court of justice or a court-martial in due course 
    of law.”  
  
 
Form of Affirmation   
 

    “I.................do solemnly affirm that I will to the best of my ability 
    carry out the duties of Judge-Advocate in accordance with the Air Force Act, 
    1950, and the rules made thereunder and without partiality, favour or 
    affection, and I do further solemnly, affirm that I will not on any account 
    at any time whatsoever disclose or discover the vote or opinion on any 
    matter of any particular member of this court-martial, unless required to 
    give evidence thereof by a court of justice or a court-martial, in due 
    course of law.”  
  
 </section><section>
<number>B</number> Officer Attending for the purposes 
    of instruction  
 
Form of Oath  
  
 

    “I...................do swear in the name of God that I will not, on any 
    account, at any time, whatsoever, disclose or discover the vote or opinion 
    of any particular member of this court-martial, unless required to give 
    evidence thereof by a court of justice or a court-martial in due course of 
    law”.  
  
 
Form of Affirmation  
 

    “I....................do solemnly, affirm that I will not on any account, at 
    any time whatsoever, disclose or discover the vote or opinion of any 
    particular member of this court-martial, unless required to give evidence 
    thereof by a court of justice or a court-martial in due course of law.”  
  
 </section><section>
<number>C</number> Shorthand Writer  
 
Form of Oath  
 

    “I................., do swear in the name of God that I will truly take down 
    to the best of my power the evidence to be given before this court-martial 
    and such other matters as I may be required and will, when required, deliver 
    to the court a true transcript of the same.”  
  
 
Form of Affirmation  
 

    “I.............do solemnly affirm that I will truly take down to the best of 
    my power the evidence to be given before this court-martial and such other 
    matters as I may be required, and will, when required, deliver to the court 
    a true transcript of the same”.  
  
 </section><section>
<number>D</number> Interpreter
 
Form of Oath
 

    “I............do swear in the name of God that I will faithfully interpret 
    and translate, as I shall be required to do, touching the matter before this 
    court-martial”.  
  
 
Form of Affirmation
 

    “I............do solemnly affirm that I wll faithfully interpret and 
    translate, as I shall be required to do, touching the matter before this 
    court-martial”.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>55</number> 
    Persons to administer oaths and affirmations.—All 
    oaths and affirmations shall be administered by a member of the court, the 
    judge advocate, or some other person empowered by the court to administer 
    such oath or affirmation.  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>56</number> 
    Arraignment of accused.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    After the members of the court and other persons are sworn or affirmed as 
    above-mentioned, the accused shall be arraigned, on the charges against him.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    charges upon which the accused is arraigned shall be read and, if necessary, 
    translated to him, and he shall be required to plead separately to each 
    charge.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>57</number> 
    Objection by accused to charge.—The 
    accused, when required to plead to any charge, may object to the charge on 
    the ground that it does not disclose an offence under the Act or is not in 
    accordance with these rules.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>58</number> 
    Amending of charge.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    At any time during the trial, if it appears to the court that there is any 
    mistake in the name or description of the accused in the charge-sheet, the 
    court may amend the charge-sheet so as to correct that mistake.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    on the trial of any charge it appears to the court at any time before they 
    have begun to examine the witnesses, that in the interests of justice any 
    addition to, omission from, or alteration in the charge is required, they 
    may report their opinion to the convening authority, and may adjourn, and 
    the convening authority may either direct a new trial to be commenced, or 
    amend the charge and order the trial to proceed with such amended charge 
    after due notice to the accused.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>59</number> 
    Special plea to the jurisdiction.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The accused, before pleading to a charge may offer a special plea to the 
    general jurisdiction of the court; and if he does so and the court considers 
    that anything stated in such plea shows that the court has no jurisdiction, 
    they shall receive any evidence offered in support, together with any 
    evidence offered by the prosecutor in disproof or qualification thereof, and 
    any address by the accused and reply by the prosecutor in reference thereto.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    the court overrules the special plea, they shall proceed with trial.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If 
    the court allows the special plea, it shall record its decision and the 
    reasons for it, and report it to the convening authority and adjourn; such 
    decision shall not require any confirmation, and the convening authority 
    shall either forthwith convene another court for the trial of the accused, 
    or order the accused to be released.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If 
    the court is in doubt as to the validity of the plea, it may refer the 
    matter to the convening authority, and may adjourn for that purpose, or may 
    record a special decision with respect to such plea, and proceed with the 
    trial.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>60</number> 
    General plea of “guilty” or “not guilty”.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If no special plea to the general jurisdiction of the court is offered, or 
    if such plea being offered, is overruled or is dealt with by a special 
    decision under sub-rule (4) of rule 59, the accused person’s plea—“guilty” 
    or “not guilty” (or if he refuses to plead, or does not plead intelligibly 
    either one or the other, a plea of “not guilty”)—shall be recorded on each 
    charge.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>
    

    1[If an accused person 
    plead “guilty”, that plea shall be recorded; but, before it is recorded, the 
    offcer conducting the proceeding, on behalf of the court, shall ascertain 
    that the accused understands the nature of the charge to which he has 
    pleaded guilty, and shall inform him of the general effect of that plea, and 
    in particular of the meaning of the charge to whch he has pleaded guilty, 
    and of the difference in procedure which will be made by the plea of guilty, 
    and shall advise him to wthdraw that plea if it appears from the summary of 
    evidence that the accused ought to plead “not guilty”].  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> When 
    an accused person pleads “guilty” to the first of two or more charges laid 
    in the alternative, the prosecutor may, after the provisions of sub-rule (2) 
    have been complied with by the court and before the accused is arraigned on 
    the alternative charge or charges, withdraw such alternative charge or 
    charges without requiring the accused to plead thereto and a record to that 
    effect shall be made upon the proceedings of the court.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A plea of 
    “guilty” shall not be accepted in cases where the accused is liable, if 
    convicted, to be sentenced to death and where such plea is offered, a plea 
    of “not guilty” shall be recorded and the trial shall proceed accordingly.
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>61</number> 
    Plea in bar.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The accused, at the time of his general plea of “guilty” or “not guilty” to 
    a charge for an offence, may offer a plea in bar of trial on the ground 
    that—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    he has been previously convicted 
    or acquitted of the offence by a competent criminal court or by a 
    court-martial or has been dealt with summarily under section 82 or section 
    86 for the offence or a charge in respect of the offence has been dismissed 
    as provided in sub-rule (2) of rule 24; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the offence has been pardoned or 
    condoned by competent air force authority ; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the time which has elapsed 
    between the commission of the offence and the commencement of the trial is 
    more than three years, and the limit of time for trial is not extended under 
    section 121.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    he offers such plea in bar, the court shall record it as well as his general 
    plea, and if it considers that any fact or facts stated by him are 
    sufficient to support the plea in bar it shall receive any evidence offered, 
    and hear any address made by the accused and the prosecutor in reference to 
    the plea.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If 
    the court finds that the plea in bar is proved, it shall record its finding, 
    and notify it to the confirming authority, and shall either adjourn, or if 
    there is any other charge against the accused, whether in the same or in a 
    different charge-sheet, which is not affected by the plea in bar, may 
    proceed with the trial of the accused on that charge.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If 
    the finding that the plea in bar is proved is not confirmed, the court may 
    be reassembled by the confirming authority, and proceed as if the plea had 
    been found not proved.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If 
    the court finds that the plea in bar is not proved; it shall proceed with 
    the trial, and the said finding shall be subject to confirmation like any 
    other finding of the court.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>62</number> Procedure after 
    plea of “guilty”.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Upon the record of the plea of “guilty”, if there are other charges in the 
    same charge-sheet to which the plea is “not guilty”, the trial shall first 
    proceed with respect to those other charges, and after fndings on those 
    charges, shall proceed with the charges on which a plea of “guilty” has been 
    entered; but if they are alternative charges, the court may either proceed 
    with respect to all the charges as if the accused had not pleaded “guilty” 
    to any charge or may, subject to sub-rule (2), instead of so trying him, 
    proceed under sub-rule (3) in respect of the charges to which he has pleaded 
    guilty.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where alternative charges are preferred and the accused pleads “not guilty” 
    to the charge which alleges the more serious offence and “guilty” to the 
    other, the court shall try the acused person as if he had pleaded “not 
    guilty” to all the charges:  
 
Provided 
    that this sub-rule shall not apply if the concurrence of the convening 
    officer has been signified by the prosecutor.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    procedure of the court in respect of a charge on which a plea of “guilty” 
    has been recorded, shall be as follows:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    The court shall receive any 
    statement which the accused desires to make with reference to the charge, 
    and shall read the summary of evidence, and annex it to the proceedings, or 
    if there is no such summary, shall take and record sufficient evidence to 
    enable them to determine the sentence and the confirming officer to know all 
    the circumstances connected with the offence. This evidence will be taken in 
    like manner as is directed by these rules in the case of a plea of “not 
    guilty”;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    After the evidence has been so 
    taken, or the summary of evidence has been read, as the case may be, the 
    accused may make a statement on mitigation of punishment and may call 
    witnesses as to his character. If the accused at any court-martial states 
    anything in mitigation of punishment which, in the opinon of the court, 
    requires to be proved and would, if proved affect the amount of punishment, 
    the court may permit the acused to call witnesses to prove the same;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    If from the statement of the 
    accused, or from the summary of evidence or otherwise it appears to the 
    court that the accused did not understand the effect of his plea of 
    “guilty”, the court shall record its opinion and proeed with the trial as on 
    a plea of “not guilty”; otherwise the court shall, subject to rule 71, 
    record a finding of “guilty” on the charge;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    When a court has recorded an 
    opinion as is referred to in clause (c) and proceeds with the trial as on a 
    plea of “not guilty”, they shall, if there was a charge laid in the 
    alternative which the prosecutor withdrew under rule 60, reinstate such 
    alternative charge, arraign the accused thereon and proceed wth the trial as 
    if such charge had never been withdrawn.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> If a plea 
    of “guilty” is recorded on any charge, and the trial proceeds with respect 
    to other charges in the same charge-sheet, the proceedings under sub-rule 
    (3) shall take place when the findings on the other charges in the same 
    charge-sheet have been recorded.]
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>63</number> 
    Withdrawal of plea of “not guilty”.—The 
    accused may, if he thinks fit, at any time during the trial, withdraw his 
    plea of “not guilty”, and plead “guilty”, and in such case the court will at 
    once, subject to a compliance with sub-rules (2) and (4) of rule 60, record 
    a plea and finding of “guilty”, and shall, so far as is necessary, proceed 
    in the manner directed by rule 62.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>64</number> 
    Plea of “not guilty” and case for prosecution.—After 
    the plea of “not-guilty” to any charge is recorded, the trial shall proceed 
    as follows:—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    the prosecutor may, if he 
    desires, make an opening address;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    the evidence for the prosecutor 
    shall then be taken;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    if it should be necessary for the 
    prosecutor to give evidence for the prosecution on the facts of the case, he 
    shall give it after the delivery of his address, and he must be sworn and 
    give his evidence in detail;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    he may be cross-examined by the 
    accused and afterwards may make any statement which might be made by a 
    witness on re-examination.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>65</number> 
    Plea of no case.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    At the close of the case for prosecution, the accused may offer a plea that 
    the evidence given on behalf of the prosecution, in respect of any one or 
    more charges, has not established a prima facie case against him and 
    that he should not, therefore, be called upon for his defence as respects 
    such charge or charges.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    court shall hear the address by the accused in support of such plea and the 
    reply by the prosecutor thereto, and shall consider the plea in closed 
    court; and if it is satisfied that the plea is well-founded in respect of 
    any one or more charges to which it relates, it shall record a finding of 
    “not-guilty” in respect of such charge or charges, and the accused shall 
    thereafter be called upon for his defence only in respect of the remaining 
    charges, if any, in the charge-sheet.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>66</number> 
    Procedure for defence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    At the close of the evidence for the prosecution if the plea for “no case” 
    is not offered by the accused, or if offered is overruled, the accused may, 
    if he so desires, make an opening address.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    accused shall be asked if he has any thing to say in his defence and may 
    make a statement in his defence.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any 
    statement allowed under this or any other of these rules to be made by the 
    accused, may be made either orally or in writing; but the accused making the 
    statement shall not be sworn.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    court or the judge advocate, if any, may question the accused for the 
    purpose of enabling him to explain any circumstances appearing in his 
    statement or in the evidence against him. The accused shall not render 
    himself liable to punishment by refusing to answer such questions or by 
    giving answers to them which he knows not to be true, but the court may draw 
    such inference from such refusal or answers as it thinks fit.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    accused shall then be asked if he intends to call any witness to the facts 
    of the case. If the accused does not state that he intends to call witnesses 
    to the facts of the case, the procedure shall be as specified in rule 67, 
    and if he states that he intends to call witnesses to the facts of the case, 
    the procedure shall be as specified in rule 68.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>66A</number> Accused 
    competent witness for defence.—A 
    person accused of an offence before a Court Martial shall be a competent 
    witness for the defence and may give evidence on oath or affirmation in 
    disproof of the charges made against him or any person charged together with 
    him at the same trial:  
 
Provided 
    that—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    he shall not be called as a 
    witness except on his own request in writing; or  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    his failure to give evidence shall not 
    be made the subject of any comment by any of the parties or the Court or 
    give rise to any presumption against himself or any person charged together 
    with him at the same trial.]
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>67</number> 
    Procedure where accused does not call witnesses to the facts of the case.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The accused may call witnesses as to character.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    prosecutor may, in reply to the witnesses as to character, produce proof of 
    formal conviction either by a court-martial or by a criminal court and 
    entries in the service conduct sheets.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    prosecutor may address the court for the purpose of summing up the evidence 
    for the prosecution.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    accused may then address the court in his defence. The time at which such 
    address is allowed is in these rules referred to as the time for the second 
    address of the accused.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>68</number> 
    Procedure where accused calls witnesses to the facts of the case.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The accused may call witnesses, including witnesses as to character.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    prosecutor may with the permission of the court, call witnesses in reply.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    accused may again address the court. The time at which such second address 
    is allowed is in these rules referred to as the time for the second address 
    of the accused.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    prosecutor shall be entitled to address the court in reply.  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>69</number> 
    Summing up by judge-advocate.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The judge-advocate, if any, shall unless both he and the court think summing 
    up necessary, sum up in open court the whole case.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    After the summing up of the judge-advocate, no other address shall be 
    allowed.  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>70</number> 
    Consideration of finding.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The court shall deliberate on its finding in closed court.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    opinion of each member of the court shall be taken separately on each 
    charge.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>71</number> 
    Form, record and announcement of finding.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The finding on every charge shall be recorded, and, except, as mentioned in 
    these rules, shall be recorded simply as a finding of “guilty” or of “not 
    guilty”.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where the court is of opinion as regards any charge that the facts proved do 
    not disclose the offence charged or any offence of which he might under the 
    Act be found guilty on the charge as laid, the court shall acquit the 
    accused of the charge.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If 
    the court doubts as regards any charge whether the facts proved show the 
    accused to be guilty or not of the offence charged, or of any offence of 
    which he might under the Act be found guilty on the charge as laid, it may, 
    before recording a finding on that charge, refer to the confirming authority 
    for an opinion setting out the facts which it finds to be proved, and may, 
    if necessary, adjourn for that purpose.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Where the court is of opinion as regards any charge that the facts which it 
    fine to be proved in evidence differ materially from the facts alleged in 
    the statement of particulars in the charge, but are nevertheless sufficient 
    to prove the offence stated in the charge, and that the difference is not so 
    material as to have prejudiced the accused in his defence, it may, instead 
    of a finding of “not guilty”, record a special finding.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    special finding may find the accused guilty on a charge subject to the 
    statement of exceptions or variations specified therein.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> 
    Where there are alternative charges and the facts proved appears to the 
    court not to constitute the offence mentioned in any of those alternative 
    charges, the court shall record a finding of “not guilty” on that charge, 
    but if the court thinks that the facts proved constitute one of the offences 
    stated in two or more of the alternative charges, but doubts which of those 
    offences the facts do at law constitute, then it may, before recording a 
    finding on those charges, refer to the confirming authority for an opinion, 
    setting out the facts which it finds to be proved, and stating that it 
    doubts whether those facts constitute in law the offence in such one or 
    another of the alternative charges and may, if necessary, adjourn for the 
    purpose.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The 
    court shall not find the accused guilty on more than one of two or more 
    charges laid in the alternative, even if conviction upon one charge 
    necessarily connotes guilt upon the alternative charge or charges.  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> In 
    any case where the court is empowered by section 138 to find the accused 
    guilty of an offence other than that charged, or guilty of committing an 
    offence in circumstances involving a less degree of punishment or where it 
    could after hearing the evidence have made a special finding of guilty 
    subject to exceptions or variations in accordance with sub-rules (4) and 
    (5), it may, if it is satisfied of the justice of such course, and if the 
    concurrence of the convening officer is signified by the prosecutor, accept 
    and record a plea of guilty of such other offence as having been committed, 
    in circumstances involving such less degree of punishment, or of the offence 
    charged subject to such exceptions or variations.  
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> The 
    finding on each charge shall be announced forthwith in open court as subject 
    to confirmation.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>72</number> 
    Procedure on acquittal.—If 
    the finding on all the charges is “not guilty” the presiding officer shall 
    date and sign the finding and such signature shall authenticate the whole of 
    the proceedings, and the proceedings, upon being signed by the judge 
    advocate, if any, shall be at once transmitted for confirmation to the 
    person specified in rule 101.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>73</number> 
    Procedure on conviction.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If the finding on any charge is “guilty”, then for the guidance of the court 
    in determining its sentence, and of the confirming authority in considering 
    the sentence, the court, before deliberating on its sentence shall whenever 
    possible, take evidence of and record general character, age, service, rank 
    and any recognised acts of gallantry or distinguished conduct of the 
    accused, any previous convictions of the accused either by a court-martial 
    or a criminal court, any previous punishments awarded to him by an officer 
    exercising authority under section 82 or 86 the length of time he has been 
    in arrest or in confinement on any previous sentence, and any military or 
    air force decoration or military or air force reward, of which he may be in 
    possession or to which he is entitled.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Evidence on the above matters may be given by a witness verifying a 
    statement which contains a summary of the entries in the service records 
    respecting the accused and identifying the accused as the person referred to 
    in that summary.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    accused may cross-examine any such witness, and may call witnesses to rebut 
    such evidence; and if the accused so requests, the service records or a duly 
    certified copy of the material entries therein, shall be produced; and if 
    the accused alleges that the summary is in any respect not in accordance 
    with the service records or such certified copy, as the case may be, the 
    court shall compare the summary with those records or copy, and if it finds 
    it is not in accordance therewith, shall cause the summary to be corrected 
    accordingly.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> When 
    all the evidence on the above matters has been given the accused may address 
    the court thereon.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>74</number> 
    Sentence.—The 
    court shall award one sentence in respect of all the offences of which the 
    accused is found guilty, and such sentence shall be deemed to be awarded in 
    respect of the offence in each charge in respect of which it can be given, 
    and not to be awarded in respect of any offence in a charge in respect of 
    which it cannot be given.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>75</number> 
    Recommendation to mercy.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If the court makes a recommendation to mercy it shall give its reasons for 
    its recommendation.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    number of opinions by which a recommendation to mercy mentioned in this 
    rule, or any question relative thereto, is adopted or rejected, may be 
    entered in the proceedings.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>76</number> 
    Announcement of sentence and signing and transmission of proceedings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The sentence together with any recommendation to mercy and the reasons for 
    any such recommendation shall be announced in open court as subject to 
    confirmation.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Upon 
    the court awarding the sentence, the presiding officer shall date and sign 
    the sentence and such signature shall authenticate the whole of the 
    proceedings and the proceedings upon being signed by the judge advocate, if 
    any, shall at once be transmitted for confirmation.  
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>77</number> 
    Revision.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the finding or sentence is sent back for revision under section 159, 
    the court shall re-assemble in open Court, the revision order shall be read 
    and if the court is directed to take fresh evidence, such evidence shall 
    also be taken in open Court. The Court shall then deliberate on its findings 
    in closed Court.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where the finding is sent back for revision and the court does not adhere to 
    its former finding, it shall revoke the finding and sentence, and record a 
    new finding, and if such new finding involves a sentence, pass sentence 
    afresh.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Where the sentence alone is sent back for revision, the court shall not 
    revise the findings.  
 


    1[(3A) The accused 
    shall, if he so desires, be allowed to address the court before the court 
    closes for deliberating on its findings or the sentence.]  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> After 
    revision, the presiding officer shall date and sign the decision of the 
    court, and the proceedings, upon being signed by the judge advocate, if any, 
    shall be at once transmitted for confirmation.
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>78</number> 
    Promulgation.—The 
    charge, findings, sentence, and any recommendations to mercy shall, together 
    with the confirmation or non-confirmation of the proceedings, be promulgated 
    in such manner as the confirming authority may direct; and if no direction 
    is given, according to the custom of the service.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>79</number> 
    Mitigation of sentence on partial confirmation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where a sentence has been awarded by a court-martial in respect of offences 
    in several charges, and the confirming authority confirms the finding on 
    some but not on all of such charges, that authority shall take into 
    consideration the fact of such non-confirmation and shall if it seems just, 
    mitigate, remit, or commute the punishment awarded according as seems just, 
    having regard to the offences in the charges the findings on which are 
    confirmed.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where a sentence has been awarded by a court-martial in respect of offences 
    in several charges and has been confirmed, and any one of such charges or 
    the finding thereon is found to be invalid, the authority having power to 
    mitigate, remit or commute the punishment awarded by the sentence shall take 
    into consideration the fact of such invalidity, and if it seems just, 
    mitigate remit or commute the punishment awarded according as seems just 
    having regard to the offences in the charges which with the findings thereon 
    are not invalid, and the punishment as so modified shall be as valid as if 
    it had been originally awarded only in respect of those offences.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>80</number> 
    Confirmation notwithstanding informality in, or excess of punishment.—If 
    the sentence of a court-martial is informally expressed, the confirming 
    authority may, in confirming the sentence, vary the form so that it shall be 
    properly expressed; and if the punishment awarded by the sentence is in 
    excess of the punishment authorised by law, the confirming authority may 
    vary the sentence so that the punishment shall not be in excess of the 
    punishment authorized by law; and the confirming authority may confirm the 
    finding and the sentence, as so varied, of the court-martial.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>81</number> 
    Member or prosecutor not to confirm proceedings.—A 
    member of a court-martial or an officer who has acted as prosecutor at a 
    court-martial, shall not confirm the finding or sentence of that 
    court-martial, and where such member or prosecutor becomes the confirming 
    officer, he shall refer the finding and sentence of the court-martial to a 
    superior authority competent to confirm the findings and sentences of the 
    like description of court-martial.  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>82</number> 
    Seating of members.—The 
    members of a court-martial shall take their seats according to their rank.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>83</number> 
    Responsibility of Presiding Officer.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The presiding officer is responsible that the trial is conducted in proper 
    order, and in accordance with the Act and these rules, and will take care 
    that every thing is conducted in a manner befitting a court of justice.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    is the duty of the presiding officer to see that justice is administered, 
    that the accused has a fair trial, and that he does not suffer any 
    disadvantage in consequence of his position as a person under trial, or of 
    his ignorance, or of his incapacity to examine or cross-examine witnesses or 
    otherwise.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>84</number> 
    Power of court over address of prosecutor and accused.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    It shall be the duty of the prosecutor to assist the court in the 
    administration of justice, to behave impartially, to bring the whole of the 
    transaction before the court, and not to take any unfair advantage of or 
    suppress any evidence in favour of the accused.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    prosecutor may not refer to any matter, not relevant to the charge or 
    charges then before the court and it is the duty of the court to stop him 
    from so doing and also to restrain any undue violence of language or want of 
    fairness or moderation on the part of the prosecutor.  
 


    1[(3) The court shall 
    allow great latitude to the accused in makng his defence, he must abstain 
    from any remakrs contemptuous or disrespectful towards the court, and from 
    coarse and insulting language towards others, but he may for the purpose of 
    his defence impeach the evidence and the motives of witnesses and 
    prosecutor, and charge other persons with blame and even criminality, 
    subject, if he does so, to any liability to further proceedings to which he 
    would otherwise be subject. The court may caution the accused as to the 
    irrelevance of his defence, but shall not unless in specal cases, stop his 
    defence solely on ground of such irrelevance.]
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>85</number> 
    Procedure on trial of accused persons together.—Where 
    two or more accused persons are tried together and any evidence as to the 
    facts of the case is tendered by any one or more of them, the evidence and 
    addresses on the part of all accused persons shall be taken before the 
    prosecutor replies, and the prosecutor shall make one address only in reply 
    as regards all the accused persons.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>86</number> 
    Separate charge-sheets.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    When the convening officer directs any charges against an accused person to 
    be inserted in different charge-sheets, the accused shall be arraigned and 
    until after the finding tried, upon each charge-sheet separately, and 
    accordingly the procedure in rules 56 to 71 (both inclusive) shall until 
    after the finding, be followed in respect of each charge-sheet, as if it 
    contained the whole of the charges against the accused.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    trials upon the several charge-sheets shall be in such order as the 
    convening officer directs.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> When 
    the court has tried the accused upon all the charge-sheets it shall, in the 
    case of the finding being “not guilty” on all the charges, proceed as 
    directed by rule 72 and in case of the finding on any one or more of the 
    charges being “guilty” proceed as directed by rules 62 and 73 to 76 (both 
    inclusive), in the manner in each case as if all the charges in the 
    different charge-sheets had been contained in one charge-sheet, and the 
    sentence passed shall be of the same effect as if all the charges had been 
    contained in one charge-sheet.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If 
    the convening officer directs that, in the event of the conviction of the 
    accused person upon a charge in any charge-sheet, he need not be tried upon 
    the subsequent charge-sheets, the court in such event may, without trying 
    the accused upon any of the subsequent charge-sheets, proceed as before 
    directed by sub-rule (3).  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> 
    Where a charge-sheet contains more than one charge, the accused may, before 
    pleading, claim to be tried separately in respect of any charge or charges 
    in that charge-sheet, on the ground that he will be embarrassed in his 
    defence if he is not so tried separately; and in such case the court, unless 
    it thinks his claim unreasonable, shall arraign and try the accused in like 
    manner as if the convening officer had inserted the said charge or charges 
    in different charge-sheets.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> If 
    the accused pleads “guilty” to a charge in a charge-sheet, and the trial 
    does not proceed as mentioned in sub-rule (1) of rule 62 with respect to the 
    other charges in that charge-sheet the court shall, subject to the 
    directions of the convening officer, proceed to try the accused on the 
    charges in the next charge-sheet before it proceeds as directed by sub-rules 
    (3) and (4) of rule 62.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>87</number> 
    Sitting in closed court.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    When a court-martial sits in closed court on any deliberation amongst the 
    members or otherwise, no person shall be present except the members of the 
    court, the judge advocate, any officers under instruction, and if 
    interpreter has been appointed and the court considers his presence 
    necessary, the interpreter; and the court may either retire, or may cause 
    the place where they sit to be cleared of all other persons not entitled to 
    be present.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Except as above-mentioned, all the proceedings, including the view of any 
    place, shall be in open court and in the presence of the accused.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>87A</number> Courts Martial 
    to be public.—Subject 
    to rule 87, the place in which a Court Martial is held for the purpose of 
    trying an offence under the Act shall be deeemed to be an open Court to 
    which the public generally may have access, so far as the same can 
    conveniently contain them:  
 
Provided that, 
    if the Court is satisfied that it is necessary or expedient in the public 
    interest or for the ends of justice so to do, the Court may at any stage of 
    the trial of any particular case order that the public generally or any 
    portion thereof or any particular person shall not have access to, or be or 
    remain in the place in which the court is held.]
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>88</number> 
    Hours of sitting.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A court-martial may sit at such times and for such period between the hours 
    of six in the morning and six in the afternoon as may be directed by the 
    proper air force authority or, in the absence of any such direction, as the 
    court-martial may, from time to time, determine:  
 
Provided 
    that no court-martial shall, subject to the provisions of sub-rules (2) and 
    (3), sit for more than six hours in any one day.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where the court-martial considers it necessary to continue the trial after 
    six in the afternoon or to sit for more than six hours in any one day, it 
    may do so but if it does so, the court-martial shall record in the 
    proceedings the reasons for so doing.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In 
    cases requiring an immediate disposal or when the convening officer 
    certifies under his hand that it is expedient in public interest, trials may 
    be held at any hour.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Where the court-martial or the convening officer or the senior officer on 
    the spot is of the opinion that service exigencies or the interests of 
    discipline require the court-martial to sit on Sunday or any other day 
    declared as a holiday, the court-martial may sit accordingly but in no other 
    case the court-martial shall sit on any of these days.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>89</number> 
    Continuity of trial and adjournment of court.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    When a court is once assembled and the accused has been arraigned the court 
    shall, subject to the provisions of rule 88, continue the trial from day to 
    day unless it appears to the court that an adjournment is necessary for the 
    ends of justice, or that such continuance is impracticable.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    court may adjourn from time to time, and from place to place, and may, when 
    necessary, view any place.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A 
    court-martial, in the absence of a judge advocate (if such has been 
    appointed for that court-martial), shall not proceed, and, if necessary 
    shall adjourn.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    senior officer on the spot, may also, for exigencies of the service adjourn 
    or prolong the adjournment of the court.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If 
    the time to which an adjournment is made is not specified, the adjournment 
    shall be until further orders from the proper air force authority; and if 
    the place to which an adjournment is made is not specified, the adjournment 
    shall be to the same place or to such other place as may be specified in 
    further orders from the proper air force authority.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>90</number> 
    Suspension of trial.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where, in consequence of anything arising while the court is sitting, the 
    court is unable by reason of dissolution, as specified in section 17, or 
    otherwise, to continue the trial, the presiding officer, or in his absence, 
    the senior member present shall immediately report the facts to the 
    convening authority.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where a court-martial is dissolved before the finding, or, in case of a 
    finding of guilty, before award of the sentence, the proceedings of the 
    court-martial, shall be null, and the accused may be tried by another court-martial.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>91</number> Proceedings on 
    death or illness of the accused.—In 
    case of the death of the accused, or of such illness of the accused as 
    renders it impossible to continue the trial, the court shall ascertain the 
    fact of the death or illness by evidence and record the same, and adjourn, 
    and transmit the proceedings to the convening authority.
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>92</number> 
    Death, retirement or absence of presiding officer.—In 
    the case of the death, retirement on challenge or unavoidable absence of the 
    presiding officer, the next senior officer shall take the place of the 
    presiding officer and the trial shall proceed if the court is still composed 
    of not less than the minimum number of officers of which it is required by 
    law to consist.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>93</number> 
    Presence of members during trial.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A member of a court, who has been absent while any part of the evidence on 
    the trial of an accused person is taken, shall take no further part in the 
    trial by that court of that person, but the proceedings of the court shall 
    not be invalid unless reduced below the required minimum.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An 
    officer shall not be added to a court-martial after the accused has been 
    arraigned.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>94</number> 
    Taking of opinions of members of court.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every member of a court must give his opinion on every question which the 
    court has to decide and must give his opinion as to the sentence, 
    notwithstanding that he has given his opinion in favour of acquittal.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    opinions of the members of the court shall be taken in succession beginning 
    with the member lowest in rank.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>95</number> 
    Procedure on incidental question.—If 
    any question arises incidentally during the trial, the person, whether 
    prosecutor or accused, requesting the opinion of the court, is to speak 
    first; the other person is then to answer, and the first person is to be 
    allowed to reply.   


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>96</number> 
    Swearing of court to try several accused persons.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A court may be sworn or affirmed at one time to try any number of accused 
    persons then present before it, whether those persons are to be tried 
    together or separately and each accused person shall have power to object to 
    the members of the court, and shall be asked separately whether he objects 
    to any member.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    the case of several accused persons to be tried separately, the court, upon 
    one of those persons objecting to a member, may, according as it thinks fit 
    proceed to determine that objection or postpone the case of that person and 
    swear or affirm the members of the court for the trial of the others alone.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In 
    the case of several accused persons to be tried separately, the court, when 
    sworn or affirmed, shall proceed with one case, postponing the other cases 
    and taking them afterwards in succession.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Where several accused persons are tried separately by the same court-martial 
    upon charges arising out of the same transaction, the court may, if it 
    considers it desirable in the interests of justice, postpone consideration 
    of sentence to be awarded to any one or more of such accused persons until 
    the trials of all such accused persons have been completed.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>97</number> 
    Swearing of interpreter and shorthand writer.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    At any time during the trial an impartial person may, if the court thinks it 
    necessary, and shall if either the prosecutor or the accused request it on 
    any reasonable ground, be sworn or affirmed to act as interpreter.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An 
    impartial person may, at any time of the trial, if the court thinks it 
    desirable, be sworn or affirmed to act as a shorthand writer.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Before a person is sworn or affirmed as interpreter or shorthand writer, the 
    accused shall be informed of the person who is proposed to be sworn or 
    affirmed and may object to the person as not being impartial or for any 
    reasonable cause; and the court, if it thinks that the objection is 
    reasonable, shall not swear or affirm that person as interpreter or 
    shorthand writer.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>98</number> 
    Evidence, when to be translated.—When 
    any evidence is given in a language which any of the officers composing the 
    court, the judge advocate, the prosecutor or the accused or his defending 
    officer or counsel does not understand, that evidence shall be interpreted 
    to such officer or person in a language which he understands. If an 
    interpreter in such language has been appointed by the convening officer, 
    and duly sworn or affirmed, the evidence shall be interpreted by him. If no 
    such interpreter has been appointed and sworn or affirmed an impartial 
    person shall be sworn or affirmed by the court as required by rule 97. When 
    documents are put in for the purpose of formal proof, it shall be in the 
    discretion of the court to cause as much to be interpreted as appears 
    necessary.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>99</number> 
    Record in proceedings of transactions of courts-martial.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    At a court-martial the judge advocate, or, if there is none, the presiding 
    officer, shall record, or cause to be recorded in the English language, all 
    transactions of that court, and shall be responsible for the accuracy of the 
    record (in these rules referred to as the proceedings); and if the 
    judge-advocate is called as a witness by the accused, the presiding officer 
    shall be responsible for the accuracy of the record in the proceedings of 
    the evidence of the judge advocate.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    evidence shall be taken down in a narrative form in as nearly as possible 
    the words used; but in any case where the prosecutor, the accused person, 
    judge advocate or the court consider it material, the question and answer 
    shall be taken down verbatim.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    question which has been objected to, and the tender of any evidence which 
    has been objected to, shall, if the prosecutor or accused so requests, or 
    the court thinks fit, be entered with the grounds of the objection, and the 
    decision of the court thereon.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Where any address by, or on behalf of, the prosecutor or the accused person 
    is not in writing, it shall not be necessary to record the same in the 
    proceedings further or otherwise than the court thinks proper, except that—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the court shall in every case make such 
    record of the defence made by the accused as will enable the confirming 
    officer to judge of the reply made by, or on behalf, of the accused to each 
    charge against him; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the court shall also record any 
    particular matters in the address by, or on behalf of, the prosecutor or 
    accused person, which the prosecutor or accused person, as the case may be, 
    requires.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    court shall not enter in the proceedings any comment or anything not before 
    the court, or any report of any fact not forming part of the trial; but if 
    any such comment or report seems to the court necessary, the court may 
    forward it to the proper air force authority in a separate document, signed 
    by the presiding officer.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>100</number> 
    Custody and inspection of proceedings.—The 
    proceedings shall be deemed to be in the custody of the judge advocate (if 
    any), or, if there is none, of the presiding officer, but may, with proper 
    precaution for their safety, be inspected by the members of the court, the 
    prosecutor and accused, respectively, at all reasonable times.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>101</number> 
    Transmission of proceedings.—The 
    proceedings shall, as required under rule 72 or rule 76 be at once sent by 
    the person having the custody thereof to such person as may be directed by 
    the order convening the court, or, in default of any such direction, to the 
    confirming officer.  
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>102</number> 
    Defending officer and friend of accused.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    At any court-martial an accused person may be represented by any officer 
    subject to air force law who shall be called “the defending officer” or 
    assisted by any person whose services he may be able to procure and who 
    shall be called “the friend of the accused.”  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    shall be the duty of the convening officer to ascertain whether an accused 
    person desires to have a defending officer assigned to represent him at his 
    trial and, if he does so desire, the convening officer shall use his best 
    endeavours to ensure that the accused shall be so represented by suitable 
    officer. If owing to service exigencies or for any other reason, there shall 
    in the opinion of the convening officer be no such officer available for the 
    purpose the convening officer shall give a written notice to the presiding 
    officer of the court-martial, and such notice shall be attached to the 
    proceedings.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    defending officer shall have the same rights and duties as appertain to 
    counsel under these rules and shall be under the like obligations.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    friend of the accused may advise the accused on all points and suggest the 
    questions to be put to the witnesses, but he shall not examine or 
    cross-examine the witnesses or address the court.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>103</number> 
    Counsel allowed in certain general and district courts-martial—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to these rules counsel shall be allowed to appear on behalf of the 
    prosecutor and accused at general and district courts-martial if the Chief 
    of the Air Staff, or the convening officer declares that it is expedient to 
    allow the appearance of counsel thereat, and such declaration may be made as 
    regards all general and district courts-martial held in any particular 
    place, or as regards any particular general or district court-martial, and 
    may be made subject to such reservation as to cases on active service or 
    otherwise, as seems expedient.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Save 
    as provided in rule 102, the rules with respect to counsel shall apply only 
    to the courts-martial at which counsel are under this rule allowed to 
    appear.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>104</number> 
    Requirements for appearance of counsel.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where an accused person gives notice of his intention to have counsel to 
    assist him during the trial either on the day on which he is informed of the 
    charge or at any time not being less than seven days before the trial, or 
    such shorter time before the trial as the opinion of the court would have 
    enabled the prosecutor to obtain, if he had thought fit, counsel to assist 
    him during the trial or where such notice is given to the accused on the 
    part of the prosecution, counsel may appear at the court-martial to assist 
    the accused.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    the convening officer so directs, counsel may appear on behalf of the 
    prosecutor, but in that case, unless the notice under sub-rule (1) has been 
    given by the accused, notice of the direction for counsel to appear shall be 
    given to the accused at such time (not in any case less than seven days) 
    before the trial, as would, in the opinion of the court, have enabled the 
    accused to obtain counsel to assist him at the trial.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    counsel, who appears before a court-martial on behalf of the prosecutor or 
    accused, shall have the same right as the prosecutor or accused for whom he 
    appears, to call and orally examine, cross-examine and re-examine witnesses, 
    to make an objection or statement, to address the court, to put in any plea 
    and to inspect the proceedings and shall have the right otherwise to act in 
    the course of the trial in the place of the person on whose behalf he 
    appears, and he shall comply with these rules as if he were that person, and 
    in such case that person shall not have the right himself to do any of the 
    above matters except as regards the statement allowed by sub-rule (3) of 
    rule 62 or sub-rule (2) of rule 66 or except so far as the court permits him 
    so to do.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> When 
    counsel appears on behalf of the prosecutor, the prosecutor, if called as a 
    witness may be examined and re-examined as any other witness and clauses (c) 
    and (d) of rule 64 shall not apply.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>105</number> 
    Counsel for prosecution.—The 
    counsel appearing on behalf of the prosecution shall have the same duty as 
    the prosecutor, and is subject to be stopped and restrained by the court in 
    the manner provided by sub-rule (2) of rule 84.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>106</number> 
    Counsel for accused.—The 
    counsel appearing on behalf of the accused has the like rights and is under 
    the like obligations as are specified in sub-rule (3) of rule 84 in the case 
    of accused.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>107</number> 
    General rules as to counsel.—A 
    counsel, whether for the prosecution or for the accused, shall conform 
    strictly to these rules and to the rules of criminal courts in India 
    relating to the examination, cross-examination and re-examination of 
    witnesses, and relating to the duties of counsel.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>108</number> 
    Qualifications of counsel.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Neither the prosecutor nor the accused has any right to object to any 
    counsel if properly qualified.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    counsel shall be deemed to be properly qualified if he is a legal practioner 
    authorized to practise with right of audience in a Court of Sessions in 
    India, or if he is recognised by the convening officer in any other country 
    where the trial is held as having in that country rights and duties similar 
    to those of such a legal practitioner in India and as being subject to 
    punishment or disability for a breach of professional rules.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>109</number> 
    Statement by accused when defended by counsel or officer.—Notwithstanding 
    the fact that he is represented at the trial by a counsel or an officer 
    subject to 

    1[***] air force law, 
    an accused may, if he thinks fit, make a statement as provided in sub-rule 
    (3) of rule 62 and sub-rule (2) of rule 66 giving his own account of the 
    subject of the charges against him.
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>110</number> 
    Disqualifications of judge-advocate.—An 
    officer who is disqualified for sitting on a court-martial, shall be 
    disqualified for acting as judge-advocate at that court-martial.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>111</number> 
    Powers and duties of judge-advocate.—The 
    powers and duties of a judge-advocate are as follows:—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    The prosecutor or the accused, is 
    at all times, after the judge-advocate is named to act on the court, 
    entitled to his opinion on any question of law relative to the charge or 
    trial, whether he is in or out of court, subject, when he is in court, to 
    the permission of the court;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    At a court-martial he represents 
    the 1[Chief 
    Legal Advisor].  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    He is responsible for informing 
    the court of any informality or irregularity in the proceedings. Whether 
    consulted or not, he shall inform the convening officer and the court of any 
    informality or defect in the charge, or in the constitution of the court, 
    and shall give his advice on any matter before the court.  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    Any information or advice given 
    to the court on any matter before the court shall, if he or the court 
    desires it, be entered in the proceedings.  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    At the conclusion of the case he 
    shall, unless both he and the court consider it unnecessary, sum up the 
    evidence and give his opinion upon the legal bearing of the case before the 
    court proceeds to deliberate upon its finding.  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    The court, in following the 
    opinion of the judge-advocate on a legal point may record that it has 
    decided in consequence of that opinion.  
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    The judge-advocate has, equally 
    with the presiding officer, the duty of taking care that the accused does 
    not suffer any disadvantage in consequence of his position as such, or of 
    his ignorance or incapacity to examine or cross-examine witnesses or 
    otherwise, and may, for that purpose, with the permission of the court, call 
    witnesses and put questions to witnesses, which appear to him necessary or 
    desirable to elicit the truth.  
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>    In fulfilling his duties, the 
    judge-advocate must be careful to maintain an entirely impartial position.
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>112</number> 
    Calling of all prosecutor’s witnesses.—The 
    prosecutor is not bound to call all the witnesses for the prosecution whose 
    evidence is in the summary of evidence or whom the accused has been informed 
    it is intended to call, but should ordinarily call such of them as the 
    accused desires in order that he may cross-examine them and shall, for this 
    reason, so far as practicable, secure the attendance of all such witnesses.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>113</number> 
    Calling of witnesses whose evidence is not contained in summary.—If 
    the prosecutor intends to call a witness whose evidence is not contained in 
    any summary given to the accused, notice of the intention shall be given to 
    the accused, a reasonable time before the witness is called; and if such 
    witness is called without such notice having been given, the court shall, if 
    the accused to desires it, either adjourn after taking the evidence of the 
    witness, or allow the cross-examination of such witness to be postponed, and 
    the court shall inform the accused of his right to demand such adjournment 
    or postponement.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>114</number> 
    List of witnesses for accused.—The 
    accused shall not be required to give to the prosecutor or court a list of 
    the witnesses whom he intends to call, but it shall rest with the accused 
    alone to secure the attendance of any witness whose evidence is not 
    contained in the summary, and for whose attendance the accused has not 
    requested steps to be taken as provided by sub-rule 
<section><number>1</number> of rule 40.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>115</number> 
    Procuring attendance of witnesses.—The 
    commanding officer of the accused, the convening officer, or after the 
    assembly of the court, the presiding officer, shall take proper steps to 
    procure the attendance of the witnesses whom the prosecutor or accused 
    desires to call, and whose attendance can reasonably be procured, but the 
    person requiring the attendance of a witness may be required to undertake to 
    defray the cost, if any, of their attendance.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>116</number> 
    Procedure when essential witness is absent.—If 
    such proper steps as mentioned in the preceding rule have not been taken as 
    to any witness, or if any witness whose attendance could not reasonably be 
    procured before the assembly of the court is essential to the prosecution or 
    defence, the court shall—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    take steps to procure the issue 
    of a commission for the examination of such witness; or  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    adjourn and report the 
    circumstances to the convening officer.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>117</number> 
    Withdrawal of witnesses from court.—During 
    the trial a witness other than the prosecutor, shall not, except by special 
    leave of the court, be permitted to be present in court while not under 
    examination and if, while he is under examination, a discussion arises as to 
    the allowance of a question, or the sufficiency of his answers or otherwise 
    as to his evidence, he may be directed to withdraw.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>118</number> 
    Oath or affirmation to be administered to witnesses.—An 
    oath or affirmation shall, if so required by the Act, be administered to 
    every witness, before the gives his evidence, by a member of the court, the 
    judge-advocate, or some other person empowered by the court, in one of the 
    following forms or in such other form to the same purport as the court 
    ascertains to be according to the religion or otherwise binding on the 
    conscience of the witness.  
  
 
Form of Oath
 

    “I,...............do swear in the name of God that what I shall state shall 
    be the truth, the whole truth, and nothing but the truth.”
  
 
Form of Affirmation
 
“I, 
    ...................................do solemnly affirm that what I shall 
    state shall be the truth, the whole truth, and nothing but the truth.”

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>119</number> 
    Mode of questioning witness.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every question shall be put to witness orally by the presiding officer, the 
    judge-advocate, the prosecutor or the accused person and the witness will 
    forthwith reply, unless an objection is made by the court, judge-advocate, 
    prosecutor, or accused, in which case he shall not reply until the objection 
    is disposed of. The witness shall address his reply to the court.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    evidence of a witness as taken down shall be read to him after he has given 
    all his evidence and before he leaves the court, and shall, if necessary, be 
    corrected.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If 
    the witness denies the correctness of any part of the evidence when the same 
    is read over to him, the court may instead of correcting the evidence, 
    record the objection made to it by the witness.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If 
    the evidence is not given in English and the witness does not understand 
    that language the evidence as recorded shall be interpreted to him in the 
    language in which it was given or in a language which he understands.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>120</number> 
    Question to witness by court or judge-advocate—
<section><number>1</number> 
    At any time before the time for the second address of the accused the 
    presiding officer, the judge-advocate and with the permission of the court, 
    any member of the court may address any question to a witness.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Upon 
    any such question being answered, the officer conducting the proceeding 
    shall also put to the witness any question relative to that answer which he 
    may be requested to put by the prosecutor or the accused, and which the 
    court deems reasonable.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>121</number> 
    Recalling of witnesses and calling of witnesses in reply.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    At the request of the prosecutor or accused person, a witness may, by leave 
    of the court, be recalled at any time before the time for the second address 
    of the accused, for the purpose of having any question put to him through 
    the officer conducting the proceedings.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    witness may, in special cases, be allowed by the court to be called or 
    recalled by the prosecutor before the time for the second address of the 
    accused, for the purpose of rebutting any material statement made by a 
    witness for the defence upon his examination by the accused on any new 
    matter which the prosecutor could not reasonably have foreseen.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Where the accused has called witnesses to character, the prosecutor, before 
    the time for the second address of the accused, may call or recall witnesses 
    for the purpose of proving a previous conviction or entries in the service 
    records against the accused.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    court may call or recall any witness at any time before finding if it 
    considers that it is necessary for the ends of justice.  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>122</number> 
    Addresses may be in writing.—Addresses 
    by the prosecutor and the accused and the summing up of the judge-advocate 
    may either be given orally or be in writing, and, if in writing, shall be 
    read in open court.  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>123</number> 
    Provisions as to finding of insanity.—Where 
    the court finds either that the accused is of unsound mind and consequently 
    incapable of making his defence or that he committed the act alleged but was 
    by reason of unsoundness of mind incapable of knowing the nature of the act 
    or that it was wrong or contrary to law, the presiding officer shall date 
    and sign the finding and the proceedings, upon being signed by the 
    judge-advocate if any, shall be at once transmitted to be confirming 
    officer.  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>124</number> 
    Preservation of proceedings.—The 
    proceedings of a court-martial shall after promulgation be forwarded, as 
    circumstances require, to the office of the 

    1[Chief Legal Adviser] 
    and there preserved for not less, in the case of a general court-martial, 
    than seven years, and in the case of any other court-martial, than three 
    years.
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>125</number> Right of person 
    tried to copy of proceedings.—Every 
    person tried by a court martial shall, after the proceedings have been 
    signed by the presiding officer and where applicable, by the judge advocate, 
    and before they are destroyed, on a request made by such person in writing 
    for the supply of a copy of such proceedings, be furnished within a 
    reasonable time and free of cost a copy thereof including the proceedings 
    upon revision, if any.]  
 
 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>126</number> 
    Copy of proceedings not to be given in certain cases.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in rule 125, if the Central Government certifies that it 
    is against the interest or the security of the State or friendly relations 
    with foreign States to supply a copy of the proceedings or any part thereof 
    under the said rule, he shall not be furnished with such copy:  
 
Provided 
    that if the Central Government is satisfied that the person demanding the 
    copy is desirous of submitting a petition in accordance with the Act or 
    instituting any action in a court of law in relation to a finding or 
    sentence, it shall permit inspection of the proceedings by such person or 
    his legal adviser, if any, on the following conditions, namely:—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    the inspection shall be made at 
    such times and such places as the Central Government or any authority 
    authorised by it may direct, and  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    the person allowed to inspect the 
    proceedings shall, before such inspection furnish—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    an undertaking, in writing, that 
    he shall not make copies of the proceedings or any part thereof and that the 
    information or documents contained in such proceedings shall not be used by 
    him, for any purpose whatsoever other than for the purpose of submitting a 
    petition in accordance with the Act or instituting any action in a court of 
    law in relation to the said finding or sentence; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    a certificate that he is aware 
    that he may render himself liable to prosecution under sections 3 and 5 of 
    the Official Secrets Act, 1923 (19 of 1923), if he commits any act specified 
    in the said sections in relation to the documents or information contained 
    in the said proceedings.  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>127</number> 
    Loss of proceeding.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If before confirmation the original proceedings of a court-martial, or any 
    part thereof, are lost, a copy thereof, if any certified by the presiding 
    officer of or the judge-advocate at the court-martial may be accepted in 
    lieu of the original.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    there is no such copy, and sufficient evidence of the charge, finding, 
    sentence, and transactions of the court can be procured, that evidence may, 
    with the consent of the accused, be accepted in lieu of the original 
    proceedings, or part thereof lost.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In 
    any case mentioned above the finding and sentence may be confirmed, and 
    shall be as valid as if the original proceedings, or part thereof, had not 
    been lost.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If 
    the proceedings, or part thereof, were lost before confirmation, and there 
    is no such copy or evidence, or the accused refuses such consent as 
    mentioned above, the accused may be tried again, and on the issue of an 
    order convening the court for the trial, the finding and sentence of the 
    previous court, of which the proceedings were so lost, shall be null.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If, 
    after confirmation, the original proceedings of a court-martial or any part 
    thereof are lost and there is sufficient evidence of the charge, finding, 
    sentence, and transactions of the court, and of the confirmation of the 
    finding and sentence, that evidence shall be valid and sufficient record of 
    the trial for all purposes.  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>128</number> 
    Validity or irregular procedure in certain cases.—Whenever 
    it appears that a court-martial had jurisdiction to try any person and make 
    a finding and that there is legal evidence or a plea of guilty to justify 
    such finding, such finding and any sentence which the court-martial had 
    jurisdiction to pass thereon may be confirmed, and shall, if so confirmed, 
    be valid notwithstanding any deviation from these rules, or notwithstanding 
    that the charge-sheet has not been signed by the commanding officer or the 
    convening officer, provided that the charges have, in fact, before trial 
    been approved by the commanding officer and the convening officer, or 
    notwithstanding any defect or objection, technical or other unless it 
    appears that any injustice has been done to the offender and where any 
    finding and sentence are otherwise valid they shall not be invalid by reason 
    only of a failure to administer an oath or affirmation to the interpreter or 
    shorthand writer; but nothing in this rule shall relieve an officer from any 
    responsibility for any wilful or negligent disregard of any of these rules.  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>129</number> 
    Offences of witnesses and others.—When 
    any court-martial is of opinion that there is ground for inquiring into any 
    offence specified in sections 59 and 60 of the Act and committed before it 
    or brought under its notice in the course of its proceedings, or into any 
    act done before it or brought under its notice, in the course of its 
    proceedings which would if done by a person subject to the Act, have 
    constituted such an offence, such court-martial may proceed as follows, that 
    is to say—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    if the person who appears to have 
    committed the offence is subject to the Act, the court may bring his conduct 
    to the notice of the proper air force authority and may also order him to be 
    placed in air force custody with a view to his punishment by an officer 
    exercising authority under section 82 or section 86 or to his trial by 
    court- martial;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    if the person who appears to have 
    done the act is subject to the Army Act, 1950 or the Navy Act, 1957, the 
    court may bring his conduct to the notice of the proper military or naval 
    authority;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    if the person who appears to have 
    done the act is not subject to military, naval or air force law, then in the 
    case of acts which would, if done by a person subject to the Act, have 
    constituted an offence under clause (a), clause (b), clause (c) or clause 
    (d) of section 59 the officer who summoned the witness to appear or the 
    presiding officer of the court-martial, as the case may be, may forward a 
    written complaint to the nearest Magistrate of the first class having 
    jurisdiction, and in the case of acts which would, if done as aforesaid, 
    have constituted an offence under clause (e) of section 59 or under section 
    60, the court, after making any preliminary inquiry that may be necessary, 
    may send the case to the nearest Magistrate of the first class having 
    jurisdiction for inquiry or trial in accordance with section 476 of the Code 
    of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (8 of 1898)1.
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>130</number> 
    Convening the court and record of proceedings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The court may be convened and the proceedings of the court recorded in 
    accordance with Form F.3 in the Sixth Schedule, with such variations as the 
    circumstances of each case may require.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    officer convening the court shall appoint or detail the officers to form the 
    court, and may also appoint or detail such officers as waiting members as he 
    thinks expedient. Such officers should have held commissions for not less 
    than one year, but if any officers, who have held commission for not less 
    than three years, are available they shall be selected in preference to 
    officers of less service.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A 
    provost-marshal, assistant provost-marshal or officer who is a prosecutor or 
    witness for prosecution shall not be appointed a member of the court.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>131</number> 
    Charge.—The 
    statement of an offence may be made briefly in any language sufficient to 
    describe or disclose an offence under the Act.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>132</number> 
    Trial of several accused persons.—The 
    court may be sworn at the same time to try any number of accused persons 
    than present before it, but except as provided in rule 41, the trial of each 
    accused person shall be separate.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>133</number> 
    Challenges.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The names of the presiding officer and members of the court shall be read 
    over to the accused who shall thereupon be asked if he objects to be tried 
    by any of these officers.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any 
    objection shall be decided as provided for in section 129 and rule 52, the 
    vacancies being filled from among the waiting members, if any, or by fresh 
    members being appointed by the convening officer.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>134</number> 
    Swearing or affirming the court, judge-advocate etc.—The 
    provisions of rules 53, 54 and 55 relating to administering and taking of 
    oaths and making of affirmations shall apply to every Summary General Court-Martial.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>135</number> 
    Arraignment.—When 
    the court is sworn or affirmed, the judge-advocate, if any, or the presiding 
    officer shall inform the accused then to be tried, the offence with which he 
    is charged, if necessary, with an explanation giving him full information of 
    the act or omission with which he is charged, and shall ask the accused 
    whether he is guilty or not of the offence.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>136</number> 
    Plea to jurisdiction.—If 
    a special plea to the general jurisdiction is offered by the accused, and is 
    considered by the court to be proved, the court shall report the same to the 
    convening officer.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>137</number> 
    Evidence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The witnesses for the prosecution will be called and the accused shall be 
    allowed to cross-examine them and to call any available witnesses for his 
    defence.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An 
    oath or affirmation as laid down in rule 118 shall be administered to every 
    witness, if so required by the Act, before he gives his evidence, by one of 
    the persons specified in that rule.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>138</number> 
    Defence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The accused shall be asked what he has to say in his defence and shall be 
    allowed to make his defence. He may be allowed to have any person to assist 
    him during the trial, whether a legal adviser or any other person.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    court, or the judge-advocate, if any, may question the accused for the 
    purpose of enabling him to explain any circumstances appearing in his 
    statement or in the evidence against him. The accused shall not render 
    himself liable to punishment by refusing to answer such questions or by 
    giving answers to them which he knows not to be true, but the court may draw 
    such inference from such refusal or answers as it thinks fit.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>139</number> 
    Record of the evidence and defence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The judge-advocate, if any, or the presiding officer shall take down or 
    cause to be taken down a brief record of the evidence of the witnesses at 
    the trial and of the defence of the accused, the record so taken down shall 
    be attached to the proceedings:  
 
Provided 
    that if it appears to the convening officer that exigencies of the service 
    or other circumstances prevent compliance with this provision, he may direct 
    that the trial may be carried on without any such brief record being taken 
    down.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    the accused pleads “guilty” the summary of evidence, if any, may be read and 
    attached to the proceedings, and it shall not be necessary for the court to 
    hear witnesses for the prosecution respecting matters contained in the 
    summary of evidence so read.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>140</number> 
    Finding and sentence.—The 
    court shall then be closed to consider its finding. If the finding on any 
    charge is “guilty” the court may receive any evidence as to previous 
    convictions and character which is available. The court shall then 
    deliberate in closed court as to its sentence.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>141</number> 
    Adjournment.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A Summary General Court-Martial may adjourn from time to time and from place 
    to place and may when necessary inspect any place.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    proceedings shall be held in open court, in the presence of the accused, 
    except on any deliberation among the members, when the court may be closed.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>142</number> 
    Application of rules.—The 
    rules specified in the Table below shall, so far as practicable, apply to 
    Summary General Courts-Martial as if Summary Courts-Martial were District 
    Courts-Martial.  
  
 

Table
  
 
Rule     24          :     
    Disposal of the charge or adjournment for taking down the summary of 
    evidence.
 
”          25          
    :     Remand of accused.  
 
”          26          :     
    Application of rules 24 and 25 to officers exercising powers of a commanding 
    officer.
 
”          39          :     
    Opportunity for accused to prepare defence.
 
”          40          :     
    Warning of accused for trial.
 
”          42          :     
    Suspension of rules on the grounds of the exigencies of the service or the 
    necessities of discipline.
 
”          44          :     
    Adjournment for insufficient number of officers.
 
”          57          :     
    Objection by accused to the charge.
 
”          59          :     
    Special plea to the jurisdiction.
 
”          60          :     
    General plea of “guilty” or “not guilty”.
 
”          61          :     
    Plea in bar.
 
”          62          :     
    Procedure after plea of “guilty”.
 
”          63          :     
    Withdrawal of plea of “not guilty”.
 
”          70          :     
    Consideration of finding.
 
”          71          :     
    Form and record of finding.
 
”          72          :     
    Procedure on acquittal.
 
”          73          :     
    Procedure on conviction.
 
”          74          :     
    Sentence.
 
”          75          :     
    Recommendation to mercy.
 
”          76          :     
    Signing and transmission of proceedings.
 
”          77          :     
    Revision.
 
”          78          :     
    Promulgation.
 
”          79          :     
    Mitigation of sentence on partial confirmation.
 
”          80          :     
    Confirmation notwithstanding informality in or excess of punishment.
 
”          81          :     
    Member or prosecutor not to confirm proceedings.
 
”          83          :     
    Responsibility of Presiding Officer.
 
”          84          :     
    Power of court over address of prosecutor and accused.
 
”          85          :     
    Procedure on trial of accused persons together.
 
”          87          :     
    Sitting in closed court.
 

1[”    
    87A           :     Court Martial to be public.]
 
”          90          :     
    Suspension of trial.
 
”          91          :     
    Proceedings on death or illness of the accused.
 
”          92          :     
    Death, retirement or absence of Presiding Officer.
 
”          93          :     
    Presence of members during trial.
 
”        100          :     
    Custody and inspection of proceedings.
 
”        101          :     
    Transmission of proceedings after finding.
 
”        102          :     
    Defending officer and friend of accused.
 
”        110          :     
    Disqualification of judge-advocate.
 
”        111          :     
    Powers and duties of judge-advocate.
 
”        123          :     
    Provisions as to finding of insanity.
 
”        124          :     
    Preservation of proceedings.
 
”        125          :     
    Right of person tried to copies of proceedings.
 
”        126          :     Copy 
    of proceedings not to be given in certain cases.
 
”        127          
    :     Loss of proceedings.  
 
”        128          :     
    Validity of irregular procedure in certain cases.
 
”        129          :     
    Offences of witnesses and others.
 

 
 

 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>143</number> 
    Evidence of opinion of convening officer.—Any 
    statement in an order convening a summary general court-martial as to the 
    opinion of the convening officer shall be conclusive evidence of that 
    opinion, but this rule shall not prejudice the proof at any time of any such 
    opinion when not so stated.  
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>144</number> 
    Committal warrant.—A 
    warrant for the committal of a person to a civil prison, or to a military or 
    an Air Force prison or to detention barracks under the provisions of section 
    165, section 166 or section 170 shall be in the relevant Form given in the 
    Seventh Schedule. Such warrant shall be signed and forwarded by the 
    commanding officer of the prisoner or by an officer superior in command to 
    such commanding officer or by any staff officer of such superior officer.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>145</number> 
    Warrants under section 171.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every warrant issued under section 171 shall be in the relevant Form given 
    in the Seventh Schedule, and shall be signed by the officer making the order 
    in pursuance of which such warrant is issued, or by his staff officer.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Prescribed Officer for the purpose of forwarding the warrant under section 
    171 shall be the officer commanding the unit or detachment to which the 
    person belongs or is attached.   

 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>146</number> 
    Sentence of cashiering or dismissal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A sentence of cashiering awarded by a court-martial shall take effect from 
    the date on which the sentence is promulgated to the person under sentence:  
 
Provided 
    that when cashiering is not combined with imprisonment or death and the 
    confirming officer has specified a date for cashiering to take effect, the 
    cashiering shall take effect from the date of promulgation or from the date 
    so specified, whichever is later.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    sentence of dismissal awarded by a court-martial shall take effect from the 
    date on which the sentence is promulgated to the person under the sentence, 
    or from such subsequent date as may be specified by the commanding officer 
    at the time of such promulgation:  
 
Provided 
    that where dismissal is combined with imprisonment or detention which is 
    carried out in a military or air force prison, or in military or air force 
    detention barracks, detention cells or other military or air force custody, 
    or with field punishment, the dismissal shall not take effect until the date 
    on which the prisoner is duly released from such military or air force 
    prison or military or air force detention barracks, detention cells or other 
    military or air force custody, or until the completion of the field 
    punishment, unless such field punishment is remitted by competent authority:  
 
Provided 
    further that, when dismissal is combined with imprisonment which is carried 
    out in a civil prison, the dismissal shall not take effect until the date on 
    which the prisoner is received in the civil prison.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>147</number> 
    Custody of person under sentence of death.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in rule 22, when a person is sentenced by 
    court-martial to suffer death, the commanding officer for the time being of 
    such person may, if he thinks fit, by a warrant in the relevant form in the 
    Seventh Schedule, commit the said person for safe custody in an air force, 
    military or civil prison or in air force or military detention barracks 
    pending confirmation or the carrying out of the sentence.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where a person under sentence of death is in air force custody, or in air 
    force prison or detention barracks, the rules, regulations and orders (other 
    than those relating to work and training) governing such custody, prison or 
    detention barracks shall, subject to the following provisions, apply to him, 
    namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    he shall be deprived of every article 
    which it might be dangerous or inexpedient to leave in his possession.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    he shall be confined in a 
    separate cell and kept apart from all other persons under sentence of death, 
    imprisonment or detention or in custody;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    he shall be kept by day and by 
    night in the constant charge of two officers, warrant officers or 
    non-commissioned officers;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    he shall not be requested to 
    perform any duties other than to keep clean his person and cell;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    he shall be allowed daily 
    physical exercise;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    he shall be granted facilities to 
    correspond with his relatives, friends and legal advisers;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    he shall be permitted to smoke;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    he shall be visited once daily by 
    the commanding officer or the commandant of the unit, prison or detention 
    barracks as well as by the medical officer;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    he shall not be visited by any 
    person other than a member of the staff on duty unless prior permission in 
    writing has been given by the confirming authority or an authority specified 
    by the confirming authority in his behalf;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>    where the confirming authority or 
    the officer specified by it in this behalf has given a written permission to 
    any person other than a member of the staff on duty to visit the person 
    sentenced to death the visit shall take place in the sight of a member of 
    the staff, and unless the confirming authority or the specified officer 
    orders otherwise, in the hearing of a member of the staff.  
 
Explanation.—In 
    this rule reference to “a member of the staff” means a member of the staff 
    of the air force unit, prison or detention barracks in which the person 
    under sentence has been held in custody.  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>148</number> 
    Opportunity for petition against sentence of death.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    While confirming a sentence of death, the confirming authority shall specify 
    the period within which the person sentenced may, after the sentence has 
    been promulgated to him, submit a petition against the finding or sentence 
    against him of the court-martial.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    person against whom a sentence of death has been confirmed shall, at the 
    time of promulgation, be informed of his rights under sub-section (2) of 
    section 161 and of the period specified by the confirming authority within 
    which he may, if he so wishes to do, submit a petition against the finding 
    or sentence against him of the court-martial.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Every petition against a finding or sentence submitted by a person against 
    whom a sentence of death has been confirmed, and every order in respect of 
    such petition shall be transmitted, where the confirming authority is the 
    Chief of the Air Staff or the Central Government, through the Air officer 
    incharge Administration at the Air Headquarters and in any other case, 
    through the confirming officer.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A 
    sentence of death shall not be carried into effect until the expiry of the 
    period specified by the confirming authority under sub-rule (1) or if, 
    within the period so specified, the person under sentence submits a petition 
    against the finding or sentence of the court-martial, until the authority 
    legally competent to dispose of such petition finally, after considering the 
    petition, orders that the sentence of death may be carried into effect.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>149</number> 
    Death warrant.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The officer commanding the air force station to which the person sentenced 
    belongs or is attached, or where there is no such air force station, the air 
    or other officer commanding the command or the group to which such person 
    belongs or is attached shall nominate a provost-marshal or other officer not 
    below the rank of Squadron Leader who shall be responsible for the due 
    execution of the sentence of death passed under the Act, and shall issue to 
    such officer the death warrant in the relevant form contained in the Seventh 
    Schedule.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    officer specified in sub-rule (1) shall not issue the death warrant until he 
    is satisfied that having regard to the provisions of rule 148, the sentence 
    of death may be carried into effect.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No 
    sentence of death passed under the Act shall be carried into effect until 
    the death warrant has been received by the provost-marshal or other officer 
    nominated under sub-rule (1).  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>150</number> 
    Execution of sentence of death.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    On receipt of the death warrant, the provost-marshal or other officer, 
    nominated under sub-rule (1) of rule 149 shall—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    inform the person sentenced as 
    soon as possible of the date on which the sentence will be carried out;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    if the person sentenced has been 
    committed to an air force, military or civil prison or to air force or 
    military detention barracks, obtain the custody of his person by issuing a 
    warrant in the relevant form contained in the Seventh Schedule.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    proceed to carry out the sentence 
    as required by the death warrant and in accordance with any general or 
    special instructions which may from time to time be given by or under the 
    authority of the Chief of the Air Staff.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    During the execution of a sentence of death passed under the Act, no person, 
    except those specified below, shall be present without the authority of the 
    officer who issued the death warrant. The following persons shall attend the 
    execution of the sentence of death:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the provost-marshal or other 
    officer who is responsible for the due execution of the sentence in 
    accordance with these rules;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    a commissioned medical officer of 
    the armed forces of the Union.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    an officer nominated by the 
    officer who issued the death warrant, who is able to identify the person 
    under sentence as the person described in the death warrant and as the 
    person who was tried and sentenced by the court-martial mentioned therein;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    such non-commissioned officers as 
    may be detailed by the provost-marshal or the other officer aforesaid for 
    escort and security purposes or to assist at the execution;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    if the execution is carried into 
    effect in an air force unit or station, the officer for the time being in 
    command of such station or unit.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    After the sentence of death has been carried into effect, the 
    provost-marshal or other officer nominated under sub-rule (1) of rule 149 
    shall complete or cause to be completed parts II and III of the death 
    warrant and shall, without unnecessary delay return the completed death 
    warrant to the officer who had issued the same to him.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>151</number> 
    Procedure on pardon, or where proceedings are set aside or where sentence of 
    death is commuted or remitted.—Where 
    a person sentenced to death is pardoned, or where the proceedings against 
    him are set aside under the Act or where the sentence of death is not 
    confirmed or is commuted or remitted under the Act, then—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    if he is in custody in an air force, 
    military or civil prison, or in an air force or military detention barracks 
    under a warrant issued under rule 147, a further warrant in the relevant 
    form given in the Seventh Schedule shall be issued by the commanding officer 
    of such person; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    if he has been detained in air force 
    custody he shall be released or, as the case may be, any warrant which may 
    be necessary to give effect to the sentence as so commuted or remitted shall 
    be issued by such commanding officer.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>152</number> 
    Field punishment.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A court-martial or an officer exercising authority under section 82 may, for 
    the purpose of awarding field punishment under the Act, sentence an offender 
    for a period not exceeding, in the case of a court-martial three months, and 
    in the case of such an officer, twenty-eight days, to one of the following 
    punishments, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    field punishment No. 1.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    field punishment No. 2.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where an offender is sentenced to field punishment No. 1, he may, during the 
    continuance of his sentence unless the court-martial or the officer, as the 
    case may be, otherwise directs, be punished as follows :—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    he may be kept in irons, that is 
    to say, in fetters or hand-cuffs or both fetters and hand-cuffs, and may be 
    secured so as to prevent his escape,  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    when in irons, he may be attached 
    for a period or periods not exceeding two hours in any one day to a fixed 
    object, but he must not be so attached during more than three out of any 
    four consecutive days nor during more than twenty-one days in all.  
 
Explanation.—(1) 
    The offenders must be attached so as to be standing firmly on his feet 
    which, if tied, must not be more than twelve inches apart and it must be 
    possible for him to move each foot at least three inches. If he is tied 
    round the body there must be no restriction of his breathing. If his arms or 
    wrists are tied, there must be six inches of play between them and the fixed 
    object. His arms must hang either by the side of his body or behind his 
    back.  
 
Explanation.—(2) 
    For the purpose of this punishment, irons should be used when available, but 
    straps or ropes may be used in lieu of them when necessary. Any straps or 
    ropes used for the purpose must be of sufficient width to inflict no bodily 
    harm, and leave no permanent mark on the offender.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    He may be subjected to the like 
    labour, employment and restraint and dealt with in like manner as if he were 
    undergoing a sentence of rigorous imprisonment.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Where an offender is sentenced to field punishment No. 2, the provisions of 
    sub-rule (2) with respect to field punishment No.1 shall apply in his case 
    except that he shall not be liable to be attached to a fixed object as 
    provided in clause (b) of that sub-rule.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Every portion of a field punishment shall be inflicted in such a manner as 
    is calculated not to cause injury or leave any permanent mark on the 
    offender; and a portion of a field punishment must be discontinued upon a 
    report by a responsible Medical Officer that the continuance of that portion 
    would be prejudicial to the offender’s health.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> 
    Field punishment shall be carried out within the unit to which the offender 
    belongs or is attached so long as that unit is actually on the move, but 
    when the unit is halted at any place where there is a provost-marshal or any 
    other officer appointed by the commander of the forces or the air forces in 
    the field to execute such punishment, the punishment shall be carried out 
    under the orders of such officer.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> When 
    the unit to which the offender belongs or is attached is actually on the 
    move, an offender awarded field punishment No. 1 shall be exempt from the 
    operation of clause (b) of sub-rule (2) but all offenders awarded field 
    punishment shall march with their unit, carry their arms and equipment, 
    perform all their air force duties as well as extra fatigue duties, and be 
    treated as defaulters.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>153</number> 
    Nature of punishment of detention.—A 
    sentence of detention awarded by a court-martial or by an officer exercising 
    authority under section 82 may be carried out—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    in a military or air force 
    detention barrack;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    in a barrack detention room under 
    the control of a military or air force unit;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    on active service, when the unit 
    is halted at any place where there is a provost-marshal, under the orders of 
    such officer.  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>154</number> 
    General.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A court of inquiry is an assembly of officers or of officers and warrant 
    officers directed to collect evidence and if so required, to report with 
    regard to any matter which may be referred to them.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    court of inquiry may be assembled by the officer in command of any unit or 
    portion of the Air Force.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    court may consist of any number of officers of any rank or of one or more 
    officers together with one or more warrant officers. The members of the 
    court may belong to any branch or department of the service, according to 
    the nature of the investigation.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Previous notice shall be given of the time and place of the meeting of a 
    court of inquiry, and of all adjournments of the court, to all persons 
    concerned in the inquiry (except a prisoner of war who is still absent).  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> It 
    is the duty of a court of inquiry to put such questions to a witness as it 
    thinks desirable for testing the truth or accuracy of any evidence he has 
    given and otherwise for eliciting the truth.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    whole of the proceedings of a court of inquiry shall be forwarded by the 
    presiding officer to the officer who assembled the court.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The 
    court may be reassembled as often as the officer who assembled the court may 
    direct, for the purpose of examining additional witnesses, or further 
    examining any witnesses, or recording further information.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>155</number> 
    Courts of inquiry under section 107 for the purpose of determining the 
    illegal absence of persons subject to the Act.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A court of inquiry under section 107 shall, when assembled, require the 
    attendance of such witnesses as it thinks sufficient to prove the absence 
    and other facts specified as matter of inquiry in that section.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    court of inquiry shall take down the evidence given by them in writing and 
    at the end of proceedings shall make a declaration of the conclusions at 
    which it has arrived in respect of the facts it is assembled to inquire 
    into.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    court of inquiry shall examine all witnesses who may be desirous of coming 
    forward on behalf of the absentee, and shall put such questions to them as 
    may be desirable for testing the truth or accuracy of any evidence they have 
    given, and otherwise for eliciting the truth, and the court in making its 
    declaration shall give weight to the evidence of all such witnesses.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    court of inquiry shall administer the same oath or affirmation to the 
    witnesses as if the court were a court-martial, but the members of such 
    court shall not themselves be sworn or affirmed.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    commanding officer of the unit to which the absent person belongs shall 
    enter in the court-martial book of the unit a record of the declaration of 
    the court, and the original proceedings will be destroyed.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Any 
    person, the subject of the inquiry, shall be entitled to a copy of the 
    declaration of the court, to be supplied by the person having custody of the 
    court-martial book, on payment at the rate laid down in sub-rule (7) of rule 
    156.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>156</number> 
    Courts of inquiry other than those held under section 107.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The court shall be guided by the written instructions of the authority which 
    assembled the court. The instructions shall be full and specific, and shall 
    state the general character of the information required. They shall also 
    state whether a report is required or not.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Save 
    in the case of a prisoner of war who is still absent, whenever any inquiry 
    affects the character or service reputation of a person subject to the Act, 
    full opportunity must be afforded to such person of being present throughout 
    the inquiry and of making any statements and of giving any evidence he may 
    wish to make or give, and of cross-examining and witness whose evidence, in 
    his opinion, affects his character or service reputation, and producing any 
    witnesses in defence of his character or service reputation.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> When 
    a court of inquiry is held on prisoners of war, and in any other case in 
    which the officer who assembled the court has so directed, the evidence 
    shall be taken on oath or affirmation, in which case the court shall 
    administer the same oath or affirmation to witnesses as if the court were a 
    court-martial.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    officer who assembled the court shall, when the court is held on a returned 
    prisoner of war or on a prisoner of war who is still absent, direct the 
    court to record its opinion whether the person concerned was taken prisoner 
    through his own wilful neglect of duty, or whether he served with or under, 
    or aided the enemy; he shall also direct the court to record its opinion in 
    the case of a returned prisoner of war, whether he returned as soon as 
    possible to the service, and in the case of prisoner of war still absent, 
    whether he failed to return to the service when it was possible for him to 
    do so. The officer who assembled the court shall also record his own opinion 
    on these points. In other cases, the court shall give no opinion on the 
    conduct of any person unless so directed by the officer who assembled the 
    court.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    members of the court shall not themselves be sworn or affirmed, but when the 
    court is a court of inquiry on recovered prisoners of war, the members shall 
    make the following declaration:—  
 
 “I...................A..................B......................, do declare 
    upon my honour that I will duly and impartially inquire into and give my 
    opinion as to the circumstances in which ...............became a prisoner of 
    war, according to the true spirit and meaning of the rules and regulations 
    made under the Air Force Act, 1950, and I do further declare, upon my honour, 
    that I will not on any account or at any time, disclose or discover my own 
    vote or opinion, or that of any particular member of the court, unless 
    required to do so by competent authority.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    proceedings of a court of inquiry, or any confession or statement or answer 
    to a question made or given at a court of inquiry, shall not be admissible 
    in evidence against a person subject to Air Force Law, nor shall any 
    evidence respecting the proceedings of the court be given against any such 
    person except upon the trial of such person for wilfully giving false 
    evidence before that court.  
 


    1[(7) Any person 
    subject to the Act whose character or service reputation is in the opnion of 
    the Chief of the Air Staff, affected by anything in the evidence before or 
    in the report of a court of inquiry shall be entitled to a copy of the 
    proceedings of such court unless the Chief of the Air Staff sees reason to 
    order otherwise.  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> Any 
    person subject to the Act who is tred by a court-martial in respect of any 
    matter or thing which has been reported on by a court of inquiry shall be 
    entitled to a copy of the proceedngs of such court, including any report 
    made by the Court:  
 
Provided 
    that if the Chief of the Air Staff considers that it is against the 
    interests or the security of the State or friendly relations with a foreign 
    State to supply a copy of the proceedings or any part thereof, such person 
    shall not be furnished with such copy, but in such cases he shall, subject 
    to suitable precautions as to security, be permitted inspection of such 
    portions of the proceedings of the court of inquiry, on the basis of which 
    the charges, on which he is arraigned before the court-martial, have been 
    framed.  
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> A 
    copy of the proceedings of the court of inquiry shall be furnished under 
    sub-rules (7) and (8) on payment for the same of a sum calculated at the 
    rate of fifty paise for every two hundred words or part thereof.  
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> A person 
    subject to the Act before he is, under sub-rule (7) or sub-rule (8), 
    furnshed wth a copy of the proceedngs of the court of inquiry or is permtted 
    to inspect any portion of the proceedngs shall be required to render 
    certificate that he is aware that he may render himself liable to 
    prosectuion under the Official Secrets Act, 1923 (19 of 1923) for any breach 
    of the provision of the said Act, in relation to such proceedings or portion 
    thereof.]
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>157</number> Imposition of 
    collective fines under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 90.—The 
    collective fine imposed under sub-section (1) of section 90 shall not exceed 
    the current official prices of the weapons or part of the weapon, the loss 
    or their of which was reported upon by the court of inquiry, or where more 
    than one such weapon or parts of weapons were so reported upon, the 
    aggregate of the current official prices of such weapons or parts of 
    weapons”].
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>158</number> 
    Conditions prescribed under section 4 (xxiii) (b).—For 
    the purposes of the Act and these rules, the expression “officer”, in 
    relation to a person subject to the Act, includes a person gazetted, 
    commissioned or in pay as an officer of the regular Army or the Navy, as the 
    case may be, when the person subject to the Act is serving under any of the 
    following conditions, namely:—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    when he has been placed under the 
    orders of such officer;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    when he is being conveyed in or is on 
    board a vehicle, vessel or aircraft which is being commanded by such 
    officer;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    when he is serving in or is a patient 
    in a hospital or medical establishment in which such officer is on duty;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    when he forms part of or is serving 
    with a body of the Air Force which is acting with a body of the regular Army 
    or the Navy, and any one of these bodies is on active service.
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    when he forms part of or is serving 
    with a body of the Air Force acting in an emergency with a body of the 
    regular Army or the Navy and an order in writing is made by the officer 
    commanding that body of the Air Force that an emergency exists and it is 
    necessary for the officers of the regular Army or the Navy, as the case may 
    be, to exercise command over persons subject to the Act;
 
Note.—A copy of every such order shall 
    forwith be sent to the Central Government;
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    when he is serving in any place in 
    which or with any body of the Air Force with which, there is present any 
    officer of the regular Army or the Navy and the Central Government has by 
    special order declared that it is necessary for the officers of the regular 
    Army or the Navy to exercise command over persons subject to the Act in that 
    place or with that body of the Air Force.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>159</number> 
    Conditions prescribed under section 4 (xxvii).—When 
    a person subject to the Act has been placed under the orders of an officer, 
    junior commissioned officer, warrant officer, petty officer or 
    non-commissioned officer of the regular Army or the Navy, such officer, 
    junior commissioned officer, warrant officer, petty officer or 
    non-commissioned officer, as well as those other officers, junior 
    commissioned officers, warrant officers, petty officers or non-commissioned 
    officers of the regular Army or the Navy who are directly superior in 
    command to such officer, junior commissioned officer, warrant officer, petty 
    officer or non-commissioned officer shall for the purposes of the Act and 
    these rules be superior officers in relation to such persons.
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>160</number> 
    Prescribed officer under section 7
<section><number>1</number>.—The 
    prescribed officer for the purposes of sub-section (1) of section 7 shall be 
    the officers commanding a station wing, squadron or unit, nominated in this 
    behalf by the Air or other officer commanding the command or group in which 
    the person is for the time being serving.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>160A</number> Prescribed 
    officers under setion 20(3).—The 
    Prescribed Officer for the purpose of sub-section (3) of section 20 shall be 
    the air or other officer commanding a group 

    2[and in respect of 
    airmen serving at Air Headquarters or unit directly under Air Headquarters, 
    the Air Officer incharge Administration.]]
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>161</number> 
    Prescribed officer under section 80.—The 
    prescribed officer for the purposes of section 80 shall be the officer 
    commanding the Forces in the field, or the air or other officer commanding 
    the Command, group, or in the field any detached portion of the air force, 
    in which the trial was held, or any officer superior in command to such air 
    or other officer.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>162</number> 
    Prescribed officer under section 92
<section><number>i</number>.—The 
    prescribed officer for the purposes of clause (i) of section 92 shall be the 
    Chief of the Air Staff.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>163</number> 
    Prescribed officer under section 94 of the Act.—The 
    prescribed officer for purposes of section 94 shall, in the case of an 
    officer or a warrant officer, be the Chief of the Air Staff and, in the case 
    of a person other than an officer or a warrant officer, be the officer 
    empowered to convene a court-martial for his trial.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>164</number> 
    Prescribed authority under section 98.—Any 
    penal deduction from the pay and allowances of a person subject to the Act, 
    made under Chapter VIII thereof, may be remitted as provided below—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    the Central Government may remit 
    to any extent any penal deduction from the pay and allowances of any person.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    where an airman absents himself 
    without leave for a period not exceeding five days, the officer who is in 
    command of the unit, from which he absented himself, at the time when such 
    absence terminates, or the Chief of the Air Staff may, if a satisfactory 
    explanation is given by such airman, remit in whole or in part the 
    forfeiture of pay and allowances to which that absence renders him liable 
    provided that the airman is not convicted by a court-martial on a charge for 
    such absence.  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    A forfeiture of pay and 
    allowances incurred by any person subject to the Act owing to his absence as 
    a prisoner of war may in whole or in part be remitted by the Chief of Air 
    Staff or by the officer commanding the air forces in the field, except when 
    such forfeiture has been ordered by the Central Government under clause (h) 
    of section 91.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>165</number> 
    Prescribed authorities under sections 99 and 100.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The prescribed authorities for the purposes of sections 99 and 100 shall be 
    the officer commanding the air forces in the field under whom the person was 
    serving at the time he became a prisoner of war or was found missing, or the 
    Director of Personal Services, Air Headquarters, or any authority superior 
    either to the said officer commanding or the said Director.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any 
    such authority may, in its discretion and subject to a maximum of 50 per 
    cent of the pay and allowances of the prisoner of war or the person missing, 
    make such provisions from time to time for the dependents of the prisoner of 
    war or the person missing, as the case may be, for whom in its judgment such 
    provision should be made.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>166</number> 
    Prescribed officers under section 108
<section><number>1</number>.—The 
    following shall be the prescribed officers for the purposes of sub-section 
    (1) of section 108, namely:—  
 

1[(a)    
    an air or other officer commanding a command or an independent group, may 
    appoint any person subject to the Act and serving under him, to exercise the 
    powers of a provost-marshal in relation to the persons serving under his 
    command of such air or other officer;]  
 <subsection>
<number>b</number>    the Air Officer incharge of 
    Administration at the Air Headquarters may appoint any person subject to the 
    Act serving in the Air Headquarters or the units directly under the Air 
    Headquarters to exercise the powers of a provost-marshal in relation to all 
    persons serving in the Air Headquarters and such units.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    an officer commanding the air forces in 
    the field may appoint any person subject to Act and serving under him to 
    exercise the powers of a provost-marshal in relation to such air forces.
 
 



 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>167</number> 
    Prescribed officers under section 124.—The 
    prescribed officers for the purposes of section 124 shall be the air or 
    other officer commanding the command or the officer commanding the Forces or 
    the air forces in the field, under whom the accused person is serving.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>168</number> 
    Prescribed officer under section 141
<section><number>1</number>.—The 
    prescribed officer for the purposes of sub-section (1) of section 141 shall 
    be the officer commanding the unit to which the person appears to have 
    belonged, or alleges that he belongs or had belonged, but:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    in the case of officers, the Director 
    of Personnel (Officers) ; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    in the case of airmen, Officer 
    Commanding, Air Force Record Office, shall also be the prescribed officer.
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>169</number> 
    Manner of custody under section 144(4).—For 
    the purposes of sub-section (4) of section 144, the accused shall be 
    confined in such manner as may, in the opinion of the proper air force 
    authority, be best calculated to keep him securely without unnecessary 
    harshness.  
  
  
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>170</number> 
    Prescribed officer under section 145.—The 
    prescribed officer for the purposes of section 145 shall be the Chief of the 
    Air Staff or the air or other officer who has powers to convene a 
    court-martial for the trial of the accused person.  
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>171</number> 
    Prescribed officer under section 161(2).—The 
    prescribed officer for the purposes of sub-section (2) of section 161 shall 
    be any officer superior in command to the officer who confirmed the 
    proceedings, provided that he has powers not less than that of an air 
    officer commanding a command.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>172</number> 
    Prescribed officer under section 162 and annulment of proceedings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The prescribed officer for the purposes of section 162 shall be any officer 
    superior in command to the officer who confirmed, the proceedings.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    proceedings of any court-martial may be annulled under the said section 
    after considering the advice of the Chief Legal Adviser or Deputy Chief 
    Legal Adviser.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>173</number> 
    Prescribed officer under section 166
<section><number>1</number>.—The 
    prescribed officer for the purposes of sub-section (1) of section 166 shall 
    be any officer superior in command to the officer who confirmed the 
    proceedings.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>174</number> 
    Prescribed officer under section 177.—The 
    prescribed officer for the purposes of section 177 shall be the air or other 
    officer commanding a command but in relation to persons convicted on active 
    service, the officer commanding the air forces in the field shall also be 
    the prescribed officer.  
  
  
  
 
  


</article><form>
 



The Air 
Force Rules, 1969
 

 
 


Second Schedule
 


(See
rule 23)
 


FORM OF DELAY REPORT UNDER 
SECTION 104
 


Air Force Act, 1950
 


Eight Day Delay Report 
pursuant to the Air Force Act, 1950, section 104 and rule 23 of the Air Force 
Rule, 1969.
 


First (Second, Third 
...........................etc.) Report
 


unit 
at................................                               Reference 
No............................ Command/Group 
........................................Date 
.................................................
 


          1.  Number, rank  
and name of the accused....................................................................
 



             ..............................................................................................................................
 


          2. Particulars of 
offences:—
 


 


Sl. No.       
  Date of                  
  Particulars of offence (Give       Date of 
  Discovery              
 


 
           
  Commission             
  facts, brief)                             
  of offence
 


 
 


 
 


 


 
 


 
 


          3. Date and 
nature of initial arrest i.e., close or open .........
 


          4. Total period 
of arrest upto the date of this report (to be calculated  

as 
per section 39, Air Force Act, 1950).
 


             (a)     
Close arrest  Total period in 
days
 


                  From 
...........................to..........................  
..........................................................
 


                  From 
...........................to..........................  
..........................................................
 


                  Total 
period in close arrest ..............days
 


             (b)     
Open Arrest Total period in 
days.
 


                  From 
...........................to..........................  
..........................................................
 


                  From 
...........................to..........................  
..........................................................
 



                                                            
....................................
 


                  Total 
period in open arrest ..................................................days
 



                                                            
..............................
 


             (c)     Total 
period of arrest (i.e............................................days (a) plus 
(b) above)
 


          5. On the date of 
this report the accused
 


              is in close 
arrest*
 


              is in open 
arrest*
 


              has been 
released without
 


              prejudice to 
re-arrest*
 


          6. Reasons for 
his continued retention in arrest are 
.......................................................
 


          7. If the total 
period of retention in arrest exceeds 60/90 days quote Air Headquarters letter 
communicating the approval of the C.A.S./Central Government for continued 
retention in arrest............. Air/HQ/...................... dated ......
 


          8. Investigation 
under rule 24 of the Air Force Rules, 1969:—
 


              completed on 
the same date *
 


              completed on 
..................(date)*
 


              is in 
progress.*
 


        (a) Commenced on 
...............(date) and
 


        (b) Reasons for 
delay in the commencement/completion of the investigation are 
.................................
 


          9. Summary of 
evidence:—
 



                                                                                
completed on the same date*
 



                                                                                
completed on ............(date)*
 



                                                                                
is in progress*
 


             (a) Commenced 
on ..............(date) and 
 


             (b) Reasons 
for delay in the commencement/completion of the summary of evidence are 
..............................................................................................................
 


        10. Application for 
trial:—
 


           *(a)     made 
vide letter No 
.......................................................................... 
dated ..................................
 


           *(b) not yet 
made 
because.............................................................................................

 


      
..................................................................................................................................
 


        11. Date of trial 
has not yet been fixed*/has been fixed as 
..............................................*
 



                                                                              
Name and Rank
 



                                                                              
Officer Commanding
 



                                                                              
............................... (Unit)
 


To 
 


      The 
................................................................................................(Convening 
Officer)
 


Copy to:—
 


        (1)  Air or other 
officers commanding intermediate formations            
 


        (2)  *C.L.A. 
.........................................Air HQ        In the case of third and

 


              *D.C.L.A. 
.........................Command HQ          subsequent reports only. 

 



                                                                        [See 
rule 23(2) of the Air Force 
                                                                  Rules, 1969.]
 


—————
 


*Strike out whatever is not 
required.
 

 
</form><form>
 



The Air 
Force Rules, 1969
 


 
 


Third Schedule
 


[See rule 24 (9)]
 


Froms of Summons
 



1[Form C-1
 


form of summons to a witness to attend the hearing of the
 

charge by the commanding officer or to attend the  

taking of a summary of evidence
 


 
 



To.................................
 


(a) whereas a charge for having committed an offence 
triable by Court Martial has been preferred before me against.
 


(b) Number ................................. Rank 
................................. Name ................................. Unit 
................................. and whereas I have directed the hearing of the 
charge to take place or (c) a Summary of Evidence to be taken in writing at 
(place) ................................. (d) on the 
................................. day of........... 20..... at 
................................. O’Clock in the (e) 
................................. 
noon. Now, therefore, in 
pursuance of section 134 of the Air Force Act, 1950 and sub-rule (9) of rule 24 
of Air Force Rules, 1969, I do hereby summon and require you to attend as a 
witness the hearing of the said charge or (f) the taking of the said summary of 
evidence at the said place and hour and to bring with you the documents 
hereinafter mentioned namely................................. (g) whereof you 
shall fail at your peril. Given under my hand at 
................................. the ................................. day of 
................................. 20..... 
 



                                                              Signature
 



                                                              Name
 



                                                              Rank and Unit
 



                                                              Commanding Officer 
of the accused
 


(a) Insert the name and address of the person to whom the 
summons is to be sent.
 


(b) Insert the number, rank, name and Unit of the accused.
 


(c) Delete one of the purposes.
 


(d) Insert the place where hearing of the charge is to take 
place or the Summary of Evidence is to be taken.
 


(e) Specify forenoon or afternoon.
 


(f) Delete one of the purposes.
 


(g) Specify the documents (if any) which the witness is to 
bring (otherwise delete).
 


Note.—The summons shall be served in the manner specified in section 134 of 
the Air Force Act, 1950.]
 


 
 


Form C-2
 


Form of Summons to a witness summoned to  

attend a Court-Martial
 


...................................A.B...........................................
 


Whereas a 
...................................................Court-Martial has been 
ordered to assemble 
at........................................................................................ 
on the ..........................day of 
........................................................20.............,  for 
the trial of ................................................ Name of the 
(unit), now therefore, pursuant of section 134 of the Air Force Act, 1950, I do 
hereby summon and require you 
A................................................... B .................... 
................................................ to attend, as a witness, the 
sitting of the said Court at ............................................. on 
the ..................... day of ...................................... 
at............................................................O’clock in the 
afternoon (and to bring with you the documents hereinafter mentioned, 
namely,....................) 
........................................................),  and so to attend 
from day to day until you shall be duly charged, whereof you shall fail at your 
peril.
 


Given under my hand at 
...............................................on the 
............................................. day of .............20........
 



                                                              (Signature)
 



                                                              Convening Officer 
(or Judge-Advocate
 



                                                              or Presiding 
Officer of the Court or
 



                                                              Commanding Officer 
of the Accused).
 


 
 

 
 


—————
 


   1.  Subs. by S.R.O. 5(E), dated 8th 
November, 1990.
 

 
</form><form>
 



The Air 
Force Rules, 1969
 

 
 


Seventh Schedule
 


[See rules 144, 145, 147(1), 
149(1) and 150(1), 151]
 


forms of Warrants
 


Form G-1
 


Warrant for use when prisoner sentenced to detention is  

to be delivered into the custody of an officer in charge  

of a military or air force detention barrack 
 


(Air Force Act, 1950 section 170)
 


To the Officer in charge
 


of the Military/Air Force Detention Barrack at 
(a)..........................................
 


Whereas (number Rank, Name Unit) ....................was on 
the..................... day of ............... 20............convicted of the 
offence to be briefly state).......... by his commanding officer/a(b) ...... 
Court-Martial and was sentenced to undergo detention for (sentence to be entered 
in full but without signature);
 


And whereas the said sentence has been duly confirmed by 
(c) ..... as required by law (d) ..............
 


This is to require and authorise you to receive (Name) 
........ into your custody together with this warrant, and there carry the 
aforesaid sentence of detention into execution according to law. The sentence 
has effect from the (e)..................
 


Given under my hand at ..........................this the 
....................day of .................. 20.......
 


Unit stamp   Signature (f)
 


        (a)  Enter place.
 


        (b)  General, District or Summary General.
 


        (c)  Enter name and description of confirming 
authority or in the case of an award by Commanding Officer delete this portion.
 


        (d)  Add, if necessary, “with a remission 
of               ”.
 


        (e)  Enter date on which the original sentence was 
signed.
 


         (f)  Signature of Commanding Officer of prisoner 
or other prescribed officer—See rule 144.
 


Form G-2
 


Warrant of commitment for use when a prisoner  

is sentenced to imprisonment which is to be  

undergone in a military or Air Force prison 
 


(Air Force Act, 1950, section 166)
 


To: The Commandant of the Military/Air Force Prison at (a) 
...................................
 


Whereas at a (b) ....................................... 
Court-Martial held at.............................. on the day 
of...............20....... (Number, Rank, Name)...................of 
......................... (Unit) was duly convicted 
of............................(the offence is to be briefly stated here as 
“desertion”, “theft”, “receiving stolen goods”, “disobedience of lawful command” 
or as the case may be).
 


And whereas the said 
(b)...........................Court-Martial on the............................. 
................... day of ......................20............; passed the 
following sentence upon the said (Name) ........................ that is to say,
 


(Sentence to be entered in full, but without signature).
 


And whereas the said sentence has been duly confirmed by 
(c) ..................................... as required by law (d)...............
 


This is to require and authorise you to receive the said 
(Name) ...................................... into your   custody   together   
with   this  warrant  and  there  carry  the  aforesaid  sentence of 
rigorous/simple imprisonment into execution according to law. The sentence has 
effect form (e)..........................
 


Given under my hand at ...........this the 
......................... day of ...........20....
 


Unit Stamp  Signature (f)
 


        (a)  Enter name of military or air force prison.
 


        (b)  General, District or Summary General.
 


        (c)  Name and description of confirming authority.
 


        (d)  Add, if necessary, “with a remission of        
”.
 


        (e)  Enter date upon which original sentence was 
signed.
 


         (f)  Signature of Commanding Officer of prisoner 
or other prescribed officer—See rule 144.
 


Form G-3
 


Warrant of commitment for use when a prisoner is  

sentenced to rigorous or simple imprisonment  

which is to be undergone in civil prison 
 


(Air Force Act, 1950, section 166)
 


To the Superintendent of the (a) .................Prison
 


Whereas at a (b) .....................Court-Martial held at 
......................... on the ........... day of 
...........20...........(Number, Rank Name) ................................ of 
the ....................... Unit was duly convicted of (the offence to be 
briefly stated here, as “desertion”, “theft”, “receiving stolen goods”, 
“forgery”, “disobedience of lawful command” or as the case may be).
 


And whereas the said (b) ............... Court-Martial, on 
the ............... day of ............20..... passed the following sentence 
upon the said (Name) ........., that is to say—
 


(Sentence to be entered in 
full, but without signature)
 


And whereas the said sentence has been duly confirmed by 
(c) ......................................  as required by law 
(d).................................
 


This is to require and authorise you to receive the said 
(Name) ..............................into your custody together with this 
warrant, and there carry the aforesaid sentence Rigorous/Simple imprisonment 
into execution according to law. The sentence has effected from the (e) 
.....................
 


The confirming authority has recommended that while 
undergoing imprisonment in the civil prison the prisoner be placed in 
division/class A(or I)/B(or II)/C(or III)* and if there are only two devisions/classifications 
in the civil prison, he be placed in division/class A(or I)/B(or II)*
 


Enter name and description of confirming authority or in 
the case of an award by Commanding Officer delete this portion.
 


Given under my hand at ...........................this the 
.......................day of ............20........
 


Unit Stamp  Signature(f)
 


        (a)  Enter name of prison.
 


        (b)  General, District, or Summary General.
 


        (c)  Name and description of confirming authority.
 


        (d)  Add if necessary “with a remission of     ”.
 


        (e)  Enter date on which the original sentence was 
signed.
 


         (f)  Signature of Commanding Officer of prisoner 
or other prescribed officer—See rule 144.
 


—————
 


    *  Strike out whichever is inapplicable.
 


Form G-4
 


Warrant of commitment for use when a prisoner is  

sentenced to Imprisonment for life 
 


(Air Force Act, 1950, section 165)
 


To the Superintendent of the (a) .........Prison.
 


Whereas at a (b) ...................... Court-Martial, held 
at ................................. on the .....................day of 
.............., 20.................  (Number, Rank, Name) 
........................... of the................Unit was convicted of (the 
offence to be briefly stated here, as “treacherously corresponding with the 
enemy”, “mutiny”, “desertion on active service”, or as the case may be).
 


And whereas the said 
(b).......................Court-Martial on the 
.................................. day of ............... 20, .......passed the 
following sentence upon the said (Name); that is to say:—
 


Sentence to be entered in 
full, but without signature)
 


And whereas the said sentence has been duly confirmed by 
(c) ..... ............................................ as required by law (d) 
.................................
 


This is to require and authorise you to receive the said 
(Name) ......................... into your custody in the said prison as by law 
is required, together with this warrant, until he shall be delivered over by you 
with the said warrant to the proper authority and custody for the purpose of 
undergoing the aforesaid sentence of imprisonment for life. The aforesaid 
sentence has effect from the (e) .............
 


The confirming authority has recommended that while 
undergoing imprisonment in the civil prison, the prisoner be placed in 
division/class A (or I)/B (or II)/C (or III)*; and if there are only two 
divisions/classifications in the civil prison, he be placed in division/class 
A(or I)/B(or II)*.
 


Given under my hand at 
..........................this........................day of 
.....................20........
 


Unit Stamp  Signature (f)
 


        (a)  Enter name of prison.
 


        (b)  General or Summary General.
 


        (c)  Name and description of confirming authority.
 


        (d)  Add if necessary “with a remission of       “.
 


        (e)  Enter date on which the original sentence was 
signed.
 


         (f)  Signature of Commanding Officer of prisoner 
or other prescribed officer—See rule 144.
 


—————
 


    *  Strike out whichever is inapplicable.
 


Form G-5
 

(See 
rule 147)
 


Warrant for committing a person sentenced to death by 
a court-martial to the custody of an air force, military or civil prison or air 
force or military detention barrack pending confirmation or the carrying out of 
the sentence
 


To
 


The Superintendent/Commandant
 


(a) 
...............................................................................................................................................

 


Whereas at a (b) 
..................................................................court-martial 
held at (c) .............................. on the 
................................... day of ...................20............ 
(Number) ...................(Rank) ............................. (Name) 
...................................... of the (Unit) 
............................................. was convicted of the following 
offence (s), that is to say (d) .,... 
.............................................................................................................................................................. 
And whereas the said (b) 
.......................................................................................court-martial, 
on the 
.......................................................................day of 
..........................20 ........... passed sentence of death of the said 
(name) ..................................................... 
........................................................................................................
 


This is to require and authorise you to receive and hold 
the said (name) ........................................................ into 
your custody in the (a) .............................................. 
................................................................... as by law if 
required, together with this warrant, until such time as a further warrant in 
respect of the said (name) ............................shall be issued to you.
 


Given under my hand at 
..........................this........................day of 
.....................20........
 


Unit Stamp  Signature (e)
 


        (a)  Enter name of prison or detention barrack.
 


        (b)  Enter “General” or “Summary General”.
 


        (c)  Enter the name of place where trial was held.
 


        (d)  Here briefly set out the offences and the 
relevant sections of the Air Force Act, 1950.
 


        (e) Signature of the Commanding Officer.
 

Form G-6
 

(See 
rule 150)
 


Warrant to obtain person sentenced to death from air force, 
military or civil prison or air force or military detention barrack to carry out 
such sentence 
 


(Air Force Rule 150)
 


To
 


The Superintendent/Commandant
 


(a) 
...............................................................................................................................................
 


Whereas No. .................................(Rank) 
........................................... (Name ...................of the 
(Unit).......................................................... was by a (b) 
.........................................................  court-martial held at 
(place) ......................................... on the 
...........................date of.....................20........ was convicted 
of the offence (s) of (c) ............................................... 
.................................................................................................................................................................... 
................................................................................................................................................................. 
and by a sentence passed on the 
.................................................................................. 
day of .................................20........ sentenced to suffer death;
 


And whereas the said sentence having been duly confirmed by 
(d) ......................as by law required, a warrant to carry out the said 
sentence has been issued to me;
 


And whereas the aforesaid person under sentence is held in 
your custody in the said (a) under a warrant issued by (e) .....
 


This is to require and authorise you to deliver forthwith 
the said (name) ..................... to the officer/warrant 
officer/non-commissioned officer bringing this warrant.
 


Given under my hand at 
..........................this........................day of 
.....................20........
 


Unit Stamp  Signature (f) 
 


        (a)  Enter name of the prison or detention barrack.
 


        (b)  Enter “General” or “Summary General”.
 


        (c)  Here briefly set out the offences and the 
relevant section of the Air Force Act, 1950.
 


        (d)  Name and designation of confirming authority.
 


        (e)  Enter name and designation of officer who 
signed original warrant.
 


         (f)  Signature, name and designation of the 
provost-marshal or other officer nominated in the death warrant for carrying out 
the sentence of death.
 


Form G-7
 

(See 
rule 149)
 


Death Warrant
 


Part I
 


To
 


(a) ....................................................
 


Whereas number 
...........................................................................Rank  
...............................  (Name) 
........................................................................................................................................... 
of Unit 
..................................................................................................................................................... 
was by a (b) 
.............................................................................. 
court-martial held at (Place) 
............................................................................................................. 
convicted of the offence (s) of (c) 
................................................................................................................................................. 
................................................................................................................................................................ 
and by a sentence passed on the 
...................................................................... day of 
..................................... 20 ......  sentenced  to  suffer death by 
(d) .......................
 


And whereas in accordance with the Air Force Act, 1950, the 
finding and sentence of the said court-martial have been confirmed and 
promulgated;
 


And whereas I am satisfied, having regard to the provisions 
of rule 148 of the Air Force Rules, 1969, that the sentence of death may be 
carried into effect.
 


Now, therefore, I hereby order you to carry into effect the 
said sentence on the above named (number) 
................................................................................................................. 
(rank) 
..................................................................................... 
(name) .........................................................  
.........................................................................by (e) 
.......................................................... at 
............................................................. hours on (day) 
................................................................. 
...............................................................................................day 
of ................................................  

20..........................................., and for so doing this shall be 
sufficient warrant.
 


When the said sentence has been carried into effect the 
return below shall be completed and the warrant returned to me.
 


Signed 
at...............................................................this the 
............................................. day of 
......................................................20.................
 


(Signature) 
(f)........................................
 



Rank.....................................................
 



Commanding........................................
 


 
 


Part II
 

Return of 
Warrant 
 


The above sentence passed on (number) 
............................................................................  
(rank..................................................................................... 
(name) ....................................... was carried into effect at (g) 
.........................................................................  hours 
on the ....................................................................... 
day of ................................................20...........
 


(Signature) (a) 
....................................
 


(Signature) (h) 
...................................
 


 
 


Part III
 


Certificate of Medical Officer
 


I, (i) 
....................................................................................................................... 
a commissioned medical officer in the Armed Forces of India, hereby certify that 
I have this day examined the body of (number) 
............................................................ 
...................................................................................   
(rank) ......................................... (name) 
..................................................... upon whom sentence of 
death was this  day carried into effect at (g) 
................................................................................................................. 
and that on examination I found that the said person was dead.
 


Signed at 
..........................................................................................this 
the ................................. day of ........................20........
 



                                                  (Signature) (i) 
......................
 



                                                  (Rank and Unit) ..............
 



                                                  Commissioned Medical Officer 
of the Armed
 


 



                                                    Forces of 
India.
 


        (a)  Enter the rank, name and designation of the 
provost-marshal or other officer responsible for carrying the sentence of death 
into effect.
 


        (b)  Insert “General” or “Summary General”.
 


        (c)  Here briefly set out the offences and the 
relevant sections of the Air Force Act, 1950.
 


        (d)  Insert “being shot to death” or “being hanged 
by the neck until he be dead”.
 


        (e)  Insert “shooting” or “hanging”.
 


         (f)  Signature of the officer issuing the warrant 
under rule 149 of the Air Force Rules, 1969.
 


        (g)  Insert the name and address of the prison or 
establishment or description of the place where the sentence of death was 
carried into effect.
 


        (h)  Signature of the officer nominated under rule 
150(2)(c) of the Air Force Rules, 1969.
 


         (i)  Rank, name, number and unit of the 
commissioned medical officer.
 


Form G-8
 

(See 
section 171)
 


Warrant for use when prisoner under a sentence other 
than of death is to be delivered into military or air force custody
 


To the 
Superintendent/Commandant................................................................................... 

............................. of the (a) 
................................................................................. 
Prison.
 


Whereas (Number, Rank, Name) 
...................................................................................... 
(late) of the 
.................................................................................................................................. 
Unit is confined in the (a) 
........................................................................................................... 
prison under a warrant issued by (b) 
...................................................................................... 
in pursuance of a sentence of (c) 
..........................................................................................passed 
upon him by a (d) 
.............................................................................................. 
Court-Martial held at....................................................on 
.................................................................; and whereas 
(e) .......................................................................  has 
in the exercise of the powers conferred upon him by the Air Force Act, 1950, 
passed the following order regarding the  aforesaid  sentence, that is to say—
 


(f) 
..............................................................................................................................................
 



.......................................................................................................................................................................
 



......................................................................................................................................................................
 


This is to require and authorise you to forthwith deliver 
the said (Name) ...................................... of the officer or 
non-commissioned officer bringing this warrant.
 


Given under my hand at .........................this the 
............................... day of ...............20........
 


 


Unit stamp   Signature(g)
 


        (a)  Enter name of civil, military or air force 
prison.
 


        (b)  Enter name of designation of officer who 
signed original warrant.
 


        (c)  Enter original sentence (if this was reduced 
by the Confirming Officer or other superior authority the sentence should be 
entered thus—
 


              (“2 years’ rigorous imprisonment reduced by 
Confirming Officer to I year”).
 


        (d)  General, District or Summary General.
 


        (e)  Name and designation of authority issuing 
order.
 


         (f)  Order to be set out in full.
 


        (g)  Signature of prescribed officer—See 
rule 145.
 


Form G-9
 

(See 
section 171)
 


Warrant for use when a prisoner under sentence other 
than of death is pardoned or his trial set aside, or when the whole sentence, or 
the unexpired portion thereof, is remitted
 


To the Superintendent/Commandant  
.......................................................................... 
.............................................................of the (a) 
.....................................................Prison.
 


Whereas (Number, Rank, Name) 
................................................................................ 
(late) of the 
...................................................................................................................... 
Unit is confined in the  (a) 
................................................................................................................. 
prison under a warrant  issued by (b) 
..........................................................................issued 
in pursuance of a sentence of (c) 
....................................................................................passed 
upon him by a (d) 
................................................................................................................. 
Court-Martial held at 
...............................................................on 
............................................; and  whereas (e) 
............................................................................................................has, 
in the exercise of the powers conferred upon him by the Air Force Act, 1950 
passed the following order regarding the aforesaid sentence, that is to say—
 


(f) 
............................................................................................................................................... 
................................................................................................................................................................. 
......................................................................................................................................................................

 


This is to require and authorise you to forthwith discharge 
the said (Name .......................... from your custody unless he is liable 
to be detained for some other caused; and for your so discharging him this shall 
be your sufficient warrant.
 


Given under my hand at 
.............................................. this the ..................... 
day ...................... of 20........
 


 


Unit Stamp  Signature (g)
 


        (a)  Enter name of civil, military or air force 
prison.
 


        (b)  Enter name or designation of officer who 
signed original warrant.
 


        (c)  Enter original sentence (if this was reduced 
by the Confirming Officer or other superior authority the sentence should be 
entered thus—
 


              (“2 years’ rigorous imprisonment reduced by 
Confirming Officer to 1 year”).
 


        (d)  General, District or Summary General.
 


        (e)  Name and designation of authority pardoning 
prisoner, mitigating sentence or setting aside trial.
 


         (f)  Order to be set out in full.
 


        (g)  Signature of prescribed officer—See 
rule 145.
 


 
 


Form G-10
 

(See 
section 171)
 


Warrant for use when a sentence of rigorous or simple 
imprisonment is reduced by 
superior 
authority or  

when one of imprisonment for life is commuted  

to one of rigorous or simple imprisonment
 


To the Superintendent1 Commandant................................................................................... 

.............................. of the (a) 
...........................................................................................Prison.
 


Whereas (Number, Rank, Name) 
.............................................................................. 
(late) of the 
........................................................................................................................ 
Unit is confined in the (a) 
.................................................................................................................... 
prison under a warrant issued by (b) 
............................................................................. in 
pursuance of a sentence of (c) 
....................................................................................................... 
passed upon him by a (d) 
........................................................................Court-Martial 
held at ......................................................................on 
...........................................................;  and whereas (e) 
.................................................................................................................has, 
in the exercise of the power conferred upon him by the Air Force Act, 1950, 
passed the following order regarding the aforesaid sentence, that is to say—
 


(f) 
.............................................................................................................................................. 
................................................................................................................................................................. 
......................................................................................................................................................................

 


This is to require and authorise you to keep the said 
(Name) .... .................................................. in your custody 
together with this warrant and there to carry into execution the punishment a 
Rigorous/Simple imprisonment under the said order according to law. And this is 
further to require and authorise you to return to me the original warrant of 
commitment in lieu whereof this warrant is issued. The  period of such 
rigorous/simple imprisonment will reckon from the (g) ..........................

 


Given under my hand at .....................this the 
........ day of .....................20............
 


 


Unit Stamp Signature (h)
 


        (a) Enter name of civil, military or air force.
 


        (b) Enter name or designation of officer who signed 
original warrant.
 


        (c) Enter original sentence (if this was reduced by 
the Confirming Officer or other superior authority the sentence should be 
entered thus—
 


              (“2 years’ rigorous imprisonment reduced by 
Confirming Officer to 1 year”).
 


        (d) General, District or Summary General.
 


        (e) Name and designation of authority 
reducing/commuting sentence.
 


         (f) Order to be set out in full.
 


        (g) Enter date on which original sentence was 
signed.
 


        (h) Signature of prescribed officer—See rule 
145.
 


 
 


Form G-11
 

(See 
rule 151)
 

Air Force 
Rules, 1969
 


Warrant to obtain into air force custody person 
sentenced to death from air force, military or civil prison or air force or 
military detention barrack for a purpose other than carrying out the sentence of 
death
 


To
 


The Superintendent/Commandant
 


(a) 
.........................................................................
 


Whereas (number) 
........................................................ (rank) 
..................................(name) ............................ of the 
(unit) ......................... having been convicted by a (b) 
........................................................................................................ 
court-martial held at (place) ....................................on the 
....................................day of 
....................................................... 20........... for the 
offence(s) of (c) 
......................................................................... 
....................................................................................................................................................................................and 
sentenced by the said court-martial to suffer death is held in your custody in 
the said 
.................................................................................................................................................., 
under a warrant issued by (d) ...........................;
 


And whereas (e) 
.................................................................................................has 
in exercise of the powers conferred upon him by the Air Force Act, 1950 passed 
the following order regarding the aforesaid sentence, that is to say—
 



...................................................................................................................................................................... 
...................................................................................................................................................................
 


This is to require and authorise you to forthwith deliver 
the said (name) ....................the officer/warrant officer or 
non-commissioned officer bringing this warrant.
 


Given under my hand at 
............................................................ this the ..... 
..............................................day of 
......................................................... 20..............
 


 


Unit Stamp  (Signature) (g)
 


        (a) Enter name of the prison or detention barrack.
 


        (b) Enter “General” or “Summary General”.
 


        (c) Here briefly set out the offences and the 
relevant sections of the Air Force Act, 1950.
 


        (d) Enter name or designation of officer who signed 
original warrant.
 


        (e) Name and designation of the authority issuing 
order.
 


         (f) Order to be set out in full.
 


        (g) Signature of Commanding Officer.
 


 
 


Form G-12
 

(See 
rule 151)
 

Air Force 
Rules, 1969
 


Warrant for use when a prison sentenced to death is 
pardoned or his trial is set aside, or when the sentence of death is not 
confirmed or is remitted
 


To
 


The Superintendent/Commandant
 


(a)...............................................................................................................
 


Whereas (number) 
................................................ 
(rank)......................................... (name) 
................................................................................................................................... 
of the (unit) 
.................................................................................................................. 
having been convicted by a  (b) 
.................................................................................................. 
court-martial held at (place) 
.........................................................on the 
............................................day of 
.................20..........., of the offence(s) of 
(c)............................................................................... 
........................................................................... and  
sentenced  by  the  said  court-martial  to  suffer  death  is  held  in   your  
custody  in  the  said  (a) 
......................................................... under a warrant issued 
by (d) ..............................................
 


And whereas (e) 
................................................................................................................... 
has in exercise of the powers conferred upon him by (f) 
................................................................... passed the 
following order that is to say—
 


(g) 
..............................................................................................................................................
 


This is to require and authorise you to forthwith discharge 
the said (name) .................................... from your custody unless he 
is liable to be detained for some other cause; and for your so discharging him 
this shall be your sufficient warrant.
 


Given under my hand at 
...................................................................................................... 
this the ..................................................day of 
.................................20.............
 


 


Unit Stamp              
  (Signature) (h)
 


        (a) Enter name of the prison or detention  barrack.
 


        (b) Enter “General” or “Summary General”.
 


        (c) Here briefly set out the offences and the 
relevant sections of the Air Force Act, 1950.
 


        (d) Enter name and designation of officer who 
signed original warrant.
 


        (e) Enter name or designation of the confirming 
authority or the authority pardoning or remitting the sentence of death, or 
setting aside the trial.
 


         (f) Enter the section and the Act, or the article 
of the Constitution under which the order has been passed.
 


        (g) Order to be set out in full.
 


        (h) Signature, rank, name and designation of the 
Commanding Officer.
 

Form G-13
 

(See 
section 171)
 

Air Force 
Act, 1950
 


Warrant for use when sentence of death is commuted to 
imprisonment (including life imprisonment) or the sentence  

of death or imprisonment (including life imprisonment) is commuted to detention, 
to be served at the same place
 


To
 


The Superintendent/Commandant
 


(a) 
.................................................................... 
 


Whereas 
(number)............................................. (rank) 
........................................................ (name) 
........................................................................................................................ 
of the (unit) .................................................. having been 
convicted by a (b) .................................................. 
court-martial held at (place) 
................................................................................................on 
the ......................................................... day of 
...................................20......................., of the offence(s) 
of (c) 
................................................................................................................................ 
and sentenced by the court-martial to (d) 
................................................................................is 
held in your custody in the said (a) 
.................................................................................under 
a warrant issued by (e) 
................................................................................................
 


And whereas (f) 
.................................................................................................................... 
has, in exercise of powers conferred upon him by the Air Force Act, 1950 passed 
the following order regarding the aforesaid sentence, that is to say (g) 
.............................................................................................................................................................
 


This is to require and authorise you to keep the said 
(name) ....................................................... in your  custody  
together  with  this  warrant,  and  there  to  carry  into  execution  the 
punishment of (h) 
.................................................................... under the 
said order  according  to law. And  this is further to require and authorise you 
to return to me the original  warrant  of  commitment in  lieu  whereof this 
warrant is issued. The period of such (i) 
.......................................................................................... 
will reckon from the (j) ..........................................day of  
..........................., 20.................
 


Given under my hand at 
......................................................................................................, 
this the .............................................................. day of 
......................................20.............
 


 


Unit Stamp Signature (k)
 


        (a) Enter name of the prison or detention barrack.
 


        (b) Enter “General”, “District” or “Summary 
general”.
 


        (c) Here briefly set out the offences and the 
relevant sections of the Air Force Act, 1950.
 


        (d) Enter original sentence e.g. death, life 
imprisonment, rigorous/simple imprisonment for 2 years etc., (if the original 
sentence of imprisonment was reduced by the confirming or other superior 
authority, the sentence should be entered thus “2 years’ rigorous imprisonment 
reduced by the confirming officers to 1 year”.
 


        (e) Enter name or designation of officer who signed 
original warrant.
 


         (f) Enter name and designation of the authority 
commuting the sentence.
 


        (g) Order to be set out in full.
 


        (h) Enter “imprisonment for life”, “rigorous/simple 
imprisonment for ............ or “detention for ...............” as the case may 
be.
 


         (i) Enter “life imprisonment”, “imprisonment” or 
“detention” as the case may be.
 


         (j) Enter date on which original sentence was 
signed.
 


        (k) Signature of Commanding Officer or Prescribed 
Officer (See rules 145 and 151 of the Air Force Rules, 1969.)
 


 
 


Form G-14
 


Warrant for use when sentence of death is commuted to 
imprisonment (including life imprisonment) or the sentence  

of death or imprisonment (including life imprisonment) is commuted to detention, 
to be served at a different place 
 


(Air Force Act, 1950, section 171)
 


To
 


The Superintendent/Commandant
 


(a) 
...................................................................................................
 


Whereas (number) 
............................................................(rank) 
.......................................... 
(name)......................................................of the (unit) 
................................................................... having been 
convicted by a (b) 
..................................................................................... 
court-martial held at (place) 
.................................................................... on the 
................................................. day of 
...............................20................, of the offence(s) of (c) 
.......................................................................................................................................... 
and sentence by the said court-martial to (d) 
..................................................... is held in your custody in 
the said (a) ................................................................  
under a warrant issued by (e) ........................................... 

 


And whereas (f) 
............................................................................................. 
has, in exercise of the powers conferred upon him by the Air Force Act, 1950 
passed the following order regarding the aforesaid sentence, that is to say (g) 
................................................................................................... 
This is to require and authorise you to keep the said 
(name)............................................................... in your 
custody together with this warrant in the said (a) 
........................................................... as by law is 
required until he shall be delivered over by you with the said warrant to the 
proper authority and custody for the purpose of undergoing the punishment of (h) 
.......................................................... under the said order. 
And this is further to require and authorise you to return to me the original 
warrant of commitment in lieu whereof this warrant is issued. The period of such 
(i) 
.............................................................................. 
will reckon from the (j) ....................................................day 
of .......................... 20............
 


Given under my hand at 
................................................this the 
........................ ......................................day of 
............................................. 20...............
 


 


Unit Stamp  Signature (k)
  

 


        (a) Enter name of the prison or detention barrack.
 


        (b) Enter “General”, 
“District” or “Summary General”.
 


        (c) Here briefly set 
out the offences and the relevant sections of the Air Force Act, 1950.
 


        (d) Enter original 
sentence e.g. death, life imprisonment, rigorous/simple imprisonment for 
2 years etc., (if the original sentence of imprisonment was reduced by the 
confirming or other superior authority, the sentence should be entered thus—
 


              “2 years’ 
rigorous imprisonment reduced by the confirming officer to 1 year”.
 


        (e) Enter name or 
designation of officer who signed original warrant.
 


         (f) Enter name and 
designation of the authority commuting the sentence.
 


        (g) Order to be set 
out in full.
 


        (h) Enter 
“imprisonment for life”, or “rigorous/simple imprisonment for .........”
 


              or “detention 
for .................”, as the case may be.
 


         (i) Enter “life 
imprisonment”, “imprisonment” or “detention”, as the case may be.
 


         (j) Enter date on 
which original sentence was signed.
 


        (k) Signature of 
Commanding Officer or prescribed officer. (See rules 145 and 151 of the 
Air Force Rules, 1969).
 


 
 


 
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by S.R.O. 127, dated 27th July, 1995.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Subs. by S.R.O. 24(E), dated 16th August, 1974.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   Subs. by S.R.O. 24(E), dated 16th August, 1974.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   Ins. by S.R.O. 5(E), dated 8th November, 1990.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>   Ins. by S.R.O. 24(E), dated 16th August, 1974.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>   Subs. by S.R.O. 24(E), dated 16th August, 1974.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>   Ins. by S.R.O. 5(E), dated 8th November, 1990.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>   Omitted by S.R.O. 24(E), dated 16th August, 1974.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>   Subs. by S.R.O. 83, dated 19th December, 1970.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>   Subs. by S.R.O. 24(E), dated 16th August, 1974.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>   Subs. by S.R.O. 83, dated 19th December, 1970.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>   See now sec. 340 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 
    of 1974).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>   Subs. by S.R.O. 5(E), dated 8th November, 1990.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>   Subs. and ins. by S.R.O. 83, dated 19th December, 1970.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>   Subs. and ins. by S.R.O. 83, dated 19th December, 1970.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>   Ins. by S.R.O. 24(E), dated 16th August, 1974.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number>   Subs. by S.R.O. 24(E), dated 16th August, 1974.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>