<act><tid>1596533</tid>
<title>THE AMENDING ACT, <year>1897</year></title>

ACT No. 5 OF <year>1897</year>
[ 25th February, <year>1897</year>.]

An Act <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> to amend and facilitate the citation of certain 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> enactments.

<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>

<footcitenum>4</footcitenum> WHEREAS it is <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> expedient that certain formal amendments 
should be made in the enactments specified in the second schedule to 
this Act;

AND WHEREAS it is also expedient to facilitate the citation of 
the enactments specified in the third schedule to this Act;

It is hereby enacted as follows:--





<article><tid>226821</tid>
<number> 1</number> Title.-
<section><tid>1258357</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Amending Act, <year>1897</year>;  
 <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>
<footcitenum>7</footcitenum>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>678464</tid>
<number>2</number>[ Enactments repealed and amended.] Rep. partly by the 
Repealing and Amending Act, <year>1903</year> (1 of <year>1903</year>), s. 4 and Sch. III and 
partly by the Repealing Act, <year>1938</year> (1 of <year>1938</year>), s. 2 and Sch.


</article>



<article><tid>230008</tid>
<number>3</number>[ Savings.]- Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, <year>1903</year> (1 of  
  <year>1903</year>), s. 4 and Sch. III.


</article>



<article><tid>101389</tid>
<number>4</number>Citation of certain enactments.- Each of the enactments 
described in the first three columns of the third schedule may, 
without prejudice to any other mode of citation, be cited for all 
purposes by the short title mentioned in that behalf in the fourth 
column thereof.
SCHEDULE I[ Repealed.]

THE FIRST SCHEDULE.--[ Repeals.] Rep. by the Repealing and 
Amending Act, <year>1903</year> (1 of <year>1903</year>), s. 4 and Sch. III.

SCHEDULE II[ Repealed]

THE SECOND SCHEDULE.--[ Amendments.] Rep. by the Repealing Act, 
 <year>1938</year> (1 of <year>1938</year>), s. 2 and Sch.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" to repeal certain obsolete enactments and" omitted by 
Act 1 of <year>1903</year>, s. 4 and Sch. III. 
2. The word" other" omitted by s. 4 and Sch. III, ibid. 
3. The first recital of the preamble rep. by s. 4 and Sch. III, 
ibid. 
4. The word" And" omitted by s. 4 and Sch. III, ibid. 
5. The word" also" omitted by s. 4 and Sch. III, ibid. 
6. The words" Repealing and" omitted by s. 4 and Sch. III, ibid. 
7. The word" and" at the end of sub- section (1), and sub- section 
 (2), omitted by Act 10 of <year>1914</year>, s. 3 and Sch. II.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


SCHEDULE. III

THE THIRD SCHEDULE


<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 2 3 4 
Year No Subject Short title 
Part I.-- Local Acts of the Governor General in Council in 
force in Assam.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>1850</number>XXV For the forfeiture to Government of The Forfeited 
deposits made on incomplete sales Deposits Act, 
of land under Regulation VIII, <year>1819</year>. <year>1850</year>.

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>1853</number>VI Relating to summary suits for arrears The Rent 
of rent, to sales of patni taluqs and Recovery 
other saleable tenures, and to sales Act, <year>1853</year>. 
of land in satisfaction of summary 
decrees for rent.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>1853</number>XIX To amend the law of evidence in the The Recusant 
Civil Courts of the East India Com- Witnesses Act, 
pany in the Bengal Presidency. <year>1853</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>1856</number>XII To amend the law respecting the The Civil 
employment of Amins by the Civil Courts 
Courts in the Presidency of Fort Amins Act, <year>1856</year> 
William.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>1867</number>III To provide for the punishment of The Public 
public gambling and the keeping Gambling 
of common gaming- houses in the Act, <year>1867</year>. 
North- Western Provinces of the 
Presidency of Fort William, and 
in the Punjab, Oudh, the Central 
Provinces and British Burma.

<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>1874</number>VIII To provide for the exercise of the The Assam 
powers hitherto exercised by the Chief Com- 
Lieutenant- Governor and Board of missionership 
Revenue of Bengal in the territories Act, <year>1874</year>. 
forming the Chief Commissionership 
of Assam.

<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>1886</number>III To amend the Northern India Ferries The Northern 
Act, <year>1878</year>. India Ferries 
Act, Amendment 
Act, <year>1886</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>1892</number>IV To amend the Bengal Court of Wards The Court of 
Act, <footcitenum>1879</footcitenum> Act IX (B. C.) of <year>1879</year>]. Wards Act 
 (Bengal) Amend- 
ment Act, <year>1892</year>. 
1. The entries relating to Act 33 of <year>1850</year> rep. by Act 12 of <year>1927</year>, 
s. 2 and Sch. 
2. The entries relating to Act 19 of <year>1871</year> rep. by s. 2 and Sch, 
ibid. 
3. The entries relating to Act 12 of <year>1874</year> rep. by Act 35 of <year>1950</year>, 
s. 3 and Sch. II.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

Part II.-- Regulation made under the Government of India Act, <year>1870</year> 
 (33 Vict., c. 3).

 <year>1884</year> III To empower the extension of the Assam The Assam Fro- 
Frontier Tracts Regulation, <year>1880</year>, to ntier Tracts 
certain tracts in Assam and to dec- Regulation, 
lare that Act X of <year>1872</year> (the Code <year>1884</year>.  
  of Criminal Procedure) shall be deemed 
never to have come into force in the 
Garo Hills District, the Naga Hills 
District and the Khasi and Jaintia 
Hills District.

Part III.-- Regulations of the Bengal Code in force in Assam.

 1793 I For enacting into a Regulation certain The Bengal 
Articles of a Proclamation bearing Permanent 
date the 22nd March, 1793. Settlement 
Regulation, 
1793.

 1793 II For abolishing the Courts of Mal Ada- The Bengal 
lat or Revenue Courts, and transfer- Land- Revenue 
ring the trial of the suits which Regulation, 
were cognizable in those Courts, to 1793. 
the Courts of Dewani Adalat; and 
prescribing Rules for the conduct 
of the Board of Revenue and the 
Collectors.

 1793 VIII For re- enacting, with modifications The Bengal 
and amendments, the rules for the Decennial 
Decennial Settlement of the public Settlement 
revenue payable from the lands of Regulation, 
the zamindars, independent taluq- 1793. 
dars and other actual proprietors 
of land, in Bengal, Behar and Ori- 
ssa, passed for those provinces 
respectively on the 18th September, 
1789; the 25th November, 1789; and 
the 10th February, 1790, and subse- 
quent dates.

 1793 XI For removing certain restrictions to The Bengal 
the operation of the Hindu and Mu- Inheritance 
hammadan laws with regard to the Regulation, 
inheritance of landed property 1793. 
subject to the payment of revenue 
to Government.

 1793 XXXVIII For re- enacting, with modifications, The Indian 
such part of the rule passed on the Civil Service 
 27th June, 1787, as prohibits Cove- (Bengal) Loans 
nanted Civil Servants of the Com- Prohibition 
pany employed in the administration Regulation, 
of justice or the collection of the 1793. 
public revenue lending money to zam- 
indars, independent taluqdars or other 
actual proprietors of land, or depend- 
ent taluqdars or farmers of land hold- 
ing

<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


farms immediately of Government, or 
the under- farmers or raiats of the 
several descriptions of proprietors 
and farmers of land above mentioned, 
or their respective sureties.

 1799 V To limit the interference of the Zila The Bengal 
Court of Dewani Adalat in the execu- Wills and 
tion of wills and administration to Intestacy 
the estates of persons dying Regulation, 
intestate. 1799.

 1800 X For preventing the division of The Bengal 
landed estates in the Jangal Mahals Inheritance 
of the Zila of Midnapore and other Regulation, 
Districts. 1800.

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>

 <year>1806</year> XI For facilitating the progress of The Bengal Tr- 
detachments of troops through the oops Transport 
Company' s territories for afford- and Travellers 
ing any requisite assistance to Assistance Re- 
persons travelling through those gulation, <year>1806</year>. 
territories.

 <year>1812</year> XI To empower the Governor General in The Bengal 
Council to order the removal of Foreign 
emigrants from foreign countries, Immigrants 
and their descendants, from any Regulation, 
place in the vicinity of the <year>1812</year>. 
frontier of the State from which 
they may have emigrated; and, in 
certain cases, to place and detain 
any such persons in safe custody; 
and likewise to provide for the 
trial of emigrants and their des- 
cendants who may excite disturb- 
ances in the countries from which 
they may have emigrated, and of 
persons aiding them in the prosecu- 
tion of such attempts.

 <year>1818</year> III For the confinement of State The Bengal 
Prisoners. State Prisone- 
rs Regulation, 
<year>1818</year>.

 <year>1819</year> VIII To declare the validity of The Bengal 
certain tenures, and to define Patni Taluqs 
the relative rights of zamin- Regulation, 
dars and patni taluqdars; also <year>1819</year>. 
to establish a process for the 
sale of such taluqs in satis- 
faction of the zamindar' s 
demand of rent.

 <year>1820</year> I For providing that all sales of The Bengal 
certain taluqs made answerable Patni Taluqs 
by sale for Regulation, 
<year>1820</year>.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The entries relating to the Bengal State Offences Regulation, 
<year>1804</year> (10 of <year>1804</year>) rep. by Act 4 of <year>1922</year>, s. 3 and Sch.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


arrears by the zamindar' s rent shall 
be conducted in the mode provided 
by Regulation VIII, <year>1819</year>, for the 
sales therein described.

 <year>1823</year> VII For prohibiting loans by Covenanted The Indian 
Civil Servants from persons subject Civil Service 
to their official authority and (Bengal) Loans 
influence. Prohibition 
Regulation, 
<year>1823</year>.

 <year>1825</year> VI For rendering more effectual the The Bengal 
rules in force relative to supplies Troops Transp- 
and preparations for troops pro- ort Regula- 
ceeding through the British tion, <year>1825</year>. 
territories.

 <year>1825</year> XI For declaring the rules to be ob- The Bengal 
served in determining claims to Alluvion and 
lands gained by alluvion, or by Diluvion 
dereliction of a river or the sea. Regulation, 
<year>1825</year>.

 <year>1827</year> III For modifying and amending the The Bengal 
rules in force relative to the Corruption and 
law officers and ministerial Extortion 
native officers of the Courts Regulation, 
of Judicature, who may be <year>1827</year>. 
guilty of corruption or exto- 
rtion.

 <year>1827</year> V For modifying the rules at present The Bengal 
in force for the management of es- Attached Esta- 
tates under attachments by orders tes Management 
of the Courts of Justice in cer- Regulation, 
tain cases. <year>1827</year>.

 <year>1829</year> XVII For declaring the practice of Sati The Bengal 
or of burning or burying alive Sati Regula- 
the widows of Hindus illegal and tion <year>1829</year>. 
punishable by the Criminal Courts.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>6</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>