<act><title>

    The Weapons of mass Destruction And Their Delivery Systems (Prohibition of 
    Unlawful Activities) Act, 2005</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>1</number> Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Weapons of Mass Destruction and their Delivery 
    Systems (Prohibition of Unlawful Activities) Act, 2005. 
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> It shall come into force on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as 
    the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>2</number> Act in addition to other laws.—Save 
    as otherwise expressly provided in this Act, the provisions of this Act 
    shall be in addition to any other relevant Act for the time being in force 
    in relation to any matter covered under this Act. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>3</number> Extent and application.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    It extends to the whole of India including its Exclusive Economic Zone. 
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> Every person shall be liable to 
    punishment under this Act for every act or omission contrary to the 
    provisions thereof, of which he is held guilty in India.  
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> Any person who commits an offence beyond 
    India, which is punishable under this Act, shall be dealt with according to 
    the provisions of this Act in the same manner as if such act had been 
    committed in India.  
 </section><section>

<number>4</number> The provisions of this Act shall also 
    apply to—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    citizens of India 
    outside India;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    companies or bodies 
    corporate, registered or incorporated in India or having their associates, 
    branches or subsidiaries, outside India;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    any ship, aircraft or 
    other means of transport registered in India or outside India, wherever it 
    may be;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    foreigners while in 
    India;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    persons in the service 
    of the Government of India, within and beyond India.  
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>5</number> Notwithstanding the applicability of the 
    provisions of any other Central Act relating to any activity provided 
    herein, the provisions of this Act shall apply to export, transfer, 
    re‑transfer, transit and trans-shipment of material, equipment or technology 
    of any description as are identified, designated, categorised or considered 
    necessary by the Central Government, as pertinent or relevant to India as a 
    Nuclear Weapon State, or to the national security of India, or to the 
    furtherance of its foreign policy or its international obligations under any 
    bilateral, multilateral or international treaty, Covenant, Convention or 
    arrangement relating to weapons of mass destruction or their means of 
    delivery, to which India is a Party.  
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>4</number> Definitions.—In 
    this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “biological weapons” 
    are—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    microbial or other 
    biological agents, or toxins whatever their origin or method of production, 
    of types and in quantities that have no justification for prophylactic, 
    protective or other peaceful purposes; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    weapons, equipment or 
    delivery systems specially designed to use such agents or toxins for hostile 
    purposes or in armed conflict;  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number>    “brought in transit” 
    means to bring goods from any country into India by land, air, or amphibious 
    means of transportation, where the goods are to be taken out from India on 
    the same conveyance on which they are brought into India without any landing 
    in India, but does not include a conveyance in innocent passage through 
    Indian territory, Indian territorial waters or Indian airspace of a foreign 
    conveyance carrying goods.  
 
Explanation I.—A 
    conveyance is a foreign conveyance if it is not registered in India.  
 
Explanation II.—A 
    conveyance is in “innocent passage” if it is not engaged in relevant 
    activity and passes through or above Indian territorial waters or airspace 
    without stopping or anchoring in India;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>  “chemical weapons” means,—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    the toxic chemicals and 
    their precursors, except where intended for—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>a</number>    industrial, 
    agricultural, research, medical, pharmaceutical or other peaceful purposes;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>b</number>    protective purposes, 
    namely those purposes directly related to protection against toxic chemicals 
    and to protection against chemical weapons;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>c</number>    military purposes not 
    connected with the use of chemical weapons and not dependent on the use of 
    the toxic properties of chemicals as a method of warfare; or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>d</number>    law enforcement 
    including domestic riot control purposes,  
 
as long as the types and 
    quantities are consistent with such purposes;  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    the munitions and 
    devices, specifically designed to cause death or other harm through the 
    toxic properties of those toxic chemicals specified in sub‑clause (i), which 
    would be released as a result of the employment of such munitions and 
    devices; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    any equipment 
    specifically designed for use directly in connection with the employment of 
    munitions and devices specified in sub‑clause (ii),  
 
together or separately;  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>d</number>    “export” shall have the 
    meaning assigned to this expression in the Foreign Trade (Development and 
    Regulation) Act, 1992 (22 of 1992);  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    “fissile material” and 
    “radioactive material” shall have the meanings assigned to these expressions 
    in the Atomic Energy Act, 1962 (33 of 1962);  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    “item” means materials, 
    equipment, and technology, of any description, notified under this Act or 
    any other Act related to relevant activity;  
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    “non‑State actor” is a 
    person or entity not acting under the lawful authority of any country;  
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>    “nuclear weapon or other 
    nuclear explosive device” means any nuclear weapon or other nuclear 
    explosive device as may be determined by the Central Government, whose 
    determination in the matter shall be final;  
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>    “public domain” means 
    domain that has no restrictions upon dissemination of information within or 
    from it; the existence of any legal rights to intellectual property in that 
    information does not remove such information from being in public domain;  
 </section><section>
<number>j</number>    “relevant activity” 
    means,—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    the development, 
    production, handling, operation, maintenance, storage or dissemination of a 
    nuclear, chemical or biological weapon; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    the development, 
    production, maintenance, storage or dissemina­tion of missiles specially 
    designed for delivering any such weapon;  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>k</number>    “re-transfer” means 
    transfer of any item notified under this Act from any country or entity to 
    which it has been exported from India, to yet another country or entity;  
 </section><section>
<number>l</number>    “technology” means any 
    information (including information embodied in software) other than 
    information in the public domain, that is capable of being used in—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    the development, 
    production or use of any goods or software;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    the development of, or 
    the carrying out of, an industrial or commercial activity or the provision 
    of a service of any kind.  
 
Explanation.—When 
    technology is described wholly or partly by reference to the uses to which 
    it (or the goods to which it relates) may be put, it shall include services 
    which are provided or used, or which are capable of being used, in the 
    development, production or use of such technology or goods;  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>m</number>    “terrorist” shall have 
    the meaning assigned to this expression in the Unlawful Activities 
    (Prevention) Act, 1967 (37 of 1967);  
 </section><section>
<number>n</number>    “trans-shipment” means 
    to remove goods from the conveyance on which they were brought into India 
    and to place the goods on the same or another conveyance for the purpose of 
    taking them out of India, where these acts are carried out on a “through 
    bill of lading”, “through airway bill” or “through manifest”.  
 
Explanation.—“through 
    bill of lading”, “through airway bill” and “through manifest” mean 
    respectively a bill of lading, airway bill and manifest, for the consignment 
    of goods from a place outside India to a destination which is also outside 
    India without a consignee in India;  
 </section><section>
<number>o</number>    “unlawful” means without 
    the authority of the Central Government and the expression “unlawfully” 
    shall be construed accordingly;  
 </section><section>
<number>p</number>    “weapons of mass 
    destruction” means any biological, chemical or nuclear weapons.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>5</number> Power to identify, designate, categories 
    or regulate certain activities.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may identify, designate, categorise or regulate, the 
    export, transfer, re-transfer, trans-shipment, or transit of any item 
    related to relevant activity in such manner as may be prescribed.  
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> The Central Government may, by order 
    published in the Official Gazette, designate or notify any item related to 
    relevant activity for the purposes of this Act.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>6</number> Power to appoint Advisory Committees.—For 
    the purposes of this Act, the Central Government may appoint such Advisory 
    Committees as it deems fit, and may appoint to them persons to exercise such 
    powers and perform such duties as the Central Government may, by rules, 
    prescribe.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>7</number> Delegation of powers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of this Act and any other law for the time being 
    in force, related to relevant activity, the Central Government shall have 
    the power to direct or assign to any authority, in such manner as it may 
    deem appropriate, such powers as may be necessary to implement the 
    provisions of this Act.  
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> The Central Government may appoint a 
    Licensing Authority and an Appellate Authority, and make provisions relating 
    to such authority and for licensing in such manner and in such form as the 
    Central Government may, by rules, prescribe.  
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> Without prejudice to the generality of 
    the provisions contained in this Act, the authorities and mechanisms 
    provided under other relevant Acts shall continue to deal with matters 
    covered under those Acts:  
 

Provided that in case of any doubt as to 
    whether a matter falls within the scope of such relevant Acts or under this 
    Act, the decision of the Central Government thereon shall be final.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>8</number> Prohibition relating to weapons of mass 
    destruction.—
<section><number>1</number> No person shall 
    unlawfully manufacture, acquire, possess, develop or transport a nuclear 
    weapon or other nuclear explosive device and their means of delivery.  
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> No person shall unlawfully transfer, 
    directly or indirectly, to any one a nuclear weapon or other nuclear 
    explosive device, or transfer control over such a weapon, knowing it to be a 
    nuclear weapon or other nuclear explosive device.  
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> No person shall unlawfully manufacture, 
    acquire, possess, develop or transport a biological or chemical weapon or 
    their means of delivery.  
 </section><section>

<number>4</number> No person shall unlawfully transfer, 
    directly or indirectly, to any one biological or chemical weapons.  
 </section><section>

<number>5</number> No person shall unlawfully transfer, 
    directly or indirectly, to any one missiles specially designed for the 
    delivery of weapons of mass destruction.  
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>9</number> Prohibition relating to non-State actor 
    or terrorist.—No person shall, 
    directly or indirectly, transfer to a non-State actor or terrorist, any 
    material, equipment and technology notified under this Act or any other Act 
    related to relevant activity:  
 

Provided that such transfer made to a 
    non‑State actor shall not include a transfer made as such to any person 
    acting under lawful authority in India.  
  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>10</number> Prohibition as regards intimidating 
    acts.—No person shall transfer, 
    acquire, possess, or transport fissile or radioactive material, which is 
    intended to be used to cause, or in a threat to cause, death or serious 
    injury or damage to property for the purpose of intimidating people or a 
    section of the people in India or in any foreign country, or compelling the 
    Government of India or the Government of a foreign country or an 
    international organisation or any other person to do so or abstain from 
    doing any act.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>11</number> Prohibition on export.—No 
    person shall export any material, equipment or technology knowing that such 
    material, equipment or technology is intended to be used in the design or 
    manufacture of a biological weapon, chemical weapon, nuclear weapon or other 
    nuclear explosive device, or in their missile delivery systems.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>12</number> Prohibition on brokering.—No 
    person who is a resident in India shall, for a consideration under the terms 
    of an actual or implied contract, knowingly facilitate the execution of any 
    transaction which is prohibited or regulated under this Act:  
 

Provided that a mere carriage, without 
    knowledge, of persons, goods or technology, or provision of services, 
    including by a public or private carrier of goods, courier, 
    telecommunication, postal service provider, or financial service provider, 
    shall not be an offence for the purposes of this section.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>13</number> Regulation of export, transfer, 
    re-transfer, transit and trans-shipment.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No item notified under this Act shall be exported, transferred, 
    re‑transferred, brought in transit or trans-shipped except in accordance 
    with the provisions of this Act or any other relevant Act.  
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> Any transfer of technology of an item 
    whose export is prohibited under this Act or any other relevant Act relating 
    to relevant activity shall be prohibited.  
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> When any technology is notified under 
    this Act or any other relevant Act, as being subject to transfer controls, 
    the transfer of such technology shall be restricted to the extent notified 
    thereunder.  
 

Explanation.—The 
    transfer of technology may take place through either or both of the 
    following modes of transfer, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    by a person or from a 
    place within India to a person or place outside India;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    by a person or from a 
    place outside India to a person, or a place, which is also outside India 
    (but only where the transfer is by, or within the control of, person, who is 
    a citizen of India, or any person who is a resident in India).  
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>4</number> The Central Government may notify any 
    item as being subject to the provisions of this Act, whether or not it is 
    covered under any other relevant Act; and when such item is exhibited, sold, 
    supplied or transferred to any foreign entity or a foreigner who is 
    resident, operating, visiting studying, or conducting research or business 
    within the territorial limits of India, or in its airspace or Exclusive 
    Economic Zone, it shall constitute an offence.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>14</number> Offences and penalties.—Any 
    person who contravenes, or attempts to contravene or abets, the provisions 
    of section 8 or section 10 of this Act, shall be punishable with 
    imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than five years but which 
    may extend to imprisonment for life, and shall also be liable to fine.  
  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>15</number> Punishment for aiding non-State actor or 
    terrorist.—
<section><number>1</number> Any person who, 
    with intent to aid any non‑State actor or terrorist contravenes the 
    provisions of section 9 of this Act, shall be punishable with imprisonment 
    for a term which shall not be less than five years but which may extend to 
    imprisonment for life, and shall also be liable to fine.  
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> Any person who, with intent to aid any 
    non‑State actor or terrorist, attempts to contravene or abets, or does any 
    act preparatory to contravention of sub‑section (1), shall be deemed to have 
    contravened that provision and the provision of sub‑section (1) shall apply 
    subject to the modification that the reference to “imprisonment for life” 
    therein shall be construed as a reference to “imprisonment for ten years”.  
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> While determining the punishment under 
    this section, the court shall take into consideration whether the accused 
    had the knowledge about the transferee being a non‑State actor or not.  
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>16</number> Punishment for unauthorised export.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person who knowingly contravenes, abets or attempts to contravene, the 
    provisions of sub‑section (4) of section 13 of this Act, shall be punishable 
    with fine which shall not be less than three lakh rupees and which may 
    extend to twenty lakh rupees.  
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> If any person is again convicted of the 
    same offence under sub‑section (1), then he shall be punishable for the 
    second and every subsequent offence with imprisonment for a term which shall 
    not be less than six months but which may extend to five years and shall 
    also be liable to fine.  
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>17</number> Punishment for violation of other 
    provisions of the Act.—
<section><number>1</number> Where 
    any person contravenes, or abets or attempts to contravene, any provision of 
    this Act other than the provisions under sections 8, 9, 10 and sub‑section 
    (4) of section 13 of this Act, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for 
    a term which shall not be less than six months but which may extend to five 
    years and shall also be liable to fine.  
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> If any person is again convicted of the 
    same offence under sub‑section (1), then he shall be punishable for the 
    second and every subsequent offence with imprisonment for a term which shall 
    not be less than one year but which may extend to seven years and shall also 
    be liable to fine.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>18</number> Penalty for using false or making forged 
    documents, etc.—Where any person 
    signs or uses, or causes to be signed or used, any declaration, statement or 
    document submitted to the competent authority knowing or having reason to 
    believe that such declaration, statement or document is forged or tampered 
    with or is false in any material particular, and relates to items notified 
    under this Act or any other relevant Act, including those related to 
    relevant activity, he shall be punishable with fine which shall not be less 
    than five lakh rupees or five times the value of the materials, equipment, 
    technology or services, whichever is more.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>19</number> Punishment for offences with respect to 
    which no provision has been made.—Whoever 
    contravenes any other provision of this Act or any rule or order made 
    thereunder for which no specific punishment is provided, shall be punishable 
    with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or with fine, or 
    with both.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>20</number> Offences by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where an offence under this Act has been committed by a company, every 
    person who at the time the offence was committed was in charge of, and was 
    responsible to, the company for the conduct of the business of the company 
    as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and 
    shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:  
 

Provided that nothing contained in this 
    sub‑section shall render any such person liable to any punishment, if he 
    proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or that he had 
    exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.  
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in 
    sub‑section (1), where any offence under this Act has been committed by a 
    company and it is proved that the offence has been committed with the 
    consent or connivance of, or is attributable to, any neglect on the part of, 
    any director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such 
    director, manager, secretary or other officer shall be deemed to be guilty 
    of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished 
    accordingly.  
 

Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “company” means any body 
    corporate and includes a firm and other association of individuals; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    “director”, in relation 
    to a firm, means a partner in the firm.  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>21</number> Cognizance of offences.—No 
    Court shall take cognizance of any offence under this Act without the 
    previous sanction of the Central Government or any officer authorised by the 
    Central Government in this behalf.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>22</number> Bar of jurisdiction of civil courts.—No 
    action or proceedings taken under section 5 and sub‑sections 
<section><number>1</number> and (2) of 
    section 7 of this Act by the Central Government or any officer authorised by 
    it in this behalf ­shall be called in question in any civil court in any 
    suit or application or by way of appeal or revision, and no injunction shall 
    be granted by any civil court or other authority in respect of any action 
    taken or to be taken in pursuance of any power conferred under those 
    provisions.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>23</number> Effect of other laws.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
    inconsistent therewith contained in any enactment other than this Act or any 
    other instrument having effect by virtue of any enactment other than this 
    Act.  
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> Where any act or omission constitutes an 
    offence punishable under this Act and also under any other relevant Act, 
    then the offender found guilty of such offence shall be liable to be 
    punished under that Act which imposes a greater punishment.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>24</number> Protection of action taken in good 
    faith.—No suit, prosecution or 
    other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central Government or any 
    officer or authority of the Central Government or any other authority on 
    whom powers have been conferred pursuant to this Act, for anything which is 
    in good faith done or purported to be done in pursuance of this Act or any 
    rule or order made thereunder.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>25</number> Special provisions as to Central 
    Government.—Nothing in this Act 
    shall affect the activities of the Central Government in the discharge of 
    its functions relating to the security or the defence of India.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>26</number> Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by notification, make rules to carry out the 
    provisions of this Act.  
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> In particular and without prejudice to 
    the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any 
    of the following matters, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    manner of regulating any 
    item related to relevant activity under sub‑section (1) of section 5;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    appointment of Advisory 
    Committees, their powers and duties under section 6;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    appointment of Licensing 
    and Appellate Authority and the manner of licensing under sub‑section (2) of 
    section 7; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    any other matter which 
    has to be, or may be, prescribed.  
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>3</number> Every rule made under this Act shall be 
    laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, 
    while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be 
    comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, 
    before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
    successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification 
    in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule 
    shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
    as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment 
    shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under 
    that rule.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>27</number> Power to remove difficulties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the 
    Central Government may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make 
    such provisions, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as may 
    appear to be necessary for removing the difficulty:  
 

Provided that no order shall be made under 
    this section after the expiry of the period of two years from the date of 
    commencement of this Act.  
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> Every order made under this section 
    shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of 
    Parliament.  

 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>    Came into force 
    on 17-11-2006, vide S.O. 1990(E), dated 17th November, 2006.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>