<act><title>


The Industrial Employment (Standing Orders) Central Rules, 19461</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> 

<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the Industrial Employment (Standing Orders) Central Rules, 1946.
 

2[(2) They extend 
to all Union territories, and shall also apply in any State (other than a Union 
territory) to industrial establishments under the control of the Central 
Government or a Railway administration or in a major port, mine or oil field.]
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
In these rules, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,—
 <section>
    <number>a</number> ‘Act’ means the 
Industrial Employment (Standing Orders) Act, 1946 (20 of 1946),
 </section><section>
    <number>b</number> ‘Form’ means a 
form set out in Schedule II appended to these Rules.
 
 
</section></article> 

  
 <article>1[<number>2A</number> In the Schedule to the 
Act, after item 10, the following additional matters shall be inserted, 
namely:—
 “10A. Additional matters to be 
provided in Standing Orders relating to all industrial establishments in coal 
mines—
 <section>    <number>1</number> Medical aid 
in case of accident;
 </section><section>    <number>2</number> Railway 
travel facilities;
 </section><section>    <number>3</number> Method of 
filling vacancies;
 </section><section>    <number>4</number> 
Transfers;
 </section><section>    <number>5</number> Liability 
of manager of the establishment or mine;
 </section><section>    <number>6</number> Service 
certificate;
 </section><section>    <number>7</number> Exhibition 
and supply of Standing Orders.
 “10B. Additional matters to be 
provided in the Standing Orders relating to all Industrial 
Establishments,—
 </section><section>    <number>1</number> Service 
Record—matters relating to service card, token tickets, certification of 
service, change of residential address of workers and record of age;
 </section><section>    <number>2</number> 
Confirmation;
 </section><section>    <number>3</number> Age of 
retirement;
 </section><section>    <number>4</number> 
Transfer;
 </section><section>    <number>5</number> Medical aid 
in case of accidents;
 </section><section>    <number>6</number> Medical 
examination;
 </section><section>    <number>7</number> 
Secrecy;
 </section><section>    <number>8</number> Exclusive 
service.”]
  


</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>3</number> 

<section><number>1</number> Save as otherwise provided in sub-rule (2), the Model Standing Orders for 
the purposes of the Act shall be those set out in Schedule I appended to these 
rules.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Model Standing 
Orders for the purposes of the Act in respect of industrial establishments in 
coal mines shall be those set out in Schedule IA appended to these rules.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
An application for certification of Standing Orders shall be made in Form I.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
The prescribed particulars 
of workmen for the purposes of sub-section (3) of section 3 of the Act shall be—
 <section>
    <number>1</number> Total number 
employed;
 </section><section>
    <number>2</number> Number of 
permanent workmen;
 </section><section>
    <number>3</number> Number of 
temporary workmen;
 

1[(3A) Number of 
casual workmen;]
 </section><section>
    <number>4</number> Number of badlis 
or substitutes;
 

2[(4A) Number of 
fixed term employment workmen;]
 </section><section>
    <number>5</number> Number of 
probationers;
 </section><section>
    <number>6</number> Number of 
apprentices;
 </section><section>
    <number>7</number> Name of the trade 
union, or trade unions, if any, to which the workmen belong;
 </section><section>
    <number>8</number> Remarks.
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
As soon as may be after he 
receives an application under rule 4 in respect of an industrial establishment, 
the Certifying Officer shall—
 <section>
    <number>a</number> where there is a 
trade union of the workmen, forward a copy of the draft Standing Orders to the 
trade union together with a notice in Form II;
 </section><section>
    <number>b</number> where there is no 
such trade union, call a meeting of the workmen to elect three representatives, 
to whom he shall, upon their election, forward a copy of the draft Standing 
Orders together with a notice in Form II.
 
 
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
Standing Orders certified in pursuance of sub-section (3) of section 5 or 
sub-section (2) of section 6 of the Act shall be authenticated by the signature 
and seal of office of the Certifying Officer or the appellate authority as the 
case may be and shall be forwarded by such officer or authority within a week of 
authentication by registered letter post to the employer and to the trade union, 
or, as the case may be, the representatives of the workmen elected in pursuance 
of rule 6.
 
 
</article> 

  
 <article>1[<number>7A</number> 
<section><number>1</number> Any person 
desiring to prefer an appeal in pursuance of sub-section (1) of section 6 of the 
Act shall draw up a memorandum of appeal setting out the grounds of appeal and 
forward it in quintuplicate to the appellate authority accompanied by a 
certified copy of the Standing Orders, amendments or modifications, as the case 
may be. 
2[The memorandum of 
appeal shall be in 3[Form IVA] set out in Schedule II 
to these rules.]
 </section><section><number>2</number> The appellate authority shall, 
after giving the appellant an opportunity of being heard, confirm the Standing 
Orders, amendments or modifications as certified by the Certifying Officer 
unless it considers that there are reasons for giving the other parties to the 
proceedings a hearing before a final decision is made in the appeal.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where the appellate authority 
does not confirm the Standing Orders, amendments or modifications, it shall fix 
a date for the hearing of the appeal and direct notice thereof to be 
given—
 <subsection>    <number>a</number> where the 
appeal is filed by the employer or a workman, to trade unions of the workmen of 
the industrial establishments, and where there are no such trade unions to the 
representatives of workmen elected under clause (b) of rule 6, or as the case 
may be, to the employer;
 </subsection><subsection>    <number>b</number> where the 
appeal is filed by a trade union, to the employer and all other trade unions of 
the workmen of the industrial establishment;
 </subsection><subsection>    <number>c</number> where the 
appeal is filed by the representatives of the workmen, to the employer and any 
other workman whom the appellate authority joins as a party to the 
appeal.
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number> The appellant shall furnish 
each of the respondents with a copy of the memorandum of appeal.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The appellate authority may at 
any stage call for any evidence it considers necessary for the disposal of the 
appeal.
 </section><section><number>6</number> On the date fixed under 
sub-rule (3) for the hearing of the appeal, the appellate authority shall take 
such evidence as it may have called for or consider to be relevant.]
  




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
The register required to 
be maintained by section 8 of the Act shall be in Form III and shall be properly 
bound and the Certifying Officer shall furnish a copy of Standing Orders 
approved for an Industrial Establishment to any person applying therefor on 
payment of a fee 

1[calculated at the 
following rates per copy—
 <section>
     <number>i</number> for the first two 
hundred words or less seventy-five paise;
 </section><section>
    <number>ii</number> for every 
additional one hundred words or fraction thereof thirty-seven paise:
 
Provided that, where the 
said Standing Order exceeds five pages, the approximate number of words per page 
shall be taken as the basis for calculating the total number of words to the 
nearest hundred, for the purpose of assessing the copying fee.]
 
 



</section></article><form>
 




The Industrial Employment (Standing Orders) Central Rules, 1946
 


 
 




SCHEDULE I
 




1[Model 
Standing Orders in respect of Industrial Establishment not being Industrial 
Establishments in coal mines]
 


1. 
These orders shall come 
into force on......
 


2. Classification of 
workmen.—(a) 
Workman shall be classified as—
 


        (1)  Permanent

 


        (2)  probationers
 


        (3)  badlis
 



    2[(3A)  fixed 
term employment;]
 


        (4)  temporary
 


        (5)  casual
 


        (6)  apprentices.
 


(b) A ‘permanent’ workman 
is a workman who has been engaged on a permanent basis and includes any person 
who has satisfactorily completed a probationary period of three months in the 
same or another occupation in the industrial establishment including breaks due 
to sickness, accident, leave, lockout, strike (not being an illegal strike) or 
involuntary closure of the establishment.
 


(c) A ‘probationer’ is a 
workman who is provisionally employed to fill a permanent vacancy in a post and 
has not completed three months’ service therein. If a permanent employee is 
employed as a probationer in a new post he may, at any time during the 
probationary period of three months, be reverted to his old permanent post.
 


(d) A ‘badli’ is a 
workman who is appointed in the post of a permanent workman or probationer who 
is temporarily absent.
 


(e) A ‘temporary’ workman 
is a workman who has been engaged for work which is of an essentially temporary 
nature likely to be finished within a limited period.
 


(f) A ‘casual’ workman is a 
workman whose employment is of a casual nature.
 


(g) An ‘apprentice’ is a 
learner who is paid an allowance during the period of his training.
 



2[(h) A ’fixed term 
employment’ workman is a workman who has been engaged on the basis of contract 
of employment for a fixed period. However, his working hours, wages, allowances 
and other benefits shall not be less than that of a permanent workman. He shall 
also be eligible for all statutory benefits available to a permanent workman 
proportionately according to the period of service rendered by him even though 
his period of employment does not extend to the qualifying period of employment 
required in the statute.]
 


3. Tickets.—(1) 
Every workman shall be given a permanent ticket unless he is a probationer, 
badli, temporary worker or apprentice.
 


(2) Every permanent workman 
shall be provided with a departmental ticket showing his number, and shall, on 
being required to do so, show it to any person authorised by the manager to 
inspect it.
 


(3) Every badli 
shall be provided with a badli card, on which shall be entered the days 
on which he has worked in the establishment, and which shall be surrendered if 
he obtains permanent employment.
 


(4) Every temporary workman 
shall be provided with a ‘temporary’ ticket which he shall surrender on his 
discharge.
 


(5) Every casual worker 
shall be provided with a ‘casual’ card, on which shall be entered the days on 
which he has worked in the establishment.
 


(6) Every apprentice shall 
be provided with an ‘apprentice’ card, which shall be surrendered if he obtains 
permanent employment.
 


4. Publication of 
working time.—The 
periods and hours of work for all classes of workers in each shift shall be 
exhibited in English and in the principal languages of workmen employed in the 
establishment on notice boards maintained at or near the main entrance of the 
establishment and at time-keeper’s office, if any. 
 


5. Publication of 
holidays and pay days.—Notices 
specifying (a) the days observed by the establishment as holidays, and (b) pay 
days shall be posted on the said notice boards.
 


6. Publication of wage 
rates.—Notice 
specifying the rates of wages payable to all classes of workmen and for all 
classes of work shall be displayed on the said notice boards.
 



3[7. Shift 
working.—More than one shift may be worked in a department or departments or 
any section of a department of the establishment at the discretion of the 
employer. If more than one shift is worked, the workmen shall be liable to be 
transferred from one shift to another. No shift working shall be discontinued 
without two months’ notice being given in writing to the workmen prior to such 
discontinuance, provided that no such notice shall be necessary if the closing 
of the shift is under an agreement with the workmen affected. If as a result of 
the discontinuance of the shift working, any workmen are to be retrenched, such 
retrenchment shall be effected in accordance with the provisions of the 
Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 (14 of 1947), and the rules made thereunder. If 
shift working is re-started, the workmen shall be given notice and re-employed 
in accordance with the provisions of the said Act and the said rules.]
 




4[7A. Notice of 
change in shift working.—Any 
notice of discontinuance or of re-starting of a shift working required by 
Standing Order 7 shall be in the 

5[Form IVA] and 
shall be served in the following manner, namely:—
 


The notice shall be 
displayed conspicuously by the employer on a notice board at the main entrance 
to the establishment 

6[***]:
 


Provided that where any 
registered trade union of workmen exists, a copy of the notice shall also be 
served by registered post to the secretary of such union.]
 


8. Attendance and late 
coming.—A 
workman shall be at work at the establishment at the times fixed and notified 
under paragraph 4. Workmen attending late will be liable to the deductions 
provided for in the Payment of Wages Act, 1936.
 


9. Leave.—(1) 
Holidays with pay will be allowed as provided for in 

7[Chapter VIII of 
the Factories Act, 1948] and other holidays in accordance with law, contract, 
custom and usage.
 


(2) A workman who desires 
to obtain leave of absence shall apply to the 

7[employer or any 
other officer of the industrial establishment specified in this behalf by the 
employer], who shall issue orders on the application within a week of its 
submission or two days prior to the commencement of the leave applied for, 
whichever is earlier, provided that if the leave applied for is to commence on 
the date of the application or within three days thereof, the order shall be 
given on the same day. If the leave asked for is granted, a leave pass shall be 
issued to the worker. If the leave is refused or postponed, the fact of such 
refusal or postponement and the reasons therefor shall be recorded in writing in 
a register to be maintained for the purpose, and if the worker so desires, a 
copy of the entry in the register shall be supplied to him. If the workman after 
proceeding on leave desires an extension thereof, he shall apply to 

8[employer or the 
office specified in this behalf by the employer] who shall send a written reply 
either granting or refusing extension of leave to the workman if his address is 
available and if such reply is likely to reach him before the expiry of the 
leave originally granted to him.
 


(3) If the workman remains 
absent beyond the period of leave originally granted or subsequently extended, 
he shall lose his lien on his appointment unless he (a) returns within 8 days of 
the expiry of the leave, and (b) explains to the satisfaction of the 

7[employer or the 
officer specified in this behalf by the employer] his inability to return before 
the expiry of his leave. In case the workman loses his lien on his appointment, 
he shall be entitled to be kept on the badli list.
 


10. Casual leave.—A 
workman may be granted casual leave of absence with or without pay not exceeding 
10 days in the aggregate in a calendar year. Such leave shall not be for more 
than three days at a time except in case of sickness. Such leave is intended to 
meet special circumstances which cannot be foreseen. Ordinarily, the previous 
permission of the head of the department in the establishment shall be obtained 
before such leave is taken, but when this is not possible, the head of the 
department shall, as soon as may be practicable, be informed in writing of the 
absence from and of the probable duration of such absence.
 


11. Payment of wages.—(1) 
Any wages, due to the workman but not paid on the usual pay day on account of 
their being unclaimed, shall be paid by the employer on an unclaimed wage pay 
day in each week, which shall be notified on the notice boards as aforesaid.
 


(2) All workmen will be 
paid wages on a working day before the expiry of the seventh or the tenth day 
after the last day of the wage period in respect of which the wages are payable, 
according as the total number of workmen employed in the establishment does not 
or does exceed one thousand.
 


12. Stoppage of work.—(1) 
The employer may, at any time, in the event of fire, catastrophe, breakdown of 
machinery or stoppage of power supply, epidemics, civil commotion or other cause 
beyond his control, stop any section or sections of the establishment, wholly or 
partially for any period or periods without notice.
 


(2) In the event of such 
stoppage during working hours, the workmen affected shall be notified by notices 
put upon the notice board in the departments concerned 

8[and at the office 
of the employer and at the time-keeper’s office, if any], as soon as 
practicable, when work will be resumed and whether they are to remain or leave 
their place of work. The workmen shall not ordinarily be required to remain for 
more than two hours after the commencement of the stoppage. If the period of 
detention does not exceeds one hour the workmen so detained shall not be paid 
for the period of detention. If the period of detention exceeds one hour, the 
workmen so detained shall be entitled to receive wages for the whole of the time 
during which they are detained as a result of the stoppage. In the case of 
piece-rate workers, the average daily earning for the previous month shall be 
taken to be the daily wage. No other compensation will be admissible in case of 
such stoppages. Wherever practicable, reasonable notice shall be given of 
resumption of normal work.
 


(3) In cases where workmen 
are laid off for short periods on account of failure of plant or a temporary 
curtailment of production, the period of unemployment shall be treated as 
compulsory leave either with or without pay, as the case may be. When, however, 
workmen have to be laid off for an indefinitely long period, their services may 
be terminated after giving them due notice or pay in lieu thereof.
 


(4) The employer may in the 
event of a strike affecting either wholly or partially any section or department 
of the establishment close down either wholly or partially such section or 
department and any other section or department affected by such closing down. 
The fact of such closure shall be notified by notices put on the notice board in 
the section or department concerned and in the time-keeper’s office, if any, as 
soon as practicable. The workmen concerned shall also be notified by a general 
notice, prior resumption of work, as to when work will be resumed.
 


13. Termination of 
employment.—(1) 
For terminating employment of a permanent workman, notice in writing shall be 
given either by the employer or the workmen—one month’s notice in the case of 
monthly-rated workmen and two weeks’ notice in the case of other workmen: one 
month’s or two weeks’ pay, as the case may be, may be paid in lieu of notice.
 



9[(2) Subject to the 
provisions of the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 (14 of 1947), no temporary 
workman whether monthly rated or weekly rated or piece rated, and no probationer 
or badli or fixed term employment workman as a result of non-renewal of 
contract of employment or on its expiry, shall be entitled to any notice or pay 
in lieu thereof, if his services are terminated, but the services of a temporary 
workman shall not be terminated as a punishment unless he has been given an 
opportunity of explaining the charges of misconduct alleged against him in the 
manner prescribed in paragraph 14.]
 


(3) Where the employment of 
any workman is terminated, the wages earned by him and other dues, if any, shall 
be paid before the expiry of the second working day from the day on which his 
employment is terminated.
 


14. Disciplinary action 
for misconduct.—(1) 
A workman may be fined up to two per cent. of his wages in a month for any of 
the following acts and omissions, namely:—
 


              
......................................................................................................................
 


              
......................................................................................................................
 


Note.—Specify 
the acts and omissions which the employer may notify with the previous approval 
of the....... Government or of the prescribed authority in pursuance of section 
8 of the Payment of Wages Act, 1936.
 


(2) A workman may be 
suspended for a period not exceeding four days at a time or dismissed without 
notice or any compensation in lieu of notice, if he is found to be guilty of 
misconduct.
 


(3) The following acts and 
omissions shall be treated as misconduct:—
 


        (a) wilful 
in-subordination or disobedience, whether alone or in combination with others, 
to any lawful and reasonable order of a superior;
 


        (b) theft, fraud, 
or dishonesty in connection with the employer’s business or property;
 


        (c) wilful damage 
to or loss of employer’s goods or property;
 


        (d) taking or 
giving bribes or any illegal gratification;
 


        (e) habitual 
absence without leave or absence without leave for more than 10 days;
 


         (f) habitual late 
attendance;
 


        (g) habitual breach 
of any law applicable to the establishment;
 


        (h) riotous or 
disorderly behaviour during working hours at the establishments or any act 
subversive of discipline;
 


         (i) habitual 
negligence or neglect of work;
 


         (j) frequent 
repetition of any act or omission for which a fine may be imposed to a maximum 
of 2 per cent. of the wages in a month;
 


        (k) striking work 
or inciting others to strike work in contravention of the provisions of any law, 
or rule having the force of law.
 



       10[(l)  
sexual harassment which includes such un-welcome sexual determined behaviour 
(whether directly or by implication) as—
 


             (i)  physical 
contact and advances; or
 


            (ii)  demand or 
request for sexual favours; or
 


           (iii)  sexually 
coloured remarks; or
 


           (iv)  showing 
pornography; or
 


            (v)  any other 
un-welcome physical, verbal or non-verbal conduct of sexual nature.]
 



11[Provided that 
where there is a complaint of sexual harassment within the meaning of clause (l) 
of sub-paragraph (3), the Complaints Committee constituted under sub-paragraph 
(3B) in each establishment for inquiring into such complaints, shall, 
notwithstanding anything contained in paragraph 15, be deemed to be the 
inquiring authority appointed by the employer for the purpose of these rules.
 


(3A) The Complaints 
Committee shall hold the inquiry, unless separate procedure has been prescribed 
for the Complaints Committee for holding such inquiry into the complaints of 
sexual harassment, as far as practicable, in accordance with the procedure laid 
down in these rules.
 


(3B) The Complaints 
Committee shall consist of—
 


        (a)  a Chairperson 
who shall be a woman;
 


        (b)  two members 
representing Non-Government Organisation (NGO) or any other body which is 
familiar with the issue of sexual harassment or nominees of the National or 
State Human Rights Commission or the National or State Commission for Women 
familiar with the issue of sexual harassment,
 


to be nominated by the 
employer:
 


Provided that one of the 
two members of the Complaints Commitee shall be a woman.
 


(3C) The Complaints 
Commitee shall make and submit every year an annual report, to the appropriate 
Government, of the complaints and action taken.
 


(3D) The employers or their 
agents shall report, to the appropriate Government, on the compliance of the 
guidelines issued by the Central Government in pursuance of the directions of 
the Supreme Court in Writ Petition (Criminal) Nos. 666-670 of 1992 (Vishaka
v. State of Rajasthan and Others) including on the reports of the 
Complaints Committee.]
 



12[(4) (a) Where a 
disciplinary proceeding against a workman is contemplated or is pending or where 
criminal proceedings against him in respect of any offence are under 
investigation or trial and the employer is satisfied that it is necessary or 
desirable to place the workman under suspension, he may, by order in writing, 
suspend him with effect from such date as may be specified in the order. A 
statement setting out in detail the reasons for such suspension shall be 
supplied to the workman within a week from the date of suspension.]
 



13[(b) A workman who 
is placed under suspension shall be paid subsistence allowance in accordance 
with the provisions of section 10A of the Act.]
 



14[(ba) In the 
inquiry, the workman shall be entitled to appear in person or to be represented 
by an office bearer of a trade union of which he is a member.
 


(bb) The proceedings of the 
inquiry shall be recorded in Hindi or in English or the language of the State 
where the industrial establishment is located, whichever is preferred by the 
workman.
 


(bc) The proceedings of the 
inquiry shall be completed within a period of three months:
 


Provided that the period of 
three months may, for reasons to be recorded in writing, be extended for such 
further period as may be deemed necessary by the inquiry officer.]
 


(c) If on the conclusion of 
the inquiry or, as the case may be, of the criminal proceedings, the workman has 
been found guilty of the charges framed against him and it is considered, after 
giving the workman concerned a reasonable opportunity of making representation 
on the penalty proposed, that an order of dismissal or suspension or fine or 
stoppage of annual increment or reduction in rank would meet the ends of 
justice, the employer shall pass an order accordingly:
 


Provided that when an order 
of dismissal is passed under this clause, the workman shall be deemed to have 
been absent from duty during the period of suspension and shall not be entitled 
to any remuneration for such period, and the subsistence allowance already paid 
to him shall not be recovered:
 


Provided further that where 
the period between the date on which the workman was suspended from duty pending 
the inquiry or investigation or trial and the date on which an order of 
suspension was passed under this clause exceeds four days, the workman shall be 
deemed to have been suspended only for four days or for such shorter period as 
is specified in the said order of suspension and for the remaining period he 
shall be entitled to the same wages as he would have received if he had not been 
placed under suspension, after deducting the subsistence allowance paid to him 
for such period:
 


Provided also that where an 
order imposing fine or stoppage of annual increment or reduction in rank is 
passed under this clause, the workman shall be deemed to have been on duty 
during the period of suspension and shall be entitled to the same wages as he 
would have received if he had not been placed under suspension after deducting 
the subsistence allowance paid to him for such period:
 


Provided also that in the 
case of a workman to whom the provisions of clause (2) of article 311 of the 
Constitution apply, the provisions of that article shall be complied with.
 


(d) If on the conclusion of 
the inquiry, or as the case may, of the criminal proceedings, the workman has 
been found to be not guilty of any of the charges framed against him, he shall 
be deemed to have been on duty during the period of suspension and shall be 
entitled to the same wages as he would have received if he had not been placed 
under suspension, after deducting the subsistence allowance paid to him for such 
period.
 


(e) The payment of 
subsistence allowance under this standing order shall be subject to the workman 
concerned not taking up any employment during the period of suspension.
 



15[(5)] In awarding 
punishment under this standing order, the 

16[authority 
imposing the punishment] shall take into account the gravity of the misconduct, 
the previous record, if any, of the workmen and any other extenuating or 
aggravating circumstances that may exist. A copy of the order passed by the


16[authority 
imposing the punishment] shall be supplied to the workman concerned.
 



16[(6)(a) A workman 
aggrieved by an order imposing punishment, may within twenty-one days from the 
date of receipt of the order, appeal to the appellate authority;
 


(b) the employer shall, for 
the purposes of clause (a), specify the appellate authority;
 


(c) the appellate 
authority, after giving an opportunity to the workman of being heard shall pass 
such order as he thinks proper on the appeal within fifteen days of its receipt 
and communicate the same to the workman in writing.]
 


15. Complaints.—All 
complaints arising out of employment including those relating to unfair 
treatment or wrongful exaction on the part of the employer or his agent, shall 
be submitted to the manager or other person specified in this behalf with the 
right of appeal to the employer.
 


16. Certificate on 
termination of service.—Every 
permanent workman shall be entitled to a service certificate at the time of his 
dismissal, discharge or retirement from service.
 


17. Liability of 

17[employer].—The


17[employer] of the 
establishment shall personally be held responsible for the proper and faithful 
observance of the standing orders.
 



18[17A.—(1) 
Any person desiring to prefer an appeal in pursuance of sub-section (1) of 
section 6 of the Act shall draw up a memorandum of appeal setting out the ground 
of appeal and forward it in quintuplicate to the appellate authority accompanied 
by a certified copy of the standing orders, amendments or modifications, as the 
case may be.
 


(2) The appellate authority 
shall, after giving the appellant an opportunity of being heard, confirm the 
standing orders, amendments or modifications as certified by the Certifying 
Officer unless it considers that there are reasons for giving the other parties 
to the proceedings a hearing before a final decision is made in the appeal.
 


(3) Where the appellate 
authority does not confirm the standing orders, amendments or modifications it 
shall fix a date for the hearing of the appeal and direct notice thereof to be 
given—
 


        (a) where the 
appeal is filed by the employer or a workman, to trade unions of the workmen of 
the industrial establishments, and where there are no such trade unions, to the 
representatives of the workmen elected under clause (b) of rule 6, or as the 
case may be, to the employer;
 


        (b) where the 
appeal is filed by a trade union to the employer and all other trade unions of 
the workmen of the industrial establishment;
 


        (c) where the 
appeal is filed by the representatives of the workmen, to the employer and any 
other workman whom the appellate authority joins as a party to the appeal.
 


(4) The appellant shall 
furnish each of the respondents with a copy of the memorandum of appeal.
 


(5) The appellate authority 
may at any stage call for any evidence it considers necessary for the disposal 
of the appeal.
 


(6) On the date fixed, 
under sub-rule (3) of the hearing of the appeal, the appellate authority shall 
take such evidence as it may have called for or consider to be relevant.]
 


18. Exhibition of 
standing orders—A 
copy of these orders in English and in local language shall be posted 

19[***] and on a 
notice board maintained at or near the main entrance to the establishment and 
shall be kept in a legible condition.
 



20[***]
 


 
 


—————
 


   1. Subs. by G.S.R. 732, 
dated 12th May, 1971.
 


   2.  Ins. by G.S.R. 
936(E), dated 10th December, 2003 (w.e.f. 10-12-2003).
 


   3. Subs. by G.S.R. 557, 
dated 30th April, 1959.
 


   4. Ins. by G.S.R. 655, 
dated 3rd June, 1960.
 


   5. Subs. by G.S.R. 910, 
dated 10th August, 1984.
 


   6. Omitted by G.S.R. 
824, dated 30th June, 1975.
 


   7. Subs. by G.S.R. 732, 
dated 12th May, 1971.
 


   8. Subs. by G.S.R. 824, 
dated 30th June, 1975.
 


   9.  Subs. by G.S.R. 
936(E), dated 10th December, 2003 (w.e.f. 10-12-2003).
 


  10.  Ins. by G.S.R. 386, 
dated 5th November, 1999 (w.e.f. 20-11-1999).
 


  11.  Ins. by G.S.R. 
25(E), dated 19th January, 2006 (w.e.f. 19-1-2006).
 


  12. Subs. by G.S.R. 1123, 
dated 18th July, 1967.
 


  13. Subs. by G.S.R. 910, 
dated 10th August, 1984.
 


  14. Ins. by G.S.R. 824, 
dated 30th June, 1975.
 


  15. Clause (6) 
re-numbered as clause (5) by G.S.R. 1128, dated 18th July, 1967.
 


  16. Subs. by G.S.R. 824, 
dated 30th June, 1975.
 


  17. Subs. by G.S.R. 824, 
dated 30th June, 1975.
 


  18. Ins. by G.S.R. 1166, 
dated 28th June, 1963.
 


  19. Omitted by G.S.R. 
824, dated 30th June, 1975.
 


  20. Form omitted by G.S.R. 
910, dated 10th August, 1984.
 


 
</form><form>
 




The Industrial Employment (Standing Orders) Central Rules, 1946
 


 
 



1[SCHEDULE 
IA
 




Model Standing Orders for Industrial Establishments in Coal Mines
 


1. 
These orders shall come 
into force on........
 


2. Definition.—In 
these orders, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 


        (a) ‘attendance’ 
means presence of the workman concerned at the place or places where by the 
terms of his employment he is required to report for work and getting his 
attendance marked;
 


        (b) the expression 
‘employer’ and ‘workman’ shall have the meanings assigned to them in section 
2(d) and (i) respectively of the Industrial Employment (Standing Orders) Act, 
1946 (20 of 1946);
 


        (c) ‘Manager’ means 
the manager of the mine and includes an acting manager for the time being 
appointed in accordance with the provisions of the Mines Act, 1952 (35 of 1952);

 


        (d) words importing 
masculine gender shall be taken to include females;
 


        (e) words in the 
singular shall include the plural and vice versa.
 


3. Classification of 
workmen.—(a) 
‘Workmen’ shall be classified as—
 


         (i)  permanent;
 


        (ii)  probationers;
 


        (iii)  badlis
or substitutes;
 


 

2[(iiiA)  fixed term 
employment;]
 


       (iv)  temporary;
 


        (v)  apprentices; 
and
 


       (vi)  casual.
 


(b) A ‘permanent’ workman 
is one who is appointed for an unlimited period or who has satisfactorily put in 
three months’ continuous service in permanent post as a probationer;
 


(c) A ‘probationer’ is one 
who is provisionally employed to fill a vacancy in a permanent post and has not 
completed three months’ service in that post unless the probationary period is 
extended. If a permanent workman is employed as a probationer in a new post, he 
may, at any time, during the probationary period not exceeding three months, be 
reverted to his old permanent post unless the probationary period is extended.
 


(d) A ‘badli’ or 
substitute is one who is appointed in the post of a permanent workman or a 
probationer who is temporarily absent; but he would cease to be a ‘badli’ 
on completion of a continuous period of service of one year (190 attendances in 
the case of below ground workman and 240 attendances in the case of any other 
workman) in the same post or other post or posts in the same category or earlier 
if the post is vacated by the permanent workman or probationer. A ‘badli’ 
working in place of a probationer would be deemed to be permanent after 
completion of the probationary period.
 


(e) A ‘temporary’ workman 
is a workman who has been engaged for work which is of an essentially temporary 
nature likely to be finished within a limited period. The period within which it 
is likely to be finished should also be specified but it may be extended from 
time to time, if necessary.
 


(f) An ‘apprentice’ is a 
learner who is either paid an allowance or not paid any allowance during the 
period of his training, which shall inter alia be specified in his term 
of contract.
 


(g) A ‘casual’ workman is a 
workman who has been engaged for work which is of an essentially casual nature.
 



2[(h) A ‘fixed term 
employment’ workman is a workman who has been engaged on the basis of contract 
of employment for a fixed period. However, his working hours, wages, allowances 
and other benefits shall not be less than that of a permanent workman. He shall 
also be eligible for all statutory benefits available to a permanent workman 
proportionately according to the period of service rendered by him even though 
his period of employment does not extend to the qualifying period of employment 
required in the statute.]
 


4. 
Every workman shall be 
given a ticket appropriate to his classification at the time of his appointment 
and shall on being required to do so, show it to the person authorised by the 
employer in that behalf. The said ticket shall carry the signature or thumb 
impression of the workman concerned. If the workman loses his ticket, the 
manager shall provide him with another ticket on a payment of 25 paise.
 


5. Display of notices.—(a) 
The period and hours of work for all classes of workmen in each shift shall be 
exhibited in English and in the language understood by the majority of workmen 
employed in the establishment on notice boards maintained at or near the main 
entrance of the establishment and at the time-keeper’s office, if any.
 


(b) Notices specifying (a) 
the days observed by the establishment as holidays and (b) pay days shall be 
posted on the said notice boards. (c) Notices specifying the rates of wages and 
scales of allowances payable to all classes of workmen and for all classes of 
work shall be displayed on the said notice boards.
 


6. Payment of wages.—(a) 
Wages shall be paid direct to the individual workman on any working day between 
the hours 6.00 A.M. and 6.00 P.M. at the office of the Mine. The manager or any 
other responsible person authorised by him shall witness and attest the payments 
and note the date of payment in the wage register. Payment of wages to a 
contractor’s workman shall be made at a place to be specified by the manager and 
it shall be witnessed by a nominee of the employer deputed for this purpose in 
writing.
 


(b) Any wages due to a 
workman but not paid on the usual pay day on account of their being unclaimed 
shall be paid by the employer on such unclaimed wage pay day in each week as may 
be notified to the workmen. If the workman so desires, the unpaid wages and 
other dues payable to him shall be remitted to his address by money order after 
deducting therefrom the money order commission charges. All claims for the 
unpaid wages shall be presented to the employer within a period of twelve months 
from the date on which the wages became due.
 


(c) Overtime shall be 
worked and wages thereof paid in accordance with the provisions of the Mines 
Act, 1952 as amended by the Mines (Amendment) Act, 1959 and as may be prescribed 
from time to time. For work on weekly rest day, the workman shall be paid as 
laid down in any agreement or award or as the case may be, as per usage or 
custom.
 


7. Shift working.—More 
than one shift may be worked in a department or departments or any section of a 
department of the establishment at the discretion of the employer. If more than 
one shift is worked, a workman shall be liable to be transferred from one shift 
to another. No shift working shall be discontinued without two months’ notice 
being given in writing to the workmen prior to such discontinuance, provided 
that no such notice shall be necessary if the closing of the shift is under an 
agreement with the workman affected. If as a result of the discontinuance, of 
the shift working, any workmen are to be retrenched, such retrenchment shall be 
effected in accordance with the provisions of the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 
(14 of 1947), and the rules made thereunder. If shift working is re-started, the 
workmen shall be given notice and re-employed in accordance with the provisions 
of the said Act and the said rules.
 


8. Attendance.—All 
workmen shall be at work at the Mine at the time fixed and notified to them.
 


9. Absence from place of 
work.—Any 
workman, who after going underground or after coming to his work in the 
department in which he is employed, is found absent from his proper place of 
work during working hours without permission from the appropriate authority or 
without any sufficient reason shall be liable to be treated as absent for the 
period of his absence.
 


10. Festival holidays 
and leave.—(a) 
There shall be seven paid festival holidays or as laid down in the agreement or 
an award in force. Out of these seven days, the Republic Day, Independence Day 
and Mahatma Gandhi’s Birthday shall be allowed without option and the rest of 
the days shall be fixed by agreement or local custom. Whenever a workman has to 
work on any of these holidays, he shall, at his option be entitled to either 
thrice the wages for the day or twice the wages for the day on which he works 
and in addition to avail himself of a substituted holiday with wages on any 
other day or as laid down in an agreement or an award in force.
 


(b) (i) The workmen shall 
be entitled to leave with wages in accordance with the provision contained in 
Chapter VII of the Mines Act, 1952.
 


(ii) Normally a workman 
will not be refused the leave applied for by him. But the employer may refuse, 
revoke or curtail the leave applied for by workman, if the exigencies of work so 
demand. Wages in lieu of leave shall be paid to a workman, where he has been 
refused the leave asked for and in cases where he cannot accumulate the leave 
any further. If a workman is refused leave in a particular year in the interest 
of work, it would be open to him next year either to avail of leave on two 
occasions with the usual railway concessions or in case he avails of leave on 
only one occasion, the railway fare for the unavailed trip would be paid to him 
in the shape of National Savings/National Defence/Certificates.
 


(c) Quarantine leave shall 
be granted to a workman, who is prevented from attending to his duty because of 
his coming into contact, through no fault of his own, with a person suffering 
from a contagious disease. The leave shall be granted for such period as is 
covered by a certificate from the Medical Officer of the mine. Payment for the 
period of quarantine leave shall be at the rate of 50 per cent. of the wages 
(basic plus dearness allowance) payable to a workman. Quarantine leave cannot be 
claimed, if a workman has refused to accept during the previous three months’, 
prophylactic treatment for the disease in question.
 


(d) A workman who desires 
to obtain leave of absence shall apply to the manager not less than fifteen days 
before the commencement of the leave, except where leave is required in 
unforeseen circumstances, and the manager shall issue orders on the application 
within a week of its submission or two days prior to the commencement of the 
leave applied for, whichever is earlier, provided that if the leave applied for 
is to commence on the date of the application or within three days thereof, 
orders shall be given on the same day. If the leave asked for is granted, a 
leave-pass shall be given to the workman. If the leave is refused or postponed, 
the fact of such refusal or postponement and the reasons therefor shall be 
recorded in writing in a register to be maintained for the purpose, and if the 
worker so desires, a copy of the entry in the register shall be supplied to him. 
If the workman after proceeding on leave desires an extension thereof, he shall 
apply to the manager, who shall send a written reply either granting or refusing 
extension of leave to the workman. Sanction/refusal of leave should be 
communicated to the workman in writing invariably.
 


(e) If a workman remains 
absent beyond the period of leave originally granted or subsequently extended, 
he shall lose lien on his appointment unless he—
 


        (a) returns within 
ten days of expiry of his leave, and
 


        (b) explains to the 
satisfaction of the manager his inability to return on the expiry of his leave.
 


In case, the workman loses 
as aforesaid, his lien on the appointment, he shall be entitled to be kept on 
the ‘badli list’.
 


(f) A workman may be 
granted casual leave of absence with pay not exceeding five days in the 
aggregate in a calendar year. Such leave shall not be for more than three days 
at a time except in case of sickness. Such leave is intended to meet special 
circumstances which cannot be foreseen. Ordinarily, the previous permission of 
the head of the department in the establishment shall be obtained before such 
leave is taken, but where this is not possible, the head of the department 
shall, as soon as may be practicable, be informed in writing of such absence and 
of the probable duration thereof.
 


(g) Notwithstanding 
anything mentioned above, any workman who overstays his sanctioned leave or 
remains absent without reasonable cause will render himself liable for 
disciplinary action.
 


11.


3[***]
 


12. Railway travel 
facilities.—(a) 
When a workman proceeds on leave and is qualified for free railway fare, the 
employer shall give him the cost equivalent of his ticket (including bus fare) 
and for boat to his home.
 


(b) Every workman who has 
completed a period of twelve months’ continuous service would qualify for 
railway fare or bus fare or both for going home on leave and returning to the 
mine on the expiry of the leave. The twelve months’ service shall be deemed to 
have been completed if, during the twelve months preceding the date on which he 
applies for leave, he has worked for not less than two hundred and forty days.
 


(c) If on the expiry of the 
leave, a workman returns, he shall then receive a cash payment equivalent to the 
return fare. If on his return the mine is unable to have him back, he shall be 
paid return fare at once.
 


(d) If the journey home is 
by bus or partly by bus and partly by train, the cost of the journey shall be 
adjusted accordingly.
 


(e) The workman shall be 
entitled to railway fare by mail or express train, wherever under the Railway 
Rules tickets are available for such travel.
 


(f) The class by which a 
workman is entitled to travel shall be:—
 


         (i)  if his basic 
wage is Rs. 165 or less per month           III Class.
 


        (ii)  if his basic 
wage is above Rs. 165 and upto Rs. 265 per month        II Class.
 


        (iii)  if his basic 
wage is above Rs. 265 per month            I Class.
 


13. Termination of 
services.—(a) 
For terminating the services of a permanent workman having less than one year of 
continuous service, notice of one month in writing with reasons or wages in lieu 
thereof shall be given by the employer:
 


Provided that no such 
notice shall be required to be given when the services of the workman are 
terminated on account of mis-conduct established in accordance with the Standing 
Orders.
 



4[(b) Subject to the 
provisions of the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 (14 of 1947),—
 


         (i)  no notice of 
termination of employment shall be necessary in the case of temporary and 
badli workmen;
 


        (ii)  no workman 
employed on fixed term employment basis as a result of non-renewal of contract 
of employment or on its expiry, shall be entitled to any notice or pay in lieu 
thereof, if his services are terminated.]
 


(c) No workman shall leave 
the service of an employer unless notice in writing is given at the scale 
indicated below:
 


         (i) For monthly 
paid workmen                            One month
 


        (ii) For weekly 
paid workmen                              Two weeks:
 


Provided that it will be 
for the employer to relax this condition and the workman may pay cash in lieu of 
such notice.
 


(d) For purposes of 
Standing Orders 13(a), (b) and (c) the terms ‘service’ and ‘wages’ shall have 
the same meaning as assigned to these in sections 25(B) (1) and 2(rr) 
respectively of the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947.
 


14. Stoppage of work and 
re-opening.—(a) 
Subject to the provisions of Chapter VA of the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947, 
the employer may at any time, in the event of underground trouble, fire, 
catastrophe, break-down of machinery, stoppage of power-supply, epidemic, civil 
commotion or any other cause beyond the control of the employer, stop any 
section or sections of the mine wholly or partly for any period or periods.
 


(b) In the event of such 
stoppage during working hours, the workmen affected shall be notified by notice 
put up on the notice board in the departments concerned and of the office as 
soon as practicable as to when work will be resumed and whether they are to 
remain or leave their place of work. The workmen will not ordinarily be required 
to remain for more than two hours after the commencement of the stoppage. 
Whenever workmen are laid off on account of failure of plant or a temporary 
curtailment of production or other causes they shall be paid compensation in 
accordance with the provisions of the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947. Where no 
such compensation is admissible, they shall be granted leave with or without 
wages as the case may be at the option of the workman concerned, leave with 
wages being granted to the extent of any leave due to them. When workmen are to 
be laid off for an indefinitely long period, their services may be terminated 
subject to the provisions of the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947. If normal work 
is resumed two weeks’ notice thereof shall be given by the posting of notices at 
or near the Mine office and workmen discharged earlier by the employer shall, if 
they present themselves for work, have preference for re-employment.
 


(c) The employer may be in 
the event of a strike affecting either wholly or partially any section of the 
mine close down either wholly or partially such section of the mine and any 
other section affected by such closure. The fact of such closure shall be 
notified by notices put up on notice board in the manager’s office. Prior to 
resumption of work, the workmen concerned will be notified by a general notice 
indicating as to when work will be resumed. A copy of such notice shall be sent 
to the registered trade union or unions functioning in the establishment.
 


15. Method of filling 
vacancies.—In 
the matter of filling up of permanent vacancies badli and temporary 
workmen and probationers would be given preference in the order of their 
seniority.
 


16. 

5[* * *]
 




6[17. Disciplinary 
action for misconduct.—(i) 
A workman may be suspended by the employer pending investigation or departmental 
enquiry and shall be paid subsistence allowance in accordance with the 
provisions of section 10A of the Act. The employer shall normally complete the 
enquiry within 10 days. The payment of subsistence allowance shall be subject to 
the workman not taking any employment elsewhere during the period of 
suspension.]
 


The following shall denote 
misconduct:—
 


        (a) theft, fraud, 
or dishonesty in connection with the employer’s business or property;
 


        (b) taking or 
giving of bribes or an illegal gratification whatsoever in connection with the 
employer’s business or in his own interests;
 


        (c) wilful 
in-subordination or dis-obedience, whether along or in conjunction with another 
or others, or of any lawful or reasonable order of a superior. The order of the 
superior should normally be in writing;
 


        (d) habitual late 
attendance and habitual absence without leave or without sufficient cause;
 


        (e) drunkenness, 
fighting or riotous, disorderly or indecent behaviour while on duty at the place 
of work;
 


         (f) habitual 
neglect of work;
 


        (g) habitual 
indiscipline;
 


        (h) smoking 
underground or within the mine area or in places, where it is prohibited;
 


         (i) causing wilful 
damage to work in progress or to property of the employer.
 


         (j) sleeping on 
duty;
 


        (k) malingering or 
slowing down work;
 


         (l) acceptance of 
gifts from subordinate employees;
 


       (m) conviction in 
any court of law for any criminal offence involving moral turpitude;
 


        (n) continuous 
absence without permission and without satisfactory cause for more than ten 
days;
 


        (o) giving, false 
information regarding one’s name, age, father’s name, qualification or previous 
service at the time of the employment;
 


        (p) leaving work 
without permission or sufficient reason;
 


        (q) any breach of 
the Mines Act, 1952, or any other Act or any rules, regulations or bye-laws 
thereunder, or of any standing orders;
 


         (r) threatening, 
abusing or assaulting any superior or co-worker;
 


        (s) habitual 
money-lending;
 


         (t) preaching of 
or inciting to violence;
 


        (u) abetment of or 
attempt at abetment of any of the above acts of misconduct;
 


        (v) going on 
illegal strike either single or with other workers without giving 14 days 
previous notice;
 


       (w) disclosing to 
any unauthorised person of any confidential information in regard to the working 
or process of the establishment which may come into the possession of the 
workman in the course of his work;
 


        (x) refusal to 
accept any charge-sheet or order or notice communicated in writing;
 


        (y) failure or 
refusal to wear or use any protective equipment given by the employers;
 



       7[(z)  sexual 
harassment which includes such un-welcome sexual determined behaviour (whether 
directly or by implication) as—
 


         (i)  physical 
contact and advances; or
 


        (ii)  a demand or 
request for sexual favours; or
 


        (iii)  sexually 
coloured remarks; or
 


       (iv)  showing 
pornography; or
 


        (v)  any other 
un-welcome physical, verbal or non-verbal conduct of sexual nature.]
 



8[Provided that 
where there is a complaint of sexual harassment within the meaning of clause (z) 
of sub-paragraph (i), the Complaints Committee constituted under sub-paragraph (iB) 
in each establishment for inquiring into such complaints, shall, notwithstanding 
anything contained in paragraph 18, be deemed to be the inquiring authority 
appointed by the employer for the purpose of these rules.
 


(iA) The Complaints 
Committee shall hold the inquiry, unless separate procedure has been prescribed 
for the Complaints Committee for holding such inquiry into the complaints of 
sexual harassment, as far as practicable, in accordance with the procedure laid 
down in these rules.
 


(iB) The Complaints 
Committee shall consist of—
 


        (a)  a Chairperson 
who shall be a woman;
 


        (b)  two members 
representing Non-Governmental Organisation (NGO) or any other body which is 
familiar with the issue of sexual harassment or nominees of the National or 
State Human Rights Commission or the National or State Commission for Women 
familiar with the issue of sexual harassment,
 


to be nominated by the 
employer:
 


Provided that one of the 
members of the Complaints Committee shall be woman.
 


(iC) The Complaints 
Committee shall make and submit every year an annual report, to the appropriate 
Government, of the complaints and action taken.
 


(iD) The employers or their 
agents shall report, to the appropriate Government, on the compliance of the 
guidelines issued by the Central Government in pursuance of the directions of 
the Supreme Court in Writ Petition (Criminal) Nos. 666-670 of 1992 (Vishaka
v. State of Rajasthan and Others) including on the reports of the 
Complaints Committee.]
 


(ii) No order of punishment 
under Standing Order No. 17(i) shall be made unless the workmen concerned is 
informed in writing of the alleged misconduct and is given an opportunity to 
explain the allegations made against him. A departmental enquiry shall be 
instituted before dealing with the charges. During the period of enquiry, the 
workman concerned may be suspended. The workman may take the assistance of a 
co-worker to help him in the enquiry, if he so desires. The records of the 
departmental enquiry shall be kept in writing. The approval of the owner, agent 
or the chief mining engineer of the employer or a person holding similar 
position shall be obtained before imposing the punishment of dismissal. A copy 
of the enquiry proceedings shall be given to the workman concerned on the 
conclusion of the enquiry, on request by the workman.
 


(iii) If a workman is not 
found guilty of the charges framed against him, he shall be deemed to be on duty 
during the full period of his suspension and he shall be entitled to receive the 
same wages as he would have received if he had not been suspended.
 


(iv) In awarding punishment 
under this standing order, the authority awarding punishment shall take into 
account the gravity of the misconduct, the previous record, if any, of the 
workman and any other extenuating or aggravating circumstances that may exist. A 
copy of the order passed by the authority awarding punishment shall be supplied 
to the workman concerned.
 


18. Time limit for 
making complaints, appeals, etc.—All 
complaints arising out of employment including those relating to unfair 
treatment or wrongful exaction on the part of the employer or his servant shall 
be submitted within 7 days of such cause of complaint to the manager, of the 
mine, with the right of appeal to the employer. Any appeal to the employer shall 
be made within 3 days of the decision of the manager. The employer shall 
normally give his decision within 3 days of the receipt of the appeal.
 


19. Liability of manager 
of the mine.—The 
manager of the mine shall personally be held responsible for the proper 
enforcement of these standing orders provided that where a manager is over-ruled 
by his superior, the latter shall be held responsible for the decision taken.
 


20. Service certificate.—Every 
workman who was employed continuously for a period of more than three months 
shall be entitled to a service certificate at the time of his leaving the 
service of employer.
 


21. Entry and exit.—All 
workmen shall enter and leave the premises of the establishment through 
authorised gates and shall be liable for search while going in or coming out of 
the premises. In case of women workmen search will only be made by women.
 


22. Exhibition and 
supply of Standing Orders.—A 
copy of these orders in English and in the regional languages of the local area 
in which the mine is situated shall be posted at the manager’s office and in 
such other places of the mine as the employer may decide and it shall be kept in 
a legible condition. A copy of the standing orders shall be supplied to a 
workman on application, on payment of a reasonable price. A trade union in the 
establishment will, however, be entitled to the free supply of a copy of the 
Standing Orders, provided the union is one which is recognised by the employer.]
 


 
 


—————
 


   1. Ins. by G.S.R. 732, 
dated 12th May, 1971.
 


   2.  Ins. by G.S.R. 
936(E), dated 10th December, 2003 (w.e.f. 10-12-2003).
 


   3. Rule 11 omitted by 
G.S.R. 910, dated 10th August, 1984.
 


   4.  Subs. by G.S.R. 
936(E), dated 10th December, 2003 (w.e.f. 10-12-2003).
 


   5. Rule 16 omitted by 
G.S.R. 910, dated 10th August, 1984.
 


   6. Subs. by G.S.R. 910, 
dated 10th August, 1984.
 


   7.  Ins. by G.S.R. 386, 
dated 5th November, 1999 (w.e.f. 20-11-1999).
 


   8.  Ins. by G.S.R. 
25(E), dated 19th January, 2006 (w.e.f. 19-1-2006).
 


 
</form><form>
 




The Industrial Employment (Standing Orders) Central Rules, 1946
 


 
 



1[SCHEDULE 
IB
 




Model Standing Orders on additional items 
 




applicable to all industries
 


(1) Service record
 


Matters relating to service 
card, token tickets, certification of service, change of residential address of 
workers and record of age:
 


(i) Service card.—Every 
industrial establishment shall maintain a service card in respect of each 
workman in the form appended to these orders, wherein particulars of that 
workman shall be recorded with the knowledge of that workman and duly attested 
by an officer authorised in this behalf together with date.
 


(ii) Certification of 
service.—(a) Every workman shall be entitled to a service certificate, 
specifying the nature of work (designation) and the period of employment 
(indicating the days, months, years) at the time of discharge, termination, 
retirement or resignation from service.
 


(b) The existing entries in 
para 16 of Schedule I and para 20 of Schedule I-A shall be omitted.
 


(iii) Residential 
address of workman.—A workman shall notify the employer immediately on 
engagement the details of his residential address and thereafter promptly 
communicate to his employer any change of his residential address. In case, the 
workman has not communicated to his employer the change in his residential 
address, his last known address shall be treated by the employer as his 
residential address for sending any communication.
 


(iv) Record of age.—(a) 
Every workman shall indicate his exact date of birth to the employer or the 
officer authorised by him in this behalf, at the time of entering service of the 
establishment. The employer or the officer authorised by him in this behalf may 
before the date of birth of a workman is entered in his service card, require 
him to supply:
 


         (i) his 
matriculation or school leaving certificate granted by the Board of Secondary 
Education or similar educational authority; 
 


        (ii) a certified 
copy of his date of birth as recorded in the registers of a municipality, local 
authority or Panchayat or Registrar of Births;
 


        (iii) in the 
absence of either of the aforesaid two categories of certificates, the employer 
or the officer authorised by him in this behalf may require the workman to 
supply, a certificate from a Government Medical Officer not below the rank of an 
Assistant Surgeon, indicating the probable age of the workman provided the cost 
of obtaining such certificate is borne by the employer;
 


       (iv) where it is not 
practicable to obtain a certificate from a Government Medical Officer, an 
affidavit sworn, either by the workman or his parents, or by a near relative, 
who is in a position to know about the workman’s actual or approximate date of 
birth, before a First Class Magistrate or Oath Commissioner, as evidence in 
support of the date of birth given by him.
 


(b) The date of birth of a 
workman, once entered in the service card of the establishment shall be the sole 
evidence of his age in relation to all matters pertaining to his service 
including fixation of the date of his retirement from the service of the 
establishment. All formalities regarding recording of the date of birth shall be 
finalised within three months of the appointment of a workman.
 


(c) Cases where date of 
birth of any workman had already been decided on the date these rules come into 
force shall not be re-opened under these provisions.
 


Note.—Where 
the exact date of birth is not available and the year of birth is only 
established then the 1st July of the said year shall be taken as the date of 
birth.
 


(2) Confirmation
 


The employer shall in 
accordance with the terms and conditions stipulated in the letter of 
appointment, confirm the eligible workman and issue a letter of confirmation to 
him. Whenever a workman is confirmed, an entry with regard to the confirmation 
shall also be made in his service card within a period of thirty days from the 
date of such confirmation.
 


(3) Age of retirement
 


The age of retirement or 
superannuation of a workman shall be as may be agreed upon between the employer 
and the workman under an agreement or as specified in a settlement or award 
which is binding on both the workman and the employer. Where there is no such 
agreed age, retirement or superannuation shall be on completion of 

2[58] years of age 
by the workman.
 


(4) Transfer
 


A workman may be 
transferred according to exigencies of work from one shop or department to 
another or from one station to another or from one establishment to another 
under the same employer:
 


Provided that the wages, 
grade, continuity of service and other conditions of service of the workman are 
not adversely affected by such transfer:
 


Provided further that a 
workman is transferred from one job to another, which he is capable of doing, 
and provided also that where the transfer involves moving from one State to 
another such transfer shall take place, either with the consent of the workman 
or where there is a specific provision to that effect in the letter of 
appointment, and provided also that (i) reasonable notice is given to such 
workman, and (ii) reasonable joining time is allowed in case of transfers from 
one station to another. The workman concerned shall be paid travelling allowance 
including the transport charges, and fifty per cent. thereof to meet incidental 
charges.
 


(5) Medical aid in case 
of accidents
 



3[Where a workman 
meets with an accident in the course of] or arising out of his employment, the 
employer shall, at the employer’s expense make satisfactory arrangements for 
immediate and necessary medical aid to the injured workman and shall arrange for 
his further treatment, if considered necessary by the doctor attending on him. 
Wherever the workman is entitled for treatment and benefits under the Employees’ 
State Insurance Act, 1948, or the Workmen’s Compensation Act, 1923, the employer 
shall arrange for the treatment and compensation 

3[accordingly].
 


(6) Medical examination
 


Wherever the recruitment 
rules specify medical examination of a workman on his first appointment, the 
employer shall, at the employer’s expense, make arrangements for the medical 
examination by a registered medical practitioner.
 


(7) Secrecy
 


No workman shall take any 
papers, books, drawings, photographs, instruments, apparatus, documents or any 
other property of an industrial establishment out of the work premises except 
with the written permission of his immediate superior, nor shall he in any way 
pass or cause to be passed or disclose or cause to be disclosed any information 
or matter concerning the manufacturing process, trade secrets and confidential 
documents of the establishment to any unauthorised person, company or 
corporation without the written permission of the employer.
 


(8) Exclusive service
 


A workman shall not at any 
time work against the interest of the industrial establishment in which he is 
employed and shall not take any employment in addition to his job in the 
establishment, which may adversely affect the interest of his employer.
 


 
 


—————
 


   1. Ins. by G.S.R. 30(E), 
dated 17th January, 1983.
 


   2. Subs. by G.S.R. 1040, 
dated 12th September, 1984.
 


   3.  Vide 
Corrigenda G.S.R. 739, dated 18th June, 1984.
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>