<act> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Granite Conservation and Development Rules, 1999.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force from the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Application.—These 
rules shall apply to prospecting and quarrying of granite.
 
 
</article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <subsection>
         <number>a</number>  “Act” means the Mines and 
Minerals 

2[(Development and Regulation)] Act, 
1957 (67 of 1957);
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>b</number>  “agent” when used in relation 
to a quarry, means any person whether appointed as such or not, who acts as the 
repre­sentative of the owner in respect of the management of the quarry or any 
part thereof;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>c</number>  “development” means removing 
overburden or unproductive or waste materials as preparatory to mining;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>d</number>  “drilling” means the 
penetration of alluvial material, rocks or formations by holes for obtaining 
geological information and for drawing samples therefrom;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>e</number>  “environment” and 
“environmental pollution” shall have the same meanings assigned respectively to 
these terms in the Environment (Protection) Act, 1986 (29 of 1986);
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>f</number>  “Form” means a Form set forth 
in Schedule to these rules;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>g</number>  “geologist” means a person 
appointed in writing by the prospecting licensee, owner or agent to perform the 
duties of a geologist under these rules;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>h</number>  “granite” means dolerites, 
granite geneisses, migma­tities, gabbros, anorthosites, rhyolites, syenites, 
leptynites, charnockites and any other igneous and orthometamorphic rock types 
which are—
 </subsection><subsection>
               <number>i</number>  amenable to be recovered 
as dimensional stone;
 <subsubsection>
              <number>ii</number>  capable of taking polish; 
and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>iii</number>  commercially exploitable.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
          <number>i</number> “lease” means a lease granted 
for the purpose of under­taking mining or quarryung operations for granite;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
          <number>j</number>  “manager” when used in 
relation to a mine or a quarry, means any person appointed by the owner or agent 
and includes the owner or the agent if he appoints himself to be such manager, 
under section 17 of the Mines Act, 1952 (35 of 1952);
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
         <number>k</number>  “mining engineer” means a 
person appointed in writing by the owner or agent to perform the duties of a 
mining engineer under these rules;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
          <number>l</number>  “prospect” means an area where 
existence of granite has been established.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        <number>m</number>  “prospecting licence” means a 
licence granted for the purpose of undertaking any operation for the purpose of 
explor­ing, locating or proving granite deposits;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
         <number>n</number>  “quarry” means an opencast 
working as defined in Mines Act, 1952 (35 of 1952);
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
         <number>o</number>  “recognised person” means a 
qualified person granted recognition by the competent authority under these 
rules to prepare mining plan;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
         <number>p</number>  “sheet rock” means massive 
granite bodies but does not include boulders;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
         <number>q</number>  “year” means the twelve months 
period beginning from the first day of April and ending on the thirty-first day 
of March of the following year. 
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> All other words and 
expressions used in these rules but not defined shall have the meanings 
respectively assigned to them in the Act.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Prospecting to precede 
mining operations.—No 
lease shall be granted by the State Government unless it is satisfied that there 
is evidence to show that the area for which the lease is applied for has been 
prospected earlier for granite of the exist­ence of granite therein has been 
established otherwise.
 
 
</article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Period for which 
prospecting licence may be granted or re­newed.—The 
period for which a prospecting licence may be granted shall not exceed two 
years.
 
 
</article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Period for which leases 
may be granted or renewed.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The maximum period for which a lease may be granted shall not exceed thirty 
years:
 
Provided that the minimum 
period for which any such lease may be granted shall not be less than twenty 
years.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A lease may be renewed 
for a period not exceeding twenty years.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-rule (2), if the State Government is of the opinion 
that in the interest of development of granite it is necessary to do so, it may, 
for reasons to be recorded, authorise the renewal of a lease for a further 
period or periods not exceeding twenty years in each case.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Minimum and maximum 
area for grant of a mining lease.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The minimum area that may be granted or renewed under a lease for ensuring 
mining activities to optimum depth shall not be less than one hectare;
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The maximum area that 
may be granted under a mining lease shall not exceed fifty hectares:
 
Provided that the State 
Government, if it is satisfied on the basis of proposed production level, 
geological or topographical conditions, may for the reasons to be recorded in 
writing, grant or renew a lease over an area more than the maximum area or less 
than the minimum area specified under this rule.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Scheme of prospecting.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every holder of a prospecting licence for granite shall submit to the State 
Government or any person authorised in this behalf by that Government within a 
period of sixty days from the date of execution of the prospect­ing licence, a 
scheme of prospecting indicating the manner in which he proposes to carry out 
the prospecting operation, in the area covered by the licence and the scheme 
shall incorporate the following, namely:—
 <subsection>
         <number>a</number>  particulars of the area;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>b</number>  the scale of the plan and the 
area of geological map­ping;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>c</number>  the number of pits, trenches, 
and bore holes which he proposes to put in the area and the locations thereof;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>d</number>  the particulars of the machines 
to be used;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>e</number>  the details of exploratory 
mining to be undertaken;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>f</number>  the number of samples proposed 
to be drawn and tested;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>g</number>  baseline information of 
prevailing environmental condi­tions before the beginning of the prospecting 
operations;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>h</number>  any other matter relevant for 
the preparation of a scheme of prospecting, as directed by the State Government 
or any person so authorised from time to time by a general or specific order.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The prospecting scheme 
under sub-rule (1) shall be prepared by a recognised person or a geologist or a 
mining engineer employed under clause (a) of sub-rule (1) of rule 38.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Modification of scheme 
of prospecting.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A prospecting scheme prepared and submitted under rule 8 may be modified at any 
time on geological considerations by the holder of a prospecting licence during 
continuance of the prospecting licence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any modification 
carried out under sub-rule (1) shall be intimated to the State Government or any 
person authorised in this behalf by that Government, by the holder of a 
prospecting licence within a period of fifteen days.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Prospecting operations 
to be carried out in accordance with scheme of prospecting.—Every 
holder of a prospecting licence for granite shall carry out the prospecting 
operations in accor­dance with the scheme of prospecting submitted under rule 8 
or with such modifications, if any, as intimated under rule 9 or as directed by 
the State Government or any person authorised by that Government in this behalf.
 
 
</article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Report of prospecting 
operations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every holder of a pros­pecting licence for granite shall submit to the State 
Government or any person authorised in this behalf by that Government 

1[***] an annual 
report in Form A so as to reach them by 30th April for the previous year:
 
Provided that a report in 
Form A shall be submitted within a period of three months after the completion 
of abandonment of the prospecting operations or the expiry of the prospecting 
licence, whichever is earlier.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where prospecting 
operations for granite are carried out by any authority specified in the second 
proviso to sub-section (1) of section 4 of the Act without a prospecting licence, 
such authority shall submit the annual report in Form A to the State Government 
or any person authorised by that Government 

1[***] in respect 
of each area where prospecting operations for granite have been undertak­en by 
them:
 
Provided that this 
sub-rule shall not apply in a case where field operations consist of only 
geological mapping or geo-physical or geo-chemical investigations.
 

2[(3) The State 
Government or any person authorized in this behalf by that Government shall 
forward a copy, each of the annual report in Form A received under sub-rule (1) 
or sub-rule (2), as the case may be, to the Controller General, India Bureau of 
Mines, within thirty days from the date of such receipt.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Mining plan as a 
pre-requisite to the grant of lease.—No 
lease shall be granted or renewed by the State Government unless there is a 
mining plan duly approved by the State Government or any person authorised in 
this behalf by that Government for the development of the granite deposit in the 
area concerned.
 
 
</article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Mining plan to be 
prepared by a recognised person.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No mining plan shall be approved unless it is prepared by a qualified person 
recognised in this behalf by the State Govern­ment or any person authorised by 
that Government or by a recog­nised person under rule 22B of the Mineral 
Concession Rules, 1960.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No person shall be 
granted recognition for the purposes of sub-rule (1) by the State Government or 
any person authorised by that Government unless he holds—
 <subsection>
          <number>i</number>  a degree in mining engineering 
or a post-graduate degree in geology granted by a university established or 
incorpo­rated by or under an Act of Parliament or any institution recog­nised by 
the University Grants Commission established under section 4 of the University 
Grants Commission Act, 1956 (3 of 1956) or any qualification equivalent thereto; 
and 
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>ii</number>  professional experience of 
five years of working in a supervisory capacity in the field of mining or 
mineral adminis­tration after obtaining a degree or qualification required under 
clause (i).
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Grant recognition by 
State Government.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any person possessing the qualifications and experience required under sub-rule 
(2) of rule 13 may apply for recognition to the competent authority designated 
by the State Government for this purpose.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The competent 
authority after making such enquiry as it deems fit, may grant or refuse to 
grant recognition and where recog­nition is refused, the competent authority 
shall record reasons in writing and communicate the same to the applicant.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A recognition shall be 
granted for an intial period of ten years and may be renewed for further periods 
not exceeding ten years at a time:
 
Provided that the 
competent authority may refuse to renew recognition for reasons to be recorded 
in writing after giving an opportunity of hearing to the person concerned.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Approval and 
submission of mining plan.—On 
receipt of the application for grant of mining lease for undertaking mining 
operations for granite, the State Government shall take decision to grant 
precise area for the said purpose and communicate such decision to the applicant 
and on receipt of the communication from the State Government of the precise 
area to be granted, the applicant shall submit a mining plan within a period of 
three months from the date on which such communication is received or such other 
period as may be allowed by the State Government for approval and the said 
mining plan shall incorporate—
 <section>
          <number>i</number>  the plan of the precise area 
showing the nature and extent of the granite body; spot or spots where the 
excavation is to be done in the first year and its extent; a detailed 
cross-section and detailed plan of spots of excavation based on the prospecting 
data gathered by the applicant; a tentative scheme of mining for the first five 
years of the lease;
 </section><section>
         <number>ii</number>  details of the geology and 
lithology of the precise area including granite reserves of the area;
 </section><section>
         <number>iii</number>  the extent of manual mining 
or mining by the use of machinery and mechanical devices on the precise area;
 </section><section>
        <number>iv</number>  the plan of the precise area 
showing natural water courses, limits of reserved and other forest areas and 
density of trees, if any, assessment of impact of mining activity on forest, 
land surface and environment including air and water pollution; details of 
scheme for restoration of the area by afforestation, land reclamation, use of 
pollution control devices and of such other measures as may be directed by the 
Central or the State Government from time to time;
 </section><section>
         <number>v</number>  annual programme and plan for 
excavation on the precise area from year to year for five years;
 </section><section>
        <number>vi</number>  any other matter which the 
State Government or any person so authorised may require the applicant to 
provide in the mining plan.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Mining plan as a 
pre-requisite to the commencement of mining operations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No person shall commence mining operations for granite in any area except in 
accordance with a mining plan approved under these rules.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The State Government 
or any person authorised in this behalf by that Government may require the 
holder of a lease to make such modifications in the mining plan referred to in 
sub-rule (1) or impose such conditions as it considers necessary by an order in 
writing if such modifications or imposition of condi­tions are considered 
necessary in the light of the experience of operation of mining plan or in view 
of the change in the techno­logical development.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A holder of a lease, 
desirous of seeking modifications in the approved mining plan as are considered 
expedient, in the interest of safe and scientific mining, conservation of 
granite, or for the protection of environment, shall apply to the State 
Government or any person authorised in this behalf by that Gov­ernment, setting 
forth the intended modifications and explaining the reasons for the same.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The State Government 
or any person authorised in this behalf by that Government may approve the 
modifications under sub-rule (3) or approve with such alterations as it may 
consider expedient.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Mining plan to be 
submitted by the existing lessee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where mining operations for granite have been undertak­en before the 
commencement of these rules without an approved mining plan, the holder of such 
lease shall submit a mining plan within a period of one year from the date of 
commencement of these rules, to the State Government or any person authorised in 
this behalf by that Government for its approval.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If a holder of a lease 
has not been able to submit the mining plan within the specified time for 
reasons beyond his control, he may apply for extension of time giving reasons to 
the State Government or any person authorised in this behalf by that Government.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The State Government 
or any person authorised in this behalf by that Government on receiving an 
application made under sub-rule (2) may, on being satisfied, extend the period 
for submission of the mining plan for a period which may not exceed 

1[four years].
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The State Government 
or any person authorised in this behalf by that Government may approve the 
mining plan submitted by the lessee under sub-rule (1), or may require 
modifications to be carried out in the mining plan and the lessee shall carry 
out such modifications and resubmit the modified mining plan for approval of the 
State Government or the person so authorised, as the case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The State Government 
or any person authorised in this behalf by that Government shall, within a 
period of ninety days from the date of receipt of the mining plan or the 
modified plan, convey its or his approval or disapproval to the applicant and in 
case of disapproval it or he shall also convey the reasons for disapproving the 
said mining plan or the modified mining plan.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> If no decision is 
conveyed within the period stipulated under sub-rule (5), the mining plan or the 
modified mining plan, as the case may be, shall be deemed to have been 
provisionally approved and such approval shall be subject to the final decision 
whenever communicated.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The mining plan 
submitted under sub-rule (1) shall be prepared by a recognised person.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Review of mining plan.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every mining plan duly ap­proved under these rules shall be valid for the entire 
duration of the lease.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The owner, agent, 
mining engineer or manager of every mine or quarry shall review the mining plan 
as prescribed under sub-rule (1) and submit a scheme of mining for the next five 
years of the lease to the State Government or any person author­ised in this 
behalf by that Government for approval.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The scheme of mining 
shall be submitted to the State Government or any person authorised in this 
behalf by that Gov­ernment at least one hundred twenty days before the expiry of 
the five years’ period, for which it was approved on the last occa­sion.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The State Government 
or any person authorised in this behalf by that Government shall convey its or 
his approval or refusal to the scheme of mining within ninety days of the date 
of its receipt.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If approval or refusal 
of the scheme of mining is not conveyed to the holder of the lease within the 
stipulated period, the scheme of mining shall be deemed to have been 
provisionally approved and such approval shall be subject to final decision 
whenever communicated.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The provisions of rule 
13 shall apply to the scheme of mining in the same way as they are applicable to 
the mining plan.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Every scheme of mining 
submitted under sub-rule (2) shall be prepared by a recognised person or a 
person employed under sub-rule (1) of rule 38.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Mining operations to 
be in accordance with mining plan.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every holder of a lease shall carry out mining operations for granite in 
accordance with the approved mining plan with such conditions as may have been 
prescribed under sub-rule (2) of rule 16 or with such modifications, if any, as 
permitted under sub-rule (4) of rule 16 or the mining plan or the scheme 
approved under rule 12 or 17 or 18 as the case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the mining 
operations are not carried out in accor­dance with the mining plan as referred 
to under sub-rule (1), the State Goevrnment or any person authorised in this 
behalf by that Government may order suspension of all or any of the mining 
operations and permit continuance of only such operations as may be necessary to 
restore the conditions in the quarry as envisaged under the said mining plan.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Prospecting and mining 
operations.—The 
prospecting and mining operations shall be carried out in such a manner so as to 
ensure systematic development and conservation of granite depos­its and 
protection of environment.
 
 
</article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> System of working.—
<section><number>1</number> 
System of working in granite quar­ries in sheet rock shall be performed by 
formation of benches.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Such benches in 
granites and overburden including weathered granite shall be formed separately 
and the benches in overburden or weathered granite shall be kept sufficiently in 
advance so that their working does not interfere with the working of granite.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Separate stacking of 
non-saleable granite.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The non-saleable granite rejects at quarry bottom should regularly be collected 
and transported to the surface and the quarry floor kept reasonably clear of 
debris.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Small granite blocks 
from such non-saleable granite suitable for possible use in manufacture of 
bricks as well as flooring or wall tiles by small scale industries sector shall 
not be used as road metal or stone aggregate and such material shall be 
segregated from the dumps of granite rejects and stored separately for future 
use as far as possible, whenever such dumps are worked for recovery of stone 
aggregate or used as quarry backfill.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The ground selected 
for dumping of top soil, overbur­den, waste material or non-saleable granite 
shall be away from working quarry.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Before starting mining 
or quarrying operations, concep­tual ultimate limits of the quarry shall be 
determined and dump­ing ground shall be so selected that dumping is not carried 
out within the limits of the ultimate size of the quarry except where 
simultaneous back filling is proposed.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Notice for opening of 
a mine and intimation of existence of a mine.—The 
owner, agent, mining engineer or manager of every granite quarry shall send to 
the State Government or any person authorised in this behalf by that Government


1[***] an 
intimation in Form B of the opening of a mine so as to reach them within fifteen 
days of such opening or of the existence of a mine at the time of the 
commencement of the rules within ninety days from such commence­ment, as the 
case may be.
 
 



</article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>24</number> Abandonment or 
surrender of quarries.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The owner, agent, mining engineer, or manager of every granite quarry shall not 
abandon or surrender a granite quarry or a part of such quarry during the 
subsistence of the lease except with prior permission in writing of the State 
Government or any person authorised in this behalf by that Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notice for abandonment 
or surrender of a granite quarry or a part thereof shall be given in Form C and 
shall be accompa­nied by plans and sections on a scale of not less than 1 cm=10 
metres showing accurately the work done in such quarry upto the date of 
submission of the notice.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The State Government 
or any person authorised in this behalf by that Government may by an order in 
writing prohibit abandonment or refuse surrender or allow the abandonment or 
surrender of a granite quarry or part thereof with such condi­tions as he may 
specify in the order.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where an abandonment 
of a granite quarry or part there­of takes place as a result of the occurrence 
of a natural calamity beyond the control of the owner, agent, mining engineer or 
mana­ger of a such quarry, or the lease is terminated in compliance of any order 
or directions issued by any stautory authority estab­lished under any law for 
the time being in force or any tribunal or a court, an intimation shall be sent 
to the State Government or any person authorised in this behalf by that 
Government within a period of twenty-four hours of such abandonment or 
termination and the notice of abandonment as provided in sub-rule (2) shall be 
submitted to the State Government or any person in this behalf by that 
Government authorised within a period of fifteen days of such abandonment or 
termination.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Notice of temporary 
discontinuance of work in quarries.—The 
owner, agent, mining engineer, or manager of every granite quarry shall send to 
the State Government or any person author­ised in this behalf by that Government


1[***], a notice in 
Form D when the work in such quarry is discontinued for a period exceeding sixty 
days of as to reach them within seventy-five days from the date of such 
temporary discontinuance.
 
 



</article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Intimation of 
reopening of a quarry.—The 
owner, agent, mining engineer or manager of every granite quarry shall send to 
the State Government or any person authorised in this behalf by that Government


1[***] an 
intimation in Form E of reopening of such quarry after temporary discontinuance 
so as to reach them within fifteen days from the date of such reopening.
 
 




</article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Copies of plans and 
sections to be submitted.—The 
owner, agent, mining engineer or manager of every granite quarry shall submit to 
the State Government or any person authorised in this behalf by that Government, 
a copy of the plans and sections maintained under these rules, as and when 
required by that Gov­ernment or such person, as the case may be.
 
 
</article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Preparation of plans.—
<section><number>1</number> 
All plans, sections and trac­ings or copies thereof kept at the granite quarry 
shall be seri­ally numbered or suitably indexed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every plan, section or 
part thereof prepared under these rules shall carry thereon a certificate for 
its correctness and shall be signed by the mining engineer with date.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every copy of a plan 
and section or part thereof sub­mitted or maintained under these rules shall 
bear a reference to the original plan or section from which it was copied and 
shall be certified thereon by the owner, agent, mining engineer or manager to be 
a true copy of the original plan or section.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>29</number> Protection of 
environment.—Every 
holder of a prospecting licence or a lease shall take all possible precautions 
for the protection of environment and control of pollution while conduct­ing 
prospecting, mining or processing of granite in the area for which such licence 
or lease is granted.
 
 
</article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>30</number> Removal and 
utilisation of top soil.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where top soil exist and is to be excavated for prospecting or mining operations 
for granite, it should be removed separately.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The top soil so 
removed shall be utilised for restora­tion and rehabilitation of the land which 
is no longer required for prospecting or mining operations or for stabilising or 
land­scaping the external dumps.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where top soil cannot 
be used concurrently, it shall be stored separately for future use.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>31</number> Storage of overburden, 
waste rock, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The overburden, waste rock and non-saleable granite generated during prospecting 
or mining operations for granite shall be stored separately in properly formed 
dumps on grounds earmarked.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Such dumps shall be 
properly secured to prevent the escape of material in harmful quantities which 
may cause degrada­tion of the surrounding land or silting of water courses.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Wherever possible, 
such waste rock or overburden or other rejects, shall be backfilled into the 
worked out granite quarry, where granite has been recovered upto the optimum 
depth, with a view to restore land to its original use or desired alter­nate 
use, as far as possible and where the backfilling is not feasible, the waste 
dumps shall be suitable terraced and sta­bilised by planting vegetation or 
otherwise.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>32</number> Reclamation and 
Rehabilitation of lands.—Every 
lease holder shall undertake in a phased manner restoration, reclamation and 
rehabilitation of lands affected by prospecting or mining operations and shall 
complete this work before the conclusion of such operations and the abandonment 
of the granite quarry.
 
 
</article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>33</number> Precaution against air 
pollution.—Air 
pollution due to dust, exhaust emissions or fumes during prospecting, mining or 
processing operations for granite and related activities shall be controlled and 
kept within permissible limits specified under any environmental laws for the 
time being in force.
 
 
</article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>34</number> Discharge of 
effluents.—Every 
holder of a prospecting licence or a lease shall take all possible precautions 
to prevent or reduce to a minimum the discharge of toxic and objectionable 
liquid effluents from granite quarry, workshop or processing plant, into surface 
or ground water bodies, and usable lands. These effluents shall conform to the 
standards laid down in this re­gard.
 
 
</article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>35</number> Precaution against 
noise.—Noise 
arising out of prospect­ing, mining and processing operations for granite shall 
be abated or controlled by the holder of prospecting licence or a lease at the 
source so as to keep it within the permissible limit.
 
 
</article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>36</number> Permissible limits and 
standard.—The 
standards and permis­sible limits of all pollutants, toxins and noise referred 
to in rules 33, 34 and 35 shall be those notified by the concerned authorities 
under the provisions of the relevant statutes from time to time.
 
 
</article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>37</number> Restoration of flora.—Every 
lease holder shall take immediate measures for planting in the area held under 
the lease or any other area selected by the State Government for this purpose, 
such number of trees sufficient to improve the environ­ment and to minimise 
effects of land degradation during the entire period of such lease. He shall 
look after such tree plan­tations during the subsistence of the lease.
 
 
</article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>38</number> Employment of mining 
engineer.—
<section><number>1</number> 
For the purpose of carrying out prospecting and mining operations in accordance 
with these rules, every holder of a granite quarry lease shall employ,—
 <subsection>
         <number>a</number>  in the case of a mechanised 
granite quarry, a whole time mining engineer qualifications, possessing the 
following namely:—
 <subsubsection>
               <number>i</number>  Degree in mining 
engineering with minimum one year’s experience of working in mines including 
granite quarries, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
              <number>ii</number>  Post Graduate degree in 
geology with First Class Metalliferous Mines Manager’s Certificate or Post 
Graduate Degree in geology with minimum three years’ experience of working in 
supervisory capacity in mines including granite quarries, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>iii</number>  Diploma in Mining with 
First Class Metalliferous Mines Manager’s Certificate or Diploma in Mining with 
three year’s experience in supervisory capacity in mines including granite 
quarries, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>iv</number>  First Class Metalliferous 
Mines Manager’s Certifi­cate with minimum two years’ experience of working in 
mines including granite quarries after obtaining the certificate.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
         <number>b</number> in the case of a granite quarry 
lease other than the mechanised granite quarry lease,—
 <subsubsection>
               <number>i</number>  a part time mining 
engineer possessing qualification as prescribed under clause (a) above; or

 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
              <number>ii</number>  a part time mining 
engineer, possessing a post graduate degree in geology or Second Class 
Metalliferous Mines Manager’s Certificate, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>iii</number> a whole time mining 
engineer possessing Secondary School Leaving Certificate and mine Foreman 
Certificate with minimum five years’ experience of working as Mines Foreman or 
Mate in mines including granite quarries.
 
Explanation.—For 
the purpose of this sub-rule, mechanised granite quarry means a granite quarry 
where machine capable of deep drilling is deployed or heavy machinery for 
excavation, handling or lifting or transporting of overburden and granite blocks 
is deployed.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A part time mining 
engineer possessing qualifications prescribed in sub-clause (i) of clause (a) of 
sub-rule (1) may be employed to supervise upto a maximum of six granite quarries 
provided that all such granite quarries are located within a radius of fifty 
Kilometers:
 
Provided that a person 
possessing the qualifications other than those prescribed in sub-clause (i) of 
clause (a) of sub-rule (1) may be employed as part time mining engineer in 
quarries upto a maximum of three granite quarries provided that such quarries 
are located within a radius of fifty kilometers.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>39</number> Duties of mining 
engineer.—
<section><number>1</number> 
It shall be the duty of the mining engineer to take all necessary steps to plan 
and conduct mining operations, so as to ensure conservation of gra­nite, 
systematic development of the granite deposits and protec­tion of environment in 
and around the granite quarry lease area in accordance with these rules.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> He shall be 
responsible for the preparation and main­tenance of plans, sections, reports and 
schemes in accordance with these rules.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> He shall carry out all 
such orders and directions as may be given in writing under these rules by the 
State Government or any person authorised in this behalf by that Government and 
shall forward a copy of each of such orders or directions to the holder of 
prospecting licence or, as the case may be, the granite quarry lease.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>40</number> Supply of materials, 
appliances and facilities.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The mining engineer shall ensure that there is suffi­cient provision of proper 
materials, appliances and facilities at all times at granite quarry for the 
purpose of carrying out the provisions of these rules and orders issued 
thereunder and where he is not the owner or agent of the granite quarry, he 
shall make requisition in writing to the owner or agent for anything re­quired 
for the aforesaid purpose. A copy of every such requisi­tion shall be recorded 
in bound paged book kept of the purpose.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On receipt of a 
requisition under sub-rule (1), the owner or agent shall provide as soon as 
possible the materials and facilities requisitioned by the mining engineer.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>41</number> Half 
yearly and annual returns.—
<section><number>1</number> The owner, agent, mining engineer or manager 
of every granite quarry shall submit to the State Government or any person 
authorized in this behalf by that Government returns in respect of such granite 
quarry within the time specified in respect of such returns, namely:—
 <subsection>
         <number>a</number>  a half yearly return in Form F 
for every half year ending 30th September and 31st March before the 15th of the 
following month for the preceding half yearly period;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>b</number>  an annual return in Form G 
which shall be submitted before the 1st July of each year for the preceding 
year:
 
Provided that in case of 
abandonment or surrender of a granite quarry, such annual return shall be 
submitted within ninety days of the date of abandonment or surrender.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The State Government 
or any person authorized in this behalf by that Government shall forward a copy, 
each of the half yearly return in Form F and annual return in Form G received 
under clauses (a) and (b) of sub-rule (1), to the Controller General, Indian 
Bureau of Mines, within thirty days from the date of such receipt.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>42</number> Notice of certain 
appointments.—When 
any new appointment is made of an agent, mining engineer, geologist and manager 
for the purpose of these rules or when the employment of any such person is 
terminated or any such person leaves the said employ­ment or when any change 
occurs in the address of any such person, the owner of the granite quarry or the 
holder of the prospecting licence, relating to such appointment, termination, 
living or change in address shall, within fifteen days from the date of such 
appointment, termination, leaving or change in address, give a notice in Form H 
to the State Government or any person author­ised in this behalf by that 
Government.
 
 
</article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>43</number> Records of boreholes.—The 
owner, agent, mining engineer, geologist or manager of every granite quarry or 
the holder of a prospecting licence shall keep a record of all boreholes in Form 
I and shall retain all records and samples of the strata passed through. He 
shall not destroy such records of boreholes and samples of strata except with 
the prior approval of the State Government or any person so authorised on this 
behalf.
 
 
</article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>44</number> Transfer of records of 
transferees.—When 
the ownership of a prospecting licence or a granite quarry lease is transferred, 
the previous owner or his agent shall make over to the new owner or his agent 
within a period of seven days of the transfer of the ownership, borehole cores 
preserved if any, all plans, sections, reports, registers and other records 
maintained in pursuance of the Act, rules or orders made thereunder, and all 
correspondence relevant thereto relating to the prospecting licence or granite 
quarry lease; and when the requirements of these rules have been duly complied 
with, both previous and the new owners of their respec­tive agents shall 
forthwith send to the State Government or any person authorised in this behalf 
by that Government a detailed list of borehole cores, plans, sections, reports, 
registers and other records that have been transferred.
 
 
</article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>45</number> Copies of notices and 
returns to be maintained.—The 
owner, agent, mining engineer or manager of every granite quarry or a holder of 
a prospecting licence shall maintain the labour atten­dance register, production 
and despatch register, explosives consumption register, test reports and details 
of mining machin­ery and copies of all notices and returns, plans, sections and 
schemes submitted to the State Government or any person author­ised in this 
behalf by that Government under these rules, at an office established by the 
license or lessee and these shall be made available at an reasonable times to 
the State Government or any person authorised in this behalf by that Government 
for inspection.
 
 
</article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>46</number> Revision.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any person aggrieved by any order made or direction issued by any person 
authorised by the State Govern­ment to make or issue such order or direction 
under these rules may within ninety days of the communication of such order 
apply to the State Government for revision of the said order:—
 
Provided that any such 
application may be entertained after the said period of ninety days if the 
applicant satisfies the State Government that he had sufficient cause for not 
making the application within time.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every order, against 
which a revision application is preferred under sub-rule (1), shall be complied 
with pending the decision of the State Government in such revision:
 
Provided that the State 
Government may on an application by the applicant, suspend the operation of the 
order appealed against pending disposal of the revision application.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On receipt of an 
application for revision under sub-rule (1), the State Government after giving a 
reasonable oppor­tunity of being heard to the aggrieved person, may confirm, 
modify or set aside the order or direction.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every application 
submitted under the provisions of this rule shall be accompanied by a Treasury 
Receipt showing that a fee of five hundred rupees has been paid into a State 
Govern­ment Treasury or any branch of the State Bank of India doing Treasury 
Business to the credit of the State Government.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>47</number> Penalty.—Whoever 
contravenes any of the provisions of these rules shall be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or with fine which may 
extend to five thou­sand rupees or with both and in the case of continuing 
contraven­tion with an additional fine which may extend to five hundred rupees 
for every day during which such contravention continues after conviction for the 
first such contravention.
 
 
</article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>48</number> Facilities for 
undertaking research or training.—Every 
holder of a prospecting licence or a lease shall afford all reasonable 
facilities to persons authorised by the Central Gov­ernment or the State 
Government for the purpose of undertaking research or training in matters 
relating to mining or geology.
 
 
</article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>49</number> Territorial 
jurisdiction.—The 
territorial jurisdiction of a person authorised by the Central Government or the 
State Government for the purpose of these rules shall be as notified by the 
Central Government or the State Government, as the case may be, in the Official 
Gazette from time to time.
 
 
</article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>50</number> Obligation to supply 
other information.—The 
owner, agent, mining engineer, geologist or manager of every granite quarry 
shall furnish such information regarding such quarry or any matter connected 
therewith as the Central Government or the State Government or any person 
authorised in this behalf by the Central Government or the State Government, as 
the case may be, may require by an order in writing and the information shall be 
furnished within such time as may be specified in the aforesaid order.
 
 
</article> 
 The Granite Conservation and 
Development Rules, 1999
  
 <article><number>51</number> Provisions of these rules to 
be applicable to Government.—The Government or its agencies 
carrying out mining opera­tions without a lease shall be bound by all the 
provisions of these rules in the same manner as they are applicable to holders 
of granite quarry leases.
  </article> 
 The Granite Conservation and 
Development Rules, 1999
  
 <article><number>52</number> Applicability of the 
provisions of Minor Mineral Concession Rules framed by the State 
Government.—The 
provisions of the Minor Mineral Concession Rules or any other rules framed by 
the State Government under section 15 of the Act shall be applicable to granite 
quarry leases to the extent they are not repugnant to or inconsistent with these 
rules.
  </article> 
 
The Granite Conservation and 
Development 
Rules, 1999
 
 
 <article>
<number>53</number> Delegation of powers.—The 
State Government may, by noti­fication in the Official Gazette, direct that any 
power exercisa­ble by it under these rules may, in relation to such matters and 
subject to such conditions, if any, be exercisable also by such officer or 
authority subordinate to the State Government as may be specified in the 
notification.
 
 
  
</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>