<act><title>THE PREVENTION OF MONEY-LAUNDERING (FORMS, SEARCH 
AND SEIZURE AND THE MANNER OF FORWARDING THE REASONS AND MATERIAL TO THE 
ADJUDICATING AUTHORITY, IMPOUNDING AND CUSTODY OF RECORDS AND THE PERIOD OF 
RETENTION) RULES, 20051 </title> 
 the PREVENTION OF MONEY-LAUNDERING (FORMS, 
SEARCH AND SEIZURE AND THE MANNER OF FORWARDING THE REASONS AND MATERIAL TO THE 
ADJUDICATING AUTHORITY, IMPOUNDING AND CUSTODY OF RECORDS AND THE PERIOD OF 
RETENTION) RULES, 20051
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be called 
the Prevention of Money-laundering (Forms, Search and Seizure and the Manner of 
Forwarding the Reasons and Material to the Adjudicating Authority, Impounding 
and Custody of Records and the Period of Retention) Rules, 2005.
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force 
on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
  


</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, unless the context 
otherwise requires,— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> “Act” means the Prevention of Money-laundering Act, 2002 (15 of 2003); 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> “Adjudicating Authority” means an Adjudicating Authority appointed 
  under sub-section (1) of section 6 of the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> “authority” for the purposes of sub-section (2) of section 17 of the 
  Act means an officer subordinate to the Director and authorised by the 
  Director under sub-section (1) of section 17 of the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> “authority” for the purposes of sub-section (1) of section 18 of the 
  Act means an authority from among the classes of authorities specified in 
  section 48 of the Act, authorized by the Central Government by general or 
  special order; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> “designated officer” means the officer designated by the Adjudicating 
  Authority for the purpose of sub-rule (1) of rule 10; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> “Director” for the purpose of sub-section (1) of section 17 of the Act 
  means the Director appointed under sub-section (1) of section 49 of the Act; 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> “Director” or “Additional Director” or “Joint Director” or “Deputy 
  Director” or “Assistant Director” for the purpose of sub-section (5) of 
  section 50 of the Act, means a Director or Additional Director or Joint 
  Director or Deputy Director or Assistant Director appointed by the Central 
  Government under sub-section (1) of section 49 of the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> “Form” means forms appended to these rules; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> “impounding authority” for the purpose of sub-section (5) of 
   section 50 of the Act, means the Director or Additional Director or Joint 
  Director or Deputy Director or Assistant Director appointed by the Central 
  Government under sub-section (1) of section 49 of the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>j</number> “material for the purpose of sub-section (2) of section 17 
  of the Act” means the material in possession of the authority, referred to in 
  clause (c) of sub-rule (1) of rule 2, after search and seizure under 
  sub-section (1) of section 17 of the Act, including a report forwarded to a 
  Magistrate under section 157 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 
  1974) or a complaint filed before a Magistrate or a court by a person 
  authorized to investigate the scheduled offence for taking cognizance of such 
  scheduled offence;] 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>k</number> “material for the purposes of sub-section (2) of section 
  18 of the Act” means the material in possession of the authority referred to 
  in  clause (d) of sub-rule (1) of rule 2, after search and seizure under 
  sub-section (1) of section 18 of the Act including a report forwarded to a 
  Magistrate under section 173 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 
  1974) or a complaint filed before a Magistrate or a court by a person 
  authorized to investigate the scheduled offence for taking cognizance of such 
  scheduled offence;] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number> “place” means a place, where an act which constitutes the commission of 
  the offence of money-laundering is carried on and includes any other place, 
  whether any activity is carried on therein or not, in which the person 
  carrying on such activity states that any of his records or any part of his 
  property relating to such act are or is kept; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>m</number> “records” include the records maintained in the form of books or stored 
  in a computer or tapes or discs or in any other electronic form or transcribed 
  information of any type whether expressed in ordinary or machine language and 
  such other documents as may be useful for the purposes of these rules; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>n</number> “Schedule” means the Schedule to the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>o</number> “section” means a section of the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>p</number> “Summoning Officer” means an officer who has the power to summon any 
  person under sub-section (2) of section 50 of the Act. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> All other words and expressions used and not defined in these rules but 
defined in the Act shall have the meaning respectively assigned to them in the 
Act. 









</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Procedure relating to search. </title>— <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number> The Director or any other officer authorised by him may, for the purposes of the sub-section (1) of section 17 of the Act, further authorize any officer subordinate to him and such authorization shall be in the Form 1.] 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The authority referred to in clause (c) of sub-rule (1) of rule 2, shall be empowered to— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> enter and search any building, place, vessel, vehicle or aircraft where he has reason to suspect that such records or proceeds of crime are kept; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> break open the lock of any door, box, locker, safe, almirah or other receptacle for exercising the powers conferred by clause (a) where the keys thereof are not available; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> seize any record or property found as a result of such search; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> place marks of identification on such record or make or cause to be made extracts or copies therefrom; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> make a note or an inventory of such record or property; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> examine on oath any person, who is found to be in possession or control of any record or property, in respect of all matters relevant for the purposes of any investigation under this Act: 
</subsection>
 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[Provided that no search under sub-section (1) of section 17 of the Act shall be conducted unless a report has been forwarded to a Magistrate under  
  section 157 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) or a complaint has been filed before a Magistrate or a court by a person authorized to investigate the scheduled offence for taking cognizance of such scheduled offence;] 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Before making a search, the authority, shall— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> where a building or place is to be searched, call upon two or more respectable persons of that locality in which the building or place to be searched is situated; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> where a vessel, vehicle or aircraft is to be searched, call upon any two or more respectable persons, to attend and witness the search and may issue an order in writing to them or any of them so to do. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>4</number> Any person in charge of, or, in any building, place, vessel, vehicle or aircraft shall, on production of the authorisation, allow the authority free ingress thereto and afford all reasonable facilities for search therein. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> If ingress into such building or place cannot be obtained, it shall be lawful for the authority executing the authorisation, with such assistance of police officers or of such other officers as specified in section 54 of the Act, as may be required, to enter such building or place and search therein and in order to effect an entrance into such building or place, to break open any lock of any door or window of any building or place, whether that of the person to be searched or of any other person, if after production of authorisation and demand of admittance duly made, he cannot otherwise obtain admittance: 
 Provided that, if any such building or place is an apartment in actual occupancy of a woman, who according to custom does not appear in public, the authority shall before entering such apartment, give notice to such woman that she is at liberty to withdraw and shall afford her every reasonable facility for withdrawing and may then break open the apartment and enter it. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> If ingress into any vessel, vehicle or aircraft authorized to be searched cannot be obtained because such vessel, vehicle or aircraft is moving or for any other reason, it shall be lawful for the authority executing the authorisation, with such assistance as may be required of police officers and such officers, as specified in section 54 of the Act, to stop any such vessel or vehicle or in the case of an aircraft, compel it to stop or land, and search any part of the vessel, vehicle or aircraft, and in order to effect an entrance into such vessel, vehicle or aircraft to break open any door or window of any such vessel, vehicle or aircraft, whether that of the person to be searched or of any other person, if after production of the authorisation and demand of admittance duly made, he cannot otherwise obtain admittance: 
 Provided that if any such vessel, vehicle or aircraft is occupied by a woman, who according to custom does not appear in public, the authority shall, before entering such vessel, vehicle or aircraft, give notice to such woman that she is at liberty to withdraw and shall afford her every reasonable facility for withdrawing and may then break open the door of any vessel, vehicle or aircraft and enter it. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> The authority may require any person who, is the owner, or has the immediate possession, or control, of any box, locker, safe, almirah or any other receptacle situated in such building, place, vessel, vehicle or aircraft, to open the same and allow access to inspect or examine its contents, and, where the keys thereof are not available or where such person fails to comply with any such requirement, may break open the lock of such box, locker, safe, almirah or other receptacle which the authority may deem necessary for carrying out all or any of the purposes specified by the Director in this behalf. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> The occupant of the building, place, vessel, vehicle or aircraft searched, including the person in charge of such vessel, vehicle or aircraft, or some person on his behalf, shall be permitted to attend during the search. 






 
 <subsection><number>a</number> in relation to an offence under paragraph 1 of Part A and Part B of the Schedule, a report under section 173 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) has been forwarded to a Magistrate; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> in relation to an offence under paragraph 2 of Part A of the Schedule, a police report or a complaint has been filed for taking cognizance of an offence by the Special Court constituted under sub-section (1) of section 36 of the Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances Act, 1985 (61 of 1985);”. 
</subsection>
</section></article> 
 the PREVENTION OF MONEY-LAUNDERING (FORMS, 
SEARCH AND SEIZURE AND THE MANNER OF FORWARDING THE REASONS AND MATERIAL TO THE 
ADJUDICATING AUTHORITY, IMPOUNDING AND CUSTODY OF RECORDS AND THE PERIOD OF 
RETENTION) RULES, 2005
  
 <article><number>4</number> Procedure relating to 
seizure.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The authority may seize any record or property found as a result of search of 
any building, place, vessel, vehicle or aircraft:
 Provided that where it is not 
practicable to seize any record or property, the authority may serve an order on 
the owner or the person who is in immediate possession or control of any such 
record or property that he shall not remove, part with or otherwise deal with it 
except with the previous permission of the authority, who may take such steps as 
may be necessary for ensuring such compliance.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The authority shall prepare 
a seizure memo (inventory of items) in Form II appended to these rules which 
shall be delivered to the occupant of the building, place, vessel, vehicle or 
aircraft searched, including the person in charge of such vessel, vehicle or 
aircraft, or some person on his behalf and the authority shall also forward a 
copy of the inventory so prepared to the Director and the Adjudicating 
Authority.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The authority shall place or 
cause to be placed the records of properties including bullion, jewellery and 
other valuable articles and things seized during the search in a package which 
shall contain the details of the bullion, jewellery and other valuable article 
and things placed therein, such packages shall bear an identification mark and 
the seal of the authority, and the occupant of such building, place, vehicle or 
aircraft, including the person in charge of such vessel, vehicle or aircraft 
searched or any other person on his behalf shall also be permitted to place his 
seal on packages.
 </section><section><number>4</number> A copy of the list prepared 
in accordance with sub-rule (3) shall be delivered to the occupant of the 
building, place, vehicle or aircraft, including the person in charge of such 
vessel, vehicle or aircraft searched or any other person on his behalf and the 
authority shall also forward a copy thereof to the Director and the Adjudicating 
Authority.
  </section></article> 
 the PREVENTION OF MONEY-LAUNDERING (FORMS, 
SEARCH AND SEIZURE AND THE MANNER OF FORWARDING THE REASONS AND MATERIAL TO THE 
ADJUDICATING AUTHORITY, IMPOUNDING AND CUSTODY OF RECORDS AND THE PERIOD OF 
RETENTION) RULES, 2005
  
 <article><number>5</number> Applicability of the 
provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973.—The provisions of the Code of 
Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) shall apply, in so far as they are not 
inconsistent with the provisions of the Act relating to search and 
seizure.
  </article> 
 the PREVENTION OF MONEY-LAUNDERING (FORMS, 
SEARCH AND SEIZURE AND THE MANNER OF FORWARDING THE REASONS AND MATERIAL TO THE 
ADJUDICATING AUTHORITY, IMPOUNDING AND CUSTODY OF RECORDS AND THE PERIOD OF 
RETENTION) RULES, 2005
  
 <article><number>6</number> Impounding of 
records.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The impounding authority may impound any records produced before him in any 
proceedings under the Act:
 Provided that where the 
impounding authority is a Deputy Director or an Assistant Director, he shall not 
impound any records without recording his reasons in writing, and shall 
immediately forward such reasons to the Director.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If the impounding authority 
requires assistance of police or officers of the Central Government, or both, it 
shall be lawful for him to seek such assistance as necessary under section 54 of 
the Act while impounding any records under sub-section (5) of section 50 of the 
Act.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The impounding authority, 
other than the Director, shall prepare an inventory of impounded records in 
triplicate. Where the impounding authority is the Director, he shall prepare 
such inventory in duplicate.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Each page of an inventory of 
records shall be signed by the impounding authority and the person from whom 
records have been impounded. In case where the person from whom records have 
been impounded refuses to sign, the impounding authority shall record such 
refusal therein.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The impounding authority 
other than the Director shall give one copy of such inventory to the person from 
whom records have been impounded and shall forward immediately one copy to the 
Director while retaining one copy with him. Where the impounding authority is 
the Director, he shall give one copy of such inventory to the person from whom 
records have been impounded and shall retain one copy with him.
 </section><section><number>6</number> The impounding authority 
other than the Director may, after obtaining the previous approval of the 
Director in writing, return any records impounded under this rule, to the person 
from whom records were impounded if such records are no longer useful and 
relevant for any proceedings under this Act.
  </section></article> 
 the PREVENTION OF MONEY-LAUNDERING (FORMS, 
SEARCH AND SEIZURE AND THE MANNER OF FORWARDING THE REASONS AND MATERIAL TO THE 
ADJUDICATING AUTHORITY, IMPOUNDING AND CUSTODY OF RECORDS AND THE PERIOD OF 
RETENTION) RULES, 2005
  
 <article><number>7</number> Custody of 
records.—Any 
records impounded by the impounding authority under sub-section (5) of section 
50 of the Act may be retained in his custody:
 Provided that where the 
impounding authority is a Deputy Director or an Assistant Director he shall not 
retain in his custody any such records for a period exceeding three months, 
without obtaining the previous approval of the Director in writing.
  </article> 
 the PREVENTION OF MONEY-LAUNDERING (FORMS, 
SEARCH AND SEIZURE AND THE MANNER OF FORWARDING THE REASONS AND MATERIAL TO THE 
ADJUDICATING AUTHORITY, IMPOUNDING AND CUSTODY OF RECORDS AND THE PERIOD OF 
RETENTION) RULES, 2005
  
 <article><number>8</number> Manner of forwarding of a 
copy of the reasons and the material relating to search and seizure under 
sub-section (2) of section 17 of the Act and search of persons under sub-section 
(2) of section 18 of the Act to the Adjudicating Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> The authority, as the case 
may be, shall prepare an index of a copy of the reasons recorded along with the 
material in his possession and sign each page of such index and shall also write 
a letter while forwarding copy of reasons and material to the Adjudicating 
Authority in a sealed envelope.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The authority, as the case 
may be, shall place an acknowledgement slip in Form III appended to these rules 
inside the envelope before sealing it.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The authority, as the case 
may be, shall indicate a reference number and date of despatch on the sealed 
envelope.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The sealed envelope shall be 
marked “Confidential” and “To be opened by the addressee only” and the complete 
address of the Adjudicating Authority including his name shall be mentioned on 
the sealed envelope with official seal.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The authority, as the case 
may be, shall place the sealed envelope inside the outer envelope, and shall 
place an acknowledgement slip in Form IV appended to these rules.
 </section><section><number>6</number> The outer envelope shall be 
sealed and marked “Confidential”. Complete address of the Adjudicating Authority 
shall be mentioned on the sealed outer envelope.
 </section><section><number>7</number> The authority, as the case 
may be, shall maintain registers and other records such as acknowledgement slip 
register, dak register for the purposes of this rule and shall ensure that 
necessary entries are made in the register immediately as soon as a copy of the 
reasons along with the material are forwarded to the Adjudicating 
Authority.
  </section></article> 
 the PREVENTION OF MONEY-LAUNDERING (FORMS, 
SEARCH AND SEIZURE AND THE MANNER OF FORWARDING THE REASONS AND MATERIAL TO THE 
ADJUDICATING AUTHORITY, IMPOUNDING AND CUSTODY OF RECORDS AND THE PERIOD OF 
RETENTION) RULES, 2005
  
 <article><number>9</number> Acknowledgement of receipt of 
a copy of the reasons and the material relating to search and seizure and search 
of person by the Adjudicating Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> On receipt of the outer 
sealed envelope along with Form IV, the Adjudicating Authority or in his 
absence, the designated officer of the office of Adjudicating Authority shall 
forward Form IV duly filled in, signed and his name legibly written below his 
signature. The seal of the office of the Adjudicating Authority shall be affixed 
before forwarding Form IV to the authority as a token of receipt of the sealed 
envelope.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Adjudicating Authority 
shall, on opening of the sealed envelope, forward Form III duly filled in, 
signed and his name legibly written below his signature. The seal of the office 
of the Adjudicating Authority shall be affixed before forwarding of Form III to 
the authority as a token of receipt of a copy of the reasons and the 
material.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Adjudicating Authority 
shall maintain registers and other records such as acknowledgement slip 
register, dak register and register showing details of receipt of a copy of the 
reasons recorded along with the material for the purposes of this rule and shall 
ensure that necessary entries are made in the register immediately on receipt of 
such copy of the reasons and the material.
  </section></article> 
 the PREVENTION OF MONEY-LAUNDERING (FORMS, 
SEARCH AND SEIZURE AND THE MANNER OF FORWARDING THE REASONS AND MATERIAL TO THE 
ADJUDICATING AUTHORITY, IMPOUNDING AND CUSTODY OF RECORDS AND THE PERIOD OF 
RETENTION) RULES, 2005
  
 <article><number>10</number> Period of retention of copy 
of the reasons and the material relating to search and seizure and search of 
persons by the Adjudicating Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> The Adjudicating Authority 
shall retain copy of the reasons and the material relating to search and seizure 
and search of persons for a period of ten years or if, before the expiry of the 
said period of ten years,—
 <subsection>        
<number>i</number>  any proceedings under section 8 of the Act have been commenced, until 
the disposal of such proceedings, or
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>ii</number>  where an appeal has been preferred to the Appellate Tribunal under 
section 26 of the Act, until the disposal of such appeal by the Appellate 
Tribunal, or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number>  
where an appeal has been filed in the High Court under section 42 of the Act, 
until the disposal of such appeal by the High Court; 
 whichever is later.
  </subsection></section></article> 
 the PREVENTION OF MONEY-LAUNDERING (FORMS, 
SEARCH AND SEIZURE AND THE MANNER OF FORWARDING THE REASONS AND MATERIAL TO THE 
ADJUDICATING AUTHORITY, IMPOUNDING AND CUSTODY OF RECORDS AND THE PERIOD OF 
RETENTION) RULES, 2005
  
 <article><number>11</number> Forms of 
records.—The 
Summoning Officer shall, while exercising powers under sub-sections (2) and (3) 
of section 50 of the Act, issue summons in Form V appended to these 
rules.
  </article> 
 the PREVENTION OF MONEY-LAUNDERING (FORMS, 
SEARCH AND SEIZURE AND THE MANNER OF FORWARDING THE REASONS AND MATERIAL TO THE 
ADJUDICATING AUTHORITY, IMPOUNDING AND CUSTODY OF RECORDS AND THE PERIOD OF 
RETENTION) RULES, 2005
  
 <article><number>12</number> 
Interpretation.—If any question arises relating 
to the interpretation of these rules, the matter shall be referred to the 
Central Government and the decision of the Central Government shall be 
final.
  </article><form>
 

the PREVENTION OF MONEY-LAUNDERING (FORMS, 
SEARCH AND SEIZURE AND THE MANNER OF FORWARDING THE REASONS AND MATERIAL TO THE 
ADJUDICATING AUTHORITY, IMPOUNDING AND CUSTODY OF RECORDS AND THE PERIOD OF 
RETENTION) RULES, 2005
 

 
 

FORM I
 

[See sub-rule (1) of rule 3]
 

AUTHORISATION FOR SEARCH AND SEIZURE UNDER 
SUB-SECTION (1) OF SECTION 17 OF THE ACT
 

Authorisation 
Number................. of...........[year]  Dated ............... 

 

Whereas I 
........................................................................., 
Director, have reason to believe 
that............................................................... [name and 
complete address of the person]
 

         
(i)  has committed an act which constitutes money-laundering, or
 

        
(ii)  is in possession of proceeds of crime involved in money-laundering, 
or 
 

        
(iii)  is in possession of records relating to money-laundering, 
and
 

certain documents including proceeds of crime 
and/or records relating to money-laundering, which in my opinion, will be useful 
for or relevant to the investigation and proceedings under the Prevention of 
Money-laundering Act, 2002 (15 of 2003) are secreted in the premises specified 
in the Schedule below.
 

I hereby authorise 
...................................................................... [Name and 
designation of the authority] to conduct the search and seizure of the premises 
specified in Schedule below, under sub-section (1) of section 17 of the 
Prevention of Money-laundering Act, 2002 (15 of 2003) and rule 3 of the 
Prevention of Money-laundering (Forms, Search and Seizure and the Manner of 
Forwarding the Reasons and Material to the Adjudicating Authority, Impounding 
and Custody of Records and the Period of Retention) Rules, 2005.
 

Given under my hand and seal this .............. 
day of ...................... two thousand 
...........................
 

 
 

            
Schedule of premises
 

 
 

                                                                                      
[Director]
 

                                                                                      
[Signature with Seal]
 

 </form><form>
 

the PREVENTION OF MONEY-LAUNDERING (FORMS, 
SEARCH AND SEIZURE AND THE MANNER OF FORWARDING THE REASONS AND MATERIAL TO THE 
ADJUDICATING AUTHORITY, IMPOUNDING AND CUSTODY OF RECORDS AND THE PERIOD OF 
RETENTION) RULES, 2005
 

 
 

FORM II
 

[See sub-rule (2) of rule 4]
 

SEIZURE MEMO (INVENTORY OF ITEMS)
 

                                                            
Dated............................
 

                                                            
From ................ [time] to................ [time]
 

Panch Witnesses:
 

1. 
........................................................ [name with complete 
address]
 

2. 
........................................................ [name with complete 
address]
 

We, the above named panchas having been called upon 
by Shri ........................................................ [name, 
designation and complete address of Officer] have presented ourselves 
at.................................................. [complete address of the 
premises]. Here we were shown an authorisation dated............... issued by 
Shri ................................................................... [name, 
designation and complete address of the Director] under section 17 of the 
Prevention of Money-laundering Act, 2002 (15 of 2003) authorising Shri 
............................................................................... 
[name, designation and complete address of the officer authorized by the 
Director] to conduct search and seizure of the above mentioned premises. We as 
well as Shri ............................................................ [name 
of the occupier of the premises] put our dated signatures on the authorisation 
in token of having seen the same. Before the actual start of search and after 
the conclusion of search by 
Shri.......................................................... [name, 
designation and complete address of the authority] and the accompanying officers 
viz. 
Sarvashri/Shri/Shrimati......................................................................................... 
offered their personal search which was declined/taken by 
Sarvashri/Shri/Shrimati.......................................................... 
[the occupier of the premises] on both the occasions in our presence. The search 
started at ....................hours on................. and concluded at 
..............hours on.....................As a result of 
search...............................................................................................................[specify 
proceeds of crime or records] were checked and verified and inventory prepared 
or recovered and seized as per details given in the Schedule below. The search 
was conducted in a peaceful and orderly manner and no damage to the person or 
property was caused during the course of search.
 

                                                                                           
[Signature]
 

                                                                                             
Authority
 

                                                                                               
[Seal] 
 

SCHEDULE
 

[Inventory of items recovered and 
seized]
 

Panch Witnesses:
 

1. ........................... [signature with 
date]
 

2. ........................... [signature with 
date]
 

......................................
 

[signature of the person searched]
 

(Authority)
 

Signature with Seal
 

          
(Received copy)
 

[signature of the person searched]
 

Note.—Each page of the seizure memo is to be signed and 
dated by the Panch Witnesses, the person searched and the Authority.
 

 </form><form>
 

the PREVENTION OF MONEY-LAUNDERING (FORMS, 
SEARCH AND SEIZURE AND THE MANNER OF FORWARDING THE REASONS AND MATERIAL TO THE 
ADJUDICATING AUTHORITY, IMPOUNDING AND CUSTODY OF RECORDS AND THE PERIOD OF 
RETENTION) RULES, 2005
 

 
 

FORM III
 

[See sub-rule (2) of rule 8]
 

ACKNOWLEDGEMENT SLIP
 

Serial Number.....................
 

Received a copy of the letter bearing 
Number...................... dated .................... along with the reasons 
and the material containing 
pages..............from................................. [designation of the 
authority] on..................[date] at............... [time].
 

 
 

Signature of the Adjudicating 
Authority
 

Date..........................
 

                                                                  
.................................................................
 

                                                                  
Name of the Adjudicating Authority
 

                                                                  
Office seal
 

To
 

....................................................
 

[Name and designation of the authority]
 

Address
 

....................................................
 

....................................................
 

....................................................
 

 </form><form>
 

the PREVENTION OF MONEY-LAUNDERING (FORMS, 
SEARCH AND SEIZURE AND THE MANNER OF FORWARDING THE REASONS AND MATERIAL TO THE 
ADJUDICATING AUTHORITY, IMPOUNDING AND CUSTODY OF RECORDS AND THE PERIOD OF 
RETENTION) RULES, 2005
 

 
 

FORM IV
 

[See sub-rule (5) of rule 8]
 

ACKNOWLEDGEMENT SLIP
 

Serial Number.....................
 

Received a sealed envelope bearing 
number.............................. Dated....................... from 
............................................................................................. 
[designation of the authority] on .................[date] at............ 
[time].
 

Signature of the Adjudicating 
Authority/designated
 

officer of the office of 
Adjudicating Authority.
 

                                               
............................................................................
 

Name of the Adjudicating 
Authority/designated 
officer of the office of Adjudicating 
Authority.
 

[Office seal)]
 

To
 

....................................................
 

[Name and designation of the authority]
 

Address
 

....................................................
 

....................................................
 

....................................................
 

 </form><form>
 

the PREVENTION OF MONEY-LAUNDERING (FORMS, 
SEARCH AND SEIZURE AND THE MANNER OF FORWARDING THE REASONS AND MATERIAL TO THE 
ADJUDICATING AUTHORITY, IMPOUNDING AND CUSTODY OF RECORDS AND THE PERIOD OF 
RETENTION) RULES, 2005
 

 
 

FORM V
 

(See rule 11)
 

FORM FOR SUMMONS
 

....................................................
 

....................................................
 

....................................................
 

[ADDRESS OF THE SUMMONING 
OFFICER]
 

No. ....................
 

Whereas I....................................................................Director 
or Additional Director or Joint Director or Deputy Director or Assistant 
Director, am making investigation under the provisions of the Prevention of 
Money-laundering Act, 2002 (15 of 2003).
 

And 
Whereas, I consider the attendance 
of........................................................[name of the person 
summoned and his address] necessary in connection with the said investigations. 

 

Now, 
Therefore, in exercise of the powers 
conferred upon me under sub-section (2) and sub-section (3) of section 50 of the 
said Act, I require the said .......................... 
.............................................................................. 
[name of the person summoned and his address] to appear before me at my office 
on ................. at .................. alongwith the documents as per 
schedule below:—
 

 
 

SCHEDULE
 

Given under my hand and seal this 
...................... day of ............................. two 
thousand......................
 

                                                                                             
Summoning Officer
 

                                                                                             
...................................
 

                                                                                             
Name and complete address
 

                                                                                             
Seal
 

To
 

....................................................
 

....................................................
 

....................................................
 

(Name of the person summoned and his 
address]
 

Note.—1. Every proceeding under sub-section (2) 
and sub-section (3) of section 50 of the Prevention of Money-laundering Act, 
2002 shall be deemed to be a judicial proceeding within the meaning of section 
193 and section 228 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).
 

2. 
Without prejudice to the provisions of any other law for the time being in 
force, if you fail to give evidence as mentioned in the schedule, you shall be 
liable to penal proceedings under the Prevention of Money-laundering Act, 2002 
(15 of 2003).
 

 </form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 19(E), dated 7th January, 2010, for clause 
(j) (w.e.f. 7-1-2010). Clause (j), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 19(E), dated 7th January, 2010, for clause 
(k) (w.e.f. 7-1-2010). Clause (k), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 19(E), dated 7th January, 2010, for sub-rule (1) (w.e.f. 7-1-2010). Sub-rule (1), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 19(E), dated 7th January, 2010, for the proviso (w.e.f. 7-1-2010). The proviso, before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>