<act><title>


    The Passports Rules, 19801</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>1</number> Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These Rules may be called the Passports Rules, 1980.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> They shall come into force from the date 
    of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
    these Rules, unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   “Act” means the Passports 
    Act, 1967 (15 of 1967); 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   “Form” means a Form set 
    out in Schedule III; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   “miscellaneous service”, 
    in relation to a passport or travel document includes— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   varying the entries in a 
    passport or travel document; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   making additional 
    endorsement on a passport or travel document in respect of foreign 
    countries; 
 

1[(iii)   
    issuing a fresh passport booklet when the pages in the booklet held are 
    almost exhausted; or] 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   any other service in 
    respect of a passport or travel document which the holder thereof may 
    require; 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>d</number>   “Schedule” means a 
    Schedule appended to these Rules; 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   “section” means a section 
    of the Act. 
 

 
  






 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Passport authorities. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> In addition to the Central Government, the officers specified in column (2) of Schedule I shall, subject in the provisions of sub-rule (2), be the passport authorities for all purposes of the Act and these Rules. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> An officer referred to in column (2) of Schedule 1 shall, for the purpose of issue of a passport or travel document, exercise jurisdiction in respect of applications for such issue made by persons ordinarily residing in the territories specified in the corresponding entries in column 3 of the said Schedule: 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[Provided that in exceptional and urgent cases the said officer may entertain an application for the issue of a passport or travel document from a person not ordinarily residing within his jurisdiction and may issue a passport or travel document to such a person for a period not exceeding twenty-four months.] 













</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Passport authorities. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> In addition to the Central Government, the officers specified in column (2) of Schedule I shall, subject in the provisions of sub-rule (2), be the passport authorities for all purposes of the Act and these Rules. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> An officer referred to in column (2) of Schedule 1 shall, for the purpose of issue of a passport or travel document, exercise jurisdiction in respect of applications for such issue made by persons ordinarily residing in the territories specified in the corresponding entries in column 3 of the said Schedule: 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[Provided that in exceptional and urgent cases the said officer may entertain an application for the issue of a passport or travel document from a person not ordinarily residing within his jurisdiction and may issue a passport or travel document to such a person for a period not exceeding twenty-four months.] 













</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>4</number> Classes of persons to whom the different 
    classes of passports and travel documents may be issued.—The 
    classes of persons to whom the classes of passports or travel documents 
    referred to respectively in sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> and sub-section (2) of section 4 
    may be issued, shall be as specified respectively in Part I or Part II, as 
    the case may be, of Schedule II.  

 
  


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Form of applications:—</title><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number>] An application for the issue of a passport or travel document or for the renewal thereof or for any miscellaneous service shall be made in the appropriate Form set out therefore in Part I of Schedule III and in accordance with the procedure and instructions set out in such form:  
 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[Provided that every application for any of the aforesaid purposes shall be made only in the form printed and supplied by—

 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the Central Government; or  
 3[(b)] Any other person whom the Central Government may by notification specify, subject to the condition that such person complies with the conditions specified by that Government in this behalf:  
 Provided further that] in the course of any inquiry under sub-section (2) of 
    section 5, a passport authority may require an applicant to furnish such additional information, documents or certificates, as may be considered necessary by such authority for the proper disposal of the application.  
</subsection>
 4[(2) The price of the new application forms referred to in sub-rule (1) shall be as specified in column 3 or 4, as the case may be, of Schedule III A for that particular category:  
 5[***]
 6[(3) The Passport Authority may authorise any person or authority to collect passport applications on its behalf for issue of a passport or travel document or for the renewal thereof or for any miscellaneous service on payment of a service charge specified by the Central Government under sub-rule (2) of rule 8 in addition to the fee payable under sub-rule (1) of rule 8 and the service charge shall be paid by the applicant to such person or authority.]













</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 


    1[***]
 

 






 



 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Named foreign country. </title>—Each of the following countries 
shall be a named foreign country for the purposes of the Explanation to 
sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 5, namely:— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> Bangladesh ; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> Sri Lanka . 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>iii</number> Saudi Arabia ] </subsection>






</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number> Fee payable on applications. </title>— <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number>] The fee payable on every application mentioned in column (2) of Schedule IV shall be at the rates specified in the corresponding entry in <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[column (3), 4 or (5), as the case may be], of that Schedule. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> The Central Government may specify service charge payable by the applicant to the person or authority for collection of passport applications under sub-rule (3) of rule 5. 













</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number> Fee payable on applications. </title>— <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number>] The fee payable on every application mentioned in column (2) of Schedule IV shall be at the rates specified in the corresponding entry in <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[column (3), 4 or (5), as the case may be], of that Schedule. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> The Central Government may specify service charge payable by the applicant to the person or authority for collection of passport applications under sub-rule (3) of rule 5. 













</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>9</number> Collection of 
    fees.—
<section><number>1</number> All fees 
    payable in respect of applications under sub-rule (1) of rule 8 be remitted 
    by demand draft drawn in favour of the passport authority or paid in cash at 
    the counter of the passport authority concerned stating in the receipt the 
    particulars in respect of which such fees have been remitted or paid.  
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> The service charge payable under 
    sub-rule (2) of rule 8 shall be paid to the person or the authority referred 
    to in sub-rule (3) of rule 5.]  
 

 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>10</number> Refund of fees.—Fees 
    shall be refunded if applied for within one year from the date of payment 
    thereof in the following cases:—  
 <section>
<number>i</number>   if after paying the fee, 
    a person does not submit the application for issue of passport or travel 
    document or for any service on a passport or travel document already held by 
    him, as the case may be;  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>   if the fee paid is in 
    excess of the prescribed fee; and  
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>   if the fee paid is for 
    a service for which no fee has been prescribed.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>11</number> Forms of passport or travel document.—A 
    passport or travel document issued under the Act shall be in the appropriate 
    form set out in Part III of Schedule III:  
 


    1[Provided that with 
    effect from the date after commencement of the Passport (2nd Amendment) 
    Rules 1992 the forms of diplomatic, official and India-Sri Lanka passports 
    shall be as specified in Form P-1A, Form P-2A and Form P-7A respectively, of 
    Part III of Schedule III.] 
 

 
  






 



</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>12</number> Duration of passports or travel documents. </title>— <footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number> An ordinary passport for persons other than children below the age of 15 years, containing thirty-six pages or sixty pages shall be in force for a period of 10 years <footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[***], from the date of its issue. 
 </section><section><number>1A</number> An ordinary passport for a child below the age of 15 years, containing thirty-six pages shall be in force for a period of 5 years from the date of its issue or until the child attains the age of 15 years, whichever is earlier.] 
 </section><section><number>2</number> An India-Bangladesh passport shall continue in force for a period of three years from the date of its issue. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> An India-Sri Lanka passport shall continue in force for a period of four years from the date of its issue. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> An emergency certificate shall continue in force for a period of <footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[three months] from the date of its issue. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[<number>5</number> A certificate of identity shall continue in force for a period of ten years from the date of its issue.] 
 </section><section><number>6</number> A diplomatic and an official passport shall continue in force for a period to be decided in each case by the Central Government or the passport authority which issues the passport: 
 Provided that the total life of a diplomatic or an official passport shall be ten years from the date of its issue. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[<number>7</number> The passport for Haj pilgrims shall be valid for a period of eight months from the date of issue.] 















</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>12</number> Duration of passports or travel documents. </title>— <footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number> An ordinary passport for persons other than children below the age of 15 years, containing thirty-six pages or sixty pages shall be in force for a period of 10 years <footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[***], from the date of its issue. 
 </section><section><number>1A</number> An ordinary passport for a child below the age of 15 years, containing thirty-six pages shall be in force for a period of 5 years from the date of its issue or until the child attains the age of 15 years, whichever is earlier.] 
 </section><section><number>2</number> An India-Bangladesh passport shall continue in force for a period of three years from the date of its issue. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> An India-Sri Lanka passport shall continue in force for a period of four years from the date of its issue. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> An emergency certificate shall continue in force for a period of <footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[three months] from the date of its issue. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>20</footcitenum>[<number>5</number> A certificate of identity shall continue in force for a period of ten years from the date of its issue.] 
 </section><section><number>6</number> A diplomatic and an official passport shall continue in force for a period to be decided in each case by the Central Government or the passport authority which issues the passport: 
 Provided that the total life of a diplomatic or an official passport shall be ten years from the date of its issue. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>21</footcitenum>[<number>7</number> The passport for Haj pilgrims shall be valid for a period of eight months from the date of issue.] 















</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>13</number> Issue of additional passport or travel 
    document in special circumstances.—A 
    person holding a passport or travel document shall not be entitled to 
    another passport or travel document unless he surrenders to the passport 
    authority the passport or travel document already held by him:  
 

Provided that separate passports or travel 
    documents may be issued to the same person in respect of different countries 
    if it is necessary so to do for facilitating his visits to such countries.  
  
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>14</number> Appellate authorities.—For 
    the purpose of the Act and these Rules, the appellate authority to whom an 
    appeal shall lie from an order specified in column 
<section><number>1</number> of the Table below 
    shall be that specified in the corresponding entry of column (2) thereof and 
    every such appeal shall be filed within thirty days from the date on which 
    the order sought to be appealed against is communicated to the appellant. 
  
 
Table
 
 
 
Orders Appealed Against
 
Appellate Authority

 
 
(1)
 
(2)

 
 
 </section><section>
<number>1</number> An order of the passport authority 
        other than the central government under.
 <subsection>
<number>i</number> clause (b) or clause (c) or 
        sub-section (2) or section 5; or  
        (ii) clause (b) of the proviso to section 7; or 
        (iii) sub-section (1) or sub-section (3) of section 10. 
 
The Chief Passport 
        Officer, Ministry of External Affairs, New Delhi

 
 
        An order under sub-section (6) of section 10 of the authority to whom 
        passport Delhi, authority is subordinate
 
        Additional Secretary or Secretary, Ministry of External Affairs, New 
        Delhi

 
 

 



  
 


 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>15</number> Fee payable in respect of appeal.—Every 
    petition for appeal shall be accompanied by a fee of twenty-five rupees 
    which shall be paid in cash at the treasury and a copy of the receipted 
    challan shall be enclosed with such petition.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>16</number> Procedure to be followed by appellate 
    authority.—On receipt of an 
    appeal, the appellate authority may call for the records of the case from 
    the authority which passed the order appealed against and after giving the 
    appellant a reasonable opportunity of representing his case, pass final 
    order.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>17</number> Authority and Form for special 
    endorsement under section 19.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The authority for the purposes of section 19 shall be the passport 
    authority.  
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> Every special endorsement referred to in 
    section 19 shall be in the following Form, namely:—  
  
 

Form
 

This passport is hereby made valid under 
    section 19 of the Passports Act, 1967 (15 of 1967), for travel through, or 
    visiting,............................................. for a maximum period 
    of........................ days/months from the date of this endorsement.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>18</number> Inspection of passport or travel 
    document.—The authorities for the 
    purposes of clause (c) of sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 12 shall be—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   any passport authority;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   any officer of Police 
    not below the rank of a Sub-Inspector; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   any officer of Customs 
    empowered by general or special order of Central Government in this behalf.  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>19</number> The conditions of a passport or travel 
    document.—The conditions subject 
    to which a passport or travel document shall be issued or renewed shall be 
    as set out in Schedule V.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>20</number> Repeal.—The 
    Passports Rules, 1967 are hereby repealed:  
 

Provided that such repeal shall not affect 
    the previous operation of the said Rules or anything duly done or suffered, 
    or any right, privilege, obligation or liability acquired, accepted or 
    incurred, thereunder.  

 
  


</article><form>
 

THE PASSPORTS RULES, 19801
 

SCHEDULE V 
 

( See  rule 19) 
 

CONDITIONS RELATING TO THE ISSUE OF PASSPORT AND 
  TRAVEL DOCUMENT 
 

1. A passport or travel document is available for travel only to the countries specified therein and must not be utilised for travel to other countries. 
 

2. A passport or travel document must not be utilised for travel to countries not recognised by the Government of India. 
 

3. A passport or travel document should not be sent out of any country by post. 
 

4. A passport or travel document should not be allowed to pass into the possession of any unauthorised person. 
 

5. The holder of a passport or travel document is personally responsible for its safe custody. It must not be wilfully lost, damaged or destroyed. In case of an unintentional loss or destruction, the fact and circumstances of such loss or destruction should be immediately reported to the nearest passport authority in India or (if the holder of the passport is abroad) to the nearest Indian Mission or Post and to the local police. 
 

6. A Passport or travel document must not be altered or mutilated in any way nor any endorsement made in it by any person other than a duly authorised official. 
 

7. If the particulars of children are included in the passport or travel document of parent or guardian, as the case may be, the children shall not travel alone. 
 

8. Children, whose names are included in the passport or travel document of their parent or legal guardian, should apply for a separate passport on attaining the age of 15 years. 
 

9. When a citizen of India abroad is to be repatriated to India at the expense of Government of India, he shall surrender his passport or travel document to the Indian Mission or Post repatriating him and obtain an Emergency Certificate for direct return to India . 
 

10. The holder of an Emergency Certificate, on arrival in India , shall surrender it to the Immigration Check Post. 
 

11. The passport or travel document should be surrendered to the passport authority if he ceases to be eligible to hold one. 
 

12. A diplomatic or official passport shall automatically cease to be valid if the person to whom it was issued ceases to exercise the functions which rendered him eligible to receive a diplomatic or official passport. In such an event, the passport shall be surrendered to the passport authority. 
 

---------
 

1. Vide  G.S.R. 691 (E), dated 11th December, 1980, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., 
Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 11th December, 1980 and as amended in recent past, vide 
 

G.S.R. 235(E), dated 28-3-2002 ,G.S.R. 417(E), dated 29-5-2002 
 

G.S.R. 718(E), dated 28-10-2004,G.S.R. 674(E), dated 27-10-2006 
 

G.S.R. 768(E), dated 23-12-2006,G.S.R. 396(E), dated 25-5-2007 
 

G.S.R. 526(E), dated 2-8-2007. ,G.S.R. 43(E), dated 22-1-2008. 
 

G.S.R. 103(E), dated 22-2-2008. ,G.S.R. 850(E), dated 11-12-2008. 
 

G.S.R. 390(E), dated 4-6-2009. ,G.S.R. 93, dated 26-6-2009. 
 

G.S.R. 372(E), dated 27-4-2010. ,G.S.R. 675(E), dated 26-6-2010. 
 

G.S.R. 633(E), dated 23-8-2011. 
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 633(E), dated 23rd August, 2011, for first and second proviso (w.e.f. 23-8-2011). The first and second proviso, before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 633(E), dated 23rd August, 2011, for first and second proviso (w.e.f. 23-8-2011). The first and second proviso, before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 100(E), dated 4th March, 1991 (w.e.f. 4-3-1991).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Clause (b) omitted and clause (c) re-numbered as clause (b) by G.S.R. 721 (E), dated 7th August, 1992, (w.e.f. 17-8-1992).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 390(E), dated 4th June, 2009 (w.e.f. 
5-6-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Rule 8 renumbered as sub-rule (1) thereof by G.S.R. 529(E), dated 8th June, 2000 
  (w.e.f. 8-6-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 633(E), dated 23rd August, 2011, for “column (3) or column (4), as the case may be” (w.e.f. 22-8-2011). Earlier it was substituted by G.S.R. 860(E), dated 1st November, 1985 (w.e.f. 1-11-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 529 (E), dated 8th June, 2000 (w.e.f. 8-6-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> Rule 8 renumbered as sub-rule (1) thereof by G.S.R. 529(E), dated 8th June, 2000 
  (w.e.f. 8-6-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 633(E), dated 23rd August, 2011, for “column (3) or column (4), as the case may be” (w.e.f. 22-8-2011). Earlier it was substituted by G.S.R. 860(E), dated 1st November, 1985 (w.e.f. 1-11-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 529 (E), dated 8th June, 2000 (w.e.f. 8-6-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 605 (E), dated 5th October, 1998 (w.e.f. 8-10-1998).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number> The words “or 20 years as the case may be “omitted by G.S.R. 633(E), dated 23rd August, 2011 (w.e.f. 23-8-2011).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 633(E), dated 23rd August, 2011, for “sixth months'” (w.e.f. 23-8-2011).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 527 (E), dated 9th July, 2001 (w.e.f. 13-7-2001).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 390(E), dated 4th June, 2009 (w.e.f. 5-6-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 605 (E), dated 5th October, 1998 (w.e.f. 8-10-1998).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number> The words “or 20 years as the case may be “omitted by G.S.R. 633(E), dated 23rd August, 2011 (w.e.f. 23-8-2011).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 633(E), dated 23rd August, 2011, for “sixth months'” (w.e.f. 23-8-2011).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 527 (E), dated 9th July, 2001 (w.e.f. 13-7-2001).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 390(E), dated 4th June, 2009 (w.e.f. 5-6-2009).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>