<act><tid>332258</tid>
<title>THE SHORE NUISANCES (BOMBAY AND KOLABA) ACT, <year>1853</year></title>

ACT NO. 11 OF <year>1853</year> 
[ 15th July, <year>1853</year>.]
An Act to facilitate the removal of nuisances and encroachments below 
high- water mark in the Islands of Bombay and Kolaba.

Preamble.-- WHEREAS there is a large sea- shore in the islands of 
Bombay and Kolaba, and it is expedient, with a view to the safe 
navigation of the harbour of Bombay, and to the public interests 
generally, to facilitate the removal of nuisances, obstructions and 
encroachments below high- water mark in the said harbour, or upon or 
about the shores of the said islands; It is enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>721629</tid>
<number>1</number>Power to give notice to remove nuisance. Mode of giving 
notice. Contents. Form.-- It shall be lawful for the Collector of Land- 
revenue at Bombay to give notice requiring the removal of any 
nuisance, obstruction or encroachment anywhere below high- water mark 
in the said harbour of Bombay, or upon or about the shores of the said 
islands; such notice shall be given by affixing the same in some 
conspicuous place on or near to the encroachment, obstruction or 
nuisance complained of, and by publication thereof in the 2 
[ Official Gazette], and shall state that, unless the nuisance, 
obstruction or encroachment be removed or abated within one month, the 
same will be removed or abated by the said Collector; such notice may 
be in the Form No. 1, in the Schedule to this Act annexed, or to the 
like effect.


</article>



<article><tid>1138576</tid>
<number>2</number>Petition by person denying right to remove nuisance. Procedure 
thereupon.-- If any person shall deny the right of the said Collector 
to effect such abatement or removal, he shall, within one month after 
such notice shall have been given as aforesaid, apply to the Supreme 
Court of Judicature at Bombay by petition, setting forth the grounds 
of his alleged right and praying that the said Collector may be 
restrained from causing such abatement or removal; and the said Court 
may thereupon (on the petitioner' s giving sufficient security for  
  costs), fix a time for hearing and adjudicating upon such petition, 
and give such direction, and make such orders as the said Court may 
think just, and the said Court may also make an order for restraining 
the alleged nuisance, obstruction or encroachment from being extended, 
or from being abated or removed by the said Collector, until after 
adjudication upon the said petition, or the dismissal thereof for want 
of prosecution.


</article>



<article><tid>1024626</tid>
<number>3</number>Onus of proving right.-- Upon the hearing of every such 
petition, the onus of proving the alleged right shall be on the 
petitioner.


</article>



<article><tid>913778</tid>
<number>4</number>Limitation of time for petition.-- No person shall be allowed, 
after the expiration of such period of one month, to present any such 
petition as aforesaid, unless on satisfactorily accounting to the said 
Court for the delay.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>34</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Short title given by the Bombay Short Titles Act, <year>1921</year> (Bom. Act  
  2 of <year>1921</year>).

This Act, so far it relates to the removal of any obstruction, 
impediment or public nuisance affecting, or likely to affect the 
navigation of the port of Bombay, rep. by Act 22 of <year>1855</year>, s. 2.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" Bombay Govt. Gazette."


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>209531</tid>
<number>5</number>When Collector may cause removal of nuisance. Form of warrant. 
Indemnity.-- If no such petition shall be presented within the said 
period of one month, or if the same be presented and determined 
against the right of the petitioner, or be dismissed for want of 
prosecution, it shall be lawful for the Collector to cause such 
abatement or removal as aforesaid by any person or persons to be 
authorized by warrant under his hand, and such warrant may be in the 
From No. 2 in the Schedule to this Act annexed, or to the like effect; 
and the said Collector, and any person acting under his warrant, shall 
not be answerable for any damage unavoidably occasioned in the removal 
of any such nuisance, obstruction or encroachment.


</article>



<article><tid>1716997</tid>
<number>6</number>Power to sell materials of encroachment.-- The said Collector 
may sell the materials of any encroachment or obstruction removed 
under this Act, and may apply the proceeds of sale in or towards 
payment of the expenses of the removal, and, if any surplus shall 
remain, the same shall be forfeited, and be paid and applied in such 
manner as the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Central Government] shall direct.


</article>



<article><tid>1810586</tid>
<number>7</number>Saving of rights of Government.-- Nothing in this Act shall 
prejudice or affect the rights of <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the Government in any part of 
the said harbour, or of the sea- shore of the said lands, or preclude 
or interfere with any such proceedings, civil or criminal, for abating 
such nuisances and encroachments as aforesaid, as might have been had 
if this Act had not been passed.


</article>



<article><tid>943653</tid>
<number>8</number>" High- water mark" defined.-- The words" high- water mark" in 
this Act shall mean the ordinary line of high- water at monsoon tides.

</article>



 </act>