<act><tid>1855450</tid>
<title>THE NORTH- EASTERN HILL UNIVERSITY ACT, <year>1973</year></title>

ACT NO. 24 OF <year>1973</year>
[ 26th May, <year>1973</year>]

An Act to establish and incorporate a teaching and affiliating 
University for the hill areas of the North- Eastern region.

WHEREAS it is expedient to establish and incorporate a teaching 
and affiliating University for the benefit of the people of the hill 
areas of the North- Eastern region and to develop the intellectual, 
academic and cultural background of the said people;

AND WHEREAS in pursuance of clause (1) of article 252 of the 
Constitution, resolutions have been passed by the Legislatures of the 
States of Meghalaya and Nagaland to the effect that the setting up of 
a Central University for the hill areas of the North- Eastern region 
shall be regulated by Parliament by law;

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- fourth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-





<article><tid>1517867</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>575587</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the North- Eastern Hill University Act, <year>1973</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1413304</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the[ State of Meghalaya] <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> and the Union 
territories of Arunachal Pradesh and Mizoram.

</section>

<section><tid>1214067</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>526510</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, and in all Statutes made hereunder, 
unless the context otherwise requires,-
<section><tid>453295</tid>
<number>a</number>" Academic Council" means the Academic Council of the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>173324</tid>
<number>b</number>" academic staff" means such categories of staff as are 
designated as academic staff by the Ordinances;

</section>

<section><tid>351114</tid>
<number>c</number>" Board of Studies" means the Board of Studies of the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>1604433</tid>
<number>d</number>" Chancellor"," Vice- Chancellor" and" Pro- Vice- 
Chancellor" mean, respectively, the Chancellor, Vice- 
Chancellor and Pro- Vice- Chancellor of the University;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>212</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 35 of <year>1989</year>, s. 48 (w. e. f. 6- 9- <year>1994</year>). 
2.  19th July, <year>1973</year>: Vide Notification No. S. O. 2231, dated 19- 7- 
<year>1973</year>, see Gazette of India, Pt. II, Sec. 3 (ii), p. 2742.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1913912</tid>
<number>e</number>" College" means a College maintained by, or admitted to 
the privileges of, the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1167412</tid>
<number>f</number>" Court" means the Court of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1494136</tid>
<number>g</number>" Department" means a Department of Studies, and 
includes a Centre of Studies;

</section>

<section><tid>238868</tid>
<number>h</number>" employee" means any person appointed by the 
University, and includes teachers and other staff of 
the University;

</section>

<section><tid>150484</tid>
<number>i</number>" Executive Council" means the Executive Council of the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>763426</tid>
<number>j</number>" Hall" means a unit of residence or of corporate life 
for the students of the University, College or 
Institution, provided, maintained or recognised by the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>680296</tid>
<number>k</number>" Institution" means an academic institution, not being 
a College, maintained by, or admitted to the privileges 
of, the University;

</section>

<section><tid>591782</tid>
<number>l</number>" North- Eastern region" means the North- Eastern region 
of India comprising the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State of Meghalaya] and the 
Union territories of Arunachal Pradesh and Mizoram;

</section>

<section><tid>1460271</tid>
<number>m</number>" Principal" means the Head of a College or an 
Institution, and includes where there is no Principal, 
the person for the time being duly appointed to act as 
Principal, and, in the absence of the Principal or the 
acting Principal, a Vice- Principal duly appointed as 
such;

</section>

<section><tid>750792</tid>
<number>n</number>" recognised teachers" means such persons as are 
recognised by the University for the purpose of 
imparting instruction in a College or an Institution 
admitted to the privileges of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>386589</tid>
<number>o</number>" School" means a School of Studies of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1984851</tid>
<number>p</number>" Statutes"," Ordinances" and" Regulations", mean, 
respectively, the Statutes, Ordinances and Regulations 
of the University for the time being in force;

</section>

<section><tid>979213</tid>
<number>q</number>" teachers of the University" means Professors, Readers, 
Lecturers and such other persons as may be appointed 
for imparting instruction or conducting research in the 
University or in any College or Institution maintained 
by the University and are designated as teachers by the 
Ordinances;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>213</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 35 of <year>1989</year>, s. 48 (w. e. f. 6- 9- 94).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1067905</tid>
<number>r</number>" University" means the North- Eastern Hill University.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1620829</tid>
<number> 3</number> The University.
<section><tid>1237794</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be established a University by  
the name of" North- Eastern Hill University".

</section>

<section><tid>1531319</tid>
<number>2</number>The headquarters of the University shall be at Shillong and 
it shall have campuses in the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State of Meghalaya] it may also 
establish campuses at such other places within its jurisdiction as it 
may deem fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1708918</tid>
<number>3</number>The first Chancellor and the first Vice- Chancellor and the 
first members of the Court, the Executive Council and the Academic 
Council and all persons who may hereafter become such officers or 
members, so long as they continue to hold such office or membership, 
are hereby constituted a body corporate by the name of" North- Eastern 
Hill University".

</section>

<section><tid>794307</tid>
<number>4</number>The University shall have perpetual succession and a common 
seal, and shall sue and be sued by the said name.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>529127</tid>
<number>4</number>Objects. The objects of the University shall be to disseminate 
and advance knowledge by providing instructional and research 
facilities in such branches of learning as it may deem fit; to pay 
special attention to the improvement of the social and economic 
conditions and welfare of the people of the hill areas of the North- 
Eastern region and, in particular, their intellectual, academic and 
cultural advancement.


</article>



<article><tid>973485</tid>
<number> 5</number> Powers of the University. The University shall have the 
following powers, namely:-
<section><tid>1667596</tid>
<number>1</number>to provide for instruction in such branches of learning 
as the University may, from time to time, determine and 
to make provision for research and for the advancement 
and dissemination of knowledge;

</section>

<section><tid>1459390</tid>
<number>2</number>to take such academic steps as would contribute to the 
improvement of the economic conditions and welfare of 
the people of the hill areas of the North- Eastern 
region;

</section>

<section><tid>1469284</tid>
<number>3</number>to grant, subject to such conditions as the University 
may determine, diplomas or certificates to, and confer 
degrees and other academic distinctions on the basis of 
examinations, evaluation or any other method of 
testing, on persons, and to withdraw any such diplomas, 
certificates, degrees or other academic distinctions 
for good and sufficient cause;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>214</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 35 of <year>1989</year>, s. 48 (w. e. f. 6- 9- <year>1994</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1552530</tid>
<number>4</number>to organise and to undertake extra- mural studies and 
extension services;

</section>

<section><tid>577463</tid>
<number>5</number>to confer honorary degrees or other distinctions in the 
manner prescribed by the Statutes;

</section>

<section><tid>58734</tid>
<number>6</number>to provide instruction, including correspondence and 
such other courses, to such persons as are not members 
of the University, as it may determine;

</section>

<section><tid>1551712</tid>
<number>7</number>to institute principalships, professorships, 
readerships, lecturerships, and other teaching or 
academic posts required by the University and to 
appoint persons to such principalships, professorships, 
readerships, lecturerships or other posts;

</section>

<section><tid>1251421</tid>
<number>8</number>to recognise persons for imparting instruction in any 
College or Institution admitted to the privileges of 
the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1959959</tid>
<number>9</number>to appoint persons working in any other University or 
organisation as teachers of the University for a 
specified period;

</section>

<section><tid>1329405</tid>
<number>10</number>to create administrative, ministerial and other posts 
and to make appointments thereto;

</section>

<section><tid>576457</tid>
<number>11</number>to co- operate or collaborate with any other University 
or authority in such manner and for such purposes as 
the University may determine;

</section>

<section><tid>1119811</tid>
<number>12</number>to establish such campuses, centres, specialised 
laboratories or other units for research and 
instruction as are, in the opinion of the University, 
necessary for the furtherance of its objects;

</section>

<section><tid>1530639</tid>
<number>13</number>to institute and award fellowships, scholarships, 
studentships, medals and prizes;

</section>

<section><tid>393959</tid>
<number>14</number>to establish and maintain Colleges, Institutions and 
Halls;

</section>

<section><tid>122023</tid>
<number>15</number>to admit to its privileges Colleges and Institutions 
not maintained by the University; to withdraw all or 
any of those privileges in accordance with such 
conditions as may be prescribed by the Statutes; and to 
recognise Halls not maintained by the University and to 
withdraw any such recognition;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>215</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>715480</tid>
<number>16</number>to declare a college, an Institution or a Department as 
an autonomous College or an Institution or a 
Department, as the case may be;

</section>

<section><tid>1711806</tid>
<number>17</number>to determine standards for admission into the 
University, which may include examination, evaluation 
or any other method of testing;

</section>

<section><tid>1631099</tid>
<number>18</number>to demand and receive payment of fees and other 
charges;

</section>

<section><tid>417131</tid>
<number>19</number>to supervise the residences of the students of the 
University and to make arrangements for promoting their 
health and general welfare;

</section>

<section><tid>1307125</tid>
<number>20</number>to make special arrangements in respect of women 
students as the University may consider desirable;

</section>

<section><tid>1294843</tid>
<number>21</number>to regulate and enforce discipline among the employees 
and students of the University and take such 
disciplinary measures in this regard as may be deemed 
necessary;

</section>

<section><tid>1442187</tid>
<number>22</number>to make arrangements for promoting the health and 
general welfare of the employees;

</section>

<section><tid>17315</tid>
<number>23</number>to acquire, hold, manage and dispose of property, 
movable or immovable, including trust and endowment 
properties for the purposes of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1392405</tid>
<number>24</number>to borrow, with the approval of the Central Government, 
on the security of the property of the University, 
money for the purposes of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>632635</tid>
<number>25</number>to do all such other acts and things as may be 
necessary, incidental or conducive to the attainment of 
all or any of its objects.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1688461</tid>
<number> 6</number> Jurisdiction.
<section><tid>1982651</tid>
<number>1</number>The jurisdiction of the University shall  
extend to the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State of Meghalaya] and the Union territories of 
Arunachal Pradesh and Mizoram.

</section>

<section><tid>1322331</tid>
<number>2</number>No College or Institution situated within the local limits of 
the jurisdiction of the University shall be compulsorily affiliated to 
the University, and affiliation shall be granted by the University 
only to such Colleges or Institutions as may agree to accept the 
Statutes and Ordinances.

</section>

<section><tid>802010</tid>
<number>3</number>Any College or Institution admitted to the privileges of the 
University shall cease to be associated with, or be admitted to the 
privileges of, any other University.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>216</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 35 of <year>1989</year>, s. 48 (w. e. f. 6- 9- <year>1994</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>938919</tid>
<number>4</number>No College or Institution situated within the local limits of 
the jurisdiction of the University, but not admitted to its 
privileges, shall be associated with, or be admitted to the privileges 
of, any other University except with the previous approval of the 
Government of the State in which, or the Administrator of the Union 
territory in which, such College or Institution is situate.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>739757</tid>
<number>7</number>University open to all classes, castes and creed. The 
University shall be open to persons of either sex and of whatever 
race, creed, caste, or class, and it shall not be lawful for the 
University to adopt or impose on any person any test whatsoever of 
religious belief or profession in order to entitle him to be admitted 
therein, as a teacher or student, or to hold any office therein, or to 
graduate thereat:
Provided that nothing in this section shall be deemed to prevent 
the University from making special provisions for admission of 
students of the weaker sections of the people in the North- Eastern 
region and, in particular, of the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled 
Tribes.



</article>



<article><tid>1752110</tid>
<number> 8</number> Visitor.
<section><tid>1499813</tid>
<number>1</number>The President of India shall be the Visitor of  
the University.

</section>

<section><tid>1563788</tid>
<number>2</number>The Visitor shall have the right to cause an inspection to be 
made by such person or persons as he may direct, of the University, 
its buildings, laboratories and equipment, and of any College or 
Institution maintained by the University or admitted to its 
privileges; and also of the examinations, teaching and other work 
conducted or done by the University and to cause an inquiry to be made 
in like manner in respect of any matter connected with the 
administration or finances of the University, Colleges or 
Institutions.

</section>

<section><tid>935408</tid>
<number>3</number>The Visitor shall, in every case, give notice of his 
intention to cause an inspection or inquiry to be made,-

<subsection><tid>1032312</tid>
<number>a</number>to the University, if such inspection or inquiry is to 
be made in respect of the University, College or 
Institution maintained by it, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1424930</tid>
<number>b</number>to the management of the College or Institution, if the 
inspection or inquiry is to be made in respect of a 
College or an Institution admitted to the privileges of 
the University,
and the University or the management, as the case may be, shall have 
the right to make such representations to the Visitor, as it may 
consider necessary.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>217</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1435333</tid>
<number>4</number>After considering the representations, if any, made by the 
University or the management, as the case may be, the Visitor may 
cause to be made such inspection or inquiry as is referred to in sub- 
section (2).

</section>

<section><tid>278223</tid>
<number>5</number>Where any inspection or inquiry has been caused to be made by 
the Visitor, the University or the management, as the case may be, 
shall be entitled to appoint a representative who shall have the right 
to be present and be heard at such inspection or inquiry.

</section>

<section><tid>463659</tid>
<number>6</number>The Visitor may, if the inspection or inquiry is made in 
respect of the University or any College or Institution maintained by 
it, address the Vice- Chancellor with reference to the result of such 
inspection or inquiry, and the Vice- Chancellor shall communicate to 
the Executive Council the views of the Visitor with such advice as the 
Visitor may be pleased to offer upon the action to be taken thereon.

</section>

<section><tid>1717638</tid>
<number>7</number>The Visitor may, if the inspection or inquiry is made in 
respect of any College or Institution admitted to the privileges of 
the University, address the management concerned through the Vice- 
Chancellor with reference to the result of such inspection or inquiry, 
his views thereon and such advice as he may be pleased to offer upon 
the action to be taken thereon.

</section>

<section><tid>1298847</tid>
<number>8</number>The Executive Council or the management, as the case may be, 
shall communicate through the Vice- Chancellor to the Visitor such 
action, if any, as it is proposed to take or has been taken upon the 
result of such inspection or inquiry.

</section>

<section><tid>930387</tid>
<number>9</number>Where the Executive Council or the management does not, 
within a reasonable time, take action to the satisfaction of the 
Visitor, the Visitor may, after considering any explanation furnished 
or representation made by the Executive Council or management, issue 
such directions as he may think fit and the Executive Council or 
management, as the case may be, shall comply with such directions.

</section>

<section><tid>179328</tid>
<number>10</number>Without prejudice to the foregoing provisions of this 
section, the Visitor may, by order in writing, annul any proceeding of 
the University which is not in conformity with this Act, the Statutes 
or Ordinances:
Provided that before making any such order, he shall call upon 
the University to show cause why such an order should not be made, 
and, if any cause is shown within a reasonable time, he shall consider 
the same.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>218</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1865633</tid>
<number>11</number>The Visitor shall have such other powers as may be 
prescribed by the Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1702017</tid>
<number>9</number>Chief Rector. The Governor of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State of Meghalaya] shall 
be the Chief Rector of the University.


</article>



<article><tid>1075936</tid>
<number> 10</number> Officers of the University. The following shall be the 
officers of the University:-
<section><tid>240068</tid>
<number>1</number>The Chancellor;

</section>

<section><tid>1997234</tid>
<number>2</number>The Vice- Chancellor;

</section>

<section><tid>629385</tid>
<number>3</number>The Pro- Vice- Chancellors;

</section>

<section><tid>368008</tid>
<number>4</number>The Deans of Schools;

</section>

<section><tid>1225673</tid>
<number>5</number>The Registrar;

</section>

<section><tid>1012847</tid>
<number>6</number>The Finance Officer; and

</section>

<section><tid>816057</tid>
<number>7</number>Such other officers as may be declared by the Statutes 
to be officers of the University.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1851283</tid>
<number> 11</number> The Chancellor.
<section><tid>950622</tid>
<number>1</number>The Chancellor shall be appointed by the  
Visitor in such manner as may be prescribed by the Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>839507</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chancellor shall, by virtue of his office, be the Head of 
the University.

</section>

<section><tid>661376</tid>
<number>3</number>The Chancellor shall, if present, preside at the convocations 
of the University held for conferring degrees.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>880343</tid>
<number> 12</number> The Vice- Chancellor.
<section><tid>430918</tid>
<number>1</number>The Vice- Chancellor shall be  
appointed by the Visitor in such manner as may be prescribed by the 
Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>1560683</tid>
<number>2</number>The Vice- Chancellor shall be the principal executive and 
academic officer of the University, and shall exercise general 
supervision and control over the affairs of the University and give 
effect to the decisions of all the authorities of the University.

</section>

<section><tid>1730431</tid>
<number>3</number>The Vice- Chancellor may, if he is of opinion that immediate 
action is necessary on any matter, exercise any power conferred on any 
authority of the University by or under this Act and shall report to 
such authority the action taken by him on such matter:
Provided that if the authority concerned is of opinion that such 
action ought not to have been taken, it may refer the matter to the 
Visitor whose decision thereon shall be final:

Provided further that any person in the service of the University 
who is aggrieved by the action taken by the Vice- Chancellor under this 
sub- section shall have the right to appeal against such action

<pagefootnote><pagenum>219</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 35 of <year>1989</year>, s. 48 (w. e. f. 6- 9- <year>1994</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


to the Executive Council within three months from the date on which 
decision on such action is communicated to him and thereupon the 
Executive Council may confirm, modify or reverse the action taken by 
the Vice- Chancellor.


</section>

<section><tid>1218941</tid>
<number>4</number>The Vice- Chancellor shall exercise such other powers and 
perform such other functions as may be prescribed by the Statutes or 
Ordinances.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1773208</tid>
<number>13</number>The Pro- Vice- Chancellors. Every Pro- Vice- Chancellor shall be 
appointed in such manner and shall exercise such powers and perform 
such duties as may be prescribed by the Statutes.


</article>



<article><tid>1232410</tid>
<number>14</number>Deans of Schools. Every Dean of a School shall be appointed 
in such manner and shall exercise such powers and perform such duties 
as may be prescribed by the Statutes.


</article>



<article><tid>1349664</tid>
<number> 15</number> The Registrar.
<section><tid>1595684</tid>
<number>1</number>The Registrar shall be appointed in such  
manner as may be prescribed by the Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>1274061</tid>
<number>2</number>The Registrar shall have the power to enter into agreements, 
sign documents and authenticate records on behalf of the University 
and shall exercise such other powers and perform such other duties as 
may be prescribed by the Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>137088</tid>
<number>16</number>The Finance Officer. The Finance Officer shall be appointed 
in such manner and shall exercise such powers and perform such duties 
as may be prescribed by the Statutes.


</article>



<article><tid>908125</tid>
<number>17</number>Other officers. The manner of appointment and powers and 
duties of other officers of the University shall be prescribed by the 
Statutes.


</article>



<article><tid>512988</tid>
<number> 18</number> Authorities of the University. The following shall be the 
authorities of the University:-
<section><tid>1747270</tid>
<number>1</number>The Court;

</section>

<section><tid>804564</tid>
<number>2</number>The Executive Council;

</section>

<section><tid>1197047</tid>
<number>3</number>The Academic Council;

</section>

<section><tid>1948099</tid>
<number>4</number>The Boards of Schools; and

</section>

<section><tid>372629</tid>
<number>5</number>Such other authorities as may be declared by the 
Statutes to be authorities of the University.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>393935</tid>
<number> 19</number> The Court.
<section><tid>1955826</tid>
<number>1</number>The constitution of the Court and the term of  
office of its members shall be prescribed by the Statutes.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>220</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1841968</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Court shall have 
the following powers and functions, namely:-

<subsection><tid>174982</tid>
<number>a</number>to review, from time to time, the broad policies and 
programmes of the University and to suggest measures 
for the improvement and development of the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>521940</tid>
<number>b</number>to consider and pass resolutions on the annual report 
and the annual accounts of the University and the audit 
report on such accounts;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>683426</tid>
<number>c</number>to advise the Visitor in respect of any matter which 
may be referred to it for advice; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>804548</tid>
<number>d</number>to perform such other functions as may be prescribed by 
the Statutes.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1606765</tid>
<number> 20</number> The Executive Council.
<section><tid>1154121</tid>
<number>1</number>The Executive Council shall be the  
principal executive body of the University.

</section>

<section><tid>1047331</tid>
<number>2</number>The constitution of the Executive Council, the term of office 
of its members and its powers and duties shall be prescribed by the 
Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1573937</tid>
<number> 21</number> The Academic Council.
<section><tid>15213</tid>
<number>1</number>The Academic Council shall be the  
principal academic body of the University and shall, subject to the 
provisions of this Act, the Statutes and Ordinances, co- ordinate and 
exercise general supervision over the academic policies of the 
University.

</section>

<section><tid>1574836</tid>
<number>2</number>The constitution of the Academic Council, the term of office 
of its members and its powers and duties shall be prescribed by the 
Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>291110</tid>
<number>22</number>Other authorities of the University. The constitution, powers 
and functions of the Boards of Schools and of such other authorities 
as may be declared by the Statutes to be authorities of the 
University, shall be prescribed by the Statutes.


</article>



<article><tid>512952</tid>
<number> 23</number> Planning Board.
<section><tid>796951</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be constituted a Planning  
Board of the University which shall advise generally on the planning 
and development of the University and keep under review the standard 
of education and research in the University.

</section>

<section><tid>1044966</tid>
<number>2</number>The Planning Board shall consist of-

<subsection><tid>800388</tid>
<number>a</number>The Vice- Chancellor, who shall be the Chairman, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>196312</tid>
<number>b</number>not more than eight persons of high academic standing 
who shall be appointed in such manner as may be 
prescribed by the Statutes.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>221</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>361928</tid>
<number>3</number>The Visitor may determine a date with effect from which the 
Planning Board shall stand dissolved.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>401554</tid>
<number> 24</number> Power to make Statutes. Subject to the provisions of this 
Act, the Statutes may provide for all or any of the following matters, 
namely:-
<section><tid>1505917</tid>
<number>a</number>the constitution, powers and functions of the 
authorities and other bodies of the University, as may 
be constituted from time to time;

</section>

<section><tid>1263219</tid>
<number>b</number>the election and continuance in office of the members 
of the said authorities and bodies, the filling of 
vacancies of members, and all other matters relative to 
those authorities and other bodies for which it may be 
necessary or desirable to provide;

</section>

<section><tid>1922723</tid>
<number>c</number>the appointment, powers and duties of the officers of 
the University and their emoluments;

</section>

<section><tid>235165</tid>
<number>d</number>the appointment of teachers of the University and other 
academic staff and their emoluments;

</section>

<section><tid>1046234</tid>
<number>e</number>the appointment of teachers and other academic staff 
working in any other University or organisation for a 
specified period for undertaking a joint project;

</section>

<section><tid>515474</tid>
<number>f</number>the conditions of service of employees including 
provision for pension, insurance and provident fund, 
the manner of termination of service and disciplinary 
action;

</section>

<section><tid>683684</tid>
<number>g</number>the principles governing seniority of service of 
employees;

</section>

<section><tid>1846540</tid>
<number>h</number>the procedure for arbitration in cases of dispute 
between employees or students and the University;

</section>

<section><tid>646056</tid>
<number>i</number>the procedure for appeal to the Executive Council by 
any employee or student against the action of any 
officer or authority of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>805474</tid>
<number>j</number>the establishment and recognition of Students' Union or 
associations of teachers, academic staff or other 
employees;

</section>

<section><tid>142367</tid>
<number>k</number>the participation of students in the affairs of the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>443649</tid>
<number>l</number>the conferment of honorary degrees;

</section>

<section><tid>1025943</tid>
<number>m</number>the withdrawal of degrees, diplomas, certificates and 
other academic distinctions;

</section>

<section><tid>397539</tid>
<number>n</number>the institution of fellowships, scholarships, 
studentships, medals and prizes;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>222</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1617252</tid>
<number>o</number>the maintenance of discipline among the students;

</section>

<section><tid>544469</tid>
<number>p</number>the establishment and abolition of Schools, 
Departments, Halls, Colleges and Institutions;

</section>

<section><tid>702999</tid>
<number>q</number>the conditions under which Colleges and Institutions 
may be admitted to the privileges of the University and 
the withdrawal of such privileges;

</section>

<section><tid>39965</tid>
<number>r</number>the delegation of powers vested in the authorities or 
officers of the University; and

</section>

<section><tid>177220</tid>
<number>s</number>all other matters which by this Act are to be, or may 
be, provided by the Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1380965</tid>
<number> 25</number> Statutes how made.
<section><tid>1784570</tid>
<number>1</number>The first Statutes are those set out  
in the Schedule.

</section>

<section><tid>301709</tid>
<number>2</number>The Executive Council may, from time to time, make new or 
additional Statutes or may amend or repeal the Statutes referred to in 
sub- section (1):
Provided that the Executive Council shall not make, amend or 
repeal any Statute affecting the status, powers or constitution of any 
authority of the University until such authority has been given an 
opportunity of expressing an opinion in writing on the proposed 
changes, and any opinion so expressed shall be considered by the 
Executive Council.


</section>

<section><tid>411509</tid>
<number>3</number>Every new Statute or addition to the Statutes or any 
amendment or repeal of a Statute shall require the approval of the 
Visitor who may assent thereto or withhold assent or remit to the 
Executive Council for consideration.

</section>

<section><tid>203619</tid>
<number>4</number>A new Statute or a Statute amending or repealing an existing 
Statute shall have no validity unless it has been assented to by the 
Visitor.

</section>

<section><tid>1284372</tid>
<number>5</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing sub- 
sections, the Visitor may make new or additional Statutes or amend or 
repeal the Statutes referred to in sub- section (1) during the period 
of three years immediately after the commencement of this Act:
Provided that the Visitor may, on the expiry of the said period 
of three years make, within one year from the date of such expiry, 
such detailed Statutes as he may consider necessary and such detailed 
Statutes shall be laid before both Houses of Parliament.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>32827</tid>
<number> 26</number> Ordinances.
<section><tid>1804233</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act and the  
Statutes, the Ordinances may provide for all or any of the following 
matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>208694</tid>
<number>a</number>the admission of students to the University and their 
enrolment as such;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>223</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>665027</tid>
<number>b</number>the courses of study to be laid down for all degrees, 
diplomas and certificates of the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1003146</tid>
<number>c</number>the medium of instruction and examination;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>274547</tid>
<number>d</number>the award of degrees, diplomas, certificates and other 
academic distinctions, the qualifications for the same 
and the means to be taken relating to the granting and 
obtaining of the same;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1897037</tid>
<number>e</number>the fees to be charged for courses of study in the 
University and for admission to the examinations, 
degrees and diplomas of the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>175020</tid>
<number>f</number>the conditions of award of fellowships, scholarships, 
studentships, medals and prizes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1850902</tid>
<number>g</number>the conduct of examinations, including the term of 
office and of appointment and the duties of examining 
bodies, examiners and moderators;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>413628</tid>
<number>h</number>the conditions of residence of the students of the 
University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1257916</tid>
<number>i</number>the special arrangements, if any, which may be made for 
the residence, discipline and teaching of women 
students and the prescribing of special courses of 
studies for them;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1357462</tid>
<number>j</number>the appointment and emoluments of employees other than 
those for whom provision has been made in the Statutes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1341385</tid>
<number>k</number>the establishment of Centres of Studies, Boards of 
Studies, Special Centres, specialised laboratories and 
other Committees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>383540</tid>
<number>l</number>the manner of co- operation and collaboration with other 
Universities and authorities including learned bodies 
or associations;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1364362</tid>
<number>m</number>the creation, composition and functions of any other 
body which is considered necessary for improving the 
academic life of the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1317065</tid>
<number>n</number>such other terms and conditions of service of teachers 
and other academic staff as are not prescribed by the 
Statutes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1788460</tid>
<number>o</number>the management of Colleges and Institutions established 
by the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1901301</tid>
<number>p</number>the supervision and management of Colleges and 
Institutions admitted to the privileges of the 
University; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>41282</tid>
<number>q</number>all other matters which by this Act or the Statutes may 
be provided for by the Ordinances.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>224</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>455061</tid>
<number>2</number>The first Ordinances shall be made by the Vice- Chancellor 
with the previous approval of the Central Government and the 
Ordinances so made may be amended, repealed or added to at any time by 
the Executive Council in the manner prescribed by the Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>576000</tid>
<number>27</number>Regulations. The authorities of the University may make 
Regulations consistent with this Act, the Statutes and the Ordinances 
for the conduct of their own business and that of the Committees 
appointed by them and not provided for by this Act, the Statutes or 
the Ordinances in the manner prescribed by the Statutes.


</article>



<article><tid>1887466</tid>
<number> 28</number> Annual report.
<section><tid>1589250</tid>
<number>1</number>The annual report of the University shall  
be prepared under the direction of the Executive Council and shall be 
submitted to the court on or after such date as may be prescribed by 
the Statutes and the Court shall consider the report in its annual 
meeting.

</section>

<section><tid>1799051</tid>
<number>2</number>The Court shall submit the annual report to the Visitor along 
with its comments, if any.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>531963</tid>
<number> 29</number> Annual accounts.
<section><tid>535010</tid>
<number>1</number>The annual accounts and balance- sheet of  
the University shall be prepared under the directions of the Executive 
Council and shall once at least every year and at intervals of not 
more than fifteen months be audited by the Comptroller and Auditor- 
General of India.

</section>

<section><tid>411899</tid>
<number>2</number>The annual accounts when audited shall be published in the 
Gazette of India and a copy of the accounts together with the report 
of the Comptroller and Auditor- General shall be submitted to the Court 
and the Visitor along with the observations of the Executive Council.

</section>

<section><tid>1270338</tid>
<number>3</number>Any observations made by the Visitor on the annual accounts 
shall be brought to the notice of the Court and the observations of 
the Court, if any, shall, after being considered by the Executive 
Council, be submitted to the Visitor.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>218759</tid>
<number> 30</number> Conditions of service of employees.
<section><tid>661310</tid>
<number>1</number>Every employee shall  
be appointed under a written contract which shall be lodged with the 
University and a copy of which shall be furnished to the employee 
concerned.

</section>

<section><tid>595638</tid>
<number>2</number>Any dispute arising out of a contract between the University 
and any employee shall, at the request of the employee, be referred to 
a Tribunal of Arbitration consisting of one member appointed by the 
Executive Council, one member nominated by the employee concerned and 
an umpire appointed by the Visitor. The decision of

<pagefootnote><pagenum>225</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

the Tribunal shall be final, and no suit shall lie in any civil court 
in respect of the matters decided by the Tribunal. Every such request 
shall be deemed to be a submission to arbitration upon the terms of 
this section within the meaning of the Arbitration Act, <year>1940</year> (2 of  
  <year>1940</year>).




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1681085</tid>
<number> 31</number> Procedure of appeal and arbitration in disciplinary cases 
against students.
<section><tid>34706</tid>
<number>1</number>Any student or candidate for an examination  
whose name has been removed from the rolls of the University by the 
orders or resolution of the Vice- Chancellor, Discipline Committee or 
Examination Committee, as the case may be, and who has been debarred 
from appearing at the examinations of the University for more than one 
year, may, within ten days of the date of receipt of such orders or 
copy of such resolution by him, appeal to the Executive Council and 
the Executive Council may confirm, modify or reverse the decision of 
the Vice- Chancellor or the Committee, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1190816</tid>
<number>2</number>Any dispute arising out of any disciplinary action taken by 
the University against a student shall, at the request of such 
student, be referred to a Tribunal of Arbitration and the provisions 
of sub- section (2) of section 30 shall, as far as may be, apply to a 
reference made under this sub- section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1051378</tid>
<number>32</number>Right to appeal. Every employee or student of the University 
or of a College or Institution shall, notwithstanding anything 
contained in this Act, have a right to appeal, within such time as may 
be prescribed by the Statutes, to the Executive Council against the 
decision of any officer or authority of the University or of the 
Principal or the management of any College or Institution, as the case 
may be, and thereupon the Executive Council may confirm, modify or 
reverse the decision appealed against.


</article>



<article><tid>300069</tid>
<number> 33</number> Provident and pension funds.
<section><tid>131652</tid>
<number>1</number>The University shall  
constitute for the benefit of its employees such pension or provident 
fund or provide such insurance schemes as it may deem fit in such 
manner and subject to such conditions as may be prescribed by the 
Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>258635</tid>
<number>2</number>Where such provident or pension fund has been so constituted, 
the Central Government may declare that the provisions of the 
Provident Funds Act, <year>1925</year> (19 of <year>1925</year>), shall apply to such fund, as 
if it were a Government provident fund.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1933933</tid>
<number>34</number>Disputes as to constitution of University authorities and 
bodies. If any question arises as to whether any person has been duly 
elected or appointed as, or is entitled to be, a member of any 
authority or other body of the University, the matter shall be 
referred to the Visitor whose decision thereon shall be final.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>226</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1892286</tid>
<number>35</number>Constitution of Committees. Where any authority of the 
University is given power by this Act or the Statutes to appoint 
Committees, such Committees shall, save as otherwise provided, consist 
of the members of the authority concerned and of such other persons 
 (if any) as the authority in each case may think fit.


</article>



<article><tid>867809</tid>
<number>36</number>Filling of casual vacancies. All casual vacancies among the 
members (other than exofficio members) of any authority or other body 
of the University shall be filled, as soon as conveniently may be, by 
the person or body who appointed, elected or co- opted the member whose 
place has become vacant and the person appointed, elected or co- opted 
to a casual vacancy shall be a member of such authority or body for 
the residue of the term for which the person whose place he fills 
would have been a member.


</article>



<article><tid>909195</tid>
<number>37</number>Proceedings of University authorities or bodies not 
invalidated by vacancies. No act or proceedings of any authority or 
other body of the University shall be invalidated merely by reason of 
the existence of a vacancy or vacancies among its members.


</article>



<article><tid>634938</tid>
<number>38</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit or other 
legal proceedings shall lie against any officer or employee of the 
University for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be 
done in pursuance of any of the provisions of this Act, the Statutes 
or Ordinances.


</article>



<article><tid>440049</tid>
<number>39</number>Mode of proof of University record. A copy of any receipt, 
application, notice, order, proceeding, resolution of any authority or 
Committee of the University, or other documents in possession of the 
University, or any entry in any register duly maintained by the 
University, if certified by the Registrar, shall be received as prima 
facie evidence of such receipt, application, notice, order, proceeding 
or resolution, documents or the existence of entry in the register and 
shall be admitted as evidence of the matters and transactions therein 
where the original thereof would, if produced, have been admissible in 
evidence, notwithstanding anything contained in the Indian Evidence 
Act, <year>1872</year> (1 of <year>1872</year>) or in any other law for the time being in force.


</article>



<article><tid>818257</tid>
<number>40</number>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in 
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions, 
not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as appear to it to 
be necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>227</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Provided that no such order shall be made under this section 
after the expiry of three years from the commencement of this Act.



</article>



<article><tid>901935</tid>
<number> 41</number> Transitional provisions. Notwithstanding anything contained 
in this Act and the Statutes-
<section><tid>1815353</tid>
<number>a</number>the first Chancellor and the first Vice- Chancellor 
shall be appointed by the Visitor and each of the said 
officers shall hold office for a term of five years;

</section>

<section><tid>1555413</tid>
<number>b</number>the first Registrar and the first Finance Officer shall 
be appointed by the Visitor and each of the said 
officers shall hold office for a term of three years;

</section>

<section><tid>448464</tid>
<number>c</number>the first Court and the first Executive Council shall 
consist of not more than thirty members and eleven 
members respectively, who shall be nominated by the 
Visitor and shall hold office for a term of three 
years;

</section>

<section><tid>362072</tid>
<number>d</number>the first Academic Council shall be constituted on the 
expiry of a period of six months from the commencement 
of this Act and during the said period of six months, 
the powers of the Academic Council shall be performed 
by the Planning Board constituted under section 23;

</section>

<section><tid>328642</tid>
<number>e</number>the first Academic Council shall consist of not more 
than twenty- one members, who shall be nominated by the 
Visitor and shall hold office for a term of three 
years:
Provided that if any vacancy occurs in the above offices or 
authorities, the same shall be filled by appointment or nomination, as 
the case may be, by the Visitor, and the person so appointed or 
nominated shall hold office for so long as the officer or member in 
whose place he is appointed or nominated would have held office, if 
such vacancy had not occurred.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>293771</tid>
<number>42</number>Completion of courses of students in Colleges or Institutions 
affiliated to the University. Notwithstanding anything contained in 
this Act, or in the Statutes or the Ordinances, any student of a 
College or Institution, who, immediately before the admission of such 
College or Institution to the privileges of the North- Eastern Hill 
University, was studying for a degree, diploma or certificate of the 
Gauhati University, shall be permitted by the North- Eastern Hill 
University to complete his course for that degree, diploma or 
certificate, as the case may be, and the North- Eastern Hill University 
and such College or Institution shall provide for the instruction and 
examination of such student in accordance with the syllabus of studies 
of the Gauhati University.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>228</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1517867</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>575587</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the North- Eastern Hill University Act, <year>1973</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1413304</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the States of Meghalaya and Nagaland and the 
Union territories of Arunachal Pradesh and Mizoram.

</section>

<section><tid>1214067</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such 1date as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>526510</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, and in all Statutes made hereunder, 
unless the context otherwise requires,-
<section><tid>453295</tid>
<number>a</number>" Academic Council" means the Academic Council of the 
University;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>149</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 19- 7- 73: Vide Notifn. No. S. O. 2231, dt. 19- 7- 73, gaz of India, Pt. II, 
Sec. 3 (ii), p- 2742.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>173324</tid>
<number>b</number>" academic staff" means such categories of staff as are 
designated as academic staff by the Ordinances;

</section>

<section><tid>351114</tid>
<number>c</number>" Board of Studies" means the Board of Studies of the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>1604433</tid>
<number>d</number>" Chancellor"," Vice- Chancellor" and" Pro- Vice- Chancellor" 
mean, respectively, the Chancellor, Vice- Chancellor and Pro- 
Vice- Chancellor of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1913912</tid>
<number>e</number>" College" means a College maintained by, or admitted to 
the privileges of, the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1167412</tid>
<number>f</number>" Court" means the Court of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1494136</tid>
<number>g</number>" Department" means a Department of Studies, and includes 
Centre of Studies;

</section>

<section><tid>238868</tid>
<number>h</number>" employee" means any person appointed by the University, 
and includes teachers and other staff of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>150484</tid>
<number>i</number>" Executive Council" means the Executive Council of the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>763426</tid>
<number>j</number>" Hall" means a unit of residence or of corporate life for 
the students of the University, College or Institution, 
provided, maintained or recognised by the University;

</section>

<section><tid>680296</tid>
<number>k</number>" Institution" means an academic Institution, not being a 
College. maintained by, or admitted to the privileges of, the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>591782</tid>
<number>l</number>" North- Eastern region" means the North- Eastern region of 
India comprising the States of Meghalaya and Nagaland and the 
Union territories of Arunachal Pradesh and Mizoram;

</section>

<section><tid>1460271</tid>
<number>m</number>" Principal" means the Head of a College or an 
Institution, and includes where there is no Principal, the 
person for the time being duly appointed to act as Principal, 
and, in the absence of the Principal or the acting Principal, 
a Vice- Principal duly appointed as such;

</section>

<section><tid>750792</tid>
<number>n</number>" recognised teachers" means such persons as are 
recognised by the University for the purpose of imparting 
instruction in a College or an Institution admitted to the 
privileges of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>386589</tid>
<number>o</number>" School" means a School of Studies of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1984851</tid>
<number>p</number>" Statutes"," Ordinances" and" Regulations", mean, 
respectively, the Statutes, Ordinances and Regulations of the 
University for the time being in force;

</section>

<section><tid>979213</tid>
<number>q</number>" teachers of the University" means Professors, Readers, 
Lecturers and such other persons as may be appointed for 
imparting instruction or conducting research in the 
University or in any College or Institution maintained by the 
University and are designated as teachers by the Ordinances;

</section>

<section><tid>1067905</tid>
<number>r</number>" University" means the North- Eastern Hill University.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>150</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1620829</tid>
<number> 3</number> The University.
<section><tid>1237794</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be established a University by  
the name of" North- Eastern Hill University".

</section>

<section><tid>1531319</tid>
<number>2</number>The headquarters of the University shall be at Shillong and 
it shall have campuses in the States of Meghalaya and Nagaland; it may 
also establish campuses at such other places within its jurisdiction 
as it may deem fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1708918</tid>
<number>3</number>The first Chancellor and the first Vice- Chancellor and the 
first members of the Court, the Executive Council and the Academic 
Council and all persons who may hereafter become such officers or 
members, so long as they continue to hold such office or membership, 
are hereby constituted a body corporate by the name of" North- Eastern 
Hill University".

</section>

<section><tid>794307</tid>
<number>4</number>The University shall have perpetual succession and a common 
seal, and shall sue and be sued by the said name.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>529127</tid>
<number>4</number>Objects. The objects of the University shall be to disseminate 
and advance knowledge by providing instructional and research 
facilities in such branches of learning as it may deem fit; to pay 
special attention to the improvement of the social and economic 
conditions and welfare of the people of the hill areas of the North- 
Eastern region and, in particular, their intellectual, academic and 
cultural advancement.


</article>



<article><tid>973485</tid>
<number> 5</number> Powers of the University. The University shall have the 
following powers, namely:-
<section><tid>1667596</tid>
<number>1</number>to provide for instruction in such branches of learning 
as the University may, from time to time, determine and to 
make provision for research and for the advancement and 
dissemination of knowledge;

</section>

<section><tid>1459390</tid>
<number>2</number>to take such academic steps as would contribute to the 
improvement of the economic conditions and welfare of the 
people of the hill areas of the North- Eastern region;

</section>

<section><tid>1469284</tid>
<number>3</number>to grant, subject to such conditions as the University 
may determine, diplomas or certificates to, and confer 
degrees and other academic distinctions on the basis of 
examinations, evaluation or any other method of testing, on 
persons, and to withdraw any such diplomas, certificates, 
degrees or other academic distinctions for good and 
sufficient cause;

</section>

<section><tid>1552530</tid>
<number>4</number>to organise and to undertake extra- mural studies and 
extension services;

</section>

<section><tid>577463</tid>
<number>5</number>to confer honorary degrees or other distinctions in the 
manner prescribed by the Statutes;

</section>

<section><tid>58734</tid>
<number>6</number>to provide instruction, including correspondence and such 
other courses, to such persons as are not members of the 
University, as it may determine;

</section>

<section><tid>1551712</tid>
<number>7</number>to institute principalships, professorships, readerships, 
lecturerships, and other teaching or academic posts required 
by the University and to appoint persons to such 
principalships, professorships, readerships, lecturerships or 
other posts;

</section>

<section><tid>1251421</tid>
<number>8</number>to recognise persons for imparting instruction in any 
College or Institution admitted to the privileges of the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>1959959</tid>
<number>9</number>to appoint persons working in any other University or 
organisation as teachers of the University for a specified 
period;

</section>

<section><tid>1329405</tid>
<number>10</number>to create administrative, ministerial and other posts 
and to make appointments thereto;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>151</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>576457</tid>
<number>11</number>to co- operate or collaborate with any other University 
or authority in such manner and for such purposes as the 
University may determine;

</section>

<section><tid>1119811</tid>
<number>12</number>to establish such campuses, centres, specialised 
laboratories or other units for research and instruction as 
are, in the opinion of the University, necessary for the 
furtherance of its objects;

</section>

<section><tid>1530639</tid>
<number>13</number>to institute and award fellowships, scholarships, 
studentships, medals and prizes;

</section>

<section><tid>393959</tid>
<number>14</number>to establish and maintain Colleges, Institutions and 
Halls;

</section>

<section><tid>122023</tid>
<number>15</number>to admit to its privileges Colleges and Institutions not 
maintained by the University; to withdraw all or any of those 
privilege' s in accordance with such conditions as may be 
prescribed by the Statutes; and to recognise Halls not 
maintained by the University and to withdraw any such 
recognition;

</section>

<section><tid>715480</tid>
<number>16</number>to declare a College, an Institution or a Department as 
an autonomous College or an Institution or a Department, as 
the case may be;

</section>

<section><tid>1711806</tid>
<number>17</number>to determine standards for admission into the 
University, which may include examination, evaluation or any 
other method of testing;

</section>

<section><tid>1631099</tid>
<number>18</number>to demand and receive payment of fees and other charges;

</section>

<section><tid>417131</tid>
<number>19</number>to supervise the residences of the students of the 
University and to make arrangements for promoting their 
health and general welfare;

</section>

<section><tid>1307125</tid>
<number>20</number>to make special arrangements in respect of women 
students as the University may consider desirable;

</section>

<section><tid>1294843</tid>
<number>21</number>to regulate and enforce discipline among the employees 
and students of the University and take such disciplinary 
measures in this regard as may be deemed necessary;

</section>

<section><tid>1442187</tid>
<number>22</number>to make arrangements for promoting the health and 
general welfare of the employees;

</section>

<section><tid>17315</tid>
<number>23</number>to acquire, hold, manage and dispose of property, 
movable or immovable, including trust and endowment 
properties for the purposes of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1392405</tid>
<number>24</number>to borrow, with the approval of the Central Government, 
on the security of the property of the University, money for 
the purposes of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>632635</tid>
<number>25</number>to do all such other acts and things as may be 
necessary, incidental or conducive to the attainment of all 
or any of its. objects.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1688461</tid>
<number> 6</number> Jurisdiction.
<section><tid>1982651</tid>
<number>1</number>The jurisdiction of the University shall  
extend to the States of Meghalaya and Nagaland and the Union 
territories of Arunachal Pradesh and Mizoram.

</section>

<section><tid>1322331</tid>
<number>2</number>No College or Institution situated within the local limits of 
the jurisdiction of the University shall be compulsorily affiliated to 
the University, and affiliation shall be granted by the University 
only to such

<pagefootnote><pagenum>152</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Colleges or Institutions as may agree to accept the Statutes and Ordi- 
nances.


</section>

<section><tid>802010</tid>
<number>3</number>Any College or Institution admitted to the privileges of the 
University shall cease to be associated with, or be admitted to the 
privileges of any other University.

</section>

<section><tid>938919</tid>
<number>4</number>No College or Institution situated within the local limits of 
the jurisdiction of the University, but not admitted to its 
privileges, shall be associated with, or be admitted to the privileges 
of, any other University except with the previous approval of the 
Government of the State in which, or the Administrator of the Union 
territory in Which, such College or Institution is situate.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>739757</tid>
<number>7</number>University open to all classes, castes and creed. The 
University shall be open to persons of either sex and of whatever 
race, creed, caste, or class, and it shall not be lawful for the 
University to adopt or impose on any person any test whatsoever of 
religious belief or profession in order to entitle him to be admitted 
therein, as a teacher or student, or to hold any office therein, or to 
graduate thereat:
Provided that nothing in this section shall be deemed to prevent 
the University from making special provisions for admission of 
students of the weaker sections of the people in the North- Eastern 
region and, in particular, of the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled 
Tribes.



</article>



<article><tid>1752110</tid>
<number> 8</number> Visitor.
<section><tid>1499813</tid>
<number>1</number>The President of India shall be the Visitor of  
the University.

</section>

<section><tid>1563788</tid>
<number>2</number>The, Visitor shall have the right to cause an inspection to 
be made by such person or persons as he may direct, of the University, 
its buildings, laboratories and equipment, and of any College or 
Institution maintained by the University or admitted to its 
privileges; and also of the examinations, teaching and other work 
conducted or done by the University and to cause an inquiry to be made 
in like manner in respect of any matter connected with the 
administration or finances of the University, Colleges or 
Institutions.

</section>

<section><tid>935408</tid>
<number>3</number>The Visitor shall, in every case, give notice of his 
intention to cause an inspection or inquiry to be made,-

<subsection><tid>1032312</tid>
<number>a</number>to the University, if such inspection or inquiry is to be 
made in respect of the University, College or Institution 
maintained by it, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1424930</tid>
<number>b</number>to the management of the College or Institution, if the 
inspection or inquiry is to be made in respect of a College 
or an Institution admitted to the privileges of the 
University,
and the University or the management, as the case may be, shall have 
the right to make such representations to the Visitor, as it may 
consider necessary.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1435333</tid>
<number>4</number>After considering the representations, if any, made by the 
University or the management, as the case may be, the Visitor may 
cause to be made such inspection or inquiry as is referred to in sub- 
section (2).

</section>

<section><tid>278223</tid>
<number>5</number>Where any inspection or inquiry has been caused to be made by 
the Visitor, the University or the management, as the case may be, 
shall be entitled to appoint a representative who shall have the right 
to be present and be heard at such inspection or inquiry.

</section>

<section><tid>463659</tid>
<number>6</number>The Visitor may, if the inspection or inquiry is made in 
respect of the University or any College or Institution maintained by 
it, address the Vice- Chancellor with reference to the result of such 
inspection or inquiry, and the Vice- Chancellor shall communicate to 
the Executive Council the views of the Visitor with such advice as the 
Visitor may be pleased to offer upon the action to be taken thereon.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>153</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1717638</tid>
<number>7</number>The Visitor may, if the inspection or inquiry is made in 
respect of any College or Institution admitted to the privileges of 
the University, address the management concerned through the Vice- 
Chancellor with reference to the result of such inspection or inquiry, 
his views thereon and such advice as he may be pleased to offer upon 
the action to be taken thereon.

</section>

<section><tid>1298847</tid>
<number>8</number>The Executive Council or the management, as the case may be, 
shall communicate through the Vice- Chancellor to the Visitor such ac- 
tion, if any, as it is proposed to take or has been taken upon the 
result of such inspection or inquiry.

</section>

<section><tid>930387</tid>
<number>9</number>Where the Executive Council or the management does not within 
reasonable time take action to the satisfaction of the Visitor, the 
Visitor may after considering any explanation furnished or 
representation made by the Executive Council or management, issue such 
directions as he may think, fit and the Executive Council or 
management, as the case may be shall comply with such directions.

</section>

<section><tid>179328</tid>
<number>10</number>Without prejudice to the foregoing provisions of this 
section, the Visitor may, by order in writing, annul any proceeding of 
the University which is not in conformity with this Act, the Status or 
Ordinances:
Provided that before making any such order, he shall call upon 
the University to show cause why such an order should not be made, 
and, if any cause is' shown within a reasonable time, he shall 
consider the same.


</section>

<section><tid>1865633</tid>
<number>11</number>The Visitor shall have such other powers as may be 
prescribed by the Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1702017</tid>
<number>9</number>Chief Rector. The Governor of the States of Meghalaya and 
Nagaland shall be the Chief Rector of the University.




</article>



<article><tid>1851283</tid>
<number> 11</number> The Chancellor.
<section><tid>950622</tid>
<number>1</number>The Chancellor shall be appointed by the  
Visitor in such manner as may be prescribed by the Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>839507</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chancellor shall, by virtue of his office, be the Head of 
the University.

</section>

<section><tid>661376</tid>
<number>3</number>The Chancellor shall, if present, preside at the convocations 
of the University held for conferring degrees.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>880343</tid>
<number> 12</number> The Vice- Chancellor.
<section><tid>430918</tid>
<number>1</number>The Vice- Chancellor shall be  
appointed by the Visitor in such manner as may be prescribed by the 
Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>1560683</tid>
<number>2</number>The Vice- Chancellor shall be the principal executive and 
academic officer of the University, and shall exercise general 
supervision and control over the affairs of the University and give 
effect to the decisions of all the authorities of the University.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>154</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1730431</tid>
<number>3</number>The Vice- Chancellor may, if he is of opinion that immediate 
action is necessary on any matter, exercise any power conferred on any 
authority of the University by or under this Act and shall report to 
such authority the action taken by him on such matter:
Provided that if the authority concerned is of opinion that such 
action ought not to have been taken, it may refer the matter to the 
Visitor whose decision thereon shall be final:

Provided further that any person in the service of the University 
who is aggrieved by the action taken by the Vice- Chancellor under this 
subsection shall have the right to appeal against such action to the 
Executive Council within three months from the date on which decision 
on such action is communicated to him and thereupon the Executive 
Council may confirm, modify or reverse the action taken by the Vice- 
Chancellor.


</section>

<section><tid>1218941</tid>
<number>4</number>The Vice- Chancellor shall exercise such other powers and 
perform such other functions as may be prescribed by the Statutes or 
Ordinances.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1773208</tid>
<number>13</number>The Pro- Vice- Chancellors. Every Pro- Vice- Chancellor shall be 
appointed in such manner and shall exercise such powers and perform 
such duties, as may be prescribed by the Statutes.


</article>



<article><tid>1232410</tid>
<number>14</number>Deans of Schools. Every Dean of a School shall be appointed 
in such manner and shall exercise such powers and perform such duties 
as may be prescribed by the Statutes.


</article>



<article><tid>1349664</tid>
<number> 15</number> The Registrar.
<section><tid>1595684</tid>
<number>1</number>The Registrar shall be appointed in such  
manner as may be prescribed by the Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>1274061</tid>
<number>2</number>The Registrar shall have the power to enter into agreements, 
sign documents and authenticate records on behalf of the University 
and shall exercise such other powers and perform such other duties as 
may be prescribed by the Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>137088</tid>
<number>16</number>The Finance Officer. The Finance Officer shall be appointed 
in such manner and shall exercise such powers and perform such duties 
as may be prescribed by the Statutes.


</article>



<article><tid>908125</tid>
<number>17</number>Other officers. The manner of appointment and powers and 
duties of other officers of the University shall be prescribed by the 
Statutes.


</article>



<article><tid>512988</tid>
<number> 18</number> Authorities of the University. The following shall be the 
authorities of the University:-
<section><tid>1747270</tid>
<number>1</number>The Court;

</section>

<section><tid>804564</tid>
<number>2</number>The Executive Council;

</section>

<section><tid>1197047</tid>
<number>3</number>The Academic Council;

</section>

<section><tid>1948099</tid>
<number>4</number>The Board of Schools; and

</section>

<section><tid>372629</tid>
<number>5</number>Such other authorities as may be declared by the 
Statutes to be authorities of the University.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>393935</tid>
<number> 19</number> The Court.
<section><tid>1955826</tid>
<number>1</number>The constitution of the Court and the term of  
office of its members shall be prescribed by the Statutes.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>155</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1841968</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Court shall have 
the following powers and functions, namely:-

<subsection><tid>174982</tid>
<number>a</number>to review, from time to time, the broad policies and pro- 
grammes of the University and to suggest measures for the 
improvement and development of the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>521940</tid>
<number>b</number>to consider and pass resolutions on the annual report and 
the annual accounts of the University and the audit report on 
such accounts;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>683426</tid>
<number>c</number>to advise the Visitor in respect of any matter which may 
be referred to it for advice; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>804548</tid>
<number>d</number>to perform such other functions as may be prescribed by 
the Statutes.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1606765</tid>
<number> 20</number> The Executive Council.
<section><tid>1154121</tid>
<number>1</number>The Executive Council shall be the  
principal executive body of the University.

</section>

<section><tid>1047331</tid>
<number>2</number>The constitution of the Executive Council, the term of office 
of its members and its powers and duties shall be prescribed by the 
Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1573937</tid>
<number> 21</number> The Academic Council.
<section><tid>15213</tid>
<number>1</number>The Academic Council shall be the  
principal academic body of the University and shall, subject to the 
provisions of this Act, the Statutes and Ordinances, co- ordinate and 
exercise general supervision over the academic policies of the 
University.

</section>

<section><tid>1574836</tid>
<number>2</number>The constitution of the Academic Council, the term of office 
of its members and its powers and duties shall be prescribed by the 
Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>291110</tid>
<number>22</number>Other authorities of the University. The constitution, powers 
and functions of the Boards of Schools and of such other authorities 
as may be declared by the Statute' s to be authorities of the 
University, shall be prescribed by the Statutes.


</article>



<article><tid>512952</tid>
<number> 23</number> Planning Board.
<section><tid>796951</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be constituted a Planning  
Board of the University which shall advise generally on the planning 
and development of the University and keep under review the standard 
of education and research in the University.

</section>

<section><tid>1044966</tid>
<number>2</number>The Planning Board shall consist of-

<subsection><tid>800388</tid>
<number>a</number>the Vice- Chancellor, who shall be the Chairman, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>196312</tid>
<number>b</number>not more than eight persons of high academic standing who 
shall be appointed in such manner as, may be prescribed by 
the Statutes.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>361928</tid>
<number>3</number>The Visitor may determine a date with effect from which the 
Planning Board shall stand dissolved.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>401554</tid>
<number> 24</number> Power to make Statutes. Subject to the provisions of this 
Act, the Statutes may provide for all or any of the following Matters, 
namely:-
<section><tid>1505917</tid>
<number>a</number>the constitution, powers and functions of the authorities 
and other bodies of the University, as may be constituted 
from time to time;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>156</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1263219</tid>
<number>b</number>the election and continuance in office of the members of 
the said authorities and bodies, the filling of vacancies of 
members, and all other matters relative to those authorities 
and other bodies for which it may be necessary or desirable 
to provide;

</section>

<section><tid>1922723</tid>
<number>c</number>the appointment, powers and duties of the officers of the 
University and their emoluments;

</section>

<section><tid>235165</tid>
<number>d</number>the appointment of teachers of the University and other 
academic staff and their emoluments;

</section>

<section><tid>1046234</tid>
<number>e</number>the appointment of teachers and other academic staff 
working in a other University or organisation for a specified 
period for undertaking a joint project;

</section>

<section><tid>515474</tid>
<number>f</number>the conditions of service of employees including 
provision for pension, insurance and provident fund, the 
manner of termination of service and disciplinary action;

</section>

<section><tid>683684</tid>
<number>g</number>the principles governing seniority of service of 
employees;

</section>

<section><tid>1846540</tid>
<number>h</number>the procedure for arbitration in cases of dispute between 
employees or students and the University;

</section>

<section><tid>646056</tid>
<number>i</number>the procedure for appeal to the Executive Council by any 
employee or student against the action of any officer or 
authority of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>805474</tid>
<number>j</number>the establishment and recognition of Student' s Union or 
associations of teachers, academic staff or other employees;

</section>

<section><tid>142367</tid>
<number>k</number>the participation of students in the affairs of the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>443649</tid>
<number>l</number>the conferment of honorary degrees;

</section>

<section><tid>1025943</tid>
<number>m</number>the withdrawal of degrees, diplomas, certificates and 
other academic distinctions;

</section>

<section><tid>397539</tid>
<number>n</number>the institution of fellowships, scholarships, 
studentships, medals and prizes;

</section>

<section><tid>1617252</tid>
<number>o</number>the maintenance of discipline among the students;

</section>

<section><tid>544469</tid>
<number>p</number>the establishment and abolition of Schools. Departments. 
Halls, Colleges and Institutions;

</section>

<section><tid>702999</tid>
<number>q</number>the conditions under which Colleges and Institutions may 
be admitted to the privileges of the University and the 
withdrawal of such privileges;

</section>

<section><tid>39965</tid>
<number>r</number>The delegation of powers vested in the authorities or 
officers of the University; and

</section>

<section><tid>177220</tid>
<number>s</number>all other matters which by this Act are to be, or may be, 
provided by the Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1380965</tid>
<number> 25</number> Statutes how made.
<section><tid>1784570</tid>
<number>1</number>The first Statutes are those set out  
in the Schedule.

</section>

<section><tid>301709</tid>
<number>2</number>The Executive Council may, from time to time, make new or 
additional Statutes or may amend or repeal the Statutes referred to in 
subsection (1):
Provided that the Executive Council shall not make, amend or 
repeal any Statute affecting the status, powers or constitution of any 
authority


<pagefootnote><pagenum>157</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

of the University until such authority has been given an opportunity 
of expressing an opinion in writing on the proposed changes, and any 
opinion so expressed shall be considered by the Executive Council.


</section>

<section><tid>411509</tid>
<number>3</number>Every new Statute or addition to the Statutes or any 
amendment or repeal of a Statute shall require the approval of the 
Visitor who may assent thereto or withhold assent or remit to the 
Executive Council for consideration.

</section>

<section><tid>203619</tid>
<number>4</number>A new Statute or a Statute amending or repealing an existing 
Statute shall have no validity unless it has been assented to by the 
Visitor.

</section>

<section><tid>1284372</tid>
<number>5</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing sub- 
sections, the Visitor may make new or additional Statutes or amend or 
repeal the Statutes referred to in sub- section (1) during the period 
of three years immediately after the commencement of this Act:
Provided that the Visitor may, on the expiry of the said period 
of three years make, within one year from the date of such expiry, 
such detailed Statutes as he may consider necessary and such detailed 
Statutes shall be laid before both Houses of Parliament.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>32827</tid>
<number> 26</number> Ordinances.
<section><tid>1804233</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act and the  
Statutes, the Ordinances may provide for all or any of the following 
matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>208694</tid>
<number>a</number>the admission of students to the University and their 
enrolment as such;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>665027</tid>
<number>b</number>the courses of study to be laid down for all degrees, 
diplomas and certificates of the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1003146</tid>
<number>c</number>the medium of instruction and examination;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>274547</tid>
<number>d</number>the award of degrees, diplomas, certificates and other 
academic distinctions, the qualifications for the same and 
the means to be taken relating to the granting and obtaining 
of the same;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1897037</tid>
<number>e</number>the fees to be charged for courses of study in the 
University and for admission to the examinations, degrees and 
diplomas of the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>175020</tid>
<number>f</number>the conditions of award of fellowships, scholarships, 
student ships, medals and prizes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1850902</tid>
<number>g</number>the conduct of examinations, including the term of office 
and of appointment and the duties of examining bodies, 
examiners and moderators;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>413628</tid>
<number>h</number>the conditions of residence of the students of the 
University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1257916</tid>
<number>i</number>the special arrangements, if any, which may be made for 
the residence, discipline and teaching of women students and 
the prescribing of special courses of studies for them;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1357462</tid>
<number>j</number>the appointment and emoluments of employees other than 
those for whom provision has been made in the Statutes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1341385</tid>
<number>k</number>the establishment of Centres of Studies, Boards of 
Studies, Special Centres, specialised laboratories and other 
Committees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>383540</tid>
<number>l</number>the manner of co- operation and collaboration with other 
Universities and authorities including learned bodies or 
associations;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>158</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1364362</tid>
<number>m</number>the creation, composition and functions of any other body 
which is considered necessary for improving the academic life 
of the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1317065</tid>
<number>n</number>such other terms and conditions of service of teachers 
and other academic staff as are not prescribed by the 
Statutes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1788460</tid>
<number>o</number>the management of Colleges and Institutions established 
by the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1901301</tid>
<number>p</number>the supervision and management of Colleges and 
Institutions admitted to the privileges of the University; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>41282</tid>
<number>q</number>all other matters which by this Act or the Statutes may 
be provided for by the Ordinances.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>455061</tid>
<number>2</number>The first Ordinances shall be made by the Vice- Chancellor 
with the previous approval of the Central Government and the 
Ordinances so made may be amended, repealed or added to at any time by 
the Executive Council in the manner prescribed by the Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>576000</tid>
<number>27</number>Regulations. The authorities of the University may make 
Regulations consistent with this Act, the Statutes and the Ordinances 
for the conduct of their own business and that of the Committees 
appointed by them and not provided for by this Act, the Statutes or 
the Ordinances in the manner prescribed by the Statutes.


</article>



<article><tid>1887466</tid>
<number> 28</number> Annual report.
<section><tid>1589250</tid>
<number>1</number>The annual report of the University shall  
be prepared under the direction of the Executive Council and shall be 
submitted to the Court on or after such date as may be prescribed by 
the Statutes and the Court shall consider the report in its annual 
meeting.

</section>

<section><tid>1799051</tid>
<number>2</number>The Court shall submit the annual report to the Visitor along 
with its comments, if any.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>531963</tid>
<number> 29</number> Annual accounts.
<section><tid>535010</tid>
<number>1</number>The annual accounts and balance- sheet of  
the University shall be prepared under the directions of the Executive 
Council and shall once at least every year and at intervals of not 
more than fifteen months be audited by the Comptroller and Auditor- 
General of India.

</section>

<section><tid>411899</tid>
<number>2</number>The annual accounts when audited shall be published in the 
Gazette of India and a copy of the accounts together with the report 
of the Comptroller and Auditor- General shall be submitted to the Court 
and the Visitor along with the observations of the Executive Council.

</section>

<section><tid>1270338</tid>
<number>3</number>Any observations made by the Visitor on the annual accounts 
shall be brought to the notice of the Court and the observations of 
the Court, if any, shall, after being considered by the Executive 
Council, be submitted to the Visitor.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>218759</tid>
<number> 30</number> Conditions of service of employees.
<section><tid>661310</tid>
<number>1</number>Every employee shall  
be appointed under a written contract which shall be lodged with the 
University and a copy of which shall be furnished to the employee 
concerned.

</section>

<section><tid>595638</tid>
<number>2</number>Any dispute arising out of a contract between the University 
and any employee shall, at the request of the employee, be referred to 
a Tribunal of Arbitration consisting of one member appointed by the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>159</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Executive Council, one member nominated by the employee concerned and 
an umpire appointed by the Visitor. The decision of the Tribunal 
shall be final, and no suit shall lie in any civil court in respect of 
the matters decided by the Tribunal. Exery such request shall be 
deemed to be a submission to arbitration upon the terms of this 
section within the meaning of the Arbitration Act, <year>1940</year>. (2 of <year>1940</year>)




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1681085</tid>
<number> 31</number> Procedure of appeal and arbitration in disciplinary cases 
against students.
<section><tid>34706</tid>
<number>1</number>Any student or candidate for an examination  
whose name has been removed from the rolls of the University by the 
orders or resolution of the Vice- Chancellor, Discipline Committee or 
Examination Committee, as the case may be, and who has been debarred 
from appearing at the examinations of the University for more than one 
year, may, within ten days of the date of receipt of such orders or 
copy of such resolution by him, appeal to the Executive Council and 
the Executive Council may confirm, modify or reverse the decision of 
the Vice- Chancellor or the Committee, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1190816</tid>
<number>2</number>Any dispute arising out of any disciplinary action taken by 
the University against a student shall, at the request of such 
student, be referred to a Tribunal of Arbitration and the provisions 
of sub- section (2) of section 30 shall, as far as may be, apply to a 
reference made under this sub- section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1051378</tid>
<number>32</number>Right to appeal. Every employee or student of the University 
or of a College or Institution shall, notwithstanding anything 
contained in this Act, have a right to appeal, within such time as may 
be prescribed by the Statutes, to the Executive Council against the 
decision of any officer or authority of the University or of the 
Principal or the management of any college or Institution, as the case 
may be, and thereupon the Executive Council may confirm, modify or 
reverse the decision appealed against.


</article>



<article><tid>300069</tid>
<number> 33</number> Provident and pension funds.
<section><tid>131652</tid>
<number>1</number>The University shall  
constitute for the benefit of its employees such pension or provident 
fund or provide such insurance schemes as it may deem fit in such 
manner and subject to such conditions as may be prescribed by the 
Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>258635</tid>
<number>2</number>Where such provident or pension fund has been so constituted, 
the Central Government may declare that the provisions of the 
Provident Funds Act, <year>1925</year>, (19 of <year>1925</year>) shall apply to such fund, as 
if it were a Government provident fund.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1933933</tid>
<number>34</number>Disputes as to constitution of University authorities and 
bodies. If any question arises as to whether any person has been duly 
elected or appointed as, or is entitled to be, a member of any 
authority or other body of the University, the matter shall be 
referred to the Visitor whose decision thereon shall be final.


</article>



<article><tid>1892286</tid>
<number>35</number>Constitution of Committees. Where any authority of the 
University is given power by this Act or the Statutes to appoint 
Committees, such Committees shall, save as otherwise provided, consist 
of the members of the authority concerned and of such other persons 
 (if any) as the authority in each case may think fit.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>160</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>867809</tid>
<number>36</number>Filling of casual vacancies. All casual vacancies among the 
members (other than ex- officio members) of any authority or other body 
of the University shall be filled as soon as conveniently may be, by 
the person or body who appointed elected or co- opted the member whose 
place has become vacant and the person appointed, elected or co- opted 
to a casual vacancy shall be a member of such authority or body for 
the residue of the term for which the person whose place he fills 
would have been a member.


</article>



<article><tid>909195</tid>
<number>37</number>Proceedings of University authorities of bodies not 
invalidated by vacancies. No act or proceedings of any authority or 
other body of the University shall be invalidated merely by reason of 
the existence' of a vacancy or vacancies among its members.


</article>



<article><tid>634938</tid>
<number>38</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit or other 
legal proceedings shall lie against Any officer or employee of the 
University for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be 
done in pursuance of any of the provisions of this Act, the Statutes 
or Ordinances.


</article>



<article><tid>440049</tid>
<number>39</number>Mode of proof of University record. A copy of any receipt, 
application, notice, order, proceeding, resolution of any authority or 
Committee of the University, or other documents in possession of the 
University, or any entry in any register duly maintained by the 
University, if certified by the Registrar, shall be received as prima 
facie evidence of such receipt, application, notice, order, proceeding 
or resolution, documents or the existence of entry in the register and 
shall be admitted as evidence of the matters and transactions' therein 
where the original thereof would, if produced, have been admissible in 
evidence, notwithstanding anything contained in the Indian Evidence 
Act, <year>1872</year> (1 of <year>1872</year>) or in any other law for the time being in 
force.


</article>



<article><tid>818257</tid>
<number>40</number>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in 
giving effect to the provisions of this the Central Government may, by 
order published in the official Gazette, make such Provisions, not 
inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as appear to it to be 
necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty:
Provided that no such order shall be made under this section 
after the expiry of three years from the commencement of this Act.



</article>



<article><tid>901935</tid>
<number> 41</number> Transitional provisions. Notwithstanding anything contained 
in this Act and the Statutes-
<section><tid>1815353</tid>
<number>a</number>the first Chancellor and the first Vice- Chancellor shall 
be' appointed by the Visitor and each of the said officers 
shall hold office for a term of five years;

</section>

<section><tid>1555413</tid>
<number>b</number>the first Registrar and the first Finance Officer shall 
be appointed by the Visitor and each of the said officers 
shall hold office for a term of three years;

</section>

<section><tid>448464</tid>
<number>c</number>the first Court and the first Executive Council shall 
consist of not more than thirty members and eleven members 
respectively, who shall be nominated by the Visitor and shall 
hold office for a term of three years;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>161</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>362072</tid>
<number>d</number>the first Academic Council shall be constituted on the 
expiry of a period of six months from the commencement of 
this Act and during the said period of six months, the powers 
of the Academic Council shall be performed by the Planning 
Board constituted under section 23;

</section>

<section><tid>328642</tid>
<number>e</number>the first Academic Council shall consist of not more than 
twenty- one members, who shall be nominated by the Visitor and 
shall hold office for a term of three years:
Provided that if any vacancy occurs in the above offices or 
authorities, the same shall be filled by appointment or nomination, as 
the case may be, by the Visitor, and the, person so appointed or 
nominated shall hold office for so long as the officer or member in 
whose place he is appointed or nominated would have held office, if 
such vacancy had not occurred.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>293771</tid>
<number>42</number>Completion of courses of students in Colleges or Institutions 
affiliated to the University. Notwithstanding anything contained in 
this Act, or in the Statutes or the Ordinances, any student of a 
College or Institution, who, immediately before the admission of such 
College or Institution to the privileges of the North- Eastern Hill 
University, was studying for a degree, diploma or certificate of the 
Gauhati University, shall be permitted by the North- Eastern Hill 
University to complete his course for that degree, diploma or 
certificate, as the case may be, and the North- Eastern Hill University 
and such College or Institution shall provide for the instruction and 
examination of such student in accordance with the syllabus of studies 
of the Gauhati University.


</article>



<article><tid>1517867</tid>
<number> 1</number> The Vice- Chancellor.
<section><tid>575587</tid>
<number>1</number>The Vice- Chancellor shall be a whole-  
time salaried officer of the University.

</section>

<section><tid>1413304</tid>
<number>2</number>The Vice- Chancellor shall hold office for a term of five 
years from the date on which he enters upon his office and shall be 
eligible for reappointment for not more than another term:
Provided that notwithstanding the expiry of the said period of 
five years, he shall continue in office until his successor is 
appointed and enters upon his office:

Provided further that the Visitor may direct that a Vice- 
Chancellor, whose term of office has expired, shall continue in office 
for such period, not exceeding a total period of one year, as may be 
specified in the direction.


</section>

<section><tid>1214067</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in clause (2), a person 
appointed as Vice- Chancellor shall, if he completes the age of sixty- 
five years during the term of his office or any extension thereof, 
retire from office.

</section>

<section><tid>885720</tid>
<number>4</number>The emoluments and other terms and conditions of service of 
the Vice- Chancellor shall be as follows:-

<subsection><tid>1685729</tid>
<number>i</number>There shall be paid to the Vice- Chancellor a salary of 
two thousand and five hundred rupees per mensem and he shall 
be entitled, without payment of rent, to use a furnished 
residence throughout his term of office and no charge shall 
fall on the Vice- Chancellor personally in respect of the 
maintenance of such residence.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1902520</tid>
<number>ii</number>The Vice- Chancellor shall not be entitled to the 
benefits of the University Provident Fund:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>162</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Provided that where an employee of--


<subsubsection><tid>1638862</tid>
<number>a</number>the University or College or Institution maintained by, 
or affiliated to, it; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1385579</tid>
<number>b</number>any other University or College or Institution maintained 
by, or affiliated to, that University,
is appointed as Vice- Chancellor, he shall be allowed to 
continue to contribute to the provident fund to which he is a 
subscriber, and the contribution of the University shall be 
limited to what he had been contributing immediately before 
his appointment as Vice- Chancellor.


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1678053</tid>
<number>iii</number>The Vice- Chancellor shall be entitled to travelling 
allowances at such rates as may be fixed by the Executive 
Council.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>89661</tid>
<number>iv</number>The Vice- Chancellor shall be entitled to leave on full 
pay for one- eleventh of the period spent by him on active 
service.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1793678</tid>
<number>v</number>The Vice- Chancellor shall also be entitled, on medical 
grounds or otherwise, to leave without pay for a period not 
exceeding three months during the term of his office:
Provided that such leave may be converted into leave on full pay 
to the extent to which he is entitled to leave under sub- clause (iv).


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>757192</tid>
<number>5</number>If the office of the Vice- Chancellor becomes vacant due to 
death, resignation or otherwise or if he is unable to perform his 
duties owing to absence, illness or any other cause, the Pro- Vice- 
Chancellor or if there is more than one Pro- Vice- Chancellor, the 
senior- most Pro- Vice- Chancellor, shall perform the duties of the Vice- 
Chancellor until a new Vice- Chancellor assumes office or until the 
existing Vice- Chancellor attends to the duties of his office, as the 
case may be:
Provided that if a Pro- Vice- Chancellor is not available, the 
seniormost Professor shall perform the duties of the Vice- Chancellor.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>526510</tid>
<number> 2</number> Powers and duties of the Vice- Chancellor.
<section><tid>1282617</tid>
<number>1</number>The Vice-  
Chancellor shall be ex- officio Chairman of the Court, the Executive 
Council, the Academic Council and the Finance Committee, and shall, in 
the absence of the Chancellor, preside at the Convocations of the 
University held for conferring degrees. The Vice- Chancellor shall be 
entitled to be present at, and to address, any meeting of any 
authority or other body of the University, but shall not be entitled 
to vote thereat unless he is a member of such authority or body.

</section>

<section><tid>63730</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be the duty of the Vice- Chancellor to see that this 
Act, these Statutes, the Ordinances and the Regulations are duly 
observed, and he shall have all powers necessary to ensure such 
observance.

</section>

<section><tid>945577</tid>
<number>3</number>The Vice- Chancellor shall have the power to convene or cause 
to be convened meetings of the Court, the Executive Council, the 
Academic Council and the Finance Committee.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1620829</tid>
<number> 3</number> Pro- Vice- Chancellor.
<section><tid>1237794</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Pro- Vice- Chancellor shall be  
appointed by the Executive Council on the recommendations of the Vice- 
Chancellor:
Provided that where the recommendation of the Vice- Chancellor is 
not accepted by the Executive Council, the matter shall be referred to 
the Visitor who may either appoint the person recommended by the Vice- 
Chancellor or ask the Vice- Chancellor to recommend another person to 
the Executive Council:

Provided further that the Executive Council may, on the recommen- 
dation of the Vice- Chancellor, appoint a Professor to discharge the 
duties of a Pro- Vice- Chancellor in addition to his own duties as a 
Professor.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>163</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1531319</tid>
<number>2</number>The term of office of a Pro- Vice- Chancellor shall be such as 
may be decided by the Executive Council, but it shall not in any case 
exceed five years or until the expiration of the term of office of the 
Vice- Chancellor, whichever is earlier, and he shall be eligible for 
reappointment:
Provided that a Pro- Vice- Chancellor shall retire on attaining the 
age of sixty- five years.


</section>

<section><tid>1708918</tid>
<number>3</number>The emoluments and other terms and conditions of service of a 
Pro- Vice- Chancellor shall be such as may be prescribed by the 
Ordinances.

</section>

<section><tid>794307</tid>
<number>4</number>A Pro- Vice- Chancellor shall assist the Vice- Chancellor in 
respect of such matters as may be specified by the Vice- Chancellor in 
this behalf, from time to time, and shall also exercise such powers 
and perform such duties as may be assigned or delegated to him by the 
Vice- Chancellor.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>529127</tid>
<number> 4</number> Registrar.
<section><tid>137854</tid>
<number>1</number>The Registrar shall be a whole- time salaried  
officer of the University.

</section>

<section><tid>638196</tid>
<number>2</number>The emoluments and other terms and conditions of service of 
the Registrar shall be such as may be prescribed by the Ordinances:
Provided that the Registrar shall retire on attaining the age of 
sixty years:

Provided further that a Registrar shall, notwithstanding his 
attaining the age of sixty years, continue in office until his 
successor is appointed and enters upon his office or until the expiry 
of a period of one year Whichever is earlier.


</section>

<section><tid>1012903</tid>
<number>3</number>When the office of the Registrar is vacant or when the 
Registrar is, by reason of illness, absence or any other cause, unable 
to perform the duties of his office, the duties of the office shall be 
performed by such person as the Vice- Chancellor may appoint for the 
purpose.

</section>

<section><tid>1695986</tid>
<number>4</number> (a) The Registrar shall have power to take disciplinary 
action against such of the employees, excluding teachers and academic 
staff as may be specified in the orders of the Executive Council and 
to suspend them pending inquiry, to administer warnings to them or to 
impose on them the penalty of censure or the withholding' of 
increment:
Provided that no such penalty shall be imposed unless the person 
concerned has been given a reasonable opportunity of showing cause 
against the action proposed to be taken in regard to him.


<subsection><tid>869284</tid>
<number>b</number>An appeal shall lie to the vice- Chancellor against any order 
of the Registrar imposing any of the penalties specified in sub- clause 
 (a).

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1300008</tid>
<number>c</number>In a case where the inquiry discloses that a punishment 
beyond the powers of the Registrar is called for, the Registrar shall, 
upon conclusion of the inquiry, make a report to the Vice- Chancellor 
along with his recommendations:
Provided that an appeal shall lie to the Executive Council 
against an order of the Vice- Chancellor imposing any penalty.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>256435</tid>
<number>5</number>The Registrar shall be ex- officio Secretary of the Executive 
Council, the Academic Council and the Boards of Schools, but shall not 
be deemed to, be a member of any of these authorities. He' shall be 
ex- officio Member- Secretary of the Court.

</section>

<section><tid>373069</tid>
<number>6</number>It shall be the duty of the Registrar,---

<subsection><tid>108058</tid>
<number>a</number>to be the custodian of the records, the common seal and 
such

<pagefootnote><pagenum>164</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

other property of the University as the Executive Council 
shall commit to his charge;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1923633</tid>
<number>b</number>to issue all notices convening meetings of the Court, the 
Executive Council, the Academic Council, the Boards of 
Schools, the Boards of Studies, the Boards of Examiners and 
of any Committees appointed by the authorities of the 
University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1253582</tid>
<number>c</number>to keep the minutes of all the meetings of the Court, the 
Executive Council, the Academic Council, the Boards of 
Schools and of any Committees appointed by the authorities of 
the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>721806</tid>
<number>d</number>to conduct the official correspondence of the Court, the 
Executive Council and the Academic Council;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>673805</tid>
<number>e</number>to arrange for and superintend the examinations of the 
University in accordance with the manner prescribed by the 
Ordinances;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1378468</tid>
<number>f</number>to supply to the Visitor, copies of the agenda of the 
meetings of the authorities of the University as soon as they 
are issued and the minutes of such meetings;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1712372</tid>
<number>g</number>to represent the University in suits or proceedings by or 
against the University, sign powers of attorney and verify 
pleadings or depute his representative for the purpose; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>598755</tid>
<number>h</number>to perform such other duties as may be specified in these 
Statutes, the Ordinance' s or the Regulations or as may be 
required, from time to time, by the Executive Council or the 
Vice- Chancellor.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>973485</tid>
<number> 5</number> Finance Officer.
<section><tid>1667596</tid>
<number>1</number>The Finance Officer shall be a whole- time  
salaried officer of the University.

</section>

<section><tid>1459390</tid>
<number>2</number>The emoluments and other terms and conditions of service of 
the Finance Officer shall be such as may be prescribed by the 
Ordinances:
Provided that a Finance Officer shall retire on attaining the age 
of sixty years:

Provided further that the Finance Officer shall, notwithstanding 
his attaining the age of sixty years, continue in office until his 
successor is appointed and enters upon his office or until the expiry 
of a period of one year whichever is earlier.


</section>

<section><tid>1469284</tid>
<number>3</number>When the office of the Finance Officer is vacant or when the 
Finance Officer is, by reason of illness, absence or any other cause, 
unable to perform the duties of his office, the duties of the office 
shall be performed by such person as the Vice- Chancellor may appoint 
for the purpose.

</section>

<section><tid>1552530</tid>
<number>4</number>The Finance Officer shall be ex- officio Secretary of the 
Finance Committee, but shall not be deemed to be a member of such 
Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>577463</tid>
<number>5</number>The Finance Officer shall-

<subsection><tid>1872907</tid>
<number>a</number>exercise general supervision over the funds of the 
University and shall advise it as regards its financial 
policy; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1105163</tid>
<number>b</number>perform such other financial functions as may be 
assigned to him by the Executive Council or as may be 
prescribed by these Statutes or the Ordinances:
Provided that the Finance Officer shall not incur any expenditure 
or make any investment exceeding ten thousand rupees without the 
previous approval of the Executive Council.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>58734</tid>
<number>6</number>Subject to the control of the Executive Council, the Finance 
Officer shall-

<subsection><tid>1364036</tid>
<number>a</number>hold and manage the property and investments of the 
University including trust and endowed property;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>165</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1718942</tid>
<number>b</number>ensure that the limits fixed by the Executive council for 
recurring and non- recurring expenditure for a year are not 
exceeded and that all moneys are expended on the purposes for 
which they are granted or allotted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1289820</tid>
<number>c</number>be responsible for the preparation of annual accounts and 
the budget of the University and for their presentation to 
the Executive Council;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1336670</tid>
<number>d</number>keep a constant watch on the state of the cash and bank 
balances and on the state of investments;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1918941</tid>
<number>e</number>watch the progress of the collection of revenue and 
advise on the methods of collection employed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>482452</tid>
<number>f</number>ensure that the registers of buildings, land, furniture 
and equipment are maintained up- to- date and that stock- 
checking is conducted, of equipment and other consumable 
materials in all offices, Special Centres, specialised 
laboratories, Colleges and Institutions maintained by the 
University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1612455</tid>
<number>g</number>call for explanation for unauthorised expenditure and for 
other financial irregularities and suggest disciplinary 
action against persons at fault; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1094951</tid>
<number>h</number>call for from any office, Centre, laboratory, College or 
Institution maintained by the University, any information or 
returns that he may consider necessary for the performance of 
his duties.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1551712</tid>
<number>7</number>The receipt of the Finance Officer or of the person or 
persons duly authorised in this behalf by the Executive Council for 
any money payable to the University shall be sufficient discharge for 
payment of such money.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1688461</tid>
<number> 6</number> Deans of Schools of Studies.
<section><tid>1982651</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Dean of a School of  
Studies shall be appointed by the Vice- Chancellor from among the 
Professors in the School for a period of three years and he shall be 
eligible for re- appointment,
Provided that a Dean on attaining the age of sixty years shall 
cease to hold office as such:

Provided further that if at any time there is no Professor in a 
School, the Vice- Chancellor, or a Pro- Vice- Chancellor if authorised by 
the Vice- Chancellor in this behalf, shall exercise the powers of the 
Dean of the school.


</section>

<section><tid>1322331</tid>
<number>2</number>When the office of the Dean is vacant or when the Dean is, by 
reason of illness, absence or any other cause, unable to perform the 
duties of his office, the duties of the office shall be performed by 
such person as the Vice- Chancellor may appoint for the purpose.

</section>

<section><tid>802010</tid>
<number>3</number>The Dean shall be the Head of the School and shall be 
responsible for the conduct and maintenance of the standards of 
teaching and research in the School The Dean shall have such other 
functions as may be prescribed by the Ordinances.

</section>

<section><tid>938919</tid>
<number>4</number>The Dean shall have the right to be present and to speak at 
any meeting of the Boards of Studies or Committees of the School, as 
the case may be, but shall not have the right to vote thereat unless 
he is a member thereof.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>739757</tid>
<number> 7</number> Heads of Departments.
<section><tid>1034238</tid>
<number>1</number>In the case of Departments which  
have more than one Professor, the Head of the Department shall be 
appointed by the Executive Council on the recommendation of the Vice- 
Chancellor from among the Professors.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>166</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1960951</tid>
<number>2</number>In the case of Departments where there is only one Professor, 
the Executive Council shall have the option to appoint, on the recom- 
mendation of the Vice- Chancellor, either the Professor or a Reader as 
the Head of the Department;
Provided that it shall be open to a Professor or Reader to 
decline the offer of appointment as the Head of the Department.


</section>

<section><tid>484844</tid>
<number>3</number>A person appointed as the Head of the Department shall hold 
office as such for a period of three years and shall be eligible for 
reappointment.

</section>

<section><tid>1464890</tid>
<number>4</number>A Head of a Department may resign his office at any time 
during his tenure of office.

</section>

<section><tid>1460818</tid>
<number>5</number>A Head of a Department shall perform such functions as may be 
prescribed by the Ordinances.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1752110</tid>
<number> 8</number> Deans of Students' Welfare.
<section><tid>1499813</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Dean of Students'  
Welfare shall be appointed from amongst the teachers of the 
University, not below the rank of a Reader, by the Executive Council 
on the recommendation of the Vice- Chancellor.

</section>

<section><tid>1563788</tid>
<number>2</number>Every Dean appointed under clause (1) shall be a whole- time 
officer and shall hold office for a term of three years and shall be 
eligible for re- appointment:
Provided that the Executive Council may, if it is considered 
necessary appoint, on the recommendation of the Vice- Chancellor, a 
teacher, not below the rank of a Reader, to discharge the duties of 
the Dean of Students' Welfare in addition to his duties as such 
teacher, and in such a case, the Executive Council may sanction a 
suitable allowance to be paid to him.


</section>

<section><tid>935408</tid>
<number>3</number>A person who is appointed as a Dean of Students' Welfare 
shall continue to hold his lien on his substantive post and shall be 
eligible to all the benefits that would have otherwise accrued to him, 
but for his appointment as the Dean of Students' Welfare.

</section>

<section><tid>1435333</tid>
<number>4</number>When the office of a Dean of Students' Welfare is vacant or 
when the Dean of Students' Welfare is, by reason of illness or absence 
or any other cause, unable to perform the duties of his office, the 
duties of the office shall be performed by such person as the Vice- 
Chancellor may appoint for the purpose.

</section>

<section><tid>278223</tid>
<number>5</number>The duties and powers of a Dean of Students' Welfare shall be 
prescribed by the Ordinances.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1702017</tid>
<number> 9</number> Proctors.
<section><tid>1994474</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Proctor shall be appointed by the  
Executive Council on the recommendation of the Vice- Chancellor and 
shall exercise such powers and perform such duties as may be assigned 
to him by the Vice- Chancellor.

</section>

<section><tid>882922</tid>
<number>2</number>Every Proctor shall hold office for a term of two years and 
shall be eligible for re- appointment.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1075936</tid>
<number> 10</number> Librarians.
<section><tid>240068</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Librarian shall be appointed by the  
Executive Council on the recommendation of a Selection Committee 
constituted for the purpose and he shall be a whole- time officer of 
the University.

</section>

<section><tid>1997234</tid>
<number>2</number>Every Librarian shall exercise such powers and perform such 
duties as may be assigned to him by the Executive Council.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1851283</tid>
<number> 11</number> Meetings of the Court.
<section><tid>950622</tid>
<number>1</number>An annual meeting of the Court  
shall be held on a date to be fixed by the Executive Council unless 
some other date has been fixed by the Court in respect of any year.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>167</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>839507</tid>
<number>2</number>At an annual meeting of the Court, a report on the working of 
the University during the previous year, together with a statement of 
the receipts and expenditure, the balance- sheet, as audited, and the 
financial estimates for the next year shall be presented.

</section>

<section><tid>661376</tid>
<number>3</number>A copy a the statement of receipts and expenditure, the 
balancesheet and the financial estimates referred to in clause (2) 
shall be sent to every member of the Court at least seven days before 
the date of the annual meeting.

</section>

<section><tid>1017965</tid>
<number>4</number>Twelve members of the Court shall form a quorum for a meeting 
of the Court.

</section>

<section><tid>1048023</tid>
<number>5</number>Special meetings of the Court may be convened by the 
Executive Council or the Vice- Chancellor, or, if there is no Vice- 
Chancellor, by a Pro- Vice- Chancellor, or if there is no Pro- Vice- 
Chancellor, by the Registrar.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>880343</tid>
<number>12</number>Quorum for meetings of the Executive Council. Five members of 
the Executive Council shall form a quorum for a meeting of the 
Executive Council.


</article>



<article><tid>1773208</tid>
<number> 13</number> Powers and functions of Executive Council.
<section><tid>352934</tid>
<number>1</number>The Executive  
Council shall have the management and administration of the revenue 
and property of the University and the conduct of all administrative 
affairs of the University not otherwise provided for.

</section>

<section><tid>685003</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act, these Statutes and the 
Ordinances, the Executive Council shall, in addition to. all other 
powers vested in it, have the following powers, namely:-

<subsection><tid>612179</tid>
<number>i</number>to create teaching and academic posts, to determine the 
number and emoluments of such posts and to define the duties 
and conditions of service of Professors, Readers, Lecturers 
and other academic staff and Principals of Colleges and 
Institutions maintained by the University:
Provided that no action shall be taken by the Executive 
Council in respect of the number, qualifications and the 
emoluments of teachers and academic staff otherwise than 
after consideration of the recommendations of the Academic 
Council;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1763107</tid>
<number>ii</number>to appoint such Professors, Readers, Lecturers and other 
academic staff, as may be necessary, and Principals of 
Colleges and Institutions maintained by the University on the 
recommendation of the Selection Committee constituted for the 
purpose and to fill up temporary vacancies therein;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1342502</tid>
<number>iii</number>to create administrative, ministerial and other 
necessary posts and to make appointments thereto in the 
manner prescribed by the Ordinances;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1619567</tid>
<number>iv</number>to grant leave of absence to any officer of the 
University, other than the Chancellor and the Vice- 
Chancellor, and to make necessary arrangements for the 
discharge of the functions of such officer during his 
absence;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1175888</tid>
<number>v</number>to regulate and enforce discipline among employees in 
accordance with these Statutes and the Ordinances:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>168</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1848203</tid>
<number>vi</number>to manage and regulate the finances, accounts, 
investments, property, business and all other administrative 
affairs of the University, and for that purpose, to appoint 
such agents as it may think fit;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>194231</tid>
<number>vii</number>to fix limits on the total recurring and the total non- 
recurring expenditure for a year on the recommendations of 
the Finance Committee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1636706</tid>
<number>viii</number>to invest any money belonging to the University, 
including any unapplied income, in such stocks, funds, shares 
or securities as it shall, from time to time, think fit, or 
in the purchase of immovable property in India, with the like 
powers of varying such investments from time to time;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1971188</tid>
<number>ix</number>to transfer or accept transfers of any movable or immov- 
able property on behalf of the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>664227</tid>
<number>x</number>to provide buildings, premises, furniture and apparatus 
and other means needed for carrying on the work of the 
University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>79438</tid>
<number>xi</number>to enter into, vary, carry out and cancel contracts on 
behalf of the University;

<subsubsection><tid>1884647</tid>
<number>xii</number>to entertain, adjudicate upon, and, if thought fit, to 
redress any grievances of the employees and students of the 
University, who may, for any reason feel aggrieved;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>982234</tid>
<number>xiii</number>to appoint examiners and moderators and, if necessary 
to remove them, and to fix their fees, emoluments and 
travelling and other allowances, after consulting the 
Academic Council;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1176307</tid>
<number>xiv</number>to select a common seal for the University and provide 
for the custody and use of such seal;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>914097</tid>
<number>xv</number>to make such special arrangements as may be necessary 
for the residence and discipline of women students;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>378019</tid>
<number>xvi</number>to delegate any of its powers to the Vice- Chancellor, 
the Pro- Vice- Chancellors, the Registrar or the Finance 
Officer or such other employee or authority of the University 
or to a Committee appointed by It as it may deem fit;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1561474</tid>
<number>xvii</number>to institute fellowships, scholarships, studentships, 
medals and prizes; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>871586</tid>
<number>xviii</number>to exercise such other powers and perform such other 
duties as may be conferred or imposed on it by this Act, or 
these Statutes.



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1232410</tid>
<number>14</number>Quorum for meetings of the Academic Council. Nine members of 
the Academic Council shall form a quorum for a meeting of the Academic 
Council.


</article>



<article><tid>1349664</tid>
<number> 15</number> Powers of the Academic Council. Subject to this Act, these 
Statutes and the Ordinances, the Academic Council shall, in addition 
to all other powers vested in it, have the following powers, namely:-
<section><tid>1878553</tid>
<number>a</number>to exercise general supervision over the academic 
policies of the University and to give directions regarding 
methods of

<pagefootnote><pagenum>169</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

instruction, co- operative teaching among Colleges and 
Institutions, evaluation of research or improvements in 
academic standards;


</section>

<section><tid>1574471</tid>
<number>b</number>to bring about inter- School co- ordination, to establish 
or appoint Committees or Boards, for taking up projects on an 
inter- School basis;

</section>

<section><tid>1525111</tid>
<number>c</number>to consider matters of general academic interest either 
on its own initiative or on a reference by a School or the 
Executive Council and to take appropriate action thereon; and

</section>

<section><tid>1163317</tid>
<number>d</number>to frame such regulations and rules consistent with 
these. Statutes and the Ordinances regarding the academic 
functioning of the University, discipline, residences, 
admissions, award of fellowships and studentships, fee 
concessions, corporate life and, attendance.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>137088</tid>
<number> 16</number> The Planning Board.
<section><tid>280388</tid>
<number>1</number>The members of the Planning Board  
shall be appointed by the Visitor and shall hold office for such 
period as he may determine.

</section>

<section><tid>1463890</tid>
<number>2</number>The Planning Board shall, in addition to all other powers 
vested in it by this Act, have the right to advise the Executive 
Council and the Academic Council on any academic matter.

</section>

<section><tid>1739490</tid>
<number>3</number>On the date determined by the Visitor under sub- section (3) 
of section 23, this Statute shall cease to have effect.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>908125</tid>
<number> 17</number> Schools of Studies and Departments.
<section><tid>848856</tid>
<number>1</number>The University shall  
have such Schools of Studies as may be specified by the Ordinances.

</section>

<section><tid>1511951</tid>
<number>2</number>Every School shall have a School Board. The members of the 
first School Board shall be nominated by the Executive Council and 
shall hold office for a period of three years.

</section>

<section><tid>534306</tid>
<number>3</number>The powers and functions of a School Board shall be 
prescribed by the Ordinances.

</section>

<section><tid>576231</tid>
<number>4</number>The conduct of the meetings of a School Board and the quorum 
required for such meetings shall be prescribed by the Ordinances.

</section>

<section><tid>354959</tid>
<number>5</number> (a) Each School shall consist of such Departments as may be 
assigned to it by the Ordinances.

<subsection><tid>103376</tid>
<number>b</number>No Department shall be established or abolished except by 
these Statutes:
Provided that the Executive Council may, on the recommendation of 
the Academic Council, establish Centres of Studies to which may be 
assigned such teachers of the University as the Executive Council may 
consider necessary.


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>772012</tid>
<number>c</number>Each Department shall consist of the following members, 
namely:-

<subsubsection><tid>1027504</tid>
<number>i</number>teachers of the Department;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>520236</tid>
<number>ii</number>persons conducting research in the, Department;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>170</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>495673</tid>
<number>iii</number>Dean of the School or Deans of, the Schools concerned;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>7480</tid>
<number>iv</number>honorary Professors, if any, attached to the Department; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1057830</tid>
<number>v</number>such other persons as may be members of the Department in 
accordance with the provisions of the Ordinances.



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>512988</tid>
<number> 18</number> Boards of Studies.
<section><tid>1747270</tid>
<number>1</number>Each Department shall have two Boards  
of Studies, one for Post- graduate Studies and the other for Under- 
graduate Studies.

</section>

<section><tid>804564</tid>
<number>2</number>The constitution of a Board of Post- graduate Studies and the 
term of office of its emmbers shall be prescribed by the Ordinances.

</section>

<section><tid>1197047</tid>
<number>3</number>The functions of a Board of Post- graduate Studies shall be to 
approve subjects for research for various degrees and other 
requirements of research degrees and to recommend to the concerned 
School Board in the manner prescribed by the Ordinances:-

<subsection><tid>1206596</tid>
<number>a</number>courses of studies and appointment of examiners for post- 
graduate courses, but excluding research degrees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1728228</tid>
<number>b</number>appointment of supervisors of research; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>446630</tid>
<number>c</number>measures for the improvement of the standard of post- 
graduate teaching and research.
Provided that the above functions of a Board of Post- graduate 
Studies shall, during the period of three years immediately after the 
commencement of this Act, be performed by the Department.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1948099</tid>
<number>4</number>The constitution and functions of a Board of Under- graduate 
Studies and the term of office of its members shall be prescribed by 
the Ordinances.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>393935</tid>
<number> 19</number> Finance Committee.
<section><tid>1955826</tid>
<number>1</number>The Finance Committee shall consist of  
the following members, namely:-

<subsection><tid>630799</tid>
<number>i</number>The Vice- Chancellor;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>855394</tid>
<number>ii</number>A Pro- Vice- Chancellor appointed by the Executive Council;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>222201</tid>
<number>iii</number>Three persons nominated by the Executive Council, out of 
whom at least one shall be a member of the Executive Council; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1819451</tid>
<number>iv</number>Three persons nominated by the Visitor.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1841968</tid>
<number>2</number>Five members of the Finance Committee shall form a quorum for 
meeting of the Finance Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>1623424</tid>
<number>3</number>All the members of the Finance Committee, other than ex- 
officio, members, shall hold office for a term of three years.

</section>

<section><tid>271379</tid>
<number>4</number>A member of the Finance Committee shall have the right to 
record a minute of dissent if he does not agree with any decision of 
the Finance Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>481086</tid>
<number>5</number>The Finance Committee shall meet at least twice every year to 
examine the accounts and to scrutinise proposals for expenditure.

</section>

<section><tid>623938</tid>
<number>6</number>The annual accounts and the financial estimates of the 
University prepared by the Finance Officer shall be laid before the 
Finance Committee for consideration and comments and thereafter 
submitted to the Executive Council for approval.

</section>

<section><tid>610368</tid>
<number>7</number>The Finance Committee shall recommend limits for the total 
recurring expenditure and the total non- recurring expenditure for the 
year, based on the income and resources of the University (which, in  
  the case of productive works, may include the proceeds of loans).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1606765</tid>
<number> 20</number> Selection Committees.
<section><tid>1154121</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be Selection Committees  
for making recomemndations to, the Executive Council for appointment 
to the posts of Professor,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>171</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Reader, Lecturer, Librarian and Principals of Colleges and 
Institutions maintained by the University.


</section>

<section><tid>1047331</tid>
<number>2</number>The Selection Committee for appointment to the posts 
specified in column 1 of the Table below shall consist of the Vice- 
Chancellor, a Pro- Vice- Chancellor appointed by the Executive Council, 
a nominee of the Visitor and the persons specified in the 
corresponding entry in column 2 of the said Table:
TABLE 
 1 2

Professor (i) The Head of the Department concerned, if he is a 
Professor.


<subsection><tid>921816</tid>
<number>ii</number>One Professor to be nominated by the Vice Chancellor.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>998952</tid>
<number>iii</number>Three persons not in the service of the University, nominated by 
the Executive Council, out of a panel of names recommended by the 
Academic Council for their special knowledge of or interest in the 
subject with which the Professor will be concerned.
Reader (i) The Head of the Department concerned. 
Lecturer (ii) One Professor to be nominated by the Vice- 
Chancellor.


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>998952</tid>
<number>iii</number>Two persons not in the service of the University, nominated by 
the Executive Council, out of a panel of names recommended by the Aca- 
demic Council for their special knowledge of or interest in the 
subject with which the Reader or Lecturer will be concerned.
Librarian (i) Two persons not in the service of the University, 
who have special knowledge of the subject of Library Science Library 
Administration to be nominated by the Executive Council.


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>921816</tid>
<number>ii</number>One person, not in the service of the University, nominated by 
the Executive Council.
Principal Three persons not in the service of the Uni- 
of College versity of whom two shall be nominated by the 
or Institu- Executive Council and one by the Academic 
tion main- Council for their special knowledge of or interest 
tained by in a subject in which instruction is being provided 
the Uni- by the College or Institution. 
versity

NOTE 1.- Where the appointment is being made for an inter- 
disciplinary project, the Head of the project shall be deemed to be 
the Head of the Department concerned.

NOTE 2.- The Professor to be nominated shall be a Professor 
concerned with the speciality for which the selection is being made 
and that the Vice- Chancellor shall consult the Head of the Department 
and the Dean of School before nominating the Professor.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>172</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>668550</tid>
<number>3</number>The Vice- Chancellor, or in his absence, the senior- most Pro- 
Vice- Chancellor, shall preside at the meetings of a Selection 
Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>1144948</tid>
<number>4</number>The meetings of a Selection Committee shall be convened by 
the Vice- Chancellor or In his absence, by the senior- most Pro- Vice- 
Chancellor.

</section>

<section><tid>97909</tid>
<number>5</number>The procedure to be followed by a Selection Committee in 
making recommendations shall be laid down in the Ordinances.

</section>

<section><tid>419066</tid>
<number>6</number>If the Executive Council Is unable to accept the 
recommendations made by a Selection Committee, it shall record its 
reasons and submit the case to the Visitor for final orders.

</section>

<section><tid>433</tid>
<number>7</number>Appointments to temporary posts shall be made in the manner 
Indicated below:-

<subsection><tid>1662999</tid>
<number>i</number>If the temporary vacancy is for a duration longer than one 
academic session, it shall be filled on the advice of the 
Selection Committee in accordance with the procedure 
indicated in the foregoing clauses:
Provided that if the Vice- Chancellor is satisfied that in the 
Interests of work it is necessary to fill the vacancy, the 
appointment may be made on a purely temporary basis by a 
local Selection Committee referred to in sub- clause (ii) for 
a period not exceeding six months.


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>381586</tid>
<number>ii</number>If the temporary vacancy is for a period less than a 
year, an appointment to such vacancy shall be made on the 
recommendation of a local Selection Committee consisting of 
the Dean of the School concerned, the Head of the Department 
and a nominee of the Vice- Chancellor:
Provided that if the same person holds the offices of the 
Dean and the Head of the Department. the Selection Committee 
may contain two nominees of the Vice- Chancellor:

Provided further that in case of sudden casual vacancies of 
teaching posts caused by death or any other reason, the Dean 
may, in consultation with the Heed of the Department 
concerned, make a temporary appointment for a month and 
report to the Vice- Chancellor and the Registrar about such 
appointment.


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>481111</tid>
<number>iii</number>No teacher appointed temporarily shall, if he is not 
recommended by a regular Selection Committee for appointment 
under these Statutes, be continued in service on such 
temporary employment, unless he is subsequently selected by a 
local Selection Committee or a regular Selection Committee, 
for a temprory or permanent appointment, as the case may be.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1573937</tid>
<number> 21</number> Special mode of appointment.
<section><tid>15213</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything  
contained in Statute 20, the Executive Council may invite a person of 
high academic distinction and professional attainments to accept a 
post of Professor or Reader or any other academic past in the 
University, as the case may be on such terms and conditions as it 
deems fit, and on the person agreeing to do so, appoint him to the 
post.

</section>

<section><tid>1574836</tid>
<number>2</number>The Executive Council may appoint a teacher or any other 
academic staff working in any other University or Organisation for 
undertaking a joint project in accordance with the manner laid down in 
the Ordinances.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>173</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>291110</tid>
<number>22</number>Appointment for a fixed tenure. The Executive Council may 
appoint a person selected in acocrdance with the procedure laid down 
in Statute 20 for a fixed tenure on such terms and conditions as it 
deems fit.


</article>



<article><tid>512952</tid>
<number> 23</number> Recognised teachers.
<section><tid>796951</tid>
<number>1</number>The qualifications of recognised  
teachers shall be such as may be prescribed by the Ordinances.

</section>

<section><tid>1044966</tid>
<number>2</number>All applications for the recognition of teachers shall be 
made in such manner as may be laid down in the Ordinances.

</section>

<section><tid>361928</tid>
<number>3</number>No teacher shall be recognised as a teacher except on the 
recommendation of a Selection Committee constituted for the purpose in 
the manner laid down in the Ordinances.

</section>

<section><tid>1777672</tid>
<number>4</number>The period of recognition of a teacher shall be determined by 
Ordinances made in that behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>1802232</tid>
<number>5</number>The Academic Council may, by a special resolution passed by a 
majority of not less than two- thirds of the members present and 
voting, withdraw recognition from a teacher:
Provided that no such resolution shall be passed until a notice 
in writing has been given to the person concerned calling upon him to 
show cause, within such time as may be specified in the notice, why 
such resolution should not be passed and until his objections, if any, 
and any evidence he may produce in support of them, have been 
considered by the Academic Council.


</section>

<section><tid>656391</tid>
<number>6</number>Any person aggrieved by an order of withdrawal under clause 
 (5) may, within three months from the date of communication to him of 
such order, appeal to the Executive Council which may pass such orders 
thereon as it thinks fit.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>401554</tid>
<number>24</number>Committees. Any authority of the University may appoint as 
many standing or special committees as it may deem fit, and may 
appoint to such committees persons who are not, members of such 
authority. Any such committee may deal with any subject delegated to 
it subject to subsequent confirmation by the authority appointing it.


</article>



<article><tid>1380965</tid>
<number> 25</number> Terms and conditions of service of University teachers.
<section><tid>1784570</tid>
<number>1</number> 
All the teachers of the University shall, in the absence of any 
agreement to the contrary, be governed by the terms and conditions of 
service as specified in these Statutes, the Ordinances and the 
Regulations.

</section>

<section><tid>301709</tid>
<number>2</number>Every teacher of the University shall be appointed on a 
written contract, the form of which shall be prescribed by the 
Ordinances. A copy of the contract shall be deposited with the 
Registrar.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>32827</tid>
<number> 26</number> Seniority lists.
<section><tid>1804233</tid>
<number>1</number>Whenever, in accordance with these  
Statutes, any person is to hold an office or be a member of an 
authority of the University by rotation according to seniority, such 
seniority shall be determined according to the length of continuous 
service of such person in his grade, and, in accordance with such 
other principles as the Executive Council may, from time to time, 
prescribe.

</section>

<section><tid>455061</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be the duty of the Registrar to prepare and 
maintain, in respect of each class of persons to whom the provisions 
of these Statutes apply, a. complete and up- to- date seniority list in 
accordance with the provisions of clause (1).

<pagefootnote><pagenum>174</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>710235</tid>
<number>3</number>If two or more persons have equal length of continuous 
service in a particular grade or the relative seniority of any person 
or persons is otherwise in doubt, the Registrar may, on his own motion 
and shall at the request of any such person, submit the matter to the 
Executive Council whose decision thereon shall be final.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>576000</tid>
<number> 27</number> Removal of teachers.
<section><tid>196974</tid>
<number>1</number>Where there is an allegation of  
misconduct against a teacher, or a member of the academic staff, the 
Vice- Chancellor may, if he thinks fit, by order in writing, place the 
teacher under suspension and shall forthwith report to the Executive 
Council the circumstances in which the order was made:
Provided that the Executive Council may, if it is of the opinion, 
that the circumstances of the case do not warrant the suspension of 
the teacher or a member of the academic staff, revoke such order.


</section>

<section><tid>1350719</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the terms of his 
contract of service or of his appointment, the Executive Council shall 
be entitled to remove a teacher or a member of the academic staff on 
the ground of misconduct.

</section>

<section><tid>834696</tid>
<number>3</number>Save as aforesaid, the Executive Council shall not be 
entitled to remove a teacher or a member of the academic staff except 
for good cause and after giving three months' notice in writing or on 
payment of three months' salary in lieu of notice.

</section>

<section><tid>1496898</tid>
<number>4</number>No teacher or a member of the academic staff shall be removed 
under clause (2) or under clause (3) until he has been given a 
reasonable opportunity of showing cause against the action proposed to 
be taken in regard to him.

</section>

<section><tid>1586433</tid>
<number>5</number>The removal of a teacher or a member of the academic staff 
shall require a two- thirds majority of the members of the Executive 
Council present and voting.

</section>

<section><tid>1207848</tid>
<number>6</number>The removal of a teacher or a member of the academic staff 
shall take effect from the date on which the order of removal is made:
Provided that where a teacher or a member of the academic staff 
is under suspension at the time of his removal, the removal shall take 
effect from the date on which he was placed under suspension.


</section>

<section><tid>811936</tid>
<number>7</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in these Statutes, a 
teacher or a member of the academic staff may resign by giving three 
months' notice in writing to the Executive Council or on payment of 
three months' salary in lieu thereof.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1887466</tid>
<number> 28</number> Removal of employees other than teachers of the University.

<section><tid>1589250</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the terms of his contract of  
service or of his appointment, an employee, other than a teacher or a 
member of the academic staff, may be removed by the authority which is 
competent to appoint the employee-

<subsection><tid>539991</tid>
<number>a</number>if he is of unsound mind or is a deaf- mute or suffers 
from contagious leprosy;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>553165</tid>
<number>b</number>if he is an undischarged insolvent;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1826114</tid>
<number>c</number>if he has been convicted by a court of law of any offence 
involving moral turpitude and sentenced in respect thereof to 
imprisonment for not less than six months;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>175</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1516162</tid>
<number>d</number>if he is otherwise guilty of misconduct:
Provided that no employee shall be removed from his office unless 
a resolution to that effect is passed by the Executive Council by a 
Majority of two- thirds of its members present and voting.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1799051</tid>
<number>2</number>No employee shall be removed under clause (1) until he has 
been given a reasonable opportunity of showing cause against the 
action proposed to be taken in regard to him.

</section>

<section><tid>930808</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the removal of such employee is for a reason other than 
that specified in sub- clause (c) or sub- clause (d) of clause (1), he 
shall be given three months' notice in writing or paid three months' 
salary in lieu of such notice.

</section>

<section><tid>123291</tid>
<number>4</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in these Statutes, an em- 
ployee, not being a teacher or a member of the academic staff, shall 
be entitled to resign,-

<subsection><tid>322588</tid>
<number>i</number>if he is a permanent employee, only after giving three 
month' s notice in writing to the appointing authority or 
paying to the University three months' salary in lieu 
thereof;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>148646</tid>
<number>ii</number>if he is not a permanent employee, only after giving one 
months' notice in writing to the appointing authority or 
paying to the University one month' s salary in lieu thereof:
Provided that such resignation shall take effect, from the date 
on which the resignation is accepted by the appointing authority.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>531963</tid>
<number> 29</number> Honorary degrees.
<section><tid>535010</tid>
<number>1</number>The Executive Council may, on the  
recommendation of the Academic Council and by a resolution passed by a 
majority of not less than two- thirds of the members present and 
voting, make proposals to the Visitor for the conferment of honorary 
degrees:
Provided that in case of emergency, the Executive Council may, on 
its own, make such proposals.


</section>

<section><tid>411899</tid>
<number>2</number>The Executive Council may, by a resolution passed by a 
majority of not less than two- thirds of the members present and 
voting, withdraw, with the previous sanction of the Visitor, any 
honorary degree conferred by the University.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>218759</tid>
<number>30</number>Withdrawal of degrees, etc. The Executive Council may, by a 
special resolution passed by a majority of not less than two- thirds of 
the members present and voting, withdraw any degree or academic 
distinction conferred on, or any certificate or diploma granted to, 
any person by the University for good and sufficient cause:
Provided that no such resolution shall be passed until a notice 
in writing has been given to that person calling upon him to show 
cause within such time as may be specified in the notice why such a 
resolution should not be passed and until his objections, if any, and 
any evidence he may produce. in support of them, have been considered 
by the Executive Council.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>176</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1681085</tid>
<number> 31</number> Maintenance of discipline among students of the University.

<section><tid>34706</tid>
<number>1</number>All powers relating to discipline and disciplinary action in  
relation to students of the University shall vest in the Vice- 
Chancellor.

</section>

<section><tid>1190816</tid>
<number>2</number>The Vice- Chancellor may delegate all or any of his powers as 
he deems proper to a Proctor and to such other officers as he may 
specify in this behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>52768</tid>
<number>3</number>Without prejudice to the generality of his powers relating to 
the maintenance of discipline and taking such action, as may seem to 
him appropriate for the maintenance of discipline, the Vice- Chancellor 
may, in the exercise of his powers, by order, direct that any student 
or students be expelled, or rusticated, for a specified period, or be 
not admitted to a course or courses of study in a College, Institution 
or Department of the University for a stated period, or be punished 
with fine for an amount to be specified in the order, or be debarred 
from taking an examination or examinations conducted by the 
University, College, Institution or a Department for one or more 
years, or that the results of the student or students concerned in the 
examination or examinations in which he or they have appeared be 
cancelled.

</section>

<section><tid>1162071</tid>
<number>4</number>The Principals of Colleges, Institutions, Heads of Special 
Centres, Deans of Schools of Studies and Heads of teaching Departments 
in the University shall have the authority, to exercise all such 
disciplinary powers over the students in their respective Colleges, 
Institutions, Special Centres, Schools and teaching Departments in the 
University as may be necessary for the proper conduct of such 
Colleges, Institutions, Special Centres, Schools and teaching in the 
Departments.

</section>

<section><tid>375786</tid>
<number>5</number>Without prejudice to the powers of the Vice- Chancellor, the 
Principals and other persons specified in clause (4), detailed rules 
of discipline and proper conduct shall be made by the University. The 
Principals of Colleges, Institutions, Heads of Special Centres, Deans 
of Schools of Studies and Heads of teaching Departments in the 
University may also make the supplementary rules as they deem 
necessary for the aforesaid purposes. Every student shall be supplied 
with a copy of the rules made by the University and a copy of the 
supplementary rules shall be supplied tot the students concerned.

</section>

<section><tid>281758</tid>
<number>6</number>At the time of admission, every student shall be required to 
sign a declaration to the effect that he submits himself to the 
disciplinary jurisdiction of the Vice- Chancellor and other authorities 
of the University.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1051378</tid>
<number>32</number>Maintenance of discipline among students of College, etc. All 
powers relating to discipline and disciplinary action in relation to 
students of a College or an Institution, not maintained by the Univer- 
sity, shall vest in the Principal of the College or Institution, as 
the case may be, in accordance with the procedure prescribed by the 
Ordinances.


</article>



<article><tid>300069</tid>
<number> 33</number> Admission of College, etc., to the privileges of the 
University.
<section><tid>131652</tid>
<number>1</number>Colleges and other Institutions situated within the  
jurisdiction of the University may be admitted to such privileges of 
the University as the Executive Council may decide on the following 
conditions, namely:-

<subsection><tid>486281</tid>
<number>i</number>Every such College or Institution shall have a regularly 
constituted Governing Body, consisting of not more than 
fifteen persons approved by the Executive Council and 
including, among others, two teachers of the University to be 
nominated by the Executive Council

<pagefootnote><pagenum>177</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

and three representatives of the teaching staff of whom the 
Principal of the College or Institution shall be one. The 
procedure for appointment of members of the Governing Body 
and other matters affecting the management of a College or an 
Institution shall be prescribed by the Ordinances:

Provided that the said condition shall not apply in the case 
of Colleges and Institutions maintained by Government which 
shall, however, have an Advisory Committee consisting of not 
more than fifteen persons which shall consist of, among 
others, three teachers including the Principal of the College 
or Institution, and two teachers of the University nominated 
by the Executive Council. 
 (ii) Every such College or Institution shall satisfy the 
Executive Council on the following matters, namely:-


<subsubsection><tid>1298338</tid>
<number>a</number>the suitability and adequacy of its accommodation 
and equipment for teaching;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>128994</tid>
<number>b</number>the qualifications and adequacy of its teaching 
staff and the conditions of their service;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1228198</tid>
<number>c</number>the arrangements for the residence, welfare, 
discipline and supervision of students;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1476807</tid>
<number>d</number>the adequacy of financial provision made for the 
Continued maintenance of the College or Institution; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1350565</tid>
<number>e</number>such other matters as are essential for the 
maintenance of the standards of University education.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>520771</tid>
<number>iii</number>No College or Institution shall be admitted to any 
privileges of the University except on the 
recommendation of the Academic Council made after 
considering the report of a Committee of Inspection 
appointed for the purpose by the Academic Council.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1617761</tid>
<number>iv</number>Colleges and Institutions desirous of admission to 
any privileges of the University shall be required to 
intimate their intention to do so in writing so as to 
reach the Registrar not later than the 15th August, 
preceding the year from which permission applied for is 
to have effect.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1535637</tid>
<number>v</number>A College or an Institution shall not, without the 
previous permission of the Executive Council and the 
Academic Council, suspend instruction in any subject or 
course of study which it is authorised to teach and 
teaches.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>258635</tid>
<number>2</number>Appointment to the teaching staff and Principals of Colleges 
or Institutions admitted to the privileges of the University shall be 
made in the manner prescribed by the Ordinances:
Provided that nothing in this clause shall apply to Colleges and 
Institutions maintained by Government.


</section>

<section><tid>211456</tid>
<number>3</number>The service conditions of the administrative and other non- 
academic staff of every College or Institution referred to in clause 
 (2) shall be such as may be laid down in the Ordinances:
Provided that nothing in this clause shall apply to Colleges and 
Institutions maintained by Government.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>178</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1012703</tid>
<number>4</number>Every College or Institution admitted to the privileges of 
the University shall be inspected at least once in every two academic 
years by a Committee appointed by the Academic Council, and the report 
of that Committee shall be submitted to the Academic Council, which 
shall forward the same to the Executive Council with such 
recommendations as it may deem fit to make. The Executive Council, 
after considering the report and the recommendations, if any, of the 
Academic Council, shall forward a copy of the report to the Governing 
Body of the College or Institution with such remarks, if any, as it 
may deem fit, for suitable action.

</section>

<section><tid>328289</tid>
<number>5</number>The Executive Council may, after consulting the Academic 
Council, withdraw any privileges granted to a College or Institution,. 
at any lime it considers that the College or Institution does not 
satisfy any of the conditions on the fulfilment of which the College 
or Institution was admitted to such privileges:
Provided that before any privileges are so withdrawn, the 
Governing Body of the College or Institution concerned shall be given 
an opportunity to represent to the Executive Council why such action 
should not be taken.


</section>

<section><tid>1147288</tid>
<number>6</number>Subject to the conditions set forth in clause (1), the 
Ordinances may prescribe-

<subsection><tid>1047236</tid>
<number>i</number>such other conditions as may be considered necessary;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1819076</tid>
<number>ii</number>the procedure for the admission of Colleges and 
Institutions to the privileges of the University and for the 
withdrawal of those privileges.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1933933</tid>
<number>34</number>Convocations. Convocations of the University for the 
conferring of degrees or for tither purposes shall be held in such 
manner as may be prescribed by the Ordinances.


</article>



<article><tid>1892286</tid>
<number>35</number>Acting Chairman of meetings. Where no provision is made for a 
President or Chairman to preside over a meeting of any authority of 
the University or any Committee of such authority or when the 
President or Chairman so provided for is absent, the members present 
shall elect one from among themselves to preside at such meeting.


</article>



<article><tid>867809</tid>
<number>36</number>Resignation. Any member, other than an ex- officio member of 
the Court, the Executive Council, the Academic Council or any other 
authority of the University or any Committee of such authority may 
resign by letter addressed to the Registrar and the resignation shall 
take effect as soon as such letter is received by the Registrar.


</article>



<article><tid>909195</tid>
<number> 37</number> Disqualifications.
<section><tid>622059</tid>
<number>1</number>A person shall be disqualified for  
being chosen as, and for being, a member of any of the authorities of 
the University-

<subsection><tid>1094835</tid>
<number>a</number>if he is of unsound mind or is a deaf- mute or 
suffers from contagious leprosy;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>58005</tid>
<number>b</number>if he is an undischarged insolvent;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1549590</tid>
<number>c</number>if he has been convicted by a court of law of an 
offence involving moral turpitude and sentenced in 
respect thereof to imprisonment for not less than six 
months.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>480049</tid>
<number>2</number>If any question arises as to whether a person is or had been 
subjected to any of the disqualifications mentioned in clause (1), the 
question shall be referred for the decision of the Visitor and his 
decision shall be final and no suit or other proceeding shall lie in 
any civil court against such decision.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>179</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>634938</tid>
<number>38</number>Residence condition for membership and office. 
Notwithstanding anything contained in these Statutes, no per who is 
not ordinarily resident in India shall be eligible to be ail officer 
of the University or a member of any authority of the University.


</article>



<article><tid>440049</tid>
<number>39</number>Membership of authorities by virtue of membership of other 
bodies. Notwithstanding anything contained in these Statutes, a 
person who holds any post in the University or- is a member of any 
authority or body of the University in his capacity as a member of a 
particular authority or body or as the holder of a particular 
appointment shall hold such office or membership only for so long as 
he continues to be a member of that particular authority or body or 
the holder of that particular appointment, as the case may be.


</article>



<article><tid>818257</tid>
<number> 40</number> Alumni Association.
<section><tid>635863</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be an Alumni Association  
for the University.

</section>

<section><tid>1927598</tid>
<number>2</number>The subscription for membership of the Alumni Association 
shall be prescribed by the Ordinances.

</section>

<section><tid>1616349</tid>
<number>3</number>No member of the Alumni Association shall be entitled to vote 
or stand for election unless he has been a member a. the Association 
for at least one year prior to the date of the election and is a 
graduate of the University of at least five years' standing:
Provided that the condition relating to the completion of one 
year' s membership shall not apply in the case of the first election.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>901935</tid>
<number> 41</number> Ordinance how made.
<section><tid>712126</tid>
<number>1</number>The first Ordinances made under sub-  
section (2) of section 26 may be amended, repealed or added to at any 
time by the Executive Council in the manner specified below.

</section>

<section><tid>108926</tid>
<number>2</number>No Ordinance in respect of the matters enumerated in section 
26, other than those enumerated in clause (n) of subsection (1) 
thereof, shall be made by the Executive Council unless a draft of such 
Ordinance has been proposed by the Academic Council.

</section>

<section><tid>1855437</tid>
<number>3</number>The Executive Council shall not have power to amend any draft 
of any Ordinance proposed by the Academic Council under clause (2), 
but may reject the proposal or return the draft to the Academic 
Council for reconsideration, either in whole or in part, together with 
any amendment which the Executive Council may suggest.

</section>

<section><tid>789095</tid>
<number>4</number>Where the Executive Council has rejected or returned the 
draft of an Ordinance proposed by the Academic Council, the Academic 
Council many consider the question afresh and in case the original 
draft is re- affirmed by a majority of not less than two- thirds of the 
members present; and voting and more than half the total number of 
members of the Academic Council, the draft may be sent back to the 
Executive Council which shall either adopt it or refer it to the 
Visitor whose decision shall be final.

</section>

<section><tid>1177802</tid>
<number>5</number>Every Ordinance made by the Executive Council shall come into 
effect immediately.

</section>

<section><tid>823317</tid>
<number>6</number>Every Ordinance made by the Executive Council shall be sub- 
mitted to the Visitor within two weeks from the date of its adoption. 
The Visitor shall have the power to direct the University within four 
weeks of the receipt of the Ordinance to suspend the operation of any 
such Ordinance and he shall, as soon as possible, inform the Executive 
Council about his objection to the proposed Ordinance. The Visitor 
may

<pagefootnote><pagenum>180</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

after receiving the comments of the University, either withdraw the 
order suspending the Ordinance or disallow the Ordinance, and his 
decision shall be final.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>293771</tid>
<number> 42</number> Regulations.
<section><tid>1101051</tid>
<number>1</number>The authorities of the University may make  
Regulations consistent with this Act, and these Statutes and the 
Ordinances:-

<subsection><tid>1624180</tid>
<number>a</number>laying down the procedure to be observed at their 
meetings and the number of members required to form a quorum;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1111948</tid>
<number>b</number>providing for all matters which are required by this Act 
these Statutes or the Ordinances to be prescribed by 
Regulations;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>940484</tid>
<number>c</number>providing for all other matters solely concerning such 
authorities or committees appointed by them and not provided 
for by this Act, these Statutes or the Ordinances.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>767266</tid>
<number>2</number>Every authority of the University shall make. Regulations 
providing for the giving of notice to the members of such authority of 
the dates of meetings and of the business to be considered at meetings 
and for the keeping of a record of the proceedings of meetings.

</section>

<section><tid>1831423</tid>
<number>3</number>The Executive Council may direct the amendment in such manner 
as it may specify, of any Regulation made under this Statute or the 
annulment of any such Regulation.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>934097</tid>
<number>43</number>Delegation of powers. Subject to the provisions of this Act 
and these Statutes. any officer or authority of the University may 
delegate his or its powers to any other officer or authority or person 
under his or its respective control and subject to the condition that 
overall responsibility for the exercise of the powers so delegated 
shall continue to vest in the officer or authority delegating such 
powers.

</article>



 </act>