<act><title>

    The ANAND 
    MARRIAGE ACT, 1909</title> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and extent.—
<section><number>1</number> This Act may 
    be called the Anand Marriage Act, 1909; and
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[except the 
    State of Jammu and Kashmir].



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>2</number> Validity of Anand marriage.—All 
    marriages which may be or may have been duly solemnised according to the 
    Sikh Marriage ceremony called Anand shall be and shall be deemed to have 
    been with effect from the date of the solemnization of each respectively, 
    good and valid in law.

 
 
In view of the diversity of 
      our population, rites and customs of marriage vary from community to 
      community. Sometimes doubts might arise as to the validity of certain 
      marriages. The Act seeks to give statutory recognition to a marriage rite 
      of the sikhs called 'Anand’. 
      Thus, any marriage performed according to the 'Anand' ceremony is valid 
      with effect from the date of its solemnisation.


  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>3</number> Exemption of certain marriages from 
      Act.—Nothing in this Act shall 
      apply to—
 
 <section><number>a</number>   any marriage between persons not professing the 
        Sikh religion, or
 </section><section><number>b</number>   any marriage which has been judicially declared 
        to be null and void.</section>
  </article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Saving of 
    marriages solemnized according to other ceremonies.—Nothing 
    in this Act shall affect the validity of any marriage duly solemnized 
    according to any other marriage ceremony customary among the Sikhs.
  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Non-validation of marriages within prohibited degrees.—Nothing 
    in this Act shall be deemed to validate any marriage between persons who are 
    related to each other in any degree of consanguinity or affinity which 
    would, according to the customary law of the Sikhs, render a marriage 
    between them illegal.
  


</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>             Subs. by 
    Act 48 of 1959, sec. 3 and Sch. I, for certain words (w.e.f. 1-2-1960).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>