<act><title>THE TELECOM DISPUTES SETTLEMENT AND APPELLATE 
TRIBUNAL (FORM, VERIFICATION AND THE FEE FOR FILING AN APPEAL) RULES, 
20031 </title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the Telecom Disputes Settlement and Appellate Tribunal (Form, 
Verification and the Fee for Filing an Appeal) Rules, 2003. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the 
Official Gazette. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions.</title>
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, unless context otherwise 
requires,
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> Act means the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India Act, 1997 (24 of 
  1997);
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> Appellate Tribunal means the Telecom Disputes Settlement and 
  Appellate Tribunal established under section 14 of the Telecom Regulatory 
  Authority of India Act, 1997 (24 of 1997).</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The words and expressions used and not defined in these rules but defined 
in the Act, shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the 
Act.

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> The form and verification while filing an appeal.</title>The 
form of filing an appeal under sub-section (2) of section 14A of the Act and its 
verification shall be in the format specified in Form A appended to these 
rules.

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Fee for filing an appeal</title>.
<section><number>1</number> The fee accompanied with an 
appeal filed under sub-section (2) of section 14A of the Act shall be Rs. 
10,000/- (Rupees ten thousand only) where the respondents are less than four and 
in the case of four or more respondents the said fee shall be increased by Rs. 
50/- (Rupees fifty only) per respondent exceeding three in number and shall be 
in the form of demand drafts in favour of Drawing and Disbursing Officer, 
Telecom Disputes Settlement and Appellate Tribunal and payable at the place of 
the Bench of the Appellate Tribunal:
 Provided that the Chairperson of the Appellate Tribunal may at his discretion 
either reduce or waive fee payable for filing of appeal.

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Procedure for service of notices.</title>
<section><number>1</number> All notices 
required to be served in accordance with the orders of the Appellate Tribunal 
shall be served in the manner specified in sub-rules (2), (3) and (4).
 </section><section><number>2</number> The service of a notice shall be made by hand delivery (Dasti) by the 
Appellant or respondent, as the case may be, or by a process server or by 
registered post with acknowledgement due or by speed post or by such courier 
service or by any other means of transmission of documents (including fax 
message), as the case may be, and the notice shall be addressed to the 
respondent or to the appellant, as the case may be.
 </section><section><number>3</number> When an acknowledgement or any other receipt purporting to be signed by 
the respondent or his agent or by the appellant or his agent, as the case may 
be, is received by the Appellate Tribunal or postal article containing the 
notice is received back with an endorsement purporting to have been made by a 
postal employee or by any person authorised by the courier service to the effect 
that the respondent or his agent or the appellant or his agent, as the case may 
be, had refused to take delivery of the postal article containing the notice or 
had refused to accept the notice by any other means specified in sub-rule (2) 
when tendered or transmitted to him, the Appellate Tribunal shall declare that 
the notice had been duly served on the opposite party or to the Appellant: 
 Provided that where the notice was properly addressed, pre-paid and duly 
sent by registered post with acknowledgement due, a declaration referred to 
above, shall be made notwithstanding the fact that the acknowledgement has been 
lost or mislead, or for any other reason has not been received by the Appellate 
Tribunal within thirty days from the date of issue of notice.
 </section><section><number>4</number> All notices required to be served on the respondent or the appellant 
shall be deemed to be sufficiently served, if served in the manner specified in 
sub-rule (2) and (3) on the address in the case of a respondent to the place 
where business or profession is carried by the respondent and in case of an 
appellant where the appellant actually and voluntarily resides or carries on 
business.

</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>