<act><tid>792073</tid>
<title>THE RUBBER ACT, <year>1947</year></title>

ACT NO. 24 OF <year>1947</year>
[ 18th April, <year>1947</year>.]

An Act to provide for the development <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> under the control of the 
Union] of the rubber industry <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>.

WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the development <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> under 
the control of the Union] of the rubber industry <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>;

It is hereby enacted as follows:--





<article><tid>797295</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>407208</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Rubber  
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Act, <year>1947</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>886949</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> except the State of Jammu 
and Kashmir].



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>637802</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Declaration as to expediency of Union control. It is hereby 
declared that it is expedient in the public interest that the Union 
should take under its control the rubber industry.]


</article>



<article><tid>969442</tid>
<number> 3</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant 
in the subject or context,--
<section><tid>1079327</tid>
<number>a</number>" Board" means the <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Rubber Board constituted under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>43704</tid>
<number>b</number>" dealer" means any person who deals in rubber, whether 
wholesale or retail, or holds stocks of rubber, and in- 
cludes the representative or agent of a dealer;

</section>

<section><tid>1681533</tid>
<number>c</number>" estate" means any area administered as one unit which 
contains land planted with rubber plants;

</section>

<section><tid>228271</tid>
<number>d</number>" export" and" import" mean respectively taking out of, 
and bringing into, <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> India] by sea, land or air;

</section>

<section><tid>797220</tid>
<number>dd</number><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>" India" means the territory of India excluding the 
State of Jammu and Kashmir;]

</section>

<section><tid>603024</tid>
<number>e</number>" manufacturer" means any person engaged in the 
manufacture of any article in the making of which 
rubber is used;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>52</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>999999</number> The Act comes into force in Pondicherry on 1. 10. <year>1963</year> vide Reg. 7 of 
<year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch. I.

Extended to, and brought into force in Dadra and Nagar Havoli (w. e. f.  
  1. 7. 65) by Reg. 6 of <year>1963</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 54 of <year>1954</year>, s. 2, for" under central control". 
2. Certain words omitted by s. 2, ibid. 
3. The brackets and words" (Prodution and Marketing)" omitted by s. 
3, ibid. 
4. Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch., for" except Part B 
States". 
5. Subs. by Act 54 of <year>1954</year>, s. 4, for the former section. 
6. The word" Indian" omitted by s. 5, ibid. 
7. Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch., for" the States". 
8. Ins. by s. 3 and Sch., ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1604781</tid>
<number>f</number>" owner" includes any agent of an owner and a mortgagee 
in possession and a lessee of an estate;

</section>

<section><tid>323966</tid>
<number>g</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1736001</tid>
<number>h</number>" rubber" means--

</section>

<section><tid>132160</tid>
<number>i</number>crude rubber, that is to say, rubber prepared 
from the leaves, bark or latex of any rubber plant;

<subsection><tid>58471</tid>
<number>ii</number>the latex of any rubber plant, whether fluid 
or coagulated, in any stage of the treatment to which 
it is subjected during the process of conversion into 
rubber;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>990285</tid>
<number>iii</number>latex (dry rubber content) in any state of 
concentration, 
and includes scrap rubber, sheet rubber, rubber in 
powder and all forms and varieties of crepe rubber, but 
does not include rubber contained in any manufactured 
article;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1605143</tid>
<number>i</number>" rubber plant" includes plants, trees, shrubs or vines 
of any of the following:--

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1605143</tid>
<number>i</number>Hevea Braziliensis (Para Rubber),

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>58471</tid>
<number>ii</number>Manihot Glaziovii (Ceara Rubber),

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>990285</tid>
<number>iii</number>Castilloa elastica,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>21796</tid>
<number>iv</number>Ficus elastica (Rambong), and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1488138</tid>
<number>v</number>any other plant which the Board may, by 
notification in the Gazette of India, declare to 
be a rubber plant for the purposes of this Act;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>114598</tid>
<number>j</number>" Rubber Production Commissioner" means the Rubber 
Production Commissioner appointed under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>798217</tid>
<number>k</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>" small grower" means an owner whose estate does not 
exceed fifty acres in area.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1961923</tid>
<number> 4</number> Constitution of the Board.
<section><tid>558214</tid>
<number>1</number>As soon as may be after the  
commencement of this Act, the Central Government shall, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, constitute for the purposes of 
this Act a Board to be called the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Rubber Board.

</section>

<section><tid>1617669</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board shall be a body corporate by the name of the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> 
Rubber Board having perpetual succession and a common seal, with power 
to acquire and hold property, both movable and immovable, and to 
contract, and shall by the said name sue and be sued.

</section>

<section><tid>637398</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> The Board shall consist of--

<subsection><tid>1351466</tid>
<number>a</number>a Chairman to be appointed by the Central Government:
<pagefootnote><pagenum>53</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 54 of <year>1954</year>, s. 5. 
2. The word" Indian" omitted by s. 6, ibid. 
3. Subs. by s. 6, ibid., for sub- sections (3), (4) and (5).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>315798</tid>
<number>b</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> two members to represent the State of <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Tamil Nadu], 
one of whom shall be a person representing rubber 
producing interest;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>878032</tid>
<number>c</number>eight members to represent the State of Kerala, six of 
whom shall be persons representing the rubber producing 
interests, three of such six being persons representing 
the small growers;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1277254</tid>
<number>d</number>ten members to be nominated by the Central Government, 
of whom two shall represent the manufacturers and four 
labour;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>849707</tid>
<number>e</number>three members of Parliament of whom two shall be elected 
by the House of the People and one by the Council of 
States; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1506316</tid>
<number>f</number>the Rubber Production Commissioner, ex officio.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>72221</tid>
<number>4</number>The persons to represent the States of <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Tamil Nadu] and 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Kerala] shall be elected or nominated as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>634374</tid>
<number>5</number>Any officer of the Central Government when deputed by that 
Government in this behalf shall have the right to attend the meetings 
of the Board and take part in the proceedings thereof but shall not be 
entitled to vote.

</section>

<section><tid>1976073</tid>
<number>6</number>The Board shall elect from among its members a Vice- Chairman 
who shall exercise such of the powers, and perform such of the 
functions of the Chairman as may be prescribed or as may be delegated 
to him by the Chairman.

</section>

<section><tid>7440</tid>
<number>7</number>The members of the Board shall receive from the Board such 
allowances as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>391502</tid>
<number>8</number>It is hereby declared that the office of member of the Board 
shall not disqualify its holder for being chosen as, or for being, a 
member of either House of Parliament.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>370595</tid>
<number> 5</number> Vacancies in the Board.
<section><tid>1185017</tid>
<number>1</number>If any authority or body fails to  
make within a reasonable time any nomination which it is entitled to 
make under section 4, the Central Government may itself nominate a 
member to fill the vacancy.

</section>

<section><tid>1521717</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a member of the Board dies, resigns or is removed, or 
ceases to reside in India, or becomes incapable of acting, the Central 
Government shall, on the recommendation of the authority or body 
entitled to nominate the member under section 4, or where such 
recommendation is not made
<pagefootnote><pagenum>54</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>, for the 
former cls. (b) and (c). 
2. Subs. by the Madras State (Alteration of Name)  (Adaptation of  
  Laws on Union Subjects) Order, <year>1970</year>, for" Madras" (w. e. f. 14. 1. <year>1969</year>). 
3. Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>," Travancore- 
Cochin".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


within a reasonable time, then on its own initiative, appoint a person 
to fill the vacancy.


</section>

<section><tid>1110178</tid>
<number>3</number>No act done by the Board shall be questioned on the ground 
merely of the existence of any vacancy in, or defect in the 
constitution of the Board.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1209678</tid>
<number>6</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Salary and allowances of Chairman. The Chairman shall be 
entitled to such salary and allowances and be governed by such 
conditions of service in respect of leave, pension, provident fund and 
other matters as may from time to time be fixed by the Central 
Government.


</article>



<article><tid>1942511</tid>
<number> 6A</number> Executive officers of the Board.
<section><tid>833423</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government  
shall appoint a Rubber Production. Commissioner to exercise such 
powers and perform such duties under the direction of the Board as may 
be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1774743</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government shall appoint a Secretary to the Board 
to exercise such powers and perform such duties under the direction of 
the Board as may be prescribed or as may be delegated to him by the 
Chairman.

</section>

<section><tid>343236</tid>
<number>3</number>The Rubber Production Commissioner and the Secretary to the 
Board shall be entitled to such salaries and allowances and be 
governed by such conditions of service regarding leave, pension, 
provident fund and other matters as may be fixed by the Central 
Government.

</section>

<section><tid>818770</tid>
<number>4</number>The Chairman, the Rubber Production Commissioner and the 
Secretary shall not undertake any work unconnected with their duties 
under this Act except with the permission of the Central Government.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>65191</tid>
<number> 7</number> Committees of the Board. <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>
<section><tid>523512</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board may appoint such <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Committees as may be necessary 
for the efficient performance of its duties and functions under this 
Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1642422</tid>
<number>3</number>The Board shall have the power to co- opt as members of any 
Committee appointed under sub- section (2) such number of persons who 
are not members of the Board, as it may think fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1446983</tid>
<number>4</number>The Board may appoint and authorize agents to discharge on 
its behalf any of its functions in relation to the marketing or 
storing of rubber.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>742298</tid>
<number> 8</number> Functions of the Board.
<section><tid>1477220</tid>
<number>1</number>It shall be the duty of the Board  
to promote by such measures as it thinks fit the development of the 
rubber industry <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>55</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 54 of <year>1954</year>, s. 7, for the former section. 
2. Sub- section (1) omitted by s. 8, ibid. 
3. The word" other" omitted by s. 8, ibid. 
4. The words" so far as regards the production and marketing of 
rubber" omitted by s. 9, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1391248</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
provision, the measures referred to therein may provide for--

<subsection><tid>382681</tid>
<number>a</number>undertaking, assisting or encouraging scientific, 
technological and economic research;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>344397</tid>
<number>b</number>training students in improved methods of planting, 
cultivation, manuring and spraying;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>600227</tid>
<number>c</number>the supply of technical advice to rubber growers;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>612009</tid>
<number>d</number>improving the marketing of rubber;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>882242</tid>
<number>e</number>the collection of statistics from owners of estates, 
dealers, and manufacturers;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1514346</tid>
<number>f</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> securing better working conditions and the provisions 
and improvement of amenities and incentives for 
workers;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>347045</tid>
<number>g</number>carrying out any other duties which may be vasted in the 
Board under rules made under this Act.]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1975347</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall also be the duty of the Board--

<subsection><tid>1456916</tid>
<number>a</number>to advise the Central Government on all matters relating 
to the development of the rubber industry, including 
the import and export of rubber;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1142971</tid>
<number>b</number>to advise the Central Government with regard to 
participation in any International Conference or scheme 
relating to rubber;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>826111</tid>
<number>c</number>to submit to the Central Government and such other 
authorities as may be prescribed half- yearly reports on 
its activities and the working of this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>902187</tid>
<number>d</number>to prepare and furnish such other reports relating to 
the rubber industry as may be required by the Central 
Government from time to time.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>550031</tid>
<number>8A</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Power of the Board to import rubber for sale, or to 
purchase rubber, in the internal market. It shall be lawful for the 
Board with the previous approval of the Central Government to import 
rubber for sale, or to purchase rubber, in the internal market at such 
prices as the Central Government may fix.


</article>



<article><tid>1677993</tid>
<number>8B</number>Consultation with the Board. Before taking any action 
touching the affairs of the Board under this Act, the Central 
Government shall ordinarily consult the Board:
Provided that no action taken by the Central Government shall be 
invalid or called in question merely on the ground that the action was 
taken without such consultation.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>56</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 54 of <year>1954</year>, s. 9. 
2. Ins. by s. 10, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>1928129</tid>
<number> 9</number> Funds of the Board.
<section><tid>1875093</tid>
<number>1</number>The Indian Rubber Production Board  
constituted under the Rubber Control and Production Order, <year>1946</year>, is 
hereby dissolved, and all funds and other property vested in, and all 
liabilities of, that Board shall respectively vest in, and be 
liabilities of, the Board constituted under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>328766</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The Board shall maintain two funds, a general fund and a 
pool fund.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>932728</tid>
<number> 9A</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> General fund.
<section><tid>1630651</tid>
<number>1</number>To the general fund shall be credited-- 

<subsection><tid>889790</tid>
<number>a</number>all sums forming the funds of the Board immediately 
before the commencement of the Rubber (Production and  
  Marketing) Amendment Act, <year>1954</year>;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>825394</tid>
<number>b</number>all amounts paid to the Board by the Central Government 
under sub- section (7) of section 12.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>797371</tid>
<number>2</number>The general fund shall be applied--

<subsection><tid>332917</tid>
<number>a</number>to meet the expenses of the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>5098</tid>
<number>b</number>to meet the costs of the measures referred to in section 
8;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>8999</tid>
<number>c</number>to meet the expenditure incurred in the performance of 
its functions under this Act or under rules made 
thereunder; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1591369</tid>
<number>d</number>for making such grants to rubber estates or for meeting 
the cost of such other assistance to rubber estates as 
the Board may think necessary for the development of 
such estates.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>245953</tid>
<number> 9B</number> Pool fund.
<section><tid>1963655</tid>
<number>1</number>To the pool fund shall be credited-- 

<subsection><tid>836804</tid>
<number>a</number>all sums realized by sales of rubber imported or 
purchased under section 8A;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1080108</tid>
<number>b</number>any other sum which the Board may, with the previous 
approval of the Central Government, transfer from the 
general fund to the pool fund.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1593174</tid>
<number>2</number>The pool fund shall be applied only to the rehabilitation of 
small grower in such manner as may be prescribed.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>650783</tid>
<number> 10</number> Registration.
<section><tid>555914</tid>
<number>1</number>Every person owning land planted with  
rubber plants, whether such land is comprised in one estate or in more 
than one estate and whether it is situated wholly or only partly in 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> India], shall, before the expiry of one month from the date of 
commencement of this Act, apply to the Board to be registered as an 
owner in respect of each estate owned by him.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>57</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 54 of <year>1954</year>, s. 11, for sub- section (2). 
2. Ins. by s. 12, ibid. 
3. Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch., for" the States".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>643373</tid>
<number>2</number>A registration once made shall continue in force until it is 
cancelled by the Board.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1693255</tid>
<number> 11</number> Power to prohibit or control imports and exports of rubber.

<section><tid>1895018</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> by order published in the Official  
Gazette, make provision for prohibiting, restricting or otherwise 
controlling the import or export of rubber, either generally or in 
specified classes of cases.

</section>

<section><tid>160040</tid>
<number>2</number>All goods to which any order under sub- section (1) applies 
shall be deemed to be goods of which the import or export has been 
prohibited or restricted under section 19 of the Sea Customs Act, 
 <year>1878</year> (8 of <year>1878</year>), and all the provisions of that Act shall have 
effect accordingly, except that section 183 thereof shall have effect 
as if for the word" shall" therein the word" may" were substituted.

</section>

<section><tid>1613507</tid>
<number>3</number>If any person contravenes any order made under sub- section 
 (1) he shall, without prejudice to any confiscation or penalty to 
which he may be liable under the provisions of the Sea Customs Act, 
 <year>1878</year> (8 of <year>1878</year>), as applied by sub- section (2), be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year or with fine or 
with both.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>554577</tid>
<number> 12</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Imposition of new rubber cess.
<section><tid>1713459</tid>
<number>1</number>With effect from such  
date as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, appoint, there shall be levied as a cess for the purposes of 
this Act, a duty of excise on all rubber produced in India at such 
rate, not exceeding <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> two rupees] per kilogram of rubber so 
produced, as the Central Government may fix.

</section>

<section><tid>1352310</tid>
<number>2</number>The duty of excise levied under sub- section (1) shall be 
collected by the Board in accordance with rules made in this behalf 
either from the owner of the estate on which the rubber is produced or 
from the manufacturer by whom such rubber is used.

</section>

<section><tid>1865555</tid>
<number>3</number>The owner or, as the case may be, the manufacturer shall pay 
to the Board the amount of the duty within one month from the date on 
which he receives a notice of demand therefor from the Board and, if 
he fails to do so, the duty may be recovered from the owner or the 
manufacturer, as the case may be, as an arrear of land revenue.

</section>

<section><tid>1956041</tid>
<number>4</number>For the purpose of enabling the Board to assess the amount of 
the duty of excise levied under this section--

<subsection><tid>1277798</tid>
<number>a</number>the Board shall, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, fix a period in respect of which assessments 
shall be made; and
<pagefootnote><pagenum>58</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" after consulting the Board" omitted by Act 54 of <year>1954</year>, 
s. 13. 
2. Subs. by Act 21 of <year>1960</year>, s. 2, for s. 12 (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1960</year>). 
3. Subs. by Act 33 of <year>1994</year>, s. 2.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1886971</tid>
<number>b</number>without prejudice to the provisions of section 20, every 
owner and every manufacturer shall furnish to the Board 
a return not later than fifteen days after the expiry 
of the period to which the return relates, stating,--

<subsubsection><tid>109738</tid>
<number>i</number>in the case of an owner, the total quantity of 
rubber produced on the estate in each such period:
Provided that in respect of an estate situated 
only partly in India, the owner shall in the said 
return show separately the quantity of rubber produced 
within and outside India;


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1531619</tid>
<number>ii</number>in the case of a manufacturer, the total 
quantity of rubber used by him in such period out of 
the rubber produced in India.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1975884</tid>
<number>5</number>If any owner or manufacturer fails to furnish, within the 
time prescribed, the return referred to in sub- section (4) or 
furnishes a return which the Board has reason to believe is incorrect 
or defective, the Board may assess the amount of the duty of excise in 
such manner as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1667127</tid>
<number>6</number>Any person aggrieved by an assessment made under this section 
may, within three months of the service of the notice under sub- 
section (3), apply to the District Judge for the cancellation or 
modification of the assessment, and the District Judge shall, after 
giving the Board an opportunity of being heard, pass such order (which  
  shall be final) as he thinks proper.

</section>

<section><tid>726308</tid>
<number>7</number>The proceeds of the duty of excise collected under this 
section reduced by the cost of collection as determined by the Central 
Government shall first be credited to the Consolidated Fund of India, 
and then be paid by the Central Government to the Board for being 
utilised for the purposes of this Act, if Parliament by appropriation 
made by law in this behalf so provides.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1264806</tid>
<number> 13</number> Power to fix maximum and minimum prices for sale of rubber.

<section><tid>256704</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>, by order <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> published in the  
Official Gazette, fix the maximum price or the minimum price or the 
maximum and minimum prices to be charged, in the course of a business 
of any class specified in the order, for rubber of any description so 
specified.

</section>

<section><tid>726779</tid>
<number>2</number>Any such order may fix different maximum or minimum prices to 
be charged in the course of businesses of different classes for the 
same description of rubber.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>58A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words, brackets and figures" after consulting the Rubber 
Price Advisory Committee constituted under sub- section (1) of section 
7" omitted by Act 54 of <year>1954</year>, s. 15. 
2. For such orders, see Gazette of India, <year>1947</year>, Pt. I, p. 1380 and 
ibid., Extraordinary, p. 1383.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1426084</tid>
<number>3</number>If any person buys or sells, or agrees to buy or sell, rubber 
at a price which is more than the maximum price, or less than the 
minimum price, fixed under sub- section (1) in that behalf, he shall be 
punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, 
or with fine, or with both.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>59</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1612735</tid>
<number>14</number>Licensing of transactions in rubber. No person shall sell or 
otherwise dispose of, and no person shall buy or otherwise acquire, 
rubber except under and in accordance with the terms of a general or 
special licence issued by the Board:


</article>



<article><tid>485772</tid>
<number> 15</number> Provisions regarding licences under section 14.
<section><tid>1732285</tid>
<number>1</number>Every  
general licence issued under section 14 shall be published by the 
Board in the Gazette of India and in such newspapers as the Board may 
direct.

</section>

<section><tid>667053</tid>
<number>2</number>A special licence issued under section 14 shall be valid only 
for such period as may be a specified therein:
Provided that the Board may from time to time extend the period 
of validity of any such licence.


</section>

<section><tid>102293</tid>
<number>3</number>The Board may at any time for reasons to be recorded by it in 
writing revoke a special licence granted under section 14, and on such 
revocation it shall be returned to the Board by the person to whom it 
was issued.

</section>

<section><tid>1693318</tid>
<number>4</number>No application for a special licence made by a person who was 
carrying on business as a dealer or manufacturer immediately before 
the commencement of this Act shall be rejected by the Board except for 
special reasons to be recorded in writing.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1824200</tid>
<number> 16</number> Restriction on possession of rubber.
<section><tid>1827486</tid>
<number>1</number>No person not being  
the owner or occupant of an estate or a person who has acquired rubber 
under a general or special licence issued by the Board under section 
 14 shall have any rubber in his possession.

</section>

<section><tid>832007</tid>
<number>2</number>Any Court trying a contravention of sub- section (1) may, 
without prejudice to the provisions of section 26, direct that any 
rubber in respect of which the Court is satisfied that such 
contravention has been committed shall be forfeited to Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>351828</tid>
<number> 17</number> Licences for planting or replanting.
<section><tid>1538310</tid>
<number>1</number>No person shall  
plant or replant rubber except under and in accodance with the 
conditions of a special licence issued by the Board.

</section>

<section><tid>396188</tid>
<number>2</number>A licence issued under this section shall specify the area in 
which rubber may be planted or replanted and the period for which the 
licence shall be valid.

</section>

<section><tid>827149</tid>
<number>3</number>No licence issued under this section shall be transferable 
except with the land to which it relates.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1189761</tid>
<number> 18</number> Reports to be submitted by licencees.
<section><tid>1432251</tid>
<number>1</number>Every holder of a  
licence issued under section 17 shall, at such times as the Board may 
require, furnish to it a report specifying the areas newly planted or 
replanted during the period to which
<pagefootnote><pagenum>61</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Proviso omitted by Act 50 of <year>1949</year>, s. 2.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


section 14, section 15 or section 17 may, within sixty days of the 
making of the order and on payment of the prescribed fee, appeal to 
the Central Government, and the decision of the Central Government 
thereon, and subject only to such decision the order of the Board, 
shall be final and shall not be called in question in any Court.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>748925</tid>
<number> 24</number> Accounts of the Board.
<section><tid>791914</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board shall keep such  
accounts, in such manner and in such form as may be prescribed, of all 
moneys received and expended by it.

</section>

<section><tid>173556</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board shall cause the accounts to be audited annually by 
auditors appointed by the Central Government, and the auditors shall 
have the power to disallow any item of expenditure which in their 
opinion has not been properly incurred under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>866193</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government may, on the application of the Board, 
allow any item of expenditure disallowed by the auditors under sub- 
section (2).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1776159</tid>
<number> 25</number> Power of Central Government to make rules.
<section><tid>256702</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> rules 
to carry out the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>484215</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of 
the for going power, rules made under this section may provide for all 
or any of the following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1640992</tid>
<number>i</number>principles regulating the nomination of members of the 
Board by the Central Government under clause (d) 
of sub- section (3) of section 4, and the election 
or nomination of the members referred to in 
clauses (b) and (c) thereof:
Provided that before making any nomination in 
the exercise of its powers the Central Government 
shall call for panels of names from the respective 
associations recognised by it of the interests 
referred to in clause (d);


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1873579</tid>
<number>ii</number>the term of office of members of the Board, the 
circumstances in which and the authority by which 
members may be removed and the filling of casual 
vacancies in the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>23690</tid>
<number>iii</number>the procedure to be followed at meetings of the Board 
and at committees thereof for the conduct of 
business, and the number of members which shall 
form a quorum at any meeting;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>62</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>For the Rubber (Production and Marketing) Rules, <year>1947</year>, see 
Gazette of India, <year>1947</year>, Extraordinary, p. 1241. 
2. Subs. by Act 54 of <year>1954</year>, s. 18, for the former sub- section.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1565327</tid>
<number>iv</number>the maintenance by the Board of records of business 
transacted by the Board and the submission of 
copies thereof to the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1445947</tid>
<number>v</number>the holding of a minimum number of meetings of the Board 
every year;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>243848</tid>
<number>vi</number>the powers of the Board, its Chairman and committees 
thereof with respect to the incurring of 
expenditure and the powers and duties of the 
Rubber Production Commissioner and the Secretary 
of the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1365781</tid>
<number>vii</number>the conditions subject to which the Board may incur 
expenditure outside India;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>572993</tid>
<number>viii</number>the preparation of budget estimates of receipts and 
expenditure of the Board and the authority by 
which the estimates are to be sanctioned;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>904980</tid>
<number>ix</number>the maintenance of the accounts of income and 
expenditure of the Board and the audit of such 
accounts;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1453593</tid>
<number>x</number>the deposit of the funds of the Board in banks and the 
investment of such funds;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1039345</tid>
<number>xi</number>the re- appropriation of the estimated savings from any 
budget head to any other budget head;

<subsubsection><tid>262904</tid>
<number>xii</number>the conditions subject to which the Board may borrow 
funds;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1146186</tid>
<number>xiii</number>the conditions subject to which and the manner in 
which contracts may be entered into by or on 
behalf of the Board;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1496125</tid>
<number>xiv</number>the delegation to committees or the Chairman or Vice- 
Chairman or members or officers of the Board of 
any of the powers and duties of the Board under 
this Act;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1110462</tid>
<number>xv</number>the staff which may be employed by the Board and the 
pay and allowances and leave and other conditions 
of service of officers and other employees of the 
Board;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1003878</tid>
<number>xvi</number>the travelling and other allowances of members of the 
Board and of committees thereof;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>924525</tid>
<number>xvii</number>the purposes for which the funds of the Board may be 
expended;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>717966</tid>
<number>xviii</number>the maintenance of the registers and other records 
of the Board and of its various committees;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1544065</tid>
<number>xix</number>the collection of any information or statistics in 
respect of rubber or any product of rubber;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1793410</tid>
<number>xx</number>the form of application for registration under section 
 10 or the cancellation of such registration, the 
fee

<pagefootnote><pagenum>63</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

payable on such applications, the procedure to be 
followed in granting or cancelling registration 
and the registers to be kept by the Board;


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>549595</tid>
<number>xxa</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the cases and circumstances in which the duty of 
excise under section 12 shall be payable by the 
owner and the manufacturers respectively, the 
manner in which the duty may be assessed, paid or 
collected, the regulation of the production, 
manufacture, transport or sale of rubber in so far 
as such regulation is necessary for the proper 
levy, payment or collection of the duty;]

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1586476</tid>
<number>xxi</number>the form of application for special licences under 
section 14 or section 17, the fees for the grant 
or renewal of such licences, and the forms of such 
licences;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1440882</tid>
<number>xxii</number>the manner in which rubber shall be graded and 
marketed;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>570905</tid>
<number>xxiii</number>the fee payable on appeals under section 23;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>103066</tid>
<number>xxiv</number>any other matter which is to be or may be 
prescribed.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1428837</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon 
as may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is 
in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or in two successive sessions, and if before the expiry of 
the session in which it is so laid or the session immediately 
following, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be, so however that any such modification or annulment 
shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done 
under that rule.]]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1629498</tid>
<number> 26</number> Penalties. <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>
<section><tid>748717</tid>
<number>1</number>] If any person-- 

<subsection><tid>144593</tid>
<number>a</number>contravenes any provision of this Act, other than 
section 11 or section 13, or any rule made under this 
Act, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>667389</tid>
<number>b</number>in any report or return to be furnished under this Act, 
makes any statement which is false and which he knows 
to be false or does not believe to be true, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>82232</tid>
<number>c</number>obstructs any officer of the Board in the discharge of 
any duty imposed on or entrusted to him by or under 
this Act, or
<pagefootnote><pagenum>64</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 21 of <year>1960</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 1. 11. <year>1960</year>). 
2. Subs. by s. 3, ibid, for sub- section (3)  (w. e. f. 1. 11. <year>1960</year>). 
3. S. 26 was renumbered as sub- section (1) of that section by Act 54 
of <year>1954</year>, s. 19.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1444254</tid>
<number>d</number>having the control or custody of any account book or 
other record, fails to produce such book or record when 
required by any authorized officer to do so,
he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to one year, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or 
with both.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1249419</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> If the person committing any offence under sub- section (1) 
is a company, every person who at the time the offence was committed 
was in charge of, and was responsible to, the company for the conduct 
of the business of the company, as well as the company, shall be 
deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded 
against and punished accordingly:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to any punishment provided in this Act if he 
proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or that he 
exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.


</section>

<section><tid>1634032</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (2), where 
an offence under sub- section (1) has been committed by a company and 
it is proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or 
connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any 
director or manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such 
director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to 
be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against 
and punished accordingly.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section,--


<subsection><tid>1975358</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means any body corporate, and includes a firm 
or other association of individuals; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>975164</tid>
<number>b</number>" director" in relation to a firm means a partner in the 
firm.]



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>315637</tid>
<number>27</number>Procedure for prosecutions. No prosecution for any offence 
punishable under this Act shall be instituted except by or with the 
consent of the Central Government or the Board.


</article>



<article><tid>1749902</tid>
<number>27A</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Jurisdiction of Courts. No Court inferior to that of a 
Presidency Magistrate or a Magistrate of the first class shall try any 
offence punishable under this Act.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>64A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 54 of <year>1954</year>, s. 19. 
2. Ins. by s. 20, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>1413642</tid>
<number>28</number>Bar of legal proceedings. No suit, prosecution or other legal 
proceedings shall lie against the Board or any officer of the Board 
for anything in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1944523</tid>
<number>29</number>[ Temporary powers of the Central Government.] Rep. by the 
Rubber (Production and Marketing) Amendment Act, <year>1954</year> (54 of <year>1954</year>), s. 
21.
</article>



 </act>