<act> 
 
The ARMED FORCES (JAMMU 
AND KASHMIR)  
SPECIAL POWERS ACT, 1990
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title, extent 
and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
This Act may be called the Armed Forces (Jammu 
and Kashmir) 
Special Powers Act, 1990.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends to the 
whole of the State of Jammu and Kashmir.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall be deemed to 
have come into force on the 5th day of July, 1990.
</section></article> 
 
The ARMED FORCES (JAMMU AND 
KASHMIR)  
 SPECIAL POWERS ACT, 1990
 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  “armed forces” means the 
military forces and the air forces operating as land forces and includes any 
other armed forces of the Union so 
operating;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  “disturbed area” means an area 
which is for the time being declared by notification under section 3 to be a 
disturbed areas;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  all other words and expressions 
used herein, but not defined and defined in the Air Force Act, 1950 (45 of 
1950), or the Army Act, 1950 (46 of 1950), shall have the meanings respectively 
assigned to them in those Acts.
</section></article> 
 
The ARMED FORCES (JAMMU AND 
KASHMIR)  
 SPECIAL POWERS ACT, 1990
 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Power to declare areas 
to be disturbed areas.—If, 
in relation to the State of Jammu and Kashmir, the Governor of that State or 
the Central Government, is of opinion that the whole or any part of the State 
is in such a disturbed and dangerous condition that the use of armed forces in 
aid of the civil power is necessary to prevent— 
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  activities involving terrorist 
acts directed towards overawing the Government as by law established or 
striking terror in the people or any section of the people or alienating any 
section of the people or adversely affecting the harmony amongst different 
sections of the people;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  activities directed towards 
disclaiming, questioning or disrupting the sovereignty and territorial 
integrity of India or bringing about cession of a part of the territory of 
India or secession of a part of the territory of India from the Union or 
causing insult to the Indian National Flag, the Indian National Anthem and the 
Constitution of India,
 
the Governor of the State or the Central Government, may, by notification in 
the Official Gazette, declare the whole or any part of the State to be a 
disturbed area.
 
Explanation.—In 
this section, “terrorist act” has the same meaning as in Explanation to 
Article 248 of the Constitution of India as applicable to the State of Jammu and Kashmir.


</section></article> 
 
The ARMED FORCES (JAMMU AND 
KASHMIR)  
 SPECIAL POWERS ACT, 1990
 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Special powers of the 
armed forces.—Any 
commissioned officer, warrant officer, non-commissioned officer or any other 
person of equivalent rank in the armed forces may, in a disturbed area,— 

 <section>
       <number>a</number>  if he is of opinion that it is 
necessary so to do for the maintenance of public order, after giving such due 
warning as he may consider necessary, fire upon or otherwise use force, even to 
the causing of death, against any person who is acting in contravention of any 
law or order for the time being in force in the disturbed area prohibiting the 
assembly of five or more persons or the carrying of weapons or of things 
capable of being used as weapons or of fire-arms, ammunition or explosive 
substances;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  if he is of opinion that it is 
necessary so to do, destroy any arms dump, prepared or fortified position or 
shelter from which armed attacks are made or are likely to be made or are 
attempted to be made, or any structure used as a training camp for armed 
volunteers or utilised as a hide-out by armed gangs or absconders wanted for 
any offence;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  arrest, without warrant, any 
person who has committed a cognizable offence or against whom a reasonable 
suspicion exists that he has committed or is about to commit a cognizable 
offence and may use such force as may be necessary to effect the arrest;
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  enter the search, without 
warrant, any premises to make any such arrest as aforesaid or to recover any 
person believed to be wrongfully restrained or confined or any property 
reasonably suspected to be stolen property or any arms, ammunition or explosive 
substances believed to be unlawfully kept in such premises, and may for that 
purpose use such force as may be necessary, and seize any such property, arms, 
ammunition or explosive substances;
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number>  stop, search and seize any 
vehicle or vessel reasonably suspected to be carrying any person who is a 
proclaimed offender, or any person who has committed a non-cognizable offence, 
or against whom a reasonable suspicion exists that he has committed or is about 
to commit a non-cognizable offence, or any person who is carrying any arms, 
ammunition or explosive substance believed to be unlawfully held by him, and 
may, for that purpose, use such force as may be necessary to effect such 
stoppage, search of seizure, as the case may be.


</section></article> 
 
The ARMED FORCES (JAMMU AND 
KASHMIR)  
 SPECIAL POWERS ACT, 1990
 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Power of search to 
include powers to break open locks, etc.—Every 
person making a search under this Act shall have the power to break open the 
lock of any door, almirah, safe, box, cupboard, drawer, package or other thing, 
if the key thereof is withheld.
</article> 
 
The ARMED FORCES (JAMMU AND 
KASHMIR)  
 SPECIAL POWERS ACT, 1990
 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Arrested persons and 
seized property to be made over to the police.—Any 
person arrested and taken into custody under this Act and every property, arms, 
ammunition or explosive substance or any vehicle or vessel seized under this 
Act, shall be made over to the officer-in-charge of the nearest police station 
with the least possible delay, together with a report of the circumstances 
occasioning the arrest, or as the case may be, occasioning the seizure of such 
property, arms, ammunition or explosive substance or any vehicle or vessel, as 
the case may be.


</article> 
 The ARMED FORCES (JAMMU AND KASHMIR) 
  SPECIAL POWERS ACT, 1990
  
 <article><number>7</number> Protection of persons acting 
in good faith under this Act.—No prosecution, suit or other 
legal proceeding shall be instituted, except with the previous sanction of the 
Central Government, against any person in respect of anything done or purported 
to be done in exercise of the powers conferred by this Act.
  </article> 
 
The ARMED FORCES (JAMMU AND 
KASHMIR)  
 SPECIAL POWERS ACT, 1990
 
 
 <article>
 <number>8</number> Repeal and saving.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Armed Forces (Jammu 
and Kashmir) Special Powers Ordinance, 1990 (Ord. 3 of 1990), is hereby 
repealed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding such 
repeal, anything done or any action taken under the said Ordinance shall be 
deemed to have been done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this 
Act.
 
 

</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>