<act><title>

The Criminal 
    Courts and Border Security Force Courts (Adjustment
    of Jurisdiction) rules, 19691</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title.—These 
    rules may be called the Criminal Court and Border Security Force Courts 
    (Adjustment of Jurisdiction) Rules, 1969.
 



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 <section>
<number>i</number>    “Act” means the Border Security Force 
    Act, 1968 (47 of 1968); 
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    “Commandant” in relation to a person 
    subject to the Act, means the Officer Commanding the unit or detachment to 
    which such person belongs or is attached; 
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>    “Competent Authority” means the 
    Director-General, Inspector General, or a Deputy Inspector General of the 
    Border Security Force; 
 </section><section>
<number>iv</number>    Words and expressions used in these 
    rules and not defined but defined in the Act, shall have the meaning 
    respectively assigned to them in the Act. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Trial of person subject to the Act.—Where 
    a person subject to the Act, is brought before a magistrate and charged with 
    an offence for which he is liable to be tried by the Border Security Force 
    Court, such a Magistrate shall not proceed to try such persons or to inquire 
    with a view to his commitment for trial by the Court of Sessions or the High 
    Court for any offence triable by such Court, unless,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    he is of opinion, for reasons to be 
    recorded in writing that he should so proceed without being moved thereto by 
    the Competent Authority; or 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    he is moved thereto by such authority. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Notice by Magistrate.—Before 
    proceeding under clause 
<section><number>a</number> of rule 3, the Magistrate shall give written 
    notice to the commandant of the accused and until the expiry of a period 
    of,— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    three weeks, in the case of a notice 
    given to a commandant in command of a unit or detachment located in any of 
    the following areas, that is to say— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>a</number>    State of Nagaland; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>b</number>    Mizo Hill, Garo Hill, Khasi and Jaintia 
    Hill and North Cachar Hill Districts of Assam, or 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    ten days in the case of a notice given 
    to any other commandant in command of a unit or detachment located elsewhere 
    in India, from the date of the service of such notice, he shall not— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>a</number>    convict or acquit the accused under 
    section 243 or section 245 or section 247 or section 248 of the Code of 
    Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898) or hear him in his defence under 
    section 244 of the said Code; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>b</number>    frame in writing a charge against the 
    accused under section 254 of the said Code; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>c</number>    make an order committing the accused 
    for trial by the High Court or the Court of Sessions under section 213 of 
    the said Code; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>d</number>    transfer the case for inquiry or trial 
    under section 192 of the said Code. 

 
  


</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Procedure on notice to the Magistrate.—Where 
    within the period mentioned in Rule 4 above, or at any time thereafter 
    before the Magistrate has done any act or made any order referred to in that 
    rule, the commandant of the accused or the competent authority, as the case 
    may be, gives notice to the Magistrate that in the opinion of such 
    authority, the accused should be tried by a Border Security Force Court, the 
    Magistrate shall stay proceedings and if the accused is in his power or 
    under his control, shall deliver him with the statement prescribed in 
    sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 549 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 
    1898) to the authority specified in said sub-section. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Procedure on notice to Magistrate before commencement of trial.—Where 
    a Magistrate has been moved by the competent authority under Clause (b) of 
    rule 3, and the Commandant of the accused or the competent authority, as the 
    case may be, subsequently gives notice to such Magistrate that in the 
    opinion of such authority the accused should be tried by a Border Security 
    Force Court, such magistrate if he has not before receiving such notice, 
    done any act or made any order referred to in rule 4, shall stay 
    proceedings, and, if the accused is in his power or under his control, shall 
    in the like manner deliver him, with the statement prescribed in sub-section 
    
<section><number>1</number> of section 549 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898) to 
    the authority specified in the said sub-section. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Intimation regarding trial of accused.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    When an accused has been delivered by the Magistrate under rules 5 or 6, the 
    commandant of the accused or the competent authority, as the case may be, 
    shall, as soon as may be, inform the Magistrate whether the accused has been 
    tried by a Border Security Force Court or other effectual proceedings have 
    been taken or ordered to be taken against him. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When 
    the Magistrate has been informed under sub-rule (1) that the accused has not 
    been tried or other effectual proceedings have not been taken or not ordered 
    to be taken against him, the Magistrate shall report the circumstances to 
    the State Government, take appropriate steps to ensure that the accused 
    person is dealt with in accordance with law. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Reference to Central Government for determination of court of trial.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in the foregoing rules, where it comes to the notice of a 
    Magistrate, that a person subject to the Act has committed an offence, 
    proceedings in respect of which ought to be instituted before him and that 
    the presence of such person cannot be procured except through the commandant 
    or the competent authority, the Magistrate may, by written notice, require 
    the commandant of such person either to deliver such person to a Magistrate 
    to be named in the said notice for being proceeded against according to law, 
    or to stay the proceedings against such person before the Border Security 
    Force Court, if since instituted, and to make reference to the Central 
    Government for determination as to the court before which proceedings should 
    be instituted. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Delivery of accused to the Magistrate.—Where 
    a person subject to the Act has committed an offence which, in the opinion 
    of competent authority ought to be tried by a Magistrate in accordance with 
    the Civil law in force or where the Central Government, on a reference 
    mentioned in rule 8, decides that the proceedings against such person should 
    be instituted before a Magistrate, the commandant of such person shall, 
    after giving a written notice to the Magistrate concerned deliver such 
    person under proper escort to that Magistrate. 
  

 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>