<act><tid>807876</tid>
<title>THE COMPANY SECRETARIES (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2006</year></title>

NO. 8 OF <year>2006</year>
[ 17th March, <year>2006</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Company Secretaries Act, <year>1980</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- seventh Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>124121</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>57672</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Company Secretaries (Amendment) Act, <year>2006</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>869345</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint:
Provided that different dates may be appointed for different 
provisions of this Act and any reference in any such provision to the 
commencement of this Act shall be construed as a reference to the 
commencement of that provision.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1359410</tid>
<number> 2</number> Amendment of section 2.- In the Company Secretaries Act, <year>1980</year> (56  
  of <year>1980</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the principal Act), in sub- 
section
<section><tid>66808</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 2,- 

<subsection><tid>977695</tid>
<number>i</number>after clause (a), the following clauses shall be inserted, 
namely:-
' (aa)" Authority" means the Appellate Authority referred to in 
section 22A;


<subsubsection><tid>243303</tid>
<number>aaa</number>" Board" means the Quality Review Board constituted under 
section 29A;';

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>712484</tid>
<number>ii</number>after clause (g), the following clause shall be inserted, 
namely:-
' (ga)" notification" means a notification published in the Official 
Gazette;'; 
 (iii) after clause (j), the following clauses shall be inserted, 
namely:-

' (ja)" specified" means specified by rules made by the Central 
Government under this Act;


<subsubsection><tid>1212746</tid>
<number>jb</number>" Tribunal" means a Tribunal established under sub- section (1) of 
section 10B;'.



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1022654</tid>
<number>3</number>Amendment of section 4.- In section 4 of the principal Act, for 
sub- section (3), the following sub- section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (3) Every person belonging to any of the classes mentioned in 
clauses (c), (d) and (e) of sub- section (1) shall have his name 
entered in the Register on application being made and granted in the 
prescribed manner and on payment of such fees, as may be determined, 
by notification, by the Council, which shall not exceed rupees three 
thousand:

Provided that the Council may with the prior approval of the Central 
Government, determine the fee exceeding rupees three thousand, which 
shall not in any case exceed rupees six thousand.".



</article>



<article><tid>224645</tid>
<number>4</number>Amendment of section 5.- In section 5 of the principal Act, for 
sub- section (3), the following sub- section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (3) A person, being an Associate who has been in continuous practice 
in India as a Company Secretary for at least five years and a person 
who has been an Associate for a continuous period of not less than 
five years and who possesses such qualifications or practical 
experience as the Council may prescribe with a view to ensuring that 
he has experience equivalent to the experience normally acquired as a 
result of continuous practice for a period of five years as a Company 
Secretary shall, on payment of such fees, as may be determined, by 
notification, by the Council, which shall not exceed rupees five 
thousand, and on application made and granted in the prescribed 
manner, be entered in the Register as a Fellow:

Provided that the Council may with the prior approval of the Central 
Government, determine the fee exceeding rupees five thousand, which 
shall not in any case exceed rupees ten thousand.

Explanation I.- For the purposes of this sub- section, a person shall 
be deemed to have practised in India for any period for which he has 
held a certificate of practice under section 6, notwithstanding that 
he did not actually practise during that period.

Explanation II.- In computing the continuous period during which a 
person has been an Associate of the Institute, there shall be 
included any continuous period during which the person has been an 
Associate of the dissolved company immediately before he became an 
Associate of the Institute.".



</article>



<article><tid>1496593</tid>
<number> 5</number> Amendment of section 6.- In section 6 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1555589</tid>
<number>i</number>for sub- section (2), the following sub- section shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (2) A member who desires to be entitled to practise shall make an 
application in such form and pay such annual fee, for his certificate 
as may be determined, by notification, by the Council, which shall 
not exceed rupees three thousand, and such fee shall be payable on or 
before the 1st day of April in each year:

Provided that the Council may with the prior approval of the Central 
Government, determine the fee exceeding rupees three thousand, which 
shall not in any case exceed rupees six thousand.";


</section>

<section><tid>350622</tid>
<number>ii</number>after sub- section (2), the following sub- section shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (3) The certificate of practice obtained under sub- section (1) may 
be cancelled by the Council under such circumstances as may be 
prescribed.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1455392</tid>
<number> 6</number> Amendment of section 9.- In section 9 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>292999</tid>
<number>i</number>for sub- section (2), the following sub- section shall be 
substituted, namely:- 
" (2) The Council shall be composed of the following persons, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1535064</tid>
<number>a</number>not more than fifteen persons elected by the members of the 
Institute, from amongst the Fellows of the Institute chosen in such 
manner and from such regional constituencies as may be specified:
Provided that a Fellow of the Institute, who has been found guilty of 
any professional or other misconduct and whose name is removed from 
the Register or has been awarded penalty of fine, shall not be 
eligible to contest the election,-


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>292999</tid>
<number>i</number>in case of misconduct falling under the First Schedule of this 
Act, for a period of three years;

</section>

<section><tid>1863815</tid>
<number>ii</number>in case of misconduct falling under the Second Schedule of this 
Act, for a period of six years,
from the completion of the period of removal of name from the 
Register or payment of fine, as the case may be;


<subsection><tid>326468</tid>
<number>b</number>not more than five persons nominated in the specified manner by 
the Central Government.";

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1863815</tid>
<number>ii</number>after sub- section (2), the following sub- sections shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (3) No person holding a post under the Central Government or a State 
Government shall be eligible for election to the Council under clause 
 (a) of sub- section (2).


<subsection><tid>506064</tid>
<number>4</number>No person who has been auditor of the Institute shall be eligible 
for election to the Council under clause (a) of sub- section (2) for a 
period of three years after he ceases to be an auditor.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1103999</tid>
<number>7</number>Substitution of new section for section 10.- For section 10 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
" 10. Re- election or re- nomination to Council.- A member of the 
Council, elected or nominated under sub- section (2) of section 9, 
shall be eligible for re- election or, as the case may be, re- 
nomination:

Provided that no member shall hold the office for more than two 
consecutive terms:

Provided further that a member of the Council, who is or has been 
elected as President under sub- section (1) of section 12, shall not 
be eligible for election or nomination as a member of the Council.".



</article>



<article><tid>784011</tid>
<number>8</number>Insertion of new sections 10A and 10B.- After section 10 of the 
principal Act, the following sections shall be inserted, namely:-
" 10A. Settlement of disputes regarding election.- In case of any 
dispute regarding any election under clause (a) of sub- section (2) of 
section 9, the aggrieved person may make an application within thirty 
days from the date of declaration of the result of election to the 
Secretary of the Institute, who shall forward the same to the Central 
Government.

</article>



<article><tid>1933463</tid>
<number> 10B</number> Establishment of Tribunal.-
<section><tid>1578338</tid>
<number>1</number>On receipt of any application  
under section 10A, the Central Government shall, by notification, 
establish a Tribunal consisting of a Presiding Officer and two other 
Members to decide such dispute and the decision of such Tribunal 
shall be final.

</section>

<section><tid>1605801</tid>
<number>2</number>A person shall not be qualified for appointment,-

<subsection><tid>620474</tid>
<number>a</number>as a Presiding Officer of the Tribunal unless he has been a 
member of the Indian Legal Service and has held a post in Grade I of 
the service for at least three years;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1221316</tid>
<number>b</number>as a Member unless he has been a member of the Council for at 
least one full term and who is not a sitting member of the Council or 
who has not been a candidate in the election under dispute; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>461026</tid>
<number>c</number>as a Member unless he holds the post of a Joint Secretary to the 
Government of India or any other post under the Central Government 
carrying a scale of pay which is not less than that of a Joint 
Secretary to the Government of India.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1907821</tid>
<number>3</number>The terms and conditions of service of the Presiding Officer and 
Members of the Tribunal, their place of meetings and allowances shall 
be such as may be specified.

</section>

<section><tid>368606</tid>
<number>4</number>The expenses of the Tribunal shall be borne by the Council.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1802022</tid>
<number> 9</number> Amendment of section 12.- In section 12 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1277161</tid>
<number>i</number>in sub- section (2), for the words" Chief Executive Authority", 
the word" Head" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>571041</tid>
<number>ii</number>in sub- section (3), after the words" he shall be eligible for 
re- election", the words, brackets and figure" under sub- section (1)" 
shall be inserted;

</section>

<section><tid>192941</tid>
<number>iii</number>for sub- section (4), the following sub- section shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (4) On the expiration of the duration of the Council, or of the term 
of office of the President and the Vice- President thereof, the 
President and the Vice- President shall continue to hold office until 
such time as a new President and the Vice- President is elected and 
takes over charge of their duties.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1594144</tid>
<number> 10</number> Amendment of section 13.- In section 13 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>263029</tid>
<number>i</number>in sub- section (2), after the words" meetings of the Council", 
the words" or he has been found guilty of any professional or other 
misconduct and awarded penalty of fine," shall be inserted;

</section>

<section><tid>642339</tid>
<number>ii</number>in the proviso to sub- section (3), for the words" six months", 
the words" one year" shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>120894</tid>
<number>11</number>Amendment of section 14.- In section 14 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, for the words" three years", the words" four years" 
shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1232855</tid>
<number> 12</number> Substitution of new section for section 15.- For section 15 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
" 15. Functions of Council.- (1) The Institute shall function under the 
overall control, guidance and supervision of the Council and the duty 
of carrying out the provisions of this Act shall be vested in the 
Council.

<section><tid>1334614</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing powers, the duties of the Council shall include-

<subsection><tid>1772898</tid>
<number>a</number>to approve academic courses and their contents;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1359511</tid>
<number>b</number>the prescribing of fees for the examination of candidates for 
enrolment;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1290916</tid>
<number>c</number>the prescribing of qualifications for entry in the Register;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>166872</tid>
<number>d</number>the recognition of foreign qualifications and training for 
purposes of enrolment;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1751676</tid>
<number>e</number>the prescribing of guidelines for granting or refusal of 
certificates of practice under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>889068</tid>
<number>f</number>the levy of fees from members, examinees and other persons;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1175728</tid>
<number>g</number>the regulation and maintenance of the status and standard of 
professional qualifications of members of the Institute;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>755731</tid>
<number>h</number>the carrying out, by granting financial assistance to persons 
other than members of the Council or in any other manner, of research 
in such matters of interest to Company Secretaries as may be 
prescribed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1835775</tid>
<number>i</number>to enable functioning of the Director (Discipline), the Board of 
Discipline, the Disciplinary Committee and the Appellate Authority 
constituted under the provisions of this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1536462</tid>
<number>j</number>to enable functioning of the Quality Review Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>837752</tid>
<number>k</number>consideration of the recommendations of the Quality Review Board 
made under clause (a) of section 29B and details of action taken 
thereon in its annual report; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1883544</tid>
<number>l</number>to ensure the functioning of the Institute in accordance with the 
provisions of this Act and in performance of other statutory duties 
as may be entrusted to the Institute from time to time.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1632443</tid>
<number> 13</number> Insertion of new sections 15A and 15B.- After section 15 of the 
principal Act, the following sections shall be inserted, namely:-
" 15A. Functions of Institute.- The functions of the Institute shall 
include-

<section><tid>1898014</tid>
<number>a</number>the examination of candidates for enrolment;

</section>

<section><tid>1961984</tid>
<number>b</number>the regulation of training of students;

</section>

<section><tid>1709135</tid>
<number>c</number>the maintenance and publication of a Register of persons 
qualified to practice as Company Secretaries;

</section>

<section><tid>1920080</tid>
<number>d</number>collection of fees from members, examinees and other persons;

</section>

<section><tid>1924463</tid>
<number>e</number>subject to the orders of the appropriate authorities under this 
Act, the removal of names from the Register and the restoration to 
the Register of names which have been removed;

</section>

<section><tid>1357311</tid>
<number>f</number>the maintenance of a library and publication of books and 
periodicals relating to management of companies and allied subjects;

</section>

<section><tid>543538</tid>
<number>g</number>the conduct of elections to the Council of the Institute; and

</section>

<section><tid>345242</tid>
<number>h</number>the granting or refusal of certificates of practice as per 
guidelines issued by the Council.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>726120</tid>
<number> 15B</number> Imparting education by Universities and other bodies.-
<section><tid>279300</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Subject to the provisions of this Act, any University established by 
law or any body affiliated to the Institute, may impart education on 
the subjects covered by the academic courses of the Institute.

</section>

<section><tid>622024</tid>
<number>2</number>The Universities or bodies referred to in sub- section (1) shall, 
while awarding degree, diploma or certificate or bestowing any 
designation, ensure that the award or designation do not resemble or 
is not identical to one awarded by the Institute.

</section>

<section><tid>221978</tid>
<number>3</number>Nothing contained in this section shall enable a University or a 
body to adopt a name or nomenclature which is in any way similar to 
that of the Institute.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>466571</tid>
<number> 14</number> Substitution of new section for section 16.- For section 16 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
" 16. Officers and employees, salary, allowances, etc.- (1) For the 
efficient performance of its duties, the Council shall-

<section><tid>1565397</tid>
<number>a</number>appoint a Secretary of the Council to perform such duties as may 
be prescribed;

</section>

<section><tid>1743169</tid>
<number>b</number>appoint a Director (Discipline) to perform such functions as 
assigned to him under this Act and the rules and regulations framed 
thereunder;

</section>

<section><tid>1742526</tid>
<number>c</number>designate an officer of the Council or the Institute to carry out 
the administrative functions of the Institute as its chief executive.

<subsection><tid>520345</tid>
<number>2</number>The Council may also-

<subsubsection><tid>1179666</tid>
<number>a</number>appoint such other officers and employees to the Council and the 
Institute as it considers necessary;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>231454</tid>
<number>b</number>require and take from the Secretary or from any other officer or 
employee of the Council and the Institute such security for the due 
performance of his duties, as the Council considers necessary;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>392799</tid>
<number>c</number>prescribe the salaries, fees, allowances of the officers and 
employees of the Council and the Institute and their terms and 
conditions of service;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>966991</tid>
<number>d</number>with the previous sanction of the Central Government, fix the 
allowances of the President, Vice- President and other members of the 
Council and members of its Committees;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1731096</tid>
<number>3</number>The Secretary of the Council shall be entitled to participate in 
the meetings of the Council but shall not be entitled to vote 
thereat.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1004671</tid>
<number> 15</number> Amendment of section 17.- In section 17 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>790509</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1), for clause (b), the following clause shall 
be substituted, namely:-
" (b) a Finance Committee; and"; 
 (b) for sub- section (3), the following sub- section shall be 
substituted, namely:-

" (3) Each of the Standing Committees shall consist of the President 
and the Vice- President ex officio, and minimum of three and maximum 
of five members to be elected by the Council from amongst its 
members.";


</section>

<section><tid>572861</tid>
<number>c</number>sub- sections (4) and (5) shall be omitted;

</section>

<section><tid>1209017</tid>
<number>d</number>in sub- section (6), for the words" two- thirds of the total 
membership of the Committee", the words" one- third of the total 
membership of the Committee" shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>686833</tid>
<number> 16</number> Amendment of section 18.- In section 18 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1371085</tid>
<number>i</number>for sub- sections (3), (4) and (5), the following sub- sections 
shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (3) The Council shall keep proper accounts of the fund 
distinguishing capital from revenue in the manner prescribed.


<subsection><tid>838476</tid>
<number>4</number>The Council shall prepare in the manner prescribed and approve, 
prior to the start of the financial year, an annual financial 
statement (the budget) indicating all its anticipated revenues as 
well as all proposed expenditures for the forthcoming year.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1093659</tid>
<number>5</number>The annual accounts of the Council shall be prepared in such 
manner as may be prescribed and be subject to audit by a Chartered 
Accountant in practice to be appointed annually by the Council:
Provided that no member of the Council or a person who has been a 
member of the Council during the last four years or a person who is 
in partnership with such member shall be eligible for appointment as 
an auditor under this sub- section:

Provided further that, in the event it is brought to the notice of 
the Council that the accounts of the Council do not represent a true 
and fair view of its finances, then, the Council may itself cause a 
special audit to be conducted:

Provided also that if such information, that the accounts of the 
Council do not represent a true and fair view of its finances, is 
sent to the Council by the Central Government, then, the Council may, 
wherever appropriate cause a special audit or take such other action 
as it considers necessary and shall furnish an action taken report on 
it to the Central Government.";


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>478871</tid>
<number>ii</number>after sub- section (5), the following sub- sections shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (5A) As soon as may be practicable at the end of each year, the 
Council shall circulate the audited accounts to its members at least 
fifteen days in advance and consider and approve these accounts in a 
special meeting convened for the purpose.


<subsection><tid>1467728</tid>
<number>5B</number>The Council shall cause to be published in the Gazette of India 
not later than the 30th day of September of the year next following, 
a copy of the audited accounts and the Report of the Council for that 
year duly approved by the Council and copies of the said accounts and 
Report shall be forwarded to the Central Government and to all the 
members of the Institute.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1964216</tid>
<number> 17</number> Amendment of section 19.- In section 19 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>852374</tid>
<number>i</number>in sub- section (3), the words" on payment of such amount as may 
be prescribed" shall be inserted at the end;

</section>

<section><tid>357579</tid>
<number>ii</number>for sub- section (4), the following sub- section shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (4) Every member of the Institute shall, on his name being entered 
in the Register, pay such annual membership fee as may be determined, 
by notification, by the Council, which shall not exceed rupees five 
thousand:

Provided that the Council may with the prior approval of the Central 
Government, determine the fee exceeding rupees five thousand which 
shall not in any case exceed rupees ten thousand.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1489372</tid>
<number>18</number>Amendment of section 20.- In section 20 of the principal Act, 
after sub- section (2), the following sub- section shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" (3) If the name of any member has been removed from the Register 
under clause (c) of sub- section (1), on receipt of an application, 
his name may be entered again in the Register on payment of the 
arrears of annual fee and entrance fee along with such additional 
fee, as may be determined, by notification, by the Council, which 
shall not exceed rupees two thousand:

Provided that the Council may with the prior approval of the Central 
Government, determine the fee exceeding rupees two thousand, which 
shall not in any case exceed rupees four thousand.".


</article>



<article><tid>798425</tid>
<number> 19</number> Substitution of new section for section 21.- For section 21 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
" 21. Disciplinary Directorate.- (1) The Council shall, by 
notification, establish a Disciplinary Directorate headed by an 
officer of the Institute designated as Director (Discipline) and such 
other employees for making investigations in respect of any 
information or complaint received by it.

<section><tid>13703</tid>
<number>2</number>On receipt of any information or complaint along with the 
prescribed fee, the Director (Discipline) shall arrive at a prima 
facie opinion on the occurrence of the alleged misconduct.

</section>

<section><tid>1253941</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the Director (Discipline) is of the opinion that a member 
is guilty of any professional or other misconduct mentioned in the 
First Schedule, he shall place the matter before the Board of 
Discipline and where the Director (Discipline) is of the opinion that 
a member is guilty of any professional or other misconduct mentioned 
in the Second Schedule or in both the Schedules, he shall place the 
matter before the Disciplinary Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>1522792</tid>
<number>4</number>In order to make investigations under the provisions of this Act, 
the Disciplinary Directorate shall follow such procedure as may be 
specified.

</section>

<section><tid>1054015</tid>
<number>5</number>Where a complainant withdraws the complaint, the Director 
 (Discipline) shall place such withdrawal before the Board of 
Discipline or as the case may be, the Disciplinary Committee, and the 
said Board or Committee may, if it is of the view that the 
circumstances so warrant, permit the withdrawal at any stage.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>52132</tid>
<number> 20</number> Insertion of new sections 21A, 21B, 21C and 21D.- After section 21 
of the principal Act, the following sections shall be inserted, 
namely:-
' 21A. Board of Discipline.- (1) The Council shall constitute a Board 
of Discipline consisting of-

<section><tid>497600</tid>
<number>a</number>a person with experience in law and having knowledge of the 
disciplinary matters and the profession, to be its presiding officer;

</section>

<section><tid>1506017</tid>
<number>b</number>two members one of whom shall be a member of the Council elected 
by the Council and the other member shall be the person designated 
under clause (c) of sub- section (1) of section 16;

</section>

<section><tid>1113954</tid>
<number>c</number>the Director (Discipline) shall function as the Secretary of the 
Board.

<subsection><tid>792267</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board of Discipline shall follow summary disposal procedure 
in dealing with all the cases before it. 
 (3) Where the Board of Discipline is of the opinion that a member is 
guilty of a professional or other misconduct mentioned in the First 
Schedule, it shall afford to the member an opportunity of being heard 
before making any order against him and may thereafter take any one 
or more of the following actions, namely:-

<subsubsection><tid>307525</tid>
<number>a</number>reprimand the member;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>615842</tid>
<number>b</number>remove the name of the member from the Register up to a period of 
three months;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1680616</tid>
<number>c</number>impose such fine as it may think fit which may extend to rupees 
one lakh.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1913083</tid>
<number>4</number>The Director (Discipline) shall submit before the Board of 
Discipline all information and complaints where he is of the opinion 
that there is no prima facie case and the Board of Discipline may, 
if it agrees with the opinion of the Director (Discipline), close the 
matter or in case of disagreement, may advise the Director 
 (Discipline) to further investigate the matter.

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1465972</tid>
<number> 21B</number> Disciplinary Committee.-
<section><tid>771323</tid>
<number>1</number>The Council shall constitute a  
Disciplinary Committee consisting of the President or the Vice- 
President of the Council as the Presiding Officer and two members to 
be elected from amongst the members of the Council and two members to 
be nominated by the Central Government from amongst the persons of 
eminence having experience in the field of law, economics, business, 
finance or accountancy:
Provided that the Council may constitute more Disciplinary Committees 
as and when it considers necessary.


</section>

<section><tid>1933492</tid>
<number>2</number>The Disciplinary Committee, while considering the cases placed 
before it, shall follow such procedure as may be specified.

</section>

<section><tid>266804</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the Disciplinary Committee is of the opinion that a member 
is guilty of a professional or other misconduct mentioned in the 
Second Schedule or both the First Schedule and the Second Schedule, 
it shall afford to the member an opportunity of being heard before 
making any order against him and may thereafter take any one or more 
of the following actions, namely:-

<subsection><tid>151860</tid>
<number>a</number>reprimand the member;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1453304</tid>
<number>b</number>remove the name of the member from the Register permanently or 
for such period, as it thinks fit;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>450540</tid>
<number>c</number>impose such fine as it may think fit, which may extend to rupees 
five lakhs.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>133516</tid>
<number>4</number>The allowances payable to the members nominated by the Central 
Government shall be such as may be specified.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1583976</tid>
<number> 21C</number> Authority, Disciplinary Committee, Board of Discipline and 
Director (Discipline) to have powers of civil court.- For the purposes 
of an inquiry under the provisions of this Act, the Authority, the 
Disciplinary Committee, Board of Discipline and the Director 
 (Discipline) shall have the same powers as are vested in a civil 
court under the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>), in respect 
of the following matters, namely:-
<section><tid>388694</tid>
<number>a</number>summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person and 
examining him on oath;

</section>

<section><tid>943263</tid>
<number>b</number>the discovery and production of any document; and 
 (c) receiving evidence on affidavit.
Explanation.- For the purposes of sections 21, 21A, 21B, 21C and 22, 
" member of the Institute" includes a person who was a member of the 
Institute on the date of the alleged misconduct although he has 
ceased to be a member of the Institute at the time of the inquiry.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>331808</tid>
<number>21D</number>Transitional provisions.- All complaints pending before the 
Council or any inquiry initiated by the Disciplinary Committee or any 
reference or appeal made to a High Court prior to the commencement of 
the Company Secretaries (Amendment) Act, <year>2006</year> shall continue to be 
governed by the provisions of this Act, as if this Act had not been 
amended by the Company Secretaries (Amendment) Act, <year>2006</year>.'.


</article>



<article><tid>1401275</tid>
<number>21</number>Substitution of new section for section 22.- For section 22 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
' 22. Professional or other misconduct defined.- For the purposes of 
this Act, the expression" professional or other misconduct" shall be 
deemed to include any act or omission provided in any of the 
Schedules, but nothing in this section shall be construed to limit or 
abridge in any way the power conferred or duty cast on the Director 
 (Discipline) under sub- section (1) of section 21 to inquire into the 
conduct of any member of the Institute under any other 
circumstances.'.



</article>



<article><tid>1279003</tid>
<number>22</number>Insertion of new section 22A, 22B, 22C, 22D and 22E.- After 
section 22 of the principal Act, the following sections shall be 
inserted, namely:-
' 22A. Constitution of Appellate Authority.- The Appellate Authority 
constituted under sub- section (1) of section 22A of the Chartered 
Accountants Act, <year>1949</year> (38 of <year>1949</year>), shall be deemed to be the 
Appellate Authority for the purposes of this Act subject to the 
modification that for clause (b) of said sub- section (1), the 
following clause had been substituted, namely:-

" (b) the Central Government shall, by notification appoint two part- 
time members from amongst the persons who have been members of the 
Council of the Institute of Company Secretaries of India for at least 
one full term and who is not a sitting member of the Council;".

</article>



<article><tid>391539</tid>
<number>22B</number>Term of office of members of Authority.- A person appointed as a 
member shall hold office for a term of three years from the date on 
which he enters upon his office or until he attains the age of sixty- 
two years, whichever is earlier. 
22C. Procedure, etc., of Authority.- The provisions of section 22C, 
section 22D and section 22F of the Chartered Accountants Act, <year>1949</year> 
 (38 of <year>1949</year>) shall apply to the Authority in relation to allowances 
and terms and conditions of service of its Chairperson and members, 
and in the discharge of its functions under this Act as they apply to 
it in the discharge of its functions under the Chartered Accountants 
Act, <year>1949</year>.
</article>



<article><tid>1605939</tid>
<number> 22D</number> Officers and other staff of Authority.-
<section><tid>245620</tid>
<number>1</number>The Council shall  
make available to the Authority such officers and other staff members 
as may be necessary for the efficient performance of the functions of 
the Authority.

</section>

<section><tid>1087700</tid>
<number>2</number>The salaries and allowances and conditions of service of the 
officers and other staff members of the Authority shall be such as 
may be prescribed.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1940681</tid>
<number> 22E</number> Appeal to Authority.-
<section><tid>900218</tid>
<number>1</number>Any member of the Institute aggrieved  
by any order of the Board of Discipline or the Disciplinary Committee 
imposing on him any of the penalties referred to in sub- section (3) 
of section 21A and sub- section (3) of section 21B, may within ninety 
days from the date on which the order is communicated to him, prefer 
an appeal to the Authority:
Provided that the Director (Discipline) may also appeal against the 
decision of the Board of Discipline or the Disciplinary Committee to 
the Authority if so authorised by the Council, within ninety days:

Provided further that the Authority may entertain any such appeal 
after the expiry of the said period of ninety days, if it is 
satisfied that there was sufficient cause for not filing the appeal 
in time.


</section>

<section><tid>1464371</tid>
<number>2</number>The Authority may, after calling for the records of any case, 
revise any order made by the Board of Discipline or the Disciplinary 
Committee under sub- section (3) of section 21A and sub- section (3) of 
section 21B and may-

<subsection><tid>409734</tid>
<number>a</number>confirm, modify or set aside the order;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1370275</tid>
<number>b</number>impose any penalty or set aside, reduce, or enhance the penalty 
imposed by the order;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1853171</tid>
<number>c</number>remit the case to the Board of Discipline or Disciplinary 
Committee for such further enquiry as the Authority considers proper 
in the circumstances of the case; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>339738</tid>
<number>d</number>pass such other order as the Authority thinks fit: 
Provided that the Authority shall give an opportunity of being heard 
to the parties concerned before passing any order.'.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1463369</tid>
<number>23</number>Amendment of section 25.- In section 25 of the principal Act, sub- 
section (3) shall be omitted. 
24.
Amendment of section 27.

</article>



<article><tid>75793</tid>
<number>24</number>Amendment of section 27.- In section 27 of the principal Act, for 
sub- section (2), the following sub- section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (2) Any person who contravenes the provisions of sub- section (1) 
shall, without prejudice to any other proceedings which may be taken 
against him, be punishable on first conviction with a fine not less 
than five thousand rupees but which may extend to one lakh rupees, 
and in the event of a second or subsequent conviction with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year or with a fine 
not less than ten thousand rupees but which may extend to two lakh 
rupees or with both.".



</article>



<article><tid>221913</tid>
<number>25</number>Insertion of new Chapter VIIA.- After Chapter VII of the principal 
Act, the following Chapter shall be inserted, namely:-
" CHAPTER VII A

QUALITY REVIEW BOARD

</article>



<article><tid>683076</tid>
<number> 29A</number> Establishment of Quality Review Board.-
<section><tid>1913482</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government shall, by notification, constitute a Quality Review Board 
consisting of a Chairperson and four other members.

</section>

<section><tid>1200962</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chairperson and members of the Board shall be appointed from 
amongst the persons of eminence having experience in the field of 
law, economics, business, finance or accountancy.

</section>

<section><tid>620784</tid>
<number>3</number>Two members of the Board shall be nominated by the Council and 
other two members shall be nominated by the Central Government.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1750322</tid>
<number> 29B</number> Functions of Board.- The Board shall perform the following 
functions, namely:-
<section><tid>477428</tid>
<number>a</number>to make recommendations to the Council with regard to the quality 
of services provided by the members of the Institute;

</section>

<section><tid>589780</tid>
<number>b</number>to review the quality of services provided by the members of the 
Institute including secretarial services; and

</section>

<section><tid>532785</tid>
<number>c</number>to guide the members of the Institute to improve the quality of 
services and adherence to the various statutory and other regulatory 
requirements.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>914929</tid>
<number> 29C</number> Procedure of Board.- The Board shall meet at such time and place 
and follow in its meetings such procedure as may be specified. 
29D. Terms and conditions of service of Chairperson and members of 
Board and its expenditure.-
<section><tid>349324</tid>
<number>1</number>The terms and conditions of service of  
the Chairperson and the members of the Board, and their allowances 
shall be such as may be specified.

</section>

<section><tid>861686</tid>
<number>2</number>The expenditure of the Board shall be borne by the Council.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1249343</tid>
<number>26</number>Omission of section 30.- Section 30 of the principal Act shall be 
omitted.


</article>



<article><tid>666283</tid>
<number>27</number>Substitution of new section for section 36.- For section 36 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
" 36. Protection of action taken in good faith.- No suit, prosecution 
or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central Government or 
the Council or the Authority or the Disciplinary Committee or the 
Tribunal or the Board or the Board of Discipline or the Disciplinary 
Directorate or any officer of that Government, Council, Authority, 
Disciplinary Committee, Tribunal, Board, Board of Discipline or the 
Disciplinary Directorate, for anything which is in good faith done or 
intended to be done under this Act or any rule, regulation, 
notification, direction or order made thereunder.".



</article>



<article><tid>642915</tid>
<number>28</number>Insertion of new section 36A.- After section 36 of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 36A. Members, etc. to be public servants.- The Chairperson, Presiding 
Officer, members and other officers and employees of the Authority, 
Disciplinary Committee, Tribunal, Board, Board of Discipline or the 
Disciplinary Directorate shall be deemed to be public servants within 
the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code.".


</article>



<article><tid>1435895</tid>
<number> 29</number> Insertion of new section 38A.- After section 38 of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 38A. Power of Central Government to make rules. (1) The Central 
Government may, by notification, make rules to carry out the 
provisions of this Act.

<section><tid>1583889</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing powers, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1138722</tid>
<number>a</number>the manner of election and nomination in respect of members to 
the Council under sub- section (2) of section 9;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1118162</tid>
<number>b</number>the terms and conditions of service of the Presiding Officer and 
Members of the Tribunal, place of meetings and allowances to be paid 
to them under sub- section (3) of section 10B;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>682940</tid>
<number>c</number>the procedure of investigation under sub- section (4) of section 
21;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>10288</tid>
<number>d</number>the procedure while considering the cases by the Disciplinary 
Committee under sub- section (2) and fixation of allowances of the 
nominated members under sub- section (4) of section 21B;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>200817</tid>
<number>e</number>the procedure to be followed by the Board in its meetings under 
section 29C; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>145244</tid>
<number>f</number>the terms and conditions of service of the Chairperson and 
members of the Board under sub- section (1) of section 29D.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1601733</tid>
<number> 30</number> Amendment of section 39.- In section 39 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1920518</tid>
<number>i</number>in sub- section (2),-

<subsection><tid>732414</tid>
<number>a</number>in clause (a), for the word, brackets and figures" items (1), 
 (3)", the word, brackets and figure" item (2)" shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1293254</tid>
<number>b</number>in clause (d), the words, brackets and letter" clause (a) of" 
shall be omitted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1769811</tid>
<number>c</number>clause (g), clause (l) and clause (q) shall be omitted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>60629</tid>
<number>d</number>in clause (i), for the word, brackets and letter" clause (i)", 
the word, brackets and letter" clause (g)" shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>959411</tid>
<number>e</number>in clause (j), for the word, brackets and letter" clause (j)", 
the word, brackets and letter" clause (h)" shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1906926</tid>
<number>f</number>in clause (k), for the words, brackets, letter and figures 
" clause (k) of sub- section (2) of section 15", the words, brackets, 
letters and figures" clause (f) of section 15A" shall be substituted;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>165214</tid>
<number>ii</number>sub- section (4) shall be omitted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1454022</tid>
<number>31</number>Insertion of new section 40.- After section 39 of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 40. Rules, regulations and notifications to be laid before 
Parliament.- Every rule and every regulation made and every 
notification issued under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be 
after it is made or issued, before each House of Parliament, while it 
is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be 
comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and 
if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the 
session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in 
making any modification in the rule, regulation or notification, or 
both Houses agree that the rule, regulation or notification should 
not be made, or issued, the rule, regulation or notification shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule, regulation or notification.".



</article>



<article><tid>1816869</tid>
<number> 32</number> Substitution of new Schedules for First Schedule and Second 
Schedule.- For the First Schedule and the Second Schedule to the 
principal Act, the following Schedules shall be substituted, namely:-
' THE FIRST SCHEDULE

[ See sections 21 (3), 21A (3) and 22]

PART I

Professional misconduct in relation to company secretaries in 
practice 
A Company Secretary in practice shall be deemed to be guilty of 
professional misconduct, if he-

<section><tid>1755153</tid>
<number>1</number>allows any person to practice in his name as a Company Secretary 
unless such person is also a Company Secretary in practice and is in 
partnership with or employed by him;

</section>

<section><tid>575354</tid>
<number>2</number>pays or allows or agrees to pay or allow, directly or indirectly, 
any share, commission or brokerage in the fees or profits of his 
professional business, to any person other than a member of the 
Institute or a partner or a retired partner or the legal 
representative of a deceased partner, or a member of any other 
professional body or with such other persons having such 
qualifications as may be prescribed, for the purpose of rendering 
such professional services from time to time in or outside India.
Explanation.- In this item," partner" includes a person residing 
outside India with whom a Company Secretary in practice has entered 
into partnership which is not in contravention of item (4) of this 
Part;


</section>

<section><tid>1514744</tid>
<number>3</number>accepts or agrees to accept any part of the profits of the 
professional work of a person who is not a member of the Institute:
Provided that nothing herein contained shall be construed as 
prohibiting a member from entering into profit sharing or other 
similar arrangements, including receiving any share commission or 
brokerage in the fees, with a member of such professional body or 
other person having qualifications, as is referred to in item (2) of 
this part;


</section>

<section><tid>733351</tid>
<number>4</number>enters into partnership, in or outside India, with any person 
other than a Company Secretary in practice or such other person who 
is a member of any other professional body having such qualifications 
as may be prescribed, including a resident who but for his residence 
abroad would be entitled to be registered as a member under clause 
 (e) of sub- section (1) of section 4 or whose qualifications are 
recognised by the Central Government or the Council for the purpose 
of permitting such partnerships;

</section>

<section><tid>302525</tid>
<number>5</number>secures, either through the services of a person who is not an 
employee of such company secretary or who is not his partner or by 
means which are not open to a Company Secretary, any professional 
business: 
Provided that nothing herein contained shall be construed as 
prohibiting any arrangement permitted in terms of items (2), (3) and 
 (4) of this Part;

</section>

<section><tid>625560</tid>
<number>6</number>solicits clients or professional work, either directly or 
indirectly, by circular, advertisement, personal communication or 
interview or by any other means:
Provided that nothing herein contained shall be construed as 
preventing or prohibiting-


<subsection><tid>62824</tid>
<number>i</number>any company secretary from applying or requesting for or inviting 
or securing professional work from another company secretary in 
practice; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>147391</tid>
<number>ii</number>a member from responding to tenders or enquiries issued by 
various users of professional services or organisations from time to 
time and securing professional work as a consequence;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1599998</tid>
<number>7</number>advertises his professional attainments or services, or uses any 
designation or expressions other than Company Secretary on 
professional documents, visiting cards, letterheads or sign boards, 
unless it be a degree of a University established by law in India or 
recognised by the Central Government or a title indicating membership 
of the Institute of Company Secretaries of India or of any other 
institution that has been recognised by the Central Government or may 
be recognised by the Council:
Provided that a member in practice may advertise through a write up 
setting out the services provided by him or his firm and particulars 
of his firm subject to such guidelines as may be issued by the 
Council; 
 (8) accepts a position as a Company Secretary in practice previously 
held by another Company Secretary in practice without first 
communicating with him in writing;


</section>

<section><tid>151521</tid>
<number>9</number>charges or offers to charge, accepts or offers to accept, in 
respect of any professional employment, fees which are based on a 
percentage of profits or which are contingent upon the findings, or 
results of such employment, except as permitted under any regulation 
made under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1261534</tid>
<number>10</number>engages in any business or occupation other than the profession 
of Company Secretary unless permitted by the Council so to engage:
Provided that nothing contained herein shall disentitle a Company 
Secretary from being a director of a company except as provided in 
the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>);


</section>

<section><tid>1863136</tid>
<number>11</number>allows a person not being a member of the Institute in practice, 
or a member not being his partner to sign on his behalf or on behalf 
of his firm, anything which he is required to certify as a Company 
Secretary, or any other statements relating thereto.
PART II

Professional misconduct in relation to members of the Institute in 
service

A member of the Institute (other than a member in practice) shall be 
deemed to be guilty of professional misconduct, if he, being an 
employee of any company, firm or person-


</section>

<section><tid>1755153</tid>
<number>1</number>pays or allows or agrees to pay, directly or indirectly, to any 
person any share in the emoluments of the employment undertaken by 
him;

</section>

<section><tid>575354</tid>
<number>2</number>accepts or agrees to accept any part of fees, profits or gains 
from a lawyer, a Company Secretary or broker engaged by such company, 
firm or person or agent or customer of such company, firm or person 
by way of commission or gratification.
PART III

Professional misconduct in relation to members of the Institute 
generally

A member of the Institute, whether in practice or not, shall be 
deemed to be guilty of professional misconduct, if he-


</section>

<section><tid>1755153</tid>
<number>1</number>not being a Fellow of the Institute, acts as a Fellow of the 
Institute;

</section>

<section><tid>575354</tid>
<number>2</number>does not supply the information called for, or does not comply 
with the requirements asked for, by the Institute, Council or any of 
its Committees, Director (Discipline), Board of Discipline, 
Disciplinary Committee, Quality Review Board or the Appellate 
Authority;

</section>

<section><tid>1514744</tid>
<number>3</number>while inviting professional work from another Company Secretary 
or while responding to tenders or enquiries or while advertising 
through a write up, or anything as provided for in items (6) and (7) 
of Part I of this Schedule, gives information knowing it to be false.
PART IV

Other misconduct in relation to members of the Institute generally 
A member of the Institute, whether in practice or not, shall be 
deemed to be guilty of other misconduct, if-


</section>

<section><tid>1755153</tid>
<number>1</number>he is held guilty by any civil or criminal court for an offence 
which is punishable with imprisonment for a term not exceeding six 
months;

</section>

<section><tid>575354</tid>
<number>2</number>in the opinion of the Council, he brings disrepute to the 
profession or the institute as a result of his action whether or not 
related to his professional work.
THE SECOND SCHEDULE

[ See sections 21 (3), 21B (3) and 22]

PART I

Professional misconduct in relation to company secretaries in 
practice

A Company Secretary in practice shall be deemed to be guilty of 
professional misconduct, if he-


</section>

<section><tid>1755153</tid>
<number>1</number>discloses information acquired in the course of his professional 
engagement to any person other than his client so engaging him, 
without the consent of his client, or otherwise than as required by 
any law for the time being in force;

</section>

<section><tid>575354</tid>
<number>2</number>certifies or submits in his name, or in the name of his firm, a 
report of an examination of the matters relating to company 
secretarial practice and related statements unless the examination of 
such statements has been made by him or by a partner or an employee 
in his firm or by another Company Secretary in practice;

</section>

<section><tid>1514744</tid>
<number>3</number>permits his name or the name of his firm to be used in connection 
with any report or statement contingent upon future transactions in a 
manner which may lead to the belief that he vouches for the accuracy 
of the forecast;

</section>

<section><tid>733351</tid>
<number>4</number>expresses his opinion on any report or statement given to any 
business or enterprise in which he, his firm, or a partner in his 
firm has a substantial interest;

</section>

<section><tid>302525</tid>
<number>5</number>fails to disclose a material fact known to him in his report or 
statement but the disclosure of which is necessary in making such 
report or statement, where he is concerned with such report or 
statement in a professional capacity;

</section>

<section><tid>625560</tid>
<number>6</number>fails to report a material mis- statement known to him and with 
which he is concerned in a professional capacity;

</section>

<section><tid>1599998</tid>
<number>7</number>does not exercise due diligence, or is grossly negligent in the 
conduct of his professional duties;

</section>

<section><tid>387769</tid>
<number>8</number>fails to obtain sufficient information which is necessary for 
expression of an opinion or its exceptions are sufficiently material 
to negate the expression of an opinion;

</section>

<section><tid>151521</tid>
<number>9</number>fails to invite attention to any material departure from the 
generally accepted procedure relating to the secretarial practice;

</section>

<section><tid>1261534</tid>
<number>10</number>fails to keep moneys of his client other than fees or 
remuneration or money meant to be expended in a separate banking 
account or to use such moneys for purposes for which they are 
intended within a reasonable time. 
PART II
Professional misconduct in relation to members of the Institute 
generally

A member of the Institute, whether in practice or not, shall be 
deemed to be guilty of professional misconduct, if he-


</section>

<section><tid>1755153</tid>
<number>1</number>contravenes any of the provisions of this Act or the regulations 
made thereunder or any guidelines issued by the Council;

</section>

<section><tid>575354</tid>
<number>2</number>being an employee of any company, firm or person, discloses 
confidential information acquired in the course of his employment, 
except as and when required by any law for the time being in force or 
except as permitted by the employer;

</section>

<section><tid>1514744</tid>
<number>3</number>includes in any information, statement, return or form to be 
submitted to the Institute, Council or any of its Committees, 
Director (Discipline), Board of Discipline, Disciplinary Committee, 
Quality Review Board or the Appellate Authority any particulars 
knowing them to be false;

</section>

<section><tid>733351</tid>
<number>4</number>defalcates or embezzles moneys received in his professional 
capacity.
PART III

Other misconduct in relation to members of the Institute generally

A member of the Institute, whether in practice or not, shall be 
deemed to be guilty of other misconduct, if he is held guilty by any 
civil or criminal court for an offence which is punishable with 
imprisonment for a term exceeding six months.'.

T. K. VISWANATHAN,

Secy. to the Govt. of India.





</section>

</article>



 </act>