<act><tid>447410</tid>
<title>THE LAND IMPROVEMENT LOANS ACT, <year>1883</year></title>

ACT NO. 19 OF <year>1883</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 12th October, <year>1883</year>.]

An Act to consolidate and amend the law relating to loans of money by 
the Government for agricultural improvements.





<article><tid>1005067</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title.
<section><tid>1553457</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Land Improvement  
Loans Act, <year>1883</year>.
Local extent, Commencement.


</section>

<section><tid>1221956</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India except <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the territories 
which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in 
Part B States], but shall not come into force in any part of <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the 
territories to which this Act extends] until such date as the State 
Government <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint 
in this behalf.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>198725</tid>
<number> 2</number> Acts 26 of <year>1871</year> and 21 of <year>1876</year> repealed.
<section><tid>187000</tid>
<number>1</number>The Land  
Improvement Act, <year>1871</year>, and Act XXI of <year>1876</year> (An Act to amend the Land  
  Improvement Act, <year>1871</year>), shall, except as regards the recovery of 
advances made before this Act comes into force and costs incurred by 
the Government in respect of such advances, be repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>526436</tid>
<number>2</number>When in any Act, Regulation or Notification passed or issued 
before this Act comes into force, reference is made to either of those
<pagefootnote><pagenum>20</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The Act has been amended in its application to the State of 
Madhya Pradesh by the C. P. and Berar Land Improvement Loans 
 (Amendment) Act <year>1949</year> (C. P. and B. 55 of <year>1949</year>) to Bombay by Bom. Act 27 
of <year>1958</year>, to U. P. by U. P. Act 42 of <year>1958</year> and to state of Haryana by 
Haryana Act 26 of <year>1971</year>.

The Act has been extended to-- 
Madhya Pradesh by M. P. Act 23 of <year>1958</year>; 
Hyderabad and Saurashtra area of the State of Bombay by 
Bombay Act 27 of <year>1958</year>; 
Goa, Daman and Diu with modifications by Reg. 12 of <year>1962</year>, s. 
3 and Sch.; and the whole of the union territory of Lakshadweep 
by Reg. 8 of <year>1965</year>, s. 3 and Sch. (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1967</year>).:

The Act has been rep. in its application to-- 
Bellary District by Mysore Act 14 of <year>1955</year>; 
Malabar District in the State of Karala by Kerala Act 
27 of <year>1961</year>.

Instruments executed by persons taking loans, or by their 
sureties, as security for the repayment of such loans, are exempted 
from stamp- duty-- see the Indian Stamp Act, <year>1899</year> (2 of <year>1899</year>), Sch. I, 
Art. 40, exemption (1), and notification under s. 9.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" Part B 
States". 
3 Subs. ibid., for" a Part A State or a Part C State". 
4 The words" with the previous sanction of the G. G. in C." rep. by 
Act 8 of <year>1906</year>, s. 2.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Acts, the reference shall, so far as may be practicable, be read as 
applying to this Act or the corresponding part of this Act.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1815636</tid>
<number>3</number>" Collector" defined. In this Act," Collector" <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> means the 
Collector of land- revenue of a district, or the Deputy Commissioner, 
or any officer empowered by the State Government by name or by virtue 
of his office to discharge the functions of a Collector under this 
Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1468228</tid>
<number> 4</number> Purposes for which loans may be granted under this Act.
<section><tid>480666</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Subject to such rules as may be made under section 10, loans may be 
granted under this Act, by such officer as may, from time to time, be 
empowered in this behalf by the State Government, for the purpose of 
making any improvement, to any person having a right to make that 
improvement, or, with the consent of that person, to any other person.

</section>

<section><tid>296942</tid>
<number>2</number>" Improvement" means any work which adds to the letting value 
of land, and includes the following, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1798231</tid>
<number>a</number>the construction of wells, tanks and other works for the 
storage, supply or distribution of water for the 
purposes of agriculture, or for the use of men and 
cattle employed in agriculture;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1111723</tid>
<number>b</number>the preparation of land for irrigation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>66564</tid>
<number>c</number>the drainage, reclamation from rivers or other waters, 
or protection from floods or from erosion or other 
damage by water, or land used for agricultural purposes 
or wasteland which is culturable;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1242053</tid>
<number>d</number>the reclamation, clearance, enclosure or permanent 
improvement of land for agricultural purposes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1335427</tid>
<number>e</number>the renewal or reconstruction of any of the foregoing 
works, or alterations therein or additions thereto; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1233770</tid>
<number>f</number>such other works as the State Government <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> may, from 
time to time, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
declare to be improvements for the purposes of this 
Act.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>240348</tid>
<number> 5</number> Mode of dealing with applications for loans.
<section><tid>1355399</tid>
<number>1</number>When an  
application for a loan is made under this Act, the officer to whom the 
application is made may, if it is, in his opinion, expedient that 
public notice be given of the application, publish a notice, in such 
manner as the State Government may, from
<pagefootnote><pagenum>20A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Cf. the definition in s. 3 (10) of the General Clauses Act, <year>1897</year> 
 (10 of <year>1897</year>). 
2 The words" with the previous sanction of the G. G. in C." rep. by 
Act 8 of <year>1906</year>, s. 2.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


time to time, direct, calling upon all persons objecting to the loan 
to appear before him at a time and place fixed therein and submit 
their objections.


</section>

<section><tid>1799451</tid>
<number>2</number>The officer shall consider every objection submitted under 
sub- section (1), and make an order in writing either admitting or 
overruling it:
Provided that, when the question raised by an objection is, in 
the opinion of the officer, one of such a nature that it cannot be 
satisfactorily decided except by a Civil Court, he shall postpone his 
proceedings on the application until the question has been so decided.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1132961</tid>
<number> 6</number> Period for repayment of loans.
<section><tid>1495615</tid>
<number>1</number>Every loan granted under  
this Act shall be made repayable by instalments (in the form of an  
  annuity or otherwise), within such period from the date of the actual 
advance of the loan, or, when the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>21</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

loan is advanced in instalments, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> from the date of the advance of 
the last instalment actually paid] as may, from time to time, be fixed 
by the rules made under this Act.


</section>

<section><tid>1080958</tid>
<number>2</number>The period fixed as aforesaid shall not ordinarily exceed 
thirty- five years.

</section>

<section><tid>1603654</tid>
<number>3</number>The State Government <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>, in making <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the rules fixing 
the period, shall, in considering whether the period should extend to 
thirty- five years, or whether it should extend beyond thirty- five 
years, have regard to the durability of the work for the purpose of 
which the loan is granted, and to the expediency of the cost of the 
work being paid by the generation of persons who will immediately 
benefit by the work.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>218692</tid>
<number> 7</number> Recovery of loans.
<section><tid>1648988</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to such rules as may be made  
under section 10, all loans granted under this Act, all interest (if  
  any) chargeable thereon, and costs (if any) incurred in making the 
same, shall, when they become due, be recoverable by the Collector in 
all or any of the following modes, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1570769</tid>
<number>a</number>from the borrower-- as if they were arrears of land- 
revenue due by him;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>402460</tid>
<number>b</number>from his surety (if any)-- as if they were arrears of 
land- revenue due by him;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1300496</tid>
<number>c</number>out of the land for the benefit of which the loan has 
been granted-- as if they were arrears of land- revenue 
due in respect of that land;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1838949</tid>
<number>d</number>out of the property comprised in the collateral security 
 (if any)-- according to the procedure for the 
realization of land- revenue by the sale of immovable 
property other than the land on which that revenue is 
due:
Provided that no proceeding in respect of any land under clause 
 (c) shall affect any interest in that land which existed before the 
date of the order granting the loan, other than the interest of the 
borrower, and of mortgagees of, or persons having charges on, that 
interest, and, where the loan is granted under section 4 with the 
consent of another person, the interest of that person, and of 
mortgagees of, or persons having charges on, that interest.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>855811</tid>
<number>2</number>When any sum due on account of any such loan, interest or 
costs is paid to the Collector by a surety or an owner of property 
comprised in any collateral security, or is recovered under sub- 
section (1) by the Collector from a surety or out of any such 
property, the
<pagefootnote><pagenum>22</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1899</year>, s. 2, for" from the date of the actual 
advance of the last instalment". 
2 The words" and G. G. in C." rep. by Act 8 of <year>1906</year>, s. 3. 
3 The words" and sanctioning" rep. by s. 3, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Collector shall, on the application of the surety or the owner of that 
property (as the case may be), recover that sum on his behalf from the 
borrower, or out of the land for the benefit of which the loan has 
been granted, in manner provided by sub- section (1).


</section>

<section><tid>1741784</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall be in the discretion of a Collector acting under 
this section to determine the order in which he will resort to the 
various modes of recovery permitted by it.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1088278</tid>
<number> 8</number> Order granting loan conclusive on certain points. A written 
order under the hand of an officer empowered to make loans under this 
Act granting a loan to, or with the consent of, a person mentioned 
therein, for the purpose of carrying out a work described therein, for 
the benefit of land specified therein, shall, for the purposes of this 
Act, be conclusive evidence--
<section><tid>1908729</tid>
<number>a</number>that the work described is an improvement within the 
meaning of this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1969920</tid>
<number>b</number>that the person mentioned had at the date of the order a 
right to make such an improvement; and

</section>

<section><tid>1982508</tid>
<number>c</number>that the improvement is one benefiting the land 
specified.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1834183</tid>
<number>9</number>Liability of joint borrowers as among themselves. When a loan 
is made under this Act to the members of a village- community or to any 
other persons on such terms that all of them are jointly and severally 
bound to the Government for the payment of the whole amount payable in 
respect thereof, and a statement showing the portion of that amount 
which as among themselves each is bound to contribute is entered upon 
the order granting the loan and is signed by each of them and by the 
officer making the order, that statement shall be conclusive evidence 
of the portion of that amount which as among themselves each of those 
persons is bound to contribute.


</article>



<article><tid>1060576</tid>
<number> 10</number> Power to make rules. The State Government <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> may, from 
time to time, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules 
consistent with this Act to provide for the following matters, 
namely:--
<section><tid>1689044</tid>
<number>a</number>the manner of making applications for loans;

</section>

<section><tid>1294118</tid>
<number>b</number>the officers by whom loans may be granted;

</section>

<section><tid>1685722</tid>
<number>c</number>the manner of conducting inquiries relative to 
applications for loans, and the powers to be exercised 
by officers conducting those inquiries;

</section>

<section><tid>342152</tid>
<number>d</number>the nature of the security to be taken for the due 
application and repayment of the money, the rate of 
interest at which, and the conditions under which, 
loans may be granted, and the manner and time of 
granting loans;

</section>

<section><tid>1911820</tid>
<number>e</number>the inspection of works for which loans have been 
granted;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>23</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" subject to the control of the G. G. in C." rep. by Act 
4 of <year>1914</year>, s. 2 and Sch., Part I.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1143029</tid>
<number>f</number>the instalments by which, and the mode in which, loans, 
the interest to be charged on them and the costs 
incurred in the making thereof, shall be paid;

</section>

<section><tid>580298</tid>
<number>g</number>the manner of keeping and auditing the accounts of the 
expenditure of loans and of the payments made in 
respect of the same; and

</section>

<section><tid>285820</tid>
<number>h</number>all other matters pertaining to the working of the Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>808728</tid>
<number> 11</number> Exemption of improvements from assessment to land- revenue. 
When land is improved with the aid of a loan granted under this Act, 
the increase in value derived from the improvement shall not be taken 
into account in revising the assessment of land- revenue on the land:
Provided as follows--

<section><tid>229109</tid>
<number>1</number>where the improvement consists of the reclamation of 
waste- land, or of the irrigation of land assessed at 
unirrigated rates, the increase may be so taken into 
account after the expiration of such period as may be 
fixed by rules to be framed by the State Government 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>;

</section>

<section><tid>370777</tid>
<number>2</number>nothing in this section shall entitle any person to call 
in question any assessment of land- revenue otherwise 
than as it might have been called in question if this 
Act had not been passed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>807586</tid>
<number>12</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Certain powers of State Government to be exercisable by 
Board of Revenue or Financial Commissioner. The powers conferred on a 
State Government by sections 4 (1), 5 (1) and 10 may, in a State for 
which there is a Board of Revenue or a Financial Commissioner, be 
exercised in the like manner and subject to the like conditions by 
such Board or Financial Commissioner, as the case may be: Provided 
that rules made by a Board of Revenue or Financial Commissioner shall 
be subject to the control of the State Government.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>24</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" with the approval of the G. G. in C." rep. by Act 8 of 
<year>1906</year>, s. 5. 
2 S. 12 ins. by Act 4 of <year>1914</year>, s. 2 and Sch., Pt. I. The original 
s. 12 had been rep. by Act 16 of <year>1908</year>. The application of this section 
has been barred in U. P. by the U. P. Board of Revenue Act, <year>1922</year> (U.  
  P. 12 of <year>1922</year>).

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>