<act><tid>1340538</tid>
<title>THE BANKING SERVICE COMMISSION (REPEAL) ACT, <year>1978</year></title>

ACT NO. 20 OF <year>1978</year>
[ 18th May, <year>1978</year>.] BE

An Act to repeal the Banking Service Commission Act, <year>1975</year>





<article><tid>318474</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>794900</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Banking Service Commission (Repeal) Act, <year>1978</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>574518</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 19th day of 
September, <year>1977</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>582160</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>730262</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means the 19th day of September, <year>1977</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>904739</tid>
<number>b</number>" Banking Service Commission" means the Banking Service 
Commission established under section 3 of the Banking 
Service Commission Act, <year>1975</year> (42 of <year>1975</year>).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1563200</tid>
<number>3</number>Repeal of Act 42 of <year>1975</year> and the dissolution of the Banking 
Service Commission.- On the appointed day the Banking Service 
Commission Act, <year>1975</year>, shall stand repealed and the Banking Service 
Commission shall stand dissolved.


</article>



<article><tid>180182</tid>
<number> 4</number> Consequential provisions.- On the dissolution of the Banking 
Service Commission,--
<section><tid>1739926</tid>
<number>a</number> (i) the person appointed as the Chairman of the Banking 
Service Commission; and

<subsection><tid>1146508</tid>
<number>ii</number>every other person appointed by the Banking Service 
Commission,
and holding office as such immediately before the appointed 
day shall vacate their respective offices and no such 
Chairman or other person shall be entitled to claim any 
compensation for the premature termination of the term 
of his office or of any contract of service;


<pagefootnote><pagenum>278</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1894615</tid>
<number>b</number>any proceeding of whatever nature pending before the 
Banking Service Commission immediately before the 
appointed day shall stand terminated;

</section>

<section><tid>878832</tid>
<number>c</number>the balance of all monies (including any fee) received 
by, or advanced to, the Banking Service Commission and 
not spent by it before the appointed day shall, on the 
appointed day, stand transferred to, and shall vest 
in, the Central Government and shall be utilised for 
the purposes of clauses (e) and (f);

</section>

<section><tid>182849</tid>
<number>d</number>all property of whatever kind owned by, or vested in, 
the Banking Service Commission immediately before the 
appointed day, shall, on the appointed day, stand 
transferred to, and shall vest in, the Central 
Government;

</section>

<section><tid>1873517</tid>
<number>e</number>all liabilities and obligations of whatever kind 
incurred by the Banking Service Commission and 
subsisting immediately before the appointed day shall, 
on and from the appointed day, be deemed to be the 
liabilities or obligations, as the case may be, of the 
Central Government; and any proceeding or cause of 
action, pending or existing immediately before the 
appointed day by or against the Banking Service 
Commission in relation to such liability or obligation 
may, as from the appointed day, be continued or 
enforced by or against the Central Government.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this clause," liability" does 
not include any liability for any money advanced to the Banking 
Service Commission under sub- section (3) of section 19 of the Banking 
Service Commission Art, <year>1975</year> (42 of <year>1975</year>);


</section>

<section><tid>888905</tid>
<number>f</number>all monies vested in the Central Government under clause 
 (c) shall, after deducting the amount incurred for 
discharging the liabilities and obligations under 
clause (e), be refunded by the Central Government to 
each public sector bank as defined in clause (h) of 
section 2 of the Banking Service Commission Act, <year>1975</year> 
 (42 of <year>1975</year>), in proportion to the amount advanced by 
such public sector bank to the Banking Service 
Commission under sub- section (3) of section 19 of that 
Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>279</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>667657</tid>
<number> 5</number> Savings.-
<section><tid>397508</tid>
<number>1</number>Anything done or any action taken under the  
Banking Service Commission (Repeal) Ordnance, <year>1977</year> (10 of <year>1977</year>), which 
ceased to operate, shall be deemed to have been done or taken under 
the corresponding provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1572842</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing in this Act shall be deemed to affect the right of 
the Chairman of the Banking Service Commission or of any other person 
appointed by the said Commission to receive salary, allowances or 
other benefits, in accordance with the terms and conditions of service 
applicable to him, for the period from the date of cesser of operation 
of the said Ordinance till the date on which this Act receives the 
assent of the President (both days inclusive).


</section>

</article>



 </act>