<act><tid>1275601</tid>
<title>THE TERRITORIAL ARMY ACT, <year>1948</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum></title>

ACT NO. 56 OF <year>1948</year>
[ 10th September, <year>1948</year>.]

An Act to provide for the constitution of Territorial Army.

WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the constitution of a 
Territorial Army;

It is hereby enacted as follows





<article><tid>1263850</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and application.
<section><tid>561988</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Territorial Army Act, <year>1948</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1731361</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> and applies to all 
classes of persons in the Territorial Army, wherever they may be.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1672242</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything 
repugnant in the subject or context,-
<section><tid>465184</tid>
<number>a</number>" enrolled" means enrolled in the Territorial Army under 
the provisions of this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>50049</tid>
<number>b</number>" officer" means an officer of any of the two classes 
specified in section 5;

</section>

<section><tid>93038</tid>
<number>c</number>" non- commissioned officer" means a person holding a 
non- commissioned rank in the Territorial Army, and includes 
an acting non- commissioned officer;

</section>

<section><tid>1672884</tid>
<number>d</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1048279</tid>
<number>dd</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>" public utility service" means any undertaking which 
supplies power, light, gas or water to the public, or carries 
on a public transport, or maintains any system of public 
conservancy or sanitation and which is declared, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, by the Central Govern- 
ment to be a public utility service to which this Act applies 
:
Provided that no such notification shall be issued unless the 
Central Government is satisfied that, having regard to the 
needs of the Territorial Army, the persons


<pagefootnote><pagenum>112</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been extended to- 
Goa, Daman and Diu with modifications by Reg. 12 of <year>1962</year>, s. 3 
and Sch. and comes into force in Pondicherry vide Reg. 7 of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 
and Sch. I (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1963</year>);

and brought into force in Dadra and Nagar Haveli by Reg. 6 of 
<year>1963</year>. s. 2 and Sch. I (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1965</year>);

the whole of the Union Territory of Lakshadweep vide Reg. 8 of 
<year>1965</year>, s. 3 and Sch. (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1967</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The words" except the State of Hyderabad", ins. by the A. O. 
<year>1950</year>. were omitted by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by Act 92 of <year>1956</year>. s. 2.






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

employed in any such public utility service should, in the 
public interest, be made compulsorily liable for service in 
that Army under this Act;]


</section>

<section><tid>1262459</tid>
<number>e</number>the expression"'[ Regular Army]" means officers and 
other ranks who, by their commission, terms of enrolment or 
otherwise, are liable to render continuously for a term 
military service under <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the Army Act, <year>1950</year>]; (46 of <year>1950</year>.) 
and

</section>

<section><tid>308954</tid>
<number>f</number>all words and expressions used herein and defined in 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the Army Act, <year>1950</year>], and not hereinbefore defined, shall be 
deemed to have the meanings respectively attributed to them 
by that Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1133620</tid>
<number> 3</number> Constitution of the Territorial Army.
<section><tid>1751297</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be  
raised and maintained in the manner hereinafter provided an army to be 
designated the Territorial Army.

</section>

<section><tid>1802046</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may constitute such number of units 
of the Territorial Army as it thinks fit and may disband or 
reconstitute any unit so constituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>749975</tid>
<number> 4</number> Personal of the Territorial Army. There shall be the 
following classes of persons in the Territorial Army, namely,-
<section><tid>1790469</tid>
<number>a</number>officers; and

</section>

<section><tid>879880</tid>
<number>b</number>enrolled persons.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1901242</tid>
<number> 5</number> Officers. Officers in the Territorial Army shall be of the 
two following classes, namely,-
<section><tid>52285</tid>
<number>a</number>officers holding commissions in the Territorial Army 
granted by the President with designations of rank 
corresponding to those of Indian commissioned officers <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> of 
the Regular Army]; and

</section>

<section><tid>1809546</tid>
<number>b</number>junior commissioned officers holding commissions in the 
Territorial Army granted by the President with designations 
of rank corresponding to those of <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> junior commissioned 
officers of the Regular Army].



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>388998</tid>
<number>6</number>Persons eligible for enrolment. <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Amy person who is a 
citizen of India] may offer himself for enrolment in the Territorial 
Army, and may, if he satisfies the prescribed conditions, be enrolled 
for such period and subject to such conditions as may be prescribed.
</article>



<article><tid>322424</tid>
<number> 6A</number> <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Liability of certain persons for compulsory service in the 
Territorial Army.
<section><tid>403101</tid>
<number>1</number>Without prejudice to the provision contained in  
section 6, every person employed under the Government or in a public 
utility

<pagefootnote><pagenum>113</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year> for" regular forces.".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch.., for" the Indian Army 
Act, <year>1911</year>".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ing. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs., ibid., for" Viceroy' s commissioned officers".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Subs., ibid., for" Any person domiciled in India".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Ins. by Act 92 of <year>1956</year>. s. 3.





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

service who has attained the age of twenty years but has not completed 
the age of forty years shall, subject to the other provisions 
contained in this section and subject to such rules as may be made in 
this behalf, be liable, when so required to do, to perform service in 
the Territorial Army.


</section>

<section><tid>617708</tid>
<number>2</number>Where it appears to the prescribed authority that, having 
regard to the strength of the Territorial Army or of any unit thereof 
in any area or place or, having regard to the exigencies of service in 
the Territorial Army, it is necessary that persons compulsorily liable 
to perform service in the Territorial Army under sub- section (1) 
should be called upon for such service, the prescribed authority may 
call upon such number of persons as he thinks fit for the purpose of 
performing service in the Territorial Army.

</section>

<section><tid>221928</tid>
<number>3</number>In requisitioning the services of any persons under sub- 
section (2), the prescribed authority shall have regard to the age, 
physical fitness, qualifications and experience of the persons to be 
called upon for service and the nature of the work previously 
performed by them while employed under the Government or in the public 
utility service, and the work to be performed by them in the 
Territorial Army.

</section>

<section><tid>1749441</tid>
<number>4</number>Every person liable to perform service under sub- section (1) 
shall, if so required by the prescribed authority, be bound to fill up 
such forms as may be prescribed and sign and lodge them with the 
prescribed authority within such time as may be specified in the 
requisition.

</section>

<section><tid>1276518</tid>
<number>5</number>The prescribed authority may require any person in- charge of 
the management of a public utility service to furnish within such time 
as may be specified in the requisition such particulars as may be 
prescribed with respect to persons employed under him, who may be 
liable to perform service under sub- section (1).

</section>

<section><tid>705994</tid>
<number>6</number>Any person whose services are requisitioned under this 
section may be required to join the Territorial Army as an officer or 
as an enrolled person according to the rules made in this behalf by 
the Central Government, and where any person has so joined the Terri- 
torial Army, he shall be entitled to the same rights and privileges 
and be subject to the same liabilities as an officer or enrolled 
person under the provisions of this Act.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section, the expression 
" person employed under the Government or in a public utility service" 
shall not include-


<subsection><tid>1963664</tid>
<number>a</number>a woman;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1288931</tid>
<number>b</number>a member of the Regular Army, the Navy or the Air Force 
or a member of any Reserve Force;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>114</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>307971</tid>
<number>c</number>a person who is not a citizen of India;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>274786</tid>
<number>d</number>a person employed under the Government in any country 
or place outside India for so long as he is so employed; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>122837</tid>
<number>e</number>any other persons as may be exempted from the operation 
of this Act by the Central Government, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, on the ground that, having regard to the 
nature of the service performed by such persons or to the 
exigencies of the service in which they are employed, it is, 
in the opinion of the Central Government, expedient in the 
public interest that they should not be liable to perform 
service under this Act.]



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1386187</tid>
<number> 7</number> Liability for military service.
<section><tid>704621</tid>
<number>1</number>No officer or enrolled  
person shall be required to perform military service beyond the limits 
of India save under a general or special order of the Central 
Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1165437</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (1), every officer 
or enrolled person shall, subject to such conditions as may be 
prescribed, be bound to serve in any unit of the Territorial Army to 
which he is for the time being attached, and shall be subject to all 
the rules made under this Act in relation to such unit.

</section>

<section><tid>1151670</tid>
<number>3</number>Every officer or enrolled person shall be liable to perform 
military service,-

<subsection><tid>1116295</tid>
<number>a</number>when called out in the prescribed manner to act in 
support of the civil power or to provide essential guards;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1333336</tid>
<number>b</number>when embodied in the prescribed manner for training or 
for supporting or supplementing the regular forces; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>25803</tid>
<number>c</number>when attached to any regular forces either at his own 
request or under the prescribed conditions.

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>319282</tid>
<number> 7A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Reinstatement in civil employ of persons required to 
perform military service.
<section><tid>1031261</tid>
<number>1</number>It shall be the duty of every employer  
by whom a person who is required to perform military service under 
section 7 was employed to reinstate him in his employment on the 
termination of the military service in an occupation and under 
conditions not less favourable to him than those which would have been 
applicable to him had his employment not been so interrupted:
Provided that if the employer refuses to reinstate such person or 
denies his liability to reinstate such person, or if for any reason 
reinstatement of such person is represented by the employer to be 
impracticable, either party may refer the matter to the prescribed 
authority and that authority shall, after considering all matters 
which


<pagefootnote><pagenum>115</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 33 of <year>1952</year>, s. 2.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

may be put before it and after making such further inquiry into the 
matter as may be prescribed, pass an order-


<subsection><tid>1450240</tid>
<number>a</number>exempting the employer from the provisions of this 
section, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1832296</tid>
<number>b</number>requiring him to re- employ such person on such terms as 
he thinks suitable, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>163887</tid>
<number>c</number>requiring him to pay to such person by way of 
compensation for failure or inability to re- employ a sum not 
exceeding an amount equal to six months' remuneration at the 
rate at which his last remuneration was payable to him by the 
employer.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>799240</tid>
<number>2</number>If any employer fails to obey the order of any such 
authority as is referred to in the proviso to sub- section (1), he 
shall be punishable with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, 
and the court by which an employer is convicted under this section 
shall order him (if he has not already been so required by the said  
  authority) to pay to the person whom he has failed to re- employ a sum 
equal to six months' remuneration at the rate at which his last 
remuneration was payable to him by the employer, and any amount so 
required to be paid either by the said authority or by the court shall 
be recoverable as if it were a fine imposed by such court.

</section>

<section><tid>1253709</tid>
<number>3</number>In any proceeding under this section it shall be a defence 
for an employer to prove that the person formerly employed did not 
apply to the employer for reinstatement within a period of two months 
from the termination of his military service.

</section>

<section><tid>1130179</tid>
<number>4</number>The duty imposed by sub- section (1) upon an employer to 
reinstate in his employment a person such as is described in that sub- 
section shall attach to an employer who, before such person is 
actually required to perform military service under section 7, 
terminates his employment in circumstances such as to indicate an 
intention to evade the duty imposed by that sub- section, and such 
intention shall be presumed until the contrary is proved if the 
termination takes place after the issue of orders requiring him to 
perform military service under this Act.]

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1097948</tid>
<number>7B</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Preservation of certain rights of persons required to 
perform military service. When any person required to perform 
military service under section 7 has any rights under any provident 
fund or superannuation fund or other scheme for the benefit of 
employees maintained in connection with the employment he 
relinquishes, he shall continue, so long as he is engaged in military 
service and if he is reinstated, until such reinstatement under the 
provisions of this Act, to have in respect of such fund or scheme such 
rights as may be prescribed.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>116</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 33 of <year>1952</year>, s. 2.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>64905</tid>
<number>8</number>Discharge. Every person enrolled under this Act shall be 
entitled to receive his discharge from the Territorial Army on the 
expiration of the period for which he was enrolled and any such person 
may, prior to the expiration of that period, be discharged from the 
said army by such authority and subject to such conditions as may be 
prescribed:
Provided that no enrolled person who is for the time being 
engaged in military service under the provisions of this Act, shall be 
entitled to receive his discharge before the termination of such 
service.



</article>



<article><tid>1163814</tid>
<number> 9</number> Application of the Army Act, <year>1950</year>.
<section><tid>1651653</tid>
<number>1</number>Every officer, when  
doing duty as such officer, and every enrolled person when called out 
or embodied or attached to <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Regular Army], shall, subject to such 
adaptations and modifications as may be made therein by the Central 
Government by notification in the Official Gazette, be subject to the 
provisions of <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the Army Act, <year>1950</year>], (46 of <year>1950</year>.) and the rules or 
regulations made thereunder in the same manner and to the same extent 
as if such officer or enrolled person held the same rank in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the 
Regular Army] as he holds for the time being in the Territorial Army.

</section>

<section><tid>753810</tid>
<number>2</number>When an offence punishable under <footcitenum>12</footcitenum> the Army Act, <year>1950</year>], (46  
  of <year>1950</year>.) has been committed by any person whilst subject to that Act 
under the provisions of sub- section (1) such person may be taken into 
and kept in military custody and tried and punished for such offence 
as aforesaid in like manner as he might have been taken into and. kept 
in military custody, tried and punished if he had continued to be so 
subject.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1339625</tid>
<number>10</number>Summary trial and punishment. In addition to, or in 
substitution for, any punishment or punishments to which he may be 
liable under <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the Army Act, <year>1950</year>], (46 of <year>1950</year>.) any enrolled person 
may be punished either by a Criminal Court or summarily by order of 
the prescribed authority for any offence under that Act or for the 
contravention of any of the provisions of this Act or of any rules 
made thereunder with fine which may extend to one hundred rupees to be 
recovered in such manner and by such authority as may be prescribed:
Provided that no fine shall be summarily inflicted by order of 
the prescribed authority in any case in which the accused claims to be 
tried by a Criminal Court.

</article>



<article><tid>736855</tid>
<number> 10A</number> <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Punishment for failure to lodge forms duly filled up, 
etc. If any person fails without sufficient cause
<section><tid>1544747</tid>
<number>a</number>to comply with any requisition under sub- section (4) or 
sub- section (5) of section 6A, or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>116A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year> for" any regular forces".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch., for" the Indian Army 
Act, <year>1911</year>".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year> for" the regular forces".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Ins. by Act 92 of <year>1956</year>. s. 4.







</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>588857</tid>
<number>b</number>to report himself for service when so required to do by the 
prescribed authority under sub- section (2) of that section, or

</section>

<section><tid>1862450</tid>
<number>c</number>to submit himself to medical or other examination when so called 
upon to do by the prescribed authority under rules made under this 
Act,
he shall be punishable with imprisonment which may extend to three 
months, or with fine which may extend to two hundred rupees, or with 
both.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>469440</tid>
<number>11</number>Jurisdiction to try offences. No Court inferior to that of a 
Presidency Magistrate or a Magistrate of the first class shall try any 
offence made punishable by or under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1516822</tid>
<number>12</number>Presumption as to certain documents. Where an enrolled 
person is required by or in pursuance of any rule made under this Act 
to attend at any place, a certificate purporting to be signed by the 
prescribed officer stating that the person so required to attend 
failed to do so in accordance with such requirement shall, without 
proof of the signature or appointment of such officer, be evidence of 
the matters stated therein.


</article>



<article><tid>1633710</tid>
<number>13</number>Persons subject to this Act to be deemed part of Regular 
Army for certain purposes. For the purposes of sections 128, 130 and 
 131 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1898</year>, (5 of <year>1898</year>.) all 
officers, non- commissioned officers and other enrolled persons who 
have been attached to a unit shall be deemed to be officers non- 
commissioned officers and soldiers respectively of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Regular 
Army].


</article>



<article><tid>1246829</tid>
<number> 14</number> Power to make rules. 2
<section><tid>508604</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may make  
rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1857557</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of 
the foregoing power, such rules may-
[ (a) prescribe the form under sub- section (4) of section 6A, 
the particulars that should be furnished therein and the 
authority with which, and the period within which, the form 
should be lodged;


<subsection><tid>1616891</tid>
<number>aa</number>prescribe the procedure for requiring persons liable for 
compulsory service in the Territorial Army to be medically or 
otherwise examined with a view to determining whether they 
satisfy the conditions imposed under this Act;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>116B</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year> for regular forces".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>For Territorial Army Rules, <year>1948</year>, see Notification No. 252A, 
dated 12th February, <year>1949</year>, Gazette of India, <year>1949</year>, Pt. I, Sec. 3, p. 
205.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by Act 92 of <year>1956</year>, s. 5.





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>708357</tid>
<number>aaa</number>] prescribe the manner in which, and the period for 
which and the conditions subject to which any person may be 
enrolled under this Act <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or may be required to perform 
compulsory service in the Territorial Army];

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1872685</tid>
<number>b</number>prescribe the manner in which and the conditions 
subject to which officers and enrolled persons may be called 
out for service, or embodied for training or for supporting 
or for supplementing <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Regular Army] or attached to <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> the 
Regular Army],

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1548075</tid>
<number>c</number>prescribe preliminary and periodical military training, 
compulsory and voluntary, for any enrolled person and provide 
for the embodiment of any unit for that purpose;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>189645</tid>
<number>d</number>define the manner in which and the conditions under 
which any enrolled person may be excused from training;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>787826</tid>
<number>dd</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> specify the authority for the purpose of the proviso 
to sub- section (1) of section 7A and the manner in which any 
inquiry may be held by him;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>221524</tid>
<number>ddd</number>define the rights under section 7B

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1953706</tid>
<number>e</number>prescribe the authorities by which and the conditions 
subject to which enrolled persons may be discharged under 
section 8;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>832027</tid>
<number>f</number>prescribe the authorities by which offences under 
this Act may be punished and the fine inflicted may be 
recovered;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>742183</tid>
<number>g</number>prescribe the officers by whom certificates may be 
signed under section 12;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>393357</tid>
<number>h</number>generally provide for any other matter which under this 
Act is to be or may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1734940</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon 
as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it 
is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be com- 
prised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, 
before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or 
the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule."



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>638481</tid>
<number>15</number>[ Repeal of Act XLVIII of <year>1920</year>.] Rep. by the Repealing and 
mending Act, <year>1950</year> (35 of <year>1950</year>), s. 2 and Sch.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>999999</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Cl. (a) was relettered as (aaa). by Act 92 of <year>1956</year>, s. 5.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by s. 5, ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year> for" the regular forces

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs., ibid., for" any regular forces".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Ins. by Act 33 of <year>1952</year>, S. 3.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Ins. by Act 53 of <year>1980</year>, s. 2.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>