<act><title>


    The Civil Defence Rules, 19681</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title.—These rules may be called 
    the Civil Defence Rules, 1968. 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>2</number> Control 
    of light and sounds.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Central Government or the State Government may by order provide—
 <subsection>
    <number>a</number>    for prohibiting or regulating the display of lights of 
    any specified description;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>b</number>    for the screening of any lighting apparatus, whether 
    for the time being alight or not, carried on, or attached to any speci­fied 
    class of vehicles;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>c</number>    for securing that, in specified circumstances 
    indication of the position of such premises and places, and warning of the 
    presence of such vehicles and vessels as may be specified shall be given by 
    means of such light as may be specified, and for prescribing the manner in 
    which any apparatus used for the pur­pose of exhibiting such lights is to be 
    constructed, installed or used;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>d</number>    for prohibiting or regulating the use of roads by any 
    partic­ular class of traffic, so far as appears to it to be necessary for 
    avoiding danger consequent on compliance with any provisions of an order 
    made under this rule which relates to the lighting of roads or of vehicles 
    on roads;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>e</number>    for prohibiting or regulating such activities as may 
    be specified, being activities which consist of or involve the emission of 
    smoke, flames, sparks or glare or the making of noise.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> An order 
    under sub-rule (1) may be made so as to apply to any specified area or 
    premises, may make different provisions as respects different parts of an 
    area or different classes of premises, places, vehicles or vessels therein, 
    may provide for exempting any premises, places, vehicles or vessels (either 
    absolutely or conditionally), from the operation of any of the provisions of 
    the order, and may contain such incidental and supplementary provisions as 
    appear to the authority making the order to be necessary or expedient for 
    the purposes of the order.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If any 
    order made under sub-rule (1) is contravened in re­spect of, or in relation 
    to, any light, premises, place, vehi­cles, vessel, apparatus, road, or 
    activity to which the order applies, any police officer, or any person 
    authorised in this behalf by the authority making the order may take such 
    steps and use such force as may, in his opinion, be reasonably necessary for 
    giving effect to the order and in the exercise of this power shall have a 
    right of access to any land or other property what­soever.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If any 
    order made under this rule is contravened in respect of any premises, place, 
    vehicle or vessel, the occupier of the premises or place, the person in 
    charge of the vehicle, or the master of the vessel, as the case may be 
    shall, without prejudice to any proceedings which may be taken against any 
    other person, be deemed to have contravened the provisions of this rule:
 
Provided that 
    in any proceedings which by virtue of this sub-rule are taken against any 
    person in respect of a contravention of such an order on the part of another 
    person, it shall be a defence for the accused to prove that the 
    contravention or non-compliance occurred without his knowledge and that he 
    exercised all due diligence to secure compliance with the order.
 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Measures 
    for dealing with outbreaks of fire.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    With a view to preventing the spread, or facilitating the detection and 
    extinction of fire caused by hostile attack, the Central Govern­ment or the 
    State Government may by order make provisions for requiring the owners or 
    occupiers of the premises to which the order applies to take within such 
    period as may be specified in the order such measures as may be specified.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any police 
    officer, or any person authorised in this behalf by the Central Government 
    or the State Government may at any time enter and inspect any premises to 
    which an order made under sub-rule (1) applies for the purpose of seeing 
    whether the order has been complied with, and if that officer or person 
    finds that the order has not been complied with, he may, without prejudice 
    to any other proceedings which may be taken in respect of the con­travention 
    of the order, take such steps and use such force as may appear to him to be 
    reasonably necessary for giving effect to the order.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If in the 
    opinion of the Central Government or the State Government any person who has 
    been ordered under sub-rule (1) to take any measure has failed to take or is 
    unlikely to complete the measures within the period specified in the order, 
    then, without prejudice to any other proceedings which may be taken in 
    respect of the contravention of the order, that Government may cause the 
    said measures to be taken or completed and the cost thereof shall be 
    recoverable from the owner or occupier of the premises by the Collector.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> In the 
    event of any outbreak of fire any person authorised in this behalf by the 
    Central Government or the State Government, may take or cause to be taken 
    such steps and give such directions as appear to him to be necessary for 
    preventing the spread of fire; and the steps which may be so taken including 
    entering upon any land or the property whatsoever and the destruction or 
    remov­al of anything in, on or over any land or property.
 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Camouflage.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
    Government or the State Govern­ment may by order, as respects such premises 
    as may be specified in the order—
 <subsection>
    <number>a</number>    require the owner of the premises to take within such 
    period as may be specified in the order, such measures as may be so 
    specified, or
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>b</number>    authorise any person to take such measures as may be so 
    specified, being measures which are in the opinion of that Govern­ment 
    necessary to secure that such premises are or can be made less readily 
    recognisable in the event of hostile attack.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If in the 
    opinion of the Central Government or, as the case may be, the State 
    Government, any person who has been ordered under sub-rule (1) to take any 
    measures has failed to take, or is unlikely to complete, the measures within 
    the period specified in the order, then, without prejudice to any other 
    proceedings which may be taken in respect of the contravention of the order, 
    that Government may cause the said measures to be taken or completed, and 
    the cost thereof shall be recoverable from such person by the Collector.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No person 
    shall, except with permission granted by or on behalf of the Central 
    Government or the State Government, as the case may be, remove, alter, or 
    tamper with any work done in pursuance of this rule.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Keeping 
    of dangerous articles and substances.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government or the State Government may, by order, in respect of 
    any articles or substances of toxic, explosive or inflammable nature from 
    which special risks are in the opinion of that Gov­ernment likely to arise 
    in the event of hostile attack, issue directions—
 <subsection>
    <number>a</number>    prohibiting the keeping of such articles or substances 
    in or on such premises as may be specified in the order;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>b</number>    prescribing the quantity of such articles or 
    substances which may be kept in or on any premises;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>c</number>    requiring the owner or occupier of any premises in or 
    on which such articles or substances are kept to take such measures as may 
    be specified in the order for the protection of persons or property therein 
    or thereon, or in the vicinity thereof;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>d</number>    for any incidental or supplementary matters for which 
    that Government thinks it expedient for the purposes of the order, to 
    provide, including in particular, the entering the inspection of premises to 
    which the order relates with a view to securing compliance with the order.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If in the 
    opinion of the Central Government or, as the case may be, the State 
    Government, any person who has been ordered under sub-rule (1) to take any 
    measures has failed to take or is unlikely to complete, the measures within 
    the period specified in the order, then without prejudice to any other 
    proceedings which may be taken in respect of the contravention of the order, 
    that Government may cause the said measures to be taken or com­pleted and 
    the cost thereof shall be recoverable from the owner or occupier of the 
    premises by the Collector.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Evacuation of area.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Central Government or the State Government may, if it appears necessary for 
    the purpose of meet­ing any actual apprehended attack or of protecting 
    persons and property from the dangers involved in or resulting from such 
    attack or of facilitating any operation of the Armed forces of the Union, by 
    order direct, in respect of any specified area, that, subject to any 
    exemptions made by general order or special permission—
 <subsection>
    <number>a</number>    all persons or any class of persons shall remove 
    themselves or be removed from the said area or to any specified part 
    there­of;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>b</number>    all persons or any class of persons in the said area 
    shall remain therein for such period as may be specified;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>c</number>    any animals or property or any specified class of 
    animals or property shall be removed from the said area or to any specified 
    part thereof;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>d</number>    within a specified time any building or other property 
    speci­fied in the order shall be destroyed or rendered useless,
 
and may do any other act involving 
    interference with private rights of property which is necessary for any of 
    the purposes aforesaid.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> An order 
    made under sub-rule (1) for the removal of persons, animals or property may 
    specify—
 <subsection>
    <number>a</number>    the route or routes which all or any class of persons, 
    ani­mals or property are to remove themselves or be removed from the 
    specified area or to any specified part thereof;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>b</number>    the time or times by which they are to remove 
    themselves or be removed therefrom or to any specified part thereof;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>c</number>    the place or places to which they are to proceed or be 
    taken on removing themselves or being removed from the specified area,
 and may make such 
    other incidental and supplementary provisions as may appear necessary or 
    expedient for the purposes of the said order.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> If any 
    order made under sub-rule (1) is contravened in re­spect of any animal or 
    property, the person in charge of such animal or property shall be deemed to 
    have contravened the order.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The State 
    Government may, if it appears necessary for any of the purposes specified in 
    sub-rule (1) or for facilitating the evacuation of any area, by general or 
    special order provide for the release, whether temporary or permanent or 
    whether without conditions or upon such conditions as may be specified of 
    any prisoners or class of prisoners.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Accommodation of evacuated persons.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Govern­ment or the State Government may, for the purpose of 
    accommodating any persons who have left or been removed from their homes in 
    accordance with any order made under rule 6 (or who have left their homes on 
    account of actual or apprehended attack) take possession of any premises 
    other than those exclu­sively used by the public for religious worship.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Whenever 
    in pursuance of sub-rule (1) the Central Government or a State Government 
    takes possession of any premises, rent shall be paid for in accordance with 
    the provisions relating to the payment of compensation in respect of 
    immovable property which has been requisitioned under the law for the time 
    being in force.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Central Government or the State Government, as the case may be, may at any 
    time, restore possession of any premises in respect of which action has been 
    taken under sub-rule (1) to the owner or occupier thereof and may order that 
    no person shall thereafter be in those premises except with the consent of 
    the occupier.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Billeting.—
<section><number>1</number> In this rule, “the 
    appropriate Government” means in relation to premises in cantonment areas, 
    the Central Government and in relation to premises in other areas the 
    Central Government or the State Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    appropriate Government may by order require the occupier of any premises to 
    furnish therein while the order remains in force, such accommodation by way 
    of lodging or food or both, and either with or without attendance, as may be 
    specified in the order for such persons as may be so specified.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    appropriate Government may by order require the owner or occupier of any 
    premises to furnish to such authority as may be specified in the order such 
    information with respect to the accommodation contained in the premises and 
    with respect to the persons living therein as may be specified.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The price 
    payable in respect of any accommodation furnished in any premises to any 
    person in accordance with an order made under sub-rule (2) shall be such as 
    may be determined by the appropriate Government, and shall be paid to the 
    occupier by that Government; and the amount of any sum paid in accordance 
    with this sub-rule by the appropriate Government in respect of 
    accom­modation furnished to any persons may be recovered by that Gov­ernment 
    from that person.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    appropriate Government may by order appoint authority to hear complaints in 
    respect of orders made under sub-rule (2) and any person who is aggrieved by 
    the service upon him or by the operation, of such an order may make a 
    complaint to such authori­ty and upon hearing the complaint such authority 
    may cancel or vary such order as he thinks fit.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Power to 
    slaughter dangerous and injured animals in the event of hostile attack.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In the event of the occurrence of hos­tile attack in the vicinity, any 
    person authorised by the Central Government or the State Government in this 
    behalf may, with a view to securing the public safety or maintain public 
    order, slaughter any animal which appears to him to be:—
 <subsection>
    <number>a</number>    at large or out of control;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>b</number>    dangerous or seriously injured.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The power 
    to slaughter an animal conferred under sub-rule (1) shall include powers—
 <subsection>
    <number>a</number>    to cause or procure the animal to be slaughtered by 
    some other person;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>b</number>    to enter, and to authorise any such other persons to 
    enter, upon any land for the purpose of the slaughter;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>c</number>    to remove and dispose of the carcass, or cause it to 
    be removed and disposed of:
 
Provided that 
    except where an animal is slaughtered in a place to which the public have 
    access, the power to remove the carcass shall not be exercised if the owner 
    of the animal is present and objects.

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Maintenance of water supply.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government or the State Government may, by order, require the 
    owner, or any person having control, of any source of water supply which is 
    or is capable of being used for drinking or fire fighting or any other 
    purpose—
 <subsection>
    <number>a</number>    to keep the same in good order, clear if from time to 
    time of silt, refuse and decaying vegetation, and protect it from 
    contami­nation, in such manner as may be specified in the order;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>b</number>    to make the same available at all reasonable times for 
    the use of the public or of such section of the public as may be speci­fied 
    in the order.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person 
    authorised in this behalf by the Central Govern­ment or, as the case may be, 
    the State Government, may, at any time, inspect any source of water-supply 
    in respect of which an order under sub-rule (1) has been made for the 
    purpose of seeing whether the order has been or is being complied with.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>11</number> Power 
    to require local authorities to take precautionary measures.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In this rule, “the appropriate Government” means, in relation to cantonment 
    authorities and in relation to port authorities in major ports, the Central 
    Government, and in rela­tion to other local authorities, the State 
    Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    appropriate Government may by order require any local authority to take, 
    within such period as may be specified in the order, such measures as may be 
    so specified, being measures which are in the opinion of that Government 
    necessary for the protec­tion of persons and property under the control or 
    within the jurisdiction of such authority from injury or damage, or for 
    ensuring the due maintenance of the vital services of the author­ity, in the 
    event of hostile attack and thereupon—
 <subsection>
    <number>a</number>    it shall be the duty of the local authority to comply 
    with the order,
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>b</number>    the funds of the local authority shall be applicable 
    to the payment of charges and expenses incidental to such compliance, and
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>c</number>    priority shall be given to such compliance over all 
    other duties and obligations of the local authority.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> If in the 
    opinion of the appropriate Government any local authority which has been 
    ordered under sub-rule (2) to take any measures has failed to take or is 
    unlikely to complete, the measures within the period specified in the order, 
    then, without prejudice to any other proceedings which may be taken in 
    respect of the contravention of the order, the appropriate Government may 
    authorise any person to take or complete the said measures; and any person 
    so authorised may, for the purpose of taking or completing the said 
    measures, exercise all or any of the powers of the local authority or of its 
    officers, issue such directions as he thinks fit to the officers or servants 
    of the local authority and employ an outside agency, and all charges and 
    expenses incurred by him shall, except to such extent, if any, as the 
    appropriate Government may direct to be paid out of its Consolidated Fund be 
    paid out of the funds of the local authority.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Any person 
    authorised in this behalf by the appropriate Government may if he considers 
    it necessary or expedient so to do,—
 <subsection>
    <number>a</number>    by order direct a local authority or any of its 
    officers or servants to take such action as may be specified in the order, 
    being action which is in his opinion necessary for the protection of persons 
    and property under the control or within the jurisdiction of the local 
    authority from the danger involved in or resulting from an actual or 
    apprehended hostile attack;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>b</number>    impress and use or cause to be used for the aforesaid 
    purpose any property belonging to or in the possession of the local 
    authority in such manner as he thinks fit and it shall be the duty of the 
    local authority and of its officers and servants to comply forthwith with 
    any order made under this rule, and the funds of the local authority shall 
    be applicable to the payment of any charges and expenses incidental to such 
    compliance.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    appropriate Government may, if it considers it necessary or expedient so to 
    do, by order authorise any person to take over from a local authority and 
    administer in accordance with such directions as may be issued from time to 
    time by that Government such of the services of the local authority as may 
    be specified in the order; and any person so authorised may, for the purpose 
    of administering the said services, exercise all or any of the powers of the 
    local authority or of any Committee or officer of the local authority, issue 
    such directions as he thinks fit to the officers or servants of the local 
    authority and employ any outside agency, and all charges and expenses 
    incurred by him shall, except to such extent, if any, as the appropriate 
    Government may direct to be paid out of its Consolidated fund be paid out of 
    the funds of the local authority.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Protection of major ports and their environs against fire etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, with a view to ensuring the protection of any 
    major port and any city, town or other place adjoining or in the vicinity of 
    such port against fire, explosion or any other calamity, by order or 
    notified order providing for precautionary measures (including arrangements 
    for co-ordinating the fire fighting, water supply and conservancy services 
    of the port and local authorities concerned) to be taken by the port 
    authority of any such port, any local authority having jurisdiction in any 
    such city, town or place, any person using such port and the owners or 
    occupiers of any premises situated in such port, city, town or place; and 
    thereupon—
 <subsection>
    <number>a</number>    it shall be the duty of such port authority, local 
    authori­ties and all persons concerned, including public servants, members 
    of the Armed forces of the Union and officers and servants of such port 
    authority and local authorities, to comply or act in conformity with the 
    order;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>b</number>    the funds of the port authority or local authorities 
    shall be applicable to the payment of charges and expenses incidental to 
    such compliances;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>c</number>    priority shall be given to such compliance over all 
    other duties and obligations of the port authority or local authori­ties.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If any fire, explosion or other calamity 
    occurs in any major port or in any city, town or other place adjoining or in 
    the vicinity of such port, there shall be placed at the disposal of an 
    authority appointed in this behalf by the Central Government such of—
 <subsection>
    <number>a</number>    the fire fighting, water supply and conservancy 
    services of the port authority of such port and of any local authority 
    having jurisdiction in any such city, town or place, together with the 
    personnel employed in operating such services;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>b</number>    the fire fighting personnel and appliances maintained 
    by any owner or occupier of premises in such port, city, town or place,
 as the authority 
    so appointed may require; and such port authori­ty, local authorities, 
    owners or occupiers and personnel shall comply with any orders given by the 
    said authority.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Nothing in this rule or in any order 
    made or given thereunder shall be deemed to affect the discharge by any 
    local authority of the duty imposed on it by any other laws for the time 
    being in force of extinguishing fire and of protecting life and property in 
    the event of fire, within any such port, city, town or place as aforesaid.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article> <number>13</number> 
      Ordinary avocations of life to be interfered with as little as 
      possible.—Any authority or 
      person acting in pursuance of this Act shall interfere with the ordinary 
      avocations of life and the enjoyment of property as little as may be 
      consonant with the purpose of ensuring the public safety and civil 
      defence.
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Precaution against hostile attack.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government or the State Government may, with a view to 
    protecting the general public or any members thereof against the dangers 
    involved in any apprehended attack by land, sea or air, or with a view to 
    acquainting the general public or any members, thereof with the action to be 
    taken in such an emergency, by order specify the action to be taken by any 
    person or authority on such occasions as may be specified.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An order 
    made under sub-rule (1) may provide that upon the giving of any specified 
    notice or signal any person or class of persons may, subject to such 
    conditions and in such circumstances as may be specified, enter and remain 
    in or on any premises or property notwithstanding that such premises or 
    property would not otherwise be open to the public which may be specified or 
    which may be appointed for the purpose of this rule by any specified 
    authority or person.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No person 
    shall—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    wilfully obstruct any 
    person entering or seeking to enter any premises or property in accordance 
    with an order made under this rule, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    eject from any premises 
    or property any person who is entitled to remain there by virtue of such an order. 
 


 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Watching of premises to detect fire.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government or the State Government may by general or special 
    order make provision—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    for requiring the 
    occupiers of any premises to which the order applies to make and carry out 
    such arrangements as may be specified in the order with a view to securing 
    the fires occurring at the premises as a result of hostile attack will be 
    immediately detected and combated;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    for requiring the 
    occupiers of several premises jointly to make and carry out such 
    arrangements as aforesaid for all those premises, and in particular for 
    requiring that they shall take turns, of duty at specified premises and 
    perform such fire prevention duties as may be allotted to them under those 
    arrangements;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>c</number>    for empowering any authority, in such circumstances as 
    may be specified in the order, to make and carry out such arrangements as 
    aforesaid, including a joint arrangement as respects any premises to which 
    the order applies, and where it carries out such arrangements to recover 
    from the occupiers concerned the expenses of so doing.
 

    Explanation.—In clause (b) of 
    this sub-rule, “fire prevention duties” means the duties of keeping a watch 
    for the fall of incendiary bombs, taking such steps as are immediately 
    practicable to combat a fire caused by such bombs and summoning such 
    assistance as may be necessary, and includes the duty of being in readiness 
    to perform any such duties as aforesaid.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> An order 
    under sub-rule (1) shall entitle any person required thereof be present on 
    premises to which the order applies to have access to those premises for the 
    purpose of complying with the order notwithstanding that the premises would 
    not otherwise be open to the public, and any one, who obstructs access 
    thereto by any such person for that purpose shall be deemed to contravene 
    the provisions of the order.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any police 
    officer, or any other person authorised in this behalf by the Central 
    Government or the State Government may at any time enter and inspect any 
    premises to which any order made under sub-rule (1) applies for the purpose 
    of seeing whether the order is being complied with.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>16</number> Safety 
    measures in premises.—The Central 
    Government or the State Government may by order as respects such premises as 
    may be specified in the order—
 <section>
    <number>a</number>    require the owner or the occupier of the premises to 
    take such measures as may be specified in the order, or
 </section><section>
    <number>b</number>    authorise any person to take such measures as may be so 
    specified, being measures which are in the opinion of that Government 
    necessary to minimise danger to persons being in or in the vicinity of such 
    premises in the event of hostile attack.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Prevention of spread of disease.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If the Central or the State Government is of the opinion that it is 
    necessary or expedient to prevent the spread of human or animal disease and 
    to safeguard the public health in any area for securing the civil defence, 
    it may, by order, provide for any or all of the following measures being 
    taken in that area, namely:—
 <subsection>
    <number>i</number>    compulsory vaccination against small-pox;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>ii</number>    compulsory inoculation against cholera, plague, 
    enteric fever or other infectious or contagious disease wherever an outbreak 
    thereof is apprehended;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>iii</number>    supplying of information regarding infectious or 
    contagious diseases;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>iv</number>    isolation of persons suffering from infectious and 
    contagious diseases;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>v</number>    inspection of hotels, restaurants, clubs and other 
    places suspected to be infected premises and disinfection thereof;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>vi</number>    prohibition of fouling of places and grazing of 
    cattle;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>vii</number>    destruction of stray dogs and other dangerous 
    animals;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>viii</number>    prohibition of sale of unhygienic or adulterated 
    articles of food or drink or medicines or drugs;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>ix</number>    safeguarding of sources of water supply for the 
    troops;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>x</number>    any other measure necessary for safeguarding the 
    public health in the area.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> An order 
    under sub-rule (1) may also empower any officer or authority to take, or 
    cause to be taken, such steps as may be necessary for giving effect to that 
    order.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>18</number> Air 
    raid shelters.—
<section><number>1</number> If in respect 
    of any premises the Central Government or the State Government considers it 
    necessary or expedient so to do for the purpose of affording protection to 
    persons living or employed therein or thereon, that Government may by order 
    require the owner of the premises to construct therein or thereon an air 
    raid shelter, within such period and in accordance with such requirement as 
    to lay-out, materials and construction as may be specified in the order.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any police 
    officer, or any person authorised in this behalf by the Central Government 
    or, as the case may be, the State Government, may at any time enter and 
    inspect any premises to which an order under sub-rule (1) applies for the 
    purpose of selling whether the order has been complied with.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If in the 
    opinion of the Central Government or, as the case may be, the State 
    Government any person who has been ordered under sub-rule (1) to construct 
    an air raid shelter has failed to do so or is unlikely to complete doing so 
    within the period specified in the order, that Government may cause the 
    shelter to be constructed and the cost thereof shall be recoverable from the 
    owner of the premises by the Collector.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>19</number> Civil 
    Defence Exercises.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Central Government or State Government may by notified order authorise the 
    carrying out of civil defence exercises in such area and during the period 
    as may be specified in the order, and thereupon, within the area and during 
    the period so specified—
 <subsection>
    <number>a</number>    any person engaged in the civil defence exercises may 
    pass over, or encamp, construct works of a temporary character or execute 
    manoeuvre on any land, or supply themselves with water from any source of 
    water;
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>b</number>    any officer of the Civil Defence Corps, who may be 
    authorised so to do by the Director, Civil Defence by a general or special 
    order, may for the purpose of the Civil Defence exercises give directions 
    prohibiting or restricting the use of any part of a railway, water-way, road 
    or path, or any telegraph or telephone service or any premises ordinarily 
    open to the public, and take such further measures as may be necessary.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any 
    civil defence exercises are held under the provisions of sub-rule (1), 
    compensation shall be paid for any damage to person or property or 
    interference with rights or privileges arising from such exercises, 
    including expenses reasonably incurred in protecting persons, property, 
    rights or privileges; and assessment and payment of compensation shall be 
    made in accordance with the provisions of the law for the time being in 
    force:
 
Provided that 
    no compensation shall be payable in respect of such interference arising out 
    of any directions given or further measures taken under clause (b) of 
    sub-rule (1).

 
  


</section></article> 
  
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>20</number> 
    Penalties.—If 
    any person contravenes any of the provisions of these rules or any order 
    made thereunder, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which 
    may extend to three years, or with fine, or with both.]
 




 



</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 
    1847, dated  
8th December, 1971 (w.e.f.
    8-12-1971 ).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>