<act><title>


The Intimation of Accidents (Form
     and Time of Service of Notice) 
    Rules, 20051</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title and commencement.—2[
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Intimation of Accidents (Form and Time of 
    Service of Notice) Rules, 2005.]  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.  
 
 
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “Act” means the Electricity Act, 2003 
    (36 of 2003);  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    “Inspector” means the Chief Electrical 
    Inspector or the Electrical Inspector appointed under sub-section (1) of 
    section 162 of the Act.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Words and 
    expression used and not defined in these rules but defined in the 
    Electricity Act, 2003 (36 of 2003), shall have the meanings respectively 
    assigned to them in that Act.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Intimation of accidents.—
<section><number>1</number> If 
    any accident occurs in connection with the generation, transmission, supply 
    or use of electricity in or in connection with, any part of the electric 
    lines or other works of any person and the accidents results in or is likely 
    to have resulted in loss of human or animal life or in any injury to a human 
    being or an animal, such person or any authorised person of the generating 
    company or licensee, not below the rank of a Junior Engineer or equivalent 
    shall send to the Inspector a telegraphic report within 24 hours of the 
    knowledge of the occurrence of the fatal accident and a report in writing in 
    Form A within 48 hours of the knowledge of occurrence of fatal and all other 
    accidents. Where possible a telephonic message should also be given to the 
    Inspector immediately, if the accident comes to the knowledge of the 
    authorised officer of the generating company/licensee or other person 
    concerned.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> For the 
    intimation of the accident, telephone numbers, fax numbers and addresses of 
    Chief Electrical Inspector or Electrical Inspectors, District Magistrate, 
    police station, fire brigade and nearest hospital shall be displayed at the 
    conspicuous place in the generating station, sub-station, enclosed 
    sub-station/switching station and maintained in the office of the 
    in-charge/owner of the Medium Voltage (MV)/High Voltage (HV)/Extra High 
    Voltage (EHV) installations.  
  
 
  


</section></article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



The 
    Intimation of Accidents (Form 

     and Time of Service of Notice)  

    Rules, 2005
 



 



Form A
 



Form for Reporting Electrical Accidents
 

 
 


1.   Date and time to accident.  
 


2.   Place of accident.  
 


     (Village/Town, Tehsil/Thana, District and 
    State).  
 


3.   System and voltage of supply [Whether 
    Extra High Voltage (EHV)/High Voltage (HV)/Low Voltage (LV) Line, 
    sub-station/generation station/consumer’s installations/service lines/other 
    installations].  
 


4.   Designation of the officer-in-charge of 
    the generating company/licensee in whose jurisdiction the accident occurred.  
 


5.   Name of owner/user of energy in whose 
    premises the accident occurred.  
 


6.   Details of victim(s):  
 


(a)    Human
 
 
 Sl. No.
 Name
 Father's 
        Name
 Sex of 
        Victim
 Full 
        Postal Address
 
        Approximate Age
 Fatal / 
        Non-Fatal

 
 1
 2
 3
 4
 5
 6
 7

 
   

 
  
  
   

 
  
  
  


 

 
 


          (b)   Animal
 
 
 Sl. No.
 
        Description of Animal(s)
 Number 
        (s)
 Name(s) 
        of Owner(s)
 
        Address(es) of Owner(s)
 Fatal / 
        Non-Fatal

 
 1
 2
 3
 4
 5
 6

 
   

 
 

 
  
  
  
  
  


 


    7.   In case the victim(s) is/are 
    employee(s) of supplier:—  
 


(a)   designation of such person(s);  
 


(b)   brief description of the job undertaken, 
    if any;  
 


(c)   whether such person/persons was/were 
    allowed to work on the job.
 


8.   In case the victim(s) is/are employees(s) 
    of a licensed contractor,—  
 


(a)   did the victim(s) possess any electric 
    workmen’s permit(s), supervisor’s certificate of competency?
 


If yes, give number and date of issue and the 
    name of issuing authority;
 


(b)   name and designation of the person who 
    assigned the duties of the victim(s).
 


9.   In case of accident in the system of the 
    generating company/licensee, was the permit to work (PTW) taken?  
 


10.(a)   Describe fully the nature and extent 
    of injuries, e.g., fatal/disablement (permanent or temporary) of any 
    portion of the body or burns or other injuries.  
 


    (b)   In case of fatal 
    accident, was the post mortem performed?  
 


11.   Detailed causes leading to the accident.  
 


       (To be 
    given in a separate sheet annexed to this form).  
 


12.   Action taken regarding first aid, 
    medical attendance etc. immediately after the occurrence of the accident 
    (Give details).  
 


13.   Whether the District Magistrate and 
    Police Station concerned have been informed of the accident (If so, give 
    details).  
 


14.   Steps taken to preserve the evidence in 
    connection with the accident to extent possible.  
 


15.   Name and designation(s) of the person(s) 
    assisting, supervising the person(s) killed or injured.  
 


16.   What safety equipments were given to or 
    used by the person(s) who met with this accident (e.g., rubber 
    gloves, rubber mats, safety belts and ladders etc.)?  
 


17.   Whether  isolating switches and other 
    sectionalizing devices were employed to deaden the sections for working on 
    the same. Whether working section was earthed at the site of work.  
 


18.   Whether the work on the live lines was 
    undertaken by authorised person(s)? If so, the name and the designation of 
    such person(s) may be given.  
 


19.   Whether artificial resuscitation 
    treatment was given to the person(s) who met with the electric accident. If 
    yes, how long was it continued before its abandonment?  
 


20.   Names and designations of persons 
    present at, and witnessed, the accident.  
 


21.   Any other information/remarks.  
 

 
 



    Place......................................                                               Signature............................................
 



    Time......................................                                                Name..................................................
 



    Date......................................                                                Designation.......................................
 



                                                                                                Address 
    of the 
 



                                                                                                person 
    reporting..............................
 


 
 

 
 

 
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>