<act><tid>801750</tid>
<title>THE INDIAN IRON AND STEEL COMPANY (ACQUISTION OF SHARES) ACT, <year>1976</year></title>

ACT NO. 89 OF <year>1976</year>
[ 2nd September, <year>1976</year>.]

An Act to provide for the acquistion of certain shares of the Indian 
Iron and Steel Company Limited with a view to securing the proper 
management of the affairs of the Company and the continuity and 
development of the production of goods which are vital to the needs of 
the country and for matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>932673</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>757651</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Indian Iron and Steel Company (Acquistion of Shares) Act, <year>1976</year>.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>514</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1769931</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 17th day of 
July, <year>1976</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>172526</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>999525</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means the 17th day of July, <year>1976</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>1904185</tid>
<number>b</number>" bank" means a banking company within the meaning of the 
Banking Regulation Act, <year>1949</year> (10 of <year>1949</year>.);

</section>

<section><tid>1183493</tid>
<number>c</number>" Company" means the Indian Iron and Steel Company 
Limited, being a company within the meaning of the 
Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>.), and having its 
registered office at IISCO House, 50, Chowringhee Road, 
Calcutta;

</section>

<section><tid>600927</tid>
<number>d</number>" Commissioner" means the Commissioner of Payments 
appointed under section 5;

</section>

<section><tid>954305</tid>
<number>e</number>" notification" means a notification published in the 
Official Gazette;

</section>

<section><tid>1819807</tid>
<number>f</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>949793</tid>
<number>g</number>" share" means a share, whether equity or preference, in 
the capital of the Company, and includes a share 
pledged by any shareholder with any bank or other 
creditor, but does not include any share in the capital 
of the Company held by--

<subsection><tid>575982</tid>
<number>i</number>any State Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1772436</tid>
<number>ii</number>the State Bank of India, established under 
section 3 of the State Bank of India Act, <year>1955</year> (23 of  
  <year>1955</year>.) and its subsidiary banks;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>838207</tid>
<number>iii</number>the Steel Authority of India Limited, a 
company formed and registered under the Companies Act, 
<year>1956</year>, (1 of <year>1956</year>.) and having its registered office at 
Hindustan Times House, Kasturba Gandhi Marg, New Delhi;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>244737</tid>
<number>iv</number>the Life Insurance Corporation of India, 
established under section 3 of the Life Insurance 
Corporation Act, <year>1956</year> (31 of <year>1956</year>.);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>533230</tid>
<number>v</number>the Unit Trust of India, established under 
section 3 of the Unit Trust of India Act, <year>1963</year> (52 of  
  <year>1963</year>.);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>488504</tid>
<number>vi</number>any corresponding new bank, within the 
meaning of the Banking Companies (Acquisition and  
  Transfer of Undertakings) Act, <year>1970</year> (5 of <year>1970</year>.);

<pagefootnote><pagenum>515</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>641739</tid>
<number>vii</number>any general insurance company nationalised 
by the General Insurance Business (Nationalisation) 
Act, <year>1972</year> (57 of <year>1972</year>.);

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>309828</tid>
<number>h</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>" shareholder" means,--

</section>

<section><tid>285623</tid>
<number>i</number>a person who, immediately before the appointed 
day, was registered by the Company as the holder of any 
share and includes his legal representative; or

<subsection><tid>1475332</tid>
<number>ii</number>a person who, before the appointed day, had 
lodged with the Company a proper instrument of transfer 
of any share in the form prescribed under section 108 
of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year>, (1 of <year>1956</year>.) and executed 
in accordance with the provisions of that section; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>220059</tid>
<number>iii</number>a person who claims under a proper 
instrument of transfer of any share in the form 
prescribed under section 108 of the Companies Act, 
<year>1956</year>, (1 of <year>1956</year>.) and delivers such instrument, duly 
executed, to the Commissioner <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> before the expiry of 
one hundred and twenty days from the date of 
commencement of the Indian Iron and Steel Company 
 (Acquistion of Shares) Amendment Act, <year>1981</year>];]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1028298</tid>
<number>i</number>" specified date" means such date as the 
Central Government may, for the purpose of any 
provision of this Act, by notification, specify.
CHAP

ACQUISITION OF THE SHARES OF THE COMPANY

CHAPTER II

ACQUISITION OF THE SHARES OF THE COMPANY




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>245046</tid>
<number> 3</number> Transfer and vesting of shares of the Company in the Central 
Government.
<section><tid>62256</tid>
<number>1</number>On the appointed day, all the shares of the Company  
shall, by virtue of this Act, stand transferred to, and vested in, the 
Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1065541</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government shall be deemed, on and from the 
appointed day, to have been registered in the Register of members of 
the Company as the holder of each share which stands transferred to, 
and vested in, it by virtue of the provisions of sub- section (1).

</section>

<section><tid>1031925</tid>
<number>3</number>All the shares which have vested in the Central Government 
under sub- section (1), shall, by force of such vesting, be freed and 
discharged of all trusts, liabilities, obligations, mortgages, 
charges, liens and other incumbrances affecting them, and any 
attachment, injunction or any decree or order of the court, tribunal 
or other
<pagefootnote><pagenum>516</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs by Act 39 of <year>1977</year>, s. 2, for the original clause (w. e. f. 13-  
  10- <year>1977</year>). 
2 Subs. by Act 59 of <year>1981</year>, s. 2 (Act respectively).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


authority restricting the use of such shares in any manner, shall be 
deemed to have been withdrawn.


</section>

<section><tid>1592363</tid>
<number>4</number>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that the 
provisions of sub- sections (1) and (2) shall not be deemed to affect--

<subsection><tid>233418</tid>
<number>a</number>any right of the Company subsisting, immediately before 
the appointed day, against any shareholder to recover 
from such shareholder any sum of money on the ground 
that the shareholder has not paid or credited to the 
Company the whole or any part of the value of the 
shares held by him, or on any other ground whatsoever; 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1623382</tid>
<number>b</number>any right of the shareholder subsisting, immediately 
before the appointed day, against the Company to 
receive any dividend or other payment due from the 
Company.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1890252</tid>
<number> 4</number> Payment of amounts.
<section><tid>1144710</tid>
<number>1</number>For the transfer to, and vesting in,  
the Central Government, under section 3, of the shares of the Company, 
there shall be given by the Central Government to the shareholders of 
the Company, in cash and in the manner specified in section 6, an 
amount of rupees seven crores, twenty- three lakhs, ninety- five 
thousand and one hundred and thirty- seven and fifteen paise.

</section>

<section><tid>900479</tid>
<number>2</number>The amount, referred to in sub- section (1), shall carry 
simple interest at the rate of four per cent, per annum for the period 
commencing on the appointed day and ending on the date on which 
payment of such amount is made by the Central Government to the 
Commissioner.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>883824</tid>
<number> 5</number> Appointment of Commissioner, of Payments.
<section><tid>1431964</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government shall, for the purpose of disbursing the amounts payable to 
the Company under section 4, by notification, appoint a Commissioner 
of Payments.

</section>

<section><tid>1526670</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may appoint such other persons as it 
may think fit to assist the Commissioner and thereupon the 
Commissioner may authorise one or more of such persons also to 
exercise all or any of the powers exercisable by him under this Act, 
and different persons may be authorised to exercise different powers.

</section>

<section><tid>1125856</tid>
<number>3</number>Any person authorised by the Commissioner to exercise any of 
the powers exercisable by the Commissioner may exercise those powers 
in the same manner and with the same effect as if they have

<pagefootnote><pagenum>517</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

been conferred on that person directly by this Act, and not by way of 
authorisation.


</section>

<section><tid>694381</tid>
<number>4</number>The salaries and allowances of the Commissioner and other 
persons appointed under this section shall be defrayed out of the 
Consolidated Fund of India.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1832955</tid>
<number> 6</number> Payment by the Central Government to the Commissioner.
<section><tid>1940786</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Central Government shall, within thirty days from the specified date 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>, pay, in cash, to the Commissioner, for payment to the shareholders 
of the Company,--

<subsection><tid>622678</tid>
<number>a</number>an amount equal to the amount specified in sub- section 
 (1) of section 4; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>613767</tid>
<number>b</number>an amount equal to the amount determined under sub- 
section (2) of section 4.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1196727</tid>
<number>2</number>A deposit account shall be opened by the Central Government 
in favour of the Commissioner, in the Public Account of India, and 
every amount paid under this Act to the Commissioner shall be 
deposited by him to the credit of the said deposit account and the 
said deposit account shall be operated by the Commissioner.

</section>

<section><tid>1979668</tid>
<number>3</number>The interest accruing on the amount standing to the credit of 
the deposit account, referred to in sub- section (2), shall enure to 
the benefit of the shareholders of the Company.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1120293</tid>
<number> 7</number> Claims to be made to the Commissioner.
<section><tid>473489</tid>
<number>1</number>Every shareholder,  
having a claim in relation to any share acquired by this Act, shall 
prefer such claim before the Commissioner <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> before the expiry of one 
hundred and twenty days from the date of commencement of the Indian 
Iron and Steel Company (Acquisition of Shares) Amendment Act, <year>1981</year>]
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Provided that if the Commissioner is satisfied that the 
claimant was prevented by sufficient cause from preferring the claim 
before the expiry of the said period of one hundred and twenty days, 
he may entertain the claim within a further period of one hundred and 
twenty days and not thereafter.]


</section>

<section><tid>426633</tid>
<number>1A</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Every claim preferred under sub- section (1) as it stood 
before the commencement of the Indian Iron and Steel Company 
 (Acquisition of Shares) Amendment Act, <year>1981</year>, after the expiry of the 
period or date specified therein shall be deemed to have been 
preferred under the said sub- section as amended by the said Amendment 
Act and shall be dealt with (even if it had been disallowed before  
  such commencement) as if it had been preferred within time.]

</section>

<section><tid>346742</tid>
<number>2</number>Every shareholder of a preference share shall have a 
prevential claim with regard to the amount paid by the Central 
Government to the Commissioner.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>997680</tid>
<number>7A</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Power of Commissioner to inquire into disputes as to 
persons entitled to any amount. Where there is any dispute as to the 
person or persons who are entitled to any amount payable under this 
Act (including any dispute as to who are the legal representatives of  
any deceased
<pagefootnote><pagenum>518</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 19- 11- <year>1976</year>: vide Notifn No. S. O. 4392, dt. 4- 11- <year>1976</year>. 
2 Subs by Act 59 of <year>1981</year>, s. 3 (retrospectively). 
3 Ins. by s. 3, ibid. 
4 Ins. by Act 39 of <year>1977</year>, s. 4 ibid., (w. e. f. 13- 10- <year>1977</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


  claimant to the amount), the Commissioner may, after making such 
inquiry as he may deem fit, make the payment to such person as appears 
to him to be best entitled to receive the amount:

Provided that if the Commissioner is unable to determine as to 
who is the person entitled to the amount and considers that the matter 
could more appropriately be dealt with by the principal civil court of 
original jurisdiction within the local limits of whose jurisdiction 
the registered office of the Company is situated, he may refer such 
dispute to the said court, whose decision thereon shall be final:

Provided further that nothing contained herein shall affect the 
liability of any person, who may receive the whole or any part of the 
amount allowed under this Act, to pay the same to the person lawfully 
entitled thereto.



</article>



<article><tid>137016</tid>
<number>7B</number>Deposit of amount in court. Where any dispute has been 
referred under section 7A by the Commissioner to the civil court 
referred to therein, he shall deposit the amount in that court.]


</article>



<article><tid>292456</tid>
<number>8</number>Examination of claims. On receipt of the claims made under 
section 7, the Commisioner shall separately arrange the claims in 
relation to preference shares and in relation to the equity shares and 
examine the claims in relation to each such share.


</article>



<article><tid>1627716</tid>
<number> 9</number> Admission or rejection of claims.
<section><tid>19850</tid>
<number>1</number>After examining the  
claims, the Commissioner shall fix a certain date on or before which 
every claimant shall file the proof of his claim or be excluded from 
the benefit of the disbursements made by the Commissioner.

</section>

<section><tid>1898212</tid>
<number>2</number>Not less than fourteen days' notice of the date so fixed 
shall be given by advertisement in one issue of the daily newspaper in 
the English language and in one issue of such daily newspaper in the 
regional language as the Commissioner may consider suitable, and every 
such notice shall call upon the claimant to file the proof of his 
claim with the Commissioner within the time specified in the 
advertisement.

</section>

<section><tid>1222285</tid>
<number>3</number>Every claimant, who fails to file the proof of his claim 
within the time specified by the Commissioner, shall be excluded from 
the disbursement made by the Commissioner.

</section>

<section><tid>139531</tid>
<number>4</number>The Commissioner shall, after such investigation as may, in 
his opinion, be necessary, and after giving the Company an opportunity 
of

<pagefootnote><pagenum>519</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

refuting the claim and after giving the claimant a reasonable 
opportunity of being heard, in writing, admit or reject the claim in 
whole or in part.


</section>

<section><tid>50413</tid>
<number>5</number>The Commissioner shall have the power to regulate his own 
procedure in all matters arising out of the discharge of his 
functions, including the place or places at which he will hold his 
sittings and shall, for the purpose of making an investigation under 
this Act, have the same powers as are vested in a civil court under 
the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year>, (5 of <year>1908</year>.) while trying a suit, 
in respect of the following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1669459</tid>
<number>a</number>the summoning and enforcing the attendance of any 
witness and examining him on oath;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1917629</tid>
<number>b</number>the discovery and production of any document or other 
material object producible as evidence;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>807312</tid>
<number>c</number>the reception of evidence on affidavits;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>742550</tid>
<number>d</number>the issuing of any commission for the examination of 
witnesses.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1458064</tid>
<number>6</number>Any investigation before the Commissioner shall be deemed to 
be a judicial proceeding within the meaning of sections 193 and 228 of 
the Indian Penal Code (65 of <year>1960</year>.) and the Commissioner shall be 
deemed to be a civil court for the purposes of section 345 and Chapter 
XXVI of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>.).

</section>

<section><tid>1350633</tid>
<number>7</number>A claimant, who is dissatisfied with the decision of the 
Commissioner, may prefer an appeal against the decision to the 
principal civil court of original jurisdiction within the local limits 
of whose jurisdiction the registered office of the Company is 
situated.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1591406</tid>
<number> 10</number> Disbursement of money by the Commissioner to claimants.
<section><tid>1276316</tid>
<number>1</number> 
After admitting a claim under this Act, the amount due in respect of 
each share acquired by virtue of this Act shall be paid by the 
Commissioner at the rate of rupees thirty- two and paise seventy- five 
per preference share, and at the rate of rupees four and paise seventy 
per equity share to the person or persons to whom such sums are due, 
and on such payment, the liability of the Central Government in 
respect of the share so acquired shall stand discharged.

</section>

<section><tid>1112480</tid>
<number>2</number>The Commissioner shall also apportion amongst the 
shareholders, the amount paid to him by way of interest under sub-

<pagefootnote><pagenum>520</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

section (3) of section 6, and such apportionment shall be made on the 
basis of the amount due to each shareholder.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1693517</tid>
<number>11</number>Undisburse or unciaimed amount to be deposited to the general 
revenue account. Any money paid to the Commissioner which remains 
undisbursed or unclaimed for a period of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> six months] from the last 
day on which the disbursement was made, shall be transferred by the 
Commissioner to the general revenue account of the Central Government; 
but a claim to any money so transferred may be preferred to the 
Central Government by the person entitled to such payment and shall be 
dealt with as if such transfer had not been made, the order, if any, 
for payment of the claim being treated as an order for the refund of 
revenue.


</article>



<article><tid>891863</tid>
<number> 12</number> Power of inspection. For the purposes of ascertaining whether 
any person claiming payment under this Act is a shareholder, the 
Commissioner shall have the right to--
<section><tid>1106222</tid>
<number>a</number>require any person, having the possession, custody or 
control, of any register or record of the Company, to 
produce such register or record before the 
Commissioner,

</section>

<section><tid>1045440</tid>
<number>b</number>require any person to make any statement or furnish any 
information which may be required by the Commissioner.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER III

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1691336</tid>
<number>13</number>Act to have overriding effect. The provisions of this Act 
shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith 
contained in any law, other than this Act, or in any instrument having 
effect by virtue of any law, other than this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>201911</tid>
<number> 14</number> Penalties. If any person,--
<section><tid>1827327</tid>
<number>a</number>makes any claim for any payment under this Act, knowing 
or having reason to believe that such claim is false or 
without any basis; or

</section>

<section><tid>1732141</tid>
<number>b</number>when required under this Act so to do,--

<subsection><tid>1537811</tid>
<number>i</number>omits or fails to produce any register or 
record of the Company; or
<pagefootnote><pagenum>521</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 59 of <year>1981</year>, s. 4.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1846226</tid>
<number>ii</number>makes any statement or furnishes any 
information which is false in any material particular 
and which he knows or believes to be false or does not 
believe to be true; or

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1809958</tid>
<number>c</number>makes any such statement as aforesaid in any book, 
account, record, register, return or other document.
he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to two years, or with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees, or 
with both.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1067626</tid>
<number> 15</number> Offences by companies.
<section><tid>508820</tid>
<number>1</number>Where an offence under this Act  
has been committed by a company, every person who, at the time the 
offence was committed, was in charge of, and was responsible to, the 
company for the conduct of the business of the company as well as the 
company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be 
liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the 
offence was committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised 
all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.


</section>

<section><tid>1365522</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where 
any offence under this Act has been committed with the consent or 
connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any 
director, manager, secretary or other officer, such director, manager, 
secretary or other officer shall be deemed to be guilty of that 
offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished 
accordingly.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section,--


<subsection><tid>826607</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm 
or other association of individuals; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1299497</tid>
<number>b</number>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner in 
the firm.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1313460</tid>
<number>16</number>Limitation of cognizance of offences. No court shall take 
cognizance of an offence punishable under this Act, except with the 
previous sanction of the Central Government or of an officer 
authorised by that Government in this behalf.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>522</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>565208</tid>
<number> 17</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1115977</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification, make rules to carry out the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>227831</tid>
<number>2</number>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act 
shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House 
of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty 
days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>483492</tid>
<number>18</number>Repeal and saving. The Indian Iron and Steel Company 
 (Acquisition of Shares) Ordinance, <year>1976</year> (10 of <year>1976</year>.), is hereby 
repealed:
Provided that notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any 
action taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been 
done or taken under the corresponding provision of this Act.


</article>



 </act>