<act><tid>1521888</tid>
<title>THE SPECIAL BEARER BONDS (IMMUNITIES AND EXEMPTIONS) ACT, <year>1981</year></title>

ACT NO. 7 OF <year>1981</year>
[ 27th March, <year>1981</year>.]

An Act to provide for certain immunities to holders of Special Bearer 
Bonds, <year>1991</year> and for certain exemptions from direct taxes in relation 
to such bonds and for matters connected therewith.

WHEREAS for effective economic and social planning it is 
necessary to canalise for productive purposes black money which has 
become a serious threat to the national economy;

AND WHEREAS with a view to such canalisation the Central 
Government has decided to issue at par certain bearer bonds to be 
known as the Special Bearer Bonds, <year>1991</year>, of the face value of ten 
thousand rupees and redemption value, after ten years, of twelve 
thousand rupees;

AND WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for certain immunities and 
exemptions to render it possible for persons in possession of black 
money to invest the same in the said Bonds;

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty- second Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--





<article><tid>1999138</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.-
<section><tid>716609</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Special Bearer Bonds (Immunities and Exemptions) Act, <year>1981</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>395422</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.

</section>

<section><tid>619449</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 12th day of 
January, <year>1981</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>16795</tid>
<number>2</number>Definition.- In this Act," Special Bearer Bonds" means the 
Special Bearer Bonds, <year>1991</year>, issued by the Central Government.


</article>



<article><tid>437172</tid>
<number> 3</number> Immunities.-
<section><tid>182032</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in any  
other law for the time being in force,--

<subsection><tid>427037</tid>
<number>a</number>no person who has subscribed to or has otherwise 
acquired Special Bearer Bonds shall be required to disclose, for 
any purpose whatsoever, the nature and source of acquisition of 
such Bonds;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>21</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1981044</tid>
<number>b</number>no inquiry or investigation shall be commenced against 
any person under any such law on the ground that such person has 
subscribed to or has otherwise acquired Special Bearer Bonds; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1949131</tid>
<number>c</number>the fact that a person has subscribed to or has 
otherwise acquired Special Bearer Bonds shall not be taken into 
account and shall be inadmissible as evidence in any proceedings 
relating to any offence or the imposition of any penalty under 
any such law.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>849996</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing in sub- section (1) shall apply in relation to 
prosecution for any offence punishable under Chapter IX or Chapter 
XVII of the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>), the Prevention of Corrup- 
tion Act, <year>1947</year> (2 of <year>1947</year>) or any offence which is punishable under 
any other law and which is similar to an offence punishable under 
either of those Chapters or under that Act or for the purpose of 
enforcement of any civil liability.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this sub- section," civil 
liability" does not include liability by way of tax under any law for 
the time being in force.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>148892</tid>
<number> 4</number> Acquisition, etc., of Bonds not to be taken into account for 
certain proceedings.- Without prejudice to the generality of the 
provisions of section 3, the subscription to, or acquisition of, 
Special Bearer Bonds by any person shall not be taken into account for 
the purpose of any proceedings under the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> (43 of  
  <year>1961</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the Income- tax Act), the Wealth- tax 
Act, <year>1957</year> (27 of <year>1957</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the Wealth- tax  
  Act) or the Gift- tax Act, <year>1958</year> (18 of <year>1958</year>)  (hereinafter referred to  
  as the Gift- tax Act) and, in particular, no person who has subscribed 
to, or has otherwise acquired, the said Bonds shall be entitled--
<section><tid>305295</tid>
<number>a</number>to claim any set- off or relief in any assessment, re- 
assessment, appeal, reference or other proceeding under the 
Income- tax Act or to reopen any assessment or re- assessment made 
under that Act on the ground that he has subscribed to or has 
otherwise acquired the said Bonds;

</section>

<section><tid>1112191</tid>
<number>b</number>to claim, in relation to any period before the date of 
maturity of the said Bonds, that any asset which is includible in 
his net wealth for any assessment year under the Wealth- tax Act 
has been converted into the said Bonds; or

</section>

<section><tid>196835</tid>
<number>c</number>to claim, in relation to any period before the date of 
maturity of the said Bonds, that any asset held by him or any sum 
credited in his books of account or otherwise held by him 
represents the consideration received by him for the transfer of 
the said Bonds.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>788302</tid>
<number>5</number>[ Amendment of Act 43 of <year>1961</year>.] Rep. by the Repealing and 
Amending Act, <year>1988</year> (19 of <year>1988</year>), s. 2 and the First Schedule.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>22</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1985206</tid>
<number>6</number>[ Amendment of Act 27 of <year>1957</year>.] Rep. by the Repealing and 
Amending Act, <year>1988</year> (19 of <year>1988</year>), s. 2 and the First Schedule.
" (xvib) Special Bearer Bonds, <year>1991</year>;".



</article>



<article><tid>1415701</tid>
<number>7</number>Amendment of Act 18 of <year>1958</year>.- In section 5 of the Gift- tax Act, 
in sub- section 1, after clause (iiia), the following clause shall be 
inserted, namely:--
" (iiib) of property in the form of Special Bearer Bonds, <year>1991</year>;".



</article>



<article><tid>58158</tid>
<number> 8</number> Power to remove difficulties.
<section><tid>721831</tid>
<number>1</number>If any difficulty arises in  
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, 
remove the difficulty.

</section>

<section><tid>1403045</tid>
<number>2</number>Every order made under this section shall, as soon as may be 
after it is made, be laid before each House of Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1910078</tid>
<number>9</number>[ Repeal and saving.] Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, 
 <year>1988</year> (19 of <year>1988</year>), s. 2 and the First Schedule.

</article>



 </act>