<act><title>


the PREVENTION OF MONEY-LAUNDERING (RECEIPT 
    AND MANAGEMENT OF CONFISCATED PROPERTIES) RULES, 20051</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Prevention of Money-laundering (Receipt and 
    Management of Confiscated Properties) Rules, 2005.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “Act” means the Prevention of 
    Money-laundering Act, 2002 (15 of 2003);  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    “Adjudicating Authority” means an 
    Adjudicating Authority appointed under sub-section (1) of section 6 of the 
    Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    “Administrator” means an officer 
    appointed by the Central Government under sub-section (1) of section 10 of 
    the Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    “attachment” means prohibition of 
    transfer, conversion, disposition or movement of property by an order issued 
    under Chapter III of the Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    “Form” means forms appended to these 
    rules;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    “order” means an order made by the 
    Adjudicating Authority under sub-section (6) of section 8 of the Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    “section” means a section of the Act.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> All other 
    words and expressions used and not defined in these rules but defined in the 
    Act, shall have the meaning respectively assigned to them in the Act.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Receipt 
    of confiscated property.—The 
    Administrator shall, at the time of receiving the confiscated properties, 
    ensure proper identification of such property with reference to its 
    particulars mentioned in the order confiscating such property.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Management of confiscated property.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the property confiscated is of such a nature that its removal from the 
    place of attachment is impracticable or its removal involves expenditure out 
    of proportion to the value of the property, the Administrator shall arrange 
    for the proper maintenance and custody of the property at the place of 
    attachment.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the 
    property confiscated consists of cash, Government or other securities, 
    bullion, jewellery or other valuables, the Administrator shall cause to 
    deposit them for safe custody in the nearest Government Treasury or a branch 
    of the Reserve Bank of India or State Bank of India or its subsidiaries or 
    of any authorised bank.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Administrator shall maintain a register containing the details in Form I for 
    recording entries in respect of moveable property, such as cash, Government 
    or other securities, bullion, jewellery or other valuables.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Administrator shall obtain a receipt from the Treasury or the bank, as the 
    case may be, against the deposit of moveable properties stated in sub-rule 
    (3) of this rule.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Administrator shall maintain a register containing the details in Form II 
    for recording entries in respect of property other than the properties 
    referred to in sub-rule (3) of this rule.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Assistance to the Administrator.—The 
    Central Government may provide from time to time such members of staff and 
    other persons as it thinks fit to assist the Administrator in exercise of 
    his powers and performance of duties under these rules.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Interpretation.—If any question 
    arises relating to the interpretation of these rules, the matter shall be 
    referred to the Central Government and the decision of the Central 
    Government shall be final.  
  
 
  


</article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




the PREVENTION OF MONEY-LAUNDERING (RECEIPT 
    AND MANAGEMENT OF CONFISCATED PROPERTIES) RULES, 2005
 

 
 


FORM I 
 


[See sub-rule (3) of rule 4]
 



    Management of Confiscated Property (Moveable) Register
 

 
 


1.  Order number :
 


2.  Date of receipt of properties :
 


3.  Description of properties (quantity, 
    amount, estimated value) :
 


4.  Name(s) and address(es) of the accused :
 


5.  Name and address of the Treasury or bank 
    where the properties are deposited for safe custody :
 


6.  Date and time of deposit of confiscated 
    properties in the Treasury or bank :
 


7.  Receipt number with date of the receipt 
    obtained from the Treasury or bank :
 


8.  Remarks of the Administrator :  
 

 
 


Signature of the Administrator.         
    
 



    .................................................
 


Name and designation of the Administrator
 


Date...........................
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




the PREVENTION OF MONEY-LAUNDERING (RECEIPT 
    AND MANAGEMENT OF CONFISCATED PROPERTIES) RULES, 2005
 

 
 


FORM II
 


[See sub-rule (5) of rule 4]
 


Management of Confiscated Property 
    (Immoveable) Register
 

 
 


1.  Order Number : 
 


2.  Date of receipt of properties : 
 


3.  Description of properties : 
 


(In case of land : area, survey number, plot 
    number, location and complete address. In case of building : house number, 
    location and complete address): 
 


4.  Name(s) and address(es) of the accused: 
 


5.  Remarks of the Administrator: 
 

 
 


Signature of the Administrator.                  
    
 



    .........................................................
 


Name and designation of the Administrator.
 


Date...........................
 

 
 

 
 

 
 

 
 

 
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>