<act><tid>1474968</tid>
<title>THE CODE OF CRIMINAL PROCEDURE (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2001</year></title>

ACT NO. 50 OF <year>2001</year>
[ 24th September, <year>2001</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- second Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>630445</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title.- This Act may be called the Code of Criminal Procedure 
 (Amendment) Act, <year>2001</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>78238</tid>
<number> 2</number> Amendment of section 125.- In the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> 
 (2 of <year>1974</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the principal Act), in section 
125,-
<section><tid>367521</tid>
<number>i</number>in sub- section (1),-

<subsection><tid>1156965</tid>
<number>a</number>the words" not exceeding five hundred rupees in the whole," shall 
be omitted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>219226</tid>
<number>b</number>after the proviso and before the Explanation, the following 
provisos shall be inserted, namely:-
" Provided further that the Magistrate may, during the pendency of the 
proceeding regarding monthly allowance for the maintenance under this 
sub- section, order such person to make a monthly allowance for the 
interim maintenance of his wife or such child, ather or mother, and 
the expenses of such proceeding which the Magistrate considers 
reasonable, and to pay the same to such person as the Magistrate may 
from time to time direct:

Provided also that an application for the monthly allowance for the 
interim maintenance and expenses for proceeding under the second 
proviso shall, as far as possible, be disposed of within sixty days 
from the date of the service of notice of the applica ion to such 
person.";


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>529069</tid>
<number>ii</number>for sub- section (2), the following sub- section shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (2) Any such allowance for the maintenance or interim maintenance and 
expenses for proceeding shall be payable from the date of the order, 
or, if so ordered, from the date of the application for maintenance or 
interim maintenance and expenses of proceed ng, as the case may be.";


</section>

<section><tid>1666687</tid>
<number>iii</number>in sub- sections (3) and (4), for the word" allowance", wherever 
it occurs, the words'' allowance for the maintenance or the interim 
maintenance and expenses of proceeding, as the case may be," shall be 
substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>160908</tid>
<number> 3</number> Amendment of section 127.- In section 127 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>512172</tid>
<number>i</number>for sub- section (1), the following sub- section shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (1) On proof of a change in the circumstances of any person, 
receiving, under section 125 a monthly allowance for the maintenance 
or interim maintenance, or ordered under the same section to pay a 
monthly allowance for the maintenance, or interim mainte ance, to his 
wife, child, father or mother, as the case may be, the Magistrate may 
make such alteration, as he thinks fit, in the allowance for the 
maintenance or the interim maintenance, as the case may be.";


</section>

<section><tid>279871</tid>
<number>ii</number>in sub- section (3), in clause (c), for the word" maintenance", 
the words'' maintenance or interim maintenance, as the case may be," 
shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1201479</tid>
<number>iii</number>in sub- section (4),-

<subsection><tid>1155712</tid>
<number>a</number>for the words" monthly allowance has been ordered", the words 
" monthly allowance for the maintenance and interim maintenance or any 
of them has been ordered'' shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1862791</tid>
<number>b</number>for the words" as monthly allowance in pursuance of", the words 
" as monthly allowance for the maintenance and interim maintenance or 
any of them, as the case may be, in pursuance of'' shall be 
substituted.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>335611</tid>
<number> 4</number> Amendment of section 128.- In section 128 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>200596</tid>
<number>i</number>for the word" maintenance", the words" maintenance or interim 
maintenance and expenses of proceeding, as the case may be," shall be 
substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>58950</tid>
<number>ii</number>for the words" whom the allowance", the words" whom the allowance 
for the maintenance or the allowance for the interim maintenance and 
expenses of proceeding, as the case may be," shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>869406</tid>
<number>iii</number>for the words" allowance due", the words" allowance, or as the 
case may be, expenses, due" shall be substituted.


</section>

</article>



 </act>