<act> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title, extent 
and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
This Act may be called the Chit Funds Act, 1982. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends to the 
whole of India 
except the State of Jammu and Kashmir. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall come into 
force on such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, appoint and different dates may be appointed for different 
States*.  
 
 



























</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
   <number>a</number>  “approved bank” means the State Bank 
of India constituted under section 3 of the State Bank of India Act, 1955 (23 
of 1955), or a subsidiary bank constituted under section 3 of the State Bank of 
India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, 1959 (38 of 1959), or a corresponding new bank 
constituted under section 3 of the Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer 
of Undertakings) Act, 1970 (5 of 1970), or a Regional Rural Bank established 
under section 3 of the Regional Rural Banks Act, 1976 (21 of 1976), or a 
corresponding new bank constituted under section 3 of the Banking Companies 
(Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings) Act, 1980 (40 of 1980), or a banking 
company as defined under clause (e) of section 35 of the Banking Regulation 
Act, 1949 (10 of 1949), or a banking institution notified by the Central 
Government under section 51 of the Act or such other banking institution as the 
State Government may, in consultation with the Reserve Bank, approve for the 
purposes of this Act; 
 </section><section>
   <number>b</number>  “chit” means a transaction whether 
called chit, chit fund, chitty, kuri or by any other name by or under 
which a person enters into an agreement with a specified number of persons that 
every one of them shall subscribe a certain sum of money (or a certain quantity 
of grain instead) by way of periodical instalments over a definite period and 
that each such subscriber shall, in his turn, as determined by lot or by 
auction or by tender or in such other manner as may be specified in the chit 
agreement, be entitled to the prize amount; 
 
              Explanation.—A 
transaction is not a chit within the meaning of this clause, if in such 
transaction,—
 <subsection>
    <number>i</number>  some alone, but not all, of the 
subscribers get the prize amount without any liability to pay future 
subscriptions; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>ii</number>  all the subscribers get the chit 
amount by turns with a liability to pay future subscriptions; 
 </subsection></section><section>
   <number>c</number>  “chit agreement” means the document 
containing the articles of agreement between the foreman and the subscribers 
relating to the chit; 
 </section><section>
   <number>d</number>  “chit amount” means the sum-total of 
the subscriptions payable by all the subscribers for any instalment of a chit 
without any deduction of discount or otherwise; 
 </section><section>
   <number>e</number>  “chit business” means the business 
of conducting a chit; 
 </section><section>
    <number>f</number>  “defaulting subscriber” means a 
subscriber who has defaulted in the payment of subscriptions due in accordance 
with the terms of the chit agreement; 
 </section><section>
   <number>g</number>  “discount” means the sum of money or 
the quantity of grain which a prized subscriber is, under the terms of the chit 
agreement required to forego and which is set apart under the said agreement to 
meet the expenses of running the chit or for distribution among the subscribers 
or for both; 
 </section><section>
   <number>h</number>  “dividend” means the share of the 
subscriber in the amount of discount available under the chit agreement for 
rateable distribution among the subscribers at each instalment of the chit;

 </section><section>
    <number>i</number>  “draw” means the manner specified 
in the chit agreement for the purpose of ascertaining the prized subscriber at 
any instalment of the chit; 
 </section><section>
    <number>j</number>  “foreman” means the person who 
under the chit agreement is responsible for the conduct of the chit and 
includes any person discharging the functions of the foreman under section 39;

 </section><section>
   <number>k</number>  “non-prized subscriber” does not 
include a defaulting subscriber; 
 </section><section>
    <number>l</number>  “prescribed” means prescribed by 
rules made under this Act; 
 </section><section>
   <number>m</number>  “prize amount” means the difference 
between the chit amount and the discount, and in the case of a fraction of a 
ticket means the difference between the chit amount and the discount 
proportionate to the fraction of the ticket, and when the prize amount is 
payable otherwise than in cash, the value of the prize amount shall be the 
value at the time when it becomes payable; 
 </section><section>
   <number>n</number>  “prized subscriber” means a 
subscriber who has either received or is entitled to receive the prize amount;

 </section><section>
   <number>o</number>  “Registrar” means the Registrar of 
Chits appointed under section 61, and includes an Additional, a Joint, Deputy 
or an Assistant Registrar appointed under that section; 
 </section><section>
   <number>p</number>  “Reserve Bank” means the Reserve 
Bank of India constituted under the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 of 
1934); 
 </section><section>
   <number>q</number>  “State Government”, in relation to a 
Union territory, means the administrator of that Union territory appointed by 
the President under article 239 of the Constitution; 
 </section><section>
    <number>r</number>  “subscriber” includes a person who 
holds a fraction of a ticket and also a transferee of a ticket or fraction 
thereof by assignment in writing or by operation of law; 
 </section><section>
   <number>s</number>  “ticket”, means the share of a 
subscriber in a chit. 



</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Act to override other 
laws, memorandum, articles, etc.—Save 
as otherwise expressly provided in this Act,—
 <section>
   <number>a</number>  the provisions of this Act shall 
have effect notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any other law 
for the time being in force or in the memorandum or articles of association or 
bye-laws or in any agreement or resolution whether the same be registered, 
executed or passed, as the case may be, before or after the commencement of 
this Act; and 
 </section><section>
   <number>b</number>  any provision contained in the 
memorandum, articles, bye-laws, agreement or resolution aforesaid, shall, to 
the extent to which it is repugnant to the provisions of this Act, become null 
or be void, as the case may be. 


</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Prohibition of chits 
not sanctioned or registered under the Act.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No chit shall be commenced or conducted without obtaining the previous sanction 
of the State Government within whose jurisdiction the chit is to be commenced 
or conducted or of such officer as may be empowered by that Government in this 
behalf, and unless the chit is registered in that State in accordance with the 
provisions of this Act: 
 
Provided that a sanction 
obtained under this sub-section shall lapse if the chit is not registered 
within twelve months from the date of such sanction or within such further 
period or periods not exceeding six months in the aggregate as the State 
Government may, on application made to it in this behalf, allow. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An application for 
the purpose of obtaining a sanction under sub-section (1) shall be made by the 
foreman in such form and in such manner as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The previous sanction 
referred to in sub-section (1) may be refused, if the foreman,— 
 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>  had been convicted of any offence 
under this Act or under any other Act regulating chit business and sentenced to 
imprisonment for any such offence; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>  had defaulted in the payment of fees 
or the filing of any statement or record required to be paid or filed under 
this Act or had violated any of the provisions of this Act or the rules made 
thereunder; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>c</number>  had been convicted of any offence 
involving moral turpitude and sentenced to imprisonment for any such offence 
unless a period of five years has elapsed since his release: 
 
Provided that before 
refusing any such sanction, the foreman shall be given a reasonable opportunity 
of being heard. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The order of the 
State Government, and, subject to the provisions of sub-section (5), the order 
of the officer empowered under sub-section (1), issuing or refusing previous 
sanction under this section shall be final. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Any person aggrieved 
by the refusal to issue previous sanction by any officer empowered under 
sub-section (1) may appeal to the State Government within thirty days of the 
date of communication to him of such refusal and the decision of that 
Government on such appeal shall be final. 





</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Prohibition of 
invitation for subscription except under certain conditions.—No 
person shall issue or cause to be issued any notice, circular, prospectus, 
proposal or other document inviting the public to subscribe for tickets in any 
chit unless such notice, circular, prospectus, proposal or document contains a 
statement that the previous sanction required under section 4 has been obtained 
and the particulars of such sanction. 
</article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Form of chit 
agreement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every chit agreement shall be in duplicate and shall be signed by each of the 
subscribers or by any person authorised by him in writing and the foreman and 
attested by at least two witnesses and it shall contain the following 
particulars, namely:— 
 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>  full name and residential address of 
every subscriber; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>  the number of tickets including the 
fraction of a ticket held by each subscriber; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>c</number>  the number of instalments, the 
amount payable for each ticket at every instalment and the interest or penalty, 
if any, payable on any default in the payment of such instalments; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>d</number>  the probable date of commencement 
and the duration of the chit; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>e</number>  the manner of ascertaining the 
prized subscriber at each instalment; 
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>f</number>  the maximum amount of discount 
which the prized subscriber has to forego at any instalment; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>g</number>  the mode and proportion in which the 
discount is distributable by way of dividend, foreman’s commission or 
remuneration or expenses for running the chit, as the case may be; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>h</number>  the date, time and place at which 
the chit is to be drawn; 
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>i</number>  the instalment at which the foreman 
is to get the chit amount; 
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>j</number>  the name of the approved bank in 
which chit moneys shall be deposited by the foreman under the provisions of 
this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>k</number>  where the foreman is an individual, 
the manner in which a chit shall be continued when such individual dies or 
becomes of unsound mind or is otherwise incapacitated; 
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>l</number>  the consequences to which a 
non-prized or prized subscriber or the foreman shall be liable in case of 
violation of any of the provisions of the chit agreement; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>m</number>  the conditions under which a 
subscriber shall be treated as a defaulting subscriber; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>n</number>  the nature and particulars of the 
security to be offered by the foreman; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>o</number>  the dates on which and time during 
which the foreman shall, subject to the provisions contained in section 44, 
allow inspection of chit records to non-prized and un-paid prized subscribers;

 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>p</number>  the names of the nominees of each 
subscriber, that is to say, the name of the persons to whom the benefits 
accruing to the subscriber under the chit may be paid in the case of the death 
of the subscriber or when he is otherwise incapable of making an agreement;

 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>q</number>  any other particulars that may, from 
time to time, be prescribed. 
 
Explanation.—For 
the purpose of this sub-section, it shall be sufficient if the signature of 
each subscriber is obtained in separate copies of the agreement. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The duration of a 
chit shall not extend beyond a period of five years from the date of its 
commencement:
 
Provided that the State 
Government may permit the duration of a chit up to a period of ten years if it 
is satisfied that it is necessary so to do, having regard to,— 
 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>  the financial condition of the 
foreman; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>  his methods of operation; 

 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>c</number>  the interests of prospective 
subscribers; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>d</number>  the requirements as to security; and

 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>e</number>  such other factors as the 
circumstances of the case may require. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The amount of 
discount referred to in clause (f) of sub-section (1) shall not exceed 

1[forty per cent.] 
of the chit amount. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where the prized 
subscriber at any instalment of the chit is required to be determined by 
auction and more than one person offer the maximum discount, the prized 
subscriber shall be determined by lot. 
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Filing of chit 
agreement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every chit agreement shall be filed in duplicate by the foreman with Registrar.

 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Registrar shall 
retain one copy of the chit agreement and return the duplicate to the foreman 
with an endorsement that the chit agreement has been registered: 
 
Provided that the 
Registrar may refuse to register the chit agreement on any one or more of the 
following grounds, namely:— 
 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>  that the security offered by the 
foreman under section 20 is insufficient; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>  that the foreman had been convicted 
of any offence under this Act or under any other Act regulating chit business 
and sentenced to imprisonment for any such offence; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>c</number>  that the foreman had defaulted in 
the payment of fees or the filing of any statement or record required to be 
paid or filed under this Act or had violated any of the provisions of this Act 
or the rules made thereunder; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>d</number>  that the foreman had been convicted 
of any offence involving moral turpitude and sentenced to imprisonment for any 
such offence unless a period of five years has elapsed since his release:

 
Provided further that 
before refusing to register a chit under the first proviso, the foreman shall 
be given a reasonable opportunity of being heard. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Every endorsement 
made under sub-section (2) shall be conclusive evidence that the chit is duly 
registered under this Act and the registration of a chit shall lapse if the 
declaration by the foreman under sub-section (1) of section 9 is not filed 
within three months from the date of such endorsement or within such further 
period or periods not exceeding three months in the aggregate as the Registrar 
may, on application made to him in this behalf, allow. 
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Minimum capital 
requirements for the commencement, etc., of a chit, and creation of a reserve 
fund, by a company.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), but 
subject to the provisions of this Act, a company shall not commence or carry on 
chit business unless it has a paid-up capital of not less than rupees one lakh.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every company having 
a paid-up capital of less than rupees one lakh and carrying on chit business on 
the commencement of this Act, shall, before the expiry of a period of three 
years from such commencement, increase its paid-up capital to not less than 
rupees one lakh: 
 
Provided that the State 
Government may, if it considers it necessary in the public interest or for 
avoiding any hardship, extend the said period of three years in respect of any 
company by such further period or periods not exceeding two years in the 
aggregate: 
 
Provided further that no 
such company shall commence any new chit the duration of which would extend 
beyond the said period of three years or such extended period or periods under 
the first proviso unless it increases its paid-up capital to not less than 
rupees one lakh. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every company 
carrying on chit business shall create and maintain a reserve fund and shall, 
out of the balance of profit of each year as disclosed in its profit and loss 
account and before any dividend on its shares is declared, transfer to such 
reserve fund, a sum equal to not less than ten per cent. of such profit. 

 </section><section>
<number>4</number> No company shall 
appropriate any sum or sums from the reserve fund except with the prior 
approval of the Registrar and, for the purpose of obtaining such approval, it 
shall make an application in the prescribed form to the Registrar explaining 
the circumstances relating to such appropriation. 
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Commencement of chit.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every foreman shall, after all the tickets specified in the chit agreement are 
fully subscribed, file a declaration to that effect with the Registrar. 

 </section><section>
<number>2</number> As soon as may be 
after a declaration is filed under sub-section (1), the Registrar shall, after 
satisfying himself that all the requirements relating to sanction, registration 
of chit and other matters have been duly complied with, grant a certificate of 
commencement to the foreman. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No foreman shall 
commence any auction or the draw of any chit or appropriate any chit amount 
unless a certificate of commencement referred to in sub-section (2) is obtained 
by him. 


</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Copies of chit 
agreement to be given to subscribers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A foreman shall, as soon as may be after he has obtained the certificate of 
commencement under sub-section (2) of section 9, but not later than the date of 
the first draw of the chit, furnish to every subscriber, a copy of the chit 
agreement certified to be a true copy. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A foreman shall, 
within fifteen days after the close of the month in which the draw for the 
first instalment of the chit is held, file with the Registrar, a certificate to 
the effect that the provisions of sub-section (1) have been complied with.

</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Use of the words 
“chit”, “chit fund”, “chitty” or “kuri”.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No person shall carry on chit business unless he uses as part of his name any 
of the words “chit”, “chit fund”, “chitty” or “kuri” and no 
person other than a person carrying on chit business shall use as part of his 
name any such word. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where at the 
commencement of this Act,—
 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>  any person carrying on chit business 
without using as part of his name any of the words specified in sub-section 
(1); or 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>  any person not carrying on chit 
business is using any such word as part of his name, 
 
he shall, within a period 
of one year from such commencement, add as part of his name any such word or, 
as the case may be, delete such words from his name: 
 
Provided that the State 
Government may, if it considers it necessary in the public interest or for 
avoiding any hardship, extend the said period of one year by such further 
period or periods not exceeding one year in the aggregate. 
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Prohibition of 
transacting business other than chit business by a company.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Except with the general or special permission of the State Government, no 
company carrying on chit business shall conduct any other business.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where at the 
commencement of this Act, any company is carrying on any business in addition 
to chit business, it shall wind up such other business before the expiry of a 
period of three years from such commencement: 
 
Provided that the State 
Government may, if it considers it necessary in the public interest or for 
avoiding any hardship, extend the said period of three years by such further 
period or periods not exceeding two years in the aggregate. 


</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Aggregate amount of 
chits.—
<section><number>1</number> No 
foreman, other than a firm or other association of individuals or a company or 
co-operative society, shall commence or conduct chits, the aggregate chit 
amount of which at any time exceeds 

1[rupees one lakh].
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the foreman is 
a firm or other association of individuals, the aggregate chit amount of the 
chits conducted by the firm or other association shall not at any time exceed,—

 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>  where the number of partners of the 
firm or the individuals constituting the association is not less than four, a 
sum of rupees 

2[six lakhs]; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>  in any other case, a sum calculated 
on the basis of 

1[rupees one lakh] rupees with 
respect to each such partner or individual. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the foreman is 
a company or co-operative society, the aggregate chit amount of the chits 
conducted by it shall not at any time exceed ten times the net-owned funds of 
the company or the co-operative society, as the case may be. 
 
Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this sub-section, “net-owned funds” shall mean the aggregate of 
the paid-up capital and free reserves as disclosed in the last audited 
balance-sheet of the company or co-operative society, as reduced by the amount 
of accumulated balance of loss, deferred revenue, expenditure and other 
intangible assets, if any, as disclosed in the said balance-sheet. 








</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Utilisation of funds.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No person carrying on chit business shall utilise the moneys collected in 
respect of such business (other than commission or remuneration payable to such 
person or interest or penalty, if any, received from a defaulting subscriber), 
except for—
 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>  carrying on chit business; or 

 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>  giving loans and advances to 
non-prized subscribers on the security of subscriptions paid by them; or 

 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>c</number>  investing in trustee securities 
within the meaning of section 20 of the Indian Trusts Act, 1882 (2 of 1882); or

 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>d</number>  making deposits with approved banks 
mentioned in the chit agreement. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any person 
carrying on chit business has utilised the moneys collected in respect of such 
business before the commencement of this Act, otherwise than for the purposes 
specified in sub-section (1), he shall secure that so much of such moneys as 
have not been realised before such commencement are realised before the expiry 
of a period of three years from such commencement: 
 
Provided that the State 
Government may, if it considers it necessary in the public interest or for 
avoiding any hardship, extend the said period of three years by such further 
period or periods not exceeding one year in the aggregate. 
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Alteration of chit 
agreement.—A 
chit agreement shall not be altered, added to or cancelled except with the 
consent in writing of the foreman and all the subscribers to the chit. 

</article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Date, time and place 
of conducting chits.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every draw in a chit shall be held on the date, at the time and place mentioned 
in the chit agreement and a notice therefor in such form and in such manner as 
may be prescribed shall be issued by the foreman to all the subscribers.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every such draw shall 
be conducted in accordance with the provisions of the chit agreement and in the 
presence of not less than two subscribers. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where any draw was 
not conducted on the ground that two subscribers required to be present at a 
draw under sub-section (2) were not present or on any other ground, the 
Registrar may, on his own motion or on an application made by the foreman or 
any of the subscribers, direct that the draw shall be conducted in his presence 
or in the presence of any person deputed by him. 
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Minutes of 
proceedings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The minutes of the proceedings of every draw shall be prepared and entered in a 
book to be kept for that purpose immediately after the closure of the draw and 
shall be signed by the foreman, the prized subscribers, if present, or their 
authorised agents, and at least two other subscribers who are present, and 
where a direction has been made under sub-section (3) of section 16, also by 
the Registrar or the person deputed by him under that sub-section. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The minutes referred 
to in sub-section (1) shall state clearly— 
 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>  the date and hour when proceedings 
began and ended and the place where the draw was held; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>  the number of the instalment of the 
chit to which the proceedings relate; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>c</number>  the names of the subscribers 
present; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>d</number>  the person or persons who become 
entitled to the prize amount in the instalment; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>e</number>  the amount of discount; 
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>f</number>  full particulars regarding the 
disposal of the unpaid prize amount, if any, in respect of any previous 
instalment; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>g</number>  any other particulars that may be 
prescribed. 


</subsection></section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Copies of minutes to 
be filed with Registrar.—A 
true copy of the minutes of the proceedings of every draw certified as such by 
the foreman shall be filed by the foreman with the Registrar within twenty-one 
days from the date of the draw to which it relates. 
</article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Restriction on 
opening of new place of business.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No person carrying on chit business shall open a new place of business without 
obtaining the prior approval of the Registrar within whose territorial 
jurisdiction his registered office or, as the case may be, the place or the 
principal place of business is situated.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Before granting 
approval under sub-section (1), the Registrar shall consult the Registrar of 
that State within whose territorial jurisdiction the new place of business is 
proposed to be opened and shall also keep in view the financial condition and 
methods of operation of the foreman, the extent to which public interest will 
be served by the opening of the new place of business and such other matters as 
may be prescribed. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where a person 
carrying on chit business opens a new place of business in a State other than 
the State (hereinafter referred to as the State of origin) in which his 
registered office or the place or the principal place of his business is 
situated, the Registrar of the State in which such new place of business is 
opened may also exercise and perform any of the powers and functions which the 
Registrar of the State of origin may exercise and perform in respect of the 
chit business carried on at such new place of business. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> For the purposes of 
this section, “place of business” shall include any branch office, sub-office, 
or any place of business where the chit business may be conducted by such 
person. 


</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Security to be given 
by foreman.—
<section><number>1</number> 
For the proper conduct of the chit, every foreman shall, before applying for a 
previous sanction under section 4,—
 

1[(a)  deposit in the name of the 
Registrar, an amount equal to,—
 <subsection>
    <number>i</number>  fifty per cent. of the chit amount 
in cash in an approved bank; and
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>ii</number>  fifty per cent. of the chit amount 
in the form of bank guarantee from an approved bank; or]
 <subsubsection>
   <number>b</number>  transfer Government securities of 
the face value or market value (whichever is less) of not less than one and a 
half times the chit amount in favour of the Registrar; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>c</number>  transfer in favour of the Registrar 
such other securities, being securities in which a trustee may invest money 
under section 20 of the Indian Trusts Act, 1882 (2 of 1882), of such value, as 
may be prescribed by the State Government from time of time: 
 
Provided that the value 
of the securities referred to in clause (c) shall not, in any case, be less 
than one and a half times the value of the chit amount. 
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where a foreman 
conducts more than one chit, he shall furnish security in accordance with the 
provisions of sub-section (1) in respect of each chit. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Registrar may, at 
any time during the currency of the chit, permit the substitution of the 
security: 
 
Provided that the face 
value or market value (whichever is less) of the substituted security shall not 
be less than the value of the security given by the foreman under sub-section 
(1). 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The security given by 
the foreman under sub-section (1), or any security substituted under 
sub-section (3), shall not be liable to be attached in execution of a decree or 
otherwise until the chit is terminated and the claims of all the subscribers 
are fully satisfied. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where the chit is 
terminated and the Registrar has satisfied himself that the claims of all the 
subscribers have been fully satisfied, he shall order the release of the 
security furnished by the foreman under sub-section (1), or the security 
substituted under sub-section (3), as the case may be, and in doing so, he 
shall follow such procedure as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Notwithstanding 
anything to the contrary contained in any other law for the time being in 
force, the security furnished under this section shall not be dealt with by the 
foreman during the currency of the chit to which it relates and any dealing by 
the foreman with respect thereto by way of transfer or other encumbrances shall 
be null and void. 
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Rights of foreman.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The foreman shall be entitled,—
 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>  in the absence of any provision in 
the chit agreement to the contrary, to obtain the chit amount at the first 
instalment without deduction of the discount specified in the chit agreement, 
subject to the condition that he shall subscribe to a ticket in the chit:

 
              Provided that in a case where 
the foreman has subscribed to more than one ticket, he shall not be eligible to 
obtain more than one chit amount in a chit without discount; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>  to such amount not exceeding five 
per cent. of the chit amount as may be fixed in the chit agreement, by way of 
commission, remuneration or for meeting the expenses of running of the chit;

 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>c</number>  to interest and penalty, if any, 
payable on any default in the payment of instalments and to such other amounts 
as may be payable to him under the provisions of the chit agreement; 

 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>d</number>  to receive and realise all 
subscriptions from the subscribers and to distribute the prize amounts to the 
prized subscribers; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>e</number>  to demand sufficient security from 
any prized subscriber for the due payment of future subscriptions payable by 
him. 
 
              Explanation.—A 
security shall be deemed to be sufficient for the purposes of this clause if 
its value exceeds by one-third, or if it consists of immoveable properties, the 
value of which exceeds by one-half, of the amount due from prized subscriber;

 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>f</number>  to substitute subscribers in place 
of defaulting subscribers; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>g</number>  to do all other acts that may be 
necessary for the due and proper conduct of the chit. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any dispute 
arises with regard to the value of the property offered as security under 
clause (e) of sub-section (1), it shall be referred to the Registrar for 
arbitration under section 64. 



</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Duties of foreman.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The foreman shall, on the prized subscriber furnishing sufficient security for 
the due payment of future subscriptions, be bound to pay him the prize amount:

 
Provided that the prized 
subscriber shall be entitled to the payment of the prize amount without any 
security whatsoever if he agrees to the deduction therefrom of the amount of 
all future subscriptions and in such a case, the foreman shall pay the prize 
amount to the prized subscriber within seven days after the date of the draw or 
before the date of the next succeeding instalment, whichever is earlier: 

 
Provided further that 
where the prize amount has been paid to the prized subscriber under the first 
proviso, the amount deducted shall be deposited by the foreman in an approved 
bank mentioned in the chit agreement and he shall not withdraw the amount so 
deposited except for the payment of future subscriptions. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If, owing to the 
default of the prized subscriber, the prize amount due in respect of any draw 
remains unpaid until the date of the next succeeding instalment, the foreman 
shall deposit the prize amount forthwith in a separate account in an approved 
bank mentioned in the chit agreement and intimate in writing the fact of such 
deposit and the reasons therefor to the prized subscriber and the Registrar:

 
Provided that where any 
prized subscriber does not collect the prize amount in respect of any 
instalment of a chit within a period of two months from the date of the draw, 
it shall be open to the foreman to hold another draw in respect of such 
instalment. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every payment of the 
prize amount or the amount of future subscriptions under sub-section (1), and 
the deposit of the prize amount under sub-section (2), shall be intimated to 
the subscribers at the next succeeding draw and the particulars of such payment 
or deposit shall be entered in the minutes of the proceedings of that draw.

 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The foreman shall not 
appropriate to himself any amount in excess of what he is entitled to under 
clause (b) or clause (c) of sub-section (1) of section 21: 
 
Provided that where the 
foreman is himself a prized subscriber, he shall be entitled to appropriate to 
himself the prize amount subject to his complying with provisions of section 
31: 
 
Provided further that the 
foreman may appropriate to himself the interest accruing on the amount 
deposited under the second proviso to sub-section (1). 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The foreman shall not 
admit any person as a subscriber to a chit, if, by such admission, the total 
number of tickets mentioned in the chit agreement is increased. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The foreman shall 
distribute among the subscribers in accordance with the chit agreement, the 
dividend either in cash, grain or by way of adjustment towards the 
subscriptions payable for the next instalment, if any. 
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Books, records, etc., 
to be kept by foreman.—The 
foreman shall maintain in the registered office, or, as the case may be, in the 
place or the principal place of his business, or, where the foreman has any 
branch office, sub-office or any place of business for the conduct of chit 
business in a State other than the State in which his registered office or the 
principal place of his business is situated, in such branch office, sub-office 
or place of business in respect of the business conducted in that State—
 <section>
   <number>a</number>  a register containing—
 <subsection>
    <number>i</number>  the names and full particulars of 
the subscribers in each chit together with the number of tickets held by each 
subscriber; 
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>ii</number>  the dates on which the subscribers 
signed the chit agreement; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>iii</number>  in the case of an assignment of a 
ticket by a subscriber, the name and full address of the assignee with the date 
of assignment and the date on which the assignment had been recognised by the 
foreman; 
 </subsection></section><section>
   <number>b</number>  a book containing the minutes of the 
proceedings of each draw; 
 </section><section>
   <number>c</number>  a ledger containing — 
 <subsection>
    <number>i</number>  the amounts paid by the prized 
subscribers in each chit and the dates of such payments; 
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>ii</number>  the amounts paid to the prized 
subscribers and the dates of such payments; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>iii</number>  in the case of any deposit in an 
approved bank mentioned in the chit agreement, the date and the amount of such 
deposit; 
 </subsection></section><section>
   <number>d</number>  a register in the prescribed form 
showing the amounts deposited in approved banks as required under the 
provisions of this Act in respect of all chits conducted by the foreman at his 
office; and 
 </section><section>
   <number>e</number>  such other registers and books in 
such form as may be prescribed by the State Government within whose 
jurisdiction the chit is conducted. 
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>24</number> Balance-sheet.—Without 
prejudice to the provisions of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), every 
foreman shall prepare and file with the Registrar within such time as may be 
prescribed, a balance-sheet as on the last date of each calendar year, or, as 
the case may be, the financial year of the foreman, and a profit and loss 
account relating to the year of account, in the forms set out in Parts I and II 
of the Schedule, or as near thereto as circumstances admit, in respect of the 
chit business and audited by auditors qualified to act as auditors under the 
Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), or by a chit auditor appointed under section 
61: 
 
Provided that where a 
balance-sheet is audited by an auditor qualified to act as auditor under the 
Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), a chit auditor appointed under section 61 
shall have the right to audit the balance-sheet at any time if so authorised by 
the Registrar in this behalf. 
</article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Liability of foreman 
to subscribers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every foreman shall be liable to account to the subscribers for the amounts due 
to them.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where there are more 
than one foreman in a chit, each one of them jointly and severally and, if the 
foreman is a firm or other association of individuals, each one of the partners 
or individuals thereof jointly and severally and, if the foreman is a company, 
the company as such, shall be liable to the subscribers in respect of the 
obligations arising out of the chit. 
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Withdrawal of 
foreman.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No foreman, or where there are more than one foreman in a chit, none of them 
shall withdraw from the chit until its termination unless such withdrawal is 
assented to in writing by all the non-prized and unpaid prized subscribers and 
a copy of such assent has been filed with the Registrar under section 41.

 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The withdrawal from a 
chit of any one of the foreman shall not effect the security given by him under 
section 20 or section 31. 
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Non-prized 
subscribers to pay subscriptions and obtain receipts.—Every 
non-prized subscriber shall pay his subscription due in respect of every 
instalment on the dates and times and at the places mentioned in the chit 
agreement and shall, on such payment, be entitled to obtain a receipt from the 
foreman. 
</article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Removal of defaulting 
subscribers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A non-prized subscriber who defaults in payment his subscription in accordance 
with the terms of the chit agreement shall be liable to have his name removed 
from the list of subscribers and a written notice of such removal shall be 
given by the foreman to the defaulting subscriber within fourteen days of the 
date of such removal: 
 
Provided that if the 
defaulter pays the defaulted instalment with interest at such rate as may be 
prescribed within seven days of the date of receipt of such notice, his name 
shall be re-entered in the list of such subscribers. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every such removal 
under sub-section (1), shall, with the date thereof, be entered in the relevant 
book maintained by the foreman. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A true copy of the 
entry referred to in sub-section (2) shall be filed by the foreman with the 
Registrar within fourteen days from the date of removal. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Any defaulting 
subscriber aggrieved by the removal of his name from the list of subscribers 
may, within seven days of the date of receipt of the notice of removal refer 
the matter to the Registrar for arbitration under section 64. 
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>29</number> Substitution of 
subscribers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A foreman may substitute in the list of subscribers any person (hereinafter in 
this Chapter referred to as the substituted subscriber) in place of the 
defaulting subscriber whose name has been removed under sub-section (1) of 
section 28. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every substitution 
referred to in sub-section (1) shall, with the date thereof, be entered in the 
relevant book maintained by the foreman and a true copy of every such entry 
shall be filed by the foreman with the Registrar within fourteen days from the 
date of substitution. 
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>30</number> Amounts due to 
defaulting subscribers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A foreman shall, out of the amounts payable by and realized from the 
substituted subscriber towards the instalment relatable to the period before 
the date of the substitution (including the arrears due from the defaulting 
subscriber), deposit, before the date of the next succeeding instalment, in a 
separate identifiable account in an approved bank mentioned in the chit 
agreement, an amount equal to the contributions made by the defaulting 
subscriber less such deductions as may be provided for in the chit agreement, 
and shall inform the defaulting subscriber as well as the Registrar of the fact 
of such deposit and shall not withdraw the amount so deposited except for 
payment to the defaulting subscriber.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The amount so 
deposited under sub-section (1) shall be paid to the defaulting subscriber as 
and when he claims the amount and the amount so deposited shall not be 
withdrawn by the foreman for any purpose other than for such payment. 

 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The contributions of 
any defaulting subscriber who has not been substituted till the termination of 
the chit shall be paid to him within fifteen days from the date of termination 
of the chit subject to such deductions as may be provided for in the chit 
agreement. 
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>31</number> Prized subscriber to 
furnish security.—Every 
prized subscriber shall, if he has not offered to deduct the amount of all 
future subscriptions from the prize amount due to him, furnish, and a foreman 
shall take, sufficient security for the due payment of all future subscriptions 
and, if the foreman is a prized subscriber, he shall give security for the due 
payment of all the future subscriptions to the satisfaction of the Registrar.

</article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>32</number> Prized subscriber to 
pay subscriptions regularly.—Every 
prized subscriber shall pay his subscriptions regularly on the dates and times 
and at the place mentioned in the chit agreement and, on his failure to do so, 
he shall be liable to make a consolidated payment of all the future 
subscriptions forthwith. 
</article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>33</number> Foreman to demand 
future subscriptions by written notice.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A foreman shall not be entitled to claim a consolidated payment from a 
defaulting prized subscriber under section 32 unless he makes a demand to that 
effect in writing. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where a dispute is 
raised under this Act by a foreman for a consolidated payment of future 
subscriptions from a defaulting prized subscriber and if the subscriber pays to 
the foreman on or before the date to which the dispute is posted for hearing 
the arrears of subscriptions till that date together with the interest thereon 
at the rate provided for in the chit agreement and the cost of adjudication of 
the dispute, the Registrar or his nominee hearing the dispute shall, 
notwithstanding any contract to the contrary, make an order directing the 
subscriber to pay to the foreman the future subscriptions on or before the 
dates on which they fall due, and that, in case of any default of such payments 
by the subscriber, the foreman shall be at liberty to realise, in execution of 
that order, all future subscriptions and interest together with the costs, if 
any, less the amount, if any, already paid by the subscriber in respect 
thereof: 
 
Provided that if any such 
dispute is on a promissory note, no order shall be passed under this 
sub-section unless such promissory note expressly states that the amount due 
under the promissory note is towards the payment of subscriptions to the chit.

 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any person who holds 
any interest in the property furnished as security or part thereof, shall be 
entitled to make the payment under sub-section (2). 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> All consolidated 
payment of future subscriptions realised by a foreman shall be deposited by him 
in an approved bank mentioned in the chit agreement before the date of the 
succeeding instalment and the amount so deposited shall not be withdrawn except 
for payment of future subscriptions. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where any property is 
obtained as security in lieu of the consolidated payment of future 
subscriptions, it shall remain as security for the due payment of future 
subscriptions. 


</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>34</number> Restrictions on 
transfer of rights of foreman.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No transfer of the rights of a foreman to receive subscriptions from the prized 
subscribers shall be made without the previous sanction in writing of 
Registrar. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any transfer of the 
rights of a foreman to receive subscriptions from the prized subscribers shall, 
if it is likely to defeat or delay the interests of a non-prized or unpaid 
prized subscriber, be voidable at the instance of such subscriber. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> When under 
sub-section (2), a transfer is disputed by a subscriber, the burden of 
providing that the foreman was in solvent circumstances at the time of the 
transfer and that the transfer does not defeat or delay the interests of such 
subscriber is on the transferee. 
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>35</number> Transfer of 
non-prized subscriber’s right to be in writing.—Every 
transfer by a non-prized subscriber of his rights in the chit shall be in 
writing duly attested by at least two witnesses and shall be filed with the 
foreman. 
</article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>36</number> Recognition of 
transfer by foreman.—Every 
transfer under section 35 shall, within a period of fourteen days from the date 
of receipt of the proposal for transfer by the foreman, be recognised by him 
unless the transferee is not solvent or the transfer was effected with a view 
to defeating the provisions of any law including this Act and the decision of 
the foreman to recognise the transfer or not shall forthwith be communicated to 
the parties concerned.
</article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>37</number> Entry of transfer.—Every 
transfer under section 34 or section 35 shall be entered by the foreman in the 
books of the chit forthwith and a true copy of such entry shall be filed by the 
foreman with the Registrar within fourteen days from the date of making such 
entry. 
</article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>38</number> Meetings of general 
body of subscribers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The foreman may, on his own motion, convene a special meeting of the general 
body of subscribers for considering any proposal to pass a special resolution.

 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The foreman shall 
convene such a meeting on the requisition in writing of not less than 
twenty-five per cent. of the number of non-prized and unpaid prized 
subscribers, and the meeting so convened shall be held within thirty days of 
the date of receipt of the requisition and if the foreman refuses or fails to 
call such a meeting within fourteen days of the date of receipt of such 
requisition, not less than twenty-five per cent. of the number of non-prized 
and unpaid prized subscribers may give notice of the fact to the Registrar.

 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Registrar shall, 
within twenty-one days of the receipt of the notice under sub-section (2), 
convene or direct the convening of a special meeting of the general body of the 
subscribers and on receipt of such a direction, it shall be the duty of the 
foreman to comply with such direction. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Notice of not less 
than fourteen days shall be given to all the subscribers of a meeting under 
this section specifying the object, date, hour and place of meeting and a copy 
of the special resolution shall also be sent along with the notice of the 
meeting. 
 
Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this section and section 39, “special resolution” means a 
resolution which is passed at a meeting of the general body of the subscribers 
specially convened for the purpose, by a majority of not less than two-thirds 
of the subscribers to the chit present at the meeting in person or by proxy and 
representing not less than three-fourths of the amount or, as the case may be, 
the value of the grain, subscribed by all non-prized and unpaid prized 
subscribers, if any.
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>39</number> Provision for 
continuation of chits in certain cases.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where a foreman dies or becomes of unsound mind or is otherwise incapacitated, 
the chit may continue in accordance with the provisions of the chit agreement.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where a foreman is 
adjudicated as insolvent, or withdraws from the chit under section 26, or fails 
to conduct the chit at any instalment or on any other date before the next 
succeeding instalment as may have been agreed upon by a special resolution, any 
one or more of such subscribers authorised by such resolution may, in the 
absence of any provision in the chit agreement for the future conduct of the 
chit, take the place of the foreman and continue the chit or make other 
arrangements for the further conduct of the chit. 
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>40</number> Termination of chits.—A 
chit shall be deemed to have terminated,—
 <section>
   <number>a</number>  when the period specified therefor 
in the chit agreement has expired provided the payment of dues to all the 
subscribers has been completed; or 
 </section><section>
   <number>b</number>  when all the non-prized and unpaid 
prized subscribers and the foreman consent in writing to the termination of the 
chit and a copy of such consent is filed with the Registrar as required under 
section 41; or 
 </section><section>
   <number>c</number>  where a foreman dies or becomes of 
unsound mind or is otherwise incapacitated and the chit is not continued in 
accordance with the provisions of the chit agreement: 
 
Provided that, in a case 
where the foreman is a firm, if a partner thereof dies or becomes of unsound 
mind or is otherwise incapacitated, the chit shall not be deemed to have 
terminated and the surviving partner or partners shall conduct the chit in the 
absence of any provision to the contrary in the chit agreement.
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>41</number> Copy of assent or 
consent to be filed with Registrar.—A 
true copy of every assent referred to in section 26 and of every consent 
referred to in clause (b) of section 40 with their dates shall be filed by the 
foreman or by the surviving partner or partners, as the case may be, with the 
Registrar within fourteen days from the date of such assent or consent. 

</article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>42</number> Refund of non-prized 
subscribers’s subscriptions.—Except 
in the cases referred to in clauses 
<section><number>a</number> and (b) of section 40,—
 </section><section>
   <number>a</number>  every non-prized subscriber shall, 
unless otherwise provided for in this Act or in the chit agreement, be entitled 
to get back his subscriptions at the termination of the chit without any 
deduction for dividend, if any, earned by him: 
 
              Provided that, any person to 
whom the rights of a non-prized subscriber are transferred in accordance with 
the provisions of section 35, shall, in addition to his own subscriptions, be 
entitled to get back the subscriptions paid by such non-prized subscriber, 
subject to the conditions specified in this section;
 </section><section>
   <number>b</number>  if a chit terminates on a date 
earlier than the date originally fixed in the chit agreement, the non-prized 
subscriber’s claim shall be deemed to have arisen on the date on which he has 
notice thereof. 
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>43</number> Subscribers’ dues to 
be first charge on chit assets.—Any 
amount due to the subscriber from a foreman in relation to the chit business 
shall be a first charge on the chit assets. 
</article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>44</number> Foreman to allow 
certain subscribers to inspect chit records.—Every 
foreman shall, on payment of such fee not exceeding five rupees as may be 
specified in the chit agreement, allow the non-prized subscribers and unpaid 
prized subscribers reasonable facilities on all the dates of draw or on such 
other dates and within such hours as may be provided for in the chit agreement, 
for the inspection of security bonds and documents, receipts and other records 
taken from the prized subscribers, or furnished by the foreman as a subscriber 
and all chit records, including books of accounts, pass-books, balance-sheet 
and profit and loss accounts and such other records as may show the actual 
financial position of the chit. 
</article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>45</number> Preservation of chit 
records by foreman.—All 
the records pertaining to a chit shall be kept by the foreman for a period of 
eight years from the date of termination of the chit.
</article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>46</number> Inspection of chit 
books and records by Registrar.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Without prejudice to the provisions of sections 209 and 209A of the Companies 
Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), the Registrar or an officer authorised by the State 
Government in this behalf may inspect chit books and all the records of a chit 
during working hours on any working day at the premises of the foreman with or 
without giving notice and it shall be the duty of every foreman to produce to 
the Registrar or the officer so authorised, all such books and records as are 
in his custody or power and to furnish him with any statement or information 
relating to the chits as he may require from the foreman within such time as he 
may specify.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Registrar or an 
officer authorised by the State Government in this behalf may, after giving 
seven days’ notice in writing to the foreman, direct him to produce before him 
for inspection such chit books and records as he may require at the time and 
place mentioned in the notice. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If on an inspection 
made under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2), any defects are found, the 
Registrar may bring such defects to the notice of the foreman and may also make 
an order directing the foreman to take such action as may be specified in the 
order to remedy the defects within the time specified therein. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every foreman shall 
be bound to comply with the directions contained in an order made under 
sub-section (3). 
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>47</number> Power of Reserve Bank 
to inspect chit books and records.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Nothing in section 46 shall be deemed to affect the power of the Reserve Bank 
to inspect the books and records of any foreman under the provisions of section 
45N of the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934). 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Reserve Bank may, 
if it considers necessary, forward a copy of its report or of any part of its 
report on the inspection of the books and records of a foreman to the foreman 
for taking necessary action.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every foreman shall, 
on receipt of the report or part thereof under sub-section (2), be bound to 
comply with the directions, if any, given by the Reserve Bank in this behalf 
and shall, if so required, submit periodical reports in regard to the action 
taken by him. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Reserve Bank may 
also forward a copy of the report on the inspection of the books and records of 
a foreman to the State Government within whose jurisdiction the registered 
office of the company, if the foreman is a company, or the place or the 
principal place of business of the foreman in any other case, is situated for 
such action as may be considered necessary.
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>48</number> Circumstances under 
which chits may be wound up.—A 
chit may be wound up by the Registrar within whose territorial jurisdiction the 
chit has been registered, either on his own motion or on an application made by 
any non-prized or unpaid-prized subscriber,—
 <section>
   <number>a</number>  if the chit has terminated under 
clause (c) of section 40; or
 </section><section>
   <number>b</number>  if the foreman commits any such act 
in respect of the security specified in section 20 as is calculated to impair 
materially the nature of the security or the value thereof; or 
 </section><section>
   <number>c</number>  if he fails to deposit any amount 
required to be deposited under any of the provisions of this Act; or 

 </section><section>
   <number>d</number>  if it is proved to the satisfaction 
of the Registrar that the foreman is unable to pay the amounts due to the 
subscribers; or 
 </section><section>
   <number>e</number>  if the execution or other process 
issued on an order passed by the Registrar in favour of any subscriber in 
respect of amounts due to him from the foreman in relation to the chit business 
is returned unsatisfied in whole or in part; or 
 </section><section>
    <number>f</number>  if it is proved that there has been 
a fraud or collusion on the part of the foreman in the matter of taking 
securities from any prized subscriber; or 
 </section><section>
   <number>g</number>  if the foreman has appropriated the 
prize amount in his capacity as a subscriber without furnishing sufficient 
security for future subscriptions; or 
 </section><section>
   <number>h</number>  if the Registrar is satisfied that 
the affairs of the chit are being conducted in a manner prejudicial to the 
interests of the subscribers; or 
 </section><section>
    <number>i</number>  if it is just and equitable that 
the chit should be wound up. 
 
Explanation.—For 
the purpose of clause (d), in determining whether the foreman is unable to pay 
the amount due to the subscribers, the Registrar shall,   take into account his 
contingent and future liabilities in respect of the chit. 
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>49</number> Application for 
winding up.—An 
application for the winding up of a chit shall be made by a petition presented 
by any non-prized or unpaid prized subscriber to the Registrar signed and 
verified in the manner laid down by the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 
1908), and shall contain such particulars as may be prescribed: 
 
Provided that no 
application for the winding-up of a chit under clause (d) or clause 
<section><number>i</number> of 
section 48 shall lie unless such application is presented,— 
 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>  by non-prized and unpaid prized 
subscribers representing not less than twenty-five per cent. of the amount or, 
as the case may be, the value of the grain subscribed by all the non-prized and 
unpaid prized subscribers, if any; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>  with the previous sanction of the 
State Government within whose jurisdiction the chit is commenced or conducted.

 
Explanation.—For 
the purposes of clause (a) of the proviso, a subscriber of a fraction of a 
ticket shall be deemed to be a subscriber only to the extent of such fraction.

</subsection></section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>50</number> Bar to winding up 
proceedings.—Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sections 48 and 49, no petition for the winding up of a 
chit shall be entertained by the Registrar,—
 <section>
   <number>a</number>  if proceedings relating to 
insolvency are pending against the foreman; or 
 </section><section>
   <number>b</number>  where the foreman is a firm, if 
proceedings relating to insolvency are pending against all the partners or all 
the partners except one thereof, or proceedings for the dissolution of the firm 
are pending; or 
 </section><section>
   <number>c</number>  where the foreman is a company or 
co-operative society, if proceedings for the winding-up of such company or 
co-operative society are pending. 
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>51</number> Commencement and 
effect of winding up order.—An 
order for the winding-up of a chit shall operate in favour of all the 
subscribers to whom amounts are due from the foreman and it shall be deemed to 
have commenced from the date of the presentation of the application for the 
winding up. 
</article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>52</number> Injunction order.—The 
Registrar may, on the application of the foreman or of any subscriber to whom 
amounts are due in respect of a chit, at any time after the presentation of the 
application for the winding up of the chit under this Act and before the making 
of an order for the appointment of an interim receiver or for the winding up of 
the chit, restrain any other proceedings instituted against the foreman for the 
realisation of amounts due from him on such terms as the Registrar thinks fit.

</article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>53</number> Powers of Registrar.—The 
Registrar may, after hearing an application under this Chapter, dismiss it with 
or without costs, or adjourn the hearing conditionally or unconditionally or 
make an interim or any other order that he deems fit. 
</article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>54</number> Vesting of chit 
assets in Registrar or other person.—On 
the making of an order for the winding up of a chit, all the chit assets 
pertaining to such chit shall vest in the Registrar or in any person appointed 
by him for distribution amongst the subscribers to whom amounts are due in 
respect of the chit. 
</article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>55</number> Suits, etc., to be 
stayed on winding up order.—When 
a winding up order has been made or a receiver has been appointed, no suit or 
other legal proceedings shall be continued or commenced against the foreman by 
a subscriber for the realisation of amounts due to him in respect of the chit 
except with the leave of the Registrar winding up the chit and on such terms as 
he may impose. 
</article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>56</number> Notification of 
winding up order.—On 
the making of a winding up order, the Registrar shall make an entry in his book 
relating to the chit and shall notify in the official Gazette that the order 
has been made. 
</article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>57</number> Cessation of winding 
up proceedings on insolvency of foreman, etc., or the winding up of the company 
and transfer of such proceedings.—Where 
during the pendency of the proceedings for the winding up of a chit, the 
foreman is adjudicated an insolvent, or where the foreman is a firm, all the 
partners or all the partners except one thereof are adjudicated insolvents, or 
where the foreman is a company, the company has been ordered to be wound up by 
the court, the winding-up proceeding under this Chapter shall cease and the 
distribution of the chit assets shall, subject to the provisions of sections 43 
and 52, be made by the insolvency court or the court winding up the company, as 
the case may be. 
</article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>58</number> Award of compensation 
to foreman.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where an application for the winding-up of a chit is dismissed and the 
Registrar is satisfied that the petition is frivolous or vexatious, he may, on 
the application of the foreman, award against the petitioner such amount, not 
exceeding one thousand rupees, as he deems reasonable as compensation to the 
foreman for the expenses or injury caused to him by the presentation of the 
application and the proceedings thereon, and such amount may be realised as if 
the award were a decree of a civil court. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On the making of an 
award under sub-section (1), no suit for compensation in respect of an 
application for any winding-up of the chit shall be entertained. 
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>59</number> Right to appeal.—The 
foreman or any subscriber or any other person aggrieved by a decision or order 
of the Registrar in any proceedings for the winding up of a chit may, within 
sixty days from the date of such decision or order, appeal to the State 
Government. 
</article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>60</number> Limitation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where an order refusing to wind up a chit has been made under this Act, the 
chit shall be deemed to have been under suspension from the date of 
presentation of the application to the date of such order in respect of 
non-prized subscribers; and, notwithstanding anything contained in the chit 
agreement, no non-prized subscriber who was not a defaulter on the date of the 
presentation of the petition for winding-up, shall be deemed to be a defaulter 
on the date of such order. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where an order 
refusing to wind up a chit has been made under this Act, in computing a period 
of limitation prescribed for any suit or other legal proceedings (other than a 
suit or application in respect of which the leave of the Court has been 
obtained) which might have been brought or instituted, but for the presentation 
of the application for the winding-up of the chit, the period from the date of 
the presentation of the application to the date of the order refusing to wind 
up a chit shall be excluded. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Nothing contained in 
this Chapter shall affect the rights of a subscriber to proceed against the 
foreman personally for the balance, if any, of the amount due to him after the 
declaration of the final dividend in the proceedings for the winding up of the 
chit and in computing the period of limitation prescribed for any such 
proceedings, the period from the date of the presentation of the application 
for the winding-up of the chit to the date of the declaration of the final 
dividend shall be excluded. 
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>61</number> Appointment of 
Registrar and other officers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint a 
Registrar of Chits and as many Additional, Joint, Deputy and Assistant 
Registrars as may be necessary for the purpose of discharging the duties 
imposed upon the Registrar by or under this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Registrar may 
appoint as many inspectors of chits and chit auditors as may be necessary for 
the purpose of discharging the duties imposed on the inspectors of chits or 
chit auditors by or under this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All inspectors of 
chits and chit auditors shall discharge the duties imposed upon them by or 
under this Act under the general superintendence and control of the Registrar.

 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If the Registrar is 
of opinion that the accounts of any chit are not properly maintained and that 
such accounts should be audited, it shall be lawful for him to have such 
accounts audited by a chit auditor. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> It shall be the duty 
of the foreman of the chit whose accounts are to be audited by a chit auditor 
under sub-section (4) to produce before the chit auditor, all accounts, books 
and other records relating to the chit, to furnish him with such information as 
may be required and afford him all such assistance and facilities as may be 
necessary and reasonable in regard to the audit of the accounts of the chit.

 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The foreman shall pay 
to the chit auditor such fees as may be prescribed for the audit of accounts of 
the chit under sub-section (4); 
 
Provided that different 
scales of fees may be prescribed for different chits depending on the quantum 
of the chit amount. 
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>62</number> Inspection of 
documents in Registrar’s Office.—The 
foreman of a chit or any subscriber in a chit or the heirs or legal 
representatives of any foreman or subscriber may, on payment of such fees as 
may be prescribed,— 
 <section>
   <number>a</number>  inspect the documents of the 
concerned chit kept by the Registrar; or 
 </section><section>
   <number>b</number>  obtain a certified copy or an 
extract of any such document on record. 
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>63</number> Levy of fees.—
<section><number>1</number> 
There shall be paid to the Registrar such fees as the State Government may, 
from time to time, prescribe for,—
 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>  the issue of previous sanction under 
section 4; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>  the filing of the chit agreement 
with the Registrar and the registration of the chit under section 7; 

 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>c</number>  the filing of a declaration with the 
Registrar and the grant of a certificate of commencement under section 9;

 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>d</number>  the filing of copies of documents 
under any of the provisions of this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>e</number>  the audit of the accounts of the 
foreman under section 61; 
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>f</number>  the inspection of documents under 
section 62; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>g</number>  the obtaining of certified copies or 
extracts of documents and records under section 62; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>h</number>  such other matters as may appear 
necessary to the State Government. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A table of fees 
prescribed under sub-section (1) shall be exhibited on a notice-board in the 
office of the Registrar. 
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>64</number> Disputes relating to 
chit business.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being in 
force, any dispute touching the management of chit business shall be referred 
by any of the parties to the dispute, to the Registrar for arbitration if each 
party thereto is one or the other of the following, namely:—
 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>  a foreman, a prized subscriber or a 
non-prized subscriber, including a defaulting subscriber, past subscriber or a 
person claiming through a subscriber, or a deceased subscriber to a chit;

 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>  a surety of a subscriber, past 
subscriber, or a deceased subscriber. 
 
Explanation—For 
the purposes of this sub-section, a dispute touching the management of a chit 
business shall include,—
 <subsubsection>
    <number>i</number>  a claim by or against a foreman for 
any debt or demand due to him from a subscriber, or due from him to a 
subscriber, past subscriber or the nominee, heir or legal representative of a 
deceased subscriber whether such debt or demand is admitted or not; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>ii</number>  a claim by a surety for any sum or 
demand due to him from the principal borrower in respect of a loan by a foreman 
and recovered from the surety owing to the default of the principal borrower, 
whether such sum or demand is admitted or not; and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>iii</number>  a refusal or failure by a 
subscriber, past subscriber or the nominee, heir or legal representative of a 
deceased subscriber to deliver possession to a foreman of land or any other 
asset resumed by him for breach of conditions of the assignment. 
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any question 
arises as to whether any matter referred to for the award of the Registrar is a 
dispute or not for the purposes of sub-section (1), the same shall be decided 
by the Registrar whose decision thereon shall be final. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No civil court shall 
have jurisdiction to entertain any suit or other proceedings in respect of any 
dispute referred to in sub-section (1). 


</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>65</number> Period of limitation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in the Limitation Act, 1963 (36 of 1963), 
but subject to the specific provisions contained in this Act, the period of 
limitation in the case of a dispute referred to the Registrar under section 64, 
shall— 
 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>  if the dispute relates to the 
recovery of any sum, including interest thereon, due to a foreman from a 
deceased subscriber, be three years, computed from the date on which such 
subscriber dies or ceases to be a subscriber; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>  if the dispute is between a foreman 
and a subscriber or a past subscriber, or the nominee, heir or legal 
representative of a deceased subscriber, and the dispute relates to any act or 
omission on the part of either party to the dispute, be three years from the 
date on which the act or omission with reference to which the dispute arose, 
took place. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The period of 
limitation in the case of any dispute other than those referred to in 
sub-section (1) which are required to be referred to the Registrar under 
section 64 shall be regulated by the provisions of the Limitation Act, 1963 (36 
of 1963), as if the dispute were a suit, and the Registrar, a civil court.

 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-sections (1) and (2), the Registrar may admit a 
dispute after the expiry of the period of limitation specified therein, if the 
applicant satisfies the Registrar that he had sufficient cause for not 
referring the dispute within such period. 
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>66</number> Settlement of 
disputes.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If the Registrar is satisfied that any matter referred to him or brought to his 
notice is a dispute within the meaning of section 64, he shall, subject to such 
rules as may be prescribed, settle the dispute himself, or refer it for 
disposal to a person appointed by him (hereinafter in this Chapter referred to 
as the nominee). 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any dispute is 
referred under sub-section (1) for settlement of the nominee, the Registrar 
may, at any time for reasons to be recorded in writing, withdraw such dispute 
from the nominee and may settle the dispute himself, or refer it again for 
settlement to any other nominee appointed by him. 
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>67</number> Procedure for 
settlement of disputes and powers of Registrar or nominee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Registrar or the nominee hearing a dispute under section 66, shall, in 
addition to the powers conferred on him under that section, have the same 
powers as are vested in a civil court while trying a suit under the Code of 
Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), in respect of the following matters, 
namely:— 
 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>  summoning and enforcing the 
attendance of persons and examining them on oath; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>  requiring the discovery and 
inspection of documents; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>c</number>  receiving evidence on affidavits;

 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>d</number>  requisitioning any public record or 
copies thereof from any court or office; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>e</number>  issuing commissions for the 
examination of witnesses or documents; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>f</number>  any other matter which may be 
prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Except with the 
permission of the Registrar or the nominee, no party shall be represented at 
the hearing of a dispute by a legal practitioner. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> (a) If the Registrar 
or the nominee is satisfied that any person, whether he is a subscriber or not 
has acquired any interest in the property of a person who is a party to a 
dispute, he may order that the person who has acquired the interest in the 
property may be joined as a party to the dispute and any decision that may be 
given by the Registrar or the nominee on the dispute shall be binding on the 
party so joined, in the same manner as if he were an original party to the 
dispute. 
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> Where a dispute has 
been referred in the name of a wrong person, or where all the necessary parties 
have not been included, the Registrar or the nominee may, if he is satisfied 
that it was due to a genuine mistake, order any other person to be substituted 
or added as parties to the dispute at any stage of hearing of the dispute on 
such terms as he thinks just. 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> The Registrar or the 
nominee may, at any stage of the proceedings, either upon or without the 
application of either party and on such terms as may appear to the Registrar or 
the nominee to be just, order that the name of any party improperly joined be 
struck off. 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> Any person who is a 
party to the dispute and entitled to more than one relief in respect of the 
same cause of action may claim all or any such reliefs, but if he omits to 
claim any such relief, he shall not be entitled to claim that relief, except 
with the leave of the Registrar or the nominee. 
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>68</number> Attachment before 
judgment and other interlocutory orders.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where a dispute has been referred under section 64 and the Registrar or the 
nominee hearing the dispute is satisfied on enquiry or otherwise that a party 
to such dispute, with intent to defeat or obstruct the execution of any award 
or the carrying out of any order that may be made,— 
 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>  is about to dispose of the whole or 
any part of his property; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>  is about to remove the whole or any 
part of the property from the jurisdiction of the Registrar, 
 
he may, unless adequate 
security is furnished, direct conditional attachment of the said property, and 
such attachment shall have the same effect as if it is made by competent civil 
court. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the Registrar 
or the nominee directs the attachment of any property under sub-section (1), he 
shall issue a notice calling upon the person whose property is so attached to 
furnish such security as he thinks adequate within a specified period, and if 
the person fails to provide such security, the Registrar or the nominee may 
confirm the order, and may, after the decision in the dispute, direct the 
disposal of the property so attached towards the claim, if awarded. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any attachment made 
under this section shall not affect the rights, subsisting prior to the 
attachment of the property, of persons who are not parties to the dispute, or 
bar any person holding a decree against the person whose property is so 
attached from applying for the sale of the property under the attachment of 
such decree. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Registrar or the 
nominee may, in order to prevent the ends of justice being defeated, make such 
interlocutory order pending the award in a dispute referred to in sub-section 
(1) as may appear to be just and convenient. 
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>69</number> Decision of Registrar 
or nominee.—When 
a dispute is referred to arbitration under this Chapter, the Registrar or the 
nominee, may, after giving a reasonable opportunity to the parties to the 
dispute to be heard, make an award on the dispute, on the expenses incurred by 
the parties to the dispute in connection with the proceedings and the fees and 
expenses payable to the Registrar or the nominee, and such an award shall not 
be invalid merely on the ground that it was made after the expiry of the 
period, if any, fixed for deciding the dispute by the Registrar, and shall, 
subject to appeal under section 70, be final and binding on the parties to the 
dispute. 
</article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>70</number> Appeal against 
decision of Registrar or nominee.—Any 
party aggrieved by any order passed by the Registrar or the nominee or the 
award of the Registrar or the nominee under section 69, may, within two months 
from the date of the order or award, appeal to the State Government. 

</article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>71</number> Money how recovered.—Every 
order passed by the Registrar or the nominee under section 68 or section 69 and 
every order passed by the State Government in appeal under section 70 for 
payment of any money shall, if not carried out, — 
 <section>
   <number>a</number>  on a certificate issued by the 
Registrar, be deemed to be a decree of a civil court, and shall be executed in 
the same manner as a decree of such court, or 
 </section><section>
   <number>b</number>  be executed in accordance with the 
provisions of any law for the time being in force for the recovery of amounts 
as arrears of land revenue: 
 
Provided that no application for execution 
under clause (b) shall be made after the expiry of three years from the date 
fixed in the order, and if no such date is fixed, from the date of the order.

</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>72</number> Private transfer of 
property made after issue of certificate void against foreman.—Any 
private transfer or delivery of, or encumbrance or charge on property made or 
created after the issue of the certificate by the Registrar under section 71 
shall be null and void against the foreman on whose application the said 
certificate was issued. 
</article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>73</number> Advisory role of 
Reserve Bank.—The 
Reserve Bank may tender to any State Government such advice on questions of 
policy with respect to this Act as it thinks fit either on its own motion or on 
a request made by the State Government. 
</article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>74</number> Appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any foreman aggrieved by the decision of the Registrar, —
 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>  refusing to register the chit 
agreement under section 7; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>  refusing to grant a certificate of 
commencement under sub-section (2) of section 9; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>c</number>  refusing to accept any security 
under sub-section (1) of section 20 or under section 31; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>d</number>  refusing to release the security 
charged under section 20 or section 31; 
 
may, within thirty days 
of the communication to him of such decision, appeal to the State Government or 
to such officer or authority as may be empowered by notification in the 
Official Gazette by the State Government in that behalf. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Any foreman or other 
person aggrieved by the order of the Registrar under sub-section (1) of section 
34 may, within thirty days of the communication to him of such decision, appeal 
to the State Government or to such officer or authority as may be empowered by 
notification in the Official Gazette by the State Government in that behalf.

 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The State Government 
or such officer or authority aforesaid may, after giving the appellant an 
opportunity of making his representation, pass such order on the appeal as it 
or he thinks fit and such order shall be final. 
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>75</number> Powers of Registrar 
to give extension of time for filing documents.—The 
Registrar may, in his discretion and upon an application in writing by a 
foreman made within the period specified for the filing of documents, under 
sub-section (3) of section 28, sub-section (2) of section 29, section 37 or 
section 41, allow the foreman further time not exceeding fifteen days to file 
copies of such documents. 
</article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>76</number> Penalties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Whoever contravenes or abets the contravention of any of the provisions of 
sections 4, 5, 8, 9, 11, 12, 13, 14, 19, 20, 22, 24, 30, 31, sub-section (4) of 
section 33, sections 46, 47 or sub-section (5) of section 61 shall, on 
conviction, be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to two 
years, or with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees, or with both.

 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any foreman, — 

 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>  who fails to file any document 
required to be filed under this Act within the period specified therefor or 
within such further time as may be allowed; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>  who fails to comply with the 
requirements of the chit agreement regarding the date, time and place at which 
the chit is to be drawn or who fails to comply with the requirements of any 
direction given under sub-section (3) of section 38; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>c</number>  who contravenes or fails to comply 
with any other requirement under this Act, 
 
shall, on conviction, be 
punishable with fine which may extend to three thousand rupees. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Whoever wilfully 
makes a statement in any document required to be filed under this Act which is 
false in any material particular shall, on conviction, be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years or with fine which may 
extend to five thousand rupees or with both. 
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>77</number> Penalty for second 
and subsequent convictions.—If 
any person convicted of an offence under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> or sub-section (3) of 
section 76 is again convicted of an offence under any of the said sub-sections 
he shall be punishable for the second and for every subsequent offence with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years and shall also be liable 
to fine. 
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>78</number> Application of fine.—A 
court imposing any fine under this Act may direct that the whole or any part 
thereof shall be applied in, or towards payment of, the cost of the 
proceedings. 
</article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>79</number> Offences by 
companies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where an offence under this Act has been committed by a company, every person 
who, at the time the offence was committed was in charge of, and was 
responsible to, the company, for the conduct of the business of the company, as 
well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be 
liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly: 
 
Provided that nothing 
contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to any 
punishment provided in this Act, if he proves that the offence was committed 
without his knowledge or that he exercised all due diligence to prevent the 
commission of such offence. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence under this Act has been 
committed by a company and it is proved that the offence has been committed 
with the consent or connivance of, or is attributable to, any neglect on the 
part of, any director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such 
director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to be guilty 
of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished 
accordingly. 
 
Explanation—For 
the purposes of this section,—
 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>  “company” means any body corporate 
and includes a firm or other association of individuals; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>  “director” in relation to a firm 
means a partner in the firm. 


</subsection></section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>80</number> Cognizance of 
offences.—
<section><number>1</number> 
All offences under section 11 shall be cognizable. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No court inferior to 
that of a Metropolitan Magistrate or a Judicial Magistrate of the first class 
shall try an offence punishable under this Act. 
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>81</number> Power to compound 
offences.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to such conditions as may be prescribed, any officer empowered by the 
State Government in this behalf may, either before or after the institution of 
criminal proceedings under this Act, accept from the person who has committed 
or is reasonably suspected to have committed an offence under this Act, by way 
of composition of such offence, a sum of money not exceeding such amount as may 
be prescribed. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where an offence has 
been compounded under sub-section (1), the offender, if in custody, shall be 
discharged and no further proceedings shall be taken against him in respect of 
such offence. 
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>82</number> Power to enter and 
search any place and to seize any documents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If the Registrar or any other officer authorised by him in this behalf has 
reason to suspect that any person conducts, or is responsible for the conduct 
of a chit in any place in contravention of the provisions of this Act, he may, 
for reasons to be recorded in writing and at any reasonable time, enter into 
and search such place, and may seize such books, registers, accounts, or 
documents as may be necessary. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Registrar or 
officer authorised by him in this behalf, may apply for assistance to an 
officer in charge of a police station and take police officers to accompany and 
assist him in discharging his duties under sub-section (1). 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All searches under 
sub-section (1) shall be made in accordance with the provisions of the Code of 
Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974). 
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>83</number> Officers to be public 
servants.—The 
Registrar and all officers appointed by the State Government to perform any 
function under this Act shall be deemed to be public servants within the 
meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860). 
</article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>84</number> Power to delegate.—The 
State Government may, by notification in the official Gazette, direct that any 
power (other than the power to hear appeals or to make rules) exercisable by it 
under this Act or the rules made thereunder may be exercised also by any 
officer of the State Government subject to such terms and conditions, if any, 
as may be specified therein. 
</article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>85</number> Act not to apply to 
certain chits.—Nothing 
in this Act shall apply in respect of—
 <section>
   <number>a</number>  any chit started before the 
commencement of this Act; or 
 </section><section>
   <number>b</number>  any chit the amount of which, or 
where two or more chits were started or conducted simultaneously by the same 
foreman, the aggregate amount of which does not exceed one hundred rupees.

</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>86</number> Banks not to conduct 
chit business.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, no bank shall commence or carry 
on chit business after the commencement of this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where a chit had been 
started by any bank before such commencement, such chit may be continued after 
such commencement until it is completed, and the provisions of the chit 
agreement and such laws, if any, as were applicable to it immediately before 
the commencement of this Act shall apply to such chit. 
 
Explanation—For 
the purposes of this section “bank” means an approved bank or a co-operative 
bank as defined in clause (bii) of section 2 of the Reserve Bank of India Act, 
1934 (2 of 1934). 
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>87</number> Power to exempt.—The 
State Government may, in consultation with the Reserve Bank, by notification in 
the Official Gazette, and subject to such conditions as may be specified in the 
notification, exempt any person or class of persons or any chit or class of 
chits from all or any of the provisions of this Act. 
</article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>88</number> Protection of action 
taken under the Act.—No 
suit, prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against the State 
Government, the Registrar or other officers of the State Government or of the 
Reserve Bank or any of its officers exercising any powers or discharging any 
functions under this Act in respect of anything which is in good faith done or 
intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or the rules made thereunder.

</article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>89</number> Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The State Government may, in consultation with the Reserve Bank, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for giving effect to the 
provisions of this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular, and 
without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may 
provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:— 
 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>  the form and manner in which an 
application for obtaining the previous sanction may be made under sub-section 
(2) of section 4; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>  the additional particulars that a 
chit agreement may contain under clause (q) of sub-section (1) of section 6;

 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>c</number>  the particulars that may be included 
in the minutes of the proceedings of a draw under section 17; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>d</number>  the method of valuation by the 
Registrar in a grain chit for the purpose of furnishing security under section 
20; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>e</number>  the procedure that may be followed 
by the Registrar in releasing the security furnished by the foreman under 
section 20; 
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>f</number>  the registers and books and the 
form in which such registers and books may be maintained by the foreman under 
section 23; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>g</number>  the time within which the 
balance-sheet and the profit and loss account in respect of a chit business 
shall be filed under section 24; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>h</number>  the rate at which interest shall be 
payable on the defaulted instalments by a defaulted subscriber under section 
28; 
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>i</number>  the particulars that may be 
included in an application for the winding up of chits under section 49; 

 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>j</number>  the procedure to be followed for 
the winding up of chits under Chapter X; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>k</number>  the fees payable under section 63;

 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>l</number>  the auditing of balance-sheet and 
the profit and loss accounts of chit business and the issue of audit 
certificates; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>m</number>  the form and manner in which a 
dispute shall be referred to the Registrar under section 64; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>n</number>  the procedure to be followed by the 
Registrar or his nominee for settling the disputes referred to him under 
section 64; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>o</number>  the matters referred to in clause 
(f) of sub-section (1) of section 67; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>p</number>  the conditions subject to which and 
the amount on the payment of which composition of offences may be made under 
section 81; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>q</number>  the form and manner in which an 
appeal may be preferred under this Act and the fees payable for such appeal;

 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>r</number>  the issue and service of notices or 
other process under this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>s</number>  the procedure for, and the manner 
of, receiving any sum payable under this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>t</number>  any other matter which is required 
to be or may be prescribed. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Every rule made under 
this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each 
House of the State Legislature where it consists of two Houses, or, where such 
Legislature consists of one House, before the House. 
</section></article> 
 
The chit funds act, 1982
 
 
 <article>
<number>90</number> Repeal and saving.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Andhra Pradesh Chit Funds Act, 1971 (Andhra Pradesh Act 9 of 1971), the 
Kerala Chitties Act, 1975 (Kerala Act 23 of 1975), the Maharashtra Chit Funds 
Act, 1974 (Maharashtra Act LV of 1974), the Tamil Nadu Chit Funds Act, 1961 
(Tamil Nadu Act 24 of 1961), as in force in the State of Tamil Nadu and in the 
Union territories of Chandigarh and Delhi, the Uttar Pradesh Chit Funds Act, 
1975 (Uttar Pradesh Act 53 of 1975), the Goa, Daman and Diu Chit Funds Act, 
1973 (Goa, Daman and Diu Act 16 of 1973), and the Pondicherry Chit Funds Act, 
1966 (Pondicherry Act 18 of 1966), are hereby repealed and the provisions of 
section 6 of the General Clauses Act, 1897 (10 of 1897), shall apply to such 
repeal as if each such Act so repealed were a Central Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding such 
repeal, the Acts mentioned in sub-section (1) shall continue to apply to chits 
in operation on the commencement of this Act, in the same manner as they 
applied to such chits before such commencement. 
 
 
</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>