<act><title>


THE PLASTICS MANUFACTURE, SALE AND USAGE RULES, 19991</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—2[
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Plastics Manufacture, Sale and Usage Rules, 1999.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>2</number> 
Application.—The 
provisions of rules 4 and 8 shall not apply to the manufacture of carry bags 
exclusively for export purpose, against an order for export received by the 
owner or occupier of the concerned manufacturing unit.]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>3</number> 
Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
    <number>a</number> “Act” means the 
Environment (Protection) Act, 1986 (29 of 1986);
 </section><section>
    <number>b</number> “carry bags” means 
plastic bags which have a self carrying feature commonly known as vest type bags 
or any other feature used to carry commodities such as “D” punched bags; as 
illustrated in the Annexure to these rules;
 </section><section>
    <number>c</number> “commodities” 
includes articles such as vegetables, fruits, pharmaceuticals and the like;
 </section><section>
    <number>d</number> “container” means 
flexible or rigid containers made of virgin plastics or recycled plastics with 
or without lid used to store, carry or dispense commodities;
 </section><section>
    <number>e</number> “food-stuffs” 
means ready to eat food articles and food products, fast food, processed or 
cooked food in liquid, powder, solid or semi-solid form;
 </section><section>
     <number>f</number> “registration” 
means registration of units manufacturing carry-bags and containers made of 
virgin or recycled plastics with the concerned State Pollution Control Board or 
Pollution Control Committee as the case may be;
 </section><section>
    <number>g</number> 
“vendor” means a person who sells food stuffs packed or stored in plastic carry 
bags or containers.]
 
  
 </section></article><article>
<number>3</number> Prescribed 
Authority.—
<section><number>a</number> 
The prescribed authority for enforcement of the provisions of these rules 
related to manufacture and recycling shall be the State Pollution Control Boards 
in respect of States and the Pollution Control Committees in respect of Union 
Territories.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> The prescribed 
authority for enforcement of the provisions of these rules related to the use, 
collection, segregation, transportation and disposal shall be the District 
Collector/Deputy Commissioner of the concerned district where no such Authority 
has been constituted by the State Government/Union Territory administration 
under any law regarding non-biodegradable garbage.
 
 




</section></article> 

  
 <article>1[<number>4</number> Restriction on manufacture, 
sale, distribution and use of virgin and recycled plastic carry bags and 
recycled plastic containers.—
<section><number>1</number> No person shall manufacture, 
stock, distribute or sell carry bags made of virgin or recycled plastic bags 
which are less than 8 x 12 inches (20 x 30 cms) in size and which do not conform 
to the minimum thickness specified in rule 8.
 </section><section><number>2</number> No vendor shall use carry bags 
made of recycled plastic for storing, carrying, dispensing or packaging of 
foodstuffs.
 </section><section><number>3</number> No vendor shall use containers 
made of recycled plastics for storing, carrying, dispensing or packaging of 
foodstuffs.
 Explanation.—For the purposes of this rule, 
the minimum weight of 50 carry bags made of virgin or recycled plastics shall be 
105 gms. plus or minus 5% variation and the carry bags of larger sizes shall be 
of proportionate increase in weight.]
  


</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>5</number> Conditions of manufacture of 
carry bags and containers made of plastics.—subject to the provisions of rule 
4, any person may manufacture carry bags or containers made of plastics if the 
following conditions are satisfied, namely:—
 <section>    <number>a</number> Carry bags 
and containers made of virgin plastic shall be in natural shade or 
white;
 </section><section>    <number>b</number> Carry bags 
and containers made of recycled plastic and used for purpose other than storing 
and packaging foodstuffs shall be manufactured using pigments and colourants as 
per IS:9833:1981 entitled “List of pigments and colourants for use in plastics 
in contact with foodstuffs, pharmaceuticals and drinking 
water”.</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Recycling.—Recycling 
of plastics shall be undertaken strictly in accordance with the Bureau of Indian 
Standards specification: IS:14534:1998 entitled “The Guidelines for Recycling of 
Plastics”.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
Marking/codification.—1[Subject 
to the provisions of rules 4 and 5 manufacturers of] recycled plastic carry bags 
having printing facilities shall code/mark carry bags and containers as per 
Bureau of India Standard Specification: IS: 14534:1998 entitled  “The Guidelines 
for Recycling of Plastics” and the end product made out of recycled plastics 
shall be marked as “recycled” along with the indication of the percentage of use 
of recycled material. Other manufactures, who do not have printing facilities, 
shall comply with the condition within one year of publication of these rules. 
Manufacturers shall print on each packet of carry bags as to whether these are 
made of “recycled material” or of “virgin plastic”.
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Thickness of carry 
bags.—The 
minimum thickness of carry bags made of virgin plastics or recycled plastics 
shall not be less than 20 microns.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Self regulation by 
certain persons.—Without 
prejudice to the provisions contained in rule 3, the Plastics Industry 
Association, through their member units, shall undertake self-regulatory 
measures.
</article> 

  
 <article>1[<number>10</number> Grant of registration for 
manufactures.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every occupier manufacturing carry bags or containers of virgin plastic or 
recycled plastic or both shall make an application in Form 1 appended to these 
rules to the State Pollution Control Board or Pollution Control Committee of the 
union territory concerned for grant of registration or renewal of registration 
for his unit within four months from the date of publication of the Recycled 
Plastics Manufacture and Usage (Amendments) Rules, 2003 in the Official 
Gazette.
 </section><section><number>2</number> On or after the commencement 
of the Recycled Plastics Manufacture and Usage (Amendment) Rules, 2003, no 
person shall manufacture carry bags or containers irrespective of its size or 
weight unless the occupier of the unit has registered the unit with the State 
Pollution Control Board/Pollution Control Committee prior to the commencement of 
production.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The State Pollution Control 
Board or Pollution Control Committee shall not issue and renew a registration 
certificate of a unit unless that unit meets the norms prescribed under rules 5, 
6, 7 and 8 of these rules and also possess a valid consent under the Water 
(Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1974 (6 of 1974) and the Air 
(Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1981 (14 of 1981) as per the 
requirements laid down by the State Pollution Control Board or Pollution Control 
Committee.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Every State Pollution Control 
Board or State Pollution Control Committee shall grant registration within 
thirty days of receipt of application complete in all respects.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The registration granted under 
this rule shall, unless revoked, suspended or cancelled earlier, be valid for a 
period of three years.
 </section><section><number>6</number> Every application for renewal 
of registration shall be made in the Form 1 appended to these rules at least 
sixty days before the expiry of the validity of registration.]
  



</section></article><form>
 

The 
Plastics Manufacture, Sale 
and Usage Rules, 1999
 

 
 

Form 
II
 

[See rule 
10 (3)]
 

Certificate 
of registration for the manufacture of  
plastic carry bags and 
containers
 

                                                                                                              
File No. ...................................
 

                                                                                                              
Dated......................................
 

To
 

...................................
 

...................................
 

...................................
 

Ref: Your 
application No. ..............dated ...................seeking registration for 
manufacturing of carry bags and containers.
 

The 
...................................State Pollution Control Board or Pollution 
Control Committee after examining the application, hereby certifies 
that................................... (Name and Address of the Unit) has been 
registered as a unit manufacturing...................................
 

This certificate of registration 
shall be valid for a period of three years unless revoked or 
suspended.
 

The certificate is granted subject 
to the following conditions:—
 

(i)
 

(ii)
 

(iii)
 

Date 
...................................                                                                                            
             
  (Member Secretary)
 

Place 
.................................                                                                                                    State 
Pollution Control Board/
 

                                                                                                                                                 Pollution 
Control Committee
 

 
 

 </form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>