<act><tid>701797</tid>
<title>THE SPECIAL COURTS ACT, <year>1979</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum></title>

ACT NO. 22 OF <year>1979</year> AN ACT TO PROVIDE FOR THE SPEEDY TRIAL OF A CERTAIN C 
LASS OF OFFENCES.
[ 16th May, <year>1979</year>.]

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirtieth Year of the 
Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>913183</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>1813078</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Special Courts Act, <year>1979</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>672562</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu 
and Kashmir.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>706692</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>1742723</tid>
<number>a</number>" Code" means the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year>; (2 of  
  <year>1974</year>)

</section>

<section><tid>1956857</tid>
<number>b</number>" declaration", in relation to an offence, means a 
declaration made under section 5 in respect of such offence;

</section>

<section><tid>1690484</tid>
<number>c</number>" Special Court" means a Special Court established under 
section 3;

</section>

<section><tid>395152</tid>
<number>d</number>words and expressions used but not defined in this Act 
but defined in the Code shall have the same meanings as in 
the Code.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1249080</tid>
<number> 3</number> Establishment of Special Courts.
<section><tid>737907</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government  
shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, establish an adequate 
number of courts to be called Special Courts.

</section>

<section><tid>558490</tid>
<number>2</number>A Special Court shall consist of a sitting Judge of a High 
Court nominated by the Chief Justice of the High Court within the 
local limits of whose jurisdiction the Special Court is situated, with 
the concurrence of the Chief Justice of India.
Explanation.- Any reference to a High Court or to the Chief 
Justice or Judge of a High Court shall, in relation to a Union 
territory having a Court of the Judicial Commissioner, be construed as 
a reference to the said Court of the Judicial Commissioner or to the 
Judicial Commissioner or any Additional Judicial Commissioner, as the 
case may be.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1887434</tid>
<number>4</number>Cognizance of cases by Special Courts. A Special Court shall 
take cognizance of or try such cases as are instituted before it or 
transferred to it as hereinafter provided.


</article>



<article><tid>1902247</tid>
<number> 5</number> Declaration by Central Government of cases to be dealt with 
under this Act.
<section><tid>245740</tid>
<number>1</number>If the Central Government is of opinion that there  
is prima facie evidence of the commission of an offence alleged to 
have been committed by a person who held high public or political 
office in India and that in accordance with the guidelines contained 
in the preamble hereto the said offence ought to be dealt with under 
this Act, the Central Government shall make a declaration to that 
effect in every case in which it is of the aforesaid opinion.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>167</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>868884</tid>
<number>2</number>Such declaration shall not be called in question in any 
court.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>654149</tid>
<number>6</number>Effect of declaration. On such declaration being made in 
respect of any offence, notwithstanding anything in the Code, any 
prosecution in respect of such offence shall be instituted only in a 
Special Court designated by the Central Government and any prosecution 
in respect of such offence pending in any court shall stand 
transferred to a Special Court designated by the Central Government.


</article>



<article><tid>1304459</tid>
<number>7</number>Pending appeal or revision to be transferred to Supreme 
Court. If at the date of the declaration in respect of any offence an 
appeal or revision against any judgment or order in a prosecution in 
respect of such offence, whether pending or disposed of, is itself 
pending ill any court of appeal or revision, the same shall stand 
transferred for disposal to the Supreme Court.


</article>



<article><tid>1389547</tid>
<number>8</number>Jurisdiction of Special Courts as to joint trials. A Special 
Court shall have jurisdiction to try any person concerned in the 
offence in respect of which a declaration has been made, either as 
principal, conspirator or abettor and all other offences and accused 
persons as can be jointly tried therewith at one trial in accordance 
with the Code.


</article>



<article><tid>1384592</tid>
<number> 9</number> Procedure and powers of Special Courts.
<section><tid>1091821</tid>
<number>1</number>A Special Court  
shall in the trial of such cases follow the procedure prescribed by 
the Code, for the trial of warrant cases before a magistrate.

</section>

<section><tid>1024728</tid>
<number>2</number>A Special Court may, with a view to obtaining evidence of 
any person suspected to have been directly or indirectly concerned in 
or privy to an offence, tender a pardon to such person on condition of 
his making full and true disclosure of the whole circumstances within 
his knowledge relating to the offence and to every other person 
concerned whether as principal, conspirator or abettor in the 
commission thereof and any pardon so tendered shall for the purposes 
of section 308 of the Code be deemed to have been tendered under 
section 307 thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>1493778</tid>
<number>3</number>Save as expressly provided in this Act, the provisions of 
the Code shall, in so far as they are not inconsistent with the 
provisions of this Act, apply to the proceedings before a Special 
Court and for the purposes of the said provisions of the Code a 
Special Court shall be deemed to be a Court of Session and shall have 
all the powers of a Court of Session and the person conducting a 
prosecution before a Special Court shall be deemed to be a Public 
Prosecutor.

</section>

<section><tid>2111</tid>
<number>4</number>A Special Court may pass upon any person convicted by it any 
sentence authorised by law for the punishment of the offence of which 
such person is convicted.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>168</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1005854</tid>
<number> 10</number> Power of Supreme Court to transfer cases.
<section><tid>415785</tid>
<number>1</number>Whenever it is  
made to appear to the Supreme Court that an order under this section 
is expedient for the ends of justice, it may direct that any 
particular case be transferred from one Special Court to another 
Special Court.

</section>

<section><tid>77103</tid>
<number>2</number>The Supreme Court may act under this section only on the 
application of the Attorney- General of India or of a party interested, 
and every such application shall be made by motion, which shall, 
except when the applicant is the Attorney- General of India or the 
Advocate- General of a State, be supported by affidavit or affirmation.

</section>

<section><tid>1324445</tid>
<number>3</number>Where any application for the exercise of the powers 
conferred by this section is dismissed, the Supreme Court may, if it 
is of opinion that the application was frivolous or vexatious, order 
the applicant to pay by way of compensation to any person who has 
opposed the application such sum not exceeding one thousand rupees as 
it may consider appropriate in the circumstances of the case.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>347123</tid>
<number> 11</number> Appeal.
<section><tid>775070</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything in the Code, an appeal  
shall lie as of right from any judgment, sentence or order, not being 
interlocutory order, of a Special Court to the Supreme Court both on 
facts and on law.

</section>

<section><tid>876567</tid>
<number>2</number>Except as aforesaid, no appeal or revision shall lie to any 
court from any judgment, sentence or order of a Special Court.

</section>

<section><tid>170451</tid>
<number>3</number>Every appeal under this section shall be preferred within a 
period of thirty days from the date of any judgment sentence or order 
of a Special Court:
Provided that the Supreme Court may entertain an appeal after the 
expiry of the said period of thirty days if it is satisfied that the 
appellant had sufficient cause for not preferring the appeal within 
the period of thirty days.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>107837</tid>
<number>12</number>Power to make rules. The Supreme Court may, by notification 
in the Official Gazette, make such rules, if any, as it may deem 
necessary for carrying out the purposes of this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>209430</tid>
<number> 13</number> Notifications under section 3 and declarations under 
section 5 to be laid before Parliament. Every notification made under 
sub- section
<section><tid>77557</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 3 and every declaration made under sub-  
section (1) of section 5 shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is 
made, before each House of Parliament.

</section>

</article>



 </act>