<act> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 20061
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the National Commission for Minority Educational Institutions (Procedure 
for Appeal) Rules, 2006.
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force 
on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
  



</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  “Act” means the National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions Act, 2004 (18 of 2006); 
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  “appeal” means an appeal made to the Commission 
under sub-section (1) of section 12A or under sub-section (1) of section 12B of 
the Act;
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  “Appellant” means a person making an appeal to 
the Commission under sub-section (1) of section 12A or under sub-section (1) of 
section 12B of the Act;
 </section><section>       <number>d</number>  “Chairperson” means the Chairperson of the 
Commission nominated by the Central Government under sub-section (2) of section 
3 of the Act;
 </section><section>       <number>e</number>  “competent authority” means an authority 
appointed by the appropriate Government to grant No Objection Certificate for 
the establishment of any educational institution of their choice by the 
minorities or to grant minority status certificate to any minority educational 
institution;
 </section><section>        <number>f</number>  “Form” means a form appended to these rules;
 </section><section>       <number>g</number>  “Pleader” has the same meaning assigned to it in 
clause (xv) of section 2 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908);
 </section><section>       <number>h</number>  “Secretary” means the Secretary of the 
Commission; 
 </section><section>        <number>i</number>  the words and expressions used herein but not 
defined in the Act shall have the same meaning respectively assigned to them in 
the Act.
</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>3</number> Language of the Commission.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The proceedings of the Commission shall be conducted in English or Hindi.
 </section><section><number>2</number> No appeal, reference, 
application, representation, document or other matters shall be accepted by the 
Commission unless the same is accompanied by a true copy of translation thereof 
in English or Hindi.
</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>4</number> Procedure for filing 
appeals.—
<section><number>1</number> A memorandum of appeal 
shall be presented in the Form annexed to these rules by the appellant either in 
person, or by a pleader authorised by him for such purpose to the Secretary or 
shall be sent by registered post addressed to the Secretary.
 </section><section><number>2</number> An appeal sent by post under 
sub-rule (1) shall be deemed to have been presented to the Secretary on the day 
on which it is received in the office of the Secretary.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The memorandum of appeal 
under sub-rule (1) shall be presented in four complete sets in a paper book Form 
along with an empty file size envelope bearing full address of the respondent 
and where the number of respondents is more than one, as many extra copies of 
the appeal in a paper book form as there are respondents together with unused 
file size envelopes bearing full address of each respondent to be furnished by 
the appellant.
  
</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>5</number> Presentation and scrutiny 
of the memorandum of appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
Secretary shall endorse on every memorandum of appeal the date on which it is 
presented under rule 4 or deemed to have been presented under that rule and 
shall sign the endorsement.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If, on scrutiny, the 
memorandum of appeal is found to be in order, it shall be duly registered in a 
book of appeal and such book shall be called the register of appeal.
 </section><section><number>3</number> If the memorandum of appeal 
on scrutiny is found to be defective, and the defect noticed is formal in 
nature, the Secretary may allow the appellant such time to rectify the defect as 
he may deem fit.
 </section><section><number>4</number> If the appellant fails to 
rectify the defect within the time allowed under sub-rule (4), the Secretary 
may, by order and for reasons to be recorded in writing, decline to register 
such memorandum of appeal and inform the appellant accordingly.
 </section><section><number>5</number> An appeal against the order 
of the Secretary under sub-rule (5) shall be made, within fifteen days from the 
date of making of such order, to the Chairperson, whose decision shall be final.
  
</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>6</number> Contents of the memorandum 
of appeal.—Every memorandum of appeal 
filed under rule 4 shall set forth, concisely and under distinct heads, the 
grounds of such appeal, without any argument or narrative, and such grounds 
shall be numbered, consecutively. Every appeal shall be typed in double space on 
one side on these papers of good quality.
</article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>7</number> Documents to accompany 
memorandum of appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> Every 
memorandum of appeal shall be in quadruplicate and shall be accompanied by four 
copies of the order, under appeal, attested by a notary or the pleader.
</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>8</number> Rejection or amendment of 
memorandum of appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> Where the 
memorandum of appeal is not submitted in the manner prescribed above, it may be 
rejected, or be returned to the appellant for the purposes of being amended 
within a time to be fixed by the Commission or be amended then and there.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where the Commission rejects 
any memorandum it shall record the reasons for such rejection.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where a memorandum of appeal 
is amended, the Chairperson, or such officer, as he appoints in this behalf, 
shall sign or initial the amendment.
</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>9</number> Application for condonation 
of delay.—
<section><number>1</number> Where an appeal is filed 
after the expiry of the period of limitation specified therefor, it shall be 
accompanied by an application supported by an affidavit setting forth the facts 
on which the appellant relies to satisfy the Commission that he had sufficient 
cause for not filing the appeal within such period.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If the Commission sees no 
reason to reject the application, a notice thereof shall be issued to the 
respondent and the matter shall be finally decided by the Commission before it 
proceeds to deal with the appeal under rule 10.
</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>10</number> Power to dismiss appeal 
without sending notice to the authority under whose order the appeal is 
preferred.—
<section><number>1</number> The Commission after 
fixing a day for hearing the appellant or his pleader and hearing him 
accordingly if he appears on that day may dismiss the appeal.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If on the day fixed or any 
other day to which hearing may be adjourned, the appellant does not appear when 
the appeal is called on for hearing, the Commission may make an order that the 
appeal be dismissed.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where the Commission 
dismisses an appeal under sub-rule (1), it shall deliver an order recording in 
brief the grounds for doing so.
</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>11</number> Time within which hearing 
under rule 10 should be concluded.—Every 
appeal shall be heard under rule 10 as expeditiously as possible and endeavour 
shall be made to conclude such hearing within sixty days from the date on which 
the memorandum of appeal is filed.
  
</article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>12</number> Day for hearing of appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Unless the Commission dismisses the appeal under rule 10, it shall fix a date 
for hearing the appeal.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Such day shall be fixed with 
reference to the current business of the Commission.
  
</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>13</number> Publication and service of 
notice of day for hearing appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Notice of the day fixed under rule 12 shall be affixed in the office of the 
Commission, and a like notice shall be sent by the Commission to the competent 
authority from whose order the appeal is preferred, and shall be served on the 
respondent or on his pleader, and all the provisions applicable to such summons, 
and to proceedings with reference to the service thereof prescribed by the Code 
of Civil Procedure, shall apply to the service of such notice.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Instead of sending the notice 
to the competent authority from whose order the appeal is preferred, the 
Commission may itself cause the notice to be served on the respondent or on his 
pleader under the provisions above referred to.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The notice to be served on 
the respondent shall be accompanied by a copy of the memorandum of appeal.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Notwithstanding anything to 
the contrary contained in sub-rule (1), it shall not be necessary to serve 
notice of any proceeding incidental to an appeal on any respondent other than a 
person impleaded for the first time in the Commission, unless he has appeared 
and filed an address for the service in the office of the competent authority, 
or has appeared in the appeal.
 </section><section><number>5</number> Nothing in sub-rule (4) shall 
bar the respondent referred to in the appeal from defending it.
</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>14</number> Right to begin.—
<section><number>1</number> 
On the day fixed, or on any other day to which the hearing may be adjourned, the 
appellant shall be heard in support of the appeal.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Commission shall then, if 
it does not dismiss the appeal at once, hear the respondent against the appeal, 
and in such case the appellant shall be entitled to reply.
  
</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>15</number> Dismissal of appeal for 
appellant’s default.—
<section><number>1</number> Where on the 
day fixed, or on any other day to which the hearing may be adjourned, the 
appellant does not appear when the appeal is called on for hearing the 
Commission may make an order that the appeal be dismissed.
 Explanation.—Nothing 
in this sub-rule shall be construed as empowering the Commission to dismiss the 
appeal on the merits.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Hearing of appeals 
ex parte.—Where, on the day fixed for hearing or any other date to which the 
hearing may be adjourned, the appellant appears and the respondent does not 
appear, the appeal shall be heard ex parte.
  
</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>15</number> Dismissal of appeal for 
appellant’s default.—
<section><number>1</number> Where on the 
day fixed, or on any other day to which the hearing may be adjourned, the 
appellant does not appear when the appeal is called on for hearing the 
Commission may make an order that the appeal be dismissed.
 Explanation.—Nothing 
in this sub-rule shall be construed as empowering the Commission to dismiss the 
appeal on the merits.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Hearing of appeals 
ex parte.—Where, on the day fixed for hearing or any other date to which the 
hearing may be adjourned, the appellant appears and the respondent does not 
appear, the appeal shall be heard ex parte.
  
</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>16</number> Re-admission of an appeal 
dismissed for default.—Where an appeal 
is dismissed under rule 15, the appellant may apply to the Commission for the 
re-admission of the appealed and, where it is proved that he was prevented by 
any sufficient cause from appearing when the appeal was called on for hearing, 
the Commission shall re-admit the appeal on such terms as to costs or otherwise 
as it thinks fit.
  
</article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>17</number> Power to adjourn hearing 
and direct persons appearing interested to be made respondents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where it appears to the Commission at the hearing that any person who was a 
party to the proceedings before the competent authority from whose order the 
appeal is preferred, but who has not been made a party to the appeal is 
interested in the result of the appeal, the Commission may adjourn the hearing 
to a future day to be fixed by the Commission and direct that such person be 
made a respondent.
 </section><section><number>2</number> No respondent shall be added 
under this rule, after the expiry of the period of limitation for appeal, unless 
the Commission, for reasons to be recorded, allows that to be done, on such 
terms as to costs as it thinks fit.
  
</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>18</number> Re-hearing of appeal on 
the application of respondent.—Where 
the appeal is heard ex parte and order is pronounced against the 
respondent, he may apply to the Commission to re-hear the appeal; and, if he 
satisfies the Commission that the notice was not duly served, or that he was 
prevented by sufficient cause from appearing when the appeal was called on for 
hearing, the Commission shall re-hear the appeal on such terms as to costs or 
otherwise as it thinks fit to impose upon him.
  
</article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>19</number> Upon hearing respondent 
may object to order as if he had preferred a separate appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any respondent, though he may not have appealed from any part of the order, may 
not only support the order but may also state that the finding against him by 
the competent authority in respect of any issue ought to have been in his favour; 
and may also take any cross-objection to the order which he could have taken by 
way of appeal provided he has filed such objection in the Commission within one 
month from the date of service on him or his pleader of notice of the day fixed 
for hearing the appeal, or within such further time as the Commission may see 
fit to allow.
 Explanation.—A 
respondent aggrieved by a finding of the competent authority in the order on 
which the order appealed against is based may, under this rule, file 
cross-objection in respect of the order in so far as it is based on that 
finding.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Such cross-objection shall be 
in the form of a memorandum, and the provisions of rule 6, so far as they relate 
to the form and contents of the memorandum of appeal, shall apply thereto.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where, in any case, in which 
any respondent has under this rule filed a memorandum of objection, the original 
appeal is withdrawn or is dismissed for default, the objection so filed may 
nevertheless be heard and determined after such notice to the other parties as 
the Commission thinks fit.
  
</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>20</number> Where evidence on record 
is sufficient, Commission may determine case finally.—Where 
the evidence upon the record is sufficient to decide the appeal, the Commission 
may finally decide the appeal.
  
</article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>21</number> Production of additional 
evidence in appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> The parties to 
the appeal shall not be entitled to produce additional evidence, either oral or 
documentary, in the Commission. But if—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  the competent authority from whose order the 
appeal is preferred has refused to admit evidence which ought to have been 
admitted, or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  the party seeking to produce additional 
evidence, establishes that notwithstanding the exercise of due diligence, such 
evidence was not within his knowledge or could not, after the exercise of due 
diligence, be produced by him at the time when the order appealed against was 
passed, or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  the Commission requires any document to be 
produced or any witness to be examined to enable it to pronounce order, or for 
any other substantial cause, 
 the Commission may allow such evidence or document to be produced, 
or witness to be examined. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Wherever additional evidence 
is allowed to be produced by the Commission, the Commission shall record the 
reason for its admission.
  
</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>22</number> Mode of taking additional 
evidence.—Such document may be 
produced or such witness examined or such evidence adduced before the 
Commission.
</article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>23</number> Order when and where 
pronounced.— The Commission, after 
hearing the parties or their pleaders and referring to any part of the 
proceedings, whether on appeal or in the competent authority from whose order 
the appeal is preferred, to which reference may be considered necessary, shall 
pronounce order, either at once or on some future day of which notice shall be 
given to the parties or their pleaders.
  
</article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>24</number> Dissent to be recorded.—Any 
member of the Commission dissenting from the order of the Commission shall state 
in writing the decision or order which he thinks should be passed on the appeal, 
and he may state his reasons for the same.
  
</article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>25</number> Adjournment of hearing.—The 
Commission may if sufficient cause is shown at any stage of proceedings grant 
time to the parties or any of them, and adjourn the hearing of the appeal.
  
</article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>26</number> Order to be signed and 
dated.—
<section><number>i</number> Every order of the 
Commission shall be in writing and shall be signed by the Presiding Officer who 
pronounced the order.
</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>27</number> Copies of orders to be 
furnished to parties.—Certified copies 
of the orders shall be furnished to the parties on the application to the 
Commission.
</article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>28</number> Certified copy of orders 
to be sent to the competent authority whose order was appealed from.—A 
copy of the order, certified by the Secretary, or such officer as the 
Chairperson appoints in this behalf, shall be sent to the competent authority 
which passed the order appealed from.
</article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>29</number> Inspection of records and 
certified copies of orders.—
<section><number>1</number> Any 
person who is a party in an appeal or a pleader authorized by such person may 
make an application for inspecting the records of such appeal to the Secretary 
and the Secretary may allow the inspection of the record by such person or the 
pleader, as the case may be.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any person or a pleader 
authorized by such person may make an application to the Secretary for obtaining 
a certified copy of any order of the Commission and the Secretary shall order 
furnishing of a certified copy of such order to such person or the pleader, as 
the case may be.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every certified copy of the 
order of the Commission shall be prepared in the office of the Commission and 
shall be authenticated by the Secretary or any officer authorised by him in this 
behalf.
</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>30</number> Orders and directions in 
certain cases.—The Commission may make 
such orders or give such directions as may be necessary or expedient to give 
effect to its orders or prevent abuse of its process or to secure the ends of 
justice.
</article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>31</number> Working hours of the 
Commission.—
<section><number>1</number> Except on Saturdays, 
Sundays and other public holidays, the office of the Commission shall, subject 
to any other order, made by the Chairperson, remain open daily from 9:30 A.M. to 
6:00 P.M. but no work, unless of an urgent nature, shall be entertained after 
4:30 P.M. on any working day.
</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>32</number> Sitting hours of the 
Commission.—The sitting hours of the 
Commission shall ordinarily be from 10:30 A.M. to 1:30 P.M. and 2:30 P.M. to 
5:00 P.M. subject to any general or special order made by the Chairperson of the 
Commission.
</article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>33</number> Holidays.—Where 
the last day for doing any official act falls on a day on which the office of 
the Commission is closed, and by reason thereof, such an act cannot be done on 
that day, it may be done on the next opening day.
</article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>34</number> Powers and functions of 
the Secretary.—
<section><number>1</number> The Secretary shall 
have the custody of the records of the Commission and shall exercise such other 
powers as may be assigned to him by the Chairperson.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The official seal of the 
Commission shall be kept in the custody of the Secretary.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Subject to any general or 
special direction by the Chairperson, the seal of the Commission shall not be 
affixed on any order, notice or other process, save under the authority in 
writing of the Secretary.
</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>35</number> Seal and emblem.—The 
official seal and emblem of the Commission shall be as in Form No. 5.
</article><form>
 

The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
 

 
 




FORM No. 1
 


(See
rule 4)
 




MEMORANDUM OF APPEAL UNDER SECTIONs 12A(1) AND 12B(1)  

OF THE NATIONAL COMMISSION FOR MINORITY  

EDUCATIONAL Institutions ACT, 2004
 


For 
use of Commission’s office
 


Date of 
filing....................................... 
 


Date of receipt by 
post......................  
 


Registration 
No................................... 
 


Signature 
 


Secretary 
 


IN 
THE NATIONAL COMMISSION FOR MINORITY  

EDUCATIONAL INSTITUTIONS
 



......................Appellant 
 


......................Respondent(s)
 


Details of appeal:
 


    1. (a)  Name and 
address of the Institution
 


        (b)  Name and 
address of the President/Secretary of the Trust/Society 
 


2. Whether the appellant 
institution’s claim is based on religious or linguistic minority?
 


3. Whether the appellant 
institution has been established or administered by:—
 


        (a)  Religious 
minority, or
 


        (b)  Linguistic 
minority
 


4. Particulars of the 
respondent(s) including address for service of notice
 


5. Particulars of the order 
under appeal:—
 


         (i)  Order Number
 


        (ii)  Date of the 
order
 


        (iii)  Name of the 
authority, whose order has been challenged in the appeal.
 


6. Limitation.—The 
appellant further declares that the appeal is within the limitation prescribed 
under the Act.
 


7. Facts of the case and 
orders passed by the competent authority.—The facts of the case are given 
below:
 


(Give herein a concise 
statement of facts and grounds of appeal against the order passed by the 
competent authority.
 


8. Matter not pending 
with any other Commission, etc.—The appellant further declares that the 
matter regarding which this appeal has been made is not pending before any 
Commission of law or any other authority or any other Tribunal.
 


9. Relief sought.—In 
view of the facts mentioned in paragraph eight above, the appellant prays for 
the following reliefs; (specify below the reliefs sought by the appellant).
 


11. Details of index.—An 
index in duplicate containing the details of the documents to be relied upon is 
enclosed.
 


12. List of enclosures:
 



VERIFICATION
 


I, ................(name in 
full in block letters) son/daughter/wife of Shri..............do hereby verify 
that the contents of paras 1 to 12 are true to my personal knowledge and belief 
and that I have not suppressed any material facts.
 


Signature of the Appellant
 


Place....................
 


Date.....................
</form><form>
 

The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
 

 
 




Form No. 2
 


[See
rule 13(1)]
 




INTIMATION TO COMPETENT AUTHORITY OF  

ADMISSION OF APPEAL
 


(Title)
 


To
 


....................
 


....................
 


You are hereby directed to 
take notice that the appellant (Name of the appellant) has preferred an 
appeal to this Commission from the order passed by you therein on 
the...............day of...........20..........    
 


You are requested to send 
with all practicable dispatch all material papers in the proceeding on or before 
the...........day of............20........          
 


Dated the............day 
of...............20.....     
 


Secretary
</form><form>
 

The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
 

 
 




Form No. 3
 


(See
rule 13)
 




NOTICE TO RESPONDENT OF THE DAY FIXED FOR  

THE HEARING OF THE APPEAL
 


(Title)
 


Appeal from the order dated 
the.............day of...............20......passed by................(name 
of the competent authority).
 


To
 



....................Respondent.
 


Take notice that an appeal 
from the order of....................(Name of the competent authority)
in this case has been presented by the appellant and registered in this 
Commission, and that the..........day of.........20........., has been fixed by 
this Commission for the hearing of this appeal.
 


If no appearance is made on 
your behalf by yourself, your pleader, or by some one by law authorized to act 
for you in this appeal, it will be heard and decided in your absence.
 


Given under my hand and the 
seal of the Commission, this..........day of............20........
 


Secretary 
</form><form>
 

The National Commission for Minority 
Educational Institutions (Procedure for Appeal) Rules, 2006
 

 
 




Form No. 4 
 


(See
rule 17)
 




NOTICE TO A PARTY TO A PROCEEDING NOT MADE  

A PARTY TO THE APPEAL BUT JOINED BY THE  

COMMISSION AS A RESPONDENT
 


(Title)
 


To
 


...........................
 


...........................
 


Whereas the appellant, 
named above, has preferred an appeal to this Commission from the order passed 
against him in the proceedings before....................(Name of the 
competent authority) and it appears to this Commission that you are 
interested in the result of the said appeal.
 


This is to give you notice 
that this Commission has directed you to be made a respondent in the said appeal 
and has adjourned the hearing thereof till the..............day 
of..........20.........., at 10.30 A.M. If no appearance is made on your behalf 
on the said day and at the said hour, the appeal will be heard and decided in 
your absence.
 


Given under my hand and the 
seal of the Commission, this............day of.........20.....
 


Secretary
 


6. Limitation.—The 
appellant further declares that the appeal is within the limitation prescribed 
under the Act.
 


7. Facts of the case and 
orders passed by the competent authority.—The facts of the case are given 
below:
 


(Give herein a concise 
statement of facts and grounds of appeal against the order passed by the 
competent authority.
 


8. Matter not pending 
with any other Commission, etc.—The appellant further declares that the 
matter regarding which this appeal has been made is not pending before any 
Commission of law or any other authority or any other Tribunal.
 


9. Relief sought.—In 
view of the facts mentioned in paragraph eight above, the, appellant prays for 
the following reliefs; (specify below the reliefs sought by the appellant).
 


11. Details of index.—An 
index in duplicate containing the details of the documents to be relied upon is 
enclosed.
 


12. List of enclosures:
 



VERIFICATION 
 


I, 
....................(name in full in block letters) son/daughter/wife of Shri......................do 
hereby verify that the contents of paras 1 to 12 are true to my personal 
knowledge and belief and that I have not suppressed any material facts.
 


Signature of the Appellant
 


Place....................
 


Date....................
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>