<act><title>

The 
    Prevention of Money-Laundering Act, 2002</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Prevention of Money-laundering Act, 2002.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends 
    to the whole of India. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It 
    shall come into force on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central Government 
    may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint, and different dates 
    may be appointed for different provisions of this Act and any reference in 
    any such provision to the commencement of this Act shall be construed as a 
    reference to the coming into force of that provision. 

 
 




 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> In this Act, unless the context 
otherwise requires,— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> “Adjudicating Authority” means an Adjudicating Authority appointed 
  under sub-section (1) of section 6; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> “Appellate Tribunal” means the Appellate Tribunal established under 
  section 25; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> “Assistant Director” means an Assistant Director appointed under 
  sub-section (1) of section 49; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> “attachment” means prohibition of transfer, conversion, disposition or 
  movement of property by an order issued under Chapter III; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>da</number> “authorised person” means an authorised person as defined 
  in clause (c) of section 2 of the Foreign Exchange Management Act, 1999 (42 of 
  1999);] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> “banking company” means a banking company or a co-operative bank to 
  which the Banking Regulation Act, 1949 (10 of 1949) applies and includes any 
  bank or banking institution referred to in section 51 of that Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> “Bench” means a Bench of the Appellate Tribunal; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> “Chairperson” means the Chairperson of the Appellate Tribunal; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> “chit fund company” means a company managing, conducting or 
  supervising, as foreman, agent or in any other capacity, chits as defined in 
  section 2 of the Chit Funds Act, 1982 (40 of 1982); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> “co-operative bank” shall have the same meaning as assinged to it in 
  clause (dd) of section 2 of the Deposit Insurance and Credit Guarantee 
  Corporation Act, 1961 (47 of 1961); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> “Deputy Director” means a Deputy Director appointed under 
   sub-section (1) of section 49; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>ja</number> “designated business or profession” means carrying on 
  activities for playing games of chance for cash or kind, and includes such 
  activities associated with casino or such other activities as the Central 
  Government may, by notification, so designate, from time to time;] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number> “Director” or “Additional Director” or “Joint Director” means a 
  Director or Additional Director or Joint Director, as the case may be, 
  appointed under sub-section (1) of section 49; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number> “financial institution” means a financial institution as defined in 
  clause (c) of section 45-I of the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934) 
  and includes a chit fund company, a co-operative bank, a housing finance 
  institution and <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[an authorised person, a payment system operator 
  and a non-banking financial company]; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>m</number> “housing finance institution” shall have the meaning as assigned to it 
  in clause (d) of section 2 of the National Housing Bank Act, 1987 (53 of 
  1987); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>n</number> “intermediary” means a stock-broker, sub-broker, share transfer agent, 
  banker to an issue, trustee to a trust deed, registrar to an issue, merchant 
  banker, underwriter, portfolio manager, investment adviser and any other 
  intermediary associated with securities market and registered under section 12 
  of the Securities and Exchange Board of India Act, 1992 (15 of 1992); 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>na</number> “investigation” includes all the proceedings under this 
  Act conducted by the Director or by an authority authorised by the Central 
  Government under this Act for the collection of evidence;] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>o</number> “Member” means a Member of the Appellate Tribunal and includes the 
  Chairperson; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>p</number> “money-laundering” has the meaning assigned to it in section 3; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>q</number> “non-banking financial company” shall have the same meaning as assigned 
  to it in clause (f) of section 45-I of the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 
  of 1934) <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[and includes a person carrying on designated business or 
  profession]; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>r</number> “notification” means a notification published in the Official Gazette; 
  
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>ra</number> “offence of cross border implications”, means— 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> any conduct by a person at a place outside India which constitutes an 
    offence at that place and which would have constituted an offence specified 
    in Part A, Part B or Part C of the Schedule, had it been committed in India 
    and if such person remits the proceeds of such conduct or part thereof to 
    India; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> any offence specified in Part A, Part B or Part C of the Schedule 
    which has been committed in India and the proceeds of crime, or part thereof 
    have been transferred to a place outside India or any attempt has been made 
    to transfer the proceeds of crime, or part thereof from India to a place 
    outside India. 
 Explanation .—Nothing contained in this clause shall adversely 
    affect any investigation, enquiry, trial or proceeding before any authority 
    in respect of the offences specified in Part A or Part B of the Schedule to 
    the Act before the commencement of the Prevention of Money-laundering 
    (Amendment) Act, 2009.] </subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>rb</number> “payment system” means a system that enables payment to 
  be effected between a payer and a beneficiary, involving clearing, payment or 
  settlement service or all of them. </subsection>
 Explanation .—For the purposes of this clause, “payment system” 
includes the systems enabling credit card operations, debit card operations, 
smart card operations, money transfer operations or similar operations;] 
 
 <subsection><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>rc</number> “payment system operator” means a person who operates a 
  payment system and such person includes his overseas principal. 
</subsection>
 Explanation .—For the purposes of this clause, “overseas principal” 
means,— 
 
 <subsection><number>A</number> in the case of a person, being an individual, such individual residing 
  outside India, who owns or controls or manages, directly or indirectly, the 
  activities or functions of payment system in India; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>B</number> in the case of a Hindu undivided family, Karta of such Hindu undivided 
  family residing outside India who owns or controls or manages, directly or 
  indirectly, the activities or functions of payment system in India; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>C</number> in the case of a company, a firm, an association of persons, a body of 
  individuals, an artificial juridical person, whether incorporated or not, such 
  company, firm, association of persons, body of individuals, artificial 
  juridical person incorporated or registered outside India or existing as such 
  and which owns or controls or manages, directly or indirectly, the activities 
  or functions of payment system in India;] 
 <subsubsection><number>s</number> “person” includes;— 
 
 <subsubsubsection><number>i</number> an individual, 
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>ii</number> a Hindu undivided family, 
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>iii</number> a company, 
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>iv</number> a firm, 
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>v</number> an association of persons or a body of individuals, whether 
    incorporated or not, 
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>vi</number> every artificial juridical person, not falling within any of the 
    preceding sub-clauses, and 
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>vii</number> any agency, office or branch owned or controlled by any of the 
    above persons mentioned in the preceding sub-clauses; </subsubsubsection>
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>t</number> “prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>u</number> “proceeds of crime” means any property derived or obtained, directly or 
  indirectly, by any person as a result of criminal activity relating to a 
  scheduled offence or the value of any such property; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>v</number> “property” means any property or assets of every description, whether 
  corporeal or incorporeal, movable or immovable, tangible or intangible and 
  includes deeds and instruments evidencing title to, or interest in, such 
  property or assets, wherever located; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>w</number> “records” include the records maintained in the form of books or stored 
  in a computer or such other form as may be prescribed; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>x</number> “Schedule” means the Schedule to this Act; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>y</number> “scheduled offence” means— 
 
 
 <subsubsubsection><number>i</number> the offences specified under Part A of the Schedule; or 
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[<number>ii</number> the offences specified under Part B of the Schedule 
      if the total value involved in such offences is thirty lakh rupees or 
      more; or] 
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[<number>iii</number> the offences specified under Part C of the 
      Schedule;] </subsubsubsection>
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>z</number> “Special Court” means a Court of Session designated as Special Court 
  under sub-section (1) of section 43; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>za</number> “transfer” includes sale, purchase, mortgage, pledge, gift, loan or 
  any other form of transfer of right, title, possession or lien; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>zb</number> “value” means the fair market value of any property on the date of its 
  acquisition by any person, or if such date cannot be determined, the date on 
  which such property is possessed by such person. </subsubsection></subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any reference, in this Act or the Schedule, to any enactment 
or any provision thereof shall, in relation to an area in which such enactment 
or such provision is not in force, be construed as a reference to the 
corresponding law or the relevant provisions of the corresponding law, if any, 
in force in that area. 








</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Offence 
    of money-laundering.—Whosoever 
    directly or indirectly attempts to indulge or knowingly assists or knowingly 
    is a party or is actually involved in any process or activity connected with 
    the proceeds of crime and projecting it as untainted property shall be 
    guilty of offence of money-laundering.
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Punishment for money-laundering.—Whoever 
    commits the offence of money-laundering shall be punishable with rigorous 
    imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than three years but which 
    may extend to seven years and shall also be liable to fine which may extend 
    to five lakh rupees: 
 
Provided that 
    where the proceeds of crime involved in money-laundering relates to any 
    offence specified under paragraph 2 of Part A of the Schedule, the 
    provisions of this section shall have effect as if for the words “which may 
    extend to seven years”, the words “which may extend to ten years” had been 
    substituted.
  


 



</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Attachment of property involved in money-laundering. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where the Director, or any other officer not below the rank of Deputy Director 
authorised by him for the purposes of this section, has reason to believe (the 
reason for such belief to be recorded in writing), on the basis of material in 
his possession, that— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> any person is in possession of any proceeds of crime; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> such person has been charged of having committed a scheduled offence; 
  and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> such proceeds of crime are likely to be concealed, transferred or dealt 
  with in any manner which may result in frustrating any proceedings relating to 
  confiscation of such proceeds of crime under this Chapter, he may, by order in 
  writing, provisionally attach such property for a period not exceeding 
  <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[one hundred and fifty days] from the date of the order, in the 
  manner provided in the Second Schedule to the Income-tax Act, 1961 (43 of 
  1961) and the Director or the other officer so authorised by him, as the case 
  may be, shall be deemed to be an officer under sub-rule (e) of rule 1 of that 
  Schedule: </subsection>
 <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[Provided that no such order of attachment shall be made unless, 
in relation to the scheduled offence, a report has been forwarded to a 
Magistrate under section 173 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 
1974), or a complaint has been filed by a person, authorised to investigate the 
offence mentioned in the Schedule, before a Magistrate or court for taking 
cognizance of the scheduled offence, as the case may be: 
 Provided further that, notwithstanding anything contained in clause (b), any 
property of any person may be attached under this section if the Director or any 
other officer not below the rank of Deputy Director authorised by him for the 
purposes of this section has reason to believe (the reasons for such belief to 
be recorded in writing), on the basis of material in his possession, that if 
such property involved in money-laundering is not attached immediately under 
this Chapter, the non-attachment of the property is likely to frustrate any 
proceeding under this Act.] 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Director, or any other officer not below the rank of Deputy Director, 
shall, immediately after attachment under sub-section (1), forward a copy of the 
order, along with the material in his possession, referred to in that 
sub-section, to the Adjudicating Authority, in a sealed envelope, in the manner 
as may be prescribed and such Adjudicating Authority shall keep such order and 
material for such period as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every order of attachment made under sub-section (1) shall cease to have 
effect after the expiry of the period specified in that sub-section or on the 
date of an order made under sub-section (2) of section 8, whichever is earlier. 

 </section><section><number>4</number> Nothing in this section shall prevent the person interested in the 
enjoyment of the immovable property attached under sub-section (1) from such 
enjoyment. 
 Explanation.— For the purposes of this sub-section “person 
interested”, in relation to any immovable property, includes all persons 
claiming or entitled to claim any interest in the property. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Director or any other officer who provisionally attaches any property 
under sub-section (1) shall, within a period of thirty days from such 
attachment, file a complaint stating the facts of such attachment before the 
Adjudicating Authority. 






 
 <subsection><number>i</number> Paragraph 1 of Part A and Part B of the Schedule, a report 
  has been forwarded to a Magistrate under section 173 of the Code of Criminal 
  Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974); or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> Paragraph 2 of Part A of the Schedule, a police report or 
  a complaint has been filed for taking cognizance of an offence by the Special 
  Court constituted under sub-section (1) of section 36 of the Narcotic Drugs 
  and Psychotropic Substances Act, 1985 (61 of 1985).”. 
</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number>Adjudicating Authorities, composition, powers, etc. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government shall, by notification, appoint <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[an 
Adjudicating Authority] to exercise jurisdiction, powers and authority conferred 
by or under this Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> An Adjudicating Authority shall consist of a Chairperson and two other 
Members: 
 Provided that one Member each shall be a person having experience in the 
field of law, administration, finance or accountancy. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> A person shall, however, not be qualified for appointment as Member of an 
Adjudicating Authority,— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> in the field of law, unless he— 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> is qualified for appointment as District Judge; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> has been a member of the Indian Legal Service and has held a post in 
    Grade I of that service; </subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> in the field of finance, accountancy or administration unless he 
  possesses such qualifications, as may be prescribed. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Central Government shall appoint a Member to be the Chairperson of 
the Adjudicating Authority. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Subject to the provisions of this Act,— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the jurisdiction of the Adjudicating Authority may be exercised by 
  Benches thereof; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> a Bench may be constituted by the Chairperson of the Adjudicating 
  Authority with one or two Members as the Chairperson of the Adjudicating 
  Authority may deem fit; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the Benches of the Adjudicating Authority shall ordinarily sit at New 
  Delhi and such other places as the Central Government may, in consultation 
  with the Chairperson by notification, specify; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> the Central Government shall, by notification, specify the areas in 
  relation to which each Bench of the Adjudicating Authority may exercise 
  jurisdiction. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>6</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (5), the Chairperson 
may transfer a Member from one Bench to another Bench. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> If at any stage of the hearing of any case or matter it appears to the 
Chairperson or a Member that the case or matter is of such a nature that it 
ought to be heard by a Bench consisting of two Members, the case or matter may 
be transferred by the Chairperson or, as the case may be, referred to him for 
transfer, to such Bench as the Chairperson may deem fit. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> The Chairperson and every Member shall hold office as such for a term of 
five years from the date on which he enters upon his office: 
 Provided that no Chairperson or other Member shall hold office as such after 
he has attained the age of <footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[sixty-five] years. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> The salary and allowances payable to and the other terms and conditions 
of service of the Member shall be such as may be prescribed: 
 Provided that neither the salary and allowances nor the other terms and 
conditions of service of the Member shall be varied to his disadvantage after 
appointment. 
 </section><section><number>10</number> If, for reasons other than temporary absence, any vacancy occurs in the 
office of the Chairperson or any other Member, then the Central Government shall 
appoint another person in accordance with the provisions of this Act to fill the 
vacancy and the proceedings may be continued before the Adjudicating Authority 
from the stage at which the vacancy is filled. 
 </section><section><number>11</number> The Chairperson or any other Member may, by notice in writing under his 
hand addressed to the Central Government, resign his office: 
 Provided that the Chairperson or any other Member shall, unless he is 
permitted by the Central Government or relinquish his office sooner, continue to 
hold office until the expiry of three months from the date of receipt of such 
notice or until a person duly appointed as his successor enters upon his office 
or until the expiry of his term of office, whichever is the earliest. 
 </section><section><number>12</number> The Chairperson or any other Members shall not be removed from his 
office except by an order made by the Central Government after giving necessary 
opportunity of hearing. 
 </section><section><number>13</number> In the event of the occurrence of any vacancy in the office of the 
Chairperson by reason of his death, resignation or otherwise, the senior-most 
Member shall act as the Chairperson of the Adjudicating Authority until the date 
on which a new Chairperson appointed in accordance with the provisions of this 
Act to fill such vacancy, enters upon his office. 
 </section><section><number>14</number> When the Chairperson of the Adjudicating Authority is unable to 
discharge his functions owing to absence, illness or any other cause, the 
senior-most Member shall discharge the functions of the Chairperson of the 
Adjudicating Authority until the date on which the Chairperson of the 
Adjudicating Authority resumes his duties. 
 </section><section><number>15</number> The Adjudicating Authority shall not be bound by the procedure laid down 
by the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908, (5 of 1908) but shall be guided by the 
principles of natural justice and, subject to the other provisions of this Act, 
the Adjudicating Authority shall have powers to regulate its own procedure. 













</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Staff of 
    Adjudicating Authorities.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Central Government shall provide each Adjudicating Authority with such 
    officers and employees as that Government may think fit. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    officers and employees of the Adjudicating Authority shall discharge their 
    functions under the general superintendence of the Chairperson of the 
    Adjudicating Authority. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    salaries and allowances and other conditions of service of the officers and 
    employees of the Adjudicating Authority shall be such as may be prescribed. 

 
  


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number>Adjudication. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> On receipt of a complaint under 
sub-section (5) of section 5, or applications made under sub-section (4) of 
section 17 or under sub-section (10) of section 18, if the Adjudicating 
Authority has reason to believe that any person has committed an 
<footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[offence under section 3 or is in possession of proceeds of crime], 
he may serve a notice of not less than thirty days on such person calling upon 
him to indicate the sources of his income, earning or assets, out of which or by 
means of which he has acquired the property attached under sub-section (1) of 
section 5, or, seized under section 17 or section 18, the evidence on which he 
relies and other relevant information and particulars, and to show cause why all 
or any of such properties should not be declared to be the properties involved 
in money-laundering and confiscated by the Central Government: 
 Provided that where a notice under this sub-section specifies any property as 
being held by a person on behalf of any other person, a copy of such notice 
shall also be served upon such other person: 
 Provided further that where such property is held jointly by more than one 
person, such notice shall be served to all persons holding such property. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Adjudicating Authority shall, after— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> considering the reply, if any, to the notice issued under sub- 
   section (1); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> hearing the aggrieved person and the Director or any other officer 
  authorised by him in this behalf, and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> taking into account all relevant materials placed on record before him, 
  </subsection>
 by an order, record a finding whether all or any of the properties referred 
to in the notice issued under sub-section (1) are involved in money-laundering: 

 Provided that if the property is claimed by a person, other than a person to 
whom the notice had been issued, such person shall also be given an opportunity 
of being heard to prove that the property is not involved in money-laundering. 

 </section><section><number>3</number> Where the Adjudicating Authority decides under sub-section (2) that any 
property is involved in money-laundering, he shall, by an order in writing, 
confirm the attachment of the property made under sub-section (1) of section 5 
or retention of property or record seized under section 17 or section 18 and 
record a finding to that effect, such attachment or retention of the seized 
property or record shall— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> continue during the pendency of the proceedings relating to any 
  scheduled offence before a court; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> become final after the guilt of the person is proved in the trial court 
  and order of such trial court becomes final. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>4</number> Where the provisional order of attachment made under sub-section (1) of 
section 5 has been confirmed under sub-section (3), the Director or any other 
officer authorised by him in this behalf shall forthwith take the possession of 
the attached property. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Where on conclusion of a trial for any scheduled offence, the person 
concerned is acquitted, the attachment of the property or retention of the 
seized property or record under sub-section (3) and net income, if any, shall 
cease to have effect. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> Where the attachment of any property or retention of the seized property 
or record becomes final under clause (b) of sub-section (3), the Adjudicating 
Authority shall, after giving an opportunity of being heard to the person 
concerned, make an order confiscating such property. 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Vesting 
    of property in Central Government.—Where 
    an order of confiscation has been made under sub-section (6) of section 8 in 
    respect of any property of a person, all the rights and title in such 
    property shall vest absolutely in the Central Government free from all 
    encumbrances: 
 
Provided that 
    where the Adjudicating Authority, after giving an opportunity of being heard 
    to any other person interested in the property attached under this Chapter 
    or seized under Chapter V is of the opinion that any encumbrance on the 
    property or lease-hold interest has been created with a view to defeat the 
    provisions of this Chapter, it may, by order, declare such encumbrances or 
    lease-hold interest to be void and thereupon the aforesaid property shall 
    vest in the Central Government free from such encumbrances or lease-hold 
    interest: 
 
Provided 
    further that nothing in this section shall operate to discharge any person 
    from any liability in respect of such encumbrances which may be enforced 
    against such person by a suit for damages. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>10</number> Management of properties confiscated under 
      this Chapter.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
      Government may, by order published in the Official Gazette, appoint as 
      many of its officers (not below the rank of a Joint Secretary to the 
      Government of India) as it thinks fit, to perform the functions of an 
      Administrator. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Administrator appointed under 
      sub-section (1) shall receive and manage the property in relation to which 
      an order has been made under sub-section (6) of section 8 in such manner 
      and subject to such conditions as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Administrator shall also take such 
      measures, as the Central Government may direct, to dispose of the property 
      which is vested in the Central Government under section 9. 
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>11</number> Power regarding summons, production of 
      documents and evidence, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> The Adjudicating Authority shall, for the 
      purposes of this Act, have the same powers as are vested in a civil court 
      under the Code of civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) while trying a suit in 
      respect of the following matters, namely:— 
 <subsection><number>a</number>    discovery 
      and inspection; 
    
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>    enforcing 
      the attendance of any person, including any officer of a banking company 
      or a financial institution or a company, and examining him on oath; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>    compelling 
      the production of records; 
    
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>    receiving 
      evidence on affidavits; 
    
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>    issuing 
      commissions for examination of witnesses and documents; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>    any other 
      matter which may be prescribed. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> All the persons so summoned shall be bound 
      to attend in person or through authorised agents, as the Adjudicating 
      Authority may direct, and shall be bound to state the truth upon any 
      subject respecting which they are examined or make statements, and produce 
      such documents as may be required. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every proceeding under this section shall be 
      deemed to be a judicial proceeding within the meaning of section 193 and 
      section 228 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860). 
  
 
  </section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>12</number> Banking companies, financial institutions and intermediaries to 
maintain records. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Every banking company, financial institution and 
intermediary shall— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> maintain a record of all transactions, the nature and value of which 
  may be prescribed, whether such transactions comprise of a single transaction 
  or a series of transactions integrally connected to each other, and where such 
  series of transactions take place within a month; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> furnish information of transactions referred to in clause (a) to the 
  Director within such time as may be prescribed; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> verify and maintain the records of the identity of all its clients, in 
  such manner as may be prescribed: </subsection>
 Provided that where the principal officer of a banking company or financial 
institution or intermediary, as the case may be, has reason to believe that a 
single transaction or series of transactions integrally connected to each other 
have been valued below the prescribed value so as to defeat the provisions of 
this section, such officer shall furnish information in respect of such 
transactions to the Director within the prescribed time. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> (a) The records referred to in clause (a) of sub-section (1) 
shall be maintained for a period of ten years from the date of transactions 
between the clients and the banking company or financial institution or 
intermediary, as the case may be. 
 
 <subsection><number>b</number> The records referred to in clause (c) of sub-section (1) shall be 
  maintained for a period of ten years from the date of cessation of 
  transactions between the clients and the banking company or financial 
  institution or intermediary, as the case may be.] </subsection>


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> Powers 
    of Director to impose fine.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Director may, either of his own motion or on an application made by any 
    authority, officer or person, call for records referred to in sub-section 
    (1) of section 12 and may make such inquiry or cause such inquiry to be 
    made, as he thinks fit. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the 
    Director, in the course of any inquiry, finds that a banking company, 
    financial institution or an intermediary or any of its officers has failed 
    to comply with the provisions contained in section 12, then, without 
    prejudice to any other action that may be taken under any other provisions 
    of this Act, he may, by an order, levy a fine on such banking company or 
    financial institution or intermediary which shall not be less than ten 
    thousand rupees but may extend to one lakh rupees for each failure. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Director shall forward a copy of the order passed under sub-section (2) to 
    every banking company, financial institution or intermediary or person who 
    is a party to the proceedings under that sub-section. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>14</number> No civil proceedings against banking 
      companies, financial institutions, etc., in certain cases.—Save as otherwise provided in section 13, the 
      banking companies, financial institutions, intermediaries and their 
      officers shall not be liable to any civil proceedings against them for 
      furnishing information under clause (b) of sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 
      12. 
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>15</number> Procedure and manner of furnishing 
      information by banking company, financial institution and 
      intermediary.—The Central 
      Government may, in consultation with the Reserve Bank of India, prescribe 
      the procedure and the manner of maintaining and furnishing information 
      under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 12 for the purpose of implementing the 
      provisions of this Act. 
  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> Power of 
    survey.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in any other provisions of this Act, where an authority, 
    on the basis of material in his possession, has reason to believe (the 
    reasons for such belief to be recorded in writing) that an offence under 
    section 3 has been committed, he may enter any place— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    within the limits of the 
    area assigned to him; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    in respect of which he 
    is authorised for the purposes of this section by such other authority, who 
    is assigned the area within which such place is situated,  
    
 
at which any act constituting the commission 
    of such offence is carried on, and may require any proprietor, employee or 
    any other person who may at that time and place be attending in any manner 
    to, or helping in, such act so as to,—
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    afford him the necessary 
    facility to inspect such records as he may require and which may be 
    available at such place;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    afford him the 
    necessary facility to check or verify the proceeds of crime or any 
    transaction related to proceeds of crime which may be found therein; and  
    
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    furnish such 
    information as he may require as to any matter which may be useful for, or 
    relevant, to any proceedings under this Act.  
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    this sub-section, a place, where an act which constitutes the commission of 
    the offence is carried on, shall also include any other place, whether any 
    activity is carried on therein or not, in which the person carrying on such 
    activity states that any of his records or any part of his property relating 
    to such act are or is kept. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    authority referred to in sub-section (1) shall, after entering any place 
    referred to in that sub-section immediately after completion of survey, 
    forward a copy of the reasons so recorded along with material in his 
    possession, referred to in that sub-section, to the Adjudicating Authority 
    in a sealed envelop in the manner as may be prescribed and such Adjudicating 
    Authority shall keep such reasons and material for such period as may be 
    prescribed. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An 
    authority acting under this section may— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    place marks of 
    identification on the records inspected by him and make or cause to be made 
    extracts or copies therefrom, 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    make an inventory of 
    any property checked or verified by him, and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    record the statement 
    of any person present in the place which may be useful for, or relevant to, 
    any proceeding under this Act. 

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>17</number> Search and seizure. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Where <footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[the Director 
or any other officer not below the rank of Deputy Director authorised by him for 
the purposes of this section,] on the basis of information in his possession, 
has reason to believe (the reason for such belief to be recorded in writing) 
that any person— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> has committed any act which constitutes money-laundering, or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> is in possession of any proceeds of crime involved in 
  money-laundering, or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> is in possession of any records relating to money-laundering, then, 
  subject to the rules made in this behalf, he may authorise any officer 
  subordinate to him to— 
 
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> enter and search any building, place, vessel, vehicle or aircraft 
    where he has reason to suspect that such records or proceeds of crime are 
    kept; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> break open the lock of any door, box, locker, safe, almirah or other 
    receptacle for exercising the powers conferred by clause (a) where the keys 
    thereof are not available; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>c</number> seize any record or property found as a result of such search; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>d</number> place marks of identification on such record or make or cause to be 
    made extracts or copies therefrom; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>e</number> make a note or an inventory of such record or property; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>f</number> examine on oath any person, who is found to be in possession or 
    control of any record or property, in respect of all matters relevant for 
    the purposes of any investigation under this Act: </subsubsection></subsection>
 <footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[Provided that no search shall be conducted unless, in relation 
to the scheduled offence, a report has been forwarded to a Magistrate under 
section 157 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), or a complaint 
has been filed by a person, authorised to investigate the offence mentioned in 
the Schedule, before a Magistrate or court for taking cognizance of the 
scheduled offence, as the case may be.] 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The authority, who has been authorised under sub-section (1) shall, 
immediately after search and seizure, forward a copy of the reasons so recorded 
along with material in his possession, referred to in that sub-section, to the 
Adjudicating Authority in a sealed envelope, in the manner, as may be prescribed 
and such Adjudicating Authority shall keep such reasons and material for such 
period, as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where an authority, upon information obtained during survey under section 
16, is satisfied that any evidence shall be or is likely to be concealed or 
tampered with, he may, for reasons to be recorded in writing, enter and search 
the building or place where such evidence is located and seize that evidence: 

 Provided that no authorisation referred to in sub-section (1) shall be 
required for search under this sub-section. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The authority, seizing any record or property under this section shall, 
within a period of thirty days from such seizure, file an application, 
requesting for retention of such record or property, before the Adjudicating 
Authority. 






 
 <subsection><number>a</number> Paragraph 1 of Part A and Part B of the Schedule, a report 
  has been forwarded to a Magistrate under section 173 of the Code of Criminal 
  Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974); or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> Paragraph 2 of Part A of the Schedule, a police report or 
  a complaint has been filed for taking cognizance of an offence by the Special 
  Court constituted under sub-section (1) of section 36 of the Narcotic Drugs 
  and Psychotropic Substances Act, 1985 (61 of 1985).”. 
</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>18</number> Search of persons. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> If an authority, authorised in 
this behalf by the Central Government by general or special order, has reason to 
believe (the reason for such belief to be recorded in writing) that any person 
has secreted about his person or in anything under his possession, ownership or 
control, any record or proceeds of crime which may be useful for or relevant to 
any proceedings under this Act, he may search that person and seize such record 
or property which may be useful for or relevant to any proceedings under this 
Act: 
 <footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[Provided that no search of any person shall be made unless, in 
relation to the scheduled offence, a report has been forwarded to a Magistrate 
under section 173 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), or a 
complaint has been filed by a person authorised to investigate the offence 
mentioned in the Schedule, before a Magistrate or court for taking cognizance of 
the scheduled offence, as the case may be.] 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The authority, who has been authorised under sub-section (1) shall, 
immediately after search and seizure, forward a copy of the reasons so recorded 
along with material in his possession, referred to in that sub-section, to the 
Adjudicating Authority in a sealed envelope, in the manner, as may be prescribed 
and such Adjudicating Authority shall keep such reasons and material for such 
period, as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where an authority is about to search any person, he shall, if such 
person so requires, take such person within twenty-four hours to the nearest 
gazetted officer, superior in rank to him, or a Magistrate: 
 Provided that the period of twenty-four hours shall exclude the time 
necessary for the journey undertaken to take such person to the nearest gazetted 
officer, superior in rank to him, or Magistrate's Court. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> If the requisition under sub-section (3) is made, the authority shall not 
detain the person for more than twenty-four hours prior to taking him before the 
Gazetted Officer superior in rank to him, or the Magistrate referred to in that 
sub-section: 
 Provided that the period of twenty-four hours shall exclude the time 
necessary for the journey from the place of detention to the office of the 
Gazetted Officer, superior in rank to him, or the Magistrate's Court. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Gazetted Officer or the Magistrate before whom any such person is 
brought shall, if he sees no reasonable ground for search, forthwith discharge 
such person but otherwise shall direct that search be made. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> Before making the search under sub-section (1) or sub-section (5) the 
authority shall call upon two or more persons to attend and witness the search, 
and the search shall be made in the presence of such persons. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> The authority shall prepare a list of record or property seized in the 
course of the search and obtain the signatures of the witnesses on the list. 

 </section><section><number>8</number> No female shall be searched by any one except a female. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> The Authority shall record the statement of the person searched under 
sub-section (1) or sub-section (5) in respect of the records or proceeds of 
crime found or seized in the course of the search: 
 <footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[***] 
 </section><section><number>10</number> The authority seizing any record or property under sub-section (1) 
shall, within a period of thirty days from such seizure, file an application 
requesting for retention of such record or property, before the Adjudicating 
Authority. 






 
 <subsection><number>a</number> Paragraph 1 of Part A or Paragraph 1 or Paragraph 2 or 
  Paragraph 3 or Paragraph 4 or Paragraph 5 of Part B of the Schedule, a report 
  has been forwarded to a Magistrate under section 173 of the Code of Criminal 
  Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974); or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> Paragraph 2 of Part A of the Schedule, a police report or 
  a complaint has been filed for taking cognizance of an offence by the Special 
  Court constituted under sub-section (1) of section 36 of the Narcotic Drugs 
  and Psychotropic Substances Act, 1985 (61 of 1985).”. 
</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> Power to 
    arrest.—
<section><number>1</number> If the Director, 
    Deputy Director, Assistant Director, or any other officer authorised in this 
    behalf by the Central Government by general or special order, has on the 
    basis of material in his possession reason to believe (the reason for such 
    belief to be recorded in writing) that any person has been guilty of an 
    offence punishable under this Act, he may arrest such person and shall, as 
    soon as may be, inform him of the grounds for such arrest. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Director, Deputy Director, Assistant Director or any other officer shall, 
    immediately after arrest of such person under sub-section (1), forward a 
    copy of the order, along with the material in his possession, referred to in 
    that sub-section, to the Adjudicating Authority, in a sealed envelope, in 
    the manner, as may be prescribed and such Adjudicating Authority shall keep 
    such order and material for such period, as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every 
    person arrested under sub-section (1) shall within twenty-four hours, be 
    taken to a Judicial Magistrate or a Metropolitan Magistrate, as the case may 
    be, having jurisdiction: 
 
Provided that 
    the period of twenty-four hours shall exclude the time necessary for the 
    journey from the place of arrest to the Magistrate’s Court. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> 
    Retention of property.—
<section><number>1</number> Where 
    any property has been seized under section 17 or section 18, and the officer 
    authorised by the Director in this behalf has, on the basis of material in 
    his possession, reason to believe (the reason for such belief to be recorded 
    by him in writing) that such property is required to be retained for the 
    purposes of adjudication under section 8 such property may be retained for a 
    period not exceeding three months from the end of the month in which such 
    property was seized. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The officer 
    authorised by the Director immediately after he has passed an order for 
    retention of the property for purposes of adjudication under section 8 shall 
    forward a copy of the order along with the material in his possession, 
    referred to in sub-section (1), to the Adjudicating Authority, in a sealed 
    envelop in the manner as may be prescribed and such Adjudicating Authority 
    shall keep such order and material for such period as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On the 
    expiry of the period specified in sub-section (1), the property shall be 
    returned to the person from whom such property was seized unless the 
    Adjudicating Authority permits retention of such property beyond the said 
    period. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Adjudicating Authority, before authorising the retention of such property 
    beyond the period specified in sub-section (1), shall satisfy himself that 
    the property is prima facie involved in money-laundering and the 
    property is required for the purposes of adjudication under section 8. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> After 
    passing the order of confiscation under sub-section (6) of section 8, the 
    Adjudicating Authority shall direct the release of all properties other than 
    the properties involved in money-laundering to the person from whom such 
    properties were seized.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (5), the Director or any 
    officer authorised by him in this behalf may withhold the release of any 
    property until filing of appeal under section 26 or forty-five days from the 
    date of order under sub-section (5), whichever is earlier, if he is of the 
    opinion that such property is relevant for the proceedings before the 
    Appellate Tribunal. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>21</number> 
    Retention of records.—
<section><number>1</number> Where 
    any records have been seized under section 17 or section 18, and the 
    Investigating Officer or any other officer authorised by the Director in 
    this behalf has reason to believe that any of such records are required to 
    be retained for any inquiry under this Act, he may retain such records for a 
    period not exceeding three months from the end of the month in which such 
    records were seized. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The person, 
    from whom records were seized, shall be entitled to obtain copies of records 
    retained under sub-section (1). 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On the 
    expiry of the period specified under sub-section (1), the records shall be 
    returned to the person from whom such records were seized unless the 
    Adjudicating Authority permits retention of such records beyond the said 
    period. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Adjudicating Authority, before authorising the retention of such records 
    beyond the period mentioned in sub-section (1), shall satisfy himself that 
    the records are required for the purposes of adjudication under section 8. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> After 
    passing of an order of confiscation under sub-section (6) of section 8, the 
    Adjudicating Authority shall direct the release of the records to the person 
    from whom such records were seized. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (5), the Director or any 
    officer authorised by him in this behalf may withhold the release of any 
    records until filing of appeal under section 26 or after forty-five days 
    from the date of order under sub-section (5), whichever is earlier, if he is 
    of the opinion that such records are relevant for the proceedings before the 
    Appellate Tribunal. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Presumption as to records or property in certain cases.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where any records or property are or is found in the possession or control 
    of any person in the course of a survey or a search, it shall be presumed 
    that— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    such records or property 
    belong or belongs to such person; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    the contents of such 
    records are true; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    the signature and 
    every other part of such records which purport to be in the handwriting of 
    any particular person or which may reasonably be assumed to have been signed 
    by, or to be in the handwriting of, any particular person, are in that 
    person’s handwriting, and in the case of a record, stamped, executed or 
    attested, that it was executed or attested by the person by whom it purports 
    to have been so stamped, executed or attested.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any 
    records have been received from any place outside India, duly authenticated 
    by such authority or person and in such manner as may be prescribed, in the 
    course of proceedings under this Act, the Special Court, the Appellate 
    Tribunal or the Adjudicating Authority, as the case may be, shall— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    presume, that the 
    signature and every other part of such record, which purports to be in the 
    handwriting of any particular person or which the court may reasonably 
    assume to have been signed by, or to be in the handwriting of, any 
    particular person, is in that person’s handwriting; and in the case of a 
    record executed or attested, that it was executed or attested by the person 
    by whom it purports to have been so executed or attested;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    admit the document in 
    evidence, notwithstanding that it is not duly stamped, if such document is 
    otherwise admissible in evidence.

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> 
    Presumption in inter-connected transactions.—Where 
    money-laundering involves two or more inter-connected transactions and one 
    or more such transactions is or are proved to be involved in 
    money-laundering, then for the purposes of adjudication or confiscation 
    under section 8, it shall unless otherwise proved to the satisfaction of the 
    Adjudicating Authority, be presumed that the remaining transactions form 
    part of such inter-connected transactions.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> Burden 
    of Proof.—When a person is accused 
    of having committed the offence under section 3, the burden of proving that 
    proceeds of crime are untainted property shall be on the accused.
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Establishment of Appellate Tribunal.—The 
    Central Government shall, by notification, establish an Appellate Tribunal 
    to hear appeals against the orders of the Adjudicating Authority and the 
    authorities under this Act.
  





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>26</number> Appeals 
    to Appellate Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> Save as 
    otherwise provided in sub-section (3), the Director or any person aggrieved 
    by an order made by the Adjudicating Authority under this Act, may prefer an 
    appeal to the Appellate Tribunal. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any banking 
    company, financial institution or intermediary aggrieved by any order of the 
    Director made under sub-section (2) of section 13, may prefer an appeal to 
    the Appellate Tribunal. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every 
    appeal preferred under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) shall be filed 
    within a period of forty-five days from the date on which a copy of the 
    order made by the Adjudicating Authority or Director is received and it 
    shall be in such form and be accompanied by such fee as may be prescribed: 
 
Provided that 
    the Appellate Tribunal may after giving an opportunity of being heard 
    entertain an appeal after the expiry of the said period of forty-five days 
    if it is satisfied that there was sufficient cause for not filing it within 
    that period. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> On receipt 
    of an appeal under sub-section (1), or sub-section (2), the Appellate 
    Tribunal may, after giving the parties to the appeal an opportunity of being 
    heard, pass such orders thereon as it thinks fit, confirming, modifying or 
    setting aside the order appealed against. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Appellate Tribunal shall send a copy of every order made by it to the 
    parties to the appeal and to the concerned Adjudicating Authority or the 
    Director, as the case may be. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The appeal 
    filed before the Appellate Tribunal under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) 
    shall be dealt with by it as expeditiously as possible and endeavour shall 
    be made by it to dispose of the appeal finally within six months from the 
    date of filing of the appeal. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>27</number> 
    Composition, etc., of Appellate Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Appellate Tribunal shall consist of a Chairperson and two other Members. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to 
    the provisions of this Act,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the jurisdiction of the 
    Appellate Tribunal may be exercised by Benches thereof;  
    
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    a Bench may be 
    constituted by the Chairperson with one or two Members as the Chairperson 
    may deem fit;  
    
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the Benches of the 
    Appellate Tribunal shall ordinarily sit at New Delhi and at such other 
    places as the Central Government may, in consultation with the Chairperson, 
    by notification, specify;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the Central Government 
    shall, by notification, specify the areas in relation to which each Bench of 
    the Appellate Tribunal may exercise jurisdiction.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (2), the Chairperson may 
    transfer a Member from one Bench to another Bench. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If at any 
    stage of hearing of any case or matter it appears to the Chairperson or a 
    Member that the case or matter is of such a nature that it ought to be heard 
    by a Bench consisting of two Members, the case or matter may be transferred 
    by the Chairperson or, as the case may be referred to him for transfer, to 
    such Bench as the Chairperson may deem fit. 

 
  


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>28</number> Qualifications for appointment. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> A person shall not 
be qualified for appointment as Chairperson unless he is or has been a Judge of 
the Supreme Court or of a <footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[High Court or is qualified to be a Judge 
of the High Court]. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> A person shall not be qualified for appointment as a Member unless he— 

 <footcitenum>20</footcitenum>[***] 
 
 <subsection><number>b</number> has been a Member of the Indian Legal Service and has held a post in 
  Grade I of that Service for at least three years; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> has been a member of the Indian Revenue Service and has held the post 
  of Commissioner of Income-tax or equivalent post in that Service for at least 
  three years; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> has been a member of the Indian Economic Service and has held the post 
  of Joint Secretary or equivalent post in that Service for at least three 
  years; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> has been a member of the Indian Customs and Central Excise Service and 
  has held the post of a Joint Secretary or equivalent post in that Service for 
  at least three years; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> has been in the practice of accountancy as a chartered accountant under 
  the Chartered Accountants Act, 1949 (38 of 1949) or as a registered accountant 
  under any law for the time being in force or partly as a registered accountant 
  and partly as a chartered accountant for at least ten years: 
 Provided that one of the members of the Appellate Tribunal shall be from 
  category mentioned in clause (f); or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> has been a member of the Indian Audit and Accounts Service and has held 
  the post of Joint Secretary or equivalent post in that Service for at least 
  three years. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> No sitting Judge of the Supreme Court or of a High Court shall be 
appointed under this section except after consultation with the Chief Justice of 
India. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>21</footcitenum>[<number>4</number> The Chairperson or a Member holding a post as such in any 
other Tribunal, established under any law for the time being in force, in 
addition to his being the Chairperson or a Member of that Tribunal, may be 
appointed as the Chairperson or a Member, as the case may be, of the Appellate 
Tribunal under this Act.] 




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>22</footcitenum>[<number>29</number> 
    Term of office.—[Rep. 
    by the Money-Laundering (Amendment) Act, 2005, sec. 4.]
 
 








 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>30</number> 
    Conditions of service.—The 
    salary and allowances payable to and the other 
<footcitenum>23</footcitenum>[terms and 
    conditions of service (including tenure of office)] of the Chairperson and 
    other Members shall be such as may be prescribed:
 
Provided 
    that neither the salary and allowances nor the other 
<footcitenum>23</footcitenum>[terms 
    and conditions of service (including tenure of office)] of the Chairperson 
    or any other Member shall be varied to his disadvantage after appointment.
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>31</number> 
    Vacancies.—If, for reason other 
    than temporary absence, any vacancy occurs in the office of the Chairperson 
    or any other Member, then the Central Government shall appoint another 
    person in accordance with the provisions of this Act to fill the vacancy and 
    the proceedings may be continued before the Appellate Tribunal from the 
    stage at which the vacancy is filled. 

 
  


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>32</number> Resignation and removal. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The Chairperson or any 
other Member may, by notice in writing under his hand addressed to the Central 
Government, resign his office: 
 Provided that the Chairperson or any other Member shall, unless he is 
permitted by the Central Government to relinquish his office sooner, continue to 
hold office until the expiry of three months from the date of receipt of such 
notice or until a person duly appointed as his successor enters upon his office 
or until the expiry of his term of office, whichever is the earliest. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Chairperson or any other Member shall not be removed from his office 
except by an order made by the Central Government on the ground of proved 
misbehaviour or incapacity, after an inquiry made by a person appointed by the 
President in which such Chairperson or any other Member concerned had been 
informed of the charges against him and given a reasonable opportunity of being 
heard in respect of those charges: 
 <footcitenum>24</footcitenum>[Provided that the Chief Justice of India shall be consulted 
before removal of the Chairperson or a Member who was appointed on the 
recommendation of the Chief Justice of India.] 

</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>33</number> Member 
    to act as Chairperson in certain circumstances.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In the event of the occurrence of any vacancy in the office of the 
    Chairperson by reason of his death, resignation or otherwise, the 
    senior-most Member, shall act as the Chairperson until the date on which a 
    new Chairperson, appointed in accordance with the provisions of this Act to 
    fill such vacancy, enters upon his office. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When the 
    Chairperson is unable to discharge his functions owing to absence, illness 
    or any other cause, the senior-most Member shall discharge the functions of 
    the Chairperson until the date on which the Chairperson resumes his duties. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>34</number> Staff of 
    Appellate Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Central Government shall provide the Appellate Tribunal with such officers 
    and employees as that Government may think fit. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    officers and employees of the Appellate Tribunal shall discharge their 
    functions under the general superintendence of the Chairperson. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    salaries and allowances and other conditions of service of the officers and 
    employees of the Appellate Tribunal shall be such as may be prescribed. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>35</number> 
    Procedure and powers of Appellate Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Appellate Tribunal shall not be bound by the procedure laid down by the 
    Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) but shall be guided by the 
    principles of natural justice and, subject to the other provisions of this 
    Act, the Appellate Tribunal shall have powers to regulate its own procedure. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Appellate Tribunal shall have, for the purposes of discharging its functions 
    under this Act, the same powers as are vested in a civil court under the 
    Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) while trying a suit, in respect of 
    the following matters, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    summoning and enforcing 
    the attendance of any person and examining him on oath;  
    
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    requiring the discovery 
    and production of documents;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    receiving evidence on 
    affidavits;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    subject to the 
    provisions of sections 123 and 124 of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 
    1872), requisitioning any public record or document or copy of such record 
    or document from any office;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    issuing commissions for 
    the examination of witnesses or documents;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    reviewing its decisions;
     
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    dismissing a 
    representation for default or deciding it ex parte;  
    
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    setting aside any order 
    of dismissal of any representation for default or any order passed by it 
    ex parte; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    any other matter, which 
    may be, prescribed by the Central Government.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> An order 
    made by the Appellate Tribunal under this Act shall be executable by the 
    Appellate Tribunal as a decree of civil court and, for this purpose, the 
    Appellate Tribunal shall have all the powers of a civil court. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (3), the Appellate 
    Tribunal may transmit any order made by it to a civil court having local 
    jurisdiction and such civil court shall execute the order as if it were a 
    decree made by that court. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> All 
    proceedings before the Appellate Tribunal shall be deemed to be judicial 
    proceedings within the meaning of sections 193 and 228 of the Indian Penal 
    Code, 1860 (45 of 1860) and the Appellate Tribunal shall be deemed to be a 
    civil court for the purposes of sections 345 and 346 of the Code of Criminal 
    Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974). 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>36</number> 
    Distribution of business amongst Benches.—Where 
    any Benches are constituted, the Chairperson may, from time to time, by 
    notification, make provisions as to the distribution of the business of the 
    Appellate Tribunal amongst the Benches and also provide for the matters 
    which may be dealt with by each Bench. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>37</number> Power of 
    Chairperson to transfer cases.—On 
    the application of any of the parties and after notice to the parties, and 
    after hearing such of them as he may desire to be heard, or on his own 
    motion without such notice, the Chairperson may transfer any case pending 
    before one Bench, for disposal, to any other Bench. 

 
  


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>38</number> Decision to be by majority. </title>—If the Members of a Bench 
consisting of two Members differ in opinion on any point, they shall state the 
point or points on which they differ, and make a reference to the Chairperson 
who shall either hear the point or points himself or refer the case for hearing 
on such point or points by <footcitenum>25</footcitenum>[third Member] of the Appellate Tribunal 
and such point or points shall be decided according to the opinion of the 
majority of the Members of the Appellate Tribunal who have heard the case, 
including those who first heard it. 

</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>39</number> Right of 
    appellant to take assistance of authorised representative and of Government 
    to appoint presenting officers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A person preferring an appeal to the Appellate Tribunal under this Act may 
    either appear in person or take the assistance of any authorised 
    representative of his choice to present his case before the Appellate 
    Tribunal. 
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    this sub-section, the expression “authorised representative” shall have the 
    same meaning as assigned to it under sub-section (2) of section 288 of the 
    Income-tax Act, 1961 (43 of 1961). 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Central 
    Government or the Director may authorise one or more authorised 
    representatives or any of its officers to act as presenting officers and 
    every person so authorised may present the case with respect to any appeal 
    before the Appellate Tribunal. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>40</number> Members, 
    etc., to be public servants.—The 
    Chairperson, Members and other officers and employees of the Appellate 
    Tribunal, the Adjudicating Authority, Director and the officers subordinate 
    to him shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of section 
    21 of the Indian Penal Code, 1860 (45 of 1860). 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>41</number> Civil 
    court not to have jurisdiction.—No 
    civil court shall have jurisdiction to entertain any suit or proceeding in 
    respect of any matter which the Director, an Adjudicating Authority or the 
    Appellate Tribunal is empowered by or under this Act to determine and no 
    injunction shall be granted by any court or other authority in respect of 
    any action taken or to be taken in pursuance of any power conferred by or 
    under this Act. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>42</number> Appeal 
    to High Court.—Any person 
    aggrieved by any decision or order of the Appellate Tribunal may file an 
    appeal to the High Court within sixty days from the date of communication of 
    the decision or order of the Appellate Tribunal to him on any question of 
    law or fact arising out of such order: 
 
Provided that 
    the High Court may, if it is satisfied that the appellant was prevented by 
    sufficient cause from filing the appeal within the said period, allow it to 
    be filed within a further period not exceeding sixty days. 
 
Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section, "High Court" means— 
 <section>
<number>i</number>    The High Court within 
    the jurisdiction of which the aggrieved party ordinarily resides or carries 
    on business or personally works for gain; and  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    Where the Central 
    Government is the aggrieved party, the High Court within the jurisdiction of 
    which the respondent, or in a case where there are more than one respondent, 
    any of the respondents, ordinarily resides or carries on business or 
    personally works for gain. 
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>44</number> Offences 
    triable by Special Courts.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 
    (2 of 1974),—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the sucheduled offence 
    and offence punishable under section 4 shall be triable only by the Special 
    Court constituted for the area in which the offence has been committed:
 
      Provided that 
    the Special Court, trying a scheduled offence before the commencement of 
    this Act, shall continue to try such scheduled offence; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    a Special Court may,
    <footcitenum>26</footcitenum>[***] upon a complaint made by an authority authorised in this 
    behalf under this Act take cognizance of the offence for which the accused 
    is committed to it for trial. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Nothing 
    contained in this section shall be deemed to affect the special powers of 
    the High Court regarding bail under section 439 of the Code of Criminal 
    Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) and the High Court may exercise such powers 
    including the power under clause (b) of sub-section (1) of that section as 
    if the reference to "Magistrate" in that section includes also a reference 
    to a "Special Court" designated under section 43.
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>45</number> 
    Offences to be cognizable and non-bailable.—
<section><number>1</number>
    

    1[Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), no 
    person accused of an offence punishable for a term of imprisonment of more 
    than three years under Part A of the Schedule shall be released on bail or 
    on his own bond unless—]
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    the Public Prosecutor 
    has been given an opportunity to oppose the application for such release; 
    and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    where the Public 
    Prosecutor opposes the application, the court is satisfied that there are 
    reasonable grounds for believing that he is not guilty of such offence and 
    that he is not likely to commit any offence while on bail: 
 
Provided that a 
    person who is under the age of sixteen years or is a woman or is sick or 
    infirm, may be released on bail, if the special court so directs: 
 
Provided 
    further that the Special Court shall not take cognizance of any offence 
    punishable under section 4 except upon a complaint in writing made by— 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    the Director; or  
    
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    any officer of the 
    Central Government or State Government authorised in writing in this behalf 
    by the Central Government by a general or a special order made in this 
    behalf by that Government.  
 </subsection></section><section>

<footcitenum>28</footcitenum>[<number>1A</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 
    (2 of 1974), or any other provision of this Act, no police officer shall 
    investigate into an offence under this Act unless specifically authorised, 
    by the Central Government by a general or special order, and, subject to 
    such conditions as may be prescribed.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    limitation on granting of bail specified in <footcitenum>29</footcitenum>[***] sub-section 
    (1) is in addition to the limitations under the Code of Criminal Procedure, 
    1973 (2 of 1974) or any other law for the time being in force on granting of 
    bail.
 
 
 











 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>46</number> 
    Application of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 to proceedings before 
    Special Court.—
<section><number>1</number> Save as 
    otherwise provided in this Act, the provisions of the Code of Criminal 
    Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) (including the provisions as to bails or bonds), 
    shall apply to the proceedings before a Special Court and for the purposes 
    of the said provisions, the Special Court shall be deemed to be a Court of 
    Session and the persons conducting the prosecution before the Special Court, 
    shall be deemed to be a Public Prosecutor: 
 
Provided that 
    the Central Government may also appoint for any case or class or group of 
    cases a Special Public Prosecutor. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A person 
    shall not be qualified to be appointed as a Public Prosecutor or a Special 
    Public Prosecutor under this section unless he has been in practice as an 
    Advocate for not less than seven years, under the Union or a State, 
    requiring special knowledge of law. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every 
    person appointed as a Public Prosecutor or a Special Public Prosecutor under 
    this section shall be deemed to be a Public Prosecutor within the meaning of 
    clause (u) of section 2 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) 
    and the provisions of that Code shall have effect accordingly. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>47</number> Appeal 
    and revision.—The High Court may 
    exercise, so far as may be applicable, all the powers conferred by Chapter 
    XXIX or Chapter XXX of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), on 
    a High Court, as if a Special Court within the local limits of the 
    jurisdiction of the High Court were a Court of Session trying cases within 
    the local limits of the jurisdiction of the High Court. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>48</number> 
    Authorities under the Act.—There 
    shall be the following classes of authorities for the purposes of this Act, 
    namely:—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    Director or Additional 
    Director or Joint Director,  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    Deputy Director,  
    
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    Assistant Director, and  
    
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    such other class of 
    officers as may be appointed for the purposes of this Act. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>49</number> 
    Appointment and powers of authorities and other officers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may appoint such persons as it thinks fit to be 
    authorities for the purposes of this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Without 
    prejudice to the provisions of sub-section (1), the Central Government may 
    authorise the Director or an Additional Director or a Joint Director or a 
    Deputy Director or an Assistant Director appointed under that sub-section to 
    appoint other authorities below the rank of an Assistant Director. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Subject to 
    such conditions and limitations as the Central Government may impose, an 
    authority may exercise the powers and discharge the duties conferred or 
    imposed on it under this Act.
 








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>50</number> Powers 
    of authorities regarding summons, production of documents and to give 
    evidence, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> The Director 
    shall, for the purposes of section 13, have the same powers as are vested in 
    a civil court under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) while 
    trying a suit in respect of the following matters, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    discovery and 
    inspection;
     
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    enforcing the attendance 
    of any person, including any officer of a banking company or a financial 
    institution or a company, and examining him on oath;  
    
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    compelling the 
    production of records; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    receiving evidence on 
    affidavits; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    issuing commissions for 
    examination of witnesses and documents; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    any other matter which 
    may be prescribed. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Director, Additional Director, Joint Director, Deputy Director or Assistant 
    Director shall have power to summon any person whose attendance he considers 
    necessary whether to give evidence or to produce any records during the 
    course of any investigation or proceeding under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All the 
    persons so summoned shall be bound to attend in person or through authorised 
    agents, as such officer may direct, and shall be bound to state the truth 
    upon any subject respecting which they are examined or make statements, and 
    produce such documents as may be required.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every 
    proceeding under sub-sections (2) and (3) shall be deemed to be a judicial 
    proceeding within the meaning of section 193 and section 228 of the Indian 
    Penal Code, 1860 (45 of 1860).
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Subject to 
    any rules made in this behalf by the Central Government, any officer 
    referred to in sub-section (2) may impound and retain in his custody for 
    such period, as he thinks fit, any records produced before him in any 
    proceedings under this Act:
 
Provided that 
    an Assistant Director or a Deputy Director shall not—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    impound any records 
    without recording his reasons for so doing; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    retain in his custody 
    any such records for a period exceeding three months, without obtaining the 
    previous approval of the Director.

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>51</number> 
    Jurisdiction of authorities.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The authorities shall exercise all or any of the powers and perform all or 
    any of the functions conferred on, or, assigned, as the case may be, to such 
    authorities by or under this Act or the rules framed thereunder in 
    accordance with such directions as the Central Government may issue for the 
    exercise of powers and performance of the functions by all or any of the 
    authorities. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In issuing 
    the directions or orders referred to in sub-section (1), the Central 
    Government may have regard to any one or more of the following criteria, 
    namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    territorial area; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    classes of persons;  
    
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    classes of cases; and  
    
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    any other criterion specified by the 
    Central Government in this behalf. 
  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>52</number> Power of 
    Central Government to issue directions, etc.—The 
    Central Government may, from time to time, issue such orders, instructions 
    and directions to the authorities as it may deem fit for the proper 
    administration of this Act and such authorities and all other persons 
    employed in execution of this Act shall observe and follow such orders, 
    instructions and directions of the Central Government:
 
Provided that 
    no such orders, instructions or directions shall be issued so as to— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    require any authority to decide a 
    particular case in a particular manner; or  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    interfere with the discretion of the 
    Adjudicating Authority in exercise of his functions. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>53</number> 
    Empowerment of certain officers.—The 
    Central Government may, by a special or general order, empower an officer 
    not below the rank of Director of the Central Government or of a State 
    Government to act as an authority under this Act: 
 
Provided that 
    the Central Government may empower an officer below the rank of Director if 
    the officer of the rank of the Director or above are not available in a 
    particular area. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>54</number> Certain 
    officers to assist in inquiry, etc.—The 
    following officers are hereby empowered and required to assist the 
    authorities in the enforcement of this Act, namely:— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    officers of the Customs and Central 
    Excise Departments;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    officers appointed under sub-section 
    (1) of section 5 of the Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances Act, 1985 
    (61 of 1985); 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    income-tax authorities under 
    sub-section (1) of section 117 of the Income-tax Act, 1961 (43 of 1961);
    
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    officers of the stock exchange 
    recognised under section 4 of the Securities Contracts (Regulation) Act, 
    1956 (42 of 1956); 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    officers of the Reserve Bank of India 
    constituted under sub-section (1) of section 3 of the Reserve Bank of India 
    Act, 1934 (2 of 1934);  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    officers of police;  
    
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    officers of enforcement appointed under 
    sub-section (1) of section 36 of the Foreign Exchange Management Act, 1999 
    (40 of 1999);  
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>    officers of the Securities and Exchange 
    Board of India established under section 3 of the Securities and Exchange 
    Board of India Act, 1992 (15 of 1992);  
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>    officers of any other body corporate 
    constituted or established under a Central Act or a State Act;  
    
 </section><section>
<number>j</number>    such other officers of the Central 
    Government, State Government, local authorities or banking companies as the 
    Central Government may, by notification, specify, in this behalf. 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>55</number> 
    Definitions.—In this Chapter, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    "contracting State" means any country 
    or place outside India in respect of which arrangements have been made by 
    the Central Government with the Government of such country through a treaty 
    or otherwise; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    "identifying" includes establishment of 
    a proof that the property was derived from, or used in the commission of an 
    offence under section 3; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    "tracing" means determining the nature, 
    source, disposition, movement, title or ownership of property.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>56</number> 
    Agreements with foreign countries.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may enter into an agreement with the Government of 
    any country outside India for— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    enforcing the provisions of this Act;  
    
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    exchange of information for the 
    prevention of any offence under this Act or under the corresponding law in 
    force in that country or investigation of cases relating to any offence 
    under this Act, w in force in that country or 
    investigation of cases relating to any offence under this Act," 
 
and may, by notification in the Official 
    Gazette, make such provisions as may be necessary for implementing the 
    agreement.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Central 
    Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that the 
    application of this Chapter in relation to a contracting State with which 
    reciprocal arrangements have been made, shall be subject to such conditions, 
    exceptions or qualifications as are specified in the said notification. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>57</number> Letter of request to a contracting State in 
      certain cases.—
<section><number>1</number> 
      Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act or the Code of Criminal 
      Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) if, in the course of an investigation into an 
      offence or other proceedings under this Act, an application is made to a 
      Special Court by the Investigating Officer or any officer superior in rank 
      to the Investigating Officer that any evidence is required in connection 
      with investigation into an offence or proceedings under this Act and he is 
      of the opinion that such evidence may be available in any place in a 
      contracting State, and the Special Court, on being satisfied that such 
      evidence is required in connection with the investigation into an offence 
      or proceedings under this Act, may issue a letter of request to a court or 
      an authority in the contracting State competent to deal with such request 
      to—
 <subsection><number>i</number>    examine 
      facts and circumstances of the case, 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>    take such 
      steps as the Special Court may specify in such letter of request, and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number>    forward 
      all the evidence so taken or collected to the Special Court issuing such 
      letter of request. 
    
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The letter of request shall be transmitted 
      in such manner as the Central Government may specify in this 
behalf. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every statement recorded or document or 
      thing received under sub-section (1) shall be deemed to be the evidence 
      collected during the course of investigation. 
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>58</number> Assistance to a contracting State in certain 
      cases.—Where a letter of 
      request is received by the Central Government from a court or authority in 
      a contracting State requesting for investigation into an offence or 
      proceedings under this Act and forwarding to such court or authority any 
      evidence connected therewith, the Central Government may forward such 
      letter of request to the Special Court or to any authority under the Act 
      as it thinks fit for execution of such request in accordance with the 
      provisions of this Act or as the case may be, any other law for the time 
      being in force. 
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>59</number> Reciprocal arrangements for processes and 
      assistance for transfer of accused persons.—
<section><number>1</number> Where a Special Court, in relation to an 
      offence punishable under section 4, desires that—
 <subsection><number>a</number>    a summons to 
      an accused person, or 
    
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>    a warrant 
      for the arrest of an accused person, or
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>    a summons to 
      any person requiring him to attend and produce a document or other thing, 
      or to produce a document or other thing, or to produce it, or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>    a 
      search-warrant, 
    
 issued by it shall be served or 
      executed at any place in any contracting State, it shall send such summons 
      or warrant in duplicate in such form, to such Court, Judge or Magistrate 
      through such authorities, as the Central Government may, by notification, 
      specify in this behalf and that Court, Judge or Magistrate, as the case 
      may be, shall cause the same to be executed.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Where a Special Court, in relation to an 
      offence punishable under section 4 has received for service or 
      execution— 
 <subsection><number>a</number>    a summons to 
      an accused person, or 
    
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>    a warrant 
      for the arrest of an accused person, or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>    a summons to 
      any person requiring him to attend and produce a document or other thing, 
      or to produce it, or 
    
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>    a 
      search-warrant, 
    
 issued by a Court, Judge or Magistrate in a 
      contracting State, it shall cause the same to be served or executed as if 
      it were a summons or warrant received by it from another Court in the said 
      territories for service or execution within its local jurisdiction; and 
      where—
 <subsubsection><number>i</number>    a warrant of 
      arrest has been executed, the person arrested shall, be dealt with in 
      accordance with the procedure specified under section 19; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number>    a search 
      warrant has been executed, the things found in this search shall, so far 
      as possible be dealt with in accordance with the procedure specified under 
      sections 17 and 18: 
    
 Provided that in a case where a summon or search 
      warrant received from a contracting State has been executed, the documents 
      or other things produced or things found in the search shall be forwarded 
      to the Court issuing the summons or search warrant through such authority 
      as the Central Government may, by notification, specify in this 
      behalf. 
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section><number>3</number> Where a person transferred to a contracting 
      State pursuant to sub-section (2) is a prisoner in India, the Special 
      Court or the Central Government may impose such conditions as that Court 
      or Government deems fit. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Where the person transferred to India 
      pursuant to sub-section (1) is a prisoner in a contracting State, the 
      Special Court in India shall ensure that the conditions subject to which 
      the prisoner is transferred to India are complied with and such prisoner 
      shall be kept in such custody subject to such conditions as the Central 
      Government may direct in writing. 
 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>60</number> Attachment, seizure and confiscation, etc., of property in a 
contracting State or India. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Where the Director has made an order 
for attachment of any property under section 5 or where an Adjudicating 
Authority has made an order confirming such attachment or confiscation of any 
property under section 8, and such property is suspected to be in a contracting 
State, the Special Court, on an application by the Director or the Administrator 
appointed under sub-section (1) of section 10, as the case may be, may issue a 
letter of request to a court or an authority in the contracting State for 
execution of such order. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where a letter of request is received by the Central Government from a 
court or an authority in a contracting State requesting attachment or 
confiscation of the property in India, derived or obtained, directly or 
indirectly, by any person from the commission of an offence under section 3 
committed in that contracting State, the Central Government may forward such 
letter of request to the Director, as it thinks fit, for execution in accordance 
with the provisions of this Act. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Director shall, on receipt of a letter of request under section 58 or 
section 59, direct any authority under this Act to take all steps necessary for 
tracing and identifying such property. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The steps referred to in sub-section (3) may include any inquiry, 
investigation or survey in respect of any person, place, property, assets, 
documents, books of account in any bank or public financial institutions or any 
other relevant matters. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Any inquiry, investigation or survey referred to in sub-section (4) shall 
be carried out by an authority mentioned in sub-section (3) in accordance with 
such directions issued in accordance with the provisions of this Act. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The provisions of this Act relating to attachment, adjudication, 
confiscation and vesting of property in Central Government contained in Chapter 
III and survey, searches and seizures contained in Chapter V shall apply to the 
property in respect of which letter of request is received from a court or 
contracting State for attachment or confiscation of property. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>30</footcitenum>[<number>7</number> When any property in India is confiscated as a result of 
execution of a request from a contracting State in accordance with the 
provisions of this Act, the Central Government may either return such property 
to the requesting State or compensate that State by disposal of such property on 
mutually agreed terms that would take into account deduction for reasonable 
expenses incurred in investigation, prosecution or judicial proceedings leading 
to the return or disposal of confiscated property.] 

</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>61</number> Procedure in respect of letter of 
      request.—Every letter of 
      request, summons or warrant, received by the Central Government from and 
      every letter of request, summons or warrant, to be transmitted to a 
      contracting State under this Chapter shall be transmitted to a contracting 
      State or, as the case may be, sent to the concerned Court in India and in 
      such form and in such manner as the Central Government may, by 
      notification, specify in this behalf. 
  
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>62</number> 
    Punishment for vexatious search.—Any 
    authority or officer exercising powers under this Act or any rules made 
    thereunder, who without reasons recorded in writing,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    searches or causes to be searched any 
    building or place; or  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    detains or searches or arrests any 
    person, 
 
shall for every such offence be liable on 
    conviction for imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years or fine 
    which may extend to fifty thousand rupees or both.
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>63</number> 
    Punishment for false information or failure to give information, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person wilfully and maliciously giving false information and so causing 
    an arrest or a search to be made under this Act shall on conviction be 
    liable for imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years or with 
    fine which may extend to fifty thousand rupees or both. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any 
    person,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    being legally bound to state the truth 
    of any matter relating to an offence under section 3, refuses to answer any 
    question put to him by an authority in the exercise of its powers under this 
    Act; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    refuses to sign any statement made by 
    him in the course of any proceedings under this Act, which an authority may 
    legally require to sign; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    to whom a summon is issued under 
    section 50 either to attend to give evidence or produce books of account or 
    other documents at a certain place and time, omits to attend or produce 
    books of account or documents at the place or time, 
 
he shall pay, by way of penalty, a sum which 
    shall not be less than five hundred rupees but which may extend to ten 
    thousand rupees for each such default or failure.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> No order 
    under this section shall be passed by an authority referred to in 
    sub-section (2) unless the person on whom the penalty is proposed to be 
    imposed is given an opportunity of being heard in the matter by such 
    authority.
  


 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>64</number> 
    Cognizance of offences.—
<section><number>1</number> No 
    court shall take cognizance of any offence under section 62 or sub-section 
    (1) of section 63 except with the previous sanction of the Central 
    Government. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Central 
    Government shall, by an order either give sanction or refuse to give 
    sanction within ninety days of the receipt of the request in this behalf. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>65</number> Code of 
    Criminal Procedure, 1973 to apply.—The 
    provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) shall apply, 
    insofar as they are not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, to 
    arrest, search and seizure, attachment, confiscation, investigation, 
    prosecution and all other proceedings under this Act. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>66</number> 
    Disclosure of information.—The 
    Director or any other authority specified by him by a general or special 
    order in this behalf may furnish or cause to be furnished to— 
 <section>
<number>i</number>    any officer, authority or body 
    performing any functions under any law relating to imposition of any tax, 
    duty or cess or to dealings in foreign exchange, or prevention of illicit 
    traffic in the narcotic drugs and psychotropic substances under the Narcotic 
    Drugs and Psychotropic Substances Act, 1985 (61 of 1985); or  
    
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    such other officer, authority or body 
    performing functions under any other law as the Central Government may, if 
    in its opinion it is necessary so to do in the public interest, specify, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, in this behalf, any information 
    received or obtained by such Director or any other authority, specified by 
    him in the performance of their functions under this Act, as may, in the 
    opinion of the Director or the other authority, so specified by him, be 
    necessary for the purpose of the officer, authority or body specified in 
    clause (i) or clause (ii) to perform his or its functions under that law. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>67</number> Bar of 
    suits in civil courts.—No suit 
    shall be brought in any civil court to set aside or modify any proceeding 
    taken or order made under this Act and no prosecution, suit or other 
    proceeding shall lie against the Government or any officer of the Government 
    for anything done or intended to be done in good faith under this Act.
 



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>68</number> Notice, 
    etc., not to be invalid on certain grounds.—No 
    notice, summons, order, document or other proceeding, furnished or made or 
    issued or taken or purported to have been furnished or made or issued or 
    taken in pursuance of any of the provisions of this Act shall be invalid, or 
    shall be deemed to be invalid merely by reason of any mistake, defect or 
    omission in such notice, summons, order, document or other proceeding if 
    such notice, summons, order, document or other proceeding is in substance 
    and effect in conformity with or according to the intent and purpose of this 
    Act. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>69</number> Recovery 
    of fines.—Where any fine imposed 
    on any person under section 13 or section 63 is not paid within six months 
    from the day of imposition of fine, the Director or any other officer 
    authorised by him in this behalf may proceed to recover the amount from the 
    said person in the same manner as prescribed in Schedule II of the 
    Income-tax Act, 1961 (43 of 1961) for the recovery of arrears and he or any 
    officer authorised by him in this behalf shall have all the powers of the 
    Tax Recovery Officer mentioned in the said Schedule for the said purpose. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>70</number> Offences 
    by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> Where a person 
    committing a contravention of any of the provisions of this Act or of any 
    rule, direction or order made thereunder is a company, every person who, at 
    the time the contravention was committed, was in charge of, and was 
    responsible to the company, for the conduct of the business of the company 
    as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the contravention 
    and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly: 
 
Provided that 
    nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to 
    punishment if he proves that the contravention took place without his 
    knowledge or that he exercised all due diligence to prevent such 
    contravention. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where a contravention 
    of any of the provisions of this Act or of any rule, direction or order made 
    thereunder has been committed by a company and it is proved that the 
    contravention has taken place with the consent or connivance of, or is 
    attributable to any neglect on the part of any director, manager, secretary 
    or other officer of any company, such director, manager, secretary or other 
    officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of the contravention and shall be 
    liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly. 
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    this saction,— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    “company” means any body corporate and 
    includes a firm or other association of individuals; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    “director”, in relation to a firm, 
    means a partner in the firm. 
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>71</number> Act to 
    have overriding effect.—The 
    provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
    inconsistent therewith contained in any other law for the time being in 
    force. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>72</number> 
    Continuation of proceedings in the event of death or insolvency.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    any property of a person has been 
    attached under section 8 and no appeal against the order attaching such 
    property has been preferred; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    any appeal has been preferred to the 
    Appellate Tribunal, and— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    in a case referred to in clause (a) 
    such person dies or is adjudicated an insolvent before preferring an appeal 
    to the Appellate Tribunal; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    in a case referred to in clause (b), 
    such person dies or is adjudicated an insolvent during the pendency of the 
    appeal, 
 
then, it shall be lawful for the legal 
    representatives of such person or the official assignee or the official 
    receiver, as the case may be, to prefer an appeal to the Appellate Tribunal 
    or as the case may be, to continue the appeal before the Appellate Tribunal, 
    in place of such person and the provisions of section 26 shall, so far as 
    may be, apply, or continue to apply, to such appeal.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    after passing of a decision or order by 
    the Appellate Tribunal, no appeal has been preferred to the High Court under 
    section 42; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    any such appeal has been preferred to 
    the High Court, 
 
then—
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    in a case referred to in clause (a), 
    the person entitled to file the appeal dies or is adjudicated an insolvent 
    before preferring an appeal to the High Court, or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    in a case referred to in clause (b), 
    the person who had filed the appeal dies or is adjudicated an insolvent 
    during the pendency of the appeal before the High Court,  
    
 
then, it shall be lawful for the legal 
    representatives of such person, or the official assignee or the official 
    receiver, as the case may be, to prefer an appeal to the High Court or to 
    continue the appeal before the High Court in place of such person and the 
    provision of section 42 shall, so far as may be, apply or continue to apply 
    to such appeal.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The powers 
    of the official assignee or the official receiver under sub-section (1) or 
    sub-section (2) shall be exercised by him subject to the provisions of the 
    Presidency-towns Insolvency Act, 1909 (3 of 1909) or the Provincial 
    Insolvency Act, 1920 (5 of 1920), as the case may be. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>73</number> Power to 
    make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
    Government may, by notification, make rules for carrying out the provisions 
    of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the form in which records referred to 
    in this Act may be maintained;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the manner in which the order and the 
    material referred to in sub-section (2) of section 5 to be maintained;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    matters in respect of experience of 
    Members under sub-section (3) of section 6; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the salaries and allowances payable to 
    the other terms and conditions of service of Members of the Adjudicating 
    Authority under sub-section (9) of section 6; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the salaries and allowances payable to 
    and other terms and conditions of service of the officers and employees of 
    the Adjudicating Authority under sub-section (3) of section 7; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    the manner in which and the conditions 
    subject to which the properties confiscated may be received and managed 
    under sub-section (2) of section 10; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    the additional matters in respect of 
    which the Adjudicating Authority may exercise the powers of a civil court 
    under clause (f) of sub-section (1) of section 11;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    the nature and value of transactions in 
    respect of which records shall be maintained under clause (a) of sub-section 
    (1) of section 12;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    the time within which the information 
    of transactions under clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 12 shall be 
    furnished;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>    the manner in which records shall be 
    verified and maintained by banking companies, financial institutions and 
    intermediaries under clause (c) of sub-section (1) of section 12;  
    
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>    the procedure and the manner of 
    maintaining and furnishing information under sub-section (1) of section 12 
    as required under section 15; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>    the manner in which the reasons and the 
    material referred to in sub-section (2) of section 16 shall be maintained;  
    
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number>    the rules relating to search and 
    seizure under sub-section (1) of section 17; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>n</number>    the manner in which the reasons and the 
    material referred to in sub-section (2) of section 17 shall be maintained; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>o</number>    the manner in which the reasons and the 
    material referred to in sub-section (2) of section 18 shall be maintained; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>p</number>    the manner in which the order and the 
    material referred to in sub-section (2) of section 19 shall be maintained.  
    
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>q</number>    the manner in which records 
    authenticated outside India may be received under sub-section (2) of section 
    22;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>r</number>    the form of appeal and the fee for 
    filing such appeal, under sub-section (3) of section 26;  
    
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>s</number>    the salary and allowances payable to 
    and the other <footcitenum>31</footcitenum>[terms and conditions of service (including tenure 
    of office)] of the Chairperson and other Members of the Appellate Tribunal 
    under section 30; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>t</number>    the salaries and allowances and the 
    conditions of service of the officers and employees of the Appellate 
    Tribunal under sub-section (3) of section 34; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>u</number>    the additional matters in respect of 
    which the Appellate Tribunal may exercise the powers of a civil court under 
    clause (i) of sub-section (2) of section 35;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<footcitenum>32</footcitenum>[<number>ua</number>    
    conditions subject to which a police officer may be authorised to 
    investigate into an offence under sub-section (1A) of section 45;]2[(ua) 
    conditions subject to which a police officer may be authorised to 
    investigate into an offence under sub-section (1A) of section 45;]" 
 <subsubsection>
<number>v</number>    the additional matters in respect of 
    which the authorities may exercise powers of a civil court under clause (f) 
    of sub-section (1) of section 50;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>w</number>    the rules relating to impounding and 
    custody of records under sub-section (5) of section 50;  
    
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>x</number>    any other matter which is required to 
    be, or may be, prescribed.
 
 






 



</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>74</number> Rules to 
    be laid before Parliament.—Every 
    rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, 
    before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period 
    of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
    successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
    following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses 
    agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the 
    rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
    modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
    such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of 
    anything previously done under that rule.
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>75</number> Power to 
    remove difficulties.—
<section><number>1</number> If any 
    difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the 
    Central Government may, by order, published in the Official Gazette, make 
    such provisions not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act as may 
    appear to be necessary for removing the difficulty:
 
Provided that 
    no order shall be made under this section after the expiry of two years from 
    the commencement of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every order 
    made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, 
    before each House of Parliament.
 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Came into force on 
    1-7-2005, vide G.S.R. 436(E), dated 1st July, 2005, published in the 
    Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 1st July, 2005.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Ins. by Act 21 of 2009, sec. 2(i).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Ins. by Act 21 of 2009, sec. 2(ii).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Subs. by Act 21 of 2009, sec. 2(iii), for “a non-banking 
financial company”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Ins. by Act 20 of 2005, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 1-7-2005 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Ins. by Act 21 of 2009, sec. 2(iv).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Ins. by Act 21 of 2009, sec. 2(v).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Subs. by Act 21 of 2009, sec. 2(vi), for sub-clause (ii). 
Sub-clause (ii), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> Subs. by Act 21 of 2009, sec. 3(a), for “ninety days”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> Subs. by Act 21 of 2009, sec. 3(b), for the proviso. The 
proviso, before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number> Subs. by Act 21 of 2009, sec. 4(i), for “one or more 
Adjudicating Authorities”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number> Subs. by Act 21 of 2009, sec. 4(ii), for “sixty-two”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number> Subs. by Act 21 of 2009, sec. 5, for “offence under section 
3”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number> Subs. by Act 21 of 2009, sec. 6, for sub-section (2). 
Sub-section (2), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number> Subs. by Act 21 of 2009, sec. 7(i), for “the Director”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number> Subs. by Act 21 of 2009, sec. 7(ii), for the proviso. The 
proviso, before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number> Ins. by Act 21 of 2009, sec. 8(i).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number> Proviso omitted by Act 21 of 2009, sec. 8(ii). Proviso, 
before omission, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number> Subs. by Act 20 of 2005, sec. 3, for “High Court” (w.e.f. 
1-7-2005 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number> Clause (a) omitted by Act 21 of 2009, sec. 9. Clause (a), 
before omission, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number> Ins. by Act 20 of 2005, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-7-2005 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number>   Section “29. 
    Term of office.—The Chairperson and every other Member shall hold office 
    as such for a term of five years from the date on which he enters upon his 
    office:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number>   
    Subs. by Act 20 of 2005, sec. 5, for “terms and conditions of service” (w.e.f. 
    1-7-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number> Ins. by Act 21 of 2009, sec. 10.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number> Subs. by Act 21 of 2009, sec. 11, for “one or more of the 
other Members”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number>   The words “upon 
    perusal of police report of the facts which constitute an offence under this 
    Act or“ omitted by Act 20 of 2005, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 1-7-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number>   Subs. by Act 20 
    of 2005, sec. 7, for “Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of 
    Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974),— tc " 1. Subs. 
    by Act 20 of 2005, sec. 7, for “Notwithstanding anything contained in the 
    Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974),—"</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>28</number>   
    Ins. by Act 20 of 2005, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 1-7-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>29</number>   
    The words “clause (b) of” omitted by Act 20 of 2005, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 
    1-7-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>30</number> Ins. by Act 21 of 2009, sec. 12.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>31</number>   Subs. by Act 20 of 
    2005, sec. 8, “terms and conditions of service” (w.e.f. 1-7-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>32</number>   Ins. by Act 20 of 
    2005, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-7-2005).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>