<act><title>THE POST-GRADUATE MEDICAL EDUCATION REGULATIONS, 20001 </title> 

 <title></title>
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>-
<section><number>1</number>. These regulations may be called The Post-graduate Medical Education Regulations, 2000. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>. They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette. 
  




</section></article> 

 <title></title>
 <article><title><number>2</number> General conditions to be observed by post-graduate teaching Institutions. </title>-
<section><number>i</number> Post-graduate Medical Education in broad specialities shall be of three years duration in the case of degree course and two years in the case of Diploma course after MBBS and in the case of super specialities the duration shall be of three years after MD/MS [***]. 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> Post-graduate curriculum shall be competency based. 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> Learning in Post-graduate programme shall be essentially autonomous and self directed. 
 </section><section><number>iv</number> A combination of both formative and summative assessment is vital for the successful completion of the PG programme. 
 </section><section><number>v</number> A modular approach to the course curriculum is essential for achieving a systematic exposure to the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[various areas concerned with the discipline]. 
 </section><section><number>vi</number> The training of PG students shall involve learning experience 'derived from' or 'targeted to' the needs of the community. It shall, therefore, be necessary to expose the students to community based activities. <title></title>
  



</section></article> 

 <title></title>
 <article><title><number>3</number> Goals and General objectives of Post-graduate Medical Education Programme to be observed by Post-graduate Teaching Institution. </title>- 
 
 
  


</article><article><number>3</number>1 Goal. -The goal of post-graduate medical education shall be to produce competent specialists and/or medical teachers- 
 
 <section><number>i</number> who shall recognize the health needs of the community, and carry out professional obligations ethically and in keeping with the objectives of the national health policy; 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> who shall have mastered most of the competencies pertaining to the speciality, that are required to be practiced at the secondary and the tertiary levels of the health care delivery system; 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> who shall be aware of the contemporary advance and developments in the discipline concerned; 
 </section><section><number>iv</number> who shall have acquired a spirit of scientific inquiry and is oriented to the principles of research methodology and epidemiology; and 
 </section><section><number>v</number> who shall have acquired the basic skills in teaching of the medical and paramedical professionals; 
</section>
 </article><article><number>3</number>2 General objectives of post-graduate training expected from students at the end of post-graduate training. -At the end of the post-graduate training in the discipline concerned the student shall be able to- 
 
 <section><number>i</number> Recognize the importance to the concerned speciality in the context of the health needs of the community and the national priorities in the health section. 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> Practice the speciality concerned ethically and in step with the principles of primary health care. 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> Demonstrate sufficient understanding of the basic sciences relevant to the concerned speciality. 
 </section><section><number>iv</number> Identify social, economic, environmental, biological and emotional determinants of health in a given case, and take them into account while planning therapeutic, rehabilitative, preventive and primitive measure/strategies. 
 </section><section><number>v</number> Diagnose and manage majority of the conditions in the speciality concerned on the basis of clinical assessment, and appropriately selected and conducted investigations. 
 </section><section><number>vi</number> Plan and advise measures for the prevention and rehabilitation of patients suffering from disease and disability related to the speciality. 
 </section><section><number>vii</number> Demonstrate skills in documentation of individual case details as well as morbidity and mortality rate relevant to the assigned situation. 
 </section><section><number>viii</number> Demonstrate empathy and humane approach towards patients and their families and exhibit interpersonal behaviour in accordance with the societal norms and expectation. 
 </section><section><number>ix</number> Play the assigned role in the implementation of national health programme effectively and responsibly. 
 </section><section><number>x</number> Organize and supervise the chosen/assigned health care services demonstrating adequate managerial skills in the clinic/hospital or the field situation. 
 </section><section><number>xi</number> Develop skills as a self-directed learner, recognize continuing education needs; select and use appropriate learning resources. 
 <subsection><number>xii</number> Demonstrate competence in basic concepts of research methodology and epidemiology, and be able to critically analyze relevant published research literature. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>xiii</number> Develop skills in using educational methods and techniques as applicable to the teaching of medical/nursing students, general physicians and paramedical health workers. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>xiv</number> Function as an effective leader of a health team engaged in health care, research or training. 
</subsection></section>
</article> 

 <title></title>
 <article><title><number>4</number> Statement of the competencies. </title>-Keeping in view the general objectives of post-graduate training, each discipline shall aim at development of specific competencies which shall be defined and spelt out in clear terms. Each department shall produce a statement and bring it to the notice of the trainees in the beginning of the programme so that he or she can direct the efforts towards the attainment of these competencies. 
  


</article> 

 <title></title>
 <article><title><number>5</number> Components of the post-graduate curriculum. </title>-The major components of the post-graduate curriculum shall be- 
 
 . Theoretical knowledge. 
 . Practical and clinical skills. 
 . [Writing Thesis/Research articles.] 
 . Attitudes including communication skills. 
 . [Training in Research Methodology, Medical Ethics and Medicolegal aspects.] 



</article> 

 <title></title>
 <article><title></title><title>[<number>6</number> Starting of Post-Graduate Medical Courses and their recognition. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> An institution intending to start a post-graduate medical education course or to increase the annual intake capacity in an already ongoing course shall obtain prior permission of the Central Government as provided under section 10A of the Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The institution shall apply for recognition of the post-graduate medical qualification to the Central Government through the affiliating university, when the first admitted batch shall be due to appear for the examination to be conducted by the affiliating university. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Failure to seek timely recognition as required in sub-clause (2) shall invariably result in stoppage of admission to the concerned Post-Graduate Course. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The recognition so granted to a Post-Graduate Course shall be for a maximum period of 5 years, upon which it shall have to be renewed. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The procedure for renewal of recognition shall be same as applicable for the Award of recognition. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> Failure to seek timely renewal of recognition as required in sub-clause (4) shall invariably result in stoppage of admissions to the concerned Post-Graduate Course. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> In a period of 5 years from the date of Letter of Permission the college should have all pre and para clinical Post-Graduate Courses. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> The existing/new medical colleges should mandatorily have the department of Blood Bank with component of blood separation unit and Transfusion Medicine.] 
  


</section></article> 

 <title></title>
 <article><title><number>7</number> Nomenclature of post-graduate courses. </title>-The nomenclature of 
post-graduate medical courses shall be as provided in the Schedule annexed to these Regulation: 
 Provided that in the case of post-graduate medical degree and diploma courses instituted prior to the commencement of these regulations with the approval of the Medical Council of India and which have not been included in these regulations, the institutions concerned shall continue such course till the students admitted complete the said courses. 
  


</article> 

 <title></title>
 <article><title><number>8</number> General. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> The institutions recognised by the Medical Council of India for running post-graduate courses prior to the commencement of the Indian Medical Council (Amendment) Act, 1993 and those medical colleges recognised for running Bachelor of Medicine and Bachelor of Surgery (MBBS) course or institutions established by the Central Government for the purpose of imparting post-graduate medical education shall be eligible for starting any post-graduate degree or diploma and higher specialty course. 
 [However, the medical college/institute which is not yet recognised by Medical Council of India for the award of MBBS degree may apply for starting of a postgraduate course in pre clinical and para clinical subjects of Anatomy, Physiology, Biochemistry, Pharmacology, Forensic Medicine &amp; Community Medicine at the time of third renewal - i.e.,  alongwith the admission of fourth batch for the MBBS Course.] 
 </section><section><number>1A</number> The Central Government shall exempt any such existing/proposed  
  non-teaching institutions or specialist institution or autonomous body owned and managed by the Central Government/State Government from fulfilling the prescribed provision of having an under graduate teaching facility, and allow starting Post-graduate medical course. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The maximum number of students for a post-graduate medical course, who can be registered in any recognised department, for training for the award of  
  post-graduate degree or diploma by the affiliating university, shall be determined by the facilities available in the department in terms of infrastructure, teaching staff and clinical teaching material. 
 </section><section>[<number>3</number> Every student, selected for admission to a post-graduate medical course in any of the medical institutions on acquiring MBBS Degree or an equivalent qualification thereto shall have obtained permanent registration with the Medical Council of India, or any of the State Medical Council(s) or shall obtain the same within a period of one month from the date of his/her admission, failing which his/her admission shall stand cancelled:] 
 Provided that in the case of a foreign national, the Medical Council of India may, on payment of the prescribed fee for registration, grant temporary registration for the duration of the post-graduate [course limited to the Medical College/Institution to which he/she is admitted for the time being exclusively for pursuing the post-graduate studies]: 
 Provided further that temporary registration to such foreign national shall be subject to the condition that such person is duly registered [with appropriate registering authority in his own country wherefrom he has obtained his basic medical qualification, and is duly recognized by the corresponding Medical Council or concerned authority]. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The students undergoing post-graduate courses shall be exposed to the following:- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> Basics of statistics to understand and critically evaluate published research paper. 
 </subsection><subsection>[<number>b</number> Exposure to Human Behaviour studies.] 
 [***] 
</subsection>
  


</section></article> 

 <title></title>
 <article><title><number>9</number> Selection of post-graduate students. </title>- <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number> 
<subsection><number>a</number> Students for Post-Graduate medical courses shall be selected strictly on the basis of their inter-se academic merit. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> 50% of the seats in Post-Graduate Diploma courses shall be reserved for Medical Officers in the Government service, who have served for at least three years in remote and difficult areas. After acquiring the PG Diploma, the Medical Officers shall serve for two more years in remote and/or difficult areas. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> For determining the 'Academic Merit', the University/Institution may adopt the following methodology:- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> On the basis of merit as determined by a 'Competitive Test' conducted by the state government or by the competent authority appointed by the state government or by the university/group of universities in the same state; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> On the basis of merit as determined by a centralized competitive test held at the national level; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> On the basis of the individual cumulative performance at the first, second and third MBBS examinations provided admissions are University wise; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> Combination of (a) and (c): 
</subsection>
 Provided that wherever 'Entrance Test' for post-graduates admission is held by a state government or a university or any other authorized examining body, the minimum percentage of marks for eligibility for admission to post-graduate medical course shall be 50 percent for general category candidates and 40 percent for the candidates belonging to Scheduled Castes, Scheduled Tribes and Other Backward Classes: 
 Provided further that in non-Governmental institutions fifty percent of the total seats shall be filled by the competent authority notified by the State Government and the remaining fifty percent by the management(s) of the institution on the basis of inter-se academic merit.] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>3</number>(i) The Universities and other authorities concerned shall organize admission process in such a way that teaching in post-graduate courses starts by 2nd May and by 1st August for super speciality courses each year. For this purpose, they shall follow the time schedule indicated in Appendix-III. 
 <subsection><number>ii</number> There shall be no admission of students in respect of any academic session beyond 31st May for post-graduate courses and 30th September for super speciality courses, under any circumstances. The Universities shall not register any student admitted beyond the said date. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> The Medical Council of India may direct, that any student identified as having obtained admission after the last date for closure of admission, be discharged from the course of study, or any medical qualification granted to such a student shall not be a recognized qualification for the purpose of the Indian Medical Council Act, 1956 (102 of 1956). 
   The institution which grants admission to any student after the last date specified for the same shall also be liable to face such action as may be prescribed by MCI including surrender of seats equivalent to the extent of such admission made from its sanctioned intake capacity for the succeeding academic year.] 



 
 "(1) Students for postgraduate medical courses shall be selected on the basis of their academic merit. 
 1(a) 3% seats of the annual sanctioned intake capacity shall be filled up by candidates with locomotory disability of lower limbs between 50% to 70: 
 Provided that in case any seat in this 3% quota remains unfilled on account of unavailability of candidates with locomotory disability of lower limbs between 50% to 70% then any such unfilled seat in this 3% quota shall be filed up by persons with locomotory disability of lower limb between 40% to 50% -  
    before they are included in the annual sanctioned seats for General Category candidates: 
 Provided further that this entire exercise shall be completed by each medical college/institution as per the statutory time schedule for admissions and in no case any admission will be made in the Postgraduate Medical course after 31 st of May." 
 

</subsection></section><section><number>2</number> For determining the academic merit, the university/institution may adopt any one of the following procedures both for degree and diploma courses:- 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> On the basis of merit as determined by the competitive test conducted by the State Government or by the competent authority appointed by the State Government or by the university/group of universities in the same state; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> On the basis of merit as determined by a centralized competitive test held at the national level; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> On the basis of the individual cumulative performance at the first, second and their MBBS examination, if such examination have been passed from the same university; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> Combination of (i) and (iii): 
</subsection>
 Provided that wherever entrance test for Postgraduate admission is held by the State Government or a university or any other authorized examining body, the minimum percentage of marks for eligibility for admission to postgraduate medical courses shall be fifty per cent for general category candidates 45%, for persons with locomotory disability of lower links in the same manner as stipulated in Clause 9(1)(a) above and 40 per cent for the candidate belonging to Scheduled Castes, Scheduled Tribes and Other Backward classes: 
 Provided further that in non-Governmental institutions fifty percent of the total seats shall be filled by the competent authority and the remaining fifty per cent by the management of the institution on the basis of merit." 
</section></article> 

 <title></title>
 <article><title><number>10</number> Period of training. </title>-The period of training for the award of various 
post-graduate degrees or diplomas shall be as follows:- 
 <section><title><number>1</number> Doctor of Medicine (M.D.)/Master of Surgery (M.S.) </title>
 
 The period of training for obtaining these degrees shall be three completed years including the period of examination: 
 Provided that in the case of students <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[possessing] a recognised two year 
    post-graduate diploma course in the same subject, the period of training, including the period of examination, shall be two years. 

 </section><section><title><number>2</number> Doctor of Medicine (D.M.)/Master Chirurgiae (M.Ch.) </title>
 
 [The period of training for obtaining these Degrees shall be three completed years including the examination period]: 
 [Provided that where an institution, on the date of commencement of these Regulations, is imparting five year training in Neurology and Neurosurgery, such institution shall alter it to six-year training course.] 

 </section><section><title><number>3</number> Diploma </title>
 
 The period of training for obtaining a post-graduate diploma shall be two completed years including the examination period. 
 [MIGRATION 
 Under no circumstance, Migration/transfer of student undergoing any  
    Post-Graduate Degree/Diploma/Super Specialty course shall be permitted by any University/Authority.] 




</section></article> 

 <title></title>
 <article><title><number>11</number> Departmental Training Facilities. </title>- <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[A department having an independent academic identity in a teaching institution, comprising of one or more units, having prescribed strength of faculty, staff and teaching beds shall be recognised for post-graduate training.] 
 </article><article><footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<number>11</number>1 Staff - Faculty. -
<section><number>a</number> A clinical department or its unit training candidates for Broad or Super Specialities, shall have a minimum of three full time faculty members belonging to the concerned disciplines of whom one shall be a Professor, one Associate Professor/Reader and one Astt. Professor/Lecturer, possessing requisite qualification and teaching experience prescribed by the Medical Council of India: 
 Provided that the second or subsequent unit may be headed by an Associate Professor along with two Assistant Professors/Lecturers of these faculty members only those who possess a total of eight years teaching experience, of which at least five years teaching experience is as Assistant Professor gained after obtaining 
  post-graduate degree, shall be recognised as Post-Graduate Teachers. 
 </section><section><number>b</number> In a Department, training candidates for Super Speciality, there shall be a minimum of three faculty members with requisite post-graduate qualification and experience, one shall be Professor, One Associate Professor/Reader and one Assistant Professor/Lecturer: 
 Provided that the second or subsequent unit may be headed by an Associate Professor along with two Assistant Professors/Lecturers of these, only those faculty members who possess eight years teaching experience of which at least five years teaching experience is as Assistant Professor or above gained after obtaining the post-graduate degree shall be recognised as Post-Graduate Teachers: 
 Provided that in the case of super speciality courses which are newly instituted, relaxation of qualification and experience for recognition as  
  Post-Graduate Teachers, may be granted by the Medical Council of India for sufficient cause.] 
 </section></article><article><number>11</number>2 Minimum requirements for a post-graduate institution.- <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[
<section><number>a</number> An institution conducting both Undergraduate and Post-Graduate teaching shall fulfil the prescribed minimum requirements for undergraduate training and also additional requirements for post-graduate training depending on the type of work being carried out in the department. The additional staff required to be provided in following departments shall be as under: 
 
 <subsection><number>1</number> Department of Pathology: 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> Associate Professor/Reader - 1 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> Assistant Professor/Lecturer - 1 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number> Tutor/Demonstrator - 1 
</subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>2</number> Department of Radio-diagnosis: 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> Associate Professor/Reader - 1 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> Assistant Professor/Lecturer - 1 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number> Tutor/Demonstrator - 1 
</subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>3</number> Department of Anaesthesiology: 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> Associate Professor/Reader - 1 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> Assistant Professor/Lecturer - 1 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number> Tutor/Demonstrator - 1] 
</subsubsection>
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>b</number> A department imparting only post-graduate training shall:- 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> Provide facilities consistent with the all round training including training in basic medical science and other departments related to the subject of training as recommended by the Medical Council of India. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> have as many autopsies, biopsies and cytopsies as possible for teaching purposes; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> make available facilities of ancillary department for coordination of Training. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[<number>c</number> An institution eligible to start post-graduate course(s) under 
  sub-regulation (1A) of Regulation 8 may enter into a comprehensive Memorandum of Understanding with an ongoing recognized medical college, located within a reasonable distance from it as would not disrupt the smooth running of the said course(s), for the purpose of availing the facilities of the basic medical sciences departments of the college concerned; or it shall create the requisite facilities in its own set-up as per the guidelines indicated in Appendix-III. In addition, such an institution shall set up full-fledged departments of Pathology, Biochemistry, Microbiology and Radiology.] 
 </section></article><article><footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[<number>11</number>3 Bed Strength in Clinical Departments. -A Department to be recognised for training of post-graduate students, shall have at least 60 (Sixty) beds each of General Medicine, General Surgery, Obstetrics and Gynecology and 30 (thirty) beds each for others specialties for Degree and Diploma courses, and 20 (twenty) beds each in case of Super Specialty courses. 
 Explanation .-A unit shall consist of not less than 30 and more than 40 beds for Degree/Diploma courses and not less than 20 and more than 30 beds for Super Specialty Courses respectively.] 
 </article><article><number>11</number>4 Out - Patient Departments. -There shall be adequate space and sufficient number of examination cubicles available in the out - patient Department. Besides the general outpatient services, speciality clinics shall also be available for the training of post-graduate students in the relevant broad and super speciality;  
 To determine the number of students who may be admitted for training, outpatient attendance, work turnover and ambulatory care, also have to be taken into consideration. 
 </article><article><number>11</number>5 Laboratory Facilities. -The institution shall have adequate laboratory facilities for the training of the post-graduate students, and such laboratories shall provide all the investigative facilities required and shall be regularly updated keeping in view the advancement of knowledge and technology and research requirements, and for training of students in non-clinical departments, proper and contemporary laboratory facilities shall be made available. 
 </article><article><footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[<number>11</number>6 Equipment. -The department shall have adequate number of all such equipments including the latest ones necessary for training and as may be prescribed by the Council for each speciality from time to time.] 
  




 
 " 11.1 Staff - Faculty 
 
 <section><number>a</number> A clinical department or its unit training candidates for broad or super specialities, shall have a minimum of three full time faculty members belonging to the concerned disciplines of whom one shall be a Professor, one Associate Professor/Reader/and one Astt. Professor/Lecturer, possessing the qualification and experience prescribed by the Medical Council of India; 
 Provided that the second or subsequent additional unit may be headed by an Associate professor.  
 Of these faculty members only those who possess a total of eight years teaching experience, out of which at least five years teaching experience as Assistant Professor/Lecturer gained after obtaining post-graduate degree, shall be recognised as post-graduate teachers. 
 </section><section><number>b</number> In each department, training candidates for super specialities, there shall be a minimum of three faculty members with requisite post-graduate qualification and experience - One Professor, One Associate Professor/Reader and one Assistant Professor/Lecturer, with atleast two of them holding the degree of D.M./M.Ch. in the concerned discipline. 
 Of these faculty members only those who possess eight years teaching experience out of which at least five years teaching experience as Assistant Professor/Lecturer gained after obtaining the higher speciality degree shall be recognised as  
      post-graduate teachers: 
 Provided that in the case of super speciality courses which are being newly instituted relaxation of qualification and experience of post-graduate teachers may be granted by the Medical Council of India for sufficient cause. 
 </section><section><number>c</number> In addition to the faculty staff, the strength of Residents/Registrars/Tutors/Demonstrators, as well as technical and other para medical staff shall be as per the staff strength prescribed for 50 or 100 or 150 students in the "Minimum Requirements for 50/100/150 MBBS Admissions Annually Regulations. 
 </section><section><number>d</number> Consultants of specialists who have the experience of working for a period of not less than 18 years and 10 years in the teaching and other general departments in the institution or hospitals, not attached to any medical college, where with the affiliation from any university, postgraduate teaching is being imparted as contemplated under sub-regulation (1A) of regulation 8, shall respectively be eligible to be equated as Professor and Associate Professor in the department concerned the requisite department of the said institution or hospitals as professor and Associate Professor shall respectively be 16 years and 8 years. Consultants or Specialists having postgraduate degree qualification, working in such an institution or hospital, who do not have the said period of experience, shall be eligible to be equated as Assistant Professor in the department concerned." 
</section>


 
 "
<section><number>a</number> An institution conducting both undergraduate and post-graduate teaching shall satisfy the minimum requirement for undergraduate training as prescribed by the Medical Council of India and shall also fulfil additional requirements for  
    post-graduate training depending on the type of work being carried out in the department. The extra staff required to be provided in various departments shall be as given in Appendix-I.". 
</section>


 
 " 11.3 Bed Strength in Clinical Departments .-A department to be recognised for training of Post-Graduate students, shall have not less than 60 (Sixty) beds each of General Medicine, General Surgery, Obstetrics and Gynecology, 30 (thirty) beds each for others incase of M.D/M.S. and diploma and 20 (twenty) beds each in case of D.M./M.Ch. 
 Explaination .-A unit shall consist of 30 beds for MD/MS and 20 beds for DM/M.Ch. respectively.". 


 
 " 11.6 Equipment .-The department shall have adequate number of all equipments including the latest ones necessary for training and as may be prescribed by the Council for each speciality from time to time.". 

</article> 

 <title></title>
 <article><title><number>12</number> Number of post-graduate students to be admitted. </title>- <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number> The ratio of recognized post-graduate teacher to the number of students to be admitted for 
the degree course where diploma is not prescribed shall be 1:2 for a Professor and 1:1 for other cadres in each unit per year subject to a maximum of 4 PG seats 
for the degree per unit per academic year provided a complement of 10 teaching beds is added to the prescribed bed strength of 30 for the unit for broad specialities. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The ratio of recognized post-graduate teacher to the number of students to be admitted for the degree course in broad specialities where diploma is prescribed shall be 1:2 for a Professor and 1:1 for other cadres in each unit per year subject to a maximum of 4 PG seats including diploma per unit per academic year provided a complement of 10 teaching beds is added to the prescribed bed strength of 30 for the unit. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The requirement of units and beds shall not apply in the case of 
  Post-graduate degree or diploma courses in basic and para-clinical departments: 
 Provided that against the very same units, teaching personnel and infrastructure, no other post-graduate courses under any other streams like National Board of Examinations, College of Physicians &amp; Surgeons etc. are permitted.] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[<number>4</number> The ratio of PG teacher to the number of students to be admitted for super specialities course shall be 1:2 for Professor/Associate Professor and 1:1 for remaining cadre in each unit per year subject to a maximum of 4 PG seats for the course per unit per academic year provided the complement of 10 teaching beds per seat is added to the prescribed bed strength of 20 for the unit: 
 Provided that against the very same units, teaching personnel and infrastructure, no other post-graduate courses under any other streams like National Board of Examinations, College of Physicians &amp; Surgeons etc. are permitted.] 
  



 
 "(1) The ratio of recognised post-graduate teacher to number of students to be admitted for the degree and diploma courses shall be 1:1 each for degree and diploma courses in each unit per year, to the extent that in no circumstances more than two students for degree and one for Diploma shall be registered in a unit in one academic year. 
 

 
 "(4) The number of students to be admitted in case of post-graduate degree (Super speciality) courses shall be one student per year per recognised post-graduate teacher in a department having a minimum of three faculty members (one Professor, one Associate Professor/Reader &amp; one Asstt. Professor/Lecturer) and twenty beds. If the number of post-graduate teachers in the unit is more than one then the number of students may be increased proportionately but not more than two in a unit per year in any circumstances. For this purpose one student should associate with one 
    post-graduate teacher:  Provided that no post-graduate seats left unfilled in an academic year, shall be carried forward to the next or subsequent academic years, being from 1st January to 31st December of any calendar year." 

</section><section><number>2</number> In case the institution is having only post-graduate diploma courses in any subject then it shall have a unit of 30 beds with three full time teachers. The ratio of number of students and recognised post-graduate teachers shall be 1:1 and in no circumstances more than three students can be admitted in a unit per year. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The requirement of units and beds shall not apply in the case of post-graduate degree or diploma courses in Basic and para-clinical departments. The ratio of recognised post-graduate teacher to students shall, however be maintained at 1:1 both at degree as well as diploma level." 
</section></article> 

 <title></title>
 <article><title><number>13</number> Training Programme. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> The training given with due care to the 
post-graduate students in the recognised institutions for the award of various  
post-graduate medical degrees/diplomas shall determine the expertise of the specialist and/or medical teachers produced as a result of the educational programme during the period of stay in the institution. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> All the candidates joining the post-graduate training programme shall work as 'Full Time Residents' during the period of training and shall attend not less than 80% (Eighty percent) of the imparted training during each academic year including assignments, assessed full time responsibilities and participation in all facets of the educational process.] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[<number>3</number> The post-graduate students undergoing Post-Graduate Degree/Diploma/Super-Specialty Course shall be paid stipend on par with the stipend being paid to the post-graduate students of State Government Medical Institutions/Central Government Medical Institutions, in the State/Union Territory where the institution is located. Similarly, the matter of grant of leave to post-graduate students shall be regulated as per the respective State Government rules.] 
 </section><section><number>4</number> (a) Every institution undertaking post-graduate training programme shall set up an Academic Cell or a Curriculum Committee, under the chairmanship of a senior faculty member, which shall work out the details of the training programme in each speciality in consultation with other department faculty staff and also coordinate and monitor the implementation of these training Programmes. 
 <subsection><number>b</number> The training programmes shall be updated as and when required. The structured training programme shall be written up and strictly followed, to enable the examiners to determine the training undergone by the candidates and the Medical Council of India inspectors to assess the same at the time of inspection. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> Post-graduate students shall maintain a record (log) book of the work carried out by them and the training programme undergone during the period of training including details of surgical operations assisted or done independently by M.S./M.Ch. candidates. 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[<number>d</number> The Record (Log) Books shall be checked and assessed periodically by the faculty members imparting the training.] 
 </subsection></section><section><footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[<number>5</number> During the training for award of Degree/Superspecialty/Diploma in clinical disciplines, there shall be proper training in Basic medical sciences related to the disciplines concerned; so also in the applied aspects of the subject; and allied subjects related to the disciplines concerned. In the post-graduate training programmes including both clinical and basic medical sciences, emphasis has to be laid on preventive and social aspects. Emergency care, facilities for Autopsies, Biopsies, Cytopsies, Endoscopy and Imaging etc. shall also be made available for training purposes.] 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The post-graduate students shall be required to participate in the teaching and training programme of undergraduate students and interns. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> Training in Medical Audit, Management, Health Economics, Health Information System, Basics of Statistics, Exposure to Human Behaviour Studies, Knowledge of pharmaco - economics and introduction to non-linear mathematics shall be imparted to the post-graduate students. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[<number>8</number> Implementation of the training programmes for the award of various 
  post-graduate Degree and Diplomas shall include the following:- 
 
 <subsection><title><number>a</number> Doctor of Medical (M.D.)/Master of surgery (M.S.) </title>
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> <title>Basic Medical Sciences - </title>The teaching and training of the students shall be through Lectures, Seminars, Journal clubs, Group discussions, Participation in laboratory and experimental work, and involvement in research studies in the concerned speciality and exposure to the 'applied aspects' of the subject relevant to clinical specialities. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> <title>Clinical disciplines - </title>The teaching and training of the students shall include graded responsibility in the management and treatment of patients entrusted to their care; participation in seminars, journal clubs, group discussions, clinical meetings, grand rounds, and  
      Clinico-Pathological Conferences; practical training in Diagnosis and Medical and Surgical treatment; training in the Basic Medical Sciences, as well as in allied clinical specialitites. 
</subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><title><number>b</number> </title><title>Doctor of Medicine (D.M.) / Magister Chirurgiae (M.Ch.) </title>-The training programme shall be on the same pattern as for M.D./M.S. in clinical disciplines; with practical training including advanced Diagnostic, Therapeutic and Laboratory techniques, relevant to the subject of specialization. Post-graduate Degree/Diploma/Superspecialty Residents in Surgical Specialties shall participate in Surgical operations as well. 
 </subsection><subsection><title><number>c</number> Diplomas </title>-The teaching and training of the students shall include graded clinical responsibility; Lectures, Seminars, Journal clubs, Group Discussions and participation in Clinical and Clinico-Pathological Conferences, practical training to manage independently common problems in the specialty; and training in the Basic Medical Sciences.] 
</subsection>



 
 "(2) All candidates joining the post-graduate training programme shall work as full time residents during the period of training, attending not less than 80% (Eighty percent) of the training during each calendar year, and given full time responsibility, assignments and participation in all facets of the educational process." 


 
 "(3) The post-graduate students of the institutions which are located in various States/Union Territories shall be paid remuneration at par with the remuneration being paid to the post-graduate students of State Government medical institutions/Central Government Medical Institutions, in the State/Union Territory in which the institution is located. Similar procedure shall be followed in the matter of grant of leave to post-graduate students.". 


 
 "(d) The record books shall be checked and assessed by the faculty members imparting the training. ". 


 
 "(5) During the training for Degree/Diploma to be awarded in clinical disciplines, there shall be proper training in basic medical sciences related to the disciplines concerned; during the training for the degree to be awarded in basic medical sciences, there shall be training in applied aspects of the subject; and there shall be training in allied subjects related to the disciplines concerned. In all post-graduate training programmes, both clinical and basic medical sciences, emphasis is to be laid on preventive and social aspects and emergency care facilities for autopsies, biopsies, cytopsies, endoscopic and imaging etc. also be made available for training purposes.". 


 
 "(8) Implementation of the training programmes for the award of various post-graduate degree and diplomas shall include the following:- 
 <subsection><number>a</number> <title>Doctor of Medical (M.D.)/Master of surgery (M.S.) </title>
 <subsubsection><title><number>i</number> Basic Medical Sciences </title>
 Lectures, Seminars, Journal Clubs, Group Discussions, Participation in laboratory and experimental work, and involvement in research studies in the concerned speciality and exposure to the applied aspects of the subject relevant to clinical specialities. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><title><number>ii</number> Clinical disciplines </title>
 In service training, with the students being given graded responsibility in the management and treatment of patients entrusted to their care; participation in Seminars, Journal clubs, Group Discussions, Clinical Meetings, Grand rounds, and Clinico - Pathological Conferences; practical training in Diagnosis and medical and Surgical treatment; training in the Basic Medical Sciences, as well as in allied clinical specialitites. 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>b</number> <title>Doctor of Medicine (D.M.)/Magister Chirurgiae (M.Ch.) </title>
 The training programme shall be on the same pattern as for M.D./M.S. in clinical disciplines; practical training including advanced Diagnostic, Therapeutic and Laboratory techniques, relevant to the subject of specialisation. For M.Ch. Candidates, there shall be participation in surgical operations. 
</subsection>
</section></article> 

 <title></title>
 <article><title><footcitenum>18</footcitenum></title><title>[<number>14</number> Examinations. </title>-The examinations shall be organised on the basis of 'Grading' or 'Marking system' to evaluate and to certify candidate's level of knowledge, skill and competence at the end of the training. Obtaining a minimum of 50% marks in 'Theory' as well as 'Practical' separately shall be mandatory for passing examination as a whole. The examination for M.D./ MS, D.M., M.Ch shall be held at the end of 3rd academic year and for diploma at the end of 2nd academic year. An academic term shall mean six month's training period.] 
 <section><title><number>1</number> Examiners </title><title></title>
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> All the post-graduate examiners shall be recognised post-graduate teachers holding recognised post-graduate qualifications in the subject concerned. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> For all post-graduate examinations, the minimum number of examiners shall be four, out of which at least two (50%) shall be external examiners, who shall be invited from other recognised universities from outside the State. Two sets of internal examiners may be appointed one for M.D./M.S. and one for diploma. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> Under exceptional circumstances, examinations may be held with 3 (three) examiners provided two of them are external and Medical Council of India is intimated the justification of such action prior to publication of result for approval. Under no circumstances, result shall be published in such cases without the approval of Medical Council of India. 
 <footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[***] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> The examining authorities may follow the guidelines regarding appointment of examiners given in Appendix-II. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><title><number>2</number> Number of candidates </title> - The maximum number of candidates to be examined in Clinical/Practical and Oral on any day shall not exceed eight for M.D./M.S. degree, eight for diploma and three for D.M./M/Ch examinations. 
 </section><section><title><number>3</number> Number of examinations </title> - The university shall conduct not more than two examinations in a year, for any subject, with an interval of not less than 4 and not more than 6 months between the two examinations. 
 </section><section><title><number>4</number> Doctor of Medicine (M.D.)/Master of Surgery (M.S.) </title> - M.D./M.S. examinations, in any subject shall consist of Thesis, Theory Papers, and Clinical/Practical and Oral examinations. 
 <subsection><title><number>a</number> Thesis </title>
 
 Every candidate shall carry out work on an assigned research project under the guidance of a recognised post-graduate teacher, the result of which shall be written up and submitted in the form of a Thesis.  
 Work for writing the Thesis is aimed at contributing to the development of a spirit of enquiry, besides exposing the candidate to the Techniques of research, Critical analysis, Acquaintance with the latest advances in medical science and the manner of identifying and consulting available literature. <footcitenum>20</footcitenum>[Thesis shall be submitted at least six months before the Theory and Clinical/Practical examination.] 
 <footcitenum>21</footcitenum>[The Thesis shall be examined by a minimum of three examiners; one internal and two external examiners, who shall not be the examiners for Theory and Clinical examination. A candidate shall be allowed to appear for the Theory and Practical/Clinical examination only after the acceptance of the Thesis by the examiners.] 

 </subsection><subsection><title><number>b</number></title> <title>Theory </title>
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> There shall be four theory papers. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> Out of these one shall be of <footcitenum>22</footcitenum>[Basic Medical Sciences] and one shall be of Recent Advances. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number> The theory examinations shall be held <footcitenum>23</footcitenum>[well in advance before] the Clinical and Practical examination, so that the answer books can be assessed and evaluated before the <footcitenum>24</footcitenum>[commencement] of the Clinical/Practical and Oral examination: 
 <footcitenum>25</footcitenum>[***] 
</subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><title><number>c</number></title> <title>Clinical/Practical and Oral </title>
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> Clinical examination for the subjects in Clinical Sciences shall be conducted to test the knowledge and competence of the candidates for undertaking independent work as a specialist/Teacher, for which candidates shall examine a minimum one long case and two short cases. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> Practical examination for the subjects in Basic Medical Sciences shall be conducted to test the knowledge and competence of the candidates for making valid and relevant observations based on the experimental/Laboratory studies and his ability to perform such studies as are relevant to his subject. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number> The Oral examination shall be thorough and shall aim at assessing the candidate knowledge and competence about the subject, investigative procedures, therapeutic technique and other aspects of the speciality, which form a part of the examination. 
 A candidate shall secure not less than 50% marks in each head of passing which shall include (1) Theory, (2) Practical including Clinical and Viva-Voce examination. 
</subsubsection>
 <subsubsection><number>II</number> Doctor of Medicine (D.M.)/Magister of Chirurgiae (M.Ch.) 
 
 <footcitenum>26</footcitenum>[The examination shall consist of: 
 
 
 <subsubsubsection><number>a</number> <title>Theory </title>
 <footcitenum>27</footcitenum>[There shall be four theory papers, one paper out of these shall be on 'Basic Medical Sciences', and another paper on 'Recent Advances'. The theory examination shall be held in advance before the Clinical and Practical examination, so that the answer books can be assessed and evaluated before the commencement of the Clinical/Practical and Oral examination.] 
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>b</number> <title>Clinical/Practical and Oral </title>
 Practical examination <footcitenum>28</footcitenum>[may] consist of carrying out special investigative techniques for Diagnosis and Therapy. M.Ch candidates shall also be examined in surgical procedures. Oral examination shall be <footcitenum>29</footcitenum>[comprehensive enough] to test the candidate's overall knowledge of the subject. 
 A candidate shall secure not less than 50% marks in each head of passing which shall include (1) Theory (2) Practical including <footcitenum>30</footcitenum>[Clinical and viva voce examination.] 
</subsubsubsection>
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>i</number> Theory and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> Clinical/Practical and Oral.] 
</subsubsection><subsubsection><number>III</number> Post Graduate Diploma 
 
 Diploma examination in any subject shall consist of <footcitenum>31</footcitenum>[Theory, Practical/Clinical and Oral.] 
 <subsubsubsection><number>a</number> <title>Theory </title>
 <footcitenum>32</footcitenum>[There shall be three 'Theory' papers, one paper out of these shall be on 'Basic Medical Sciences' <title>. </title>The theory of examination will be held well in advance before the Clinical examination, so that the answer books can be assessed before the commencement of the Practical/Clinical and Viva-Voce examination.] 
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>b</number> <title>Clinical and Oral </title>
 Clinical examination for the subject in clinical Science shall be conducted to test/aimed at assessing the knowledge and competence of the candidate for undertaking independent work as a Specialist/Teacher for which a candidate shall examine a minimum of one long case and two short cases. 
 The oral examination shall be thorough and shall aim at assessing the candidate's knowledge and competence about the subject, investigative procedures, therapeutic technique and other aspects of the speciality which shall form a part of the examination. 
 The candidate shall secure not less than 50% marks in each head of passing which shall include (1) Theory (2) Practical including Clinical and Viva-Voce examinations. <title></title>
</subsubsubsection>



 
 " 14.  Examinations .-The examinations shall be organised on the basis of grading or marking system to evaluate and certify candidates level of knowledge, skill and competence at the end of the training and obtaining a minimum of 50% marks in theory as well as practical separately shall be mandatory for passing the whole examination. The examination for M.S., M.D, M.Ch shall be held at the end of 3 academic years (six academic terms) and for diploma at the end of 2 academic years (four academic terms). The academic terms shall mean six months training period.". 


 
 "(d) In the event of there being more than one centre in one city, the external examiners at all the centres in that city shall be the same. Where there is more than one centre of examination, the University shall appoint a Supervisor to coordinate the examination on its behalf.". 



 
 "The Thesis shall be examined by a minimum of three examiners; one internal and two external examiners, who shall not be the examiners for Theory and Clinical; and on the acceptance of the Thesis by two examiners, the candidate shall appear for the final examination.". 





 
 "Provided that after five years from the commencement of these regulations, there shall be one theory paper of 'multiple choice questions'; unless any institution wants to have such paper earlier.". 



 
 "There shall be four theory papers, one paper out of these shall be on Basic Medical Sciences, and another paper on Recent Advances. The theory examination will be held sufficiently earlier than the Clinical and Practical examination, so that the answer books can be assessed and evaluated before the start of the clinical/Practical and Oral examination.". 






 
 There shall be three theory papers. One paper out of these shall be on Basic Medical Sciences. The examination shall be held sufficiently earlier than the clinical examination, so that the answer books can be assessed before the start of the clinical examination..

</subsubsection></subsection></section></article><form>
 

THE POST-GRADUATE MEDICAL EDUCATION REGULATIONS, 20001 
 


 

2[


 ***]
  
 

---------------
 

1. Vide Notification No. MCI-18(1)/90-Med., dated 22nd August, 2000, published in the Gazette of India, Pt. III, Sec. 4, dated 7th October, 2000.
 

2. Appendix I omitted by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./29544, dated 20th October, 2008.
</form><form>
 

THE POST-GRADUATE MEDICAL EDUCATION REGULATIONS, 20001 
 


 

Appendix II 
 

POST GRADUATE EXAMINATION  

  GUIDELINES ON APPOINTMENT  

  OF POST GRADUATE EXAMINERS 
 

2[1. No person shall be appointed as an internal examiner in any subject unless he/she has three years experience as recognized PG teacher in the concerned subject. For external examiners, he/she should have minimum six years of experience as recognized PG teacher in the concerned subject.] 
 

2. There shall be at least four examiners in each subject at an examination out of which at least 50% (Fifty percent) shall be external examiners. The external examiner who fulfils the condition laid down in clause (1) above shall ordinarily be invited from another recognised university, from outside the State: provided that in exceptional circumstances examinations may be held with 3 (three) examiners if two of them are external and Medical council of India is intimated with the justification of such examination 2 [the result in such a case shall be published with the approval of Medical Council of India]. 
 

3. 2[An examiner shall ordinarily be appointed for not more than two consecutive terms.] 
 

4. The internal examiner in a subject shall not accept external examinership for a college from which external examiner is appointed in his subject. 
 

5. 3[***] 
 

6. 3[***] 
 

7. There shall be a Chairman of the Board of paper - setters who shall be an external examiner and shall moderate the question papers. 
 

8. 4[Where there is more than one centre of examination, there shall be 
  Co-ordinator/Convenor/Chairman who shall be the seniormost internal examiner, appointed by the university &amp; shall supervise and co-ordinate the examination on behalf of the university with independent authority.] 
 

9. 2[***] 
  
 

---------------
 

1. Vide Notification No. MCI-18(1)/90-Med., dated 22nd August, 2000, published in the Gazette of India, Pt. III, Sec. 4, dated 7th October, 2000.
 

 2. Subs. by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./29544, dated 20th October, 2008.  

 

3. Paras 5 and 6 omitted by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./29544, dated 20th October, 2008. 

 

4. Subs. by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./29544, dated 20th October, 2008. 

 

5. Para 9 omitted by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./29544, dated 20th October, 2008.
</form><form>
 

THE POST-GRADUATE MEDICAL EDUCATION REGULATIONS, 20001 
 


 

2[ Appendix III 
 

[ See regulation 11.2(c)] 
 

Criteria to be fulfilled by institutions eligible to start post-graduate course(s) under sub-regulation (1A) of Regulation 8, which are required to create their own facilities for setting up departments in basic medical sciences: 
 

A. The basic subjects identified for the purpose of creation of facilities shall be: 
 
 

(i) Anatomy 
 

(ii)  Physiology 
 

(iii) Pharmacology 
 

(iv)  Community Medicine with Forensic Medicine being optional. 

 

B. Staff requirements: 
 
 

(1) The minimum staff required in each of the departments of Anatomy, Physiology, Pharmacology and Community Medicine shall be: 
 
 

1. Professor or Associate Professor One 
 

2. Assistant Professor  Two 

 

Provided that the department of Community Medicine shall also have: 
 
 

(a) Epidemiologist-cum-Lecturer 
 

(b) Statistician-cum-Lecturer 
 

(c) Health Educator-cum-Lecturer 

 

Provided further that the person in charge of a Unit shall not be below the rank of Associate Professor. 
 

(2) The required strength of the teaching personnel shall be in proportion to the number of post-graduate courses started by the institution in a manner that the ultimate upper limit of the requirement shall be on a par with the requirement indicated in the regulation of the council titled 'Minimum Requirements for Establishment of Medical College for Annual Intake Capacity of 50'. 

 

C. Infrastructural requirements: 
 

(1) The infrastructural requirements in terms of lecture theatres and demonstration rooms could be common. 
 

(2) The research laboratories shall be well-equipped so that the teachers in the departments concerned shall be able to work on solicited research projects. 
 

(3) Department of Anatomy: Apart from the common facilities, there shall be placed for dissection with adequate accommodation, along with an embalming room, cold room and also a museum:   
 

Provided that Histology and Research laboratory may be clubbed together. 
 

(4) Department of Physiology: There shall be clinical, experimental and animal physiology laboratories along with a museum. 
 

(5) Department of Pharmacology: The facilities could be common except for research laboratory, which shall be separate. 
 

(6) Department of Community Medicine: There shall be a museum along with a well-equipped Rural/Urban Health Centre with necessary staff.] 
 

 
 

---------------
 

1. Vide Notification No. MCI-18(1)/90-Med., dated 22nd August, 2000, published in the Gazette of India, Pt. III, Sec. 4, dated 7th October, 2000.
 

 	2.	Ins. by the Post-graduate Medical Education (Amendment) Regulations, 2005 (w.e.f. 
16-3-2005).
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./29544, dated 20th October, 2008, for various sub-specialities concerned with a discipline.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Subs. by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2009, Med./22653, dated 21st July, 2009, for 
  sub-clause (1). Earlier sub-clause (1) was amended by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./54470, dated 25th March, 2009. Sub-clause (1)(a), before substitution by MCI-18(1)/2009-Med./22653, dated 21st July, 2009 stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Ins. by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2006-Med./27395, dated 23rd March, 2006.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> . Subs. by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./29544, dated 20th October, 2008, for having. (w.e.f. 20-10-2008).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Subs. by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./29544, dated 20th October, 2008, for "A department having an independent academic entity of a teaching institution, consisting of one or more units, each having the prescribed minimum strength of faculty, staff and beds shall be recognised for post-graduate training.".</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Subs. by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./29544, dated 20th October, 2008, for sub-clause 11.1. Earlier Clause 11.1 was amended by the Post-graduate Medical Education (Amendment) Regulations, 2005 (w.e.f. 16-3-2005). Clause 11.1, before substitution by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./2008, dated 20th October, 2008, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Subs. by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./29544, dated 20th October, 2008, for sub-clause 11.2(a). Sub-clause 11.2(a), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>	Ins. by the Post-graduate Medical Education (Amendment) Regulations, 2005 (w.e.f 16-3-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> Subs. by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./29544, dated 20th October, 2008, for sub-clause 11.3. Sub-clause 11.3, before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> Subs. by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./29544, dated 20th October, 2008, for sub-clause 11.6. Sub-clause 11.6, before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number> Subs. by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2009-Med./22653, dated 21st July, 2009, for</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number> Subs. by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2009-Med./22653, dated 21st July, 2009, for 
  sub-clause (4). Sub-clause (4), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number> Subs. by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./29544, dated 20th October, 2008, for sub-clause (2). Sub-clause (2), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number> Subs. by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./29544, dated 20th October, 2008, for sub-clause (3). Sub-clause (3), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number> Subs. by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./29544, dated 20th October, 2008, for sub-clause (4)(d). Sub-clause (4)(d), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number> Subs. by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./29544, dated 20th October, 2008, for sub-clause (5). Sub-clause (5), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number> Subs. by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./29544, dated 20th October, 2008, for sub-clause (8). Sub-clause (8), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number> Subs. by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./29544, dated 20th October, 2008, for clause 14. Clause 14, before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number> Clause 14.1(d) omitted by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./29544, dated 20th October, 2008. Clause 14.1(d), before omission, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number>  Subs. by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./29544, dated 20th October, 2008, for "Thesis shall be submitted at least six months before the theoritical and clinical/practical examination.".</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number> Subs. by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./29544, dated 20th October, 2008, for para 3. Para 3, before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number> Subs. by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./29544; dated 20th October, 2008, for "Basic Medical Science".</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number> Subs. by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./29544, dated 20th October, 2008, for "sufficiently earlier than".</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number> Subs. by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./29544, dated 20th October, 2008, for "start".</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number> Proviso omitted by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./29544, dated 20th October, 2008. Proviso, before omission, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number> Subs. by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./29544, dated 20th October, 2008, for "The examination shall consist of: Theory and clinical/practical and oral".</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number> Subs. by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./29544, dated 20th October, 2008, for Clause 14(II)(a) para. Clause 14(II)(a) para, before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>28</number> Subs. by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./29544, dated 20th October, 2008, for "shall"</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>29</number> Subs. by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./29544, dated 20th October, 2008, for "comprehensive"</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>30</number> Subs. by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./29544, dated 20th October, 2008, for "clinical  viva voce  examination".</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>31</number> Subs. by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./29544, dated 20th October, 2008, for "Theory, Clinical and Oral".</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>32</number> Subs. by Notification No. MCI-18(1)/2008-Med./29544, dated 20th October, 2008, for Clause 14(III)(a) para. Clause 14(III)(a) para, before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>