<act><title>


THE NAVY ACT, 1957</title> 

 



 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
This Act may be called the Navy Act, 1957.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It shall come into 
force on such date1 as 
the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Persons subject to 
naval law.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The following persons shall be subject to naval law wherever they may be, 
namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  every person 
belonging to the Indian Navy during the time that he is liable for service under 
this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  every person 
belonging to the Indian Naval Reserve Forces when he is—
 <subsubsection>
             <number>i</number>  on 
active service, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>ii</number>  in or on 
any property of the naval service including naval establishments, ships and 
other vessels, aircraft, vehicles and armouries, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>iii</number>  called 
up for training or undergoing training in pursuance of regulations made under 
this Act, until he is duly released from his training, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           <number>iv</number>  called up 
into actual service in the Indian Navy in pursuance of regulations made under 
this Act, until he is duly released therefrom, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>v</number>  in 
uniform;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  members of the 
regular Army and the Air Force when embarked on board any ship or aircraft of 
the Indian Navy, to such extent and subject to such conditions as may be 
prescribed;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  every person 
not otherwise subject to naval law, who enters into an engagement with the 
Central Government under section 6;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  every person 
belonging any auxiliary forces raised under this Act, to such extent and subject 
to such conditions as may be prescribed; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  every person 
who, although he would not otherwise be subject to naval law, is by any other 
Act or during active service by regulations made under this Act in this behalf 
made subject to naval law, to such extent and subject to such conditions as may 
be prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The following persons 
shall be deemed to be persons subject to naval law, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  every person 
ordered to be received, or being a passenger, on board any ship or aircraft of 
the Indian Navy, to such extent and subject to such conditions as may be 
prescribed;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  every person 
sentenced under this Act to imprisonment or detention, during the term of his 
sentence, notwithstanding that he is discharged or dismissed with or without 
disgrace from the naval service or would otherwise but for this provision cease 
to be subject to naval law.



</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 

 <article>
<number>3</number> Definitions.—In 
this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
       <number>1</number>  “active 
service” means service or duty—
 <subsection>
            <number>a</number>  during 
the period of operation of a Proclamation of Emergency issued under clause (1) 
of article 352 of the Constitution, or
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>b</number>  during 
any period declared by the Central Government by notification in the Official 
Gazette as a period of active service with reference to any area in which any 
person or class of persons subject to naval law may be serving;
 </subsection></section><section>
       <number>2</number>  “Chief of the 
Naval Staff” means the flag officer appointed by the President as Chief of the 
Naval Staff or in his absence on leave or otherwise an officer appointed by the 
Central Government to officiate as such or in the absence of such officiating 
appointment the officer on whom the command devolves in accordance with 
regulations made under this Act;
 </section><section>
       <number>3</number>  “Civil 
offence” means an offence triable by a court of ordinary criminal jurisdiction 
in India;
 </section><section>
       <number>4</number>  “Civil prison” 
means any jail or place used for the detention of any criminal prisoner under 
the Prisons Act, 1984 (9 of 1894) or under any other law for the time being in 
force;
 </section><section>
       <number>5</number>  “Commissioned 
officer” means a person holding a commission from the President in the Indian 
Navy or the Indian Naval Reserve Forces;
 </section><section>
       <number>6</number>  
“court-martial” means a court-martial constituted under this Act;
 </section><section>
       <number>7</number>  “enemy” 
includes all armed rebels, armed mutineers, armed rioters and pirates and any 
person in arms against whom it is the duty of any person subject to naval law to 
act;
 </section><section>
       <number>8</number>  “flag officer” 
means an officer of the rank of Admiral of the Fleet, Admiral, Vice-Admiral or 
Rear-Admiral;
 </section><section>
       <number>9</number>  “Indian Naval 
Reserve Forces” means the naval reserve forces raised and maintained by the 
Central Government;
 </section><section>
      <number>10</number>  “Indian Navy” 
means the regular naval forces raised and maintained by the Central Government;
 </section><section>
      <number>11</number>  “Indian 
waters”, for the purposes of sections 31, 97 and 99, means the seas extending 
from the shores of India to such limits as may be prescribed;
 </section><section>
      <number>12</number>  “naval 
custody” means the arrest or confinement of a person in the prescribed manner or 
in accordance with the usages of the naval service, and includes military or air 
force custody;
 </section><section>
    <number>12A</number>  “naval 
establishment” means an establishment belonging to, or under the control of, the 
Indian Navy whether within or without India;
 </section><section>
      <number>13</number>  “naval 
offence” means any of the offences under section 34 to 76;
 </section><section>
      <number>14</number>  “naval 
service” means the naval organisation of India;
 </section><section>
      <number>15</number>  “naval 
tribunal” means a court-martial constituted under section 97 and includes a 
disciplinary court constituted under section 96, a commanding officer or other 
officer or authority exercising powers of punishment under this Act;
 
 

1[(16)  “officer” 
means a commissioned officer and includes—
 <subsection>
            <number>a</number>  a 
subordinate officer other than a petty officer;
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>b</number>  a 
commissioned officer re-employed as such;]
 </subsection></section><section>
      <number>17</number>  “Petty 
officer” means a sailor rated as such and includes a chief petty officer and a 
master chief petty officer;
 </section><section>
      <number>18</number>  “prescribed” 
means prescribed by regulations made under this Act;
 </section><section>
      <number>19</number>  
“provost-marshal” means a person appointed as such under section 89 and includes 
any of his deputies or assistants or any other person lawfully exercising 
authority under him or on his behalf;
 </section><section>
      <number>20</number>  “sailor” means 
a person in the naval service other than an officer;
 </section><section>
      <number>21</number>  “ship”, except 
in the expression “on board a ship” includes an establishment of the Indian Navy 
commissioned as a ship in accordance with the custom of the navy;
 </section><section>
      <number>22</number>  “subject to 
naval law” means liable to be arrested and tried under this Act for any offence;
 </section><section>
      <number>23</number>  “subordinate 
officer” means a person appointed as an acting sub-lieutenant, a midshipman or a 
cadet in any branch of the Indian Navy or the Indian Naval Reserve Forces, but 
does not include a cadet whilst under training in a joint service institution;
 </section><section>
      <number>24</number>  “superior 
officer”, when used in relation to a person subject to naval law, means any 
officer or petty officer who is senior to that person under regulations made 
under this Act and any officer or petty officer, who though not so senior to 
that person, is entitled under this Act or the regulations made thereunder to 
give a command to that person, and includes, when such person is serving under 
prescribed conditions, an officer, junior commissioned officer, warrant officer, 
non-commissioned officer of the regular Army or the Air Force of higher relative 
rank to that person or entitled under this Act or the regulations made 
thereunder to give a command to that person;
 </section><section>
      <number>25</number>  all words and 
expressions used but not defined in this Act but defined in the Indian Penal 
Code (45 of 1860), shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in that 
Code.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Fundamental rights 
to apply to persons subject to naval law with modifications.—The 
rights conferred by Part III of the Constitution in their application to persons 
subject to naval law shall be restricted or abrogated to the extent provided in 
this Act.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Power of Central 
Government to raise and maintain naval forces.—The 
Central Government may raise and maintain a regular naval force and also reserve 
and auxiliary naval forces.
 



</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>6</number> Provision respecting 
discipline of persons under engagement to serve Central Government.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If any person not otherwise subject to naval law enters into an engagement with 
the Central Government to serve,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  in a 
particular ship; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  in such 
particular ship or in such ships as the Central Government, the Chief of the 
Naval Staff, or the prescribed officer may, from time to time, determine;
 
and agrees to become 
subject to naval law upon entering into the engagement, that person shall, so 
long as the engagement remains in force and notwithstanding that for the time 
being he may not be serving in any ship, be subject to naval law.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Central Government 
may, by order, direct that subject to such exceptions as may in particular cases 
be made by or on behalf of the Chief of the Naval Staff, persons of any such 
class as may be specified in the order shall, while being subject to naval law 
by virtue of this section, be deemed to be officers, petty officers or other 
sailor as the case may be, for the purposes of this Act or of such provisions of 
this Act as may be so specified.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Relations between 
the members of the Navy, Army and Air Force acting together.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When members of the regular Army and the Air Force or of either of these forces 
are serving with members of the Indian Navy or Indian Naval Reserve Force under 
prescribed conditions, then those members of the regular Army or the Air Force 
shall exercise such command, if any, and be subject to such discipline as may be 
prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Nothing in sub-section 
(1) shall be deemed to authorise the exercise of powers of punishment by members 
of the regular Army or the Air Force over members of the Indian Navy or the 
Indian Naval Reserve Forces, except as provided in clause (e) of sub-section (3) 
of section 93, or in such cases and subject to such conditions as may be 
prescribed.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Provision respecting 
discipline of master of merchant vessel under convoy.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every master or other person for the time being in command of any merchant or 
other vessel comprised in a convoy under the command of an officer of the Indian 
Navy shall obey, in all matters relating to the navigation or security of the 
convoy, any directions which may be given by such officer, and shall take such 
precautions for avoiding the enemy as may be required by any such direction.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any such directions 
are not obeyed, any such officer or any person acting under his orders may 
compel obedience by force of arms without being liable for any injury or loss of 
life or any danger to or loss of property resulting therefrom.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Eligibility for 
appointment or enrolment.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No person who is not a citizen of India shall be eligible for appointment or 
enrolment in the Indian Navy or the Indian Naval Reserve Forces except with the 
consent of the Central Government:
 
Provided that nothing in 
this section shall render a person ineligible for appointment or enrolment in 
the Indian Navy or the Indian Naval Reserve Forces on the ground that he is a 
subject of Nepal.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No woman shall be 
eligible for appointment for enrolment in the Indian Navy or the Indian Naval 
Reserve Forces except in such department, branch or other body forming part 
thereof or attached thereto and subject to such conditions as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette specify in this behalf.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Commissions and 
appointments.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Officers other than subordinate officers shall be appointed by commission 
granted by the President.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The grant of the 
commission shall be notified in the Official Gazette and such notification shall 
be conclusive proof of the grant of such commission.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Subordinate officers 
shall be appointed in such manner and shall hold such rank as may be prescribed.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Enrolment.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Save as otherwise provided in this Act, the terms and conditions of service of 
sailors, the person authorised to enrol for service as sailors and the manner 
and procedure of such enrolment shall be such as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No person shall be 
enrolled as a sailor in the Indian Navy for a period exceeding 

1[twenty years] in 
the first instance:
 
Provided that in the case 
of a minor the said period of 

1[twenty years] 
shall be reckoned from the date on which he attains the age of seventeen.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in any other law for the time being in force,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the enrolment 
of any person under this Act shall be binding on him both during his minority 
and after he attains majority;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  neither the 
parent or guardian of a minor duly enrolled under this Act nor any other person 
shall be entitled to claim custody of the said minor as against the Central 
Government or any of its officers or other persons set over him.
 


comment
 
Sections 9, 10 and 11 
clearly shows that an officer who is not a subordinate officer is ‘appointed’ by 
commission granted by the President, Subordinate officers may be ‘appointed in 
the prescribed manner, but the sailors are ‘enrolled’ in the Navy; Anuj Kumar 
Dey v. Union of India, (1997) 66 DLT 592.
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Validity of 
enrolment.—Where 
a person after his enrolment has for a period of three months from the date of 
such enrolment been in receipt of pay as a sailor, he shall be deemed to have 
been duly enrolled and shall not thereafter be entitled to claim his discharge 
on the ground of any irregularity or illegality in his engagement or any other 
ground whatsoever; and if within the said three months such person claims his 
discharge, no such irregularity or illegality or other ground shall, until such 
person is discharged in pursuance of his claim affect his position as a sailor 
in the naval service or invalidate any proceedings, act or thing taken or done 
prior to his discharge.
 


Comment
 
Where a person joined 
Indian Navy as trainee Artificier Apprentice and was made to take oath which 
every officer or sailor is bound to take under section 13 of the Naval Act, 
1957, and he was also paid salary as a sailor, it could not be said, that he 
could not even be treated as a sailor during training period; Anuj Kumar Dey 
v. Union of India, (1997) 66 DLT 592.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Oath of allegiance.—Every 
officer and every sailor shall, as soon as may be, after appointment or 
enrolment make and subscribe before the commanding officer of the ship to which 
he belongs, or the prescribed officer on oath or affirmation in the following 
form that is to say:—
 

                                              swear in the name of God
 

“I......................................do———————————————that
 

                                                     solemnly affirm
 
I will bear true faith and 
allegiance to the Constitution of India as by law established and that I will, 
as in duty bound, honestly and faithfully serve in the naval service and go 
wherever ordered by sea, land or air, and that I will observe and obey all 
commands of the President and the commands of any superior officer set over me, 
even to the peril of my life.”
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Liability for 
service of officers and sailors.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to the provisions of sub-section (4), officers and sailors shall be 
liable to serve in the Indian Navy or the Indian Naval Reserve Forces, as the 
case may be, until they are duly discharged, dismissed with disgrace, retired, 
permitted to resign, or released.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No officer shall be at 
liberty to resign his office except with the permission of the Central 
Government and no sailor shall be at liberty to resign his post except with the 
permission of the prescribed officer.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The acceptance of any 
resignation shall be a matter within the discretion of the Central Government or 
the officer concerned, as the case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Officers retired or 
permitted to resign shall be liable to recall to naval service in an emergency 
in accordance with regulations made under this Act, and on such recall shall be 
liable to serve until they have been duly discharged, dismissed, dismissed with 
disgrace, retired, permitted to resign, or released.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Tenure of service 
of officers and sailors.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every officer and sailor shall hold office during the pleasure of the President.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to the 
provisions of this Act and the regulations made thereunder,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the Central 
Government may dismiss or discharge or retire from the naval service any officer 
or sailor;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the Chief of 
the Naval Staff or any prescribed officer may dismiss or discharge from the 
naval service any sailor.
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Discharge on expiry 
of engagement.—Subject 
to the provisions of section 18, a sailor shall be entitled to be discharged at 
the expiration of the term of service for which he is engaged unless—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  such 
expiration occurs during active service in which case he shall be liable to 
continue to serve for such further period as may be required by the Chief of the 
Naval Staff; or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  he is 
re-enrolled in accordance with the regulations made under this Act.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Provisions as to 
discharge.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A sailor entitled to be discharged under section 16 shall be discharged with all 
convenient speed and in any case within one month of his becoming so entitled:
 
Provided that where a 
sailor is serving overseas at the time he becomes entitled to be discharged, he 
shall be returned to India for the purpose of being discharged with all 
convenient speed, and in any case within three months of his becoming so 
entitled:
 
Provided further that 
where such enrolled person serving overseas does not desire to return to India, 
he may be discharged at the place where he is at the time.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every sailor 
discharged shall be entitled to be conveyed free of cost from any place he may 
be at the time to any place in India to which he may desire to go.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in the preceding sub-sections, an enrolled person shall 
remain liable to serve until he is duly discharged.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every sailor who is 
dismissed, discharged, retired, permitted to resign or released from service 
shall be furnished by the prescribed officer with a certificate in the language 
which is the mother tongue of such sailor and also in the English language 
setting forth—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the authority 
terminating his service;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the cause for 
such termination; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  the full 
period of his service in the Indian Navy and the Indian Naval Reserve Forces.
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Saving of powers of 
dismissal by Naval tribunals.—Nothing 
in this Chapter shall affect the award by a naval tribunal of the punishment of 
dismissal with disgrace, or dismissal from the naval service under this Act.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Restriction 
respecting right to form associations, freedom of speech, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No person subject to naval law shall, without the express sanction of the 
Central Government,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  be a member 
of, or be associated in any way with, any trade union, labour union, political 
association or with any class of trade unions, labour unions or political 
associations, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  be a member 
of, or be associated in any way with, any other society, institution, 
association or organisation that is not recognised as part of the Armed Forces 
of the Union or is not of a purely social, recreational or religious nature.
 
Explanation.—If 
any question arises as to whether any society, institution, association or 
organisation is of a purely social, recreational or religious nature, the 
decision of the Central Government thereon shall be final.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> No person subject to 
naval law shall attend or address any meeting or take any part in any 
demonstration organised by any body of persons for any political purposes or for 
such other purposes as may be specified in this behalf by the Central 
Government.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No person subject to 
naval law shall communicate with the press or publish or cause to be published 
any book, letter or other document having bearing on any naval, army or air 
force subject or containing any fact or opinion calculated to embarrass the 
relations between the Government and the people or any section thereof or 
between the Government and any foreign country, except with the previous 
sanction of the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> No person subject to 
naval law shall whilst he is so subject practise any profession or carry on any 
occupation, trade or business without the previous sanction of the Chief of the 
Naval Staff.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>19A</number> Re-instalment of 
persons belonging to the Indian Naval Reserve Forces on termination of period of 
training or actual service with the Indian Navy.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If a person belonging to the Indian Naval Reserve Forces is, during the period 
of his employment under an employer called up for training or called up into 
actual service with the Indian Navy in pursuance of his liability under any 
regulations made under this Act, it shall be the duty of every such employer to 
reinstate the person in his employment on the termination of the period of his 
training or service with the Indian Navy in an occupation and under conditions 
not less favourable to him than those which would have been applicable to him 
had his employment not been so interrupted:
 
Provided that if the 
employer refuses to reinstate such person or denies his liability to reinstate 
such person, or if for any reason reinstatement of such person is represented by 
the employer to be impracticable, either party may refer the matter to the 
authority prescribed in this behalf and that authority shall, after considering 
all matters which may be put before it and after making such further inquiry 
into the matter as may be prescribed, pass an order—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  exempting the 
employer from the provisions of this section, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  requiring the 
employer to re-employ such person on such terms as the authority thinks 
suitable, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  requiring the 
employer to pay to such person by way of compensation for failure or inability 
to re-employ a sum not exceeding an amount equal to six months’ remuneration at 
the rate at which his last remuneration was payable to him by the employer.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If any employer fails 
to obey the order of any such authority as is referred to in the proviso to 
sub-section (1), he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to one 
thousand rupees, and the court by which an employer is convicted under this 
sub-section shall order him (if he has not already been so required by the said 
authority) to pay to the person whom he has failed to re-employ a sum equal to 
six months’ remuneration at the rate at which his last remuneration was payable 
to him by the employer, and any amount so required to be paid either by the said 
authority or by the court shall be recoverable as if it were a fine imposed by 
such court.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In any proceeding 
under this section it shall be a defence for an employee to prove that the 
person formerly employed did not apply to the employer for reinstatement within 
a period of two months from the termination of the period of his training or 
service with the Indian Navy.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The duty imposed by 
sub-section (1) upon an employer to reinstate in his employment a person such as 
is described in that sub-section shall attach to an employer who, before such 
person is actually called up for training, or called up into actual service with 
the Indian Navy, terminates his employment in circumstances such as to indicate 
an intention to evade the duty imposed by that sub-section, and such intention 
shall be presumed until the contrary is proved, if the termination takes place 
after the issue of orders calling him up for training or service with the Indian 
Navy under this Act.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>19B</number> Preservation of 
service rights belonging to the Indian Naval Reserve Forces when called up for 
training or actual service with the Indian Navy.—When 
any person belonging to the Indian Naval Reserve Forces and called up for 
training or called up into actual service with the Indian Navy in pursuance of 
his liability under any regulations made under this Act, has any rights under 
any provident fund or superannuation fund or other scheme for the benefit of 
employees maintained in connection with the employment he relinquishes, he shall 
continue, so long as he is engaged in training, or service with the Indian Navy 
and if he is reinstated, until such reinstatement under the provisions of this 
Act, to have in respect of such fund or scheme such rights as may be prescribed.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Immunity from 
attachment.—The 
arms, clothes, equipments, accoutrements or necessaries of any person in the 
naval service, while subject to naval law, shall not be seized, nor shall the 
pay and allowances or any part thereof of such person be attached under any 
process or direction issued by, or by the authority of, any court or public 
servant in respect of any claim, decree or order enforceable against him.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Immunity from 
arrest for debt.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No person in the naval service shall, so long as he is subject to naval law, be 
liable to be arrested for debt under any process or direction issued by, or the 
authority of, any court or public servant.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any such person is 
arrested in contravention of the provisions of sub- section (1), the court of 
public servant by whom or by whose authority such process of direction was 
issued shall on complaint by the person arrested or by his superior officer 
enquire into the case and if satisfied that the arrest was made in contravention 
of sub-section (1), shall make an order for the immediate discharge of the 
person arrested and may award to the complainant the costs of the complaint to 
be recoverable in the same manner as if such costs were awarded to him by a 
decree against the person at whose instance such process or direction was 
issued.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No court-fee shall be 
payable on a complaint made under sub-section (2) or for recovery of the costs 
that may be awarded under that sub-section.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Immunity of persons 
attending court-martial or disciplinary court from arrest.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No president or other member of a court-martial or disciplinary court, no judge 
advocate, no party to any proceeding before a court-martial or disciplinary 
court or no advocate or agent of such party, and no witness acting in obedience 
to a summon to attend a court-martial or disciplinary court shall, while 
proceeding to, attending or returning from, a court-martial or disciplinary 
court, be liable to arrest under any civil or revenue process.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any such person is 
arrested under any such process, he may be discharged by order of the 
court-martial or disciplinary court, as the case may be.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Remedy of aggrieved 
persons.—
<section><number>1</number> If 
an officer or sailor thinks that he has suffered any personal, oppression, 
injustice or other ill-treatment at the hands of any superior officer, he may 
make a complaint in accordance with the regulations made under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The regulations 
referred to in sub-section (1) shall provide for the complaint to be forwarded 
to the Central Government for its consideration if the complainant is not 
satisfied with the decision on his complaint.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>24</number> Priority of hearing 
of cases concerning persons in the naval service.—
<section><number>1</number> 
On the presentation to any civil or revenue court by or on behalf of any person 
in the naval service while subject to naval law of a certificate from the proper 
naval authority of leave of absence having been granted to or applied for by him 
for the purpose of prosecuting of defending any suit or other proceeding in such 
court, the court shall, on the application of such person, arrange, so far as 
may be possible, for the hearing and final disposal of such suit or other 
proceeding within the period of the leave so granted or applied for.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The certificate from 
the proper naval authority shall state the first and last day of the leave 
granted or applied for and set forth a description of the case with respect to 
which the leave has been granted or applied for, and shall be duly signed and 
authenticated by such authority.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No fee shall be 
payable to the court in respect of the presentation of any such certificate, or 
in respect of any application by or on behalf of any such person for priority 
for the hearing of his case and every such certificate duly signed and 
authenticated as aforesaid shall be conclusive evidence of the correctness of 
the contents thereof.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where the court is 
unable to arrange for the hearing and final disposal of the suit or other 
proceeding within the period of the leave granted or applied for as aforesaid, 
it shall record its reasons for having been unable to do so, and shall cause a 
copy thereof to be furnished to such person on his application, without any 
payment whatever by him in respect either of the application for such copy or of 
the copy itself.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Every criminal court 
before which a case is pending against a person in the naval service, shall, so 
far as may be possible, arrange for the early hearing and final disposal of such 
case.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Right of the Chief 
of the Naval Staff or commanding officers to obtain copies of judgments or 
orders made by a criminal court.—A 
criminal court before which any proceedings have been taken against a person in 
the naval service while subject to naval law shall, on application by the Chief 
of the Naval Staff or the commanding officer of that person, grant copies of the 
judgement and final orders in the case free of cost and without delay.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Saving of rights 
and privileges under other laws.—The 
rights and privileges specified in the preceding sections of this Chapter shall 
be in addition to, and not in derogation of, any other rights and privileges 
conferred on persons in the naval service while subject to naval law or on 
members of the regular Army, Navy and Air Force generally by any other law for 
the time being in force.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Deductions from 
pay, etc., not to be made unless authorised.—No 
deductions other than those authorised by or under this or any other Act shall 
be made from the pay, pensions, gratuities, allowances and other benefits due to 
officers and sailors under any regulations for the time being in force.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Deductions from pay 
and allowances of officers.—The 
following deductions may be made from the pay and allowances of an officer 
without recourse to trial by a naval tribunal, namely:—
 <section>
       <number>1</number>  all pay and 
allowances for everyday of absence without leave unless an explanation is given 
to the satisfaction of the commanding officer for such absence and approved by 
the Chief of the Naval Staff:
 
                 Provided 
that the officer is not dealt with by a naval tribunal for the said absence;
 </section><section>
       <number>2</number>  all pay and 
allowances for everyday while he is in civil or naval custody or under 
suspension from duty on a charge for an offence of which he is afterwards 
convicted by a competent naval tribunal or criminal court and sentenced to 
imprisonment;
 </section><section>
       <number>3</number>  all pay and 
allowances for everyday while he is in hospital on account of sickness certified 
by the prescribed medical officer to have been caused by an act amounting to an 
offence punishable under this Act:
 
                 Provided 
that such certificate is accepted by the Chief of the Naval Staff;
 </section><section>
       <number>4</number>  any sum 
required to make good the pay and allowances of any person subject to naval law 
which he has unlawfully retained or refused to pay;
 </section><section>
       <number>5</number>  any sum 
required to make good any loss, damage or destruction of Government property or 
property belonging to a naval mess, band or institution which after due 
investigation appears to the Central Government, the Chief of the Naval Staff or 
the prescribed officer to have been occasioned by the wrongful act or negligence 
on the part of the officer;
 </section><section>
       <number>6</number>  any sum 
required to be paid for the maintenance of his wife or legitimate or 
illegitimate children under the provisions of section 31;
 </section><section>
       <number>7</number>  any sum which 
after due investigation appears to the prescribed officer to be due to a service 
mess or canteen.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>29</number> Deductions from pay 
and allowances of sailors.—The 
following deductions may be made from the pay and allowances of a sailor without 
recourse to trial by a naval tribunal, namely:—
 <section>
       <number>1</number>  all pay and 
allowances for everyday of absence without leave unless an explanation is given 
to the satisfaction of the commanding officer for such absence;
 
                 Provided 
that the sailor is not dealt with by a naval tribunal for the said absence;
 </section><section>
       <number>2</number>  all pay and 
allowances for everyday he is in confinement on a charge for an offence of which 
he is afterwards convicted by a competent naval tribunal or criminal court;
 </section><section>
       <number>3</number>  all pay and 
allowances for everyday he is in hospital on account of sickness certified by 
the prescribed medical officer to have been caused by an act amounting to an 
offence punishable under this Act:
 
                 Provided 
that such certificate is accepted by the Chief of the Naval Staff or the 
prescribed officer;
 </section><section>
       <number>4</number>  any sum 
required to make good any loss, damage or destruction of any property which 
after due investigation appears to the Central Government or the Chief of the 
Naval Staff or the prescribed officer to have been occasioned by the wrongful 
act or negligence on the part of the sailor;
 </section><section>
       <number>5</number>  any sum 
required to be paid for the maintenance of his wife or legitimate or 
illegitimate children under the provisions of section 31.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>30</number> Deductions awarded 
by naval tribunals.—Deductions 
may be made from the pay and allowances of an officer or sailor in respect of 
any sentence of fine, forfeiture or mulcts of pay and allowances awarded in 
pursuance of this Act by a naval tribunal.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>31</number> Liability for 
maintenance of wife and children.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A person subject to naval law shall be liable to maintain his wife and his 
legitimate or illegitimate children to the same extent as if he were not so 
subject; but the execution or enforcement of any decree or order for maintenance 
passed or made against such person shall not be directed against his person, 
pay, arms, ammunition, equipments, instruments or clothing.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-section (1),—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  where it 
appears to the satisfaction of the Central Government or the Chief of the Naval 
Staff or the prescribed authority that a person subject to naval law has without 
reasonable cause deserted or left in destitute circumstances his wife or any 
legitimate child unable to maintain himself or has by reason of contracting a 
second marriage become liable to provide separate maintenance to his first wife; 
or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  where any 
decree or order is passed under any law against a person who is, or subsequently 
becomes, subject to naval law for the maintenance of his wife or his legitimate 
or illegitimate children and a copy of the decree or order is sent to the 
Central Government or the Chief of the Naval Staff of the prescribed authority;
 
the Central Government, or 
the Chief of the Naval Staff or the prescribed authority may direct a portion of 
the pay of the person so subject to naval law to be deducted from such pay and 
appropriated in the prescribed manner towards the maintenance of his wife or 
children but the amount deducted shall not exceed the amount fixed by the decree 
or order (if any) and shall not be at a higher rate than the rate fixed by 
regulations made under this Act in this behalf:
 
Provided that in the case 
of a decree or order for maintenance referred to in clause (b) no deduction from 
pay shall be directed unless the Central Government or the Chief of the Naval 
Staff or the prescribed authority is satisfied that the person against whom such 
decree or order has been passed or made, has had a reasonable opportunity of 
appearing, or has actually appeared either in person or through a duly appointed 
legal practitioner, to defend the case before the Court by which the decree or 
order was passed or made.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Where arrears of 
maintenance under a decree or order referred to in sub-section (2) have 
accumulated while the person against whom the decree or order has been made is 
subject to naval law whether or not deductions in respect thereof have been made 
from his pay under this section, no step for the recovery of those arrears shall 
be taken in any court after such person has ceased to be so subject unless the 
court is satisfied that he has, since he ceased to be subject to naval law, the 
ability to pay the arrears or any part thereof and has failed to do so.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in any other law, where a proceeding for obtaining a decree 
or order for maintenance is started against a person subject to naval law—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the court may 
send the process for service on that person to the commanding officer of the 
ship on which such person is serving or on the books of which he is born, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  if, by reason 
of the ship being at sea or otherwise, it is impracticable for the court to send 
the process to the commanding officer, the court may, after not less than three 
weeks’ notice to the Central Government send it to a Secretary to that 
Government for transmission to the commanding officer for service on that 
person:
 
Provided that such service 
shall not be valid unless there is sent along with the process such sum of money 
as may be prescribed to enable that person to attend the hearing of the 
proceeding and to return to his ship or quarters after such attendance.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> If a decree or order 
is passed or made in the proceeding against the person on whom the process is 
served, the sum sent along with the process shall be awarded as costs of the 
proceeding against that person.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> No process in any 
proceeding under this section shall be valid against a person subject to naval 
law if served on him after he is under orders for service at a foreign station 
or beyond Indian waters.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The production of a 
certificate of the receipt of the process purporting to be signed by such 
commanding officer as aforesaid shall be evidence that the process has been duly 
served, unless the contrary is proved.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> Where by a decree or 
order a copy whereof has been sent to the Central Government or the Chief of the 
Naval Staff or the prescribed authority under clause (b) of sub-section (2), the 
person against whom the decree or order has been passed or made is directed to 
pay as costs any sum sent along with the process referred to in the proviso to 
sub-section (4), the Central Government may pay to the person entitled an amount 
in full satisfaction of that sum and the amount so paid by the Central 
Government shall be deemed to be a public demand recoverable from the person 
against whom the decree or order has been passed or made, and without prejudice 
to any other mode of recovery, may be recovered by deduction from his pay, in 
addition to the deductions authorised by sub-section (2).
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> Where any person 
subject to naval law has made an allotment of any part of his pay and allowances 
for the benefit of his wife, that allotment shall not be discontinued or reduced 
until the Central Government or the Chief of the Naval Staff or the prescribed 
authority is satisfied that the allotment should no longer be made or should be 
reduced.
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> In this section the 
expression “pay” includes all sums payable to a person subject to naval law in 
respect of his services other than allowances in lieu of lodgings, rations, 
provisions, clothing and travelling allowances.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>32</number> Limit of certain 
deductions.—Except 
when the deductions are made under sub-sections 
<section><number>1</number>, (2) and (4) of section 28 
or sub-sections (1) and (2) of section 29, the total deductions from the pay and 
allowances of an officer or sailor shall not exceed in any one month one-half of 
his pay and allowances for that month.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>33</number> Remission of 
deductions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any deduction from the pay and allowances authorised by or under this Act may be 
remitted by the Chief of the Naval Staff in his discretion.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Such deduction may 
also be remitted in such manner and to such extent and by such other authority 
as may be prescribed.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>34</number> Misconduct by 
officers or persons in command.—Every 
flag officer, captain or other person subject to naval law who, being in command 
on any ship, vessel or aircraft of the Indian Navy, or any naval establishment—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  fails to use 
his utmost exertions to bring into action any such ship, vessel or, aircraft 
which it is his duty to bring into action; or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  surrenders any 
such ship vessel or aircraft to the enemy when it is capable of being 
successfully defended or destroyed; or
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  fails to 
pursue the enemy whom it is his duty to pursue or to assist to the utmost of his 
ability any friend whom it is his duty to assist; or
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  in the course 
of any action by or against the enemy improperly withdraws from the action or 
from his station or fails in his own person and according to his rank to 
encourage the persons under his command to fight courageously; or
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number>  surrenders any 
such naval establishment or any part of such an establishment to the enemy when 
it is capable of being successfully defended or when it is his duty to cause it 
to be destroyed;
 
shall,—
 </section><section>
       <number>a</number>  if such act is 
committed with intent to assist the enemy or from cowardice, be punished with 
death or such other punishment as is hereinafter mentioned; and
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  in any other 
case, be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to seven years 
or such other punishment as is hereinafter mentioned.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>35</number> Misconduct by 
persons other than those in command.—Every 
person subject to naval law who, not being in command of any naval establishment 
or any ship, vessel or aircraft of the Indian Navy, fails when ordered to 
prepare for action by or against the enemy, or during any such action, to use 
his utmost exertions to carry the lawful orders of his superior officers into 
execution shall,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  if such act is 
committed with intent to assist the enemy, be punished with death or such other 
punishment as is hereinafter mentioned; and
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  in any other 
case, be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to seven years 
or such other punishment as is hereinafter mentioned.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>36</number> Delaying or 
discouraging action or service commanded.—Every 
person subject to naval law who wilfully delays or discourages upon any pretext 
whatsoever, any action or service which has been commanded on the part of the 
Navy, regular Army, or Air Force or of any forces co-operating therewith shall,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  if such act is 
committed with intent to assist the enemy, be punished with death or such other 
punishment as is hereinafter mentioned; and
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  in any other 
case, be punished with imprisonment which may extend to seven years or such 
other punishment as is hereinafter mentioned.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>37</number> Penalty for 
disobedience in action.—Every 
person subject to naval law who, being in the presence or vicinity of the enemy 
or having been ordered to be prepared for action by or against the enemy—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  deserts his 
post; or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  sleeps upon 
his watch,
 
shall be punished with 
death or such other punishment as is hereinafter mentioned.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>38</number> Penalty for spying.—Every 
person not otherwise subject to naval law who is or acts as a spy for the enemy 
shall be punished under this act with death or such other punishment as is 
hereinafter mentioned as if he were a person subject to naval law.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>39</number> Correspondence, etc., 
with the enemy.—Every 
person subject to naval law, who,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  traitorously 
holds correspondence with the enemy or gives intelligence to the enemy; or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  fails to make 
known to the proper authorities any information he may have received from the 
enemy; or
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  assists the 
enemy with any supplies; or
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  having been 
made a prisoner of war, voluntarily serves with or aids to enemy,
 
shall be punished with 
death or such other punishment as is hereinafter mentioned.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>40</number> Improper 
communication with the enemy.—Every 
person subject to naval law who without any traitorous intention holds any 
improper communication with the enemy shall be punished with imprisonment for a 
term which may extend to fourteen years or such other punishment as is 
hereinafter mentioned.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>41</number> Deserting post and 
neglect of duty.—Every 
person subject to naval law, who,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  deserts his 
post; or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  sleeps upon 
his watch; or
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  fails to 
perform or negligently performs the duty imposed on him; or 
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  wilfully 
conceals any words, practice or design tending to the hindrance of the naval 
service,
 
shall be punished with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years or such other punishment 
as is hereinafter mentioned.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>42</number> Mutiny defined.—Mutiny 
means any assembly or combination of two or more persons subject to naval law, 
the Army Act, 1950 (46 of 1950), or the Air Force Act, 1950 (45 of 1950), or 
between persons two at least of whom are subject to naval law or any such Act,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  to overthrow 
or resist lawful authority in the Navy, regular Army or Air Force or any part of 
any one or more of them or any forces co-operating therewith or any part 
thereof; or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  to disobey 
such authority in such circumstances as to make the disobedience subversive of 
discipline or with the object of avoiding any duty or service against, or in 
connection with operations against, the enemy; or
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  to show 
contempt to such authority in such circumstances as to make such conduct 
subversive of discipline; or
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  to impede the 
performance of any duty or service in the Navy, regular Army or Air Force or any 
part of any one or more of them or any forces co-operating therewith or any part 
thereof.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>43</number> Punishment for 
mutiny.—Every 
person subject to naval law, who,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  joins in a 
mutiny; or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  begins, 
incites, causes or conspires with any other persons to cause a mutiny; or
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  endeavours to 
incite any person to join in a mutiny or to commit an act of mutiny; or
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  endeavours to 
seduce any person in the regular Army, Navy or Air Force from his allegiance to 
the Constitution or loyalty to the State or duty to his superior officers or 
uses any means to compel or induce any such person to abstain from acting 
against the enemy or discourage such person from acting against the enemy; or
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number>  does not use 
his utmost exertions to suppress or prevent a mutiny; or
 </section><section>
        <number>f</number>  wilfully 
conceals any traitorous or mutinous practice or design or any traitorous words 
spoken against the State; or
 </section><section>
       <number>g</number>  knowing or 
having reason to believe in the existence of any mutiny or of any intention to 
mutiny does not without delay give information thereof to the commanding officer 
of his ship or other superior officer; or
 </section><section>
       <number>h</number>  utters word of 
sedition or mutiny,
 
shall be punished with 
death or such other punishment as is hereinafter mentioned.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>44</number> Persons on board 
ships or aircraft seducing naval personnel from allegiance.—Every 
person not otherwise subject to naval law who being on board any ship or 
aircraft of the Indian Navy or on board any ship in the service of the 
Government endeavours to seduce from his allegiance to the Constitution or 
loyalty to the State or duty to superior officers any person subject to naval 
law shall be punished under this Act with death or such other punishment as is 
hereinafter mentioned as if he were a person subject to naval law.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>45</number> Striking Superior 
officers.—Every 
person subject to naval law who commits any of the following offences that is to 
say,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  strikes or 
attempts to strike his superior officer; or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  draws or lifts 
up any weapon against such officer; or
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  uses or 
attempts to use any violence against such officer,
 
shall be punished,—
 
if the offence is 
committed on active service with imprisonment for a term which may extend to ten 
years or such other punishment as is hereinafter mentioned; and
 
in any other case, with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years or such other punishment 
as is hereinafter mentioned.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>46</number> Ill-treating 
subordinates.—Every 
person subject to naval law who is guilty of ill-treating any other person 
subject to such law, being his subordinate in rank or position, shall be 
punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to seven years or such 
other punishment as is hereinafter mentioned.



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>47</number> Disobedience and 
insubordination.—Every 
person subject to naval law, who,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  wilfully 
disobeys any lawful command of his superior officer; or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  in the 
presence of his superior officer, or otherwise shows or expresses his intention 
to disobey a lawful command given by such superior officer; or
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  uses 
insubordinate, threatening or insulting language to his superior officer; or
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  behaves with 
contempt to his superior officer,
 
shall, if the offence is 
committed on active service or in a manner to show wilful defiance of authority, 
be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to ten years or such 
other punishment as is hereinafter mentioned and in other, cases be punished 
with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years or such other 
punishment as is hereinafter mentioned.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>48</number> Quarrelling, 
fighting and disorderly behaviour.—Every 
person subject to naval law, who,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  quarrels, 
fights with or strikes any other person, whether such person is or is not 
subject to naval law; or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  uses 
reproachful or provoking speeches or gestures tending to make a quarrel or 
disturbance; or
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  behaves in a 
disorderly manner,
 
shall be punished with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years or such other punishment 
as is hereinafter mentioned.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>49</number> Desertion.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every person subject to naval law who absents himself from his ship or from the 
place where his duty requires him to be, with an intention of not returning to 
such ship or place, or who at any time and under any circumstances when absent 
from his ship or place of duty does any act which shows that he has an intention 
of not returning to such ship or place is said to desert.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every person who 
deserts shall,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  if he deserts 
to the enemy, be punished with death or such other punishment as is hereinafter 
mentioned; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  if he deserts 
under any other circumstances, be punished with imprisonment for a term which 
may extend to fourteen years or such other punishment as is hereinafter 
mentioned,
 
and in every such case he 
shall forfeit all pay, head money, bounty, salvage prize money and allowances 
that have been earned by him and all annuities, pensions, gratuities, medals and 
decorations that may have been granted to him and also all clothes and effects 
which he may have left on board the ship or the place from which he deserted, 
unless the tribunal by which he is tried or the Central Government or the Chief 
of the Naval Staff, otherwise directs.
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>50</number> Seducing person to 
desert.—Every 
person subject to naval law who endeavours to seduce any other person subject to 
naval law to desert shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may 
extend to two years or such other punishment as is hereinafter mentioned.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>51</number> Breaking out of 
ship and absence without leave.—Every 
person subject to naval law who without being guilty of desertion improperly 
leaves his ship or place of duty or any place where he is required to be or is 
absent without leave shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may 
extend to two years or such other punishment as is hereinafter mentioned and 
shall also be punished by such mulcts of pay and allowances as may be 
prescribed.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>52</number> Drunkenness.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every person subject to naval law who is guilty of drunkenness shall, if the 
offence is committed on active service, be punished with imprisonment for a term 
which may extend to two years or such other punishment as is hereinafter 
mentioned and in other cases be punished with imprisonment for a term which may 
extend to six months or such other punishment as is hereinafter mentioned.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> For the purpose of 
sub-section (1), a person shall be deemed to be guilty of drunkenness if owing 
to the influence of alcohol or any drug whether alone or in combination with any 
other circumstances, he is unfit to be entrusted with his duty or with any duty 
which he may be called upon to perform or behaves in a disorderly manner or in a 
manner likely to bring discredit to the naval service.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>53</number> Uncleanness or 
indecent acts.—Every 
person subject to naval law who is guilty of,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  uncleanness; 
or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  any indecent 
act,
 
shall be punished with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years or such other punishment 
as is hereinafter mentioned.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>54</number> Cruelty and conduct 
unbecoming the character of an officer.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every officer subject to naval law who is guilty of cruelty shall be punished 
with imprisonment for a term which may extend to seven years or such other 
punishment as is hereinafter mentioned.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every officer subject 
to naval law who is guilty of any scandalous or fraudulent conduct or of any 
conduct unbecoming the character of an officer shall be punished with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years or such other punishment 
as is hereinafter mentioned.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>55</number> Losing ship or 
aircraft.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every person subject to naval law who wilfully loses, strands or hazards or 
suffers to be lost, stranded or hazarded any ship of the Indian Navy or in the 
service of the Government, or loses or suffers to be lost any aircraft of the 
Indian Navy or in the service of the Government shall be punished with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to fourteen years or such other 
punishment as is hereinafter mentioned.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every person subject 
to naval law who negligently or by any default loses, strands or hazards or 
suffers to be lost, stranded or hazarded any ship of the Indian Navy or in the 
service of the Government, or loses or suffers to be lost any aircraft of the 
Indian Navy or in the service of the Government shall be punished with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years or such other punishment 
as is hereinafter mentioned.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>55A</number> Dangerous 
authorised flying.—Every 
person subject to naval law, who is guilty of any act or neglect in flying or in 
the use of any aircraft of the Indian Navy or in relation to any such aircraft 
or aircraft material, which causes or is likely to cause loss of life or bodily 
injury to any person shall,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  if he acts 
wilfully or with wilful neglect, be punished with imprisonment for a term which 
may extend to fourteen years 

1[or such other 
punishment as is hereinafter mentioned]; and
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  in any other 
case be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years or 
such other punishment as is hereinafter mentioned.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>55B</number> Inaccurate 
certificate.—Every 
person subject to naval law who signs any certificate in relation to an aircraft 
or aircraft material belonging to or in the service of the Government without 
ensuring the accuracy thereof, shall be punished with imprisonment for a term 
which may extend to two years or such other punishment as is hereinafter 
mentioned.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>55C</number> Low flying and 
annoyance by flying.—Every 
person subject to naval law being the pilot of an aircraft of the Indian Navy, 
who,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  flies it at a 
height less than the minimum height authorised by his commanding officer or 
appropriate service authority except while taking off or landing, or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  flies it so as 
to cause or likely to cause unnecessary annoyance to any person,
 
shall be punished with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years or such other punishment 
as is hereinafter mentioned.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>55D</number> Disobedience of 
lawful command of captain of an aircraft.—Every 
person subject to naval law, who, while he is in an aircraft belonging to or in 
the use of the Government, disobeys any lawful command given by the captain of 
the aircraft, whether such captain is subject to naval law or not, in relation 
to all matters relating to flying or handling of the aircraft or affecting the 
safety thereof shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to fourteen years or such other punishment as is hereinafter mentioned.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>56</number> Offences by 
officers in charge of convoy.—
<section><number>1</number> 
All officers appointed for the convoy and protection of any ships or vessels 
shall diligently perform their duty without delay according to their 
instructions in that behalf.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every such officer 
subject to naval law, who,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  does not 
defend the ships and goods under his convoy without deviation to any other 
objects; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  refuses to 
fight in their defence if they are assailed; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  cowardly 
abandons and exposes the ships in his convoy to hazard; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  demands or 
exacts any money or other reward from any merchant or master for convoying any 
ships or vessels entrusted to his care; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  misuses the 
masters or mariners thereof,
 
shall be punished with 
death or such other punishment as is hereinafter mentioned, and shall also make 
such reparation in damages to the merchants, owners and others as a civil court 
of competent jurisdiction may adjudge.
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>57</number> Taking unauthorised 
goods on board ship.—Every 
officer subject to naval law in command of any ship of the Indian Navy who 
receives on board or permits to be received on board such ship any goods or 
merchandise whatsoever other than for the sole use of the ship or persons 
belonging to the ship, except goods and merchandise on board any ship which may 
be ship-wrecked or in imminent danger either on the high seas or in some port, 
creek, or harbour, for the purpose of preserving them for their proper owners, 
or except such goods or merchandise as he may at any time be ordered to take or 
receive on board by order of the Central Government or his superior officer, 
shall be punished with dismissal from the naval service or such other punishment 
as is hereinafter mentioned.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>58</number> Offences in respect 
of property.—Every 
person subject to naval law who wastefully expends or fraudulently buys, sells 
or receives any property of Government or property belonging to a naval, 
military or air force mess, band or institution, and every person who knowingly 
permits any such wasteful expenditure, or any such fraudulent purchase, sale or 
receipt, shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to two 
years or such other punishment as is hereinafter mentioned.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>59</number> Arson.—Every 
person subject to naval law who unlawfully sets fire to any dockyard, 
victualling yard or steam factory yard, arsenal, magazine, building stores or to 
any ship, vessel, hoy, barge, boat, aircraft, or other craft or furniture 
thereunto belonging, not being the property of an enemy, shall be punished with 
death or such other punishment as is hereinafter mentioned.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>60</number> Falsifying official 
documents and false declarations.—Every 
person subject to naval law—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  who knowingly 
makes or signs a false report, return, list, certificate, book, muster or other 
document to be used for official purposes; or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  who commands, 
counsels or procures the making or signing thereof; or
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  who aids or 
abets any other person in the making or signing thereof; or
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  who knowingly 
makes, commands, counsels or procures the making of, a false or fraudulent 
statement or a fraudulent omission in any such document,
 
shall be punished with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to seven years or such other punishment 
as is hereinafter mentioned.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>61</number> Malingering, 
etc.—Every 
person subject to naval law—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  who wilfully 
does any act or wilfully disobeys any orders whether in hospital or elsewhere 
with intent to produce or to aggravate any disease or infirmity or to delay his 
cure; or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  who feigns any 
disease, infirmity or inability to perform his duty,
 
shall be punished with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years or such other punishment 
as is hereinafter mentioned.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>62</number> Penalty for 
endeavouring to stir up disturbance on account of unwholesomeness of victuals or 
other just grounds.—Every 
person subject to naval law who has any cause of complaint either of the 
unwholesomeness of the victuals or upon any other just ground shall quietly make 
the same known to his superior or captain or to the Chief of the Naval Staff 
shall, in accordance with the prescribed channels of communication and the said 
superior captain or Chief of the Naval Staff, as far as he is able, cause the 
same to be presently remedied; and every person subject to naval law who upon 
any pretence whatever attempts to stir up any disturbance shall be punished with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to fourteen years or such other 
punishment as is hereinafter mentioned.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>63</number> Offences in respect 
of papers relating to prize.—
<section><number>1</number> 
All the papers, charter-parties, bills of lading, passports and other writings 
whatsoever that shall be taken, seized, or found aboard any ships which are 
taken as prize, shall be duly preserved and the commanding officer of the ship 
which takes such prize shall send the originals entire and without fraud to the 
court of competent jurisdiction or such other court or commissioners as shall be 
authorised to determine whether such prize be lawful capture, there to be 
viewed, made use of and proceeded upon according to law.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every commanding 
officer who wilfully fails to send the papers, charter-parties, bills of lading, 
passports or other writings whatsoever that shall be taken, seized or found 
aboard any ships which are taken as prize to the proper court or other authority 
shall be punished with dismissal from the naval service or such other punishment 
as is hereinafter mentioned and in addition shall forfeit and lose any share of 
the capture.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>64</number> Offences in respect 
of prize.—Every 
person subject to naval law who takes out of any prize or ship seized for prize, 
any money, plate, or goods, unless it is necessary for the better securing 
thereof, or for the necessary use and service of any ships of war of the Indian 
Navy, before the same be adjudged lawful prize in a court of competent 
jurisdiction, shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
two years or such other punishment as is hereinafter mentioned, and in addition 
shall forfeit and lose his share of the capture.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>65</number> Offences in respect 
of persons on board of prize ship.—Every 
person subject to naval law who in any sort pillages, beats, or ill-treats 
officers, mariners or other persons on board a ship or vessel taken as prize or 
who unlawfully strips them of their clothes, shall be punished with imprisonment 
for a term which may extend to two years or such other punishment as is 
hereinafter mentioned.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>66</number> Unlawful taking or 
ransoming of prize.—Every 
commanding officer of ship of the Indian Navy subject to naval law, who,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  by collusion 
with the enemy takes as prize any vessel, goods or thing; or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  unlawfully 
agrees with any person for the ransoming of any vessel, goods or thing taken as 
prize; or
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  in pursuance 
of any unlawful agreement for ransoming or otherwise by collusion actually quits 
or restores any vessel, goods or thing taken as prize,
 
shall be punished with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years or such other punishment 
as is hereinafter mentioned.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>67</number> Breaking bulk on 
board a prize ship.—Every 
person subject to naval law who breaks bulk on board any vessel taken as prize, 
or detained in the exercise of any belligerent right or under any law relating 
to piracy or to the slave trade or to the customs, with intent dishonestly to 
misappropriate anything therein or belonging thereto, shall be punished with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years or such other punishment 
as is hereinafter mentioned.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>68</number> Violation of the 
Act, regulations and orders.—Every 
person subject to naval law who neglects to obey or contravenes any provisions 
of this Act or any regulation made under this Act or any general or local order, 
shall, unless other punishment is provided in this Act for such neglect or 
contravention, be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to two 
years or such other punishment as is hereinafter mentioned.
 


comment
 
Where the officer was 
proved to have intimate contacts with foreign national whom he invited to visit 
India and travelled with her all over the country and he did not also take 
permission of superior officials for the same, such acts of the officer indicate 
grave misconduct on the part of naval officer who was closely connected with the 
security of our country, the punishment of dismissal of service would neither be 
held to be disproportionate not hars; (1994) 2 Cur LR 919 (1922) (Bom). 

 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>69</number> Offences in 
relation to court-martial.—Every 
person subject to naval law, who,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  being duly 
summoned or ordered to attend as a witness before a court-martial wilfully or 
without reasonable excuse fails to attend; or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  refuses to 
take an oath or make an affirmation legally required by a court-martial to be 
taken or made; or
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  being sworn, 
refuses to answer any questions which he is in law bound to answer; or
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  refuses to 
produce or deliver up a document in his power which the court may legally 
demand; or
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number>  is guilty of 
contempt of court-martial,
 
shall be punished with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years or such other punishment 
as is hereinafter mentioned.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>70</number> Fraudulent entry.—Every 
person who upon entry into or offering himself to enter the naval service 
wilfully makes or gives any false statement whether orally or in writing to any 
officer or person authorised to enter or enrol sailors or others in or for such 
naval service, shall, if he has become subject to naval law, be punished with 
imprisonment of a term which may extend to five years or such other punishment 
as is hereinafter mentioned.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>71</number> Escape from 
custody.—Every 
person subject to naval law who being in lawful custody escapes or attempts to 
escape from such custody shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which 
may extend to five years or such other punishment as is hereinafter mentioned.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>72</number> Failure to assist 
in detention of offenders.—Every 
person subject to naval law, who,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  does not use 
his utmost endeavours to detect, apprehend or bring to punishment all offenders 
against this Act; or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  does not 
assist the officers appointed for that purpose,
 
shall be punished with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years or such other punishment 
as is hereinafter mentioned.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>73</number> Penalty for failure 
to attend by members of reserve forces when called up.—Every 
member of the Indian Naval Reserve Forces and every person belonging to any 
auxiliary forces raised under this Act who, when called up for training or when 
called up into actual service with the Indian Navy in pursuance of the 
regulations made under this Act, and required by such call to join any ship or 
attend at any place, fails without reasonable excuse to comply with such 
requirement, shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
three years or such other punishment as is hereinafter mentioned.
 
 
</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>74</number> Offences against good order and naval discipline. </title>-Every person subject to naval law who is guilty of an act, disorder, or neglect to the prejudice of good order and naval discipline, not hereinbefore specified, shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years or such other punishment as is hereinafter mentioned. 
 <title>COMMENT </title>
 Mens rea  seems to be implied in the words used in this section. However, it is not possible to infer an inclusion of the element of mens rea ; Commander Ranvir Kumar Sinha  v.  Union of India , 1991 Cri LJ 1729 (DB) (Bom). 
  
</article> 

  
 <article><number>75</number> Attempts.—Every person subject to naval law 
who attempts to commit any of the offences specified in sections 34 to 74 and 76 
and in such attempt does any act towards the commission of the offence shall, 
where no express provision is made by this Act for the punishment of such 
attempt, be punished—
 <section>       
<number>a</number>  if the offence attempted to be committed is punishable with death, 
with imprisonment for a term which may extend to fourteen years or such other 
punishment as is hereinafter mentioned, and
 </section><section>       
<number>b</number>  if the offence attempted to be committed is punishable with 
imprisonment, with one-half of the maximum punishment provided for the offence 
or with such other punishment as is hereinafter mentioned.
  </section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>76</number> Abetment of 
offences.—Any 
person subject to naval law who abets the commission of any of the offences 
specified in sections 34 to 74 shall, whether the act abetted is committed or 
not in consequence of the abetment, and where no express provision is made by 
this Act for the punishment of such abetment, be punished with the punishment 
provided for that offence.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>77</number> Civil offences.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every person subject to naval law who commits a civil offence punishable with 
death or with imprisonment for life shall be punished with the punishment 
assigned for that offence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every person subject 
to naval law who commits any other civil offence shall be punished either with 
the punishment assigned for the offence or with imprisonment for a term which 
may extend to three years or such other punishment as is hereinafter mentioned.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>78</number> Jurisdiction as to 
place and offences.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to the provisions of sub-section (2), every person subject to naval law 
who is charged with a naval offence or a civil offence may be tried and punished 
under this Act regardless of where the alleged offence was committed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A person subject to 
naval law who commits an offence of murder against a person not subject to army, 
naval or air force law or an offence of culpable homicide not amounting to 
murder against such person or an offence of rape in relation to such person 
shall not be tried and punished under this Act unless he commits any of the said 
offences—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  while on 
active service; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  at any place 
outside India; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  at any place 
specified by the Central Government by notification in this behalf.
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>79</number> Jurisdiction as to 
time.—No person 
unless he is an offender who has avoided apprehension or fled from justice or 
committed the offence of desertion or fraudulent entry or the offence of mutiny 
shall be tried or punished in pursuance of this Act for any offence committed by 
him unless such trial commences within three years from the commission of such 
offence:
 
Provided that in the 
computation of the said period of three years any time during which an offender 
was outside India or any time during which he was a prisoner of war shall be 
deducted:
 

1[Provided further 
that in computation of the said period of three years, any time during which,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  the commission 
of the offence was not known to the person aggrieved by the offence or to the 
authority competent to initiate action, the first day on which such offence 
comes to the knowledge of such person or authority, whichever is earlier;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  it was not 
known by whom the offence was committed, the first day on which the identity of 
the offender is known to the person aggrieved by the offence or to the authority 
investigating into the offence, whichever is earlier, shall be excluded:
 
Provided also that where 
the institution of the prosecution in respect of an offence has been stayed by 
an injunction or order, then, in computing the said period of three years, the 
period of the continuance of the injunction or order, the day on which it was 
issued or made and the day on which it was withdrawn shall be excluded: 

 
Provided also that] no 
trial for an offence of desertion other than desertion on active service or 
fraudulent entry shall be commenced if the person in question not being an 
officer has subsequently to the commission of the offence served continuously in 
an exemplary manner for not less than three years in the Indian Navy.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>80</number> Trial after a 
person ceases to be subject to naval law.—When 
any offence mentioned in this Chapter has been committed by any person while 
subject to naval law and such person has since the commission of the offence 
ceased to be subject to naval law, he may be taken into and kept in custody, 
tried and punished under this Act for such offence in like manner as he may have 
been taken into and kept in custody, tried and punished if he had continued 
subject to naval law:
 
Provided that he shall not 
be tried for such offence except in the case of an offence of mutiny or 
desertion, unless the trial against him commences within six months after he has 
ceased to be so subject.
 


comment
 
A retired naval officer 
charged under section 307 of the Indian Penal Code cannot as of right claim to 
be tried by a court-martial even though he was in service and was not on the 
retired list on date of the incident: 1979 All Cri R 38.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>81</number> Punishments.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The following punishments may be inflicted under this Act, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  death;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  imprisonment 
which may be for the term of life or any other lesser term;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  dismissal with 
disgrace from the naval service;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  detention;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  dismissal from 
the naval service;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  forfeiture of 
seniority in rank in the case of officers 

1[and master chief 
petty officers];
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>g</number>  forfeiture of 
time for promotion in the case of 

2[officers below 
the rank of commander and master chief petty officers];
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>h</number>  dismissal from 
the ship to which the offender belongs;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>i</number>  

3[reduction in 
rank] in the case of 

2[petty officers] 
and persons holding leading rates;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>j</number>  fine, in 
respect of civil officers;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>k</number>  mulcts of pay 
and allowances;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>l</number>  severe 
reprimand or reprimand;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>m</number>  forfeiture of 
pay, head money, bounty, salvage, prize money and allowances earned by, and all 
annuities, pensions, gratuities, medals and decorations granted to, the offender 
or of any one or more of the above particulars; also in the case of desertion, 
of all clothes and effects left by the deserter in the ship to which he belongs;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>n</number>  such minor 
punishments as are inflicted according to the custom of the navy or may from 
time to time be prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Each of the 
punishments specified in sub-section (1) shall be deemed to be inferior in 
degree to every punishment preceding it in the above scale.
 


comment
 
In an inquiry into 
irregularities committed by certain persons, the petitioner, though not directly 
charged, was permitted to sit through inquiry and to cross-examine witness who 
spoke against him though in fact, he did not cross-examine. Held, punishment of 
censure against him, not illegal on ground of denial of reasonable opportunity;
Commodre C.P. George v. Chief of Naval Staff, 1995 Lab IC 1868 
(Del).
 
On reversal of Censure by 
the Government on statutory representation before it, the Chief of Naval Staff 
did not communicate such renersal to officer concerned, the Chief of Naval 
Staff,. however, personally met the Minister for reconsideration of the matter. 
Held, the procedure followed was violative of principles of natural justice; 
Commondre C.P. Geroge v. Chief of Naval Staff, 1995 Lab IC 1868 
(Del).
 
 





</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>82</number> Provisions as to 
award of punishment.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The punishments that may be inflicted under this Act shall be awarded in 
accordance with the provisions of the following sub-sections.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Except in the case of 
mutiny in time of war or on active service, the punishment of death shall not be 
inflicted on any offender until the sentence has been confirmed by the Central 
Government.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The punishment of 
imprisonment for a term exceeding two years shall in all cases be accompanied by 
a sentence of dismissal with disgrace from the naval service.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The punishment of 
imprisonment for a term not exceeding two years may in all cases be accompanied 
by a sentence of dismissal with disgrace or dismissal from the naval service:
 
Provided that in the case 
of officers, unless the sentence of dismissal with disgrace is also awarded, 
such sentence of imprisonment shall involve dismissal from the naval service.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The sentence of 
imprisonment may be rigorous or simple, or partly rigorous and partly simple.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The sentence of 
dismissal with disgrace shall involve in all cases forfeiture of all pay, head 
money, bounty, salvage, prize money and allowances that have been earned by and 
of all annuities, pensions, gratuities, medals and decorations that may have 
been granted to the offender and an incapacity to serve Government again in a 
defence service, or a civil service, or to hold any post connected with defence 
or any civil post under the Government:
 
Provided that the 
forfeiture of moneys shall not apply except in the case of deserters, to moneys 
which should have been paid on the last pay day preceding conviction.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The punishment of 
dismissal from the naval service shall in the case of persons who hold any lien 
on appointments in the regular Army or Air Force, involve dismissal from such 
army or air force service.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> The punishment of 
detention may be inflicted for any term not exceeding two years, but no sentence 
of detention shall be awarded unless naval detention quarters or army or air 
force detention barracks are in existence.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> The punishment of 
imprisonment or detention whether on board ship or on shore shall, subject to 
the provisions of sub-section (14), involve 

1[reduction in 
rank] in the case of a petty officer or a person holding a leading 

1[rank], and shall 
in all cases be accompanied by stoppage of pay and allowances during the term of 
imprisonment or detention:
 
Provided that where the 
punishment awarded is detention for a term not exceeding fourteen days, the 
sentence may direct that the punishment shall not be accompanied by stoppage of 
pay and allowances during the term of detention.
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> No officer shall be 
subject to detention.
 </section><section>
<number>11</number> The punishment of 
forfeiture of seniority shall be imposed in the substantive rank held at the 
date of the sentence, and shall involve a corresponding forfeiture of seniority 
in every higher acting rank subject always to the condition that forfeiture of 
seniority in any rank shall in no case exceed the seniority in that rank at the 
date of the sentence.
 </section><section>
<number>12</number> The punishment of 
forfeiture of seniority shall involve the loss of the benefit of service 
included in the seniority forfeited for the purposes of pay, pension, gratuity, 
promotion and such other purposes, as may be prescribed, provided that such pay, 
pension, gratuity and promotion and other purposes depend upon such service.
 

2[(12A) No master 
chief petty officer shall be subject to the punishment of forfeiture of 
seniority of more than twelve months.]
 </section><section>
<number>13</number> The punishment of 
forfeiture of time for promotion shall delay the promotion by time specified.
 

2[(13A) No master 
chief petty officer shall be subject to the punishment of forfeiture of time for 
promotion of more than twelve months.]
 </section><section>
<number>14</number> No person shall be


3[reduced in rank] 
below the limits prescribed, or lower either actually or relatively than the


3[rank] in which he 
entered or was appointed in the naval service.
 </section><section>
<number>15</number> Mulcts of pay and 
allowances shall not be awarded except as provided in sub-sections (16) and 
(17).
 </section><section>
<number>16</number> Mulcts of pay and 
allowances shall be awarded in accordance with the regulations made under this 
Act on conviction of offences under section 51.
 </section><section>
<number>17</number> Mulcts of pay may 
also be awarded to make good any proved loss or damage occasioned by the offence 
on which there is a conviction, and for the offence of drunkenness by sailors.
 </section><section>
<number>18</number> The punishment of 
fine may be awarded in respect of civil offences in addition to, or in lieu of, 
other punishments specified in this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>19</number> The forfeiture of 
moneys under clause (m) of sub-section (l) of section 81 shall not, except in 
case of desertion, apply to moneys which should have been paid on the last pay 
day preceding conviction.
 </section><section>
<number>20</number> All other punishments 
authorised by this Act may be inflicted in such manner as is heretofore in use 
in the naval service or as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>21</number> Subject to the 
provisions of the foregoing sub-sections, where any punishment is specified by 
this Act as the penalty for an offence and it is further declared that “such 
other punishment as is hereinafter mentioned” may be awarded in respect of the 
same offence, the expression “such other punishment” shall be deemed to comprise 
any one or more of the punishments inferior in degree to the specified 
punishment according to the scale of punishments laid down in sub-section (1) of 
section 81.
 
 





</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>83</number> Power to issue 
warrants of arrest.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chief of the Naval Staff, every officer in command of a fleet or squadron of 
ships of the Indian Navy or of any ship of the Indian Navy or the senior officer 
present at a port or an officer having by virtue of sub-section (2) and (3) of 
sections 93 power to try offences, may, by warrant under his hand, authorise any 
person to arrest any offender subject to naval law for any offence triable under 
this Act mentioned in such warrant and any such warrant may include the names of 
more persons that one in respect of several offences of the same nature.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person named in 
any such warrant as aforesaid may forthwith on his arrest, if the warrant so 
directs, be taken to the ship of the Indian Navy to which he belongs or some 
other ship of the Indian Navy.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A person authorised to 
arrest an offender may use such force as may be necessary for the purpose of 
effecting such arrest.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where a warrant under 
sub-section (1) is issued to a police officer, the police officer shall take 
steps to execute the warrant and arrest the offender in like manner as if such 
warrant had been issued by a magistrate of competent jurisdiction and shall, as 
soon as may be, deliver the person when arrested into naval custody.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>84</number> Arrest without 
warrant.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any person subject to naval law may be ordered without warrant into naval 
custody by any superior officer for any offence triable under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A person subject to 
naval law may arrest without warrant any other person subject to naval law 
though he may be of a higher rank who in his view commits an offence punishable 
with death, or imprisonment for life or for a term which may extend to fourteen 
years.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A provost-marshal may 
arrest any person subject to naval law in accordance with the provisions of 
section 89.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> It shall be lawful for 
the purpose of effecting arrest, or taking a person into custody, without 
warrant to use such force as may be necessary for the purpose.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>85</number> Procedure and 
conditions of naval custody.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No person subject to naval law who is arrested under this Act shall be detained 
in naval custody without being informed, as soon as may be, of the grounds for 
such arrest.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every person subject 
to naval law who is arrested and detained in naval custody shall be produced 
before his commanding officer or other officer prescribed in this behalf within 
a period of forty-eight hours of such arrest excluding the time necessary for 
the journey from the place of arrest to such commanding or other officer and no 
such person shall be detained in custody beyond the said period without the 
authority of such commanding or other officer.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>86</number> Investigation after 
arrest.—The 
charge made against any person subject to naval law taken into custody shall 
without any unnecessary delay be investigated by the proper authority and as 
soon as may be either proceedings shall be taken for the trial or such person 
shall be discharged from custody.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>87</number> Duty to receive or 
keep in custody.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The commanding officer shall be responsible for the safe custody of every person 
who is in naval custody on board his ship or in his establishment.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The officer or sailor 
in charge of a guard, or a provost-marshal shall receive and keep any person who 
is duly committed to his custody.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>88</number> Procedure before 
trial.—Subject 
to the provisions of this Act, the procedure before trial and the manner of 
investigation shall be as prescribed.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>89</number> Provost-marshals.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Provost-marshals may be appointed by the Chief of the Naval Staff or the 
prescribed officer.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The duties of a 
provost-marshal are to take charge of persons in naval custody, to preserve good 
order and discipline and to prevent breaches of the same by persons subject to 
naval law or to the law in force relating to the government of the regular Army 
or the Air Force.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A provost-marshal may 
at any time arrest and detain for trial any person subject to naval law who 
commits, or is charged with, an offence and may also carry into effect any 
punishment to be inflicted in pursuance of sentence passed under this Act, but 
shall not inflict any punishment on his own authority:
 
Provided that no officer 
shall be so arrested or detained otherwise than on the order of another officer.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> For the purpose of 
sub-sections (2) and (3) a provost-marshal shall be deemed to include 
provost-marshal and any of his assistants appointed under the law in force 
relating to the government of the regular Army or the Air Force.
 


comment
 
A person subject to naval 
law was convicted for murder by ordinary criminal court. His detention in naval 
jail after conviction under the Navy Act, 1957 was held to be un-authorised; 
Anant Chintaman Lagu v. The State of 
Bombay, 
AIR 1960 Bom 502.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>90</number> Joinder of charges.—For 
every distinct offence of which any person is accused, there shall be separate 
charge but except as otherwise provided by regulations made under this Act all 
separate charges may be tried together.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>91</number> Acts amounting to 
different offences.—If 
a single act or series of acts is of such a nature that it is doubtful which of 
several offences the facts which can be proved will constitute, the accused may 
be charged with having committed all or any of such offences, and any number of 
such charges may be tried at one trial; or he may be charged in the alternative 
with having committed some one of the said offences.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>92</number> Joinder of accused 
persons.—The 
following persons may be charged and tried together, namely:—
 <section>
        <number>i</number>  persons 
accused of the same offence committed in the course of the same transaction;
 </section><section>
        <number>ii</number>  persons 
accused of an offence and persons accused of abetment of, or an attempt to 
commit, such offence; and
 </section><section>
       <number>iii</number>  persons 
accused of different offences committed in the course of the same transaction:
 
Provided that in a trial 
by a court-martial, the trial judge advocate may, on the application made in 
this behalf by any accused, direct that each of the accused be tried separately 
by the same court-martial.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>93</number> Power of 
court-martial and commanding officers to try offences.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An offence triable under this Act may be tried and punished by court-martial.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An offence not capital 
which is triable under this Act and which is committed by a person other than an 
officer (and in cases by this Act expressly provided for when committed by an 
officer), may, subject to regulations made under this Act be summarily tried and 
punished by the commanding officer of the ship to which the offender belongs at 
the time either of the commission or of the trial of the offence, subject to the 
restriction that the commanding officer shall not have power to award 
imprisonment or detention for more than three months, or to award dismissal with 
disgrace from the naval service:
 
Provided that no sentence 
of imprisonment or dismissal shall be carried into effect until approved by the 
prescribed authorities.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The power by this 
section vested in a commanding officer of a ship may, subject to regulations 
made under this Act,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  as respects 
sailors on board a tender to the ship, be exercised in the case of a single 
tender absent from the ship, by the officer in command of such tender and in the 
case of two or more tenders absent from the ship in company or acting together, 
by the officer in immediate command of such tenders;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  as respects 
sailors on board any boat belonging to the ship, be exercised when such boat is 
absent on detached service by the officer in command of the boat;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  as respects 
sailors on detached service either on shore or otherwise, be exercised by the 
officer in immediate command of those persons;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  as respects 
sailors quartered in naval barracks, be exercised by the officer in command of 
the barracks;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  as respects 
sailors attached to or serving with any body of the regular Army or the Air 
Force under prescribed conditions, be exercised by the commanding officer of any 
such body of the regular Army or the Air Force.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The commanding officer 
of a ship or barracks may delegate the power of awarding punishments inferior in 
scale to dismissal, to other officers under his command in accordance with the 
regulations made under this Act.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>94</number> Power of Central 
Government, Chief of the Naval Staff and other officers to impose forfeiture of 
time or seniority.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may impose on any officer below the rank of commander one 
or more of the following punishments, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  forfeiture of 
seniority in rank of not more than twelve months;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  forfeiture of 
time for promotion of not more than twelve months;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  mulcts of pay 
and allowances.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Chief of the Naval 
Staff may impose on any officer below the rank of commander one or more of the 
following punishments, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  forfeiture of 
seniority in rank of not more than six months;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  forfeiture of 
time for promotion of not more than six months;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  mulcts of pay 
and allowances.
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>2A</number> The Flag 
Officer Commanding-in-Chief of a naval command may, subject to regulations made 
under this Act, impose on any officer below the rank of commander one or more of 
the following punishments, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  forfeiture of 
seniority in rank of not more than three months;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  forfeiture of 
time for promotion of not more than three months;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  severe 
reprimand or reprimand;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  mulcts of pay 
and allowances.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The commanding officer 
of a ship may, subject to regulations made under this Act, impose on any 
subordinate officer one or more of the following punishments, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  forfeiture of 
seniority in rank of not more than three months;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  forfeiture of 
time for promotion of not more than three months;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  mulcts of pay 
and allowances:]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> In imposing 
punishments under sub-sections (1) 

2[, (2) and (2A)], 
it shall not be necessary for the Central Government or the Chief of the Naval 
Staff, as the case may be, to hear the accused in person or by any friend or 
counsel.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The commanding officer 
of a 

3[ship] or the 
officer-in-charge of a naval academy may impose on any subordinate officer 
whilst under training such minor punishments, not higher than the punishment of 
severe reprimand or reprimand, as may, from time to time, be prescribed.
 
 











</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>95</number> Disciplinary courts 
when may be constituted.—When 
an officer is, in time of war or during active service, alleged to have been 
guilty of a disciplinary offence, that is to say, of a breach of sections 41, 
47, 48, 49, 51, 52, 68, and 74 or of any of those sections read with section 75 
or 76, the officer having the power to order a court-martial may, if he 
considers the offence to be of such a character as not to necessitate trial by 
court-martial, in lieu of ordering a court-martial, order a disciplinary court 
constituted as hereinafter mentioned.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>96</number> Constitution and 
procedure of disciplinary courts.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A disciplinary court shall be composed of not less than three nor more than five 
officers:
 
Provided that the majority 
of the officers including the president shall be officers of the executive 
branch of the naval service.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> At least one of these 
officers composing the court shall be superior in rank to the officer under 
trial and in any case shall be of the rank of substantive or acting commander or 
of a higher rank.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A disciplinary court 
shall have power to impose any punishment inferior to detention in the scale 
hereinbefore contained, but no greater punishment.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The officers composing 
the disciplinary court shall be named by the authority ordering the same or by 
an officer empowered in this behalf by such authority.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Subject to the 
provisions of the foregoing sub-sections, the procedure and practice of 
courts-martial provided by or under this Act shall apply to the procedure and 
practice of disciplinary courts subject to such modifications as may be 
prescribed.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>97</number> Constitution of 
courts-martial.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Courts-martial shall be constituted and convened subject to the provisions of 
the following sub-sections.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The President, the 
Chief of the Naval Staff, or any officer empowered in this behalf by commission 
from the Chief of the Naval Staff shall have the power to order courts-martial 
for the trial of offences under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Unless otherwise 
prescribed in respect of any specified port or station, an officer holding a 
commission from the Chief of the Naval Staff to order court martial shall not be 
empowered to do so if there is present at the place where such court-martial is 
to be held an officer superior in rank to himself and in command of one or more 
of the ships of the Indian Navy although such last mentioned officer may not 
hold a commission to order courts-martial and in such a case such last mentioned 
officer may order a court-martial although he does not hold a commission for the 
purpose.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If an officer holding 
a commission from the Chief of the Naval Staff to order courts-martial, having 
the command of a fleet or squadron and being outside Indian waters die, be 
recalled, leave his station or be removed from his command, the officer upon 
whom the command of the fleet or squadron devolves and so from time to time the 
officer who shall have the command of the fleet or squadron, shall without any 
commission from the Chief of the Naval Staff have the same power to order 
courts-martial as the first mentioned officer was vested with.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If an officer holding 
a commission from the Chief of the Naval Staff to order courts-martial and 
having the command of any fleet or squadron of the Indian Navy outside Indian 
waters shall detach any part of such fleet or squadron, or separate himself from 
any part of such fleet or squadron he may by commission under his hand empower 
in the first mentioned case, the commanding officer of the squadron or 
detachment ordered on such separate service and in the case of death or ceasing 
so to command, the officer to whom the command of such separate squadron or 
detachment shall belong, and in the second mentioned case, the senior officer of 
the ships of the Indian Navy on the division of the station from which he is 
absent, to order courts-martial during the time of such separate service or 
during his absence from that division of the station as the case may be, and 
every such authority shall continue in force until revoked or until the officer 
holding it returns to India or until he comes into the presence of a superior 
officer empowered to order courts-martial in the same squadron, detachment or 
division of station but so that such authority shall revive on the officer 
holding it ceasing to be in the presence of such a superior officer and so from 
time to time as often as the case so requires.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> A court-martial shall 
consist of not less than five nor more than nine officers.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> No officer shall be 
qualified to sit as a member of a court-martial unless—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  he is subject 
to naval law,
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  he is an 
officer of the Indian Navy of the rank of lieutenant or higher rank, and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  he is of or 
over twenty-one years of age.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>8</number> A prosecutor shall not 
be qualified to sit on the court-martial for the trial of the person he 
prosecutes.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> The officer ordering 
the court-martial, the officer who was the commanding officer of the ship to 
which the accused belonged at the time of the commission of the alleged offence 
and the officer investigating the offence shall not be qualified to sit on a 
court-martial for the trial of such accused.
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> Subject to the 
provisions of sub-sections (7) to (9), officers of the Indian Navy shall be 
eligible to sit as members of a court-martial irrespective of the branch of the 
naval service to which they belong:
 
Provided that—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the majority 
of the members of the court-martial, including the president, shall be officers 
of the executive branch of the naval service, and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  at trials for 
offences against sections 34, 35, 55 

1[, 55A, 55C] and 
56, officers other than officers of the executive branch of the naval service 
shall not be eligible to sit.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>11</number> A court-martial shall 
not be deemed to be duly constituted unless the members thereof are drawn from 
at least two ships not being tenders, and commanded by officers of the rank of 
lieutenant or higher rank.
 </section><section>
<number>12</number> The president of a 
court-martial shall be named by the authority ordering the same or by any 
officer empowered by such authority to name the president.
 </section><section>
<number>13</number> No court-martial for 
the trial of a flag officer shall be duly constituted unless the president is a 
flag officer and the other officers composing the court are of the rank of 
captain or of higher rank.
 </section><section>
<number>14</number> No court-martial for 
the trial of a captain shall be duly constituted unless the president is a 
captain or of higher rank and the other officers composing the court are 
commanders or officers of higher rank.
 </section><section>
<number>15</number> No court-martial for 
the trial of a commander shall be duly constituted unless the president is a 
commander or of higher rank and two other members are commanders or officers of 
higher rank.
 </section><section>
<number>16</number> No court-martial for 
the trial of a person below the rank of commander shall be duly constituted 
unless the president is a substantive or acting commander or of higher rank.
 </section><section>
<number>17</number> No commander or 
lieutenant-commander or lieutenant shall be required to sit as a member of a 
court-martial when four officers of higher rank and junior to the president can 
be assembled at the place where the court-martial is to be held, but the 
regularity or validity of any court-martial or of the proceedings thereof shall 
not be affected by any commander, lieutenant-commander or lieutenant being 
required to sit or sitting thereon under any circumstances and when any 
commander, lieutenant-commander or lieutenant sits on any court-martial, the 
members of it shall not exceed five.
 </section><section>
<number>18</number> Members of the 
court-martial other than the president shall be appointed subject to the 
provisions of the foregoing sub-sections, in the manner provided in sub-section 
(19).
 </section><section>
<number>19</number> Subject to the 
provisions of sub-section (11), the president shall summon all officers except 
such as are exempted under the provisions of sub-section (20), next in seniority 
to himself present at the place where the court-martial shall be held, to sit 
thereon until the number of nine or such other number not less than five as is 
attainable is complete.
 </section><section>
<number>20</number> The officer convening 
the court-martial or the senior naval officer present at the place where the 
court-martial is to be held, may exempt by writing under his hand conveyed to 
the president of the court-martial any officer from attending as member on 
ground of sickness or urgent public duty.
 </section><section>
<number>21</number> In this section 
references to specified ranks of officers shall, unless otherwise stated, be 
deemed to be references to substantive ranks and to include references to 
equivalent ranks in all branches of the naval service.
 </section><section>
<number>22</number> When the naval forces 
are on active service, officers of the Indian Naval Reserve Forces subject to 
naval law shall be eligible to sit as members of courts-martial on the same 
basis and under the same conditions as officers of the Indian Navy.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>98</number> Where 
courts-martial to be held.—A 
court-martial may be held ashore or afloat.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>99</number> Trial judge 
advocate.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every court-martial shall be attended by a person (in this Act referred to as 
the trial judge advocate) who shall be either a judge advocate in the department 
of the Judge Advocate General of the Navy or any fit person appointed by the 
convening officer:
 
Provided that in the case 
of a court-martial for the trial of a capital offence the trial judge advocate 
shall be a person nominated by the Judge Advocate General of the Navy unless 
such trial is held outside Indian waters.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The trial judge 
advocate shall administer oath to every witness at the trial and shall perform 
such other duties as are provided in this Act and as may be prescribed.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>100</number> Courts-martial to 
be public.—The 
place in which a court-martial is held for the purpose of trying an offence 
under this Act shall be deemed to be an open court to which the public generally 
may have access, so far as the same can conveniently contain them:
 
Provided that, if the 
court is satisfied that it is necessary or expedient in the public interest, for 
the ends of justice so to do, the court may at any stage of the trial of any 
particular case order that the public generally or any portion thereof or any 
particular person shall not have access to, or be or remain in, the place in 
which the court is held.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>101</number> Commencement of 
proceedings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
As soon as the court has been assembled the accused shall be brought before it 
and the prosecutor, the person or persons, if any defending the accused and the 
audience admitted.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Except where the 
accused defends himself, he may be defended by such person or persons as may be 
prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The trial judge 
advocate shall read out the warrant for assembling the court and the names of 
officers who are exempted from attending under sub-section (20) of section 97 
together with the reasons for such exemption.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The trial judge 
advocate shall read out the names of the officers composing the court and shall 
ask the prosecutor whether he objects to any of them.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If the prosecutor 
shall have made no objection or after any objection made by the prosecutor has 
been disposed of, the trial judge advocate shall ask the accused if he objects 
to any member of the court.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>102</number> Objections to 
members.—The 
following provisions shall apply to the disposal of objections raised by the 
prosecutor as well as the accused:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  any member may 
be objected to on a ground which affects his competency to act as an impartial 
judge; and the trial judge advocate may reject summarily without reference to 
the members of the court any objection not made on such grounds;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  objections to 
members shall be decided separately, those to the officer lowest in rank being 
taken first : provided that if the objection is to the president, such objection 
shall be decided first and all the other members whether objected to or not 
shall vote as to the disposal of the objection;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  on an 
objection being allowed by one-half or more of the Officers entitled to decide 
the objection, the member objected to shall at once retire and his place shall 
be filled up before an objection against another member is taken up;
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  should the 
president be objected to and the objection be allowed, the court shall adjourn 
until a new president has been appointed by the convening authority or by the 
officer empowered in this behalf by the convening authority; and
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number>  should a 
member be objected to on the ground of being summoned as a witness, and should 
it be found that the objection has been made in good faith and that the officer 
is to give evidence as to facts and not merely as to character, the objection 
shall be allowed.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>103</number> Further 
objections.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The trial judge advocate shall then ask the accused whether he has any further 
objections to make respecting the constitution of the court; and should the 
accused raise any such objection, it shall then be decided by the court, which 
decision shall be final and the constitution of the court-martial shall not be 
after wards impeached and it shall be deemed in all respects to have been duly 
constituted.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the accused should 
have no further objection to make to the constitution of the court or if any 
objection is disallowed, the members and the trial judge advocate shall then 
make an oath or affirmation in the form set out in section 104.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>104</number> Administering oath 
or affirmation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Before the court shall proceed to try the person charged, an oath or affirmation 
in the following form and manner shall be administered to the president and 
every member of the court-martial in the order of their seniority by the trial 
judge advocate:—
 

                                                     swear in the name of God
 
              
“I....................................do————————————————
 
                 
                                             solemnly affirm
 
              that I will 
duly and faithfully and to the best of my ability, knowledge and judgment 
administer justice according to law, without fear or favour, affection or 
ill-will, and that I will not on any account at any time whatsoever disclose or 
discover the vote or opinion of any particular member of this court-martial 
unless thereunto required in due course of law.”.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The trial judge 
advocate shall then be sworn or affirmed by the president in the following 
form:—
 

                                                       swear in the name of God
 
              
“I.......................................do————————————————
 
                 
                                                  solemnly affirm
 
              that I will 
duly and faithfully and to the best of my ability, knowledge and judgment 
perform the duties of my office according to law, without fear or favour, 
affection or ill-will, and that I will not upon any account at any time 
whatsoever disclose or discover the vote or opinion of any particular member of 
this court-martial unless thereunto required in due course of law.”.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>105</number> Arraignment.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When the court is ready to commence the trial, the trial judge advocate shall 
read out the charges and shall ask the accused whether he pleads guilty or not 
guilty.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the accused pleads 
guilty, then, before such plea is recorded, the trial judge advocate shall 
ensure that the accused understands the charge to which he has pleaded guilty 
and the difference of procedure which will result from the plea of guilty.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If it appears from the 
accused’s replies or from the summary of evidence prepared in the prescribed 
manner that he should not plead guilty, the trial judge advocate may advise the 
accused to withdraw his plea.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If the court accepts 
the plea of guilty, it shall be recorded as the finding of the court and the 
court shall proceed to take steps to pass sentence unless there are other 
charges to be tried in which event the sentence shall be deferred until after 
the findings on such charges are given.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>106</number> Opening of 
prosecution case.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If the accused pleads not guilty or refuses to, or does not, plead or if he 
claims to be tried or if in the circumstances mentioned in sub-section (3) of 
section 105 withdraws the plea of guilty or if the court does not accept the 
plea of guilty, the court shall proceed to try the accused.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The prosecutor shall 
open his case by reading the circumstantial letter prepared in accordance with 
the regulations made under this Act, reading from this Act or the Indian Penal 
Code (45 of 1860) or other law the description of the offence charged and 
stating shortly by what evidence he expects to prove the guilt of the accused.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The prosecutor shall 
then examine his witnesses.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>107</number> Calling of 
prosecution witness not in the original list.—No 
witness whose name was not included in the original list of witnesses supplied 
to the trial judge advocate and the accused in accordance with regulations made 
under this Act shall be called by the prosecutor unless the trial judge advocate 
has given notice to the accused of the prosecutor’s intention to call such 
witness and has supplied the accused with a summary of the evidence of such 
witness.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>108</number> Swearing of 
interpreter and shorthand-writer.—
<section><number>1</number> 
At any time during the trial, should the court think it necessary, an impartial 
person may be employed to serve as an interpreter and sworn or affirmed as such 
in the following manner:—
 

                                                       swear in the name of God
 
              
“I....................................do————————————————
 

                                                                   solemnly 
affirm
 
              that I will 
to the best of my ability truly interpret and translate as I will be required to 
touching the matter before this court-martial”.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> During the trial, an 
impartial person shall be employed as a shorthand-writer and duly sworn or 
affirmed as such in the following manner:—
 

                                                       swear in the name of God
 
              
“I.......................................do————————————————
 

                                                                   solemnly 
affirm
 
              that I will 
truly take down to the best of my power the evidence to be given before this 
court-martial and such other matters as I will be required, and when required, 
will deliver to the court a true transcript of the same.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>109</number> Objection to 
interpreter or shorthand-writer.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Before any person is sworn or affirmed as an interpreter or a shorthand-writer, 
the accused shall be asked if he objects to such person as not being impartial 
and the court shall decide the objection.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The evidence given by 
a witness shall be read over to him by shorthand-writer before the witness 
leaves the court, if so required by the court or the witness.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>110</number> Swearing of 
witnesses.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No witness shall be examined until he has been duly sworn or affirmed in the 
following manner:—
 

                                                       swear in the name of God
 
              
“I....................................do————————————————
 

                                                                   solemnly 
affirm
 
              that the 
evidence which I shall give before this court shall be the truth, the whole 
truth and nothing but the truth.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every person giving 
evidence on oath or affirmation before a court-martial shall be bound to state 
the truth.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>111</number> Plea of no case 
and defence of accused.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When the examination of the witness for the prosecution is concluded, the 
accused shall be called on for his defence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Before entering on his 
defence, the accused may raise a plea of no case to answer.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If such a plea is 
raised the court will decide the plea after hearing the accused and the 
prosecutor and the advice of the trial judge advocate.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If the court accepts 
the plea, the accused shall be acquitted on the charge or charges in respect 
whereof the plea has been accepted.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If the court overrules 
the plea, the accused shall be called upon to enter on his defence.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The trial judge 
advocate shall then inform the accused that he may give evidence as a witness on 
his own behalf shall he desire to do so and should he make a request in writing 
to do so, but that he will thereby render himself liable to cross-examination.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> If the accused does 
not apply to give evidence, he may make a statement as to the facts of the case, 
and if he has no defence witnesses to examine as to facts the prosecutor may sum 
up his case and the accused shall be entitled to reply.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> If the accused or any 
one of the several accused applies to give evidence and there are no other 
witnesses in the case for the defence, other than witnesses as to character, 
then the evidence of such accused shall be recorded and if the accused so 
desires the witnesses as to character shall be examined and the prosecutor shall 
then sum up his case and the accused may reply.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> If the accused or any 
one of the accused adduces any oral evidence as to facts other than his own 
evidence, if any, the accused may then sum up his case on the conclusion of that 
evidence and the prosecutor shall be entitled to reply.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>112</number> Adjournment to 
view.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Whenever the court thinks that it should view the place in which the officer 
charged is alleged to have been committed or any other place in which any other 
transaction material to the trial is alleged to have occurred, the court shall 
make an order to that effect and may then adjourn to the place to be viewed, 
along with the prosecutor and the accused and the person, if any, by whom the 
accused is represented.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The court on 
completion of the view shall adjourn and reassemble in the court-room.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>113</number> Summing up by the 
trial judge advocate.—When 
the case for the defence and the prosecutor’s reply, if any, are concluded, the 
trial judge advocate shall proceed to sum up in open court the evidence for the 
prosecution and the defence and lay down the law by which the court is to be 
guided.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>114</number> Duties of the 
trial judge advocate.—
<section><number>1</number> 
At all trials by courts-martial it is the duty of the trial judge advocate to 
decide all questions of law arising in the course of the trial, and specially 
all questions as to the relevancy of facts which it is proposed to prove and the 
admissibility of evidence or the propriety of the questions asked by or on 
behalf of the parties; and in his discretion to prevent the production of 
inadmissible evidence whether it is or is not objected to by the parties.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Whenever in the course 
of a trial it appears desirable to the trial judge advocate that arguments and 
evidence as to the admissibility of evidence or arguments in support of an 
application for separate trials or on any other points of law should not be 
heard in the presence of the court, he may advise the president of the court 
accordingly and the president shall thereupon make an order for the court to 
retire or direct the trial judge advocate to hear the arguments in some other 
convenient place.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>115</number> Duties of the 
court.—It is 
the duty of the court to decide which view of the facts is true and then arrive 
at the finding which under such view ought to be arrived at.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>116</number> Retirement to 
consider finding.—
<section><number>1</number> 
After the trial judge advocate has finished his summing up, the court will be 
cleared to consider the finding.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The trial judge 
advocate shall not sit with the court when the court is considering the finding 
and no person shall speak to or hold any communication with the court while the 
court is considering the finding.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>117</number> Announcement of 
the finding.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When the court has considered the finding the court shall be reassembled and the 
president shall inform the trial judge advocate in open court what is the 
finding of the court as ascertained in accordance with section 124.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The court shall give 
its findings on all the charges on which the accused is tried.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>118</number> Drawing up of the 
finding.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The trial judge advocate shall then draw up the finding as announced by the 
court.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The finding so drawn 
up shall be signed by all the members of the court by way of attestation 
notwithstanding any difference of opinion there may have been among the members 
and shall be countersigned by the trial judge advocate.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the finding on 
any charges is one of not guilty the court shall acquit the accused of that 
charge.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If the accused is 
acquitted of all the charges, the court shall, after signing the findings as 
provided in sub-section (2), be dissolved.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Neither the court nor 
the trial judge advocate shall announce in open court whether the finding was 
unanimous or not; but the president shall make a record of the division of 
voting on each finding without disclosing the vote or opinion of any particular 
member of the court-martial and such record shall be communicated to the trial 
judge advocate for transmission to the Judge Advocate General of the Navy.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>119</number> Evidence of 
character and previous convictions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If the accused is found guilty on any or all of the charges, the court before 
awarding punishment may call evidence as to the previous character and 
qualifications of the accused and in addition to any oral evidence of general 
character that may be adduced, shall take into consideration the following 
documents which shall be read by the trial judge advocate in open court:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  for any 
officer—
 <subsubsection>
             <number>i</number>  any 
entries against him relating to his previous convictions in the list of officers 
who have been tried by court-martial; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>ii</number>  any 
previous entries against him in the log of the ship to which he may have 
belonged when the offence or offences for which he is being tried were committed 
and also any documents, other than such entries in the log, of the nature of a 
definite censure by superior authority, which log and documents the prosecution 
is to produce; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>iii</number>  any 
certificate or other documents of character which the accused may produce;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  for a sailor—
 <subsubsection>
             <number>i</number>  the 
entries against him in the conduct and offences record sheets prior to the date 
of the offence charged, but subsequent to his joining his present ship, with 
character assessed from the previous 31st day of December to the date of the 
offence for which he may be under trial but excluding all consideration of the 
later;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>ii</number>  his 
certificate of service; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>iii</number>  any 
entries against him relating to his previous convictions in the list of those 
who have been tried by court-martial.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The accused may then 
make a statement in mitigation of punishment and lead any evidence of character 
if he has not already done so before the finding.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>120</number> Consideration of 
the sentence.—The 
court shall then retire and consider and determine on the punishment proper to 
be inflicted in conformity with the finding, and all the members of the court, 
whether they have voted for an acquittal or not, shall vote on the question of 
what punishment is proper to be awarded for the offence of which the accused has 
been found guilty.
 <section>
<number>2</number> The trial judge 
advocate shall sit with the court while they are considering the sentence and 
assist the court in the determination of the sentence but shall not vote 
thereon.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>121</number> Announcement of 
the sentence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When the court has decided on the sentence whether unanimously or by majority, 
the trial judge advocate shall draw up the sentence in the prescribed from which 
shall be signed by every member of the court by way of attestation 
notwithstanding any difference of opinion there may have been among the members 
and shall be countersigned by the trial judge advocate.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The court shall then 
be reassembled and the accused brought in and the trial judge advocate shall by 
direction of the court pronounce the sentence.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The accused shall then 
be removed and the court dissolved.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>122</number> Adjournment.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A court-martial may, if it appears to the court that an adjournment is 
desirable, be adjourned accordingly, but except where such an adjournment is 
ordered, shall sit from day to day with the exception of Sundays until the trial 
is concluded, unless prevented from so doing by stress of weather or unavoidable 
accident.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The proceedings of a 
court-martial shall not, after the commencement of a trial, be delayed by the 
absence of a member:
 
Provided that no less than 
four members are present; and
 
Provided further that if 
any member is absent from any part of the trial, he shall not thereafter take 
any part in the proceedings.
 


comment
 
The word “trial” is well 
understood in criminal law and it ends when the proceedings in trial court come 
to an end. The various provisions of the Navy Act, 1957 also show that the word 
“trial” is used in the same sense in the Act; AIR 1969 Bom 502.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>123</number> Provisions 
relating to dissolution of courts-martial.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A court-martial assembled under this act shall be dissolved—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  when the 
number of members comprising the court is after the commencement of a trial 
reduced below four;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  by the 
prolonged illness of the president, trial judge advocate or the accused;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  by the death 
of the president or the trial judge advocate;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  on the making 
of a report under sub-section (2) of section 143.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Whenever a 
court-martial is dissolved by virtue of sub-section (1) the accused may be 
retried.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>124</number> Ascertaining the 
opinion of the court.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to the provisions of sub-sections (2) and (3), every question for 
determination by a court-martial shall be decided by the vote of the majority:
 
Provided that where there 
is an equality of votes, the decision most favourable to the accused shall 
prevail.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The sentence of death 
shall not be passed on any offender unless four at least of the members present 
at the court-martial where the number does not exceed five, and in all other 
cases a majority of not less than two-thirds of the members present, concur in 
the sentence.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where in respect of an 
offence, the only punishment which may be awarded is death, a finding that a 
charge for such offence is proved shall not be given unless four at least of the 
members present at the court-martial where the number does not exceed five, and 
in all other cases a majority of not less than two-thirds of the members 
present, concur in the finding.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>125</number> Finding that the 
offence was committed with intent involving less degree of punishment.—Where 
the amount of punishment for any offence depends upon the intent with which it 
has been committed and any person is charged with having committed such an 
offence with an intent involving a greater degree of punishment, a court-martial 
may find that the offence was committed with an intent involving less degree of 
punishment and award such punishment accordingly.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>126</number> Alternative 
findings.—If 
the accused is charged with one offence and it appears in evidence that he 
committed a different offence for which he might have been charged under section 
91, he may be convicted of the offence which he is shown to have committed 
although he was not charged with it.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>127</number> Finding lesser 
offence proved on charge of greater offence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When a person is charged with an offence consisting of several particulars, a 
combination of some only of which constitutes a complete minor offence and such 
combination is proved, but the remaining particulars are not proved, he may be 
convicted of the minor offence although he was not charged with it.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When a person is 
charged with an offence and facts are proved which reduce it to a minor offence, 
he may be convicted of the minor offence although he was not charged with it.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> When a person is 
charged with an offence, he may be convicted of an attempt to commit such an 
offence, although the attempt is not separately charged.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>128</number> Transmission of 
proceedings to the Judge Advocate General of the Navy.—The 
trial judge advocate shall transmit in accordance with the prescribed procedure 
with as much expedition as may be, the original proceedings or a complete and 
authenticated copy thereof and the original sentence of every court-martial 
attended by him, to the Judge Advocate General of the Navy to be dealt with by 
him in accordance with the provisions of Chapter XV.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>129</number> Right of accused 
to copy of proceedings and sentence.—Every 
person tried by a court-martial and convicted shall be entitled on demand to one 
copy of the proceedings and sentence of such court-martial free of cost but no 
such demand shall be allowed after the lapse of one year from the date of the 
final decision of such court.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>130</number> Application of the 
Evidence Act.—Subject 
to the provisions of this Act, the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872), shall 
apply to all proceedings before a court-martial.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>131</number> Accused competent 
witness for defence.—A 
person accused of an offence before a court-martial shall be a competent witness 
for the defence and may give evidence on oath in disproof of the charges made 
against him or any person charged together with him at the same trial:
 
Provided that—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  he shall not 
be called as a witness except on his own request in writing; or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  his failure to 
give evidence shall not be made the subject of any comment by any of the parties 
or the court or give rise to any presumption against himself or any person 
charged together with him at the same trial.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>132</number> Judicial notice.—A 
court-martial may take judicial notice of any matter within the general naval, 
army or air force experience and knowledge of the members.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>133</number> Presumptions as to 
certain documents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Whenever it is necessary for the purpose of either the prosecution or the 
defence to prove the contents of any voucher, receipt, account, muster, ship’s 
book, letter, signal, telegram or other document made or kept in pursuance of 
any Act of the legislature, any regulations framed under this Act or of the 
custom of the service, a copy of the same purporting to be signed and certified 
as a correct copy by the officer for the time being commanding the ship in which 
the same was made or kept or by a Secretary to the Central Government, may be 
received as evidence of such document and of the matters, transactions and 
accounts therein recorded.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A Navy List or Gazette 
or other official document purporting to be published by authority of the 
Central Government or the Chief of the Naval Staff shall be evidence of the 
status and rank of officers therein mentioned and of any appointment held by 
such officers until the contrary is proved.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where it is shown that 
a person is borne on the books of a ship of the Indian Navy, such fact shall be 
evidence that such person is subject to naval law until the contrary is proved.
 
Explanation.—In 
this section, the term “books of a ship” shall include any official book, 
document or list purporting to contain the name or names of person appointed to 
the ship.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where any person 
subject to naval law is being tried on a charge of desertion, improperly leaving 
his ship, or absence without leave and such person has surrendered himself into 
custody of or has been apprehended by any person subject to naval law or by a 
person subject to the law relating to the government of the regular Army or the 
Air Force, a certificate purporting to be signed by such person and stating the 
fact, date and place of such surrender or apprehension shall be evidence of the 
matters so stated unless the contrary is proved.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where any person 
subject to naval law is being tried on a charge of desertion, improperly leaving 
his ship, or absence without leave and such person has on arrest or surrender 
been taken to a police station, a certificate purporting to be signed by the 
officer-in-charge of the station and stating the fact, date and place of such 
surrender or apprehension shall be evidence of the matters stated unless the 
contrary is proved.
 

1[(6) Any document 
purporting to be a report, under the hand of—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  any Chemical 
Examiner or Assistant Chemical Examiner to the Government;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the Chief 
Inspector of Explosives;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  the Director 
of Finger Print Bureau;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  the Director 
of Haffkeine Institute, Bombay;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  the Director, 
Deputy Director or Assistant Director of a Central Forensic Science Laboratory 
or a State Forensic Science Laboratory;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  the 
Serologist to the Government,
 
upon any matter or thing 
duly submitted to him for examination or analysis, may be used as evidence in 
any proceeding under this Act.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>7</number> The statement of a 
naval, army or air force medical officer taken and attested by the commanding 
officer of a ship or establishment may be given in evidence in any proceeding 
under this Act:
 
Provided that the court 
may, if it thinks fit, and shall if so required by the prosecutor or the 
accused, summon and examine such medical officer as to the subject matter of his 
statement.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> If it is proved that 
an offender under this Act has absconded and that there is no immediate prospect 
of arresting him, the commanding officer or other prescribed person may, in his 
absence, examine any persons who might appear to him to be acquainted with the 
case and record their depositions on oath and any such deposition may on the 
arrest of such person be used in evidence against him in any proceeding under 
this Act, if the deponent is dead or incapable of giving evidence or his 
attendance cannot be procured without an amount of delay, expense or 
inconvenience which under the circumstances of the case would be unreasonable.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>134</number> Summoning of 
witnesses.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every person who may be required to give evidence or produce a document before a 
court-martial shall be summoned in the prescribed manner in writing under the 
hand of the Judge Advocate General of the Navy or the trial Judge advocate.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every person who may 
be required to give evidence before a commanding officer or the officer 
preparing a summary of evidence in accordance with the regulations made under 
this Act or before a board of inquiry shall be summoned in the prescribed manner 
by writing under the hand of the Judge Advocate General of the Navy or the 
senior officer in the station or such other officer prescribed in this behalf.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In the case of a 
witness subject to naval law or to the law relating to the government of the 
regular Army or the Air Force, the summons shall be served in the manner 
prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> In the case of any 
other witness, the summons shall be served either in the prescribed manner, or 
it shall be sent to the magistrate within whose jurisdiction the witness may be 
or resides and such magistrate shall give effect to the summons as of the 
witness were required in the court of such magistrate.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> When a witness is 
required to produce any particular document or thing in his possession or power, 
the summons shall describe it with reasonable precision.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Every person not 
subject to naval law who may be summoned as aforesaid shall be allowed and paid 
such reasonable expenses as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Nothing in this 
section shall be deemed to affect the operation of sections 123 and 124 of the 
Indian Evidence Act, 1872, or to apply to any document in the custody of the 
postal or telegraph authorities.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>135</number> Commissions for 
examination of witnesses.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Whenever in the course of a trial by court-martial, it appears to the trial 
judge advocate that the examination of a witness is necessary for the ends of 
justice and that the attendance of such witness cannot be procured without an 
amount of delay, expense or inconvenience which under the circumstances of the 
case would be unreasonable, the trial judge advocate may dispense with such 
attendance and may apply to the Judge Advocate General of the Navy to issue a 
commission to 

1[any metropolitan 
magistrate or judicial magistrate of the first class] within the local limits of 
whose jurisdiction such witness resides, to take the evidence of such witness.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The trial in such an 
event may be adjourned for a specified time reasonably sufficient for the 
execution and return of the commission.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Judge Advocate 
General of the Navy on receipt of an application under sub-section (1) may, if 
thinks fit, issue a commission to the 

2[metropolitan 
magistrate or judicial magistrate of the first class or an authority exercising 
the powers equivalent to those of a judicial magistrate of the first class under 
the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973], for the examination of the witness.

 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The magistrate or 
authority to whom the commission is issued or 

2[if he is a Chief 
Metropolitan Magistrate or Chief Judicial Magistrate, he or such metropolitan 
magistrate or judicial magistrate of the first class as is appointed by him in 
this behalf] shall proceed to such place where the witness is or shall summon 
the witness before him and shall take down his evidence in the same manner and 
may for this purpose exercise the same powers as in trials of warrant cases 
under the 

3[Code of Criminal 
Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974)], or of any corresponding law in force at the place 
where the evidence is recorded.
 
 





</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>136</number> Examination of 
witnesses on commission.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where a commission is issued under the provisions of section 135, the prosecutor 
and the accused may respectively forward any interrogatories in writing which 
the trial judge advocate may think relevant to the issue and the magistrate or 
authority to whom the commission is directed or to whom the duty of executing 
such commission has been delegated shall examine the witness upon such 
interrogatories.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The prosecutor and the 
accused may appear before such magistrate or authority by counsel or, except in 
the case of an accused person in custody, in person, and may examine, 
cross-examine and re-examine, as the case may be, the said witness.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> After commission 
issued under section 135 has been duly executed, it shall be returned together 
with the deposition of the witness examined thereunder to the Judge Advocate 
General of the Navy who issued the commission.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> On receipt of the 
commission and the deposition returned under sub- section (3), the judge 
Advocate General of the Navy shall forward the same to the trial judge advocate 
at whose instance the commission was issued.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The commission, the 
return thereto and the deposition shall be open to inspection by the prosecutor 
and the accused and may subject to all just exceptions be read in evidence in 
the case by either the prosecutor or the accused and shall form part of the 
proceedings of the trial.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Any deposition so 
taken shall be received in evidence at any subsequent stage of the trial whether 
before the same court or, if the said court is dissolved meanwhile, before 
another court convened for the trial of the accused in respect of the same 
charges.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>137</number> Power to summon 
and examine material witnesses.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The trial judge advocate may, at any stage of the trial, summon any person as a 
witness or examine any person in attendance, though not summoned as a witness, 
or recall and re-examine any person already examined; and the trial judge 
advocate shall summon and examine or recall and re-examine any such person if 
his evidence appears to the court or to the trial judge advocate as essential to 
the just decision of the case.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Summons to the 
witnesses shall be issued as provided under this Act.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>138</number> Power of court to 
pay compensation out of fine.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Whenever a court-martial imposes a fine as a punishment, the court may when 
passing judgment order the whole or any part of the fine recovered to be 
applied,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  in the payment 
to any person aggrieved as compensation for any loss or injury caused by the 
offence;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  when any 
person is convicted of any civil offence which includes theft, criminal 
misappropriation, criminal breach of trust or cheating, or of having dishonestly 
received or retained, or of having voluntarily assisted in disposing of stolen 
property knowing or having reason to believe the same to be stolen property, in 
compensating any bona fide purchaser of the property for the loss of the 
same if such property is restored to the possession of the person entitled 
thereto.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> No such payment or 
compensation, shall, however, be made before the expiry of fifteen days from the 
date of the sentence, and when a petition is presented against the conviction or 
sentence until the said petition is disposed of.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>139</number> Summary punishment 
for contempt of court by person subject to naval law.—When 
any person subject to naval law commits any offence as is described in section 
69 in the presence of or in relation to a proceeding before a court-martial such 
court-martial may punish the offender summarily by imprisonment for a term which 
may extend to three months or such other less punishment as may be awarded for 
that offence under section 69.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>140</number> Summary punishment 
for contempt of court by person not subject to naval law.—When 
any person not subject to naval law commits an offence as is described in 
section 165 in the presence of a court-martial, such court-martial may take such 
person into custody and at any time before the rising of the court on the same 
day, if it thinks fit, take cognizance of the offence and sentence the offender 
of fine not exceeding two hundred rupees or in default of payment to simple 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to one month, unless such fine shall be 
sooner paid.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>141</number> Powers of 
court-martial when certain offences are committed by persons not subject to 
naval law.—When 
any such offence as is described in section 165 of this Act or section 193, 
section 194, section 195, section 196, section 199, section 200, section 228, 
section 463 or section 471 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860) is committed by 
any person not subject to naval law in or in relation to a proceeding before a 
court-martial, such court-martial or the officer ordering the same if such 
court-martial is dissolved, may exercise the powers 

1[under section 340 
of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974)], as if it or he were a 
criminal court within the meaning of that section.
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>142</number> Powers of 
courts-martial and disciplinary courts in relation to proceedings under this 
Act.—Any trial 
by a court-martial or disciplinary court under the provisions of this Act shall 
be deemed to be a judicial proceeding within the meaning of sections 193 and 228 
of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860), and the court-martial or disciplinary 
court shall be deemed to be a court within the meaning of 

1[sections 345 and 
346 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974)].
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>143</number> Accused found 
insane during trial.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where it appears in the course of the trial by court-martial of any person 
charged with an offence that such person is insane, the court shall find 
specially the fact of his insanity and shall order such person to be kept in 
strict custody in such place and in such manner as the court may deem fit until 
the directions of the Central Government thereupon are known.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every such case shall 
be reported by the court to the convening authority for orders of the Central 
Government and it shall be lawful for the Central Government to give orders for 
the safe custody of such person in such place and in such manner as the Central 
Government may deem fit.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Whenever on the 
receipt of a report from the Central Government or otherwise the convening 
authority considers that such person is capable of making his defence, the 
convening authority may take steps to convene a court-martial for the trial of 
such person.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>144</number> Lunacy of the 
accused at the time of offence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Whenever any person subject to naval law is acquitted upon the ground that, at 
the time at which he is alleged to have committed an offence, he was, by reason 
of unsoundness of mind, incapable of knowing the nature of the act alleged as 
constituting the offence, or that it was wrong or contrary to law, the finding 
shall specifically state whether he committed the act or not.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Whenever the finding 
made under sub-section (1) states that the accused person committed the act 
alleged, the court-martial shall, if such act would, but for the incapacity 
found, have constituted an offence, order such person to be detained in safe 
custody in such place and in such manner as may be prescribed and shall report 
the action taken to the officer convening the court.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The officer convening 
the court shall then report the case for the orders of the Central Government 
and shall take necessary steps to detain the said person in safe custody pending 
receipt of such orders.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Central Government 
may on receipt of a report under sub-section (3) order the accused person to be 
detained in a mental hospital or other suitable place of safe custody.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>145</number> Disposal of 
property pending trial.—When 
any property regarding which an offence appears to have been committed or which 
appears to have been used for the commission of an offence is produced before a 
court-martial, the court may make such order as it thinks fit for the proper 
custody of such property pending the conclusion of the trial and if the property 
is subject to speedy or natural decay may after recording such evidence as it 
thinks necessary order it to be sold or otherwise disposed of.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>146</number> Disposal of 
property regarding which offence is committed.— 

<section><number>1</number> When the trial before any court-martial is concluded, the court may make 
such order as it thinks fit for the disposal by destruction, confiscation or 
delivery to any person claiming to be entitled to possession thereof or 
otherwise of any property or document produced before it or in its custody or 
regarding which an offence appears to have been committed or which has been used 
for the commission of any offence:
 
Provided that except in 
the case of property which is subject to speedy or natural decay such property 
or document shall, if so required by regulations, made under this Act, be kept 
in custody until the orders of the Chief of the Naval Staff are known.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An order under 
sub-section (1) shall not be carried out for one month, unless the property is 
subject to speedy or natural decay.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> When an order under 
this section cannot be conveniently carried out by persons in the naval service, 
a copy of such order certified by the Chief of the Naval Staff or an officer 
prescribed in this behalf, may be sent to a magistrate within whose jurisdiction 
the property is for the time being situate and such magistrate shall thereupon 
take steps to cause the order to be carried into effect as if it were an order 
passed by him.
 
Explanation.—In 
this section, the term “property” includes, in the case of property regarding 
which an offence appears to have been committed, not only such property as has 
been originally in the possession or under the control of any person, but also 
any property into or for which the same may have been converted or exchanged and 
anything acquired by such conversion or exchange whether immediately or 
otherwise.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>147</number> Form of sentence 
of death.—In 
awarding a sentence of death, a court-martial shall in its discretion direct 
that the offender shall suffer death by being hanged by the neck until he be 
dead or shall suffer death by being shot to death.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>148</number> Interim custody 
until execution of sentences of death.—A 
person sentenced to death may be detained in naval custody or may be removed to 
a civil prison to be kept in custody until further orders be received from the 
Central Government, the Chief of the Naval Staff or the officer ordering 
court-martial by which he was sentenced to death or other prescribed officer and 
the order in the prescribed form of the Central Government, the Chief of the 
Naval Staff or the convening authority or such officer shall be sufficient 
warrant for detaining the person in custody.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>149</number> Execution of 
sentences of death.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When a sentence of death is to be executed, the Chief of the Naval staff or 
convening authority or the prescribed officer shall give directions as to the 
time, place and manner in which such sentence is to be carried out and the order 
of such officer or authority in the prescribed form shall be sufficient warrant 
for the execution of such sentence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> There shall be 
attached to the prescribed form an order of the Central Government certifying 
the confirmation of the sentence by the Central Government in all cases where 
such confirmation is necessary; and where such confirmation is not necessary, a 
certificate of the Chief of the Naval staff or other prescribed offices stating 
that such confirmation is not necessary.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>150</number> Place of 
imprisonment and detention.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every term of imprisonment whether imprisonment was awarded as an original or 
commuted punishment may be served in a naval prison, naval detention quarters or 
in any civil prison, house of correction or military or air force prison or 
detention barracks.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every term of 
detention whether the detention was awarded as an original or commuted 
punishment may be served in any naval detention quarters or army or air force 
detention barracks.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where in pursuance of 
this Act, a person is sentenced to imprisonment or detention or has his sentence 
commuted to imprisonment or detention, the order in the prescribed form of the 
Central Government or the Chief of the Naval Staff or the officer ordering the 
court-martial by which such person was sentenced or the senior officer present 
in port or, if he was sentenced by the commanding officer of a ship, or other 
officer empowered under this Act to exercise like powers, the order in the 
prescribed form of such commanding officer or other officer, shall be a 
sufficient warrant for the sending of such person to the place of imprisonment 
or detention, as the case may be, there to undergo the sentence according to 
law, or until he reaches such place of imprisonment of detention for detaining 
him in naval custody or in the case of a person sentenced to imprisonment, in 
any civil prison or place of confinement.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>151</number> Commencement of 
sentence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to the provisions of 

1[sub- sections (2) 
and (3)] every term of imprisonment or detention awarded in pursuance of this 
Act shall be reckoned as commencing on the day on which the sentence was 
awarded.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where by reason of a 
ship being at sea or off a place at which there is no proper prison or naval 
detention quarters, a sentence of imprisonment or detention, as the case may be, 
cannot be duly executed, then subject as hereinafter mentioned, an offender 
under the sentence of imprisonment or detention, as the case may be, may be sent 
with all reasonable speed to some place at which there is a proper prison or 
naval detention quarters or in the case of an offender under sentence of 
detention to some place at which there are some naval detention quarters in 
which the sentence can be duly executed; and on arrival there, the offender 
shall undergo his sentence in like manner as if the date of such arrival were 
the day on which the sentence was awarded and notwithstanding that in the 
meanwhile he has returned to his duty or become entitled to his discharge; and 
the term of imprisonment or detention, as the case may be, shall be reckoned 
accordingly, subject however to the deduction of any time during which he has 
been kept in confinement in respect of the said offence.
 

2[(3) Whenever any 
offender is sentenced by a court-martial to a term of imprisonment, in pursuance 
of this Act, not being imprisonment in default of payment of fine, the period 
spent by him in civil or naval custody during investigation, inquiry or trial of 
the same case, and before the date of order of such sentence, shall be set off 
against the terms of imprisonment imposed upon him, and the liability of such 
offender to undergo imprisonment on such order of sentence shall be restricted 
to the remainder, if any, of the term of imprisonment imposed upon him.]
 


comment
 
The provisions for set of 
contained in section 428 of the Code of Criminal Procedure can never be 
attracted in the case of persons convicted and sentenced by court martial to 
undergo imprisonment; Ajmer Singh v. Union of India, AIR 1987 SC 
1646.
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>152</number> Imprisonment of 
offender already under sentence.—Whenever 
a sentence shall be passed by a court-martial on an offender already under 
sentence either of detention or imprisonment passed upon him under this Act for 
a former offence, the court may award a sentence of detention or imprisonment 
for the offence for which he is under trial to commence at the expiration of the 
sentence of detention or imprisonment to which he has been previously sentenced:
 
Provided that so much of 
any term of detention imposed on a person by a sentence in pursuance of this 
section as will prolong the total term of detention beyond two years shall be 
deemed to be remitted.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>153</number> Change of place of 
confinement.—Whenever 
it is deemed expedient, it shall be lawful for the Central Government, the Chief 
of the Naval Staff or senior officer present, by an order in writing in the 
prescribed form, from time to time to change the place of confinement of any 
offender imprisoned or sentenced to be imprisoned or detained in pursuance of 
this Act or of any offender undergoing or sentenced to undergo detention; and 
the gaoler or other person having the custody of such offender shall immediately 
on the receipt of such order remove such offender to the gaol, prison or house 
of correction or, in the case of an offender undergoing or sentenced to undergo 
detention, to the naval detention quarters mentioned in the said order, or shall 
deliver him over to naval custody for the purpose of the offender being removed 
to such prison or naval detention quarters, and every gaoler or keeper of such 
last-mentioned prison, gaol, or house of correction or naval detention quarters 
shall, upon being furnished with such order of removal, receive into his custody 
and shall confine pursuant to such sentence or order every such offender.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>154</number> Discharge or 
removal of prisoners.—Whenever 
any offender is undergoing imprisonment or detention in pursuance of this Act, 
it shall be lawful for the Central Government or the Chief of the Naval Staff, 
or where an offender is undergoing imprisonment or detention by orders of his 
commanding officer, for such commanding officer or the Central Government or the 
Chief of the Naval Staff, to give an order in writing in the prescribed form 
directing that the offender be discharged; and it shall also be lawful for the 
Central Government and the Chief of the Naval Staff, by order in writing in the 
prescribed form, to direct that any such offender be delivered over to naval 
custody for the purpose of being brought before a court-martial, either as a 
witness or for trial or otherwise, and such offender shall accordingly, on the 
production of any such order, be discharged, or be delivered over to such 
custody.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>155</number> Time of detention 
in naval custody.—The 
time during which any offender under sentence of imprisonment or detention is 
detained in naval custody shall be reckoned as imprisonment or detention under 
his sentence for whatever purpose he is so detained; and the governor, gaoler, 
keeper or superintendent who shall deliver over any such offender shall again 
receive him from naval custody, so that he may undergo the remainder of his 
punishment.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>156</number> Removal of insane 
prisoners.—If 
any person imprisoned or undergoing detention by virtue of this Act shall become 
insane, and certificate to that effect shall be given by two physicians or 
surgeons, the Central Government shall by warrant in the prescribed form, direct 
the removal of such person to such asylum or other proper receptacle for insane 
persons in India as it may judge proper for the unexpired term of his 
imprisonment or detention; and if any such person shall in the same manner be 
certified to be again of sound mind, the Central Government may issue a warrant 
in the prescribed form for his being removed to such prison or place of 
confinement or in the case of a person sentenced to detention, such naval 
detention quarters as may be deemed expedient, to undergo the remainder of his 
punishment, and every gaoler or keeper of any prison, gaol, or house of 
correction shall receive him accordingly.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>157</number> Naval prisons and 
naval detention quarters.—The 
Central Government may set apart any buildings or vessels or any parts thereof 
as naval prisons or naval detention quarters and any buildings, vessels or parts 
of buildings or vessels so set apart as naval prisons or naval detention 
quarters, as the case may be, shall be deemed to be naval prisons or naval 
detention quarters respectively within the meaning of this Act.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>158</number> Execution of 
sentence of fine.—When 
a sentence of fine is imposed under this Act by a court-martial or disciplinary 
court, the officer ordering the court-martial or disciplinary court may transmit 
a copy of the order imposing the fine duly certified under his hand to any 
magistrate in India, and such magistrate shall thereupon cause the fine to be 
recovered in accordance with the provisions of the 

1[Code of Criminal 
Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974)], or any law corresponding thereto in force in the 
State of Jammu and Kashmir as if it were a sentence of fine imposed by such 
magistrate.
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>159</number> Power to make 
regulations in respect of naval prisons and detention quarters.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette make 
regulations providing,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  for the 
Government, management and regulation of naval prisons and detention quarters;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  for the 
appointment and removal and powers of inspectors, visitors and officers thereof;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  for the food, 
bedding and clothing of prisoners or persons undergoing detention therein;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  for the labour 
of such prisoners or persons therein and for enabling such prisoners or persons 
to earn by special industry and good conduct remission of a portion of their 
sentence; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  for the care 
of such prisoners or persons, their safe custody and the maintenance of good 
order and discipline among them and the punishment by personal correction, 
restraint or otherwise of offences committed by such prisoners or persons.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The regulations to be 
made under this section may apply to naval prisons or detention quarters any of 
the provisions of the Prisons Act, 1894 (9 of 1894), and rules made thereunder, 
imposing punishment on any persons not being prisoners or relating to the duties 
of gaoler, medical officers and other officers of the prisons.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The regulations to be 
made under this section shall not authorise corporal punishment to be inflicted 
for any offence.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>160</number> Judicial review by 
the Judge Advocate General of the Navy.—
<section><number>1</number> 
All proceedings of trials by court-martial or by disciplinary courts shall be 
reviewed by the Judge Advocate General of the Navy either on his own motion or 
on application made to him within the prescribed time by any person aggrieved by 
any sentence or finding, and the Judge Advocate General of the Navy shall 
transmit the report of such review together with such recommendations as may 
appear just and proper to the Chief of the Naval Staff for his consideration and 
for such action as the Chief of the Naval Staff may think fit.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any person 
aggrieved has made an application under sub-section (1), the Judge Advocate 
General of the Navy may, if the circumstances of the case so require, give him 
an opportunity of being heard either in person or through a legal practitioner 
or an officer of the Indian Navy.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>161</number> Consideration by 
the Chief of the Naval Staff.—
<section><number>1</number> 
On receipt of the report and recommendations if any, under section 160, the 
Chief of the Naval Staff shall in all cases of capital sentence and in all cases 
where the court-martial is ordered by the President, and may in other cases may 
transmit the proceedings and the report to the Central Government together with 
such recommendations as he may deem fit to make.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Nothing in section 160 
or this section shall authorise the Judge Advocate General of the Navy or the 
Chief of the Naval Staff to make any recommendation for setting aside, or the 
Central Government to set aside, an order of acquittal passed under this Act.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>162</number> Petitions to the 
Central Government or Chief of the Naval Staff against findings of sentences.—Any 
person subject to naval law who considers himself aggrieved by finding or 
sentence of any court-martial may present a petition to the Central Government 
or to the Chief of the Naval Staff, and the Central Government or the Chief of 
the Naval Staff, as the case may be, may pass such order thereon as may be 
thought fit.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>163</number> Powers of Central 
Government and the Chief of the Naval Staff in respect of findings and 
sentences.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where any person is tried under the provisions of this Act, the Central 
Government or the Chief of the Naval Staff, may, in the case of a conviction—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  set aside the 
finding and sentence and acquit or discharge the accused or order him to be 
retried, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  alter the 
finding, maintaining the sentence (provided that such sentence may be legally 
passed on the altered finding), or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  with or 
without altering the finding, reduce the sentence or commute the punishment 
awarded for any punishment inferior in scale, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  either with or 
without conditions, pardon the person or remit the whole or any part of the 
punishment awarded, or
 
 

1[***]
 
Provided that a sentence 
of imprisonment shall not be commuted for a sentence of detention for a term 
exceeding the term of imprisonment awarded, and a sentence of dismissal with 
disgrace not accompanied by a sentence of imprisonment shall not be commuted for 
a sentence of detention:
 
Provided further that 
nothing in this section shall authorise the Central Government or the Chief of 
the Naval Staff to enhance the sentence.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Any sentence modified 
under the provisions of sub-section (1) shall be carried into execution as if it 
had been originally passed.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If any condition on 
which a person has been pardoned or released on parole or a punishment has been 
remitted is in the opinion of the authority which granted the pardon, release or 
remission not fulfilled, such authority may cancel the pardon or release or 
remission and thereupon the sentence awarded shall be carried into effect as if 
such pardon, release or remission had not been granted:
 
Provided that in the case 
of a person sentenced to imprisonment or detention such person shall undergo 
only the unexpired portion of the sentence.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>163A</number> 
Provision relating to parole.—Where any person is tried under the provision 
of this Act, the Central Government or the Chief of the Naval Staff or the Flag 
Officers Commanding-in-Chief of the Naval Commands may in the case of conviction 
either with or without conditions release the person on parole.]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>164</number> Suspension of 
sentences.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where a person has been sentenced to imprisonment or detention, the Central 
Government or the officer who by virtue of the foregoing section or sub-section 
(3) of section 150 has power to issue an order of committal (hereinafter in this 
section referred to as “the committing authority”) may, in lieu of issuing such 
an order, order that the sentence be suspended until an order of committal is 
issued, and in such case—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  
notwithstanding anything in this Act, the term of the sentence shall not be 
reckoned as commencing until an order of committal is issued;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the case may 
at any time, and shall at intervals of not more than three months, be 
reconsidered by the Central Government or committing authority or such 
prescribed officer, and if on any such reconsideration it appears to the Central 
Government or committing authority or such prescribed officer that the conduct 
of the offender since his conviction has been such as to justify a remission of 
the sentence, the Central Government or committing authority or such prescribed 
officer shall remit the whole or any part of it;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  subject to 
regulation made under this Act, the Central Government or the commuting 
authority or such prescribed officer may at any time whilst the sentence is 
suspended issue an order of committal and thereupon the sentence shall cease to 
be suspended;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  where a person 
subject to naval law, whilst a sentence on him is so suspended, is sentenced to 
imprisonment or detention for any other offence then, if he is at any time 
committed either under the suspended sentence or under any such subsequent 
sentence, and whether or not any such subsequent sentence has also been 
suspended, the committing authority may direct that the two sentences shall run 
either concurrently or consecutively, so, however, as not to cause a person to 
undergo detention for a period exceeding the aggregate of two consecutive years.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> when a person has been 
sentenced to imprisonment or detention and an order of committal has been 
issued, the Central Government or the committing authority, or prescribed 
officer may order the sentence to be suspended, and in such cases the person 
whose sentence is suspended shall be discharged and the currency of the sentence 
shall be suspended until he is again committed under the same sentence, and the 
provision of clauses (b), (c) and (d) of sub-section (1) shall apply in like 
manner as in the case where a sentence has been suspended before an order of 
committal has been issued.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where a sentence is 
suspended under this section, whether before or after committal, the Central 
Government or, subject to regulations made under this Act, the committing 
authority or officer by whom the sentence is suspended, may direct that any 
penalty which is involved by the punishment of imprisonment or detention either 
shall be or shall not be remitted or suspended.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>165</number> Offences by 
persons not subject to naval law in relation to courts-martial and disciplinary 
court.—Every 
person not subject to naval law, who,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  being duly 
summoned or ordered to attend as a witness before a court-martial or 
disciplinary court fails to attend without due cause, or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  refuses to 
take an oath or make an affirmation legally required by a court-martial or 
disciplinary court to be taken or made, or
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  being sworn or 
affirmed, refuses to answer any questions put by or before a court-martial or 
disciplinary court, which he is in law bound to answer, or
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  refuses to 
produce or deliver up a document in his power which the court-martial or 
disciplinary court may legally demand, or
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number>  is guilty of 
contempt of court-martial or disciplinary court,
 
shall be punished with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years, or with fine, or with 
both.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>166</number> Penalties for 
aiding escape or attempt to escape of prisoners and for breach of prison 
regulations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every person, who,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  conveys or 
causes to be conveyed into any naval prison or naval detention quarters any 
arms, tools, or instruments, or any mask or other disguise to facilitate the 
escape of any prisoner or person undergoing detention, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  by any means 
whatever aids any prisoner or person undergoing detention to escape or in an 
attempt to escape from such prison or naval detention quarters, whether an 
escape be actually made or not,
 
shall be punished with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to fourteen years.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every person who 
brings or attempts to bring into a naval prison or naval detention quarters, in 
contravention of regulations made under this Act, by spirituous or fermented 
liquor, shall for every such offence be punished with a fine not exceeding two 
hundred rupees and not less than one hundred rupees.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every person, who,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  brings into a 
naval prison or naval detention quarters or to or for any prisoner or person 
undergoing detention, without the knowledge of the officer having charge or 
command thereof any money, clothing, provision, tobacco, letters, papers, or 
other articles not allowed by the rules of the prison or naval detention 
quarters, to be in the possession of a prisoner or person undergoing detention, 
or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  throws into 
the said prison or naval detention quarters, any such articles, or by desire of 
any prisoner or person undergoing detention, without the sanction of the said 
officer carries out of the prison or naval detention quarters any of the 
articles aforesaid,
 
shall for every such 
offence be punished with a fine not exceeding two hundred rupees.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> Every person, who,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  interrupts any 
officer of a naval prison or naval detention quarters in the execution of his 
duty, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  aids or abets 
any person to assault, resist, or interrupt any such officer, shall for every 
such offence be punished with imprisonment which may extend to two years, or 
with fine, or both.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> Every fine recovered 
under the foregoing sub-sections of this section shall be applied as the Central 
Government may direct notwithstanding any law, charter, or custom to the 
contrary.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>167</number> Penalty as regards 
gaolers, etc.—Every 
governor, gaoler, and keeper of any prison, gaol, or house of correction or of 
any naval detention quarters, and every person having the charge or command of 
any place, ship, or vessel for imprisonment, who shall without lawful excuse, 
refuse or neglect to receive or confine, remove, discharge, or deliver up any 
offender against the provisions of this Act, or any of them, shall incur for 
every such refusal or neglect a penalty not exceeding one thousand rupees and 
every such penalty shall be applied as the Central Government may direct 
notwithstanding any law, charter, or custom to the contrary.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>168</number> Appointment of the 
Judge Advocate General of the Navy and his subordinate officers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
There shall be appointed by the Central Government a Judge Advocate General of 
the Navy and as many judge advocates in the department of the Judge Advocate 
General of the Navy as the Central Government may deem necessary.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Out of the judge 
advocates so appointed, the Central Government may designate any one to be the 
Deputy Judge Advocate General of the Navy.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A person shall not be 
qualified for appointment as Judge Advocate General of the Navy unless he—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  is a citizen 
of India, and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  has for at 
least ten years held a judicial office in the territory of India, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  has for at 
least ten years been an advocate of a High Court or two or more such courts in 
succession:
 
Provided that the Central 
Government may, if it is of opinion that it is necessary or expedient so to do 
in the exigencies of service, relax, for reasons to be recorded in writing, the 
qualification specified in clause (b) or clause (c) in respect of any person.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> A person shall not be 
qualified for appointment as Deputy Judge Advocate General of the Navy unless 
he—
 <subsection>
     <number>a</number>      is a citizen 
of India, and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  has for at 
least seven years held a judicial office in the territory of India, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  has for at 
least seven years been an advocate of a High Court or two or more such courts in 
succession:
 
Provided that the Central 
Government may, if it is of opinion that it is necessary or expedient so to do 
in the exigencies of service, relax, for reasons to be recorded in writing, the 
qualification specified in clause (b) or clause (c) in respect of any person.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> A person shall not be 
qualified for appointment as a Judge Advocate unless he—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  is a citizen 
of India, and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  is qualified 
for enrolment as an advocate or a pleader of a High Court.
 
Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this section,—
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>a</number>  in computing 
the period during which a person has been an advocate of a High Court, there 
shall be included any period during which the person has held judicial office 
after he became an advocate;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  in computing 
the period during which a person has held judicial office in the territory of 
India or been an advocate of a High Court, there shall be included any period 
before the commencement of the Constitution during which he has held judicial 
office in any area which was comprised before the 15th day of August, 1947, 
within India as defined in the Government of India Act, 1935, or has practised 
as an advocate of any High Court in any such area as the case may be;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  the expression 
“judicial office” shall be deemed to include the office of the Judge Advocate of 
the fleet or any of his deputies or assistants and any other legal or judicial 
office in the department of the Judge Advocate of the fleet held before the 
commencement of this Act, and the office of the Judge Advocate General of the 
Navy or of a Judge Advocate held after the commencement of this Act.
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>169</number> Functions of the 
Judge Advocate General of the Navy.—It 
shall be the duty of the Judge Advocate General of the Navy to perform such 
duties of a legal and judicial character pertaining to the Indian Navy as may 
from time to time be referred or assigned to him by the Central Government or 
the Chief of the Naval Staff, and to discharge the functions conferred on him by 
or under this Act, or any other law for the time being in force.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>170</number> Discharge of 
functions of the Judge Advocate General of the Navy in his absence.—The 
functions of the Judge Advocate General of the Navy shall in his absence on 
leave or otherwise, be performed by such one the judge advocates in his 
department as may be designated in this behalf by the Chief of the Naval Staff.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>171</number> Disposal of 
property of deceased sailors.—
<section><number>1</number> 
On the death of a sailor while subject to naval law, the commanding officer of 
the ship to which the sailor belonged shall as soon as may be,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  secure all 
movable property belonging to the deceased that is in the ship or quarters and 
cause an inventory thereof to be made;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  draw the pay 
and allowances due to such persons;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  if he thinks 
fit, and subject to any regulations made in this behalf, collect all moneys left 
by the deceased in any banking company, including any post office saving bank, 
co-operative bank or society, or any other institution receiving deposits in 
money however named, and for that purpose may require the agent, manager or 
other proper authority of such banking company, society or other institution to 
pay the moneys to the commanding officer forthwith, notwithstanding anything in 
the rules of the banking company, society or institution; and such agent, 
manager or other authority shall, notwithstanding anything contained in any 
other law, be bound to comply with the requisition.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any money has 
been paid by the banking company, society or other institution in compliance 
with the requisition under clause (c) of sub-section (1), no person shall have 
any claim against the said banking company, society or other institution in 
respect of such money.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The commanding officer 
shall, if in his opinion it is necessary for the purpose of securing the payment 
of the ship and service debts and other debts in the ship or quarters of the 
deceased and the expenses, if any, incurred by the commanding officer in respect 
of the estate of the deceased, cause the movable property of the deceased to be 
sold or converted into money.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If the representative 
of the deceased is on the spot and either pays or gives security for the payment 
of the ship and service debts and other debts in ship or quarters due from the 
deceased the commanding officer shall not take action under clause (c) of 
sub-section (1) or under sub-section (3).
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The commanding officer 
shall, out of the moneys so received, collected or realised under sub-sections 
(1) and (3), pay the ship and service debts and other debts in ship or quarters 
of the deceased, and the expenses incurred in connection with the realisation of 
the assets of the deceased.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Any property left over 
after meeting the expenditure indicated in sub- section (5), or where the 
representative had paid or given security for the payment of the ship and 
service debts and other debts in ship or quarters the entire property of the 
deceased, shall be delivered over by the commanding officer to the 
representative of the deceased, whereupon his responsibility for the 
administration of the estate of the deceased shall cease.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> If no claim is made in 
respect of the said no surplus by a representative of the deceased within twelve 
months of the death, the commanding officer shall take steps to hand over the 
property to the prescribed person who shall continue the administration of the 
estate of the deceased as provided for in section 176.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>172</number> Disposal of 
property of deceased officers.—The 
provisions of section 171 shall also apply to the disposal of the property of an 
officer who dies while subject to naval law, but with the following 
modifications, namely:—
 <section>
        <number>i</number>  the functions 
of the commanding officer under section 171 shall be performed by a Committee of 
Adjustment constituted in this behalf in the prescribed manner; and
 </section><section>
        <number>ii</number>  the surplus, 
if any, after the payment of debts and expenses specified in sub-section (3) of 
section 171 shall be paid to the person prescribed in this behalf.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>173</number> Decision of 
questions as to ship and service debts and other debts in ship or quarters.—If 
in any case a doubt or difference arises as to what are the ship or service 
debts and the debts in ship or quarters of a deceased officer or sailor or as to 
the amount payable in respect thereof, the decision of the prescribed person 
shall be final and shall be binding on all persons for all purposes.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>174</number> Nature of the 
powers of commanding officer or Committee of Adjustment.—For 
the purpose of the exercise of his or its duties under section 171 or 172, as 
the case may be, the commanding officer or the Committee of Adjustment, as the 
case may be, shall, to the exclusion of all other persons and authorities have 
the same rights and powers as if the commanding officer or the Committee had 
taken out representation to the estate of the deceased, and any receipt given by 
such commanding officer or the Committee, as the case may be, shall have effect 
accordingly.
 
Explanation.—“Representation” 
includes probate, letters of administration with or without the will annexed and 
a succession certificate issued by a court of competent jurisdiction 
constituting a person executor or administrator of the estate of the deceased 
person or authorising him to receive or realise the assets of a deceased person.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>175</number> Powers of Central 
Government to hand over estate of deceased persons to the Administrator General.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in the Administrator-General’s Act, 1913 (3 
of 1913), an Administrator-General shall not interpose in any manner in relation 
to any property of a deceased which has been dealt with under section 171 or 
section 172 except in so far as he is expressly required or competent to do so 
by or under the provisions of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Central Government 
may, at any time and in such circumstances as it thinks fit, direct that the 
estate of a deceased sailor or officer shall be handed over by the commanding 
officer or the Committee of Adjustment, as the case may be, to the 
Administrator-General of a State for administration and thereupon such 
commanding officer or the Committee shall make over the estate to such 
Administrator-General.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where under this 
section any estate is handed over to the Administrator-General, the latter shall 
administer such estate in accordance with the provisions of the 
Administrator-General’s Act, 1913 (3 of 1913):
 
Provided that where the 
estate is handed over to the Administrator-General before the ship and service 
debts and other debts in ship or quarters of the deceased are paid, it shall be 
the duty of the Administrator-General to pay these debts in priority to any 
other debts due by the deceased.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
Administrator-General shall pay the surplus, if any, remaining in his hands 
after discharging all debts and charges, to the heirs of the deceased and if no 
heir is traceable, shall make over the surplus to the person prescribed in this 
behalf.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
Administrator-General shall not charge in respect of his duties under this 
section any fee exceeding three per cent. of the total amount coming to or 
remaining in his hands after payment of the ship and service debts and the other 
debts in ship or quarters.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>176</number> Disposal of 
surplus by prescribed persons.—On 
receipt of the surplus referred to in sub-section (7) of section 171 or clause 
(ii) of section 172 or sub-section (4) of section 175, the prescribed person 
shall,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  if he knows of 
a legal representative of the deceased, pay the surplus to that representative;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  if the surplus 
does not exceed 

1[the prescribed 
amount not exceeding rupees one lakh in value] and if he thinks fit, pay or 
deliver to any person appearing to him to be entitled to receive the same, 
without requiring such person to produce any probate, letters of administration, 
succession certificate or other conclusive evidence of title;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  if the 
prescribed person does not know of any such representative to whom the surplus 
could be paid under clause (a), or if the surplus has not been disposed of under 
clause (b), publish every year a notice in the prescribed form and manner for 
six consecutive years; and if no claim to the surplus is made by the legal 
representative of the deceased within six months even after the publication of 
the last of such notices, the prescribed person shall deposit the surplus 
together with any income or accumulation of income accrued therefrom, to the 
credit of the Central Government:
 
Provided that such deposit 
shall not prejudice the claims of any person to such surplus or any part 
thereof, if he is otherwise entitled to it.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>177</number> Disposal of 
effects not converted into money.—Where 
any part of the estate of a deceased officer or sailor consists of effects, 
securities or other property not converted into money, the provisions of 
sub-section (7) of section 171 or clause (ii) of section 172 and section 176 
with respect to the payment of the surplus shall, save as may be prescribed, 
extend to the delivery, transmission or transfer of such effects, securities or 
property, and the prescribed person shall have the same power of converting the 
same into money as a legal representative of the deceased.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>178</number> Termination of 
liability of commanding officer, Committee, prescribed person and the Central 
Government.—Any 
payment or application of money or delivery sale or other disposition of any 
property made, or purported to be made by the commanding officer, the Committee 
or the prescribed person in good faith in pursuance of sections 171 to 176 shall 
be valid and shall fully absolve the commanding officer, the Committee or the 
prescribed person, as the case may be, as well as the Central Government from 
all liability in respect of the money or property so paid, applied or disposed 
of; but nothing herein contained shall be deemed to affect the right of any 
executor or administrator or other legal representative or of any creditor of 
the deceased against any person to whom any such payment or delivery as 
aforesaid has been made.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>179</number> Saving of rights 
of representative.—Nothing 
in this Chapter shall affect the rights and duties of the representative of a 
deceased sailor or officer or any Administrator-General, in respect of the 
property of such deceased sailor or officer not collected by the commanding 
officer or the Committee, as the case may be, and not forming part of the 
surplus handed over to the prescribed person either under sub-section (7) of 
section 171 or clause (ii) of section 172.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>180</number> Application of 
sections 171 to 179 to persons of unsound mind.—The 
provisions of sections 171 to 179 shall, so far as they can be made applicable, 
also apply in the case of an officer or sailor subject to naval law who is 
ascertained in the prescribed manner to be of unsound mind notwithstanding 
anything contained in the Indian Lunacy Act, 1912 (4 of 1912), or who, while on 
active service, is officially reported missing, as if the said officer or sailor 
had died on the day on which his unsoundness of mind is so ascertained or, as 
the case may be, on the day on which he is officially reported missing:
 
Provided that in the case 
of an officer or sailor so reported missing, no action shall be taken to dispose 
of the property under sections 171, 172 and 175 until such time as a certificate 
under the regulations made under this Act is issued by or under the authority of 
the Chief of the Naval Staff or other prescribed person that he is confirmed or 
presumed to be dead.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>181</number> Appointment of 
Standing Committee of Adjustment in certain cases.—When 
an officer while subject to naval law dies or is ascertained in the prescribed 
manner to be of unsound mind or while on active service is officially reported 
missing, the reference in the foregoing provisions of this Chapter to the 
Committee shall be construed as references to the Standing Committee of 
Adjustment, if any, constituted in this behalf in the prescribed manner and such 
Standing Committee, if constituted, shall alone be entitled to perform all the 
functions of such Committee unless otherwise directed by the Chief of the Naval 
Staff.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>182</number> Exercise of powers 
by other persons.—The 
functions and powers of the commanding officer in the Chapter may in any case be 
performed or exercised by any other person appointed in this behalf by the Chief 
of the Naval Staff.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>183</number> Forfeiture of 
effects for absence without leave.—If 
any person subject to naval law is absent without leave for a period of one 
month (whether he is guilty of desertion or of improperly leaving his ship or 
place of duty or not) but is not apprehended or tried for his offence, he shall 
be liable for forfeiture of pay and allowances and other benefits as the Central 
Government from time to time by regulations provide, and the Central Government, 
the Chief of the Naval Staff or the prescribed officer may by an order 
containing a statement of the absence without leave direct that the clothes and 
effects, if any, left by him on board ship or at his place of duty be forfeited, 
and the same be sold and the proceeds of the same shall be disposed of as 
provided in the regulations made under this Act, and every order under this 
provision for forfeiture or sale shall be conclusive for the purpose of this 
section as to the fact of the absence without leave as therein stated of the 
person therein named; but in any case the Central Government may, if it deems 
fit on sufficient cause being shown at any time after forfeiture and before 
sale, remit the forfeiture, or after sale pay or dispose of the proceeds of the 
sale or any part thereof to or for the use of the person to whom the clothes or 
effects belonged, or his representatives.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>184</number> Power to make 
regulations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, by notification in the official Gazette, make 
regulations for the governance, command, discipline, recruitment, conditions of 
service and regulation of the naval forces and generally for the purpose of 
carrying into effect the provisions of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular, and 
without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such regulations may 
provide for—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the rank, 
precedence, powers of command and authority of officers and sailors in the naval 
service;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the relative 
rank, precedence, powers of command and authority of officers and sailors in the 
naval service in relation to members of the regular Army and the Air Force;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  the cases in 
which, and the conditions subject to which powers of punishment may be exercised 
under sub-section (2) of section 7;
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>ca</number>  the 
retirement, discharge and dismissal of persons in the naval service;
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>cb</number>  the authority 
to which any matter referred to in section 19A may be referred and the manner in 
which an enquiry may be made by that authority;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  the convening 
and constitution of courts-martial and the appointment of prosecutors at trials 
by court-martial;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  the 
adjournment, dissolution and sittings of courts-martial;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  the procedure 
to be observed in trials by courts-martial, the persons by whom an accused may 
be defended in such trials and the appearance of such persons thereat;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>g</number>  the forms of 
orders to be made under the provisions of this Act relating to courts-martial 
and the awards and infliction of death, imprisonment and detention;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>h</number>  the carrying 
into effect of sentences of courts-martial;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>i</number>  any matter 
necessary for the purpose of carrying this Act into execution as far as it 
relates to the investigation, arrest, custody, trial and punishment of offences 
triable or punishable under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>j</number>  the terms and 
conditions of service, the pay, the pensions, allowances and other benefits of 
persons in the naval service, including special provision in this behalf during 
active service;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>k</number>  the 
ceremonials to be observed and marks of respect to be paid in the naval service;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>l</number>  the convening 
of, the constitution, procedure and practice of boards of inquiry, the summoning 
of witnesses before them and the administration of oaths by such boards;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>m</number>  the 
computation of time of absence without leave or custody of deserters and 
absentees without leave;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>n</number>  any matter 
relating to the realisation and disposal of the estates of officers or sailors 
who are deceased, ascertained to be of unsound mind or reported missing on 
active service;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>o</number>  the enquiry 
into the conduct of prisoners of war, and their pay and allowances;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>p</number>  the provision 
to be made for the wives and children of prisoners of war or missing persons;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>q</number>  the procedure 
relating to the exercise of powers under section 163;
 
 

1[(qa)  the amount 
required to be prescribed under clause (b) of section 176;]
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>r</number>  any other 
matter which is to be, may be, or is required to be, prescribed under this Act.
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>184A</number> Power to 
make regulations with retrospective effect.—The power to make regulations 
conferred by this Act shall include the power to give retrospective effect, from 
a date not earlier than the date of commencement of this Act, to the regulations 
or any of them, but no retrospective effect shall be given to any regulation so 
as to prejudicially affect the interests of any person to whom such regulation 
may be applicable.]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>185</number> Regulations to be 
laid before Parliament.—Every 
regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is 
made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session for a total period 
of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in 
making any modification in the regulation or both Houses agree that the 
regulation should not be made, the regulation shall thereafter have effect only 
in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that 
any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of 
anything previously done under that regulation.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>186</number> Repealed.—[Rep. 
by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1960 (58 of 1960), sec. 2 and Sch. I.]
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>187</number> Provisions as to 
existing naval forces, appointment, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Indian Navy in existence at the commencement of this Act shall be deemed to 
be the regular naval force raised under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Indian Naval 
Reserve, the Indian Naval Volunteer Reserve and the Indian Fleet Reserve in 
existence at the commencement of this Act shall be deemed to be the Indian Naval 
Reserve Forces raised under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Officer in the Indian 
Navy or the Indian Naval Reserve Forces at the commencement of this Act shall be 
deemed to have been appointed as such under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The person holding 
office as Judge Advocate of the Fleet at the commencement of this Act shall, on 
such commencement, be deemed to have been appointed as the Judge Advocate 
General of the Navy under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Sailors in the Indian 
Navy or in the Indian Naval Reserve Forces at the commencement of this Act shall 
be deemed to have been duly enrolled as such under this Act.
 


</section></article> 

 



 <article>

1[<number>188</number> Power of 
officers of the Royal Navy.­—[Rep. by the Navy Amendment) Act, 2005 (23 
of 2005), sec. 11 (w.e.f. 
23-6-2005).]]
 
 







</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>