<act><tid>829836</tid>
<title>THE HOMOEOPATHY CENTRAL COUNCIL (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 51 OF <year>2002</year>
[ 8th December, <year>2002</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Homoeopathy Central Council Act, <year>1973</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>1209839</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>203114</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Homoeopathy Central Council (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>227015</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>403886</tid>
<number>2</number>Insertion of new Chapter II- A.- After Chapter II of the Homoeopathy 
Central Council Act, <year>1973</year> (59 of <year>1973</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the  
  principal Act), the following Chapter shall be inserted, namely:-
CHAPTER II- A

</article>



<article><tid>635353</tid>
<number> 12A</number> Permission for establishment of new medical institution, new 
course of study, etc.-
<section><tid>121584</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this  
Act or any other law for the time being in force,-

<subsection><tid>1902020</tid>
<number>a</number>no person shall establish a Homoeopathic Medical College; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1263902</tid>
<number>b</number>no Homoeopathic Medical College shall-

<subsubsection><tid>1414010</tid>
<number>i</number>open a new or higher course of study or training (including  
  post- graduate course of study or training) which would enable students 
of each course or training to qualify himself for the award of any 
recognized medical qualification; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>809103</tid>
<number>ii</number>increase its admission capacity in any course of study or 
training (Including the post- graduate course of study or training), 
except with the previous permission of the Central Government obtained 
in accordance with the provisions of this section.
Explanation 1.- For the purposes of this section," person" includes any 
University or a trust, but does not include the Central Government.

Explanation 2.- For the purposes of this section," admission capacity", 
in relation to any course of study or training (including  
  post- graduate course of study or training) in a medical institution, 
means the maximum number of students as may be decided b the Central 
Council from time to time for being admitted to such course or 
training.


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1413188</tid>
<number>2</number> (a) Every person or medical institution shall, for the purpose of 
obtaining permission under sub- section (1) submit to the Central 
Government a scheme in accordance with the provisions of clause (b) 
and the Central Government shall refer the scheme t the Central 
Council for its recommendations.

<subsection><tid>93516</tid>
<number>b</number>the scheme referred to in clause (a) shall be in such form and 
contain such particulars and be preferred in such manner and be 
accompanied with such fee as may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1759448</tid>
<number>3</number>On receipt of a scheme from the Central Government under 
sub- section (2), the Central Council may obtain such other particulars 
as may be considered necessary by it from the person or the medical 
institution concerned, and thereafter, it may,-

<subsection><tid>1818813</tid>
<number>a</number>if the scheme is defective and does not contain any necessary 
particulars, give a reasonable opportunity to the person or medical 
institution concerned for making a written representation and it shall 
be open to such person or medical institution to ectify the defects, 
if any, specified by the Central Council;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>34420</tid>
<number>b</number>consider the scheme, having regard to the factors referred to in 
sub- section (7), and submit it to the Central Government together with 
its recommendations thereon within a period not exceeding six months 
from the date of receipt of the reference fro the Central Government.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1478621</tid>
<number>4</number>The Central Government may, after considering the scheme and the 
recommendations of the Central Council under sub- section (3) and after 
obtaining, where necessary, such other particulars as may be 
considered necessary by it from the person or medical institution 
concerned, and having regard to the factors referred to in sub- section 
 (7), either approve (with such conditions, if any, as it may consider  
  necessary) or disapprove the scheme and any such approval shall 
constitute as a permission under sub- ection (1):
Provided that no scheme shall be disapproved by the Central Government 
except after giving the person or medical institution concerned a 
reasonable opportunity of being heard:

Provided further that nothing in this sub- section shall prevent any 
person or medical institution whose scheme has not been approved by 
the Central Government to submit a fresh scheme and the provisions of 
this section shall apply to such scheme, as if s ch scheme had been 
submitted for the first time under sub- section (2).


</section>

<section><tid>1710838</tid>
<number>5</number>Where, within a period of one year from the date of submission of 
the scheme to the Central Government under sub- section (2), no order 
is communicated by the Central Government to the person or medical 
institution submitting the scheme, such scheme s all be deemed to have 
been approved by the Central Government in the form in which it was 
submitted, and, accordingly, the permission of the Central Government 
required under sub- section (1) shall also be deemed to have been 
granted.

</section>

<section><tid>306628</tid>
<number>6</number>In computing the time- limit specified in sub- section (5), the time 
taken by the person or medical institution concerned in submitting the 
scheme, in furnishing any particulars called for by the Central 
Council, or by the Central Government, shall be xcluded.

</section>

<section><tid>1913523</tid>
<number>7</number>The Central Council, while making its recommendations under clause 
 (b) of sub- section (3) and the Central Government, while passing an 
order, either approving or disapproving the scheme under sub- section 
 (4), shall have due regard to the following fa tors, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1901587</tid>
<number>a</number>whether the proposed medical institution or the existing medical 
institution seeking to open a new or higher course of study or 
training, would be in a position to offer the minimum standards of 
medical education as prescribed by the Central Council nder section 
20;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1953603</tid>
<number>b</number>whether the person seeking to establish a medical institution or 
the existing medical institution seeking to open a new or higher 
course of study or training or to increase its admission capacity has 
adequate financial resources;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1446898</tid>
<number>c</number>whether necessary facilities in respect of staff, equipment, 
accommodation, training, hospital and other facilities to ensure 
proper functioning of the medical institution or conducting the new 
course of study or training or accommodating the increas d admission 
capacity have been provided or would be provided within the time- limit 
specified in the scheme;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>929398</tid>
<number>d</number>whether adequate hospital facilities, having regard to the number 
of students likely to attend such medical institution or course of 
study or training or as a result of the increased admission capacity, 
have been provided or would be provided within he time- limit specified 
in the scheme;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>73653</tid>
<number>e</number>whether any arrangement has been made or programme drawn to impart 
proper training to students likely to attend such medical institution 
or the course of study or training by the persons having the 
recognised medical qualifications;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>86110</tid>
<number>f</number>the requirement of manpower in the field of practice of 
homoeopathic medicine in the medical institution; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1690350</tid>
<number>g</number>any other factors as may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1518152</tid>
<number>8</number>Where the Central Government passes an order either approving or 
disapproving a scheme under this section, a copy of the order shall be 
communicated to the person or medical institution concerned.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1079424</tid>
<number> 12B</number> Non- recognition of medical qualifications in certain cases.-
<section><tid>1127053</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Where any medical institution is established without the previous 
permission of the Central Government in accordance with the provisions 
of section 12A, medical qualification granted to any student of such 
medical institution shall not be deemed to be a recognised medical 
qualification for the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>253284</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any medical institution opens a new or higher course of 
study or training (including a post- graduate course of study or  
  training) without the previous permission of the Central Government in 
accordance with the provisions of section 12A, medica qualification 
granted to any student of such institution on the basis of such study 
or training shall not be deemed to be recognised medical qualification 
for the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>459684</tid>
<number>3</number>Where any medical institution increases its admission capacity in 
any course of study or training without the previous permission of the 
Central Government in accordance with the provisions of section 12A, 
medical qualification granted to any student of such medical 
institution on the basis of the increase in its admission capacity 
shall not be deemed to be recognised medical qualification for the 
purposes of this Act.'.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1268148</tid>
<number> 3</number> Insertion of new section 25A.- After section 25 of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 25A. Provisional registration for practice.- If the courses of study 
to be undergone for obtaining a recognised medical qualification in 
homoeopathy include a period of training after a person has passed the 
qualifying examination and before such qualifi ation is conferred on 
him, any such person shall, on application made by him in this behalf, 
be granted provisional registration in a State Register of Homoeopathy 
by the Board concerned in order to enable him to practice homoeopathy 
in an approved insti ution for the purpose of such training and for no 
other purpose for the period aforesaid.". 4. Amendment of section 
33.- In section 33 of the principal Act, in sub- section (1), after 
clause (g), the following clauses shall be inserted, namely:-

" (ga) the form of the scheme, the particulars to be given in such 
scheme, the manner in which the scheme is to be preferred and the fee 
payable with the scheme under clause (b) of sub- section (2) of section 
12A;

<section><tid>1926592</tid>
<number>gb</number>any other factor under clause (g) of sub- section (7) of section 
12A;".
----

SUBHASH C. JAIN,

Secy. to the Govt. of India.



</section>

</article>



 </act>