<act><tid>637824</tid>
<title>THE CENTRAL SILK BOARD ACT, <year>1948</year></title>

ACT NO. 61 OF <year>1948</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 20th September, <year>1948</year>.]

An Act to provide for the development under Central control of the 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> silk industry and for that purpose to establish a Central 
Silk Board.

WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the development under 
Central control of the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> silk industry and for that purpose to 
establish a Central Silk Board;

It is hereby enacted as follows:--





<article><tid>755739</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>735052</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Central  
Silk Board Act, <year>1948</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>392696</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1616793</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Declaration as to expediency of Union control. It is hereby 
declared that it is expedient in the public interest that the Union 
should take under its control the silk industry.]


</article>



<article><tid>1287932</tid>
<number> 3</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant 
in the subject or context,--
<section><tid>982269</tid>
<number>a</number>" Board" means the Central Silk Board constituted under 
this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1052915</tid>
<number>b</number>" charkha raw silk" means raw silk reeled from silk worm 
cocoons with the help of any instrument not worked by 
power;

</section>

<section><tid>625828</tid>
<number>c</number>" filature raw silk" means raw silk reeled from silk worm 
cocoons with the help of any instrument worked by 
power;

</section>

<section><tid>1534393</tid>
<number>d</number>" power" means any form of energy which is mechanically 
transmitted and is not generated by human or animal 
agency, and includes electrical energy;

</section>

<section><tid>1912906</tid>
<number>e</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>253884</tid>
<number>f</number>" spun silk" means silk yarn spun from pierced or spoilt 
cocoons, fluff from cocoons, pieces of silk, noils, or 
other silk waste;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>68</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The Act has been extended to Dadra and Nagar Haveli by Reg. 6 of 
<year>1963</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I and to Pondicherry by Reg. 7 of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 and 
Sch. I. 
2. The word" raw" omitted by Act 31 of <year>1963</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 25- 3-  
  <year>1954</year>). 
3. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for sub- section (2). 
4. The words" except the Sate of Jammu and Kashmir" omitted by Act 
21 of <year>1970</year>, s. 2. 
5. Subs. by Act 31 of <year>1953</year>, s. 3, for the former section.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>838975</tid>
<number>g</number>" Standing Committee" means the Standing Committee of the 
Board constituted under sub- section (2) of section 6.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1665007</tid>
<number> 4</number> Constitution of the Board.
<section><tid>1919967</tid>
<number>1</number>As soon as may be after the  
commencement of this Act, the Central Government shall, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, constitute for the purposes of 
this Act a Board to be called the Central Silk Board.

</section>

<section><tid>196286</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board shall be a body corporate by the name aforesaid, 
having perpetual succession and a common seal, with power to acquire, 
hold and dispose of property, both movable and immovable, and to 
contract, and shall by the said name sue and be sued.

</section>

<section><tid>1272265</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The Board shall consist of the following members, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1372070</tid>
<number>a</number>a chairman to be appointed by the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>923887</tid>
<number>b</number>not more than three officials to be nominated by the 
Central Government:
Provided that it shall be lawful for any such official to 
depute in the prescribed circumstances another official 
to attend any meeting of the Board on his behalf;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>872746</tid>
<number>c</number>six persons to be elected by Parliament, four from the 
House of the People by the members of the House of the 
People and two from the Council of States by the 
members of the Council of States;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>544132</tid>
<number>d</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> five persons] to be nominated by the Government of 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Karnataka], one of whom shall represent the filature 
raw silk industry and two shall represent the rest of 
the sericulture industry;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>517686</tid>
<number>e</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> one person] to be nominated by the Government of 
 <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Tamil Nadu];

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>187870</tid>
<number>f</number>two persons to be nominated by the Government of West 
Bengal;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1168811</tid>
<number>g</number>one person to be nominated by each of the Governments of 
 <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Andhra Pradesh], Assam, Bihar, <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> Gujarat], <footcitenum>8</footcitenum> 
Madhya Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>645384</tid>
<number>h</number>one person to be nominated by the Government of Jammu 
and Kashmir:--
<pagefootnote><pagenum>69</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 31 of <year>1953</year>, s. 4, for sub- section (3)  (w. e. f. 25- 3-  
  <year>1954</year>). 
2. Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" four 
persons". 
3. Subs. by the Mysore State (Alteration of Name)  (Adaptation of  
  Laws on Union Subjects) Order, <year>1974</year>, for" Mysore" (w. e. f 1- 11- <year>1973</year>). 
4. Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" two 
persons". 
5. Subs. by the Madras State (Alteration of Name)  (Adaptation of  
  Laws on Union Subjects) Order, <year>1970</year>, for" Madras" (w. e. f. 14- 1- <year>1969</year>). 
6. Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>, for 
" Andhra". 
7. Subs. by the Bombay Reorganisation (Adaptation of Laws on Union  
  Subjects) Order, <year>1961</year>, for" Bombay" (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1960</year>). 
8. The words" Madhya Bharat" omitted by the Adaptation of Laws (No.  
  3) Order, <year>1956</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1188624</tid>
<number>i</number>not more than three persons to be nominated by the 
Central Government to represent the producers of raw 
silk and areas other than the States specified in 
clauses (d) to (g) inclusive;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1217970</tid>
<number>j</number>eight persons to be nominated by the Central Government, 
of whom one shall represent the spun silk industry, one 
the silk throwing and twisting industry, one the silk 
weaving industry, one labour; and two of them shall be 
experts in sericulture.]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>499815</tid>
<number>4</number>The members of the Board shall receive from its funds such 
travelling and other allowances as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1943495</tid>
<number> 5</number> Power of the Central Government in default of nominations.
<section><tid>679091</tid>
<number>1</number> 
If any Government other than the Central Government fails to make any 
nomination which it is entitled to make under sub- section (3) of 
section 4 within the time prescribed in that behalf, the Central 
Government may make the nomination itself.

</section>

<section><tid>1628512</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a member of the Board dies, resigns, is removed, ceases 
to reside in India, or becomes incapable of acting, the authority or 
body entitled to nominate the member under sub- section (3) of section 
 4 may nominate a person to fill the vacancy; and where such nomination 
is not made within the time prescribed in that behalf, the Central 
Government on its own initiative, may make the nomination itself.

</section>

<section><tid>1969906</tid>
<number>3</number>No act done by the Board shall be questioned on the ground 
merely of the existence of any vacancy in, or defect in the 
constitution of, the Board.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>404711</tid>
<number> 6</number> Vice- Chairman and Standing Committee.
<section><tid>525644</tid>
<number>1</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The Central  
Government shall appoint from among the members of the Board] a Vice- 
Chairman who shall exercise such of the powers and perform such of the 
duties of the Chairman as may be prescribed or as may be delegated to 
him by the Chairman.

</section>

<section><tid>1329852</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board may, in its discretion, constitute a Standing 
Committee for the purpose of exercising such of its powers and 
performing such of its duties as may be delegated by it, not being 
powers or duties the delegation of which is prohibited by rules made 
under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1778008</tid>
<number>3</number>The Standing Committee shall consist of the Chairman, the 
Vice- Chairman, and five others elected by the Board from among its 
members.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1415402</tid>
<number>7</number>Secretary of the Board. The Central Government shall <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> 
appoint a Secretary to the Board who shall, under the control and 
direction of the Board, exercise such powers and perform such duties 
as may be prescribed or as may be delegated to him by the Board or the 
Chairman.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>70</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 56 of <year>1952</year>, s. 3, for" The Board shall elect from 
among its members". 
2. The words" in consultation with the Board" omitted by Act 31 of 
<year>1953</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 25- 3- <year>1954</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>625488</tid>
<number> 8</number> Functions of the Board.
<section><tid>1382651</tid>
<number>1</number>It shall be the duty of the Board  
to promote the development of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> silk industry by such measures 
as it thinks fit.

</section>

<section><tid>934111</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
provision, the measures referred to therein may provide for--

<subsection><tid>1436735</tid>
<number>a</number>undertaking, assisting or encouraging scientific, 
technological and economic research;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1658040</tid>
<number>b</number>devising means for improved methods of mulberry 
cultivation rearing, developing and distributing 
healthy silk- worm seeds, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> reeling or, as the case 
may be, spinning of silk- worm cocoons and silk 
waste], improving the quality and production of raw 
silk, if necessary, by making it compulsory for all 
raw silk to be marketed only after the same has 
been tested and graded in properly equipped raw silk 
conditioning houses;
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>170453</tid>
<number>d</number>improving the marketing of raw silk;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1927812</tid>
<number>e</number>the collection of statistics from such persons as may be 
prescribed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>845361</tid>
<number>f</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> carrying out any other duties which may be vested in 
the Board under rules made under this Act.]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1202509</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall also be the duty of the Board--

<subsection><tid>1065560</tid>
<number>a</number>to advise the Central Government on all matters relating 
to the development of the raw silk industry, 
including the import and export of raw silk;
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>523680</tid>
<number>c</number>to prepare and furnish such <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> reports relating to the 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> silk industry as may be required by the Central 
Government from time to time.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1795789</tid>
<number> 9</number> Funds of the Board.
<section><tid>469858</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government shall from time  
to time make grants to the Board of such sums as the Central 
Government may consider necessary for enabling the Board to exercise 
its powers and discharge its duties under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1158323</tid>
<number>2</number>The funds of the Board shall be kept in such bank, or 
invested in such manner, as may be prescribed, and shall be expended 
by the Board
<pagefootnote><pagenum>71</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The word" raw" omitted by Act 31 of <year>1953</year>, s. 6 (w. e. f. 25- 3-  
  <year>1954</year>). 
2. Subs. by Act 21 of <year>1970</year>, s. 3, for" reeling of Silkworm cocoons". 
3. Clause (c) omitted by s. 3, ibid. 
4. Ins. by Act 31 of <year>1953</year>, s. 6 (w. e. f. 25- 3- <year>1854</year>). 
5. Clause (b) omitted by Act 21 of <year>1970</year>, s. 3. 
6. The word" other" omitted by s. 3, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


only in the performance of its functions under this Act or for meeting 
such expenses as are authorised by this Act or by rules made 
thereunder.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1581541</tid>
<number> 10</number> Imposition of cess on certain kinds of silk.
<section><tid>683452</tid>
<number>1</number>With effect  
from such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette appoint, there shall be levied and collected as a 
cess for the purposes of this Act a duty of exercise on all filature 
raw silk, and on all spun silk, reeled in the territories to which 
this Act for the time being extends at such rate as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, from time to 
time fix.

</section>

<section><tid>502900</tid>
<number>2</number>The said duty of excise shall be payable by the reelers of 
filature raw silk or spun silk and shall be paid by them to the Board 
within one month from the date of the receipt of the notice of demand 
from the Board in that behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>1079036</tid>
<number>3</number>The said duty of excise may be recovered as if it were an 
arrear of land revenue.

</section>

<section><tid>173254</tid>
<number>4</number>For the purpose of enabling the Board to assess the amount of 
the duty of excise payable under this section by the reelers of 
filature raw silk or spun silk,--

<subsection><tid>1639113</tid>
<number>a</number>the Board shall, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, fix the period in respect of which assessments 
shall be made, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>281590</tid>
<number>b</number>every reeler of filature raw silk or spun silk shall 
furnish to the Board within the prescribed time a 
return specifying the total amount of filature raw silk 
or spun silk reeled during such period.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1587639</tid>
<number>5</number>If any reeler of filature raw silk or spun silk fails to 
furnish such return within the prescribed time or furnishes a return 
which the Board has reason to believe to be incorrect or defective, 
the Board may assess the amount payable by such reeler in such manner 
as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1970737</tid>
<number>6</number>Any reeler feeling himself aggrieved by an assessment made 
under this section may, within three months of the receipt of the 
notice under sub- section (2), apply to the District Judge or such 
other civil judicial officer as may be prescribed, for the 
cancellation or modification of the assessment; and such District 
Judge or judicial officer shall, after giving the Board an opportunity 
of being heard, pass such order as he thinks proper; and such order 
shall be final.

</section>

<section><tid>867711</tid>
<number>7</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The proceeds of the duties of excise paid to the Board 
shall first be credited to the Consolidated Fund of India and the 
Central Government may, thereafter, from time to time, pay to the 
Board from and out of such proceeds such sums of money as its may 
think fit.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>72</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 31 of <year>1953</year>, s. 7 (w. e. f. 25- 3- <year>1954</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>35893</tid>
<number> 11</number> Control by the Central Government.
<section><tid>822620</tid>
<number>1</number>All acts of the Board  
shall be subject to the control of the Central Government which may 
cancel, suspend or modify as it thinks fit any action taken, or order 
passed, by the Board.

</section>

<section><tid>499128</tid>
<number>2</number>The records of the Board shall be open to inspection at all 
reasonable times by any officer authorized in this behalf by the 
Central Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1935686</tid>
<number> 12</number> Accounts of the Board.
<section><tid>826327</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board shall keep such  
accounts, and in such manner and form, as may be prescribed, in 
respect of all moneys received and expended by it.

</section>

<section><tid>14614</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The accounts of the Board shall be audited by the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General of India at such intervals as may be 
specified by him and any expenditure incurred in connection with such 
audit shall be payable by the Board to the Comptroller and Auditor- 
General.

</section>

<section><tid>998087</tid>
<number>3</number>The Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any person 
appointed by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the 
Board shall have the same rights, privileges and authority in 
connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor- General of 
India has in connection with the audit of Government accounts, and, in 
particular, shall have the right to demand the production of books, 
accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and to 
inspect any of the offices of the Board.

</section>

<section><tid>1554914</tid>
<number>4</number>The accounts of the Board as certified by the Comptroller and 
Auditor- General of India or any person appointed by him in this behalf 
together with the audit report thereon shall be forwarded annually to 
the Central Government and that Government shall cause a copy of the 
same to be laid before each House of Parliament.

</section>

<section><tid>92492</tid>
<number>5</number>A copy of the accounts of the Board as so certified together 
with the audit report thereon shall be forwarded simultaneously to the 
Board.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1741731</tid>
<number>12A</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Annual report. The Board shall prepare for every 
financial year a report of its activities and achievements during that 
year and submit the report to the Central Government in such form and 
on or before such date as may be prescribed, and that Government shall 
cause a copy of the report to be laid before each House of 
Parliament.]


</article>



<article><tid>580276</tid>
<number> 13</number> Power of Central Government to make rules.
<section><tid>667971</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> 
to carry out the purposes of this Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>73</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 21 of <year>1970</year>. s. 4, for sub- sections (2) and (3). 
2. Ins. by s. 5, ibid. 
3. For the Central Silk Board (Election) Rules, <year>1949</year>, see Gazette of 
India, <year>1949</year>, Pt. I, p. 91 and for the Central Silk Board Rules, <year>1955</year>, 
see Gazette of India, <year>1955</year>, Extraordinary, Pt. II, Sec. 3, p. 401.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>789236</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of 
the foregoing power, rules made under this section may provide for all 
or any of the following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1508862</tid>
<number>i</number>the term of office of members of the Board, the 
circumstances in which and the authority by which 
members may be removed and the filling of casual 
vacancies in the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1423347</tid>
<number>ii</number>the procedure to be followed at meetings of the Board 
and at the Standing Committee for the conduct of 
business and the number of members which shall 
form a quorum at any meeting;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>692106</tid>
<number>iii</number>the maintenance by the Board of records of business 
transacted by the Board and the submission of 
copies thereof to the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1039893</tid>
<number>iv</number>the holding of a minimum number of meetings every 
year;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1581872</tid>
<number>v</number>the power of the Board, its Chairman and Standing 
Committee with respect to the incurring of 
expenditure;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1262536</tid>
<number>vi</number>the conditions subject to which the Board may incur 
expenditure outside India;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1090891</tid>
<number>vii</number>the preparation of budget estimates of receipts and 
expenditure of the Board and the authority by 
which the estimates are to be sanctioned;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1827886</tid>
<number>viii</number>the maintenance of the accounts of income and 
expenditure of the Board <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>;

<subsubsection><tid>705684</tid>
<number>viiia</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the form of the annual report of the Board and 
the date on or before which it shall be 
submitted to the Central Government;]

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>63634</tid>
<number>ix</number>the deposit of the funds of the Board in bank and the 
investment of such funds;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>492481</tid>
<number>x</number>the re- appropriation of estimated savings from one 
budget head to any other budget head;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>979096</tid>
<number>xi</number>the conditions subject to which the Board may borrow 
funds;

<subsubsection><tid>837539</tid>
<number>xii</number>the conditions subject to which and the manner in 
which contracts may be entered into by or on 
behalf of the Board;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>989621</tid>
<number>xiii</number>the delegation to the Standing Committee or the 
Chairman or the Vice- Chairman or members or 
officers of the Board of any of the powers and 
duties of the Board under this Act;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>74</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 31 of <year>1953</year>, s. 8, for sub- section (2)  (w. e. f. 25- 3-  
  <year>1954</year>). 
2. The words" and the audit of such accounts" omitted by Act 21 of 
<year>1970</year>, s. 60. 
3. Ins. by s. 6, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1010492</tid>
<number>xiv</number>the staff which may be employed by the Board and the 
pay and allowances, leave and other conditions of 
service of officers and other employees of the 
Board;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1690301</tid>
<number>xv</number>the travelling and other allowances of members of the 
Board and of the Standing Committee;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1567159</tid>
<number>xvi</number>the purposes for which funds of the Board may be 
expended;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1000381</tid>
<number>xvii</number>the maintenance of the registers and other records of 
the Board and of its Standing Committee;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1215524</tid>
<number>xviii</number>the collection of any information or statistics in 
respect of raw silk or any product of silk;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1966337</tid>
<number>xix</number>the manner in which raw silk shall be graded and 
marketed;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1110260</tid>
<number>xx</number>any other matter which is to be or may be prescribed.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1325682</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon 
as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament while it 
is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised 
in one session or in two successive sessions, and if, before the 
expiry of the session in which it is so laid or the session 
immediately following both Houses agree in making any modification in 
the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the 
rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of 
no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification 
or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that ruel.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>502495</tid>
<number> 14</number> Penalties. <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>
<section><tid>845067</tid>
<number>1</number>] If any person-- 

<subsection><tid>117720</tid>
<number>a</number>in any return to be furnished under this Act makes any 
statement which is false and which he knows to be false 
or does not believe to be ture, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1671541</tid>
<number>b</number>obstructs any officer of the Board in the exercise of 
any power, conferred, or the discharge of any duty 
imposed, on him by or under this Act, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>506744</tid>
<number>c</number>having the control or custody of any account book or 
other record, fails to produce such book or record when 
required so to do under this Act,
he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to one year, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or 
with both.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1469099</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> If the person committing any offence specified in sub- 
section (1) is a company, every person who, at the time the offence 
was committed
<pagefootnote><pagenum>75</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 21 of <year>1970</year>, s. 6, for sub- section (3). 
2. Section 14 was renumbered as sub- section (1) of that section by 
Act 31 of <year>1953</year>, s. 9 (w. e. f. 25- 3- <year>1954</year>). 
3. Ins. by s. 9, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


was in charge of, and was responsible to, the company for the conduct 
of the business of the company as well as the company shall be deemed 
to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded 
against and punished accordingly:

Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to any punishment provided in this Act, if he 
proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or that he 
exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.


</section>

<section><tid>529334</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (2), where 
an offence under sub- section (1) has been committed by a company and 
it is proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or 
connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any 
director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such 
director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to 
be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against 
and punished accordingly.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section.--


<subsection><tid>1530497</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm 
or other association of individuals; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>60181</tid>
<number>b</number>" director" in relation to a firm means a partner in the 
firm.]



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>805762</tid>
<number>15</number>Prosecution to be with consent of Central Government. No 
prosecution for any offence punsihable under this Act shall be 
instituted except by, or with the consent of, the Central Government.


</article>



<article><tid>1892200</tid>
<number>15A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Jurisdiction of Courts. No Court inferior to that of a 
Presidency Magistrate or a Magistrate of the first class shall try any 
offence punishable under section 14.]


</article>



<article><tid>7512</tid>
<number>16</number>Bar of legal proceedings. No suit, prosecution or other legal 
proceeding shall lie against the Board, or any member or officer of 
the Board, for anything in good faith done or intended to be done 
under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>507284</tid>
<number>17</number>[ Temporary powers of the Central Government.] Rep. by the 
Central Silk Board (Amendment) Act, <year>1953</year> (31 of <year>1953</year>), s. 11.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>76</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 31 of <year>1953</year>, s. 10 (w. e. f. 25- 3- <year>1954</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>