<act><tid>17159</tid>
<title>THE TWO- MEMBER CONSTITUENCIES (ABOLITION) ACT, <year>1961</year></title>

ACT NO. 1 OF <year>1961</year>
[ 9th March, <year>1961</year>.]

An Act to provide for the abolition of two- member parliamentary 
and assembly constituencies and for the creation of single- member 
constituencies in their place.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twelfth Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-


<pagefootnote><pagenum>1</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Short title.



<article><tid>115419</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Two- Member 
Constituencies (Abolition) Act, <year>1961</year>

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Definition.

</article>



<article><tid>11819</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definition. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>1179932</tid>
<number>a</number>" Commission" means the Election Commission appointed 
by the President under article 324 of the Constitution;

</section>

<section><tid>1622090</tid>
<number>b</number>" Delimitation Order" means the Delimitation of 
Parliamentary and Assembly Constituencies Order, <year>1956</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>476826</tid>
<number>c</number>" sitting member" means a person who, immediately 
before the date of publication of a notification under clause 
 (c) of section 4 in the Official Gazette of the State 
concerned, is a member of the House of the People from that 
State or, as the case may be, of the Legislative Assembly of 
that State;

</section>

<section><tid>1596301</tid>
<number>d</number>State" includes a Union territory

</section>

<section><tid>1984491</tid>
<number>e</number>two- member constituency" means a two- member par- 
liamentary constituency specified in the First Schedule or a 
two- member assembly constituency specified in the Second 
Schedule, to the Delimitation Order.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Division of two member constituencies.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>665961</tid>
<number> 3</number> Division of two member constituencies. The Commission shall, as 
soon as may be practicable and in the manner herein provided, divide 
every two- member constituency (other than a two- member assembly  
  constituency in the State of Gujarat) into two single- member 
constituencies, delimit their extent and decide in which of them the 
seat shall be reserved' for the Scheduled-. castes or, as the case 
may. be, for the scheduled tribes, having regarded to the following 
provisions., namely:
<section><tid>1104887</tid>
<number>a</number>all the single member constituencies shall, as far as 
practicable, be geographically compact areas and in 
delimiting

<pagefootnote><pagenum>158</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

them regard shall be had to physical features, existing 
boundaries of administrative units, facilities of com- 
munication and public convenience; and


</section>

<section><tid>637405</tid>
<number>b</number>the seat shall be reserved in that single- member 
constituency which in the opinion of the Commission has the 
greater concentration of population of the scheduled castes 
or, as the case may be, of the scheduled tribes.
Explanation.- In this section-" population" means the population 
as ascertained at the census held in <year>1951</year>.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Manner of division.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>627717</tid>
<number> 4</number> Manner of Division. The Commission shall, as respects each 
State,-
<section><tid>205443</tid>
<number>a</number>formulate its proposals in regard to the matters 
mentioned in section 3 and publish them in the Gazette of 
India, in the Official Gazette of the State and in such 
newspapers in the regional languages of the State as are 
considered important by the Commission, together with a 
notice inviting objections and suggestions in relation to the 
proposals and specifying a date on or after which the 
proposals will be further considered by it;

</section>

<section><tid>1512354</tid>
<number>b</number>after considering all objections and suggestions 
which may have been received by it before the date so 
specified, determine the matters referred to in section 3; 
and

</section>

<section><tid>910749</tid>
<number>c</number>direct, by notification published in the Official 
Gazette of the State and in the Gazette of India, such 
amendments to be made in the Delimitation Order as appear to 
it to be necessary for giving effect to its decisions.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Effect of division.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1771120</tid>
<number> 5</number> Effect of division. As from the date of publication of a 
notification under clause (c) of section 4 in the Official Gazette of 
the State concerned,-
<section><tid>893948</tid>
<number>a</number>every two- member constituency in the State (other than  
  a two- member assembly constituency in the State of Gujarat) 
shall cease to exist and, in lieu thereof, there shall come 
into existence two single- member constituencies (hereinafter  
  referred to as" the corresponding new constituencies") as 
provided in the amended Delimitation Order;

</section>

<section><tid>1805034</tid>
<number>b</number>the sitting member of any two- member constituency. in 
the State elected to fill the reserved seat therein shall be 
deemed to have been elected to the House of the People or 
as the case may be, of the scheduled tribes is from that one 
of the corresponding new constituencies in which the seat 
has been reserved, and the other

<pagefootnote><pagenum>159</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

sitting member of that two- member constituency shall be 
deemed to have been elected from the other of the 
corresponding new constituencies; and


</section>

<section><tid>1002960</tid>
<number>c</number>any casual vacancy existing immediately before the said 
date in any two- member constituency in the State shall, if it 
be in the reserved seat, be deemed to be a casual vacancy in 
that one of the corresponding new constituencies in which the 
seat has been reserved, and if it be in the other seat, be 
deemed to be a casual vacancy in the other of the 
corresponding new constituencies.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>6</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Special provision for Gujarat amendment of section 19 of Act 11 of <year>1960</year>.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1421721</tid>
<number> 6</number> Special provision for Gujarat; amendment of section 19 of Act 11 
of <year>1960</year>. In section 19 of the Bombay Reorganisation Act, <year>1960</year>,-
<section><tid>688059</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (2), for clause (b), the following 
clause shall be substituted, namely:-
" (b) the assembly constituencies into which the State shall 
be divided, the extent of each of such constituencies and in 
which of them seats shall be reserved for the scheduled 
castes or for the scheduled tribes; and";


</section>

<section><tid>1825074</tid>
<number>b</number>for sub- section (3), the following sub- section shall be 
substituted, namely---
" (3) In determining the matters referred to in clauses (b) 
and (c) of sub- section (2), the Election Commission hall 
have regard to the following provisions, namely:-


</section>

<section><tid>688059</tid>
<number>a</number>all the constituencies shall be single- member 
constituencies;

</section>

<section><tid>1825074</tid>
<number>b</number>all the constituencies shall, as far as practicable, be 
geographically compact areas and in delimiting them regard 
shall be had to physical features, existing boundaries of 
administrative units, facilities of communication and public 
convenience; and

</section>

<section><tid>809597</tid>
<number>c</number>constituencies in which seats are reserved either for 
the scheduled castes or for the scheduled tribes shall as 
far as practicable, be located in the areas in which the 
population of the scheduled castes or, as the case may be, of 
the scheduled tribes is most, concentrated, but in regard to 
scheduled castes, care should be taken to distribute the 
reserved seats in different areas of the State."

<pagefootnote><pagenum>7</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Revision of the Delimitation Order.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1110420</tid>
<number> 7</number> Revision of the Delimitation Order.
<section><tid>281330</tid>
<number>1</number>After all the  
notifications have been published under clause (c) of section 4 and 
the order referred to in sub- section (5) of

<pagefootnote><pagenum>160</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

section 19 of the Bombay Reorganisation Act, <year>1960</year>, has been 
made,. the Commission shall-


<subsection><tid>1903958</tid>
<number>a</number>make such further- amendments in the Delimitation Order 
as appear to it to be necessary for bringing up- to- date the 
description of the extent of all constituencies and for 
better arranging the order in which they are set out in the 
Schedules to the Delimitation Order; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>620270</tid>
<number>b</number>send authenticated Copies of the Delimitation 
Order as so amended and revised to the Central Government and 
to each of the State Governments.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1184958</tid>
<number>2</number>As soon as may be after the revised Delimitation Order is 
received by the Central Government or a State Government, it shall be 
laid before the House of the People or, as the case may be, before the 
Legislative Assembly of the State.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>8</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Power to maintain Delimitation Order up to date.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1926901</tid>
<number> 8</number> Power to maintain Delimitation Order up to date. The Commission 
may from time to time, by notification published in the Gazette of 
India and in the Official Gazette of the State Concerned,-
<section><tid>1838603</tid>
<number>a</number>correct any printing, mistake in the revised 
Delimitation Order or any error arising therein from an 
inadvertent slip or omission, and

</section>

<section><tid>1867880</tid>
<number>b</number>where the boundaries or name of any district or any 
territorial division mentioned in a Schedule to the said 
Order are or is altered, make such amendments as appear to it 
to be necessary or expedient for bringing the Schedule up- to- 
date.


</section>

</article>



 </act>