<act><tid>676326</tid>
<title>THE MISCELLANEOUS PERSONAL LAWS (EXTENSION) ACT, <year>1959</year></title>

ACT NO. 48 OF <year>1959</year>
An Act to provide for the extension of certain personal laws to 
parts of India in which they are not now in force.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Tenth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>1143797</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>1972090</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Miscellaneous Personal Laws (Extension) Act, <year>1959</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>247452</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date 1 as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>236707</tid>
<number>2</number>Definition.- In this Act," appointed day" means the date on 
which this Act comes into force.


</article>



<article><tid>1124230</tid>
<number>3</number>Extension and amendment of certain Acts.- On and from the 
appointed day, the Acts specified in Schedule I shall stand amended in 
the manner specified therein.


</article>



<article><tid>1908453</tid>
<number> 4</number> Repeals and savings.-
<section><tid>1383764</tid>
<number>1</number>On and from the appointed day, the  
enactments specified in Schedule II and other enactments 
corresponding to the Acts specified in Schedule I shall stand repealed 
in the territories to which they respectively extended immediately 
before that day.

</section>

<section><tid>1786267</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing in sub- section (1) shall affect-

<subsection><tid>64684</tid>
<number>a</number>the previous operation of any enactment so repealed or 
anything duly done or suffered thereunder; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>843827</tid>
<number>b</number>any right, privilege, obligation or liability acquired, 
accrued or incurred under any enactment so repealed; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1965161</tid>
<number>c</number>any penalty, forfeiture or punishment incurred in 
respect of any offence committed against any enactment so 
repealed; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1910593</tid>
<number>d</number>any investigation, legal proceeding or remedy in 
respect of any such right, privilege, obligation, liability, 
penalty, forfeiture or punishment as aforesaid

<pagefootnote><pagenum>40B</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1st February, <year>1960</year>. See Notification No. S. O. 308, dated the 29th 
January, <year>1960</year>, Gazette of India, Extraordinary, <year>1960</year>, Pt, II, Sec. 
3 (ii), p. 37.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

and any such investigation, legal proceeding or remedy may be 
instituted, continued or enforced, and any such penalty, forfeiture or 
punishment may be imposed as if this Act had not been passed:

Provided that anything done or any action taken under any such 
enactment shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the 
corresponding provision of the Act now extended to the territory 
concerned and shall continue to be in force accordingly, unless and 
until superseded by anything done or any action taken under the said 
Act.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



 </act>