<act><title>


The Procedure for Holding 
    Inquiry 
    by adjudicating Officer Rules, 20041</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Procedure for Holding Inquiry by Adjudicating 
    Officer Rules, 2004. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette. 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> In these rules 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “Act” means the Electricity Act, 2003 
    (36 of 2003);  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    “adjudicating officer” means the 
    adjudicating officer appointed under sub-section (1) of section 143 of the 
    Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    “section” means a section of the Act.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Words and 
    expression used and not defined in these rules but defined in the Act shall 
    have the meanings respectively assigned to them in that Act.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Procedure 
    for holding Inquiry by adjudicating officer.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whenever the Central Commission appoints an adjudicating officer, a copy of 
    the appointment order shall be provided to the person concerned.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In holding 
    an inquiry under the Act, the adjudicating officer shall, in the first 
    instance, issue a notice to the person concerned requiring him to show cause 
    within twenty one days from the date of issue of such notice, as to why an 
    inquiry should not be held against him.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every 
    notice under sub-rule (2) shall indicate the nature of contravention alleged 
    to have been committed.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If, after 
    considering the cause, if any, shown by concerned person or where no cause 
    is shown, the adjudicating officer is of the opinion that an inquiry should 
    be held, he shall for reasons to be recorded in writing, issue a notice for 
    fixing a date for the appearance of that person either personally or through 
    an authorised representative.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    adjudicating officer shall provide an opportunity to the concerned person to 
    produce such evidence as he may consider relevant and necessary for the 
    inquiry.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> If any 
    person fails, neglects or refuses to appear before the adjudicating officer 
    as required under sub-rule (2), the adjudicating officer may proceed with 
    the inquiry in the absence of such person after recording the reasons for 
    doing so.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The 
    adjudicating officer, while holding an inquiry, shall follow as far as 
    possible the same procedure as is followed in the proceedings of the Central 
    Commission in exercise of its powers and in discharge of its functions under 
    the provisions of the Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> The 
    adjudicating officer shall complete the inquiry within sixty days from the 
    date of his appointment.  
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> Where the 
    inquiry may not be completed within the period of sixty days, the 
    adjudicating officer may, after recording reasons in writing, seek extension 
    of time from the Central Commission for a further period of sixty days.  
  
  
 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>