<act><title>


The Appellate Tribunal for Electricity Salary, 
    Allowances and other Conditions of Service of the Officers
    and Employees Rules, 20041</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Appellate Tribunal for Electricity Salary, 
    Allowances and other Conditions of Service of the Officers and Employees 
    Rules, 2004. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette. 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Application.—These rules shall 
    apply to the posts specified in column 1 of the Schedule annexed to these 
    rules.  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Number of 
    posts, classification and scale of pay.—The 
    number of posts, their classification and the scale of pay attached thereto, 
    shall be as specified in columns 2 to 4 of the said Schedule.  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Method of 
    recruitment, age limit and other qualifications etc.—The 
    method of recruitment, age limit, qualifications and other matters relating 
    to the said posts shall be as specified in columns 5 to 14 of the aforesaid 
    Schedule.  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Disqualification.—No person,—  
 <section>
<number>i</number>    who has entered into or contracted a 
    marriage with a person having a spouse living; or  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    who, having a spouse living, has 
    entered into or contracted a marriage with any person,  
 
shall be eligible for appointment to the said 
    post:
 
Provided that 
    the Central Government may, if satisfied that such marriage is permissible 
    under the personal law applicable to such person and the other party to the 
    marriage and that there are other grounds for so doing, exempt any person 
    from the operation of this rule.  
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Power to 
    relax.—Where the Central 
    Government is of the opinion that it is necessary or expedient so to do, it 
    may, by order and for reasons to be recorded in writing, relax any of the 
    provisions of these rules with respect to any class or category of persons.  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Saving.—Nothing 
    in these rules shall affect reservations, relaxation of age limit and other 
    concessions required to be provided for the Scheduled Castes, the Scheduled 
    Tribes, the ex-servicemen and other special categories of persons in 
    accordance with the orders issued by the Central Government from time to 
    time in this regard.  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Other 
    conditions of service.—Other 
    conditions of service of the officers and employees of the Appellate 
    Tribunal for Electricity, for which no specific provisions have been 
    provided, shall be regulated in accordance with such rules as are, from time 
    to time, applicable to officers and employees of the Central Government 
    Group drawing the pay and allowances in corresponding scales of pay.  
 
 
  
 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>