<act><title>


    THE EMPLOYMENT EXCHANGES (COMPULSORY NOTIFICATION OF VACANCIES) ACT, 1959</title> 
 THE EMPLOYMENT EXCHANGES (COMPULSORY NOTIFICATION OF 
VACANCIES) ACT, 1959
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title, extent and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> This Act may be 
called the Employment Exchanges (Compulsory Notification of Vacancies) Act, 
1959.
 </section><section><number>2</number> It extends to the whole of 
India 

1[***].
 </section><section><number>3</number> It shall come into force in 
a State on such date2 as 
the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint in 
this behalf for such State and different dates may be appointed for different 
States or for different areas of a State.
  








</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In this Act, unless 
    the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>   “appropriate Government” means—
 <subsection>
<number>1</number>   in relation to— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>a</number>   any establishment of any railway, major 
    port, mine or oil-field, or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>b</number>   any establishment owned, controlled or 
    managed by— 
 <subsubsubsection>
<number>i</number>   the Central Government or a department 
    of the Central Government, 
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   a company in which not less than 
    fifty-one per cent of the share capital is held by the Central Government or 
    partly by the Central Government and partly by one or more State 
    Governments, 
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
<number>iii</number>   a corporation (including a 
    co-operative society) established by or under a Central Act which is owned, 
    controlled or managed by the Central Government, 
 
the Central Government; 
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>2</number>   in relation to any other establishment, 
    the Government of the State in which that other establishment is situate; 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number>   “employee” means any person who is 
    employed in an establishment to do any work for remuneration; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   “employer” means any person who employs 
    one or more other persons to do any work in an establishment for 
    remuneration and includes any person entrusted with the supervision and 
    control of employees in such establishment; 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   “employment exchange” means any office 
    or place established and maintained by the Government for the collection and 
    furnishing of information, either by the keeping of registers or otherwise, 
    respecting— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   persons who seek to engage employees, 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   persons who seek employment, and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   vacancies to which persons seeking 
    employment may be appointed; 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>e</number>   “establishment” means— tc 
    " (e) “establishment” means—" 
 </section><section>
<number>a</number>   any office, or 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   any place where any industry, trade, 
    business or occupation is carried on; 
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   “establishment in public sector” means 
    an establishment owned, controlled or managed by— 
 <subsection>
<number>1</number>   the Government or a department of the 
    Government; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>2</number>   a Government company as defined in 
    section 617 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956); 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>3</number>   a corporation (including a co-operative 
    society) established by or under a Central, provincial or State Act, which 
    is owned, controlled or managed by the Government; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>4</number>   a local authority; 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>g</number>   “establishment in private sector” means 
    an establishment which is not an establishment in public sector and where 
    ordinarily twenty-five or more persons are employed to work for 
    remuneration; 
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>   “prescribed” means prescribed by rules 
    made under this Act; 
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>    “unskilled office work” means work done 
    in an establishment by any of the following categories of employees, 
    namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>1</number>   daftri; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>2</number>   Jemadar, orderly and peon; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>3</number>   dusting man or farash; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>4</number>   bundel or record lifter; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>5</number>   process server; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>6</number>   watchman; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>7</number>   sweeper; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>8</number>   any other employees doing any routine or 
    unskilled work which the Central Government may, by notification in the 
    Official Gazette, declare to be unskilled office work. 
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>3</number> Act not to apply in relation to certain 
      vacancies.—
<section><number>1</number> This Act shall 
      not apply in relation to vacancies— 
 <subsection><number>a</number>   in any employment 
      in agriculture (including horticulture) in any establishment in private 
      sector other than employment as agricultural or farm machinery operatives; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>   in any employment 
      in domestic service; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>   in any employment 
      the total duration of which is less than three months; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>   in any employment to do 
      unskilled office work; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>   in any employment 
      connected with the staff of Parliament. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Unless the Central Government otherwise 
      directs by notification in the Official Gazette in this behalf, this Act 
      shall not also apply in relation to— 
 <subsection><number>a</number>   vacancies which are 
      proposed to be filled through promotion or by absorption of surplus staff 
      of any branch or department of the same establishment or on the result of 
      any examination conducted or interview held by, or on the recommendation 
      of, any independent agency, such as the Union or a State Public Service 
      Commission and the like; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>   vacancies in an 
      employment which carries a remuneration of less than sixty rupees in a 
      month. 
 
 
  </subsection></section></article> 
 <article><number>4</number> Notification of vacancies 
to employment exchanges.—
<section><number>1</number> After 
the commencement of this Act in any State or area thereof, the employer in every 
establishment in public sector in that State or area shall, before filling up 
any vacancy in any employment in that establishment, notify that vacancy to such 
employment exchanges as may be prescribed.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The appropriate Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, require that from such date as may 
be specified in the notification, the employer in every establishment in private 
sector or every establishment pertaining to any class or category of 
establishments in private sector shall, before filling up any vacancy in any 
employment in that establishment, notify that vacancy to such employment 
exchanges as may be prescribed, and the employer shall thereupon comply with 
such requisition.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The manner in which the 
vacancies referred to in sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) shall be notified to 
the employment exchanges and the particulars of employments in which such 
vacancies have occurred or are about to occur shall be such as may be 
prescribed.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Nothing in sub-sections (1) 
and (2) shall be deemed to impose any obligation upon any employer to recruit 
any person through the employment exchange to fill any vacancy merely because 
that vacancy has been notified under any of those sub-sections.



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Employers to furnish information and returns in prescribed form. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> After the commencement of this Act in any State or area thereof, the employer in every establishment in public sector in that State or area shall furnish such information or return as may be prescribed in relation to vacancies that have occurred or are about to occur in that establishment, to such employment exchanges as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The appropriate Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, require that from such date as may be specified in the notification, the employer in every establishment in private sector or every establishment pertaining to any class or category of establishments in private sector shall furnish such information or return as may be prescribed in relation to vacancies that have occurred or are about to occur in that establishment to such employment exchanges as may be prescribed, and the employer shall thereupon comply with such requisition. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The form in which, and the intervals of time at which, such information or return shall be furnished and the particulars which they shall contain shall be such as may be prescribed. 
  
</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>6</number> Right of access to records or 
      documents.—Such officer of 
      Government as may be prescribed in this behalf, or any person authorised 
      by him in writing, shall have access to any relevant record or document in 
      the possession of any employer required to furnish any information or 
      returns under section 5 and may enter at any reasonable time any premises 
      where he believes such record or document to be and inspect or take copies 
      of relevant records or documents or ask any question necessary for 
      obtaining any information required under that section. 
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Penalties.—
<section><number>1</number> If any employer 
    fails to notify to the employment exchanges prescribed for the purpose any 
    vacancy in contravention of sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) of section 4, 
    he shall be punishable for the first offence with fine which may extend to 
    five hundred rupees and for every subsequent offence with fine which may 
    extend to one thousand rupees. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any 
    person— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   required to furnish any information or 
    return— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   refuses or neglects to furnish such 
    information or return, or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   furnishes or causes to be furnished any 
    information or return which he knows to be false, or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>   refuses to answer, or gives a false 
    answer to, any question necessary for obtaining any information required to 
    be furnished under section 5; or 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   impedes the right of access to relevant 
    records or documents or the right of entry conferred by section 6; 
 
he shall be punishable for the first offence 
    with fine which may extend to two hundred and fifty rupees and for every 
    subsequent offence with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees. 
 

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Cognizance of offences.—No 
    prosecution for an offence under this Act shall be instituted except by, or 
    with the sanction of, such officer of Government as may be prescribed in 
    this behalf or any person authorised by that officer in writing. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Protection of action taken in good faith.—No 
    suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any person for 
    anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette and 
    subject to the condition of previous publication, make rules1 for 
    carrying out the purposes of this Act.—(1) 
    The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette and 
    subject to the condition of previous publication, make rules1 for 
    carrying out the purposes of this Act." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide, for all or any of the following matters, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the employment exchange or exchanges to 
    which, the form and manner in which, and the time within which, vacancies 
    shall be notified, and the particulars of employments in which such 
    vacancies have occurred or are about to occur; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   the form and manner in which, and the 
    intervals at which, information and returns required under section 5 shall 
    be furnished, and the particulars which they shall contain; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   the officers by whom and the manner in 
    which the right of access to documents and the right of entry conferred by 
    section 6 may be exercised; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   any other matter which is to be, or may 
    be, prescribed under this Act. 
 


    2[(3) Every rule made 
    under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before 
    each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of 
    thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
    successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
    following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses 
    agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the 
    rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
    modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
    such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of 
    anything previously done under that rule.] 
  





 



</subsection></section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>