<act><tid>1315964</tid>
<title>THE DESTRUCTION OF RECORDS ACT, <year>1917</year></title>

ACT NO. 5 OF <year>1917</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 28th February, <year>1917</year>.]

An Act to consolidate and amend the law providing for the destruction 
or other disposal of certain documents in the possession or custody of 
Courts and Revenue and other public officers.

WHEREAS it is expedient to consolidate and amend the law 
providing for the destruction or other disposal of certain documents 
in the possession or custody of Courts and Revenue and other public 
officers; It is hereby enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>207571</tid>
<number>1</number>Short Title. Extent. This Act may be called the Destruction of 
Records Act, <year>1917</year>.
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> It extends to the whole of India except <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the territories 
which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in 
Part B States].]



</article>



<article><tid>74363</tid>
<number>2</number>[ Definitions.] Rep. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1706226</tid>
<number> 3</number> <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Power to certain authorities to make rules for disposal of 
documents.
<section><tid>1362593</tid>
<number>1</number>The authorities hereinafter specified may, from time to  
time, make rules for the disposal, by destruction or otherwise, such 
documents as are, in the opinion of the authority making the rules, 
not of sufficient public value to justify their preservation.

</section>

<section><tid>1745069</tid>
<number>2</number>The authorities shall be--

<subsection><tid>902082</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of documents in the possession or custody 
of a High Court or of the Courts of civil or criminal 
jurisdiction subordinate thereto,-- the High Court;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>465990</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of documents in the possession or custody 
of Revenue Courts and officers,-- the Chief Controlling 
Revenue- authority <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>917874</tid>
<number>c</number>in the case of documents in the possession or custody 
of any other public officer,--

<subsubsection><tid>472031</tid>
<number>i</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum> if the documents relate to purposes of a 
State, the State Government or any officer specially 
authorized in that behalf by that Government;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>42</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Rep in Kerala by Kerala Act 2 of <year>1962</year>. Extended to the 
Transferred territoris of Andhra Pradesh by Andhra Act 3 of <year>1962</year>. 
Extended to Goa, Daman and Diu with modifications, by Reg. 12 of 
<year>1962</year>, s. 3 and Sch. Extended to Laccadive, Minicoy and Amindivi 
Islands (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1967</year>): vide Reg. 8 of <year>1965</year>, s. 3 and Sch. 
Extended to the Union territory of Pondicherry by Act 26 of <year>1968</year>, S. 
3 and Schedule.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>. 
3. Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order <year>1956</year>, for" Part B 
States". 
4. S. 3 has been amended in its application to the U. P. by the U. 
P. Board of Revenue Act, <year>1922</year> (U. P. 12 of <year>1922</year>), s. 2 and Sch. 
5. For definition of Chief Controlling Revenue- authority, formerly 
included in s. 2, see now the General Clauses Act, <year>1897</year> (10 of <year>1897</year>), 
s. 3 (10). 
6. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for" the L. G., or any officer specially 
authorized in that behalf by the L. G.".



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>409530</tid>
<number>ii</number>in any other case, the Central Government or 
an officer specially authorized in that behalf by that 
Government.]

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>288186</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Rules made under this section by any High Court or by a 
Chief Controlling Revenue- authority <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or by an officer specially 
authorized in that behalf by any State Government shall be subject to 
the previous approval of the State Government; and rules made by an 
officer specially authorized in that behalf by the Central Government 
shall be subject to the previous approval of the Central Government.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1879094</tid>
<number>4</number>Validation of former rules for disposal of documents. All 
rules and orders directing or authorizing the destruction or other 
disposal of documents in the possession or custody of any public 
officer, heretofore made by a State Government, or with the approval 
of the State Government by any authority not empowered to make such 
rules under the Destruction of Records Act, <year>1879</year> (3 of <year>1879</year>), shall be 
deemed to have had the force of law from the date on which they were 
made, and all such rules and orders now in force shall continue to 
have the force of law until they are superseded by rules made under 
this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>87040</tid>
<number>5</number>Saving of certain documents. Nothing in this Act shall be 
deemed to authorize the destruction of any document which, under the 
provisions of any law for the time being in force, is to be kept and 
maintained.


</article>



<article><tid>1863481</tid>
<number>6</number>[ Repeals.] Rep. by the Repealing Act, <year>1927</year> (12 of <year>1927</year>).
</article>



 </act>