<act><tid>809486</tid>
<title>THE NORTH- WESTERN PROVINCES AND OUDH ACT, <year>1890</year></title>

ACT NO. 20 OF <year>1890</year>
[ 16th October, <year>1890</year>.]

An Act to provide for the better administration of the North- 
Western Provinces and Oudh and to amend certain enactments in force 
in those Provinces and in Oudh.

WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the better administration 
of the territories respectively administered by the Lieutenant- 
Governor of the North- Western Provinces and the Chief Commissioner of 
Oudh, and for that purpose to amend certain enactments which are in 
force in the said Provinces and in Oudh; It is hereby enacted as 
follows:--





<article><tid>602822</tid>
<number>1</number>Title. This Act may be called the North- Western Provinces and 
Oudh Act, <year>1890</year>.
PART

THE NORTH- WESTERN PROVINCES

PART I

THE NORTH- WESTERN PROVINCES

</article>



<article><tid>1315990</tid>
<number>2</number>This Part shall come into force on such day <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the said 
Lieutenant- Governor may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
direct.
 3 an

Commencement of Part I.

 3 and 4. Commencement of Part I.[ Amendment of Act 19 of <year>1873</year>.] 
Rep. by the United Provinces Land- revenue Act, <year>1901</year> (U. P. Act 3 of  
  <year>1901</year>).

And whereas it has been determined to annex the Jhansi Division, 
comprising the districts of Jhansi, Jalaun and Lalatpur, to the 
Allahabad Division;

And whereas the said Jhansi Division is a Schedule District under 
the Scheduled Districts Act, <year>1874</year> (14 of <year>1874</year>); <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>

And whereas it is expedient that the law in force in the same 
division should, on such annexation, be the same as the law in force 
in the temporarily- settled districts comprised in the Allahabad 
Division, and that the said division should cease to be a Scheduled 
District;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>78</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The 1st April, <year>1891</year>, see North- Western Provinces and Oudh 
Gazette, <year>1891</year>, Pt. I, p. 130. 
2. Since rep. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


It is hereby enacted as follows:--



</article>



<article><tid>1004001</tid>
<number> 5</number> Laws in force in certain districts of the Allahabad Division 
to apply to Jhansi.
<section><tid>320664</tid>
<number>1</number>All enactments which shall on the day <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> when  
this Part comes into force be in force in the said temporarily- settled 
districts and not in the said Jhansi Division shall be deemed to come 
into force in that Division on and from the said day.

</section>

<section><tid>1190348</tid>
<number>2</number>Except the Jhansi Encumbered Estates Act, <year>1882</year> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> (16 of  
  <year>1882</year>), and the Jhansi and Morar Act, <year>1886</year> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>, (17 of <year>1886</year>), all 
enactments which shall on the said day <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> be in force in the said 
division and not in the said temporarily- settled districts, including 
the Jhansi Courts Act, <year>1867</year> (18 of <year>1867</year>), and Act No. 27 of <year>1867</year>, 
shall be deemed to be repealed on and from the said day <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in the said 
division.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1066693</tid>
<number>6</number>[ Amendment of Act 16 of <year>1882</year>.] Rep. by the Bundelkhand 
Encumbered Estates Act, <year>1903</year> (U. P. Act 1 of <year>1903</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>231685</tid>
<number>7</number>Discharge of functions assigned to Deputy Commissioner and 
Commissioner by Act 17 of <year>1886</year>. The functions assigned to the Deputy 
Commissioner and the Commissioner by the Jhansi and Morar Act, <year>1886</year>, 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> (17 of <year>1886</year>), shall be discharged by the District Judge and the 
High Court, respectively, and references to Courts in the Jhansi 
district subordinate to the Commissioner shall be deemed to apply to 
the Civil Courts established in that district under the Bengal, 
 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> North- Western Provinces and Assam Civil Courts Act, <year>1887</year> (12 of  
  <year>1887</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>53426</tid>
<number> 8</number> Jhansi Division to cease to be a Scheduled District.
<section><tid>1355194</tid>
<number>1</number>On  
and from the said day <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the said division shall cease to be a 
Scheduled District <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1555336</tid>
<number> 9</number> Application of Act 12 of <year>1887</year> to Jhansi, and disposal of 
pending cases. <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1777206</tid>
<number>2</number>All cases or proceedings pending in any Civil Court in the 
said division on the said day <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> shall be disposed of as follows:--

<subsection><tid>911020</tid>
<number>a</number>if pending in the Court of a Tahsildar or of an 
Assistant Commissioner of the second class-- by the 
Munsif;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>79</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>That is, the 1st April, <year>1891</year>. 
2. Since rep. by the Bundelkhand Encumbered Estates Act, <year>1903</year> (U. P.  
  1 of <year>1903</year>). 
3. Rep. by Act 42 of <year>1953</year>. 
4." Agra" has been subs. for" North- Western Provinces" by Act 16 of 
<year>1911</year>. 
5. The second clause of sub- section (1), and sub- section (2) were 
rep. by Act 1 of <year>1938</year>, s. 2 and Sch. 
6. Sub- section (1) rep., ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1239218</tid>
<number>b</number>if pending in the Court of an Assistant Commissioner of 
the first class- by the Subordinate Judge;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1830110</tid>
<number>c</number>if pending in the Court of a Deputy Commissioner-- by the 
District Judge;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1548690</tid>
<number>d</number>if pending in the Court of the Commissioner-- by the 
District Judge, unless the case pending is an appeal 
from a decree or order of the Deputy Commissioner, in 
which case the appeal shall be disposed of by the High 
Court.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1791602</tid>
<number>3</number>For the purposes of sections 20 to 22, both inclusive, of the 
Bengal, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> North- Western Provinces and Assam Civil Courts Act, <year>1887</year> 
 (12 of <year>1887</year>), all decrees and orders passed by Civil Courts in the 
said division and not appealed against before the said day <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> shall be 
deemed--

<subsection><tid>1591776</tid>
<number>a</number>if passed by the Court of a Tahsildar or an Assistant 
Commissioner of the second class-- to have been passed 
by a Munsif;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>29546</tid>
<number>b</number>if passed by the Court of an Assistant Commissioner of 
the first class-- to have been passed by a Subordinate 
Judge;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1095860</tid>
<number>c</number>if passed by the Court of a Deputy Commissioner or the 
Commissioner-- to have been passed by a District Judge.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1906442</tid>
<number>4</number>Where any Civil Court ceases by reason of the passing of this 
Act to have jurisdiction with respect to any case, any proceeding in 
relation to that case which, if that Court had not ceased to have 
jurisdiction, might have been had therein, may be had in the Court to 
which the business of the former Court is transferred by sub- section 
 (2); but this sub- section shall not apply to cases for which provision 
is made in section 623 or section 649 of the Code of Civil Procedure. 
 (14 of <year>1882</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>1189811</tid>
<number>5</number>In the case of appeals from the decrees and orders mentioned 
in sub- section (3) the period of limitation shall be calculated in 
accordance with the provisions of section 15 of the Jhansi Courts Act, 
 <year>1867</year> <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> (18 of <year>1867</year>), as though this Act had not been passed.
PART

OUDH

PART II

OUDH




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1392627</tid>
<number>10</number>Commencement of Part II. This Part shall come into force on 
such day <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> as the Chief Commissioner of Oudh may, by notification in 
the Official Gazette, direct.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>80</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>" Agra" has been subs. for" North- Western Provinces" by Act 16 of 
<year>1911</year>. 
2. That is, the 1st April, <year>1891</year>. 
3. See now the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>). 
4. Act 18 of <year>1867</year> rep. by s. 5 (2) of this Act. 
5.  1st January, <year>1891</year>, see the North- Western Provinces and Oudh 
Gazette, <year>1890</year>, Pt. I, p. 661.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>325042</tid>
<number> 11</number> Board of Revenue of the North- Western Provinces to be the 
Board of Revenue- of, and Chief Revenue- authority in, Oudh.
<section><tid>1599571</tid>
<number>1</number>On and  
from the day on which this Part comes into force the Board of Revenue 
constituted under the North- Western Provinces Land- revenue Act, <year>1873</year>, 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> (19 of <year>1873</year>.) shall be deemed to be also the Board of Revenue for 
the territories administered by the Chief Commissioner of Oudh, and 
shall be known and designated as the Board of Revenue of the North- 
Western Provinces and Oudh. <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>

</section>

<section><tid>1538954</tid>
<number>2</number>All references made in any enactment as amended by this Part 
to the Board of Revenue shall be deemed, so far as they relate to 
Oudh, to refer to the said Board.

</section>

<section><tid>1611003</tid>
<number>3</number>In any enactment for the time being in force in the 
territories administered by the Chief Commissioner of Oudh, in which 
the expression" Chief Revenue- authority" or" Chief Controlling 
Revenue- authority" is used, the expression shall, subject to the 
provisions of any enactment passed after the said day, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> be 
construed, so far as the said territories are concerned, as referring 
to the Board of Revenue of the North- Western Provinces and Oudh. <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1754056</tid>
<number>54</number>Pending appeals. All appeals pending when this Part comes 
into force <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> from decrees or orders passed under the same Act shall 
be disposed of as if this Act had not been passed:
<pagefootnote><pagenum>81</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Since rep. by the U. P. Land- revenue Act, <year>1901</year> (U. P. 3 of <year>1901</year>), 
s. 2, but not so as to affect anything done under Act 19 of <year>1873</year>, see 
s. 3. 
2. Now the Board of Revenue of the U. P. 
3.  1st January, <year>1891</year>, see the North- Western Provinces and Oudh 
Gazette <year>1890</year>, Pt. I, p. 661. 
4. These sections amended certain Central Acts:--

Ss. 12 to 34..... Act 17 of <year>1876</year>.

S. 35....... Act 18 of <year>1876</year> and 14 of <year>1878</year>.

Ss. 36 and 37..... Act 4 of <year>1878</year>.

S. 38....... Act 3 of <year>1879</year>.

Ss. 39 to 42..... Act 13 of <year>1879</year>.

S. 43....... Act 22 of <year>1881</year>.

Ss. 44 to 53..... Act 22 of <year>1886</year>.

They have been repealed as follows:-- 
Ss. 12 to 16, 18 to 27 and 32 to 34 by U. P. Act 3 of <year>1901</year>; 
Ss. 17, 35, 48 and 50 by Central Act 12 of <year>1891</year>; 
Ss. 28 to 31 by U. P. Act 3 of <year>1899</year>; 
Ss. 36 and 37 by U. P. Act 5 of <year>1894</year>; 
Ss. 39 to 42 by U. P. Act 4 of <year>1925</year>; 
Ss. 38, 44 to 47, 49 and 51 to 53 by Central Act 1 of <year>1938</year>; and 
S. 43 by Central Act 12 of <year>1891</year>. 
5 That is, the 1st January, <year>1891</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Provided that the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State Government] may, by order, transfer to 
the District Judge any appeals then pending before the Commissioner or 
Collector in cases in which the appeal will, under the Oudh Rent Act, 
<year>1886</year>, (22 of <year>1886</year>.) as amended by this Part, lie to the District 
Judge.

PART

THE NORTH- WESTERN PROVINCES AND OUDH

PART III

THE NORTH- WESTERN PROVINCES AND OUDH



</article>



<article><tid>745898</tid>
<number>62</number>Commencement of Part III. This part shall come into force on 
such day <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> as the Lieutenant- Governor of the North- Western Provinces 
and Chief Commissioner of Oudh may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, direct.


</article>



<article><tid>313790</tid>
<number> 63</number> Place where the Board may sit.
<section><tid>113189</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything  
 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> in section 128 of the Oudh Rent Act, <year>1886</year> (22 of <year>1886</year>), the Board 
of Revenue of the North- Western Provinces and Oudh shall, for the 
disposal of cases under those Acts, sit in such place or places in the 
North- Western Provinces or Oudh as <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> the State Government] may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> appoint in respect to cases 
under either of those Acts.

</section>

<section><tid>886641</tid>
<number>2</number>For the disposal of cases other than those referred to in 
sub- section (1) the said Board may, subject to the orders of <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> the 
State Government], sit in any place in the North- Western Provinces or 
Oudh that the Board thinks fit.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1108045</tid>
<number>64</number>[ Amendment of section 4, Act 19 of <year>1873</year>.] Rep. by the United 
Provinces Land- revenue Act, <year>1901</year> (U. P. Act 3 of <year>1901</year>).
<pagefootnote><pagenum>82</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for" Chief- Commissioner". 
2. Ss. 55 to 60 amended Act 22 of <year>1886</year> and s. 61 amended Act 9 of 
<year>1881</year>. Ss. 55 and 57 to 61 were rep. by Act 1 of <year>1938</year> and s. 56 by Act 
12 of <year>1891</year>. 
3.  1st January, <year>1891</year>, see the North- Western Provinces and Oudh 
Gazette, <year>1890</year>, Pt. I, p. 661. 
4. Section 63, so far as it relates to Act 12 of <year>1881</year>, that is the 
words" in s. 152 of the North- Western Provinces Rent Act, <year>1881</year>, or" 
were rep. by the Agra Tenancy Act, <year>1901</year> (U. P. 2 of <year>1901</year>). 
5. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for" the said Lieutenant- Governor and 
Chief Commissioner". 
6. For notification declaring that the Board of Revenue may sit at 
the head- quarters of any district of the United Provinces, see U. P. 
Local Rules and Orders.

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>