<act><title>THE MEDICAL COUNCIL OF INDIA (CRITERIA FOR IDENTIFICATION OF STUDENTS ADMITTED IN EXCESS OF ADMISSION CAPACITY OF MEDICAL COLLEGES) REGULATIONS, 19971 </title> 

  
 <article> <title><number>1</number> Short tile and commencement. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> These regulations may be called the Medical Council of India (Criteria for Identification of Students Admitted in Excess of Admission Capacity of Medical Colleges) Regulations, 1997. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> These regulations shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette. 
  


</section></article> 

  
 <article> <title><number>2</number> Application. </title>-These regulations shall apply to all medical colleges/institutions/universities conducting undergraduate/postgraduate medical courses (hereinafter referred to as the medical college). 
  


</article> 

  
 <article> <title><number>3</number> Definitions. </title>-Under these regulations unless the context otherwise requires:- 
 
 <section><number>a</number> "Act" means the Indian Medical Council Act, 1956 (102 of 1956) as amended from time to time. 
 </section><section><number>b</number> "Admission capacity" has the same meaning as referred to in Explanation 2 of Section 10A of the Act. 
 </section><section><number>c</number> "Competent Authority" means the Central Government or State Government or medical college or any other authority as may be designated by the Central Government or the State Government, as the case may be, to allot students for admission to various medical colleges in a State or Union Territory . Where there is no designated authority as defined in the Medical College conducting undergraduate or postgraduate medical course shall be deemed to be the competent authority for that medical college. 
 </section><section><number>d</number> All other words and expressions shall have the same meaning as defined in the Act. 
</section>


</article> 

  
 <article> <title><number>4</number> Sanctioned intake capacity in medical college. </title>-The Council shall every year, prior to the start of undergraduate/postgraduate academic medical course, intimate the medical colleges and State/Union Territory Governments, the sanctioned intake capacity of the students for undergraduate/postgraduate courses in medical colleges. 
  


</article> 

  
 <article> <title><number>5</number> Medical Colleges to furnish year-wise list of students. </title>-All medical colleges conducting undergraduate/postgraduate course shall, within 3 months of publication of these regulations in the official gazette, furnish year-wise lists of students admitted during the academic sessions commencing in the year 1992 till the year in which these regulations are published for Bachelor of Medicine and Bachelor of Surgery and postgraduate course (for each course separately) to the Council. 
  


</article> 

  
 <article> <title><number>6</number> Furnishing of list by competent Authority. </title>-The competent authority shall furnish lists of students admitted during each academic year for Bachelor of Medicine and Bachelor of Surgery and postgraduate courses to the Council and State Medical Council and the affiliating university within one month of the closure of admission or 31st October of that year, whichever is earlier. 
  


</article> 

  
 <article> <title><number>7</number> List of students to be furnished to the Council. </title>-A list of students to be furnished under these regulations to the Council shall be prepared by a competent authority in order of merit on the basis of which admissions have been made. The list shall be supported by affidavit of the Dean/Principal of a Medical College stating the sanctioned admission capacity of that medical college and that no admission has been made in excess of the admission capacity. The names of students admitted in a medical college through all India Entrance Examination/Central Pool Quota/Mandatory Reservation for Scheduled Castes/Scheduled Tribes, shall find mention in the list. 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>