<act><title>THE INSURANCE REGULATORY AND DEVELOPMENT AUTHORITY (INVESTMENT) REGULATIONS, 20001</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement </title>.-
<section><number>1</number> <title></title>These regulations may be called 
the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority (Investment) Regulations, 2000. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>-In these regulations, unless the context otherwise requires,- <title></title>
 
 <section><number>a</number> 'Act' means the Insurance Act, 1938 (4 of 1938); 
 </section><section><number>b</number> 'accretion of funds' means investment income, gains on sale/redemption of existing investment and operating surplus; 
 </section><section><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>ba</number> 'Investment Assets' mean all investments made out of- 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> in the case of a Life Insurer- 
 
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> shareholders funds representing solvency margin, non-unit reserves of unit linked insurance business, participating and non-participating funds of policyholders, 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> policyholders funds of pension and general annuity fund at their carrying value, and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>c</number> policyholders unit reserves of unit linked insurance business at their market value, and 
</subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> in the case of a General Insurer- 
 
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> shareholder funds representing solvency margin and policyholders funds at their carrying value as shown in its balance sheet drawn as per the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority (Preparation of Financial Statements and Auditors' Report of Insurance Companies) Regulations, 2000, but excluding items under the head 'Miscellaneous Expenditure'.] 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>c</number> 'Authority' means the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority established under sub-section (1) of section 3 of the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority Act, 1999 (41 of 1999); 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>ca</number> 'Group' means,- 
 
 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>cb</number> 'Financial Derivatives' means a derivative as defined under clause (aa) of section 2 of the Securities Contracts (Regulation) Act, 1956 (42 of 1956), and includes a contract which derives its value from interest rates of underlying debt securities and such other derivative contracts as may be stipulated by the Authority, from time to time.] 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>cc</number> Money Market Instruments.-Money Market Instruments shall comprise of short term funds with maturity not more than one year comprising of the following instruments: 
</subsubsection>
</subsection><subsection><number>i</number> two or more individuals, associations of individuals, firms, trusts, trustees or bodies corporate or any combination thereof, which exercises, or is established to be in a position to exercise, control, directly, or indirectly, over any body corporate, firm or trust, or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> Associated persons, as may be stipulated by the Authority, from time to time, by issuance of guidelines under these regulations.] 
</subsection>
</section>
 <section><number>1</number> Certificate of deposit rated by a credit rating agency registered under SEBI (Credit Rating Agencies) Regulations, 1999. 
 </section></article><article><number>2</number> Commercial paper rated by a credit rating agency registered under SEBI (Credit Rating Agencies) Regulations, 1999. 
 </article><article><number>3</number> Repos, Reverse Repo. 
 </article><article><number>4</number> Treasury Bills. 
 </article><article><number>5</number> Call, Notice, Term Money. 
 </article><article><number>6</number> CBLO as per Schedules I and II of these regulations. 
 </article><article><number>7</number> Any other instrument as may be prescribed by the Authority.] 
 <section><number>d</number> 'Principal Officer' means any person connected with the management of an insurer or any other person upon whom the Authority has served notice of its intention of treating him as the principal officer thereof; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> all words and expressions used herein and not defined but defined in the Insurance Act, 1938 (4 of 1938), or in the Insurance Regulatory and Development Act, 1999 (41 of 1999), or in any Rules or Regulations made thereunder, shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in those Acts or Rules or Regulations. 





</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Power to call for additional information. </title>-The Authority may, by general or special order, require from the insurers such other information in such manner, intervals and time limit as may be specified therein. 



</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>8</number> Duty to report extraordinary events affecting the investment portfolio. </title>-Every insurer shall report to the Authority forthwith, the effect or the probable effect of any event coming to his knowledge, which could have material adverse impact on the investment portfolio and consequently on the security of policyholder benefits or expectations.] 



</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>9</number> Organizational structure for Investment Management. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> Every insurer shall constitute an Investment Committee which shall consist of a minimum of two non-executive directors of the Insurer, the Chief Executive Officer, Chief of Finance, Chief of Investment division, and wherever an appointed actuary is employed, the Appointed Actuary. The decisions taken by the Investment Committee shall be recorded and be open to inspection by the officers of the Authority. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every insurer shall draw up, annually an Investment Policy (fund-wise investment policy in the case of unit linked insurance business) and place the same before its Board of Directors for its approval. While framing such policy, the Board shall ensure compliance with the following:- 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> Issues relating to liquidity, prudential norms, exposure limits, stop loss limits including securities trading, management of all investment risks, management of assets liabilities scope of internal or concurrent audit of investments and investment statistics, and all other internal controls of investment operations, the provisions of the Insurance Act, 1938 and Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority (Investment) Regulations, 2000, guidelines and circulars made there under. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> Ensuring an adequate return on Policyholders and shareholders funds consistent with the protection, safety and liquidity of such fund(s); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> the funds of the insurer shall be invested and continued to be invested in equity shares, equity related instruments and debt instruments rated as per Note below regulations 3 and 4 by a credit rating agency, registered under SEBI (Credit Rating Agencies) Regulations, 1999. The Board shall lay down clear norms for investing in 'Other Investments' as specified under sections 27A(2) and 27B(3) of the Insurance Act, 1938 by the investment committee, taking into account the safety and liquidity of the policyholders' funds and protection of their interest. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> The investment policy as approved by the Board shall be implemented by the investment committee, which shall keep the Board information on a quarterly basis about its activities and fund(s) performance. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Board shall review its investment policy and its implementation on an half-yearly basis or at such short intervals as it may decide and make such modifications to investment policy as is necessary to bring it in line with the investment provisions laid down in the Act and Regulations made there under, keeping in mind protection of policyholders' interest and pattern of investment laid down in these regulations or in terms of the agreement entered into with the policyholders in the case of unit linked insurance business. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The details of the Investment Policy or its review as periodically decided by the Board shall be made available to the internal or concurrent auditor. The auditor shall comment on such review and its impact on the investment operations, systems and processes in their report to be placed before the Board Audit Committee. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> In order to ensure proper internal control of investment functions and operations the insurer shall clearly segregate the functions and operations of front, mid and back office. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> The Authority may call for further information from time to time from the insurer as it deems necessary and in the interest of policyholders and issue such directions to the insurers as it thinks fit.] 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<title><number>10</number> Miscellaneous. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> Valuation of Assets and Accounting of Investments shall be as per the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority (Preparation of Financial Statements and Auditor's Report of Insurance Companies) Regulations, 2000. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Authority may, by any general or special order, modify or change the application of regulations (3), (4), (5) and (6) to any insurer either on its own or on an application made to it.] 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<title><number>11</number> Dealing in Financial Derivatives. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> Every Insurer carrying on the business of life insurance or general insurance may deal in financial derivatives only to the extent permitted and in accordance with the guidelines issued by the Authority in this regard from time to time. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> Any margin or unamortized premium paid by any insurer in connection with the financial derivatives to the extent they are reflected as asset position in the balance sheet of the insurer in accordance with the guidelines issued by the Authority, shall be treated as "Approved Investment" under Schedule I and Schedule II to these regulations, only to the extent the derivatives position constitutes a hedge for the underlying investment or portfolio which itself is treated as an approved investments under these regulations. All other margin or unamortized premium paid, to the extent reflected in the balance sheet of the insurer in accordance with the guidelines issued by the Authority in this regard from time to time, shall be treated as "Other Investments".]] 




</section></article><form>
 

THE INSURANCE REGULATORY AND DEVELOPMENT AUTHORITY (INVESTMENT) REGULATIONS, 20001
 

 
 

2[ Schedule I 
 

( See regulation 3) 
 

List of Approved Investments for Life Business 
 

'Approved Investments' for the purposes of section 27A of the Act shall be as follows:- 
 

(a) All investments specified in section 27A of the Act except- 
 

(i) clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 27A of the Act; 
 

(ii) first mortgages on immovable property situated in another country as stated in clause (m) of sub-section (1) of section 27A of the Act; 
 

(iii) immovable property situated in another country as stated in clause (n) of sub-section (1) of section 27A of the Act. 
 

(b) In addition the following investments shall be deemed as approved investments by the Authority under the powers vested in it vide clause (s) of sub-section (1) of section 27A of the Act. 
 

(i) All loans secured as required under Insurance Act, 1938, secured debentures, secured bonds, other secured debt instruments rated as per Note appended to regulations 3 and 4. Equity shares and preference shares and debt instruments issued by all India Financial Institutions recognised as such by Reserve Bank of India - investments to be made in terms of investment policy guidelines, benchmarks and exposure norms/limits approved by the Board of Directors of the insurer. 
 

(ii) Bonds or debentures issued by companies rated not less than AA or its equivalent and P1 or equivalent ratings for short-term bonds, debentures, certificate of deposits and commercial papers by a credit rating agency, registered under SEBI (Credit Rating Agencies) Regulations, 1999 would be considered as 'Approved Investments'. 
 

(iii) Subject to norms/limits approved by the Board of Directors of the insurers deposits (including fixed deposits as per section 27A(9) of Insurance Act, 1938) with banks ( e.g . in current account, call deposits, notice deposits, certificate of deposits etc.) included for the time being in the Second Schedule to Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934) and deposits with primary dealers duly recognised by Reserve Bank of India as such. 
 

(iv) Collateralized Borrowing and Lending Obligations (CBLO) created by the Clearing Corporation of India Limited and recognized by the Reserve Bank of India and exposure to Gilt, G Sec and liquid mutual fund forming part of Approved Investments as per Mutual Fund Guidelines issued under these regulations and money market instrument/investment. 
 

(v) Asset Backed Securities with underlying housing loans or having infrastructure assets as underlying as defined under 'infrastructure facility' in clause (h) of regulation 2 of Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority (Registration of Indian Insurance Companies) Amendment Regulations, 2008. 
 

(vi) Commercial papers issued by a company or All India Financial Institution recognized as such by Reserve Bank of India having a credit rating by a credit rating agency registered under SEBI (Credit Rating Agencies) Regulations, 1999. 
 

(vii) Money Market instruments as defined in regulation 2(cc) of these regulations. 
 

Explanation .-1. All conditions mentioned in the 'note' appended to regulations 3 and 4 shall be complied with.] 
 

--------- 
 

1. Vide Notification No. IRDA/Reg./8/2000, dated 14th August, 2000, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. III, Sec. 4, dated 16th August, 2000. 
 

2. Subs. by Notification No. IRDA/Reg./5/47/2008, dated 30th July, 2008 (w.e.f. 11-8-2008).
</form><form>
 

THE INSURANCE REGULATORY AND DEVELOPMENT AUTHORITY (INVESTMENT) REGULATIONS, 20001
 

 
 

2[ Schedule II 
 

( See regulation 4) 
 

List of Approved Investments for General Business 
 

'Approved Investments' for the purposes of section 27B of the Act shall consist of the following:- 
 

(a) All investments specified in section 27B of the Act except- 
 

(i) clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 27A of the Act; 
 

(ii) immovable property situated in another country as stated in clause (n) of sub-section (1) of section 27A of the Act; 
 

(iii) first mortgages on immovable property situated in another country as stated in clause (i) of sub-section (1) of section 27B of the Act. 
 

(b) In addition the following investments shall be deemed as approved investments by the authority under the powers vested in it vide clause (j) of sub-section (1) of section 27B of the Act. 
 

(i) All loans secured as per Insurance Act, 1938, secured-debentures, secured bonds and other debt instruments rated as per Note appended to regulations 3 and 4 equity shares, preference shares and debt instruments issued by all India Financial Institutions recognized as such by Reserve Bank of India - investments to be made in terms of investment policy guidelines, benchmarks and exposure norms, limits approved by the Board of Directors of the insurer. 
 

(ii) Bonds or debentures issued by companies rated not less than AA or its equivalent and P1 or Equivalent ratings for short-term bonds, debentures, certificate of deposits and commercial papers by a credit rating agency, registered under SEBI (Credit Rating Agencies) Regulations, 1999 would be considered as 'Approved Investments'. 
 

(iii) Subject to norms/limits approved by the Board of Directors of the insurers deposits (including fixed deposits as per section 27B(10) of Insurance Act, 1938) with banks ( e.g ., in current account, call deposits, notice deposits, certificate of deposits etc.) included for the time being in the Second Schedule to Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934) and deposits with primary dealers duly recognised by Reserve Bank of India as such. 
 

(iv) Collateralised Borrowing and Lending Obligation (CBLO) created by the Clearing Corporation of India Limited and recognized by the Reserve Bank of India and exposure to Gilt, G Sec and liquid mutual fund forming part of Approved Investments as per Mutual Fund Guidelines issued under these regulations and money market instrument/investment. 
 

(v) Asset Backed Securities with underlying housing loans or having infrastructure assets as underlying as defined under 'infrastructure facility' in clause (h) of regulation 2 of Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority (Registration of Indian Insurance Companies) Amendment Regulations, 2008. 
 

(vi) Commercial papers issued by a company or All India Financial Institution recognized as such by Reserve Bank of India having a credit rating agency registered under SEBI (Credit Rating Agencies) Regulations, 1999. 
 

(vii) Money Market instruments as defined in regulation 2(cc) of these regulations. 
 

Explanation .-1. All conditions mentioned in the 'note' appended to regulations 3 and 4 shall be complied with.] 
 

--------- 
 

1. Vide Notification No. IRDA/Reg./8/2000, dated 14th August, 2000, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. III, Sec. 4, dated 16th August, 2000. 
 

2. Subs. by Notification No. IRDA/Reg./5/47/2008, dated 30th July, 2008 (w.e.f. 11-8-2008).
</form><form>
 

THE INSURANCE REGULATORY AND DEVELOPMENT AUTHORITY (INVESTMENT) REGULATIONS, 20001
 

 
 

2[***]
 

--------- 
 

1. Vide Notification No. IRDA/Reg./8/2000, dated 14th August, 2000, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. III, Sec. 4, dated 16th August, 2000. 
 

2. Schedule III omitted by Notification No. IRDA/Reg./5/2001, dated 31st May, 2001 (w.e.f. 31-5-2001).
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by Notification No. IRDA/Reg./5/47/2008, dated 30th July, 2008 (w.e.f. 11-8-2008).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Added by Notification No. IRDA/Reg./1/2004, dated 1st January, 2004 (w.e.f. 
    5-1-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Added by Notification No. IRDA/Reg./5/47/2008, dated 30th July, 2008 (w.e.f. 11-8-2008).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Ins. by Notification No. IRDA/Reg./5/2001, dated 31st May, 2001 (w.e.f. 
31-5-2001).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Subs. by Notification No. IRDA/Reg./5/47/2008, dated 30th July, 2008 (w.e.f. 11-8-2008).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Subs. by Notification No. IRDA/Reg./5/2001, dated 31st May, 2001 (w.e.f. 
31-5-2001).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Added by Notification No. IRDA/Reg./1/2004, dated 1st January, 2004 (w.e.f. 
  5-1-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Subs. by Notification No. IRDA/Reg./5/47/2008, dated 30th July, 2008 (w.e.f. 11-8-2008).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>