<act><tid>1991903</tid>
<title>THE CANTONMENTS ACT, <year>1924</year></title>

ACT NO. 2 OF <year>1924</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 16th February, <year>1924</year>.]

An Act to consolidate and amend the law relating to the administration 
of cantonments.

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1518001</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.-
<section><tid>170782</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Cantonments Act, <year>1924</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1200869</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>.

</section>

<section><tid>724887</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, direct that this Act, or any provisions thereof which it may 
specify, shall come into force on such <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> date as it may appoint in 
this behalf.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>684874</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.- In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant 
in the subject or context,--
<section><tid>361040</tid>
<number>i</number>" Assistant Health Officer" means the medical officer 
appointed by the <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Officer Commanding- in- Chief, the 
Command,] to be the Assistant Health Officer for a 
cantonment;

</section>

<section><tid>136670</tid>
<number>ii</number>" Board" means a Cantonment Board constituted under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1441945</tid>
<number>iia</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum>" boundary wall" means a wall which abuts on a 
street and which does not exceed <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> two and a half 
metres in height].
<footcitenum>8</footcitenum>

<pagefootnote><pagenum>32</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The Act comes into force in Pondicherry vide Reg. 7 of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 
and Sch. I (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1963</year>). 
2. The words" except Part B States" were omitted by Act 53 of <year>1950</year>. 
s. 4. 
3. The words" including British Baluchistan" were rep. by the A. O. 
<year>1948</year>. 
4.  1st May, <year>1924</year>; see Gazette of India, 19p 4, Pt. I, p. p 17. 
5. Subs. by Act 35 of <year>1926</year>, s. 2, for" Officer Commanding the 
District". 
6. Ins. by Act 2 of <year>1954</year>, s. 2. 
7. Subs by Act 15 of <year>1983</year>, s. 2, for" oight feet in height" (w. e. f.  
  1- 10- <year>1983</year>). 
8. Cl. (iii) omitted by s. 2, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1983</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>538665</tid>
<number>iv</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>" building" means a house, outhouse, stable, latrine, 
shed, hut or other roofed structure whether of masonry, 
brick, wood, mud, metal or other material, and any part 
thereof, and includes a well and a wall <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> (other than  
  a boundary wall)] but does not include a tent or other 
portable and temporary shelter;]
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>


</section>

<section><tid>1904707</tid>
<number>vi</number>" causal election" means an election held to fill a 
casual vacancy;

</section>

<section><tid>365424</tid>
<number>vii</number>" casual vacancy" means a vacancy occurring otherwise 
than by efflux of time in the office of an elected 
member of a Board <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> and includes a vacancy in such 
office, arising under sub- section (1A) of section 17]

</section>

<section><tid>432970</tid>
<number>viia</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>" civil area" means an area declared to be a civil 
area by the Central Government under section 43A;

<subsection><tid>1672947</tid>
<number>viib</number>" civil area committee" means a committee appointed 
under section 43A;]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>540569</tid>
<number>viii</number>" Command" means one of the Commands into which India 
is for military purposes for the time being divided, 
and includes any area which the Central Government may, 
by notification in the Official Gazette, declare to be 
a Command for all or any of the purposes of this Act;
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum>


</section>

<section><tid>684469</tid>
<number>x</number>" dairy" includes any farm, cattle- shed, milk- store, 
milk- shop or other place from which milk is supplied or 
in which milk is kept for purposes of sale or is 
manufactured for sale into butter, ghee, cheese or 
curds, and, in relation to a dairyman who does not 
occupy any premises for the sale of milk, includes any 
place in which he keeps the vessels used by him for the 
storage or sale of milk;

</section>

<section><tid>1080055</tid>
<number>xi</number>" dairyman" includes the keeper of a cow, buffalo, goat, 
ass or other animal, the milk of which is offered or is 
intended to be offered for sale for human consumption, 
and any purveyor of milk and any occupier of a dairy;

<subsection><tid>973179</tid>
<number>xia</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>" Defence Estates Officer" means the officer 
appointed by the Central Government to perform the 
duties of the Defence Estates Officer for the purposes 
of this Act and the rules made thereunder;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1887081</tid>
<number>xib</number>" Director" means the officer appointed by the Central 
Government to perform the duties of the Director, 
Defence Lands and Cantonments, the Command, for the 
purposes of this Act and the rules made thereunder and 
includes the Joint Director;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>139331</tid>
<number>xic</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum>]" entitled consumer" means a person in a 
cantonment who is paid from the Defence Services 
Estimates and is authorised by general or special order 
of the Central Government to receive a supply of water 
for domestic purposes from the Military Engineer 
Services or the Public Works Department on such terms 
and conditions as may be specified in the order;]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>33</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 24 of <year>1936</year>, s. 2, for the original clause. 
2. Subs. by Act 2 of <year>1954</year>, s. 2, for" (other than a boundary wall  
  not exceeding eight feet in height and not abutting on a street)". 
3. Cl. (v) was rep. by Act 24 of <year>1936</year>, s. 2. 
4. Ins. by Act 15 of <year>1983</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1983</year>). 
5. Cl. (ix) was rep. by Act 12 of <year>1935</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I. 
6. Ins. by Act 24 of <year>1936</year>, s. 2. 
7. Cl. (Xia) renumbered as d (xic) by Act 15 of <year>1983</year>, s. 2 
 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1983</year>).

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1554104</tid>
<number>xii</number>" Executive Engineer" means <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Officer of the 
Military Engineer Services of that grade], having 
charge of the military works in a cantonment <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or 
where more than one such officer has charge of the 
military works in a cantonment such one of those 
officers as the Officer Commanding the station may 
designate in this behalf], and includes the officer of 
whatever grade in immediate executive engineering 
charge of a cantonment;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1941901</tid>
<number>xiii</number>" Executive Officer" means the person appointed under 
this Act to be the Executive Officer of a cantonment;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1292845</tid>
<number>xiiia</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>" factory" means a factory as defined in clause 
 (m) of section 2 of the Factories Act, <year>1948</year> (63 of  
  <year>1948</year>);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1733688</tid>
<number>xiiib</number>" Forces" means the Army, Navy and Air Force or any 
part of any one or more of them;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1359310</tid>
<number>xiv</number>" Health Officer" means the senior executive medical 
officer in military employ on duty in a cantonment;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>794571</tid>
<number>xv</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>" hospital" includes family welfare centre, child 
welfare centre, maternity centre and health centre;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>785860</tid>
<number>xvi</number>" hut" means any building, no material portion of which 
above the plinth level is constructed of masonry or of 
squared timber framing or of iron framing;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1738009</tid>
<number>xvii</number>" infectious or contagious disease" means cholera, 
leprosy, enteric fever, small- pox, tuberculosis, 
diphtheria, plague, influenza, venereal disease, and 
any other epidemic, endemic or infectious disease which 
the <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Central Government] may, be notification in the 
Official Gazette, declare to be, an infectious or 
contagious disease for the purposes of this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1705790</tid>
<number>xviii</number>" inhabitant", in relation to a cantonment, or local 
area, means any person ordinarily residing or carrying 
on business or owning or occupying immovable property 
therein, and in case of a dispute means any person 
declared by the District Magistrate to be an 
inhabitant;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>33368</tid>
<number>xix</number>" intoxicating drug" means opium, ganja, bhang, charas 
and any preparation or admixture thereof, and includes 
any other intoxicating substance, or liquid which the 
 <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Central Government] <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> may by notification in the 
Official Gazette, declare to be an intoxicating drug 
for the purposes of this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>667856</tid>
<number>xixa</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>" lower grade employee" means daftry, peon, bhisti, 
mali lamp- lighter, chowkidar, mazdoor or safaiwala or 
any other employee declared by the Central Government 
to be a lower grade employee for the purposes of this 
Act;]
<footcitenum>7</footcitenum> (xx)" market" includes any place where persons assemble 
for the sale of, or for the purpose of exposing for 
sale, meat, fish, fruits, vegetables, animals intended 
for human food or any other articles of human food 
whatsoever, with or without the consent of the owner of 
such place notwithstanding that there may be no common 
regulation for the concourse of buyers and sellers and 
whether or not any control is exercised over the 
business of, or the persons frequenting, the market by 
the owner of the place or by any other person, but 
shall not include a single shop or group of shops not 
being more than six in number and shops within unit 
lines;']

<pagefootnote><pagenum>34</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 15 of <year>1983</year>, s. 2, for certain words (w. e. f.  
  1- 10- <year>1983</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 24 of <year>1936</year>, s. 2. 
3. Ins. by Act 15 of <year>1983</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1983</year>). 
4. Cl. (xv) was rep. by Act 24 of <year>1936</year>, s. 2. and Ins. by act 15 of 
s. 2, (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1983</year>). 
5. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G." 
6. The words" with the previous sanction of the G. G. in C." were 
rep. by Act 7 of <year>1925</year>, s. 2. 
7. Subs. by Act 15 of <year>1983</year>, s. 2, for cl. (xx)  (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1983</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>

<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> (xxi)" military officer" means a person who, being an 
officer within the meaning of the Army Act, <year>1950</year> (46  
  of <year>1950</year>), the Navy Act, <year>1957</year> (62 of <year>1957</year>) or the Air 
Force Act, <year>1950</year> (46 of <year>1950</year>), is commissioned, gazetted 
or in pay as an officer doing army, naval or air force 
duty with the army, navy or air force, or is an officer 
doing such duty in any arm, branch or part of any of 
those forces;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1774611</tid>
<number>xxii</number>" nuisance" includes any act, omission, place, animal 
or thing which causes or is likely to cause injury, 
danger, annoyance or offence to the sense of sight, 
smell or hearing or disturbance to rest or sleep, or 
which is or may be dangerous to life or injurious to 
health or property;']

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1838488</tid>
<number>xxiii</number>" occupier" includes an owner in occupation of, or 
otherwise using his own land or building;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1704395</tid>
<number>xxiv</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>" Officer Commanding the Area" means the Officer 
Commanding any one of the areas into which India is for 
military purposes for the time being divided, or any 
sub- area which does not form part of any such area, or 
any area which the Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, declare to be an 
area for all or any of the purposes of this Act;']

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1337150</tid>
<number>xxiva</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>" Officer Commanding the station" means the 
military officer for the time being in command of the 
forces in a cantonment, or, if that officer is the 
Officer Commanding the <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Area] or Officer Commanding- 
in- Chief, the Command, the military officer who would 
be in command of
<pagefootnote><pagenum>35</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Cl. (xxa) omitted by Act 15 of <year>1983</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1983</year>). 
2. Subs. by s. 2, for cls (xxi) and (xxii)  (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1983</year>). 
3. Subs. by Act 15 of <year>1983</year>, s. 2 for cl (xxii)  (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1983</year>). 
4. Ins. by Act 12 of <year>1935</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I. 
5. Subs. by Act 15 of <year>1983</year>, s. 2, for" district" (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1983</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


those forces in the absence of the Officer Commanding 
the[ Area] <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> and Officer Commanding- in- Chief, the 
Command;]


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1813388</tid>
<number>xxv</number>" ordinary election" means an election held to fill a 
vacancy in the office of an elected member of a Board 
arising by efflux of time;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>910897</tid>
<number>xxvi</number>" owner" includes any person who is receiving or is 
entitled to receive the rent of any building or land 
whether on his own account or on behalf of himself and 
others or an agent or trustee, or who would so receive 
the rent or be entitled to receive it if the building 
or land were let to a tenant;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1298294</tid>
<number>xxvii</number>" party wall" means a wall forming part of a building 
and used or constructed to be used for the support or 
separation of adjoining buildings belonging to 
different owners, or constructed or adapted to be 
occupied by different persons;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>373223</tid>
<number>xxviii</number>" private market" means a market which is not 
maintained by a <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Board] and which is licensed by a 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Board] under the provisions of this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>274135</tid>
<number>xxix</number>" private slaughter- house" means a slaughter- house 
which is not maintained by a <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Board] and which is 
licensed by a <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Board] under the provisions of this 
Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>461512</tid>
<number>xxx</number>" public market" means a market maintained by a 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Board];

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1235478</tid>
<number>xxxi</number>" public place" means any place which is open to the 
use and enjoyment of the public, whether it is actually 
used or enjoyed by the public or not;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1783967</tid>
<number>xxxii</number>" public slaughter- house" means a slaughter- house 
maintained by a <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Board];

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>193642</tid>
<number>xxxiia</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> a person is deemed to reside in a cantonment if 
he maintains therein a house or a portion of a house 
which is at all times available for occupation by 
himself or his family even though he may himself reside 
elsewhere, provided that he has not abandoned all 
intention of again occupying such house either by 
himself or his family;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1382937</tid>
<number>xxxiii</number>" shed" means a slight or temporary structure for 
shade or shelter;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>36</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 15 of <year>1983</year>, s. 2, for" district" (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1983</year>). 
2. Subs. by Act 24 of <year>1936</year>, s. 69, for" Cantonment Authority". 
3. Ins. by s. 2, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>375622</tid>
<number>xxxiv</number>" slaughter- house" means any place ordinarily used 
for the slaughter of animals for the purpose of selling 
the flesh thereof for human consumption;
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> (xxxv)" soldier" means any person who is a soldier or a 
sailor or an airman subject to the Army Act, <year>1950</year> (45  
  of <year>1950</year>), the Navy Act, <year>1957</year> (62 of <year>1957</year>) or the Air 
Force Act, <year>1950</year> (46 of <year>1950</year>), as the case may be, and 
who is not a military officer;]


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>242231</tid>
<number>xxxvi</number>" spirituous liquor" means any fermented liquor, any 
wine, or any alcoholic liquid obtained by distillation 
or the sap of any kind of palm tree, and includes any 
other liquid containing alcohol which the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Central 
Government] <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> may by notification in the Official 
Gazette, declare to be a spirituous liquor for the 
purposes of this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1608516</tid>
<number>xxxvii</number>" street" includes any way, road, lane, square, 
court, alley <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> or passage] in a cantonment, whether a 
thoroughfare or not and whether built upon or not, over 
which the public have a right- of- way and also the road- 
way or footway over any bridge or causeway;
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum> (xxxviia)" sub- area" means one of the sub- areas into 
which India is for military purposes for the time being 
divided, and includes, for all or any of the purposes 
of this Act, any territory which the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare 
to be a sub- area for such purposes;']


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>952780</tid>
<number>xxxviii</number>" vehicle" means a wheeled conveyance of any 
description which is capable of being used on a street, 
and includes a motor- car, motor lorry, motor omnibus, 
cart, locomotive, tram- car, hand- cart, truck, motor- 
cycle, bicycle, tricycle and rickshaw; <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>737637</tid>
<number>xxxix</number>" water- works" includes all lakes, tanks, streams, 
cisterns, springs, pumps, wells, reservoirs, aqueducts, 
water- trucks, sluices, mains, pipes, culverts, 
hydrants, stand- pipes, and conduits, and all machinery, 
lands, buildings, bridges and things, used for, or 
intended for the purpose of, supplying water to a 
cantonment; <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>727378</tid>
<number>xl</number>" year" means the year commencing on the first day of 
April.]



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>633357</tid>
<number>2A</number>[ Rule of construction.] Rep. by the Cantonments (Amendment) 
Act, <year>1954</year> (2 of <year>1954</year>), s. 3.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>37</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 15 of <year>1983</year>, s. 2, for cl. (xxxv)  (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1983</year>). 
2. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G." 
3. The words" with the previous sanction of the G. G. in C." were 
rep. by Act 7 of <year>1925</year>, s. 2. 
4 Subs. by Act 24 of <year>1936</year>, s. 2, for" passage or open space". 
5. Ins by Act 15 of <year>1983</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1983</year>). 
6. The word" and" was rep. by Act 24 of <year>1936</year> s. 2, ibid. 
7 Ins. by s. 2, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


CHAP

DEFINITION AND DELIMITATION OF CANTONMENTS

CHAPTER II

DEFINITION AND DELIMITATION OF CANTONMENTS



</article>



<article><tid>791736</tid>
<number> 3</number> Definition of cantonments.-
<section><tid>264927</tid>
<number>1</number>The <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Central Government] <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>  
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare any place or 
places in which any part of <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the forces] is quartered or which, 
being in the vicinity of any such place or places, is or are required 
for the service of such forces to be a cantonment for the purposes of 
this Act and of all other enactments for the time being in force, and 
 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> may, by a like notification, declare that any cantonment shall 
cease to be a cantonment.

</section>

<section><tid>738647</tid>
<number>2</number>The <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Central Government] <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> may, by a like notification, 
define the limits of any cantonment for the aforesaid purposes.

</section>

<section><tid>183363</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> When any place is declared a cantonment for the first 
time, the Central Government may, until a Board is constituted in 
accordance with the provisions of this Act, by order make any 
provision which appears necessary to it either for the administration 
of the cantonment or for the constitution of the Board.]

</section>

<section><tid>750852</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum> The Central Government may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, direct that in any place declared a cantonment under 
subsection (1) the provisions of any enactment relating to local self- 
government other than this Act shall have effect only to such extent 
or subject to such modifications, or that any authority constituted 
under any such enactment shall exercise authority only to such extent, 
as may be specified in the notification.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1902108</tid>
<number> 4</number> Alteration of limits of cantonments.
<section><tid>79770</tid>
<number>1</number>The <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Central  
Government] <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> may <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> after consulting the State Government and the 
Board concerned], by notification in the Official Gazette, declare its 
intention to include within <footcitenum>8</footcitenum> the cantonment] any local area situated 
in the <footcitenum>9</footcitenum> vicinity thereof or to exclude from <footcitenum>8</footcitenum> the cantonment] any 
local area comprised therein.

</section>

<section><tid>1501802</tid>
<number>2</number>Any inhabitant of a cantonment or local area in respect of 
which a notification has been published under sub- section (1) may, 
within six weeks from the date of the notification, submit in writing 
to the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Central Government] through the Officer Commanding- in- 
Chief,
<pagefootnote><pagenum>38</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G." 
2. The words" with the previous sanction of the G. G. in C." were 
rep. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 15 of <year>1983</year>, s. 3, for certaain words (w. e. f.  
  1- 10- <year>1983</year>). 
4. The words" with the like sanction" were rep. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>. 
5. Ins. by Act 24 of <year>1936</year>, s. 3. 
6. Ins. by Act 8 of <year>1944</year>, s. 2. 
7. Ins. by Act 2 of <year>1954</year>, s. 4. 
8. Subs., ibid., for" a cantonment". 
9. The words" immediate" was rep. by Act 26 of <year>1927</year>, s. 2.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


the Command, an objection to the notification, and the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Central 
Government] shall take such objection into consideration.


</section>

<section><tid>1812012</tid>
<number>3</number>On the expiry of six weeks from the date of the notification, 
the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Central Government] may <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> after considering the objections, if 
any, which have been submitted under sub- section (2), by notification 
in the Official Gazette, include the local area in respect of which 
the notification was published under sub- section (1), or any part 
thereof, in the cantonment or, as the case may be, exclude such area 
or any part thereof from the cantonment.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1342470</tid>
<number>5</number>The effect of including area in cantonment.- When, by a 
notification under section 4, any local area is included in a 
cantonment such area shall thereupon become subject to this Act and to 
all other enactments for the time being in force throughout the 
cantonment and to all notifications, rules, regulations, bye- laws, 
orders and directions issued or made thereunder.


</article>



<article><tid>1869532</tid>
<number> 6</number> Disposal of cantonment fund when area ceases to be a 
cantonment.-
<section><tid>319348</tid>
<number>1</number>When, by a notification under section 3, any  
cantonment ceases to be a cantonment and the local area comprised 
therein is immediately placed under the control of a local authority, 
the balance of the cantonment fund and other property vesting in the 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Board] shall vest in such local authority, and the liabilities of 
the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Board] shall be transferred to such local authority.

</section>

<section><tid>194599</tid>
<number>2</number>When, in like manner, any cantonment ceases to be a 
cantonment and the local area comprised therein is not immediately 
placed under the control of a local authority, the balance of the 
cantonment fund and other property vesting in the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Board] shall vest 
in Government, and the liabilities of the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Board] shall be 
transferred to the <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Central Government].



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>260864</tid>
<number> 7</number> Disposal of cantonment fund when area ceases to be included in 
a cantonment.-
<section><tid>598415</tid>
<number>1</number>When, by a notification under section 4, any local  
area forming part of a cantonment ceases to be under the control of a 
particular <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Board] and is immediately placed under the control of 
some other local authority, such portion of the cantonment fund and 
other property vesting in the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Board] and such portion of the 
liabilities of the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Board], as the Central Government may, by 
general or special order, direct, shall be transferred to that other 
local authority.

</section>

<section><tid>1364443</tid>
<number>2</number>When, in like manner, any local area forming part of a 
cantonment ceases to be under the control of a particular <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Board] 
and is not immediately placed under the control of some other local 
authority, such portion of the cantonment fund and other property
<pagefootnote><pagenum>39</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G." 
2. The words" with the previous sanction of the G. G. in C." were 
rep. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>. 
3. Subs. by Act 24 of <year>1936</year>, s. 69, for" Cantonment Authority". 
4. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" Secretary of State in Council".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


vesting in the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Board] shall vest in Government, and such portion of 
the liabilities of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Board] shall be transferred to the 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Central Government], as the Central Government may, by general or 
special order, direct.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>126827</tid>
<number>8</number>Application of funds and property transferred under sections 6 
and 7.- Any cantonment fund or portion of a cantonment fund or other 
property of a <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Board] vesting in Government under the provisions of 
section 6 or section 7 shall be applied in the first place to satisfy 
any liabilities of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Board] transferred under such provisions to 
the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Central Government], and in the second place for the benefit of 
the inhabitants of the local area which has ceased to be a cantonment 
or, as the case may be, part of a cantonment.


</article>



<article><tid>1871527</tid>
<number> 9</number> Limitation of operation of Act.- The <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Central Government] 
may, <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> by notification in the Official Gazette, exclude from the 
operation of any part of this Act the whole or any part of a 
cantonment, or direct that any provision of this Act shall, in the 
case of any cantonment--
<section><tid>1571103</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> situated within the limits of a Presidency- town; or

</section>

<section><tid>973134</tid>
<number>b</number>in which the Board is superseded under section 54.] 
apply with such modifications as may be so specified.
CHAP

CANTONMENT BOARDS

CHAPTER III

<footcitenum>6</footcitenum> CANTONMENT BOARDS]

Boards




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>597955</tid>
<number>10</number><footcitenum>7</footcitenum> Cantonment Board and Executive Officer. For every 
cantonment there shall be a Cantonment Board <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>.]


</article>



<article><tid>1071683</tid>
<number>11</number><footcitenum>8</footcitenum> Incorporation of Cantonment Board.- Every Board shall, by 
the name of the place by reference to which the cantonment is known, 
be a body corporate having perpetual succession and a common seal with 
power to acquire and hold property both movable and immovable and to 
contract and shall, by the said name, sue and be sued.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>40</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 24 of <year>1936</year>, s. 69, for" Cantonment Authority". 
2. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" Secretary of State in Council". 
3. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G." 
4. The words" with the previous sanction of the G. G. in C." were 
rep. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>. 
5. Subs. by Act 24 of <year>1936</year>, s. 4, for" specified in the notification 
in which there is no Board". 
6. Subs. by Act 34 of <year>1939</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I, for" Boards and 
Cantonment Boards". 
7. Subs. by s. 5, ibid., for the original section. 
8. Certain words omitted by Act 15 of <year>1983</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1983</year>). 
9. Subs. by Act 24 of <year>1936</year>, s. 5, for the original section.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>



</article>



<article><tid>285060</tid>
<number> 13</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Constitution of Cantonment Boards.-
<section><tid>1059097</tid>
<number>1</number>Cantonments shall  
be divided into three classes, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1578356</tid>
<number>i</number>Class I Cantonments, in which the civil population 
exceeds ten thousand;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1887482</tid>
<number>ii</number>Class II Cantonments, in which the civil population 
exceeds two thousand five hundred, but does not exceed 
ten thousand; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1832504</tid>
<number>iii</number>Class III Cantonments, in which the civil population 
does not exceed two thousand five hundred:
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>

<pagefootnote><pagenum>41</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>S. 12 omitted by Act 15 of <year>1983</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1983</year>). 
2. Subs. by Act 24 of <year>1936</year>, s. 5, for the original section. 
3. The proviso was, rep. by the A. O. <year>1948</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1074449</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes of sub- section (1), the civil population 
shall be calculated in accordance with the latest official census, or, 
if the Central Government, by general or special order, so directs, in 
accordance with a special census taken for the purpose.

</section>

<section><tid>1053041</tid>
<number>3</number>In Class I Cantonments, the Board shall consist of the 
following members, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1223386</tid>
<number>a</number>the Officer Commanding the station or, if the Central 
Government so directs in respect of any cantonment, 
such other military officer as may be nominated in his 
place by the Officer Commanding- in- Chief, the Command;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>768989</tid>
<number>b</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> an executive Megistrate] nominated by the District 
Magistrate;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1601610</tid>
<number>c</number>the Health Officer;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1957181</tid>
<number>d</number>the Executive Engineer;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1739693</tid>
<number>e</number> (i) in cantonments of which the civil population exceeds
seven thousand five hundred, three military officers,


<subsubsection><tid>1376738</tid>
<number>ii</number>in cantonments of which the civil population exceeds 
five thousand, but does not exceed seven thousand five 
hundred, two military officers,

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>767626</tid>
<number>iii</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> in cantonments of which the civil population does 
not exceed five thousand, one military officer,]
nominated by name by the Officer Commanding the station by 
order in writing;


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>536735</tid>
<number>f</number>such number of members elected under this Act as is 
equal to the number of members constituted or nominated 
by or under clauses (b) to (e).
<pagefootnote><pagenum>42</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 15 of <year>1983</year>, s. 6, for certain words (w. e. f.  
  1- 10- <year>1983</year>). 
2. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for the former clause.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>430793</tid>
<number>5</number>In Class III Cantonments, the Board shall consist of the 
following members, namely:--

<subsection><tid>516083</tid>
<number>a</number>the Officer Commanding the station, or if the Central 
Government so directs in respect of any cantonment, 
such other military officer as may be nominated in his 
place by the Officer Commanding- in- Chief, the Command;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1372400</tid>
<number>b</number>one military officer nominated by name by the Officer 
Commanding the station by order in writing;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>929462</tid>
<number>c</number>one member elected under this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1510065</tid>
<number>6</number>The Officer Commanding the station may, if he thinks fit, 
with the sanction of the Officer Commanding- in- Chief, the Command, 
nominate in place of any military officer whom he is empowered to 
nominate under clause (e) of sub- section (3), clause (e) of sub- 
section (4) or clause (b) of sub- section (5), any person, whether in 
the service of the government or not, who is ordinarily resident in 
the cantonment or in the vicinity thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>352159</tid>
<number>7</number>Every election or nomination of a member of a Board and every 
vacancy in the membership thereof shall be notified by the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Central 
Government] in the Official Gazette.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1928221</tid>
<number> 14</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Power to vary constitution of Boards in special 
circumstances.-
<section><tid>1938298</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in section 13,  
if the Central Government is satisfied--

<subsection><tid>745950</tid>
<number>a</number>that, by reason of military operations it is necessary, 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1537990</tid>
<number>b</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> that, for the administration of the cantonment, it is 
desirable,
to vary the constitution of the Board in any cantonment under this 
section, the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, make a declaration to that effect.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>759750</tid>
<number>2</number>Upon the making of a declaration under sub- section (1), the 
Board in the cantonment shall consist of the following members, 
namely:--

<subsection><tid>1091078</tid>
<number>a</number>the Officer Commanding the station;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1158614</tid>
<number>b</number>one military officer nominated by name by the Officer 
Commanding the station by order in writing;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>198936</tid>
<number>c</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> one member, not being a person in the service of the 
Government, nominated by the Central Government in 
consultation with the Officer Commanding- in- Chief, the 
Command.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>43</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G." 
2. Subs. by Act 24 of <year>1936</year>, s. 5, for the former section. 
3. The words" after consultation with the L. G." were rep. by the A. 
O. <year>1937</year>. 
4. Subs. by Act 15 of <year>1983</year>, s. 7, for cl. (c), (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1983</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1538752</tid>
<number>3</number>Every nomination of a member of a Board constituted under 
this section, and every vacancy in the membership thereof, shall be 
notified by the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Central Government] in the Official Gazette.

</section>

<section><tid>1002612</tid>
<number>4</number>The term of office of a Board constituted by a declaration 
under sub- section (1) shall not ordinarily extend beyond one year;
Provided that the Central Government may from time to time, by a 
like declaration, extend the term of office of such a Board by any 
period not exceeding one year at a time:

Provided also that the Central Government shall forthwith direct 
that the term of office of such a Board shall cease if, in the opinion 
of the Central Government, the reasons stated in the declaration 
whereby such Board was constituted, or its term of office was 
extended, have ceased to exist.


</section>

<section><tid>1691937</tid>
<number>5</number>When the term of office of a Board constituted under this 
section has expired or ceased, the Board shall be replaced by the 
former Board which, but for the declaration under sub- section (1), 
would have continued to hold office, or, if the term of office of such 
former Board has expired, by a Board constituted under section 13.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1102025</tid>
<number> 15</number> Term of office of members.-
<section><tid>306514</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as otherwise provided in this  
section, the term of office of a member of a Board shall be[ five 
years] <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> and shall commence from the date of the notification of his 
election or nomination under <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> sub- section (7) of section 13], or 
from the date on which the vacancy has occurred in which he is elected 
or nominated, whichever date is later:
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Provided that the Central Government may, when satisfied that 
it is necessary in order to avoid administrative difficulty, extend 
the term of office of all the elected members of a Board by such 
period, not exceeding one year, as it thinks fit;]

<footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Provided further that a member whose term of office has been 
so extended, shall cease to hold office on the date of the 
notification of the election of his successor under sub- section (7) of 
section 13.]

<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>


</section>

<section><tid>153529</tid>
<number>2</number>The term of office of an ex- officio member of a Board shall 
continue so long as he holds the office in virtue of which he is such 
a member.

</section>

<section><tid>340378</tid>
<number>3</number>The term of office of a member elected to fill a casual 
vacancy shall commence from the <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> date of the notification of his 
election], and shall continue so long only as the member in whose 
place he is elected would have been entitled to hold office if the 
vacancy had not occurred.

</section>

<section><tid>649507</tid>
<number>4</number>An outgoing member shall, unless the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Central Government] 
otherwise directs, continue in office until the election or nomination 
of his successor is notified under <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> sub- section (7) of section 13].
<pagefootnote><pagenum>44</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G.". 
2. Subs. by Act 15 of <year>1983</year>, s. 8, for" three years" (w. e. f.  
  1- 10- <year>1983</year>). 
3. Subs. by Act 24 of <year>1936</year>, s. 6, for" sub- section (2) of section 
14". 
4. Ins. by s. 6, ibid. 
5. Ins. by Act 15 of <year>1983</year>, s. 8 (w. e.. f. 1- 10- <year>1983</year>). 
6. The proviso which had been inserted by Act 8 of <year>1944</year>, s. 3, was 
rep. by Act 2 of <year>1948</year>, s. 2 and Sch. 
7. Subs. by Act 15 of <year>1983</year>, s. 8, for certain words (w. e. f.  
  1- 10- <year>1983</year>).

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>764118</tid>
<number>5</number>Any outgoing member may, if qualified, be re- elected or re- 
nominated.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1295828</tid>
<number> 16</number> Filling of vacancies.-
<section><tid>1927218</tid>
<number>1</number>Vacancies arising by efflux of time  
in the office of an elected member of a Board shall be filled by an 
ordinary election to be held on such date as the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Central 
Government] may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct.

</section>

<section><tid>1825685</tid>
<number>2</number>A casual vacancy shall be filled by a casual election the 
date of which shall be fixed by the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Central Government] by 
notification in the Official Gazette, and shall be, as soon as may be, 
after the occurrence of the vacancy:
Provided that no casual election shall be held to fill a vacancy 
occurring within <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> six months] of any date on which the vacancy will 
occur by efflux of time, but such vacancy shall be filled at the next 
ordinary election.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1482293</tid>
<number> 17</number> Vacancies in special cases.-
<section><tid>374206</tid>
<number>1</number>If from any cause at an  
ordinary election no member is elected, or if the elected member is 
unwilling to serve on the Board, the outgoing member shall, if 
qualified and willing to serve, be deemed to have been re- elected:
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Provided that where there are more outgoing members qualified 
and willing to serve than there are vacancies to be filled under this 
sub- section, the outgoing members so deemed to have been re- elected 
shall, failing agreement amongst such members, be determined by lot 
under the supervision of the President of the Board and in such manner 
as he may decide.]


</section>

<section><tid>805020</tid>
<number>1A</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> If a person is elected to more than one seat in a Board, 
then, unless he resigns all but one of the seats within fourteen days 
from the date on which he is declared elected, or where the dates on 
which he is declared elected are different in respect of different 
seats, from the last of such dates, all the seats shall become 
vacant.]

</section>

<section><tid>1838302</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Vacancies arising in any of the following cases shall be 
filled by nomination by the Central Government after consultation with 
the Officer Commanding- in- Chief, the Command, namely:--

<subsection><tid>43548</tid>
<number>a</number>where at a casual election no member is elected;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>530997</tid>
<number>b</number>where at an ordinary election no member or an 
insufficient number of members is elected, or an 
elected member is unwilling to serve on the Board and 
the outgoing member is not qualified or is not willing 
to serve or is dead or cannot be found within a 
reasonable time;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>988100</tid>
<number>c</number>where at an election held when a Board is constituted 
for the first time no member or an insufficient number 
of members is elected or an elected member is unwilling 
to serve on the Board.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>45</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G." 
2. Subs. by Act 15 of <year>1983</year>, s, 9, fo 0r" three months" (w. e. f.  
  1- 10- <year>1983</year>). 
3. Ins. by Act 15 of <year>1942</year>, s. 2. 
4. Ins. by Act 15 of <year>1983</year>, s. 10 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1983</year>). 
5. Subs. by Act 15 of <year>1942</year>, s. 2, for the former sub- section (2).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>755738</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> For the purposes of sub- section (2) of section 16, a 
member nominated in pursuance of sub- section (2) of this section 
shall, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> where there has been a division of the cantonment into 
wards, be deemed to have been elected by such ward], as the Central 
Government may at the time of making the nomination or at any time 
thereafter declare.]

</section>

<section><tid>614001</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>] The term of office of a member nominated or deemed to 
have been re- elected under this section shall expire at the time at 
which it would have expired if he had been elected at the ordinary or 
casual election, as the case may be.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1324721</tid>
<number> 18</number> <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Oath or affirmation.-
<section><tid>647798</tid>
<number>1</number>Every person who is by virtue of  
his office, or who is nominated or elected to be, a member of the 
Board shall, before taking his seat, make and subscribe at a meeting 
of the Board an oath or affirmation of his allegiance to the 
Constitution of India in the following form, namely:--
become I, A. B., having been elected been nominated a member of 
this Board, do swear in the name of Good solemnly that I will bear 
true faith and allegiance to the Constitution of India as by law 
established and that I will faithfully discharge the duty upon which I 
am about to enter.".


</section>

<section><tid>286254</tid>
<number>2</number>If any such person fails to make and subscribed the oath or 
affirmation at one of the first two meetings held after the date of 
commencement of his term of office, the Central Government shall, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, declare his seat to be vacant:
Provided that a meeting where the member is absent with the leave 
of the Board shall not be taken into account.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>661496</tid>
<number> 19</number> Resignation.- <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>
<section><tid>215573</tid>
<number>1</number> (a) Any elected member of a Board who  
wishes to resign his office may give his resignation in writing to the 
President of the Board who shall forward it for orders to the Central 
Government under intimation to the Officer Commanding- in- Chief, the 
Command.

<subsection><tid>1274263</tid>
<number>b</number>Any nominated member of a Board who wishes to resign his 
office may forward his resignation in writing through the President of 
the Board to the Officer commanding- in- Cheif, the Command for orders.]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1324982</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum> It the[ Central Government or the Officer Commanding- in- 
Cheif, the Command, as the case may be,] accepts the resignation, such 
acceptance shall be communicated to the Board, and thereupon the seat 
of the member resigning shall become vacant.

</section>

<section><tid>531632</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>7</footcitenum> Notwithstanding any thing contained in sub- section (2), 
the resignation of any person elected to more than one seat in a Board 
from all but one of the seats in pursuance of sub- section (1A) of 
section 17 shall take effect when such resignation in received by the 
President of the Board."]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1634474</tid>
<number> 20</number> President and Vice- President.-
<section><tid>645647</tid>
<number>1</number>The <footcitenum>8</footcitenum> Officer Commanding  
the station] <footcitenum>9</footcitenum> if a member of the Board] shall be the President of 
the Board:
<pagefootnote><pagenum>46</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Sub- section (3) was inserted and the original sub- section (3) re- 
numbered (4) by s. 2 Act 15 of <year>1942</year>. 
2 Subs. by the A. O <year>1948</year>, for' Crown". 
3 Subs. by the A. O. <year>1948</year>, for" His Majesty the King, Emperor of 
India, his heirs and successors". 
4 subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G." 
5 Subs. by Act 7 of <year>1925</year>, s. 14, for" Commanding Officer of the 
Cantonment". 
6 Ins. by Act 24 of <year>1936</year>, s. 7. 
7 Subs. by Act 15 of <year>1983</year>, s. 10 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1983</year>). 
8 Subs. by s. 11, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1983</year>). 
9 Subs. of s. 12, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1983</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided that when a military office holding the office of 
President ceases to be the Officer commanding the station merely by 
reason of a <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> temporary absence from the station for a period not 
exceeding thirty consecutive days], he shall not vacate the office of 
President.]


</section>

<section><tid>1410484</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Where the officer Commanding the station is not a member 
of the Board, the military officer nominated in his place under clause 
 (a) of sub- section (3), sub- section (4) or sub- section (5) or section 
 13 shall be president of the Board.

</section>

<section><tid>1763363</tid>
<number>3</number>In every Board in which there is more than one elected 
member, there shall be a Vice- President elected by the elected members 
only and from among their number <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> in accordance with such procedure 
as the Central Government may be rule prescribe.].]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1453172</tid>
<number> 21</number> Term of office of Vice- President.- <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>
<section><tid>475694</tid>
<number>1</number>The term of office  
of a Vice- President shall be <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> five years] or the residue of his term 
of office as a member, whichever is less.]

</section>

<section><tid>376037</tid>
<number>2</number>A Vice- President may resign his office by notice in writing 
to the President and, on the resignation being accepted by the Board, 
the office shall become vacant.

</section>

<section><tid>1224071</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>7</footcitenum> A Vice- President may be removed from his office, at a 
special meeting convened for the purpose on a requisition for the same 
by not less than one- half of the elected members of the Board holding 
office, by a resolution passed by a majority of not less than two- 
thirds of the total number of elected members then holding office and 
attending and no member, other than an elected member, shall have the 
right to vote on the resolution.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1154476</tid>
<number> 22</number> Duties of President.-
<section><tid>1443880</tid>
<number>1</number>It shall be the duty of the  
President of every Board--

<subsection><tid>1530275</tid>
<number>a</number>unless prevented by reasonable cause, to convene and 
preside at all meetings of the Board and to regulate 
the conduct of business thereat;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1601131</tid>
<number>b</number><footcitenum>8</footcitenum> Control, direct and supervise] the financial and 
executive administration of the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1804702</tid>
<number>c</number>to perform all the duties and exercise all the powers 
specifically imposed or conferred on the President by 
or under this Act; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1524574</tid>
<number>d</number>subject to any restrictions, limitations and conditions 
imposed by this Act, to exercise executive power for 
the purpose of carrying out the provisions of this Act 
and to be directly responsible for the fulfilment of 
the purposes of this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>557381</tid>
<number>2</number>The President may, by order in writing, empower the Vice- 
President to exercise all or any of the powers and duties referred to 
in clause (c) of sub- section (1) other than any power, duty or 
function which he is by resolution of the Board expressly forbidden to 
delegate.

</section>

<section><tid>22010</tid>
<number>3</number>The exercise or discharge of any powers, duties or functions 
delegated by the President under this section shall be subject to such
<pagefootnote><pagenum>47</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 26 of <year>1927</year>, s. 3. 
2. Subs. by Act, 15 of <year>1983</year>, s. 13, for certain words (w. e. f.  
  1- 10- <year>1983</year>). 
3. Subs. by Act 24 of <year>1936</year>, s. 7, for the original sub- section. 
4. Ins. by Act 15 of <year>1942</year>, s. 3. 
5. Subs. by s. 8, ibid., for the original sub- section. 
6. Subs. by Act 15 of <year>1983</year>, s. 14, for" three years" (w. e. f.  
  1- 10- <year>1983</year>). 
7. Ins. by s. 14, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1983</year>). 
8. Subs. by s. 15, ibid., for certain words (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1983</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


restrictions, limitations and conditions, if any, as may be laid down 
by the President and to the control of, and to revision by, the 
President.


</section>

<section><tid>762268</tid>
<number>4</number>Every order made under sub- section (2) shall forthwith be 
communicated to the Board and to the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Officer Commanding- in- Chief, 
the Command].



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>417740</tid>
<number> 23</number> Duties of Vice- President.- It shall be the duty of the Vice- 
President of every Board--
<section><tid>1157156</tid>
<number>a</number>in the absence of the President and unless prevented by 
reasonable cause, to preside at meetings of the Board 
and when so presiding to exercise the authority of the 
President under sub- section (1) of section 22;

</section>

<section><tid>53956</tid>
<number>b</number>during the incapacity or temporary absence of the 
President or pending his appointment or succession, to 
perform any other duty and exercise any other power of 
the President; and

</section>

<section><tid>1584435</tid>
<number>c</number>to exercise any power and perform any duty of the 
President which may be delegated to him under sub- 
section (2) of section 22.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1766588</tid>
<number> 24</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Appointment of Executive Officer.-
<section><tid>1710857</tid>
<number>1</number>For every cantonment  
there shall be an Executive Officer appointed by the Central 
Government or by such person as the Central Government may authorise 
in this behalf:
Provided that the Board may empower any of its members or 
officers to exercise or perform in the absence of the Executive 
Officer from the cantonment all or any of such powers or duties of an 
Executive Officer under this Act as the Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf.

Explanation.-- In this proviso, the word" officers" shall mean any 
of the supervisory staff of the Board as may be specified by the 
Board.


</section>

<section><tid>238089</tid>
<number>2</number>Not less than one- half of the cost of the salary of the 
Executive Officer shall be paid by the Central Government and the 
balance from the cantonment fund.

</section>

<section><tid>1856743</tid>
<number>3</number>The Executive Officer shall be the Secretary of the Board and 
of every Committee of the Board and may participate in every meeting 
of the Board and of every Committee of the board but, shall not be a 
member of the Board or of any such Committee.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1750422</tid>
<number> 24A</number> Duties of Executive Officer.- Subject to the provisions of 
clause (b) and clause (d) of sub- section
<section><tid>564539</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 22, the  
Executive Officer shall--

<subsection><tid>577771</tid>
<number>a</number>exercise all the powers and perform all the duties 
conferred or imposed upon him by or under this Act or any other 
law for the time being in force;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1472655</tid>
<number>b</number>prescribe the duties of, and exercise supervision and 
control over the acts and proceedings of, officers and other 
employees of the Board, other than medical officer in charge of 
the cantonment general hospital or dispensary;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>602319</tid>
<number>c</number>be responsible for the custody of all records of the 
Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1457276</tid>
<number>d</number>arrange for the performance of such duties relative to 
the proceedings of the Board or of any Committee of the Board or 
of any Committee of Arbitration constituted under this Act, as 
those bodies may respectively impose on him;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>339721</tid>
<number>e</number>comply with every requisition of the Board on any matter 
pertaining to the administration of the cantonment.]



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>55494</tid>
<number>25</number>Special power of the Executive Officer.- The Executive Officer 
may, in cases of emergency, direct the execution of any work or the 
doing of any Act which would ordinarily require the sanction of the 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Board] and the immediate execution or doing of which is, in his 
opinion, necessary for the service or safety of the public, and may 
direct that the expense of executing such work or doing such act shall 
be paid from the cantonment fund:--
</article>



 </act>