<act><title>


THE NATIONAL HIGHWAYS (FEES FOR THE USE OF 
NATIONAL HIGHWAYS SECTION AND PERMANENT 
BRIDGE—PUBLIC 
FUNDED PROJECT) RULES, 19971</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title, extent 
and commencement.—
<section><number>i</number> 
These rules may be called the National Highways (Fees for the Use of National 
Highways Section and Permanent Bridge—Public Funded Project) Rules, 1997.
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> They shall come into 
force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
      
<number>a</number>  “Act” means the National Highways Act, 1956 (48 of 1956);
 </section><section>
      
<number>b</number>  “executing agency” means,—
 <subsection>
           
<number>i</number>  in the case of those national highways administratively placed under 
the charge of Border Roads Organisation, the Border Roads Development Board 
(hereinafter referred to as ‘BRDB’);
 </subsection><subsection>
           
<number>ii</number>  in the case of those national highways or part thereof entrusted to 
National Highways Authority of India (hereinafter referred to as ’NHAI’, the 
National Highways Authority of India;
 </subsection><subsection>
          
<number>iii</number>  in other cases the State Government or Union Territory, the 
Administration to which such functions are delegated under section 5 of the Act;
 </subsection></section><section>
      
<number>c</number>  “mechanical vehicle” means any laden or unladen vehicle designed to be 
driven under its own power including a motor vehicle as defined in clause (28) 
of section 2 of the Motor Vehicles Act, 1988 (59 of 1988);
 </section><section>
      
<number>d</number>  “franchisee” means a firm or a company or a person to whom the 
franchise to collect and retain the fee has been awarded through auction;
 </section><section>
      
<number>e</number>  “Fee Inspector” means a person authorised by the executing agency 
concerned to collect fee in respect of any mechanical vehicle crossing a 
permanent bridge or using the National Highway Section and includes every 
Government employee posted on such bridge or National Highway Section in 
connection with the collection of fees;
 </section><section>
      
<number>f</number>  “Form A” means Form A appended to these rules;
 </section><section>
      
<number>g</number>  “Form B” means Form B appended to these rules;
 </section><section>
      
<number>h</number>  “Form C” means Form C appended to these rules;
 </section><section>
       
<number>i</number>  “Pay and Accounts Officer” means Pay and Accounts Officer (National 
Highway), Ministry of Surface Transport, New Delhi;
 
 

1[(j)  
“permanent bridge” means a bridge with permanent structure the cost of which 
includes the cost of bridge proper, approach roads, guide bunds and protective 
works, excluding the cost of toll booths which is more than rupees 25 lakh and 
upto rupees 100 lakh for each, completed and opened to traffic on or after first 
day of April, 1976 but before the first day of May, 1992 and thereafter all the 
bridges costing more than Rs. 100 lakh before the date of the publication of 
this notification in the Official Gazette and thereafter all the bridges costing 
more than Rs. 500 lakh on National Highway, which shall be notified separately 
for levy of fee collection;] and
 </section><section>
      
<number>k</number>  “National Highway Section” means continuous length of any national 
highway or by-pass which shall be notified for separately levy of fee 
collection;
 </section><section>
       
<number>l</number>  “Sectional Officer/Junior Engineer” means the officer of the State 
Public Works Department (Roads and Building) of any other department dealing 
with National Highway having that designation of equivalent and being incharge 
of a particular road of permanent bridge located on a national highway.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Rate of fee and its 
payment.—These 
shall be levied and paid to the executing agency, on behalf of the Government of 
India, fee on mechanical vehicles for the use of National Highway Section or 
permanent bridge or both at the rates notified by the Central Government, in the 
Official Gazette in respect of such National Highway Section or permanent bridge 
or both.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Displaying of rates 
of fees.—A 
table displaying rates of fees, rates authorised to be levied at any National 
Highway Section or permanent bridge or both shall be put up in a conspicuous 
place near the fee collection booths legibly written or printed in English, 
Hindi and the regional language of the area in which National Highway Section or 
permanent bridge or both are situated.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Procedure for 
collection.—All 
fees levied under these rules shall be collected by the executing agency 
concerned departmentally or through private contractors on the basis of 
competitive bidding on behalf of the Central Government.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Collection of fees 
departmentally.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The executing agency concerned shall make necessary arrangement for putting up 
adequate number of collection booths, operated manually or by automatic 
arrangement or by combination of both as may be considered suitable by the 
executing agency.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> There shall be posted 
a Fee Inspector, with necessary police guard to assist at either end of the 
National Highways Section or permanent bridge who shall be authorised to collect 
fee in respect of any mechanical vehicle using the National Highway Section or 
permanent bridge or both, at the rates notified by the Central Government 
separately.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> There shall be 
provided at either end of the National Highway Section or permanent bridge or 
both together, a cross bar for securing the stoppage of mechanical vehicles.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Fee Inspector 
shall ensure at the cross bar that passage is not allowed to mechanical vehicles 
unless the fee leviable in respect thereof has been paid.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Mode of collection 
of fee in case of departmental fee collection.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every driver, owner or person incharge of a mechanical vehicle shall, before 
crossing the National Highway Section or permanent bridge or having crossed it, 
stop his vehicle at the cross bar and pay the fee leviable in respect of the 
vehicles at the fee collection booths. The Fee Inspector shall in return, 
prepare a receipt in duplicate in Form A and hand over one copy of the receipt 
to the driver or owner or person incharge of the mechanical vehicle.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Toll collection shall 
be done only at one place within a distance of 80 kms. from a point at the 
beginning of first National Highway Section or approach of entry of the first 
permanent bridge to be crossed under the jurisdiction of the same executing 
agency, regardless of number of projects falling within the length in order to 
facilitate free and unhindered movement of traffic. Where it is not feasible to 
do so, the number of collection point shall be kept minimum and shall be decided 
with the approval of Central Government. The fee may be collected from the 
driver, owner or person incharge of a vehicle on the first National Highway 
Section or permanent bridge which is intended to be crossed by such vehicle. The 
driver, owner or person incharge of the vehicle holding the receipt of such 
payment shall be allowed to pass through other Sections and bridges of such 
Highway unhindered after showing the receipt to the Fee Inspector posted on 
other sections or bridges. Details of such Sections and bridges shall be 
displayed at a conspicuous place near the fees collection booths of the Sections 
or bridges covered under this sub-rule legibly written or printed in English, 
Hindi and the regional language of the area in which such sections or bridges 
are situated.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Fee Inspector 
shall on receipt of the fee notified by the Central Government fill up a receipt 
in duplicate in Form A and deliver one copy thereof to the driver, owner or the 
person incharge of the vehicle in respect of which the fee has been paid and 
retain the second copy for record.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> When the same vehicle 
has to cross the National Highway Section or bridge more than once in a day, the 
user shall have the option to pay one and a half times of rate notified by the 
Government while crossing such section or bridge in the first trip itself, or if 
the vehicle has to use the section or bridge frequently the vehicle owner can 
have a monthly pass on the payment of charges equal to 30 single rates.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Remittance of fee 
collection in case of departmental fee collection.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Fee Inspector on duty shall be responsible for the collection and safe 
custody of the amounts collected during his duty period. The Fee Inspector shall 
not leave the collection booth till his reliever takes over from him.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Fee Inspector 
shall maintain a cash register as prescribed in Form B and keep it posted upto 
date.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Fee Inspector 
shall at the end of the period of his duty hand over the amount collected by him 
to his reliever after obtaining the signature of the latter in the relevant 
column of the cash register.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every day between 
16.00 hours and 17.00 hours the Fee Inspector on duty shall hand over the entire 
amount of the fee collected during the preceding 24 hours to the Sectional 
Officer/Junior Engineer-in-charge of National Highway Section or permanent 
bridge after obtaining his signature in the relevant column of the cash 
register.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Sectional 
Officer/Junior Engineer-in-charge shall keep the amounts of collection received 
from the Fee Inspector in the chest provided for the purpose at his office.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The Sectional 
Officer/Junior Engineer-in-charge shall on every Saturday or if it happens to be 
a holiday, on the next working day, remit the amount received by him in respect 
of the week preceding the Saturday by a demand draft to the Pay and Accounts 
Officer. The Pay and Accounts Officer shall account the amounts so received in 
the relevant receipt head in his books.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The Sectional 
Officer/Junior Engineer-in-charge shall maintain a register as prescribed in 
Form C showing the remittance made to the Pay and Accounts Officer and shall 
keep the register posted up to date.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> The Sectional 
Officer/Junior Engineer-in-charge shall exercise supervision and control over 
the staff posted at the National Highway Section or permanent bridge in 
connection with the collection of the fees and maintain the proper accounts and 
records.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> The Sub-Divisional 
Officer, in-charge of the National Highway Section or the permanent bridge shall 
pay surprise visits at least twice a month at the Offices of the Fee Inspector 
or the Sectional Officer/Junior Engineer-in-charge to check that the collection 
and remittance of fees by the staff is being done in accordance with the 
provisions of these rules. He shall countersign the cash register and the other 
record maintained by the staff in token of such visit. Such visit, atleast once 
in three months shall also be made by the Executive Engineer of the State Public 
Works Department (Roads and Building) or by the officer of equivalent rank in 
any other department.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Fee collection 
through franchisee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In case the fee collection is to be done through the franchisee, the collection 
of fee and retaining such fee shall be auctioned under the instructions for 
specific periods as the Central Government may issue and the money shall be 
collected by the executing agency or his authorised representative as per the 
terms and conditions of the agreement executed for such purposes.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The mode of fee 
collection shall be decided by the franchisee referred to in sub-rule (1) with 
the approval of the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A table of fees 
authorised to be collected on any National Highway Section or permanent bridge 
shall be put up by such franchisee in a conspicuous place near a fee collection 
booth legibly written or printed in English, Hindi and the regional language of 
the area in which the national highway is situated.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The franchisee 
authorised to collect and retain the fee under these rules shall nominate an 
official as in charge of fee collection who shall be responsible to ensure that 
fees are collected at not more than the notified rates and the fee collection is 
smooth without causing hardship to the road users and for all other matters 
connected with the fee collection on National Highway Section or permanent 
bridge.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The name, address and 
telephone number if any, of such official incharge of fee collection shall be 
displayed at suitable and conspicuous locations.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The executing agency 
shall remit the auction money so collected from the franchisee by a demand draft 
to the Pay and Accounts Officer, National Highways, Ministry of Surface 
Transport, New Delhi. The Pay and Accounts Officer shall account the amount so 
received in the relevant receipt head in his books.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>10</number> Special conditions when 
sections or bridges built by Government are used for developing adjacent Build, 
Operate and Transfer Projects of private parties.—To improve the financial 
viability of a Build, Operate and Transfer Project as decided by the Competent 
Authority, the concessionaire may be allowed to collect and retain the fees so 
collected for the full concession period as agreed to in the specific agreement 
in respect of the facility offered to him under National Highways (Collection of 
Fee by any Person for the Use of Section of National Highways/Permanent 
Bridges/Temporary Bridges on National Highways) Rules, 1997 and the facility 
shall revert back to the Government at the end of concession period and the 
collection of fee thereafter shall be governed by these rules.
 National Highways 
Section/permanent bridges built under public funding programme and offered for 
developing further contiguous sections of such National Highway as decided by 
the Competent Authority shall revert back to the Government at the end of the 
concession period and the collection of fee thereafter shall be governed by 
these rules.</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Tenure of fee 
collection.—The 
fee shall be collected in perpetuity by the executing agency.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Submission of 
returns.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The executing agency concerned in case of departmental fee collection shall 
furnish returns in the first week of July, October, January and April of every 
year to the Pay and Accounts Officer containing—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> Monthwise consolidated 
statement showing the amount collected and remitted on account of fee proceeds 
in respect of each National Highway Section or permanent bridge alongwith the 
details of number and date of demand draft by which the amount has been 
remitted, and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> Monthwise break up of 
the expenditure incurred on each National Highway Section or permanent bridge by 
the executing agency required to be reimbursed on account of collection of the 
fees on the basis of actual expenditure incurred.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Executing Agency 
concerned in case of fee collection through franchisee shall furnish to the Pay 
and Accounts Officer, National Highways, Government of India, Ministry of 
Surface Transport, New Delhi or any other officer so authorised, the details 
regarding the franchise, the amount and the period for which the franchise has 
been awarded, immediately, after the auction for fee collection through such 
franchise.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Furnishing of 
security in case of departmental fees collection.—Every 
Fee Inspector or the Sectional Officer/Junior Engineer-in-charge shall deposit a 
cash security of not less than Rs. 1000 by executing a security bond in the 
prescribed form as laid down in the Treasury Rules with the concerned Executive 
Engineer or the concerned officer of equivalent rank in any other department.
 
 
</article><form>
 




tHE NATIONAL HIGHWAYS (FEES FOR THE USE OF  

NATIONAL HIGHWAYS SECTION AND PERMANENT  

BRIDGE—PUBLIC 
FUNDED PROJECT) RULES, 1997
 


 
 


FORM A
 


[See rule 7(1)]
 


R. No.
 


Receipt for payment of 
fee. 
 


Name of Section/Permanent 
Bridge.
 


1.  Description of 
mechanical vehicle with Registration number.
 


2.  Whether laden or 
unladen or with or without passengers.
 


3.  Time and date of 
outward journey.
 


4.  Name of driver 
and/or owner.
 


5.  Amount of fee 
paid.
 


 
 


 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>