<act> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese Ore 
Mines and Chrome Ore Mines Labour Welfare Cess Rules, 19781
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the Iron Ore Mines 

2[Manganese Ore Mines and Chrome Ore 
Mines] Labour Welfare Cess Rules, 1978.
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force 
on the 1st day of September, 1978.
  




</section></article> 
  
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese Ore 
Mines and Chrome Ore Mines Labour Welfare Cess Rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  ‘Act’ means the Iron Ore Mines
1[, 
Manganese Ore Mines and Chrome Ore Mines] Labour Welfare Cess Act, 1976 (55 of 
1976);
 
        2[(b)  
‘Cess Commissioner’ means the Iron Ore Mines
1[, 
Manganese Ore Mines and Chrome Ore Mines] Cess Commissioner specified under rule 
3, in whose jurisdiction a metallurgical factory or an iron ore mine or a 
manganese ore mine is located;]
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  ‘Form’ means a Form appended to these rules;
 </section><section>       <number>d</number>  ‘Fund’ means the Iron Ore Mines
1[, 
Manganese Ore Mines and Chrome Ore Mines] Labour Welfare Fund;
 </section><section>       <number>e</number>  ‘month’ means a month reckoned according to the 
British calendar;
 </section><section>        <number>f</number>  ‘section’ means a section of the Act;
  




</section></article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese Ore 
Mines and Chrome Ore Mines Labour Welfare Cess Rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>3</number> Assessing and collecting 
authority for duty of excise.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify such 
officers as it thinks fit, including a Welfare Commissioner, appointed under 
section 8 of the Iron Ore Mines 

1[, Manganese Ore Mines and Chrome Ore 
Mines] Labour Welfare Fund Act, 1976 (61 of 1976) to be Iron Ore Mines 

1[, Manganese Ore Mines and Chrome Ore 
Mines] Cess Commissioners and may assign to them such local limits as it may 
think fit.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Each Cess Commissioner shall 
be responsible for the assessment and collection of the duty of excise, levied 
under the Act, within the local limits assigned to him.
  



</section></article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese Ore 
Mines and Chrome Ore Mines Labour Welfare Cess Rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>4</number> Manner of assessment and 
collection.—The duty of excise levied 
under section 3 of iron ore 

1[, manganese ore and chrome ore] produced 
in any mine shall be assessed and collected in the manner specified in these 
rules.
  



</article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese Ore 
Mines and Chrome Ore Mines Labour Welfare Cess Rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>5</number> Maintenance of registers.—
<section><number>1</number>
<subsection><number>a</number> 
Every owner of an iron ore mine or manganese ore mine 

1[or chrome ore mine] shall maintain a 
register in regard to the production and disposal of iron ore, 

2[or manganese ore or, as the case may be, 
chrome ore], in Form A and shall record therein date-wise the production and 
disposal (including use by such owner in any metallurgical factory) of such ore 
and at the close of each month the entries made against each date in the 
register shall be totalled and the total production and disposal of iron ore


2[or manganese ore or, as the case may be, 
chrome ore] during the month shall be entered therein.
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> At the close of each month 
the duty of excise, levied under section 3, payable by the owner of the mine to 
the Central Government on the iron ore, 

2[or manganese ore or, as the case may be, 
chrome ore] used by such owner during the month, in any metallurgical factory 
shall be calculated and recorded in the register maintained under clause (a).
 Explanation.—In 
calculating the duty of excise payable, a fraction of less than half a tonne in 
the total of iron ore or manganese ore used during any month in any 
metallurgical factory shall be ignored and a fraction of half or more than half 
of a tonne shall be reckoned as one tonne.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> (a) Every person by whom iron 
one or manganese ore is sold or otherwise disposed of to the occupier of a 
metallurgical factory shall maintain a register of the receipt and disposal of 
iron ore 

2[or manganese ore or, as the case may be, 
chrome ore] in Form ‘B’ and shall record therein date-wise the receipt and 
disposal of such ore and at the close of each month the entries made against 
each date shall be totalled and the total receipt and disposal of iron ore,


2[or manganese ore or, as the case may be, 
chrome ore] during the month shall be entered therein.
 <subsection><number>b</number> At the close of each month 
the duty of excise as levied under section 3 and payable by such person under 
section 4 in relation to such ore to the occupier of any metallurgical factory 
on the iron ore, 

2[or manganese ore or, as the case may be, 
chrome ore] shall be calculated and recorded in the register itself along with 
the amount of duty actually paid.
 Explanation.—In 
calculating the duty of excise payable, a fraction of less than half a tonne in 
the total of iron ore or manganese ore sold or otherwise disposed of to the 
occupier of any metallurgical factory during the month shall be ignored and a 
fraction of a half or more than half a tonne shall be reckoned as one tonne.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> Every occupier of a 
metallurgical factory shall maintain a register in Form C regarding the receipt 
of iron ore, or, as the case may be, manganese ore and the amount of the duty of 
excise payable to him in relation to such ore under section 4 and shall record 
therein date-wise the quantity of iron ore, 

2[or manganese ore or, as the case may be, 
chrome ore], sold or otherwise disposed of to him and the amount of the duty of 
excise payable in relation to such ore and received by him and at the close of 
each month, the entries made against each date in the register shall be totalled 
and the total quantity of iron ore, 

2[or manganese ore or, as the case may be, 
chrome ore] sold or otherwise disposed of to him and the total amount of the 
duty of excise payable and received during the month shall be entered therein.
  




</section></article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese Ore 
Mines and Chrome Ore Mines Labour Welfare Cess Rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>6</number> Submission of returns.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every occupier of a metallurgical factory shall submit to the Cess Commissioner 
in duplicate, a return for each month in Form D separately for each person who 
sold or otherwise disposed of to such occupier iron ore or manganese ore 

1[or chrome ore] during the month, in 
relation to the iron ore, 

2[or manganese ore or, as the case may be, 
chrome ore] so sold or otherwise disposed of to him, and the duty of excise 
payable and received by him, duly signed by him or any other person authorised 
by him in this behalf, so as to reach the Cess Commissioner not later than the 
last day of the month following the month to which the return pertains and such 
return shall be accompanied with letter quoting cheque/Demand Draft No. and date 
and No. and date of covering letter with which cheque/Demand Draft was forwarded 
showing that the duty of excise payable has been deposited as required by rule 
10.
 

3[(1A) Every owner of an iron ore mine or 
a manganese ore 

1[or chrome ore] mine, besides maintaining 
a register in Form A as provided in rule 5, shall submit return in the same form 
to the Cess Commissioner every month, not later than the last day of the month 
following the month to which the return relates.
 </section><section><number>1B</number> Every person by whom iron 
ore or manganese ore 

1[or chrome ore] is sold or otherwise 
disposed of to the occupier of a metallurgical factory, besides maintaining a 
register in Form B, as provided in rule 5, shall submit to the Cess Commissioner 
having jurisdiction over the area in which the metallurgical factory is located, 
a return in the same form, every month not later than the last day of the month 
to which the return relates.
 <subsection><number>IC</number> (i) Where the metallurgical 
factory or the mine of the iron ore or the manganese ore 

1[or chrome ore] to which a return in Form 
D relates are located within the jurisdiction of the same Cess Commissioner, he 
shall on receipt of the return in Form D verify its contents with those of the 
returns in Form A and B received by him.
 <subsubsection><number>ii</number> Where the metallurgical 
factory or the mine of the iron ore or manganese ore 

1[or chrome ore] to which a return in Form 
D relates are located within the jurisdiction of different Cess Commissioner, 
the Cess Commissioner on receipt of the return in Form D shall—
 <subsubsubsection>       <number>a</number>  verify its contents with those of the return in 
Form B received by him under rule (1B), relating to the sale or disposal of the 
iron ore or manganese ore
1[or 
chrome ore]; and
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>       <number>b</number>  send a copy of the return to the Cess 
Commissioner in whose jurisdiction the iron ore mine or the manganese ore mine
1[or 
chrome ore mine] to which the return relates is located, for verification.
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection></section><section><number>1D</number> The Cess Commissioner on 
receiving the copy of the return shall verify its contents with those of the 
returns in Form A received by him and shall return the copy of the said return 
duly verified to the Cess Commissioner from whom he received it.
 </section><section><number>1E</number> Where a Cess Commissioner 
receives any return which according to these rules relates to the jurisdiction 
of any other Cess Commissioner, he shall keep a copy of the return on his record 
and send the return to the Cess Commissioner having jurisdiction.]
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where during any month no 
iron ore or manganese ore was sold or otherwise disposed of to the occupier of a 
metallurgical factory, and for that reason no duty of excise received, such 
occupier shall submit to the Cess Commissioner, in duplicate, a nil return for 
that month, in the manner provided in sub-rule (1), accompanied by a declaration 
stating that no iron ore or manganese ore was sold or otherwise disposed of to 
him and no excise duty received by him, duly signed by him or any other person 
duly authorised by him in this behalf, so as to reach the Cess Commissioner not 
later than the last day of the month following the month to which the return 
pertains.
 </section><section><number>3</number> (a) Notwithstanding anything 
contained in sub-rule (1) or in sub-rule (2), if the Cess Commissioner is 
satisfied with respect to the occupier of any metallurgical factory that no iron 
ore, 

4[or manganese ore or, as the case may be, 
chrome ore], or duty of excise was received by such occupier during the 
preceding twelve months he may, by order in writing, allow such occupier to 
submit for any succeeding period, in the place of the monthly return, a 
consolidated return in Form D for such period not exceeding one year as may be 
prescribed in the order;
 <subsection><number>b</number> Where the occupier of a 
metallurgical factory is allowed to submit a consolidated return, such return 
shall be submitted so as to reach the Cess Commissioner not later than the last 
day of the month immediately following the expiry of the period in relation to 
which it is being submitted.
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number> Every return under this rule 
shall be sent by registered post with acknowledgment due.
  






</section></article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese Ore 
Mines and Chrome Ore Mines Labour Welfare Cess Rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>7</number> Submission of annual 
accounts and verification of returns and accounts.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every occupier of a metallurgical factory shall submit to the Cess Commissioner 
a copy of the annual account of the factory along with a copy each of the profit 
and loss account and balance sheet duly authenticated by their auditors as soon 
as may be after the actual accounts are closed and audited every year.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Cess Commissioner may 
depute an officer for the purpose of the verification of the correctness and 
completeness of the monthly return or annual accounts with reference to the 
books of account, and other books and records maintained by the occupier of the 
metallurgical factory and the officer so deputed shall be afforded by the 
occupier and the manager and other employees of the metallurgical factory in 
connection with the verification of the correctness and completeness of such 
return or accounts.
 </section><section><number>3</number> In particular, and without 
prejudice to the generality of the provisions contained in sub-rule (2), the 
officer deputed under that sub-rule may request the occupier or manager of the 
metallurgical factory to produce before him such books of accounts and other 
books and records as he deems necessary for the verification of the monthly 
return or annual accounts and such occupier or manager shall produce, within the 
time specified by such officer, such accounts, returns and records.
  
</section></article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese Ore 
Mines and Chrome Ore Mines Labour Welfare Cess Rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>8</number> Late returns and revision 
of returns.—If the occupier of any 
metallurgical factory has not furnished the return under rule 6 before the 
expiry of the date specified in that rule or having furnished it before the 
expiry of the date discovers any omission or wrong statement therein, he may 
furnish the return or a revised return, as the case may be, at any time before 
the order of final assessment is made under rule 11.
  
</article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese Ore 
Mines and Chrome Ore Mines Labour Welfare Cess Rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>9</number> Period for payment of duty 
of excise.—
<section><number>1</number> 
<subsection><number>a</number> The amount of 
excise duty payable by a person who sells or otherwise disposes of iron ore or 
manganese ore 

1[or chrome or] to the occupier of any 
metallurgical factory under clause (a) of sub-section (2) of section 4 shall be 
paid by him to the occupier concerned immediately after the despatch of the ore 
or shall be allowed to be deducted from his bill of payment.
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> Any person who sells or 
otherwise disposes of to the occupier of a metallurgical factory and without 
reasonable excuse fails to pay the duty of excise within the period specified in 
clause (a) in that behalf shall be punishable with fine which may extend to five 
hundred rupees.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The amount of excise duty 
payable by the owner of a mine, where the iron ore or the manganese ore 

1[or chrome ore] is used by such owner in 
any metallurgical factory under clause (b) of sub-section (2) of section 4 of 
the Act shall be paid by him by sending crossed cheque/crossed demand draft to 
the Cess Commissioner concerned drawn in his favour and payable at the station 
at which the Cess Commissioner is stationed, not later than the last day of the 
month following the month in which the iron ore or the manganese ore was used in 
the metallurgical factory.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The amount of excise duty 
payable by the occupier of any metallurgical factory under sub-section (3) of 
section 4 shall be paid by him by sending crossed cheque/crossed demand draft to 
the Cess Commissioner drawn in his favour and payable at the station at which 
the Cess Commissioner is stationed within a period of fifteen days of the 
realisation of the amount.
  



</section></article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese Ore 
Mines and Chrome Ore Mines Labour Welfare Cess Rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>10</number> Manner of payment of duty.—The 
payment of duty of excise by the owner of a mine under sub-rule (2) of rule 9 or 
the amount collected by the occupier of metallurgical factory under sub-rule (3) 
of that rule shall be made by sending a crossed cheque/crossed demand draft 
along with a challan duly filled in indicating the Head of Account as 

1[0038] Union Excise Duties-D-Cesses on 
Commodities—Iron Ore/Manganese Ore” creditable to the account of P.A.O. (Main 
Sectt.) Ministry of Labour, New Delhi, to the Cess Commissioner drawn in his 
favour and payable at the station at which he is stationed.
  



</article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese Ore 
Mines and Chrome Ore Mines Labour Welfare Cess Rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>11</number> Final assessment of the 
amount payable by occupier of metallurgical factory.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If, on the basis of the information available from the return in Form D or any 
other information which has come into his possession, the Cess Commissioner has 
reason to believe that any amount of the duty of excise payable by the occupier 
of a metallurgical factory has not been paid by him in the manner provided in 
those rules, he shall, after giving such occupier a reasonable opportunity of 
being heard by the issue of notice in Form ‘E’ assess the amount of duty of 
excise remaining unpaid and shall issue to him a Demand Notice in Form ‘F’ 
requiring the payment of such duty of excise within the time specified therein.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The manner of payment of the 
amount payable under sub-rule (1) shall be same as laid down in rule 10 and the 
crossed cheque/crossed demand draft sent to the Commissioner shall be 
accompanied by a covering letter quoting reference to the Demand Notice.
  
</section></article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese Ore 
Mines and Chrome Ore Mines Labour Welfare Cess Rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>12</number> Review.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The occupier of a metallurgical factory to whom a Demand Notice has been issued 
under sub-rule (1) of rule 11 may, within thirty days from the date of the 
service of such notice on him, apply to the Cess Commissioner for a review of 
the assessment in pursuance of which the Demand Notice has been issued to him:
 Provided that no such application 
for review shall lie unless the amount shown in the Demand Notice has been 
deposited in the manner referred to in sub-rule (2) of rule 11.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every application for review 
shall be accompanied by a memorandum setting forth clearly the principal grounds 
of objections against the assessment made quoting the number and date of crossed 
cheque/demand draft and number and date of letter with which it was forwarded to 
the Commissioner showing that the amount assessed has been paid.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Cess Commissioner on a 
perusal of the application and memorandum submitted by the applicant and the 
records of the case shall,—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  if he is satisfied that the assessment should 
not have been made or should have been made only for a lesser amount, annul the 
assessment or, as the case may be, reduce the amount of the duty of excise 
assessed;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  if he is not so satisfied, confirm the 
assessment provided that no order confirming the assessment shall be made unless 
the applicant has been given an opportunity of being heard.
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number> The Cess Commissioner shall 
record his reasons for his decision in the order under sub-rule (3) and the 
applicant shall be supplied with a copy of the order, as soon as may be after it 
is made, free of cost.
 </section><section><number>5</number> Where the Cess Commissioner 
annuls the order of assessment or reduces the amount of the duty of excise 
assessed, the duty of excise or, as the case may be, the excess of the duty of 
excise, paid by the occupier shall be either refunded to such occupier or 
adjusted towards any amount payable by him under the Act, as the Cess 
Commissioner may direct.
 </section><section><number>6</number> Any refund under sub-rule (5) 
shall be made by the Cess Commissioner by crossed cheque or demand draft by 
drawing the amount from the Pay and Accounts Office on an ordinary contingent 
bill on which shall be specified the review case number and date of review order 
and the amount and date of challan with which the deposit was made by him in the 
branch of 

1[accredited bank of the Ministry of 
Labour, New Delhi.]
  



</section></article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese Ore 
Mines and Chrome Ore Mines Labour Welfare Cess Rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>13</number> Refund and recovery of 
duty of customs.—Refund of the duty of 
customs erroneously levied or paid and recovery of duty of customs short levied 
or erroneously refunded shall so far as may be, made in accordance with the 
provisions of the Customs Act, 1962 (52 of 1962), and the rules made thereunder, 
relating to refund, remission and recovery of customs duties under that Act.
  
</article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese Ore 
Mines and Chrome Ore Mines Labour Welfare Cess Rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>14</number> Refunds, Remissions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If any occupier of a metallurgical factory has reason to believe that he has by 
any mistake paid any amount in excess of the duty of excise payable by him, he 
may submit a claim to the Cess Commissioner for the refund of such excess duty 
supported by relevant documents.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Claims for refund under 
sub-rule (1) shall be submitted within two years from the date of sending the 
crossed cheque/crossed demand draft to the Cess Commissioner in respect of the 
refundable amount.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where it is proved to the 
satisfaction of the Cess Commissioner that the duty of excise has been paid in 
excess by mistake, he may order refund to the occupier of the metallurgical 
factory an amount equal to the amount found to have been paid in excess.
  
</section></article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese Ore 
Mines and Chrome Ore Mines Labour Welfare Cess Rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>15</number> Authority for imposition 
of penalty for non-payment of duty of excise.—Penalty 
under section 8 shall be imposed by the Cess Commissioner.
  
</article> 
 The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese Ore 
Mines and Chrome Ore Mines Labour Welfare Cess Rules, 1978
  
 <article><number>16</number> Records of collection.—
<section><number>1</number> 
For the proper accounting of the duty of excise collected under these rules, the 
Cess Commissioner shall maintain records to show the following particulars along 
with any other particulars required:
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  assessment and collection of the duty of excise;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  particulars of petitions and orders thereon;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  refunds.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> All the papers relating to 
the assessment of the duty of excise in respect of the owner of any 
metallurgical factory shall be kept together and shall form an assessment case 
record.
  
</section></article><form>
 

The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese Ore 
Mines and Chrome Ore Mines Labour Welfare Cess Rules, 1978
 

 
 

Form E
 

(See rule 11)
 

Notice to occupier 
of Metallurgical Factory
 

To
 

............................
 

............................
 

(Name and address of occupier)
 

Whereas it has come to my notice that you have not paid the 
duty of excise realised by you as per details given below as required under rule 
9 of the Iron Ore,
1[Manganese 
Ore Mines and Chrome Ore Mines] Labour Welfare Cess Rules, 1978, and you have 
failed to furnish the return in Form ‘D’ under rule 6 of the said rules.
 

You are hereby directed to show cause within thirty days of 
the date of this letter why you may not be required to remit the said amount(s) 
by crossed cheque/crossed demand draft in support whereof you shall produce all 
the relevant documents.
 

In the event of your failure to comply with this notice, I 
shall proceed to assess the duty of excise to the best of my judgment under rule 
11 of the Iron Ore Mines
1[Manganese 
Ore Mines and Chrome Ore Mines] Labour Welfare Cess Rules, 1978.
 

Particulars about duty of excise not paid:
 


...........................................................................................................................
 


...........................................................................................................................
 

Commissioner
 

                                    
Seal of the Commissioner
 

Number............
 

Date............
 

Place............
 

 
 

 —————
 

   1.  Subs. by G.S.R. 533(E), dated 28th June, 1983 (w.e.f. 
1-7-1983).
 

 
</form><form>
 

The Iron Ore Mines, Manganese Ore 
Mines and Chrome Ore Mines Labour Welfare Cess Rules, 1978
 

 
 

Form F
 

(See rule 11)
 

Demand Notice to 
occupier of Metallurgical Factory
 

To
 

..............................
 

..............................
 

(Name and address of occupier).
 

In continuation of the notice in Form ‘E’ issued to you per 
registered post on the...............day of..............20......and after 
taking into account the objection received from you (strike out if not 
applicable), you are hereby informed that an amount of Rs................. 
(Rupees.........................) only is payable by you being the duty of 
excise realised during the month(s) of...............20........
 

2. You are hereby directed to pay the sum of Rs........... 
(Rupees...................) only as detailed below by sending crossed cheque/crossed 
demand draft to..........drawn in his favour and payable at....(station) with 
the covering letter quoting reference of the Demand Notices failing which the 
said sum of Rs........... (Rupees..................) only will be recoverable 
from you as an arrear of land revenue.
 

Details of assessed amount............................
 

         1.  Amount of Cess payable Rs.............
 

         2.  Deduct amount already paid by you as per 
crossed cheque/crossed demand draft Number.............date........
 

         3.  Net amount payable Rs..............
 


Commissioner
 

                                    
Seal of Commissioner
 

Number.............
 

Date....................
 

Place..................
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>