<act> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title, 
application and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These Rules may be called the Mines Rescue Rules, 1985.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall apply to 
belowground mines.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> They shall come into 
force on the 2nd April, 1985.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless there is anything repugnant to the subject or context,—
 <section>
         <number>a</number>  “Act” means the Mines Act, 
1952;
 </section><section>
         <number>b</number>  “belowground mine” means any 
excavation which extends below superjacent ground;
 </section><section>
         <number>c</number>  “Board of Mining Examination” 
means the Board of Mining Examinations constituted under the Coal Mines 
Regulations, 1957 or the Metalliferous Mines Regulation, 1961, as the case may 
be;
 </section><section>
         <number>d</number>  “Chief Inspector” means the 
Chief Inspector of Mines appointed under section 5 of the Act;
 </section><section>
         <number>e</number>  “Foreman’s Certificate” means 
the foreman’s certificate granted by the Board of Mining Examination;
 </section><section>
         <number>f</number>  “Inspector” means an Inspector 
of Mines appointed under the Act, and includes a district magistrate when 
exercising any power or performing any duty of an Inspector which he is 
empowered by the Act to exercise or perform;
 </section><section>
         <number>g</number>  “Instructor” means a person 
appointed as such under sub-rule (2) of rule 3;
 </section><section>
         <number>h</number>  “Manager” means a person 
appointed under section 17 of the Act;
 </section><section>
          <number>i</number>  “Manager’s Certificate” means 
the manager’s certificate granted by the Board of Mining Examinations;
 </section><section>
          <number>j</number>  “Ordinarily employed” with 
reference to any mine or part thereof means the average number of persons 
employed per day in the mine or part of mine during the preceding calendar year 
(obtained by dividing the number of man-days worked by the number of working 
days excluding rest days and other non-working days);
 </section><section>
         <number>k</number>  “Overman’s Certificate” means 
the overman’s certificate granted by the Board of Mining Examinations;
 </section><section>
          <number>l</number>  “Owner” means a person who is 
the immediate proprietor or lessees/or occupier of the mine or of any part 
thereof and in the case of a mine the business whereof is being carried on by a 
liquidator or receiver, such liquidator or receiver but does not include a 
person who merely receives a royalty, rent or fine from the mine, or is merely 
the proprietor of the mine, subject to any lease; grant or licence for working 
thereof, or is merely the owner of the soil and not interested in the minerals 
of the mine; but any contractor or sub-lessee for the working of a mine or part 
thereof shall be subject to the Act in like manner as if he were an owner, but 
not so as to exempt the owner from any liability;
 </section><section>
        <number>m</number>  “Principal Official” means the 
senior-most mine official in mining discipline on duty in the mine;
 </section><section>
         <number>n</number>  “Qualified medical 
practitioner” means a medical practitioner who possess any recognised medical 
qualification as defined in clause (h) of section 2 of the Indian Medical 
Council Act, 1956 and who is enrolled on a State medical register as defined in 
clause (k) of that section;
 </section><section>
         <number>o</number>  “rescue room” means a rescue 
room as established and maintained under rules;
 </section><section>
         <number>p</number>  “rescue station” means a rescue 
station established and maintained under rule 3;
 </section><section>
         <number>q</number>  “rescue trained person” means a 
person certified by the Superintendent to be rescue trained person under 
sub-rule (1) of rule 21;
 </section><section>
         <number>r</number>  “Schedule” means a Schedule 
appened to these rules;
 </section><section>
         <number>s</number>  “Superintendent” means a 
superintendent of rescue station appointed under sub-rule (2) of rule 3.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Establishment and 
location of rescue station.— 

<section><number>1</number> The Chief Inspector may permit or require the owner of a belowground mine or 
a group of belowground mines to establish and maintain rescue station/stations 
with such designs and specifications and at such place/places as may be 
considered necessary in consultation with the owner:
 
Provided that where there 
are belowground mines belonging to more than one owner, the Chief Inspector may 
permit or require two or more owners to jointly establish a common rescue 
station:
 
Provided further that all 
the existing rescue stations as on the date of coming into force of these rules, 
shall continue to function for a period of three years from that date.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> At every rescue 
station there shall be appointed one Superintendent and at least two instructors 
and also, there shall be maintained a rescue brigade of not less than eighteen 
rescue trained persons.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In case where the 
absence of the Superintendent at a rescue station exceeds 60 days, the owner 
shall appoint another Superintendent.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The owner shall, 
within seven days from the date of assumption of relinquishment of charge by the 
Superintendent, inform the Chief Inspector and the Inspector incharge of the 
region where the mine is situated (hereinafter referred to as Regional 
Inspector) in Form I.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Functions of rescue 
stations.—The 
functions of rescue station shall include—
 <section>
          <number>i</number> imparting initial training in 
rescue and recovery work;
 </section><section>
         <number>ii</number> imparting refresher training to 
rescue trained persons;
 </section><section>
         <number>iii</number> providing support by its own 
rescue teams and equipment in case of major accidents or long-lasting rescue and 
recovery operations; and
 </section><section>
        <number>iv</number> carrying out the functions of 
rescue room in respect of these belowground mines where there is no rescue room.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Establishment and 
location of rescue rooms.—
<section><number>1</number> 
At every belowground mine where, more than 100 persons are ordinarily employed 
belowground and there is no rescue station within its radius of 35 kms the owner 
shall establish and maintain on surface close to mine entrance a rescue room:
 
Provided that it may be 
sufficient to provide one rescue room for a number of mines belonging to the 
same owner where—
 <subsection>
         <number>a</number>  the total number of persons 
ordinarily employed in belowground workings of all such mines does not exceed 
5000; and
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>b</number>  The mines are situated within 
radius of 35 kms. from and connected by road with the rescue room:
 
Provided further that the 
Chief Inspector may permit the owner of a group of mines having the total number 
of persons ordinarily employed belowground in excess of 5000, to use the rescue 
room as a rescue station excepting the functions of imparting initial training 
in rescue work, if such rescue room is—
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>a</number>  equipped with requisite 
additional rescue apparatus including at least 15 extra sets of two-hours 
self-contained breathing apparatus; and
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>b</number>  placed under the charge of a 
person holding the qualifications prescribed under rule 8 and a minimum of five 
rescue trained persons of whom at least one shall hold the qualifications 
prescribed under rule 10, are posted thereat.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-rule (1), in the case of belowground coal mines having 
a fiery seam or gassy seam of second or third degree, the Chief Inspector may, 
for reasons to be recorded in writing require the owner to establish and 
maintain a rescue room irrespective of the number of persons ordinarily employed 
belowground therein.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> At each rescue room, 
there shall be appointed such number of rescue trained persons as may be 
necessary and one of them possessing the qualifications specified in rule 10 
shall be made incharge of the rescue room. At least one rescue trained person 
shall always be in attendance at the rescue room.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Functions of rescue 
room.—A rescue 
room shall provide facilities for the storage, assembly, testing and adjustments 
of breathing apparatus and other rescue equipments and apparatus and for their 
speedy transport to mines.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Qualifications, 
experience etc. of Superintendent.—After 
coming into force of these rules, no person shall be appointed as Superintendent 
unless he—
 <section>
          <number>i</number>  is a rescue trained person;
 </section><section>
         <number>ii</number>  has 5 years practical 
experience of belowground work in mines; and
 </section><section>
         <number>iii</number>  holds a First Class Manager’s 
Certificate of a type not restricted to opencast workings.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Qualifications, 
experience etc., of Instructors.—After 
the coming into force of these rules no person shall be appointed as Instructor 
unless he—
 <section>
          <number>i</number>  is a rescue trained person;
 </section><section>
         <number>ii</number>  has 3 years’ practical 
experience of belowground work in mines; and 
 </section><section>
         <number>iii</number>  holds a Manager’s certificate 
of a type not restricted to opencast workings.
</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Selection of rescue 
trained persons for posting rescue stations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
After coming into force of these rules, the rescue trained persons for posting 
at a rescue station shall be selected, from amongst the rescue trained persons 
employed in mines served by the rescue station, by the Superintendent in 
consultation with the managers of such mines.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A person selected 
under sub-rule (1) shall be posted for not less than one year and not more than 
three years at a rescue station at any one time.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Qualifications, 
experience etc. of rescue room Incharge.— 
No person shall be appointed as rescue room incharge unless he—
 <section>
          <number>i</number>  is a rescue trained person;
 </section><section>
         <number>ii</number>  has 3 years practical 
experience of belowground work in mines; and
 </section><section>
         <number>iii</number>  holds a Manager’s, Overman’s 
or Foreman’s Certificate of a type not restricted to opencast workings.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Equipment.—
<section><number>1</number> 
At every rescue station there shall be provided and maintained for immediate 
use, apparatus and equipment as specified in Schedule I.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> At every rescue room 
there shall be provided and maintained for immediate use, apparatus and 
equipment as specified in Schedule II.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> At a belowground mine, 
where no rescue room is located, apparatus and equipment as specified in 
Schedule III, shall be maintained at the entrance of the mine.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Self-contained 
breathing apparatus provided at a rescue station and that at rescue rooms under 
it shall be of the same type and make.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The following 
apparatus and equipments provided in pursuance of sub-rules (1), (2) and (3), 
shall be of a type or standard approved by the Chief Inspector, namely:—
 <subsection>
         <number>a</number>  breathing apparatus;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>b</number>  smoke helmets and apparatus 
serving the same purpose;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>c</number>  reviving apparatus;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>d</number>  electric safety lamps and flame 
safety lamps;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>e</number>  gas detectors; and
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>f</number>  self-rescuers. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>6</number> All breathing 
apparatus and every flow meter shall be adjusted and tested and the purity of 
oxygen for use in breathing apparatus shall be tested in such manners as are 
laid down in Schedule IV.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> In case of an accident 
in a belowground mine arising out of the use of any rescue apparatus a written 
report thereof shall be sent, within 24 hours of such accident, by the manager 
of the mine to the Chief Inspector and Regional Inspector in Form II appended to 
Mines Rules.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> In case of an accident 
in a rescue station or rescue room arising out of the use of any rescue 
apparatus, a written report thereof shall be sent, within 24 hours of such 
accident, by the Superintendent to the Chief Inspector and Regional Inspector in 
Form II aforesaid.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> No absorbent charges, 
chemicals, self-rescuer and gas detector tubes shall be kept at a rescue 
station, rescue room or belowground mine for use beyond the expiry date, which 
shall be legibly marked on the boxes thereof.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Duties and 
responsibilities of Superintendent.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Superintendent shall be in overall control of the rescue station and the 
rescue rooms served by such rescue station.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Superintendent 
shall ensure that all the rescue equipments and apparatus kept at the rescue 
station, rescue rooms and at the entrance of the belowground mines under his 
control are—
 <subsection>
         <number>a</number>  maintained in perfect working 
order;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>b</number>  inspected by Instructors at 
specified intervals; and
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>c</number>  tests are conducted and 
adjustments are made.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The Superintendent 
shall ensure that adequate stock of spare parts and supplies are kept for 
maintaining rescue equipment and apparatus in perfect working order.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Superintendent 
shall countersign the records maintained under sub-rule (1) of rule 13.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Superintendent 
shall ensure that persons selected for initial training and those undergoing 
refresher training receive the prescribed course of instructions and practices 
and are issued the certificates for the same.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The Superintendent 
shall make periodical inspection of rescue rooms and the apparatus and 
equipments under his control.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> In the event of an 
emergency at a belowground mine, Superintendent shall perform such rescue and 
recovery work as may be assigned to him by the manager or in his absence by the 
principal official present at the surface. He shall within three days of 
completion of the rescue or recovery work send a report thereof to the Regional 
Inspector or the Chief Inspector.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> The Superintendent 
shall maintain in a bound paged book a diary and shall record therein the 
results of each of his inspections and also the action taken by him to rectify 
the defects observed during inspection.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> The Superintendent 
shall submit to the Chief Inspector and to the Regional Inspector detailed 
report on the functioning of the rescue station and rescue rooms under his 
control in the preceding year on or before the 20th day of February of the 
succeeding year with particular reference to—
 <subsection>
         <number>a</number>  type and number of equipment 
and apparatus provided and maintained;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>b</number>  Superintendent, instructors, 
rescue room incharge and rescue brigades in position, as on the 31st December;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>c</number>  number of rescue trained 
persons at each belowground mine served by the rescue station and number of such 
persons given refresher practices and medically examined, with results thereof;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>d</number>  particulars of emergencies 
attended;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>e</number>  any other relevant matter.
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Duties of Instructors.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Under the direction of Superintendent the Instructor shall—
 <subsection>
         <number>a</number>  impart course of instructions 
and practices to persons selected for training in rescue and recovery work as 
well as to rescue trained persons and maintain a record thereof; and
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>b</number>  make inspection, test and 
adjustment of rescue equipment and apparatus and maintain a record thereof.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> In the event of an 
emergency at a belowground mine, Instructors shall perform such rescue and 
recovery work as may be assigned to him by the manager or in his absence by the 
principal official present at the surface.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Instructor shall not 
leave the rescue station without prior permission of the Superintendent.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> In the absence of the 
Superintendent, the instructor shall be incharge of the rescue station.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Duties and 
responsibilities of rescue room incharge.— 
Every rescue room incharge shall—
 <section>
         <number>a</number>  display prominently a list of 
mines served by his rescue room;
 </section><section>
         <number>b</number>  maintain the equipment and 
apparatus kept at the rescue room in perfect order;
 </section><section>
         <number>c</number>  maintain a proper record of all 
rescue equipment and apparatus kept at the rescue room and inspection thereof; 
and
 </section><section>
         <number>d</number>  not allow any unauthorised 
person to enter into, or permit any unauthorised person to take out any 
apparatus or equipment from the rescue room.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Duties of rescue 
trained persons posted at rescue station.—The 
rescue trained persons shall—
 <section>
         <number>a</number>  obey order of the 
Superintendent and Instructor and assist them in discharge of their functions;
 </section><section>
         <number>b</number>  attend to messages, telephone 
calls and wireless and maintain record thereof;
 </section><section>
         <number>c</number>  maintain the rescue station in 
neat and tide condition;
 </section><section>
         <number>d</number>  maintain the equipment and 
apparatus kept at the rescue station in perfect order;
 </section><section>
         <number>e</number>  perform rescue and recovery 
work in mines; and 
 </section><section>
         <number>f</number>  not leave rescue station 
without obtaining permission from the Superintendent.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Duties of rescue room 
attendant.— 
Every rescue room attendant shall—
 <section>
         <number>a</number>  not leave the rescue room until 
relieved by a substitute;
 </section><section>
         <number>b</number>  not allow any unauthorised 
person to enter in or to take out any apparatus or equipment from the rescue 
room;
 </section><section>
         <number>c</number>  attend to telephone calls and 
maintain a record thereof;
 </section><section>
         <number>d</number>  maintain the rescue room in 
neat and tide condition; and
 </section><section>
         <number>e</number>  obey orders of the rescue room 
incharge and assist him in discharge of his functions.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Telephone 
communication.—Every 
mine shall be connected telephonically with the rescue room and rescue station 
serving the mine. Wherever practicable wireless communication shall also be 
provided:
 
Provided that where there 
is no telephonic communication system, the Chief Inspector may by an order in 
writing and subject to such conditions as he may specify therein, approve any 
other means of communication.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Rescue tracings.— 
There shall be kept at a belowground mine, more than three legible tracings of 
the working of the mine upto a date not before three preceding months. The 
tracing shall show the system of ventilation in the mine, and in particular, the 
general direction of air current, every point where the quantity of air is 
measured, every air-crossing, ventilation-door stopping, booster fan and any 
other principal device for regulation and distribution of air, fire-dams, 
preparatory stoppings, every fire-fighting equipment, every water-dam with 
dimensions and other particulars of construction, every pumping, telephone and 
ambulance station, every room used for storing inflammable material, reserve 
stations and every haulage and travelling roadway. The signs specified in 
Schedule V shall be used in the said tracings.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Appointment of rescue 
trained persons in mines, their disposition and accommodation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The manager of a belowground mine, where more than 100 persons are ordinarily 
employed belowground, shall ensure that at least 5 rescue trained persons are 
readily available at surface at any time.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The manager of a 
belowground mine, where more than 500 persons are ordinarily employed 
belowground shall also ensure that persons on a scale of one man for every 100 
persons or part thereof are rescue trained persons.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall be the 
responsibility of the owner to provide suitable accommodation—
 <subsection>
          <number>i</number>  close to the rescue station to 
the Superintendent, Instructors and members of rescue brigade;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>ii</number>  close to the rescue room to 
rescue room incharge rescue trained persons and attendants attached to it; and
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>iii</number>  close to belowground mine 
entrance to rescue trained persons other than those specified in (i) and (ii).
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> There shall be 
provided at a blowground mine effective bell or other arrangements, as may be 
approved by the Regional Inspector, for immediate summoning of rescue trained 
persons.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Selection of persons 
for training in rescue.—No 
person shall be selected for training in rescue work, unless—
 <section>
          <number>i</number>  he is between 21 and 30 years 
of age and holds a valid First-aid Certificate of the standard of the St. John 
Ambulance Association (India);
 </section><section>
         <number>ii</number>  he is certified by the Manager 
that he has sufficient underground experience for the purpose of rescue work;
 </section><section>
         <number>iii</number>  he is certified by a 
qualified medical practitioner, as may be designated by the Manager after 
examination in accordance with Schedule VI, to be free from any organic disease 
or weakness and to be fit for undertaking rescue work; and
 </section><section>
        <number>iv</number>  he is considered by the 
Superintendent of Rescue Station, after such examination and interview as he 
considers necessary, to be suitable for rescue work with breathing apparatus.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
  
 <article><number>21</number> Instructions and practices 
etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every person selected for training in rescue work shall undergo the course of 
instructions and practices as set out in Part I of Schedule VII until he has 
passed and has been certified as efficient by the Superintendent.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Rescue trained person shall 
undergo practices and receive instructions as set out in Part II of Schedule 
VII.
 </section><section><number>3</number> A record shall be kept at 
every rescue station of all persons undergoing practices and receiving 
instructions. Such record shall contain—
 <subsection>          
<number>i</number>  the date and the character of each practice;
 </subsection><subsection>         
<number>ii</number>  the conditions of each person after the practice, and if anything 
abnormal was observed in his condition, whether it was due to a defect of the 
apparatus or to that person; and
 </subsection><subsection>         
<number>iii</number>  any other relevant information.
  </subsection></section></article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Medical examination
etc. of rescue trained person.—Every 
rescue trained person shall be re-examined once at least in every twelve months 
by a qualified medical practitioner as may be designated by the manager in 
accordance with Schedule VI , and in case he is declared medically unfit, he 
shall cease to be a rescue trained person with effect from the date he has been 
so declared.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Suspension of rescue 
trained persons.—If 
in the opinion of the owner, agent, manager or an Inspector a rescue trained 
person is incompetent or is guilty of negligence or misconduct in the 
performance of his duties, the owner, agent, manager or Inspector as the case 
may be, may after giving such person an opportunity to give a written expla-nation, 
suspend him from or debar him for, undertaking any rescue and recovery work.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>24</number> Duties of Manager etc. 
in emergency.—
<section><number>1</number> 
On receiving information of any emergency likely to require the services of a 
rescue team, the manager, or in his absence the principal official present at 
the surface, shall immediately—
 <subsection>
         <number>a</number>  inform the rescue room or the 
rescue station serving the mine for necessary assistance;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>b</number>  summon rescue trained person 
employed in the mine;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>c</number>  inform the owner, agent or 
manager of nearby mines to make available the services of rescue trained persons 
employed therein; if so required;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>d</number>  inform the rescue station about 
the nature of the occurrence; stating whether assistance would be needed from 
the rescue station;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>e</number>  summon medical assistance; and
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>f</number>  send information of the 
occurrence to the Regional Inspector.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> All rescue and 
recovery work at a belowground mine shall be conducted under the control, 
direction and supervision of the manager of the mine or in his absence the 
principal official present at the surface:
 
Provided that in the event 
of a major emergency, such as ignition explosion, big underground fire or an 
accident involving a number of persons, the manager or the principal official 
shall, in taking decisions regarding rescue and recovery operations, take 
guidance from a group consisting of a Senior Official of the management, a 
representative each from the Director-General of Mines Safety, concerned rescue 
station and the recognised Union of the Workers, so however that he must take 
necessary decisions and direct the operations as the situation warrants, without 
waiting for the constitution or deliberations of the said group.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Accommodation at the 
belowground mine for persons engaged in rescue work.—Whenever 
rescue trained persons are engaged in rescue or recovery work at a belowground 
mine, there shall be provided at such mine suitable accommodation for storage 
and charging of apparatus required for that work. Such accommodation shall be 
situated at a convenient place near the entrance in use, and shall be properly 
ventilated and lighted. Adequate quantity of cool and wholesome drinking water 
shall be provided at such accommodation; and proper canteen facilities shall 
also be provided for the rescue workers.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Entry into belowground 
mines for rescue or recovery works.— 

<section><number>1</number> No person shall be allowed to enter a belowground mine or part thereof which 
is unsafe for the purpose of engaging in rescue or recovery work, unless 
authorised by the manager or in his absence by the principal official of the 
mine present at the surface. Only rescue trained persons shall be permitted to 
enter the mine for the purpose of using self-contained breathing apparatus.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> During the course of 
rescue or recovery work, person or persons shall be stationed at the entrances 
to the belowground mine and shall keep a written record of all persons entering 
and leaving such mine, and the time thereof.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Fresh air bases.—
<section><number>1</number> 
As soon as possible, base or bases shall be established in fresh air, as near to 
the irrespirable zone or zones as safety permits. Every such base shall, if 
possible be connected by telephone—
 <subsection>
          <number>i</number>  if the base is belowground, to 
the surface; or
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>ii</number>  if the base is on the surface, 
to the shaft bottom.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Except in cases where 
the delay involved may result in danger to life, rescue trained persons shall 
not proceed beyond any place where a base is to be established until there have 
been provided at such base—
 <subsection>
         <number>a</number>  two persons, of whom one shall 
be a qualified medical practitioner if practicable, and other shall be a rescue 
trained person;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>b</number>  a spare team with rescue 
apparatus, ready for immediate service;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>c</number>  one or more reviving apparatus, 
oxygen revivers etc.,
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>d</number>  first aid box and stretcher;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>e</number>  means of testing for carbon 
monoxide;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>f</number>  a hygrometer; and
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>g</number>  two flame safety lamp.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Whenever men are 
already at work beyond the fresh air base, there shall be provided at the base 
as soon as possible the persons, apparatus and equipments specified in sub-rule 
(2).
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Leader.—Every 
rescue team engaged in work with breathing apparatus in a mine shall be under a 
leader who shall be appointed by the Superintendent.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>29</number> Instructions to 
leader.—Prior 
to sending a rescue team underground, the Superintendent or a person authorised 
by him shall give clear instructions to the leader of the team as to where it 
shall go and what it shall attempt.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>30</number> Test of apparatus.—Before 
proceeding belowground the leader shall test or witness the testing of 
self-contained breathing apparatus of the team for leakage. No such apparatus 
shall be used unless it is found safe. He shall check the equipment of his 
party, and immediately before entering irrespirable atmosphere shall make sure 
that all breathing apparatus are working properly.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>31</number> Duties of leader 
belowground.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The leader shall not engage in manual work. He shall give his attention solely 
to directing the team and to maintaining its safety. He shall examine the roof 
and supports during the journey, and if there is any likelihood of fall at any 
place along the road-way, shall not proceed further until the team has made the 
place secure.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The leader shall keep 
the team together and shall not allow any member of the team to stray.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If the atmosphere is 
clear, the leader shall, when passing the junction of two or more roadways, 
clearly indicate the route by means of arrow marks in chalk. If the atmosphere 
is obscure, the leader shall see that a life line is lead in from the fresh air 
base, and shall not allow any member of the team to move out of reach of that 
line; or, if that course is impracticable he shall not proceed until every 
roadway branching of from the route is fenced across the whole opening.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> When using rescue 
apparatus, the leader shall carry a watch, shall record the pressure of the 
compressed oxygen at intervals of 20 minutes or so, and shall commence the 
return journey in ample time. During travelling he shall adopt the pace of 
slowest member if any member of the team is in distress, he shall immediately 
return to the fresh air base with the whole team.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The leader shall not 
permit any member of the team using breathing apparatus in a mine to remain at 
work at any one time for a period longer than one and half hours or such other 
period as may be specified by the Chief Inspector in respect of the breathing 
apparatus being used.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>32</number> Rescue team members 
and their duties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The number of persons in any rescue team using breathing apparatus in a mine 
shall not be less than five not more than six, including the leader.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In case there is no 
provision in any of the breathing apparatus carried by the rescue team for an 
extension for supply of oxygen to another person in an emergency, the team shall 
carry a self-rescuer.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Members of rescue team 
shall, in general, use the signals prescribed in Schedule VIII in communicating 
to one another.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> In travelling with 
rescue apparatus on, every member of the team shall keep the place given to him 
when numbering off. If the pace is too quick or if distress is felt, the member 
shall at once call attention to this fact.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Every member of a 
rescue team engaged in work with breathing apparatus in a mine shall obey the 
order of the leader of the team.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>33</number> Restriction of second 
spell of work.—No 
person shall commence a second or subsequently spell of work in irrespirable 
atmosphere without being examined and found fit by a qualified medical 
practitioner.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>34</number> Obligation of owner, 
agent and manager in certain situations.— 
Whenever emergency arises at a belowground mine, whether served by a rescue room 
or rescue station or not, the owner, agent or manager may seek assistance or 
additional assistance as the case may be, from the nearest rescue room or rescue 
station and in such an event—
 <section>
         <number>a</number>  all possible assistance shall 
be promptly rendered by the rescue room or rescue station; and
 </section><section>
         <number>b</number>  the owner of the mine shall pay 
to the owner of the rescue station or rescue room, rendering such assistance, 
the full cost of rescue services and facilities borrowed.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>35</number> General management.— 
It shall be the responsibility of the owner to establish, maintain and ensure 
proper functioning of rescue room or rescue station as required under these 
rules, to appoint Superintendent, Instructors, rescue room incharge, rescue 
trained persons, and to provide necessary rescue equipment and apparatus as may 
be necessary for compliance with the provisions of these rules.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>36</number> Inspections.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chief Inspector or other Inspector, authorised by him in this behalf or the 
Regional Inspector may enter, inspect and examine any rescue station and rescue 
room and make such examination or inquiry as he thinks fit in order to ascertain 
whether the provisions of these rules and of any orders made thereunder are 
being complied with.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When the belowground 
mines served by a rescue station or rescue room fall under the jurisdiction of 
two or more Regional Inspectors, the Chief Inspector may authorise any one of 
them for enforcement of these rules.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>37</number> Power to relax.—Where 
in the opinion of the Chief Inspector, the conditions pertaining to a mine or 
rescue station or rescue room are such as to render compliance with any 
provisions contained in these rules, unnecessary or impracticable, he may by an 
order in writing and subject to such conditions as he may specify therein grant 
exemption from the said provisions.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 
 
 <article>
<number>38</number> Repeal and saving.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Coal Mines Rescue Rules, 1959 are hereby repealed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding such 
repeal anything done or any action taken under the said rules shall be deemed to 
have been done or taken under the corresponding provisions of these rules.
 
 
  
</section></article><form>
 


THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 


 
 


FORM I
 


[See rule 3(4)]
 


Intimation of 
appointment etc. of Superintendent
 


From
 



.........................................
 



..........................................
 


To
 


1.   The Chief Inspector 
of Mines,
 


      Dhanbad-826 001.
 


2.   The Regional 
Inspector of Mines,
 


      
............................................
 


I have to furnish the 
following particulars in respect of *appointment/termination of appointment of 
Superintendent at ..................................................rescue 
station of.................................................(owner)
 


Name of Superintendent..........................................................................................
 


Qualifications (a) First 
Class Manager’s (Coal/ Metalliferous*)
 



                            Certificate No. 
................................................................................
 


                      (b)  
Number of Certificate of Competency to Undertake Rescue and 
                      Recovery work 
.........................................................................
 


                      (c) 
First-aid Certificate No. 
...................................................................
 


Date of 
assumption/relinquishment of charge 
....................................................................
 


Address of Superintendent 
..............................................................................................                              

 


      Yours faithfully,
 


      Signature of owner
 


—————
 


*Delete whatever is not 
applicable
 

 
</form><form>
 




THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 


 
 



SCHEDULE I
 


[See 
rule 11(1)]
 




Equipment to be kept at a Rescue Station
 


       A.  BREATHING 
APPARATUS                                                                                        
Nos.
 


             1.  Two-hours 
self-contained breathing 
apparatus                                                 54
 


             2.  Short 
duration self-contained breathing 
apparatus                                             6
 


             3.  Absorbent 
charges                                                                                       
2,000
 


       B.  RESUSCITATING 
APPARATUS
 


             1.  
Resuscitating 
Apparatus                                                                                   
12
 


             2.  Spare 
cylinders                                                                                                    
8
 


       C.  TUBE APPARATUS
 


                  (a)  
Pressure type with 
bellows                                                                           
2
 


                  (b)  
Spare 
helmets                                                                                               
2
 


                  (c)  
Pressure type with 
fan                                                                                  
1
 


       D.  ANCILLARY 
EQUIPMENT
 


             1.  Oxygen 
cylinders                                                                                              
12
 


             2.  (a)  
oxygen pump (hand 
driven)                                                                           
4
 


                  (b)  
oxygen pump (power 
driven)                                                                         
2
 


             3.  Bobin 
meter                                                                                                         
3
 


             4.  Flow 
meter                                                                                                           
2
 


             5.  Universal 
tester                                                                                                   
2
 


             6.  Pressure 
gauge testing 
device                                                                            
2
 


             7.  Oxygen 
testing 
apparatus                                                                                   
1
 


             8.  Apparatus 
testing tool 
kit                                                                                    
8
 


 
E. LAMPS ETC. AND GAS 
TESTING DEVICE
 


             1.  Flame 
safety lamps with maintenance 
kit                                                            8
 


             2.  Electric 
safety lamps
 


                  (a)  Cap 
lamps with 
belt                                                                                    
60
 


                  (b)  
Charging rack for cap lamp with 
charger                                                       1
 


 
F. GAS DETECTORS
 


             1.  Methane 
detector with battery charger, if 
required                                             3
 


             2.  
Co-detector
 


             3.  
Co-tube                                                                                                            
30
 


             4.  Multi-gas 
detector                                                                                                
2
 


             5.  Multi-gas 
detector tubes for each of the noxious gases likely to be 

found in 
mines                                                                                                  
20
 


 
G.  AIR AND TEMPERATURE 
MEASURING INSTRUMENTS
 


             1.  Vane 
Anemometer                                                                                               
1
 


             2.  
Velometer                                                                                                            
1
 


             3.  Clinical 
Thermometer                                                                                           
2
 


             4.  Sling 
whirling Hygrometer or 
psychrometer                                                         2
 


 
H.  TELEPHONE
 


             1.  
Genophone-Portable Telephone 
sets                                                                  2
 


 
I. SAFETY 
and FIRST AID EQUIPMENT
 


             1.  Safety 
helmets                                                                                                   
60
 


             2.  Safety 
belts                                                                                                         
6
 


             3.  First Aid 
Boxes                                                                                                   
10
 


             4.  
Blankets                                                                                                             
15
 


             5.  Folding 
stretchers                                                                                              
12
 


             6.  
Self-rescuer                                                                                                       
12
 


 
J. FIRE FIGHTING EQUIPMENT
 


             1.  CO2 fire 
extinguishers                                                                                          
4
 


             2.  Foam type 
fire 
extinguishers                                                                             
10
 


             3.  Foam 
charges 
                                                                                                   
50
 


             4.  Dry powder 
type 
extinguishers                                                                         
15
 


             5.  Trailer 
pump                                                                                                         
1
 


             6.  Trailer 
for carrying 
goods                                                                                     
1
 


             7.  Hose 
pipe                                                                                                       
300
 



                                                                                                                                     
metres
 


 
K.  MISCELLANEOUS EQUIPMENT
 


             1.  Charging 
rack for car 
batteries                                                                            
1
 


             2.  Stop 
watches                                                                                                       
3
 


             3.  Rain 
gauge                                                                                                          
1
 


             4.  Life 
line                                                                                                                
1
 



                                                                                                                                           
roll
 


             5. Guide line 
                                                                                                      
1000
 



                                                                                                                                     
metres
 


             6.  (a)  
Evacuated sampling 
tubes                                                                           
10
 


                  (b)  
Two-litre capacity stoppered sampling 
bottles                                              6
 


             7. Siren (hand 
operated)                                                                                         
1
 


             8. Siren 
(power 
operated)                                                                                       
1
 


             9. 
Barometer                                                                                                            
1
 


           10.  VHF 
Equipment                                                                                                   
2
 


           11.  Rescue 
vans                                                                                                       
2
 


           12.  Station 
Wagons                                                                                                  
2
 

 
</form><form>
 




THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 


 
 



SCHEDULE II
 


[See 
rule 11(2)]
 




Equipment to be kept at rescue room
 


 
A.  BREATHING 
APPARATUS                                                                                        
Nos.
 


             1.  Two-hours 
self-contained breathing 
apparatus                                                 15
 


             2.  Short 
duration self-contained breathing 
apparatus                                             2
 


             3.  Absorbent 
charges                                                                                            
50
 


       B.  RESUSCITATING 
APPARATUS
 


             1.  
Resuscitating 
apparatus                                                                                      
3
 


             2.  Spare 
cylinders                                                                                                    
3
 


 
C.  TUBE APPARATUS
 


            (a)  Pressure 
type with 
bellows                                                                                 
1
 


            (b)  Spare 
helmets                                                                                                     
1
 


            (c)  Pressure 
type with 
fan                                                                                        
1
 


       D.  ANCILLARY 
EQUIPMENT
 


             1.  Oxygen 
cylinders                                                                                                 
3
 


             2.  Oxygen 
pump (hand 
driven)                                                                                
2
 


             3.  Bobin 
meter                                                                                                         
2
 


             4.  Universal 
tester (where 
necessary)                                                                     1
 


             5.  Pressure 
gauge testing 
device                                                                            
1
 


             6.  Apparatus 
testing tool 
kit                                                                                    
2
 


             7.  Oxygen 
testing 
apparatus                                                                                   
1 
 


       E.  LAMPS ETC. AND 
GAS TESTING DEVICE
 


             1.  Flame 
Safety lamps (re-lighter type) with maintenance tool 
kit.                          4
 


             2.  Electric 
safety lamps
 


                  (a)  Cap 
lamps with 
belts                                                                                   
20
 


                  (b)  
Charging rack for cap lamps with 
charger                                                      1
 


 
F.  GAS DETECTORS
 


             1.  Methane 
detector, with battery charger, it 
required                                            2
 


             2.  
Co-detectors                                                                                                        
2
 


             3.  
Co-tubes                                                                                                            
10
 


             4.  Multi-gas 
Detector                                                                                               
1
 


             5.  Multi-gas 
Detector tubes for each of the noxious gases
 


                  likely to 
be found in 
mines                                                                                 
10
 


 
G.  AIR AND TEMPERATURE 
MEASURING INSTRUMENTS
 


             1.  Clinical 
Thermometer                                                                                           
1
 


             2.  Sling 
whirling hygrometer or psychrometer                                                         
1
 


 
H.  TELEPHONE
 


             1.  Genophone-Portable 
Telephone sets                                                                  
1
 


 
I.  SAFETY AND FIRST AID 
EQUIPMENT
 


             1.  Safety 
Helmets                                                                                                  
20
 


             2.  Safety 
Belts                                                                                                         
2
 


             3.  First aid 
box                                                                                                         
4
 


             4.  
Blankets                                                                                                               
4
 


             5.  Folding 
stretchers                                                                                                
4
 


             6.  
Self-rescuers                                                                                                        
4
 


        J.  FIRE FIGHTING 
EQUIPMENT
 


             1.  CO2 fire 
extinguisher                                                                                            
2
 


             2.  Foam type 
fire 
extinguisher                                                                                 
2
 


             3.  Foam 
charges                                                                                                    
20
 


             4.  Dry powder 
type 
extinguisher                                                                             
5
 


 
K.  MISCELLANEOUS
 


       1.  Stop 
watch                                                                                                                
1
 


       2.  Rain 
gauge                                                                                                                
1
 


       3.  Life 
line                                                                                                                      
1
 



                                                                                                                                           
roll
 


       4.  Guide 
line                                                                                                             
1000
 



                                                                                                                                     
metres
 


        5. (a)  Evacuated 
Sampling 
tubes                                                                                  
5
 


            (b)  Two-litre 
capacity stoppered sampling 
bottles.                                                   2
 


       6.  Siren (hand 
operated)                                                                                               
1
 


       7.  Siren (power 
operated)                                                                                             
1
 


       8.  
Barometer                                                                                                                  
1
 


 


       9.  Rescue 
  van                                                                                                              
  1*
 


*Not necessary, if the 
rescue room is situated close to mine entrance and serves only one mine.
 


 
 

 
</form><form>
 




THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 


 
 



SCHEDULE III
 


[See 
rule 11(3)]
 




Minimum equipment to be kept at the surface of mine where no rescue room is 
located close to mine entrance
 


 
1. Pressure type tube 
apparatus with bellows                                        1
 


      2. Flame safety lamp 
with maintenance tool kit                                       1
 


      3.  (a)    
Co-detector                                                                                 
1
 


           (b)    
Co-tubes                                                                                   
10
 


      4.  Whirling 
hygrometer                                                                            
1
 


      5.  Safety 
belt                                                                                           
1
 


      6. Resuscitating 
apparatus                                                                   10
 


      7. First aid 
box                                                                                        
1
 


      8. 
Blankets                                                                                              
2
 


      9. Folding 
stretcher                                                                                 
1
 


 


 
 

 
</form><form>
 




THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 


 
 



SCHEDULE IV
 


[See 
rule 11(6)]
 




Adjustments and test of Breathing Apparatus, Flowmeter, Bobin meter, Oxygen etc.
 


1. Every Breathing 
apparatus shall be thoroughly tested once at least in every month or at such 
shorter interval as may be recommended by the manufacturers of the breathing 
apparatus in a manner specified in para 2.
 


   2. (i) The apparatus 
shall be examined in respect of its general condition and particular attention 
shall be given to every delicate and perishable part.
 


      (ii)  The apparatus 
shall be tested for leakage. If any leakage is observed, the apparatus shall be 
deemed unsafe for use.
 


     (iii)  The pressure at 
which any automatic relief valve discharges shall be measured and if required so 
adjusted as to operate within the limits recommended by the manufacturers.
 


     (iv)  The pressure in 
the oxygen cylinder shall be measured.
 


      (v)  The rate of 
delivery of oxygen shall be measured by a flow meter, bobin meter universal 
tester. If required, the reducing valve shall be adjusted to supply oxygen at a 
rate of flow specified by the manufacturers.
 


                A record of 
such measurements and adjustments shall be kept in a bound paged register.
 


     (vi)  If an apparatus 
has been provided with an automatic demand valve, the pressure at which it 
operates shall be measured and if required adjusted as to operate within the 
limits recommended by the manufacturers.
 


    (vii)  Other tests and 
adjustments, if any, as recommended by the manufacturers shall be performed and 
a record thereof be kept in a bound paged register.
 


3. The purity of oxygen 
supplied for use in breathing apparatus shall be tested. No oxygen which is 
found to contain more than one per cent of impurities shall be used.
 


4. Flow-meters shall be 
tested for accuracy at least once in every six months and the results of every 
test shall be recorded.
 


5. Where by this Schedule 
any particulars are required to be recorded they shall be recorded forthwith in 
a bound paged register kept at rescue room or rescue stations, as the case may 
be, and shall be signed and dated by the person making the tests and shall be 
countersigned by the Superintendent.
 

 
</form><form>
 

THE 
MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 

 
 

SCHEDULE 
VII
 

(See 
rule 
21)
 

Courses 
of Instructions and Practices
 

Part 
I—Initial Course
 

The course of instructions and 
practices shall be as follows:—
 

A. Instructions.—Instructions in the following 
subjects:—
 

       
(i)  the general methods of dealing with fires belowground and the recovery 
of mines after fires and explosions;
 

      
(ii)  the construction, use, repair, maintenance and testing of the type or 
types of breathing apparatus provided, and the smoke helmets or other apparatus 
serving the same purpose;
 

     
(iii)  the use of methods and apparatus for reviving persons; 
 

     (iv)  
the properties, and the methods of detection of noxious and inflammable gases 
which may be found in mines;
 

      
(v)  the taking of gas samples in irrespirable atmosphere;
 

     (vi)  
the reading of mine plans;
 

    (vii)  the 
requirements contained in Chapter V and Schedule VII to these Rules.
 

B. Practices.—Not less than twelve practices 
with breathing apparatus and not less than two practices with smoke helmets or 
other apparatus serving the same purpose. The practices in each case shall be 
carried out under conditions devised to resemble those likely to be encountered 
in operations belowground and requiring the use of such apparatus and shall be 
carried out as follows:—
 

      
(a)  Not more than eight and not less than five men shall take part in any 
practice.
 

      
(b)  The practices with breathing apparatus shall commence in ordinary air, 
and shall progress gradually until practices can be carried out and in hot and 
irrespirable atmosphere.
 

      
(c)  The practices with breathing apparatus shall comprise the following 
operations :—
 

             
(i)  repeatedly raising and lowering of a weight of 25 kilograms to and 
from a height of 1.8 metres by means of a rope and pulley.
 

            
(ii)  walking continuously at a fair pace for half an hour;
 

           
(iii)  building and removing temporary stoppings of stone, brick, 
sand-bags, brattice cloth or other materials, and carrying the materials 
required for such operations over a distance of at least ten metres;
 

           
(iv)  removing debris in confined space, as representing the clearing of a 
fall of roof;
 

           
(vi)  setting timber or other roof supports;
 

           
(vi)  carrying, pulling or pushing on a stretcher a live person or dummy 
body weighing 70 kilograms along the length of the gallery;
 

          
(vii)  the rapid establishment of communication.
 

Part 
II—Practices and Instructions after becoming competent
 

A. Instructions.—Revision of all subjects included 
in Part I.
 

B. Practices.—At least eight practices with 
breathing apparatus in every calendar year of which at least four months shall 
take place in mines, and the remainder in hot and irrespirable atmosphere in the 
Training Gallery at Rescue Station. As far as practicable these practices shall 
be evenly distributed, so however that the gap between two consecutive practices 
shall not exceed four months:
 

Provided that, if a rescue trained 
person fails to undergo a refresher practice over a period exceeding four 
months, the Chairman, Board of Mining Examinations may, on being satisfied that 
the discontinuance was on valid reasons, permit him subject to the provisions 
confined in rule 21, to undergo a special course of refresher practices and 
instructions, extending over five consecutive days, whereupon, he shall again 
become active.
 

Note:—(i)  All practices shall 
last at least two hours except on occasion when, in the opinion of Instructor, 
it is desirable in the interest of safety to curtail the period of practice. At 
some of the practices, breathing apparatus shall be worn continuously for a 
period of two hours.
 

            
(ii)  The Code of signals set out in Schedule VIII shall be used in 
training.
 

 
 

 </form><form>
 




THE MINES RESCUE RULES, 1985
 


 
 



SCHEDULE VIII
 


[See 
rule 32(3)]
 




Code of signals
 


A. Between members of 
rescue team.
 


One 
hoot                                                         —         
“Distress” or “Help wanted”
 



                                                                                    
(if no answer given to a call,
 



                                                                                    
“Distress” to be understood). 
 


Two 
hoots                                                        —         Halt
 


Three 
hoots                                                     —         Retire
 


Four 
hoots                                                       —         Advance
 


Five 
hoots                                                        —         To call 
attention
 


B. Between tube 
apparatus operator and user.
 


One 
tug                                                           —         More air 
required.
 


Two 
tugs                                                          —         Give 
less air.
 


Three 
tugs                                                       —         Help me 
out. 
 


 
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>