<act><tid>1973522</tid>
<title>THE CHILDREN ACT, <year>1960</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum></title>

ACT NO. 60 OF <year>1960</year> 
[ 26th December, <year>1960</year>.]
An Act to provide for the care, protection, maintenance, welfare, 
training, education and rehabilitation of neglected or delinquent 
children and for the trial of delinquent children in the Union 
territories.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Eleventh Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:--

CHAP 
PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY




<article><tid>968068</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>788100</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Children Act, <year>1960</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>923746</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to all the Union territories.

</section>

<section><tid>1872615</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force in any Union territory on such date 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> as the Administrator may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
appoint and different dates may be appointed for different areas 
thereof.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>625357</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1486013</tid>
<number>a</number>" Administrator" means the administrator of a Union 
territory, whether called a Lieutenant Governor, a 
Chief Commissioner or by any other name;

</section>

<section><tid>894527</tid>
<number>b</number>" begging" means--

<subsection><tid>779816</tid>
<number>i</number>soliciting or receiving alms in a public 
place or entering on any private premises for the 
purpose of soliciting or receiving alms, whether 
under the pretence of singing, dancing, fortune- 
telling, performing tricks or selling articles or 
otherwise;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1497050</tid>
<number>ii</number>exposing or exhibiting with the object 
of obtaining or extorting alms any sore, wound, 
injury, deformity or disease, whether of himself 
or of any other person or of an animal;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1325728</tid>
<number>iii</number>allowing oneself to be used as an 
exhibit for the purpose of soliciting or receiving 
alms;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>32</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been extended to Goa, Daman and Diu by Reg. 12 of 
<year>1962</year>, s. 3 and Sch.; to Dadra and Nagar Haveli by Reg. 6 of <year>1963</year>, s. 2 
and Sch. I and to Pondicherry by Reg. 7 of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch. I.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number> 1- 1- <year>1962</year> in the Union territory of Delhi: vide Notification No. 
F. 40 (8) 61-DSW (1), dated 1- 12- <year>1961</year>, published in the Delhi Gazette.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>512810</tid>
<number>c</number>" Board" means a Child Welfare Board constituted under 
section 4;

</section>

<section><tid>1444435</tid>
<number>d</number>" brothel"," prostitute"," prostitution" and" public 
place" shall have the meanings respectively assigned to 
them in the Suppression of Immoral Traffic in Women and 
Girls Act, <year>1956</year> (104 of <year>1956</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>406555</tid>
<number>e</number>" child" means a boy who has not attained the age of 
sixteen years or a girl who has not aftained the age of 
eighteen years;

</section>

<section><tid>519287</tid>
<number>f</number>" children' s court" means a court constituted under 
section 5;

</section>

<section><tid>1988069</tid>
<number>g</number>" children' s home" means an institution established or 
certified by the Administrator under section 9 as a 
children' s home;

</section>

<section><tid>1305477</tid>
<number>h</number>" competent authority" means, in relation to neglected 
children, a Board constituted under section 4 and, in 
relation to delinquent children a children' s court 
constituted under section 5, and where no such Board or 
children' s court has been constituted, includes any 
court empowered under sub- section (2) of section 7 to 
exercise the powers conferred on a Board or children' s 
court;

</section>

<section><tid>1314346</tid>
<number>i</number>" dangerous drug" shall have the meaning assigned to it 
in the Dangerous Drugs Act, <year>1930</year> (2 of <year>1930</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1752761</tid>
<number>j</number>" delinquent child" means a child who has been found to 
have committed an offence;

</section>

<section><tid>1385798</tid>
<number>jj</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>" fit person" or" fit institution" means any person 
or institution (not being a police station or  
  jail) found fit by the competent authority to 
receive and take care of a child entrusted to his 
or its care and protection on the terms and 
conditions specified by the competent authority;]

</section>

<section><tid>15919</tid>
<number>k</number>" guardian" in relation to a child, includes any person 
who, in the opinion of the competent authority having 
cognizance of any proceeding in relation to a child, 
has, for the time being, the actual charge of, or 
control over, that child;

</section>

<section><tid>882213</tid>
<number>l</number>" neglected child" means a child who--

<subsection><tid>652967</tid>
<number>i</number>is found begging; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1538595</tid>
<number>ii</number>is found without having any home or 
settled place of abode or any ostensible means of 
subsistence or is found destitute, whether he is 
an orphan or not; or
<pagefootnote><pagenum>33</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 15 of <year>1978</year>, s. 3.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>189210</tid>
<number>iii</number>has a parent or guardian who is unfit 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or unable] to exercise or does not exercise 
proper care and control over the child; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1965794</tid>
<number>iv</number>lives in a brothel or with a prostitute 
or frequently goes to any place used for the 
purpose of prostitution, or is found to associate 
with any prostitute or any other person who leads 
an immoral, drunken or depraved life;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>910186</tid>
<number>m</number>" observation home" means any institution or place 
established or recognised by the Administrator under 
section 11 as an observation home;

</section>

<section><tid>240300</tid>
<number>n</number>" offence" means an offence punishable under any law for 
the time being in force;

</section>

<section><tid>1765710</tid>
<number>nn</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>" place of safety" means any place or institution 
 (not being a police station or jail), the person 
in charge of which is willing temporarily to 
receive and take care of a child and which in the 
opinion of the competent authority may be a place 
of safety for the child;]

</section>

<section><tid>1298555</tid>
<number>o</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>535541</tid>
<number>p</number>" probation officer" means an officer appointed as a 
probation officer under this Act or under the Probation 
of Offenders Act, <year>1958</year> (20 of <year>1958</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1431936</tid>
<number>q</number>" special school" means an institution established or 
certified by the Administrator under section 10;

</section>

<section><tid>701075</tid>
<number>r</number>" supervision", in relation to a child placed under the 
care of any parent, guardian or other <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> fit person or 
fit institution] under this Act, means the supervision 
of that child by a probation officer for the purpose of 
ensuring that the child is properly looked after and 
that the conditions imposed by the competent authority 
are complied with;

</section>

<section><tid>731991</tid>
<number>s</number>all words and expressions used but not defined in this 
Act and defined in the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Code of Criminal Procedure, 
 <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>),] shall have the meanings assigned to 
them in that Code.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>200125</tid>
<number>3</number>Continuation of inquiry in respect of child who has ceased to 
be child. Where an inquiry has been initiated against a child and 
during the course of such inquiry the child ceases to be such, then, 
notwithstanding anything contained in this Act or in any other law for 
the time being in force, the inquiry may be continued and orders may 
be made in respect of such person as if such person had continued to 
be a child.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>34</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 15 of <year>1978</year>, s. 3. 
2. Subs. by s. 3, ibid., for" fit person". 
3. Subs. by s. 2, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


CHAP 
COMPETENT AUTHORITIES AND INSTITUTIONS FOR CHILDREN

CHAPTER II

COMPETENT AUTHORITIES AND INSTITUTIONS FOR CHILDREN


</article>



<article><tid>230360</tid>
<number> 4</number> Child Welfare Boards.
<section><tid>230094</tid>
<number>1</number>The Administrator may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, constitute for any area 
specified in the notification, one or more Child Welfare Boards for 
exercising the powers and discharging the duties conferred or imposed 
on such Board in relation to neglected children under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>116501</tid>
<number>2</number>A Board shall consist of a chairman and such other members as 
the Administrator thinks fit to appoint, of whom not less than one 
shall be a woman; and every such member shall be vested with the 
powers of a magistrate under the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> 
 (2 of <year>1974</year>)].

</section>

<section><tid>1716122</tid>
<number>3</number>The Board shall function as a Bench of magistrates and shall 
have the powers conferred by the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> 
 (2 of <year>1974</year>), on a Metropolitan Magistrate or, as the case may be, a 
Judicial Magistrate of the first class].


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>84602</tid>
<number> 5</number> Children' s courts.
<section><tid>470112</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in  
the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Code of Criminal procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>)], the 
Administrator may, by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute 
for any area specified in the notification, one or more children' s 
courts for exercising the powers and discharging the duties conferred 
or imposed on such court in relation to delinquent children under this 
Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1219747</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> a children' s court shall consist of such number of 
Metropolitan Magistrates or Judicial Magistrates of the first class, 
as the case may be, forming a Bench as the Administrator thinks fit to 
appoint, of whom one shall be designated as the principal magistrate; 
and every such Bench shall have the powers conferred by the Code of 
Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>), on a Metropolitan Magistrate 
or, as the case may be, a Judicial Magistrate of the first class.

</section>

<section><tid>1637636</tid>
<number>3</number>Every children' s court shall be assisted by a panel of two 
honorary social workers possessing such qualifications as may be 
prescribed, of whom at least one shall be a woman, and such panel 
shall be appointed by the Administrator.]


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1832444</tid>
<number> 6</number> Procedure, etc., in relation to Boards and children' s courts.

<section><tid>1506558</tid>
<number>1</number>In the event of any difference of opinion among the members of a  
Board or among the magistrates of a children' s court, the opinion of 
the majority shall prevail, but where there is no such majority, the 
opinion
<pagefootnote><pagenum>35</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 15 of <year>1978</year>, s. 2, for" Code of Criminal Procedure, 
<year>1898</year>" (5 of <year>1898</year>). 
2. Subs. by s. 4, ibid., for certain words. 
3. Subs. by s. 5, ibid., for the former sub- section.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


of the chairman or of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> principal magistrate], as the case may 
be, shall prevail.


</section>

<section><tid>1490376</tid>
<number>2</number>A Board or children' s court may act notwithstanding the 
absence of any member of the Board or, as the case may be, any 
magistrate of the children' s court, and no order made by the Board or 
children' s court shall be invalid by reason only of the absence of any 
member or magistrate, as the case may be, during any stage of the 
proceeding.

</section>

<section><tid>672016</tid>
<number>3</number>No person shall be appointed as a member of the Board or as a 
magistrate in the children' s court unless he has, in the opinion of 
the Administrator, special knowledge of child psychology and child 
welfare.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1315325</tid>
<number> 7</number> Power of Board and children' s court.
<section><tid>1729033</tid>
<number>1</number>Where a Board or a  
children' s court has been constituted for any area, such Board or 
court shall, notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for 
the time being in force but save as otherwise expressly provided in 
this Act, have power to deal exclusively with all proceedings under 
this Act relating to neglected children or delinquent children, as the 
case may be:
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Provided that a Board or a children' s court may, if it is of 
opinion that it is necessary so to do having regard to the 
circumstances of the case, transfer any proceedings to any children' s 
court or Board, as the case may be:

Provided further that where there is any difference of opinion 
between a Board and a children' s court regarding the transfer of any 
proceedings under the first proviso, it shall be referred to the Chief 
Metropolitan Magistrate or, as the case may be, the Chief Judicial 
Magistrate for decision, and in a case where the District Magistrate 
is functioning as a Board or a children' s court, such difference of 
opinion shall be referred to the Court of Session, and the decision of 
the Chief Metropolitan Magistrate or Chief Judicial Magistrate or, as 
the case may be, the Court of Session on such reference shall be 
final.]


</section>

<section><tid>728859</tid>
<number>2</number>Where no Board or children' s court has been constituted for 
any area, the powers conferred on the Board or the children' s court by 
or under this Act shall be exercised in that area, only by the 
following, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1405249</tid>
<number>a</number>the district magistrate: or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1352311</tid>
<number>b</number>the sub- divisional magistrate: or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1209287</tid>
<number>c</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> any metropolitan Magistrate or Judicial Magistrate of 
the first class, as the case may be.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>36</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 15 of <year>1978</year>, s. 6, for" senior magistrate". 
2. Added by s. 7, ibid. 
3. Subs. by s. 7, ibid., for the original clause.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1985682</tid>
<number>3</number>The powers conferred on the Board or children' s court by or 
under this Act may also be exercised by the High Court and the court 
of session, when the proceeding comes before them in appeal, revision 
or otherwise.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>782467</tid>
<number> 8</number> Procedure to be followed by a magistrate not empowered under 
the Act.
<section><tid>1662911</tid>
<number>1</number>When any magistrate not empowered to exercise the powers  
of a Board or a children' s court under this Act is of opinion that a 
person brought before him under any of the provisions of this Act 
 (otherwise than for the purpose of giving evidence) is a child, he 
shall record such opinion and forward the child and the record of the 
proceeding to the competent authority having jurisdiction over the 
proceeding.

</section>

<section><tid>167133</tid>
<number>2</number>The competent authority to which the proceeding is forwarded 
under sub- section (1) shall hold the inquiry as if the child had 
originally been brought before it.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1449910</tid>
<number> 9</number> Children' s homes.
<section><tid>186533</tid>
<number>1</number>The Administrator may establish and  
maintain as many children' s homes as may be necessary for the 
reception of neglected children under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1898522</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the Administrator is of opinion that any institution 
other than an institution established under sub- section (1) is fit for 
the reception of the neglected children to be sent there under this 
Act, he may certify such institution as a children' s home for the 
purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>839306</tid>
<number>3</number>Every children' s home to which a neglected child is sent 
under this Act shall not only provide the child with accommodation, 
maintenance and facilities for education, but also provide him with 
facilities for the development of his character and abilities and give 
him necessary training for protecting himself against moral dangers or 
exploitation and shall also perform such other functions as may be 
prescribed <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> to ensure all round growth and development of his 
personality].

</section>

<section><tid>1805695</tid>
<number>4</number>The Administrator may, by rules made under this Act, provide 
for the management of children' s homes <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>, including the standards 
and the nature of services to be maintained by them,] and the 
circumstances under which, and the manner in which, the certificate of 
a children' s home may be granted or withdrawn.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>651063</tid>
<number> 10</number> Special schools.
<section><tid>638191</tid>
<number>1</number>The Administrator may establish and  
maintain as many special schools as may be necessary for the reception 
of delinquent children under this Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>37</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Added by Act 15 of <year>1978</year>, s. 8. 
2. Ins. by s. 8, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>200552</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the Administrator is of opinion that any institution 
other than an institution established under sub- section (1) is fit for 
the reception of the delinquent children to be sent there under this 
Act, he may certify such institution as a special school for the 
purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1886341</tid>
<number>3</number>Every special school to which a delinquent child is sent 
under this Act shall not only provide the child with accommodation, 
maintenance and facilities for education but also provide him with 
facilities for the development of his character and abilities and give 
him necessary training for his reformation and shall also perform such 
other functions as may be prescribed <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> to ensure all round growth and 
development of his personality].

</section>

<section><tid>1969011</tid>
<number>4</number>The Administrator may, by rules made under this Act, provide 
for the management of special schools <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>, including the standards and 
the nature of services to be maintained by them,] and the 
circumstances under which, and the manner in which, the certificate of 
a special school may be granted or withdrawn.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1824361</tid>
<number> 11</number> Observation homes.
<section><tid>257913</tid>
<number>1</number>The Administrator may establish and  
maintain as many observation homes as may be necessary for the 
temporary reception of children during the pendency of any inquiry 
regarding them under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>71948</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the Administrator is of opinion that any institution 
other than an institution established under sub- section (1) is fit for 
the temporary reception of children during the pendency of any inquiry 
regarding them under this Act, he may recognise such institution as an 
observation home for the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1465053</tid>
<number>3</number>Every observation home to which a child is sent under this 
Act shall not only provide the child with accommodation, maintenance 
and facilities for medical examination and treatment, but also provide 
him with facilities for useful occupation.

</section>

<section><tid>1288793</tid>
<number>4</number>The Administrator may, by rules made under this Act, provide 
for the management of observation homes <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>, including the standards 
and the nature of services to be maintained by them,] and the 
circumstances under which, and the manner in which, an institution may 
be recognised as an observation home or the recognition may be 
withdrawn.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1836662</tid>
<number> 12</number> <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> After care organisations. The Administrator may, by rules 
made under this Act, provide--
<section><tid>340919</tid>
<number>a</number>for the establishment or recognition of after- care 
organisations
<pagefootnote><pagenum>38</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Added by Act 15 of <year>1978</year>, s. 9. 
2. Ins. by s. 9, ibid. 
3. Ins. by s. 10, ibid. 
4. Subs. by s. 11, ibid., for the original section.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


and the powers that may be exercised by them for 
effectively carrying out their functions under this 
Act;


</section>

<section><tid>1006868</tid>
<number>b</number>for a scheme of after- care programme to be followed by 
such after- care organisations for the purpose of taking 
care of children after they leave children' s homes or 
special schools and for the purpose of enabling them to 
lead an honest, industrious and useful life;

</section>

<section><tid>1261893</tid>
<number>c</number>for the preparation and submission of a report by the 
probation officer in respect of each child prior to his 
discharge from a children' s home or special school, as 
the case may be, regarding the necessity and nature of 
after- care of such child, the period of such after- 
care, supervision thereof and for the submission of a 
report by the probation officer on the progress of each 
such child;

</section>

<section><tid>1752928</tid>
<number>d</number>for the standards and the nature of services to be 
maintained by such after- care organisations;

</section>

<section><tid>1093534</tid>
<number>e</number>for such other matters as may be necessary for the 
purpose of effectively carrying out the scheme of 
after- care programme of children.]
CHAP 
NEGLECTED CHILDREN

CHAPTER III

NEGLECTED CHILDREN



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1031179</tid>
<number> 13</number> Production of neglected children before Boards.
<section><tid>46759</tid>
<number>1</number>If any  
police officer or any other person authorised by the Administrator in 
this behalf, by general or special order, is of opinion that a person 
is apparently a neglected child, such police officer or other person 
may take charge of that person for bringing him before a Board.

</section>

<section><tid>739031</tid>
<number>2</number>When information is given to an officer- in- charge of a police 
station about any neglected child found within the limits of such 
station, he shall enter in a book to be kept for the purpose the 
substance of such information and take such action thereon as he deems 
fit and if such officer does not propose to take charge of the child, 
he shall forward a copy of the entry made to the Board.

</section>

<section><tid>1340847</tid>
<number>3</number>Every child taken charge of under sub- section (1) shall be 
brought before the Board within a period of twenty- four hours of such 
charge taken excluding the time necessary for the journey from the 
place where the child had been taken charge of to the Board.

</section>

<section><tid>1584450</tid>
<number>4</number>Every child taken charge of under sub- section (1) shall, 
unless he is kept with his parent or guardian, be sent to an 
observation home (but not to a police station or jail) until he can be 
brought before a Board.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>39</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>736248</tid>
<number> 14</number> Special Procedure to be followed when neglected child has 
parent.
<section><tid>1040568</tid>
<number>1</number>If a person, who in the opinion of the police officer or  
the authorised person is a neglected child, has a parent or guardian 
who has the actual charge of, or control over, the child, the police 
officer or the authorised person may, instead of taking charge of the 
child, make a report to the Board for initiating an inquiry regarding 
that child.

</section>

<section><tid>455749</tid>
<number>2</number>On receipt of a report under sub- section (1), the Board may 
call upon the parent or guardian to produce the child before it and to 
show cause why the child should not be dealt with as a neglected child 
under the provisions of this Act and if it appears to the Board that 
the child is likely to be removed from its jurisdiction or to be 
concealed, it may immediately order his removal (if necessary by  
  issuing a search warrant for the immediate production of the child) to 
an observation home <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or a place of safety].


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1387877</tid>
<number> 15</number> Inquiry by Board regarding neglected children.
<section><tid>279681</tid>
<number>1</number>When a  
person alleged to be a neglected child is produced before a Board, it 
shall examine the police officer or the authorised person who brought 
the child or made the report and record the substance of such 
examination and hold the inquiry in the prescribed manner and may make 
such orders in relation to the child as it may deem fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1098000</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a Board is satisfied on inquiry that a child is a 
neglected child and that it is expedient so to deal with him, the 
Board may make an order directing the child to be sent to a children' s 
home for the period until he ceases to be a child:
Provided that the Board may, for reasons to be recorded, extend 
the period of such stay, but in no case the period of stay shall 
extend beyond the time when the child attains the age of eighteen 
years, in the case of a boy, or twenty years, in the case of a girl:

Provided further that the Board may, if it is satisfied that 
having regard to the circumstances of the case it is expedient so to 
do, for reasons to be recorded, reduce the period of stay to such 
period as it thinks fit.


</section>

<section><tid>1595412</tid>
<number>3</number>During the pendency of any inquiry regarding a child, the 
child shall, unless he is kept with his parent or guardian, be sent to 
an observation home <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or a place of safety] for such period as may be 
specified in the order of the Board:
Provided that no child shall be kept with his parent or guardian 
if, in the opinion of the Board, such parent or guardian is unfit <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or 
unable] to exercise or does not exercise proper care and control over 
the child.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>40</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 15 of <year>1978</year>, s. 12. 
2. Ins. by s. 13, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1128246</tid>
<number> 16</number> Power to commit neglected child to suitable custody.
<section><tid>1070042</tid>
<number>1</number>If  
the Board so thinks fit, it may, instead of making an order under sub- 
section (2) of section 15 for sending the child to a children' s home, 
make an order placing the child under the care of a parent, guardian 
or other fit person, on such parent, guardian or fit person executing 
a bond with or without surety to be responsible for the good behaviour 
and well- being of the child and for the observance of such conditions 
as the Board may think fit to impose.

</section>

<section><tid>81831</tid>
<number>2</number>At the time of making an order under sub- section (1) or at 
any time subsequently, the Board may, in addition, make an order that 
the child be placed under supervision for any period not exceeding 
three years in the first instance.

</section>

<section><tid>177429</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1) or sub- 
section (2), if at any time it appears to the Board, on receiving a 
report from the probation officer or otherwise, that there has been a 
breach of any of the conditions imposed by it in respect of the child, 
it may, after making such inquiry as it deems fit, order the child to 
be sent to a children' s home.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1728569</tid>
<number>17</number>Uncontrolable children. Where a parent or guardian of a child 
complains to the Board that he is not able to exercise proper care and 
control over the child and the Board is satisfied on inquiry that 
proceedings under this Act should be initiated regarding the child, it 
may send the child to an observation home <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or a place of safety] and 
make such further inquiry as it may deem fit and the provisions of 
section 15 and section 16 shall, as far as may be, apply to such 
proceedings.
CHAP 
DELINQUENT CHILDREN

CHAPTER IV

DELINQUENT CHILDREN


</article>



<article><tid>735145</tid>
<number> 18</number> Bail and custody of children.
<section><tid>1857134</tid>
<number>1</number>When any person accused of  
a bailable or non- bailable offence and apparently a child is arrested 
or detained or appears or is brought before a children' s court, such 
person shall, notwithstanding anything contained in the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Code of 
Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>)], or in any other law for the 
time being in force, be released on bail with or without surety but he 
shall not be so released if there appear reasonable grounds for 
believing that the release is likely to bring him into association 
with any reputed criminal or expose him to moral danger or that his 
release would defeat the ends of justice.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>41</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 15 of <year>1978</year>, s. 12. 
2. Subs. by s. 2, ibid., for" Code of Criminal Procedure," <year>1898</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1616966</tid>
<number>2</number>When such person having been arrested is not released on bail 
under sub- section (1) by the officer- in- charge of the police station, 
such officer shall cause him to be kept in an observation home <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or a 
place of safety] in the prescribed manner (but not in a police station  
  or jail) until he can be brought before a children' s court.

</section>

<section><tid>436088</tid>
<number>3</number>When such person is not released on bail under sub- section 
 (1) by the children' s court, it shall, instead of committing him to 
prison, make an order sending him to an observation home <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or a place 
of safety] for such period during the pendency of the inquiry 
regarding him as may be specified in the order.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>120479</tid>
<number> 19</number> Information to parent or guardian or probation officer. Where 
a child is arrested, the officer- in- charge of the police station to 
which the child is brought shall, as soon as may be after the arrest, 
inform--
<section><tid>1366178</tid>
<number>a</number>the parent or guardian of the child, if he can be found, 
of such arrest and direct him to be present at the 
children' s court before which the child will appear; 
and

</section>

<section><tid>1074480</tid>
<number>b</number>the probation officer of such arrest in order to enable 
him to obtain information regarding the antecedents and 
family history of the child and other material 
circumstances likely to be of assistance to the 
children' s court for making the inquiry.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1648433</tid>
<number>20</number>Inquiry by children' s court regarding delinquent children. 
Where a child having been charged with an offence appears or is 
produced before a children' s court, the children' s court shall hold 
the inquiry in accordance with the provisions of section 39 and may, 
subject to the provisions of this Act, make such order in relation to 
the child as it deems fit.

</article>



<article><tid>774649</tid>
<number> 21</number> Orders that may be passed regarding delinquent children.
<section><tid>1620747</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Where a children' s court is satisfied on inquiry that a child has 
committed an offence, then, notwithstanding anything to the contrary 
contained in any other law for the time being in force, the children' s 
court may, if it so thinks fit,--

<subsection><tid>1675841</tid>
<number>a</number>allow the child to go home after advice or admonition;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>255435</tid>
<number>b</number>direct the child to be released on probation of good 
conduct and placed under the care of any parent, 
guardian or other fit person on such parent, guardian 
or other fit person executing a bond, with or without 
surety as that court may require, for the good 
behaviour and well- being of the child for any period 
not exceeding three years;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>42</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 15 of <year>1978</year>, s. 12.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>422376</tid>
<number>c</number>make an order directing the child to be sent to a 
special school,--

<subsubsection><tid>1972145</tid>
<number>i</number>in the case of a boy over fourteen years 
of age or of a girl over sixteen years of age, for 
a period of not less than three years;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>518619</tid>
<number>ii</number>in the case of any other child, for the 
period until he ceases to be a child:
Provided that the children' s court may, if it 
is satisfied that having regard to the nature of 
the offence and the circumstances of the case it 
is expedient so to do, for reasons to be recorded, 
reduce the period of stay to such period as it 
thinks fit:

Provided further that the children' s court 
may, for reasons to be recorded, extend the period 
of such stay, but in no case the period of stay 
shall extend beyond the time when the child 
attains the age of eighteen years, in the case of 
a boy, or twenty years, in the case of a girl;


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1571869</tid>
<number>d</number>order the child to pay a fine if he is over fourteen 
years of age and earns money.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>782031</tid>
<number>2</number>Where an order under clause (b) or clause (d) of sub- section 
 (1) is made, the children' s court may, if it is of opinion that in the 
interests of the child and of the public it is expedient so to do, in 
addition make an order that the delinquent child shall remain under 
the supervision of a probation officer named in the order during such 
period, not exceeding three years, as may be specified therein, and 
may in such supervision order impose such conditions as it deems 
necessary for the due supervision of the delinquent child:
Provided that if at any time afterwards it appears to the 
children' s court on receiving a report from the probation officer or 
otherwise, that the delinquent child has not been of good behaviour 
during the period of supervision, it may, after making such inquiry as 
it deems fit, order the delinquent child to be sent to a special 
school.


</section>

<section><tid>1117483</tid>
<number>3</number>The children' s court making a supervision order under sub- 
section (2) shall explain to the child and the parent, guardian or 
other fit person, as the case may be, under whose care the child has 
been placed, the terms and conditions of the order and shall forthwith 
furnish one copy of the supervision order to the child, the parent, 
guardian or other fit person, as the case may be, the surcties, if 
any, and the probation officer.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>43</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1335976</tid>
<number>4</number>In determining the special school, or any person to whose 
custody a child is to be committed or entrusted under this Act, the 
court shall pay due regard to the religious denomination of the child 
to ensure that religious instruction contrary to the religious 
persuasion of the child is not imparted to him.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1847970</tid>
<number> 22</number> Orders that may not be passed against delinquent children.

<section><tid>1047120</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any other  
law for the time being in force, no delinquent child shall be 
sentenced to death or imprisonment, or committed to prison in default 
of payment of fine or in default of furnishing security:
Provided that where a child who has attained the age of fourteen 
years has committed an offence and the children' s court is satisfied 
that the offence committed is of so serious a nature or that his 
conduct and behaviour have been such that it would not be in his 
interest or in the interest of other children in a special school to 
send him to such special school and that none of the other measures 
provided under this Act is suitable or sufficient, the children' s 
court may order the delinquent child to be kept in safe custody in 
such place and manner as it thinks fit and shall report the case for 
the orders of the Administrator.


</section>

<section><tid>1629018</tid>
<number>2</number>On receipt of a report from a children' s court under sub- 
section (1), the Administrator may make such arrangement in respect of 
the child as he deems proper and may order such delinquent child to be 
detained at such place and on such conditions as he thinks fit:
Provided that the period of detention so ordered shall not exceed 
the maximum period of imprisonment to which the child could have been 
sentenced for the offence committed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1717514</tid>
<number>23</number>Proceeding under Chapter VIII of the Criminal Procedure Code 
not competent against child. Notwithstanding anything to the contrary 
contained in the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>)], no 
proceeding shall be instituted and no order shall be passed against a 
child under Chapter VIII of the said Code.

</article>



<article><tid>1833053</tid>
<number> 24</number> No joint trial of child and person not a child.
<section><tid>1405657</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> section 223 of the Code of 
Criminal procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>)] or in any other law for the 
time being in force, no child shall be charged with or tried for, any 
offence together with a person who is not a child.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>44</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 15 of <year>1978</year>, s. 2, for" Code of Criminal Procedure, 
<year>1898</year>". 
2. Subs. by s. 14, ibid., for" section 239 of the Code of Criminal 
procedure, <year>1898</year>".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>688954</tid>
<number>2</number>If a child is accused of an offence for which under 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> section 223 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>)], 
or any other law for the time being in force, such child and any 
person who is not a child would, but for the prohibition contained in 
sub- section (1), have been charged and tried together, the court 
taking cognizance of that offence shall direct separate trials of the 
child and the other person.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1036212</tid>
<number>25</number>Removal of disqualification attaching to conviction. 
Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law, a child who has 
committed an offence and has been dealt with under the provisions of 
this Act shall not suffer disqualification, if any, attaching to a 
conviction of an offence under such law.

</article>



<article><tid>165753</tid>
<number>26</number>Special provision in respect of pending cases. 
Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, all proceedings in 
respect of a child pending in any court in any area on the date on 
which this Act comes into force in that area, shall be continued in 
that court as if this Act had not been passed and if the court finds 
that the child has committed an offence, it shall record such finding 
and, instead of passing any sentence in respect of the child, forward 
the child to the children' s court which shall pass orders in respect 
of that child in accordance with the provisions of this Act as if it 
had been satisfied on inquiry under this Act that the child has 
committed the offence.
CHAP 
PROCEDURE OF COMPETENT AUTHORITIES GENERALLY AND APPEALS AND REVISIONFROM 
ORDERS OF SUCH COURTS

CHAPTER V

PROCEDURE OF COMPETENT AUTHORITIES GENERALLY AND APPEALS AND 
REVISION FROM ORDERS OF SUCH COURTS


</article>



<article><tid>430354</tid>
<number> 27</number> Sittings, etc., of Board and children' s courts.
<section><tid>1068048</tid>
<number>1</number>A Board  
or a children' s court shall hold its sittings at such place, on such 
day and in such manner, as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>363778</tid>
<number>2</number>A magistrate empowered to exercise the powers of a Board or, 
as the case may be, a children' s court under sub- section (2) of 
section 7 shall, case may be, a children' s court under sub- section (2) 
of section 7 shall, while holding any inquiry regarding a child under 
this Act, as far as practicable, sit in a building or room different 
from that in which the ordinary sittings of civil and criminal courts 
are held, or on different days or at times different from those at 
which the ordinary sittings of such courts are held.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>227271</tid>
<number> 28</number> Persons who may be present before competent authority.
<section><tid>517366</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Save as provided in this Act, no person shall be present at any 
sitting of a competent authority, except--

<subsection><tid>1093166</tid>
<number>a</number>any officer of the competent authority, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1414003</tid>
<number>b</number>the parties to the inquiry before the competent 
authority, the parent or guardian of the child and 
other persons directly
<pagefootnote><pagenum>45</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 15 of <year>1978</year>, s. 14, for" section 239 of the Code of 
Criminal Procedure, <year>1898</year>".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


concerned in the inquiry including police officers 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> and legal practitioners], and


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>719526</tid>
<number>c</number>such other persons as the competent authority may permit 
to be present.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>898037</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), if at 
any stage during an inquiry, a competent authority considers it to be 
expedient in the interest of the child or on grounds of decency or 
morality that any person including the police officers, legal 
practitioners, the parent, guardian or the child himself should 
withdraw, the competent authority may give such direction, and if any 
person refuses to comply with such direction, the competent authority 
may have him removed and may, for this purpose, cause to be used 
such force as may be necessary.
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[ (3) No legal practitioner shall be entitled to appear before 
a Board in any case or proceeding before it, except with the special 
permission of that Board.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>400881</tid>
<number>29</number>Attendance of parent or guardian of child. Any competent 
authority before which a child is brought under any of the provisions 
of this Act may, whenever it so thinks fit, require any parent or 
guardian having the actual charge of, or control over, the child to be 
present at any proceeding in respect of the child.

</article>



<article><tid>1003718</tid>
<number>30</number>Dispensing with attendance of child. If, at any stage during 
the course of an inquiry, a competent authority is satisfied that the 
attendance of the child is not essential for the purpose of the 
inquiry, the competent authority may dispense with his attendance 
and proceed with the inquiry in the absence of the child.

</article>



<article><tid>1925366</tid>
<number> 31</number> Committal to approved place of child suffering from dangerous 
disease and its future disposal.
<section><tid>199328</tid>
<number>1</number>When a child who has been brought  
before a competent authority under this Act is found to be suffering 
from a disease requiring prolonged medical treatment or physical or 
mental complaint that will respond to treatment, the competent 
authority may send the child to any place recognised to be an approved 
place in accordance with the rules made under this Act for such period 
as it may think necessary for the required treatment.

</section>

<section><tid>1239738</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a child is found to be suffering from leprosy or is of 
unsound mind, he shall be dealt with under the provisions of the 
Lepers Act, <year>1898</year> (3 of <year>1898</year>) or the Indian Lunacy Act, <year>1912</year> (4 of  
  <year>1912</year>), as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1347785</tid>
<number>3</number>Where a competent authority has taken action under sub- 
section (1) in the case of a child suffering from an infectious or 
contagious disease,
<pagefootnote><pagenum>46</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 15 of <year>1978</year>, s. 15. 
2. Subs. by s. 15, ibid., for the original sub- section.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


the competent authority before restoring the said child to his partner 
in marriage, if there has been such, or to the guardian, as the case 
may be, shall where it is satisfied that such action will be in the 
interest of the said child call upon his partner in marriage or the 
guardian, as the case may be, to satisfy the court by submitting to 
medical examination that such partner or guardian will not re- infect 
the child in respect of whom the order has been passed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>100894</tid>
<number> 32</number> Presumption and determination of age.
<section><tid>1663028</tid>
<number>1</number>Where it appears to  
a competent authority that a person brought before it under any of the 
provisions of this Act (otherwise than for the purpose of giving  
  evidence) is a child, the competent authority shall make due inquiry 
as to the age of that person and for that purpose shall take such 
evidence as may be necessary and shall record a finding whether the 
person is a child or not, stating his age as nearly as may be.

</section>

<section><tid>9165</tid>
<number>2</number>No order of a competent authority shall be deemed to have 
become invalid merely by any subsequent proof that the person in 
respect of whom the order has been made is not a child, and the age 
recorded by the competent authority to be the age of the person so 
brought before it shall, for the purposes of this Act, be deemed to be 
the true age of that person.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1293631</tid>
<number> 33</number> Circumstances to be taken into consideration in making orders 
under the Act. In making any order in respect of a child under this 
Act, a competent authority shall take into consideration the following 
circumstances, namely:--
<section><tid>1870937</tid>
<number>a</number>the age of the child;

</section>

<section><tid>1993142</tid>
<number>b</number>the circumstances in which the child is living;

</section>

<section><tid>151265</tid>
<number>c</number>the reports made by the probation officer;

</section>

<section><tid>1660591</tid>
<number>d</number>the religious persuasion of the child;

</section>

<section><tid>1567734</tid>
<number>e</number>such other circumstances as may, in the opinion of the 
competent authority, require to be taken into 
consideration in the interests of the child:
Provided that in the case of a delinquent child, the above 
circumstances shall be taken into consideration after the children' s 
court has recorded a finding against the child that he has committed 
the offence:

Provided further that if no report of the probation officer is 
received within ten weeks of his being informed under section 19, it 
shall be open to the children' s court to proceed without it.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>268170</tid>
<number>34</number>Sending a child outside jurisdiction. In the case of a 
neglected or delinquent child whose ordinary place of residence lies 
outside the jurisdiction of the competent authority before which he is 
brought, the competent authority may, if satisfied after due

<pagefootnote><pagenum>47</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

inquiry that it is expedient so to do, send the child back to a 
relative or other person who is fit and willing to receive him at his 
ordinary place of residence and exercise proper care and control over 
him, notwithstanding that such place of residence is outside the 
jurisdiction of the competent authority; and the competent authority 
exercising jurisdiction over the place to which the child is sent 
shall in respect of any matter arising sub- sequently have the same 
powers in relation to the child as if the original order had been 
passed by itself.


</article>



<article><tid>85357</tid>
<number>35</number>Reports to be treated as confidential. The report of the 
probation officer or any circumstance considered by the competent 
authority under section 33 shall be treated as confidential:
Provided that the competent authority may, if it so thinks fit, 
communicate the substance thereof to the child or his parent or 
guardian and may give such child, parent or guardian an opportunity of 
producing such evidence as may be relevant to the matter stated in the 
report.


</article>



<article><tid>538121</tid>
<number> 36</number> Prohibition of publication of names, etc., of children 
involved in any proceeding under the Act.
<section><tid>267273</tid>
<number>1</number>No report in any  
newspaper, magazine or news sheet of any inquiry regarding a child 
under this Act shall disclose the name, address or school or any other 
particulars calculated to lead to the identification of the child, nor 
shall any picture of any such child be published:
Provided that for reasons to be recorded in writing, the 
authority holding the inquiry may permit such disclosure, if in its 
opinion such disclosure is in the interest of the child.


</section>

<section><tid>115089</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person contravening the provisions of sub- section (1) 
shall be punishable with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>349195</tid>
<number> 37</number> Appeals.
<section><tid>296110</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of this section, any  
person aggrieved by an order made by a competent authority under this 
Act may, within thirty days from the date of such order, prefer an 
appeal to the court of session:
Provided that the court of session may entertain the appeal after 
the expiry of the said period of thirty days if it is satisfied that 
the appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from filing the appeal 
in time.


</section>

<section><tid>1366308</tid>
<number>2</number>No appeal shall lie from--

<subsection><tid>82165</tid>
<number>a</number>any order of acquittal made by the children' s court in 
respect of a child alleged to have committed an 
offence; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>162990</tid>
<number>b</number>any order made by a Board in respect of a finding that a 
person is not a neglected child.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>48</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1740773</tid>
<number>3</number>No second appeal shall lie from any order of the court of 
session passed in appeal under this section.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>302876</tid>
<number>38</number>Revision. The High Court may, at any time, either of its own 
motion or on an application received in this behalf, call for the 
record of any proceeding in which any competent authority or court of 
session has passed an order for the purpose of satisfying itself as to 
the legality or propriety of any such order and may pass such order in 
relation thereto as it thinks fit:
Provided that the High Court shall not pass an order under this 
section prejudicial to any person without giving him a reasonable 
opportunity of being heard.


</article>



<article><tid>57740</tid>
<number> 39</number> Procedure in inquiries, appeals and revision proceedings.
<section><tid>1987334</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Save as otherwise expressly provided by this Act, a competent 
authority while holding any inquiry under any of the provisions of 
this Act, shall follow such procedure as may be prescribed and subject 
thereto, shall follow, as far as may be, the procedure laid down in 
the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>)], for trials in 
summons cases.

</section>

<section><tid>788520</tid>
<number>2</number>Save as otherwise expressly provided by or under this Act, 
the procedure to be followed in hearing appeals or revision proceeding 
under this Act shall be, as far as practicable, in accordance with the 
provisions of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>)].


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1214652</tid>
<number> 40</number> Power to amend orders.
<section><tid>1850740</tid>
<number>1</number>Without prejudice to the  
provisions for appeal and revision under this Act, any competent 
authority may, either on its own motion or on an application 
received in this behalf, amend any order as to the institution to 
which a child as to be sent or as to the person under as to the 
institution to which a child is to be sent or as to the person under 
whose care or supervision as child is to be placed under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1659732</tid>
<number>2</number>Clerical mistakes in orders passed by a competent authority 
or errors arising therein from any accidental slip or omission may, at 
any time, be corrected by the competent authority either on its own 
motion or on an application received in this behalf.
CHAP 
SPECIAL OFFENCES IN RESPECT OF CHILDREN

CHAPTER VI

SPECIAL OFFENCES IN RESPECT OF CHILDREN



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1830622</tid>
<number> 41</number> Punishment for cruelty to child.
<section><tid>452371</tid>
<number>1</number>Whoever, having the  
actual charge of, or control over, a child, assaults, abandons, 
exposes or wilfully neglects the child or causes or procures him to be 
assaulted, abandoned, exposed or neglected in a manner

<pagefootnote><pagenum>49</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 15 of <year>1978</year>, s. 2, for" Code of Criminal Procedure, 
<year>1898</year>".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

likely to cause such child unnecessary mental and physical suffering 
shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
six months, or with fine, or with both.


</section>

<section><tid>1484708</tid>
<number>2</number>No court shall take cognizance of an offence punishable under 
sub- section (1) unless the complaint is filed with the previous 
sanction of the Administrator or an officer authorised by him in this 
behalf.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1190600</tid>
<number> 42</number> Employment of children for begging.
<section><tid>1964663</tid>
<number>1</number>Whoever employs or  
uses any child for the purposes of begging or causes any child to beg 
shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
one year, or with fine, or with both.

</section>

<section><tid>77079</tid>
<number>2</number>Whoever, having the actual charge of, or control over, a 
child, abets the commission of the offence punishable under sub- 
section (1), shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which 
may extend to one year, or with fine, or with both.

</section>

<section><tid>292482</tid>
<number>3</number>The offence punishable under this section shall be 
congnizable.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1795253</tid>
<number>43</number>Penalty for giving intoxicating liquor or dangerous drug to 
a child. Whoever gives, or causes to be given to any child any 
intoxicating liquor in a public place or any dangerous drug, except 
upon the order of a duly qualified medical practitioner or in case of 
sickness or other urgent cause, shall be punishable with fine which 
may extend to two hundred rupees.

</article>



<article><tid>807154</tid>
<number>44</number>Exploitation of child employees. Whoever ostensibly procures 
a child for the purpose of any employment and withholds the earnings 
of the child or uses such earnings for his own purposes shall be 
punishable with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees.
CHAP 
MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER VII

MISCELLANEOUS


</article>



<article><tid>1267793</tid>
<number> 45</number> Power of Administrator to discharge and transfer children.

<section><tid>855611</tid>
<number>1</number>The Administrator may, notwithstanding anything contained in this  
Act, at any time, order neglected or delinquent child to be discharged 
from the children' s home or special school, either absolutely or on 
such conditions as he may think fit to impose.

</section>

<section><tid>281768</tid>
<number>2</number>The Administrator may, notwithstanding anything contained in 
this Act, order--

<subsection><tid>1995613</tid>
<number>a</number>a neglected child t be transferred from one children' s 
home to another;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>949216</tid>
<number>b</number>a delinquent child to be transferred from one special 
school to another or from a special school to a borstal 
school where

<pagefootnote><pagenum>50</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

such school exists or from a special school to a 
children' s home;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1901602</tid>
<number>c</number>a child who has been released on licence which has been 
revoked or forfeited, to be sent to the special school 
or children' s home from which he was released or to any 
other children' s home or special school or borstal 
school:
Provided that the total period of the stay of the child in a 
children' s home or a special school shall not be increased by such 
transfer.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>728671</tid>
<number>3</number>The Administrator may, notwithstanding anything contained in 
this Act, at any time, discharge a child from the care of any person 
under whom he was placed under this Act either absolutely or on such 
conditions as the Administrator may think fit to impose.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>110858</tid>
<number> 46</number> Transfers between children' s homes, etc., under the Act, and 
children' s homes, etc., of like nature in different parts of India.

<section><tid>496416</tid>
<number>1</number>The Administrator of a Union territory may direct any neglected  
child or delinquent child to be transferred from any children' s home 
or special school within the Union territory to any other children' s 
home, special school or institution of a like nature in any other 
State with the consent of the Government of that State.

</section>

<section><tid>39436</tid>
<number>2</number>The Administrator of a Union territory may, by general or 
special order, provide for the reception in a children' s home or 
special school within the Union territory of a neglected child or 
delinquent child detained in a children' s home or special school or 
institution of a like nature in any other State where the Government 
of that State makes an order for such transfer, and upon such transfer 
the provisions of this Act shall apply to such child as if he had been 
originally ordered to be sent to such children' s home or special 
school under this Act.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>330796</tid>
<number> 47</number> Transfer of children of unsound mind or suffering from 
leprosy.
<section><tid>191248</tid>
<number>1</number>Where it appears to the Administrator that any child kept  
in a special school or children' s home in pursuance of this Act is 
suffering from leprosy or is of unsound mind, the Administrator may 
order his removal to a leper asylum or mental hospital or other place 
of safe custody for being kept there for the remainder of the term for 
which he has to be kept in custody under the orders of the competent 
authority or for such further period as may be certified by a medical 
officer to be necessary for the proper treatment of the child.

</section>

<section><tid>1916334</tid>
<number>2</number>Where it appears to the Administrator that the child is cured 
of leprosy or of unsoundness of mind, he may, if the child is still 
liable to be kept in custody, order the person having charge of the 
child to send him to the special school or children' s home from which 
he was removed or, if the child is no longer liable to be kept in 
custody, order him to be discharged.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>51</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1063105</tid>
<number> 48</number> Placing out on licence.
<section><tid>849893</tid>
<number>1</number>When a child is kept in a  
children' s home or special school, the Administrator may, if he so 
thinks fit, release the child from the children' s home or special 
school and grant him a written licence for such period and on such 
conditions as may be specified in the licence permitting him to live 
with, or under the supervision of, any responsible person named in the 
licence willing to receive and take charge of him with a view to 
educate him and train him for some useful trade or calling.

</section>

<section><tid>1068714</tid>
<number>2</number>Any licence so granted under sub- section (1) shall be in 
force for the period specified in the licence or until revoked or 
forfeited by the breach of any of the conditions on whcih it was 
granted.

</section>

<section><tid>796867</tid>
<number>3</number>The Administrator may, at any time, by order in writing 
revoke any such licence and order the child to return to the 
children' s home or special school from which he was released or to any 
other children' s home or special school, and shall do so at the desire 
of the person with whom or under whose supervision the child has been 
permitted to live in accordance with a licence granted under sub- 
section (1).

</section>

<section><tid>1156719</tid>
<number>4</number>When a licence has been revoked or forfeited and the child 
refuses or fails to return to the special school or children' s home to 
which he was directed so to return the Administrator may, if 
necessary, cause him to be taken charge of and to be taken back to the 
special school or children' s home.

</section>

<section><tid>522122</tid>
<number>5</number>The time during which a child is absent from a special school 
or children' s home in pursuance of a licence granted under this 
section shall be deemed to be part of the time for which he is liable 
to be kept in custody in the special school or children' s home:
Provided that when a child has failed to return to the special 
school or children' s home on the licence being revoked or forfeited, 
the time which elapses after his failure so to return shall be 
excluded in computing the time during which he is liable to be kept in 
custody.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>430895</tid>
<number>49</number>Provision in respect of escaped children. Notwithstanding 
anything to the contrary contained in any other law for the time being 
in force, any police officer may take charge without warrant of a 
child who has escaped from a special school or a children' s home or 
from the care of a person under whom he was placed under this Act and 
shall send the child back to the special school or the children' s home 
or that person, as the case may be; and no proceeding shall be 
instituted in respect of the child by reason of such escape but the 
special school, children' s home or the person may, after giving the 
information to the competent authority which passed the order in 
respect of the child, take such steps against the child as may be 
deemed necessary.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>52</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</article>



<article><tid>1081717</tid>
<number> 50</number> Contribution by parents.
<section><tid>1616314</tid>
<number>1</number>The competent authority which  
makes an order for sending a neglected child or a delinquent child to 
a children' s home or a special school or placing the child under the 
care of a fit person may make an order requiring the parent or other 
person liable to maintain the child to contribute to his maintenance, 
if able to do so, in the prescribed manner.

</section>

<section><tid>377182</tid>
<number>2</number>The competent authority before making any order under sub- 
section (1) shall inquire into the circumstances of the parent or 
other person liable to maintain the child and shall record evidence, 
if any, in the presence of the parent or such other person, as the 
case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1509110</tid>
<number>3</number>The person liable to maintain a child shall, for the purposes 
of sub- section (1), include in the case of illegitimacy, his putative 
father:
Provided that where the child is illegitimate and an order for 
his maintenance has been made under <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> section 125 of the Code of 
Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>)], the competent authority shall 
not ordinarily make an order for contribution against the putative 
father, but may order the whole or any part of the sums accruing due 
under the said order for maintenance to be paid to such person as may 
be named by the competent authority and such sum shall be paid by him 
towards the maintenance of the child.


</section>

<section><tid>1745847</tid>
<number>4</number>Any order made under this section may be enforced in the same 
manner as an order under <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> section 125 of the Code of Criminal 
procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>)].


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1247576</tid>
<number>51</number>Control of custodian over child. Any person in whose custody 
a child is placed in pursuance of this Act shall, while the order is 
in force, have the like control over the child as he would have if he 
were his parent, and shall be responsible for his maintenance, and the 
child shall continue in his custody for the period stated by the 
competent authority, notwithstanding that he is claimed by his parent 
or any other person:
Provided that no child while in such custody shall be married 
except with the permission of the competent authority.


</article>



<article><tid>788363</tid>
<number>52</number>Delinquent child undergoing sentence at commencement of the 
Act. In any area in which this Act is brought into force, the 
Administrator may direct that a delinquent child who is undergoing any 
sentence of imprisonment at the commencement of this Act shall, in 
lieu of undergoing such sentence, be sent to a special school or be 
kept in safe custody in such place and manner as the Administrator 
thinks fit, for the remainder of the period of the sentence; and the 
provisions of this Act shall apply
<pagefootnote><pagenum>53</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 15 of <year>1978</year>, s. 16, for" section 488 of the Code of 
Criminal procedure, <year>1898</year>".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


to the child as if he had been ordered by a children' s court to be 
sent to such special school or, as the case may be, ordered to be 
detained under sub- section (2) of section 22.


</article>



<article><tid>1612557</tid>
<number> 53</number> Appointment of officers.
<section><tid>1967525</tid>
<number>1</number>The Administrator may appoint as  
many probation officers, officers for the inspection of special 
schools, children' s homes, observation homes or after- care 
organisations and such other officers as he may deem necessary for 
carrying out the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>93034</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be the duty of the probation officer-

<subsection><tid>1617450</tid>
<number>a</number>to inquire, in accordance with the direction of a 
competent authority, into the antecedents and family 
history of any child accused of an offence, with a view 
to assist the authority in making the inquiry;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1553513</tid>
<number>b</number>to visit neglected and delinquent children at such 
intervals as the probation officer may think fit;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1001868</tid>
<number>c</number>to report to the competent authority as to the behaviour 
of any neglected or delinquent child;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1953961</tid>
<number>d</number>to advise and assist neglected or delinquent children 
and, if necessary, endeavour to find them suitable 
employment;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>800533</tid>
<number>e</number>where a neglected or delinquent child is placed under 
the care of any person on certain conditions, to see 
whether such conditions are being complied with; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1563238</tid>
<number>f</number>to perform such other duties as may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>427857</tid>
<number>3</number>Any officer empowered in this behalf by the Administrator may 
enter any special school, children' s home, observation home or after- 
care organisation and make a complete inspection thereof in all its 
departments and of all papers, registers and accounts relating thereto 
and shall submit the report of such inspection to the Administrator.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1212111</tid>
<number>54</number>Officers appointed under the Act to be public servants. 
Probation officers and other officers appointed in pursuance of this 
Act shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of 
section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>).

</article>



<article><tid>1733865</tid>
<number>55</number>Procedure in respect of bonds. The provisions of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Chapter 
XXXIII of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>)], shall, 
as far as may be, apply to bonds taken under this Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>54</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 15 of <year>1978</year>, s. 17, for" Chapter XLII of the Code of 
Criminal Procedure, <year>1898</year>".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>524980</tid>
<number>56</number>Delegation of powers. The Administrator may, by general or 
special order, direct that any power exercisable by him under this Act 
shall, in such circumstances and under such conditions, if any, as may 
be specified in the order, be exercisable also by an officer 
subordinate to the Administrator.

</article>



<article><tid>6701</tid>
<number>57</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit or other 
legal proceeding shall lie against the Administrator or any probation 
officer or other officer appointed under this Act in respect of 
anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in 
pursuance of this Act or of any rules or orders made thereunder.

</article>



<article><tid>1491826</tid>
<number> 58</number> Act 8 of <year>1897</year> and certain provisions of Act 2 of <year>1974</year> not to 
apply.
<section><tid>1989510</tid>
<number>1</number>The Reformatory Schools, Act, <year>1897</year> (8 of <year>1897</year>), and  
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> section 27 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>)], 
shall cease to apply to any area in which this Act has been brought 
into force.

</section>

<section><tid>987027</tid>
<number>2</number>The Women' s and Children' s Institutions (Licensing) Act, <year>1956</year> 
 (105 of <year>1956</year>), shall not apply to any children' s home, special school 
or observation home established and maintained under this Act.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>893971</tid>
<number> 59</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1696683</tid>
<number>1</number>The Administrator may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the 
purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1829935</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>232311</tid>
<number>a</number>the places at which, the days on which, the time at 
which, and the manner in which, a competent authority 
may hold its sittings;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1714590</tid>
<number>b</number>the procedure to be followed by a competent authority in 
holding inquiries under this Act; and the mode of 
dealing with children suffering from dangerous diseases 
or mental complaints;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>656870</tid>
<number>c</number>the circumstances in which, and the conditions subject 
to which, an institution may be certified as a special 
school or a children' s home or recognised as an 
observation home, and the certification or recognition 
withdrawn;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1108137</tid>
<number>d</number>the internal management of special schools, children' s 
home and observation homes <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> and the standards and the 
nature of services to be maintained by them];

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>795890</tid>
<number>e</number>the functions and responsibilities of special schools, 
children' s homes and observation homes;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>55</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 15 of <year>1978</year>, s. 18, for" section 29B and section 399 
of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1898</year>". 
2. Added by s. 19, ibid.

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>647792</tid>
<number>f</number>the inspection of special schools, children' s homes, 
observation homes and after- care organisations;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1506202</tid>
<number>g</number>the establishment, management and functions of after- 
care organisations; the circumstances in which, and 
the conditions subject to which, an institution may 
be recognised as an after- care organisation <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> and 
such other matters as are referred to in section 12];

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1525414</tid>
<number>h</number>the qualifications and duties of probation officers;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>619740</tid>
<number>i</number>the recruitment and training of persons appointed to 
carry out the purposes of this Act and the terms and 
conditions of their service;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1054128</tid>
<number>j</number>the conditions subject to which a girl who is a 
neglected or delinquent child may be escorted from 
one place to another, and the manner in which a 
child may be sent outside the jurisdiction of a 
competent authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1395432</tid>
<number>k</number>the manner in which contribution for the maintenance of 
a child may be ordered to be paid by a parent or 
guardian;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1269148</tid>
<number>l</number>the conditions under which a child may be placed out on 
licence and the form and conditions of such licence;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1540513</tid>
<number>m</number>the conditions subject to which children may be placed 
under the care of any parent, guardian or other 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> fit person or fit institution] under Act and the 
obligations of such <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> persons or institutions] 
towards the children so placed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>205413</tid>
<number>n</number>any other matter which has to be, or may be, 
prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>781612</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon 
as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it 
is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised 
in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to be 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.]


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1025606</tid>
<number> 60</number> Repeal and savings. If, immediately before the date on which 
this Act comes into force in any area, there is in force in that area, 
any law corresponding to this Act, that law shall stand repealed on 
the said date:
<pagefootnote><pagenum>56</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Added by Act 15 of <year>1978</year>, s. 19. 
2. Subs. by s. 19, ibid., for" fit person". 
3. Subs. by s. 19, ibid., for" persons". 
4. Subs. by s. 19, ibid., for the original sub- section.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Provided that the repeal shall not affect--

<section><tid>87341</tid>
<number>a</number>the previous operation of any law so repealed or 
anything duly done or suffered thereunder; or

</section>

<section><tid>1067914</tid>
<number>b</number>any right, privilege obligation or liability acquired, 
accrued or incurred under any law so repealed; or

</section>

<section><tid>1087100</tid>
<number>c</number>any penalty, forfeiture or punsishment incurred in 
respect of any offence committed against any law so 
repealed; or

</section>

<section><tid>1387482</tid>
<number>d</number>any investigation, legal proceeding or remedy in 
respect of any such right, privilege, obligation, 
liability, penalty, forfeiture or punishment as 
aforesaid;
and any such investigation, legal proceeding or remedy may be 
instituted, continued or enforced and any such penalty, forfeiture or 
punishment may be imposed, as if this Act had not been passed.



</section>

</article>



 </act>