<act><title>

THE 
BUREAU 
    OF INDIAN STANDARDS ACT, 1986</title> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title, extent and 
    commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Bureau of Indian Standards Act, 1986.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends to the whole 
    of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall come into 
    force on such date1 as 
    the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    appoint.





  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
    this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>   “article” means (as respects standardisation and marking) any substance, artificial or natural, or partly 
    artificial or partly natural, whether raw or partly or wholly processed or 
    manufactured;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   “Bureau” means the Bureau of 
    Indian Standards established under section 3;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   “consumer” means a consumer of 
    any article or process;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   “covering” includes any 
    stopper, cask, bottle, vessel, box, crate, cover, capsule, case, frame, 
    wrapper or other container;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   “Executive Committee” means 
    the Executive Committee constituted under sub-section (1) of section 4;
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   “Fund” means the fund 
    constituted under section 18;
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>   “Indian Standard” means the 
    standard (including any tentative or provisional standard) established and 
    published by the Bureau, in relation to any article or process indicative of 
    the quality and specification of such article or process and includes—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   any standard recognized 
    by the Bureau under clause (b) of section 10; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   any standard established and 
    published, or recognized, by the Indian Standards Institution and which is 
    in force immediately before the date of establishment of the Bureau;
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>h</number>   “Indian Standards Institution” 
    means the Indian Standards Institution set up under the Resolution of the 
    Government of India in the late Department of Industries and Supplies No. 1 
    Std. (4)/45, dated the 3rd day of September, 1946, and registered under the 
    Societies Registration Act, 1860 (21 of 1860);
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>   “inspecting officer” means an 
    inspecting officer appointed under section 25;
 </section><section>
<number>j</number>   “licence” means a licence 
    granted under section 15 to use the Indian Standards Certification Mark in 
    relation to any article or process which conforms to the Indian Standard and 
    includes any licence granted under the Indian Standards Institution 
    (Certification Marks) Act, 1952 (36 of 1952) and is in force immediately 
    before the date of establishment of the Bureau;
 </section><section>
<number>k</number>   “manufacturer” means the 
    manufacturer of any article or process;
 </section><section>
<number>l</number>   “mark” includes a device, 
    brand, heading, label, ticket, pictorial representation, name, signature, 
    word, letter or numeral or any combination thereof;
 </section><section>
<number>m</number>   “member” means a member of the 
    Bureau;
 </section><section>
<number>n</number>   “prescribed” means prescribed 
    by rules made under this Act;
 </section><section>
<number>o</number>   “process” includes any 
    practice, treatment and mode of manufacture of any article;
 </section><section>
<number>p</number>   “registering authority” means 
    any authority competent under any law for the time being in force to 
    register any company, firm or other body of persons, or any trade mark or 
    design, or to grant a patent;
 </section><section>
<number>q</number>   “regulations” means 
    regulations made by the Bureau under this Act;
 </section><section>
<number>r</number>   “rules” means rules made by 
    the Central Government under this Act;
 </section><section>
<number>s</number>   “specification” means a 
    description of an article or process as far as practicable by reference to 
    its nature, quality, strength, purity, composition, quantity, dimensions, 
    weight, grade, durability, origin, age, material, mode of manufacture or 
    other characteristics to distinguish it from any other article or process;
 </section><section>
<number>t</number>   “Standard Mark” means the 
    Bureau of Indian Standards Certification Mark specified by the Bureau to 
    represent a particular Indian Standard and also includes any Indian 
    Standards Institution Certification Mark specified by the Indian Standards 
    Institution;
 </section><section>
<number>u</number>   “trade mark” means a mark used 
    or proposed to be used in relation to goods for the purpose of indicating, 
    or so as to indicate, a connection in the course of trade between the goods 
    and some person having the right, either as proprietor or as registered 
    user, to use the mark, whether with or without any indication of the 
    identity of that person;
 </section><section>
<number>v</number>   an article is said to be 
    marked with a Standard Mark if the article itself is marked with a Standard 
    Mark or any covering containing, or label attached to, such article is so 
    marked.
 
 

  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Establishment and 
    incorporation of Bureau of Indian Standards.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    With effect from such date as the Central Government may, by notification in 
    the Official Gazette, appoint in this behalf, there shall be established for 
    the purposes of this Act, a Bureau, to be called the Bureau of Indian 
    Standards.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Bureau shall be a 
    body corporate by the name aforesaid, having perpetual succession and a 
    common seal, with power, subject to the provisions of this Act, to acquire, 
    hold and dispose of property, both movable and immovable, and to contract 
    and shall by the said name sue and be sued.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    The Bureau shall consist of the following members, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the 
    Minister in charge of the Ministry or Department of the Central Government 
    having administrative control of the Bureau who shall be ex-officio 
    President of the Bureau;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   the 
    Minister of State or a Deputy Minister, if any, in the Ministry or 
    Department of the Central Government having administrative control of the 
    Bureau who shall be ex-officio Vice-President of the Bureau, and 
    where there is no such Minister of State or Deputy Minister, such person as 
    may be nominated by the Central Government to be the Vice-President of the 
    Bureau;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   the 
    Secretary to the Government of India in charge of the Ministry or Department 
    of the Central Government having administrative control of the Bureau 
    ex-officio;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   the 
    Director-General of the Bureau ex-officio;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   such 
    number of other persons, to represent the Government, industry, scientific 
    and research institutions, and other interests, as may be prescribed, to be 
    appointed by the Central Government.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    The term of office of the members referred to in clause (e) of sub-section 
    (3) and the manner of filling vacancies among, and the procedure to be 
    followed in the discharge of their functions, by the members, shall be such 
    as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> 
    The Bureau may associate with itself, in such manner and for such purposes 
    as may be prescribed, any persons whose assistance or advice it may desire 
    in complying with any of the provisions of this Act and a person so 
    associated shall have the right to take part in the discussions of the 
    Bureau relevant to the purposes for which he has been associated but shall 
    not have the right to vote.
 
 

  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Constitution of Executive Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Bureau may, with the prior approval of the Central Government, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, constitute an Executive Committee 
    which shall consist of the following members, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   
    Director-General of the Bureau, who shall be its ex-officio Chairman;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   such 
    number of members, as may be prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Executive 
    Committee, constituted under sub-section (1) shall perform, exercise and 
    discharge such of the functions, powers and duties of the Bureau as may be 
    delegated to it by the Bureau.
 
 

  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Constitution of the 
    Advisory Committees and other committees.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to any regulations made in this behalf, the Bureau may, from time to 
    time and as and when it is considered necessary, constitute the following 
    Advisory Committees for the efficient discharge of its functions, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   Financial Committee;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   Certification Advisory 
    Committee;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   Standards Advisory Committee;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   Laboratory Advisory Committee;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   Planning and Development 
    Advisory Committees;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   such number of other 
    committees as may be determined by regulations. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Each Advisory Committee 
    shall consist of a Chairman and such other members as may be determined by 
    regulations.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Without prejudice to 
    the powers contained in sub-section (1), the Bureau may constitute, as and 
    when considered necessary, such number of technical committees of experts 
    for the formulation of standards in respect of articles or processes.
 
 

  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Vacancies, etc., not to 
    invalidate proceedings of Bureau, Executive Committee, etc.—No 
    act or proceedings of the Bureau, the Executive Committee or any Committee 
    constituted under section 5 shall be invalid merely by reason of—
 <section>
<number>a</number>   any vacancy in, or any defect 
    in the constitution of the Bureau or the Committee; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   any defect in the appointment 
    of a person acting as a member of the Bureau or Committee; or
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   any irregularity in the 
    procedure of the Bureau or the Committee not affecting the merits of the 
    case.
 
 

  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Director-General of the 
    Bureau.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Central Government shall appoint a Director-General of the Bureau.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The terms and 
    conditions of service of the Director-General of the Bureau shall be such as 
    may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Subject to the general 
    superintendence and control of the Bureau, the Director-General of the 
    Bureau shall be the Chief Executive Authority of the Bureau.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Director-General of 
    the Bureau shall exercise and discharge such of the powers and duties of the 
    Bureau as may be determined by regulations.
  


  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Officers and employees 
    of the Bureau.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Bureau may appoint such other officers and employees as it considers 
    necessary for the efficient discharge of its functions under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The terms and 
    conditions of service of officers and employees of the Bureau appointed 
    under sub-section (1) shall be such as may be determined by regulations.
  



  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>9</number> 
      Transfer of assets, liabilities and employees of Indian standards 
      Institution.—
<section><number>1</number> On and from the date of 
      establishment of the Bureau,—
 <subsection><number>a</number>   any reference 
      to the Indian Standards Institution in any law other than this Act or in 
      any contract or other instrument shall be deemed as a reference to the 
      Bureau;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>   all properties 
      and assets, movable and immovable, of, or belonging to, the Indian 
      Standards Institution shall vest in the Bureau;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>   all the rights 
      and liabilities of the Indian Standards Institution shall be transferred 
      to, and be the rights and liabilities of, the Bureau;
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>   without 
      prejudice to the provisions of clause (c), all debts, obligations and 
      liabilities incurred, all contracts entered into and all matters and 
      things engaged to be done by, with or for the Indian Standards Institution 
      immediately before that date, for or in connection with the purposes of 
      the said Institution shall be deemed to have been incurred, entered into, 
      or engaged to be done by, with or for, the Bureau;
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>   all sums of 
      money due to the Indian Standards Institution immediately before that date 
      shall be deemed to be due to the Bureau;  
    due to the Bureau;" 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>   all suits and 
      other legal proceedings instituted or which could have been instituted by 
      or against the Indian Standards Institution immediately before that date 
      may be continued or may be instituted by or against the Bureau; 
      and
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number>   every employee 
      holding any office under the Indian Standards Institution immediately 
      before that date shall hold his office in the Bureau by the same tenure 
      and upon the same terms and conditions of service as respects 
      remuneration, leave, provident fund, retirement or other terminal benefits 
      as he would have held such office if the Bureau had not been established 
      and shall continue to do so as an employee of the Bureau or until the 
      expiry of a period of six months from that date if such employee opts not 
      to be the employee of the Bureau within such period.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> 
      Notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 
      (14 of 1947), or in any other law for the time being in force, the 
      absorption of any employee by the Bureau in its regular service under this 
      section shall not entitle such employee to any compensation under that Act 
      or other law and no such claim shall be entertained by any court, tribunal 
      or other authority.
   
  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Functions of the 
    Bureau.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Bureau may exercise such powers and perform such duties as may be assigned 
    to it by or under this Act and, in particular, such powers include the power 
    to—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   establish, publish and promote 
    in such manner as may be prescribed the Indian Standard, in relation to any 
    article or process;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   recognize as an Indian 
    Standard, in such manner as may be prescribed, any standard established by 
    any other Institution in India or elsewhere, in relation to any article or 
    process;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   specify a Standard Mark to be 
    called the Bureau of Indian Standards Certification Mark which shall be of 
    such design and contain such particulars as may be prescribed to represent a 
    particular Indian Standard;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   grant, renew, suspend or cancel 
    a licence for the use of the Standard Mark;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   levy fees for the grant or 
    renewal of any licence;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   make such inspection and take 
    such samples of any material or substance as may be necessary to see whether 
    any article or process in relation to which the Standard Mark has been used 
    conforms to the Indian Standard or whether the Standard Mark has been 
    improperly used in relation to any article or process with or without a licence;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>   seek recognition of the Bureau 
    and of the Indian Standards outside India on such terms and conditions as 
    may be mutually agreed upon by the Bureau with any corresponding institution 
    or organization in any country;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>   establish, maintain and 
    recognize laboratories for the purposes of standardization and quality 
    control and for such other purposes as may be prescribed;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>   undertake research for the 
    formulation of Indian Standards in the interests of consumers and 
    manufacturers;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>   recognize any institution in 
    India or outside which is engaged in the standardization of any article or 
    process or the improvement of the quality of any article or process;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>   provide services to 
    manufacturers and consumers of articles or processes on such terms and 
    conditions as may be mutually agreed upon;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>   appoint agents in India or 
    outside India for the inspection, testing and such other purposes as may be 
    prescribed;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number>   establish branches, offices or 
    agencies in India or outside;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>n</number>   inspect any article or 
    process, at such times and at such places as may be prescribed in relation 
    to which the Standard Mark is used or which is required to conform to the 
    Indian Standard by this Act or under any other law irrespective of whether 
    such article or process is in India or is brought or intended to be brought 
    into India from a place outside India;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>o</number>   co-ordinate activities of any 
    manufacturer or association of manufacturers or consumers engaged in 
    standardization and in the improvement of the quality of any article or 
    process or in the implementation of any quality control activities;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>p</number>   perform such other functions 
    as may be prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Bureau shall 
    perform its functions under this section in accordance with, and subject to, 
    such rules as may be made by the Central Government.
  



  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>11</number> Prohibition of improper 
    use of Standard Mark.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No person shall use, in relation to any article or process, or in the title 
    of any patent, or in any trade mark or design the Standard Mark or any 
    colourable imitation thereof, except under a licence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No person shall, 
    notwithstanding that he has been granted a licence, use in relation to any 
    article or process the Standard Mark or any colourable imitation thereof 
    unless such article or process conforms to the Indian Standard.
 
 

  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Prohibition of use of 
    certain names, etc.—No 
    person shall, except in such cases and under such conditions as may be 
    prescribed, use without the previous permission of the Bureau,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>   any name which so nearly 
    resembles the name of the Bureau as to deceive or likely to deceive the 
    public or which contains the expression “Indian Standard” or any 
    abbreviation thereof; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   any mark or trade mark in 
    relation to any article or process containing the expressions “Indian 
    Standard” or “Indian Standard Specification” or any abbreviation of such 
    expression.

  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Prohibition of 
    registration in certain cases.—
<section><number>1</number>Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in any law for the time being in force, no registering 
    authority shall—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   register any company, firm or 
    other body of persons which bears any name or mark; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   register a trade mark or 
    design which bears any name or mark; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   grant a patent, in respect of 
    an invention, which bears a title containing any name or mark, 

 
if the use of such name or mark is in 
    contravention of section 11 or section 12.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If any question arises 
    before a registering authority whether the use of any name or mark is in 
    contravention of section 11 or section 12, the registering authority may 
    refer the question to the Central Government whose decision thereon shall be 
    final.
  
  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>14</number> 
      Compulsory use of Standard Mark for articles and processes to certain 
      scheduled industries.—If the Central Government, 
      after consulting the Bureau, is of the opinion that it is necessary or 
      expedient so to do, in the public interest, it may, by order published in 
      the Official Gazette,—
 <section><number>a</number>   notify any 
      article or process of any scheduled industry which shall conform to the 
      Indian Standard; and
 </section><section><number>b</number>   direct the use 
      of the Standard Mark under a licence as compulsory on such article or 
      process.
 Explanation.—For the purposes of this 
      section, the expression “scheduled industry” shall have the meaning 
      assigned to it in the Industries (Development and Regulation) Act, 1951 
      (65 of 1951).
  
  
 
  
  
  </section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Grant of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Bureau may, by order, grant, renew, suspend or cancel a licence in such 
    manner as may be determined by regulations.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The grant or renewal of 
    the licence under sub-section (1) shall be subject to such conditions and on 
    payment of such fees as may be determined by regulations.
  



  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> Appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person aggrieved by an order made under section 15 may prefer an appeal 
    to the Central Government within such period as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No appeal shall be 
    admitted if it is preferred after the expiry of the period prescribed 
    therefore:
 
Provided that an appeal may 
    be admitted after the expiry of the period prescribed therefore if the 
    appellant satisfies the Central Government that he had sufficient cause for 
    not preferring the appeal within the prescribed period.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every appeal made under 
    this section shall be made in such form and shall be accompanied by a copy 
    of the order appealed against and by such fees as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The procedure for 
    disposing of an appeal shall be such as may be prescribed:
 
Provided that before 
    disposing of an appeal, the appellant shall be given a reasonable 
    opportunity of being heard.
  
  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> Grants and loans by the 
    Central Government.—The 
    Central Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in 
    this behalf, make to the Bureau grants and loans of such sums of money as 
    that Government may consider necessary.
  
  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    There shall be constituted a Fund to be called the Bureau of Indian 
    Standards Fund and there shall be credited thereto—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   any grants and loans made to 
    the Bureau by the Central Government under section 17;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   all fees and charges received 
    by the Bureau under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   all sums received by the 
    Bureau from such other sources as may be decided upon by the Central 
    Government.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Fund shall be 
    applied for meeting—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the salary, allowances and 
    other remuneration of the members, Director-General, officers and other 
    employees of the Bureau;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   expenses of the Bureau in the 
    discharge of its functions under section 10;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   expenses on objects and for 
    purposes authorised by this Act.
  
  

 
  
 

  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>19</number> Borrowing powers of the 
    Bureau.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Bureau may, with the consent of the Central Government or in accordance with 
    the terms of any general or special authority given to it by the Central 
    Government, borrow money from any source as it may deem fit for discharging 
    all or any of its functions under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Central Government 
    may guarantee in such manner as it thinks fit, the repayment of the 
    principal and the payment of interest thereon with respect to the loans 
    borrowed by the Bureau under sub-section (1).
  



  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> Budget.—The 
    Bureau shall prepare, in such form and at such time in each financial year 
    as may be prescribed, its budget for the next financial year, showing the 
    estimated receipts and expenditure of the Bureau and forward the same to the 
    Central Government.
  
  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>21</number> Annual report.—The 
    Bureau shall prepare, in such form and at such time in each financial year 
    as may be prescribed, its annual report, giving a full account of its 
    activities during the previous financial year, and submit a copy thereof to 
    the Central Government.
  
  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> Accounts and audit.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Bureau shall maintain proper accounts and other relevant records and 
    prepare an annual statement of accounts, in such form as may be prescribed 
    by the Central Government in consultation with the Comptroller and 
    Auditor-General of India.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The accounts of the 
    Bureau shall be audited by the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India at 
    such intervals as may be specified by him and any expenditure incurred in 
    connection with such audit shall be payable by the Bureau to the Comptroller 
    and Auditor-General.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Comptroller and 
    Auditor-General of India and any person appointed by him in connection with 
    the audit of the accounts of the Bureau shall have the same rights and 
    privileges and the authority in connection with such audit a the Comptroller 
    and Auditor-General generally has in connection with the audit of Government 
    accounts and, in particular, shall have the right to demand the production 
    of books, accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and to 
    inspect any of the offices of the Bureau.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The accounts of the 
    Bureau as certified by the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India or any 
    other person appointed by him in this behalf together with the audit report 
    thereon shall be forwarded annually to the Central Government and that 
    Government shall cause the same to be laid before each House of Parliament.
  
  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> Annual report to be 
    laid before Parliament.—The 
    Central Government shall cause the annual report to be laid, as soon as may 
    be after it is received, before each House of Parliament.
  
  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> Power of Central 
    Government to issue directions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Without prejudice to the foregoing provisions of this Act, the Bureau shall, 
    in the exercise of its powers or the performance of its functions under this 
    Act, be bound by such directions on questions of policy as the Central 
    Government may give in writing to it from time to time:
 
Provided that the Bureau 
    shall, as far as practicable, be given an opportunity to express its views 
    before any direction is given under this sub-section.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The decision of the 
    Central Government whether a question is one of policy or not shall be 
    final.
  
  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>25</number> Inspecting officer.—
<section><number>1</number>The 
    Bureau may appoint as many inspecting officers as may be necessary for the 
    purpose of inspecting whether any article or process in relation to which 
    the Standard Mark has been used conforms to the Indian Standard or whether 
    the Standard Mark has been properly used in relation to any article or 
    process with or without licence, and for the purpose of performing such 
    other functions as may be assigned to them.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to any rules 
    made under this Act, an inspecting officer shall have power to—
     
    power to—"
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   inspect any operation carried 
    on in connection with any article or process in relation to which the 
    Standard Mark has been used; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   take samples of any article or 
    of any material or substances used in any article or process, in relation to 
    which the Standard Mark has been used.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Every inspecting 
    officer shall be furnished by the Bureau with a certificate of appointment 
    as an inspecting officer and the certificate shall, on demand, be produced 
    by the inspecting officer.
  
  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>26</number> Power to search and 
    seizure.—
<section><number>1</number> If 
    the inspecting officer has reason to believe that any article or process in 
    relation to which the contravention of section 11 or section 12 has taken 
    place are secreted in any place, premises or vehicles, he may enter into and 
    search such place, premises or vehicle for such article or process.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where, as a result of 
    any search made under sub-section (1), any article or process has been found 
    in relation to which contravention of section 11 or section 12 has taken 
    place, he may seize such article and other things which, in his opinion, 
    will be useful for, or relevant to, any proceeding under this Act:
 
Provided that where it is 
    not practicable to seize any such article or thing, the inspecting officer 
    may serve on the owner an order that he shall not remove, part with, or 
    otherwise deal with, the article or things except with the previous 
    permission of the inspecting officer.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The provisions of the 
    Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), relating to searches and 
    seizures shall, so far as may be, apply to every search or seizure made 
    under this section.
  
  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>27</number> Delegation.—The 
    Bureau may, by general or special order in writing, delegate to any member, 
    member of the Executive Committee, officer of the Bureau or any other person 
    subject to such conditions, if any, as may be specified in the order, such 
    of its powers and functions under this Act (except the powers under section 
    38) as it may deem necessary.
  
  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>28</number> Power to obtain 
    information.—Every 
    licensee shall supply the Bureau with such information, and with such 
    samples of any material or substance used in relation to any article or 
    process, as the Bureau may require.
  
  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>29</number> Savings.—Nothing 
    in this Act shall exempt any person from any suit or other proceeding which 
    might, apart from this Act, be brought against him.
  
  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>30</number> Certain matters to be 
    kept confidential.—Any 
    information obtained by an inspecting officer or the Bureau from any 
    statement made or information supplied or any evidence given or from 
    inspection made under the provisions of this Act shall be treated as 
    confidential:
 
Provided that nothing in 
    this section shall apply to the disclosure of any information for the 
    purpose of prosecution under this Act.
  
  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>31</number> Members, officers and 
    employees of the Bureau to be public servants.—All 
    members, officers and other employees of the Bureau shall be deemed, when 
    acting or purporting to act in pursuance of any of the provisions of this 
    Act, to be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian 
    Penal Code (45 of 1860).
  
  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>32</number> Protection of action 
    taken in good faith.—No 
    suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Government 
    or any officer of the Government or any member, officer or other employee of 
    the Bureau for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done 
    under this Act or the rules or regulations made thereunder.
  
  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>33</number> Penalty for improper 
    use of Standard Mark, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person who contravenes the provisions of section 11, or section 12 or 
    section 14 or section 15 shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term 
    which may extend to one year or with fine which may extend to fifty thousand 
    rupees, or with both.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any court trying a 
    contravention under sub-section (1) may direct that any property in respect 
    of which the contravention has taken place shall be forfeited to the Bureau.
  



  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>34</number> Cognizance of offences 
    by courts.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No court shall take cognizance of any offence punishable under this Act, 
    save on a complaint made by or under the authority of the Government or 
    Bureau or by any officer empowered in this behalf by the Government or the 
    Bureau, or any consumer or any association recognised in this behalf by the 
    Central or State Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No court inferior to 
    that of a Metropolitan Magistrate or a Judicial Magistrate of the first 
    class specially empowered in this behalf shall try any offence punishable 
    under this Act.
  
  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>35</number> Offences by companies.—
<section><number>1</number>Where 
    an offence under this Act has been committed by a company, every person who 
    at the time the offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible 
    to, the company for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as 
    the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable 
    to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
 
Provided that nothing 
    contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to any 
    punishment provided in this Act, if he proves that the offence was committed 
    without his knowledge or that he had exercised all due diligence to prevent 
    the commission of such offence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence under this Act has 
    been committed by a company and it is proved that the offence has been 
    committed with the consent or connivance of, or is attributable to any 
    neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary or other officer of 
    the company, such director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also 
    be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded 
    against and punished accordingly.
 
Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   “company” means any body 
    corporate and includes a firm or other association of individuals; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   “director”, in relation to a 
    firm, means a partner in the firm.
  
  

 
  
 

  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>36</number> Authentication of 
    orders and other instruments of the Bureau.—All 
    orders and decisions of, and all other instruments issued by, the Bureau 
    shall be authenticated by the signature of such officer or officers as may 
    be authorised by the Bureau in this behalf.
  
  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>37</number> Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make 
    rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular, and 
    without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may 
    provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the number of members of the 
    Bureau and the interest such members would represent under clause (e) of 
    sub-section (3) of section 3;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   the term of office of the 
    members of the Bureau, the manner of filling vacancies and the procedure to 
    be followed in the discharge of their functions by, the members under 
    sub-section (4) of section 3;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   the manner in, and the 
    purposes for, which the Bureau may associate with itself any person for 
    assistance and advice under sub-section (5) of section 3;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   the number of members of the 
    Bureau who will be members of the Executive Committee under clause (b) of 
    sub-section (1) of section 4;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   the terms and conditions of 
    service of the Director-General of the Bureau under sub-section (2) of 
    section 7;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   the design and the particulars 
    to represent a particular Indian Standard under clause (c) of sub-section 
    (1) of section 10;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>   the purposes for which 
    laboratories for the purposes of standardisation and quality control shall 
    be established by the Bureau under clause (h) of sub-section (1) of section 
    10;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>   the purposes for which agents 
    may be appointed by the Bureau in India or outside India under clause (l) of 
    sub-section (1) of section 10;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>   the times and places at which 
    any article or process may be inspected under clause (n) of sub-section (1) 
    of section 10;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>   the additional functions that 
    may be performed by the Bureau under section 10;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>   the cases in which, and the 
    conditions subject to which, exemption may be granted under section 12;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>   the form in which, and the 
    time at which, the Bureau shall prepare its budget under section 20 and its 
    annual report under section 21;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number>   the manner in which the 
    accounts of the Bureau shall be maintained under section 22;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>n</number>   the conditions subject to 
    which inspecting officer may exercise his powers under sub-section (2) of 
    section 25;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>o</number>   any other matter which is to 
    be, or may be, prescribed, or in respect of which provision is to be, or may 
    be, made by rules.
  
  

 
  
 

  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>38</number> Power to make 
    regulations.—
<section><number>1</number>The 
    Executive Committee may, with the previous approval of the Central 
    Government, by notification in the Official Gazette, make regulations 
    consistent with this Act and the rules generally to carry out the purposes 
    of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular, and 
    without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such regulations 
    may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the members of the Advisory 
    Committees constituted under section 5;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   the powers and duties that may 
    be exercised and discharged by the Director-General of the Bureau under 
    sub-section (4) of section 7;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   the terms and conditions of 
    service of officers and employees of the Bureau under sub-section (2) of 
    section 8;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   the manner of grant, renewal, 
    suspension or cancellation of licence under sub-section (1) of section 15;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   the conditions subject to which 
    a licence may be granted or renewed and the fees payable therefor under 
    sub-section (2) of section 15.
  
  

 
  
 

  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>39</number> Rules and regulations 
    to be laid before Parliament.—Every 
    rule and every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may 
    be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in 
    session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one 
    session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of 
    the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
    aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
    regulation or both Houses agree that the rule or regulation should not be 
    made, the rule or regulation shall thereafter have effect only in such 
    modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
    such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of 
    anything previously done under that rule or regulation.
  
  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>40</number> Act not to affect 
    operation of certain Acts.—Nothing 
    in this Act shall affect the operation of the Agricultural Produce (Grading 
    and Marking) Act, 1937 (1 of 1937) or the Drugs and Cosmetics Act, 1940 (23 
    of 1940), or any other law, for the time being in force, which deals with 
    any standardization or quality control of any article or process.
  
  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>41</number> Power to remove 
    difficulties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the 
    Central Government may, by order, published in the Official Gazette, make 
    such provisions not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act as may 
    appear to be necessary for removing the difficulty:
 
Provided that no order 
    shall be made under this section after the expiry of five years from the 
    commencement of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every order made under 
    this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each 
    House of Parliament.
  
  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>42</number> Repeal and saving.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Indian Standards Institution (Certification Marks) Act, 1952 (36 of 
    1952), is hereby repealed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding such 
    repeal, anything done or any action taken or purported to have done or taken 
    (including any rule, regulation, notification, scheme, specification, Indian 
    Standard, Standard Mark, inspection order or notice made, issued or adopted, 
    or any appointment, or declaration made or any licence, permission, 
    authorisation or exemption granted or any document or instrument executed or 
    direction given or any proceedings taken or any penalty or fine imposed) 
    under the Act hereby repealed shall, in so far as it is not inconsistent 
    with the provisions of this Act, be deemed to have been done or taken under 
    the corresponding provisions of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The mention of 
    particular matters in sub-section (2) shall not be held to prejudice or 
    affect the general application of section 6 of the General Clauses Act, 1897 
    (10 of 1897) with regard to the effect of repeal.  
  

 
  
 

  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>