<act><title>

THE INSURANCE 
    REGULATORY AND DEVELOP­MENT AUTHORITY (FORM OF ANNUAL STATEMENT OF ACCOUNTS
    
    AND RECORDS) RULES, 2001</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority (Form 
    of Annual Statement of Accounts and Records) Rules, 2001. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “Act” means the Insurance Regulatory 
    and Development Authority Act, 1999 (41 of 1999);  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “annexure” means an annexure appended 
    to the Form;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “form” means a form appended to these 
    rules;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    all other words and expressions used in 
    these rules but not defined, and defined in the Act shall have the same 
    meaning respectively assigned to them in the Act.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Annual 
    statement of accounts and other relevant records.—At 
    the expiration of a period of twelve months ending with March 31, of every 
    year, the Authority shall prepare with reference to that period, a 
    balance‑sheet, an income and expenditure account and receipt and payment 
    account in the forms as specified below:
 <section>
<number>a</number>    balance‑sheet in Form “A”;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    income and expenditure account in Form 
    “B”;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    receipt and payment account in Form ‘C’.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Maintenance of accounts, etc.—The 
    Authority shall preserve the balance‑sheet, income and expenditure account 
    and receipt and payment account referred to in rule 3 above, for a minimum 
    period of five years following the year to which they relate.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Authorised signatory.—The 
    balance‑sheet, income and expenditure account and receipt and payment 
    account mentioned in rule 3 shall be signed by the Chief Accounts Officer, 
    if any, of the Authority and for purposes of authentication be signed by the 
    Chairman and two members of the Authority. 
  
 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>