<act><tid>654270</tid>
<title>THE PRIZE COMPETITIONS ACT, <year>1955</year></title>

ACT NO. 42 OF <year>1955</year>
[ 22nd October, <year>1955</year>.]

An Act to provide for the control and regulation of prize 
competitions.

WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the control and regulation 
of prize Competitions;

AND WHEREAS the Legislatures of the States of Andhra, Bombay, 
Madras, Orissa, Uttar Pradesh, Hyderabad, Madhya Bharat, Patiala and 
East Punjab States Union and Saurashtra have passed resolutions in 
terms of clause (1) of article 252 of the Constitution in relation to 
the above- mentioned matter and matters ancillary thereto in so far as 
such matters are matters enumerated in List II in the Seventh Schedule 
to the Constitution;

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Sixth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>1124070</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1738974</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Prize Competitions Act, <year>1955</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1485940</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the territories which, immediately before the 
 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in] the States of Andhra, Bombay, 
Madras, Orissa, Uttar Pradesh, Hyderabad, Madhya Bharat, Patiala and 
East Punjab States Union and Saurashtra and all Part C States.

</section>

<section><tid>898362</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1806566</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>1257045</tid>
<number>a</number>" licensing authority" means any officer or authority 
appointed by the State Government, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, for the purpose of granting licences under 
this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1838945</tid>
<number>b</number>" money" includes a cheque, postal- order or money- 
order;

</section>

<section><tid>1554303</tid>
<number>c</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under 
this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1200122</tid>
<number>d</number>" prize competition" means any competition (whether  
called a cross- word prize competition, a missing- word prize 
competition, a picture prize competition or by any other 
  name) in which prizes are offered for the solution of any

<pagefootnote><pagenum>696</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>.

Extended to and brought into force in Dadar and Nagar Haveli 
 (w. e. f. 1. 7. 65) by Reg. 6 of <year>1963</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I.

Extended to Goa, Daman and Diu by Reg. 11 of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 and sch.

Extended to the Union territory of Pondicherry by Act 26 of <year>1968</year>, 
s. 3 and Schedule.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number> 1st April, <year>1956</year>, vide Notification No. S. R. O. 766, dated 31st 
March, <year>1956</year>, Gazette of India, Extraordinary, Pt. II, Sec. 3, p. 647.







</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

puzzle based upon the building up, arrangement, combination 
or permutation, of letters, words, or figures.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1705021</tid>
<number> 3</number> Interpretation. For the purposes of this Act,-
<section><tid>1537422</tid>
<number>a</number>references to printing shall be construed as including 
references to writing and other modes of representing or re- 
producing letters, words or figures in a visible form; and

</section>

<section><tid>940693</tid>
<number>b</number>documents or other matters shall be deemed to be 
distributed if they are distributed to persons or places 
within or outside the territories to which this Act extends 
and the word distribution' shall be construed accordingly.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>835659</tid>
<number>4</number>Prohibition of prize competitions where the prize offered 
exceeds one thousand rupees a month. No person shall promote or 
conduct any prize competition or competitions in which the total value 
of the prize or prizes (whether in cash or otherwise) to be offered in 
any month exceeds one thousand rupees; and in every prize 
competition, the number of entries shall not exceed two thousand.


</article>



<article><tid>906286</tid>
<number>5</number>Licensing of prize competitions where the prize offered does 
not exceed one thousand rupees a month. Subject to the provisions of 
section 4, no person shall promote or conduct any prize competition or 
competitions in which the total value of the prize or prizes (whether  
  in cash or otherwise) to be offered in any month does not exceed one 
thousand rupees unless he has obtained in this behalf a licence 
granted in accordance with the provisions of this Act and the rules 
made thereunder.


</article>



<article><tid>1798948</tid>
<number> 6</number> Licences for prize competitions.
<section><tid>965126</tid>
<number>1</number>Every person desiring to  
obtain a licence referred to in section 5 shall make an application in 
writing to the licensing authority in such form and manner as may be 
prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1215608</tid>
<number>2</number>On the receipt of such application, the licensing authority, 
after making such inquiry as it considers necessary, shall, by order 
in writing, either grant the licence or refuse to grant the licence.

</section>

<section><tid>1677031</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the licensing authority refuses to grant a licence it 
shall record a brief statement of the reasons for such refusal and 
furnish a copy thereof to the applicant.

</section>

<section><tid>325626</tid>
<number>4</number>The fees on payment of which, the period for which, the con- 
ditions subject to which, and the form in which, a licence may be 
granted shall be such as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>453196</tid>
<number>7</number>Promoters of prize competitions to keep accounts and submit the 
same to the licensing authority. Every person who promotes or conducts 
a prize competition in accordance with the provisions of this Act and 
the rules made thereunder shall keep accounts relating to such 
competition and submit to the licensing authority a statement of 
accounts in such form and at such intervals as may be prescribed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>697</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>325520</tid>
<number> 8</number> Power to cancel or suspend licences.
<section><tid>294174</tid>
<number>1</number>The licensing  
authority may, after giving the holder of any licence under this Act a 
reasonable opportunity of being heard, cancel or suspend the licence 
on any one or more of the following grounds, namely:

<subsection><tid>1424637</tid>
<number>a</number>that there has been a breach of any of the conditions 
subject to which the licence was granted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1496180</tid>
<number>b</number>that the holder of the licence has contravened any of 
the provisions of section 7.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>22996</tid>
<number>2</number>Whenever a licence is cancelled or suspended the licensing 
authority shall record a brief statement of the reasons for such can- 
cellation or suspension and furnish a copy thereof to the person whose 
licence has been cancelled or suspended.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1409871</tid>
<number>9</number>Penalty for promoting or conducting any prize competition in 
contravention of the provisions of sections 4 and 5. If any person 
promotes or conducts any prize competition in contravention of the 
provisions of section 4 or section 5, he shall be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to three months, or with 
fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both.


</article>



<article><tid>84043</tid>
<number>10</number>Penalty for failure to keep and submit accounts. If any 
person liable under section 7 to keep accounts or to submit statements 
of accounts fails to keep accounts or to submit statements of accounts 
as required by that section or keeps accounts or submits statements of 
accounts which are false and which he either knows or believes to be 
false or does not believe to be true, he shall be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to one month, or with fine 
which may extend to five hundred rupees, or with both, but nothing 
contained in this section shall affect the provisions contained in 
section B.


</article>



<article><tid>864034</tid>
<number> 11</number> Penalty for other offences in connection with prize 
competitions. If any person with a view to the promotion or conduct 
of any prize competition except in accordance with the provisions of a 
licence under this Act or in contravention of the provisions of this 
Act or in connection with any prize competition promoted- or conducted 
except in accordance with such provisions-
<section><tid>163012</tid>
<number>a</number>prints or publishes any ticket, coupon or other 
document for use in the prize competition; or

</section>

<section><tid>1147256</tid>
<number>b</number>sells or distributes or offers or advertises for sale 
or distribution, or has in his possession for the purpose of 
sale or distribution any ticket, coupon or other document for 
use in the prize competition; or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>698</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>705531</tid>
<number>c</number>prints, publishes or distributes, or has in his 
possession for the purpose of publication or distribution,-

<subsection><tid>1999723</tid>
<number>i</number>any advertisement of the prize competition, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1461084</tid>
<number>ii</number>any list (whether complete or not) of prize 
winners in the prize competition, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1529337</tid>
<number>iii</number>any such matter descriptive of, or otherwise 
relating to, the prize competition as is calculated to 
act as an inducement to persons to participate in that 
prize competition or any other prize competition; or

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1182566</tid>
<number>d</number>brings, or invites any person to send, into the 
territories to which this Act extends, for the purpose of 
sale or distribution, any ticket, coupon or other document 
for use in, or any advertisement of, the prize competition; 
or

</section>

<section><tid>690182</tid>
<number>e</number>sends, or attempts to send, out of the territories to 
which this Act extends any money or valuable thing received 
in respect of the sale or distribution of any ticket, coupon 
or other document for use in the prize competition; or

</section>

<section><tid>1470891</tid>
<number>f</number>uses any premises, or causes or knowingly permits any 
premises to be used, for purposes connected with the pro- 
motion or conduct of the prize competition; or

</section>

<section><tid>1516970</tid>
<number>g</number>causes or procures or attempts to procure any person to 
do any of the above- mentioned acts,
he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to three months, or with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, 
or with both.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1017080</tid>
<number> 12</number> Offences by Corporations.
<section><tid>1211196</tid>
<number>1</number>If any person guilty of an  
offence under this, Act is a company, every person who at the time the 
offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible to, the 
company, as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of that 
offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished 
accordingly:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to any punishment provided in this Act if he 
proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or that 
he exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such 
offence.


</section>

<section><tid>107177</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where 
an offence under this Act has been committed with the consent or 
connivance of, or is attributable to gross neglect on the part of, any 
director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such

<pagefootnote><pagenum>699</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to 
be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against 
and punished accordingly.

Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,-


<subsection><tid>694548</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means a body corporate and includes a firm 
or other association of individuals; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>492969</tid>
<number>b</number>" director" in relation to a firm means a partner in 
the firm.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>964227</tid>
<number> 13</number> Power of licensing authority to call for and inspect accounts and 
documents. The licensing authority may-
<section><tid>209015</tid>
<number>a</number>require any person promoting or conducting a prize 
competition to produce before it the accounts and other 
documents kept by such person or to furnish to it such other 
information relating to the prize competition as it may 
require;

</section>

<section><tid>1204226</tid>
<number>b</number>inspect at all reasonable times the accounts and other 
documents kept by such person.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1947438</tid>
<number> 14</number> Power of entry and search.
<section><tid>1676170</tid>
<number>1</number>It shall be lawful for any  
police- officer not below the rank of Sub- inspector authorised by the 
State Government in this behalf by general or special order in 
writing,-

<subsection><tid>958308</tid>
<number>a</number>to enter if necessary by force, whether by day or 
night, with such assistants as he considers necessary, any 
premises which he has reason to suspect, are being used for 
purposes connected with the promotion or conduct of any prize 
competition in contravention of the provisions of this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1197092</tid>
<number>b</number>to search the premises and the persons whom he may find 
herein;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1030950</tid>
<number>c</number>to take into custody and produce before a Magistrate 
all such persons as are concerned or against whom a reason- 
able complaint has been made or credible information has been 
received or a reasonable suspicion exists of their having 
been concerned with the user of such premises for purposes 
connected with, or with the promotion or conduct of, any 
prize competition in contravention of the provisions of this 
Act; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1003362</tid>
<number>d</number>to seize all things found therein which are intended to 
be used or reasonably suspected to have been used in 
connection with such prize competition.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1068028</tid>
<number>2</number>All searches under this section shall be made in accordance 
with the provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1898</year> (5 of <year>1898</year>).

<pagefootnote><pagenum>700</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


<pagefootnote><pagenum>15</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Forfeiture newspapers and publications containing prize competition.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1074852</tid>
<number>15</number>Forfeiture newspapers and publications containing prize 
competition. Where any newspaper or other publication contains any 
prize competition promoted or conducted in contravention of the provi- 
sions of this Act or except in accordance with the provisions of 
licence under this Act or any advertisement in relation thereto, the 
State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare 
every copy of the newspaper and every copy of the publication 
containing the prize competition or the advertisement, to be forfeited 
to Government.


</article>



<article><tid>1092896</tid>
<number>16</number>Appeals. Any person aggrieved by the decision of the licensing 
authority refusing to grant a licence or cancelling or suspending a 
licence may, within such time as may be prescribed, prefer an appeal 
to the State Government and the decision of the State Government on 
such appeal shall be final.


</article>



<article><tid>1304942</tid>
<number>17</number>Licensing authority and other officers to be public servants. 
The licensing authority and any other officer acting under this Act 
shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of section 21 
of the Indian Penal Code 45 of <year>1860</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>300831</tid>
<number>18</number>Jurisdiction to try offences. No Court inferior to that of a 
Presidency Magistrate or a Magistrate of the first class shall try any 
offence under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>981725</tid>
<number>19</number>Protection of action taken under this act. No suit, 
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the licensing 
authority or any other officer of the Government for anything which is 
in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or the rules 
made thereunder.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>20</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Power to make rules.

</article>



<article><tid>392940</tid>
<number> 20</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1968138</tid>
<number>1</number>The State Government may, by notification  
in the Official Gazette, and subject to the condition of previous 
publication, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>75176</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of 
the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>868576</tid>
<number>a</number>the form and manner of application for a licence and the 
fees, if any, for such licence;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>529218</tid>
<number>b</number>the period for which, the conditions subject to which and 
the form in which, a licence may be granted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1492490</tid>
<number>c</number>the form in which and the intervals at which statements 
ofaccounts shall be submitted to the licensing authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1598894</tid>
<number>d</number>the time within which an appeal against a decision of the 
licensing authority may be preferred to the State Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1718611</tid>
<number>e</number>any other matter which is to be or may be prescribed.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



 </act>