<act><title>THE DESIGNS ACT, 2000 </title> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
This Act may be called the Designs Act, 2000.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends to the whole of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall come into force on such date1 as 
the Central Government may, by notification, in the Official Gazette, appoint; 
and different dates may be appointed for different provisions of this Act, and 
any reference in any such provision to the commencement of this Act shall be 
construed as a reference to the coming into force of that provision.
 
 


</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. —</title>In this Act, 
unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> “article” means any article of manufacture and any substance, 
  artificial, or partly artificial and partly natural; and includes any part of 
  an article capable of being made and sold separately; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> “Controller” means the Controller-General of Patents, Designs and Trade 
  Marks referred to in section 3; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> “copyright” means the exclusive right to apply a design to any article 
  in any class in which the design is registered; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> “design” means only the features of shape, configuration, pattern, 
  ornament or composition of lines or colours applied to any article whether in 
  two dimensional or three dimensional or in both forms, by any industrial 
  process or means, whether manual, mechanical or chemical, separate or 
  combined, which in the finished article appeal to and are judged solely by the 
  eye; but does not include any mode or principle of construction or anything 
  which is in substance a mere mechanical device, and does not include any trade 
  mark as defined in clause (v) of sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Trade and 
  Merchandise Marks Act, 1958 (43 of 1958) or property mark as defined in 
  section 479 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860) or any artistic work as 
  defined in clause (c) of section 2 of the Copyright Act, 1957 (14 of 1957); 
  
 </section><section><number>e</number> “High Court” shall have the same meaning as assigned to it in clause 
  (i) of section 2 of the Patents Act, 1970 (39 of 1970); 
 </section><section><number>f</number> “legal representative” means a person who in law represents the estate 
  of a deceased person; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> “original”, in relation to a design, means originating from the author 
  of such design and includes the cases which though old in themselves yet are 
  new in their application; 
 </section><section><number>h</number> “patent office” means the patent office referred to in section 74 of 
  the Patents Act, 1970 (39 of 1970); 
 </section><section><number>i</number> “prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act; 
 </section><section><number>j</number> “proprietor of a new or original design”,— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> where the author of the design, for good consideration, executes the 
    work for some other person, means the person for whom the design is so 
    executed; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> where any person acquires the design or the right to apply the 
    design to any article, either exclusively of any other person or otherwise, 
    means, in the respect and to the extent in and to which the design or right 
    has been so acquired, the person by whom the design or right is so acquired; 
    and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> in any other case, means the author of the design; and where the 
    property in or the right to apply, the design has devolved from the original 
    proprietor upon any other person, includes that other person. 
</subsection></section>

</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Controller and other officers. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The 
Controller-General of Patents, Designs and Trade Marks appointed under 
sub-section (1) of section 4 of the Trade and Merchandise Marks Act, 1958 (43 of 
1958) shall be the Controller of Designs for the purposes of this Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> For the purposes of this Act, the Central Government may appoint as many 
examiners and other officers with such designations as it thinks fit. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Subject to the provisions of this Act, the officers appointed under 
 sub-section (2) shall discharge under the superintendence and directions of 
the Controller such functions of the Controller under this Act as he may, 
 from time to time, by general or special order in writing, authorise them to 
discharge. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Without prejudice to the generality of the provisions of sub-section (3), 
the Controller may, by order in writing and for reasons to be recorded therein, 
withdraw any matter pending before an officer appointed under sub-section (2) 
and deal with such matter himself either de novo or from the stage it 
was so withdrawn or transfer the same to another officer appointed under 
sub-section (2) who may, subject to special directions in the order of transfer, 
proceed with the matter either de novo or from the stage it was so 
transferred. </section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Prohibition of registration of certain designs. </title>—A design 
which— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> is not new or original; or 
 </section><section><number>b</number> has been disclosed to the public anywhere in India or in any other 
  country by publication in tangible form or by use or in any other way prior to 
  the filing date, or where applicable, the priority date of the application for 
  registration; or 
 </section><section><number>c</number> is not significantly distinguishable from known designs or combination 
  of known designs; or 
 </section><section><number>d</number> comprises or contains scandalous or obscene matter, shall not be 
  registered. 
 <title>COMMENTS</title></section>
 The words ‘new or original' mean that the design which has been registered 
has not been published anywhere or it has not been made known to the public. It 
had been invented for the first time or it has not been reproduced by anyone; 
Bharat Glass Tube Ltd. v. Gopal Glass Works Ltd ., 2008 (10) 
SCC 657: 2008 (7) SCR 397. </article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Application for registration of designs. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The 
Controller may, on the application of any person claiming to be the proprietor 
of any new or original design not previously published in any country and which 
is not contrary to public order or morality, register the design under this Act: 

 Provided that the Controller shall before such registration refer the 
application for examination, by an examiner appointed under sub-section (2) of 
section 3, as to whether such design is capable of being registered under this 
Act and the rules made thereunder and consider the report of the examiner on 
such reference. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every application under sub-section (1) shall be in the prescribed form 
and shall be filed in the patent office in the prescribed manner and shall be 
accompanied by the prescribed fee. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> A design may be registered in not more than one class, and, in case of 
doubt as to the class in which a design ought to be registered, the Controller 
may decide the question. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Controller may, if he thinks fit, refuse to register any design 
presented to him for registration; but any person aggrieved by any such refusal 
may appeal to the High Court. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> An application which, owing to any default or neglect on the part of the 
applicant, has not been completed so as to enable registration to be effected 
within the prescribed time shall be deemed to be abandoned. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> A design when registered shall be registered as of the date of the 
application for registration. </section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Registration to be in respect of particular article. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> 
A design may be registered in respect of any or all of the articles comprised in 
a prescribed class of articles. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any question arising as to the class within which any article falls shall 
be determined by the Controller whose decision in the matter shall be final. 

 </section><section><number>3</number> Where a design has been registered in respect of any article comprised in 
a class of article, the application of the proprietor of the design to register 
it in respect of some one or more other articles comprised in that class of 
articles shall not be refused, nor shall the registration thereof invalidated— 

 
 <subsection><number>a</number> on the ground of the design not being a new or original design, by 
  reason only that it was so previously registered; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> on the ground of the design having been previously published in India 
  or in any other country, by reason only that it has been applied to article in 
  respect of which it was previously registered: </subsection>
 Provided that such subsequent registration shall not extend the period of 
copyright in the design beyond that arising from previous registration. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Where any person makes an application for the registration of a design in 
respect of any article and either— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> that design has been previously registered by another person in respect 
  of some other article; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the design to which the application relates consists of a design 
  previously registered by another person in respect of the same or some other 
  article with modifications or variations not sufficient to alter the character 
  or substantially to affect the identity thereof, then, if at any time while 
  the application is pending the applicant becomes the registered proprietor of 
  the design previously registered, the foregoing provisions of this section 
  shall apply as if at the time of making the application, the applicant had 
  been the registered proprietor of that design. </subsection>

</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Publication of particulars of registered designs. </title>—The 
Controller shall, as soon as may be after the registration of a design, cause 
publication of the prescribed particulars of the design to be published in such 
manner as may be prescribed and thereafter the design shall be open to public 
inspection. </article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Power of Controller to make orders regarding 
substitution of application, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If the Controller is satisfied on a claim made in the prescribed manner at any 
time before a design has been registered that by virtue of any assignment or 
agreement in writing made by the applicant or one of the applicants for 
registration of the design or by operation of law, the claimant would, if the 
design were then registered, be entitled thereto or to the interest of the 
applicant therein, or to an undivided share of the design or of that interest, 
the Controller may, subject to the provisions of this section, direct that the 
application shall proceed in the name of the claimant or in the names of the 
claimants and the applicant or the other joint applicant or applicants, 
accordingly, as the case may require.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No such direction as aforesaid shall be 
given by virtue of any assignment or agreement made by one of two or more joint 
applicants for registration of a design except with the consent of the other 
joint applicant or applicants.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No such direction as aforesaid shall be 
given by virtue of any assignment or agreement for the assignment of the benefit 
of a design unless—
 <subsection>        
<number>a</number>  the design is identified therein by reference to the number of the 
application for the registration; or
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>b</number>  there is produced to the Controller an acknowledgment by the person by whom 
the assignment or agreement was made that the assignment or agreement relates to 
the design in respect of which that application is made; or
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>c</number>  the rights of the claimant in respect of the design have been finally 
established by the decision of a court; or
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>d</number>  the Controller gives directions for enabling the application to proceed or 
for regulating the manner in which it should be proceeded with under sub-section 
(5).
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> Where one of two or more joint applicants 
for registration of a design dies at any time before the design has been 
registered, the Controller may, upon a request in that behalf made by the 
survivor or survivors, and with the consent of the legal representative of the 
deceased, direct that the application shall proceed in the name of the survivor 
or survivors alone.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If any dispute arises between joint 
applicants for registration of a design whether or in what manner the 
application should be proceeded with, the Controller may, upon application made 
to him in the prescribed manner by any of the parties, and after giving to all 
parties concerned an opportunity to be heard, give such directions as he thinks 
fit for enabling the application to proceed in the name of one or more of the 
parties alone or for regulating the manner in which it should be proceeded with, 
or for both those purposes, as the case may require.


</section></article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Certificate of registration.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Controller shall grant a certificate of registration to the proprietor of 
the design when registered.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Controller may, in case of loss of the 
original certificate, or in any other case in which he deems it expedient, 
furnish one or more copies of the certificate.
</section></article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Register of designs.—
<section><number>1</number> 
There shall be kept at the patent office a book called the register of designs, 
wherein shall be entered the names and addresses of proprietors of registered 
designs, notifications of assignments and of transmissions of registered 
designs, and such other matter as may be prescribed and such register may be 
maintained wholly or partly on computer floppies or diskettes, subject to such 
safeguards as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the register is maintained wholly or 
partly on computer floppies or diskettes under sub-section (1), any reference in 
this Act to any entry in the register shall be construed as the reference to the 
entry so maintained on computer floppies or diskettes.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The register of designs existing at the 
commencement of this Act shall be incorporated with and form part of the 
register of designs under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The register of designs shall be prima 
facie evidence of any matter by this Act directed or authorized to be 
entered therein.


</section></article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Copyright on registration.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When a design is registered, the registered proprietor of the design shall, 
subject to the provisions of this Act, have copyright in the design during ten 
years from the date of registration.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If, before the expiration of the said ten 
years, application for the extension of the period of copyright is made to the 
Controller in the prescribed manner, the Controller shall, on payment of the 
prescribed fee, extend the period of copyright for a second period of five years 
from the expiration of the original period of ten years.


</section></article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Restoration of lapsed designs.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where a design has ceased to have effect by reason of failure to pay the fee for 
the extension of copyright under sub-section (2) of section 11, the proprietor 
of such design or his legal representative and where the design was held by two 
or more persons jointly, then, with the leave of the Controller one or more of 
them without joining the others, may, within one year from the date on which the 
design ceased to have effect, make an application for the restoration of the 
design in the prescribed manner on payment of such fee as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An application under this section shall 
contain a statement, verified in the prescribed manner, fully setting out the 
circumstances which led to the failure to pay the prescribed fee, and the 
Controller may require from the applicant such further evidence as he may think 
necessary.


</section></article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Procedure for disposal of applications for 
restoration of lapsed designs.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If, after hearing the applicant in cases where the applicant so desires or the 
Controller thinks fit, the Controller is satisfied that the failure to pay the 
fee for extension of the period of copyright was unintentional and that there 
has been no undue delay in the making of the application, the Controller shall 
upon payment of any unpaid fee for extension of the period of copyright together 
with prescribed additional fee restore the registration of design.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Controller may, if he thinks fit as a 
condition of restoring the design, require that any entry shall be made in the 
register of any document or matter which under the provisions of this Act, has 
to be entered in the register but which has not been so entered.
</section></article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Rights of proprietor of lapsed design which 
have been restored.—
<section><number>1</number> Where the 
registration of a design is restored, the rights of the registered proprietor 
shall be subject to such provisions as may be prescribed and to such other 
provisions as the Controller thinks fit to impose for the protection or 
compensation of persons who may have begun to avail themselves of, or have taken 
definite steps by contract or otherwise to avail themselves of, the benefit of 
applying the design between the date when the registration of the design ceased 
to have effect and the date of restoration of the registration of the design.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No suit or other proceeding shall be 
commenced in respect of piracy of a registered design or infringement of the 
copyright in such design committed between the date on which the registration of 
the design ceased to have effect and the date of the restoration of the design.
</section></article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Requirements before delivery on sales.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Before delivery on sale of any articles to which a registered design has been 
applied, the proprietor shall—
 <subsection>        
<number>a</number>  (if exact representations or specimens were not furnished on the 
application for registration) furnish to the Controller the prescribed number of 
exact representations or specimens of the design; and, if he fails to do so, the 
Controller may, after giving notice thereof to the proprietor, erase his name 
from the register and thereupon the copyright in the design shall cease; and
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>b</number>  cause each such article to be marked with the prescribed mark, or with the 
prescribed words or figures denoting that the design is registered; and, if he 
fails to do so, the proprietor shall not be entitled to recover any penalty or 
damages in respect of any infringement of his copyright in the design unless he 
shows that he took all proper steps to ensure the marking of the article, or 
unless he shows that the infringement took place after the person guilty thereof 
knew or had received notice of the existence of the copyright in the design.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where a representation is made to the 
Central Government by or on behalf of any trade or industry that in the interest 
of the trade or industry it is expedient to dispense with or modify as regards 
any class or description of articles any of the requirements of this section as 
to marking, the Central Government may, if it thinks fit, by rule under this 
Act, dispense with or modify such requirements as regards any such class or 
description of articles to such extent and subject to such conditions as it 
thinks fit.
</section></article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Effect of disclosure on copyright.—The 
disclosure of a design by the proprietor to any other person, in such 
circumstances as would make it contrary to good faith for that other person to 
use or publish the design, and the disclosure of a design in breach of good 
faith by any person, other than the proprietor of the design, and the acceptance 
of a first and confidential order for articles bearing a new or original textile 
design intended for registration, shall not be deemed to be a publication of the 
design sufficient to invalidate the copyright thereof if registration thereof is 
obtained subsequently to the disclosure or acceptance.
</article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Inspection of registered designs.—
<section><number>1</number> 
During the existence of copyright in a design, any person on furnishing such 
information as may enable the Controller to identify the design and on payment 
of the prescribed fee may inspect the design in the prescribed manner.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person may, on an application to the 
Controller and on payment of such fee as may be prescribed, obtain a certified 
copy of any registered design.


</section></article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Information as to existence of copyright.—On 
the request of any person furnishing such information as may enable the 
Controller to identify the design, and on payment of the prescribed fee, the 
Controller shall inform such person whether the registration still exists in 
respect of the design, and, if so, in respect of what classes of articles, and 
shall state the date of registration, and the name and address of the registered 
proprietor.


</article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Cancellation of registration.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any person interested may present a petition for the cancellation of the 
registration of a design at any time after the registration of the design, to 
the Controller on any of the following grounds, namely:—
 <subsection>        
<number>a</number>  that the design has been previously registered in India; or
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>b</number>  that it has been published in India or in any other country prior to the 
date of registration; or
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>c</number>  that the design is not a new or original design; or
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>d</number>  that the design is not registerable under this Act; or
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>e</number>  that it is not a design as defined under clause (d) of section 2.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> An appeal shall lie from any order of the 
Controller under this section to the High Court, and the Controller may at any 
time refer any such petition to the High Court, and the High Court shall decide 
any petition so referred.


</section></article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Designs to bind Government.—A 
registered design shall have to all intents the like effect as against the 
Government as it has against any person and the provisions of Chapter XVII of 
the Patents Act, 1970 (39 of 1970), shall apply to registered designs as they 
apply to patents.


</article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Provisions as to exhibitions.—The 
exhibition of a design, or of any article to which a design is applied, at an 
industrial or other exhibition to which the provisions of this section have been 
extended by the Central Government by notification in the Official Gazette, or 
the publication of a description of the design, during or after the period of 
the holding of the exhibition, or the exhibition of the design or the article or 
the publication of a description of the design by any person elsewhere during or 
after the period of the holding of the exhibition, without the privity or 
consent of the proprietor, shall not prevent the design from being registered or 
invalidate the registration thereof:
 
Provided that—
 <section>        
<number>a</number>  the exhibitor exhibiting the design or article, or publishing a description 
of the design, gives to the Controller previous notice in the prescribed form; 
and
 </section><section>        
<number>b</number>  the application for registration is made within six months from the date of 
first exhibiting the design or article or publishing a description of the 
design.
</section></article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Piracy of registered design.—
<section><number>1</number> 
During the existence of copyright in any design it shall not be lawful for any 
person—
 <subsection>        
<number>a</number>  for the purpose of sale to apply or cause to be applied to any article in 
any class of articles in which the design is registered, the design or any 
fraudulent or obvious imitation thereof, except with the licence or written 
consent of the registered proprietor, or to do anything with a view to enable 
the design to be so applied; or
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>b</number>  to import for the purposes of sale, without the consent of the registered 
proprietor, any article belonging to the class in which the design has been 
registered, and having applied to it the design or any fraudulent or obvious 
imitation thereof; or
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>c</number>  knowing that the design or any fraudulent or obvious imitation thereof has 
been applied to any article in any class of articles in which the design is 
registered without the consent of the registered proprietor, to publish or 
expose or cause to be published or exposed for sale that article.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If any person acts in contravention of this 
section, he shall be liable for every contravention—
 <subsection>        
<number>a</number>  to pay to the registered proprietor of the design a sum not exceeding 
twenty-five thousand rupees recoverable as a contract debt, or
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>b</number>  if the proprietor elects to bring a suit for the recovery of damages for 
any such contravention, and for an injunction against the repetition thereof, to 
pay such damages as may be awarded and to be restrained by injunction 
accordingly:
 
Provided that the total sum recoverable in 
respect of any one design under clause (a) shall not exceed fifty thousand 
rupees:
 
Provided further that no suit or any other 
proceeding for relief under this sub-section shall be instituted in any court 
below the court of District Judge.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> In any suit or any other proceeding for 
relief under sub-section (2), every ground on which the registration of a design 
may be cancelled under section 19 shall be available as a ground of defence.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in the 
second proviso to sub-section (2), where any ground on which the registration of 
a design may be cancelled under section 19 has been availed of as a ground of 
defence and sub-section (3) in any suit or other proceeding for relief under 
sub-section (2), the suit or such other proceeding shall be transferred by the 
court, in which the suit or such other proceeding is pending, to the High Court 
for decision.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> When the court makes a decree in a suit 
under sub-section (2), it shall send a copy of the decree to the Controller, who 
shall cause an entry thereof to be made in the register of designs.


</section></article> 
 The Designs ACT, 
2000
  
 <article><number>23</number> Application of certain provisions of the Act as to 
patents to designs.—The provisions of 
the Patents Act, 1970 (39 of 1970), with regard to certificates of the validity 
of a patent, and to the remedy in case of groundless threats of legal 
proceedings by a patentee shall apply in the case of registered designs in like 
manner as they apply in the case of patents, with the substitution of references 
to the copyright in a design for reference to a patent, and of references to the 
proprietor of a design for references to the patentee, and of references to the 
design for references to the invention.</article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>24</number> Fees.—
<section><number>1</number> 
There shall be paid in respect of the registration of designs and applications 
therefor and in respect of other matters relating to designs under this Act such 
fees as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A proceeding in respect of which a fee is 
payable under this Act or the rules made thereunder shall be of no effect unless 
the fee has been paid.
 
Provisions as to registers and other documents 
in the patent office
</section></article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Notice of trust not to be entered in 
registers.—There shall not be entered 
in any register kept under this Act, or be receivable by the Controller, any 
notice of any trust expressed, implied or constructive.
</article> 
 The Designs ACT, 
2000
  
 <article><number>26</number> Inspection of and extracts from 
registers.—Every register kept under 
this Act shall at all convenient times be open to the inspection of the public, 
subject to the provisions of this Act; and certified copies, sealed with the 
seal of the patent office, of any entry in any such register shall be given to 
any person requiring the same on payment of the prescribed fee:
 Provided that where such register is maintained wholly 
or partly on computer, the inspection of such register under this section shall 
be made by inspecting the computer print out of the relevant entry in the 
register so maintained on computer.

</article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Privilege of reports of Controller.—Reports 
of or to the Controller made under this Act other than the report referred to in 
section 45 shall not in any case be published or be open to public inspection.
</article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Prohibition and publication of 
specification, drawings, etc., where application abandoned, etc.—Where 
an application for a design has been abandoned or refused, the application and 
any drawings, photographs, tracings, representations or specimens left in 
connection with the application shall not at any time be open to public 
inspection or be published by the Controller.


</article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>29</number> Power of Controller to correct clerical 
errors.—The Controller may, on 
request in writing accompanied by the prescribed fee, correct any clerical error 
in the representation of a design or in the name or address of the proprietor of 
any design, or in any other matter, which is entered upon the register of 
designs.
</article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>30</number> Entry of assignment and transmissions in 
registers.—
<section><number>1</number> Where a person becomes 
entitled by assignments, transmission or other operation of law to the copyright 
in a registered design, he may make an application in the prescribed form to the 
Controller to register his title, and the Controller shall, on receipt of such 
application and on proof of title to his satisfaction, register him as the 
proprietor of such design, and shall cause an entry to be made in the prescribed 
manner in the register of the assignment, transmission or other instrument 
affecting the title.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any person becomes entitled as 
mortgagee, licensee or otherwise to any interest in a registered design, he may 
make an application in the prescribed form to the Controller to register his 
title, and the Controller shall, on receipt of such application and on proof of 
title to his satisfaction, cause notice of the interest to be entered in the 
prescribed manner in the register of designs, with particulars of the 
instrument, if any, creating such interest.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> For the purposes of sub-section (1) or 
sub-section (2), an assignment of a design or of a share in a design, a 
mortgage, licence or the creation of any other interest in a design shall not be 
valid unless the same were in writing and the agreement between the parties 
concerned is reduced to the form of an instrument embodying all the terms and 
conditions governing their rights and obligation and the application for 
registration of title under such instrument is filed in the prescribed manner 
with the Controller within six months from the execution of the instrument or 
within such further period not exceeding six months in the aggregate as the 
Controller on the application made in the prescribed manner allows:
 
Provided that the instrument shall, on entry of 
its particulars in the register under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2), have 
the effect from the date of its execution.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The person registered as the proprietor of a 
design shall, subject to the provisions of this Act and to any rights appearing 
from the register to be vested in any other person, have power absolutely to 
assign, grant licences as to, or otherwise deal with, the design and to give 
effectual receipts for any consideration for any such assignment, licence or 
dealing:
 
Provided that any equities in respect of the 
design may be enforced in like manner as in respect of any other movable 
property.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Except in the case of an application made 
under section 31, a document or instrument in respect of which no entry has been 
made in the register in accordance with the provisions of sub-sections (1) and 
(2) shall not be admitted in evidence in any court in proof of the title to 
copyright in a design or to any interest therein, unless the court, for reason 
to be recorded in writing, otherwise directs.
</section></article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>31</number> Rectification of register.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Controller may, on the application in the prescribed manner of any person 
aggrieved by the non-insertion in or omission from the register of designs of 
any entry, or by any entry made in such register without sufficient cause, or by 
any entry wrongly remaining on such register, or by an error or defect in any 
entry in such register, make such order for making, expunging or varying such 
entry as he thinks fit and rectify the register accordingly.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Controller may, in any proceeding under 
this section, decide any question that may be necessary or expedient to decide 
in connection with the rectification of a register.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An appeal shall lie to the High Court from 
any order of the Controller under this section and the Controller may refer any 
application under this section to the High Court for decision, and the High 
Court shall dispose of any application so referred.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Any order of the Court rectifying a register 
shall direct that notice of the rectification be served on the Controller in the 
prescribed manner who shall upon the receipt of such notice rectify the register 
accordingly.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Nothing in this section shall be deemed to 
empower the Controller to make any such order cancelling the registration of a 
design as is provided for in section 19.


</section></article> 
 The Designs ACT, 
2000
  
 <article><number>32</number> Powers of Controller in proceedings under 
Act.—Subject to any rules in this 
behalf, the Controller in any proceedings before him under this Act shall have 
the powers of a civil court for the purpose of receiving evidence, administering 
oaths, enforcing the attendance of witnesses, compelling the discovery and 
production of documents, issuing commissions for the examining of witnesses and 
awarding costs and such award shall be executable in any court having 
jurisdiction as if it were a decree of that court.</article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>33</number> Exercise of discretionary power by 
Controller.—Where any discretionary 
power is by or under this Act given to the Controller, he shall not exercise 
that power adversely to the applicant for registration of a design without (if 
so required within the prescribed time by the applicant) giving the applicant an 
opportunity of being heard.
</article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>34</number> Power of Controller to take directions of 
the Central Government.—The 
Controller may, in any case of doubt or difficulty arising in the administration 
of any of the provisions of this Act, apply to the Central Government for 
directions in the matter.
</article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>35</number> Refusal to register a design in certain 
cases.—
<section><number>1</number> The Controller may refuse 
to register a design of which the use would, in his opinion, be contrary to 
public order or morality.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An appeal shall lie to the High Court from 
an order of the Controller under this section.


</section></article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>36</number> Appeals to the High Court.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where an appeal is declared by this Act to lie from the Controller to the High 
Court, the appeal shall be made within three months of the date of the order 
passed by the Controller.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In calculating the said period of three 
months, the time (if any) occupied in granting a copy of the order appealed 
against shall be excluded.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The High Court may, if it thinks fit, obtain 
the assistance of an expert in deciding such appeals, and the decision of the 
High Court shall be final.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The High Court may make rules consistent 
with this Act as to the conduct and procedure of all proceedings under this Act 
before it.


</section></article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>37</number> Evidence before the Controller.—Subject 
to any rules made under section 44, in any proceeding under this Act before the 
Controller, the evidence shall be given by affidavit in the absence of 
directions by the Controller to the contrary; but in any case in which the 
Controller thinks it right so to do he may take evidence viva voce in 
lieu of or in addition to evidence by affidavit or may allow any party to be 
cross-examined on the contents of his affidavit.


</article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>38</number> Certificate of Controller to be evidence.—A 
certificate purporting to be under the hand of the Controller as to any entry, 
matter or thing which he is authorized by this Act, or any rules made thereunder 
to make or do, shall be prima facie evidence of the entry having been 
made, and of the contents thereof, and of the matter or thing having been done 
or left undone.


</article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>39</number> Evidence of documents in patent office.—Printed 
or written copies or extracts, purporting to be certified by the Controller and 
sealed with the seal of the patent office, of documents in the patent office, 
and of or from registers and other books kept there, shall be admitted in 
evidence in all courts in India, and in all proceedings, without further proof 
or production of the originals:
 
Provided that a court may, if it has reason to 
doubt the accuracy or authenticity of the copies tendered in evidence, require 
the production of the originals or such further proof as it considers necessary.


</article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>40</number> Applications and notices by post.—Any 
application, notice or other document authorized or required to be left, made or 
given at the patent office or to the Controller, or to any other person under 
this Act, may be sent by post.


</article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>41</number> Declaration by infant, lunatic, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If any person, is by reason of infancy, lunacy or other disability, incapable of 
making any statement or doing anything required or permitted by or under this 
Act, the lawful guardian, committee or manager (if any) of the person subject to 
the disability, or, if there be none, any person appointed by any court 
possessing jurisdiction in respect of his property, may make such statement or a 
statement as nearly corresponding thereto as circumstances permit, and do such 
thing in the name and on behalf of the person subject to the disability.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An appointment may be made by the court for 
the purposes of this section upon the petition of any person acting on behalf of 
the person subject to the disability or of any other person interested in the 
making of the statement or the doing of the thing.
</section></article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>42</number> Avoidance of certain restrictive conditions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
It shall not be lawful to insert—
 <subsection>         <number>i</number>  
in any contract for or in relation to the sale or lease of an article in respect 
of which a design is registered; or
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>ii</number>  in a licence to manufacture or use an article in respect of which a design 
is registered; or
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>iii</number>  in a licence to package the article in respect of which a design is 
registered, 
 
     condition the effect of which may be—
 <subsubsection>
             <number>a</number>  to require the purchaser, lessee, or licensee to acquire from 
the vendor, lessor, or licensor or his nominees, or to prohibit him from 
acquiring or to restrict in any manner or to any extent his right to acquire 
from any person or to prohibit him from acquiring except from the vendor, lessor, 
or licensor or his nominees any article other than the article in respect of 
which a design is registered; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>b</number>  to prohibit the purchaser, lessee or licensee from using or to 
restrict in any manner or to any extent the right of the purchaser, lessee or 
licensee, to use an article other than the article in respect of which a design 
is registered which is not supplied by the vendor, lessor or licensor or his 
nominee,
 and any such 
condition shall be void.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A condition of the nature referred to in 
clause (a) or clause (b) of sub-section (1) shall not cease to be a condition 
falling within that sub-section merely by reason of the fact that the agreement 
containing it has been entered into separately, whether before or after the 
contract relating to the sale, lease or licence of the article in respect of 
which a design is registered.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In proceeding against any person for any act 
in contravention of section 22, it shall be a defence to prove that at the time 
of such contravention there was in force a contract relating to the registered 
design and containing a condition declared unlawful by this section:
 
Provided that this sub-section shall not apply 
if the plaintiff is not a party to the contract and proves to the satisfaction 
of the court that the restrictive condition was inserted in the contract without 
his knowledge and consent, express or implied.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Nothing in this section shall—
 <subsection>        
<number>a</number>  affect a condition in a contract by which a person is prohibited from 
selling goods other than those of a particular person;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>b</number>  validate a contract which, but for this section, would be invalid;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>c</number>  affect a condition in a contract for the lease of, or licence to use, an 
article in respect of which a design is registered, by which the lessor or 
licensor reserves to himself or his nominee the right to supply such new parts 
of the article, in respect of which a design is registered, as may be required 
or to put or keep it in repair.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> The provision of this section shall also 
apply to contracts made before the commencement of this Act if, and in so far 
as, any restrictive conditions declared unlawful by this section continue in 
force after the expiration of one year from such commencement.
</section></article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>43</number> Agency.—
<section><number>1</number> 
All applications and communications to the Controller under this Act may be 
signed by, and all attendances upon the Controller may be made by or through a 
legal practitioner or by or through an agent whose name and address had been 
entered in the register of patent agents maintained under section 125 of the 
Patents Act, 1970 (39 of 1970).
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Controller may, if he sees fit, require—
 <subsection>        
<number>a</number>  any such agent to be resident in India;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>b</number>  any person not residing in India to employ an agent residing in India;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>c</number>  the personal signature or presence of any applicant or other person.


</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>44</number> Reciprocal arrangement with the United 
Kingdom and other convention countries or group of countries or 
inter-governmental organisations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any person who has applied for protection for any design in the United Kingdom 
or any or other convention countries or group of countries or countries which 
are members of inter-governmental organisations, or his legal representative or 
assignee shall, either alone or jointly with any other person, be entitled to 
claim that the registration of the said design under this Act shall be in 
priority to other applicants and shall have the same date as the date of the 
application in the United Kingdom or any of such other convention countries or 
group of countries or countries which are members of inter-governmental 
organisations, as the case may be:
 
Provided that—
 <subsection>        
<number>a</number>  the application is made within six months from the application for 
protection in the United Kingdom or any such other convention countries or group 
of countries or countries which are members of inter-governmental organisations, 
as the case may be; and
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>b</number>  nothing in this section shall entitle the proprietor of the design to 
recover damages for piracy of design happening prior to the actual date on which 
the design is registered in India.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The registration of a design shall not be 
invalidated by reason only of the exhibition or use of or the publication of a 
description or representation of the design in India during the period specified 
in this section as that within which the application may be made.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The application for registration of a design 
under this section has been made in the same manner as an ordinary application 
under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where it is made to appear to the Central 
Government that the legislature of the United Kingdom or any such other 
convention country or a country which is member of any group of countries or 
inter-governmental organisation as may be notified by the Central Government in 
this behalf has made satisfactory provision for the protection of designs 
registered in India, the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, direct that the provisions of this section, with such variations or 
additions, if any, as may be set out in such notification, shall apply for the 
protection of designs registered in the United Kingdom or that other convention 
country or such country which is member of any group of countries or 
inter-governmental organisation, as the case may be.
 
Explanation 1.—For 
the purposes of this section, the expression “convention countries”, “group of 
countries” or “inter-governmental organisation” means, respectively, such 
countries, group of countries or inter-governmental organisation to which the 
Paris Convention for Protection of Industrial Property, 1883 as revised at 
Stockholm in 1967 and as amended in 1979 or the Final Act, embodying the results 
of the Uruguay Round of Multilateral Trade Negotiations, provided for the 
establishment of World Trade Organisation applies.
 
Explanation 2.—Where 
more than one application for protection referred to in sub-section (1) has been 
made for similar protections in the United Kingdom or one or more convention 
countries, group of countries or countries which are members of 
inter-governmental organizations, the period of six months referred to in clause 
(a) of that sub-section shall be reckoned from the date of which the earlier or 
the earliest application, as the case may be, of such applications has been 
made.
</section></article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>45</number> Report of the Controller to be placed before 
Parliament.—The Central Government 
shall cause to be placed before both Houses of Parliament once a year a report 
respecting the execution of this Act by or under the Controller.
</article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>46</number> Protection of security of India.—Notwithstanding 
anything contained in this Act, the Controller shall—
 <section>        
<number>a</number>  not disclose any information relating to the registration of a design or 
any application relating to the registration of a design under this Act, which 
he considers prejudicial to the interest of the security of India; and
 </section><section>        
<number>b</number>  take any action regarding the cancellation of registration of such designs 
registered under this Act which the Central Government may, by notification in 
the Official Gazette, specify in the interest of the security of India.
 
Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this section, the expression “security of India” means any 
action necessary for the security of India which relates to the application of 
any design registered under this Act to any article used for war or applied 
directly or indirectly for the purposes of military establishment or for the 
purposes of war or other emergency in international relations.
</section></article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>47</number> Power of Central Government to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules 
for carrying out the provisions of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular, and without prejudice to the 
generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>        
<number>a</number>  the form of application for registration of design, the manner of filing it 
at the patent office and the fee which shall accompany it, under sub-section (2) 
of section 5;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>b</number>  the time within which the registration is to be effected under sub-section 
(5) of section 5;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>c</number>  the classification of articles for registration under sub-section (1) of 
section 6;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>d</number>  the particulars of design to be published and the manner of their 
publication under section 7;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>e</number>  the manner of making claim under sub-section (1) of section 8;
 </subsection><subsection>         
<number>f</number>  the manner of making applications to the Controller under sub-section (5) 
of section 8;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>g</number>  the additional matters required to be entered in the register of designs 
and the safeguards to be made in maintaining such register in computer floppies 
or diskettes under sub-section (1) of section 10;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>h</number>  the manner of making application and fee to be paid for extension of the 
period of copyright and the fee payable thereto, under sub-section (2) of 
section 11;
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>i</number>  
the manner of making application for restoration of design and the fee to be 
paid with it under sub-section (1) of section 12;
 </subsection><subsection>         
<number>j</number>  the manner of verification of statement contained in an application under 
sub-section (2) of section 12;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>k</number>  the additional fee to be paid for restoration of the registration of design 
under sub-section (1) of section 13;
 </subsection><subsection>         
<number>l</number>  the provisions subject to which the right of the registered proprietor 
shall be under sub-section (1) of section 14.
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>m</number>  the number of exact representation or specimen of the design to be 
furnished to the Controller under clause (a) of sub-section (1) of section 15;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>n</number>  the mark, words or figures with which the article is to be marked denoting 
that the design is registered under clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 15;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>o</number>  the rules to dispense with or modify as regards any class or description of 
articles and any of the requirements of section 15 as to marking under 
sub-section (2) of that section;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>p</number>  the fee to be paid for and the manner of inspection under sub-section (1) 
of section 17;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>q</number>  the fee to be paid to obtain a certified copy of any design under 
sub-section (2) of section 17;
 </subsection><subsection>         
<number>r</number>  the fee on payment of which the Controller shall inform under section 18;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>s</number>  the form for giving notice to the Controller under clause (a) of the 
proviso to section 21;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>t</number>  the fee to be paid in respect of the registration of designs and 
application therefor, and in respect of other matters relating to designs under 
sub-section (1) of section 24;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>u</number>  the fee to be paid for giving certified copy of any entry in the register 
under section 26;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>v</number>  the fee to be accompanied with the requests in writing for correcting any 
clerical error under section 29;
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>w</number>  the form in which an application for registration as proprietor shall be 
made and the manner in which the Controller shall cause an entry to be made in 
the register of the assignment, transmission or other instrument effecting the 
title under sub-section (1) of section 30;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>x</number>  the form in which an application for title shall be made and the manner in 
which the Controller shall cause notice of the interest to be entered in the 
register of designs with particulars of the instrument, if any, creating such 
interest under sub-section (2) of section 30;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>y</number>  the manner of filing an application for registration and for making 
application for extension of time as referred to in sub-section (3) of section 
30;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>z</number>  the manner of making application to the Controller for rectification of 
register under sub-section (1) of section 31;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>za</number>  
the manner in which the notice of rectification shall be served on the 
Controller under sub-section (4) of section 31;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>zb</number>  
the rules regulating the proceedings before the Controller under section 32;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>zc</number>  
the time which shall be granted to the applicants for being heard by the 
Controller under section 33;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>zd</number>  
the fee to be accompanied with an appeal under sub-section (1) of section 36;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>ze</number>  
any other matter which is required to be, or may be, prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The power to make rules under this section 
shall be subject to the conditions of the rules being made after previous 
publication.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every rule made under this Act shall be 
laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while 
it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of 
the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both 
Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have 
effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, 
however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to 
the validity of anything previously done under that Act. 
</section></article> 
 
The Designs 
ACT, 2000
 
 
 <article>
<number>48</number> Repeal and savings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Designs Act, 1911 (2 of 1911) is hereby repealed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Without prejudice to the provisions 
contained in the General Clauses Act, 1897 (10 of 1897) with respect to repeals, 
any notification, rule, order, requirement, registration, certificate, notice, 
decision, determination, direction, approval, authorisation, consent, 
application, request or thing made, issued, given or done under the Designs Act, 
1911 (2 of 1911), shall, in force at the commencement of this Act, continue to 
be in force and have effect as if made, issued, given or done under the 
corresponding provisions of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The provisions of this Act shall apply to 
all applications for registration of designs pending at the commencement of this 
Act and to any proceedings consequent thereon and to any registration granted in 
pursuance thereof.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in this 
Act, any proceeding pending in any court at the commencement of this Act may be 
continued in that court as if this Act has not been passed.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in 
sub-section (2), the date of expiration of the copyright in the designs 
registered before the commencement of this Act shall, subject to the provisions 
of this Act, be the date immediately after the period of five years for which it 
was registered or the date immediately after the period of five years for which 
the extension of the period of copyright for a second period from the expiration 
of the original period has been made.
</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>