<act><tid>3907</tid>
<title>THE COTTON GINNING AND PRESSING FACTORIES ACT, <year>1925</year></title>

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> ACT NO. 12 OF <year>1925</year>
[ 18th March, <year>1925</year>.]

An Act to provide for the better regulation of cotton ginning and 
cotton pressing factories.

WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the better regulation of 
cotton ginning and cotton pressing factories;

It is hereby enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>170920</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1300683</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Cotton Ginning and Pressing Factories Act, <year>1925</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1503867</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> except the State of 
Jammu and Kashmir].]

</section>

<section><tid>1205008</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> date as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1724381</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant 
in the subject or context,-
<section><tid>331257</tid>
<number>a</number>" bale" means any pressed package of cotton of whatever 
size or density;

</section>

<section><tid>1549498</tid>
<number>b</number>" cotton" means ginned or unginned cotton, or cotton 
waste;

</section>

<section><tid>110363</tid>
<number>c</number>" cotton ginning factory" means any place where cotton 
is ginned or where cotton fibre is separated from 
cotton seed by any process whatever involving the use 
of steam, water or other mechanical power or of 
electrical power;

</section>

<section><tid>1892399</tid>
<number>d</number>" cotton pressing factory" means any factory as defined 
in the <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Indian Factories Act, <year>1911</year> (12 of <year>1911</year>), in 
which cotton is pressed into bales;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>20</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>999999</number> Amended in Gujarat by Gujarat Act 23 of <year>1968</year>.

The Act comes into force in Pondicherry on 1. 10. <year>1963</year> with modification 
vide Reg. 7 of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch. I.

Amended in Maharashtra by Maha. Act 2 of <year>1974</year>.

Extended to the whole of Madhya Pradesh by M. P. Act 23 of <year>1958</year> (when  
  notified).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been amended in its application to-- 
 (1) the State of Bombay by Bom. Acts 4 of <year>1936</year> and 20 of <year>1938</year>, 
 (2) the C. P. by C. P. Act 24 of <year>1936</year> and to Madhya Pradesh by 
C. P. and Berar Acts 33 of <year>1939</year>, 1 of <year>1942</year>, 13 of <year>1947</year> and 47 
of <year>1947</year>, 
 (3) the Punjab by Pun. Act 12 of <year>1941</year>, 
 (4) the U. P. by U. P. Act 15 of <year>1941</year>, 
 (5) Madras by Mad. Act 10 of <year>1953</year>, 
 (6) Hyderabad by Hyderabad Act 33 of <year>1954</year>. 
2. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year> for the former sub- section (2). 
3. Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year> for" except Part B States". 
4.  8th August, <year>1925</year>, see Gazette of India, <year>1925</year>, Pt. I, p. 728. 
5. See now the Factories Act, <year>1948</year> (63 of <year>1948</year>), s. 2 (m). 
Am. in Madhya Bharat by Madhya Bharat Act 15 of <year>1955</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>148735</tid>
<number>e</number>" cotton waste" means droppings, strippings, fly and 
other waste products of a cotton mill or of a cotton 
ginning factory or of a cotton pressing factory, but 
does not include yarn waste;

</section>

<section><tid>1378614</tid>
<number>f</number>" Indian Central Cotton Committee" means the Indian 
Central Cotton Committee constituted under the Indian 
Cotton Cess Act, <year>1923</year> (14 of <year>1923</year>), and includes any 
sub- committee appointed by it to perform any function 
of the Indian Central Cotton Committee under this Act; 
and

</section>

<section><tid>364113</tid>
<number>g</number>" occupier" includes a managing agent or other person 
authorized to represent the occupier;

</section>

<section><tid>99457</tid>
<number>h</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by or under rules made 
under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>877253</tid>
<number> 3</number> Maintenance of registers.
<section><tid>1801614</tid>
<number>1</number>The owner of every cotton  
ginning factory shall cause to be maintained at the factory in such 
form, if any, as may be prescribed, a ginning register containing a 
record of all cotton ginned in the factory and of the names of the 
persons for whom and the dates on which the cotton has been ginned and 
of the amount ginned for each person.

</section>

<section><tid>1300677</tid>
<number>2</number>The owner of every cotton pressing factory shall cause to be 
maintained at the factory in such form, if any, as may be prescribed, 
a press register containing a daily record of the number of bales 
pressed in the factory, the serial number of each bale, and the name 
of the person for whom it has been pressed.

</section>

<section><tid>723720</tid>
<number>3</number>The owner or the person in charge of a cotton ginning or 
cotton pressing factory shall be bound to produce any ginning register 
or press register maintained under this section when required to do so 
by any person appointed by the State Government in this behalf, and 
the owner or person in charge of any cotton pressing factory shall be 
bound to furnish to the Indian Central Cotton Committee, if so 
required by it in writing, a copy, certified as correct by the owner 
or person in charge of the factory, of the entry in any press register 
maintained at the factory relating to any specified bale.

</section>

<section><tid>694257</tid>
<number>4</number>No register required to be maintained by this section shall 
be destroyed until after the expiration of three years from the date 
of the last entry therein.

</section>

<section><tid>1832746</tid>
<number>5</number>If--

<subsection><tid>870071</tid>
<number>a</number>in any factory any register required by this section to 
be maintained is not maintained or is maintained in any 
form other than the form, if any, prescribed for the 
purpose, or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>21</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>387729</tid>
<number>b</number>any entry in any such register is proved to be false in 
any material particular, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>63107</tid>
<number>c</number>any such register is destroyed before the expiration of 
the period referred to in sub- section (4).
the owner of the factory shall be punished with fine which may extend 
to fifty rupees or, if he has previously been convicted of any offence 
under this sub- section, to five hundred rupees.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1633203</tid>
<number>6</number>If the owner or the person in charge of any factory fails to 
produce any register, or to furnish a certified copy of any entry, 
when required to do so under sub- section (3), or furnishes a certified 
copy of an entry knowing or having reason to believe such copy to be 
false, he shall be punished with fine which may extend to fifty rupees 
or, if he has previously been convicted of any offence under this sub- 
section, to five hundred rupees.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1610360</tid>
<number> 4</number> Marking of bales.
<section><tid>1326460</tid>
<number>1</number>The owner of every cotton pressing  
factory shall cause every bale pressed in the factory to be marked in 
such manner as may be prescribed, before it is removed from the press- 
house, with a serial number and with the mark prescribed for the 
factory.

</section>

<section><tid>721001</tid>
<number>2</number>If any bale is removed from the press- house of any cotton 
pressing factory without having been marked as required by sub- section 
 (1), the owner of the factory shall be punished with fine which may 
extend to fifty rupees.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>547601</tid>
<number> 5</number> Returns.
<section><tid>1634334</tid>
<number>1</number>The owner of every cotton pressing factory shall  
submit to the prescribed authority, within such time and in such form 
as may be prescribed, weekly returns showing the total number of bales 
of cotton pressed during the preceding week and from the commencement 
of the season to the end of that week, and the approximate average net 
weight of the bales pressed in that week.

</section>

<section><tid>303413</tid>
<number>2</number>The State Government shall compile from the weekly returns, 
and shall publish in such manner as <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> it thinks fit], a statement 
showing the total number of bales pressed in the State during the week 
and from the commencement of the season to the end of the week, to 
which the returns relate:
Provided that the number of bales pressed in any individual 
factory shall not be published.


</section>

<section><tid>221680</tid>
<number>3</number>If default is made in submitting any return as required by 
sub- section (1), the owner of the factory shall be punished with fine 
which may extend to fifty rupees.

</section>

<section><tid>1025142</tid>
<number>4</number>Where the owner of a cotton pressing factory has notified to 
the prescribed authority that the work of pressing bales in that
<pagefootnote><pagenum>22</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" the G. G. in C. may direct".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


factory has been suspended, it shall not be necessary for the owner to 
submit returns under sub- section (1) until such work has been resumed.

Explanation.-- In this section" season" means the period notified 
in this behalf by the State Government in the Official Gazette.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1148283</tid>
<number> 5A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Returns from cotton ginning factories.
<section><tid>251756</tid>
<number>1</number>This section  
shall be in force in <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the territories which, immediately before the 
 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in Part C States] only; but the 
State Government of <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> any State] may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, bring this section into force <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> in the territories where it 
is not in force].

</section>

<section><tid>1359699</tid>
<number>2</number>The owner of every cotton ginning factory shall submit to the 
prescribed authority, within such time and in such form as may be 
prescribed, weekly returns showing the quantity of cotton ginned in 
the factory during the preceding week and from the commencement of the 
season to the end of the week.

</section>

<section><tid>528280</tid>
<number>3</number>The State Government shall compile from the weekly returns so 
submitted, and shall publish in such manner as it thinks fit, a 
statement showing the total quantity of cotton ginned in the State 
during the week and from the commencement of the season to the end of 
the week, to which the returns relate:
Provided that the quantity of cotton ginned in any individual 
factory shall not be published.


</section>

<section><tid>137927</tid>
<number>4</number>If default is made in submitting any return as required by 
sub- section (2), the owner of the factory shall be punished with fine 
which may extend to fifty rupees.

</section>

<section><tid>1304479</tid>
<number>5</number>The provisions of sub- section (4) of section 5 apply to 
cotton ginning factories and the returns referred to in sub- section 
 (2) of this section as they apply to cotton pressing factories and the 
returns referred to in sub- section (1) of section 5, and" season" in 
this section means the season as notified for the purposes of section



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>941791</tid>
<number> 6</number> Scales and weights.
<section><tid>1250090</tid>
<number>1</number>No scales or weights shall be used in  
any cotton ginning or cotton pressing factory other than the scales or 
weights, if any, prescribed by the <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Central Government] as standard 
for the district in which the factory is situated.

</section>

<section><tid>554362</tid>
<number>2</number>If in any factory any scale or weight is used in 
contravention of the provisions of sub- section (1), the owner of the 
factory shall be punished with fine which may extend to fifty rupees 
or, if he
<pagefootnote><pagenum>23</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 9 of <year>1942</year>, s. 2. 
2. Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" Part C 
States". 
3. Subs. ibid., for" any other State". 
4. Subs. ibid., for" in the State". 
5. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G.".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


has been previously convicted of any offence under this sub- section, 
to five hundred rupees.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>652764</tid>
<number> 7</number> Liability of lessee as owner.
<section><tid>543815</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the owner of a cotton  
ginning or pressing factory has leased the factory for a period of not 
less than one month, in the case of a cotton ginning factory, or three 
months in the case of a cotton pressing factory, and the lessor 
retains no interest in the management or profits of the factory and 
notice of the lease has been given by the lessor and the lessee to the 
prescribed authority, the lessee shall be deemed to be the owner of 
the factory, from the date of the notice and for the period of the 
continuance of the lease, for the purposes of section 3, in respect of 
the registers maintained or to be maintained from that date and for 
that period, and for the purposes of sections 4, 5 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 5A] and 6.

</section>

<section><tid>776027</tid>
<number>2</number>On the termination of the lease the lessee shall hand over to 
the lessor the registers maintained under section 3, and the lessor 
shall forthwith report to the prescribed authority any default of the 
lessee in complying with the provisions of this sub- section or in 
maintaining the registers in accordance with the provisions of section 
3.

</section>

<section><tid>1589890</tid>
<number>3</number>If default is made in handing over any register or making any 
report as required by this section, the lessor or the lessee, as the 
case may be, shall be punished with may extend to fifty rupees.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1447703</tid>
<number> 8</number> Liability or transfer of ownership.
<section><tid>1672535</tid>
<number>1</number>On a transfer of the  
ownership of a cotton ginning or pressing factory, the transferor 
shall hand over to the transferee the registers maintained under 
section 3, and the transferee shall forthwith report to the prescribed 
authority any default of the transferor in complying with the 
provisions of this sub- section or in maintaining the registers in 
accordance with the provisions of section 3.

</section>

<section><tid>1822908</tid>
<number>2</number>If default is made in handing over any register or making any 
report as required by sub- section (1), the transferor or the 
transferee, as the case may be, shall be punished with fine which may 
extend to fifty rupees.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>959160</tid>
<number> 9</number> Structural requirements for factories.
<section><tid>564565</tid>
<number>1</number>In the case of  
cotton ginning factories the construction of which is commenced after 
the commencement of this Act-

<subsection><tid>1616114</tid>
<number>a</number>gin- houses shall be provided with separate entrances 
and exits for the bringing in of unginned and the 
taking out of ginned cotton respectively, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1262060</tid>
<number>b</number>the factories shall be constructed in accordance with 
plans and specifications approved by the prescribed 
authority:
<pagefootnote><pagenum>24</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 9 of <year>1942</year>, s. 3.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Provided that nothing in this sub- section shall apply to any 
factory in which only roller gins are used where the number of such 
gins is not more than four.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>387074</tid>
<number>1A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> In any cotton ginning factory, whether erected before or 
after the commencement of this Act-

<subsection><tid>98865</tid>
<number>a</number>no structural alterations or additions, the 
construction of which commenced after the 27th day of 
February, <year>1939</year>, shall be made so as to minimise the 
degree of compliance of the factory as a whole with the 
requirements set forth in clauses (a) and (b) of sub- 
section (1), and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>580939</tid>
<number>b</number>every structural addition (whether actually attached to  
  any existing structure in the factory or not), the 
construction of which commenced after the last- 
mentioned date, shall be constructed in accordance with 
plans and specifications approved by the prescribed 
authority:
Provided that nothing in this sub- section shall apply to any 
factory in which, after any alteration or addition has been made, only 
roller gins are used where the number of such gins is not more than 
four.]


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>743737</tid>
<number>2</number>Within such period after the commencement of this Act as may 
be prescribed, the owner of every cotton pressing factory in which 
cotton is handled on the ground floor shall cause the press- house to 
be paved or provided with other suitable flooring to the satisfaction 
of the prescribed authority.

</section>

<section><tid>71918</tid>
<number>3</number>If the owner of any factory fails to comply with any 
provision of this section, which is applicable to the factory, he 
shall be punished with fine which may extend to one hundred rupees.

</section>

<section><tid>47105</tid>
<number>4</number> (a) Where the owner of a factory has been convicted under 
sub- section (3), the prescribed authority may serve on the owner of 
the factory an order in writing directing that such alterations shall 
be made in the factory, before a specified date, as in the opinion of 
the said authority are necessary to secure compliance with the 
provisions of sub- section (1), <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> sub- section (1A)] or sub- section 
 (2), as the case may be.

<subsection><tid>1486752</tid>
<number>b</number>Where the alterations are not made in accordance with the 
order served under clause (a) of this sub- section, the prescribed 
authority may serve on the owner and on the occupier, if any, of the 
factory an order in writing directing that the work of ginning or 
pressing cotton in such factory shall be suspended until the 
alterations have been made in accordance with the order served under 
clause (a) of
<pagefootnote><pagenum>25</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 14 of <year>1939</year>, s. 2.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


this sub- section and the owner and the occupier, if any, shall be 
jointly and severally liable to fine which may extend to fifty rupees 
for each day on which cotton is ginned or pressed in the factory in 
contravention of the order served under this clause.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1827859</tid>
<number>10</number>Liability of officers of a company. Where the person guilty 
of an offence under this Act is a company, every director, manager, 
secretary and other officer thereof who is knowingly a party to the 
default shall also be guilty of the like offence and liable to the 
like punishment.


</article>



<article><tid>1178769</tid>
<number> 11</number> Cognizance of offences.
<section><tid>686000</tid>
<number>1</number>No prosecution under this Act  
shall be instituted except by or with the previous sanction of the 
District Magistrate or a Chief Presidency Magistrate or a Magistrate 
of the first class specially empowered in this behalf by the State 
Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1616179</tid>
<number>2</number>No offence punishable under this Act shall be tried by any 
Court inferior to that of a Presidency Magistrate or of a Magistrate 
of the first class.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1209184</tid>
<number> 12</number> Power of the Central Government to make rules. The Central 
Government may make rules <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> to provide for--
<section><tid>352496</tid>
<number>a</number>the allotment of a special mark to be used by each 
pressing factory for the purpose of the marking of 
bales;

</section>

<section><tid>737362</tid>
<number>b</number>the manner in which bales shall be marked; and

</section>

<section><tid>953617</tid>
<number>c</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the standard weights and scales to be used in cotton 
ginning and cotton pressing factories in any part of 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the territories to which this Act extends] and the 
inspection of the same.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1354585</tid>
<number> 13</number> Power of the State Government to make rules. The State 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules 
consistent with this Act to provide for all or any of the following 
matters, namely:--
<section><tid>128935</tid>
<number>a</number>the forms in which registers, records and returns are 
to be maintained or submitted, and the inspection of 
records and registers;

</section>

<section><tid>857366</tid>
<number>b</number>the appointment of the authority to whom and the time 
within which the returns required by <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> sections 5 and 
5A] shall be made;
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum>

<pagefootnote><pagenum>26</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>For such rules, see Gazette of India, <year>1925</year>, Pt. I, p. 728. 
2. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for the original cl. 
3. Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year> for" Part A States and Part C States". 
4. Subs. by Act 9 of <year>1942</year>, s. 4, for" section 5". 
5. Cl. (c) rep. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>. See now cl. (c) of s. 12.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>50861</tid>
<number>d</number>the appointment of authorities for the purposes of 
sections 7, 8 and 9;

</section>

<section><tid>1329847</tid>
<number>e</number>the manner of service of orders made under section 9;

</section>

<section><tid>494918</tid>
<number>f</number>the powers of entry and inspection which may be 
exercised by District Magistrates or by any officer 
specially empowered in this behalf by the State 
Government;

</section>

<section><tid>1237841</tid>
<number>g</number>any other matter which is to be or may be prescribed or 
for which provision is necessary in order to carry out 
the purposes of this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1189945</tid>
<number> 14</number> Power to reject unmarked bales in fulfilment of contracts.

<section><tid>1820906</tid>
<number>1</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>] After the expiration of one year from the commencement of this  
Act, any person who has made a contract for the purchase of baled 
cotton may require that no bales other than bales, marked <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> with the 
mark prescribed under section 4 for the factory in which they were 
pressed,] shall be supplied in fulfilment of such contract, and, if he 
does so require, no bale not so marked shall be tenderable in 
fulfilment of the contract.
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>


</section>

<section><tid>1070189</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Any bale marked in accordance with the provisions of 
section 4 shall, within the meaning of the Indian Evidence Act, <year>1872</year> 
 (1 of <year>1872</year>). be presumed for all purposes as between the parties to a 
contract for the purchase of baled cotton, to have been so marked 
before leaving the factory in which it was pressed.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1769736</tid>
<number>15</number>Protection for acts done under Act. No suit or other legal 
proceeding shall be instituted against any person in respect of 
anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this 
Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>27</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>S. 14 re- numbered as sub- section (1) of that section and sub- 
section (2) ins. by Act 14 of <year>1939</year>, s. 3. 
2. Subs. by s. 3, ibid., for" in accordance with section 4". 
3. Proviso omitted by s. 3, ibid.

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>