<act><tid>492719</tid>
<title>THE PROMISSORY NOTES (STAMP) ACT, <year>1926</year></title>

ACT NO. 11 OF <year>1926</year>
[ 2nd March, <year>1926</year>.]

An Act to provide for the validation of certain promissory notes.

WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the validation of certain 
promissory notes stamped with postage stamps of the denomination of 
two or four annas; It is hereby enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>376452</tid>
<number> 1</number> 
<section><tid>1182077</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title and extent. This Act may be called the  
Promissory Notes (Stamp) Act, <year>1926</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1791097</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> It extends to the whole of India except <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the territories 
which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in 
Part B States].



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1601311</tid>
<number>2</number>Validation of certain promissory notes. A promissory note 
payable on demand for an amount exceeding two hundred and fifty 
rupees, executed after the 30th day of September, <year>1923</year>, and before the 
 5th day of January, <year>1925</year>, and stamped with an adhesive stamp or 
adhesive stamps inscribed for postage and of the value required by the 
law in force at the time the promissory note was executed, shall not, 
by reason only of the fact that the stamp or the stamps or any of them 
is or are of a description other than that required by such law, be 
deemed for any of the purposes of the Indian Stamp Act, <year>1899</year> (2 of  
  <year>1899</year>) or of the rules made thereunder, not to have been duly stamped.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>999999</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for the original sub- section (2).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" Part B 
States".

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>