<act><title>


THE NATIONAL HIGHWAYS (COLLECTION OF FEES BY ANY PERSON 
FOR THE USE OF SECTION OF NATIONAL HIGHWAYS/PERMANENT BRIDGE/TEMPORARY BRIDGE ON 
NATIONAL HIGHWAYS) 
RULES, 19971</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title.—
<section><number>i</number> 
These rules may be called the National Highways (Collection of Fees by any 
Person for the Use of Section of National Highways/Permanent Bridge/Temporary 
Bridge on National Highways) Rules, 1997.
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> They shall come into 
force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
       
<number>a</number>  “mechanical vehicle” means any laden or unladen vehicle designed to be 
driven under its own power, including a motor vehicle, as defined in clause (28) 
of section 2 of the Motor Vehicles Act of 1988 (59 of 1988);
 </section><section>
       
<number>b</number>  “section of national highway/permanent bridge/temporary bridge” means 
that length of national highway/permanent bridge/temporary bridge on national 
highway notified by the Central Government in Official Gazette for the 
development/maintenance of which an agreement has been entered into between the 
Central Government and any person;
 



1[(c)  
“person” shall include any company or association or body of individuals whether 
incorporated or not.]



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Agreement and rate 
of fee.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
Central Government may enter into an agreement with any person in relation to 
development and maintenance of the whole or any part of a national 
highway/permanent bridge/temporary bridge on national highway as it may decide, 
whereby the person may be permitted to invest his own funds for the 
development/maintenance of a section of national highway/permanent 
bridge/temporary bridge and to collect and retain the fees at agreed rates from 
different categories of mechanical vehicles for an agreed period for the use of 
the facilities thus created, subject to the terms and conditions of the 
agreement and these rules.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The rates of fees and 
the period of collection shall be decided and shall be specified by notification 
in the Official Gazette by the Central Government having regard to the 
expenditure involved in building, maintenance, management and operation of the 
whole or part of such section, interest on the capital invested, reasonable 
return, the volume of traffic and the period of such agreement.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On completion of the 
period of collection of fees by the person, as per the agreement, all rights 
pertaining to the section/permanent bridge/temporary bridge on national highway 
shall be deemed to have been taken over by the Central Government and that 
Government shall continue with the collection of fees as notified from time to 
time.
 

1[(4) The rates of 
fee, the categories of vehicles exempted from payment of fee and the name, 
address and telephone number of the authority to whom complaints, if any, should 
be addressed, shall be conspicuously and prominently displayed 500m ahead of the 
toll booths, 100m ahead of the toll booths and at the toll booths also, the 
height of the display boards and size of letters being such that it is easy for 
drivers to read the display boards.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Modalities of fee 
collection.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The mode of fee collection shall be decided by the person referred to in 
sub-rule (1) of rule 3.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A table of fees 
authorised to be collected on any section of national highway/permanent 
bridge/temporary bridge on national highway shall be put up by such person in a 
conspicuous place near a fee collection booth legibly written or printed in 
English, Hindi and the regional language of the area in which the national 
highway is situated.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Incharge of fee 
collection.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
The person authorised to collect and retain the fees under these rules shall 
nominate an official as in-charge of fee collection, and the person as also the 
official so nominated shall be responsible to ensure that fees are collected at 
not more than the agreed rates and the fee collection is smooth without causing 
undue hardship to the road users, and for all other matters connected with the 
fee collection of section of national highway/permanent bridge/temporary bridge:
 
Provided that no fee shall 
be payable or collected in respect of the following vehicles, namely:—
 



2[(i)  
vehicles—
 <subsection>
            
<number>A</number> having “VIP” symbols; or
 
                  
officially belonging to—
 <subsubsection>
               
<number>a</number> President of India;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
               
<number>b</number>  Vice-President of India;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
               
<number>c</number> Governor of a State or Lt. Governor of a Union Territory;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
               
<number>d</number> a Foreign Dignitary on State visit to India;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
               
<number>e</number> a foreign diplomat stationed in India using cars with “CD”/“CC” number 
plates;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                
<number>f</number> Chairman of Rajya Sabha or Speaker of Lok Sabha or Chairman of a State 
Legislative Council or Speaker of a State Legislative Assembly or a Minister for 
the union or State, or Leaders of Opposition in Lok Sabha or Rajya Sabha or 
State Legislatures having the status of Cabinet Minister, if he is sitting in 
the vehicle; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
               
<number>g</number> a Member of Parliament, in the entire country, or a Member of Legislative 
Assembly of a State or a Member of Legislative Council of a State, in the 
respective State, if he produces his identity card issued by the Parliament or 
concerned Legislature of a State, as the case may be;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
            
<number>B</number> belonging to winner of Gallantry awards such as Param Vir Chakra, Ashok 
Chakra, Maha Vir Chakra, Kirti Chakra, Vir Chakra and Shaurya Chakra, if such 
awardee produces his photo identity card duly authenticated by the Competent 
Authority for such award.]
 <subsubsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  Defence vehicles, Police vehicles, Fire-fighting vehicles, 
Ambulances, Funeral vans, Posts and Telegraphs Department vehicles and Central 
Government and State Government vehicles on duty.]
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The name, address and 
telephone number, if any, of the incharge of a fee collection shall be displayed 
at suitable and conspicuous locations.
 
 





</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Verification of fee 
collection.—
<section><number>1</number> 
It shall be the responsibility of the person referred to in sub-rule (1) of rule 
3 to strictly ensure that all fees leviable are levied, fully collected and 
correctly maintained. The person shall submit certified and audited copies of 
the statements of fee collection at specified intervals as required under the 
notification for fee collection under sub-rule (2) of rule 3. The auditor shall 
be appointed by the Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Central Government 
shall have the right to check the fee collection at any or all times through 
their designated officers.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Person to have 
rights to regulate traffic.—The 
person referred to in sub-rule 
<section><number>1</number> of rule 3 shall have powers to regulate and 
control the traffic, on such section of national highway/permanent 
bridge/temporary bridge on national highway relating to which he is authorised 
to collect fees under these rules, in accordance with the provisions contained 
in Chapter VIII of the Motor Vehicles Act, 1988 for proper management thereof.
 
 
</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>