<act><title>THE FOREIGN CONTRIBUTION (REGULATION) RULES, 1976 
</title> 
 
The Foreign 
Contribution (Regulation) Rules, 1976
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Foreign Contribution (Regulation) Rules, 1976.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the 5th day of August, 1976.
</section></article> 
 
The Foreign 
Contribution (Regulation) Rules, 1976
 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these Rules unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
   <number>a</number>   “Act” means the 
Foreign Contribution (Regulation) Act, 1976;
 </section><section>
   <number>b</number>   “Form” means a 
form appended to these rules;
 </section><section>
   <number>c</number>   “section” means a 
section of the Act;
 

1[(d)   “year” 
means the accounting year commencing from 1st day of April and ending on 31st 
day of March of the next calendar year.]
 
 


</section></article> 
 
The Foreign 
Contribution (Regulation) Rules, 1976
 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Application for 
obtaining prior permission to receive foreign contribution or foreign 
hospitality.—An 
application for obtaining prior permission of the Central Government to—
 <section>
   <number>a</number>   receive foreign 
contribution under sub-section (1) of section 5, or clause (a) of sub-section 
(2) of that section, shall be made in Form FC1;
 
1[(aa)  
receive foreign contribution under proviso to sub-section (1) of section 6, or 
under sub-section (1A) of that section or clause (b) of section 10, shall be 
made in Form FC 1A;]
 </section><section>
   <number>b</number>   accept foreign 
hospitality under section 9 
2[or 
clause (d) of section 10], shall be made in Form FC 2.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Foreign 
Contribution (Regulation) Rules, 1976
 
 
 <article>
1[<number>3A</number> 
Application for registration.—An application for registration of an 
association referred to in sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 6 for acceptance of 
foreign contribution shall be made in Form FC 8].


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Intimation regarding receipt of foreign contribution or 
scholarship or stipend or any payment of a like nature of foreign hospitality. 
</title>—
<section><number>1</number> An intimation as to the receipt of— 
 
 <subsection><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>a</number> foreign contribution by an association referred to in 
  sub-sections (1) and (1A) of section 6 shall be given for every year beginning 
  on the 1st day of April, in Form FC 3 in duplicate, within <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[nine 
  months] of the closure of the year: 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[Provided that a NIL report shall also be furnished. The 
  intimation to be furnished for the year beginning on the 1st day of April 1991 
  shall also include the receipt and utilisation of foreign contribution during 
  the period commencing from 1st January, 1991 and ending on 31st March, 1991;] 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> foreign contribution by a candidate for election, referred to in 
  sub-section (2) of section 6 shall be given in Form FC 4, within fifteen days 
  from the date on which he is duly nominated as a candidate for election; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> any scholarship, stipend or any payment of a like nature, from any 
  foreign source in relation to which an intimation is required to be given 
  under sub-section (1) of section 7, shall be given in Form FC 5, within thirty 
  days of receipt of such scholarship, stipend or other payment of a like 
  nature: 
 Provided that where the person receiving the scholarship, stipend or any 
  payment of a like nature is residing outside India, the intimation shall be 
  given within sixty days from the date of receipt of such scholarship, stipend 
  or other payment of a like nature; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>  foreign hospitality, referred to in the proviso to section 9, 
  shall be given on plain paper within thirty days from the date of receipt of 
  such hospitality specifying the particulars as to the receipt of such 
  hospitality and the source from which and the manner in which such hospitality 
  was received. </subsection>



</section></article> 
 
The Foreign 
Contribution (Regulation) Rules, 1976
 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Intimation of 
receipt of scholarship, stipend or any payment of a like nature, when not 
necessary.—It 
shall not be necessary for a citizen of India to give any intimation under 
section 7 regarding receipt of scholarship, stipend or any payment of a like 
nature from any foreign source, if the value of such scholarship, stipend or 
other payment does not exceed, during an academic year, rupees thirty-six 
thousand.
 
Explanation.—In 
calculating the value,—
 <section>
   <number>a</number>   the amount 
received by the citizen for the purchase of books, clothing and equipment and 
for sight-seeing in a foreign country or territory shall be taken into account; 
but
 </section><section>
   <number>b</number>   the amount spent 
in travel by air in economy class from India to a foreign country or territory 
and back to India from such foreign country or territory, and the amount spent 
by the foreign source in respect of such citizen towards tuition and other fees, 
shall not be taken into account.
</section></article> 
 
The Foreign 
Contribution (Regulation) Rules, 1976
 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Authority to whom an 
application or intimation to be sent.—Any 
application or intimation referred to in rule 3, 

1[rule 3A] or rule 
4, as the case may be, shall be made or given to the Secretary to the Government 
of India in the Ministry of Home Affairs, New Delhi. Such application or 
intimation shall be sent by registered post.
 
 


</article> 
 
The Foreign 
Contribution (Regulation) Rules, 1976
 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Manner of service of 
prohibitory order or any other order or direction.—A 
prohibitory order under section 12 or any other order or direction made or 
issued under the Act, shall be served on the person concerned in the following 
manner, that is to say,—
 <section>
   <number>a</number>   by delivering or 
tendering it to that person or to his duly authorised agent; or
 </section><section>
   <number>b</number>   by sending it to 
him by registered post acknowledgement due to the address of his last known 
place of residence or the place where he carries on, or is known to have last 
carried on, business or the place where he personally works for gain or is known 
to have last worked for gain, and in case the person is an organisation or an 
association, to the last known address of the office of such organisation or 
association;
 </section><section>
   <number>c</number>   if it cannot be 
served in any of the manners aforesaid, by affixing it on the outer door or some 
other conspicuous part of the premises in which that person resides, or carries 
on, or is known to have last carried on, business, or personally works for gain, 
or is known to have last worked personally for gain, and in case the person is 
an organisation or an association, on the outer door or some other conspicuous 
part of the premises in which the officer of the organisation or association is 
located, or is known to have been last located, and the written report whereof 
should be witnessed by at least two persons.
</section></article> 

 <title> </title>
 <article><title><number>8</number> Maintenance of accounts. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> A separate set of accounts and records shall be maintained, exclusively for foreign contribution received and utilised,— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> in Form FC 6, where the foreign contribution relates only to articles as referred to in item (i) of sub-clause (c) of clause (1) of section 2; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> in the cash book and ledger account on double entry basis, where the foreign contribution relates to currency received and utilised, and a separate bank account shall be maintained in respect of such contribution; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> in Form FC 7, where the foreign contribution relates to foreign securities. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> Every account specified in sub-rule (1) shall be maintained on an yearly basis, commencing on the 1st day of <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[April] each year and every such yearly account, duly certified by a chartered accountant <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[in Form FC 3 along with a balance sheet and statement of receipts and payments], shall be furnished, in duplicate, to the Secretary to the Government of India, in the Ministry of Home Affairs, New Delhi, <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[within nine months] the closure of the year.] 
 Explanation. —In this rule, “Chartered Accountant” has the meaning assigned to it in the Chartered Accountants Act, 1949 (38 of 1949). 




</section></article> 
 
The Foreign 
Contribution (Regulation) Rules, 1976
 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Limits up to which 
an officer, not below the rank of an Assistant Sessions Judge may make 
adjudication of confiscation.—An 
officer referred to in clause (b) of section 19 may adjudge confiscation in 
relation to any article or currency seized under section 16, if the value of 
such article or the amount of such currency exceeds one thousand rupees but does 
not exceed fifty thousand rupees.
</article><form>
 


The Foreign 
Contribution (Regulation) Rules, 1976
 


 
 


Form FC 1
 


[See 
rule 3(a)]
 


Application for seeking prior permission of  
the Central Government for accepting foreign contribution by or on behalf of an 
organisation of political nature not being a political party
 


[Section 5(1) and 5(2)(a) 
of the Foreign Contribution (Regulation) Act, 1976]
 


1. (a)   Particulars of the 
Organisation
 


            (Full name in 
BLOCK LETTERS and address)
 


    (b)   Address of the 
Principal Office/Head Office of the Organisation
 


2. Full particulars of the 
person applying on behalf of the Organisation
 


    (a)   Name in full (in 
BLOCK LETTERS)
 


    (b)   Name of father
 


     (c)   Occupation
 


    (d)   Residential 
address
 


    (e)   If an 
office-bearer, the office held in the Organisation.
 


3. Reference of the order 
published by the Central Government in the Official Gazette specifying the 
Organisation as an “Organisation of Political Nature, not being a political 
party”.
 


4. Nature and full details 
of contribution including value, to be received
 


5. The mode/channel of 
receipt
 


6. Purpose for which 
foreign contribution is proposed is to be received
 


7. Particulars of the 
foreign source from which contribution is to be received:
 


    (a)   if an individual, 
his personal particulars including name, present address, permanent address, 
nationality, profession
 


    (b)   if an 
Organisation/Institution/Association/Trust/Foundation/Trade Union, etc., full 
particulars thereof including—
 


      (i)   full name and 
complete address
 


     (ii)   address of Head 
Office/Principal Office
 


    (iii)   aims and 
objects
 


    (iv)   particulars of 
important office-bearers
 


8.   Nature of 
connection/dealings with the foreign source.
 


9.   Any other information 
of significance which the applicant may like to furnish
 


Declaration
 


I hereby declare that the 
above particulars furnished by me are true and correct.
 


 
 



Place:.......................                                                  
Signature of the Applicant
 



Date:...........................
 


Note.—In the 
case of application by an Organisation, it should be signed by the chief 
functionary.
</form><form>
 

THE FOREIGN CONTRIBUTION (REGULATION) RULES, 1976 
 

 
 

1[Form FC 1A 
 

[ See  rule 3(aa)] 
 

Form Of Application For Seeking Prior Permission From The Central Government Under The Foreign Contribution (Regulation) Act, 1976 (Hereinafter Referred To As The Act) For The Acceptance Of Foreign Contribution By An Association Having A Definite Cultural, Economic, Educational, Religious Or Social Programme 
 


 

No.................... Date.................. 
 

To 
 

The Secretary to the Government of India , 
 

Ministry of Home Affairs, Lok Nayak Bhavan, Khan Market, 
 

New Delhi-110003. 
 

Subject : Application for seeking the prior permission of the Central Government under the Foreign Contribution (Regulation) Act, 1976 for acceptance of foreign contribution. 
 

Sir, 
 

I,........................, on behalf of the Association named hereafter, apply for seeking prior permission of the Central Government for the acceptance of foreign contribution under proviso to sub-section (1) of section 6 or under sub-section (1A) of that section or clause (b) of section 10 of the Act. 
 

1. (i) Name of the Association and its complete postal address. 
 

Name 
 

Address 
 

Town/City 
 

State 
 

District 
 

Pin Code 
 

(ii) If the Association is a registered trust or Society please indicates its— 
 

(a) registration number 
 

(b) place of registration 
 

(c) date of registration 
 

(certified copy of the registration certificate to be attached) 
 

(iii) Nature of Association 
 

(a) religious, (b) cultural, (c) economic, (d) educational, (e) social. 
 

Note. — If a religious Association, then state whether— 
 

(a) Hindu, (b) Sikh, (c) Muslim, (d) Christian, (e) Buddhist, (f) Others. 
 

(iv) Please indicate the main aim (s) and object(s) of the Association (enclose copy of the Memorandum of Association and/or the Articles of Association, if applicable). 
 

(v) Please furnish the names and address of the members of the Executive Committee/Governing Council etc.  of the Association, including the Chief Functionary, in the following manner:— 
 

Sl. Name Name of Nationality Occupation Office held Relation Address 
 

No. Father/ in the with other Husband Association, office- 
 

if any bearers,  

  if any 
 

(1) (2) (3) (4) (5) (6) (7) (8) 
 

2. Please indicate whether any member of the Executive Committee/Governing Council etc. of the Association, including the Chief Functionary has, in the discharge of his/her official functions— 
 

(a) been convicted by any court of law, 
 

(b) a prosecution for any offence pending against him/her, 
 

(c) been found guilty of diversion or misutilisation of funds of the Association or any other association in the past. 
 

3. Please indicate whether the applicant Association— 
 

(a) is a branch/unit/associate of foreign based organisation or another association already registered under the Act. If so, name and address of the parent organisation should be furnished; 
 

(b) has been directed by the Central Government in terms of the proviso to sub-section (1) of section 6 of the Act to seek prior permission. If so, the number and date of the relevant order should be furnished. 
 

(c) has been directed by the Central Government in terms of section 10 of the Act to seek prior permission. If so, the number and date of the relevant order should be furnished. 
 

4. Please indicate— 
 

(i) whether the Association ever applied for registration under the Act in the past, if so,— 
 

(a) the date of submission of application for registration, 
 

(b) the number and date of last reference, if any, received from the Ministry, 
 

(c) whether registration was refused, 
 

(d) whether the application for registration is still pending. 
 

(ii) whether the Association has close links with another association, or its unit or branch which has been— 
 

(a) refused registration under the Act, 
 

(b) prohibited from accepting foreign contribution. 
 

5. Please indicate— 
 

(i) Whether the Association was (a) granted prior permission to receive foreign contribution under the Act in the past. If so, the number and date of the letter granting prior permission should be furnished; 
 

(b) whether the account of the receipt and utilisation of the foreign contribution received above was sent to the Central Government in the prescribed form. If so, the date of submission of the accounts should be furnished; 
 

(c) if the prior permission was granted in the current year, details of the foreign contribution received and utilised, purpose-wise, showing the unspent balance should be annexed. 
 

(ii) whether the Association has received foreign contribution without the prior permission of the Central Government, in the past. If so,— 
 

(a) full particulars of the foreign contribution received, address of the branch of the bank and account number in which deposited should be furnished; 
 

(b) whether the said violation has been condoned by the Central Government; 
 

(c) whether the Association has been prohibited from accepting foreign contribution under the Act. 
 

6. Please indicate whether the Association is owner/printer/publisher, editor of a publication which is a “registered newspaper” under the Press and Registration of Books Act, 1867. 
 

7. Please furnish— 
 

(i) Details of the activities of the Association during the past three-years; 
 

(ii) copies of the audited statement of accounts of the association for the past three years. 
 

8. (i) Please indicate— 
 

(a) the nature and value of foreign contribution to be received (a copy of the latest commitment letter from the donor should be furnished); 
 

(b) the purpose for which the foreign contribution is proposed to be received and utilised indicating also the geographical area (s) to be covered. 
 

(ii) a copy of the proposal/project which has been approved by the foreign source for funding, including projected outlays/budget breakup, should be enclosed. 
 

(iii) a copy of the proposal/project which has been approved for funding out of the foreign contribution should be enclosed. (This column applies only to subsequent recipients). 
 

9. Please indicate— 
 

(i) the name of the bank and address of the branch through which the foreign contribution is proposed to be received; 
 

(ii) the account number in the said branch of the bank. 
 

10. Please indicate the particulars of the foreign source or the sources* from which the foreign contribution* is proposed to be received— 
 

(a) if an individual, his personal particulars including name, present address, permanent address, nationality, profession; 
 

(b) if an organisation/institution/association/trust/trade union, etc., full particulars thereof, including— 
 

(i) full name and complete address, 
 

(ii) address of the Head Office/Principal Office, 
 

(iii) particulars of Chief Functionary and important office bearers; 
 

(c) Please indicate whether the foreign source is a Government of a foreign country or agency thereof. 
 

2[10A. whether a recommendation certificate from the competent authority is attached (Yes/No)]* 
 

11. Any other information which the Association may like to furnish. 
 

Yours faithfully, 
 

Signature of the Applicant 
 

[Name of the Chief Functionary or  

  authorised office bearer  

  (with seal of the Association)] 
 

 
 

Declaration 
 

I hereby declare that the above particulars furnished by me are true and correct. 
 

Signature of the Applicant 
 

[Name of the Chief Functionary or 
 

 

  Place:.............................. 
 

authorised office bearer 
 

 

  Date: ............................. 
 

(with seal of the Association)] 
 

*If the foreign contribution, whether currency or article is to be received from any person or association who has received the same as first, second or subsequent recipient, particulars of such person or association should be given against column 10 above. 
 

Notes. — 
 

1. An incomplete application i.e.  without necessary documents/details/explanation is likely to the rejected summarily 
 

2. In case the space against any column is insufficient, separate annexure should be attached. 
 

3. Please use Capital Letters. 
 

4. The application should be signed by the Chief Functionary or authorised office bearer of the Association.] 
 

3[Certificate 
 

(To be submitted along with the application) 
 

This is to certify that the..........................(name of the association) have its registered office at ............................(address) has been formed for undertaking activities in its chosen .....................(economic, educational cultural, religious and social*) field of activity. The antecedents of the organisation have been verified and there is nothing adverse against them. 
 

2. Its proposed project shall be undertaken in the.............................. (District) of.......................(State), the said project will be beneficial to the people living in the area. 
 

3. The grant of prior permission to the aforementioned association to accept foreign contribution amounting to................................ (currency/amount) from.......................(name of address of foreign donor) under the foreign Contribution (Regulation) Act, 1976 for the said project is recommended. 
 

(Recommending authority)** 
 

(With seal) 
 

* Strike out whichever is not applicable. 
 

** Any concerned— 
 

(1) Collector of District: 
 

(2) Department of the State Government; 
 

(3) Ministry/Department of the Government of India .] 
 

------------
 

1. Subs. by G.S.R. 8(E), dated 4th January, 1999 (w.e.f. 4-1-1999). 
 

2. Ins. by G.S.R. 63(E), dated 24th January, 2000 (w.e.f. 25-1-2000). 
 

3. Ins. by G.S.R. 63(E), dated 24th January, 2000 (w.e.f. 25-1-2000). 
 

 
</form><form>
 




The Foreign Contribution (Regulation) Rules, 1976
 





 




1[Form 
FC 2
 


[See rule 3(b)]
 




Application for seeking prior permission of the Central Government to accept 
foreign hospitality
 


[Section 9 read with 
sections 10(d) and 11(1) of the Foreign Contribution (Regulation) Act, 1976]
 


1.   Name in full (in BLOCK 
LETTERS)
 


2.   Date of birth
 


3.   Name of father/husband
 


4.   Present address
 


5.   Permanent address
 


6.   Passport particulars 
(if already in possession)
 


7.   Status:
 


    (a)   Member of 
Legislature
 


    (b)   Office-bearers of 
a political party
 


     (c)   Judge of Supreme 
Court/High Court
 


    (d)   Government 
Servant
 


    (e)   Employee of a 
Company/Corporation
 


     (f)   Any person or 
class of persons not specified in section 9
 


8.   Names of 
countries/places to be visited with duration of stay
 


9.   The countries and 
places where foreign hospitality is to be accepted
 


10. Duration and purpose of 
visit to the country (ies)/place(s) mentioned in column 9 with specific dates.
 


11. Particulars of host(s):—
 


    (a)   If an individual, 
his personal particulars including name, present address, permanent address, 
nationality, profession.
 


    (b)   If an 
Organisation/Institution/Association/Trust/Foundation/Trade Union, etc., full 
particulars thereof including:
 


      (i)   Full name and 
complete address
 


     (ii)   Address of Head 
Office/Principal Office
 


    (iii)   Aims and 
objects
 


    (iv)   Particulars of 
important office-bearers.
 


12. *Full particulars, as 
in Serial  No. 11 (a) and (b) of the foreign source in case the actual source 
extending the hospitality is located in a country other than actually proposed 
to be visited.
 


13. Nature and duration of 
foreign hospitality proposed to be accepted with specific dates and with 
specific details.
 


14. Nature of 
connection/dealings with the host and/or foreign source extending the 
hospitality.
 


*. Delete if not 
applicable.
 


15. Approximate expenditure 
to be incurred on hospitality.
 


16. Any other information 
of significance which the applicant may like to furnish.
 



Declaration
 


I hereby declare that the 
above particulars furnished by me are true and correct.
 



Place:                                                                  
Signature of the Applicant]
 


Date:
 


 
 


—————
 


            1.         Subs. by G.S.R. 755(E), dated 5th November, 1984 (w.e.f. 
5-11-1984).
</form><form>
 




The Foreign Contribution (Regulation) Rules, 1976
 





 




FORM FC 4
 


[See rule 4(b)]
 




Intimation to the Central Government of Receipt of  

Foreign Contribution received by a candidate for Election
 


[Section 6(2) of the 
Foreign Contribution (Regulation) Act, 1976]
 


         1.  Name in full 
(in block letters)
 


         2.  Date of birth
 


         3.  Name of father
 


         4.  Present 
address
 


         5.  Permanent 
address
 


         6.  Date which 
duly nominated as a candidate for election to a Legislature and particulars of 
Legislature [See section 2(1)(b) and 2(1)(f) of the Act]
 


         7.  Full 
particulars of foreign contribution received within 180 days immediately 
proceeding the date on which duly nominated as a candidate for election to the 
Legislature.
 


         8.  Nature and 
full details of the contribution including value.
 


         9.  The 
mode/channel of receipt.
 


       10.  Purpose for 
which contribution was received.
 


       11.  Particulars of 
the foreign source from which contribution received:
 


           (a)  if an 
individual, his personal particulars including name, present address, permanent 
address, nationality, profession
 


           (b)  if an 
Organisation/Institution/Association/Trust/Foundation/Trade Union, etc. full 
particulars thereof including—
 


                   (i)  
full name and complete address
 


                  (ii)  
address of Head Office/Principal Office
 


                 (iii)  
aims and objects
 


                 (iv)  
particulars of important office-bearers
 


       12.  Nature of 
connection/dealings with the foreign sources
 


       13.  Details of 
actual utilisation of the Contribution—
 


           (a)  specific 
purposes for which utilised
 


           (b)  full 
description of the manner in which utilised
 


       14.  Any other 
information of significance which the application may like to furnish
 



Declaration
 


I hereby declare that the 
above particulars furnished by me are true and correct.
 



Place:...............................                                        
Signature of the candidate
 



Date:................................
 


Certified that the above 
declaration was signed by Shri............................................... 
S/o.............................. Resident of..................................................... a 
candidate for election  to (*) .............................................................. before me on this ...................day 
of 20........
 



                                                                                                  
Signature 
 


(Name in block letters)
 



(Designation..................
 


(To be signed by  a Class I 
Gazetted Officer** or a Ist Class Magistrate).
 


* Here specify 
’Legislature’ as defined in section 2(1)(f) of the Act.
 


** Of the State/Central 
Government.
</form><form>
 




The Foreign Contribution (Regulation) Rules, 1976
 





 




Form FC 5
 


[See rule 4(c)]
 




Intimation to the Central Government of receipt of scholarship, stipend or any 
payment of a like nature from a foreign source
 


[Section 7(1) and 7(2) of 
the Foreign Contribution  

(Regulation) Act, 1976]
 


      1.   Name in full (in 
block letters)
 


      2.   Date of birth
 


      3.   Name of father
 


      4.   Present address
 


      5.   Permanent 
address
 


      6.   Passport 
particulars
 


      7.   Specific details 
of occupation/profession
 


      8.   Particulars of 
the foreign source from whom scholarship, stipend or payment of a like nature 
was received—
 


    (a)   if an individual, 
his personal particulars including name, present address, permanent address, 
nationality profession
 


    (b)   if an 
Organisation/Institution/Association/Trust/Foundation/ Trade Union, etc., 
full particulars thereof including—
 


      (i)   full name and 
complete address
 


     (ii)   address of Head 
Office/Principal Office
 


    (iii)   aims and 
objects
 


    (iv)   particulars of 
important office-bearers
 


9. Nature and full details 
of scholarship, stipend or any payment of a like nature received from foreign 
source, indicating (a) total amount and its break-up under various heads like 
cost of journey, equipment, clothing, maintenance, tuition fees, residence fees, 
books, etc. and (b) mode/chennel of receipt
 


10. Purpose of  the 
scholarship, stipend or any payment of a like nature with specific details of 
courses attended/to be attended
 


    11.   Duration of stay 
abroad with dates
 


    12.   Any other 
information of significance, which the applicant may like to furnish
 



Declaration
 


I hereby declare that the 
above particulars furnished by me are true and correct.
 



Place:                                                                               
Signature of applicant
 


Date:
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 179 (E), dated 25th March, 1991 (w.e.f. 
1-4-1991).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 83(E), dated 8th February, 2008, for “four 
months” (w.e.f. 12-2-2008). Earlier the words “four months” were substituted by 
G.S.R. 592(E), dated 27th December, 1996 (w.e.f. 27-12-1996).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 755 (E), dated 5th November, 1984 (w.e.f. 
5-11-1984).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 755 (E), dated 5th 
November, 1984 (w.e.f. 5-11-1984).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Subs. by S.O. 860(E), dated 29th December, 1977 (w.e.f. 29-12-1977 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 179(E), dated 25th March, 1991 (w.e.f. 1-4-1991 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 728(E), dated 10th October, 2008 for “within four months” (w.e.f. 11-10-2008 ). Earlier the words “four months” were substituted by G.S.R. 592(E), dated 27th December, 1996 (w.e.f. 27-12-1996).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>