<act><tid>1052228</tid>
<title>THE ARBITRATION ACT, <year>1940</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum></title>

ACT NO. 10 OF <year>1940</year>
[ 11th March, <year>1940</year>.]

An Act to consolidate and amend the law relating to Arbitration.

WHEREAS it is expedient to consolidate and amend the law relating 
to, arbitration <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>;

It is hereby enacted as follows:-

CHAP

INTRODUCTORY

CHAPTER I

INTRODUCTORY





<article><tid>955768</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1091470</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Arbitration Act, <year>1940</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>716151</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> except the State of 
Jammu and Kashmir].

</section>

<section><tid>198531</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on the 1st day of July, <year>1940</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>738672</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything 
repugnant in the subject or context,-
<section><tid>1430346</tid>
<number>a</number>" arbitration agreement" means a written agreement to 
submit present or future differences to arbitration, whether 
an arbitrator is named therein or not;

</section>

<section><tid>1311823</tid>
<number>b</number>" award" means an arbitration award;

</section>

<section><tid>105873</tid>
<number>c</number>" Court" means a Civil Court having jurisdiction to 
decide the questions forming the subject- matter of the 
reference if the same had been the subject- matter of a suit, 
but does not, except for the purpose of arbitration proceed- 
ings under section 21, include a Small Cause Court;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>18</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been extended to--

and brought into force in Dadra and Nagar Heveli by Reg. 6 of 
<year>1963</year>, a. 2 and Sch. I (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1965</year>);

Goa. Daman and Diu by Act 30 of <year>1965</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 15- 6- <year>1966</year>); 
the whole of the Union territory of Lakshadweep vide Reg. 8 of <year>1965</year>, 
s. 3 and Sch. (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1967</year>): and

the Union territory of Pondicherry by Act 26 of <year>1968</year>, a. 3 and 
Sch. amended in Uttar Pradesh by U. P. Act 57 of <year>1976</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The words" in the Provinces" omitted by the A. O. <year>1950</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, a. 3 and Sch., for" except Part B 
States":

The Act shall come into force in the State of sikkim on 1. 9. <year>1984</year> 
vide Notifn. No. S. O. 646 (E), dated 24. 8 84 Gaz. of India, Exty. Pt. 
II Sec. 3 (ii).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1697212</tid>
<number>d</number>" legal representative" means a person who in law 
represents the estate of a deceased person, and includes any 
person who intermeddles with the estate of the deceased, and, 
where a party acts in a representative character, the person 
on whom the estate devolves on the death of the party so 
acting;

</section>

<section><tid>85567</tid>
<number>e</number>" reference" means a reference to arbitration.
CHAP

ARBITRATION WITHOUT INTERVENTION OF A COURT

CHAPTER II

ARBITRATION WITHOUT INTERVENTION OF A COURT




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1529130</tid>
<number>3</number>Provisions implied in arbitration agreement. An arbitration 
agreement, unless a different intention is expressed therein, shall be 
deemed to include the provisions set out in the First Schedule in so 
far as they are applicable to the reference.


</article>



<article><tid>1242720</tid>
<number>4</number>Agreement that arbitrators be appointed by the third party. 
The parties to an arbitration agreement may agree that any reference 
thereunder shall be to an arbitrator or arbitrators to be appointed by 
a person designated in the agreement either by name or as the holder 
for the time being of any office or appointment.


</article>



<article><tid>1091250</tid>
<number>5</number>Authority of appointed arbitrator or umpire irrevocable 
except by leave of Court. The authority of an appointed arbitrator or 
umpire shall not be revocable except with the- leave of the Court, 
unless a contrary Intention is expressed in the arbitration agreement.


</article>



<article><tid>420705</tid>
<number> 6</number> Arbitration agreement not to be discharged by death of party 
thereto.
<section><tid>1943456</tid>
<number>1</number>An arbitration agreement shall not be discharged by the  
death of any party thereto, either as respects the deceased or any 
other party, but shall in such event be enforceable by or against 
the legal representative of the deceased.

</section>

<section><tid>1107813</tid>
<number>2</number>The authority of an arbitrator shall not be revoked by the 
death of any party by whom he was appointed.

</section>

<section><tid>1114352</tid>
<number>3</number>Nothing in this section shall affect the operation of any 
law by virtue of which any right of action is extinguished by the 
death of a person.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1737370</tid>
<number> 7</number> Provisions in case of insolvency.
<section><tid>651342</tid>
<number>1</number>Where it is provided  
by a term in a contract to which an insolvent is a party that any 
differences arising there out or in connection therewith shall be 
referred to arbitration, the said term shall, if the receiver adopts 
the contract, be enforceable by or against him so far as it relates to 
any such differences.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>18A</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1506924</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a person who has been adjudged an insolvent had, 
before the commencement of the insolvency proceedings, become a party 
to an arbitration agreement, and any matter to which the agreement 
applies is required to be determined in connection with, or for the 
purposes of, the insolvency proceedings, then, if the case is one to 
which subsection (1) does not apply, any other party to the agreement 
or the receiver may apply to the Court having jurisdiction in the 
insolvency proceedings for an order directing that the matter in 
question shall be referred to arbitration in accordance with the 
agreement, and the Court may, if it is of opinion that, having regard 
to all the circumstances of the case, the matter ought to be 
determined by arbitration, make an order accordingly.

</section>

<section><tid>185525</tid>
<number>3</number>In this section the expression" receiver" includes an 
Official Assignee.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>19</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1232861</tid>
<number> 8</number> power of Court to appoint arbitrator or umpire.
<section><tid>1788612</tid>
<number>1</number>In any  
of the following cases,-

<subsection><tid>1089985</tid>
<number>a</number>where an arbitration agreement provides that the 
reference shall be to one or more arbitrators to be appointed 
by consent of the parties, and all the parties do not, after 
differences have arisen, concur in the appointment or 
appointments; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>723478</tid>
<number>b</number>if any appointed arbitrator or umpire neglects or 
refuses to act, or is incapable of acting, or dies, and the 
arbitration agreement does not show that it was intended that 
the vacancy should not be supplied, and the parties or the 
arbitrators, as the case may be, do not supply the vacancy; 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>199379</tid>
<number>c</number>where the parties or the arbitrators are required to 
appoint an umpire and do not appoint him;
any party may serve the other parties or the arbitrators, as the case 
may be, with a written notice to concur in the appointment or 
appointments or in supplying the vacancy.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>411664</tid>
<number>2</number>If the appointment is not made within fifteen clear days 
after the service of the said notice, the Court may, on the 
application of the party who gave the notice and after giving the 
other parties an opportunity of being heard, appoint an arbitrator or 
arbitrators or umpire, as the case may be, who shall have like power 
to act in the reference and to make an award as if he or they had been 
appointed by consent of all parties.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1120409</tid>
<number> 9</number> Power to party to appoint new arbitrator or in certain 
cases, a sole arbitrator. Where an arbitration agreement provides 
that a reference shall be to two arbitrators, one to be appointed by 
each party, then, unless a different intention is expressed in the 
agreement,-
<section><tid>1106138</tid>
<number>a</number>if either of the appointed arbitrators neglects or 
refuses to act, or is incapable of acting, or dies, the party 
who appointed him may appoint a new arbitrator in his place;

</section>

<section><tid>371235</tid>
<number>b</number>if one party fails to appoint an arbitrator, either 
originally or by way of substitution as aforesaid, for 
fifteen clear days- after the sence by the other party of a 
notice in writing to make the appointment, such other party 
having appointed his arbitrator before giving the notice, the 
party who has appointed an. arbitrator may appoint that 
arbitrator to act as sole arbitrator in the reference, and 
his award shall be binding on both parties as if he had been 
appointed by consent:
Provided that the Court may set aside any appointment as sole 
arbitrator made under clause (b) and either, on sufficient cause being


<pagefootnote><pagenum>20</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

shown, allow further time to the defaulting party to appoint an 
arbitrator or pass such other order as it thinks fit.

Explanation.- The fact that an arbitrator or umpire, after a 
request by either party to enter on and proceed with the reference, 
does not within one month comply with the request may constitute a 
neglect or refusal to act within the meaning of section 8 and this 
section.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>499427</tid>
<number> 10</number> Provisions as to appointment of three or more arbitrators.

<section><tid>526429</tid>
<number>1</number>Where an arbitration agreement provides that a reference shall be  
to three Arbitrators, one to be appointed by each party and the third 
by the two appointed arbitrators, the agreement shall have effect as 
if it provided for the appointment of an umpire, and not for the 
appointment of a third arbitrator, by the two arbitrators appointed by 
the parties.

</section>

<section><tid>1559658</tid>
<number>2</number>Where an arbitration agreement provides that a reference 
shall be to three arbitrators to be appointed otherwise than as men- 
tioned in sub- section (1), the award of the majority shall, unless the 
arbitration agreement otherwise provides, prevail.

</section>

<section><tid>961419</tid>
<number>3</number>Where an arbitration agreement provides for the appointment 
of more arbitrators than three, the award of the majority, or if the 
arbitrators are equally divided in their opinions, the award of the 
umpire shall, unless the arbitration agreement otherwise provides, 
prevail.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>596725</tid>
<number> 11</number> Power to Court to remove arbitrators or umpire in certain 
circumstances.
<section><tid>1849024</tid>
<number>1</number>The Court may, on the application of any party to a  
reference, remove an arbitrator or umpire who fails to use all 
reasonable dispatch in entering on and proceeding with the reference 
and making an award.

</section>

<section><tid>206503</tid>
<number>2</number>The Court may remove an arbitrator or umpire who has mis- 
conducted himself or the proceedings.

</section>

<section><tid>987751</tid>
<number>3</number>Where an arbitrator or umpire is removed under this section, 
he shall not be entitled to receive any remuneration in respect of his 
services.

</section>

<section><tid>712376</tid>
<number>4</number>For the purposes of this section the expression" proceeding 
with the reference" includes, in a case where reference to the umpire 
becomes necessary, giving notice of that fact to the parties and to 
the umpire.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1265271</tid>
<number> 12</number> Power of Court where arbitrator is removed or his authority 
revoked.
<section><tid>584075</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the Court removes an umpire who has not entered on  
the reference or one or more arbitrators (not being all the arbitra-  
  tors), the Court may, on the application of any party to the arbitra- 
tion agreement, appoint persons to fill the vacancies.

</section>

<section><tid>1108461</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the authority of an arbitrator or arbitrators or an 
umpire is revoked by leave of the Court, or where the Court removes an 
umpire who has entered on the reference or a sole arbitrator or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>21</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

all the arbitrators, the Court may, on the application of any party to 
the arbitration agreement, either-


<subsection><tid>1314955</tid>
<number>a</number>appoint a person to act as sole arbitrator in the place 
of the person or persons displaced, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>497913</tid>
<number>b</number>order that the arbitration agreement shall cease to 
have effect with respect to the difference referred.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>135168</tid>
<number>3</number>A person appointed under this section as an arbitrator or 
umpire shall have the like power to act in the reference and to make 
an award as if he had been appointed in accordance with the arbitra- 
tion agreement.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>862520</tid>
<number> 13</number> Powers of arbitrator. The arbitrators or umpire shall, 
unless a different intention is expressed in the agreement, have power 
to-
<section><tid>481460</tid>
<number>a</number>administer oath to the parties and witnesses appearing;

</section>

<section><tid>1611763</tid>
<number>b</number>state a special case for the opinion of the Court' on 
any question of law involved, or state the award, wholly or 
in part, in the form of a special case of such question for 
the opinion of the Court;

</section>

<section><tid>318320</tid>
<number>c</number>make the award conditional or in the alternative;

</section>

<section><tid>1415515</tid>
<number>d</number>correct in an award any clerical mistake or error 
arising from any accidental slip or omission;

</section>

<section><tid>883084</tid>
<number>e</number>administer to any party to the arbitration such 
interrogatories as may, in the opinion of the arbitrators or 
umpire, be necessary.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>665266</tid>
<number> 14</number> Award to be signed and filed.
<section><tid>13574</tid>
<number>1</number>When the arbitrators or  
umpire have made their award, they shall sign it and shall give notice 
in writing to the parties of the making and signing thereof and of the 
amount of fees and charges payable in respect of the arbitration and 
award.

</section>

<section><tid>76709</tid>
<number>2</number>The arbitrators or umpire shall, at the request of any party 
to the arbitration agreement or any person claiming under such party 
or if so directed by the Court and upon payment of the fees and 
charges due in respect of the arbitration and award and of the costs 
and charges of filing the award, cause the award or a signed copy of 
it, together with any depositions and documents which may have been, 
taken and proved before them, to be filed in Court, and the Court 
shall thereupon give notice to the parties of the filing of the award.

</section>

<section><tid>1185353</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the arbitrators or umpire state a special case under 
clause (b) of section 13, the Court, after giving notice to the 
parties and hearing them, shall pronounce its opinion thereon and such 
opinion shall be added to, and shall form part of, the award.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1294263</tid>
<number> 15</number> Power of Court to modify award. The Court may by order 
modify or correct an award-
<section><tid>971137</tid>
<number>a</number>where it appears that a part of, the award is upon a 
matter not referred to arbitration and such part can be

<pagefootnote><pagenum>22</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

separated from the other part and does not affect the 
decision on the matter referred; or


</section>

<section><tid>910547</tid>
<number>b</number>where the award is imperfect in form, or contains any 
obvious error which can be amended without affecting such 
decision; or

</section>

<section><tid>1441219</tid>
<number>c</number>where the award contains a clerical mistake or an error 
arising from an accidental slip or omission.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>109140</tid>
<number> 16</number> Power to remit award.
<section><tid>628660</tid>
<number>1</number>The Court may from time to time  
remit the award or any matter referred to arbitration to the 
arbitrators or umpire for reconsideration upon such terms as it thinks 
fit-

<subsection><tid>1958229</tid>
<number>a</number>where- the award has left undetermined any of the 
matters referred to arbitration, or where it determines any 
matter not referred to arbitration and such matter cannot be 
separated without affecting the determination of the matters 
referred; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1457077</tid>
<number>b</number>where the award is so indefinite as to be incapable of 
execution; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>273851</tid>
<number>c</number>where an objection to the legality of the award is 
apparent upon the face of it.,

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1723887</tid>
<number>2</number>Where an award is remitted under sub- section (1) the Court 
shall fix the time within which the arbitrator or umpire shall submit 
his decision to the Court:
Provided that any time so fixed may be extended by subsequent 
order of the Court.


</section>

<section><tid>186495</tid>
<number>3</number>An award remitted under sub- section (1) shall become void on 
the failure of the arbitrator or umpire to reconsider it and submit 
his decision within the time fixed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1171700</tid>
<number>17</number>Judgment in terms of award. Where the Court sees no cause to 
remit the award or any of the matters referred to arbitration for 
reconsideration or to set aside the award, the Court shall, after the 
time for making an application to set aside the award has expired, or 
such application having been made, after refusing it, proceed to 
pronounce judgment according to the award, and upon the judgment so 
pronounced a decree shall follow and no appeal shall lie from such 
decree except on the ground that it is in excess of, or not otherwise 
in accordance with, the award.


</article>



<article><tid>1633982</tid>
<number> 18</number> Power of Court to pass interim orders.
<section><tid>1223643</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding  
anything contained in section 17, at any time after the filing of the 
award, whether notice of the filing has been served or not, upon being 
satisfied by affidavit or otherwise that a party has taken or is about 
to take steps to defeat, delay or obstruct the execution of any decree 
that may be passed upon the award, or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>23</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

that speedy execution of the award is just and necessary, the Court 
may pass such interim orders as it deems necessary.


</section>

<section><tid>801287</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person against whom such interim orders have been passed 
may show cause against such orders, and the Court, after hearing the 
parties, may pass such further orders as it deems necessary and just.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>710617</tid>
<number>19</number>Power to supersede arbitration where award becomes void or 
is set aside. Where an award has become void under sub- section (3) of 
section 16 or has been set aside, the Court may by order supersede the 
reference and shall thereupon order that the arbitration agreement 
shall cease to have effect with respect to the difference referred.
CHAP

ARBITRATION WITH INTERVENTION OF A COURT WHERE THERE IS NO SUITPENDING

CHAPTER III

ARBITRATION WITH INTERVENTION OF A COURT WHERE THERE IS NO 
SUIT PENDING



</article>



<article><tid>811701</tid>
<number> 20</number> Application to file in Court arbitration agreement.
<section><tid>778208</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Where any persons have entered into an arbitration agreement before 
the institution of any suit with respect to the subject matter of the 
agreement or any part of it, and where a difference has arisen to 
which the agreement applies, they or any of them, instead of 
proceeding under Chapter II, may apply to a Court having jurisdiction 
in the matter to which the agreement relates, that the agreement be 
filed in Court.

</section>

<section><tid>1518533</tid>
<number>2</number>The application shall be in writing and shall be numbered 
and registered as a suit between one or more of the parties interested 
or claiming to be interested as plaintiff or plaintiffs and the 
remainder as defendant or defendants, if the application has been 
presented by all the parties, or, if otherwise, between the applicant 
as plaintiff and the other parties as defendants.

</section>

<section><tid>1950726</tid>
<number>3</number>On such application being made, the Court shall direct 
notice thereof to be given to all parties to the agreement other than 
the applicants, requiring them to show cause within the time specified 
in the notice why the agreement should not be filed.

</section>

<section><tid>638888</tid>
<number>4</number>Where no sufficient cause is shown, the Court shall order 
the agreement to be filed, and shall make an order of reference to the 
arbitrator appointed by the parties, whether in the agreement or 
otherwise, or, where the parties cannot agree upon an arbitrator, to 
an arbitrator appointed by the Court.

</section>

<section><tid>480970</tid>
<number>5</number>Thereafter the arbitration shall proceed in accordance with, 
and shall be governed by, the other provisions of this Act so far as 
they can be made applicable.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>24</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

CHAP

ARBITRATION IN SUITS

CHAPTER IV

ARBITRATION IN SUITS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>157537</tid>
<number>21</number>Parties to suit may apply for order of reference. Where in 
any suit all the parties interested agree that any matter in 
difference between them in the suit shall be referred to arbitration, 
they may at any time before judgment is pronounced apply in writing to 
the Court for an order of reference.


</article>



<article><tid>1310890</tid>
<number>22</number>Appointment of arbitrator. The arbitrator shall be 
appointed in such manner as may be 
agreed upon between the parties.


</article>



<article><tid>238279</tid>
<number> 23</number> Order of reference.
<section><tid>1756625</tid>
<number>1</number>The Court shall, by order, refer to  
the arbitrator the matter in difference which he is required to 
determine, and shall in the order specify such time as it thinks 
reasonable for the making of the award.

</section>

<section><tid>1606794</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a matter is referred to arbitration, the Court shall 
not, save in the manner and to the extent provided in this Act, deal 
with such matter in the suit.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>363170</tid>
<number>24</number>Reference to arbitration by some of ht parties. Where some 
only of the parties to a suit apply to have the matters in difference 
between them referred to arbitration in accordance with, and in the 
manner provided by, section 21, the Court may, if it thinks fit, so 
refer such matters to arbitration (provided that the same can be  
  separated from the rest of the subject- matter of the suit) in the 
manner provided in that section, but the suit shall continue so far as 
it relates to the parties who have not joined in the said application 
and to matters not contained in the said reference as if no such 
application had been made, and an award made in pursuance of such a 
reference shall be binding only on the parties who have joined in the 
application.


</article>



<article><tid>631064</tid>
<number>25</number>Provisions applicable to arbitrations under this Chapter. 
The provisions of the other Chapters shall, so far as they can to be 
made applicable, apply to arbitrations under this Chapter:
Provided that the Court may, in any of the circumstances men- 
tioned in sections 8, 10, 11 and 12, instead of filling up the 
vacancies or making the appointments, make an order superseding the 
arbitration and proceed with the suit, and where the Court makes an 
order superseding the arbitration under section 19, it shall proceed 
with the suit.

CHAP

GENERAL

CHAPTER V

GENERAL



</article>



<article><tid>45332</tid>
<number>26</number>Application of Chapter. Save as otherwise provided in this 
Act, the provisions of this Chapter shall apply to all arbitrations.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>25</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1308041</tid>
<number> 27</number> Power of arbitrators to make an interim award.
<section><tid>383046</tid>
<number>1</number>Unless a  
different intention appears in the arbitration agreement,- the 
arbitrators or umpire may, if they think fit, make an interim award.

</section>

<section><tid>1109133</tid>
<number>2</number>All references in this Act to an award shall include 
references to an interim award made under sub- section (1).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>597719</tid>
<number> 28</number> Power to Court only to enlarge time for making award.
<section><tid>108907</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The Court may, if it thinks fit, whether the time for making the award 
has expired or not and whether the award has been made or not enlarge 
from time to time the time for making the award.

</section>

<section><tid>709576</tid>
<number>2</number>Any provision in an arbitration agreement whereby the 
arbitrators or umpire may, except with the consent of all the parties 
to the agreement, enlarge the time for making the award, shall be void 
and of no effect.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1568155</tid>
<number>29</number>Interest on awards. Where and in so far is an award is for 
the payment of money the Court may in the decree order interest, from 
the date of the decree at such rate as the Court deems reasonable, to 
be paid on the principal sum as adjudged by the award and confirmed by 
the decree.


</article>



<article><tid>1503578</tid>
<number> 30</number> Grounds for setting aside award. An award shall not be set 
aside except on one or more of the following grounds, namely:-
<section><tid>517991</tid>
<number>a</number>that an arbitrator or umpire has misconducted himself 
or the proceedings

</section>

<section><tid>1940752</tid>
<number>b</number>that an award has been made after the issue of an order 
by the Court superseding the arbitration or after arbitration 
proceedings have become invalid under section 35;

</section>

<section><tid>1430414</tid>
<number>c</number>that an award has been improperly procured or is other- 
wise invalid.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1882318</tid>
<number> 31</number> Jurisdiction.
<section><tid>205749</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the previsions of this Act, an  
award may be filed in any Court having jurisdiction in the matter to 
which the reference relates.

</section>

<section><tid>1604327</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the 
time being in force and save as otherwise provided in this Act, all 
questions regarding the validity, effect or existence of an award or 
an arbitration agreement between the parties to the agreement- or 
persons claiming under them shall be decided by the Court in which the 
award under the agreement has been, or may be, filed, and by no other 
Court.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>26</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1145875</tid>
<number>3</number>All applications regarding the conduct of arbitration 
proceedings or otherwise arising out of such proceedings shall be made 
to the Court where the award has been, or may be, filed, and to no 
other Court.

</section>

<section><tid>1684349</tid>
<number>4</number>Notwithstanding anything contained elsewhere in this Act or 
in any other law for the time being in force, where in any reference 
any application under this Act has been made in a Court competent to 
entertain it, that Court alone shall have jurisdiction over the 
arbitration proceedings-, and all subsequent applications arising, out 
of that reference, and the arbitration proceedings shall be made in 
that Court and in no other Court.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>874260</tid>
<number>32</number>Bar to suits contesting arbitration agreement or award. 
Notwithstanding any law for the time being in force, no suit shall 
lie on any ground whatsoever for a decision upon the existence, effect 
or validity of an arbitration agreement or award, nor shall any 
arbitration agreement or award be <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> enforced], set aside, amended, 
modified or in any way affected otherwise than as provided in this 
Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1154891</tid>
<number>33</number>Arbitration agreement or award to be contested by 
application. Any party to an arbitration agreement or any person 
claiming under him desiring to challenge the existence or validity of 
an arbitration agreement or an award or to have the effect of either 
determined shall apply to the Court and the Court shall decide the 
question on affidavits:
Provided that where the Court deems it just and expedient, it may 
set down the application for hearing on other evidence also, and it 
may pass such orders for discovery and particulars as it may do in a 
suit.



</article>



<article><tid>1722761</tid>
<number>34</number>Power to stay legal proceedings where there is an 
arbitration agreement. Where any party to an arbitration agreement or 
any person claiming under him commences any legal proceedings against 
any other patty to the agreement or any person claiming under him in 
respect of any matter agreed to be referred, any party to such legal 
proceedings may, at any time before filing a written statement or 
taking any other steps in' the proceedings, apply to the judicial 
authority before which the proceedings are pending to stay the pro- 
ceedings; and if satisfied that there is no sufficient reason why the 
matter should not be referred in accordance with the arbitration 
agreement and that the applicant was, at the time when the proceed-

<pagefootnote><pagenum>26A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 47 of <year>1963</year>, s. 43 (w. e. f. 1- 3- <year>1964</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

ings were commenced. and still remains, ready and willing to do all 
things necessary to the proper conduct of the arbitration, such 
authority may make an order staying the proceedings.



</article>



<article><tid>1912867</tid>
<number> 35</number> Effect of legal proceedings on arbitration.
<section><tid>715634</tid>
<number>1</number>No reference  
nor award shall be rendered invalid by reason only of the commencement 
of legal proceedings upon the subject- matter of the reference, but 
when legal proceedings upon the whole of the subject- matter of the 
reference have been commenced between all the parties to the reference 
and a notice thereof has been given to the arbitrators or umpire, all 
further proceedings in a pending reference shall, unless a stay of 
proceedings is granted under section 34, be invalid.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>27</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1206061</tid>
<number>2</number>In this section the expression" parties to the reference" 
includes any persons claiming under any of the parties and litigating 
under the same title.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1286256</tid>
<number>36</number>Power of Court, where arbitration agreement is ordered not 
to apply to a particular difference, to order that a provision making 
an award a condition precedent to an action shall not apply to such 
diffference. Where it is provided (whether in the arbitration  
  agreement or otherwise) that an award under an arbitration agreement 
shall be a condition precedent to the bringing of an action with 
respect to any matter to which the agreement applies, the Court, if it 
orders (whether under this Act or any other law) that the agreement 
shall cease to have effect as regards any particular difference, may 
further order that the said provision shall also cease to have effect 
as regards that difference.


</article>



<article><tid>1656413</tid>
<number> 37</number> Limitations.
<section><tid>346991</tid>
<number>1</number>All the provisions of the Indian  
Limitation Act, <year>1908</year>, (9 of <year>1908</year>.) shall apply to arbitrations as they 
apply to proceedings in Court.

</section>

<section><tid>1783117</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding any term in an arbitration agreement to the 
effect that no cause of action shall accrue in respect of any matter 
required by the agreement to be referred until an award is made under 
the agreement, a cause of action shall, for the purpose of limitation, 
be deemed to have accrued in respect of any such matter at the time 
when it would have accrued but for that term in the agreement.

</section>

<section><tid>382407</tid>
<number>3</number>For the purposes of this section and of the Indian 
Limitation Act, <year>1908</year>, (9 of <year>1908</year>.) an arbitration shall be deemed to 
be commenced when one party to the arbitration agreement serves on the 
other parties thereto a notice requiring the appointment of an 
arbitrator, or where the arbitration agreement provides that the 
reference shall be to a person named or designated in the agreement, 
requiring that the difference be submitted to the person so named or 
designated.

</section>

<section><tid>30646</tid>
<number>4</number>Where the terms of an agreement to refer future differences 
to arbitration provide that any claims to which the agreement applies 
shall be barred unless notice to appoint an arbitrator is given or an 
arbitrator is appointed or some other step to commence arbitration 
proceedings is taken within a time fixed by the agreement, and a 
difference arises to which the agreement applies, the Court, if it is 
of opinion that in the circumstances of the case undue hardship would 
otherwise be caused, and notwithstanding that the time so fixed has 
expired, may on such terms, if any, as the justice of the case may 
require, extend the time for such period as it thinks proper.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>38</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>237684</tid>
<number>5</number>Where the Court orders that an award be set aside or orders, 
after the commencement of an arbitration, that the arbitration agree- 
ment shall cease to have effect with respect to the difference 
referred, the period between the commencement of the arbitration and 
the date of the order of the Court shall be excluded in computing the 
time prescribed by the Indian Limitation Act, <year>1908</year>, for the com- 
mencement of the proceedings (including arbitration) with respect to 
the difference referred.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>464303</tid>
<number> 38</number> Disputes as to arbitrator' s remuneration or costs.
<section><tid>1150747</tid>
<number>1</number>If in  
any case an arbitrator or umpire refuses to deliver his award except 
on payment of the fees demanded by him, the Court may, on an 
application in this behalf, order that the arbitrator or umpire shall 
deliver the award to the applicant on payment into Court by the 
applicant of the fees demanded, and shall, after such inquiry, if any, 
as it thinks fit, further order that out of the money so paid into 
Court there shall be paid to the arbitrator or umpire by way of fees 
such sum as the Court may consider reasonable and that the balance of 
the money, if any, shall be refunded to the applicant.

</section>

<section><tid>829847</tid>
<number>2</number>An application under subsection (1) may be made by any party 
to the reference unless the fees demanded have been fixed by written 
agreement between him and the arbitrator or umpire, and the arbitrator 
or umpire shall be entitled to appear and be heard on any such 
application.

</section>

<section><tid>1740903</tid>
<number>3</number>The Court may make such orders as it thinks fit respecting 
the costs of an arbitration where any question arises respecting such 
costs and the award contains no sufficient provision concerning them.
CHAP

APPEALS

CHAPTER VI

APPEALS.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>685723</tid>
<number> 39</number> Appealable orders.
<section><tid>1666609</tid>
<number>1</number>An appeal shall lie from the  
following orders passed under this Act (and from no others) to the 
Court authorised by law to hear appeals from original decrees of the 
Court passing the order:- 
An order-

<subsection><tid>69007</tid>
<number>i</number>superseding an arbitration;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1630980</tid>
<number>ii</number>on an award stated in the form of a special case;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1008286</tid>
<number>iii</number>modifying or correcting an award;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>965875</tid>
<number>iv</number>filing or refusing to file an arbitration agreement;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>53871</tid>
<number>v</number>staying or refusing to stay legal proceedings where 
there is an arbitration agreement;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1335698</tid>
<number>vi</number>setting aside or refusing to set aside an award;
Provided that the provisions of this section shall not apply to 
any order passed by a Small Cause Court.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>29</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1267538</tid>
<number>2</number>No second appeal shall lie from an order passed in appeal 
under this section, but nothing in this section shall affect or take 
away any right to appeal to the Supreme Court.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER VII

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>256396</tid>
<number>40</number>Small Cause Court not to have jurisdiction over arbitrations 
save arbitrations in suits before it. A Small Cause Court shall have 
no jurisdiction over any arbitration proceedings or over any 
application arising thereout save on application made under section 
21.


</article>



<article><tid>28932</tid>
<number> 41</number> Procedure and powers of Court. Subject to the provisions of 
this Act and of rules made there under-
<section><tid>754255</tid>
<number>a</number>the provisions of- the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year>, 
 (5 of <year>1908</year>.) shall apply to all proceedings before the Court, 
and to all appeals, under this Act, and

</section>

<section><tid>245658</tid>
<number>b</number>the Court shall have, for the purpose of, and in 
relation to, arbitration proceedings, the same power of 
making orders in respect of any of the matters set out in the 
Second Schedule as it has for the purpose of, and in relation 
to, any proceedings before the Court:
Provided that nothing in clause (b) shall be taken to prejudice 
any power which may be vested in an arbitrator or umpire for making 
orders with respect to any of such matters.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1937908</tid>
<number> 42</number> Service of notice by party or arbitrator. Any notice 
required by this Act to be served otherwise than through the Court by 
a party to an arbitration agreement or by an arbitrator or umpire 
shall be served in the manner provided in the arbitration agreement, 
or if there is no such provision, either-
<section><tid>770273</tid>
<number>a</number>by delivering it to the person on whom it is to be 
served or

</section>

<section><tid>1102340</tid>
<number>b</number>by sending it by post in a letter addressed to that 
person at his usual or last known place of abode or business 
in India and registered under Chapter VI of the Indian Post 
Office Act, <year>1898</year>. (6 of <year>1898</year>.)



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>354483</tid>
<number> 43</number> Power of Court to issue processes for appearance before 
arbitrator.
<section><tid>1120379</tid>
<number>1</number>The Court shall issue the same processes to the  
parties and witnesses whom the arbitrator or umpire desires to examine 
as the Court may issue in suits tried before it.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>30</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1188461</tid>
<number>2</number>Persons failing to attend in accordance with such process, 
or making any other default, or refusing to give their evidence, or 
guilty of any contempt to the arbitrator or umpire during the 
investigation of the reference, shall be subject to the like 
disadvantages, penalties and punishments by order of the Court on the 
representation of the arbitrator or umpire as they would incur for the 
like offences in suits tried before the Court.

</section>

<section><tid>759740</tid>
<number>3</number>In this section the expression processes" includes sum- 
monses and commissions for the examination of witnesses- and summonses 
to produce documents.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>798789</tid>
<number> 44</number> Power to High Court to make rules. The High Court may make 
rules consistent with this Act as to-
<section><tid>1749545</tid>
<number>a</number>the filing of awards and all proceedings consequent 
thereon or incidental thereto;

</section>

<section><tid>867972</tid>
<number>b</number>the filing and hearing of special cases and all 
proceedings consequent thereon or incidental thereto;

</section>

<section><tid>454028</tid>
<number>c</number>the staying of any suit or proceeding in contravention 
of an arbitration agreement;

</section>

<section><tid>1731401</tid>
<number>d</number>the forms to be used for the purposes of this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>13924</tid>
<number>e</number>generally, all proceedings in Court under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>724501</tid>
<number>45</number>Government to be bound. The provisions of this Act shall be 
binding on the Government.


</article>



<article><tid>714093</tid>
<number> 46</number> Application of Act to statutory arbitrations. The provisions 
of this Act, except sub- section
<section><tid>963669</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 6 and sections 7, 12,  
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 36] and 37, shall apply to every arbitration under any other 
enactment for the time being in force, as if the arbitration were 
pursuant to an arbitration agreement and as if that other enactment 
were an arbitration agreement, except in so far as this Act is in- 
consistent with that other enactment or with any rules made there- 
under.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1886363</tid>
<number>47</number>Act to apply to all arbitrations. Subject to the provisions 
of section 46, and save in so far as is otherwise provided by any law 
for the time being in force, the provisions of this Act shall apply to 
all arbitrations and to all proceedings thereunder:
Provided that an arbitration award otherwise obtained may with 
the consent of all the parties interested be taken into consideration 
as a compromise or adjustment of a suit by any Court before which the 
suit is pending.



</article>



<article><tid>444899</tid>
<number>48</number>Saving for pending references. The provisions of this Act 
shall not apply to any reference pending at the commencement of this 
Act, to which the law in force immediately before the commencement of 
this Act shall, notwithstanding any repeal effected by this Act, 
continue to apply.


</article>



<article><tid>1283214</tid>
<number>49</number>[ Repeals and amendments.] Rep. by the Repealing and Amending 
Act, <year>1945</year> (6 of <year>1945</year>), s. 2 and Sch. I.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>31</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 25 of <year>1942</year>, s. 3 and Sch. II.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</article>



 </act>