<act><tid>1048477</tid>
<title>THE INTER- STATE WATER DISPUTES (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 14 OF <year>2002</year>
[ 28th March, <year>2002</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Inter- State Water Disputes Act, <year>1956</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>1333995</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>1400768</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Inter- State Water Disputes (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1091754</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>138168</tid>
<number>2</number>Amendment of section 1.- In section 1 of the Inter- State Water 
Disputes Act, <year>1956</year> (33 of <year>1956</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the  
  principal Act), in sub- section 1, for the words" Inter- State", the 
words" Inter- State River" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1575540</tid>
<number> 3</number> Amendment of section 4.- In section 4 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>386487</tid>
<number>a</number>for sub- section (1), the following sub- section shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (1) When any request under section 3 is received from any State 
Government in respect of any water dispute and the Central Government 
is of opinion that the water dispute cannot be settled by 
exceeding one year from the date of receipt of such request, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, constitute a Water Disputes 
Tribunal for the adjudication of the water dispute: negotiations, the 
Central Government shall, within a period ot

Provided that any dispute settled by a Tribunal before the 
commencement of the Inter- State Water Disputes (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year> 
shall not be re- opened.";


</section>

<section><tid>1353539</tid>
<number>b</number>for sub- section (3), the following sub- section shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (3) The Central Government may, in consultation with the Tribunal, 
appoint two or more persons as assessors to advise the Tribunal in the 
proceedings before it.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>237625</tid>
<number> 4</number> Amendment of section 5.- In section 5 of the principal Act, for 
sub- sections (2) and (3), the following sub- sections shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (2) The Tribunal shall investigate the matters referred to it and 
forward to the Central Government a report setting out the facts as 
found by it and giving its decision on the matters referred to it 
within a period of three years:

Provided that if the decision cannot be given for unavoidable reasons, 
within a period of three years, the Central Government may extend the 
period for a further period not exceeding two years.

<section><tid>865436</tid>
<number>3</number>If, upon consideration of the decision of the Tribunal, the 
Central Government or any State Government is of opinion that anything 
therein contained requires explanation or that guidance is needed upon 
any point not originally referred to the Tribuna, the Central 
Government or the State Government, as the case may be, within three 
months from the date of the decision, again refer the matter to the 
Tribunal for further consideration, and on such reference, the 
Tribunal may forward to the Central Gove nment a further report within 
one year from the date of such reference giving such explanation or 
guidance as it deems fit and in such a case, the decision of the 
Tribunal shall be deemed to be modified accordingly:
Provided that the period of one year within which the Tribunal may 
forward its report to the Central Government may be extended by the 
Central Government, for such further period as it considers 
necessary.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>542141</tid>
<number> 5</number> Amendment of section 6.- Section 6 of the principal Act shall be 
renumbered as sub- section
<section><tid>58445</tid>
<number>1</number>thereof and after sub- section (1) as so  
renumbered, the following sub- section shall be inserted, namely:-
" (2) The decision of the Tribunal, after its publication in the 
Official Gazette by the Central Government under sub- section (1), 
shall have the same force as an order or decree of the Supreme 
Court.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>727930</tid>
<number>6</number>Amendment of section 9.- In section 9 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, after clause (b), the following clause shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (ba) requisitioning of any data, as may be required by it;".



</article>



<article><tid>1412257</tid>
<number> 7</number> Insertion of new section 9A.- After section 9 of the principal Act, 
the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 9A. Maintenance of data bank and information.- (1) The Central 
Government shall maintain a data bank and information system at the 
national level for each river basin which shall include data regarding 
water resources, land, agriculture, and matters rel ting thereto, as 
the Central Government may prescribe from time to time. The State 
Government shall supply the data to the Central Government or to an 
agency appointed by the Central Government for the purpose, as and 
when required.

<section><tid>1706109</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government shall have powers to verify the data 
supplied by the State Government, and appoint any person or persons 
for the purpose and take such measures as it may consider necessary. 
The person or persons so appointed shall have the pow rs to summon 
such records and information from the concerned State Government as 
are considered necessary to discharge their functions under this 
section.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>639078</tid>
<number>8</number>Amendment of section 13.- In section 13 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (2), for clause (e), the following clause shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (e) the terms and conditions of service of officers and assessors of 
the Tribunal;".

K. N. CHATURVEDI, 
Addl. Secy. to the Govt. of India.


</article>



 </act>