<act><tid>1717201</tid>
<title>THE NATIONAL ENVIRONMENT APPELLATE AUTHORITYACT, <year>1997</year></title>

ACT NO. 22 OF <year>1997</year>
[ 26th March, <year>1997</year>.]

Appellate Authority to hear appeals with respect to restriction of 
areas in which any industries, operations or processes or class of 
industries, operations or processes shall not be carried out or shall 
be carried out subject to certain safeguards under the Environment 
 (Protection) Act, <year>1986</year> and for matters connected thereto.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- eighth Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I 
PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>597265</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>861337</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
National Environment Appellate Authority Act, <year>1997</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1133746</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 30th day of 
January, <year>1997</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>698537</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-
<section><tid>1057165</tid>
<number>a</number>" Act" means the Environment (Protection) Act, <year>1986</year> (29 of <year>1986</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1124191</tid>
<number>b</number>" Authority" means the National Environment Appellate Authority 
established under sub- section (1) of section 3;

</section>

<section><tid>1537242</tid>
<number>c</number>" Chairperson" means the Chairperson of the Authority;

</section>

<section><tid>1026438</tid>
<number>d</number>" Member" means a Member of the Authority;

</section>

<section><tid>1614900</tid>
<number>e</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1480136</tid>
<number>f</number>" Vice- Chairperson" means the Vice- Chairperson of the Authority.
CHAP

ESTABLISHMENT OF AUTHORITY

CHAPTER II 
ESTABLISHMENT OF AUTHORITY




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1174228</tid>
<number> 3</number> Establishment of Authority.-
<section><tid>1442422</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government shall, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, establish a body to be known as 
the National Environment Appellate Authority to exercise the powers 
conferred upon, and to perform the functions assigned to, it under 
this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1412757</tid>
<number>2</number>The head office of the Authority shall be at Delhi.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>945080</tid>
<number>4</number>Composition of Authority.- The Authority shall consist of a 
Chairperson, a Vice- Chairperson and such other Members not exceeding 
three, as the Central Government may deem fit.


</article>



<article><tid>431599</tid>
<number> 5</number> Qualifications for appointments as Chairperson, Vice- Chairperson 
or Member.-
<section><tid>1275421</tid>
<number>1</number>A person shall not be qualified for appointment as a  
Chairperson unless he has been-

<subsection><tid>1632116</tid>
<number>a</number>a Judge of the Supreme Court; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1911401</tid>
<number>b</number>the chief Justice of a High Court.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1186775</tid>
<number>2</number>A person shall not be qualified for appointment as a Vice- 
Chairperson unless he has-

<subsection><tid>91466</tid>
<number>a</number>for at least two years hel d the post of a Secretary to the 
Government of India or any other post under the Central or State 
Government carrying a scale of pay which is not less than that of a 
Secretary to the Government of India; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1051285</tid>
<number>b</number>expertise or experience in administrative, legal, managerial or 
technical aspects of problems relating to environment.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1044399</tid>
<number>3</number>A person shall not be qualified for appointment as a Member unless 
he has professional knowledge or practical experience in the areas 
pertaining to conservation, environmental management, law or planning 
and development.

</section>

<section><tid>1926694</tid>
<number>4</number>The Chairperson, the Vice- Chairperson and the Members shall 
be appointed by the President.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1299306</tid>
<number> 6</number> Vice- Chairperson to act as Chairperson or to discharge his 
functions in certain circumstances.-
<section><tid>1731048</tid>
<number>1</number>In the event of the occurrence  
of any vacancy in the office of the Chairperson by reason of his 
death, resignation or otherw ise, the Vice- Chairperson shall act as 
the chairperson until the date on which a new Chairperson appointed in 
accordance with the provisions of this Act to fill such vacancy enters 
upon his office.

</section>

<section><tid>1790282</tid>
<number>2</number>When the Chairperson is unable to discharge his functions owing to 
absence, illness or any other cause, the Vice- Chairperson or, as the 
case may, be such one of the Members as the Central government may, by 
notification, authorise in this behalf, shall discharge the functions 
of the Chairperson until the date on which the chairperson resumes his 
duties.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1971446</tid>
<number> 7</number> Term of office.- The Chairperson, the Vice- Chairperson or a Member 
shall hold office as such for a term of three years from the date on 
which he enters upon his office, but shall be eligible for re- appoint 
for another term of three years:
Provided that no Chairperson, Vice- Chairperson or Member shall hold 
office as such after he has attained,-

<section><tid>35520</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of the Chairperson, the age of seventy years; and

</section>

<section><tid>1360467</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of the Vice- Chairperson or a Member, the age of 
sixty- five years.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1268047</tid>
<number> 8</number> Resignation and removal.-
<section><tid>522231</tid>
<number>1</number>The Chairperson, the Vice- Chairperson  
or a Member may, by notice in writing under his hand addressed to the 
President, resign his office:
Provided that the Chairperson, the Vice- Chairperson or shall, unless 
he is permitted by the President to relinquish his office sooner, 
continue to hold office until the expiry of three months from the date 
of receipt of such notice or until a person duly appointed as his 
successor enters upon his office or until the expiry of his term 
of office whichever is the earliest.


</section>

<section><tid>1504373</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chairperson, the Vice- Chairperson or a Member shall not be 
removed from his office except by an order made by the President on 
the ground of proved misbehaviour or incapacity after an inquiry made 
by a Judge of the Supreme Court in which such Chairperson, the Vice- 
Chairperson or a Member had been informed of the charges against him 
and given a reasonable opportunity of being heard in respect of those 
charges.

</section>

<section><tid>1574545</tid>
<number>3</number>The President may suspend from office the Chairperson, the 
Vice- Chairperson or a Member in respect of whom a reference has been 
made to the Supreme Court under sub- section (2) until the President 
has passed orders on receipt of the report of the Supreme Court on 
such reference.

</section>

<section><tid>1593101</tid>
<number>4</number>The Central Government may, by rules, regulate the procedure for 
the investigation of misbehaviour or incapacity of the Chairperson, 
the Vice- Chairperson or a Member referred to in sub- section (2).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1643367</tid>
<number>9</number>Salaries and allowances and other terms and conditions of service 
of Chairperson, Vice- Chairperson and Members.- The salaries and 
allowances payable to, and the other terms and conditions of service 
 (including pension, gratuity and other retirement benefits) of, the 
Chairperson, the Vice- Chairperson and the Members shall be such as may 
be prescribed by the Central Government.


</article>



<article><tid>1445539</tid>
<number>10</number>Vacancy in Authority not to invalidate acts or proceedings.- No 
act or proceeding of the Authority shall be questioned or be invalid 
merely on the ground of existence of any vacancy or defect in the 
establishment of the Authority.
CHAP

JURISDICTION AND POWERS OF AUTHORITY

CHAPTER III 
JURISDICTION AND POWERS OF AUTHORITY



</article>



<article><tid>342728</tid>
<number> 11</number> Appeals to Authority.-
<section><tid>1161817</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person aggrieved by an order  
granting environmental clearance in the areas in which any industries, 
operations or processes or class of industries, operations and 
processes shall not be carried out or shall be carried out subject to 
certain safeguards may, within thirty days from the date of such 
order, prefer an appeal to the Authority in such form as may be 
prescribed:
Provided that the Authority may entertain any appeal after the expiry 
of the said period of thirty days but not after ninety days from the 
date aforesaid if it is satisfied that the appellant was prevented by 
sufficient cause from filing the appeal in time.


</section>

<section><tid>105323</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes of sub- section (1)," person" means-

<subsection><tid>467747</tid>
<number>a</number>any person who is likely to be affected by the grant of 
environmental clearance;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>995091</tid>
<number>b</number>any person who owns or has control over the project with respect 
to which an application has been submitted for environmental 
clearance;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1258813</tid>
<number>c</number>any association of persons (whether incorporated or not) likely to 
be affected by such order and functioning in the field of environment;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>741869</tid>
<number>d</number>the Central Government, where the environmental clearance is 
granted by the State Government and the State Government, where the 
environmental clearance is granted by the Central Government; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>543090</tid>
<number>e</number>any local authority, any part of whose local limits is within the 
neighbourhood of the area wherein the project is proposed to be 
located.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1463798</tid>
<number>3</number>On receipt of an appeal preferred sub- section (1), the Authority 
shall, after giving the appellant an opportunity of being heard, pass 
such orders, as it thinks fit.

</section>

<section><tid>830251</tid>
<number>4</number>The Authority shall dispose of the appeal within ninety days from 
the date of filing the appeal:
Provided that the Authority may for reasons to be recorded in writing, 
dispose of appeal within a further period of thirty days.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1996106</tid>
<number> 12</number> Procedure and powers of Authority.-
<section><tid>525396</tid>
<number>1</number>The Authority shall not be  
bound by the procedure laid down in the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> 
 (5 of <year>1908</year>), but shall be guided by the principles of natural justice 
and subject to the other provisions of this Act, and of any rules made 
by the Central Government, the Authority shall have power to regulate 
its own procedure including the fixing of places and time of its 
inquiry and deciding whether to sit in public or in private.

</section>

<section><tid>589396</tid>
<number>2</number>The Authority shall have, for the purposes of discharging its 
functions under this Act, the same powers as are vested in a civil 
court under the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>), while 
trying a suit, in respect of the following matters namely:-

<subsection><tid>1452530</tid>
<number>a</number>summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person and examining 
him on oath;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>253621</tid>
<number>b</number>requiring the discovery and production of documents;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1475624</tid>
<number>c</number>receiving evidence on affidavits;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1944758</tid>
<number>d</number>subject to the provisions of sections 123 and 124 of the Indian 
Evidence Act, <year>1872</year> (1 of <year>1872</year>) requisitioning any public record or 
document or copy of such record or document from any office;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1901903</tid>
<number>e</number>issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses or documents;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>361964</tid>
<number>f</number>reviewing its decisions;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1637333</tid>
<number>g</number>dismissing a representation for default or deciding it, ex parte;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>123710</tid>
<number>h</number>setting aside any order of dismissal of anyrepresentation for 
default or any order passed by it ex parte; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1629346</tid>
<number>i</number>any other matter which is required to be, or may be, prescribed by 
the Central Government.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1886472</tid>
<number>13</number>Financial and administrative powers of Chairperson.- The 
Chairperson shall exercise such financial and administrative powers as 
may be vested in him under the rules:
Provided that the Chairperson shall have authority to such of his 
financial and administrative powers as he may think fit to the 
Vice- Chairperson or any other officer subject to the condition that 
the Vice- Chairperson or such other officer shall, while exercising 
such delegated powers, continue to act under the direction, control 
and supervision of the Chairperson.



</article>



<article><tid>1722077</tid>
<number> 14</number> Staff of Authority.-
<section><tid>1571715</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government shall determine  
the nature and categories of the officers and other employees required 
to assist the Authority in the discharge of its functions and provided 
the Authority with such officers and other employees as it may think 
fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1232256</tid>
<number>2</number>The officers and other employees of the Authority shall discharge 
their functions under the general superintendence of the Chairperson.

</section>

<section><tid>54223</tid>
<number>3</number>The salaries and allowances and conditions of service of the 
officers and other employees shall be such as may be prescribed.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER IV 
MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>831892</tid>
<number>15</number>Bar of jurisdiction.- With effect from the date of establishment 
of the Authority, no civil court or other authority shall have 
jurisdiction to entertain any appeal in respect of any matter with 
which the Authority is so empowered by or under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1315267</tid>
<number>16</number>Proceedings before the Authority to be judicial proceedings. All 
proceedings before the Authority shall be deemed to be judicial 
proceedings within the meaning of sections 193, 219 and 228 of the 
Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>303529</tid>
<number>17</number>Members and staff of Authority to be public servants.- The 
Chairperson, the Vice- Chairperson and the Members and the officers and 
other employees of the Authority shall be deemed to be public servants 
within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of  
  <year>1860</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>292929</tid>
<number>18</number>Protection of action taken in good faith.- No suit, prosecution or 
other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central Government or 
against the Chairperson, the Vice- Chairperson or a Member of the 
Authority or any other person authorised by the Chairperson, the 
Vice- Chairperson or a Member for anything which is in good faith done 
or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any rule or order 
made thereunder.


</article>



<article><tid>149469</tid>
<number>19</number>Penalty for failure to comply with orders of Authority.- Whoever 
fails to comply with any order made by the Authority, he shall be 
punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to seven 
years, or with fine which may extend to one lakh rupees, or with both.


</article>



<article><tid>1946326</tid>
<number> 20</number> Offences by companies.-
<section><tid>1256538</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any offence under this Act has  
been committed by company, every person who, at the time of the 
offence was committed, was directly in charge of, and was responsible 
to, the company for the conduct of the business of the company, as 
well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and 
shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render any 
such person liable to any punishment provided in this Act, if he 
proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or that he 
has exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such 
offence.


</section>

<section><tid>1068788</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where an 
offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is 
proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or 
connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any 
director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such 
director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to 
guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and 
punished accordingly.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,-


<subsection><tid>1435856</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm or other 
association of individuals; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1774188</tid>
<number>b</number>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner in the firm.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1110924</tid>
<number> 21</number> Power to remove difficulties.-
<section><tid>462254</tid>
<number>1</number>If any difficulty arises in  
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions, 
not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as appear to it to 
be necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty:
Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of the 
period of three years from the date on which this Act receives the 
assent of the President.


</section>

<section><tid>303895</tid>
<number>2</number>Every order made under this section shall, as soon as may be after 
it is made, be laid before each House of Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>456540</tid>
<number> 22</number> Power to make rules.-
<section><tid>1929307</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification, make rules for carrying out the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>629138</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>23252</tid>
<number>a</number>the procedure under sub- section (4) of section 8 for the 
investigation of misbehaviour or incapacity of the Chairperson, the 
Vice- Chairperson or a Member;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1903280</tid>
<number>b</number>the salaries and allowances payable to and the other terms and 
conditions of service of the Chairperson, the Vice- Chairperson and the 
Members under section 9;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1730295</tid>
<number>c</number>the form which an appeal shall contain under sub- section (1) of 
section 11;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1398280</tid>
<number>d</number>financial and administrative powers of the Chairperson under 
section 13;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1131048</tid>
<number>e</number>the salaries and allowances and conditions of service of the 
officers and other employees of the Authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1289167</tid>
<number>f</number>any other matter which is required to be, or may be, prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>463623</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made under this Act, shall be laid, as soon as may be 
after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in 
session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the 
expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be with prejudice to the validity 
of anything previously done under that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1049116</tid>
<number> 23</number> Repeal and saving.-
<section><tid>1824933</tid>
<number>1</number>The National Environment Appellate  
Authority Ordinance, <year>1997</year> (Ord. 12 of <year>1977</year>) is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>458291</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken 
under the said Ordinance, shall be deemed to have been done or taken 
under the corresponding provisions of this Act.


</section>

</article>



 </act>