<act> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—These 
may be called the Border Security Force (Ceremonials and Marks of Respect) 
Rules, 19891. 
They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official 
Gazette.
 
 



</article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  “Appendix” means Appendix to 
these rules;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  “armed party” means a party 
armed with swords, guns or rifles or bearing side arms;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  “Senior Officers” means the 
Director General, Additional Director General, Inspector General, Additional 
Inspector General, Deputy Inspector General and Additional Deputy Inspector 
General of the Border Security Force;
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  All other words and expressions 
used in these rules and defined in the Border Security Force Act, 1968 shall 
have the meaning respectively assigned to them in the Act.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> National Anthem.—Two 
versions of the National Anthem viz. the full version comprising the 
first stanza of the song ‘Jana Gana Mana’ (playing time approximately 52 
seconds) and a short version consisting of the first line of the same stanza 
(playing time approximately 20 seconds) shall be played on the following 
occasions, namely:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  Full version:
 <subsection>
             <number>i</number>  On all ceremonial 
occasions when the President pays a visit to the Border Security Force 
installation.
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>ii</number>  On all ceremonial 
occasions when the Governor or the Lieutenant Governor attends Ceremonial 
Parade within his State or his union territory, as the case may be.
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>iii</number>  At Republic Day and 
Independence Day Parades when the National Flag is unfurled.
 </subsection></section><section>
       <number>b</number>  Short version:
 
              On all other ceremonial 
occasions.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> National Salute.—The 
salute is given to the accompaniment of National Anthem. It is to be given to 
the President and to the Governors or the Lieutenant Governors within their 
(respective) States or the union territories, as the case may be.
</article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> General salute.—In 
all other cases, the general salute is given for which the band plays the 
prescribed tune.
</article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Courtesy call on 
Governors.—When 
the Governor of a State is officially in a Station, the Officers of the rank of 
Commandant and above, stationed and visiting that station, will pay a courtesy 
call on him.
</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>7</number> Courtesy call by Inspectors 
General/Deputy Inspectors General or the Chief Minister of the 
State.—On the 
occasion of their first visit to a State after assumption of charge, the 
Inspector General and Deputy Inspector General of the concerned Frontier/State 
shall call on the Chief Minister of the State. Such calls are not necessary 
during such officer’s subsequent visits to the State Capital, unless in the 
meantime, a new Chief Minister has assumed office.</article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> General.—The 
strength and composition of guard of Honour shall depend on the status of the 
personage and shall be laid down in accordance with orders issued from time to 
time in this regard by the Central Government. A Guard of Honour may be drawn 
from Border Security Force alone, or in conjunction with other Police Forces.
</article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Time of guard 
mounting.—No 
Guard of Honour shall be mounted between Retreat and Reveille. It shall also 
not be mounted during the period of a State Mourning.
</article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Composition and 
Strength.—The 
composition of the Guard of Honour of one hundred and fifty personnel shall 
consist of such ranks/files as specified in the Appendix ‘A’.
</article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Band/Pipes.—The 
Guard of Honour shall be accompanied by a band/pipes and drums.
</article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Entitlement and 
Occasions.—The 
personages entitled to Guard of Honour, Gun Salute and the occasions on which 
these shall be presented shall be such as are specified in the following 
appendices:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  Civilian 
VIPs                                                           —Appendix ‘B’
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  Military 
VIPs                                                           —Appendix ‘C’
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  VIPs or D.G. Security, or Force 
or Border
 
              Guards of the Foreign 
Countries                                 —Appendix ‘D’.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Layout of Guards of 
Honour.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Guard of Honour will be formed up:
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  in one division when the Guard 
of 50 rank and file is being provided by the Border Security Force as per 
Appendix ‘B’.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  in two equal divisions when 
being provided by two Police Forces or when 100 rank and file are being 
provided by the Border Security Force as per Appendix ‘F’.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  in three equal divisions when 
three Police Forces are participating or when 150 rank and file are being 
provided by the Border Security Force as per Appendix ‘G’.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Guard will be in 
two ranks with a distance of 4 paces between the front and rear ranks, and will 
be dressed at intervals of 24 inches. The distances between each division, 
shall be 3 paces. As far as possible, the Guard of Honour when formed up, will 
face the direction from which the personage for whom it is mounted, will 
approach. The Border Security Force Guards of Honour shall be sized and 
equalised in a Company.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Position of officers 
for the Border Security Force Guard.—The 
position of Officers, Subordinate Officers and Under Officers for the Border 
Security Force Guard of Honour shall be as follows:
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  the Commander shall be 8 paces 
in front of the centre of the front rank,
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  the next senior 
officer/subordinate officer shall be 2 paces in front of the second file from 
the right, the Junior Officer/Subordinate Officer shall be 2 paces in front of 
the second file from the left,
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  the next senior 
officer/subordinate officer shall be 2 paces in front of the second file from 
the right, the Junior Officer/Subordinate Officer shall be 2 paces in front of 
the second file from the left.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Position of Officers 
for Inter Force Guard.—The 
position of Officers, Subordinate Officers and Under Officers in an Inter 
Police Force Guard of Honour shall be as follows:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  The Commander shall be 8 paces 
in front of the centre of the Guard of Honour.
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  The Commander of the Central 
Division shall be in the centre of his division and 2 paces from the front 
rank. Right division Commanders shall be 2 paces in front of the second file 
from the right and left of the Division Commanders and 2 paces in front of the 
second file from the left.
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  The Senior Under Officers of the 
Force concerned shall be the right guide and the junior shall be the left guide 
of their respective divisions.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Position of band.—The 
band shall form up on the right rank in the line with the Guard at 7 paces from 
the Rights guide of the Guard. It shall be in Column in four files, with 2 
paces between each file. The Drum-Major shall be 2 paces in front of the front 
rank of the bank and the bandmaster shall be 3 paces in front of the 
Drum-Major.
</article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Saluting dais and 
flags.—The 
diagrammatic layout of the Guard of Honour shall be such as specified in 
Appendix ‘E’.
</article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Position of Orderly 
Officers.—There 
shall always be two officers (Orderly Officers) who shall stand on either side 
of the dais, 2 paces to the right and left of the front edge of it.
</article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Position of 
Conducting Officers.—The 
Conducting Officer from the Defence Services/Civil/Border Security 
Force/Central Police Organisation/State Police, who receives the VIP and 
conducts him to the saluting dais, shall, after conducting the VIP to the dais, 
position himself in the rear centre of the dais and 3 paces from the dais. The 
VIP alone will stand on the dais.
</article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Procedure for flying 
flag.—When 
flag(s) is(are) required to be flown in conjunction with a Guard of Honour (e.g. 
National Flag for the President, or our National Flag and the flag of the 
country of the visiting head of the State, viz President and Prime 
Minister) the following procedure shall be adopted:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  When only one flag is required 
to be flown, it shall be flown from a mast positioned at a suitable distance in 
the rear centre of the dais.
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  When our National Flag and a 
Foreign National flag are both required to be flown, they will be flown from 
separate masts of equal height positioned at a distance from and to the near of 
the dais. Both flags shall be of the same size, our National Flag being on the 
right hand side of the VIP as he faces the Guard of Honour.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Salutes.—When 
the VIP has mounted the dais and is in a position to receive the salute, the 
guard of honour shall give the salute (National/General as the case may be) 
with the band playing the appropriate tune. Orderly Officers shall not salute, 
when either the National or General Salute is given to the VIP.
</article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Inspection.—The 
procedure for inspection shall be as follows:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  The Guard Commander shall march 
forward and report to the VIP. The report shall be in Hindi as under:—
 <subsection>
             <number>i</number>  for the Inter-Forces 
Guards of Honour: “Unter dal samman Guard Nirikshan Ke liey hazir hai 
Shariman/Shrimati Ji.” 
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>ii</number>  for the Border Security 
Force Guard of Honour: (name of unit) “Samman Guard Nirikshan Ke liey hazir 
hai Shriman/Shrimati Ji.”
 </subsection></section><section>
       <number>b</number>  The Guard Commander taking his 
position on the VIP’s left, shall conduct him to the end. On reaching the right 
hand man of the band, the Guard Commander shall move to the VIP’s right and in 
line with him. He shall walk and not do the slow march.
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  The orderly officer shall not 
precede the VIP during the inspection except in the case of the President of 
India. They shall, on such occasion, do the slow march during the inspection.
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  The VIP shall inspect the band, 
passing in front of the Drum-Major. The band shall not turn their head and eye 
towards the VIP during the inspection of the band but shall look straight to 
the front.
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number>  As soon as the VIP passes the 
left hand man of the band, the Bandmaster shall turn about and get the band 
ready and start playing, taking the time from the first beet of the drum, every 
officer and men of the guard will also move their heads and eyes towards the 
VIP and will look at the VIP. As the VIP moves on, the Officers and men will 
also move their heads and eyes looking at him all the time. If the VIP stops 
during inspection, the movement of heads shall also stop.
 </section><section>
        <number>f</number>  The band shall stop playing as 
soon as the VIP has finished the inspection and the Guard, taking the time from 
the last note of the music, shall turn their heads and eyes to the front.
 </section><section>
       <number>g</number>  Only the front rank of the Guard 
shall be inspected. The VIP will move in front of the officers, i.e. he 
will inspect the guard from a distance of 3 or 4 paces from the front rank.
 </section><section>
       <number>h</number>  The VIP shall be conducted by 
the Guard Commander towards the conducting officer, who shall have moved from 
his position behind the dais to a new position suitable to escort the VIP for 
the inspection. When the VIP has been received by conducting officer, the Guard 
Commander shall salute the VIP. The Guard Commander must be prepared to shake 
hand with the VIP, if the VIP so desires.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Marching off the 
guard.—The 
Guard Commander shall return to his post, and after the VIP has proceeded some 
distance away from the Guard of Honour he may then stand the Guard at Ease (Vishram). 
The guard shall, however, not march off or ‘Stand Easy’ (Aram 
se) until the VIP for whom it is mounted, has left the place of reception.
</article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>24</number> Reduction in 
strength.—When 
any local circumstances preclude the provisions of the Guard of Honour of 
required strength, the number may be reduced, subject to the condition that any 
diminution in number shall not affect the honour to which personage is 
entitled.
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  The Unit commander should not 
move with the VIP at the time of inspection of Guard of Honour by the VIP.
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  Guard of Honour should only be 
arranged with prior approval of Senior Headquarters.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Forms of guard.—There 
are two forms of Guards, the purposes and functions of which are quite 
different. These are Ceremonial Guards and Technical Guards.
</article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Selection of form of 
guard.—Having 
regard to the functions to be performed, the form of guard which is to be 
mounted will be at the discretion of the Unit or Detachment Commanders, as the 
case may be.
</article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Ceremonial Guards.—The 
Ceremonial Guards shall be mounted for one of the following purposes:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  To exercise troops in ceremonial 
drill and to instil in them in highest standards of smartness, cleanliness, 
discipline and arms drill so that they have the highest sense of pride in 
Force.
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  To pay compliments, to high 
ranking officers, or other distinguished persons, between reveille and retreat.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Time for mounting 
ceremonial guard.—
<section><number>a</number> 
A ceremonial guard shall be mounted only between reveille and retreat. It shall 
not be given any form of protective task other than the security of its own 
arms, equipment and the treasure chest.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> On conclusion of its 
ceremonial functions, or at retreat, a ceremonial guard may take over the 
duties of a tactical guard immediately and vice-versa.
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> A ceremonial guard is 
to be considered at all times the symbol of pride and efficiency of the Unit.
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> Its drill, smartness, 
and turn out shall be of the highest standard. When turned out it shall fall in 
at attention, and as such no cautionary words of command are necessary.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>29</number> Dress for Ceremonial 
guard.—The 
dress for the Ceremonial Guard both at Quarter Guard and at other places will 
be as per pattern laid down by the Inspector General contained in FHQ Circular 
No. 2/4/68-P/BSF dated 31 January, 1969 and such other instructions as may be 
issued from time to time by the Director General.
</article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>30</number> Procedure for fall in 
of guard.—Ceremonial 
Guards of strength under five shall fall in, in single line and guards of 
strength five to nine will fall in, in two ranks as specified in the Appendix 
‘H’. For guard mounting turning out of inspection, relieving Ceremonial Guards, 
posting and relieving of sentries and compliments paid by guards/sentries, “the 
Border Security Force Drill Pamphlet 1973” and such other pamphlets as may be 
issued from time to time, will be referred.
</article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>31</number> Object of ceremonial 
parades.—The 
objects of Ceremonial Drill are to promote ‘Esprit-de-corps’ and by 
attaining a high standard of steadiness and cohesion in the parade ground to 
assist in the development of the normal qualities which are essential for 
sources in field operations.
</article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>32</number> Rehearsal.—These 
objects will be attained only by careful preparation and exact execution on all 
ceremonial occasions. To this end practice and rehearsal shall be held at all 
levels, but units shall not carry out any form of ceremonials other than 
covered under these rules.
</article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>33</number> Procedure.—
<section><number>a</number> 
This Chapter deals with the Drill formations procedure applicable to normal 
ceremonial occasion and provides details of the procedure upto a Battalion 
level. These could easily be adopted for lower formations upto a Company level.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> Officers are expected 
to interpret these instructions reasonably and intelligently, bearing in mind 
that slight alterations may be made to suit the personnel, ground and other 
exceptional circumstances.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>34</number> Review and 
Inspections.—Review 
and Inspections will follow generally, the procedure laid down in the Chapter 
XIII of the Drill Pamphlet 1973 as modified from time to time.
</article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>35</number> Arrival time of 
officers senior to parade commander.—Officers 
who are senior to the officer commanding the parade, when attending such a 
parade, should arrive at the parade ground after the Commander has taken the 
salute and not before. (Time of arrival should therefore be shown in programme).
</article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>36</number> Saluting at the time 
of National Salute.—When 
the National Salute is given to the personage taking the parade all officers 
including spectators, shall salute at the first note of “Jana Gana Mana” and 
shall bring down their hands as the last bar ends. The personage for whom the 
salute is given alone will acknowledge the “Present Arm”.
</article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>37</number> Band Tunes.—The 
band must always play the tune appropriate to the type of salute which may be 
given, viz:—
 
     National 
Salute                            ‘Jana Gana Mana’
 
     General 
Salute                             ‘General Salute’.
</article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>38</number> Forms of parade.—The 
following shall be the procedure of parade:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  Troops drawn up ready for 
inspection.
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  Parade Commander arrives, is 
given the appropriate salute/compliments and takes over the parade. The 
officers of the rank of Additional Deputy Inspector General and above will be 
entitled to a General Salute by troops under his command.
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  The reviewing or Inspecting 
Officer arrives and is given due honours.
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  The Parade Commander then moves 
forward reports to the Inspecting Officer and accompanies him on his 
inspection.
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number>  After the inspection the 
Inspecting Officer returns to the saluting base and the Parade Commander 
returns to his position in front of the troops.
 </section><section>
        <number>f</number>  The troops form map, march past 
and disperse.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>39</number> Formation for 
inspection.—The 
formation for inspection may be in line, if space permits, otherwise in column. 
It may sometimes be best to have dismounted troops in line mechanised 
units/animal units in the close column.
</article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>40</number> Points for special 
attention.—When 
the inspection is not on foot, the Parade Commander will stand in the same 
vehicle (Jeep) behind the Inspecting Officer, suitable supports will be 
provided.
</article> 
 
The Border Security force 
(Ceremonials And  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>41</number> Special arrangements 
when the inspection is on foot.—
<section><number>a</number> 
The Orderly Officer will accompany the Inspecting Officer as given in rule 22. 
In order to ensure that the party moves off in the correct order and relative 
position, the Parade Commander, when reporting to the Inspecting Officer, must 
come right upto him. The staff can then position themselves correctly and the 
whole party moves off smoothly. (If the Inspecting Officer goes forward to meet 
the Parade Commander, the staff get out of position).
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> The band or bands 
shall begin to play for the inspection when the Inspecting Officer arrives 
opposite right hand man of the front rank.
</section></article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>42</number> Participation by other 
Government Forces.—The question of participation 
in the parade of detachments of other forces should always be considered where 
these are available and it should be arranged wherever 
possible.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>43</number> General 
arrangements.—In order to avoid confusion all 
arrangements in connection with an inspection or review of a large body of 
troops, necessitate careful preparation under the following 
headings:—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  
Arrangements before the ceremony.
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  
Arrangements for the ceremony.
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  
Arrangements for dispersal.
 </section><section>       <number>d</number>  
Arrangements for spectators.</section></article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>44</number> Arrangements before the 
ceremony.—These 
should normally include instructions on the following:—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  The 
formation in which units are to form up on the inspection line, including any 
special directions regarding distance and intervals.
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  The 
method by which units are to adjust their dressing on the inspection line, 
including details as to markers.
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  The 
massing of bands both the inspection and to the march past.
 </section><section>       <number>d</number>  When 
the bands are to play.
 </section><section>       <number>e</number>  
General administrative arrangement, such matters as the preparation of the 
ground, representatives of the press, traffic control.</section></article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>45</number> Arrangement for the 
ceremony.—These 
should include—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  An 
outline of various phases of the ceremonies to be executed.
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  The 
method of signalling words of command and the exact procedure to be adopted on 
each signal. Loud speakers are the best means, but they must be reliable and be 
suitably sited. An alternative method e.g. visual signalling must be laid 
down to be used in the event of loud speaker breaking down or the words of 
command not reaching the troops and the audience particularly those in the 
rear.
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  Any 
special instructions regarding distance and intervals.
 </section><section>       <number>d</number>  Any 
special instructions that may be necessary relating to the actions of the bands 
and drums.
 </section><section>       <number>e</number>  The 
action to be taken by the various units and formations after the march 
past.
 </section><section>        
<number>f</number>  The method of notifying a cancellation of the parade e.g. who 
takes the decision, who informs and who are informed, including the means of 
informing.
 </section><section>       <number>g</number>  As 
far as possible Mechanised units should march past on a different axis than 
those on foot. Former’s axis should be parallel to the latter’s but further away 
from saluting base.
 </section><section>       <number>h</number>  
Mechanised units which march past at greater speed behind units on foot, should 
be allowed to regulate their distances so that they can pass the saluting point 
at the correct speed.
 </section><section>        
<number>i</number>  After advancing in review order, an interval should be allowed for 
engines of mechanical vehicles to be switched off, so as to allow units on the 
ranks to hear the commands given.</section></article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>46</number> Arrangements for 
dispersal.—Special attention must be paid 
to “Traffic Control” which must be well co-ordinated. Spectators should be asked 
to remain in their places till the troops are cleared of the parade 
ground.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>47</number> Cordoning of 
route.—In 
addition, it is suggested that cordoning of the route by which the troops march 
off or the parade remaining at ease after the march past till the crowd has 
dispersed will assist in Traffic control.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>48</number> Arrangements for 
spectators.—
<section><number>a</number> 
It is essential that adequate arrangements are made for officials of all forces 
and for the general public. There should be the minimum of seats reserved by 
name and they should be restricted to the highest officials and most prominent 
local notables. The remainder of the officials of the civil services and armed 
forces officers and people of similar status in non-official life, should be 
allotted tickets to general enclosures for them all. They should not be 
segregated from each other.
 </section><section><number>b</number> Proper arrangements must 
also be made for the general public.
 </section><section><number>c</number> The issue of invitations to 
those given either individual reserved seats or access to seats in reserved 
enclosures, should be done in good time and assistance of local civil officials 
should be sought so that there are no omissions.</section></article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>49</number> Programmes.—It is useful to issue a 
programme of the parade, with notes for spectators as to when they stand up, 
salute, take off their hats, so on. There should also be loud speakers on all 
large parades commenting on the parade for the benefit of the spectators, 
particularly the general public who do not have copy of the 
programme.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>50</number> Arrangement.—There is a tendency in units to 
have unnecessary ostentation at Ceremonial Parades/functions specially when such 
parades/functions are in connection with the visit of the VIPs. All arrangements 
for parade functions will be simple and appropriate, befitting to the occasion 
</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>51</number> Ceremonial—“Teen Jai”.—Whenever it is desired to give 
“Teen Jai” on ceremonial parades it will take the form of a personal greeting to 
the individual concerned. No form of improvised “National Cry” will be 
used.
 “Teen Jai” may be given on 
ceremonial parades to the President, Vice President the Prime Minister and the 
Home Minister in the following manner:
 Commander—Parade
 Name of the personage………ki Jai 
(Repeated 3 times).</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>52</number> Words of command and drill 
procedure.—For 
the words of command and drill procedure, “The Border Security Force Drill 
Pamphlet, 1973” and such other pamphlets, as may be issued from time to time, 
shall be referred to.
 Note: 

<section><number>a</number> Around the dais only people in uniform shall be present. Broadcasters or 
radio recorders shall have their tables at some distance behind the dais. 
Microphones when brought up to the person taking the salute shall be brought by 
a person in uniform.
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  
While the parade is on, persons in plain clothes shall not be permitted to 
wander about in front of spectators. The Press and Photographers shall be 
properly controlled by an officer.</section></article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>53</number> Commemoration 
parade.—A 
Commemoration Parade is done annually by the Border Security Force and all other 
Police Organisations for paying Tributes to the Martyrs, which should be 
attended to the maximum number of personnel.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>54</number> Procedure.—The procedure for holding 
Border Security Force Commemoration Parade shall be as follows:—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  The 
parade shall fall in a hollow square facing the saluting base/memorials wherever 
exists.
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  On 
arrival of the Senior Officers/VIP, the parade will give present arms, after 
which the parade will be brought to “Vishram.”
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  The 
Senior Officer shall then read out the names of those who have laid down their 
lives/killed in action during the last twelve months.
 </section><section>       <number>d</number>  
After the names of the martyrs have been read out, the Parade Commander shall 
bring the parade to ‘Savdhan’, ‘Salami Shastra’ and ‘Shok Shastra’.
 </section><section>       <number>e</number>  Then 
the Buglers shall sound ‘Last Post’. All officers and Subordinate Officers shall 
salute. On completion of the Last Post all officers and Subordinate Officers 
bring down their hands and all those taking part in the parade bow down their 
heads.
 </section><section>        
<number>f</number>  On completion of two minutes’ silence the parade commander brings the 
parade to alert by saying “Parade”—All raise their heads.
 </section><section>       <number>g</number>  The 
Parade Commander then orders ‘Salami Shastra’ and the Buglers sound ‘Rouse’. All 
officers and Subordinate Officers salute.
 </section><section>       <number>h</number>  On 
completion of the Rouse, the parade commander orders ‘Bazu Shastra 
Vishram’.
 </section><section>        
<number>i</number>  The parade shall be brought to ‘Savdhan’ and the Senior Officer shall 
leave. The parade then is marched off.
 Note:—
 <subsection>        
<number>i</number>  Spectators shall come to attention when the highest ranking officer 
arrives and Parade Commander orders ‘Parade Savdhan.’
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>ii</number>  On Command.—‘Vishram’ they stand-at-ease.
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number>  
When the parade is in Mourning Arm all spectators shall come to attention. 
Officers and subordinate officers shall salute and other shall remain standing 
in attention position.</subsection></section></article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>55</number> BSF 
funerals.—The 
Border Security Force funerals shall be accorded on the death of serving members 
of the Forces as under:—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  
While on duty irrespective of the place and circumstances of death.
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  
While not on duty, only in the event of death occurring in a Station where 
troops are available and subject to the discretion of local Border Security 
Force Commander.</section></article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>56</number> BSF funerals in case of 
recruits, boys, non-combatant personnel.—The recruits, boys and 
non-combatant personnel will not be entitled to Border Security Force 
Funerals.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>57</number> Escorts.—Escorts will be provided on the 
occasion of the Border Security Force funerals at the scale mentioned below 
subject to the following conditions:—
 <section>  <number>1</number> (a)  the entitlement will be only 
for paid ranks;
 <subsection>       <number>b</number>  the 
prescribed scale of escorts are in ceilings, not compulsory 
requirement;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  the 
various scales of escorts will be inclusive of all personnel e.g. pall 
bearers, carriers, relatives and friends, bandsmen, buglers, drummers, religious 
teachers, firing party escort and guards;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  the 
escort shall not in any circumstances be provided by movement of troops from 
outstation,
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number>  
subject to (d) above, only locally available Force transport is to be used in 
the minimum extent necessary to meet the requirement of escorts for Border 
Security Force funerals as provided in this para; and
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>f</number>  the next of kin or near relatives of the deceased are authorised to 
use Border Security Force transport provided for the escort at a Border Security 
Force funeral. No separate transport will, however, be provided to them 
exclusively for this purpose.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Scale of Escorts.—The 
Director-General/Additional 
 Director-General                                                          
—600
 Inspector-General/Additional 
Inspector 
General                 
—400
 Inspector 
General/Commandants
 (Selection Grade) 
Commandants                                     
—250
 Deputy 
Commandants                                                  
—200
 Assistant 
Commandants                                                
—150
 Subordinate 
Officers                                                    
—100
 All other 
ranks/grades                                                  
—20</section></article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>58</number> Transport.—In addition to the transport 
authorised in rule 57 two Border Security Force vehicles will be provided at 
Government cost for the funeral of Force personnel entitled to Border Security 
Force funerals as under:—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  one 
service vehicle for traction of gun carriage carrying the dead body; 
and
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  one 
vehicle for miscellaneous duties connected with the funeral such as making 
arrangements for cremation or burial of the dead body.</section></article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>59</number> Border Security Force 
funeral to retired Force personnel.—The retired Force personnel are 
not entitled to a Security Force Funeral with the exception of a retired 
Director General, Border Security Force. In such cases, the scale and the 
conditions prescribed for serving officers will apply.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>60</number> Detailed 
procedure.—The 
detailed instructions on procedure and drills shall be followed as in the 
Chapter XV of the Border Security Force Drill Pamphlet, 1973 and such other 
pamphlet as may be published from time to time by the 
Director-General.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>61</number> General.—An attestation is a ceremony at 
which recruits take oath of allegiance in accordance with tenets of the 
individuals’s religion, in the following manner:—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  
before the ceremony, all recruits to be attested shall be instructed in the 
meaning and importance of the occasion both by religious teachers and sub-unit 
Commanders;
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  
whatever the detailed procedure, it must be worthy of an occasion which should 
be recollected by the newly attested men through their service;
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  the 
recruits to be attested will be formed up in a prominent position;
 </section><section>       <number>d</number>  the 
religious teachers with their holy books shall be present on the 
parade;
 </section><section>       <number>e</number>  the 
rifle or other personal armament of recruit to be attested shall be so placed to 
keep his both hands free;
 </section><section>        
<number>f</number>  the oath (all rank being at attestation) shall be administered by the 
religious teachers in suitable groups of recruits who shall place their hands on 
the holy book and each shall repeat the oath.</section></article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>62</number> Address by officer taking 
salute.—The 
officer taking salute shall address the newly attested soldiers who shall then 
march past in front of the parade to symbolise their entering to ranks as 
trained Constables.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>63</number> Departure of religious 
teachers.—After 
the completion of the attestation ceremony the religious teachers with their 
books shall leave the parade.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>64</number> Conclusion.—The parade will be 
concluded.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>66</number> Salute and National 
Anthem.—
<section><number>a</number> 
Whenever the National Anthem is played, all ranks in the Border Security Force 
in uniform not under the orders of parade Commander shall salute.
 </section><section><number>b</number> Officers in attendance on 
the President or the personal staff of Governor (when such Governor of a State 
represent the President on official occasions) will not salute when the National 
Anthem is played for the National Salute but will stand to attention. The 
exception to the above is on the occasions of unfurling of the national flag on 
the Republic Day and Independence Day when the National Anthem is played on the 
presentation of arms to the National Flag. All officers including officers in 
attendance on the personage mentioned above shall salute.
 </section><section><number>c</number> Except on the Independence 
Day and Republic Day, on a parade, after the National Salute has been given the 
Commander of the unit forming the parade shall be regarded as in attendance and 
shall take his position in rear of the President/Officer taking the 
salute.
 </section><section><number>d</number> During the presentation of a 
Guard of Honour, (AIDS De-CORPS) shall not salute, when either the 
National or General Salute in played.</section></article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>67</number> Compliments to officers in 
service of any other country.—The compliments directed in 
these regulations shall also be paid to officers in the service of the 
Government, of any country formally recognised by the Central Government, 
according to their respective ranks.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>68</number> Two minutes’ 
silence-commemoration of particular day/event.—A two minutes’ silence shall be 
observed at 11 a.m. on the 30th January every year in the memory of those who 
laid down their lives in the struggle for freedom of the country. The procedure 
for the observance of two minutes’ silence shall be notified by the local 
authorities. A commemoration of any other particular day/event shall be observed 
only under orders of the Central Government and according to the procedure 
prescribed in such orders.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>69</number> Salute to 
funeral.—The 
officers, Subordinate Officers and other ranks passing a Military, Navy, Air 
Force, Border Security Force and other Armed Forces and Civil funeral shall 
salute the body.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>70</number> Compliment by armed parties 
while marching.—The armed parties while paying 
compliments on the march, shall be cautioned and shall “Baggal Shaster” and the command “Eyes 
right or left” shall be given.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>71</number> Returning of salute by 
officer commanding.—An officer commanding of an 
armed or an unarmed party shall return the salute with the right hand as he 
gives the command “Eyes right (or Left)”. The constables in command or parties 
shall also conform to the rules laid down for officers.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>72</number> Salute by Officers while on 
duty, parade and boarding a ship.—All officers shall salute their 
senior officers before addressing them on duty or on parade in the following 
manner:—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  A 
salute made to two or more officers shall be returned by the senior only. When 
not on duty or parade but in uniform, officers under the rank of Deputy 
Commandants shall salute all officers of the rank of Deputy Commandants and 
upwards. The senior officers, Commandants and Deputy Commandants shall salute 
their superiors in rank.
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  The 
cadets (Trainees/Officers) shall salute all officers in uniform, and the 
officers of their Academy whether in uniform or not.
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  The 
Officers in uniform shall salute their seniors in rank in the Defence Services, 
Central Police Organisations and other Police Forces.
 </section><section>       <number>d</number>  All 
ranks boarding any of the Indian Naval ships or a foreign vessel shall salute on 
entering and leaving the ship. The Naval Customs of saluting on entering the 
quarter deck shall also be adhered to by all ranks.</section></article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>73</number> Saluting by subordinate 
officers and other ranks.—
<section><number>a</number> The Subordinate Officers, 
Under Officers and men shall salute all Officers whom they know to be such, 
whether in uniform or not including officers of Defence Services and other 
Police Forces when in uniform. Subordinate Officers and other ranks shall salute 
with the right hand. Where due to physical incapacity a right hand salute is 
impossible the salute shall be given with the left hand.
 </section><section><number>b</number> The Under Officers and men 
when in uniform shall salute the Subordinate Officers whether in uniform or not 
and also address them in the same manner as they do to officers.
 </section><section><number>c</number> A person junior in rank, 
when on duty shall come to attention when addressing or addressed by a person 
holding a senior rank.</section></article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>74</number> Salutation by civilian 
VIPs.—The 
position of Staff Officers Stick Orderlies, the parade commander and the senior 
most officer at the time of salutation by civilian VIPs shall be as 
under:—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  The 
VIP stands centrally on the dais with the senior most Border Security Force and 
the conducting officer behind him (senior most on the right and the conducting 
officer on the left) if he has staff officers attending on him, they may stand 
on the sides of the saluting dais, a little to the rear of the VIP. The Parade 
Commander after he has saluted and passed in front of the VIP as the head of the 
parade may leave the column and take up a position next to the VIP below the 
dais, on the flank from which the parade marches on.
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  At 
the Ceremonial Parades held on the Republic Day and the Independence Day the 
salute shall ordinarily be taken by the senior most civil representative of 
Government, e.g., the Governor, Chief Minister, Cabinet Minister, 
Commissioner, Collector or Deputy Commissioner, as the case may be.
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  In 
the state capitals where the Border Security Force also participates in the 
march past on the Republic Day, the senior most Border Security Force official 
may also stand behind the VIP along with the senior most officers of the three 
services and Police.</section></article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>75</number> National 
Flag.—The 
National Flag shall be flown at Border Out Posts, Mobile Border Out Posts in 
Boats/Crafts and Headquarters Director General Border Security 
Force.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>76</number> Border Security Force 
Flags.—The 
Border Security Force Flags shall be flown at:
 <section>       <number>a</number>  the 
Frontier Head Quarters.
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  the 
Head Quarters of Senior Deputy Inspector General.
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  the 
Training Institutions.
 </section><section>       <number>d</number>  the 
Unit Quarter Guards.
 </section><section>       <number>e</number>  the 
occasion of Inter-Frontier-Games/ Athletic Meets or any other Sports 
Occasion.
 The Frontier Flags will be flown 
at the time of Frontier Sports function.</section></article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>77</number> Flags for motor vehicles 
(Car/Jeeps).—The flags for officers, shall 
be as specified in Appendix.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>78</number> The officers shall fly their 
entitled flags as under:—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  
Within India except in Delhi
               
On staff cars or private cars, whether dressed in uniform or mufti on duty, 
including functions being attended in an official capacity, use of mufti on such 
occasion must be correct and permitted under the rules for the time being in 
force.
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  In 
Delhi
 <subsection>        
<number>i</number>  Director General, Additional Director General and Inspector General at 
Headquarters Border Security Force may fly flags on staff and private cars when 
attending officer and official functions including functions held at Rashtrapati 
Bhavan.
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>ii</number>  Inspector-General, Additional Inspector-General/Deputy Inspector 
General, Additional Deputy Inspector-General may fly flags as 
follows:—
 <subsubsection>                 
<number>1</number>  While on duty in uniform travelling in Government 
transport.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>                 
<number>2</number>  When travelling in Government transport whether in uniform or mufti, 
for attending Force functions.</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>79</number> Star Plates.—
<section><number>1</number> Distinguishing metal 
plates, denoting the rank of the occupant of the vehicle, shall be carried on 
vehicles in addition to the flag authorised for the occupant. The plates, which 
shall be 18” (0.457 m) long and 4½” silver coloured permanently fixed, five 
pointed raised metal stars in accordance with the rank of the officers, 
viz.:—
 <subsection>        
<number>i</number>  Director-General/Additional Director General.—3 Stars.
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>ii</number>  Inspector-General/Additional Inspector General.—2 Stars.
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number>  
Deputy Inspector-General/Additional Deputy Inspector General.—1 Star.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Whenever Flags are 
authorised to be flown as above star plates be displayed in addition to the 
flags. On other occasion, when officers are not entitled to fly flags but are 
travelling in uniform in Government or private cars, they may display star 
plates only.</section></article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>80</number> Star Plate.—An officer officiating in a 
higher appointment shall display the star plate of his own 
rank.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>81</number> Dress of Border Security 
Force Drivers.—The Border Security Force 
Drivers where authorised for private cars, shall not wear uniform when officers 
are travelling in a car in mufti or when their families only are using the 
car.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>82</number> Compliment by guards of the 
President and entitled VIPs.—Guards including Guards of 
Honour, mounted on the occasion of the visit of the President shall pay 
compliments only to the President. Guards including Guards of Honour, mounted 
for other entitled VIPs including Military VIPs within their own charges, shall 
pay no compliments to the officers and persons of lower rank. Any such guard, 
when visited by the officers on duty, shall turn out with “Bazu 
Shastr.”</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>83</number> Compliments by 
Guards—between Reveille and retreat.—
<section><number>a</number> At all times between 
reveille and retreat, guards shall turn out and pay the compliments specified in 
rule 66(b) and (f) in Chapter IX of the rules.
 </section><section><number>b</number> Unit guards shall turn out, 
and present arms, once a day to their Commandants, of whatever rank he may 
be.</section></article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>84</number> Turn out of guards to armed 
parties.—The 
guards shall turn out at all times when armed parties of any Force approach 
their posts; to armed corps they shall present arms and before other armed 
parties they shall stand with “Bazu Shastr”. They shall not pay compliments 
between the sounding of ‘Retreat’ and ‘Reveille’ except to grand rounds. They 
shall not turn out to unarmed parties.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>85</number> Compliments where not 
entitled.—An 
officer under the rank of an Additional Deputy Inspector General is not entitled 
to the compliment of the bugle sounding the salute or the drum beating a ruffle, 
when guards “present arms” to him. An officer not in uniform is not entitled to 
the compliments of a guard turning out except the President or his 
representatives in their official capacity entitled to a Guard of 
Honour.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>86</number> Salute to general 
officer.—When a 
senior officer in uniform or a person entitled to a salute, passes in rear of a 
guard, the commander shall caution his guard to fall in and stand with “Bazu 
Shastr”, facing the front, but no ‘drum shall beat or bugle sound. When such 
officers pass guards while in the act of relieving, both guards shall salute as 
they stand, receiving the word of command from senior 
Commander.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>88</number> Compliment to officers of 
other Forces.—All guards and sentries shall 
pay the same compliments to the Defence Services Officers, Gazetted Officers or 
other Central Police Organisations, State Police Officers and Home Guards when 
in uniform as are directed to be paid to the officers of the Border Security 
Force.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>89</number> Guards at 
residence.—The 
following shall be authorised a guard at their residence as per the strength 
mentioned below:—
 <section>        
<number>i</number>  Director-General/Additional Director General—2 Under Officers and 8 
Rifles.
 </section><section>        
<number>ii</number>  Inspector General/Additional Inspector General—1 Under Officer and 3 
Rifles.
 </section><section>       <number>iii</number>  
Deputy Inspector General/Additional Deputy Inspector General—1 Under Officer and 
3 Rifles.</section></article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>90</number> Border out post guard at 
Reveille.—Hoisting of National Flag by 
guards of both countries.
 <section><number>1</number> Daily at reveille one jawan 
each of the guard from both the countries hoist their National Flag. While 
hoisting National Flag the Indian Jawan shall stand under counter parts’ 
National Flag and the Jawan from the other side shall stand under Indian 
National Flag.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Fall-in of the guards of 
both countries.
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  At 
reveille National Flags of both the countries are hoisted at one time. First day 
Indian Guard shall fall into the right side of counter parts’ guard and the next 
day it shall be vice-versa. The Guard Commander of the Guard standing on 
the right shall order ‘Present Arms’. On this word of command the jawans of both 
the countries who are standing near the flag post shall start hoisting the flag 
gradually by putting the strings across each other. Bugler shall blow the 
reveille and guards shall ‘Present Arms.’
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  The 
speed for pulling up the flags shall be with the sound of the bugle. After 
hoisting, the jawans shall smartly move to their respective flags and shall tie 
the strings with the poles, and will fall in on the left of their respective 
guards.</subsection></section></article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>91</number> Posting of the sentry at the 
Border out post first sentry.—
<section><number>a</number> After completing all 
formalities at reveille, the Commander of the right guard will command ‘First 
Detail Fall in’.
 </section><section><number>b</number> On this word of command the 
first sentries of both the countries will march smartly and halt at boundary 
line keeping 24 inches shoulder distance between each 
other.</section></article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>92</number> On the word of command 
“Sentry Check” by the right guard commander.—The sentries of both the 
countries will check/search the pockets of each other to ensure that they are 
not carrying any grenades/knives, etc.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>93</number> Position of 
Sentries.—
<section><number>a</number> 
After having checked/searched pocket by both the sentries the right guard 
commander will command ‘Sentry Attention’.
 </section><section><number>b</number> On this the sentries will 
stand in attention position facing the respective 
guards.</section></article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>94</number> The right guard commander 
order guard march off.—The Guard commander of both the 
countries will march off their guards, to their respective lines, where they 
will be dismissed.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>95</number> Arms and ammunition carried 
by sentries.—
<section><number>a</number> The sentiries of both the 
countries will carry prescribed automatic weapons or Sten guns with one magazine 
full of ammunition. The safety catch of the weapons will be at safe.
 </section><section><number>b</number> Sentries will keep their 
weapons at sling Arm position.
 </section><section><number>c</number> Sentries will not discuss 
any matter which is against the norms of discipline.
 </section><section><number>d</number> All the sentries must be 
trained in security matters.</section></article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>96</number> Movement on beat by 
sentries.—The 
sentries of both the countries will move on their respective beats together. 
They will halt at their fixed place and stand at case.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>97</number> Compliments by the 
sentries.—
<section><number>a</number> 
If any officer is coming from Indian side, the Indian Sentry shall immediately 
stand on the right of own guard.
 </section><section><number>b</number> When the officer approaches 
the sentry shall speak gently ‘UP’ and both the sentries shall salute 
together.
 </section><section><number>c</number> If the officer is coming 
from opposite side the sentry of the other country will stand at the right side 
and action will be the same as given in sub-rule (b) 
above.</section></article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>98</number> Ceremonial guard at Border 
out post.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If any officer from India or any other country is coming or going the following 
drill shall be followed:—
         The 
Border Out Post sentry shall shout ‘Guard Fall In.—‘Guard Fall 
In’.
 On hearing this, all the guard 
personnel of both the countries will fall-in with ‘Bazu Shastr’. On arrival of 
the officer the guard commander will pay compliment as per his rank and guard 
will be made to stand in ‘Order Arms’. Then the Guard Commander will take his 
position and will report, “Ceremonial Guard is ready for your inspection. 
Sir”.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The inspecting officer will 
inspect the guard. When he has inspected the guard commander will come to 
‘Baggal Shastr’ and will follow him. After the inspection is over the guard 
commander will salute the inspecting officer and will come back to his original 
position.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The inspecting officer will 
order.—‘Guard Dismiss’. On this the guard commander will give the word of 
command ‘Guard Baggal Shastr.’ Sentry stand past, remainder dismiss.
 The sentry will stand past and 
other will dismiss, guard commander will turn left and salute the VIP and move 
to his place.</section></article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>99</number> Guard of honour at Border 
Out Post for VIP.—If any VIP is either passing 
through from/to India or visiting the Border Out Post as per programme, a guard 
of honour shall be arranged for him.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>100</number> Fall-in of 
guard.—Before 
the arrival of the VIP the guard shall fall-in with arms in line for 
alignment.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>101</number> Fall-in of 
band.—If the 
band is available with the guard, they shall fall in at 8 paces to the right of 
guard. If the space is not available on the right the band master shall stand at 
a distance of 6 paces and the rest 3 paces behind him. The bugler shall fall at 
9 paces to the right of the guard.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>102</number> Procedure.—When the VIP is approaching, 
the guard commander shall command.
 <section>       <number>a</number>  
Guard ‘Attention’
 <subsection>             
<number>i</number>  When the VIP has reached the saluting base the guard commander shall 
order—‘Guard National Salute Salami Shastr.’ The band shall play National 
Anthem/General Salute. If band is not available the bugler shall sound the 
bugle.
 </subsection><subsection>            
<number>ii</number>  At the end of this tune the guard commander shall order—
                   
‘Guard Bazu Shastr.’</subsection></section></article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>103</number> Reporting by guard 
commander.—The 
guard commander moves in quick time towards the VIP, and shall salute halt at 
place facing the VIP, and shall report—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  
“Guard of Honour is ready for your inspection Sir”, again salutes the VIP and 
follows him to his left in slow march. During inspection he shall be on the 
right and little behind the VIP. When the inspection starts the drum shall beat 
(Dum) thrice and on the third beat, all the jawans shall turn their eyes towards 
the VIP and as the VIP inspects they shall turn eyes and head to the left. The 
band shall play the appropriate tune. When the inspection is over, the drummer 
shall again beat the drum (dum) thrice and all the jawans shall look to their 
front at the last drum (dum). The VIP shall come to the saluting base and the 
guard Commander after saluting the VIP shall return to his original 
position.
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  
Guard National/ General Salute ‘Present Arms’ on this the band or bugle shall 
play. Guard Commander shall command ‘Guard Bazu Shastr’, when the VIP leaves the 
guard commander again order guard dismiss.”</section></article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>104</number> Border Out Post at the time 
of retreat.—A 
few minutes before the retreat the Guard Commander shall bring the guard at 
fall-in position and shall inspect the guard. He shall order ‘Guard Baggal 
Shaster’ and shall march the guard in quick time upto the National Boundary 
line. He shall keep the guard at place where it was standing in the morning in 
‘Baggal Shaster’ position.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>105</number> Position of guard commander 
of the other country.—
<section><number>a</number> The guard commander of the 
opposite side will also keep his guard standing at the place where it was 
standing in the morning.
 </section><section><number>b</number> Jawans detailed to remove 
the flag will untie the string from poles and will put the string across each 
other. Indian Jawan will be standing below the opposite country’s flag and 
vice-versa.</section></article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>106</number> Procedure.—When the right guard commander 
orders ‘Guard Present Arms’ the bugler will sound the retreat. The same time 
flag will be pulled down with sound of retreat. Immediately after this the jawan 
will move smartly to their flag and will untie the flags from the string. The 
string will be kept with poles. The Indian jawan shall fold the flag in such a 
way that the tri-colours are visible.
 Both the jawans will raise their 
flags and will march smartly at a distance of 2 paces from their respective 
guards. Now all other sentries will join their guards to the 
left.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>107</number> Joint briefing of guards by 
guard commander of both countries.—The guard commander of both the 
countries will jointly brief the guards and will order—Guard will move right in 
file “Right Turn”, Guard quick march. After reaching their respective lines the 
guard commander will halt the guard and will command:—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  
Guard will turn to the front ‘Left turn.’
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  
‘Guard dismiss’.</section></article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>108</number> Flag.—The flag shall be kept at 
proper place with due honour.
 Action in the Border Out Post at 
the visit of VIP company/Border Out Post commander will welcome the VIP at the 
given time. Before reporting to the VIP the company/ Border Out Post commander 
will ensure that the troops are in stand to position and all personnel are in 
their respective trenches/bunkers.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>109</number> Reporting by Company/ 
Border Out Post Commander to VIP.—The Company/Border Out Post 
Commander will report to VIP as under:
         “Sir 
Alfa Company. 73 Battalion Border Security Force, 1 Officer, 1 subordinate 
officer and 32 other Ranks ready for your inspection” (The present strength of 
the Border Out Post is to be reported).</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>110</number> Tasks.—
<section><number>a</number> The company/ Border Out 
Post commander explains the task and the area of responsibility: left and right 
flanking border Out Posts and similarly about the opposite Border Out 
Posts.
 </section><section><number>b</number> The VIP will then be led to 
each trench/ bunker for inspection, each jawan will explain his task and area of 
responsibility. When the VIP finishes the inspection of the picquet, the 
company/Border Out Post commander will stand-down 
personnel.</section></article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>111</number> Stand down.—After the stand-down the jawans 
shall fall-in in open order and their arms/ammunition shall be inspected by 
Company/Border Out Post commander. All correct report shall be given to VIP in 
attention position. If the VIP wants to speak to the men, the jawans shall keep 
standing there otherwise, under the orders of company/Border Out Post commander, 
the personnel shall dismiss.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>112</number> Visit to cook house, stores 
by VIP.—The 
company or Border Out Post commander will then take the VIP to Cook house, 
Magazine and Stores for his inspection.</article> 
 The Border Security force (Ceremonials And 
 Marks of Respect) Rules, 1989
  
 <article><number>113</number> Departure of 
VIP.—After the 
inspection of VIP, the company/ Border Out Post commander shall see off the VIP 
from the post.
  </article><form>
 

The 
Border Security Force (Ceremonials and  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 
1989
 

 
 

Appendix 
‘I’
 

[Reference rule 
77]
 

Flag for 
Motor Vehicle (Car/Jeeps)
 


 

S. 
No.      
Officers                      
Shape, Size and Colour
 


 

1        
         
2                           
           3
 

1.       
Director General 
BSF              
The flag flown by the Director General shall be rectangular 15 cms in the hoist 
and 22.5 cms in the fly. The top half will be red and bottom half will be in 
navy blue colour. The BSF crest for the flag of the Director General shall be so 
made as to be contained just within circle prescribed with 4 cms as radius with 
its centre at a point 7.25 cms from the pole of the flag an equidistant from the 
upper and lower edge. In addition to above a FHQ formation sign of the size 4 
cms (horizontal) by 5 cms (vertical) on the top of half red of flag will be so 
placed that its centre must fall on the centre of the square 7.5 cms leaving a 
distance of 1.75 cms from the flag red side edge and 1.25 cms from the 
top.
 

2.       
Addl. Director General BSF      The flag flown by the 
Addl. Director-General shall be rectangular 15 cms in the hoist and 22.5 cms in 
the fly. The top half will be red and bottom half will be in navy blue colour. 
The BSF crest for the flag of the Addl. Director General shall be so made as to 
be contained just within circle prescribed with 4 cms as radius with its centre 
at a point 7.25 cms from the pole of the flag an equi-distant from the upper and 
lower edge.
 

3.       
Inspector General 
BSF            The flag 
flown by the Inspector-General shall be swallow tail. The cloth will be 15 cms 
in the hoist and 22.5 cms in the fly. The cut of the swallow tail will be 7.5 
cms deep. The top half will be red and bottom half will be in navy blue colour. 
The BSF crest for the flag of the Inspector General shall be so made as to 
contain just within a circle prescribed within 4 cms as radius from the centre 
at a point 7.5 cms from the pole of the flag and equi-distance from the upper 
and lower edge.
 

4.       
Dy. Inspector General BSF      The flag to be flown by 
the DIG of Police shall be “penant triangular and pointed with the hoist (15 cms 
in length) as the base of an isosceles triangle with a length of 22.5 cms in the 
fly from which point the angle meeting with the ends of the hoist must be 
determined”. The top half of the flag will be red and the bottom half of the 
navy blue colour. The BSF crest of the flag of the DIG shall be so made as to be 
to be contained within a circle of 4 cms radius.
 


 

5.       
Addl. Dy. Inspr. General BSF   The flag to be flown by the Addl. DIG 
shall be “penant triangular and pointed with the hoist (15 cms in length) as the 
base of an isosceles triangle with a length of 22.5 cms in the fly from which 
point the angle meeting with the end of hoist must be determined.” The top half 
of the flag will be red and the bottom half of the navy blue colour. The 
formation sign of the frontier will be so made as to be contained just within a 
circle of 4 cms radius.
 

 
 

 
 

 
 

 </form><form>
 

The 
Border Security Force (Ceremonials and  
Marks of Respect) Rules, 
1989
 

 
 

Appendix 
‘J’
 

[Reference rule 
77]
 

Flag for 
Motor Vehicle (Car/Jeeps)
 


 

S. 
No.      
Officers                      
Shape, Size and Colour
 


 

1        
         
2                           
           3
 

1.       
Director General 
BSF              
The flag flown by the Director General shall be rectangular 15 cms in the hoist 
and 22.5 cms in the fly. The top half will be red and bottom half will be in 
navy blue colour. The BSF crest for the flag of the Director General shall be so 
made as to be contained just within circle prescribed with 4 cms as radius with 
its centre at a point 7.25 cms from the pole of the flag an equidistant from the 
upper and lower edge. In addition to above a FHQ formation sign of the size 4 
cms (horizontal) by 5 cms (vertical) on the top of half red of flag will be so 
placed that its centre must fall on the centre of the square 7.5 cms leaving a 
distance of 1.75 cms from the flag red side edge and 1.25 cms from the 
top.
 

2.       
Addl. Director General BSF      The flag flown by the 
Addl. Director-General shall be rectangular 15 cms in the hoist and 22.5 cms in 
the fly. The top half will be red and bottom half will be in navy blue colour. 
The BSF crest for the flag of the Addl. Director General shall be so made as to 
be contained just within circle prescribed with 4 cms as radius with its centre 
at a point 7.25 cms from the pole of the flag an equi-distant from the upper and 
lower edge.
 

3.       
Inspector General 
BSF            The flag 
flown by the Inspector-General shall be swallow tail. The cloth will be 15 cms 
in the hoist and 22.5 cms in the fly. The cut of the swallow tail will be 7.5 
cms deep. The top half will be red and bottom half will be in navy blue colour. 
The BSF crest for the flag of the Inspector General shall be so made as to 
contain just within a circle prescribed within 4 cms as radius from the centre 
at a point 7.5 cms from the pole of the flag and equi-distance from the upper 
and lower edge.
 

4.       
Dy. Inspector General BSF      The flag to be flown by 
the DIG of Police shall be “penant triangular and pointed with the hoist (15 cms 
in length) as the base of an isosceles triangle with a length of 22.5 cms in the 
fly from which point the angle meeting with the ends of the hoist must be 
determined”. The top half of the flag will be red and the bottom half of the 
navy blue colour. The BSF crest of the flag of the DIG shall be so made as to be 
to be contained within a circle of 4 cms radius.
 


 

5.       
Addl. Dy. Inspr. General BSF   The flag to be flown by the Addl. DIG 
shall be “penant triangular and pointed with the hoist (15 cms in length) as the 
base of an isosceles triangle with a length of 22.5 cms in the fly from which 
point the angle meeting with the end of hoist must be determined.” The top half 
of the flag will be red and the bottom half of the navy blue colour. The 
formation sign of the frontier will be so made as to be contained just within a 
circle of 4 cms radius.
 

 
 

 
 

 
 

 </form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>