<act><title>THE RIGHT OF CHILDREN TO FREE AND 
COMPULSORY EDUCATION ACT, 20091</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number>Short title, extent and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> This Act may be 
called the Right of Children to Free and Compulsory Education Act, 2009. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> It shall extend to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and 
Kashmir . 
 </section><section><number>3</number> It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, appoint. 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number>Definitions. </title>In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires, 
 
 <section><number>a</number> appropriate Government means 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> in relation to a school established, owned or controlled by the 
    Central Government, or the administrator of the Union territory, having no 
    legislature, the Central Government; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> in relation to a school, other than the school referred to in 
    sub-clause (i), established within the territory of 
 
 <subsubsection><number>A</number> a State, the State Government; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>B</number> a Union territory having legislature, the Government of that Union 
      territory; </subsubsection></subsection>
 </section><section><number>b</number> capitation fee means any kind of donation or contribution or payment 
  other than the fee notified by the school; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> child means a male or female child of the age of six to fourteen 
  years; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> child belonging to disadvantaged group means a child belonging to the 
  Scheduled Caste, the Scheduled Tribe, the socially and educationally backward 
  class or such other group having disadvantage owing to social, cultural, 
  economical, geographical, linguistic, gender or such other factor, as may be 
  specified by the appropriate Government, by notification; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> child belonging to weaker section means a child belonging to such 
  parent or guardian whose annual income is lower than the minimum limit 
  specified by the appropriate Government, by notification; 
 </section><section><number>f</number> elementary education means the education from first class to eighth 
  class; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> guardian, in relation to a child, means a person having the care and 
  custody of that child and includes a natural guardian or guardian appointed or 
  declared by a court or a statute; 
 </section><section><number>h</number> local authority means a Municipal Corporation or Municipal Council or 
  Zila Parishad or Nagar Panchayat or Panchayat, by whatever name called, and 
  includes such other authority or body having administrative control over the 
  school or empowered by or under any law for the time being in force to 
  function as a local authority in any city, town or village; 
 </section><section><number>i</number> National Commission for Protection of Child Rights means the National 
  Commission for Protection of Child Rights constituted under Section 3 of the 
  Commissions for Protection of Child Rights Act, 2005 (4 of 2006); 
 </section><section><number>j</number> notification means a notification published in the Official Gazette; 
  
 </section><section><number>k</number> parent means either the natural or step or adoptive father or mother 
  of a child; 
 </section><section><number>l</number> prescribed means prescribed by rules made under this Act; 
 </section><section><number>m</number> Schedule means the Schedule annexed to this Act; 
 </section><section><number>n</number> school means any recognised school imparting elementary education and 
  includes 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> a school established, owned or controlled by the appropriate 
    Government or a local authority; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> an aided school receiving aid or grants to meet whole or part of its 
    expenses from the appropriate Government or the local authority; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> a school belonging to specified category; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> an unaided school not receiving any kind of aid or grants to meet 
    its expenses from the appropriate Government or the local authority; 
  </subsection>
 </section><section><number>o</number> screening procedure means the method of selection for admission of a 
  child, in preference over another, other than a random method; 
 </section><section><number>p</number> specified category, in relation to a school, means a school known as 
  Kendriya Vidyalaya, Navodaya Vidyalaya, Sainik School or any other school 
  having a distinct character which may be specified, by notification, by the 
  appropriate Government; 
 </section><section><number>q</number> State Commission for Protection of Child Rights means the State 
  Commission for Protection of Child Rights constituted under Section 3 of the 
  Commissions for Protection of Child Rights Act, 2005 (4 of 2006). 
</section>

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number>Right of child to free and compulsory education. </title>
<section><number>1</number> 
Every child of the age of six to fourteen years shall have a right to free and 
compulsory education in a neighbourhood school till completion of elementary 
education. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> For the purpose of sub-section (1), no child shall be liable to pay any 
kind of fee or charges or expenses which may prevent him or her from pursuing 
and completing the elementary education: 
 Provided that a child suffering from disability, as defined in Clause (i) of 
Section 2 of the Persons with Disabilities (Equal Opportunities, Protection and 
Full Participation) Act, 1996 (1 of 1996), shall have the right to pursue free 
and compulsory elementary education in accordance with the provisions of Chapter 
V of the said Act. 




</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number>Special provisions for children not admitted to, or who have not 
completed, elementary education. </title>Where a child above six years of age 
has not been admitted in any school or though admitted, could not complete his 
or her elementary education, then, he or she shall be admitted in a class 
appropriate to his or her age: 
 Provided that where a child is directly admitted in a class appropriate to 
his or her age, then, he or she shall, in order to be at par with others, have a 
right to receive special training, in such manner, and within such time-limits, 
as may be prescribed: 
 Provided further that a child so admitted to elementary education shall be 
entitled to free education till completion of elementary education even after 
fourteen years. 




</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number>Right of transfer to other school. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Where in a school, 
there is no provision for completion of elementary education, a child shall have 
a right to seek transfer to any other school, excluding the school specified in 
sub-clauses (iii) and (iv) of Clause (n) of Section 2, for completing his or her 
elementary education. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where a child is required to move from one school to another, either 
within a State or outside, for any reason whatsoever, such child shall have a 
right to seek transfer to any other school, excluding the school specified in 
sub-clauses (iii) and (iv) of Clause (n) of Section 2, for completing his or her 
elementary education. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> For seeking admission in such other school, the Head-teacher or in-charge 
of the school where such child was last admitted, shall immediately issue the 
transfer certificate: 
 Provided that delay in producing transfer certificate shall not be a ground 
for either delaying or denying admission in such other school: 
 Provided further that the Head-teacher or in-charge of the school delaying 
issuance of transfer certificate shall be liable for disciplinary action under 
the service rules applicable to him or her. 




</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number>Duty of appropriate Government and local authority to establish 
school. </title>For carrying out the provisions of this Act, the appropriate 
Government and the local authority shall establish, within such area or limits 
of neighbourhood, as may be prescribed, a school, where it is not so 
established, within a period of three years from the commencement of this Act. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number>Sharing of financial and other responsibilities. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The 
Central Government and the State Governments shall have concurrent 
responsibility for providing funds for carrying out the provisions of this Act. 

 </section><section><number>2</number> The Central Government shall prepare the estimates of capital and 
recurring expenditure for the implementation of the provisions of the Act. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Central Government shall provide to the State Governments, as 
grants-in-aid of revenues, such percentage of expenditure referred to in 
sub-section (2) as it may determine, from time to time, in consultation with the 
State Governments. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Central Government may make a request to the President to make a 
reference to the Finance Commission under sub-clause (d) of Clause (3) of 
Article 280 to examine the need for additional resources to be provided to any 
State Government so that the said State Government may provide its share of 
funds for carrying out the provisions of the Act. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (4), the State 
Government shall, taking into consideration the sums provided by the Central 
Government to a State Government under sub-section (3), and its other resources, 
be responsible to provide funds for implementation of the provisions of the Act. 

 </section><section><number>6</number> The Central Government shall 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> develop a framework of national curriculum with the help of academic 
  authority specified under Section 29; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> develop and enforce standards for training of teachers; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> provide technical support and resources to the State Government for 
  promoting innovations, researches, planning and capacity building. 
</subsection>




</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number>Duties of appropriate Government. </title>The appropriate 
Government shall 
 
 <section><number>a</number> provide free and compulsory elementary education to every child: 
</section>
 Provided that where a child is admitted by his or her parents or guardian, as 
the case may be, in a school other than a school established, owned, controlled 
or substantially financed by funds provided directly or indirectly by the 
appropriate Government or a local authority, such child or his or her parents or 
guardian, as the case may be, shall not be entitled to make a claim for 
reimbursement of expenditure incurred on elementary education of the child in 
such other school. 
 Explanation. The term compulsory education means obligation of 
the appropriate Government to 
 
 
 <section><number>i</number> provide free elementary education to every child of the age of six to 
    fourteen years; and 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> ensure compulsory admission, attendance and completion of elementary 
    education by every child of the age of six to fourteen years; 
</section>
 <section><number>b</number> ensure availability of a neighbourhood school as specified in 
   Section 6; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> ensure that the child belonging to weaker section and the child 
  belonging to disadvantaged group are not discriminated against and prevented 
  from pursuing and completing elementary education on any grounds; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> provide infrastructure including school building, teaching staff and 
  learning equipment; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> provide special training facility specified in Section 4; 
 </section><section><number>f</number> ensure and monitor admission, attendance and completion of elementary 
  education by every child; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> ensure good quality elementary education conforming to the standards 
  and norms specified in the Schedule; 
 </section><section><number>h</number> ensure timely prescribing of curriculum and courses of study for 
  elementary education; and 
 </section><section><number>i</number> provide training facility for teachers. </section>

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>9</number>Duties of local authority. </title>Every local authority shall 

 
 <section><number>a</number> provide free and compulsory elementary education to every child: 
 Provided that where a child is admitted by his or her parents or guardian, 
  as the case may be, in a school other than a school established, owned, 
  controlled or substantially financed by funds provided directly or indirectly 
  by the appropriate Government or a local authority, such child or his or her 
  parents or guardian, as the case may be, shall not be entitled to make a claim 
  for reimbursement of expenditure incurred on elementary education of the child 
  in such other school; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> ensure availability of a neighbourhood school as specified in Section 
  6; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> ensure that the child belonging to weaker section and the child 
  belonging to disadvantaged group are not discriminated against and prevented 
  from pursuing and completing elementary education on any grounds; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> maintain records of children up to the age of fourteen years residing 
  within its jurisdiction, in such manner as may be prescribed; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> ensure and monitor admission, attendance and completion of elementary 
  education by every child residing within its jurisdiction; 
 </section><section><number>f</number> provide infrastructure including school building, teaching staff and 
  learning material; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> provide special training facility specified in Section 4; 
 </section><section><number>h</number> ensure good quality elementary education conforming to the standards 
  and norms specified in the Schedule; 
 </section><section><number>i</number> ensure timely prescribing of curriculum and courses of study for 
  elementary education; 
 </section><section><number>j</number> provide training facility for teachers; 
 </section><section><number>k</number> ensure admission of children of migrant families; 
 </section><section><number>l</number> monitor functioning of schools within its jurisdiction; and 
 </section><section><number>m</number> decide the academic calendar. </section>

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>10</number>Duty of parents and guardian. </title>It shall be the duty of 
every parent or guardian to admit or cause to be admitted his or her child or 
ward, as the case may be, to an elementary education in the neighbourhood 
school. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>11</number>Appropriate Government to provide for pre-school education. 
</title>With a view to prepare children above the age of three years for 
elementary education and to provide early childhood care and education for all 
children until they complete the age of six years, the appropriate Government 
may make necessary arrangement for providing free pre-school education for such 
children. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>12</number>Extent of school's responsibility for free and compulsory 
education. </title>
<section><number>1</number> For the purposes of this Act, a school, 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> specified in sub-clause (i) of Clause (n) of Section 2 shall provide 
  free and compulsory elementary education to all children admitted therein; 

 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> specified in sub-clause (ii) of Clause (n) of Section 2 shall provide 
  free and compulsory elementary education to such proportion of children 
  admitted therein as its annual recurring aid or grants so received bears to 
  its annual recurring expenses, subject to a minimum of twenty-five per cent; 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> specified in sub-clauses (iii) and (iv) of Clause (n) of Section 2 
  shall admit in class I, to the extent of at least twenty-five per cent. of the 
  strength of that class, children belonging to weaker section and disadvantaged 
  group in the neighbourhood and provide free and compulsory elementary 
  education till its completion: </subsection>
 Provided further that where a school specified in Clause (n) of Section 2 
imparts pre-school education, the provisions of Clauses (a) to (c) shall apply 
for admission to such pre-school education. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The school specified in sub-clause (iv) of Clause (n) of Section 2 
providing free and compulsory elementary education as specified in Clause (c) of 
sub-section (1) shall be reimbursed expenditure so incurred by it to the extent 
of per-child-expenditure incurred by the State, or the actual amount charged 
from the child, whichever is less, in such manner as may be prescribed: 
 Provided that such reimbursement shall not exceed per-child-expenditure 
incurred by a school specified in sub-clause (i) of Clause (n) of Section 2: 

 Provided further that where such school is already under obligation to 
provide free education to a specified number of children on account of it having 
received any land, building, equipment or other facilities, either free of cost 
or at a concessional rate, such school shall not be entitled for reimbursement 
to the extent of such obligation. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every school shall provide such information as may be required by the 
appropriate Government or the local authority, as the case may be. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>13</number>No capitation fee and screening procedure for admission. 
</title>
<section><number>1</number> No school or person shall, while admitting a child, collect any 
capitation fee and subject the child or his or her parents or guardian to any 
screening procedure. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any school or person, if in contravention of the provisions of sub- 
 section (1) 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> receives capitation fee, shall be punishable with fine which may extend 
  to ten times the capitation fee charged; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> subjects a child to screening procedure, shall be punishable with fine 
  which may extend to twenty-five thousand rupees for the first contravention 
  and fifty thousand rupees for each subsequent contraventions. </subsection>

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>14</number>Proof of age for admission. </title>
<section><number>1</number> For the purposes of 
admission to elementary education, the age of a child shall be determined on the 
basis of the birth certificate issued in accordance with the provisions of the 
Births, Deaths and Marriages Registration Act, 1886 (6 of 1886) or on the basis 
of such other document, as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> No child shall be denied admission in a school for lack of age proof. 

  

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>15</number>No denial of admission. </title>A child shall be admitted in a 
school at the commencement of the academic year or within such extended period 
as may be prescribed: 
 Provided that no child shall be denied admission if such admission is sought 
subsequent to the extended period: 
 Provided further that any child admitted after the extended period shall 
complete his studies in such manner as may be prescribed by the appropriate 
Government. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>16</number>Prohibition of holding back and expulsion. </title>No child 
admitted in a school shall be held back in any class or expelled from school 
till the completion of elementary education. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>17</number> Prohibition of physical punishment and mental harassment to 
child. </title> 
<section><number>1</number> No child shall be subjected to physical punishment or 
mental harassment. <title></title>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Whoever contravenes the provisions of sub-section (1) shall be liable to 
disciplinary action under the service rules applicable to such person. 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>18</number>No school to be established without obtaining certificate of 
recognition. </title>
<section><number>1</number> No school, other than a school established, owned or 
controlled by the appropriate Government or the local authority, shall, after 
the commencement of this Act, be established or function, without obtaining a 
certificate of recognition from such authority, by making an application in such 
form and manner, as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The authority prescribed under sub-section (1) shall issue the 
certificate of recognition in such form, within such period, in such manner, and 
subject to such conditions, as may be prescribed: 
 Provided that no such recognition shall be granted to a school unless it 
fulfils norms and standards specified under Section 19. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> On the contravention of the conditions of recognition, the prescribed 
authority shall, by an order in writing, withdraw recognition: 
 Provided that such order shall contain a direction as to which of the 
neighbourhood school, the children studying in the derecognised school, shall be 
admitted: 
 Provided further that no recognition shall be so withdrawn without giving an 
opportunity of being heard to such school, in such manner, as may be prescribed. 

 </section><section><number>4</number> With effect from the date of withdrawal of the recognition under 
sub-section (3), no such school shall continue to function. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Any person who establishes or runs a school without obtaining certificate 
of recognition, or continues to run a school after withdrawal of recognition, 
shall be liable to fine which may extend to one lakh rupees and in case of 
continuing contraventions, to a fine of ten thousand rupees for each day during 
which such contravention continues. 




</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>19</number>Norms and standards for school. </title>
<section><number>1</number> No school shall be 
established, or recognised, under Section 18, unless it fulfils the norms and 
standards specified in the Schedule. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where a school established before the commencement of this Act does not 
fulfil the norms and standards specified in the Schedule, it shall take steps to 
fulfil such norms and standards at its own expenses, within a period of three 
years from the date of such commencement. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where a school fails to fulfil the norms and standards within the period 
specified under sub-section (2), the authority prescribed under sub-section (1) 
of Section 18 shall withdraw recognition granted to such school in the manner 
specified under sub-section (3) thereof. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> With effect from the date of withdrawal of recognition under sub- 
 section (3), no school shall continue to function. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Any person who continues to run a school after the recognition is 
withdrawn, shall be liable to fine which may extend to one lakh rupees and in 
case of continuing contraventions, to a fine of ten thousand rupees for each day 
during which such contravention continues. 




</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>20</number>Power to amend Schedule. </title>The Central Government may, by 
notification, amend the Schedule by adding to, or omitting therefrom, any norms 
and standards. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>21</number>School Management Committee. </title>
<section><number>1</number> A school, other than a 
school specified in sub-clause (iv) of Clause (n) of Section 2, shall constitute 
a School Management Committee consisting of the elected representatives of the 
local authority, parents or guardians of children admitted in such school and 
teachers: <title></title>
 Provided that at least three-fourth of members of such Committee shall be 
parents or guardians: 
 Provided further that proportionate representation shall be given to the 
parents or guardians of children belonging to disadvantaged group and weaker 
section: 
 Provided also that fifty per cent. of Members of such Committee shall be 
women. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The School Management Committee shall perform the following functions, 
namely: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> monitor the working of the school; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> prepare and recommend school development plan; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> monitor the utilisation of the grants received from the appropriate 
  Government or local authority or any other source; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> perform such other functions as may be prescribed. </subsection>

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>22</number></title><title>School </title><title>Development Plan. 
</title>
<section><number>1</number> Every School Management Committee, constituted under sub-section 
(1) of Section 21, shall prepare a School Development Plan, in such manner as 
may be prescribed. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The School Development Plan so prepared under sub-section (1) shall be 
the basis for the plans and grants to be made by the appropriate Government or 
local authority, as the case may be. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>23</number>Qualifications for appointment and terms and conditions of service 
of teachers. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Any person possessing such minimum qualifications, as 
laid down by an academic authority, authorised by the Central Government, by 
notification, shall be eligible for appointment as a teacher. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where a State does not have adequate institutions offering courses or 
training in teacher education, or teachers possessing minimum qualifications as 
laid down under sub-section (1) are not available in sufficient numbers, the 
Central Government may, if it deems necessary, by notification, relax the 
minimum qualifications required for appointment as a teacher, for such period, 
not exceeding five years, as may be specified in that notification: 
 Provided that a teacher who, at the commencement of this Act, does not 
possess minimum qualifications as laid down under sub-section (1), shall acquire 
such minimum qualifications within a period of five years. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The salary and allowances payable to, and the terms and conditions of 
service of, teacher shall be such as may be prescribed. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>24</number>Duties of teachers and redressal of grievances. </title>
<section><number>1</number> A 
teacher appointed under sub-section (1) of Section 23 shall perform the 
following duties, namely: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> maintain regularity and punctuality in attending school; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> conduct and complete the curriculum in accordance with the provisions 
  of sub-section (2) of Section 29; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> complete entire curriculum within the specified time; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> assess the learning ability of each child and accordingly supplement 
  additional instructions, if any, as required; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> hold regular meetings with parents and guardians and apprise them about 
  the regularity in attendance, ability to learn, progress made in learning and 
  any other relevant information about the child; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> perform such other duties as may be prescribed. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> A teacher committing default in performance of duties specified in 
sub-section (1), shall be liable to disciplinary action under the service rules 
applicable to him or her: 
 Provided that before taking such disciplinary action, reasonable opportunity 
of being heard shall be afforded to such teacher. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The grievances, if any, of the teacher shall be redressed in such manner 
as may be prescribed. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>25</number>Pupil-Teacher Ratio. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Within six months from the date 
of commencement of this Act, the appropriate Government and the local authority 
shall ensure that the Pupil-Teacher Ratio, as specified in the Schedule, is 
maintained in each school. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> For the purpose of maintaining the Pupil-Teacher Ratio under sub-section 
(1), no teacher posted in a school shall be made to serve in any other school or 
office or deployed for any non-educational purpose, other than those specified 
in Section 27. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>26</number>Filling up vacancies of teachers. </title>The appointing 
authority, in relation to a school established, owned, controlled or 
substantially financed by funds provided directly or indirectly by the 
appropriate Government or by a local authority, shall ensure that vacancy of 
teacher in a school under its control shall not exceed ten per cent. of the 
total sanctioned strength. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>27</number> Prohibition of deployment of teachers for non-educational 
purposes. </title>No teacher shall be deployed for any non-educational 
purposes other than the decennial population census, disaster relief duties or 
duties relating to elections to the local authority or the State Legislatures or 
Parliament, as the case may be. 

Section 27 provides for prohibition of deployment of teachers for 
non-educational purposes, except for decennial population census, disaster 
relief, elections to local authority, State Legislature and Parliament. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>28</number> Prohibition of private tuition by teacher. </title>No teacher 
shall engage himself or herself in private tuition or private teaching activity. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>29</number>Curriculum and evaluation procedure. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The curriculum 
and the evaluation procedure for elementary education shall be laid down by an 
academic authority to be specified by the appropriate Government, by 
notification. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The academic authority, while laying down the curriculum and the 
evaluation procedure under sub-section (1), shall take into consideration the 
following, namely: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> conformity with the values enshrined in the Constitution; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> all round development of the child; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> building up child's knowledge, potentiality and talent; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> development of physical and mental abilities to the fullest extent; 

 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> learning through activities, discovery and exploration in a child 
  friendly and child-centered manner; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> medium of instructions shall, as far as practicable, be in child's 
  mother tongue; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> making the child free of fear, trauma and anxiety and helping the child 
  to express views freely; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> comprehensive and continuous evaluation of child's understanding of 
  knowledge and his or her ability to apply the same. </subsection>

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>30</number> Examination and completion certificate. </title>
<section><number>1</number> No child 
shall be required to pass any Board examination till completion of elementary 
education. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every child completing his elementary education shall be awarded a 
certificate, in such form and in such manner, as may be prescribed. 




</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>31</number> Monitoring of child's right to education. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The 
National Commission for Protection of Child Rights constituted under Section 3, 
or, as the case may be, the State Commission for Protection of Child Rights 
constituted under Section 17, of the Commissions for Protection of Child Rights 
Act, 2005 (4 of 2006), shall, in addition to the functions assigned to them 
under that Act, also perform the following functions, namely: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> examine and review the safeguards for rights provided by or under this 
  Act and recommend measures for their effective implementation; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> inquire into complaints relating to child's right to free and 
  compulsory education; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> take necessary steps as provided under Sections 15 and 24 of the said 
  Commissions for Protection of Child Rights Act. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The said Commissions shall, while inquiring into any matters relating to 
child's right to free and compulsory education under Clause (c) of sub-section 
(1), have the same powers as assigned to them respectively under Sections 14 and 
24 of the said Commissions for Protection of Child Rights Act. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where the State Commission for Protection of Child Rights has not been 
constituted in a State, the appropriate Government may, for the purpose of 
performing the functions specified in Clauses (a) to (c) of sub-section (1), 
constitute such authority, in such manner and subject to such terms and 
conditions, as may be prescribed. 




</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>32</number> Redressal of grievances. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in Section 31, any person having any grievance relating to the right 
of a child under this Act may make a written complaint to the local authority 
having jurisdiction. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> After receiving the complaint under sub-section (1), the local authority 
shall decide the matter within a period of three months after affording a 
reasonable opportunity of being heard to the parties concerned. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Any person aggrieved by the decision of the local authority may prefer an 
appeal to the State Commission for Protection of Child Rights or the authority 
prescribed under sub-section (3) of Section 31, as the case may be. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The appeal preferred under sub-section (3) shall be decided by State 
Commission for Protection of Child Rights or the authority prescribed under 
sub-section (3) of Section 31, as the case may be, as provided under Clause (c) 
of sub-section (1) of Section 31. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>33</number> Constitution of National Advisory Council. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The 
Central Government shall constitute, by notification, a National Advisory 
Council, consisting of such number of Members, not exceeding fifteen, as the 
Central Government may deem necessary, to be appointed from amongst persons 
having knowledge and practical experience in the field of elementary education 
and child development. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The functions of the National Advisory Council shall be to advise the 
Central Government on implementation of the provisions of the Act in an 
effective manner. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The allowances and other terms and conditions of the appointment of 
Members of the National Advisory Council shall be such as may be prescribed. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>34</number> Constitution of State Advisory Council. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The State 
Government shall constitute, by notification, a State Advisory Council 
consisting of such number of Members, not exceeding fifteen, as the State 
Government may deem necessary, to be appointed from amongst persons having 
knowledge and practical experience in the field of elementary education and 
child development. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The functions of the State Advisory Council shall be to advise the State 
Government on implementation of the provisions of the Act in an effective 
manner. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The allowances and other terms and conditions of appointment of Members 
of the State Advisory Council shall be such as may be prescribed. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>35</number> Power to issue directions. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government 
may issue such guidelines to the appropriate Government or, as the case may be, 
the local authority, as it deems fit for the purposes of implementation of the 
provisions of this Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The appropriate Government may issue guidelines and give such directions, 
as it deems fit, to the local authority or the School Management Committee 
regarding implementation of the provisions of this Act. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The local authority may issue guidelines and give such directions, as it 
deems fit, to the School Management Committee regarding implementation of the 
provisions of this Act. 




</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>36</number> Previous sanction for prosecution. </title>No prosecution for 
offences punishable under sub-section (2) of Section 13, sub-section (5) of 
Section 18 and sub-section (5) of Section 19 shall be instituted except with the 
previous sanction of an officer authorised in this behalf, by the appropriate 
Government, by notification. 

</article> 

  
 <title></title>
 <article><title><number>37</number> Protection of action taken in good faith. </title>No suit or 
other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central Government, the State 
Government, the National Commission for Protection of Child Rights, the State 
Commission for Protection of Child Rights, the local authority, the School 
Management Committee or any person, in respect of anything which is in good 
faith done or intended to be done, in pursuance of this Act, or any rules or 
order made thereunder. 




</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>38</number> Power of appropriate Government to make rules. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The 
appropriate Government may, by notification, make rules, for carrying out the 
provisions of this Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
powers, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely: 

 
 <subsection><number>a</number> The Manner Of Giving Special Training And The Time-Limit Thereof, Under 
  First Proviso To Section 4; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the area or limits for establishment of a neighbourhood school, under 
  Section 6; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the manner of maintenance of records of children up to the age of 
  fourteen years, under Clause (d) of Section 9; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> the manner and extent of reimbursement of expenditure, under 
  sub-section (2) of Section 12; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> any other document for determining the age of child under sub-section 
  (1) of Section 14; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> the extended period for admission and the manner of completing study if 
  admitted after the extended period, under Section 15; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> the authority, the form and manner of making application for 
  certificate of recognition, under sub-section (1) of Section 18; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> the form, the period, the manner and the conditions for issuing 
  Certificate of Recognition, under sub-section (2) of Section 18; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> the manner of giving opportunity of hearing under second proviso to 
  sub-section (3) of Section 18; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> the other functions to be performed by School Management Committee 
  under Clause (d) of sub-section (2) of Section 21; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number> the manner of preparing School Development Plan under sub-section (1) 
  of Section 22; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number> the salary and allowances payable to, and the terms and conditions of 
  service of, teacher, under sub-section (3) of Section 23; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>m</number> the duties to be performed by the teacher under Clause (f) of 
  sub-section (1) of Section 24; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>n</number> the manner of redressing grievances of teachers under sub-section (3) 
  of Section 24; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>o</number> the form and manner of awarding certificate for completion of 
  elementary education under sub-section (2) of Section 30; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>p</number> the authority, the manner of its constitution and the terms and 
  conditions therefor, under sub-section (3) of Section 31; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>q</number> the allowances and other terms and conditions of appointment of Members 
  of the National Advisory Council under sub-section (3) of Section 33; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>r</number> the allowances and other terms and conditions of appointment of Members 
  of the State Advisory Council under sub-section (3) of  Section 34. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every rule made under this Act and every notification issued under 
Sections 20 and 23 by the Central Government shall be laid, as soon as may be 
after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a 
total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or 
more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in 
making any modification in the rule or notification or both Houses agree that 
the rule or notification should not be made, the rule or notification shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the 
case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be 
without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule or 
notification. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Every rule or notification made by the State Government under this Act 
shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before the State 
Legislatures. 

</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>