<act><tid>1789632</tid>
<title>THE USURIOUS LOANS ACT, <year>1918</year></title>

ACT NO. 10 OF <year>1918</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 22nd March, <year>1918</year>.]

An Act to give additional powers to Courts to deal in certain cases 
with usurious loans of money or in kind.

WHEREAS it is expedient to give additional powers to Courts to 
deal in certain cases with usurious loans of money or in kind; It is 
hereby enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>716363</tid>
<number> 1</number> 
<section><tid>1378446</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title and extent. This Act may be called the  
Usurious Loans Act, <year>1918</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>779234</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India except <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> (the territories  
which, immediately before the lst November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in 
  Part B States) <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>.

</section>

<section><tid>1942349</tid>
<number>3</number>The State Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, direct that it shall not apply to any area, class of persons, 
or class of transactions which it may specify in its notification.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>415836</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant 
in the subject or context,-
<section><tid>63889</tid>
<number>1</number>" Interest" means rate of interest and includes the 
return to be made over and above what was actually lent, 
whether the same is charged or sought to be recovered 
specifically by way of interest or otherwise.

</section>

<section><tid>343242</tid>
<number>2</number>" Loan" means a loan whether of money or in kind and 
includes any transaction which is, in the opinion of the 
Court, in substance a loan.

</section>

<section><tid>1534067</tid>
<number>3</number>" Suit to which this Act applies" means any suit-

<subsection><tid>1688069</tid>
<number>a</number>for the recovery of a loan made after the commencement 
of this Act; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>725550</tid>
<number>b</number>for the enforcement of any security taken or any agreement, 
whether by, way of settlement of account or otherwise, made, 
after the commencement of this Act, in

<pagefootnote><pagenum>8</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>It has been amended in the U. P. by U. P. Acts 23 of <year>1934</year> and 29 o 
<year>1930</year>, fin the C. P. by C. P. Act 11 of <year>1934</year>, in Madras by Mad. Act, 8 
of <year>1937</year> in East Punjab by E. P. Act 4 of <year>1948</year>, extended to the Union 
territory of Pondicherry by Act 26 of <year>1968</year> s. 3 and Sch.

Amended in Himachal pradesh by H. P. Act 3 of <year>1970</year>. 
Amended in Andhara pradesh by A. P. Act 24 of <year>1961</year>. 
Repeeled in its application to Bellary District by mysore Act 
14 of <year>1955</year>.

Extended to the whole of Madhya pradesh by M. D. Act 23 of <year>1958</year> 
 (when notifild).

Amended in uttar pradesh by U. P. Act 29 of <year>1976</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order. <year>1956</year>. for" Part B 
States".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>The Words" including British Baluchistan" omitted by the A. O. <year>1948</year>.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

respect of any loan made either before or after the commencement 
of this Act; <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>570941</tid>
<number>c</number>for the redemption of any security given after the com- 
mencement of this Act in respect of any loan made either 
before or after the commencement of this Act.]



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>175473</tid>
<number> 3</number> 
<section><tid>978414</tid>
<number>1</number>Re- opening of transaction. Notwithstanding anything in the  
Usury Laws Repeal Act, <year>1855</year> (28 of <year>1855</year>), where, in any suit to which 
this Act applies, whether heard ex parte or otherwise, the Court has 
reason to believe,

<subsection><tid>806932</tid>
<number>a</number>that the interest is excessive; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>324356</tid>
<number>b</number>that the transaction was, as between the parties 
thereto substantially unfair,
the Court may exercise all or any of the following powers, namely 
may,-


<subsubsection><tid>785330</tid>
<number>i</number>re- open the transaction, take an account between the 
parties and relieve the debtor of all liability in respect of 
any excessive interest

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>101946</tid>
<number>ii</number>notwithstanding any agreement, purporting to close 
previous dealings and to create a new obligation, re- open any 
account already taken between them and relieve the debtor of 
all liability in respect of any- excessive interest, and if 
anything has been paid or allowed in account in respect of 
such liability, order the creditor to repay any sum which it 
considers to be repayable in respect thereof;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1340341</tid>
<number>iii</number>set aside either wholly or in part or revise or 
alter any security given or agreement made in respect of any 
loan, and if the creditor has parted with the security, order 
him to indemnify the debtor in such manner and to such 
extent as it may deem just:
Provided that, in the exercise of these powers, the Court 
shall not-


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>785330</tid>
<number>i</number>re- open any agreement purporting to close previous 
dealings and to create a new obligation which has been 
entered into by the parties or any persons from whom they 
claim at a date more than <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> twelve] years from the date of 
the transaction;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>101946</tid>
<number>ii</number>do anything which affects any decree of a Court.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>8A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 28 of <year>1926</year>, s. 2. 
2 Subs. by a. 3, ibid., for" six".




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

Explanation.- In the case of a suit brought on a series of 
transactions the expression" the transaction" means, for the purposes 
of proviso (i), the first of such transactions.


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>411954</tid>
<number>2</number> (a) In this section" excessive" means in excess of that 
which the Court deems to be reasonable having regard to the risk 
incurred

<pagefootnote><pagenum>9</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

as it appeared, or must be taken to have appeared, to the creditor at 
the date of the loan.


<subsection><tid>1062613</tid>
<number>b</number>In considering whether interest is excessive under this sec- 
tion, the Court shall take into account any amounts charged or paid, 
whether in money or in kind, for expenses, inquiries, fines, bonuses, 
premia, renewals or any other charges, and if compound interest is 
charged, the periods at which it is calculated, and the total 
advantage which may reasonably be taken to have been expected from the 
transaction.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1944315</tid>
<number>c</number>In considering the question of risk, the Court shall take 
into account the presence or absence of security and the value 
thereof, the financial condition of the debtor and the result of any 
previous transactions of the debtor, by way of loan, so far as the 
same were known, or must be taken to have been known, to the creditor.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1984200</tid>
<number>d</number>In considering whether a transaction was substantially un- 
fair, the Court shall take into account all circumstances materially 
affecting the relations of the parties at the time of the loan or 
tending to show that the transaction was unfair, including the 
necessities or supposed necessities of the debtor at the time- of the 
loan so far as the same were known, or must be taken to have been 
known, to the creditor.
Explanation.- Interest may of itself be sufficient evidence that 
the transaction was Substantially unfair.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1634794</tid>
<number>3</number>This section shall apply to any suit, whatever its form may 
be, if such suit is substantially one for the recovery of a loan or 
for the enforcement of any agreement or security in respect of a loan 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or for the redemption of any such security].

</section>

<section><tid>1165741</tid>
<number>4</number>Nothing in this section shall affect the rights of any 
transferee for value who satisfies the Court that the transfer to him 
was bona fide, and that he had at the time of such transfer no notice 
of any fact which would have entitled the debtor as against the lender 
to relief under this section.
For the purposes of this sub- section, the word" notice" shall 
have the same meaning as is ascribed to it in section 4 of the 
Transfer of Property Act, <year>1882</year> (4 of <year>1882</year>).


</section>

<section><tid>893793</tid>
<number>5</number>Nothing in this section shall be construed as derogating 
from the existing powers or jurisdiction of any Court.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1479384</tid>
<number>4</number>Insolvency proceedings. On any application relating to the 
admission or amount of a proof of a loan in any insolvency 
proceedings, the Court may exercise the like powers as may be 
exercised under section 3 by a Court in a suit to which this Act 
applies.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>10</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 28 of <year>1926</year>, s. 3.

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>