<act><title>

The 
    Young Persons (Harmful Publications) Act, 1956</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Young Persons (Harmful Publications) Act, 1956. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends 
    to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall 
    come into force on such date as the Central Government may, by notification 
    in the Official Gazette, appoint.  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In this Act,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “harmful publication” means any book, 
    magazine, pamphlet, leaflet, newspaper or other like publication which 
    consists of stories told with the aid of pictures or without the aid of 
    pictures or wholly in pictures, being stories portraying wholly or mainly—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    the commission of offences; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    acts of violence or cruelty; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    incidents of a repulsive or horrible 
    nature;  
 
in such a way that the publication as a whole 
    would tend to corrupt a young person into whose hands it might fall, whether 
    by inciting or encouraging him to commit offences or acts of violence or 
    cruelty or in any other manner whatsoever;  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number>    “State Government” in relation to a 
    Union territory, means the administrator thereof;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “young person” means a person under the 
    age of twenty years.  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Penalty 
    for sale, etc., of harmful publications.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If a person—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    sells, lets to hire, distributes, 
    publicly exhibits or in any manner puts into circulation, any harmful 
    publication, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    for purposes of sale, hire, 
    distribution, public exhibition or circulation, prints, makes or produces or 
    has in his possession any harmful publication, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    advertises or makes known by any means 
    whatsoever that any harmful publication can be procured from or through any 
    person,  
 
he shall be punishable with imprisonment which 
    may extend to six months, or with fine, or with both.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> On a 
    conviction under this section, the court may order the destruction of all 
    the copies of the harmful publication in respect of which the conviction was 
    had and which are in the custody of court or remain in the possession or 
    power of the person convicted.  
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Power of 
    Government to declare harmful publications forfeited.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government may, if it is of opinion after consultation with the 
    principal law officer of the State, whether called the Advocate-General or 
    by any other name, that any publication is a harmful publication, declare, 
    by order notified in the Official Gazette, that every copy of such 
    publication shall be forfeited to the Government and every such notification 
    shall state the ground for the order.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Without 
    prejudice to the provisions contained in sub-section (1) of section 6, where 
    there is an order of forfeiture under sub-section (1) in respect of any 
    publication it shall be lawful for any police officer to seize the same 
    wherever found in the territories to which this Act extends.  
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Appeal 
    to High Court against order of forfeiture.—Any 
    person aggrieved by an order of forfeiture passed by the State Government 
    under section 4 may, within sixty days of the date of such order, apply to 
    the High Court to set aside such order, and upon such application the High 
    Court may pass such order as it deems fit.  
  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Power to 
    seize and destroy harmful publications.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any police officer or any other officer empowered in this behalf by the 
    State Government may seize any harmful publication.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any 
    magistrate of the first class may, by warrant, authorise any police officer 
    not below the rank of sub-inspector to enter and search any place where any 
    stock of harmful publications may be or may be resonably suspected to be, 
    and such police officer may seize any publication found in such place if in 
    his opinion it is a harmful publication.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any 
    publication seized under sub-section (1) shall be produced, as soon as may 
    be, before a magistrate of the first class, and any publication seized under 
    sub-section (2) shall be produced, as soon as may be, before the court which 
    issued the warrant.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If in the 
    opinion of the magistrate or court such publication is a harmful 
    publication, the magistrate or court may cause it to be destroyed, but if, 
    in the opinion of the magistrate or court, such publication is not a harmful 
    publication, the magistrate or court shall dispose of it in the manner 
    provided in sections 523, 524 and 525 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 
    1898 (5 of 1898).  
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>7</number> Offences under this Act to be 
      cognizable.—Notwithstanding 
      anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898), 
      any offence punishable under this Act shall be cognizable.  
  



 
</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>