<act><title>


The Railway Servants (Hours of Work and Period 
    of Rest) Rules, 20051</title> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title, commencement and application.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Railway Servants (Hours of Work and Period of 
    Rest) Rules, 2005. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> They shall 
    apply only to those railway servants to whom Chapter XIV of the Act applies. 
 



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—­  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “Act”  means the Railways Act, 1989 (24 
    of 1989);  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “full‑night” means the period between 
    10.00 p.m. and 6.00 a.m.;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “long‑on” means a period of duty over 
    eight hours in the case of “intensive” workers, over ten hours in the case 
    of “continuous” workers and over twelve hours in the case of “essentially 
    intermittent” workers;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    “ordinary rate of pay” includes—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    pay as defined in rule 1303 (F.R. 9) of 
    the Indian Railway Establishment Code, Volume II (1990 Edition) and includes 
    element of running allowance to the extent of 30 per cent of basic pay in 
    the case of running staff as defined in rule 1507 of the aforesaid Code;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    Dearness Allowance, Additional 
    Dearness Allowance and Dearness Pay, if any; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    Compensatory (City) Allowance;  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>e</number>    “Railway servants employed in 
    confidential capacity” includes—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    Stenographers working either in a 
    separate confidential cell or attached to the officers in Administrative 
    offices;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    Cypher operators;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    Confidential Assistants and Personal 
    Assistants; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    any other railway servant who may be 
    so specified by the Head of the Railway Administration to have been employed 
    in confidential capacity;  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>f</number>    “Regional Labour Commissioner” means an 
    officer appointed as such by the  Government of India in the Ministry of 
    Labour by notification in the Official Gazette;  
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    “Roadside station” means a station 
    other than­—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    an important junction station;   
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    a station with marshalling yard;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    an important terminal station;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    a station from which trains are 
    ordered as a regular measure; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>    a station where a separate goods office 
    under a supervisory Goods Clerk, in the grade of Chief Goods Clerk or of 
    higher rank sanctioned on the basis of workload in that Goods Office has 
    been provided:  
 
Provided that the Head of the Railway 
    Administration or the authority to whom he may delegate this power, may draw 
    up a list of roadside stations keeping in view the above definition;  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>h</number>    “roster” means a document which shows 
    the hours that a railway servant is expected to be on duty every day, the 
    daily as well as weekly rest and break between spells of duty in a day 
    besides other necessary particulars;  
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>    “running staff” means the staff who are 
    defined to be so in rule 1507 of Indian Railway Establishment Code, Volume 
    II (1990 Edition);  
 </section><section>
<number>j</number>    “section” means a section of the Act;   
 </section><section>
<number>k</number>    “short off” means a period of rest 
    which is—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    in the case of intensive workers—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>A</number>    less than 12 hours in a roster of six 
    hours duty; and  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>B</number>    less than 14 hours in a mixed roster of 
    6 and 8 hours duty;  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    in the case of continuous worker—less 
    than 10 hours;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    in the case of essentially 
    intermittent workers—less than 8 hours;  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>l</number>    “split duty” means duty in two or more 
    spells with intervening breaks each of half or more hour necessitated by 
    exigencies of work and when the employee is free to leave his place of duty. 
    Intervals for rest and meals shall not be breaks for the purpose of split‑duty;  
 </section><section>
<number>m</number>    ”sustained attention” as used in 
    sub‑section (b), section 130 implies mental effort.  
 
Explanation.—A Pointsman waiting for 
    the arrival of a train after setting points is required to give sustained 
    attention. Similarly, a Station Master or an Assistant Station Master is 
    generally required to pay sustained attention from the time he gives line 
    clear to the Station in rear till the time the train arrives and again from 
    the time the line clear is asked for to the time the Block Section ahead is 
    cleared. Wherever circumstances justify a different treatment, the period 
    involving sustained attention may be decided by the Controlling Authority. 
    In case of any doubt, the decision of the Head of the Department shall be 
    final;  
 </section><section>
<number>n</number>    all other words and expressions used 
    but not defined in these rules shall have the meanings respectively assigned 
    to them in the Indian Railway Establishment Code or the Act.   
  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Prescribed authority to classify the employment of railway servant.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The power to declare the employment of railway servants as “intensive” or 
    “essentially intermittent” within the meaning of section 130 shall vest in 
    the Head of the Railway Administration:
 
Provided that 
    the Head of the Railway Administration may, in his discretion, delegate the 
    power vested in him under this sub‑rule to the Chief Personnel Officer:  
 
Provided 
    further that during the period of emergency such as flood, accident, the 
    power vested in the competent authority can be exercised by an officer not 
    below the rank of senior scale.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A copy of 
    every declaration made by the prescribed authority under sub‑rule (1) shall, 
    as soon as may be, sent to the Regional Labour Commissioner concerned and, 
    in case the declaration is made by an officer other than the Head of the 
    Railway Administration, to the Head of the Railway Administration or the 
    Chief Personnel Officer, as the case may be.  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> Appeals 
    against classification.—
<section><number>1</number> Any 
    railway servant aggrieved by the declaration of classification made under 
    rule 3 may, within ninety days from the date of such declaration, prefer an 
    appeal to the Regional Labour Commissioner, who after scrutiny of relevant 
    documents or if considered necessary, after a fresh job analysis, may order 
    for a change in the classification.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any 
    railway servant or Railway Administration aggrieved by a decision of the 
    Regional Labour Commissioner may, before the expiry of ninety days from the 
    date on which the decision of the Regional Labour Commissioner is 
    communicated to him, prefer an appeal to the Secretary to the Government of 
    India in the Ministry of Labour who will dispose it of after hearing the 
    parties concerned.  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Supervisory staff.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Ministry of Labour shall, by order in writing, specify the railway servants 
    or classes of railway servants who shall be treated as supervisory staff 
    under sub‑clause (iv) of clause (c) of section 130 on the ground that the 
    railway servant holds a position of responsibility, is employed on duties 
    mainly of a supervisory character and is, from the nature of his work and 
    position, comparatively free to adjust his hours of duty or work during such 
    hours:  
 
Provided that 
    the railway servants who on the date of publication of these rules are 
    treated as supervisory staff under the rules shall continue to be treated as 
    such until the order specifying the railway servants or classes of railway 
    servants as supervisory staff is issued under this sub‑rule.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A copy of 
    every such order issued under sub‑rule (1) shall be furnished to the Chief 
    Labour Commissioner (Central), New Delhi.  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> Excluded 
    staff.—The following categories 
    of staff of the Health and Medical Department shall be treated as “excluded” 
    under sub‑clause (v) of clause (c) of section 130, namely:—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    Matrons;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    Sisters‑in‑charge;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    Midwives who are not posted on regular 
    shift duty in Railway Hospitals;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    Health Educators and District Extension 
    Educators (Male and Female);  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    Family Planning Field Workers (Male and 
    Female);  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    Lady Health Visitors;  
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    Auxiliary Nurses‑cum‑Midwives;  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    Projectionists.  
 
In addition to 
    the above, the Ministry of Railways may, by order in writing, specify any 
    other category of railway staff in any of the Departments of the Indian 
    Railways who shall be treated as “excluded” on the consideration that such 
    staff are available on call.  

  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number> Criteria 
    for determining classification of railway servants.—
<section><number>1</number>
    Continuous: All employments of railway servants except those excluded 
    from the purview of the Hours of Employment Regulations are assumed to be 
    “continuous”. Thereafter, on the basis of factual job analysis the 
    employment may be classified either as “intensive” or “essentially 
    intermittent”, as the case may be.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Intensive: The two important factors in declaring an employment as 
    “intensive” under clause (d) of section 130 of the Act are—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    strenuous nature of the work tending to 
    cause mental or physical strain; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    continuous application to such work 
    with little or no periods of relaxation.  
 
Explanation 
    I.—The term “continued 
    concentration” in clause (d) of section 130 is intended to convey that the 
    attention demanded of the railway servant concerned for a particular nature 
    of job should be exclusive not to allow any other thought or idea to enter 
    the mind and must be of such nature as to cause strain (physical or mental 
    or both) upon the railway servant concerned as a result of continuous 
    application to such work over certain period without reasonable periods of 
    respite. Thus, having regard to the entire period of duty and nature of 
    work, the prescribed authority shall, before declaring any employment as 
    “intensive”, satisfy itself that the above factors are present in the job 
    concerned. In other words, the prescribed authority shall consider whether 
    the job is of such a character that it demands continued concentration 
    without any reasonable periods of relaxation.  
 
Explanation 
    II.—Factor (ii) should be 
    considered to have been satisfied where the periods of rest, inaction or 
    relaxation do not aggregate 6 hours or more in a cycle of 24 hours or one 
    hour or more in a shift of 8 hours.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Essentially intermittent: The work of an employee is to be regarded as 
    “essentially intermittent” if his daily duty hours which should be assumed 
    to be twelve hours per day include—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    one period of inaction of not less than 
    one hour, or two such periods of not less than half an hour each, and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> various periods of inaction 
    including the period of inaction specified in clause (a) aggregating 50 per 
    cent or more, during which he is not generally called upon to display either 
    physical activities or sustained attention.  
 
Note.—In 
    assessing the workload of the “essentially intermittent” classification in 
    accordance with sub‑section (b) of section 130, periods of inaction of less 
    than 5 minutes shall be ignored.  

  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>8</number> Fixation 
    of hours of work.—The hours of 
    work of a railway servant as per roster (hereinafter referred to as the 
    rostered hours of work) may be continuous or may have short interval for 
    rest, or breaks due to exigencies of service or deployment.
 <section>
<number>1</number> Subject to 
    the limit specified in section 132 and having regard to the requirements of 
    the service and the nature of work, the Railway Administration shall fix the 
    normal rostered hours of work for the various categories of railway servants 
    in the manner indicated in these rules.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    rostered hours of work of railway servants shall consist of—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    standard hours of duty;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   additional hours as may be prescribed 
    in the case of certain categories classified as essentially intermittent; 
    and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    time required to do preparatory or 
    complementary work or both for those who are required to do such work.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    standard hours of duty for different classes of employment of railway 
    servants shall be as under:
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    
    Intensive                                      ..                42 hours a week;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    
    Continuous                                    ..                48 hours a week; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    Essentially intermittent                    ..                48 hours a week.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number>(a) Railway 
    servants having essentially intermittent class of employment shall be called 
    upon to work as per rule 8(2)(ii) additional hours as indicated below: 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    Gatemen ‘C’, Caretakers of Rest 
    Houses     
       and  Reservoirs, etc., Chowkidars and  
       Saloon Attendants
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    Railway servants posted to work 
    in                       24 additonal hours  
        Essentially intermittent 
    employment                              per week 
       at road­side stations and provided 
       with residential quarters within 0.5  
       kms from their place of duty
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   Rest of employees posted to work in 
                        12 additional hours  
       Essentially intermittent class of 
                                       per week 
       employment
 <subsubsection>
<number>b</number> Such 
    additional hours of work shall be reflected in the duty rosters of the 
    railway servants concerned. 
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> The time 
    required by various categories of staff to do preparatory or complementary 
    work or both, which includes the work of handing over and taking over 
    charge, must necessarily be carried out outside the limits laid down for 
    general working of an establishment, branch or shift and shall be determined 
    by means of job analysis of such work in respect of representative posts in 
    respective categories.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The time 
    determined under sub‑rule (5) shall be added to the standard hours of duty 
    of the staff in all the various classifications subject to maximum limit 
    prescribed below: 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    when employment is 
    intensive                                ..    3 hours a week;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    when employment is 
    continuous                              ..    6 hours a week;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    when employment is essentially 
    intermittent—
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   Gatemen ‘C’, Caretakers of Rest Houses 
    and        ..    3 hours a week;
 
Reservoirs, Chowkidars, Saloon Attendants
 
and those posted at roadside stations and
 
provided with residential quarters within
 
500 metres from their place of duty
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   Railway servants other than those 
    mentioned       ..    4½ hours a week.
 
       in sub‑clause (i)
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>7</number> The time 
    required for preparatory or complementary work by the running staff shall be 
    deemed to be 4 hours a week.
 
Notes.—(i)  Where the time assessed for 
    doing preparatory or complementary work is under 15 minutes per day, the 
    same shall not be treated as duty and shall not be exhibited in the roster; 
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number>    In the case of employment of a 
    “continuous” nature, the time assessed for doing preparatory or 
    complementary work between 15 minutes and less than 45 minutes per day 
    should be treated as half an hour’s work and such time between 45 minutes 
    and one hour per day should be treated as one hour’s work; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    In the case of intensive and 
    essentially intermittent categories of employment, such time assessed 
    between 15 minutes and 30 minutes per day shall be treated as half an hour’s 
    work; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    The time assessed for the work 
    mentioned in Note (iii) shall be reflected in the duty rosters of the 
    concerned railway servants; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>    Total hours for preparatory or 
    complementary work or both shall be so fixed to ensure that the overall duty 
    hours do not exceed the limits prescribed for respective classification in 
    section 132. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>8</number> Where 
    railway servants are required to perform split‑duty, such duty shall be 
    subject to the following conditions, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> the spells of duty shall not 
    exceed three and the number of breaks shall be limited to two; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> in the case of an employment of 
    “continuous” nature, the railway servant whose place of residence is beyond 
    1.6 kilometres from the place of duty, seven hours of split‑duty shall be 
    treated as equivalent to eight hours of normal duty. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>9</number> While 
    preparing rosters, “long on” or “short off” shall, accordingly, be avoided.
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> Where, in 
    accordance with the provisions of sub‑section (4) of section 132 or 
    sub-section (3) of section 133 and in the circumstances mentioned therein, 
    a railway servant is called upon by an order of temporary exemption made 
    under rule 9 below by the competent authority to render duty beyond the 
    hours of work fixed in accordance with the foregoing sub-rules or beyond the 
    hours prescribed in sub-sections (1), (2) and (3) of section 132, it shall 
    be the duty of the railway servant concerned to render such extra hours of duty. 
 


  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>9</number> Power to 
    make temporary exemption.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of sub-section (4) of section 132 and of 
    sub‑section (3) of section 133, Head of a Railway Administration may by 
    order in writing make temporary exemption of any railway servant or class or 
    railway servants from the provisions of sub‑sections (1), (2) and (3) of 
    section 132 and sub‑sections (1) and (2) of section 133.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Head 
    of Railway Administration may by order in writing delegate his powers under 
    sub‑rule (1) to any officer subordinate to him and whom he may deem fit to 
    exercise the powers.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A copy of 
    every order of delegation made under sub‑rule (2) shall be sent to the 
    Regional Labour Commissioner concerned.  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Principle of averaging and payment of overtime allowance.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where a railway servant is required to render extra hours of duty beyond the 
    rostered hours fixed in accordance with rule 8 or beyond the limits 
    specified for different classes of railway servant under section 132, he 
    shall be paid overtime for such extra hours of work, subject to the 
    principle of averaging as specified in sub‑rule (2).
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Averaging 
    shall be done by averaging of the hours of work over the averaging periods 
    as specified in section 132 which has been adopted to provide a reasonable 
    measure of elasticity as essential in railway working for certain classes of 
    railway servants and it shall apply to— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    running staff, 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    operating staff, 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    shift workers; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    those other railway servants whose 
    work is connected with the work of any of the categories of railway servants 
    mentioned in clauses (i), (ii) and (iii). 
 
Subject to the 
    provisions contained in sub‑section (4) of section 132, payment of overtime 
    for excess hours of work shall be made as under:
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    for the excess hours of work 
    rendered by a railway servant between the limits of prescribed rostered 
    hours of work and the hours prescribed in section 132, during the relevant 
    averaging period, payment shall be made at 11/2 times 
    the ordinary rate of pay; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    for the excess hours of work rendered 
    beyond the limits prescribed in section 132, payment shall be made at two 
    times the ordinary rate of pay. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The hourly 
    rate of overtime shall be worked out on the basis of rostered hours over the 
    relevant averaging period as under:—
 

 
 
 

 
        Hourly rate of pay  
        (for staff governed by Averaging Principle)
 

 

 
        1/30 of monthly ordinary rate of pay

 
  
  
  

 
  
 

  

 
 

 
        Hourly rate of pay  
        (For those not governed by Averaging Principle)
 

 

 
        1/30 of monthly ordinary rate of pay

 
  
  
  

 
  
 

  



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Register of extra hours of work.—The 
    particulars of all extra hours of work done by a railway servant beyond the 
    prescribed rostered hours of duty shall be recorded in a register to be 
    maintained in Form A appended to these rules by the officer authorised in 
    this behalf by the Head of the Railway Administration.  

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Periodical Rest.—
<section><number>1</number> Railway 
    servant whose employment is Intensive or Continuous shall be granted, every 
    week commencing on a Sunday, rest of not less than thirty consecutive hours 
    and those whose employment is Essentially Intermittent, shall be granted 
    rest of not less than twenty‑four consecutive hours including a full night.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>  No 
    railway servant classified as Intensive, Continuous or Essentially 
    Intermittent shall be called on duty unless one has had a rest of not less 
    than
    12, 10, 8 consecutive hours respectively after completion of the previous 
    tour of duty. Such rest shall be given as far as possible through the 
    employment of rest givers and the rest givers so provided shall be separate 
    for Continuous and Essentially Intermittent categories.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Locomotive 
    or traffic running staff shall be granted, each month, a rest of at least 
    five periods of not less than twenty-two consecutive hours each, or a rest 
    of at least four periods of not less than thirty consecutive hours each 
    including a full night. The hours of work for this purpose shall be 
    calculated from “signing on”  to “signing off”.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    locomotive and traffic running staff shall not normally be away from 
    headquarters for more than three or four days at a stretch and the periodic 
    rest for such staff shall be given at headquarters. Rest at headquarters 
    shall always include a night in bed, and as far as possible be once in every 
    ten days.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Staff on 
    duty in running trains, other than locomotive and traffic running staff such 
    as Travelling Pay Clerks and Catering Staff attached to Restaurant Cars 
    shall be given periodic rest on the scale and in the manner laid down for 
    the locomotive and traffic running staff. Some portion of the periodic rest 
    may, however, be given away from their headquarters having regard to their 
    length of trips.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    working hours and periodic rest of marine staff, other than those who are 
    governed by the Factories Act shall be regulated in the same manner as those 
    of running staff.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> In 
    accordance with clause (ii) of sub-section (2) of section 133 of the Act, 
    the Head of the Railway Administration may, with the prior approval of the 
    Ministry of Railways, specify the categories of railway servants to whom the 
    periods of rest on scales less than those laid down under sub-section (1) of 
    the said section can be prescribed.  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Compensatory periods of rest.—No 
    railway servant in respect of whom an exemption has been made under rule 9 
    shall be required to work for more than fourteen days without a period of 
    rest and shall be provided with compensatory rest within this period.  

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Appointment of Supervisors.—The 
    supervisors of Railway labour shall be appointed by the Ministry of Labour. 
    The manner of their appointment and the educational qualifications etc. 
    prescribed for the purpose will be as laid down by the Ministry of Labour 
    from time to time.  

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>15</number> Display 
    of rules and notices.—Every 
    Railway Administration shall display in a conspicuous place—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    where the railway servants work, 
    notices specifying the classification of employment of railway servants; the 
    duration of their hours of employment, their period of rest and rosters; and  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    in each station or other establishment 
    a copy of Chapter XIV of the Act and these rules in English, Hindi and in 
    local language.  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>16</number> Annual 
    Return.—Every Railway 
    Administration shall send each financial year a return in Form ‘B’ appended 
    to these rules, so as to reach the Regional Labour Commissioner not later 
    than the 15th day of May following the end of the financial year to which it 
    relates.  

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>17</number> Power 
    to make modification in special cases.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything provided in these rules, where, in the interest of 
    efficient working of the Railways, there are certain conditions of special 
    nature necessitating an immediate modification of any conditions laid down 
    under these rules to suit local conditions, such modifications which are not 
    inconsistent with any provisions of Chapter XIV of the Act, may be effected 
    with prior approval of the Ministry of Railways.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A copy of 
    each such modification shall be sent to the Regional Labour Commissioner 
    concerned.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If any 
    railway servant is adversely affected by any such modification made under 
    sub-rule (1), he may prefer an appeal before the expiry of 90 days from the 
    date of effecting such modification to the Ministry of Railways whose 
    decision thereon shall be final.  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>18</number> 
      The Railway Servants (Hours of Employment) Rules, 1961 and any orders 
      issued thereunder insofar as they are inconsistent with these rules, are 
      hereby repealed; provided that—  
 <section><number>1</number>    such repeal 
      shall not affect the previous operation of the said rules or any orders 
      made or anything done or any action taken thereunder;  
 </section><section><number>2</number>    nothing in 
      these rules shall be construed as depriving any person to whom these rules 
      apply, of any right of appeal which had accrued to him under the rules or 
      orders in force before the commencement of these rules;  
 </section><section><number>3</number>    an appeal 
      pending at the commencement of these rules against an order made before 
      such commencement shall be considered and orders thereon shall be made in 
      accordance with these rules as if such orders were made and the appeals 
      were preferred under these rules;  
 </section><section><number>4</number>    as from the 
      commencement of these rules any appeal or application for review against 
      any orders made before such commencement, shall be preferred or made under 
      these rules as if such orders were made under these rules.  
  
  </section></article><form>
 
 
  
 
 



The 
    Railway Servants (Hours of Work and Period of Rest) Rules, 2005
 



 



    Form A
 


(See rule 11)
 




Register of Extra Hours of Work
 



Register 
    prescribed under rule 11 of railway servants 

     (Hours of work and period of rest) Rules, 2004
 



 


Station :
 


Division :
 
 
  

 
 
Sl. No.
 
Month and date overtime 
        worked
 
Name and Father's Name
 
Designation
 
Classification Intensive 
        Continuous Intermittent
 
Rate of Pay
 
Rostered Hours
 
Actual Hours
 
Extra Hours Worked

 
  
  
  
  
  
  
 
 
 
 
From
 
To



 
 
 
 
From
 
To



  

 
  

 
 
(1)
 
(2)
 
(3)
 
(4)
 
(5)
 
(6)
 
(7)
 
(8)
 
(9)

 
  

 
   

 
 

 
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  


 
 

 
 

 
 
 
  

 
 
Reason for working extra 
        hours
 
Compulsory rest granted
 
Number of hours for which 
        over time payable
 
Reasons for granting 
        temporary exemption under section 132(4) and 133
 
Signature of subordinate in 
        charge granting exemption under rules
 
Amount of overtime paid and 
        date of payment
 
Remarks

 
 
(10)
 
(11)
 
(12)
 
(13)
 
(14)
 
(15)
 
(16)

 
  

 
   

 
 

 
  
  
  
  
  
  

 
  



  


</form><form>
 
 
  
 
 



The 
    Railway Servants (Hours of Work and Period of Rest) Rules, 2005
 



 



    Form B
 


(See rule 16)
 



Annual Return for the year ending 31st 
    March,.....................
 
 
  

 
  
  
  
 
Intensive
 
Continuous

 
 
Sl. No.
 
Name of Railway
 
Total Number of railway 
        servants employed
 
No.
 
Percent.
 
Running Staff
 
Other than Running Staff

 
  
  
  
  
  
 
No.
 
Percent.
 
No.
 
Percent.

 
  

 
 
(1)
 
(2)
 
(3)
 
(4)
 
(5)
 
(6)
 
(7)
 
(8)
 
(9)

 
  

 
   

 
 

 
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  

 
  

 
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  

 
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  
  

 
  

 
 
Essentially Intermittent
 
Supervisory
 
Excluded Employed in 
        confidential capacity
 
Others

 
 
No. 
 
Percent.
 
No. 
 
Percent.
 
No. 
 
Percent.
 
No. 
 
Percent.
 
Remarks

 
 
(10)
 
(11)
 
(12)
 
(13)
 
(14)
 
(15)
 
(16)
 
(17)
 
(18)


 
 

 
 

 
 

 
 
 

 
 



    Place.............................
 



    Date...............................
 


Signature of Head / Incharge
 


Railways Administrative 

 


(Seal)
 


To 
 


Regional Labour Commissioner 
    (Central)
 

 
 

 
 

 
 
 
  



  


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>