<act><tid>1006568</tid>
<title>THE FORFEITURE ACT, <year>1859</year></title>

ACT NO. 9 OF <year>1859</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 
[ 30th April, <year>1859</year>.]
An Act to provide for the adjudication of claims to property seized as 
forfeited.

Preamble.-- WHEREAS it is expedient <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> to remove doubts 
concerning the powers of officers or other persons to whom commissions 
may have been issued for the trial of heinous offences in certain 
districts, and concerning the validity of convictions and 
adjudications of forfeiture made by such officers or other persons; It 
is enacted as follows:-



<article><tid>544594</tid>
<number>1</number>t
</article>



<article><tid>544594</tid>
<number>1</number>to 15.[ Constitution, procedure, and c., of Special Commission 
Courts.] Rep. by the Repealing Act, <year>1868</year> (8 of <year>1868</year>).
<pagefootnote><pagenum>63</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been declared to be in force in the whole of India 
except Part B and merged States, and the Scheduled Distrcts, by the 
Laws Local Extent Act, <year>1874</year> (15 of <year>1874</year>), s. 3.

This Act has been extended to the Union territory of Pondicherry 
by Act 26 of <year>1968</year>, s. 3 and Sch.

It hs been extended, under s. 5 of the Scheduled Districts Act, 
<year>1874</year> (14 of <year>1874</year>), to the following Scheduled Districts, namely:-

Kumaon and Garhwal.. See Gazette of India, <year>1876</year>, Pt. I, p. 606.

This Tarai of the Province of Agara.. Ditto <year>1876</year>, Pt. I, p. 505.

It has been declared, by notification under s. 3 (b) of the 
same Act, not to be in force in the District of Lahaul. See gazette of 
India, <year>1886</year>, Pt. I, P. 301.

It has been declared by notification under s. 3 (a) of the 
Scheduled Districts Act, <year>1874</year> (14 of <year>1874</year>), to be in force in the 
folowig Scheduled Districts, namely:-

West Jalpaiguri.. See Gazette of India, <year>1881</year>, Pt. I, p. 74.

The District of Hazaribagh Ditto <year>1881</year>, Pt. I, p. 507.

The District of Lohardaga (now  
the Ranchi District, see Calcutta 
  Gazete, <year>1899</year>, I, p. 44) Ditto <year>1881</year>, Pt. I, p. 508.

The District of Manbhum Ditto <year>1881</year>, Pt. I, p. 509.

Pargana Dhalbhum in the 
District of Singhbum Ditto <year>1881</year>, Pt. I, p. 510

The Scheduled portion of 
the Mirzapur District Ditto <year>1879</year>, Pt. I, p. 383.

Jaunsar Bawar Ditto <year>1879</year>, Pt. I, p. 382.

The Scheduled Districts of 
the C. P., (now Madhya Pradesh) Ditto <year>1879</year>, Pt. I, p. 771.

The Scheduled Districts in Ganjam 
and Vizagapatam Ditto <year>1898</year>, Pt. I, p. 870.

Assam (except the north  
  Lushai Hills) Ditto <year>1897</year>, Pt. I, p. 299.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Certain words were rep. by Act 12 of <year>1891</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>281874</tid>
<number>16</number>Convictions involving forfeiture not questionable in suits 
relating to forfeited property.-- Whenever any person shall have been 
convicted of an offence for which his property was forfeited to 
Government, no Court has power in any suit or proceeding relating to 
such property to question the validity of the conviction.


</article>



<article><tid>1776845</tid>
<number>17</number>Conviction not questionable because capacity of convicting 
officer not shown.-- Whenever any person shall have been convicted as 
above by an officer having power to try and convict, the validity of 
any such conviction shall not be questioned upon the ground that the 
record of the conviction does not show in what capacity such officer 
acted, or that it represents him to have acted in a different capacity 
from that in which he had power to convict.


</article>



<article><tid>1730021</tid>
<number>18</number>Attachment without adjudication of forfeiture not 
questionable unless offender be acquitted within one year, etc.-- 
Whenever any property shall have been attached or seized without 
either conviction or an adjudication of forfeiture by any officer of 
Government as property forfeited or liable to be forfeited to 
Government for an offence for which, upon conviction, the property of 
the offender would be forfeited, the validity of such attachment or 
seizure shall not be called in question by any Court or other 
authority in any suit or proceeding, unless the offender or alleged 
offender shall, within one year after the seizure of his property has 
surrendered himself for trial, and upon trial before a competent Court 
shall have been or shall be acquitted of the offence, and shall prove 
to the satisfaction of the Court that he did not escape or keep out of 
the way for the purpose of evading justice.
Exemption of pardoned persons.-- Nothing in this section shall 
extend to persons entitled to pardon upon Her Majesty' s proclamation 
published in the Calcutta Gazette Extraordinary, dated the Ist of 
November, <year>1858</year>, or, to any person who having surrendered himself 
within the period of one year after the seizure of his property shall 
be <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> duly discharged] without a prosecution.





</article>



<article><tid>754211</tid>
<number>20</number>Rights of parties not charged with offence involving 
forfeiture. Proviso.-- Nothing in this Act shall be held to affect the 
rights of parties not charged with any offence for which upon 
conviction the property of the offender is forfeited in respect of any 
property attached or seized as forfeited or liable to be forfeited to 
Government: Provided that no suit brought by any party in respect of 
such property shall be entertained unless it be instituted within the 
period of one year from the date of the attachment of seizure of the 
property to which the suit relates.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>64</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" discharged by order of Govt.".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


 1 TO

Constitution, procedure, and c.., of Special Commission Courts.

 1 to 15.[ Constitution, procedure, and c.., of Special Commission 
Courts.] Rep. by the Repealing Act, <year>1868</year> (8 of <year>1868</year>).



</article>



<article><tid>281874</tid>
<number>16</number>Conviction involving forfeiture not question able in suits 
relating to forfeited property. Whenever any person shall have been 
convicted of an offence for which his property was forfeited to 
Government, no Court has

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>999999</number> This Act has been declared to be in force in the whole of India 
except Part B and merged States, and the Scheduled Districts, by the 
Laws Local Extent Act, <year>1874</year> (15 of <year>1874</year>), s. 3.

It has been extended, under s. 5 of the Scheduled. Districts 
Act, <year>1874</year> (14 of <year>1874</year>), to the following Scheduled Districts, namely:-

Kumaon and Garhwal See Gazette of India, <year>1876</year>, Pt. I, p. 606.

The Tarai of the Province of Agra Ditto <year>1876</year>, Pt. I. p. 
505.

It has been declared, by notification under s. 3 (b) of the same 
Act, not to be in force in the District of Lahaul. See Gazette of 
India, <year>1886</year>, Pt. I, p. 301.

It has been declared, by notification under s. 3 (a) of the 
Scheduled Districts Act, <year>1874</year> (14 of <year>1874</year>), to be in force in the 
following Scheduled Districts, namely:-

West Jalpaiguri............. See Gazette ofIndia, <year>1881</year>, Pt. I. p. 74.

The District of Hazaribagh Ditto <year>1881</year>, Pt. I, p. 507. 
The District of Lohardaga (now  
the Ranchi District, see 
Calcutta Gazette, <year>1899</year> Pt. I, 
  p. 44) Ditto <year>1881</year>, Pt. I, p. 508.

The District of Manbhum Ditto <year>1881</year>, Pt. I, p. 509.

Pargana Dhalbhum in the Dis- 
trict of Singbhum Ditto <year>1881</year>, Pt. I, P. 510.

The Scheduled portion of the

Mirzapur District Ditto <year>1879</year>, Pt. I, p. 383.

Jaunsar Bawar Ditto <year>1879</year>, Pt. I, p. 382.

Extended to the Union territory of 
Pondicherry by Act 26 of <year>1968</year>, S. 3 and 
schedule

The Scheduled Districts of 
the C. P. Ditto <year>1879</year>, Pt. I, p. 771. 
 (Now Madhya Pradesh)

The scheduled Districts in 
Ganjam and Vizagapatam Ditto <year>1898</year>, Pt. I, p. 870.

Assam (except the North Lushai  
  Hills) Ditto <year>1897</year>, Pt. I, p. 299.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Certain words were rep. by Act 12 of <year>1891</year>.





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

power in any suit or proceeding relating to such property to question 
the validity of the conviction.



</article>



<article><tid>1776845</tid>
<number>17</number>Conviction not questionable because capacity of convicting 
officer not shown. Whenever any person shall have been convicted as 
above by an officer having power to try and convict, the validity of 
any such conviction shall not be questioned upon the ground that the 
record of the conviction does not show in what capacity such officer 
acted, or that it represents him to have acted in a different capacity 
from that in which he had power to convict.


</article>



<article><tid>1730021</tid>
<number>18</number>Attachment without adjudication of forfeiture not 
questionable unless offender be acquitted within one year, etc. 
Whenever any property shall have been attached or seized without 
either conviction or an adjudication of forfeiture by any officer of 
Government as property forfeited or liable to be forfeited to 
Government for an offence for which, upon conviction, the property of 
the offender would be forfeited, the validity of such attachment or 
seizure shall not be called in question by any Court or other 
authority in any suit or proceeding, unless the offender or alleged 
offender shall, within one year after the seizure of his property has 
surrendered himself for trial, and upon trial before a competent Court 
shall have been or shall be acquitted of the offence, and shall prove 
to the satisfaction of the Court that he did not escape or keep out of 
the way for the purpose of evading justice.
Exemption of pardoned persons. Nothing in this section shall 
extend to persons entitled to pardon upon Her Majesty' s proclamation 
published in the Calcutta Gazette Extraordinary, dated the 1st of 
November, <year>1858</year>, or to any person who having surrendered himself within 
the period of one year after the seizure of his property shall be 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> duly discharged] without a prosecution.



</article>



<article><tid>567781</tid>
<number>19</number>[ Release of property attached as forfeited.] Rep. by the Re- 
pealing Act, <year>1868</year> (8 of <year>1868</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>754211</tid>
<number>20</number>Rights of parties not charged with offence involving 
forfeiture Proviso. Nothing in this Act shall be held to affect the 
rights of parties not charged with any offence for which upon 
conviction the property of the offender is forfeited in respect of any 
property attached or seized as forfeited or liable to be forfeited to 
Government: Provided that no suit brought by any party in respect of 
such property shall be entertained unless it be instituted within the 
period of one year from the date of the attachment or seizure of the 
property to which the suit relates.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for" discharged by order of Govt.".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>