<act><tid>308107</tid>
<title>THE INDIAN MUSEUM ACT, <year>1910</year></title>

ACT NO. 10 OF <year>1910</year>
[ 18th March, <year>1910</year>.]

An Act to consolidate and amend the law relating to the Indian Museum.

WHEREAS it is expedient to consolidate and amend the law relating 
to the Indian Museum; It is hereby enacted as follows:-

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1197576</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>230584</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Indian Museum Act, <year>1910</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1661082</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> date as the Central 
Government, by notification in the Official Gazette, may direct.
INCORPORATION OF THE TRUSTEES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1596166</tid>
<number> 2</number> Constitution and incorporation of the Trustees of the Indian 
Museum. <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>
<section><tid>450908</tid>
<number>1</number>The Trustees of the Indian Museum (hereinafter referred   
  to as the Trustees) shall be-

<subsection><tid>7427</tid>
<number>a</number>the Governor of West Bengal, ex officio chairman:

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>613810</tid>
<number>b</number>the Secretary to the Government of India in the 
Ministry concerned with matters relating to the Indian 
Museum, ex officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>61009</tid>
<number>c</number>the Mayor of the Corporation of Calcutta, ex officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1568873</tid>
<number>d</number>the Vice- Chancellor of the University of Calcutta, ex 
officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>136696</tid>
<number>e</number>the Accountant- General, West Bengal, ex officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1226418</tid>
<number>f</number>four persons to be nominated by the Central Government, 
one of whom shall be a representative of commerce and 
industry chosen in consultation with the Government of 
West Bengal;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1212933</tid>
<number>g</number>one person to be nominated by the Government of West 
Bengal;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>611584</tid>
<number>h</number>one person to be nominated by the Council of the 
Asiatic Society, Calcutta:
Provided that if any of the Trustees referred to in clauses 
 (b), (c), (d) and (e) is unable to attend any meeting of the 
Trustees, he may, with the previous approval of the 
Chairman, authorise a person in writing to do so.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>16</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1st June, <year>1910</year>, see Gazette of India, <year>1910</year>, Pt. I, p. 411. 
2. Subs. by Act 45 of <year>1960</year>, s. 2, for sub- section (1).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1808568</tid>
<number>2</number>The Trustees shall be a body corporate, by the name of" The 
Trustees of the Indian Museum", with perpetual succession and a common 
seal, and in that name shall sue and be sued, and shall have power to 
acquire and hold property, to enter into contracts, and to do all acts 
necessary for and consistent with the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1510411</tid>
<number>3</number>The nominated Trustees shall, save as herein otherwise 
provided, hold office for a period of three years:
Provided that the authority nominating a Trustee may extend his 
term of office for one or more like periods.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1418094</tid>
<number> 3</number> Minimum number of Trustees and quorum.
<section><tid>1079569</tid>
<number>1</number>The powers of the  
said body corporate may only be exercised so long and so often as 
there are <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> six] members thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>1641351</tid>
<number>2</number>The quorum necessary for the transaction of business at a 
meeting of the Trustees shall not be less than <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> four].



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1793817</tid>
<number> 4</number> Power to appoint new Trustees. If a nominated Trustee-
<section><tid>115429</tid>
<number>a</number>dies, or

</section>

<section><tid>1469474</tid>
<number>b</number>is absent from the meetings of the Trustees for more 
than twelve consecutive months, or

</section>

<section><tid>435135</tid>
<number>c</number>desires to be discharged, or

</section>

<section><tid>582055</tid>
<number>d</number>refuses or becomes incapable to act, or

</section>

<section><tid>590727</tid>
<number>e</number>is appointed to perform the duties of <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> any of the 
offices specified in clauses (a) to (e) of sub- section 
 (1) of section 2],
the authority which nominated the Trustee may nominate a new 
Trustee in his place.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1687335</tid>
<number>5</number>[ Vacation of office by existing Trustees.] Rep. by the Indian 
Museum (Amendment) Act. <year>1960</year> (45 of <year>1960</year>), s. 5.
PROPERTY AND POWERS OF THE TRUSTEES



</article>



<article><tid>996765</tid>
<number> 6</number> Property vested in or placed under the control of the 
Trustees.
<section><tid>609661</tid>
<number>1</number>All the property, whether movable or immovable, which at  
the commencement of this Act is held by the Trustees of the Indian 
Museum constituted by the <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Indian Museum Act, <year>1876</year> (22 of <year>1876</year>), on 
trust for the purposes of the said Museum shall, together with any 
such
<pagefootnote><pagenum>17</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 45 of <year>1960</year>, s. 3, for" nine". 
2. Subs. by s. 3, ibid., for" six". 
3. Subs. by s. 4, ibid., for" any office specified in section 2, 
clause (a)". 
4. Rep. by this Act, s. 17.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


property which may hereinafter be given, bequeathed, transferred or 
acquired for the said purposes, vest in the Trustees of the Indian 
Museum constituted by this Act on trust for the purposes of the said 
Museum:

Provided that the Trustees may expend the capital of any portion 
of such property which may consist of money on the maintenance, 
improvement and enlargement of the collections deposited in, presented 
to or purchased for, the said Museum or otherwise for the purposes of 
the same as they may think fit.


</section>

<section><tid>726707</tid>
<number>2</number>The Trustees shall have the exclusive possession, occupation 
and control, for the purposes of such trust, of the land specified in 
the schedule, including any buildings which may have been, or may 
here- after be, erected thereon, other than those portions thereof 
which have been set apart by the Trustees for the records and offices 
of the Geological Survey of India.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1291482</tid>
<number> 7</number> Power to Trustees to exchange, sell and destroy articles in 
collections. Subject to the provisions of any bye- laws made in this 
behalf, the Trustees may, from time to time,-
<section><tid>221321</tid>
<number>a</number>deliver, by way of loan, to any person the whole or any 
portion of, or any article contained in, any collection 
vested in them under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>552476</tid>
<number>b</number>exchange or sell duplicates of articles contained in 
any such collection and take or purchase, in the place 
of such duplicates, such articles as may in their 
opinion be worthy of preservation in the Museum;

</section>

<section><tid>1952615</tid>
<number>c</number>present duplicates of articles contained in any such 
collection to other Museums in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India]; and

</section>

<section><tid>609671</tid>
<number>d</number>remove and destroy any article contained in any such 
collection.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1907099</tid>
<number> 8</number> Power to Trustees to make bye- laws.
<section><tid>1766077</tid>
<number>1</number>The Trustees may from  
time to time, with the previous sanction of the Central Government, 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> make, by notification in the Official Gazette, bye- laws] consistent 
with this Act <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> and the rules made thereunder] for any purpose 
necessary for the execution of their trust.

</section>

<section><tid>825518</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> bye- laws] may provide for-

<subsection><tid>795808</tid>
<number>a</number>the summoning, holding and adjournment of general and 
special meetings of the Trustees;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>18</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" the Provinces". 
2. Subs. by Act 20 of <year>1983</year>, s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 15- 3- <year>1984</year>). 
3. Ins. by Act 45 of <year>1960</year>, s. 6. 
4. Subs. by s. 6, ibid., for" rules".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>896227</tid>
<number>b</number>the securing of the attendance of Trustees at such 
meetings;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1998149</tid>
<number>c</number>the provision and keeping of minute- books and account- 
books;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1755322</tid>
<number>d</number>the compiling of catalogues;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1087982</tid>
<number>e</number>the lending of articles contained in the collections 
vested in the Trustees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>446450</tid>
<number>f</number>the exchange and sale, and the presentation to other 
Museums in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India], of duplicates of articles 
contained in such collections;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1475547</tid>
<number>g</number>the removal and destruction of articles contained in 
such collections; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1844712</tid>
<number>h</number>the general management of the Museum.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1260359</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> The Central Government shall cause every bye- law made 
under this section to be laid as soon as may be after it is made, 
before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total 
period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two 
or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the bye- law 
or both Houses agree that the bye- law should not be made, the bye- law 
shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no 
effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that bye- law.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>171617</tid>
<number> 9</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Powers of Trustees to appoint officers and servants.
<section><tid>1976448</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Subject to the provisions of sub- section (2), the Trustees may appoint 
such officers and servants as they may consider necessary or proper 
for the care or management of the trust- property, and determine their 
functions.

</section>

<section><tid>1793569</tid>
<number>2</number>The recruitment and the conditions of service of such 
officers and servants shall be regulated by rules made under this 
Act.]
DUTIES OF THE TRUSTEES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>151967</tid>
<number>10</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Budget. The Trustees shall, by such date in each financial 
year as may be specified by the Central Government, submit to that 
Government for approval, in the form specified by that Government in 
consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India, the 
budget of the next financial year, showing the estimated receipts and 
expenditure during the next financial year.


</article>



<article><tid>1475047</tid>
<number> 10A</number> Annual report and accounts.
<section><tid>12419</tid>
<number>1</number>The Trustees shall, as soon  
as possible after the commencement of each financial year, submit-

<subsection><tid>1766113</tid>
<number>a</number>to the Central Government within such time or date as 
may be specified by the Central Government, a report 
giving a true and full account of their activities 
during the previous financial year and an account of 
the activities likely to be undertaken during the 
current financial year;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>19</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" the Provinces". 
2. Subs. by Act 45 of <year>1960</year>, s. 7, for s. 9. 
3. Subs. by s. 8, ibid., for s. 10. 
4. Ins. by Act 20 of <year>1903</year>, s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 15- 3- <year>1984</year>)


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1664503</tid>
<number>b</number>to such auditor as the Central Government may appoint 
in this behalf, accounts of all moneys expended by the 
Trustees during the previous financial year, supported 
by the necessary vouchers.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1688851</tid>
<number>2</number>The Trustees shall cause such report and accounts to be 
published annually for general information.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>519969</tid>
<number> 11</number> Collections of Asiatic society to be kept distinguished in 
the Museum.
<section><tid>240039</tid>
<number>1</number>The Trustees shall cause every article in the  
collections in the said Indian Museum formerly belonging to the 
Asiatic Society of Bengal <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> (now known as the Asiatic Society,  
  Calcutta)] and all additions that may hereafter be made thereto 
otherwise than by purchase under section 6, to be marked and numbered 
and (subject to the provisions contained in sections 7 and 16) to be 
kept and preserved in the said Museum with such marks and numbers.

</section>

<section><tid>64377</tid>
<number>2</number>An inventory of such additions shall be made by the said 
Society, one copy whereof shall be signed by the Trustees and 
delivered to the said Society, and another copy shall be signed by the 
Council of the said Society and delivered to the Trustees, and shall 
be kept by them along with the inventory delivered to the predecessors 
in office of the Trustees when the said collections were deposited in 
the said Museum.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>442719</tid>
<number>12</number>Articles received in exchange or purchased and moneys 
realised from sale to be held on trust. All objects taken in exchange 
and articles purchased under section 7 and all moneys realised from 
sales made in accordance with the terms of the same section shall be 
held on trust and subject to powers and declarations corresponding as 
nearly as may be with the trusts, powers and declarations by this Act 
limited and declared.
SUPPLEMENTAL PROVISIONS



</article>



<article><tid>562655</tid>
<number> 12A</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Power of Central Government to issue directions to 
Trustees.
<section><tid>453996</tid>
<number>1</number>In the discharge of their functions under this Act, the  
Trustees shall be bound by such directions on questions of policy as 
the Central Government may give to them from time to time:
Provided that the Trustees shall be given an opportunity to 
express their views before any direction is given under this sub- 
section.


</section>

<section><tid>750557</tid>
<number>2</number>The decision of the Central Government whether a question is 
one of policy or not shall be final.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>20</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 45 of <year>1960</year>, s. 9. 
2. Ins. by s. 10, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>720770</tid>
<number>13</number>Officers under Act to be public servants. All officers and 
servants appointed under this Act shall be deemed to be public 
servants within the meaning of the Indian Penal code; <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> (45 of  
  <year>1860</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>627139</tid>
<number>14</number>Power to Trustees to keep collections not belonging to them. 
Notwithstanding anything hereinbefore contained, the Trustees may, if 
they think fit, with the previous sanction of the Central Government 
and subject in each case to such conditions as it may approve and to 
such rules as it may prescribe, assume the custody and administration 
of collections which are not the property of the Trustees for the 
purposes of their trust under this Act, and keep and preserve such 
collections either in the Indian Museum or elsewhere:
Provided that if the trust constituted by this Act is at any time 
determined, any such collections shall not by reason of their then 
being in the Indian Museum become the property of Government.



</article>



<article><tid>295175</tid>
<number>15</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Power to Trustees to part with certain property in their 
possession. Subject to such conditions as the Central Government may 
approve, the Trustees may deliver possession of the whole or any part 
of the property described in the schedule to such person as that 
Government may appoint.]


</article>



<article><tid>682347</tid>
<number> 15A</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1285142</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, in  
with the Trustees, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules 
to carry out the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>775000</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>252163</tid>
<number>a</number>the recruitment and the conditions of service of the 
officers and servants of the Museum;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1750049</tid>
<number>b</number>the form and manner in which the accounts of the Museum 
may be maintained and the manner in which such accounts 
may be audited;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1725577</tid>
<number>c</number>the circumstances in which and the conditions subject 
to which the Trustees may assume the custody and 
administration of any collections referred to in 
section 14 and keep and preserve such collections;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>20A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Certain words omitted by Act 45 of <year>1960</year>, s. 11. 
2. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for the original section. 
3. Ins. by Act 45 of <year>1960</year>, s. 12.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>142721</tid>
<number>d</number>the conditions subject to which the Trustees may 
deliver possession of any property in their possession 
to any other person.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1264514</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as 
may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is in 
one session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised 
in one session or <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in two or more successive sessions, and if, 
before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or 
the successive sessions aforesaid], both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule, or both Houses agree that the rule should 
not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however that 
any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1721030</tid>
<number> 16</number> Property in collections on determination of trust. If the 
trust constituted by this Act is at any time determined,-
<section><tid>1416791</tid>
<number>a</number>the collections and additions mentioned in section 11 
shall become the property of the said Asiatic Society 
or their assigns, and

</section>

<section><tid>1446335</tid>
<number>b</number>all the other collections then in the said Indian 
Museum shall, save as otherwise provided by section 14, 
become the property of Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>494738</tid>
<number>17</number>[ Repeals.] Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, <year>1914</year> (10  
  of <year>1914</year>), s. 3 and Sch. II.
</article>



 </act>