<act> 
 
 THE COMPETITION APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (TERM OF THE SELECTION COMMITTEE AND THE MANNER OF SELECTION OF PANEL 
    OF NAMES) RULES, 2008
  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be called the Competition Appellate Tribunal (Term of the Selection Committee and the Manner of Selection of Panel of Names) Rules, 2008. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of their publication in the Official Gazette. 




</section></article> 
 
 THE COMPETITION APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (TERM OF THE SELECTION COMMITTEE AND THE MANNER OF SELECTION OF PANEL 
    OF NAMES) RULES, 2008
  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> "Act" means the Competition Act, 2002 (12 of 2003); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> "Committee" means the Selection Committee constituted under sub-section (1) of section 53E of the Act. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Words and expressions used but not defined in these rules and defined in the Competition Act, 2002 (12 of 2003) shall have the same meaning assigned to them in that Act. 



</section></article> 
 
 THE COMPETITION APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (TERM OF THE SELECTION COMMITTEE AND THE MANNER OF SELECTION OF PANEL 
    OF NAMES) RULES, 2008
  
 <article> <title><number>3</number> Term of the Committee. </title>-The term of the Committee constituted under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 53E shall be for a period of one year from the date of its constitution. 



</section></article> 
 
 THE COMPETITION APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (TERM OF THE SELECTION COMMITTEE AND THE MANNER OF SELECTION OF PANEL 
    OF NAMES) RULES, 2008
  
  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Manner of Selection of a Panel of Names. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> Whenever any vacancy of Chairperson or other Members of the Appellate Tribunal exists or as and when such vacancy arises or is likely to arise, the Central Government may make a reference to the Committee in respect of such vacancy or vacancies for recommendation of a panel of names. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Committee shall devise its own procedure for selecting the persons for inclusion in the panel of names to be recommended for appointment as the Chairperson or a Member of the Appellate Tribunal. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Committee shall make its recommendations to the Central Government, within a period not exceeding one hundred and twenty days from the date of reference made under sub-rule (1). 
 </section><section><number>4</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[An officer not below the level of Joint Secretary] nominated by the Ministry of Corporate Affairs shall be the Convener of the Committee. 




</section></article> 
 
 THE COMPETITION APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (TERM OF THE SELECTION COMMITTEE AND THE MANNER OF SELECTION OF PANEL 
    OF NAMES) RULES, 2008
  
  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Functions of Committee. </title>-The Committee shall recommend a panel which may contain upto three names, selected under sub-rule (2) of rule 4, in respect of each vacancy that has been referred to the Committee. 



</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Came into force on 19-5-2008.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 260(E), dated 20th April, 2009, for “The Joint Secretary” (w.e.f. 
  20-4-2009).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>