<act><tid>1695780</tid>
<title>THE FOREIGN AWARDS (RECOGNITION ANDENFORCEMENT) ACT, <year>1961</year> 1</title>

ACT NO. 45 OF <year>1961</year>
[ 30th November, <year>1961</year>.]

An Act to enable effect to be given to the Convention on the 
Recognition and Enforcement of Foreign Arbitral Awards, done at New 
York, on the tenth day of June, <year>1958</year>, to which India is a party and for 
purposes connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twelfth Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>1873914</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>799969</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Foreign Awards (Recognition and Enforcement) Act, <year>1961</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1649453</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1479794</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definition. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires," foreign award" means an award on differences between 
persons arising out of legal relationships, whether contractual or 
not, considered as commercial under the law in force in India, made on 
or after the 11th day of October, <year>1960</year>-
<section><tid>155767</tid>
<number>a</number>in pursuance of an agreement in writing for arbitration 
to which the Convention set forth in the Schedule applies, 
and

</section>

<section><tid>1217974</tid>
<number>b</number>in one of such territories as the Central Government, 
being satisfied that reciprocal provisions have been made, 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare to be 
territories to which the said Convention applies.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1594965</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Stay of proceedings in respect of matters to be referred to 
arbitration. Notwithstanding anything contained in the Arbitration 
Act, <year>1940</year> (10 of <year>1940</year>), or in the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5  
  of <year>1908</year>), if any party to an agreement to which Article II of the 
Convention set forth in the Schedule applies, or any person claiming 
through or under him commences any legal proceedings in any court 
against any other party to the agreement or any person claiming 
through or under him in respect of any matter agreed to be referred to 
arbitration in such agreement, any party to such legal proceedings may, 
at any time after appearance and before filing a written statement or 
taking any other step in the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>34</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Extended to the Union territory of Pondicherry by Act 26 of 
<year>1968</year>, s. 3 and Sch.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 47 of <year>1973</year>, s. 2, for section 3.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

proceedings, apply to the Court to stay the proceedings and the Court, 
unless satisfied that the agreement is null and void, inoperative 
or. incapable of being performed or that there is not, in fact, any 
dispute between the parties with regard to the matter agreed to be 
referred, shall make an order staying the proceedings.]



</article>



<article><tid>1399829</tid>
<number> 4</number> Effect of foreign awards.
<section><tid>1668613</tid>
<number>1</number>A foreign award shall, subject  
to the provisions of this Act, be enforceable in India as if it were 
an award made on a matter referred to arbitration in India.

</section>

<section><tid>521420</tid>
<number>2</number>Any foreign award which would be enforceable under this Act 
shall be treated as binding for all purposes on the persons as between 
whom it was made, and may accordingly be relied on by any of those 
persons by way of defence, set off or otherwise in any legal 
proceedings in India and any references in this Act to enforcing a 
foreign award shall be construed as including references to relying on 
an award.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1895974</tid>
<number> 5</number> Filing of foreign award in court.
<section><tid>1800693</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person interested  
in a foreign award may apply to any court having jurisdiction over 
the subject- matter of the award that the award be filed in court.

</section>

<section><tid>768402</tid>
<number>2</number>The application shall be in writing and shall be numbered 
and registered as a suit between the applicant as plaintiff and the 
other parties as defendants.

</section>

<section><tid>336242</tid>
<number>3</number>The court shall direct notice to be given to the parties to 
the arbitration, other than the applicant, requiring them to show 
cause, within a time specified why the award should not be filed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1648362</tid>
<number> 6</number> Enforcement of foreign award.
<section><tid>1005403</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the court is satisfied  
that the foreign award is enforceable under this Act, the court shall 
order the award to be filed and shall proceed to pronounce judgment 
according to the award.

</section>

<section><tid>951941</tid>
<number>2</number>Upon the judgment so pronounced a decree shall follow, and 
no appeal shall lie from such decree except in so far as the decree is 
in excess of or not in accordance with the award.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>296505</tid>
<number> 7</number> Conditions for enforcement of foreign awards.
<section><tid>1429612</tid>
<number>1</number>A foreign  
award may not be enforced under this Act-

<subsection><tid>1680388</tid>
<number>a</number>if the party against whom it is sought to enforce the 
award proves to the court dealing with the case that-

<subsubsection><tid>1503110</tid>
<number>i</number>the parties to the agreement were, under the law 
applicable to them, under some incapacity, or the said 
agreement is not valid under the law to which the 
parties have subjected it, or failing any indication 
thereon, under the law of the country where the award 
was made; or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>35</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>703460</tid>
<number>ii</number>that party was not given proper notice of the 
appointment of the arbitrator or of the arbitration 
proceedings or was otherwise unable to present his case; 
or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>166745</tid>
<number>iii</number>the award deals with questions not referred or 
contains decisions on matters beyond the scope of the 
agreement:
Provided that if the decisions on matters submitted to 
arbitration can be separated from those not submitted, 
that part of the award which contains decisions on 
matters submitted to arbitration may be enforced; or


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>674347</tid>
<number>iv</number>the composition of the arbitral authority or the 
arbitral procedure was not in accordance with the 
agreement of the parties or, failing such agreement, was 
not in accordance with the law of the country where the 
arbitration took place; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>652757</tid>
<number>v</number>the award has not yet become binding on the 
parties or has been set aside or suspended by a com- 
petent authority of the country in which, or under the 
law of which, that award was made; or

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>765603</tid>
<number>b</number>if the court dealing with the case is satisfied that-

<subsubsection><tid>1835420</tid>
<number>i</number>the subject- matter of the difference is not cap- 
able of settlement by arbitration under the law of India; 
or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>923481</tid>
<number>ii</number>the enforcement of the award will be contrary to 
public policy.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>440885</tid>
<number>2</number>If the court before which a foreign award is sought to be 
relied upon is satisfied that an application for the setting aside or 
suspension of the award has been made to a competent authority 
referred to in sub- clause (v) of clause (a) of sub- section (1), the 
court may, if it deems proper, adjourn the decision on the enforcement 
of the award and may also, on the application of the party claiming 
enforcement of the award, order the other party to furnish suitable 
security.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>97579</tid>
<number> 8</number> Evidence.
<section><tid>756838</tid>
<number>1</number>The party applying for the enforcement of a  
foreign award shall, at the time of the application, produce-

<subsection><tid>904440</tid>
<number>a</number>the original award or a copy thereof, duly 
authenticated in the manner required by the law of the 
country in which it was made;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>36</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1358229</tid>
<number>b</number>the original agreement for arbitration or a duly 
certified copy thereof; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1545232</tid>
<number>c</number>such evidence as may be necessary to prove that the 
award is a foreign award.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1070586</tid>
<number>2</number>If the award or agreement requiring to be produced under 
sub- section (1) is in a foreign language, the party seeking to enforce 
the award shall produce a translation into English certified as 
correct by a diplomatic or consular agent of the country to which that 
party belongs or certified as correct in such other manner as may be 
sufficient according to the law in force in India.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>882364</tid>
<number> 9</number> Saving. Nothing in this Act shall-
<section><tid>1819967</tid>
<number>a</number>prejudice any rights which any person would have had of 
enforcing in India of any award or of availing himself in 
India of any award if this Act had not been passed; or

</section>

<section><tid>1082899</tid>
<number>b</number>apply to any award made on an arbitration agreement 
governed by the law of India.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>854245</tid>
<number>10</number>Repeal. The Arbitration (Protocol and Convention) Act, <year>1937</year> 
 (6 of <year>1937</year>), shall cease to have effect in relation to foreign 
awards to which this Act applies.


</article>



<article><tid>1911486</tid>
<number> 11</number> Rule making power of the High Court. The High Court may make 
rules consistent with this Act as to-
<section><tid>975849</tid>
<number>a</number>the filing of foreign awards and all proceedings 
consequent thereon or incidental thereto;

</section>

<section><tid>227714</tid>
<number>b</number>the evidence which must be furnished by a party seeking 
to enforce a foreign award under this Act; and

</section>

<section><tid>1210435</tid>
<number>c</number>generally, all proceedings in court under this Act.


</section>

</article>



 </act>