<act><title>


THE National Highways Tribunal (Financial and Administrative Powers) Rules, 20041</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called by the National Highways Tribunal (Financial and 
Administrative Powers) Rules, 2004.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date on which the Act come into force.
 
 


</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
        
<number>a</number>  “Act” means the Control of National Highways (Land and Traffic) Act, 
2002 (13 of 2003).
 </section><section>
        
<number>b</number>  “Tribunal” means the National Highways Tribunal established under 
sub-section (1) of Section 5 of the Act.
 </section><section>
        
<number>c</number>  “Presiding Officer” means a person appointed as Presiding Officer of 
the Tribunal under sub-section (1) of Section 6 of the Act;
 </section><section>
        
<number>d</number>  Words and expressions used and not defined in these rules but defined 
in the Act shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act;
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Powers of the 
Presiding Officer.—The 
Presiding Officer shall have the same powers as are conferred on a  Head of 
Department in respect of the General Financial Rules 1963, the Delegation of the 
Financial Powers Rules 1978, the Fundamental Rules, the Supplementary Rules, the 
Central Civil Services (Leave) Rules, 1972 the Central Civil Services (Joining 
Time) Rules, 1979, the Central Services (Pension) Rules, 1972, the  Central  
Civil  Services (Conduct) Rules, 1964, the Central Civil Services 
(Classification, Control and Appeal) Rules, 1965 and the General Provident Fund 
(Central Services) Rules, 1960:
 
Provided that the exercise 
of powers by the Presiding Officer under these rules these shall be subject to 
such instructions as may be issued from time to time by the Central  
Government.
 
 
 
 
</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>