<act><title>THE MOTOR TRANSPORT WORKERS ACT, 1961 </title> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title, extent, 
commencement and application.—
<section><number>1</number> 
This Act may be called the Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961.
 </section><section><number>2</number> It extends to the whole of 
India 

1[***].
 </section><section><number>3</number> It shall come into force on 
such date, not being later than the 31st day of March, 1962, as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint and different 
dates may be appointed for different States:
 

2[Provided that it shall come into force 
in the State of Jammu and Kashmir on the commencement of the Central Labour Laws 
(Extension to Jammu and Kashmir) Act, 1970 (51 of 1970).]
 </section><section><number>4</number> It applies to every motor 
transport undertaking employing five or more motor transport workers:
 Provided that the State 
Government may, after giving not less than two months’ notice of its intention 
so to do, by notification in the Official Gazette, apply all or any of the 
provisions of this Act to any motor transport undertaking employing less than 
five motor transport workers.
  




</section></article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  “adolescent” means a person who has completed 
his 1[fourteenth] 
year but has not completed his eighteenth year;
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  “adult” means a person who has completed his 
eighteenth year;
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  “child” means a person who has not completed his
1[fourteenth] 
year;
 </section><section>       <number>d</number>  “day” means a period of twenty-four hours 
beginning at midnight:
                  Provided that where a motor transport 
worker’s duty commences before midnight but extends beyond midnight, the 
following day for him shall be deemed to be the period of twenty-four hours 
beginning when such duty ends, and the hours he has worked after midnight shall 
be counted in the previous day;
 </section><section>       <number>e</number>  “employer” means, in relation to any motor 
transport undertaking, the person who, or the authority which, has the ultimate 
control over the affairs of the motor transport undertaking, and where the said 
affairs are entrusted to any other person whether called a manager, managing 
director, managing agent or by any other name, such other person;
 </section><section>        <number>f</number>  “hours of work” means the time during which a 
motor transport worker is at the disposal of the employer or of any other person 
entitled to claim his services and includes—
 <subsection>             <number>i</number>  the time spent in work done during the 
running time of the transport vehicle;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>ii</number>  the time spent in subsidiary work; and
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>iii</number>  periods of mere attendance at terminals 
of less than fifteen minutes.
               Explanation.—For the purposes of this 
clause—
 <subsubsection>            <number>1</number>  “running time” in relation to a working day 
means the time from the moment a transport vehicle starts functioning at the 
beginning of the working day until the moment when the transport vehicle ceases 
to function at the end of the working day, excluding any time during which the 
running of the transport vehicle is interrupted for a period exceeding such 
duration as may be prescribed during which period the persons who drive, or 
perform any other work in connection with the transport vehicle are free to 
dispose of their time as they please or are engaged in subsidiary work;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            <number>2</number> “subsidiary work” means work in connection 
with a transport vehicle, its passengers or its load which is done outside the 
running time of the transport vehicle, including in particular—
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>                  <number>i</number>  work in connection with accounts, the 
paying in of cash, the signing of registers, the handing in of service sheets, 
the checking of tickets and other similar work;
 </subsection><subsection>                 <number>ii</number>  the taking over and garaging of the 
transport vehicles;
 </subsection><subsection>                 <number>iii</number>  travelling from the place where a 
person signs on to the place where he takes over the transport vehicle and from 
the place where he leaves the transport vehicle to the place where he signs off;
 </subsection><subsection>                <number>iv</number>  work in connection with the upkeep and 
repair of the transport vehicle; and
 </subsection><subsection>                 <number>v</number>  the loading and unloading of the 
transport vehicle;
 <subsubsection>            <number>3</number>  “period of mere attendance” means the 
period during which a person remains at his post solely in order to reply to 
possible calls or to resume action at the time fixed in the duty schedule;
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>       <number>g</number>  “motor transport undertaking” means a motor 
transport undertaking engaged in carrying passengers or goods or both by road 
for hire or reward, and includes a private carrier;
 </section><section>       <number>h</number>  “motor transport worker” means a person who is 
employed in a motor transport undertaking directly or through an agency, whether 
for wages or not, to work in a professional capacity on a transport vehicle or 
to attend to duties in connection with the arrival, departure, loading or 
unloading of such transport vehicle and includes a driver, conductor, cleaner, 
station staff, line checking staff, booking clerk, cash clerk, depot clerk, 
time-keeper, watchman or attendant, but except in section 8 does not include—
 </section><section>             <number>i</number>  any such person who is employed in a 
factory as defined in the Factories Act, 1948 (63 of 1948);
 <subsection>            <number>ii</number>  any such person to whom the provisions of 
any law for the time being in force regulating the conditions of service of 
persons employed in shops or commercial establishments apply;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>i</number>  “prescribed” means prescribed by rules made 
under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>j</number>  “qualified medical practitioner” means a person 
having a certificate granted by an authority specified in the Schedule to the 
Indian Medical Degrees Act, 1916 (7 of 1916), or notified under section 3 of 
that Act or specified in the Schedules to the Indian Medical Council Act, 1956 
(102 of 1956), and includes any person having a certificate granted under any 
Provincial or State Medical Council Act;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>k</number>  “spread-over” means the period between the 
commencement of duty on any day and the termination of duty on that day;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>l</number>  “wages’’ has the meaning assigned to it in 
clause (vi) of section 2 of the Payment of Wages Act, 1936 (4 of 1936);
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>m</number>  “week” means the period between midnight on 
Saturday night and midnight on the succeeding Saturday night;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>n</number>  all other words and expressions used but not 
defined in this Act and defined in the Motor Vehicles Act, 1939 (4 of 1939), 
shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in that Act.
 State Amendment
 Tamil Nadu.—In section 2, in clauses (a) and (c), 
for the word “fifteenth” substitute the word “sixteenth”.
 [Vide Tamil Nadu Act 54 of 1975, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 
1-1-1970)].
 <subsubsection><number>Ed</number> In clauses (a) and (b), the word fifteenth” has been 
substituted by the word “fourteenth” vide Central Act 61 of 1986, sec. 26 
(w.e.f. 23-12-1986).








</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>3</number> Registration of motor 
transport undertaking.—
<section><number>1</number> Every 
employer of a motor transport undertaking to which this Act applies shall have 
the undertaking registered under this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> An application for the 
registration of a motor transport undertaking shall be made by the employer to 
the prescribed authority in such form and within such time as may be prescribed.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where a motor transport 
undertaking is registered under this Act, there shall be issued to the employer 
a certificate of registration containing such particulars as may be prescribed.
</section></article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
 
 
 <article><number>4</number> Chief inspector and 
inspectors.—
<section><number>1</number> The State Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint for the State a duly 
qualified person to be the chief inspector and as many duly qualified persons to 
be inspectors subordinate to the chief inspector as it thinks fit.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The chief inspector may 
declare the local limits within which inspectors shall exercise their powers 
under this Act, and may himself exercise the powers of an inspector within such 
local limits as may be assigned to him by the State Government.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The chief inspector and all 
inspectors shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of section 
21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).






















</section></article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>5</number> Powers of the inspectors.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to such conditions and restrictions as the State Government may by 
general or special order impose, the chief inspector or an inspector may—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  make such examination and inquiry as he thinks 
fit in order to ascertain whether the provisions of this Act or rules made 
thereunder are being observed in the case of any motor transport undertaking, 
and for that purpose require the driver of a transport vehicle to cause the 
transport vehicle to stop and remain stationary so long as may reasonably be 
necessary;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  with such assistance, if any, as he thinks fit, 
enter, inspect and search any premises which he has reason to believe is under 
use or occupation of any motor transport undertaking at any reasonable time for 
the purpose of carrying out the objects of the Act;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  examine any motor transport worker employed in a 
motor transport undertaking or require the production of any register or other 
document maintained in pursuance of this Act, and take on the spot or otherwise 
statements of any person which he may consider necessary for carrying out the 
purposes of this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  seize or take copy of such registers or 
documents or portions thereof as he may consider relevant in respect of an 
offence under this Act which he has reason to believe has been committed by an 
employer;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number>  exercise such other powers as may be prescribed:
 Provided that no person shall be 
compelled under this sub-section to answer any question or make any statement 
tending to incriminate himself.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The provisions of the Code 
of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898), shall, so far as may be, apply to any 
search or seizure under this section as they apply to any search or seizure made 
under the authority of a warrant issued under section 98 of the said Code.
</section></article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>6</number> Facilities to be afforded 
to inspectors.—Every employer shall 
afford the chief inspector and an inspector all reasonable facilities for making 
any entry, inspection, examination or inquiry under this Act.
</article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>7</number> Certifying surgeons.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The State Government may appoint qualified medical practitioners to be 
certifying surgeons for the purposes of this Act within such local limits or for 
such motor transport undertakings or class of motor transport undertakings as it 
may assign to them respectively.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The certifying surgeon shall 
perform such duties as may be prescribed in connection with—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  the examination and certification of motor 
transport workers;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  the exercise of such medical supervision as may 
be prescribed where adolescents are, or are to be, employed as motor transport 
workers in any work in any motor transport undertaking which is likely to cause 
injury to their health.
</subsection></section></article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>8</number> Canteens.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The State Government may make rules requiring that in every place wherein one 
hundred motor transport workers or more employed in a motor transport 
undertaking ordinarily call on duty during every day, one or more canteens shall 
be provided and maintained by the employer for the use of the motor transport 
workers.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Without prejudice to the 
generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  the date by which the canteens shall be 
provided;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  the number of canteens that shall be provided 
and the standards in respect of construction, accommodation, furniture and other 
equipment of the canteens;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  the foodstuffs which may be served therein and 
the charges which may be made therefor;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  the constitution of a managing committee for a 
canteen and the representation of the motor transport workers in the management 
of the canteen.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> The State Government may, 
subject to such conditions as it may impose, delegate to the chief inspector the 
power to make rules with reference to clause (c) of sub-section (2).
</section></article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>9</number> Rest rooms.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In every place wherein motor transport workers employed in a motor transport 
undertaking are required to halt at night, there shall be provided and 
maintained by the employer for the use of those motor transport workers such 
number of rest rooms or such other suitable alternative accommodation, as may be 
prescribed.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The rest rooms or the 
alternative accommodation to be provided under sub-section (1) shall be 
sufficiently lighted and ventilated and shall be maintained in a clean and 
comfortable condition.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The State Government may 
prescribe the standards in respect of construction, accommodation, furniture and 
other equipment of rest rooms or the alternative accommodation to be provided 
under this section.
</section></article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>10</number> Uniforms.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules 
requiring an employer of a motor transport undertaking to provide for the 
drivers, conductors and line checking staff employed in that undertaking such 
number and type of uniforms, raincoats or other like amenities for their 
protection from rain or cold as may be specified in the rules.
 </section><section><number>2</number> There shall be paid to the 
drivers, conductors and line checking staff by the employer an allowance for 
washing of uniforms provided under sub-section (1) at such rates as may be 
prescribed:
 Provided that no such allowance 
shall be payable by an employer who has made at his own cost adequate 
arrangements for the washing of uniforms.
 State Amendment
 Madhya Pradesh.—For section 10, substitute the 
following section, namely:—
                     “10. Uniform.—(1) The State 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules requiring an 
employer of a motor transport undertaking to provide for the drivers, 
conductors, cleaners, watchmen and line-checking staff employed in that 
undertaking such number and type of uniforms, rain-coats or other like amenities 
for their protection from rain or cold as may be specified in the rules.
 </section><section>                    <number>2</number> There shall be paid to drivers, 
conductors, cleaners, watchmen, and the line-checking staff by the employer an 
allowance for washing the uniforms provided under sub-section (1) at such rates 
as may be prescribed:
                     Provided that no such allowance shall 
be payable by an employer who has made at his own cost adequate arrangements for 
the washing of uniforms.”
 [Vide Madhya Pradesh Act 18 of 1967, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 
1-6-1968).]
</section></article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>11</number> Medical facilities.—There 
shall be provided and maintained by the employer so as to be readily available 
such medical facilities for the motor transport workers at such operating 
centres and halting stations as may be prescribed by the State Government.
</article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>12</number> First-aid facilities.—
<section><number>1</number> 
There shall be provided and maintained by the employer so as to be readily 
accessible during all working hours a first-aid box equipped with the prescribed 
contents in every transport vehicle.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Nothing except the 
prescribed contents shall be kept in a first-aid box.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The first-aid box shall be 
kept in the charge of the driver or the conductor of the transport vehicle who 
shall be provided facilities for training in the use thereof.
</section></article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>13</number> Hours of work for adult 
motor transport workers.—No adult 
motor transport worker shall be required or allowed to work for more than eight 
hours in any day and forty-eight hours in any week:
 Provided that where any such 
motor transport worker is engaged in the running of any motor transport service 
on such long distance routes, or on such festive and other occasions as may be 
notified in the prescribed manner by the prescribed authority, the employer may, 
with the approval of such authority, require or allow such motor transport 
worker to work for more than eight hours in any day or forty-eight hours in any 
week but in no case for more than ten hours in a day and fifty-four hours in a 
week, as the case may be:
 Provided further that in the 
case of a breakdown or dislocation of a motor transport service or interruption 
of traffic or act of God, the employer may, subject to such conditions and 
limitations as may be prescribed, require or allow any such motor transport 
worker to work for more than eight hours in any day or more than forty-eight 
hours in any week.
</article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>14</number> Hours of work for 
adolescents employed as motor transport workers.—No 
adolescent shall be employed or required to work as a motor transport worker in 
any motor transport undertaking—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  for more than six hours a day including rest 
interval of half-an-hour;
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  between the hours of 10 P.M. and 6 A.M.
</section></article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>15</number> Daily intervals for rest.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The hours of work in relation to adult motor transport workers on each day shall 
be so fixed that no period of work shall exceed five hours and that no such 
motor transport worker shall work for more than five hours before he has had an 
interval for rest for at least half-an-hour:
 Provided that the provisions of 
this sub-section in so far as they relate to interval for rest shall not apply 
to a motor transport worker who is not required to work for more than six hours 
on that day.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The hours of work on each 
day shall be so fixed that a motor transport worker is, except in any case 
referred to in the second proviso to section 13, allowed a period of rest of at 
least nine consecutive hours between the termination of duty on any one day and 
the commencement of duty on the next following day.
</section></article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>16</number> Spread-over.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The hours of work of an adult motor transport worker shall, except in any case 
referred to in the second proviso to section 13, be so arranged that inclusive 
of interval for rest under section 15, they shall not spread-over more than 
twelve hours in any day.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The hours of work of an 
adolescent motor transport worker shall be so arranged that inclusive of 
interval for rest under section 14, they shall not spread-over more than nine 
hours in any day.
</section></article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>17</number> Split duty.—Subject 
to the other provisions contained in this Act, the hours of work of a motor 
transport worker shall not be split into more than two spells on any day.
</article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>18</number> Notice of hours of work.—
<section><number>1</number> 
There shall be displayed and correctly maintained by every employer a notice of 
hours of work in such form and manner as may be prescribed showing clearly for 
every day the hours during which motor transport workers may be required to 
work.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Subject to the other 
provisions contained in this Act, no such motor transport worker shall be 
required or allowed to work otherwise than in accordance with the notice of 
hours of work so displayed.
</section></article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>19</number> Weekly rest.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules 
providing for a day of rest in every period of seven days, which shall be 
allowed to all motor transport workers.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in sub-section (1), an employer may, in order to prevent any 
dislocation of a motor transport service, require a motor transport worker to 
work on any day of rest which is not a holiday so, however, that the motor 
transport worker does not work for more than ten days consecutively without a 
holiday for a whole day intervening.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Nothing contained in 
sub-section (1) shall apply to any motor transport worker whose total period of 
employment including any day spent on leave is less than six days.
</section></article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>20</number> Compensatory day of rest.—Where, 
as a result of any exemption granted to an employer under the provisions of this 
Act from the operation of section 19, a motor transport worker is deprived of 
any of the days of rest to which he is entitled under that section, the motor 
transport worker shall be allowed within the month in which the days of rest are 
due to him or within two months immediately following that month, compensatory 
days of rest of equal number to the days of rest so lost.
 State Amendment
 West Bengal.—After section 20, insert the following 
section, namely:—
                     
“20A. Issue of appointment letter.—Notwithstanding anything in any 
contract, customer usage to the contrary, in every motor transport undertaking 
engaged in carrying passengers and goods, the employer shall issue to the motor 
transport worker a letter of appointment specifying therein—
 <section>              
<number>i</number> name of the employer, (ii) the address of the employer, (iii) the 
registration number of the motor transport undertaking, (iv) the name and 
address of the motor transport worker with designation (v) the date of 
appointment of the motor transport worker, (vi) the term of appointment, that is 
to say, whether appointed on permanent or temporary or casual or any other 
basis, (vii) the rate, or the basis of calculation, of wages, if any, and (viii) 
the total emoluments payable,
 and the letter of appointment shall bear the date and 
signature of the employer.”
 [Vide West Bengal Act 46 of 1978, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 
27-12-1978) and West Bengal Act 29 of 1979, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 17-10-1979)].
</section></article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>21</number> Prohibition of employment 
of children.—No child shall be 
required or allowed to work in any capacity in any motor transport undertaking.
</article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>22</number> Adolescents employed as 
motor transport workers to carry tokens.—No 
adolescent shall be required or allowed to work as a motor transport worker in 
any motor transport undertaking unless—
 <section><number>a</number> a certificate of fitness 
granted with reference to him under section 23 is in the custody of the 
employer; and
 </section><section><number>b</number> such adolescent carries with 
him while he is at work a token giving a reference to such certificate.
</section></article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>23</number> Certificate of fitness.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A certifying surgeon shall, on the application of any adolescent or his parent 
or guardian accompanied by a document signed by the employer or any other person 
on his behalf that such person will be employed as a motor transport worker in a 
motor transport undertaking if certified to be fit for that work, or on the 
application of the employer or any other person on his behalf with reference to 
any adolescent intending to work, examine such person and ascertain his fitness 
for work as a motor transport worker.
 </section><section><number>2</number> A certificate of fitness 
granted under this section shall be valid for a period of twelve months from the 
date thereof, but may be renewed.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Any fee payable for a 
certificate under this section shall be paid by the employer and shall not be 
recoverable from the adolescent, his parent or guardian.
</section></article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>24</number> Power to require medical 
examination.—Where an inspector is of 
opinion that a motor transport worker working in any motor transport undertaking 
without a certificate of fitness is an adolescent, the inspector may serve on 
the employer a notice requiring that such adolescent motor transport worker 
shall be examined by a certifying surgeon and such adolescent motor transport 
worker shall not, if the inspector so directs, be employed or permitted to work 
in any motor transport undertaking until he has been so examined and has been 
granted a certificate of fitness under section 23.
</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>25</number> Act 4 of 1936 to apply to payment of wages to motor transport workers .—</title>The Payment of Wages Act, 1936 (4 of 1936), as in force for the time being, shall apply to motor transport workers engaged in a motor transport undertaking as it applies to wages payable in an industrial establishment as if the said Act had been extended to the payment of wages of such motor transport workers by a notification of the State Government under sub-section (5) of section 1 thereof, and as if a motor transport undertaking were an industrial establishment within the meaning of the said Act.


</article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>26</number> Extra wages for overtime.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where an adult motor transport worker works for more than eight hours in any day 
in any case referred to in the first proviso to section 13 or where he is 
required to work on any day of rest under sub-section (2) of section 19, he 
shall be entitled to wages at the rate of twice his ordinary rate of wages in 
respect of the overtime work or the work done on the day of rest, as the case 
may be.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where an adult motor 
transport worker works for more than eight hours in any day in any case referred 
to in the second proviso to section 13, he shall be entitled to wages in respect 
of the overtime work at such rates as may be prescribed.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where an adolescent motor 
transport worker is required to work on any day of rest under sub-section (2) of 
section 19, he shall be entitled to wages at the rate of twice his ordinary rate 
of wages in respect of the work done on the day of rest.
 </section><section><number>4</number> For the purposes of this 
section, “ordinary rate of wages” in relation to a motor transport worker means 
his basic wages plus dearness allowance.


</section></article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>27</number> Annual leave with wages.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Without prejudice to such holidays as may be prescribed, every motor transport 
worker who has worked for a period of two hundred and forty days or more in a 
motor transport undertaking during a calendar year shall be allowed during the 
subsequent calendar year leave with wages for a number of days calculated at the 
rate of—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  if an adult, 
one day for every twenty days of work performed by him during the previous 
calendar year; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  if an 
adolescent, one day for every fifteen days of work performed by him during the 
previous calendar year.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> A motor transport worker 
whose service commences otherwise than on the first day of January shall be 
entitled to leave with wages at the rate laid down in clause (a) or, as the case 
may be, clause (b) of sub-section (1) if he has worked for two-thirds of the 
total number of days in the remainder of the calendar year.
 </section><section><number>3</number> If a motor transport worker 
is discharged or dismissed from service during the course of the year, he shall 
be entitled to leave with wages at the rate laid down in sub-section (1), even 
if he has not worked for the entire period specified in sub-section (1) or 
sub-section (2) entitling him to earned leave.
 </section><section><number>4</number> In calculating leave under 
this section, fraction of leave of half a day or more shall be treated as one 
full day’s leave, and fraction of less than half a day shall be omitted.
 </section><section><number>5</number> If a motor transport worker 
does not in any one calendar year take the whole of the leave allowed to him 
under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2), as the case may be, any leave not 
taken by him shall be added to the leave to be allowed to him in the succeeding 
calendar year:
 Provided that the total number 
of days of leave that may be carried forward to a succeeding year shall not 
exceed thirty in the case of an adult or forty in the case of an adolescent.
 </section><section><number>6</number> In this section “calendar 
year” means the year commencing on the first day of January.
 Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this section, leave shall not include weekly holidays or 
holidays for festival or other similar occasions whether occurring during or at 
either end of the period of leave.
</section></article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>28</number> Wages during leave 
period.—
<section><number>1</number> For the leave allowed to 
a motor transport worker under section 27, he shall be paid at the rate equal to 
the daily average of his total full time wages for the days on which he worked 
during the month immediately preceding his leave, exclusive of any overtime 
earnings and bonus, if any, but inclusive of dearness allowance and the cash 
equivalent of the advantage, if any, accruing by the concessional supply by the 
employer of foodgrains for the day on which he worked.
 </section><section><number>2</number> A motor transport worker who 
has been allowed leave for not less than four days under section 27 shall, on an 
application made by him in this behalf to the employer, be paid in advance, 
before his leave begins, an approximate amount equivalent to the wages payable 
to him for the period of his leave and any amount so paid shall be adjusted 
against the wages due to him for the aforesaid period of leave.
 </section><section><number>3</number> If a motor transport worker 
is not granted leave to which he is entitled under sub-section (3) of section 
27, he shall be paid wages in lieu thereof at the rates specified in sub-section 
(1).
</section></article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>29</number> Obstructions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Whoever obstructs an inspector in the discharge of his duties under this Act or 
refuses or wilfully neglects to afford the inspector any reasonable facility for 
making any inspection, examination or inquiry authorised by or under this Act in 
relation to any motor transport undertaking shall be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to three months, or with fine which may 
extend to five hundred rupees, or with both.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Whoever wilfully refuses to 
produce on the demand of an inspector any register or other document kept in 
pursuance of this Act, or prevents or attempts to prevent or does anything which 
he has reason to believe is likely to prevent any person from appearing before 
or being examined by an inspector acting in pursuance of his duties under this 
Act, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three 
months, or with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, or with both.
</section></article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>30</number> Use of false certificate 
of fitness.—Whoever knowingly uses or 
attempts to use as a certificate of fitness granted to himself under section 23 
a certificate granted to another person under that section, or having been 
granted a certificate of fitness to himself, knowingly allows it to be used, or 
an attempt to use it to be made, by another person, shall be punishable with 
imprisonment which may extend to one month, or with fine which may extend to 
fifty rupees, or with both.
</article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>31</number> Contravention of 
provisions regarding employment of motor transport workers.—Whoever, 
except as otherwise permitted by or under this Act, contravenes any provision of 
this Act or of any rules made thereunder, prohibiting, restricting or regulating 
the employment of persons in a motor transport undertaking, shall be punishable 
with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three months, or with fine 
which may extend to five hundred rupees, or with both, and in the case of a 
continuing contravention with an additional fine which may extend to 
seventy-five rupees for every day during which such contravention continues 
after conviction for the first such contravention.
</article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>32</number> Other offences.—Whoever 
wilfully disobeys any direction lawfully given by any person or authority 
empowered under this Act to give such direction or contravenes any of the 
provisions of this Act or of any rules made thereunder for which no other 
penalty is elsewhere provided by or under this Act shall be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to three months, or with fine which may 
extend to five hundred rupees, or with both.
</article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>33</number> Enhanced penalty after 
previous conviction.—If any person 
who has been convicted of any offence punishable under this Act is again guilty 
of an offence involving a contravention of the same provision, he shall be 
punishable on a subsequent conviction with imprisonment which may extend to six 
months, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both:
 Provided that for the purposes 
of this section no cognizance shall be taken of any conviction made more than 
two years before the commission of the offence which is being punished.
</article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>34</number> Offences by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If the person committing an offence under this Act is a company, the company as 
well as every person in charge of, and responsible to, the company for the 
conduct of its business at the time of the commission of the offence shall be 
deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against 
and punished accordingly:
 Provided that nothing contained 
in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to any punishment if he 
proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or that he exercised 
all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in sub-section (1), where an offence under this Act has been committed 
by a company and it is proved that the offence has been committed with the 
consent or connivance of, or that the commission of the offence is attributable 
to any neglect on the part of any director, manager, managing agent or any other 
officer of the company, such director, manager, managing agent or such other 
officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to 
be proceeded against and punished accordingly.
 Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this section,—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  “company” 
means any body corporate and includes a firm or other association of 
individuals; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  “director”, 
in relation to a firm, means a partner in the firm.
</subsection></section></article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>35</number> Cognizance of offences.—No 
court shall take cognizance of any offence under this Act, except on complaint 
made by, or with previous sanction in writing of, the inspector and no court 
inferior to that of a Presidency magistrate or a magistrate of the first class 
shall try any offence punishable under this Act.
 State Amendment
 Madhya Pradesh.—After section 35, insert the 
following section, namely:—
                     
“35A. Summary disposal of cases.—
<section><number>1</number> A court taking cognizance of an offence 
under section 30 shall state upon the summons to be served on the accused person 
that he—
 <subsection>             
<number>a</number> may appear by pleader and not in person; or
 </subsection><subsection>             
<number>b</number> may, by specified date prior to the hearing of the charge, plead guilty to 
the charge by registered letter acknowledgment and remit to the court, such sum 
as the court may, subject to the maximum limit of fine prescribed for the said 
offence, specify.
 </subsection></section><section>                    
<number>2</number> Where an accused person pleads guilty and remits the sum in accordance with 
the provisions of sub-section (1) no further proceedings in respect of the 
offence shall be taken against him.”
 [Vide Madhya Pradesh Act 18 of 1967, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 
1-6-1968)].
</section></article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>36</number> Limitation of 
prosecutions.—No court shall take 
cognizance of an offence punishable under this Act unless the complaint thereof 
is made within three months from the date on which the alleged commission of the 
offence came to the knowledge of an inspector:
 Provided that where the offence 
consists of disobeying a written order made by an inspector, complaint thereof 
may be made within six months of the date on which the offence is alleged to 
have been committed.
</article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 
1961
  
 <article><number>37</number> Effect of laws and 
agreements inconsistent with this Act.—
<section><number>1</number> The provisions of this Act shall have effect 
notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained in any other law or in 
the terms of any award, agreement or contract of service, whether made before or 
after the commencement of this Act:
 Provided that where under any such 
award, agreement, contract of service or otherwise a motor transport worker is 
entitled to benefits in respect of any matter which are more favourable to him 
than those to which he would be entitled under this Act, the motor transport 
worker shall continue to be entitled to the more favourable benefits in respect 
of that matter, notwithstanding that he receives benefits in respect of other 
matters under this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Nothing contained in this Act 
shall be construed as precluding any motor transport worker from entering into 
an agreement with an employer for granting him rights or privileges in respect 
of any matter which are more favourable to him than those to which he would be 
entitled under this Act.</section></article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>38</number> Exemptions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Nothing contained in this Act shall apply to or in relation to any transport 
vehicle—
 <subsection>        <number>i</number>  used 
for the transport of sick or injured persons;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>ii</number>  used 
for any purpose connected with the security of India, or the security of a 
State, or the maintenance of public order.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Without prejudice to the 
provisions of sub-section (1), the State Government may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, direct that subject to such conditions and restrictions, if 
any, as may be specified in the notification, the provisions of this Act or the 
rules made thereunder shall not apply to—
 <subsection>        <number>i</number>  any 
motor transport workers who, in the opinion of the State Government, hold 
positions of supervision or management in any motor transport undertaking,
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>ii</number>  any 
part-time motor transport worker, and 
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number>  any class 
of employers:
 Provided that before issuing any 
order under this sub-section, the State Government shall send a copy thereof to 
the Central Government.
</subsection></section></article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>39</number> Powers to give 
directions.—The Central Government 
may give directions to the Government of any State as to the carrying into 
execution in the State of the provisions contained in this Act.
</article> 
 The Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961
  
 <article><number>40</number> Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The State Government may, subject to the condition of previous publication


1[by notification in the Official 
Gazette] make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act:
 Provided that the date to be 
specified under clause (3) of section 23 of the General Clauses Act, 1897 (10 of 
1897), shall not be less than six weeks from the date on which the draft of the 
proposed rules was published.
 </section><section><number>2</number> In particular, and without 
prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, any such rules may provide 
for—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  the form of 
application for the registration of a motor transport undertaking, the time 
within which and the authority to which such application may be made;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  the grant of 
a certificate of registration in respect of a motor transport undertaking and 
the fees payable for such registration;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  the 
qualifications required in respect of the chief inspector and inspector;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  the powers 
which may be exercised by inspectors and the manner in which such powers may be 
exercised;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number>  the medical 
supervision which may be exercised by certifying surgeons;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>f</number>  
appeals, from any order of the chief inspector or inspector and the form in 
which, the time within which and the authorities to which, such appeals may be 
preferred;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>g</number>  the time 
within which facilities required by this Act to be provided and maintained may 
be so provided;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>h</number>  the medical 
facilities that should be provided for motor transport workers;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>i</number>  the 
type of equipment that should be provided in the first-aid boxes;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>j</number>  the 
manner in which long distance routes, festive and other occasions shall be 
notified by the prescribed authority;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>k</number>  the 
conditions and limitations subject to which any motor transport worker may be 
required or allowed to work for more than eight hours in any day or more than 
forty-eight hours in any week in any case referred to in the second proviso to 
section 13;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>l</number>  the 
form and manner in which notices of period of work shall be displayed and 
maintained;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>m</number>  the rates of 
extra wages in respect of the overtime work done by a motor transport worker in 
any case referred to in the second proviso to section 13;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>n</number>  the registers 
which should be maintained by employers and the returns, whether occasional or 
periodical, as in the opinion of the State Government may be required for the 
purposes of this Act; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>o</number>  any other 
matter which has to be, or may be, prescribed.
 

2[(3) Every rule made by the State 
Government under this Act, shall be laid, as soon as it is made, before the 
State Legislature.]








</subsection></section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>