<act> 
 The Foreign Exchange Management (Adjudication Proceedings 
and Appeal) Rules, 20001
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Foreign Exchange Management (Adjudication 
Proceedings and Appeal) Rules, 2000.
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force 
on the 1st day of June, 2000.
  


</section></article> 
 The Foreign Exchange Management (Adjudication Proceedings 
and Appeal) Rules, 2000
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>         <number>a</number>  “Act” means the Foreign Exchange Management 
Act, 1999 (42 of 1999);
 </section><section>         <number>b</number>  “Adjudicating Authority” means an officer 
appointed by the Central Government under sub-section (1) of section 16 of the 
Act;
 </section><section>         <number>c</number>  “applicant“ means an aggrieved person who 
makes an appeal before Special Director (Appeals) or Appellate Tribunal, as the 
case may be;
 </section><section>         <number>d</number>  “Appellate Tribunal” means the Appellate 
Tribunal for Foreign Exchange established under section 18 of the Act;
 </section><section>         <number>e</number>  “Form” means form appended to these rules;
 </section><section>          <number>f</number>  “section” means a section of the Act;
 </section><section>         <number>g</number>  “Special Director (Appeals)” means Special 
Director (Appeals) appointed by the Central Government under sub-section (1) of 
section 17 of the Act;
 </section><section>         <number>h</number> all other words and expressions used in these 
rules and not defined but defined in the Act, shall have the meaning 
respectively assigned to them in the Act.
</section></article> 
 The Foreign Exchange Management (Adjudication Proceedings 
and Appeal) Rules, 2000
  
 <article><number>3</number> Appointment of 
Adjudicating Authority.—The Central 
Government may, by an order published in the Official Gazette, appoint as many 
officers of the Central Government as it may think fit, as the Adjudicating 
Authorities for holding inquiry under the provisions of Chapter IV of the Act.
</article> 
 The Foreign Exchange Management (Adjudication Proceedings 
and Appeal) Rules, 2000
  
 <article><number>4</number> Holding of inquiry.—
<section><number>1</number> 
For the purpose of adjudicating under section 13 of the Act whether any person 
has committed any contravention as specified in that section of the Act, the 
Adjudicating Authority shall, issue a notice to such person requiring him to 
show cause within such period as may be specified in the notice (being not less 
than ten days from the date of service thereof) why an inquiry should not be 
held against him.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every notice under sub-rule 
(1) to any such person shall indicate the nature of contravention alleged to 
have been committed by him.
 </section><section><number>3</number> After considering the cause, 
if any, shown by such person, the Adjudicating Authority is of the opinion that 
an inquiry should be held, he shall issue a notice fixing a date for the 
appearance of that person either personally or through his legal practitioner or 
a chartered accountant duly authorised by him.
 </section><section><number>4</number> On the date fixed, the 
Adjudicating Authority shall explain to the person proceeded against or his 
legal practitioner or the chartered accountant, as the case may be, the 
contravention, alleged to have been committed by such person indicating the 
provisions of the Act or of rules, regulations, notifications, direction or 
orders or any condition subject to which an authorisation is issued by the 
Reserve Bank of India in respect of which contravention is alleged to have taken 
place.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Adjudicating Authority 
shall, then, given an opportunity to such person to produce such documents or 
evidence as he may consider relevant to the inquiry and if necessary, the 
hearing may be adjourned to future date and in taking such evidence the 
Adjudicating Authority shall not be bound to observe the provisions of the 
Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872).
 </section><section><number>6</number> While holding an inquiry 
under this rule the Adjudicating Authority shall have the power to summon and 
enforce attendance of any person acquainted with the facts and circumstances of 
the case to give evidence or to produce any document which in the opinion of the 
Adjudicating Authority may be useful for or relevant to the subject matter of 
the inquiry.
 </section><section><number>7</number> If any person fails, 
neglects or refuses to appear as required by sub-rule (3) before the 
Adjudicating Authority, the Adjudicating Authority may proceed with the 
adjudication proceedings in the absence of such person after recording the 
reasons for doing so.
 </section><section><number>8</number> If, upon consideration of 
the evidence produced before the Adjudicating Authority, the Adjudicating 
Authority is satisfied that the person has committed the contravention, he may, 
by order in writing, impose such penalty as he thinks fit, in accordance with 
the provisions of section 13 of the Act.
 </section><section><number>9</number> Every order made under 
sub-rule (8) of the rule 4 shall specify the provisions of the Act or of the 
rules, regulations, notifications, direction or orders or any condition subject 
to which an authorisation is issued by the Reserve Bank of India in respect of 
which contravention has taken place and shall contain 

1[***] reasons for such decisions.
 </section><section><number>10</number> Every order made under 
sub-rule (8) shall be dated and signed by the Adjudicating Authority.
 </section><section><number>11</number> A copy of the order made 
under sub-rule (8) of the rule 4 shall be supplied free of charge to the person 
against whom the order is made and all other copies of proceedings shall be 
supplied to him on payment of copying fee @ Rs. 2 per page.
 </section><section><number>12</number> The copying fee referred to 
in sub-rule (11) shall be paid in cash or in the form of demand draft in favour 
of the Adjudicating Authority.
  


</section></article> 
 The Foreign Exchange Management (Adjudication Proceedings 
and Appeal) Rules, 2000
  
 <article><number>5</number> Form of Appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every appeal presented to the Special Director (Appeals) under section 17 of the 
Act shall be in the Form I signed by the applicant. The appeal shall be filed in 
triplicate and accompanied by three copies of the order appealed against. Every 
appeal shall be accompanied by a fee of Rupees five thousand in the form of cash 
or demand draft payable in favour of the Special Director (Appeals).
 </section><section><number>2</number> The appeal shall set forth 
concisely and under distinct heads the grounds of objection to the order 
appealed against with any argument of narrative and such grounds shall be 
numbered consecutively; and shall specify the address for service at which 
notice or other processes may be served on the applicant, the date on which the 
order appealed against was served on the applicant.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where the appeal is 
presented after the expiry of the period of forty-five days referred to in 
sub-section (3) of section 17, it shall be accompanied by a petition, in 
triplicate, duly verified and supported by the documents, if any, relied upon by 
the applicant, showing cause how the applicant had been prevented from 
preferring the appeal within the said period of forty-five days.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Any notice required to be 
served on the applicant shall be served on him in the manner specified in the 
rule 9 at the address for service specified in the appeal.
</section></article> 
 The Foreign Exchange Management (Adjudication Proceedings 
and Appeal) Rules, 2000
  
 <article><number>6</number> Procedure before Special 
Director (Appeals).—
<section><number>1</number> On receipt of 
an appeal under rule 5, the Special Director (Appeals) shall send a copy of the 
appeal, together with a copy of the order appealed against, to the Director of 
Enforcement.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Special Director 
(Appeals) shall, then, issue notices to the applicant and the Director of 
Enforcement fixing a date for hearing of the appeal.
 </section><section><number>3</number> On the date fixed for 
hearing of the appeal or any other day to which the hearing of the appeal may be 
adjourned, the applicant as well as the presenting officer of the Directorate of 
Enforcement shall be heard.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Where on the date fixed, or 
any other day to which the hearing of the appeal may be adjourned, the applicant 
or the presenting officer fail to appeal when the appeal is called for hearing, 
the Special Director (Appeals) may decide the appeal on the merits of the case


1[within one hundred and eighty days from 
the date of such appeal.]
  


</section></article> 
 The Foreign Exchange Management (Adjudication Proceedings 
and Appeal) Rules, 2000
  
 <article><number>7</number> Contents of the Order in 
appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> The order of Special 
Director (Appeals) shall be in writing and shall state briefly the grounds for 
the decision.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The order referred to in 
sub-rule (1) shall be signed by the Special Director (Appeals) hearing the 
appeal.
</section></article> 
 The Foreign Exchange Management (Adjudication Proceedings 
and Appeal) Rules, 2000
  
 <article><number>8</number> Representation of party.—Any 
applicant who has filed an appeal before the Special Director (Appeals) under 
section 17 of the Act, may appoint a legal practitioner or a charterted 
accountant to appear and plead and act on his behalf before the Special Director 
(Appeals) under the Act.
</article> 
 The Foreign Exchange Management (Adjudication Proceedings 
and Appeal) Rules, 2000
  
 <article><number>9</number> Service of notices, 
requisitions or orders.—A notice, 
requisition or an order issued under these rules shall be served on any person 
in the following manner, that is to say,—
 <section>         <number>a</number>  by delivering or tendering the notice or 
requisition or order to that person or his duly authorised person;
 </section><section>         <number>b</number>  by sending the notice or requisition or order 
to him by registered post with acknowledgment due to the address of his place of 
residence or his last known place or residence or the place where he carried on, 
or last carried on, business or personally works or last worked for gain; or
 </section><section>         <number>c</number>  by affixing it on the outer door or some other 
conspicuous part of the premises in which the person resides or is known to have 
last resided or carried on business or personally works or last worked for gain 
and that written report thereof should be witnesses by two persons; or
 </section><section>         <number>d</number>  if the notice or requisition or order cannot 
be served under clause (a) or clause (b) or clause (c), by publishing in a 
leading newspaper (both in vernacular and in English) having wide circulation of 
area or jurisdiction in which the person resides or is known to have last 
resided or carried on business or personally works or last worked for gain.
</section></article> 
 The Foreign Exchange Management (Adjudication Proceedings 
and Appeal) Rules, 2000
  
 <article><number>10</number> Form of appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every appeal presented to the Appellate Tribunal under section 19 of the Act 
shall be in the Form II signed by the applicant. The appeal shall be sent in 
triplicate and accompanied by three copies of the order appealed against. Every 
appeal shall be accompanied by a fee of Rupees ten thousand in the form of cash 
or demand draft payable in favour of the Registrar, Appellate Tribunal for 
Foreign Exchange, New Delhi:
 Provided that the applicant 
shall deposit the amount of penalty imposed by the Adjudicating Authority or the 
Special Director (Appeals) as the case may be, to such authority as may be 
notified under the first proviso to section 19 of the Act:
 Provided further that where in a 
particular case, the Appellate Tribunal is of the opinion that the deposit of 
such penalty would cause undue hardship to such person, the Appellate Tribunal 
may dispense with such deposit subject to such conditions as it may deem fit to 
impose so as to safeguard the realisation of penalty.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The appeal shall set forth 
concisely and under distinct heads the grounds of objection to the order 
appealed against without any argument of narrative and such grounds shall be 
numbered consecutively; and shall specify the address for service at which 
notice or other processes may be served on the applicant, the date on which the 
order appealed against was served on the applicant; and the sum imposed by way 
of penalty under section 13 and the amount of fee prescribed in sub-rule (1) had 
been deposited or not.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where the appeal is 
presented after the expiry of the period of forty-five days referred to in 
sub-section (2) of section 19, it shall be accompanied by a petition, in 
triplicate, duly verified and supported by the documents, if any, relied upon by 
the applicant, showing cause how the applicant had been prevented from 
preferring the appeal within the said period of forty-five days.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Any notice required to be 
served on the applicant shall be served on him in the manner prescribed in rule 
14 at the address for service specified in the appeal.
</section></article> 
 The Foreign Exchange Management (Adjudication Proceedings 
and Appeal) Rules, 2000
  
 <article><number>11</number> Procedure before 
Appellate Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> On receipt of 
an appeal under rule 10, the Appellate Tribunal shall send a copy of the appeal, 
together with a copy of the order appealed against, to the Director of 
Enforcement.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Appellate Tribunal 
shall, then, issue notices to the applicant and the Director of Enforcement 
fixing a date for hearing of the appeal.
 </section><section><number>3</number> On the date fixed for 
hearing of the appeal, or any other day to which the hearing of the appeal may 
be adjourned, the applicant as well as the presenting officer of the Directorate 
of Enforcement shall be heard.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Where on the date fixed, or 
any other day to which the hearing of the appeal may be adjourned, the applicant 
or the presenting officer fail to appear when the appeal is called on for 
hearing, the Appellate Tribunal may decide the appeal on the merits of the case.
</section></article> 
 The Foreign Exchange Management (Adjudication Proceedings 
and Appeal) Rules, 2000
  
 <article><number>12</number> Contents of the Order in 
appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> The order of Appellate 
Tribunal shall be in writing and shall state briefly the grounds for the 
decisions.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The order referred to in 
sub-rule (1) shall be signed by the Chairman or Member or the Appellate Tribunal 
hearing the appeal.
</section></article> 
 The Foreign Exchange Management (Adjudication Proceedings 
and Appeal) Rules, 2000
  
 <article><number>13</number> Representation of party.—Any 
applicant who has filed an appeal before the Appellate Tribunal under section 19 
of the Act may appoint a legal practitioner or a charterted accountant to appear 
and plead and act on his behalf before the Special Director (Appeal) under the 
Act.
</article> 
 The Foreign Exchange Management (Adjudication Proceedings 
and Appeal) Rules, 2000
  
 <article><number>14</number> Service of notices, 
requisitions or orders.—A notice, 
requisition or an order issued under these rules shall be served on any person 
in the following manner, that is to say,—
 <section>         <number>a</number>  by delivering or tendering the notice or 
requisition or order to that person or his duly authorised person;
 </section><section>         <number>b</number>  by sending the notice or requisition or order 
to him by registered post with acknowledgment due to the address of his place of 
residence or his last known place or residence or the place where he carried on, 
or last carried on, business or personally works or last worked for gain; or
 </section><section>         <number>c</number>  by affixing it on the outer door or some other 
conspicuous part of the premises in which the person resides or is known to have 
last resided or carried on business or personally works or last worked for gain 
and that written report thereof should be witnesses by two persons; or
 </section><section>         <number>d</number>  if the notice or requisition or order cannot 
be served under clause (a) or clause (b) or clause (c), by publishing in a 
leading newspaper (both in vernacular and in English) having vide circulation of 
area or jurisdiction in which the person resides or is known to have last 
resided or carried on business or personally works or last worked for gain.
</section></article><form>
 

The Foreign Exchange Management (Adjudication Proceedings 
and Appeal) Rules, 2000
 

 
 

Form I
 

(See rule 5)
 

Form oF Appeal
 

From
 

(Mention the name and address of the applicant here)
 

 
 

To
 

The Special Director (Appeals)
 

(Address)
 

 
 

Sir,
 

The applicant named above, begs to prefer this appeal under 
section 17 of the Foreign Exchange Management Act, 1999 against Order No. 
………………dated ……………… passed by the Adjudicating Authority under the said Act on 
the following facts and grounds.
 

Facts
 

(Mention briefly the facts of the case here. Enclose copy of 
the order passed by the Adjudicating Authority and copies of other relevant 
documents, if any)
 

Grounds
 

(Mention here the grounds on which the appeal is made)
 

Prayer
 

In the light of what is stated above, the applicant prays that 
he/she/it may be granted the following relief.
 

Relief sought
 

(Specify the relief sought)
 

The fee of Rs. 
........................................................ for this appeal has 
been deposited in .....................................................vide
Receipt No. ..........................dated...............................
 

Place...............................
 

Date..............................
 

(Signature of the applicant or  

his Authorised representative)
 

List of documents attached:
 

 
 

(Signature of the applicant or  

his Authorised representative)
</form><form>
 

The Foreign Exchange Management (Adjudication Proceedings 
and Appeal) Rules, 2000
 

 
 

Form II
 

(See rule 10)
 

Form of Appeal
 

From
 

(Mention the name and address of the applicant here)
 

 
 

To
 

The Registrar
 

Appellate Tribunal for Foreign Exchange
 

(Address).
 

Sir,
 

The applicant named above, begs to prefer this appeal under 
section 17 of the Foreign Exchange Management Act, 1999 against Order No. 
.....................dated..................passed by the Adjudicating Authority 
under the said Act on the following facts and grounds.
 

Facts
 

(Mention briefly the facts of the case here. Enclose copy of 
the order passed by the Adjudicating Authority and copies of other relevant 
documents, if any)
 

Grounds
 

(Mention here the grounds on which the appeal is made)
 

Prayer
 

In the light of what is stated above, the applicant prays that 
he/she/it may be granted the following relief.
 

Relief sought
 

(Specify the relief sought)
 

The fee of Rs. 
................................................. for this appeal has been 
deposited in ...........................................vide Receipt 
No............................... dated................................
 

2.   The amount of penalty imposed by Adjudicating Authority 
or Special Director (Appeal), as the case may be, Rs...................................for 
this appeal has been deposited in........................ vide Receipt 
No. .................................dated........................
 

 
 

Place.............................
 

Date..............................
 

(Signature of the applicant or  

his Authorised representative)
 

List of documents attached:
 

(Signature of the applicant or  

his Authorised representative)
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>