<act><title>THE BORDER SECURITY FORCE RULES, 1969 </title> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
application.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Border Security Force Rules, 1969.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> These rules shall 
apply to all persons subject to the Act:
 
Provided that the 
provisions of Chapter IV thereof shall not apply to persons belonging to the All 
India Services and other Government servants who are on deputation with the 
Border Security Force:
 
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[Provided further 
that the provisions of Chapters IX and X thereof shall not apply to trials by 
Summary Security Force Courts in so far as they are inconsistent with any of the 
provisions contained in Chapter XI thereof pertaining to Summary Security Force 
Court.] 
 
 






</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  “the Act” means the Border 
Security Force Act, 1968 (47 of 1968);
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  “Appendix” means an Appendix 
annexed to these rules;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  “Court” means the Security Force 
Court;
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  “Detachment” includes any part of 
the battalion required or ordered to proceed on duty away from Headquarters;
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number>  “proper Force authority” when 
used in relation to any power, duty, act or matter, means such Force authority 
as, in pursuance of these rules made under the Act, exercises, or performs that 
power or duty or is concerned with that matter;
 </section><section>
        <number>f</number>  “section” means a section of the 
Act;
 </section><section>
       <number>g</number>  all words and expressions used in 
these rules and defined in the Act shall have the same meaning as in the Act.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Reports and 
applications.—Any 
report or application directed by these rules to be made to a superior officer, 
or to a proper Force authority shall be made in writing through the proper 
channel, unless the said authority, on account of exigencies of service or 
otherwise, dispenses with the writing.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Forms in appendices.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The forms set forth in the appendices, with such variations as the circumstances 
of each case may require, may be used for the respective purposes therein 
mentioned, and if used shall be sufficient, but a deviation, from such forms 
shall not, by reason only of such deviation, tender invalid any charge, warrant 
order, proceedings or any other document relevant to these rules.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any omission of any 
such form shall not, by reason only of such omission, render any act or thing 
invalid.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The directions in the 
notes to and the instructions in the form shall be duly complied with in all 
cases to which they relate, but any omission to comply with any such direction 
in the notes or instructions shall not, merely by reason of such omission, 
render any act or thing invalid.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Exercise of power 
vested in holder of an office in the Force.—Any 
power or jurisdiction given to any person holding any office in the Force to do 
any act or thing to, or before, any person may, for the purposes of these rules, 
be exercised by any other person who may, for the time being, be performing the 
functions of that office in accordance with the rules and practice of the Force.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Case unprovided for.—In 
regard to any matter not specifically provided for in these rules it shall be 
lawful for the competent authority to do such thing or take such action as may 
be just and proper in the circumstances of the case.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>7</number> 
Disqualification.—
<section><number>1</number> No person—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  who has entered into or 
contracted a marriage with a person having a spouse living, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  who having a spouse, has entered 
into or contracted a marriage with any person, shall be eligible for appointment 
into Force:
 
Provided that the Central 
Government may if satisfied that such marriage is permissible under the personal 
law applicable to such person and the other party to the marriage and that there 
are other grounds for so doing, exempt any person from the operating of this 
rule.]
 
 




</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Ineligibility of 
aliens.—No 
person who is not a citizen of India shall, except with the consent of the 
Central Government signified in writing, be appointed, enrolled or employed in 
the Force:
 
Provided that nothing 
contained in this rule shall bar the appointment, enrolment or employment of a 
subject of Nepal, 
Sikkim or Bhutan in the Force.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Appointment of 
officers.—The 
Central Government may appoint such persons as it considers to be suitable as 
officers in the Force, and their conditions of service shall be such as may be 
provided in the rules made in this behalf by the Central Government.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Probation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An Officer on first appointment to the Force 

2[***] shall be on 
probation for a period of two years and the Central Government may, for reasons 
to be recorded in writing, extend the period of probation for such further 
periods or period not exceeding one year.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Central Government 
may, during the period of probation, terminate the services of an officer 
without assigning any reasons.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Appointment of 
subordinate officers and other officers.—Appointments 
to the posts of Subedars, Sub-Inspectors and Under Officers for the Force may be 
made by the Inspector-General, the Deputy Inspector-General and the Commandant 
respectively:
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  by direct recruitment;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  by deputation from the Army, 
Navy, Air Force, State Police Force, or any other Department of the Central 
Government or of the State Government;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  by promotion as may be prescribed 
from time to time.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>11A</number> 
Commissions.—
<section><number>1</number> Officers referred to in rule 9 and Subedars and 
Sub-Inspectors referred to in rule 11 may be granted commissions as such by the 
President.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Grant of the 
commissions shall be notified in the Official Gazette and such notification 
shall be conclusive proof of the grant of such commission.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Enrolling officers.—For 
the purposes of enrolment of persons to the Force under section 6, the following 
persons shall be enrolling officers:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  Commandants of all battalions; 
and
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  any other officer of the Force 
who may be appointed as an enrolling officer by the Director-General.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Procedure for 
enrolment, mode of enrolment and other matters connected therewith.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Upon the appearance before the enrolling officer of any person desirous of being 
enrolled, the enrolling officer shall read and explain to him, or cause to be 
read and explained to him in his presence, the conditions of service for which 
he is to be enrolled; and shall put to him the questions contained in the form 
of enrolment set out in Appendix I and shall, after having cautioned him that if 
he makes a false answer to any such question he shall be liable to punishment 
under the Act, record or cause to be recorded his answer to each such question.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If, after complying 
with the provisions of sub-rule (1) and such other directions as may be issued 
in this behalf by the Director-General from time to time, the enrolling officer 
is satisfied that the person desirous of being enrolled, fully understands the 
questions put to him and consents to the conditions of service, and if the said 
officer is satisfied that there is no impediment, he shall sign and shall also 
cause such person to sign the enrolment paper, and such person shall thereupon 
be deemed to be enrolled.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> (a) Every person 
enrolled as a member of the Force under sub-rule (2) shall be administered an 
oath or affirmation in the form set out in Appendix I.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The oath or 
affirmation shall as far as possible be administered by the Commandant of the 
person to be attested or in the unavoidable absence of the Commandant by the 
person authorised in writing by the Commandant in this behalf.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> The oath or 
affirmation shall be administered when the person to be attested has completed 
his training.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>14</number> 
Constitution of the Force.—
<section><number>1</number> Border Security Force shall consist of:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  Border Security Force (Regular).
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  Border Security Force 
(Auxiliary).
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Officers, subordinate 
officers and enrolled persons appointed to or enrolled into the Border Security 
Force (Regular) shall be liable for continuous service for the term mentioned in 
their enrolment form, letter of appointment or in the rules made in this behalf.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Officers, subordinate 
officers and enrolled persons appointed to or enrolled into the Border Security 
Force (Auxiliary) shall serve as and when they are called out for service by the 
Director-General with the consent of the Central Government or for training 
under the orders of the Director-General.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>14A</number>] 
Ranks.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
officers and other members of the Force shall be classified in accordance with 
their ranks in the following categories, namely:—
 <subsection>
            <number>a</number>      Officers:
 <subsubsection>
            <number>1</number>  Director-General.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>2</number>  

2[Additional Director-General.]
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>3</number>  

2[Inspector-General.]
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>4</number>  Deputy Inspector-General.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>5</number>  Additional Deputy 
Inspector-General.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>6</number>  Commandant.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>7</number>  Deputy Commandant.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>8</number>  Assistant Commandant.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>   Subordinate Officers:
 </subsection></section><section>
            <number>9</number>  Subedar-Major.
 </section><section>
          <number>10</number>  Subedar.
 </section><section>
          <number>11</number>  Sub-Inspector.
 <subsection>
         <number>c</number>   Under Officers:
 </subsection></section><section>
          <number>12</number>  Head Constable.
 </section><section>
          <number>13</number>  Naik.
 </section><section>
          <number>14</number>  Lance Naik.
 <subsection>
        <number>d</number>   Enrolled persons other than 
Under Officers:
 </subsection></section><section>
          <number>15</number>  Constables.
 </section><section>
          <number>16</number>  Enrolled followers.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Matters relating to 
inter se seniority of persons belonging to the same rank shall be determined 
in accordance with such rules as may be made in this behalf.
 

3[4[(3) 
Notwithstanding anything contained in these rules, the Director-General may,

 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  subject to the confirmation by 
the Central Government as provided hereinafter, grant to an officer or Subedar 
of the Force, a rank mentioned against Sr. No. (6), (7) and (8), in clause (a) 
of sub-rule (1) as a local rank; 
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  subejct to prior approval of 
the Central Government, rant to an officer of the Force a rank mentioned against 
Sr. No. (2), (3), (4) and (5), in clause (a) of sub-rule (1), as a local rank;
 
whenever as considered necessary by him in the interests of better functioning 
of the Force.]]
 

5[(4) An officer


6[or Subedar] of 
the Force holding a local rank—
 <subsubsection>
       <number>a</number>  shall exercise the command and be 
vested with the powers of an officer holding that rank;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>b</number>  shall cease to hold that rank, if 
the grant of such rank is not confirmed within thirty-one days by the Central 
Government, or when so ordered by the Director-General or when he ceases to hold 
the appointment for which the rank was granted;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>c</number>  shall not be entitled to any 
extra pay and allowances for holding such rank; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>d</number>  shall not be entitled to claim 
any seniority over other Officers of the Force by virtue of having held such 
rank.]
 

     7[***]
 
 










</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> The task of the Force 
and command and control thereto.—
<section><number>1</number> 
For the purposes of sub-section (1) of section 4, the Force shall, —
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  promote a sense of security 
among the people living in the border areas;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  prevent trans-border crimes, 
un-authorised entry into or exit from the territory of India;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number>  prevent smuggling and any other 
illegal activity.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> In discharging the 
functions under sub-rule (1), the responsibility for the command, discipline, 
morale and administration shall,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  in the case of Inspector-General, 
extend to all battalions, units, head-quarters, establishment and Force 
personnel placed under him 

1[***];
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  in the case of a Deputy 
Inspector-General, extend to all the battalions, other personnel and units 
placed under him 

1[***]; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  in the case of a Commandant, 
extend to the battalion or unit placed under him and 

1[***].
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> During hostilities, 
the Inspector-General, the Deputy Inspector-General and the Commandant shall 
discharge such functions as may be assigned by their respective superiors.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The command, 
discipline, administration and training of battalions, units and establishments 
not placed under a Deputy Inspector-General or an Inspector-General shall be 
carried out by such officer and in such manner as may from time to time be laid 
down by the Director-General.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Any member of the 
Force shall be liable to perform any duties in connection with the safeguarding 
of the security of the border of India, the administration, discipline and 
welfare of the Force and such other duties as he may be called upon to perform 
in accordance with any law for the time being in Force and any order given in 
this behalf by a superior officer shall be a lawful command for the purposes of 
the Act.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Command.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An officer appointed to command shall have the power of command, over all 
officers and men, irrespective of seniority placed under his command.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> (a) In the contingency 
of an officer being unable to exercise the command, to which he has been 
appointed, due to any reason, the command shall devolve on the 
second-in-command, if one has been so appointed.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> If no 
second-in-command has been appointed, it shall devolve on the officer who may be 
appointed to officiate by the immediate superior of the officer unable to 
exercise command.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> If no such officer has 
been so appointed, command shall devolve on the senior most officer present.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> The inability of an 
officer to exercise command and its assumption by any other officer in 
accordance with this sub-rule shall be immediately reported to Force 
Headquarters by the officer who has assumed command.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> If persons belonging 
to different battalions and units are working together—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  in regard to the specific task 
on which they are engaged, the officer appointed to command or in his absence 
the senior most officer present shall exercise command over all such persons.
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  in all other matters the senior 
officer belonging to each battalion shall exercise command over persons 
belonging to his battalion.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> When officers and 
others persons belonging to the Force are taken prisoner by an enemy the 
existing relations of superior and subordinate and the duty of obedience shall 
remain unaltered and any person guilty of indiscipline or insubordination in 
this behalf shall, after his release be liable for punishment.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Disciplinary powers 
over a person subject to the Act shall be exercised by the Commandant of the 
battalion or unit to which such a person belongs or the officer on whom command 
has devolved in accordance with sub-rule (2).
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Where such a person is 
doing detachment duty, including attendance at a course of instruction the 
Commandant of the battalion, unit, centre or establishment with which he is 
doing such duty shall also have all the disciplinary powers of a Commandant.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The Director-General, 
the Inspector-General and the Deputy-Inspector-General may specify one or more 
officers of the staff who shall exercise the disciplinary powers of a Commandant 
in respect of persons belonging to or doing detachment duty at their respective 
Headquarters.
 
Explanation.—In 
this rule, except in sub-rule (2), the word “officer” shall include a 
subordinate officer and an under officer.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Retirement on grounds 
of unsuitability.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where the Director-General is of the opinion that an officer is unfit to be 
retained in service, he may recommend to the Central Government that the officer 
be retired from service.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> He shall also forward 
to the Central Government the reasons for his recommendation alongwith the 
record of service of the officer.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Central Government 
may on receipt of such recommendation and after giving the officer an 
opportunity to explain his case pass such order as it may deem fit:
 
Provided that where in the 
interest of security of the State it would be in-expedient so to do, it shall be 
lawful for the Government to pass an order as aforesaid without giving the 
officer the opportunity to explain his case.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Retirement on grounds 
of physical unfitness.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where an officer not below the rank of a Deputy Inspector-General considers that 
an officer of the Force is unfit to perform his duties because of his physical 
conditions, the officer shall be brought before a medical board.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The medical board 
shall consist of such officers and shall be constituted in such manner as may, 
from time to time, be laid down by the Director-General.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the medical 
board considers the officer to be unfit for service, the Central Government 
shall communicate to the said officer the findings of the medical board and 
thereupon, within a period of fifteen days of such communication, the officer 
may make a representation against it to the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Central Government 
may, on receiving the representation from the officer, refer the case to be 
reviewed by a fresh medical board constituted for the purpose and order the 
retirement of the said officer if the decision of the fresh medical board is 
adverse to him.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Resignation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, having regard to the special circumstances of any 
case, permit any officer of the Force to resign from the Force before the 
attainment of the age of retirement or before putting such number of years of 
service as may be necessary under the rules to be eligible for retirement:
 
Provided that while 
granting such permission the Central Government may—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  require the officer to refund to 
the Government such amount as would constitute the cost of training given to 
that officer 

1[or three months pay and allowances, 
whichever is higher]; or
 
 

2[***]
 

1[Provided further 
that an officer of the Force tendering resignation for accepting a job under 
Central or State Governments or local bodies, after having been granted cadre 
clearance for the same 

3[or who has 
completed 10 years of service], shall not be required to refund the sum as 
provided hereinabove.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Central Government 
may accept the resignation under sub-rule (1) with effect from such date as it 
may consider expedient:
 

2[***]
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Central Government 
may refuse to permit an officer to resign—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  if an emergency has been declared 
in the country either due to internal disturbances or external aggression; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  if it considers it to be 
inexpedient 

4[so to do due to exigencies of 
service or] in the interests of the discipline of the Force; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  if the officer has specifically 
undertaken to serve for a specific period and such period has been not expired.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The provisions of this 
rule shall apply to and in relation to Subordinate Officers and Enrolled Persons 
as they apply to and in relation to any officer of the Force and the powers 
vested in the Central Government under sub-rules (1) and (2) shall be exercised 
in the case of a Subordinate Officer by a Deputy Inspector-General and in the 
case of an Enrolled Person by a Commandant.
 
 







</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>20</number> 
Termination of service of officers by the Central Government on account of 
misconduct.—
<section><number>1</number> When it is proposed to terminate the service of an officer 
under section 10 on account of misconduct, he shall be given an opportunity to 
show cause in the manner specified in sub‑rule (2) against such action:
 
Provided that this 
sub‑rule shall not apply—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  where the service is terminated 
on the ground of conduct which has led to his conviction by a criminal court or 
a Security Force Court; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  where the Central Government is 
satisfied that for reasons, to be recorded in writing, it is not expedient or 
reasonably practicable to give to the officer an opportunity of showing cause.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> When after considering 
the reports on an Officer’s misconduct, the Central Government or the 
Director‑General, as the case may be, is satisfied that the trial of the Officer 
by a Security Force Court is inexpedient or impracticable, but is of the 
opinion, that the further retention of the said officer in the service is 
undesirable, the Director General shall so inform the officer together with 
particulars of allegation and report of investigation (including the statements 
of witnesses, if any, recorded and copies of documents if any, intended to be 
used against him) in cases where allegations have been investigated and he shall 
be called upon to submit, in writing, his explanation and defence:
 
Provided that the 
Director‑General may withhold disclosure of such report or portion thereof if, 
in his opinion, its disclosure is not in the interest of the Security of the 
State.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In the event of the 
explanation of the Officer being considered unsatisfactory by the 
Director‑General, or when so directed by the Central Government, the case shall 
be submitted to the recommendation of the Director‑General as to the termination 
of the Officer’s service in the manner specified in sub‑rule (4).
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> When submitting a case 
to Central Government under the provisions of sub‑rule (2) or sub‑rule (3), the 
Director‑General shall make his recommendation whether the Officer’s service 
should be terminated, and if so, whether the officer should be—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  dismissed from the service; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  removed from the service; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  retired from the service; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  called upon to resign;
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> The Central 
Government, after considering the reports and the officer’s defence, if any, or 
the judgment of the criminal court, as the case may be, and the recommendation 
of the Director‑General, may remove or dismiss the officer with or without 
pension or retire or get his resignation from service, and on his refusing to do 
so, the officer may be compulsorily retired or removed from the service with 
pension or gratuity, if any, admissible to him.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>21</number> 
Termination of service of officers by the Central Government on grounds other 
than misconduct.—
<section><number>1</number> When the Director‑General is satisfied that an officer 
is unsuitable to be retained in service, the officer—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  shall be so informed;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  shall be furnished with 
particulars of all matters adverse to him; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  shall be called upon to urge any 
reasons he may wish to put forward in favour of his retention in the service:
 
Provided that clauses (a), 
(b) and (c) shall not apply, if the Central Government is satisfied that, for 
reasons to be recorded by it in writing, it is not expedient or reasonably 
practicable to comply with the provisions thereof:
 
Provided further that the 
Director‑General may not furnish to the officer any matter adverse to him, if in 
his opinion, it is not in the interest of the security of the State to do so.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> In the event of the 
explanation being considered by the Director‑General unsatisfactory, the matter 
shall be submitted to the Central Government for orders, together with the 
officer’s explanation and the recommendation of the Director‑General.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Central Government 
after considering the reports, the explanation, if any, of the officer and the 
recommendation of the Director-General may call upon the officer to retire or 
resign and on his refusing to do so the officer may be compulsorily retired from 
the service with pension and gratuity if any, admissible to him.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>22</number> Dismissal 
or removal of persons other than officer on account of misconduct.—
<section><number>1</number>
When it is proposed to terminate the service of a person subject to the Act 
other than an officer, he shall be given an opportunity by the authority 
competent to dismiss or remove him, to show cause in the manner specified in 
sub‑rule (2) against such action:
 
Provided that this 
sub‑rule shall not apply—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  where the service is terminated 
on the ground of conduct which has led to his conviction by a criminal court or 
a Security Force Court; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  where the competent authority is 
satisfied that, for reasons to be recorded in writing, it is not expedient or 
reasonably practicable to give the person concerned an opportunity of showing 
cause.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> When after considering 
the reports on the misconduct of the person concerned, the competent authority 
is satisfied that the trial of such a person is inexpedient or impracticable, 
but, is of the opinion that his further retention in the service is undesirable, 
it shall so inform him together with all reports adverse to him and he shall be 
called upon to submit, in writing, his explanation and defence:
 
Provided that the 
competent authority may withhold from disclosure any such report or portion 
thereof, if, in his opinion, its disclosure is not in the public interest.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The competent 
authority after considering his explanation and defence if any may dismiss or 
remove him from service with or without pension:
 
Provided that a Deputy 
Inspector‑General shall not dismiss or remove from service, a Subordinate 
Officer of and above the rank of a Subedar.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> All cases of dismissal 
or removal under this rule, shall be reported to be Director-­General.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Dismissal or removal 
by Central 
Government.—Where 
the Central Government is satisfied, for reasons to be recorded in writing that—
 <section>
        <number>i</number>  it is not reasonably practicable 
to follow the procedure laid down in the said rules, or
 </section><section>
        <number>ii</number>  it is not expedient, in the 
interests of the security of the State, to follow such procedure, it may order 
the dismissal, or removal from the Force of a person subject to the Act without 
following the procedure laid down in rules 20 and 21.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>23A</number> Termination 
of service on conviction on a criminal charge.—When 
a person subject to the Act is convicted of a civil offence the competent 
authority may dismiss or remove him from service without holding any inquiry or 
issuing a show cause notice.]
 
 




</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>24</number> Retirement of 
subordinate officers and enrolled persons.—A 
subordinate officer or an enrolled person shall on the fulfilment of the terms 
and conditions of service under which he was appointed or enrolled be eligible 
to retire.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Retirement of 
subordinate officers and enrolled persons on grounds of physical unfitness.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where a Commandant is satisfied that a Subedar, a Sub-Inspector or an enrolled 
person is unable to perform his duties by reason of any physical disability, he 
may direct that the said Subedar, Sub-Inspector or the enrolled person, as the 
case may be, brought before a Medical Board.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Medical Board 
shall be constituted in such manner as may be determined by the 
Director-General.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the said Subedar, 
Sub-Inspector or enrolled person is found by the Medical Board to be unfit for 
further service in the Force, the Inspector-General, the DIG or, as the case may 
be, the Commandant may, if he agrees with the finding of the Medical Board order 
the retirement of the Subedar, the Sub-Inspector, or as the case may be, the 
enrolled person:
 
Provided that before the 
said Subedar or Sub-Inspector or as the case may be, the enrolled person is so 
retired the finding of the Medical Board and the decision to retire him shall be 
communicated to him.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The subedar, the 
Sub-Inspector or, as the case may be, the enrolled person may, within a period 
of fifteen days from the date of receipt of such communication, make a 
representation to the officer next superior in command to the one who ordered 
the retirement.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The said superior 
officer shall have the case referred to a Review Medical Board which shall be 
constituted in such manner as may be determined by the Director-General.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The superior officer 
may, having regard to the finding of the Review Medical Board, pass such order 
as he may deem fit.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Where a representation 
has been made to a superior officer under sub-rule (4), and order passed under 
sub-rule (3), shall not take effect till it is confirmed by such superior 
officer.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>26</number> Retirement of 
enrolled persons on grounds of unsuitability.—Where 
a Commandant is satisfied that an enrolled person is unsuitable to be retained 
in the Force, the Commandant may, after giving such enrolled person an 
opportunity of showing cause (except where he consider it to be impracticable or 
inexpedient in the interest of security of the State to give such opportunity), 
retire such enrolled person from the Force.
 
 




</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Retirement of 
subordinate officers on grounds of unsuitability.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where a Deputy Inspector-General is satisfied that a Sub-Inspector is unsuitable 
to be retained in the Force, he may, after giving such Sub-Inspector an 
opportunity of showing cause (except when he considers it to be impracticable or 
inexpedient in the interest of security of State, to give such opportunity), 
retire the said Sub-Inspector.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where an 
Inspector-General is satisfied that a Subedar or Subedar Major is unsuitable to 
be retained in the Force, he may after giving such Subedar or Subedar Major an 
opportunity of showing cause except when he considers it to be impracticable or 
inexpedient in the interest of security of State to give such opportunity, 
retire such Subedar or Subedar Major from the Force.]
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>28</number> Powers to be exercised by a superior officer or authority. </title>—Any power conferred by the provisions of this Chapter on an officer may also be exercised by an officer or authority superior in command to the first mentioned officer. 
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>28A</number> Petition.—Any 
person subject to the Act, who considers himself aggrieved by any order of 
termination of his service passed under this Chapter may; in the case of an 
officer, present a petition to the Central Government, in the case of an 
Assistant Sub-Inspector or a subordinate officer, present a petition to the 
Director-General and in the case of an enrolled person, present a petition to 
the Inspector-General, who may pass such orders on the petition as deemed fit:
 
Provided that the 
limitation period for filing such petition shall be three months from the date 
of order of termination or from the date of its receipt, whichever is later].
 
 




</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>29</number> Passing of orders 
relating to absence from duty.—Where 
an order of dismissal or of removal or of retirement of a person subject to the 
Act is set aside, the officer or authority setting aside such dismissal, removal 
or retirement shall pass such orders as may be necessary in respect of the 
period of absence from duty of the person whose dismissal, removal or retirement 
has been set aside.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>30</number> Date of dismissal, 
removal, resignation, retirement.—The 
effective date of dismissal, resignation or retirement shall be,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  the date mentioned in the order 
of dismissal or removal or order sanctioning or accepting resignation or 
retirement, or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  if no such date is mentioned the 
date on which the order was signed or the date on which the person concerned is 
relieved from duties, whichever is later.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>31</number> Forms of arrest.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Arrest may be either open arrest or close arrest.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An arrest, unless 
otherwise specified shall mean an open arrest.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An order imposing 
arrest may be communicated to the person to be arrested either orally or in 
writing.
</section></article> 

 . 
 <article><title><number>32</number> Authority to order arrest.— </title>
<section><number>1</number> No person subject to this Act shall be arrested on a charge under the Act except under and in accordance with the orders of a superior officer having power of command over him. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rule (1) any person subject to the Act may be placed under arrest by any superior officer,— 
 <subsection><number>a</number> if he commits an offence against such superior officer, or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> if he commits an offence in the view of such superior officer, or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> if he is behaving in a disorderly manner and the said superior officer considers it necessary to place such a person under arrest with a view to stop such disorderly behaviour. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> A superior officer effecting arrest under sub-rule (2) shall as soon as possible, and in any case within twenty four hours of such arrest send a report to the Commandant of the battalion or unit of which the person arrested is a member and in case of the arrest of officer of and above the rank of Commandant, to his immediate superior officer. 
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>33</number> Arrest how imposed—(A) 
Close arrest.—
<section><number>1</number> 

<subsection><number>a</number> Close arrest in the case of enrolled persons shall be imposed by informing 
the person to be arrested and ordering him to be marched to the place of 
confinement under an escort of person of similar or superior rank.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> Where no such escort 
is available the person arrested shall be ordered to report himself immediately 
to the quarter guard or other place of confinement.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> (a) Close arrest in 
the case of officers, subordinate officers and under officers, shall be imposed 
by placing such officer, subordinate officer or under officer under the custody 
of another person of similar or superior rank and wherever considered necessary 
such officer, subordinate officer, or under officer may be confined under charge 
of a guard.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The person under 
arrest shall not leave his quarter or tent without permission of a superior 
officer designated by the Commandant in this behalf.
 <subsubsection>
<number>B</number> Open arrest.—(3) 
(a) Open arrest shall be imposed by informing the person to be arrested (whether 
he is an officer, subordinate officer, under officer or an enrolled person) that 
he is under open arrest and that he shall confine himself within such limits as 
may be specified in this behalf by the concerned superior officer effecting such 
arrest.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> The Commandant may, 
from time to time, vary the limits referred to in clause (a) above.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>34</number> Release from arrest 
during investigation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any person arrested under rule 33 may be released from arrest under the order of 
an Assistant Commandant, Deputy Commandant, Commandant or any officer superior 
to the Commandant.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to the 
provisions of rule 35, no person except on the basis of any fresh evidence 
against him be re-arrested.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>35</number> Release without 
prejudice to re-arrest.—Pending 
the completion of the investigation or convening of a court any person who has 
been placed under arrest may without prejudice to re-arrest be released by his 
Commandant or by any officer superior to his Commandant.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>36</number> Arrest when to be 
imposed.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any person charged with,—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  an offence under section 14, or 
clause (a) clause (b) of section 16, or section 17 or section 20 or sub-section 
(1) of section 21.
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  a civil offence punishable with 
death or imprisonment for life.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number>  any other offence under the 
Act—
 <subsubsection>
            <number>a</number>  if the interest of 
discipline so require; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>b</number>  if the person concerned 
deliberately undermines discipline; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>c</number>  if the person concerned is 
of violent disposition; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>d</number>  if the person concerned is 
likely to absent himself with a view to avoid trial; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>e</number>  if the person concerned is 
likely to interfere with witnesses or tamper with evidence, 
 
shall be placed under arrest.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any person 
arrested shows symptoms of sickness, medical assistance shall be provided for 
such person.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>37</number> Special provision in 
case of arrest of intoxicated person.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where an intoxicated person has been arrested, he shall, as far as possible, be 
confined separately and shall be visited by orderly officer or orderly 
subordinate officer or orderly under officer incharge of the guard, once every 
two hours.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An intoxicated person 
shall not be taken before a superior officer for investigation of his case until 
he has become sober.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>38</number> Arrest in case of 
person whose trial has been ordered.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Unless the convening officer has otherwise directed, on the commencement of the 
trial of a person by the court, the said person shall be placed under arrest and 
shall remain under arrest during the trial.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where a sentence lower 
than imprisonment is passed by a court the arrested person shall be released by 
his Commandant pending confirmation of the finding and sentence:
 
Provided that a person who 
has been sentenced to be dismissed shall not except while on active duty, be put 
on any duty.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>39</number> Delay reports.—
<section><number>1</number> 

<subsection><number>a</number> The report on reasons for delay as required under section 59 shall be in the 
form set out in Appendix II and it shall be sent by the Commandant to the Deputy 
Inspector-General under whom the accused may be serving.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> A copy of eighth delay 
report and every succeeding report thereof shall also be sent to the 
Inspector-General under whom the accused may be serving.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the accused is 
kept under arrest for a period exceeding three months without being brought to 
trial, a special report regarding the action taken and the reasons for the delay 
shall be sent by the Commandant to the Director-General with a copy each to the 
Deputy Inspector-General and the Inspector-General concerned.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>40</number> Rights of a person 
under arrest.—
<section><number>1</number> 

<subsection><number>a</number> Any person placed under arrest shall, at the time of being placed under 
arrest, be given in writing by the officer effecting the arrest the particulars 
of the charges against him.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> The said particulars 
shall be rendered in simple language and also explained to the accused.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in clause (a), where during the investigation other offences 
committed by the accused are discovered, it shall be lawful to charge such 
person with those offences.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> (a) The orderly 
officer or the orderly subordinate officer shall every day make a visit to the 
person under arrest and take the orders of the Commandant on any request or 
representation made by the person under arrest.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The request or 
representation made by the person under arrest shall be entered in the form set 
out in Appendix III.
</subsection></section></article> 
 The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>1[<number>40A</number> 
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in these rules, the appointing authority may, at its discretion, place 
a person serving under him, under suspension,—
 <subsection>        
<number>i</number>  where a disciplinary action under the Act against him is contemplated 
or is pending; or
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>ii</number>  where in the opinion of the authority aforesaid, he has engaged 
himself in activities prejudicial to the interest or security of the State; 
or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number>  
where a case against him in respect of any civil offence is under investigation, 
inquiry or trial:
 2[Provided that the Director 
General may exercise the powers of suspension in respect of officers of the 
Force upto the rank of Deputy Commandant:
 Provided further that the 
Director General shall report the facts of each case immediately to the Central 
Government and all such orders of suspension shall become ab-initio void 
unlest confirmed by the Central Government within a period of one month from the 
date of the said orders, irrespective of the fact  that the suspension is 
revoked by the said authority within that period.]
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> A member of the Force shall 
be deemed to have been placed under suspension by an order of the appointing 
authority—
 <subsection>        
<number>i</number>  with effect from the date of his detention by civil police on criminal 
charge or otherwise for a period exceeding 48 hours, or
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>ii</number>  with effect from the date of his conviction by a Civil Court on a 
criminal charge, if the sentence awarded is imprisonment for a term exceeding 48 
hours.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> An order of suspension made 
or deemed to have been made under this rule shall continue to remain in force 
until it is modified or revoked by the authority competent to do so.
 </section><section><number>4</number> An order of suspension made 
or deemed to have been made under this rule, may, at any time, be modified or 
revoked by the authority which made the order by any authority to which that 
authority is subordinate.
 </section><section><number>5</number> When a person remains under 
suspension for more than 90 days, a report giving reasons for delay in the 
finalisation of his case shall be submitted to the Director-General by the 
Commandant of the accused, and thereafter, subsequent reports shall be submitted 
every month till the case is finalised or the order of suspension is revoked 
whichever is earlier.]
  




</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>41</number> Trial of cases either 
by Security Force Court or Criminal Court.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where an offence is triable both by a criminal court and a Security Force Court, 
an officer referred to in section 80 may,—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number> (a)  where the offence is 
committed by the accused in the course of the performance of his duty as a 
member of the Force, or
 <subsubsection>
            <number>b</number>  where the offence is 
committed in relation to property belonging to the Government or the Force or a 
person subject to the Act, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>c</number>  where the offence is 
committed against a person subject to the Act, 
 
              direct that any person subject 
to the Act, who is alleged to have committed such an offence, be tried by a 
court; and
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  in any other case, decide 
whether or not it would be necessary in the interests of discipline to claim for 
trial by a court any person subject to the Act who is alleged to have committed 
such an offence.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> In taking a decision 
to claim an offender for trial by a court, and officer referred to in section 80 
may take into account all or any of the following factors, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the offender is on active duty or 
has been warned for active duty and it is felt that he is trying to avoid such 
duty;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the offender is a young person 
undergoing training and the offence is not a serious one and the trial of the 
offender by a criminal court would materially affect his training;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  the offender can, in view of the 
nature of the case, be dealt with summarily under the Act.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>42</number> Cases not to be tried 
by Security Force Court.—Without 
prejudice to the provisions of rule 41, an offender may not be claimed for trial 
by a Security Force Court—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  where the offence is committed by 
him along with any other person not subject to the Act whose identity is known; 
or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  where the offence is committed by 
him while on leave or during absence without leave.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>43</number> Offence report.—Where 
it is alleged that a person subject to the Act 

1[other than an 
officer or a Subordinate Officer] has committed an offence punishable thereunder 
the allegation shall be reduced to writing in the form set out in Appendix IV.
 
 




</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>44</number> Charge 
Sheet.—Where it is alleged that an officer or a Subordinate Officer has 
committed an offence punishable under the Act, the allegation shall be reduced 
to writing in the form set out in Appendix VI.]
 
 




</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>45</number> Hearing of 
the charge against an enrolled person.—
<section><number>1</number> The charge shall be heard by the 
Commandant of the accused—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the charge and statement of 
witnesses if recorded shall be read over to the accused. If written statements 
of witnesses are not available, he shall hear as many witnesses as he may 
consider essential to enable him to determine the issue;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the accused shall be given an 
opportunity to cross‑examine the witnesses and make a statement in his defence.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> After hearing the 
charge under sub‑rule (1), the commandant may,—]
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  award any of the punishments 
which he is empowered to award, or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  dismiss the charge, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number> remand the accused, for 
preparing a record of evidence or for preparation of an abstract of evidence 
against him, or
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>iv</number> remand him for 
trial by a Summary Security Force Court:
 
Provided that, in cases 
where the Commandant awards more than 7 days’ imprisonment or detention he shall 
record the substance of evidence and the defence of the accused:
 
Provided further that, he 
shall dismiss the charge if in his opinion the charge is not proved or may 
dismiss it if he considers that because of the previous character of the accused 
and the nature of the charge against him it is not advisable to proceed further 
with it:
 
Provided also that in case 
of all offences punishable with death a record of evidence shall be taken:
 

2[Provided further 
that in case of offences under sections 14, 15, 17, 18 and offence of ‘murder’ 
punishable under section 46 of the Act, if the accused has absconded or 
deserted, the Commandant shall hear the charge in his absence and remand the 
case for preparation of the record of evidence.]
 
 





</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>45A</number> Hearing 
of charge by an officer specified under section 53 of the Act.—
<section><number>1</number> A 
specified officer may proceed against an enrolled person if,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the charge can be summarily dealt 
with; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the case has not been reserved by 
the Commandant for disposal by himself; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  the accused is not under arrest.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> After hearing the 
charge under sub‑rule (1) of rule 45 the specified officer may—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  award any of the punishment 
which he is empowered to award; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  dismiss the charge; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number> refer the case to Commandant.
 
 




</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>45B</number> Hearing of charge 
against an officer and a subordinate officer.—
<section><number>1</number>
<subsection><number>a</number>
The charge against an officer or subordinate officer shall be heard by his 
Commandant:
 
Provided that charge 
against a Commandant, a Deputy Inspector‑General or an Inspector‑General may be 
heard either by an officer commanding a Unit or Headquarters to which the 
accused may be posted or attached or by his Deputy Inspector‑General, or his 
Inspector‑General or, as the case may be, the Director‑General.
 

1[(b) The charge 
sheet and statements of witnesses if recorded and relevant documents, if any, 
shall be read over to the accused if he has not absconded or deserted.]
 
Provided that where 
written statement of witnesses, are not available the officer hearing the charge 
shall hear as many witnesses as he may consider essential to enable him to know 
about the case.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> The accused 

2[if he has not 
absconded or deserted,] shall be given an opportunity to make a statement in his 
defence.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> After hearing the 
charge under sub‑rule (1), the officer who heard the charge may—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  dismiss the charge; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  remand the accused, for 
preparation of a record of evidence or preparation of abstract of evidence 
against the accused:
 
Provided that be shall 
dismiss the charge if in his opinion the charge is not proved or may dismiss it 
if he considers that because of the previous character of the accused and the 
nature of the charge against him, it is not advisable to proceed further with 
it:
 
Provided further that in 
case of all offences punishable with death, a record of evidence shall be 
prepared]:
 

2[Provided also 
that in case of offences under sections 14, 15, 17, 18 and offence of ‘murder’ 
punishable under section 46 of the Act, if the accused has absconded or 
deserted, the Commandant shall hear the charge in his absence and remand the 
case for preparation of the record of evidence.]
 
 





</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>46</number> Attachment to another 
unit.—The 
Commandant shall not deal with any case—
 <section>
        <number>i</number>  where the offence with which the 
accused is charged is against the Commandant himself, or
 </section><section>
        <number>ii</number>  where the Commandant is himself 
a witness in the case against the accused, or
 </section><section>
       <number>iii</number>  where the Commandant is 
otherwise personally interested in the case and the accused shall be attached to 
another battalion or unit for disposal of the case under the order of the Deputy 
Inspector-General:
 
Provided that a Commandant 
shall not be disqualified from hearing a charge merely because the offence was 
committed against the property of a Force Mess, band or institution of which the 
Commandant is a member or trustee or because the offence is one of disobedience 
of such Commandant’s orders.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>47</number> Charges not to be 
dealt with summarily.—A 
charge for an offence under section 14 or section 15 or clauses 
<section><number>a</number> and (b) of 
section 16, or section 17 or clause 
<subsection><number>a</number> of section 18 or clause (a) of section 
20 or clause (a) of section 24 or section 46 (other than that for simple hurt or 
theft) or a charge for abetment of or an attempt to commit any of these offences 
shall not be dealt with summarily.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>48</number> Record of evidence.—
<section><number>1</number>


1[The officer 
ordering the record of evidence] may either prepare the record of evidence 
himself or detail another officer to do so.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The witnesses shall 
give their evidence in the presence of the accused and the accused shall have 
right to cross-examine all witnesses who give evidence against him.
 

2[Provided that 
where statement of any witness at a court of inquiry is available, examination 
of such a witness may be dispensed with the original copy of the said statement 
may be taken on record. A copy thereof shall be given to the accused and he 
shall have the right to cross-examine if he was not afforded an opportunity to 
cross examine the witness at the court of Inquiry.]
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> After all the 
witnesses against the accused have been examined, he shall be cautioned in the 
following terms: “You may make a statement if you wish to do so, you are not 
bound to make one and whatever you state shall be taken down in writing and may 
be used in evidence.” After having been cautioned in the aforesaid manner 
whatever the accused states shall be taken down in writing.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The accused may call 
witnesses in defence and the officer recording the evidence may ask any question 
that may be necessary to clarify the evidence given by such witnesses.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> All witnesses shall 
give evidence on oath or affirmation:
 
Provided that, no oath or 
affirmation shall be given to the accused nor shall be cross-examined.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> (a) The statements 
given by witnesses shall ordinarily be recorded in narrative form and the 
officer recording the evidence may, at the request of the accused, permit any 
portion of the evidence to be recorded in the form of question and answer.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The witnesses shall 
sign their statements after the same have been read over and explained to them.
 

3[(6A) The 
provisions of section 89 of the Act shall apply for procuring the attendance of 
witnesses before the officer preparing the Record of Evidence.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>7</number> Where a witness cannot 
be compelled to attend or is not available or his attendance cannot be procured 
without an undue expenditure of time or money and after the officer recording 
the evidence has given a certificate in this behalf, a written statement signed 
by such witness may be read to the accused and included in the record of 
evidence.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> After the recording of 
evidence is completed the officer recording the evidence shall give a 
certificate in the following form:—
 
“Certified that the record 
of evidence ordered by ………………………… ………………… Commandant ………… was made in the 
presence and hearing of the accused and the provisions of rule 48 have been 
complied with.”
 
 





</section></article> 
 The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>1[<number>48A</number> If a person subject to the Act 
absconds or deserts the Force after commission of offences under sections 14, 
15, 17, 18 and offence of ‘murder’ punishable under section 46 of the Act and 
there is no immediate prospect of his apprehension, the officer detailed to 
prepare the record of evidence shall examine the witnesses in the absence of the 
accused and such evidence may, on the apprehension of such accused, be given in 
evidence against him at the trial by a Security Force Court, if such witness is 
dead or incapable of giving evidence or cannot be found or his presence cannot 
be procured without an amount of delay, expenses or inconvenience which, under 
the circumstances of the case would be unreasonable.]
  



</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>49</number> Abstract of evidence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An abstract of evidence shall be prepared either by 

1[the ordering it] 
or an officer detailed by him.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> (a) The abstract of 
evidence, shall include—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  signed statements of witnesses 
wherever available or a precise thereof, or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  copies of all documents 
intended to be produced at the trial.
 <subsubsection>
<number>b</number> Where signed 
statements of any witnesses are not available a precise of their evidence shall 
be included.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> A copy of the abstract 
of evidence shall be given by the officer making the same to the accused and the 
accused shall be given an opportunity to make a statement if he so desires after 
he has been cautioned in the manner laid down in sub-rule (3) of rule 48:
 
Provided that the accused 
shall be given such time as may be reasonable in the circumstances but in no 
case less than twenty four hours after receiving the abstract of evidence to 
make his statement.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 
 
 <article>
<number>50</number> Investigation of cases 
by police.—Where 
the Commandant considers it necessary so to do, he may lodge a report with the 
Police for investigation of any case.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>51</number> Disposal of case


1[against an 
enrolled person] by Commandant after record or abstract of evidence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where an officer has been detailed to prepare the record of evidence or to make 
an abstract thereof he shall forward the same to the Commandant.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Commandant may, 
after going through the record or abstract of evidence—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  dismiss the charge, or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  rehear the charge and award one 
of the summary punishments, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number>  try the accused by a Summary 
Security Force Court where he is empowered so to do, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iv</number>  apply to a competent officer or 
authority to convene a court for the trial of the accused.
 
 




</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>

1[<number>51A</number> 
Disposal of case against an officer or a subordinate officer after preparation 
of record of evidence or abstract of evidence.—
<section><number>1</number> Where an officer has been 
detailed to prepare the record of evidence or abstract thereof, he shall forward 
the same to the officer who ordered for its preparation.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The officer who 
ordered for the preparation of record of evidence or abstract of evidence may, 
after going through the record or abstract of evidence,—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  dismiss the charge, or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  dispose of the case summarily 
if he is so empowered, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number>  refer the case to competent 
superior officer for disposal, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iv</number>  apply to a competent officer or 
authority to convene a General Security Force Court for the trial of the 
accused.]
 
 




</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>52</number> Application for a 
Court.—An 
application for a court shall be made by the Commandant in the form set out in 
Appendix V to these rules and shall be accompanied by five copies of the record 
or abstract of evidence and charge sheet and such other documents as are 
mentioned in that application form.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>53</number> Charge Sheet.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A charge-sheet contains the whole of the issue or issues to be tried at one time 
and may contain more than one charge, if the charges are founded on the same 
facts or form part of a series of offences of same or similar character:
 
Provided that a charge 
under section 18, section 19, section 29 and section 32 may be included in any 
charge sheet, notwithstanding that other charges in that charge sheet are not 
founded on the same facts or do not form part of a series of offences of the 
same or similar character.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every charge sheet 
shall in its lay out follow the appropriate specimen, set out in Appendix VI to 
these rules.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>54</number> Charges.—
<section><number>1</number> 
There shall be a separate charge for each offence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> (a) If a single act or 
series of acts is of such a nature that it is doubtful which of several offences 
the facts which can be proved will constitute, the accused may be charged with 
having committed all or any of such offences, and any number of such charges may 
be tried at once or he may be charged in the alternative with having committed 
some one of the said offences.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The charge for the 
more serious offence shall precede the one for the less serious offence.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Each charge shall 
consist of two parts, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  statement of the offence, and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  particulars of the offence.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The offence shall be 
stated, if not a civil offence, as nearly as practicable, in the words of the 
Act, and if a civil offence, in such words as would sufficiently describe that 
offence.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> (a) The particulars 
shall state the time and place of the alleged offence and the person (if any) 
against whom, or the thing (if any) in respect of which, it was committed and 
these should be sufficient to give the accused notice of the matter with which 
he is charged.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> In case such 
particulars are not sufficient to give the accused notice of the matter with 
which he is charged the charge shall also contain such particulars of the manner 
in which the offence was committed as will be sufficient for that purpose.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>55</number> Joint charges.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any number of accused may be charged jointly and tried together for an offence 
averred to have been committed jointly by them.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any number of accused 
though not charged jointly may also be tried together for an offence averred to 
have been committed by one or more of them and abetted by other or others.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the accused are 
so charged under sub-rule (1) or sub-rule (2), any one or more of them may be 
charged with, and tried for, any other offence with which they could have been 
charged under sub-rule (1) of rule 53.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>56</number> Validity of charge 
sheet.—A charge 
sheet shall not be invalid merely by reason of the fact that it contains any 
mistake in the name or description of the accused, and in the construction of a 
charge sheet there shall be presumed in favour of supporting it every 
proposition which may reasonably be presumed to be impliedly included, though 
not expressed therein, and the statement of the offence and the particulars of 
the offence shall be read and construed together.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>57</number> Amendment of the 
charge by the Security Force Court.—
<section><number>1</number> 
At any time during a trial, if it appears to the court that there is in the 
charge sheet—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  a mistake in the name or 
description of the accused, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  a mistake which is attributable 
to a clerical error or omission, 
 the 
Court may amend the charge-sheet so as to correct the mistake.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If at any time during 
a trial at which there is a Law Officer, it appears to the Court, before it 
closes to deliberate on its findings, that it is desirable in the interests of 
justice to make any addition to, omission from or alteration in, a charge which 
cannot be made under sub-rule (1) of this rule it may, if such addition, 
omission, or alteration can be made without unfairness to the accused, and with 
the concurrence of the Law Officer, so amend the charge.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If at any time during 
a trial at which there is no Law Officer, it appears to the Court before it 
closes to deliberate on its finding that in the interests of justice it is 
desirable to make any addition to, omission from or alteration in a charge which 
cannot be made under sub-rule (1) of this rule, it may adjourn and report its 
opinion to the convening officer, who may—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  amend the charge if permissible 
under rule 58 and direct the Court to try it as amended after due notice of the 
amendment has given been to the accused; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  direct the Court to proceed with 
the trial of the charge without amending it; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  convene a fresh Court to try the 
accused.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>58</number> Amendment of charge by 
Convening Officer.—When 
a Security Force Court reports to the Convening Officer under either rule 57 or 
rule 73 he may amend the charge in respect of which the Court has reported to 
him by making any addition to, omission from or alteration in the charge which, 
in his opinion, is desirable in the interests of justice and which he is 
satisfied can be made without unfairness to the accused.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>59</number> Action by a Superior 
Authority on receiving an application for convening a court.—
<section><number>1</number> 
As soon as a superior officer receives an application for convening a Court, he 
shall scrutinise the charge and the evidence against the accused, where 
necessary in consultation with the Chief Law Officer or a Law Officer and he—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  shall direct the Commandant to 
dismiss the charge where the evidence against the accused is insufficient and 
further evidence is not likely to be available and may direct him to do so if he 
considers it inadvisable to proceed with the trial; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  may return the case to the 
Commandant for being tried by a Summary Security Force Court or being dealt with 
summarily if he considers that the same can be adequately so tried or dealt 
with; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number>  may return the case for 
recording further evidence, if he considers the evidence record insufficient but 
considers that further evidence may be available.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> (a) In any other case 
he may either himself convene a Court or if he considers that a higher type of 
Court should be convened and he is not empowered to convene such a Court, 
forward the case to a higher authority with recommendation that such Court may 
be convened.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The higher authority 
on receiving the case may exercise any of the powers given in sub-rule (1) of 
this rule:
 
Provided that a superior 
officer or higher authority before convening a General Security Force Court or a 
Petty Security Force Court 

1[***] shall take 
the advice of the Chief Law Officer or a Law Officer:
 
Provided further that the 
superior authority or higher authority while convening a Court may reframe the 
charge sheet on which the accused is to be tried.
 
 




</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>60</number> Disqualification of 
officers for serving on 

1[General and 
Petty] Security Force Courts.—An 
officer shall be disqualified from serving on a Court if he—
 <section>
        <number>i</number>  is an officer who convened the 
Court; or
 </section><section>
        <number>ii</number>  is the prosecutor or a witness 
for the prosecution; or
 </section><section>
       <number>iii</number>  has taken any part in the 
investigation of the case, which would have necessitated applying his mind to 
any part of the evidence, or to the facts of the case; or
 </section><section>
       <number>iv</number>  is the Commandant of the 
accused; or
 </section><section>
       <number>v</number>  has a personal interest in the 
case.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>61</number> Composition of 

1[General and 
Petty] Security Force Courts.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A Court shall 
consist, as far as practicable, of officers of different battalions 

2[or units]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The members of a Court 
for the trial of an officer shall be of a rank not lower than the rank of that 
officer, unless in the opinion of the Convening Officer, officers of such rank 
are, not having due regard to the exigencies of public service, available. Such 
opinion shall be recorded in the convening order.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A Court for the trial 
of a Commandant, shall as far as possible, consist of officers who are or have 
been Commandants or who hold, or have held, a higher appointment.
 
 





</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>62</number> Duties of Convening 
Officer when convening Courts.—When 
an officer convenes a Court he shall—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  issue a convening order in the 
appropriate form set out in Appendix VII;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  direct upon what charges the 
accused is to be tried and ensure that the accused has been remanded for trial 
by a Court upon these charges, by his Commandant;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  if he is of the opinion that 
charges shall be put in separate charge sheets, so direct and shall also direct 
that order in which they are to be tried;
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  direct, if there is more than one 
accused whether the accused are to be tried jointly or separately;
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number>  appoint members of the Court and 
any waiting members;
 </section><section>
        <number>f</number>  if convening:
 <subsection>
             <number>i</number>  a General Security Force 
Court; or
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>ii</number>  a Petty Security Force 
Court which he considers should be attended by a Law Officer, take the necessary 
steps to procure the appointment of a Law Officer by or on behalf of the Chief 
Law Officer;
 </subsection></section><section>
       <number>g</number>  appoint an officer, subject to 
the Act or a counsel assisted by such an officer to prosecute or detail a 
Commandant to appoint an officer subject to the Act, to prosecute:
 
              Provided that the convening 
officer may appoint more than one such officer to prosecute if he thinks fit;
 </section><section>
       <number>h</number>  appoint an interpreter wherever 
necessary;
 </section><section>
        <number>i</number>  send to the senior member the 
charge-sheet, the convening order and a copy of the record or abstract of 
evidence from which any evidence which in his opinion would be inadmissible at 
the trial has been expurgated;
 </section><section>
        <number>j</number>  forward to each member of the 
Court and to each waiting member a copy of the charge-sheet;
 </section><section>
       <number>k</number>  forward to the prosecutor copies 
of the charge-sheet and convening order and the original record or abstract of 
evidence together with an unexpurgated copy thereof showing the passages (if 
any) which have been expurgated in the copy sent to the senior member;
 </section><section>
        <number>l</number>  forward to the Law Officer (if 
any) copies of the charge sheet and convening order and an unexpurgated copy of 
the record or abstract of evidence showing the passages (if any) which have been 
expurgated in the copy sent to the senior member;
 </section><section>
       <number>m</number>  ensure that the Commandant has 
summoned all the prosecution witnesses and such defence witnesses as the accused 
may have requested to be summoned under rule 64.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>63</number> Preparation of defence 
by the accused.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An accused, who has been remanded for trial, shall be afforded proper 
opportunity for preparing his defence and shall be allowed proper communication 
with his defending officer or counsel and with his witnesses.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A defending officer 
shall be appointed to defend an accused who has been remanded for trial unless 
the accused states in writing that he does not wish such an appointment to be 
made.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If the prosecution is 
to be undertaken by a legally qualified officer or by a counsel the accused 
shall be notified of this fact in sufficient time to enable him, if he so 
desires to make arrangements for a legally qualified officer or counsel to 
defend him.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> As soon as practicable 
after a decision has been taken to place the accused on trial and in any case, 
not less than four days before his trial he shall be given—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  a copy of the charge-sheet;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  an unexpurgated copy of the 
record or abstract of evidence showing the passages (if any), which have been 
expurgated in the copy sent to the senior member;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  notice of any additional evidence 
which the prosecution intends to adduce; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  if the accused so requires, a 
list of the ranks, names, and units of the members who are to form the Court and 
of any waiting members.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> When an accused is 
given a copy of the charge-sheet and of the record or abstract of evidence in 
accordance with this rule, he shall—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  have the charge explained to him; 
and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  be informed that, upon his making 
a written request to his Commandant not less than twenty-four hours before his 
trial requiring the attendance at his trial of a witness (other than a witness 
for the prosecution) whom he desires to call in his defence (such witness to be 
named by him), reasonable steps will be taken in accordance with these rules to 
procure the attendance of any such witness at his trial.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>6</number> The provisions of 
sub-rules (2) and (3) shall not apply in relation to a trial before a Summary 
Security Force Court and in relation to such a trial the period of four days 
referred to in sub-rule (4) shall be construed as twenty-four hours.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>64</number> 

<section><number>1</number> Subject to the 
provisions of sub-rules (2) and (3) the Commandant shall, on a request made in 
this behalf by the accused, summon such witnesses as are specified by the 
accused.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the Commandant 
is satisfied that the evidence to be given by any witness is not likely to be of 
material assistance at the trial he may refuse to summon such witness.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Commandant may 
before summoning any witness, require the accused to defray or undertake to 
defray the cost of attendance of such witness and if the accused refuses to 
defray or undertake to defray the cost aforesaid, the Commandant may refuse to 
procure the attendance of that witness.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where the Commandant 
has refused to summon the witness under sub-rule (2) or sub-rule (3) the accused 
may make an application to the Court for the summoning of such witness and the 
Court may, if it considers it to be expedient in the interests of justice, order 
the summoning of such witness and, if necessary, adjourn the proceedings for the 
attendance of such witness.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>65</number> Assembly and swearing 
of Court.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Upon a Security Force Court assembling the Court shall, before beginning the 
trial, satisfy itself in closed Court—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  that the Court has been convened 
in accordance with the Act and these rules;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  that the Court consists of not 
less than the minimum number of officers required by law;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  that the members are of the 
required rank;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  that members have been duly 
appointed and are not disqualified under the Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  that if there is a Law Officer he 
has been duly appointed;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  that the accused appears from 
the charge-sheet, to be subject to the Act and to be subject to the jurisdiction 
of the Court; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>g</number>  that each charge is correct in 
law and framed in accordance with these rules.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> (a) Where a vacancy 
occurs through a member of the Court being disqualified under the Act or being 
absent when the Court assembles, the Presiding Officer may appoint a duly 
qualified waiting member to fill that vacancy.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The presiding officer 
may if the interests of justice so require, substitute a duly qualified waiting 
member for a member appointed by the Convening Officer.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> If the Court is not 
satisfied on any of the matters mentioned in sub-rule (1) and is not competent 
to rectify such matter itself under that Act or these rules, it shall before 
commencing the trial, report thereon to the Convening Officer.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> When the Court has 
complied with this rule and is ready to proceed with the trial, the Presiding 
Officer shall open the Court and the trial shall begin.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>66</number> Commencement of trial.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The order convening the Court and the names of the officers appointed to try the 
accused shall be read in the hearing of the accused who shall be given an 
opportunity to object to any of those officers in accordance with section 84 of 
the Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When a Court is to try 
more than one accused whether separately or jointly, each accused shall be given 
an opportunity to object to any officer of the Court in accordance with the 
foregoing sub-rule and shall be asked separately whether he has any such 
objection.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An accused shall state 
the names of all the officers to whom he objects before any objection is 
disposed of.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If more than one 
officer is objected to; the objection to each officer shall be disposed of 
separately and the objection to the lowest in rank shall be disposed of first.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> An accused may make a 
statement and call any person to make a statement in support of his objection.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> An officer to whom the 
accused has objected may state in open Court anything relevant to the objection 
of the accused whether in support or in rebuttal thereof.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> An objection to an 
officer shall be considered in closed Court by any of the officers on the Court 
and the officer objected to shall not be present at that time.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> When an objection to 
an officer is allowed under sub-section (3) of section 84 that officer shall 
forthwith retire and take no further part in the proceedings.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> When an officer 
objected to retires and there is duly qualified waiting member in attendance, 
the presiding officer shall immediately appoint him to take the place of the 
officer who has retired.
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> The Court shall 
satisfy itself that a waiting member who takes the place of a member of the 
Court is of the required rank and not disqualified under the Act and shall give 
the accused an opportunity to object to him and shall deal with any such 
objection in accordance with the Act and these rules.
 </section><section>
<number>11</number> If, as a result of 
the allowance of an objection to a member, there are insufficient officers 
available to form a Court in compliance with the Act the Court shall report to 
the Convening Officer without proceeding further with the trial and convening 
officer may either appoint an officer as a member to fill the vacancy or convene 
a fresh Court to try the accused.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>67</number> Swearing or affirming 
of members.—As 
soon as the Court is constituted with the proper number of officers who are not 
objected to or objections in respect of whom have been overruled, an oath or 
affirmation shall be administered to every member in presence of the accused in 
one of the following forms or in such other form to the same purport as the 
Court ascertains to be according to his religion or otherwise binding on this 
conscience.
 
Forms of Oath
 
“I, ………………………………………… swear 
by Almighty God, that I will, well and truly, try the accused (or accused 
persons), before the Court, according to the evidence, and that I will, duly 
administer justice, according to the Border Security Force Act, 1968, without 
partiality, favour or affection; and I do further swear that I will not, on any 
account, at any time, whatsoever, disclose or discover, the vote or opinion of 
any particular member of the Court unless required to give evidence thereof by a 
Court of law.”
 
Form of Affirmation
 
“I, ……………………………………… do 
solemnly, sincerely and truly, declare and affirm, that I will well and truly, 
try the accused (or accused persons), before the Court, according to the 
evidence, and that I will, duly administer justice according to the Border 
Security Force Act, 1968 without partiality, favour or affection; and I do 
further solemnly, sincerely and truly declare and affirm that I will not, on any 
account at any time whatsoever, disclose or discover, the vote or opinion of any 
particular member of this Court unless required to give evidence thereof by a 
Court of law.”
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>68</number> Swearing or 
affirmation of Law Officer and other officers.—After 
the members of the Court are all sworn or have made affirmation, an oath or 
affirmation shall be administered to the following persons or such of them as 
are present at the Court in such of the following forms as shall be appropriate, 
or in such other form to the same purport as the Court ascertains to be 
according to the religion or otherwise binding on the conscience of the person 
to be sworn or affirmed.
 <section>
<number>A</number> Law Officer
 
Form of Oath
 
“I, …………………………………………, 
swear by Almighty God, that I will, to the best of my ability, carry out the 
duties of Law Officer, in accordance with the Border Security Force Act, 1968, 
and the rules made thereunder without partiality, favour or affection, and I do 
further swear that I will not, on any account at any time whatsoever, disclose 
or discover the vote or opinion on any matter of any particular member of this 
Court, unless required to give evidence thereof by a Court of law.”
 
Form of Affirmation
 
“I,……………………………………, do 
hereby, solemnly, sincerely and truly, declare and affirm that I will, to the 
best of my ability, carry out the duties of Law Officer in accordance with the 
Border Security Force Act, 1968 and the rules made thereunder without 
partiality, favour or affection, and I do further solemnly, sincerely and truly 
declare and affirm, that I will not, on any account, at any time, whatsoever, 
disclose or discover the vote or opinion, on any matter, of any particular 
member of this Court, unless, required to give evidence thereof by a Court of 
law.”
 </section><section>
<number>B</number> Officer attending for 
the purpose of instruction
 
Form of Oath
 
“I, …………………………………………, 
swear by Almighty God, that I will not on any account, and any time whatsoever, 
disclose or discover the vote or opinion of any particular member of this Court 
unless required to give evidence thereof by a Court of law.”
 
Form of Affirmation
 
“I,……………………………………, do 
solemnly, sincerely and truly, declare and affirm that I will not on any 
account, and any time whatsoever, disclose or discover the vote or opinion of 
any particular member of this Court unless required to give evidence thereof by 
a Court of law.”
 </section><section>
<number>C</number> Shorthand Writer
 
Form of Oath
 
“I, …………………………………………, 
swear by Almighty God, that I will truly take down to the best of my power, the 
evidence to be given before this Court and such other matters as I may be 
required to take down and will, when required, deliver to the Court a true 
transcript of the same.”
 
Form of Affirmation
 
“I,……………………………………, do 
solemnly, sincerely and truly, declare and affirm that I will truly take down to 
the best of my power the evidence to be given before this Court and such other 
matters as I may be required to take down and will, when required, deliver to 
the Court a true transcript of the same.”
 </section><section>
<number>D</number> Interpreter
 
Form of Oath
 
I, …………………………………………, swear 
by Almighty God, that I will faithfully, interpret and translate, as I shall be 
required to do, touching the matter before this Court.
 
Form of Affirmation
 
I,……………………………………, do 
solemnly, sincerely and truly, declare and affirm that I will faithfully 
interpret and translate, as I shall be required to do, touching the matter 
before this Court.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>69</number> Objection to 
interpreter or shorthand writer.—A 
person shall not be sworn or affirmed as an interpreter or shorthand writer, if 
he is objected to by the accused unless the Court, after hearing the accused and 
the prosecutor, disallows such objection as being unreasonable.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>70</number> Objection to Law 
Officer and prosecutor.—The 
accused shall not be permitted to object to the Law Officer or the prosecutor.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>71</number> Arraignment.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When the Court and the Law Officer (if any) have been sworn, the charge shall be 
read to the accused and shall be asked whether he pleads guilty or not guilty to 
the charge or charges.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If there is more than 
one charge, against the accused he shall be required to plead separately to each 
charge.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If there is more than 
one charge-sheet, against the accused, before the Court, the Court shall proceed 
with the charges in the first of such charge-sheets and shall announce its 
finding thereon and if the accused has pleaded guilty, comply with rule 78, 
before it arraigns him upon the charges in any subsequent charge-sheet.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>72</number> Plea to jurisdiction.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The accused, before pleading to the charge, may offer a plea regarding the 
jurisdiction of the Court; and in such a case—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the accused may adduce evidence 
in support of the plea and the prosecutor may adduce evidence in answer thereto; 
and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the prosecutor may address the 
Court in answer to the plea and the accused may reply to the prosecutor’s 
address.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If the Court allows 
the plea it shall adjourn and report to the convening officer.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> When the Court reports 
to the convening officer under this rule, the convening officer shall—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  if he approves the decision of 
the Court to allow the plea, dissolve the Court;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  if he disapproves the decision of 
the Court;
 
        either—
 <subsubsection>
             <number>i</number>  refer the matter back to 
the Court and direct them to proceed with trial; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>ii</number>  covene a fresh Court to try 
the accused.
</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>73</number> Objection to the 
charge.—
<section><number>1</number> An 
accused before pleading to a charge may object to it on the grounds that it is 
not correct in law or is not framed in accordance with these rules and if he 
does so, the prosecutor may address the Court in answer to the objection and the 
accused may reply to the prosecutor’s address.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the Court upholds 
the objection, it shall either amend the charge if permissible under rule 57 or 
adjourn and report to the convening officer:
 
Provided that if there is 
another charge or another charge-sheet before the Court, the Court may, before, 
adjourning under this rule, proceed with the trial of such other charge or other 
charge-sheet.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> When the Court reports 
to the convening officer under this rule, the convening officer shall—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  if he approves the decision of 
the Court to allow the objection,—
 <subsubsection>
             <number>i</number>  dissolve the Court; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>ii</number>  where there is another 
charge or another charge-sheet before the Court to which the objection does not 
relate and which the Court has not tried, direct the Court to proceed with the 
trial of such other charge or charge-sheet only; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>iii</number>  amend the charge to which 
the objection relates if permissible under rule 58 and direct the Court to try 
it as amended,
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  if he disapproves the decision of 
the Court to allow the objection,—
 <subsubsection>
             <number>i</number>  direct the Court to try the 
charge; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>ii</number>  where there is another 
charge or another charge-sheet before the Court to which the objection does not 
relate and which the Court has not tried, direct the Court to proceed with the 
trial of such other charge or charge-sheet only; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>iii</number>  convene a fresh Court to 
try the accused.
</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>74</number> Plea in bar of trial.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An accused before pleading to a charge may offer a plea that the trial is barred 
under section 75 or section 76. If he does so,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the accused may adduce evidence 
in support of the plea and the prosecutor may adduce evidence in answer thereto, 
and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the prosecutor may address the 
Court in answer to the plea and the accused may reply to the prosecutor’s 
address.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If the Court allows 
the plea it shall adjourn and report to the convening officer:
 
Provided that if there is 
another charge or another charge-sheet before the Court, the Court may, before 
adjourning under this rule, proceed with the trial of such other charge or other 
charge-sheet.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> When a Court reports 
to the convening officer under this rule, the convening officer shall,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  if he approves the decision of 
the Court to allow the plea,—
 <subsubsection>
             <number>i</number>  dissolve the Court; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>ii</number>  where there is another 
charge or another charge-sheet before the Court to which the plea does not 
relate and which the Court has not tried, direct the Court to proceed with the 
trial of such other charge or charge-sheet only.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  if he disapproves the decision of 
the Court to allow the plea—
 <subsubsection>
             <number>i</number>  direct the Court to try the 
charge; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>ii</number>  where there is another 
charge or another charge-sheet before the Court to which the plea does not 
relate and which the Court has not tried direct the Court to proceed with the 
trial of such other charge or charge-sheet only; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>iii</number>  convene a fresh Court to 
try the accused.
</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>75</number> Application for 
separate trial.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where two or more accused are charged jointly, any one of the accused may, 
before pleading to the charge, apply to the Court to be tried separately on the 
ground that he would be prejudiced in his defence if he were not tried 
separately.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the accused 
makes such an application, the prosecutor may address the Court in answer 
thereto and the accused may reply to the prosecutor’s address.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the Court is of 
the opinion that the interests of justice so require it shall allow the 
application and try separately the accused who made it.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>76</number> Application for trial 
on separate charge-sheet.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where a charge-sheet contains more than one charge, the accused may, before 
pleading to the charges, apply to the Court to be tried separately on any charge 
in that charge-sheet on the ground that he would be prejudiced in his defence if 
he were not tried separately on that charge.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the accused 
makes such an application, the prosecutor may address the Court in answer 
thereto and the accused may reply to the prosecutor’s address.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the Court is of 
the opinion that interests of justice so require it shall allow the application 
and try the accused separately on the charge to which it relates as if that 
charge had been inserted in a separate charge-sheet.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>77</number> Pleading to the 
charge.—
<section><number>1</number> 
After any plea under rules 72 and 74, any objection under rule 73 and 
applications under rules 75 and 76 have been dealt with, the accused shall be 
required subject to sub-rule (2) to plead either guilty or not guilty to each 
charge on which he is arraigned.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where a Court is 
empowered by section 93 to find an accused guilty of an offence other than that 
charged or guilty of committing the offence in circumstances involving a less 
degree of punishment or where it could after hearing the evidence, make a 
special finding of guilty subject to exceptions or variations in accordance with 
rule 99, the accused may plead guilty to such other offence or to the offence 
charged as having been committed in circumstances involving a less degree of 
punishment or to the offence charged subject to such exceptions or variations.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>78</number> Acceptance of plea of 
guilty.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where an accused pleads guilty to a charge under either sub-rule (1) or sub-rule 
(2) of rule 77, the Presiding Officer or Law Officer shall, before the Court 
decides to accept the plea, explain to the accused the nature of the charge and 
the general effect of his plea and in particular the difference in procedure 
when an accused pleads guilty and when an accused pleads not guilty.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A Court shall not 
accept a plea of guilty under either sub-rule (1) or sub-rule (2) of rule 77, 
if—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the Court is not satisfied that 
the accused understands the nature of the charge or the effect of his plea; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the presiding officer having 
regard to all the circumstances, considers that the accused should plead not 
guilty; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  the accused is liable, if 
convicted, to be sentenced to death.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> (a) In the case of a 
plea of guilty under rule 79, a Court shall not accept the plea unless the 
convening officer concurs and it is satisfied of the justice of such course.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The concurrence of the 
convening officer may be signified by the prosecutor.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> Where a plea of guilty 
under either sub-rule (1) or sub-rule (2) of rule 77 is not accepted by the 
Court or the accused either refuses to plead to the charge or does not plead to 
it intelligibly, the Court shall record a plea of not guilty.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> When a Court is 
satisfied that it can properly accept a plea of guilty under either sub-rule (1) 
or sub-rule (2) of rule 77, it shall record a finding of guilty in respect 
thereof.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>79</number> Plea on alternative 
charge.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When an accused pleads guilty to the first of two or more alternative charges, 
the Court, if it accepts the accused’s plea of guilty, shall record a finding of 
guilty in respect of the first charge and the prosecutor shall withdraw any 
alternative charge before the accused is arraigned on it.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When an accused pleads 
guilty to one of two or more charges which are laid in the alternative other 
than the first of such charges, the Court may—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  proceed as if the accused had 
pleaded not guilty to all the charges; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  (i) With concurrence of the 
convening officer (which may be signified by the prosecutor) record a finding of 
guilty on the charge to which the accused has pleaded guilty and a finding of 
not guilty on any alternative charge which is placed before it in the 
charge-sheet.
 <subsubsection>
            <number>ii</number>  Where the Court records 
such finding the prosecutor shall before the accused is arraigned on it withdraw 
any charge which is alternative to the charge of which the Court has found the 
accused guilty and which is placed after it in the charge-sheet.
</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>80</number> Order of trial where 
plea of guilty and not guilty.—
<section><number>1</number> 
After the Court has recorded a finding of guilty, if there is not other charge 
in the same charge sheet to which the accused has pleaded not guilty and no 
other accused who has pleaded not guilty to a charge in that charge-sheet, it 
shall proceed with the trial as directed by rule 81.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where there is another 
charge in the charge-sheet to which the accused has pleaded not guilty or there 
is another accused who has pleaded not guilty to a charge in that charge-sheet, 
the Court shall not comply with rule 81 until after it has dealt with such other 
charge or tried such other accused and has announced and recorded its finding in 
respect thereof.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>81</number> Procedure on plea of 
guilty.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When the Court has recorded a finding of guilty in respect of a charge to which 
an accused had pleaded guilty the prosecutor shall read the record or abstract 
of evidence to the Court or inform the Court of the facts contained therein:
 
Provided that if an 
expurgated copy of the record or abstract of evidence was sent to the Presiding 
Officer, the prosecutor shall not read to the Court those parts of the record or 
abstract of evidence which have been expurgated or inform the Court of the facts 
contained on those parts, and shall not hand over the original record or 
abstract of evidence to the Court until the trial is concluded.
 

1[***]
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> After 

2[sub-rule (1) has] 
been complied with, the accused may,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  adduce evidence of character and 
in mitigation of punishment;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  address the Court in mitigation 
of punishment.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> After sub-rule (3) has 
been complied with, the Court shall proceed as directed in rule 101.
 
 





</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>82</number> Change of plea.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An accused who has pleaded not guilty may at any time before the Court closes to 
deliberate on its finding withdraw his plea of not guilty and substitute a plea 
of guilty [including a plea of guilty under rule (79)] and in such a case the 
Court shall, if it is satisfied that it can accept the accused’s changed plea 
under these rules, record a finding in accordance with the accused’s changed 
plea and so far as is necessary proceed as directed by rule 81.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where at any time 
during the trial it appears to the Court that an accused who has pleaded guilty 
does not understand the effect of his plea or the nature of the charge the Court 
shall enter a plea of not guilty and proceed with the trial accordingly.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> When the Court records 
a plea of not guilty in respect of any charge under sub-rule (2) it shall, if 
there was a charge laid in the alternative thereto which the prosecutor withdrew 
under rule 79 reinstate such alternative charge, arraign the accused thereon and 
proceed with the trial as if it has never been withdrawn.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>83</number> Procedure on pleas of 
not guilty.—After 
a plea of not guilty to any charge has been recorded,—
 <section>
        <number>i</number>  the Court shall ask the accused 
whether he wishes to apply for an adjournment on the ground that any of these 
rules relating the procedure before trial has not been complied with and that he 
has been prejudiced thereby or on the ground that he has not had sufficient 
opportunity for preparing his defence;
 </section><section>
        <number>ii</number>  where the accused applies for 
an adjournment—
 <subsection>
            <number>a</number>  the accused may adduce 
evidence in support of his application and the prosecutor may adduce evidence in 
answer thereto, and
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>b</number>  the prosecutor may address 
the Court in answer to the application and the accused may reply to the 
prosecutor’s address.
 </subsection></section><section>
       <number>iii</number>  the Court may grant an 
adjournment if it thinks the interests of justice so require.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>84</number> Opening address.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The prosecutor may, if he so desires, and shall, if required by the Court, make 
an opening address explaining the charge and the nature and general effect of 
the evidence which he proposes to adduce.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The witnesses for the 
prosecution shall then be called and give their evidence.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>85</number> Additional witness.—Where 
the prosecutor intends to adduce evidence which is not contained in any record 
or abstract of evidence given to the accused notice of such intention together 
with the particulars of the evidence shall, when practicable, be given to the 
accused a reasonable time before the evidence is adduced. If such evidence is 
adduced without such notice or particulars having been given, the Court may, if 
the accused so desires either adjourn after receiving the evidence or allow any 
cross-examination arising out of that evidence to be postponed, and the Court 
shall inform the accused of his right to apply for such an adjournment or 
postponement.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>86</number> Dropping witnesses.—The 
prosecutor shall not be bound to call all the witnesses against the accused 
whose evidence is contained in the record or abstract of evidence, or a witness 
when he has notified the accused that he intends to call under rule 85, but if 
the prosecutor does not intend to call such witness to give evidence, he shall 
either tender him for cross-examination by the accused, or give the accused 
reasonable notice that he does not intend to call the witness and that the 
accused will be allowed to communicate with him and to call him as a witness for 
the defence, if he so desires and if the witness is available.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>87</number> Withdrawal of 
witnesses.—During 
a trial a witness other than the prosecutor or accused shall not, except by 
leave of the Court, be in Court while not under examination, and if, while he is 
under examination a discussion arises as to whether a question is to be allowed 
or not with regard to his evidence the Court may direct the witness to withdraw 
during such discussion.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>88</number> Examination of 
witnesses.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A witness may be examined by the person calling him and may be cross-examined by 
the opposite party to the proceedings and on the conclusion of any such 
cross-examination may be re-examined by the person who called him on matters 
arising out of the cross-examination.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> (a) The person 
examining a witness shall put his questions to the witness orally and unless an 
objection is made by the witness, the Court, the Law Officer, the prosecutor or 
by the accused, the witness shall reply forthwith.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> Where such an 
objection is made, the witness shall not reply until the objection has been 
disposed of.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The Court may allow 
the cross-examination or re-examination of a witness to be postponed.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Before the examination 
of a witness, he shall be administered an oath or affirmation in the following 
form or in such other form to the same purport as the Court ascertains to be in 
accordance with his religion or otherwise binding on his conscience.
 
Form of Oath
 
“I,.…………………………………………………, 
swear by Almighty God, that whatever I shall state, shall be the truth, the 
whole truth and nothing but the truth.”
 
Form of Affirmation
 
“I,…………………………………………, do 
solemnly, truly and sincerely, declare and affirm that whatever I shall state, 
shall be the truth, the whole truth and nothing but the truth.”
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>89</number> Questioning by the 
Court.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
Presiding Officer, the Law Officer and any member of the Court may put questions 
to a witness.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Upon any such question 
being answered, the prosecutor and the accused may put to the witness such 
questions arising from the answer which he has given as seem proper to the 
Court.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>90</number> Reading over of 
evidence.—
<section><number>1</number> 

<subsection><number>a</number> The record which has been made of the evidence given by a witness shall be 
read back to him before he leaves the Court and when this is done he may ask for 
the record to be corrected or explain the evidence which he has given.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> Where any such 
correction is made or explanation given, the prosecutor and the accused may put 
such questions to the witness respecting the correction or explanation as seem 
proper to the Court.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> When a shorthand 
writer is employed it shall not be necessary to comply with sub-rule (1), if, in 
the opinion of the Court and the Law Officer (if any) it is unnecessary to do 
so:
 
Provided that if any 
witness so demands, sub-rule (1) shall be complied with.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>91</number> Calling or recalling 
witnesses by the Court.—
<section><number>1</number> 

<subsection><number>a</number> Court may at any time before it closes to deliberate on its finding or if 
there is a Law Officer before he begins to sum up, call a witness or recall a 
witness, if in the opinion of the Court it is in the interest of justice to do 
so.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> Where the Court calls 
a witness or recalls a witness under this rule, the prosecutor and the accused 
may put such questions to the witness as seem proper to the Court.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The prosecutor and the 
accused may, at any time before the Court closes to deliberate on its finding or 
if there is Law Officer before he begins to sum up, recall a witness by leave of 
the Court and the prosecutor and the accused may put such questions to the 
witness as seem proper to the Court.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>92</number> Submission of no case 
to answer and stopping of cases.—
<section><number>1</number> 

<subsection><number>a</number> At the close of the case for the prosecution the accused may submit to the 
Court in respect of any charge that the prosecution has failed to establish a 
prima facie case for him to answer and that he should not be called upon to 
make his defence to that charge.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> Where the accused 
makes such submission the prosecutor may address the Court in answer thereto and 
the accused may reply to the prosecutor’s address.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Court shall not 
allow the submission unless it is satisfied that—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the prosecution has not 
established a prima facie case on the charge as laid; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  it is not open to it on the 
evidence to make a special finding under either section 93 or sub-rule (4) of 
rule 99.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> (a) Where the Court 
allows the submission, it, shall find the accused not guilty of the charge to 
which it relates and subject to confirmation the finding shall forthwith be 
announced in open Court.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> Where the Court 
disallows the submission it shall proceed with the trial of the offence as 
charged.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The Court may, of its 
own motion, after the close of the hearing of the case for the prosecution, and 
after hearing the prosecutor find the accused not guilty of the charge and 
subject to confirmation the finding shall forthwith be announced in open Court.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>93</number> Case for the defence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
After the close of the case for the prosecution, the Presiding Officer or the 
Law Officer (if any) shall explain to the accused that,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  if he wishes, he may give 
evidence on oath as a witness or make a statement without being sworn but that 
he is not obliged to do either;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  if he gives evidence on oath, he 
shall be liable to be cross-examined by the prosecutor and to be questioned by 
the Court.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> For the purpose of 
enabling the accused to explain any circumstances appearing in the evidence 
against him, the Court may, at any stage of the trial, without previously 
warning the accused, put such questions to him as the Court considers necessary, 
and shall for the purpose aforesaid, question him generally on the case after 
the witnesses for the prosecution have been examined and before he is called on 
for his defence.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The accused shall not 
render himself liable to punishment by refusing to answer such questions, or by 
giving false answers to them but the Court may draw such inference from such 
refusal or answers as it thinks just.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The answers given by 
the accused may be taken into consideration in such trial and put in evidence 
for or against him in any other inquiry into, or trial for, any other offence 
which such answers may tend to show he has committed.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If the accused intends 
to call a witness to the facts of the case other than himself, he may make an 
opening address outlining the case for the defence before the evidence for the 
defence is given.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>94</number> Witnesses for defence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
After rule 93 has been complied with, the witnesses for the defence (if any) 
shall be called to give their evidence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The provisions of 
rules 88, 89 and 90 shall apply to the witnesses for the defence as they apply 
to the evidence of witnesses for the prosecution.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>95</number> Witnesses in reply.—After 
the witnesses for the defence have given their evidence the prosecutor may by 
leave of the Court call a witness or recall a witness to give evidence on any 
matter raised by the accused in his defence which the prosecution could not 
properly have mentioned to the Court before the accused disclosed his defence or 
which the prosecution could not reasonably have foreseen.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>96</number> Closing addresses.—
<section><number>1</number> 
After all the evidence has been given the prosecutor and the accused may each 
make a closing address to the Court.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The accused shall be 
entitled to make his closing address after the closing address by the prosecutor 
unless the accused has called a witness to facts other than himself, in which 
case the prosecutor shall be entitled, subject to sub-rules (3) and (4) to make 
his closing address after the accused has made the closing address.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where two or more 
accused are tried jointly, any one of them who has called on such witness shall 
be entitled to make his closing address after the prosecutor has made the 
closing address.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> (a) Where two or more 
accused are represented by the same defending officer or counsel he may make one 
closing address only.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> Where any one of the 
accused for whom he appears has called no witness to facts other than himself 
such defending officer or counsel shall be entitled to make his closing address 
after the prosecutor has made the closing address.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>97</number> Summing up by Law 
Officer.—After 
the closing addresses, if there is a Law Officer he shall sum up the evidence 
and advise the Court on the law relating to the case in open Court.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>98</number> Deliberation on 
finding.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Court shall deliberate on its finding in closed Court in the presence of the 
Law Officer.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The opinion of each 
member of the Court as to the finding shall be given by the word of mouth on 
each charge separately starting with the junior most in rank.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>99</number> Record and 
announcement of finding.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
The finding on every charge upon which the accused is arraigned shall be 
recorded and, except as provided in these rules, shall be recorded simply as a 
finding of “Guilty” or of “Not Guilty”. After recording the finding on each 
charge, the Court shall give brief reasons in support thereof. The Law Officer 
or, if there is none, the Presiding Officer shall record or cause to be recorded 
such brief reasons in the proceedings. The above record shall be signed and 
dated by the Presiding Officer and the Law Officer, if any.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the Court is of 
opinion as regards any charge that the facts proved do not disclose the offence, 
charge or any offence of which he might under the Act legally be found guilty on 
the charge as laid, the Court shall acquit the accused of that charge.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If the Court has 
doubts as regards any charge whether the facts proved show the accused to be 
guilty on the charge as laid, it may, before recording a finding on that charge, 
refer to the confirming authority for an opinion, setting out the facts which it 
finds to be proved and may if necessary, adjourn for that purpose.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where the Court is of 
opinion as regards any charge that the facts which it finds to be proved in 
evidence differ materially from the facts alleged in the statement of 
particulars in the charge but are nevertheless sufficient to prove the offence 
stated in the charge, and that the difference is not so material as to have 
prejudiced the accused in his defence, it may, instead of a finding of “Not 
Guilty” record a special finding.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The special finding 
may find the accused guilty on a charge subject to the statement of exceptions 
of variations specified therein.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Where there are 
alternative charges, and the facts proved appear to the Court not to constitute 
the offence mentioned in any of those alternative charges, the Court shall 
record a finding of “Not Guilty” on that charge.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The Court shall not 
find the accused guilty on more than one of two or more charges laid in the 
alternative, even if conviction upon one charge necessarily connotes guilty upon 
the alternative charge or charges.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> If the Court thinks 
that the facts proved constitute one of the offences stated in two or more of 
the alternative charges, but doubts which of those offences the facts do at law 
constitute, it may, before recording a finding on those charges, refer to the 
confirming authority for an opinion, setting out the facts which it finds to be 
proved and stating that it doubts whether those facts constitute in law the 
offence stated in such one or other of the charges and may, if necessary, 
adjourn for that purpose.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> The finding on each 
charge shall be announced forthwith in open Court as subject to confirmation.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>100</number> Procedure on 
acquittal.—If 
the finding on all the charges is “Not Guilty” the presiding officer shall affix 
his signature and date on the finding and such signature shall authenticate the 
whole of the proceedings, and the proceedings upon being signed by the Law 
Officer (if any) shall be at once transmitted for confirmation.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>101</number> Procedure on 
conviction.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If the finding on any charge is “Guilty”, then, for the guidance of the Court in 
determining its sentence, and of the confirming authority in considering the 
sentence, the Court before deliberating on the sentence, shall, whenever 
possible, take evidence of and record the general character, age, service, rank, 
any recognised acts of gallantry or distinguished conduct of the accused, any 
previous convictions of the accused either by Security Force Court or a criminal 
Court, any previous punishments awarded to him by an officer exercising 
authority under sections 53 or 55 as the case may be; the length of time he has 
been in arrest or in confinement on any previous sentence, and any decoration, 
or reward, of which he may be in possession or to which he is entitled.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Evidence on the above 
matters may be given by a witness verifying a statement which contains a summary 
of the entries in the service books respecting the accused and identifying the 
accused as the person referred to in that summary.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The accused may 
cross-examine any such witness and may call witnesses to rebut such evidence; 
and if the accused so requests, the service books or a duly certified copy of 
the material entries therein, shall be produced and if the accused alleges that 
the summary is in respect not in accordance with the service books or such 
certified copy, as the case may be the Court shall compare the summary with 
those books or copy and if it finds that it is not in accordance therewith, 
shall cause summary to be corrected or the objection of the accused to be 
recorded.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> When all the evidence 
on the above matters has been given, the accused may address the Court thereon 
and in mitigation of punishment.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>102</number> Sentence.—The 
Court shall award a single sentence in respect of all the offences of which the 
accused is found guilty, and such sentence shall be deemed to be awarded in 
respect of which it can be legally given and not to be awarded in respect of 
which it cannot be legally given.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>103</number> Recommendation for 
mercy.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where the Court makes a recommendation to mercy it shall give its reasons for 
its recommendation.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The number of opinions 
by which the recommendation to mercy mentioned in this rule, or any question 
relating thereto, is adopted or rejected, may be entered in the proceedings.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>104</number> Announcement of 
sentence and signing and transmission of proceedings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The sentence together with any recommendation to mercy and the reason for any 
such recommendation shall be announced forthwith in open Court. The sentence 
will be announced as subject to confirmation.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Upon the Court 
awarding the sentence, the Presiding Officer shall affix his signature and date 
the sentence and such signature shall authenticate the whole of the proceedings 
and the proceedings upon being signed by the Law Officer (if any), shall at once 
be transmitted for confirmation.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>105</number> Revision.—
<section><number>1</number> 

<subsection><number>a</number> Where the finding is sent back for revision under section 113, the Court 
shall re-assemble in open Court, the revision order shall be read and if the 
Court, is directed to take fresh evidence such evidence shall be taken in open 
Court.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> Where such fresh 
evidence is recorded otherwise than at the instance of the accused, the accused 
shall be given a further opportunity to lead evidence in respect of matters 
brought out in such fresh evidence.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> The prosecutor and the 
accused shall be given a further opportunity to address the Court in respect of 
the fresh evidence led.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> The Law Officer may 
also give a further summing up.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the revision of 
finding does not involve taking of fresh evidence, the accused shall be given an 
opportunity to address the Court in respect of matter raised in the revision 
order.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> (a) The Court shall 
then deliberate on its finding in closed Court and if the Court does not adhere 
to its former finding, it shall revoke the finding and sentence and record a new 
finding and if such new finding involves a sentence pass sentence afresh.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> Where the original 
finding was one of “Not Guilty”, the Court shall, before passing sentence comply 
with rules 101 and 102.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> (a) Where the sentence 
alone is sent back for revision, the revision order shall be read in open Court 
and the accused given an opportunity to address the Court in regard to matters 
referred to in the revision order.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The Court shall then 
reconsider its sentence in closed Court and if it does not adhere to the 
sentence, revoke the sentence and pass sentence afresh.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> Where the sentence 
alone is sent for revision the Court shall not revise the finding.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>106</number> Confirmation and 
promulgation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When a confirming authority receives the record of the proceedings of a Court, 
it shall record its decision thereon and on any sentence and any order which the 
Court may have made under section 105 on the record of the proceedings in the 
appropriate form set out in Appendix VIII and such record of his decision shall 
form part of the record of the proceedings.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When a Court has 
accepted a plea of guilty made under rule 79 the confirming authority may 
confirm its finding notwithstanding that the Court has accepted the plea without 
the concurrence of the convening officer, if, in the opinion of the confirming 
authority it is in the interests of justice to do so.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> (a) When a Court has 
rejected a plea to the jurisdiction of the Court or a plea in bar of trial or 
has over-ruled an objection to a charge, it shall not be necessary for the 
confirming authority to approve specifically the decision of the Court, but its 
approval shall be implied from its confirming the finding on the charge to which 
the plea or objection relates.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> Where it disapproves 
the decision of the Court to reject the plea or to over-rule the objection it 
shall withhold confirmation of the finding on the charge to which the plea or 
objection relates.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> A confirming authority 
may state its reasons for withholding confirmation in any case, but if it 
withholds confirmation where a Court has rejected a plea to the jurisdiction or 
plea in bar of trial or has over-ruled an objection to the charges because it 
disapproves this decision of the Court, it shall when recording its decision 
under sub-rule (1) state that it has withheld confirmation for this reason.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where the sentence of 
a Court is improperly expressed, the confirming authority may in confirming the 
sentence vary the form thereof so that it shall be properly expressed.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Wherever it appears 
that there is sufficient evidence on a plea of guilty under either sub-rule (1) 
or sub-rule (2) of rule 79 to justify the finding of the Court, such finding and 
any lawful sentence consequent thereon may be confirmed and if confirmed shall 
be valid, notwithstanding any deviation from these rules, if the accused has not 
been prejudiced by such deviation.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> While confirming the 
finding the confirming authority may either unconditionally or subject to 
conditions which the accused accepts, reduce or remit a portion of the sentence 
or commute the punishment to one given lower in the scale of punishments in 
section 48.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> (a) When a confirming 
authority has confirmed a finding and a sentence of a Court or has withheld 
confirmation thereof, it shall send the record of the proceedings to the 
Commandant of the accused for promulgation to the accused of the finding and 
sentence or the fact that confirmation has been withheld as the case may be.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The fact of 
promulgation shall be recorded on the record of the proceedings in the form set 
out in Appendix IX.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> Where confirmation has 
been withheld because the confirming authority disapproves the Court’s decision 
to reject a plea to the jurisdiction or a plea in bar of trial or to over-rule 
an objection to the charge, the accused shall be so informed.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>107</number> Seating of members.—The 
members of a Court shall take their seats according to their rank.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>108</number> Responsibility of 
Presiding Officer.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Presiding Officer is responsible for the trial being conducted in proper 
order, and in accordance with the Act, rules made thereunder and in a manner 
befitting a Court of justice.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It is the duty of the 
Presiding Officer to see that the accused has a fair trial, and that he does not 
suffer any disadvantage in consequence of his position as a person under trial, 
or of his ignorance, or of his incapacity to examine or cross examine witnesses, 
or otherwise.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>109</number> Power of Court over 
address of prosecutor and accused.—
<section><number>1</number> 
It is duty of the prosecutor to assist the Court in the administration of 
justice, to behave impartially, to bring the whole of the transaction before the 
Court and not to take any unfair advantage of, or suppress any evidence in 
favour of the accused.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The prosecutor may not 
refer to any matter, not relevant to the charge or charges, then before the 
Court, and it is the duty of the Court to stop him from so doing and also to 
restrain any undue violence of language or want of fairness or moderation on the 
part of the prosecutor.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Court shall give 
reasonable facilities to the accused, in making his defence; the accused must 
abstain from any remarks contemptuous or disrespectful towards the Court and 
from coarse and insulting language towards others, but he may for the purpose of 
his defence impeach the evidence and charge other persons with blame and even 
criminality, subject, if he does so, to any liability which he may thereby 
incur. The Court may caution the accused as to the irrelevance of his defence, 
but shall not, unless in special cases stop his defence solely on ground of such 
irrelevance.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>110</number> Sitting in Close 
Court.—
<section><number>1</number> A 
Court shall, where it is so directed by these rules, and may in any other case 
on any deliberation amongst the members, sit in closed Court.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No person shall be 
present in closed Court except the members of the Court, the Law Officer (if 
any) and any officers under instruction.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> For the purpose of 
giving effect to the foregoing provisions of this rule, a Court may either 
retire or cause the place where it sits to be cleared of all other persons not 
entitled to be present.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Except as hereinbefore 
mentioned all proceedings, including the view of any place, shall be in open 
Court and in the presence of the accused subject to sub-rule (5).
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Court shall have 
the power to exclude from the Court any witness who has yet to give evidence or 
any other person, other than the accused, who interferes with its proceedings.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>111</number> Continuity of trial 
and adjournment of Court.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When a Court is once assembled and the accused has been arraigned, the Court 
shall continue the trial from day-to-day in accordance with these rules unless 
it appears to the Court that an adjournment is necessary for the ends of justice 
or that such continuance is impracticable.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> (a) A Court may from time to 
time adjourn its proceedings and meet at such place as may be convenient, and
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> Wherever necessary, 
visit the scene of occurrence.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The senior officer on 
the spot may also for exigencies of service adjourn or prolong the adjournment 
of the Court.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A Court in the absence 
of a Law Officer (if one has been appointed for that Court) shall not proceed, 
and shall adjourn.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If the time to which 
an adjournment is made is not specified, the adjournment shall be until further 
orders from the proper Force authority; and, if the place to which an 
adjournment is made is not specified, the adjournment shall be to the same place 
or to such other place as may be specified in further orders from the proper 
Force authority.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>112</number> Suspension of trial.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where, in consequence of anything arising while the Court is sitting, the Court 
is unable by reason of dissolution as specified in section 71 or otherwise, to 
continue the trial, the Presiding Officer or, in his absence, the senior member 
present, shall immediately report the facts to the convening authority.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>113</number> Proceedings on death 
or illness of accused.—In 
the case of the death of the accused or of such illness of the accused as 
renders it impossible to continue the trial, the Court shall ascertain the fact 
of the death or illness by evidence and record the same and adjourn and transmit 
the proceedings to the convening authority.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>114</number> Death, retirement or 
absence of Presiding Officer.—In 
the case of the death, retirement or change or unavoidable absence of the 
Presiding Officer, the next senior officer shall take the place of the Presiding 
Officer and the trial shall proceed if the Court is still composed of not less 
than the minimum number of officers of which it is required by law to consist.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>115</number> Presence throughout 
of all members of Court.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A member of a Court who has been absent while any part of the evidence on the 
trial of an accused person is taken, shall take no further part in the trial by 
that Court of that person, but the Court will not be affected unless it is 
reduced below the legal minimum.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An officer shall not 
be added to a Court after the accused has been arraigned.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>116</number> Taking of opinions of 
members of Court.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every member of a Court must give his opinion by word of mouth on every question 
which the Court has to decide, and must give his opinion as to the sentence 
notwithstanding that he has given his opinion in favour of acquittal.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The opinion of the 
members of the Court shall be taken in succession, beginning with the member 
lowest in rank.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>117</number> Procedure on 
incidental questions.—If 
any objection is raised on any matter of Law, evidence, or procedure, by the 
prosecutor or by or on behalf of the accused during the trial, the prosecutor or 
the accused or counsel or the defending officer (as the case may be) shall have 
a right to answer the same and the person raising the objection shall have a 
right to reply.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>118</number> Evidence when to be 
translated.—When 
any evidence is given in a language which any of the officers composing the 
Court, the accused or the Law Officer does not understand, it shall be 
translated into a language which he understands.
</article> 
 The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article><number>120</number> Custody and inspection of 
proceedings.—The proceedings shall be deemed 
to be in the custody of the Law Officer (if any) or, if there is none, of the 
Presiding Officer but may, with proper precaution for their safety, be inspected 
by the members of the Court, the prosecutor and accused, at all reasonable time 
before the Court is closed to consider the finding.</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>

1[<number>121</number> Review of General/Petty 
Security Force Court 
proceedings.—The 
proceedings of a General and Petty Security Force Court shall be sent by the 
person having the custody thereof to the Chief Law Officer for review, who shall 
then forward the same to the confirming authority.]
 
 




</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>122</number> Defending Officer, 
friend of accused and counsel.—
<section><number>1</number> 
At any General or Petty Security Force Court an accused person may be 
represented by a counsel or by any officer subject to the Act who shall be 
called “the defending officer” or assisted by any person whose services he may 
be able to procure and who shall be called “the friend of the accused”.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Defending Officer 
shall have the same rights and duties as appertain to a counsel under these 
rules and shall be under the like obligations.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The friend of the 
accused may advise the accused on all points and suggest the questions to be put 
to the witnesses, but he shall not examine or cross-examine the witnesses, or 
address the Court.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>123</number> Requirement for 
appearance of counsel.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An accused person intending to be represented by a counsel shall give to his 
Commandant or to the Convening Officer the earliest practicable notice of such 
intention, and, if no sufficient notice has been given, the Court may, if it 
thinks fit, on the application of the prosecutor, adjourn to enable him to 
obtain a counsel on behalf of the prosecutor at the trial.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the Convening 
Officer so directs, counsel may appear alongwith the prosecutor, but in that 
case, unless the notice referred to in sub-rule (1) has been given by the 
accused, notice of the direction for counsel to appear shall be given to the 
accused at such time (not in any case less than seven days) before the trial as 
would, in the opinion of the Court, have enabled the accused to obtain counsel 
to assist him at the trial.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The counsel, who 
appears before a Court on behalf of the prosecutor or accused, shall have the 
same rights as the prosecutor or accused for whom he appears to call, and orally 
examine, cross-examine, and re-examine witnesses, to put in any plea, and to 
inspect the proceedings and shall have the right otherwise to act in the course 
of the trial in place of the person on whose behalf he appears, and he shall 
comply with these rules as if he were that person and in such a case that person 
shall have no right himself to do any of the aforesaid matters except as regards 
the statement allowed by sub-rule (2) of rule 93 and sub-rule (4) of rule 101 or 
except so far as the Court permits him so to do.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> When counsel appears 
on behalf of the prosecutor; the prosecutor if called as witness, may be 
examined and re-examined as any other witness.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>124</number> Disqualification of 
Law Officer.—An 
officer who is disqualified for sitting on a Court, shall be disqualified for 
acting as a Law Officer at that Court.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>125</number> Substitution on 
death, illness or absence of Law Officer.—If 
the Law Officer dies, or from illness or from any cause whatever is unable to 
attend, the Court shall adjourn, and the Presiding Officer shall report the 
circumstances to the Convening Officer; and a fit person may be appointed by 
that officer who shall be sworn or affirmed, and act as Law Officer for the 
residue of the trial, or until the Law Officer returns.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>126</number> Power and duties of 
Law Officer.—Where 
a Law Officer has been named to act on the Court, he shall,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  given his opinion on any question 
of law relating to the charge or trial whenever so required by the Court, the 
prosecutor or the accused;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  inform the Court of any 
irregularity or other infirmity in the proceedings;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  inform the Convening Officer and 
the Court of any infirmity or defect in the charge or in the constitution of the 
Court;
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  sum up the evidence and give his 
opinion on any question of law, before the Court proceeds to deliberate upon its 
findings.
 <subsection>
<number>2</number> It shall be the duty 
of the Law Officer to ensure that the accused does not suffer any disadvantage 
in consequence of his position as such, or because of ignorance or incapacity to 
examine or cross-examine witnesses and for this purpose the Law Officer may with 
the permission of the Court, call witnesses and put questions to them which 
appear to him to be necessary or desirable.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>3</number> In the discharge of 
his duties, the Law Officer shall maintain an attitude of strict impartiality.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>4</number> Where any opinion has 
been given by the Law Officer to the Court on any matter before it, it may be 
entered in the proceedings, if the Law Officer or the Court desires it to be 
entered.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>5</number> The Law Officer shall 
represent the Chief Law Officer at a Security Force Court.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>127</number> Finding of insanity.—Where 
the Court finds either that the accused, by reason of unsoundness of mind, is 
incapable of making his defence, or that he committed the act alleged but was by 
reason of unsoundness of mind incapable of knowing the nature of the act or that 
it was wrong or contrary to law, the Presiding Officer or in the case of Summary 
Security Force Court, the officer holding the trial, shall affix his signature 
and the date on the finding which shall also be signed by the Law Officer (if 
any) and thereupon the proceedings shall, at once, be transmitted to the 
confirming authority or in the case of Summary Security Force Court to the 
Deputy Inspector-General empowered to countersign them.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>128</number> Preservation of 
proceedings.—The 
proceedings of every Court shall, after promulgation, be forwarded, to the 
officer of the Chief Law Officer and be preserved there for not less than seven 
years, or until the sentence awarded by the Court has expired, whichever is 
later.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>129</number> Right of person tried 
to copies of proceedings.—Every 
person tried by a Security Force Court shall be entitled to obtain on demand, at 
any time after the confirmation of the finding and sentence, when such 
confirmation is required and before the proceedings are destroyed, from the 
Chief Law Officer a copy thereof, including the proceedings upon revision, if 
any.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>130</number> Copy of proceedings 
not to be given in certain cases.—Notwithstanding 
anything contained in rule 129 if the Central Government is satisfied for 
reasons to be recorded that it is against the interests of the security of the 
State or friendly relations with foreign states to supply a copy of the 
proceedings or any part thereof under the said rule, he shall not be furnished 
with such a copy:
 
Provided that if the 
Central Government is satisfied that the person demanding the copy is desirous 
of submitting a petition in accordance with the Act or instituting any action in 
a Court of law in relation to the finding or sentence, it shall permit 
inspection of the proceedings by such a person or his legal advisor, if any, on 
the following conditions, namely:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  the inspection shall be made at 
such time and such places as the Central Government or any authority authorised 
by it may direct; and
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  the person allowed to inspect the 
proceedings shall, before such inspection, furnish,—
 <subsection>
             <number>i</number>  an undertaking, in writing 
that he shall not make copies of the proceedings or any part thereof and that 
the information or documents contained in such proceedings shall not be used by 
him, for any purpose whatsoever, other than for the purpose of submitting a 
petition in accordance with the Act or instituting an action in a Court of law 
in relation to the said finding or sentence; and
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>ii</number>  a certificate that he is 
aware that he may render himself liable to prosecution under sections 3 and 5 of 
the Indian Official Secrets Act, 1923 (19 of 1923) if he commits any act 
specified in the said sections in relation to the documents or information 
contained in the said proceedings.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>131</number> Loss of proceedings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If, before confirmation, the original proceedings of a Court which require 
confirmation or any part thereof, are lost, a copy thereof, if any, certified by 
the Presiding Officer or the Law Officer at the Court may be accepted in lieu of 
the original.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If there is no such 
copy, and sufficient evidence of the charge, finding, sentence, and transactions 
of the Court can be procured, that evidence may, with the assent of the accused, 
be accepted in lieu of the original proceedings or part which have been lost.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In any case mentioned 
above in this rule the finding and sentence may be confirmed, and shall be valid 
and if the original proceedings or part thereof had not been lost.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If the accused refuses 
the assent referred to in sub-rule (2), he may be tried again, and the finding 
and sentence of the previous Court of which the proceedings have been lost shall 
be void.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If, after confirmation 
or in any case where confirmation is not required, the original proceedings or 
any part thereof are lost, and there is sufficient evidence of the charge, 
finding, sentence, and transactions of the Court and of the confirmation (if 
required) of the finding and sentence, that evidence shall be a valid and 
sufficient record of the trial for all purposes.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>132</number> Offences by witnesses 
and others.—When 
a Court is of opinion that there is ground for inquiring into any offence 
specified in sections 37 and 38 and committed before it or brought to its notice 
in the course of its proceedings, which would if done by a person subject to the 
Act, have constituted such an offence, such Court may proceed as follows, that 
is to say—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  if the person who appears to have 
committed the offence is subject to the Act, the Court may bring his conduct to 
the notice of his Commandant;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  if the person who appears to have 
done the Act is amenable to military, navy or air force law the Court may bring 
his conduct to the notice of the proper military, navy or air force authority, 
as the case may be;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  in other cases the officer who 
summoned the witness to appear or the Presiding Officer or officer holding the 
Court, as the case may be, may forward a written complaint to the nearest 
Magistrate of the first class having jurisdiction, and in the case of acts which 
would, if done by a person subject to the Act have constituted an offence under 
clause (e) of section 37 or section 38, the Court, after making any preliminary 
inquiry that may be necessary may send the case to the nearest Magistrate of the 
first class having jurisdiction for inquiry or trial in accordance with section 
476 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898). (Ss. 37, 38)
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>133</number> Proceedings.—The 
officer holding the trial, hereinafter in this Chapter called the Court, shall 
record, or cause to be recorded the transactions of every Summary Security Force 
Court.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>134</number> Evidence when to be 
translated.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When any evidence is given in a language which the Court of the accused does not 
understand, that evidence shall be translated to the Court or accused as the 
case may be in a language which it or he does understand.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Court shall for 
this purpose either appoint an interpreter, or shall itself take the oath or 
affirmation prescribed for the interpreter at a Summary Security Force 
Court.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> When documents are 
produced for the purpose of formal proof, it shall be in the discretion of the 
Court to cause as much to be interpreted as appears necessary.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>135</number> Assembly.—When 
the Court, the interpreter (if any) and the officers and subordinate officers 
attending the trial are assembled, the accused shall be brought before the Court 
and the oath or affirmation prescribed in rule 136 shall be taken by the persons 
therein mentioned.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>136</number> Swearing or Affirming 
of Court and Interpreter.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Court shall take oath or affirmation in any one of the following forms or in 
such other form to the same purport which would, according to the religion or 
otherwise be binding on the conscience of the officer constituting the Court.
 
Form of Oath
 
“I,.…………………………………………………, 
swear by Almighty God that I will duly administer justice, according to the 
Border Security Force Act, 1968 without favour or affection.”
 
Form of Affirmation
 
“I, …………………………………………, do 
solemnly, sincerely and truly, declare and affirm that I will duly administer 
justice, according to the Border Security Force Act, 1968 without partiality, 
favour or affection.”
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Court, or any 
other person empowered by it in this behalf shall administer to the interpreter 
(if any) an oath or affirmation in any of the following forms, or in such other 
form to the same purport as the Court ascertains to be according to the religion 
or otherwise binding on the conscience of the person who is to act as 
interpreter.
 
Form of Oath
 
“I, .…………………………………………………, 
swear by Almighty God that I will faithfully interpret and translate, as I shall 
be required to do touching the matter before this Court.”
 
Form of Affirmation
 
“I, …………………………………………, do 
solemnly, sincerely and truly, declare and affirm that I will faithfully 
interpret and translate, as I shall be required to do touching the matter before 
this Court.”
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The witnesses shall, 
after the administration of the oath and the affirmation, withdraw from the 
Court.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>137</number> Swearing of Court to 
try several accused persons.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A Summary Security Force Court may be sworn or affirmed at the same time to try 
any number of accused persons then present before it whether those persons are 
to be tried collectively or separately.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In the case of several 
accused persons to be tried separately, the Court, when sworn or affirmed shall 
proceed with one case postponing the other cases and taking them afterwards in 
succession.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where several accused 
persons are tried separately, upon charges arising out of the same transaction, 
the Court, may, if it considers it to be desirable in the interests of justice, 
postpone consideration of any sentence to be awarded to any one or more such 
accused persons until the trials of all such accused persons have been 
completed.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>138</number> Arraignment of 
accused.—
<section><number>1</number> 
After the Court and interpreter (if any) are sworn or affirmed as above 
mentioned, the accused shall be arraigned on the charges against him.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The charges on which 
the accused is arraigned shall be read and, if necessary, translated to him, and 
explained and he shall be required to plead separately to each charge.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>139</number> Objection by accused 
to charge.—The 
accused, when required to plead to any charge, may object to the charge on the 
ground that it does not disclose an offence under the Act, or is not in 
accordance with these rules.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>140</number> Amendment of charge.—
<section><number>1</number> 
At any time during the trial if it appears to the Court that there is mistake in 
the name or description of the accused in the charge-sheet, it shall amend the 
charge-sheet so as to correct that mistake.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If on the trial of a 
charge it appears to the Court at any time before it has begun to examine the 
witnesses, that in the interests of justice any addition to, omission from, or 
alteration in, the charge is required, it may amend such charge and may, after 
due notice to the accused, and with the sanction of the officer empowered to 
convene a Petty Security Force Court for the trial of the accused if the amended 
charge requires such sanction, proceed with the trial on such amended charge.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>141</number> Special pleas.—If 
a special plea to the general jurisdiction of the Court, or a plea in bar of 
trial, is offered by the accused, the procedure laid down in Chapter IX for 
disposing of such pleas shall, so far as may be applicable be followed.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>142</number> General plea of 
“Guilty” or “Not Guilty”.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The accused person’s plea of “Guilty” (or “Not Guilty” or if he refuses to plead 
or does not plead intelligibly either one or the other), a plea of “Not Guilty” 
shall be recorded on each charge.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If an accused person 
pleads “Guilty”, that plea shall be recorded as the finding of the Court; but 
before it is recorded, the Court shall ascertain that the accused understands 
the nature of the charge to which he has pleaded guilty and shall inform him of 
the general effect of that plea, and in particular of the meaning of the charge 
to which he has pleaded guilty, and of the difference in procedure which will be 
made by the plea of guilty and shall advise him to withdraw that plea if it 
appears from the record or abstract of evidence (if any) or otherwise that the 
accused ought to plead not guilty.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where an accused 
person pleads guilty to the first two or more charges laid in the alternative, 
the Court may after sub-rule (2) has been complied with and before the accused 
is arraigned on the alternative charge or charges, withdraw such alternative 
charge or charges as follow the charge to which the accused has pleaded guilty 
without requiring the accused to plea thereto, and a record to that effect shall 
be made in the proceedings of the Court.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>143</number> Procedure after plea 
of “Guilty”.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Upon the record of the plea of “Guilty”, if there are other charges in the same 
charge-sheet to which the plea is “Not Guilty”, the trial shall first proceed 
with respect to those other charges, and, after the finding on those charges, 
shall proceed with the charges on which a plea of “Guilty” has been entered; but 
if there are alternative charges, the Court may either proceed with respect to 
all the charges as if the accused had not pleaded “Guilty” to any charge, or 
may, instead of trying him, record a finding of “Guilty” upon any one of the 
alternative charges to which he had pleaded “Guilty” and finding of “Not Guilty” 
upon all the other alternative charges which precede such charge.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> (a) After the record 
of the plea of “Guilty”’ on a charge (if the trial does not proceed on any other 
charges) the Court shall read the record or abstract of evidence and annex it to 
the proceedings, or if there is no such record, or abstract shall take and 
record sufficient evidence to enable it to determine the sentence, and the 
reviewing officer to know all the circumstances connected with the offence.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The evidence shall be 
taken in like manner as is directed by these rules in the case of a plea of “Not 
Guilty”.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The accused may, after 
such evidence has been taken or, as the case may be, the record or abstract of 
evidence has been read, address the Court with reference to the charge and in 
mitigation of punishment and may call witnesses as to his character.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> (a) If from the 
statement of the accused, or from the record of evidence, or otherwise, it 
appears to the Court that the accused did not understand the effect of his plea 
of “Guilty”, the Court shall alter the record and enter a plea of “Not Guilty”, 
and proceed with the trial accordingly.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> Any alternative 
charges withdrawn under sub-rule (1) shall be reinstated in the charge sheet and 
the trial shall take place as if they had never been withdrawn.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> If a plea of “Guilty” 
is recorded on some charges and the trial proceeds with respect to other charges 
in the same charge-sheet, the proceedings under sub-rules (2) and (3) shall take 
place after the findings on the other charges in the same charge-sheet are 
recorded.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> When the accused 
states anything in mitigation of punishment which in the opinion of the Court 
requires to be proved, and would, if proved, affect the amount of punishment, 
the Court may permit the accused to call witnesses to prove the same.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>144</number> Withdrawal of plea of 
“Not Guilty”.—The 
accused may, if he thinks fit at any time during the trial, withdraw his plea of 
“Not Guilty” and plead “Guilty” and in such case the Court shall at once, 
subject to compliance with sub-rule (2) of rule 142 record a plea and finding of 
“Guilty” and shall, so far as if necessary, proceed in manner directed by rule 
143.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>145</number> Procedure after plea 
of “Not Guilty”.—
<section><number>1</number> 
After the plea of “Not Guilty” to any charge, is recorded the evidence for the 
prosecution will be taken.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> At the close of the 
evidence for the prosecution the accused shall be asked if he has anything to 
say in his defence, or may defer such address until he has called his witnesses.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The accused may then 
call his witnesses, including also witnesses to character.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>146</number> Witnesses in reply to 
defence.—The 
Court may, if it thinks it necessary in the interests of justice, call witnesses 
in reply to the defence.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>147</number> Evidence of 
witnesses.—The 
provisions of rules 88, 89 and 90 shall, so far as may be, apply to the evidence 
of witnesses at a Summary Security Force Court as they apply to the evidence of 
witnesses at a General or Petty Security Force Court.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>148</number> Verdict.—The 
Court shall after the evidence for prosecution and defence has been heard give 
its opinion as to whether the accused is guilty or not guilty of the charge or 
charges.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>149</number> Finding.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The finding on every charge upon which the accused is arraigned shall be 
recorded and except as mentioned in these rules shall be recorded simply as a 
finding of “Guilty” or of “Not Guilty”.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the Court is of 
opinion as regards any charge that the facts proved do not disclose the offence 
charged or any offence of which he might under the Act legally be found guilty 
on the charge as laid, the Court shall find the accused “Not Guilty” of that 
charge.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> When the Court is of 
opinion as regards any charge that the facts found to be proved in evidence 
differ materially from the facts alleged in the statement of particulars in the 
charge, but are nevertheless sufficient to prove the offence stated in the 
charge, and that the difference is not so material as to have prejudiced the 
accused in his defence, it may, instead of a finding of “Not Guilty” record a 
special finding.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The special finding 
may find the accused guilty on a charge subject to the statement of exceptions 
or variations specified therein.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Court shall not 
find the accused guilty on more than one of two or more charges laid in the 
alternative, even if conviction upon one charge necessarily connotes guilt upon 
the alternative charge or charges.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>150</number> Procedure on 
acquittal.—Where 
the finding on each of the charges in a charge-sheet is “Not Guilty”, the Court 
shall affix its signature and date the proceedings, the findings will be 
announced in open Court, and the accused will be released if under arrest, in 
respect of these charges.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>151</number> Procedure on finding 
of “Guilty”.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where the finding on any charge is “Guilty” the Court may record of its own 
knowledge, or take evidence of any record, the general character, age, service, 
rank, and any recognised acts of gallantry, or distinguished conduct of the 
accused, and previous convictions of the accused either by a Security Force 
Court, or a Criminal Court, any previous punishment awarded to him by an officer 
exercising authority under section 53, the length of time he has been in arrest 
or in confinement on any previous sentence, and any decoration, or reward, or to 
which he may be in possession or to which he may be entitled.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the Court does 
not record the matters mentioned in this rule of its own knowledge, evidence on 
these matters may be taken in the manner directed in rule 101 for similar 
evidence.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>152</number> Sentence.—The 
Court shall award one sentence in respect of all the offences of which the 
accused is found guilty.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>153</number> Signing of 
proceedings.—The 
Court shall affix its signature and the date to the sentence and such signature 
shall authenticate the whole of the proceedings.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>154</number> Charges in different 
charge-sheets.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When the charges at a trial by Summary Security Force Court are contained in 
different charge-sheets, the accused shall be tried on each charge-sheet 
separately upto and including the stage of finding.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Court shall, 
thereafter, comply with rule 150 or 151 as the case may be.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>155</number> Clearing the Court.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The officer holding the trial may clear the Court to consider the evidence or to 
consulate with the officers, and subordinate officers, attending the trial.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to the 
provisions of sub-rule (1), all the proceedings, including the view of any 
place, shall be in open Court, and in the presence of the accused.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>156</number> Adjournment.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A Court may,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  from time to time adjourn its 
proceedings and meet at such place as may be convenient; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  wherever necessary visit the 
scene of occurrence.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>157</number> Friend of the 
accused.—During 
a trial at a
Summary Security Force Court an accused may take the assistance of any person, 
including a legal practitioner as he may consider necessary:
 
Provided that such person 
shall not examine or cross-examine witnesses or address the Court.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>158</number> Memorandum to be 
attached to proceedings.—Where 
a Summary Security Force Court tries an offence which shall not ordinarily be 
tried without reference to an authority mentioned in sub-section (2) of section 
74, an explanatory memorandum shall be attached to the proceedings.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>159</number> Promulgation.—The 
sentence of a
Summary Security Force Court shall be promulgated, in the manner usual in the 
service, at the earliest opportunity after it has been pronounced and shall, 
subject to the provisions of the Act be carried out without delay after 
promulgation.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>160</number> Review of 
proceedings.—The 
proceedings of a
Summary Security Force Court shall, immediately on promulgation be forwarded 
through the Chief Law Officer, or a Law Officer to the Deputy Inspector-General 
under whom the accused may have been serving.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>161</number> Action by the Deputy 
Inspector-General.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where the Deputy Inspector-General to whom the proceedings of a Summary Security 
Force Court have been forwarded under rule 160, is satisfied that injustice has 
been done to the accused by reason of any grave irregularity in the proceedings 
or otherwise, he may,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  set aside the proceedings of the 
Court; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  reduce the sentence or commute 
the punishment awarded to one lower in the scale of punishment given in 

1[section 48 and return it to the unit 
of the accused for promulgation.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where no action under 
sub-rule (1) has been taken he shall counter-sign the proceedings 

2[***].
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The proceedings shall, 
after its promulgation, 

3[under sub-rule 
(1) or counter-signature under sub-rule (2)], be forwarded to the Chief Law 
Officer for custody.
 
 






</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>162</number> Direction about 
sentence of imprisonment.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A confirming authority or in the case of a Summary Security Force 
Court, the Court 
shall direct that the sentence of imprisonment shall be undergone by confinement 
either in a civil prison or in Force custody.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Such direction may be 
varied by any superior officer.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>163</number> Warrants.—Warrants 
for committing a person to a civil prison to undergo sentence of imprisonment or 
to get such person back into Force custody if so required or to order the 
release of such a person from civil prison or any variation done by any superior 
officer shall be in such form as may be appropriate to each case set out in 
Appendix ‘X’.
 <section>
<number>2</number> Such warrants shall be 
signed by the Commandant of the accused or by a staff officer on behalf of a 
Deputy Inspector-General, Inspector-General or the Director-General.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>164</number> Warrant in case of 
sentences of Death.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where a person is sentenced to death by hanging, a warrant in the form set out 
in Appendix XI shall be sent by the Director-General to the Superintendent of 
the Prison where facilities for carrying out such a sentence exist, after the 
sentence has been confirmed by the Central Government and the accused shall be 
committed to the same prison by his Commandant on the appropriate warrant.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where an accused 
person is sentenced to death by being shot, a warrant on the appropriate form 
set out in Appendix XI shall be issued by the Director-General, to Deputy 
Inspector-General under whom the accused may be serving, after the sentence has 
been confirmed by the Central Government, and the Deputy Inspector-General shall 
arrange for the execution of the sentence.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>165</number> Changes in sentence.—Where 
any change is made in the sentence of a person already committed to a civil 
prison such change shall be communicated to the Superintendent of the Prison to 
which such person has been committed by the Commandant or such other person as 
is mentioned in rule 163 on the form set out in Appendix XII.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>166</number> Sentence of 
dismissal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Sentence of dismissal shall take effect from the date of promulgation of such 
sentence or from any subsequent date as may be specified at the time of 
promulgation.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A sentence of 
dismissal combined with imprisonment to be undergone in a civil prison shall not 
take effect until such person has been committed to civil prison.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>167</number> Petitions against 
finding and sentence of Court.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A person subject to the Act who has been tried by a Court shall be allowed to 
put in one petition before confirmation, to the confirming authority and one 
petition after confirmation to any officer mentioned in section 117.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In the case of a Summary Security 
Force Court he shall be allowed to put in one petition only to any of the 
officers mentioned in section 117.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>168</number> Period of limitation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A petition, before confirmation, shall be submitted, within one week of the 
conclusion of trial.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A petition after 
confirmation shall be submitted within 3 months of the date on which the 
sentence was promulgated:
 
Provided that the time 
taken by such person to obtain a copy of the proceedings shall be excluded in 
calculating this period of 3 months.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>169</number> Mode of submitting 
petitions.—
<section><number>1</number> 

<subsection><number>a</number> A petition by a person who is still a member of the Force shall be submitted 
through his Commandant.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> A petition by a person 
who has ceased to be a member of the Force shall be submitted to the Commandant 
of the unit in which the trial was held.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> An officer to whom a 
petition is submitted or to whom a petition has been forwarded shall forward it 
to the next superior within a period of one week:
 
Provided that an officer 
may not forward a petition if he is competent to give the redress asked for and 
decides to do so.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An officer reviving a 
petition may send it to the Chief Law Officer or a Law Officer for advice.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>

1[<number>170</number> Composition.—A 
Court of inquiry may consist of one or more members. Persons not subjected to 
the Act may be appointed as members when the Court is to investigate matters of 
a specialised nature, and when officers subject to the Act with specialist 
qualifications are not available to be members.]
 
 




</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>171</number> Assembly.—A 
Court of inquiry may be assembled by order of a Commandant or any officer or 
authority superior to the Commandant.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>172</number> Assembly order.—The 
order assembling the Court of inquiry shall state the composition of the Court, 
the time and place for its assembly and clearly state the matters which the 
Court will investigate. It will also provide for the administrative requirements 
of the Court.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>173</number> Procedure of Courts 
of inquiry.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The proceedings of a Court of inquiry shall not be open to the public. Only such 
persons may attend the proceedings as are permitted by the Court to do so.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The evidence of all 
witnesses shall be taken on oath or affirmation.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Evidence given by 
witnesses shall be recorded in narrative form unless the Court considers that 
any questions and answers may be recorded as such.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Court may take 
into consideration any documents even though they are not normally proved.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Court may ask 
witnesses any question, in any form, that they consider necessary to elicit the 
truth and may take into consideration any evidence, whether the same, is 
admissible under the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872) or not.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> No counsel, or legal 
practitioner shall be remitted to appear before a Court of inquiry.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Provisions of section 
89 shall apply for procuring the attendance of witnesses before the Court of 
inquiry.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> Before giving an 
opinion against any person subject to the Act, the Court will afford that person 
the opportunity to know all that has been stated against him, cross-examine any 
witnesses who have given evidence against him, and make a statement and call 
witnesses in his defence.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> The answers given by a 
witness to any question asked before the Court shall not be admissible against 
such a witness on any charge at any subsequent occasion except a charge of 
giving false evidence before such Court.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>174</number> Courts of inquiry 
when to be held.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A Court of inquiry may be held to investigate into any disciplinary matter or 
any other matter of importance.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In addition to a Court 
of inquiry required to be held under section 62, a Court of inquiry shall be 
held in the following cases:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  (i)  All unnatural deaths of 
persons subject to the Act or of other persons within the Force lines, an 
immediate report shall be sent through the messenger to the officer-in-charge of 
the Police Station within whose jurisdiction the place of such unnatural death 
is.
 <subsubsection>
            <number>ii</number>  In cases when such report 
cannot, for any reason be delivered within a reasonable time, a Court of inquiry 
shall be held into such unnatural death.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>iii</number>  Immediately on receipt of 
information of an unnatural death the Commandant or the senior most officer of 
the Battalion present shall prepare a report on the proforma set out in Appendix 
XIII.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  All injuries sustained by persons 
subject to the Act which are likely to cause full or partial disability. The 
Court shall in such case determine whether such injuries were attributable to 
service or not.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  All financial irregularities, 
losses, theft and misappropriation of public or Force property, where it is 
necessary to obtain the order of a superior officer on such irregularities, 
loss, theft or misappropriation.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  All losses of secret documents 
and any other material of secret of above security classification. Such a Court 
of inquiry shall be ordered by an officer or authority superior to the unit 
Commandant having the lost document or material on its charge.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  All damage to private persons or 
property in respect of which there is likely to be a claim against the 
Government or the Force.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>175</number> Action on the 
proceedings of a Court of inquiry.—The 
proceedings of a Court of inquiry shall be submitted by the Presiding Officer to 
the officer or authority who ordered the Court. Such officer or authority on 
receiving the proceedings may either pass final orders on the proceedings 
himself, if he is empowered to do so, or refer them to a superior authority.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>176</number> Copies of Court of 
inquiry proceedings.—A 
person subject to the Act against whom the Court of inquiry has given an opinion 
or who is being tried by a Security Force Court on a charge relating to matters 
investigated by the Court of inquiry, shall be entitled to copies of the 
proceedings of the Court of Inquiry unless the Director-General orders 
otherwise.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>177</number> Prescribed officer 
under section 11(2).—The 
Commandant may, under sub-section (2) or section 11, dismiss or remove from the 
service any person under his command other than an officer or a subordinate 
officer.
</article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>178</number> Authority prescribed 
for the purposes of section 13
<section><number>1</number>.—The 
authority for the purposes of sub-section (1) of section 13 shall be—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  Commandant, in respect of 
persons under his command;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  Deputy Inspector-General, in 
respect of a Commandant;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number>  Inspector-General, in respect 
of a Deputy Inspector-General;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iv</number>  Director-General, in respect of 
all persons subject to the Act.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>179</number> Extent of punishment.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If the Commandant is of and above the rank of a Deputy Commandant he may award 
to the full extent one or more of the punishments specified in section 53.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the Commandant is 
below the rank of a Deputy Commandant he may award punishment specified—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  in clauses (a) and (b) of section 
53 upto fourteen days.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  in other clauses of section 53 to 
the full extent.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>180</number> Manner of proceedings 
against a person under section 55
<section><number>1</number>.—The 
manner in which an officer shall, under sub-section (1) of section 55 proceed 
against a person of or below the rank of a subordinate officer who is charged 
with an offence under the Act, be as set out in Appendix XIV.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 <article>
<number>181</number> Repeal and savings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
All rules and orders relating to the matters covered by these rules shall stand 
repealed insofar as they are inconsistent with any of the provisions of these 
rules.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding such 
repeal anything done or any action taken under the provisions of the rules or 
orders so repealed shall, in so far as such thing or action is not inconsistent 
with the provisions of these rules, be deemed to have been done or taken under 
the provisions of these rules as if the said provisions were in force, when such 
thing was done or such action was taken and shall continue in force accordingly 
until superseded by anything done or any action taken under these rules.
</section></article> 
 
The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
  
 

 <article>
<number>182</number> Transitory 
provisions.—Any 
rule or order applicable to the Force on the date these rules come into force 
will unless repugnant to these rules, continue to apply unless and until 
abrogated or modified by the Central Government or any other competent 
authority.
</article><form>
 


The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 

 
 


Appendix X
 


(See rule 163)
 


Warrants under sections 121 and 125 of the 
Border  

Security Force Act, 1968
 


Form ‘A’
 


Warrant of commitment for use when a prisoner 
is  

sentenced to imprisonment for life  



(Section 121 of BSF Act)
 


To
 


The Superintendent
 


of the (a) .…………………………… Prison.
 


Whereas at a General Security Force Court, 
held at.………………… on the.……………… day of.………..............……20… No..……………… Rank 
.…..............………… Name.…………………………… Unit.……………………………) was convicted of (the 
offence to be briefly stated here, as “desertion on active duty”, 
“correspondence with the enemy”, “or as the case may be”).
 


And whereas the said General Security Force 
Court on the.…………day of.………20… passed the following sentence upon the said 
(Name.………………………) that is to say .……………………………………………….………………………………….…
 


(Sentence to be entered in full, but without 
signature).
 


And whereas the said sentence has been duly 
confirmed by (b) as required by law (c).
 


This is to require and authorise you to 
receive the said (Name .……………… …………………) into your custody in the said prison as 
by law is required, together with this warrant, until he shall be delivered over 
by you with the said warrant to the proper authority and custody for the purpose 
of undergoing the aforesaid sentence of imprisonment. The aforesaid sentence has 
effected from the (d).
 


Given under my hand at.……………this the……………day 
of.…………………20…
 


.……………………… Signature(s)
 


        (a)  Enter name of civil prison.
 


        (b)  Name and description of 
confirming authority.
 


        (c)  Add if necessary “with a 
remission of.………………………”
 


        (d)  Enter date on which the original 
sentence was signed.
 


        (e)  Signature of Commandant of the 
prisoner or other prescribed officer.
 


 
 


Form ‘B’
 


Warrant of commitment for use when a prisoner 
is sentenced to imprisonment  

which is to be undergone in a civil prison
 



(Section 121 of BSF Act)
 


To
 


The Superintendent
 


of the (a) .…………………………… Prison.
 


Whereas at a (b) .………………Security Force Court 
held at.……………on the. ……………… day of.………………………20… (No..……………… Rank.…………… 
Name.…………………………… Unit.................) was duly convicted of (the offence to be 
briefly stated have, as ’desertion’, ‘theft’, ‘receiving stolen goods’, ‘fraud’, 
‘disobedience of lawful command’ or as the case may be).
 


And whereas the said (b).……………………… Security 
Force Court on the.………… day of.……20… passed the following sentence upon the said 
(Name.……………………) that is to say .………………………………….…………………………………………………
 


(Sentence to be entered in full, but without 
signature)
 


And whereas the said sentence
 


(c) has been duly confirmed by (d) as 
required by law (e) is by law valid without confirmation
 


This is to require and authorise you to 
receive the said (Name .……………… …………………) into your custody together with the 
warrant and then carry the aforesaid sentence of imprisonment into execution 
according to law. The sentence has effect from the (f) …………………
 


Given under my hand at.………………this 
the…………………day of .…………… …………20…
 


.……………………Signature(g)
 


        (a)  Enter name of civil prison.
 


        (b)  General, Petty or Summary.
 


        (c)  Strike out inapplicable words.
 


        (d)  Name and description of 
confirming authority.
 


        (e)  Add is necessary ‘with a 
remission of.…………………………….………………
 


         (f)  Enter date on which the 
original sentence was signed.
 


        (g)  Signature of Commandant of 
prisoner or other prescribed officer.
 


 
 


Form ‘C’
 


Warrant for use when a sentence of 
imprisonment for  

life is reduced by superior authority to one of  

a shorter period
 



(Section 125 of BSF Act)
 


To
 


The Superintendent
 


of the (a) .…………………………… Prison.
 


Whereas (No..………………Rank.…………… Name.………………………) 
(late) of the unit is confined in the (a).…………………………… prison under a warrant 
issued by (b) in pursuance of a sentence of (c)………………… passed upon him by a 
(d)………… Security Force Court held at ……………………… on.………………. And whereas (e)………… 
has, in the exercise of the power conferred upon him by the Border Security 
Force Act, passed the following order regarding the aforesaid sentence: that is 
to say:—(f)……………………………………………………………………………………...…………
 


This is to require and authorise you to keep 
the said (Name) .………………………… in your custody together with this warrant in the 
said prison as by law is required until he shall be delivered over by you with 
the said warrant to the proper authority and custody, for the purpose of his 
undergoing the punishment of imprisonment for life under the said order. And 
this is further to require and authorise you to return to me the original 
warrant of commitment in lieu whereof this warrant is issued.
 


* The period of such imprisonment will reckon 
from the (g).
 


Given under my hand at.……………this the………………day 
of………………20…
 


.…………………………………Signature(h)
 


        (a)  Enter name of civil prison.
 


        (b)  Enter name or designation of 
officer who signed original warrant.
 


        (c)  Enter original sentence (if this 
was reduced by the confirming officer or other superior authority the sentence 
should be entered thus:—
 


              [“Life (imprisonment reduced by 
confirming officer to 10 years”).
 


        (d)  General.
 


        (e)  Name and designation of 
authority varying the sentence.
 


         (f)  Order to be sent out in full.
 


        (g)  Enter date on which original 
sentence was signed.
 


        (h)  Signature of prescribed officer.
 


Form ‘D’
 


Warrant for use when prisoner is to be 
delivered  

into force custody
 


To
 


The Superintendent
 


of the (a) .…………………………… Prison.
 


Whereas (No..………………Rank.…………… Name.………………………) 
(late) of the …………………………unit is confined in the (a).…………………………… prison under a 
warrant issued by (b) in pursuance of a sentence of (c)………………… passed upon him 
by a (d)………… Security Force Court held at ……………………… on.………………, and whereas 
(e)………… has, in exercise of the powers conferred upon him by the Border Security 
Force Act passed the following order regarding the aforesaid sentence: that is 
to say (f)………………………………
 



….......................................................................................................................................
 


This is to require and authorise you to 
deliver forthwith the said (name) in your custody to the officer or subordinate 
officer bringing this warrant.
 


Given under my hand at.………………this 
the…………………day of .……………… ………20…
 


.……………………………Signature(g)
 


        (a)  Enter name of civil prison.
 


        (b)  Enter name or designation of 
officer who signed original warrant.
 


        (c)  Enter original sentence (if this 
was reduced by the confirming officer or other superior authority the sentence 
should be entered thus:—“2 years rigorous imprisonment reduced by confirming 
officer to 1 year”.
 


        (d)  General, Petty or Summary.
 


        (e)  Name and designation of 
authority issuing the order.
 


         (f)  Order to be set out in full.
 


        (g)  Signature of prescribed officer.
 


 
</form><form>
 


The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 

 
 


Appendix XI
 


[See rule 164(1)]
 


Form ‘A’
 


Warrant committing to civil prison custody
 

a person sentenced to death
 


To
 


The Superintendent of the (a) .…………………………… 
Prison.
 


Whereas at a (b)………… Security Force Court 
held at …………………… on the .………………day of ………………… 20… (No.…………………Rank ……………… 
Name………) of the ……………………… Unit was convicted of …………………(Offence to be briefly 
stated);
 


And whereas the said (b)………………… Security 
Force Court on the ………day of……20…, passed sentence of death by being hanged, on 
the said
 


(Name):—
 


and the said sentence of death has been 
confirmed by the Central Government.
 


This is to require and authorise you to 
receive the said (Name)…………………… into your custody and to carry out the sentence 
of death on……………………
 


Given under my hand 
at.…....................…this the…..………day of .…………20…
 


.…………………………Signature(c)
 


        (a)  Enter name of civil prison.
 


        (b)  General.
 


        (c)  Signature of the 
Director-General.
 


 
 


Form ‘B’
 


[See rule 164(2)]
 


Warrant to obtain person sentenced to death 
from civil custody in order  

to carry out such sentence
 


To
 


The Superintendent
 


of the (a) .…………………………… Prison.
 


Whereas (No.…………… Rank…….……………… 
Name…......…………………………) (late) of the …………………….....………… Unit having been 
sentenced to suffer death on the………………day of ………20… by a (b)……………………Security 
Force Court held at …………………… is held in the said prison under a warrant by (c).
 


And whereas the said sentence having been 
duly confirmed by (d) ……………………… as by Law required an order to carry out the 
said sentence has been issued to me (e)……………………… (Name and Rank) ……………………………
 


This is to require and authorise you to 
deliver forthwith the said (Name)………………… to the officer/Under-officer bringing 
the warrant.
 


Given under my hand at.………………this day of 
.………………………20…
 


.…………………………Signature(f)
 


        (a)  Enter name of civil prison.
 


        (b)  General.
 


        (c)  Enter name or designation of 
officer who signed original warrant.
 


        (d)  Name and designation of 
confirming authority.
 


        (e)  Name and designation of the 
officer to whom the order is issued.
 


         (f)  Signature of the officer by 
whom the order is issued.
 


 
 


Form ‘C’
 


[See rule 164(2)]
 


Warrant to carry out sentence of death
 


To
 


The Deputy Inspector-General, ……………………………………
 


Whereas at a (a) …………………………… Security Force 
Court held at ………………… on the ………………………………… day of……………......…………20… (No……………… 
Rank…………………………… Name…………………………………… of the Battalion/Unit was convicted 
of……………………………(Offence to be briefly stated).
 


And whereas the said (a)……………………………… Security 
Force Court on the……………………………… day of………………………………, 20… , passed sentence of 
death by being shot on the said (Name)………………………………… and the sentence of death 
has been confirmed by the Central Government.
 


This is to require and authorise you to carry 
out the sentence of death on………………………
 


Given under my hand at………………………… this 
the…………………………… day of …………………………20…
 


Signature (b)
 


        (a)  General.
 


        (b)  Signature of the 
Director-General.
 


 
 


 
</form><form>
 


The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 

 
 


Appendix XIV
 


(See rule 180)
 


Part I
 


Form I
 


Form for use at summary trials of or below 
the rank of subordinate Officers
 



(Section 55 of BSF Act)
 


Accused ………………………………………………………………………………………
 


Rank and Name………………………………………………………………………………
 


Unit………………..……………………………………………………………………………
 


When the authority dealing summarily with the 
case decides (with the written consent of the accused) to dispense with the 
attendance of witnesses:
 


Question to accused:—
 


       1.  Have you received a copy of the 
charge-sheet and record or abstract of evidence?
 


  Answer:
 


       2.  Have you had sufficient time to 
prepare your defence?
 


Answer:
 


       3.  The charge-sheet is read.
 


            Are you guilty or not guilty of 
the charge/s against you which you have heard/read?
 


Answer:
 


       4.  Do you wish to make a statement?
 


Answer:
 


            If the accused desires to make a 
statement he should do so now. If at the conclusion of the hearing the authority 
dealing summarily with the case considers that the charge should not be 
dismissed, he is to examine the accused’s record of service or conduct sheet. If 
the authority dealing summarily with the case proposes to award a punishment 
other than a reprimand, severe reprimand or penal deductions, in the case of a 
subordinate officer, he shall put the following question to the accused.
 


       5.  Do you elect to be tried by 
Security Force Court or will you accept my award.
 


Answer:
 



Finding…………………………………………………….…………………………....…………
 


Award…………………………………………..…………………………………....……………
 



Station…………………............…………………………………………..………….......………
 


Date………………………………………………………………………………………….…...
 


Note:—Oral 
statement of the accused made in answer to question 4 will not be recorded. If 
the accused has submitted a written statement such statement is only to be 
forwarded with or attached to this form when a copy of the Record or Abstract of 
evidence is also required to be so forwarded or attached. This form will be kept 
with Confidential Character Roll of the Subordinate Officer.
 


 
 


 
 


Form II
 


Form for use at summary trials of or below 
the rank of Subordinate Officers
 



(Section 55 of BSF Act)
 


Accused ………………………………………………………………………………….……
 


Rank and Name………………………………………………………………………………
 


Unit………………………………………………………………………………………….…
 


When the authority dealing summarily with the 
case does not decide to dispense with the attendance of witnesses or when the 
accused requires their attendance.
 


Question to accused:—
 


       1.  Have you received a copy of the 
charge sheet and record or abstract of evidence?
 


Answer:
 


       2.  Have you had sufficient time to 
prepare your defence?
 


Answer:
 


       3.  Are you guilty or not guilty of 
the charge/s against you which you have heard/read?
 


            The witnesses give their 
evidence, accused being permitted to cross-examine.
 


Answer:
 


       4.  Do you wish to make a statement?
 


Answer:
 


       5.  Do you desire to call the witness:
 


Answer:
 


            The accused makes a statement and 
his witnesses give evidence.
 


            If at the conclusion of the 
hearing, the authority dealing summarily with the case considers that the charge 
should not be dismissed, he is to examine the accused’s record of service or 
conduct sheet.
 


            If the authority dealing 
summarily with the case proposes to award a punishment other than a reprimand, 
severe reprimand or penal deductions, in the case of subordinate officer, he 
shall put the following question to the accused:—
 


       6.  Do you elect to be tried by 
Security Force Court or will you accept my award.
 


Answer:
 


Finding…………………………………………………….……………………………………
 


Award…………………………………………..………………………………………………
 



Station…………………............………………………………………………………………
 


Date……………………………………………………………………………………………...
 


Note.—Oral 
statement of the accused made in answer to question 4 will not be recorded. If 
the accused has submitted a written statement, such statement is only to be 
forwarded with or attached to this form when a copy of the Record or Abstract of 
evidence is also required to be so forwarded or attached. This form will be kept 
with Confidential Character Roll of the Subordinate Officer.
 


 
 


 
</form><form>
 


The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 

 
 


Appendix II
 


(See rule 39)
 


Form of Delay Report
 



                                                      Confidential
 


      No.…………………………………….
 


      Unit address………...………………..
 


      Date………………………………...…
 


To………………………….
 


Subject: Ist, (2nd), (3rd), (4th), etc., 
Eight day delay report pursuant to the BSF Act section 59 and rule 39
 


         1.  No…………………………… Rank……………………… 
Name……………………
 


         2.  
Offence………………………………………..…………………………………………
 


         3.  Date of 
offence…………………………………………………………………………
 


         4.  Date offence was 
discovered………………………..……………………………
 


         5.  Date of (open/close) 
arrest……………………………………………………...……
 


         6.  Date of release to open 
arrest/release without prejudice to arrest (If not released, 
reasons)…………………........…………………………………….……...…
 


         7.  Record of evidence made on (If 
not recorded, reasons)…………………………....
 


         8.  Application for trial made 
on……………………………………………………..…
 


         9.  Date due to be 
tried…………………………………………………….…………..…
 


       10.  Reason for 
delay…………………………………………...………………………..…
 


…………………………………………………………...................
 


(Commandant)
 


Copy to:—
 


         1.  Inspector-General (In the case 
of the 8th and subsequent reports).
 


         2.  Director-General (Special report 
in case the accused is under close arrest for more than three months without a 
trial).
 


 
</form><form>
 


The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 

 
 


Appendix V
 


(See rule 52)
 


Form of Application for a Security Force 
Court
 


      Battalion/Unit
 


Station……………………………… Date…………………………………20…
 


Application for a Security Force Court
 


Sir,
 


I have the honour to submit charge(s) against 
No.…… Rank………………………… Name…………………………………… of the………………………………… Unit under my 
command, and request you to accord/obtain sanction, of ……………………, that a Security 
Force Court may be assembled for his trial at…………………………………
 


The case was investigated by 
(a)……………………………………………………………
 


A Court of Inquiry was held on 
(b)………………………dated ………………………… at……………………………………(Station).
 


Presiding Officer…………………………………… Rank, Name 
and Unit.
 


Members ……………………………………………………………………………………
 


The accused is now at………………………… His general 
character is (c). I enclose the following documents (d).
 


         1.  Charge sheet, 
[…………………………………………………………… copies(e)].
 


         2.  Record or abstract of evidence 
original (f) and 5 copies.
 


         3.  Original exhibits (g).
 


         4.  Correspondence (g).
 


         5.  Statement as to character ( ) 
and the conduct-sheet of the accused (g).
 


         6.  List of witnesses for the 
prosecution and defence (with their present addresses) (g).
 


         7.  List of Exhibits (h).
 


         8.  Statement by accused as to 
whether or not he desires to have an officer assigned by the Convening Officer 
to represent him at the trial [Rule 63(h)].
 


Signature of Commandant
 



......................................................................................................................................................
 


        (a)  Here insert name 
of……………………………………………………………………
 


              (i) Officer who investigated 
the charges
 


             (ii) Company/equivalent 
Commander who made preliminary hearing into the case (Rule 44).
 


            (iii) Officer who made the record 
of evidence (Rule 48).
 


        (b)  To be filled in if there has 
been a Court of Inquiry respecting any matters connected with the charges; 
otherwise to be struck out [Rule 60 (iii)].
 


        (c)  To be filled in by the 
Commandant
 


        (d)  Any items not applicable to be 
struck out.
 


        (e)  One copy each to Presiding 
Officer, Law Officer (if any), members Prosecutor and the accused.
 


         (f)  Original Record or abstract of 
Evidence to be sent to Presiding Officer.
 


        (g)  3, 4, 5 and 6 to be returned to 
the Commandant of the Unit of the accused with the notice of trial.
 


        (h)  7 &amp; 8 to be sent to the 
Presiding Officer.
 


 
</form><form>
 


The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 

 
 


Appendix VI
 


[See rule 53(2)]
 


Charge-Sheet
 


The accused No.…………........…… (if applicable) 
Rank .…...............………………… Name.………………………Battalion/Unit.……………………………, is 
charged with.
 


Disobeying The Lawful Command of His Superior 
Officer 
 


BSF Act/sec. 21(2) 
 


in that he, at .……………………… on.…………………………, 
disobeyed the lawful command of his superior officer Rank.………………………………… Name 
.………………………………… of the same Battalion, to turn out for Commandant’s parade, by 
not turning out.
 


Place.…………………
 


Date.…………………
 



                                                           Commandant.…………………… 
Bn BSF.
 


* To be tried by a General/Petty Security 
Force Court
 


Place.…………………
 


Date.…………………
 



                                                      Inspector-General/Dy. 
Inspector-General
 



                                                                  (or Staff 
Officer to IG/DIG)
 



                                                                                
Frontier. 
 


* When the sanction is accorded for the trial 
of the grave offences by Summary Security Force Court [BSF Act sec. 74(2)], a 
similar entry should be made on the charge-sheet.
 


 
</form><form>
 


The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 

 
 


Appendix VIII
 


(See rule 106)
 


In exercise of the powers conferred on me by 
section 105 of the Border Security Force Act, 1968, I, .…………………………, hereby order 
that.…………………………be delivered/paid to.…………………………… (be confiscated/destroyed).
 



Place.……………………                                                                                                                              
Signature
 



Date.………………………                                                                                                                      (Confirming 
Authority)
 


 
</form><form>
 


The Border Security Force Rules, 
1969
 

 
 


Appendix IX
 


[See rule 106(8)]
 


The finding and sentence of the General/Petty 
Security Force Court held at .………………… (place).………………from ………………… day 
to.…………………day for the trial of the accused.……………………………… were promulgated to the 
accused by me at .………………………………(place) on .………………day of………………20…
 


Extracts for battalion records have been 
taken/*No record has been kept of the finding and sentence.
 



Place.……………………                                                                  
Signature
 



Date.………………………                                                             
Commandant
 


* To be used in case of acquittal on all 
charges.
 


 
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>  Ins. by S.O. 329(E), dated 29th April, 
1981.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>  Subs. by S.O. 436(E), dated 29th May, 
1990.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>  Omitted by S.O. 166, dated 14th 
January, 1998 (w.e.f. 24-1-1998).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>  Ins. by S.O. 544, dated 15th 
February, 2002 (w.e.f. 23-2-2002).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>  Ins. by S.O. 55(E), dated 1st 
February, 1999 (w.e.f. 2-2-1999).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>  Ins. by S.O. 55(E), dated 1st 
February, 1999 (w.e.f. 2-2-1999).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>  Ins. by S.O. 436(E), dated 29th May, 
1990.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>  Ins. by S.O. 436(E), dated 29th May, 
1990.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>  Subs. by S.O. 436(E), dated 29th May, 
1990.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>  Omitted by S.O. 436(E), dated 29th 
May, 1990.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>