<act><tid>777085</tid>
<title>THE ARBITRATION (PROTOCOL AND CONVENTION) ACT, <footcitenum>19371</footcitenum></title>

ACT No. 6 OF <year>1937</year>
[ 4th March, <year>1937</year>.]

An Act to make certain further provisions respecting the law of 
arbitration in <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> India.

WHEREAS India was a State signatory to the Protocol on Arbitra- 
tion Clauses set forth in the First Schedule, and to the Convention on 
the Execution of Foreign Arbitral Awards set forth in the Second 
Schedule, subject in each case to a reservation of the right to limit 
its obligations in respect thereof to contracts which are considered 
as commercial under the law in force in <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> India;

AND WHEREAS it is expedient, for the purpose of giving effect to 
the said Protocol and of enabling the said Convention to become 
operative in <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> India, to make certain further provisions 
respecting the law of arbitration;

It is hereby enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>1644716</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and operation.-
<section><tid>572178</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Arbitration (Protocol and Convention) Act, <year>1937</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1833041</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>.]

</section>

<section><tid>673622</tid>
<number>3</number>The provisions of this Act, except this section, shall have 
effect only from such date as the Central Government may, by noti- 
fication in the Official Gazette, appoint in this behalf, and the 
Central Government may appoint different dates <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> for the coming into 
effect of different provisions of the Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1662018</tid>
<number> 2</number> Interpretation.- In this Act <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>" foreign award" means an 
award on differences relating to matters considered as commercial 
under the law in force in <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> India] made after the 28th day of July, 
<year>1924</year>,-
<section><tid>1565539</tid>
<number>a</number>in pursuance of an agreement for arbitration to which 
the Protocol set forth in the First Schedule applies, and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act ceased to have effect in relation to foreign awards to 
which Act 45 of <year>1961</year> applies vide Act 45 of <year>1961</year>, s. 10, in respect to 
territories to be notified under s. 2 (b), ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The words" the Provinces of" omitted by the A. O. <year>1950</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs., ibid., for sub- section (2).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>The words" except Part B States" omitted by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>. s. 3 
and Sch.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>S. 3 came into effect on the 30th November, <year>1937</year>, see Gazette 
of India, <year>1937</year>, Pt. I, P. <year>1945</year>; and s. 2 and 4 to 10 on the 23rd 
January, <year>1938</year>, see ibid., <year>1938</year>, Pt. I, p. 25.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Definition of" States" ins. by the A. O. <year>1950</year> was omitted by 
Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>7</number>Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch., for" the States".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1904069</tid>
<number>b</number>between persons of whom one is subject to the 
jurisdiction of some one of such Powers as the Central 
Government, being satisfied that reciprocal provisions have 
been made, may, by notification <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in the Official Gazette, 
declare to be parties to the Convention set forth in the 
Second Schedule, and of whom the other is subject to the 
jurisdiction of some other of the Powers aforesaid, and

</section>

<section><tid>1890027</tid>
<number>c</number>in one of such territories as the Central Government, 
being satisfied that reciprocal provisions have been made, 
may, by like notification, declare to be territories to which 
the said Convention applies,
and for the purposes of this Act an award shall not be deemed to be 
final if any proceedings for the purpose of contesting the validity of 
the award are pending in the country in which it was made.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1899249</tid>
<number>3</number>Stay of proceedings in respect of matters to be referred to 
arbitration.- Notwithstanding anything contained in the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Arbitration 
Act, <year>1940</year>] (10 of <year>1940</year>), or in the Code of Civil Procedure <year>1908</year> (5  
  of <year>1908</year>), if any party to a submission made in pursuance of an 
agreement to which the Protocol set forth in the First Schedule as 
modified by the reservation subject to which it was signed by India 
applies, or any person claiming through or under him, commences any 
legal proceedings in any Court against any other party to the 
submission or any person claiming through or under him in respect of 
any matter agreed to be referred, any party to such legal proceedings 
may, at any time after appearance and before filing a written 
statement or taking any other steps in the proceedings, apply to the 
Court to stay the proceedings; and the Court, unless satisfied that 
the agreement or arbitration has become inoperative or cannot proceed, 
or that there is not in fact any dispute between the parties with 
regard to the matter agreed to be referred, shall make an order 
staying the proceedings.


</article>



<article><tid>554850</tid>
<number> 4</number> Effect of foreign awards.-
<section><tid>677479</tid>
<number>1</number>A foreign award shall,  
subject to the provisions of this Act, be enforceable in <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> India] as 
if it were an award made on a matter referred to Arbitration in 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> India].

</section>

<section><tid>50989</tid>
<number>2</number>Any foreign award which would be enforceable under this Act 
shall be treated as binding for all purposes on the persons as between 
whom it was made, and may accordingly be relied on by any of those 
persons by way of defence, set off or otherwise in any legal 
proceedings in <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> India], and any references in this Act to enforcing 
a foreign award shall be construed as including references to relying 
on an award.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>4A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>For such notification, see Gazette of India, <year>1938</year>, Pt. I, 
p. 24.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 32 of <year>1940</year>, s. 3 and Sch. II, for" Indian 
Arbitration Act, <year>1899</year>".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch., for" the States"



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1903204</tid>
<number> 5</number> Filing of foreign award in Court.-
<section><tid>982901</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person interested  
in a foreign award may apply to any Court having jurisdiction over the 
subject- matter of the award that the award be filed in Court.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>425635</tid>
<number>2</number>The application shall be in writing and shall be numbered 
and registered as a suit between the applicant as plaintiff and the 
other parties as defendants.

</section>

<section><tid>721726</tid>
<number>3</number>The Court shall direct notice to be given to the parties to 
the arbitration, other than the applicant, requiring them to show 
cause, within a time specified, why the award should not be filed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1266407</tid>
<number> 6</number> Enforcement of foreign award.-
<section><tid>986978</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the Court is  
satisfied that the foreign award is enforceable under this Act, the 
Court shall order the award to be filed and shall proceed to pronounce 
judgment according to the award.

</section>

<section><tid>1978855</tid>
<number>2</number>Upon the judgment so pronounced a decree shall follow, and 
no appeal shall lie from such decree except in so far as the decree is 
in excess of or not in accordance with the award.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>65704</tid>
<number> 7</number> Conditions for enforcement of foreign awards.-
<section><tid>447722</tid>
<number>1</number>In order  
that a foreign award may be enforceable under this Act it must have-

<subsection><tid>1577671</tid>
<number>a</number>been made in pursuance of an agreement for arbitration 
which was valid under the law by which it was governed,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1707326</tid>
<number>b</number>been made by the tribunal provided for in the agreement 
or constituted in manner agreed upon by the parties,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1296409</tid>
<number>c</number>been made in conformity with the law governing the 
arbitration procedure,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>304246</tid>
<number>d</number>become final in the country in which it was made,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>892538</tid>
<number>e</number>been in respect of a matter which may lawfully be 
referred to arbitration under the law of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India],
and the enforcement thereof must not be contrary to the public policy 
or the law of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India].


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1160697</tid>
<number>2</number>A foreign award shall not be enforceable under this Act if 
the Court dealing with the case is satisfied that--

<subsection><tid>1641556</tid>
<number>a</number>the award has been annulled in the country in which it 
was made, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1908593</tid>
<number>b</number>the party against whom it is sought to enforce the 
award was not given notice of the arbitration proceedings in 
sufficient time to enable him to present his case, or was 
under some legal incapacity and was not properly represented, 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>329261</tid>
<number>c</number>the award does not deal with all the questions referred 
or contains decisions on matters beyond the scope of the 
agreement for arbitration:
Provided that if the award does not deal with all questions 
referred the Court may, if it thinks fit, either postpone the 
enforcement of the award or order its enforcement subject to the 
giving of


<pagefootnote><pagenum>6</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch., for" the States".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

such security by the person seeking to enforce it as the Court may 
think fit.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1524650</tid>
<number>3</number>If a party seeking to resist the enforcement of a foreign 
award proves that there is any ground other than the non- existence of 
the conditions specified in clauses (a), (b) and (c) of sub- section 
 (1), or the existence of the conditions specified in clauses (b) and 
 (c) of subsection (2), entitling him to contest the validity of the 
award, the Court may,. if it thinks fit, either refuse to enforce the 
award or adjourn the hearing until after the expiration of such period 
as appears to the Court to be reasonably sufficient to enable that 
party to take the necessary steps to have the award annulled by the 
competent tribunal.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1903472</tid>
<number> 8</number> Evidence.-
<section><tid>1283784</tid>
<number>1</number>The party seeking to enforce a foreign award  
must produce-

<subsection><tid>678315</tid>
<number>a</number>the original award or a copy thereof duly authenticated 
in manner required by the law of the country in which it was 
made;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1104337</tid>
<number>b</number>evidence proving that the award has become final; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>385813</tid>
<number>c</number>such evidence as may be necessary to prove that the 
award is a foreign award and that the conditions mentioned in 
clauses (a), (b) and (c) of sub- section (1) of section 7 are 
satisfied.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1571997</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any document requiring to be produced under sub- section 
 (1) is in a foreign language, the party seeking to enforce the award 
shall produce a translation into English certified as correct by a 
diplomatic or consular agent of the country to which that party 
belongs or certified as correct in such other manner as may be 
sufficient according to the law in force in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India].



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1669604</tid>
<number> 9</number> Saving.- Nothing in this Act shall-
<section><tid>1294185</tid>
<number>a</number>prejudice any rights which any person would have had of 
enforcing in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India] any award or of availing himself in 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India] of any award if this Act had not been passed, or

</section>

<section><tid>911362</tid>
<number>b</number>apply to any award made on an, arbitration agreement 
governed by the law of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India].



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1051750</tid>
<number> 10</number> Rule- making powers of the High Court.- The High Court may 
make rules consistent with this Act as to-
<section><tid>211116</tid>
<number>a</number>the filing of foreign awards and all proceedings 
consequent thereon or incidental thereto;

</section>

<section><tid>1469790</tid>
<number>b</number>the evidence which must be furnished by a party seeking 
to enforce a foreign award under this Act; and

</section>

<section><tid>1553263</tid>
<number>c</number>generally, all proceedings in Court under this Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>7</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch., for" the States".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



 </act>