<act><tid>1666002</tid>
<title>THE STATE BANK OF HYDERABAD ACT, <year>1956</year></title>

ACT NO. 79 OF <year>1956</year>
[ 22nd December, <year>1956</year>.]

An Act to transfer the share capital of the Hyderabad State Bank to 
the Reserve Bank of India and to provide for its proper management and 
other matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>485861</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>1609679</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
State Bank of Hyderabad Act, <year>1956</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>735304</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 22nd day of 
October, <year>1956</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>976662</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1937983</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means the 22nd day of October, <year>1956</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>1887666</tid>
<number>b</number>" Hyderabad Bank" means the Hyderabad State Bank renamed 
under sub- section (1) of section 3, as the State Bank 
of Hyderabad;

</section>

<section><tid>1329005</tid>
<number>c</number>" Hyderabad State Bank" means the Hyderabad State Bank 
constituted and incorporated under the Hyderabad State 
Bank Act, 1350 F (19 of 1350 F);

<pagefootnote><pagenum>142</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>539444</tid>
<number>d</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by regulations made under 
this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>176992</tid>
<number>e</number>" Reserve Bank" means the Reserve Bank of India 
constituted under the Reserve Bank of India Act, <year>1934</year> 
 (2 of <year>1934</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>396209</tid>
<number>f</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>" State Bank" means the State Bank of India 
constituted under the State Bank of India Act, <year>1955</year> 
 (23 of <year>1955</year>)]
CHAP

RE- NAMING OF THE HYDERABAD STATE BANK AND TRANSFER OF ITS SHARECAPITAL TO 
THE RESERVE BANK

CHAPTER II

RE- NAMING OF THE HYDERABAD STATE BANK AND TRANSFER OF ITS SHARE 
CAPITAL TO THE RESERVE BANK




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1113307</tid>
<number> 3</number> Change of name of Hyderabad State Bank.-
<section><tid>1018031</tid>
<number>1</number>On the appointed  
day, the body corporate constituted by the Hyderabad State Bank Act, 
 1350 F (19 of 1350 F), and known as the Hyderabad State Bank shall be 
re- named as the State Bank of Hyderabad <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>.

</section>

<section><tid>1290774</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> The said body corporate shall consist of the State Bank 
and other shareholders, if any, for the time being, of the Hyderabad 
Bank.

</section>

<section><tid>125472</tid>
<number>2A</number>The Hyderabad Bank shall carry on the business of banking 
and other business in accordance with the provisions of the State Bank 
of India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, <year>1959</year> (38 of <year>1959</year>), and shall have 
power to acquire and hold property, whether movable or immovable, for 
the purposes of its business and to dispose of the same.]

</section>

<section><tid>1218903</tid>
<number>3</number>The change of name of the Hyderabad State Bank by sub- section 
 (1) shall not affect any rights or obligations of that bank, or render 
defective any legal proceedings by or against it; and any legal 
proceedings which might have been continued or commenced by or against 
the Hyderabad State Bank by its former name may be continued by or 
against it by its new name.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1374474</tid>
<number> 4</number> Head Office and branches of Hyderabad Bank.-
<section><tid>55973</tid>
<number>1</number>Unless  
otherwise directed by the Central Government by notification in the 
Official Gazette, the Head Office of the Hyderabad Bank shall be at 
Hyderabad.

</section>

<section><tid>72483</tid>
<number>2</number>The Hyderabad Bank shall continue to maintain every branch 
and agency of the Hyderabad State Bank in existence immediately before 
the appointed day, <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> and shall not discontinue any branch or 
establish any new branch except in consultation with the State Bank 
and with the approval of the Reserve Bank].
<pagefootnote><pagenum>143</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 38 of <year>1959</year>, s. 64 and Sch. III (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1959</year>). 
2. Certain words omitted by s. 64 and Sch. III, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 10-  
  <year>1959</year>). 
3. Subs. by s. 64 and Sch. III, ibid., for sub- section (2)  (w. e. f.  
  1- 10- <year>1959</year>). 
4. Subs. by s. 64 and Sch. III, ibid., for certain words (w. e. f. 1-  
  10- <year>1959</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>643204</tid>
<number>5</number>Transfer of share capital of Hyderabad State Bank to Reserve 
Bank.- On the appointed day, all shares in the capital of the Hyderabad 
State Bank shall be transferred to, and shall vest in, the Reserve 
Bank free of all trusts, liabilities and encumbrances.


</article>



<article><tid>692400</tid>
<number> 6</number> Compensation to share- holders of Hyderabad State Bank.-
<section><tid>1079879</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Reserve Bank shall pay to the State Government of Hyderabad and every 
other person who, immediately before the appointed day, is registered 
as a holder of shares in the Hyderabad State Bank, as compensation for 
the transfer of such shares to the Reserve Bank under section 5, an 
amount calculated at the rate of ninety- four rupees four annas and six 
pies in Indian currency for each share of the face value of one 
hundred Osmania Sicca rupees.

</section>

<section><tid>1419270</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding the transfer of the shares in the capital of 
the Hyderabad State Bank to the Reserve Bank, any shareholder who, 
immediately before the appointed day, was entitled to payment of 
dividend on the shares of the Hyderabad State Bank held by him shall 
be entitled to receive from the Hyderabad Bank all dividends declared 
by the Hyderabad State Bank in respect of his shares for any year 
which ended before the appointed day and remaining unpaid.

</section>

<section><tid>1580142</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Hyderabad State 
Bank Act, 1350 F (19 of 1350 F), no such shareholder shall be 
entitled as of right to any dividend on the shares of the Hyderabad 
State Bank held by him in respect of any period before the appointed 
day for which that bank had not declared a dividend:
Provided that the Central Government may, in respect of any such 
period, authorize the payment of dividend at such rate as it may 
specify if it is satisfied that there is sufficient balance of profits 
available after such provisions and contributions for the purposes 
referred to in section 28 as the Reserve Bank considers necessary have 
been made.


</section>

<section><tid>1702004</tid>
<number>4</number>Nothing contained in sub- section (1) shall affect the rights 
inter se between the holder of any share in the Hyderabad State Bank 
and any other person who may have an interest in such share and such 
other person shall be entitled to enforce his interest against the 
compensation awarded to the holder of such share but not against the 
Reserve Bank.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>698597</tid>
<number> 7</number> Certain officers of the Hyderabad State Bank to vacate office.-

<section><tid>1069192</tid>
<number>1</number>Every person holding office as director (including the President   
  and the managing director) or as deputy managing director,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>144</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

in the Hyderabad State Bank immediately before the appointed day, 
shall be deemed to have vacated that office on the appointed day, and 
notwithstanding anything contained in this Act or in any other law for 
the time being in force or in any agreement or contract, such person 
shall not be entitled to any compensation for the loss of office or 
for the premature termination of any agreement or contract relating to 
his employment, except such pension, compensation or other benefit, as 
the Hyderabad Bank may, with the previous approval of the Reserve 
Bank, grant to him having regard to what he would have received, if 
this Act had not been passed and if his employment had ceased on the 
appointed day in the ordinary course.


</section>

<section><tid>1920364</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing in sub- section (1) shall be deemed to prevent the 
Hyderabad Bank from re- appointing or re- employing with the previous 
permission in writing of the Reserve Bank, the managing director or 
the deputy managing director of the Hyderabad State Bank on such terms 
and conditions as are agreed upon between him and the Hyderabad Bank 
and are approved by the Reserve Bank.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1448566</tid>
<number> 8</number> Special provisions regarding existing officers and employees.-

<section><tid>329871</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in any law or contract of  
service or other document, no appointment made or promotion, increment 
in salary, pension or allowance or any other benefit granted to any 
person by the Hyderabad State Bank after the 19th day of December, 
<year>1954</year>, and before the appointed day which would not ordinarily have 
been made or granted or which would not ordinarily have been 
admissible under the rules or authorizations of the Hyderabad State 
Bank, or of any provident, pension, or other fund in force before the 
 19th day of December, <year>1954</year>, shall have effect or be payable or 
claimable from the Hyderabad Bank, or from any provident, pension or 
other fund or from any authority administering any such fund, unless 
the Reserve Bank has, by general or special order, confirmed the 
appointment, promotion or increment or has directed the grant of the 
pension, allowance or other benefit, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>839699</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any officer or other employee of the Hyderabad State 
Bank has, whether before or after the appointed day, received any 
amount by reason of any such appointment, promotion or increment or 
the grant of any such pension, allowance or other benefit, as is 
referred to in sub- section (1), which has not been confirmed or 
sanctioned by the Reserve Bank in pursuance of the powers conferred

<pagefootnote><pagenum>145</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

on it by that sub- section, such officer or other employee shall be 
bound to refund such amount to the Hyderabad Bank and that bank shall 
be entitled to take all such steps as may be necessary for recovering 
such amount.


</section>

<section><tid>1428120</tid>
<number>3</number>Where any managing director, deputy managing director or 
other employee of the Hyderabad State Bank has, after the 19th day of 
December, <year>1954</year>, and before the appointed day, been paid any sum be way 
of compensation or gratuity, the Hyderabad Bank shall be entitled to 
claim refund of any sum so paid if the payment is not confirmed by the 
Reserve Bank by general or special order.

</section>

<section><tid>991463</tid>
<number>4</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time 
being in force, the re- naming of the Hyderabad State Bank or the 
transfer of its share capital to the Reserve Bank shall not entitle 
any officer or other employees of that bank to any compensation to 
which he may be entitled under any such law, and no such claim shall 
be entertained by any Court, tribunal or other authority.
CHAP

CAPITAL OF THE HYDERABAD BANK

CHAPTER III

CAPITAL OF THE HYDERABAD BANK




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>182429</tid>
<number> 9</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Authorized capital.-
<section><tid>398815</tid>
<number>1</number>The authorised capital of the  
Hyderabad Bank shall be one crore of rupees, divided into shares of 
one hundred rupees each.

</section>

<section><tid>858394</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, the State 
Bank may, with the approval of the Reserve Bank, authorise the 
Hyderabad Bank to increase or reduce its authorised capital:
Provided that where the authorised capital is so increased, the 
shares issued shall be of the denomination specified in sub- section 
 (1).




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1120407</tid>
<number> 10</number> Issued capital.-
<section><tid>1333257</tid>
<number>1</number>The issued capital of the Hyderabad Bank  
shall, on the day on which the amendments to this Act made by the 
State Bank of India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, <year>1959</year> (38 of <year>1959</year>), take 
effect, be of such amount as the State Bank, with the approval of 
the Reserve Bank, may fix in this behalf, so however that the amount 
shall be so fixed as to consist only of fully paid- up shares of one 
hundred rupees each.

</section>

<section><tid>565151</tid>
<number>2</number>All shares in the issued capital of the Hyderabad Bank shall, 
on that day, vest in the State Bank.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>146</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 38 of <year>1959</year>, s. 64 and Sch. III, for ss. 9 and 10 
 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1959</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1106864</tid>
<number>3</number>Without prejudice to the provisions contained in sub- section 
 (4), the Hyderabad Bank may, with the approval of the State Bank and 
the Reserve Bank, increase, from time to time, its issued capital and 
the capital so increased shall consist of fully paid- up shares to be 
issued in such manner as the State Bank may, with the approval of the 
Reserve Bank, direct:
Provided that the issued capital shall be so increased that at no 
time shall the State Bank hold less than fifty- five per cent. of the 
issued capital of the Hyderabad Bank.


</section>

<section><tid>1293357</tid>
<number>4</number>The State Bank shall, as soon as may be, after the 
determination, if any, of the amount of compensation by the Tribunal 
under the State Bank of India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, <year>1959</year> (38 of  
  <year>1959</year>), consider whether any increase or reduction of the issued 
capital of the Hyderabad Bank as fixed under sub- section (1) by way of 
adjustment by transfer from, or to, the reserves of the Hyderabad Bank 
or in any other manner, is necessary, expedient or appropriate and 
may, thereafter, with the approval of the Reserve Bank, direct the 
Hyderabad Bank to increase or reduce its issued capital.]
CHAP

MANAGEMENT OF THE HYDERABAD BANK

CHAPTER IV

MANAGEMENT OF THE HYDERABAD BANK




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1550943</tid>
<number> 27</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Reserve Fund.-
<section><tid>334146</tid>
<number>1</number>The reserve fund of the Hyderabad Bank  
shall, subject to the provisions of sub- section (4) of section 10, and 
sub- section (2) of this section, consist of--

<subsection><tid>1071880</tid>
<number>a</number>on the day on which the amendments to this Act made by 
the State Bank of India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, <year>1959</year> 
 (38 of <year>1959</year>), take
<pagefootnote><pagenum>147</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 38 of <year>1959</year>, s. 64 and Sch. III, for s. 27 (w. e. f. 1-  
  10- <year>1959</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


effect, such sum as the State Bank, with the approval 
of the Reserve Bank, may determine; and


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>118193</tid>
<number>b</number>after that day, the sum aforesaid together with such 
further sums as may be transferred to the reserve fund 
by the Hyderabad Bank out of its annual net profits 
before declaring a dividend.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1123966</tid>
<number>2</number>The State Bank shall, as soon as may be after the 
determination, if any, of the amount of compensation by the Tribunal, 
under the State Bank of India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, <year>1959</year> (38 of  
  <year>1959</year>) consider whether any increase or reduction of the reserve fund 
of the Hyderabad Bank is necessary by way of adjustment by transfer 
from or to any account or towards provision for bad and doubtful 
debts, depreciation in assets, or contingencies or for any other 
purpose and may thereafter, with the approval of the Reserve Bank, 
direct the Hyderabad Bank to so increase or reduce its reserve fund.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>908678</tid>
<number> 41</number> Power of Central Government to make rules.-
<section><tid>89663</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may, in consultation with the Reserve Bank, by notification 
in the Official Gazette, make rules to give effect to the provisions 
of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>464959</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for--

<subsection><tid>1461023</tid>
<number>a</number>the manner of, and the procedure for payment of, 
compensation under this Act, including the requirements 
subject to which the payment shall be made;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1464443</tid>
<number>b</number>the determination of persons to whom the said 
compensation shall be payable in all cases including 
cases where shares have been held by more than one 
person, or where they have been transferred before the 
appointed day, but the transfer has not been registered 
or where the share holder is dead;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>148</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>34531</tid>
<number>c</number>the circumstances under which claims for payment of the 
said compensation from persons claiming through or 
under a shareholder may be entertained;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1168525</tid>
<number>d</number>the requirements to be complied with before receipt of 
the said compensation by a shareholder, whose share 
certificate has been lost, destroyed, mutilated or 
stolen;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>445911</tid>
<number>e</number>the requirements, subject to which information regarding 
the payment of the said compensation may be granted or 
refused and the conditions subject to which such 
information may be given.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>299522</tid>
<number>3</number>All rules made under this section shall be laid for not less 
than thirty days before both Houses of Parliament as soon as possible 
after they are made and shall be subject to such modifications as 
Parliament may make during the session in which they are so laid for 
the session immediately following.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>664109</tid>
<number>44</number>References to Hyderabad State Bank in other laws.- On and from 
the appointed day, any reference to the Hyderabad State Bank in any 
law (other than this Act) or in any contract or other instrument 
shall, except as otherwise provided in any general or special order 
made by the Central Government, be deemed to be a reference to the 
Hyderabad Bank.

</article>



 </act>