<act><title>THE NATIONAL COMMISSION FOR THE SCHEDULED TRIBES 
(SPECIFICATION OF OTHER FUNCTIONS) RULES, 20051</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the National Commission for the Scheduled Tribe (Specification of Other 
Functions) Rules, 2005. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of their publication 
in the Official Gazette. 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>2</number> The Commission shall discharge the following 
      other functions in relation to the protection, welfare and development and 
      advancement of the Scheduled Tribes, namely:
 <section><number>i</number>    Measures 
      that need to be taken over conferring ownership rights in respect of minor 
      forest produce to the Scheduled Tribes living in forest areas;
 </section><section><number>ii</number>    Measures to 
      be taken to safeguard rights of the tribal communities over mineral 
      resources, water resources etc. as per law;
 </section><section><number>iii</number>    Measures 
      to be taken for the development of tribals and to work for more viable 
      livelihood strategies;
 </section><section><number>iv</number>    Measures to 
      be taken to improve the efficacy of relief and rehabilitation measures for 
      tribal groups displaced by development projects;
 </section><section><number>v</number>    Measures to 
      be taken to prevent alienation of tribal people from land and to 
      effectively rehabilitate such people in whose case alienation has already 
      taken place;
 </section><section><number>vi</number>    Measures to 
      be taken to elicit maximum cooperation and involvement of tribal 
      communities for protecting forests and undertaking social 
      afforestation;
 </section><section><number>vii</number>    Measures 
      to be taken to ensure full implementation of the Provisions of Panchayats 
      (Extension to the Scheduled Areas) Act, 1996 (40 of 1996);
 </section><section><number>viii</number>    Measures 
      to be taken to reduce and ultimately eliminate the practice of shifting 
      cultivation by tribals that lead to their continuous disempowerment and 
      degradation of land and the environment.
  
 
  </section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Came into force on 24-8-2005 .</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>