<act><tid>984780</tid>
<title>THE INDUSTRIAL DEVELOPMENT BANK (TRANSFER OF  
  UNDERTAKING AND REPEAL) ACT, <year>2003</year></title>

NO. 53 OF <year>2003</year>
[ 30th December, <year>2003</year>.]

An Act to provide for the transfer and vesting of the undertaking of 
the Industrial Development Bank of India to, and in, the Company to be 
formed and registered as a Company under the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> to 
carry on banking business and for matters connected therewith or 
incidental thereto and also to repeal the Industrial Development Bank 
of India Act, <year>1964</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- fourth Year of the Republic of 
India as 
follows:-

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1861221</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>1424661</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Industrial Development Bank (Transfer of Undertaking and Repeal) Act, 
<year>2003</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>784800</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>101640</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-
<section><tid>1923286</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means such date as the Central Government may, by 
notification, appoint under section 3;

</section>

<section><tid>1822398</tid>
<number>b</number>" Company" means the Industrial Development Bank of India Limited to 
be formed and registered under the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>383383</tid>
<number>c</number>" Development Bank" means the Industrial Development Bank of India 
established under sub- section (1) of section 3 of the Industrial 
Development Bank of India Act, <year>1964</year> (18 of <year>1964</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1874993</tid>
<number>d</number>" notification" means a notification published in the Official 
Gazette;

</section>

<section><tid>1011068</tid>
<number>e</number>" Reserve Bank" means the Reserve Bank of India constituted under 
the Reserve Bank of India Act, <year>1934</year> (2 of <year>1934</year>).
CHAPTER II

TRANSFER AND VESTING OF THE UNDERTAKING OF DEVELOPMENT BANK IN COMPANY

CHAPTER II

TRANSFER AND VESTING OF THE UNDERTAKING OF DEVELOPMENT BANK IN COMPANY




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1581732</tid>
<number> 3</number> Undertaking of Development Bank to vest in Company.-
<section><tid>279403</tid>
<number>1</number>On such date  
as the Central Government may, by notification, appoint, there shall be 
transferred to, and vest in, the Company, the undertaking of 
Development Bank.

</section>

<section><tid>388714</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Banking Regulation Act, 
 <year>1949</year> (10 of <year>1949</year>), the Company referred to in sub- section (1) shall be 
deemed to be a banking company within the meaning of clause (c) of 
section 5 of the Banking Regulation Act, <year>1949</year> and as such shall carry 
on banking business in accordance with the provisions of that Act, in 
addition to the business which may be carried on and transacted by the 
Development Bank: 
Provided that such Company shall not be required to-

<subsection><tid>1135548</tid>
<number>a</number>obtain licence under section 22 of the Banking Regulation Act, <year>1949</year> 
 (10 of <year>1949</year>);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>221805</tid>
<number>b</number>maintain for a period of five years from the appointed day the 
percentage of assets required to be maintained under section 24 of the 
said Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>998643</tid>
<number>3</number>The provisions of the Banking Regulation Act, <year>1949</year> (10 of <year>1949</year>) 
shall, as far as may be, to the extent they are not repugnant to any 
provision of this Act, apply to such Company.

</section>

<section><tid>1579396</tid>
<number>4</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Banking Regulation Act, 
 <year>1949</year> (10 of <year>1949</year>), the Central Government may, in consultation with the 
Reserve Bank of India, by notification, direct that any of the 
provisions of that Act specified in the notification-

<subsection><tid>1571141</tid>
<number>a</number>shall not apply to the Company; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>984767</tid>
<number>b</number>shall apply to the Company, only with such exceptions, 
modifications and the adaptations as may be specified in the 
notification.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1542262</tid>
<number>5</number>A copy of every notification proposed to be issued under sub- 
section (4), shall be laid in draft before each House of Parliament, 
while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be 
comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, 
before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or 
the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in disapproving 
the issue of the notification or both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the notification, the notification shall not be issued 
or, as the case may be, shall be issued only in such modified form as 
may be agreed upon by both the Houses.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>555017</tid>
<number> 4</number> General effect of transfer and vesting of undertaking.-
<section><tid>1112783</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Central Government, being the shareholder of the Development Bank and 
every other shareholder of the Development Bank immediately before the 
appointed day shall be deemed to be registered on and from the 
appointed day as a shareholder of the Company to the extent of the face 
value of the shares held by such shareholder.

</section>

<section><tid>1194358</tid>
<number>2</number>The undertaking of the Development Bank which is transferred to, 
and which vest in, the Company under section 3 shall be deemed to 
include all business, assets, rights, powers, authorities and 
privileges and all properties, movable and immovable, real and 
personal, corporeal and incorporeal, in possession or reservation, 
present or contingent of whatever nature and wheresoever situate 
including lands, buildings, vehicles, cash balances, deposits, foreign 
currencies, disclosed and undisclosed reserves, reserve fund, special 
reserve fund, benevolent reserve fund, any other fund, stocks, 
investments, shares, bonds, debentures, security, management of any 
industrial concern, loans, advances and guarantees given to any person 
or industrial concern, tenancies, leases and book debts and all other 
rights and interests arising out of such property as were immediately 
before the appointed day in the ownership, possession or power of the 
Development Bank in relation to its undertaking, within or without 
India, all books of account, registers, records and documents relating 
thereto and shall also be deemed to include all borrowings, liabilities 
and obligations of whatever kind within or without India then 
subsisting of the Development Bank in relation to its respective 
undertaking.

</section>

<section><tid>258042</tid>
<number>3</number>All contracts, deeds, bonds, guarantees, powers of attorney, other 
instruments and working arrangements subsisting immediately before the 
appointed day and affecting the Development Bank shall cease to have 
effect or to be enforceable against the Development Bank and shall be 
of as full force and effect against or in favour of the Company in 
which the undertaking of the Development Bank has vested by virtue of 
this Act and enforceable as fully and effectually as if instead of the 
Development Bank, the Company had been named therein or had been a 
party thereto.

</section>

<section><tid>204113</tid>
<number>4</number>Any proceeding or cause of action pending or existing immediately 
before the appointed day by or against the Development Bank in relation 
to its undertaking may, as from the appointed day, be continued and 
enforced by or against the Company in which the undertaking of the 
Development Bank has vested by virtue of this Act as it might have been 
enforced by or against the Development Bank if this Act had not been 
enacted and shall cease to be enforceable by or against the Development 
Bank.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1336511</tid>
<number> 5</number> Provisions in respect of officers and other employees of Development 
Bank.-
<section><tid>11062</tid>
<number>1</number>Every officer or other employee of the Development Bank  
 (except a director of the Board or the chairman and managing director  
  or any whole- time director) serving in the employment immediately 
before the appointed day shall, in so far as such officer or other 
employee is employed in connection with the undertaking which has 
vested in the Company by virtue of this Act, become, as from the 
appointed day, an officer or, as the case may be, other employee of the 
Company and shall hold his office or service therein by the same 
tenure, at the same remuneration, upon the same terms and conditions, 
with the same obligations and with the same rights and privileges as to 
leave, leave fare concession, welfare scheme, medical benefit scheme, 
insurance, provident fund, other funds, retirement, voluntary 
retirement, gratuity and other benefits as he would have held under the 
Development Bank if its undertaking had not vested in the Company and 
shall continue to do so as an officer or, as the case may be, other 
employee of the Company or until the expiry of a period of six months 
from the appointed day, if such officer or other employee opts not to 
continue to be the officer or other employee of the Company within such 
period.

</section>

<section><tid>72040</tid>
<number>2</number>Where an officer or other employee of the Development Bank opts 
under sub- section (1) not to be in employment or service of the 
company, such officer or other employee shall be deemed to have 
resigned.

</section>

<section><tid>441534</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial Disputes Act, 
 <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>), or in any other law for the time being in force, the 
transfer of the services of any officer or other employee of the 
Development Bank to the Company shall not entitle such officer or other 
employee to any compensation under this Act or under any other law for 
the time being in force and no such claim shall be entertained by any 
court, tribunal or other authority.

</section>

<section><tid>1994963</tid>
<number>4</number>The officers and other employees who have retired before the 
appointed day from the service of the Development Bank and are entitled 
to any benefits, rights or privileges shall be entitled to receive the 
same benefits, rights or privileges from the Company.

</section>

<section><tid>567222</tid>
<number>5</number>The trust of the provident fund or the gratuity fund of the 
Development Bank and any other bodies created for the welfare of 
officers or employees would continue to discharge their functions in 
the Company as was being done hitherto in the Development Bank and any 
tax exemption granted to the provident fund or the gratuity fund or 
pension fund would continue to be applied to the Company.

</section>

<section><tid>686651</tid>
<number>6</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act or in the Companies 
Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), or in any other law for the time being in force 
or in the regulations of the Development Bank, no director of the 
Board, chairman and managing director or any whole- time director or any 
other person entitled to manage the whole or substantial part of the 
business and affairs of the Development Bank shall be entitled to any 
compensation against the Development Bank or the Company for the loss 
of office or for the premature termination of any contract of 
management entered into by him with the Development Bank.
CHAPTER III

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER III

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>783638</tid>
<number>6</number>Concession, etc., to be deemed to have been granted to Company.- With 
effect from the appointed day, all fiscal and other concessions, 
licences, benefits, privileges and exemptions granted to the 
Development Bank, in connection with the affairs and business of the 
Development Bank under any law for the time being in force shall be 
deemed to have been granted to the Company.


</article>



<article><tid>283318</tid>
<number> 7</number> Tax exemption or benefit to continue to have effect.-
<section><tid>1672246</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any  
exemption from, or any assessment with respect to, any tax has been 
granted or made or any benefit by way of set off or carry forward of 
any unabsorbed depreciation or investment allowance or other allowance 
or loss has been extended or is available to the Development Bank under 
the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> (43 of <year>1961</year>), such exemption, assessment or 
benefit shall continue to have effect in relation to the Company.

</section>

<section><tid>1240430</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any payment made by the Development Bank is exempted from 
deduction of tax at source under any provision of the Income- tax Act, 
 <year>1961</year> (43 of <year>1961</year>), such exemption will continue to be available as if 
the provisions of the said Act made applicable to the Development Bank 
were operative in relation to the Company.

</section>

<section><tid>1965038</tid>
<number>3</number>The transfer and vesting of the undertaking of the Development Bank 
or any part thereof in terms of section 3 shall not be construed as a 
transfer within the meaning of the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> (43 of <year>1961</year>) or 
any other law for the time being in force.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>972598</tid>
<number>8</number>Guarantee to be operative.- Any guarantee given for or in favour of 
the Development Bank with respect to any loan, lease, finance or other 
assistance shall continue to be operative in relation to the Company.


</article>



<article><tid>1521814</tid>
<number>9</number>Shares, bonds and debentures to be deemed to be approved 
securities.- Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the 
time being in force, the shares, bonds and debentures of the Company 
shall be deemed to be approved securities for the purposes of the 
Indian Trusts Act, <year>1882</year> (2 of <year>1882</year>) and the Insurance Act, <year>1938</year> (4 of  
  <year>1938</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>1788480</tid>
<number>10</number>Act to have overriding effect.- The provisions of this Act shall 
have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained 
in any enactment other than this Act or in any instrument having effect 
by virtue of any enactment other than this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1455209</tid>
<number>11</number>Application of other laws not barred.- The provisions of this Act 
shall be in addition to, and not in derogation of the provisions of any 
other law for the time being in force.


</article>



<article><tid>593665</tid>
<number>12</number>Amendment to certain enactments.- The enactments specified in the 
Schedule to this Act shall be amended in the manner provided therein.


</article>



<article><tid>654125</tid>
<number> 13</number> Substitution in Acts, rules, regulations or notifications by 
Company in place of Development Bank.- In every Act, rule, regulation or 
notification in force on the appointed day,-
<section><tid>640545</tid>
<number>a</number>for the words" Industrial Development Bank of India", wherever they 
occur, the words" Industrial Development Bank of India Limited referred 
to in clause (b) of section 2 of the Industrial Development Bank 
 (Transfer of Undertaking and Repeal) Act, <year>2003</year>" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1868670</tid>
<number>b</number>for the words" Development Bank", wherever they occur, the words 
" Industrial Development Bank of India Limited referred to in clause (b) 
of section 2 of the Industrial Development Bank (Transfer of  
  Undertaking and Repeal) Act, <year>2003</year>" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>7317</tid>
<number>c</number>for the words and figures" the Development Bank means the 
Industrial Development Bank of India, established under section 3 of 
the Industrial Development Bank of India Act, <year>1964</year> (18 of <year>1964</year>)", the 
words, brackets, letter and figures" the Industrial Development Bank of 
India Limited referred to in clause (b) of section 2 of the Industrial 
Development Bank (Transfer of Undertaking and Repeal) Act, <year>2003</year>" shall 
be substituted.

</section>

<section><tid>1321538</tid>
<number>d</number>for the words and figures" the Industrial Development Bank of 
India, established under section 3 of the Industrial Development Bank 
of India Act, <year>1964</year> (18 of <year>1964</year>)", the words, brackets, letter and 
figures" the Industrial Development Bank of India Limited referred to 
in clause (b) of section 2 of the Industrial Development Bank (Transfer  
  of Undertaking and Repeal) Act, <year>2003</year>" shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>864814</tid>
<number> 14</number> Power to remove difficulties.-
<section><tid>1194564</tid>
<number>1</number>If any difficulty arises in  
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions 
not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act as may appear to it 
to be necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty:
Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of three 
years from the date of commencement of this Act.


</section>

<section><tid>1576858</tid>
<number>2</number>Every order made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may 
be after it is made, before each House of Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1482290</tid>
<number> 15</number> Repeal and saving of Act 18 of <year>1964</year>.-
<section><tid>813429</tid>
<number>1</number>On the appointed day, the  
Industrial Development Bank of India Act, <year>1964</year>, shall stand repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1497091</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding the repeal of the Industrial Development Bank of 
India Act, <year>1964</year>, the provisions of section 30A of the Act so repealed 
will continue to be applicable in respect of the arrangement entered 
into by the Development Bank with an industrial concern up to the 
appointed day and the Company will be entitled to act upon and enforce 
the same as fully and effectually as if this Act has not been enacted.


</section>

</article>



 </act>