<act><tid>1783208</tid>
<title>THE SPECIAL TRIBUNALS, (SUPPLEMENTARYPROVISIONS) ACT, <year>1946</year></title>

ACT NO. 26 OF <year>1946</year>
[ 22nd November, <year>1946</year>.]

An Act to make certain provisions in relation to sentences and orders 
passed by Special Tribunals constituted under the Criminal Law 
Amendment Ordinance, <year>1943</year>, on such Tribunals ceasing to function.

WHEREAS it is expedient to make certain provisions in relation to 
sentences and orders passed by Special Tribunals constituted under the 
Criminal Law Amendment Ordinance, <year>1943</year> (39 of <year>1943</year>), on such Tribunal 
ceasing to function;

It is hereby enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>1427399</tid>
<number> 1</number> 
<section><tid>1387950</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title and extent. This Act may be called the  
Special Tribunals (Supplementary Provisions) Act, <year>1946</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>388995</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India except <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the territories 
which immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in Par 
B States.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1564610</tid>
<number>2</number>Interpretation. In this Act," Special Tribunal" means a 
Special Tribunal constituted under the Criminal Law Amendment 
Ordinance, <year>1943</year> (39 of <year>1943</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>680432</tid>
<number>3</number>Provision regarding sentences and orders of Special Tribunal 
which cease to function. When any Special Tribunal ceases to function, 
the sentence or orders passed by it in any case shall, for the 
purposes of the provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1898</year> (5  
  of <year>1898</year>), applicable in respect of those sentences or orders, be 
deemed, to have been passed by the Court of Session within the local 
limits of whose jurisdiction the offences charged in the case are 
alleged to have taken place, or, if there be more than one such Court 
of Session, by such one of them as the High Court, either in appeal or 
in revision or on a reference made to it specially in this behalf, may 
determine:
Provided that the references in this section to a Court of 
Session shall, where the offences charged in the case are alleged to 
have taken place in a presidency- town, be construed as references 
to the Chief Presidency Magistrate.



</article>



<article><tid>1968199</tid>
<number>4</number>[ Repeal of Ordinance 23 of <year>1946</year>.] Rep. by the Repealing and 
Amending Act, <year>1950</year> (35 of <year>1950</year>), s. 2 and Sch.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>999999</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" Part 
B States".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>