<act><title>


the National Highways Tribunal (Procedure for 
Appointment as Presiding officer of The Tribunal) 
Rules, 20031</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the National Highways Tribunal (Procedure for 
appointment as Presiding Officer of the Tribunal) Rules, 2003.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date on which the Act comes into force.
 
 


</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <subsection>
        
<number>a</number> “Act” means the Control of National Highways (Land and Traffic) Act, 2002 
(13 of 2003);
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>b</number> “Tribunal” means the National Highways Tribunal established under 
sub-section (1) of section 5 of the Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>c</number> “Presiding Officer” means a person appointed as Presiding Officer of the 
Tribunal under sub‑section (1) of section 6 of the Act;
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> All other words and 
expressions used and not defined in these rules but defined in the Act shall 
have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Method of 
appointment of Presiding Officer.—
<section><number>1</number> 
For the purpose of appointment to the post of a Presiding Officer, there shall 
be a Selection Committee consisting of—
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number> a Judge of the Supreme Court of India as nominated by the Chief Justice of 
India..................... Chairman;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number> the Secretary to the Government of India in the Ministry of Road Transport 
and Highways..................... Member;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>iii</number> the Secretary to the Government of India in the Ministry of Law and 
Justice (Department of Legal Affairs)..................... Member.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Judge of the 
Supreme Court shall be the Chairman of the Selection Committee.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any two members of the 
Selection Committee including the Chairman shall form a quorum for meeting of 
such Committee.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Selection 
Committee may devise its own procedure for selecting a candidate for appointment 
as Presiding Officer.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Selection 
Committee shall recommend persons for appointment as Presiding Officer from 
amongst the persons on the list of candidates prepared by the Ministry of Road 
Transport and Highways after inviting applications therefor.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The Central Government 
shall on the basis of the recommendations of the Selection Committee make a list 
of persons selected for appointment as Presiding Officer and the said list be 
valid for a period of two years. The appointment of a Presiding Officer shall be 
made from the list so prepared.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Medical Fitness.—No 
person shall be appointed as a Presiding Officer unless he is declared medically 
fit by a Medical Board to be constituted by the Central Government for the 
purpose unless he has already been declared fit by an equivalent authority.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Direction of the 
Central Government.—If 
any question arises relating to the implementation of these rules the same shall 
be referred to the Central Government for its decision and the decision of the 
Central Government shall be implemented.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Saving.—Nothing 
in these rules shall affect reservations, relaxation of age limit and other 
concessions required to be provided for the Scheduled Castes, Scheduled Tribes, 
Other Backward Classes, ex‑servicemen and other special categories of persons, 
in accordance with the orders issued by the Central Government from time to time 
in this regard.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Oaths of office and 
secrecy.—Every 
person appointed to be Presiding Officer under sub‑section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 6 
shall, before entering upon his office, make and subscribe an oath of office and 
secrecy in the Form I and Form II annexed to these rules.
</section></article><form>
 




the National Highways Tribunal (Procedure for  

Appointment as Presiding officer of The Tribunal)  

Rules, 2003
 


 
 


FORM II
 


(See rule 7)
 




Form of oath of secrecy for Presiding Officer of the National Highways Tribunal
 


“I, 
....................................... (Name of the Presiding Officer) having 
been appointed as Presiding Officer do solemnly affirm/do swear in the name of 
God that I will not directly or indirectly communicate or reveal to any person 
or persons any matter which shall be brought under my consideration or shall 
become known to me as Presiding Officer of said National Highways Tribunal 
except as may be required for the due discharge of my duties as the Presiding 
Officer.”
 


Date .....................                                                                                                                  
Name of the Presiding Officer
 


Place .....................                                                                                                                   
National Highways Tribunal
</form><form>
 




the National Highways Tribunal (Procedure for  

Appointment as Presiding officer of The Tribunal)  

Rules, 2003
 


 
 


FORM 3
 


(See rule 7)
 




Form of oath of office for Presiding Officer of the National Highways Tribunal
 


“I,..................... 
(Name of the Presiding Officer) having been appointed as Presiding Officer do 
solemnly affirm/do swear in the name of God that I will faithfully and 
conscientiously discharge my duties as Presiding Officer to the best of my 
ability, knowledge and judgement, without fear or favour, affection or ill 
will.”
 


Date .....................                                                                                                                  
Name of the Presiding Officer
 


Place .....................                                                                                                                   
National Highways Tribunal
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>