<act> 
 The 
Standards of Weights and Measures (Inter-State Verification and stamping) 
Rules, 1987
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the Standards of Weights and Measures (Inter-State Verification and 
Stamping) Rules, 1987.
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force 
on the date2 of 
their publication in the Official Gazette.
  




</section></article> 
 The 
Standards of Weights and Measures (Inter-State Verification and stamping) 
Rules, 1987
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  “Act” means the Standards of Weights and 
Measures Act, 1976 (60 of 1976);
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  “Section” means a section of the Act;
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  “Mint” means the Government of India Mint at 
Bombay;
 </section><section>       <number>d</number>  “Schedule” means a schedule annexed to these 
rules.
</section></article> 
 The 
Standards of Weights and Measures (Inter-State Verification and stamping) 
Rules, 1987
  
 <article><number>3</number> Classification of Weights 
and Measures.—
<section><number>1</number> The classes of 
weights or 
measures specified in the First Schedule shall be deemed to fall within the 
first category as referred to in clause (a) of sub-section (1) of section 41 
and weights or measures of all other classes shall be deemed to fall within the 
second category as referred to in clause (b) of that sub-section.
 </section><section><number>2</number> A review of the items 
specified in the First Schedule shall be made on the expiry of every two years 
from the commencement of these rules and on such review, such changes, as may 
be necessary, shall be made in the said schedule.
</section></article> 
 The 
Standards of Weights and Measures (Inter-State Verification and stamping) 
Rules, 1987
  
 <article><number>4</number> Classification of 
tank-lorries, tank-wagons or other containers used for the transport of 
commodities to be sold, delivered or distributed in the course of inter-State 
trade or commerce.—Every tank-lorry, 
wagon or other container, used as a measure or measuring instrument for the 
transport of any commodity which is to be sold during the course of inter-State 
trade or commerce, shall be deemed to fall within the first category and its 
capacity shall be calibrated and authenticated by the special seal,—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  in the case of a tank-lorry, in the state in 
which such tank-lorry is registered under the Motor Vehicles Act, 1939;
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  in the case of a tank-wagon or other container, 
not being a tank-lorry, in the State in which such wagon or other container is 
manufactured;
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  in the case of any imported tank-wagon or other 
container, not being a tank-lorry, the State in which the import has been made:
 

1[Provided that in a State where such 
calibration facility is not available, the Controller of that State may permit 
calibration of the tank vehicles in other States, where such facility is 
available.]
 




</section></article> 
 The 
Standards of Weights and Measures (Inter-State Verification and stamping) 
Rules, 1987
  
 <article><number>5</number> Special Seal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The special seal referred to in sub-section (3) of section 41 shall be of such 
size and dimensions and shall contain such particulars as are specified in the 
Second Schedule, and different sizes of special seals may be specified for the 
stamping of different classes of weights or measures.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The special seal shall be 
manufactured at the Mint at Bombay.
 

1[(2A) The special seal also contain a 
code number for each State as given in the Second Schedule.]
 </section><section><number>3</number> The cost of the special 
seal shall be borne by the State Government to which such seal is supplied.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The seals as specified in 
the Second Schedule shall not be used for any purpose other than verification 
of weights and measures sent from one State to another.
  



</section></article> 
 The 
Standards of Weights and Measures (Inter-State Verification and stamping) 
Rules, 1987
  
 <article><number>6</number> Fees for Stamping.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The fee for the verification of any weight or measure of the first category and 
stamping of the weight or measure with the special seal shall be levied by the 
Government of the transferor State at the rate leviable in that State for 
verification and stamping of the same or similar weight or measure 

1[***].
 </section><section><number>2</number> The fee for the 
verification of any weight or measure of the second category and stamping 
thereof shall be levied by the Government of the transferee State at the rate 
leviable in that State for the verification and stamping of the same or similar 
weight or measure 

1[***].
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Director shall 
determine the fee for the verification and stamping of any weight or measure in 
relation to which no fee has been specified by the Government of the concerned 
State.
  



</section></article> 
 The 
Standards of Weights and Measures (Inter-State Verification and stamping) 
Rules, 1987
  
 <article>

1[<number>7</number> Verification and Stamping (How to 
be made).—
<section><number>1</number> The verification and 
stamping of any weight or measure of the first category or of the second 
category shall be made in accordance with the provisions of the Standards of 
Weights and Measures (General) Rules, 1987.
 </section><section><number>2</number> A State may authorize any 
or all the Inspectors who fulfil the essential qualification specified for the 
Inspector of Weights and Measures under the Standards of Weights and Measures 
(Enforcement) Rules of the States/Union Territories, as amended from time to 
time, for carrying out the verification of weight or measure using the special 
seal.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Enforcement authorities in 
the transferee State may make a sample checking of weight or measure of the 
first category and in case any defect of the following type is noticed, shall 
inform the Controller of the transferor State for initiating actions, including 
penal actions against the authorities.
 <subsection>        <number>i</number>  Broken Weights
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>ii</number>  Weights with 
blow holes
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number>  Broken capacity 
measures
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iv</number>  Leaking capacity 
measures
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>v</number>  Leaking water 
meters
 
The weight or measure shall then be re-verified or rejected as specified in 
section 42 of the Standards of Weights and Measures Act, 1976.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> Every manufacturer of weight or measure of the category mentioned under the 
First Schedule shall maintain a register indicating the quantity of weight or 
measure verified with the special seal and also mention the name of the 
dealer/user to whom it has been supplied. The register shall be subject to 
inspection by the Director, Legal Metrology or authorized person. The statement 
shall also contain the name and identification of the Inspector who has 
verified and affixed the special seal.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Every manufacturer shall send, along with the consignment mentioned in the 
First Schedule, a statement indicating the quantity of weight or measure being 
sent, with the dealer's/user's name and address, to whom it has been sent. The 
dealer/user shall keep this record for inspection and also maintain a register 
of receipt and sale of such weight or measure on monthly basis, which is 
subject to inspection by enforcement officials.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The verifying authorities in the transferee State shall examine the record 
maintained by the Dealers in respect of weight or measure of the First category 
and in case of discrepancy, shall indicate the details to the Controller in the 
transferor State. He in turn may verify the details of the Statement made by 
the manufacturer in his State and take action accordingly. The Controller in 
the transferor State may also initiate similar action on the basis of records 
available with him.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> On cross checking of the statistics and accounts referred to in sub-rule 
(6) above and if it is established that a fraudulent discrepancy is found, 
suitable action may be taken against the concerned enforcement officials and 
penal action initiated against the manufacturer or dealer or both including 
suspension of his license, after giving him an opportunity of being heard.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> In case of any doubt on the correctness of any weight or measure received 
from a transferor State, any Dealer/User may in the transferee State may 
request the Inspector in the transferee State to re-verify such weight or 
measure as the case may be, on payment of the specified fee and upon such 
request the Inspector shall do so.]
  



</section></article> 
 The 
Standards of Weights and Measures (Inter-State Verification and stamping) 
Rules, 1987
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Returns.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The periodical returns referred to in section 46 shall be submitted once in 
every three months within thirty days from the last date of such third month in 
the form specified in the Third Schedule.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Separate periodical returns 
shall be submitted for each category of weight or measure.
  
</section></article> 
 The 
Standards of Weights and Measures (Inter-State Verification and stamping) 
Rules, 1987
  
 THE FIRST SCHEDULE
 (See rule 3)
 CLASSES OF WEIGHTS OR MEASURES FALLING 
 WITHIN THE FIRST CATEGORY
 (Weights and Measures which are not required to be dismantled 
before despatch and which are not likely to lose their accuracy by reason of 
transport from the State to another).
 <article>         <number>1</number> Baby weighing machines.
 </article><article>         <number>2</number> Bath room scales and person weighing machine 
except those which are required to be dismantled before despatch.
 </article><article>         <number>3</number> Beam scales classes C and D.
 </article><article>         <number>4</number> Capacity measures of denominations not 
exceeding fifty litres.
 </article><article>         <number>5</number> Kitchen scales.
 </article><article>         <number>6</number>  Length measures of all types.
 </article><article>         <number>7</number> Sphygmomanometers (Blood pressure equipment).
 </article><article>         <number>8</number> Tank-lorries, tank-wagons and other 
containers.
 </article><article>         <number>9</number> Clinical thermometers.
 </article><article>       <number>10</number>  Volumetric measures such as dispensing 
measures and liquor measures.
 </article><article>       <number>11</number> Watermeters.
 </article><article>       <number>12</number> Weights of all denominations.
 </article><article>
      1[<number>13</number>  
Non-automatic weighing instruments of digital type belonging to Ordinary 
accuracy (Class IV) having maximum capacity up to and including 50 kilograms.
 </article><article>       <number>14</number>  Spring balance of dial type.]
  




</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>