<act><title>
The
prevention of cruelty to animals
(Establishment and regulation of societies
for
prevention of cruELty
to animals) Rules, 20011</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>1</number>
Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
These rules may be called the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals (Establishment
and Regulation of Societies for Prevention of Cruelty to Animals) Rules, 2001. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official
Gazette.
  


 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In these rules, unless
the context otherwise requires,—
 


 <section><number>a</number>
“Act” means the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals Act, 1960 (59 of
1960); 
 

 </section><section><number>b</number>
“Animal Welfare Organisation” means a Welfare Organisation of animals
which is registered under the Societies Registration Act of 1860 (21 of 1860) or
any other corresponding law for the time being in force and recognised by the
Board or the Central Government; 
 

 </section><section><number>c</number>
“Board” means the Animal Welfare Board of India established under the
Act; 
 

 </section><section><number>d</number>
“local authority” means a municipal board or municipal committee, a
State Animal Welfare Board, district board or any local animal welfare
organization authorized by any law, for the control and administration of any
matter relating to animals within a specified local area; 
 

 </section><section><number>e</number>
“Society” means Society for Prevention of Cruelty to Animals
(hereinafter referred to as SPCA) established in any district under the
Societies Registration Act, 1860 (21 of 1860) or any other corresponding law
applicable in a State and shall include the existing SPCA functioning in any
district; 
 

 </section><section><number>f</number>
“veterinary doctor” means a person registered with the Veterinary
Council of India established under the Indian Veterinary Council Act, 1984 (52
of 1984). 
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>3</number>
Society for Prevention of Cruelty to Animals in a district.—
<section><number>1</number>
Every State Government shall, by notification in the Official Gazette,
establish, as soon as may be and in any event within six months from the date of
commencement of these rules, a society for every district in the State to be the
SPCA in that district: 
 Provided
that any society of prevention of cruelty to animals functioning in any district
on the date of commencement of these rules shall continue to discharge its
functions till establishment of the SPCA in that district under these rules.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Managing Committee of the Society shall be appointed by the State Government
or the local authority of the district, as the case may be, with the concurrence
of the Board and shall consist of such number of other members as may be
considered necessary by the State Government or the local authority of the
district subject to the conditions that—
 


 <subsection><number>i</number>
at least two members shall be representatives of the Animal Welfare
Organization which are actively involved in the work of prevention of cruelty to
animals and welfare of animals preferably from within the district; and  
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>
at least two members shall be the persons elected by the general body of
members of the Society. 
 

 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number>
The duties and power of the Society shall be to aid the Government, the Board
and local authority in enforcing the provisions of the Act and to make such
bye-laws and guidelines as it may deem necessary for the efficient discharge of
its duties.
 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
The Society, or any person authorized by it in this behalf, if it or he has
reasonable grounds for believing that any person has committed an offence under
the Act, it or such authorized person may require such person to produce
forthwith any animal in his possession, control, custody or ownership, or any
license, permit or any other document granted to such person or required to be
kept by him under the provisions of the Act and may stop any vehicle or enter
into any premises in order to conduct a search or inquiry and may seize an
animal in respect of which it or such authorized person has reason to believe
that an offence under the Act is being committed, and deal with it in accordance
with law.
 


 </section><section><number>5</number>
In addition to the powers conferred by these rules, the State Government may, in
consultation with the Board, confer such other powers upon any Society for
exercising the powers and discharging the functions assigned to it under these
rules.
 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>4</number>
Setting up of infirmaries and animal shelters.—
<section><number>1</number>
Every State Government shall provide adequate land and other facilities to the
Society for the purpose of constructing infirmaries and animal shelters.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Every infirmary and animal shelter, shall have—
 


 <subsection><number>i</number>
a full time veterinary doctor and other staff for the effective running
and maintenance of such infirmary or animal shelter; and 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>
an administrator who shall be appointed by the Society. 
 

 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number>
Every Society shall, thought its administrator or otherwise, supervise the
overall functioning of the infirmaries and animal shelters under its control and
jurisdiction.
 </section><section><number>4</number>
All cattle pounds and pinjrapoles owned and run by a local authority shall be
managed by such authority jointly with the Society or Animal Welfare
Organisation.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>5</number>
Regulation of SPCAs.—
<section><number>1</number> Every
Society shall submit its annual report to the Board incorporating therein the
activities undertaken by it for the welfare of animals and the steps or measures
taken by it to implement various provisions of the Act and the rules made
thereunder along with annual accounts duly audited by a chartered accountant or
any other body authorized by law within a period of one month from the date of
its accounts having been finalized by its managing committee.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Board shall examine such annual report and the annual accounts submitted by
the Society and may give any directions to it for improvement of its functioning
including the supersession of the managing committee of the Society with a view
to give effect to the provisions of the Act and the rules made thereunder:
 Provided
that the Board shall give opportunity of personal hearing to the office bearers
of the Society or any representative authorized by it before giving direction of
its supersession and holding of fresh elections for electing a new managing
committee as per bye-laws of the society.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
The Board shall give any direction to any Society in the interest of smooth and
efficient functioning of the
Society including the procedure for holding the election of the managing
committee of the Society, utilization of financial resources and management of
assets of the Society with a view to give effect to the provisions of the Act
and the rules made thereunder.

 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>