<act><tid>1146196</tid>
<title>THE USURY LAWS REPEAL ACT, <year>1855</year></title>

ACT NO. 28 OF <year>1855</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 
[ 19th September, <year>1855</year>.]
An Act for the repeal of the Usury Laws.

Preamble.-- WHEREAS it is expedient to repeal the laws now in 
force relating to usury; It is enacted as follows:-




<article><tid>937025</tid>
<number>1</number>[ Repeal of enactments.] Rep. by the Repealing Act, <year>1870</year> (14 of  
  <year>1870</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>266009</tid>
<number>2</number>Rate of interest to be decreed by Courts.-- In any suit in 
which interest is recoverable the amount shall be adjudged or decreed 
by the Court at the rate (if any) agreed upon by the parties; and if 
no rate shall have been agreed upon, at such rate as the Court shall 
deem reasonable.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>41</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Short title given by the Indian Short Titles Act, <year>1897</year> (14 of  
  <year>1897</year>).

This Act has beeen declared to be in forece in the whole of 
India, except former PArt B States and the Scheduled Districts, 
by the Laws Local Extent Act, <year>1874</year> (15 fo <year>1874</year>), s. 3.

It has been declared by notification under s. 3 (a) of the 
Scheduled Districts Act, <year>1874</year> (14 of <year>1874</year>) to be in force in the 
following Scheduled Districts, namely:-

West Jalpaiguri, the Western 
Dvars the Westerns Hills of 
Darjilling, the Darjilling 
Tarai and the Damson Sub- division 
of the Darjilling Districts. See Gazette of India <year>1881</year>. Pt. I, p. 74.

The District of Hazaribagh Ditto <year>1881</year>, Pt. I, P. 507,

The District of Lohardaga (now  
the Ranchi District see Calcutta 
  Gazette, <year>1899</year>, Pt. I, p. 44).. Ditto <year>1881</year>, Pt. I, P. 508

The District of Manbhum.. Ditto <year>1881</year>, Pt. I, P. 509

Pargana Dhalbhum in the 
District of Singbhum... Ditto <year>1881</year>, Pt. I, P. 510

The Scheduled portion of the 
Mirzapur District.. Ditto <year>1879</year>, Pt. I, P. 383

Jaunsar Bawar... Ditto <year>1879</year>, Pt. I, P. 382

The District of Lahaul.. Ditto <year>1886</year>, Pt. I, P. 301

The Scheduled Districts of the C. P. Ditto <year>1879</year>, Pt. I, P. 771

The Scheduled Districts in Ganjam 
and Vizagapatam.. Ditto <year>1898</year>, Pt. I, P. 870

The Districts of Kamrup, 
Naugong, Darrang, Sibsagar, 
Lakhimpur, Goalpara (excluding  
  the Eastern Dvars) and Cachar 
 (excluding the North Cachar  
  Hills)..... Ditto <year>1878</year>, Pt. I, P. 533

It has been extended, under s. 5 of the last- mentioned Act, to 
the following Scheduled Districts, namely:-

Kumaon and Garhwal See Gazette of India, <year>1876</year> Pt. I, p. 606

The Tarai of the Province 
of Agra (now U. P.). Ditto <year>1876</year>, Pt. I, P. 505


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>1235059</tid>
<number>3</number>Rate of interest upon a judgment or decree.-- Whenever a Court 
shall direct that a judgment or decree shall bear interest, or shall 
award interest upon a judgment or decree, it may order the interest to 
be calculated at the rate allowed in the judgment or decree upon the 
principal sum adjudged, or at such other rate as the Court shall think 
fit.


</article>



<article><tid>1629749</tid>
<number>4</number>Contracts for usufruct of property in lieu of interest.-- A 
mortgage or other contract for the loan of money, by which it is 
agreed that the use or usufruct of any property shall be allowed in 
lieu of interest, shall be binding upon the parties.


</article>



<article><tid>806800</tid>
<number>5</number>Amount of interest to be deposited in certain cases of 
conditional sales under Benga Regulaions. Proviso.-- Whenever, under 
the Regulations of the Bengal Code, a deposit may be made of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 
principal sum and interest due upon any mortgage or conditional sale 
of land hereafter to be entered into, the amount of interest to be 
deposited shall be at the rate stipulated in the contract, or, if no 
rate has been stipulated and interest be payable under the terms of 
the contract, at the rate of twelve Percentum per annum:
Provided that, in the latter case, the amount deposited shall be 
subject to the decision of the Court as to the rate at which interest 
shall be calculated.



</article>



<article><tid>1840489</tid>
<number>6</number>Rate of interest on future adjustments of acconts.-- In any 
case in which an adjustment of accounts may become necessary between 
the lender and the borrower of money upon any mortgage, conditional 
sale of landed property, or other contract whatsoever, which may be 
entered into after the passing of this Act, interest shall be 
calculated at the rate stipulated therein; or, if no rate of interest 
shall have been stipulated and interest be payable under the terms of 
the contract, at such rate as the Court shall deem reasonable.

</article>



<article><tid>1393932</tid>
<number>7</number>[ Saving of prior transactions.] Rep. by the Repealing Act, 
 <year>1870</year> (14 of <year>1870</year>).

</article>



<article><tid>1778169</tid>
<number>8</number>[ Commencement of Act.] Rep., ibid.

</article>



<article><tid>1713086</tid>
<number>9</number>[ Schedule of Repealed Enactments.] Rep., ibid.
</article>



 </act>